<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-01-14"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-01-14">14 January 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="259"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0249.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0250.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0251.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0252.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0253.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0254.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0255.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0256.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0257.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0258.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0259.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-03">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-03">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0249">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0249.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0250">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0250.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0251">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0251.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0252">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0252.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0253">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0253.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0254">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0254.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0255">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0255.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0256">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0256.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0257">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0257.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0258">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0258.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0259">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0259.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="249"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0249.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">249</fw>

<!-- GL, 2017-03-03, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
            <!--<p>
     made the difference between spending and not 
     <lb/>
     Spending money on roads? When we were not 
     <lb/>
     giving them enough money, then they did not 
     <lb/>
     spend money on roads, but when we began to 
     <lb/>
     pour the money in to them, they began to spend 
     <lb/>
     it; but it's our money all the same. It's only fair 
     <lb/>
     to say that. We must give credit where it is due, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     but not where it is not due. Roads will be built in 
     <lb/>
     future and maintained and repaired only if we 
     <lb/>
     give them the money to do it, whether it is Com<lb break="no"/>mission or some other government.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The committee rose and reported progress and 
     <lb/>
     the Convention adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     January 14, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>

   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>Report of the Transportation and Communications Committee:<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Mr. Chairman, before we go 
     <lb/>
     into the section of the report dealing with posts 
     <lb/>
     and telegraphs, there are some answers to ques<lb break="no"/>tions raised in the House in the debates on pre<lb break="no"/>vious matters, that I have to table. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the Railway, there was some question as 
     <lb/>
     to the amount of money paid out in claims. The 
     <lb/>
     Manager informed the Transportation Commit<lb break="no"/>tee in a meeting this forenoon that in the year 
     <lb/>
     ending March 31, l946, the total amount of 
     <lb/>
     claims paid out by the Railway was $36,982 and 
     <lb/>
     in the previous year $26,000. The amount paid 
     <lb/>
     out in claims runs from $25,000 to $30,000 a 
     <lb/>
     year. We asked for some explanation of even that 
     <lb/>
     relatively small amount — only 1% of the freight 
     <lb/>
     handled by the Railway in the course of the year 
     <lb/>
     — and two explanations were given. The first is 
     <lb/>
     that, since the war especially, shippers have not 
     <lb/>
     been using wooden containers but paper cartons 
     <lb/>
     instead. These get broken and the contents are 
     <lb/>
     strewn around or are pilfered. In the second place, 
     <lb/>
     the amount includes compensation paid to 
     <lb/>
     owners of cattle and horses killed along the rail<lb break="no"/>way. Another matter is that of free passes issued 
     <lb/>
     to persons on the Newfoundland Railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Figary Before we go on to the question of 
     <lb/>
     passes, I would like to ask, in regard to claims, is 
     <lb/>
     the chairman of the Committee aware that we 
     <lb/>
     could not get wooden containers, and that 25% 
     <lb/>
     was charged on cardboard containers? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood The freight charged on con<lb break="no"/>tainers was not a matter into which we went.... 
     <lb/>
     On the matter of the railway passes. In the first 
     <lb/>
     place, passes are issued only to employees of the 
     <lb/>
     Railway. One holiday pass per year may or will 
     <lb/>
     be issued to any railroader working a certain 
     <lb/>
     number of years, and the dependent members of 
     <lb/>
     his family.... Passes are issued to no one else 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     except Commissioners and to His Excellency the 
     <lb/>
     Governor; when the Commissioners or His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency, have a private or special car, the 
     <lb/>
     government pays the Railway for it. This 
     <lb/>
     privilege is universal practice — to give free 
     <lb/>
     passes to railway employees. Most railways ex<lb break="no"/>change the privilege with each other.... 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Starkes Does that mean that Canadian rail<lb break="no"/>roaders coming to this country can travel on a 
     <lb/>pass? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood Yes, for employees of the rail<lb break="no"/>ways who have that arrangement with the New<lb break="no"/>foundland Railway.... The General Manager told 
     <lb/>us that very few Americans or Canadians travel 
     <lb/>to Newfoundland on passes; many more New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders go up there than Canadians or 
     <lb/>Americans come down here.... All applications 
     <lb/>for passes go to the head of the department and 
     <lb/>from him to the General Manager, and he must 
     <lb/>sign them before they are any good. In that way 
     <lb/>they keep a record and the General Manager 
     <lb/>knows exactly what is happening with regard to 
     <lb/>the issuing of free passes on the Railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Crummey Could you tell us the number of 
     <lb/>passes in 1946 and the mileage covered? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood Neither I nor any member of 
     <lb/>the Committee nor any member of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion present thought of enquiring as to the actual 
     <lb/>number of passes issued. The issuing of railway 
     <lb/>passes is so commonplace throughout the world 
     <lb/>that mere details as to the number of passes is 
     <lb/>relatively unimportant. I ought to say that these 
     <lb/>free passes are merely for travelling. They do not 
     <lb/>include meals on the train or sleepers. In fact, if 
     <lb/>a railroader travelling on a pass wants a sleeper, 
     <lb/>he must buy an upper; he is not permitted to buy 
     <lb/>a lower berth. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job raised the question about duties col<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_01">1 Volume II:75. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note><pb n="250"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0250.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">250</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>lected by the government on materials imported 
     <lb/>
     to be used on the St. John's dry dock, in the repair 
     <lb/>
     of ships by the Railway. The situation is this: so 
     <lb/>
     far as foreign ships are concerned, any duty that 
     <lb/>
     has been paid by the Railway for material —<lb/> paint, plates or anything else — is paid back to 
     <lb/>
     the Railway. There is a rebate. When a local ship 
     <lb/>
     is repaired the duty paid by the Railway on 
     <lb/>
     materials used on that local ship is not paid back; 
     <lb/>
     it stays with the Customs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There was a question asked as to whether or 
     <lb/>
     not there had been any general increase in pas<lb break="no"/>senger fares. No. Fares for passengers on the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland Railway are 5 cents a mile first 
     <lb/>
     class and 4 cents second class. That compares 
     <lb/>
     with 3 cents a mile average rate charged in 
     <lb/>
     Canada, which seems to be of some importance 
     <lb/>
     in view of the possibility that we may be con<lb break="no"/>sidering whether or not the passenger fares could 
     <lb/>
     be increased on our Railway. If they are in<lb break="no"/>creased, they will be raised above 5 cents, which 
     <lb/>
     is now 2 cents above the average on the mainland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We asked Mr. Russell if he could give us any 
     <lb/>
     idea — making allowances for all kinds of things 
     <lb/>
     that can happen in the world and in New<lb break="no"/>foundland in the next eight or ten years — when 
     <lb/>
     the Railway might balance its budget. Perhaps it 
     <lb/>
     was not a fair question, but Mr. Russell gave his 
     <lb/>
     opinion that perhaps in about ten years time the 
     <lb/>
     Railway might break even. Until then, obviously, 
     <lb/>
     there will be an operating deficit. He is not pes<lb break="no"/>simistic about it. At the end of the last war (1914- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     1918) there was a great deal of pessimism over 
     <lb/>
     the losses on the Railway when people thought 
     <lb/>
     that for years to come the operating deficit would 
     <lb/>
     be greater and greater. It did not turn out that way. 
     <lb/>
     After a number of years the operating deficit of 
     <lb/>
     the Railway was brought down, and he thinks the 
     <lb/>
     same thing can happen again in the years ahead. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Another point raised was this question of 
     <lb/>
     shunting individual cars of newsprint paper 
     <lb/>
     brought in from Grand Falls to the paper shed on 
     <lb/>
     the dock at St. John's. The cost of that shunting 
     <lb/>
     is included in the rental paid on the shed and 
     <lb/>
     wharf. The position is this: the AND Co. pays 
     <lb/>
     $20,000 a year for the use of that shed and wharf 
     <lb/>
     at St. John's. Bowaters pays $20,000 for the use 
     <lb/>
     of the shed and wharf at Port-aux-Basques. That 
     <lb/>
     $20,000 these two companies pay gives them the 
     <lb/>
     right to have individual cars of newsprint paper 
     <lb/>
     shunted for them at St. John's and Port-aux- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
           
            <cb/>
         
     Basques. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then we come to the question of what we call 
     <lb/>
     special rates. Mr. Russell and the General Freight 
     <lb/>
     Agent, Mr. Forsey, both objected to the use of the 
     <lb/>
     term "special rates." They produced for us CNR 
     <lb/>
     and CPR tariffs to show, in connection with 
     <lb/>
     pulpwood, paper, ore, oil and things like that, that 
     <lb/>
     the tariff charged is not called "special." They 
     <lb/>
     have "Pulpwood — Carload"; "Pulpwood — <lb/> Trainload." This business of hauling ore by the 
     <lb/>
     trainload only happened since Buchans began. it 
     <lb/>
     is a new thing. The hauling of paper happened 
     <lb/>
     only in recent years, also the hauling of 
     <lb/>
     pulpwood. The Railway went after those com<lb break="no"/>panies to persuade them to haul pulpwood and 
     <lb/>
     paper by the trainload to provide traffic in the 
     <lb/>
     winter months. Then the Railway had to give the 
     <lb/>
     companies a rate for hauling that. The only thing 
     <lb/>
     they had to go by was the rate charged for the 
     <lb/>
     same kind of work in Canada and the United 
     <lb/>
     States. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Smallwood gave detailed figures showing<lb/>that the freight rates on the Newfoundland Rail.<lb/>way for pulpwood and newsprint were higher<lb/>than in the Maritimes, the Gaspé coast, and Wis<lb break="no"/>consin]</hi>
            </p>

            <p>
     In connection with newsprint, the Railway is 
     <lb/>
     negotiating right now to get the paper companies 
     <lb/>
     to get the rate raised — to get more for hauling 
     <lb/>
     paper. In connection with pulpwood, they have 
     <lb/>
     already received increases of from 30% to 60% 
     <lb/>
     over the rates that were charged by the Railway 
     <lb/>
     to those companies last year. Up to a year or so 
     <lb/>
     ago the Railway was making a profit on the 
     <lb/>
     hauling of pulpwood, but their costs rose rapidly, 
     <lb/>
     so they were not making a profit, but losing 
     <lb/>
     money on hauling. They negotiated and got an 
     <lb/>
     increase which came into effect on January 1. On 
     <lb/>
     oil, they got an increase in 1943, and after the 
     <lb/>
     present deal expires, they are looking for an 
     <lb/>
     increase of 30% from the oil companies. On ore, 
     <lb/>
     they got a 30% increase from the Buchans Mini<lb break="no"/>ng Company, taking effect from January 1, 1947. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Summing it all up, by the end of 1947, the 
     <lb/>
     freight collections of the Railway will rise to 
     <lb/>
     something between $250,000 and $300,000 a 
     <lb/>
     year. I cannot help saying that the final paragraph 
     <lb/>
     in our report, where we suggest that the Railway 
     <lb/>
     might get $300,000 to $400,000 a year, was not 
     <lb/>
     far out after all. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Before we go on to posts and telegraphs, when 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="251"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0251.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">251</fw>
        
     we were debating broadcasting, a question was 
     <lb/>
     raised about the American radio stations. There 
     <lb/>
     is one at Argentia, one at Stephenville and one at 
     <lb/>
     Fort Pepperrell.<ref target="#fn_09">[1]</ref> The one at Fort Pepperrell is 240 
     <lb/>
     watts and the other two 40 or 50 watts. The 
     <lb/>
     agreement was this: they had the right to broad<lb break="no"/>cast on those wavelengths, at that power, during 
     <lb/>
     the war and for six months after the war is offi<lb break="no"/>cially over — after the peace treaty is signed — <lb/> whenever that is. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Reddy Are there any more companies get<lb break="no"/>ting concessions on freight besides the ones men<lb break="no"/>tioned? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Yes, several purely local New<lb break="no"/>foundland companies, made up of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     capital and shareholders in special circumstan<lb break="no"/>ces. For instance the Colas Company at Claren<lb break="no"/>ville.<ref target="#fn_10">[2]</ref> There are some rates that are made to apply 
     <lb/>
     to the nature of the freight carried and Mr. Reddy 
     <lb/>
     will agree, if he ships a carload and I ship a 
     <lb/>
     quarter ton, he is entitled to a better rate. It is not 
     <lb/>
     at all in the class with these big corporations, 
     <lb/>
     because the amount is not so big and the amount 
     <lb/>
     of concession given is not nearly so great. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Reddy Would you consider Gaden's<ref target="#fn_11">[3]</ref> a 
     <lb/>
     small company? They get a rate on Coca-Cola? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Crosbie With regard to the question asked 
     <lb/>
     by Mr. Reddy, I can say "yes." Mr. Reddy is a 
     <lb/>
     businessman — at least so I am told — and if he 
     <lb/>
     is, he knows that if he buys wholesale he gets a 
     <lb/>
     better price than if he buys retail. As far as the 
     <lb/>
     Railway is concerned, they sell service. If any 
     <lb/>
     company guarantees them a certain amount of 
     <lb/>
     business, they naturally look for the best rate they 
     <lb/>
     can get, and it is up to the management of the 
     <lb/>
     Railway to give that company the best rate it can 
     <lb/>
     give. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Fudge In our last session I retired from the 
     <lb/>
     house for a while, and during my absence the 
     <lb/>
     question of wages paid to the highroads was 
     <lb/>
     raised again by Mr. Jackman and replied to by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood and Mr. Ballam. Mr. Ballam 
     <lb/>
     stated that there was 14 cents in the difference 
     <lb/>
     between the highroads rate and the paper mill 
     <lb/>
     rate. That is incorrect. The mill rate is 70 cents 
     <lb/>
     per hour for an eight-hour day. The general 
     <lb/>
     labour rate, under the organisation that I repre<lb break="no"/>sent, is 63 cents per hour for a nine-hour day, and 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
            
     on the highroads, including the town council, it 
     <lb/>
     is 58 cents. For all these local rates none of our 
     <lb/>
     men require a medical examination. In the mill 
     <lb/>
     the men must have a medical examination, that's 
     <lb/>
     why the rates are not the same. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Ballam I don't think that Mr. Fudge got that 
     <lb/>
     quite clear from what I said. I was answering a 
     <lb/>
     question brought up by Mr. Jackman as to the 
     <lb/>
     difference in the labour rates in the same locality. 
     <lb/>
     I might have said 72 1/2 cents, but I was not 
     <lb/>
     questioning or debating that, I just wanted to 
     <lb/>
     point out where the difference was. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Mr. Chairman, if the House 
     <lb/>
     desires it we will incorporate the information in 
     <lb/>
     a new memo and have it attached to the report, so 
     <lb/>
     that the documents taken together will show the 
     <lb/>
     picture pretty clearly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Does that answer all the ques<lb break="no"/>tions in connection with these various matters, or 
     <lb/>
     does any member of the Convention desire any 
     <lb/>
     additional information? If not I think we will 
     <lb/>
     proceed with the reading of the next section, posts 
     <lb/>
     and telegraphs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary continued reading the report]</hi> 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood Mr. Chairman, there are two 
     <lb/>appendices, one a report by the Secretary for 
     <lb/>Posts and Telegraphs on the alterations and im<lb break="no"/>provements that they want to make, and second 
     <lb/>an estimate of the expenditure to get these im<lb break="no"/>provements brought into force. I don't know if 
     <lb/>you want these read now, or if you want to discuss 
     <lb/>and read the paragraph and deal with these ap<lb break="no"/>pendices afterwards. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Harrington Mr. Chairman, before we go 
     <lb/>
     on with the appendices I wonder if Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood would tell us if the salaries include 
     <lb/>
     cost of living bonus or not? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood The salaries include every<lb break="no"/>thing. That's the total amount of money they get. 
     <lb/>
     There is a sentence there which says "A recent 
     <lb/>
     review of salaries of all outport postmasters 
     <lb/>
     etc." That review has been completed, and certain 
     <lb/>
     raises to the outport postmasters agreed upon, and 
     <lb/>
     the cheques have been made out. It's a rather 
     <lb/>
     complicated system, and I am not going to at<lb break="no"/>tempt to explain it in any detail. It is based on the 
     <lb/>
     business done in each office. They have a system 
     <lb/>
     of units. One letter received by a postmaster is 
     <lb/>
           
   
<note xml:id="fn_09">1 The American base in St. John's.</note>

<note xml:id="fn_10">2 A manufacturer of road making material.</note>

<note xml:id="fn_11">3 A soft drink bottling company in St. John' s.</note>
             
            <pb n="252"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0252.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">252</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
           
     counted as one unit; telegrams are in a different 
     <lb/>
     class. If he is connected with a telephone, but no 
     <lb/>
     telegraph office, and takes a message and 
     <lb/>
     telephones it to a telegraph office, that counts for 
     <lb/>
     70 units. Making out or paying out a post office 
     <lb/>
     order is so many units. All the work is reduced to 
     <lb/>
     units, and the units are counted for the month and 
     <lb/>
     the salaries are based on the number of units 
     <lb/>
     handled. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That seems very good in a way, but the trouble 
     <lb/>
     was that that was started in 1936. In 1937 the 
     <lb/>
     department made a review of the units handled in 
     <lb/>
     every office, and again in 1938 and 1939. Then 
     <lb/>
     the war came, and from that day until now they 
     <lb/>
     have never made a review. Well, they did make 
     <lb/>
     a review in some cases if an outport postmaster 
     <lb/>
     wrote in complaining that the cost of living was 
     <lb/>
     going up and his wages were not going up. They 
     <lb/>
     would then review the units he handled for that 
     <lb/>
     year and base an increase in his pay on the in<lb break="no"/>crease in the units in his office for that year 
     <lb/>
     alone.... But the trouble was that between 1939 
     <lb/>
     and 1945 or 1946 there was a steady increase in 
     <lb/>
     the number of units handled, or business done, in 
     <lb/>
     the whole country and in each individual office. 
     <lb/>
     That great increase in business you have here on 
     <lb/>
     the first page of our report. For example there 
     <lb/>
     were nine million letters in 1938-39, and in 1945- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     46 there were 13 million letters. Just as the 
     <lb/>
     country's business increased, so did that of each 
     <lb/>
     individual post office. That was not taken into 
     <lb/>
     account, only the one particular year in which a 
     <lb/>
     man wrote in asking them for God's sake to give 
     <lb/>
     him an extra dollar or two to keep him out of the 
     <lb/>
     poor house. Now they have reviewed the whole 
     <lb/>
     business done in the whole period of the war, and 
     <lb/>
     they find that the business in many places has 
     <lb/>
     increased 2-5%, and on that general increase of 
     <lb/>
     the last four or five years they have computed the 
     <lb/>
     increase in salaries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now don't get excited about the increase, 
     <lb/>
     because the whole amount for all the outport 
     <lb/>
     offices is only up from $766,000 a year to 
     <lb/>
     $880,000. In other words, the total wage bill of 
     <lb/>
     the department is increased 15%. Now turn to 
     <lb/>
     page 5.<ref target="#fn_12">[1]</ref> Taking the whole list, involving 534 
     <lb/>
     postmasters, the average increase is 12.5%, but 
     <lb/>
     the man who is getting $4.80 a week may not get 
     <lb/>
     anything like 12.5%; a post office whose man is 
     <lb/>
     only getting that, is not doing so much business, 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
            
     so his increase may be only 3%, 4% or 5%.... I 
     <lb/>
     see Mr. Hollett looking at me very quizzically, as 
     <lb/>
     if to say if it is an increase of 15%, how can it be 
     <lb/>
     only 12.5? Well I don't know, because the system 
     <lb/>
     is too complicated, and 1 don't know how they 
     <lb/>
     make it up. The actual increase in pay is 12.5%, 
     <lb/>
     although the overall increase is 15%.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett There is not much 1 can say about 
     <lb/>
     this report. I assume that the members of the 
     <lb/>
     Committee were satisfied by the Secretary's 
     <lb/>
     report that this thing is so dilapidated it has to be 
     <lb/>
     scrapped and that it will cost another $500,000 to 
     <lb/>
     replace it. At least that is the impression they give 
     <lb/>
     in the report. It seems to me that the scale of 
     <lb/>
     wages is out of date. I suggest that the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment of Posts and Telegraphs think up some new 
     <lb/>
     scheme whereby those 880 employees could be 
     <lb/>
     better paid. I had a considerable amount to do 
     <lb/>
     with postal telegraph offices in the outports, and 
     <lb/>
     I know the scandalous wages paid in the past. I 
     <lb/>
     had thought that since the war started, they were 
     <lb/>
     getting something on which to keep body and 
     <lb/>
     soul together. I see in this report that only a few 
     <lb/>
     in head office can possibly live on what they are 
     <lb/>
     getting, unless they steal it. Unfortunately, I do 
     <lb/>
     know that postal clerks have had to steal in order 
     <lb/>
     to live. Two or three of them came before my 
     <lb/>
     notice. I know one in particular, a case where a 
     <lb/>
     man had a wife and four children and he was 
     <lb/>
     getting $25 a month. There are several cases like 
     <lb/>
     that — where clerks have defaulted only, I say, 
     <lb/>
     by reason of the fact that they have had such 
     <lb/>
     miserably poor pay. If a man has a wife and four 
     <lb/>
     children, I do not see how the postal telegraphs 
     <lb/>
     can keep him in an office where the system can 
     <lb/>
     pay only $25 a month on which to live — or on 
     <lb/>
     which to die. We have only to look at the record 
     <lb/>
     of 534 postmasters, 356 are receiving salaries 
     <lb/>
     under $500 a year, or under $9.61 a week. Over 
     <lb/>
     half the total number of postmasters receive 
     <lb/>
     salaries (God save the term!) of under $4.80 a 
     <lb/>
     week. It is about time to review the salaries of the 
     <lb/>
     outport postal officials. If I were head of that 
     <lb/>
     department I would not take credit for any surplus 
     <lb/>
     when so many are receiving salaries of $4.80 a 
     <lb/>
     week. If that is not worse than slave days, 1 do not 
     <lb/>
     know what it is, and we are trying to raise the 
     <lb/>
     standard of living of our people! I do not blame 
     <lb/>
     this government only; all governments have been 
     <lb/>
     at fault in this respect. If the government can do 
     <lb/>
            
   
<note xml:id="fn_12">Volume II:95-6. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
 
            <pb n="253"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0253.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">253</fw>
           

     no better than this $4.80 a week with the revenue 
     <lb/>
     that comes in, I would suggest they spend some 
     <lb/>
     of that $10 million they have overseas interest- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     free. That is $300,000 a year slipping away, and 
     <lb/>
     it could easily go to recompense people in the 
     <lb/>
     postal telegraphs department. It has not been 
     <lb/>
     mentioned what happens to the surplus; I suppose 
     <lb/>
     it goes into the revenue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood That is right. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett There is not much more to be said 
     <lb/>
     about this report. I believe the system is out-dated 
     <lb/>
     and inadequate, as the report says, and we cannot 
     <lb/>
     blame the present Secretary for that. He has not 
     <lb/>
     been long in this country, and as far as I can find 
     <lb/>
     out he is thoroughly familiar with the big job that 
     <lb/>
     lies ahead. I hope and trust he will see that the 
     <lb/>
     people working under him will get a decent wage. 
     <lb/>
     Not only in the outports, but here in St. John's, 
     <lb/>
     people are not getting sufficient money on which 
     <lb/>
     to live decently, and unless you have well-paid 
     <lb/>
     men working for you in the government, I do not 
     <lb/>
     see how we can get anything like efficiency, and 
     <lb/>
     you cannot be sure that you are going to get 
     <lb/>
     honesty.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Vardy Mr. Chairman, I presume that as this 
     <lb/>
     is the last section of the report, that in winding up 
     <lb/>
     we can touch briefly on all sections. Taking the 
     <lb/>
     report as a whole, it is generally agreed the 
     <lb/>
     Transportation Committee has done a good job. 
     <lb/>
     It certainly covers a lot of ground and gives the 
     <lb/>
     Convention as well as the whole country much 
     <lb/>
     food for thought. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now the Convention will do very little to 
     <lb/>
     justify its existence unless its members are big 
     <lb/>
     enough to face up to the indisputable facts as we 
     <lb/>
     know them, and as they are confirmed by the 
     <lb/>
     findings of the various committees. Both in our 
     <lb/>
     individual and collective stands we will at times 
     <lb/>
     say and do things which will be strongly opposed 
     <lb/>
     by certain members who have for many years 
     <lb/>
     been associated with a union, or employed by the 
     <lb/>
     body whose policy or business we are discussing; 
     <lb/>
     yet we are all imbued with the same honest desire 
     <lb/>
     to get on with the job and do it very thoroughly.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There is only one department or utility of the 
     <lb/>
     government that is not overstuffed in proportion 
     <lb/>
     to our ability to pay, and the Railway, the high<lb break="no"/>roads department and posts and telegraphs are not 
     <lb/>
     exceptions. While we are most appreciative of 
     <lb/>
     the services rendered, those who pay have every 
     <lb/>
     right to criticise their deficiencies and shortcom<lb break="no"/><cb/>ings. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I doubt if more than one claim out of ten 
     <lb/>
     against the Railway is ever filed, and when they 
     <lb/>
     are it generally takes years to get them paid. 
     <lb/>
     There is a definite lack of discipline, and little or 
     <lb/>
     no coordination between management and staff. 
     <lb/>
     I know that many of the losses need not occur. In 
     <lb/>
     most every case where I have had to make a claim 
     <lb/>
     it should not have been necessary.... Some may 
     <lb/>
     say these are details, but do not overlook the fact 
     <lb/>
     that many details such as these go to make up the 
     <lb/>
     enormous amount our Railway is losing yearly 
     <lb/>
     through negligence, careless handling, inef<lb break="no"/>ficiency and pilfering, in at least some cases, of 
     <lb/>
     other people's goods.... Here we have a utility 
     <lb/>
     crowded with traffic in the most prosperous years 
     <lb/>
     that ever Newfoundland knew, sinking almost a 
     <lb/>
     million dollars a year. We are conscious of the 
     <lb/>
     long haul through a wilderness, the money spent 
     <lb/>
     on snow clearing, the many stops at small stations 
     <lb/>
     where the limited freight and mail handled did 
     <lb/>
     not pay; but the past six years have been provid<lb break="no"/>ing more traffic in passengers and freight than the 
     <lb/>
     system could handle, and I am not satisfied that 
     <lb/>
     at least for this period it should have shown a 
     <lb/>
     profit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In the matter of special rates to large com<lb break="no"/>panies, it has been clearly shown that while they 
     <lb/>
     may be entitled to wholesale rates commensurate 
     <lb/>
     with the amount of freight offered, and the saving 
     <lb/>
     effected by bulk handling, the difference in rates 
     <lb/>
     is far too great and altogether out of proportion 
     <lb/>
     to the difference between wholesale and retail in 
     <lb/>
     any other sphere of business. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As in most, if not all government departments, 
     <lb/>
     there is the tendency to treat men who are com<lb break="no"/>paratively young and vigorous as worn out, when 
     <lb/>
     very often they are, in reality, going through the 
     <lb/>
     most useful stage of their existence. It is not 
     <lb/>
     comparable or consistent with the age we are 
     <lb/>
     living in to regard one group of workers as being 
     <lb/>
     entitled to different privileges from another, and 
     <lb/>
     it is therefore in the spirit of treating all humans 
     <lb/>
     on an equality basis that I contend that their 
     <lb/>
     pensionable age should come at the same time in 
     <lb/>
     life.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     For a small country with a struggling utility on 
     <lb/>
     which we have such huge deficits, more discre<lb break="no"/>tion should be exercised in the issue of passes. It 
     <lb/>
     is generally conceded that far too many travel 
     <lb/>
     free when their wages are on a par with those who 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="254"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0254.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">254</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            
     always must pay. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Dealing briefly with the report on posts and 
     <lb/>
     telegraphs, if we are to accept the Secretary's 
     <lb/>
     own statement and figures as correct, it changes 
     <lb/>
     the picture that was given the public for the past 
     <lb/>
     several years, when they did show small operat<lb break="no"/>ing profit. In reality, if a fair and proper amount 
     <lb/>
     had been set aside for depreciation etc., it would 
     <lb/>
     have more truly shown a loss, and we can clearly 
     <lb/>
     see that it will take far more than the so-called 
     <lb/>
     accumulated surplus to bring their equipment up 
     <lb/>
     to date — not forgetting the huge burden they 
     <lb/>
     have thrown on the country by almost starving 
     <lb/>
     most of the outport operators and postal staff. In 
     <lb/>
     this case we do not need to mention specific cases 
     <lb/>
     as the report is there — it gives you the gruesome 
     <lb/>
     picture. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It has been stated by high-ranking officials 
     <lb/>
     that the policy of the Commission of Government 
     <lb/>
     in forcing them from 1934 onwards to close out 
     <lb/>
     so many small telephone and telegraph offices 
     <lb/>
     was very unsound, like the forming of road com<lb break="no"/>mittees to replace the former road boards. In 
     <lb/>
     order to give these unfortunate people some 
     <lb/>
     semblance of service, the department I under<lb break="no"/>stand is now considering the reopening of a 
     <lb/>
     limited number of these offices each year, there<lb break="no"/>by admitting that in the light of new evidence the 
     <lb/>
     lines should have been left standing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Again, here we find a lack of co-ordination 
     <lb/>
     between the Secretary and the staff. One can go 
     <lb/>
     to one clerk or postmaster and get a rate, and go 
     <lb/>
     to another and get an entirely different rate on the 
     <lb/>
     same matter. When the rate is disputed it is 
     <lb/>
     surprising to find how their opinions differ, and 
     <lb/>
     how they entirely disagree over the wording of 
     <lb/>
     the act.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins I have only a few comments to 
     <lb/>
     make on this report. It does strike me as outstand<lb break="no"/>ing that the government should be criticised by a 
     <lb/>
     department of the government. Unless I am 
     <lb/>
     wrong, I read this into the question outlined on 
     <lb/>
     page 2. The question was put bluntly to them, "If 
     <lb/>
     the government told you that hard times are im<lb break="no"/>minent, and relentless retrenchment must be<lb break="no"/>come the rule of conduct in all departments, what 
     <lb/>
     would your reactions be? What about your plans 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
            
     for a new and improved telegraph service then?" 
     <lb/></p>
<p>
     Their reply was that in that case they would 
     <lb/>
     inform the government that they could not under<lb break="no"/>take to carry on the telegraph system as it is 
     <lb/>
     practically collapsing. It strikes me that this is an 
     <lb/>
     extraordinary situation. This is the position. It is 
     <lb/>
     not the Committee's finding that the telegraph 
     <lb/>
     system is collapsing, it is the people responsible 
     <lb/>
     for its upkeep, the people responsible for having 
     <lb/>
     it in shape. They knew it was collapsing — it did 
     <lb/>
     not suddenly fall down and go "boom". It is a 
     <lb/>
     most extraordinary policy for the government to 
     <lb/>
     collect $179,000 profit for the past seven years 
     <lb/>
     off a service that is dying on its feet. It seems 
     <lb/>
     extraordinary that you let your machine, which is 
     <lb/>
     earning you money, get into such a condition. It 
     <lb/>
     seems stupid. There is no explanation except the 
     <lb/>
     usual one, indifference. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On another matter I presume the Committee 
     <lb/>
     did discuss the matter of this radio-telegraph 
     <lb/>
     service as compared with the old land line. I 
     <lb/>
     wonder if Mr. Smallwood would enlarge on what 
     <lb/>
     the Committee's findings on that were, whether 
     <lb/>
     it is as satisfactory as the old service, and what is 
     <lb/>
     the comparative cost? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood In answer to Mr. Higgins' first 
     <lb/>
     point, it was not until the war broke out that the 
     <lb/>
     department was even paying its way. It lost 
     <lb/>
     money, year by year, as regularly as a clock ticks 
     <lb/>
     away the time.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Smallwood read a list of losses between 
     <lb/>
     1919-20 and 1929-30]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     What happened then was this — the slump 
     <lb/>
     came and the great policy of retrenchment was 
     <lb/>
     introduced. You remember when the government 
     <lb/>
     brought in Sir Percy Thompson and Mr. Penson 
     <lb/>
     (who afterwards became a Commissioner), and 
     <lb/>
     they instituted a relentless program of economy 
     <lb/>
     and retrenchment.<ref target="#fn_13">[1]</ref> In that program the postal 
     <lb/>
     telegraph system suffered tremendously. Post of<lb break="no"/>fices were wiped out or closed down. Salaries 
     <lb/>
     were reduced, and the subsidy that the depart<lb break="no"/>ment was paid for carrying mails was reduced 
     <lb/>
     tremendously. It had been up around $500,000 a 
     <lb/>
     year, and finally in 1934 it was cut down to 
     <lb/>
     $150,000.... The operating loss took a clip from 
     <lb/>
     $872,000 in 1930-31 down to $542,000; then 
     <lb/>
          
   
<note xml:id="fn_13">Sir Percy Thompson, deputy chairman of the Board of Inland Revenue, was appointed to investigate 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland's financial position in 1931. He was succeeded by John H. Penson. For further information 
     <lb/>
    see Peter Neary, Newfoundland in the North Atlantic World, 1929-1949 (Kingston and Montreal, 1988), p. 14 
     <lb/>and p. 82. </note>
    
            <pb n="255"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0255.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">255</fw>
            
     down to $136,000; then $122,000; right down to 
     <lb/>
     $16,000, due to die cut in salaries, the reduction 
     <lb/>
     in subsidies, and the reduction in the number of 
     <lb/>
     post and telegraph offices. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The war came, and during the war, although 
     <lb/>
     they began to make money and had a surplus, it 
     <lb/>
     was impossible to get the material necessary to 
     <lb/>
     put the telegraph system into operation. It is true 
     <lb/>
     they had the radio-telegraph system before the 
     <lb/>
     war began, but that is now worn out because it 
     <lb/>
     was bought when radio was comparatively new 
     <lb/>
     and the materials are now antiquated. Before the 
     <lb/>
     war they had no money. For the 21 years between 
     <lb/>
     the two wars, they lost an average of $350,000 a 
     <lb/>
     year; or, taking out the war years, they lost 
     <lb/>
     $500,000 a year in that department. Now that the 
     <lb/>
     material is to be had, when they can they want to 
     <lb/>
     buy new material for an entirely new telegraph 
     <lb/>
     and land line system. The new system will cost 
     <lb/>
     $1 million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins I am not averse to slamming the 
     <lb/>
     government if it is necessary. I would say that 
     <lb/>
     your report leaves the impression that they did 
     <lb/>
     have the opportunity of doing something about 
     <lb/>
     the system, but did nothing. I think the point that 
     <lb/>
     they had not the opportunity to purchase equip<lb break="no"/>ment should be in your report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood You will find it in the appendix. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Higgins It is not in your own report? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood No. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins I do think it might have been in<lb break="no"/>cluded in the Committee's report rather than 
     <lb/>
     coming from the Secretary. On the other matter, 
     <lb/>
     that of salaries, I think it is a disgraceful thing, in 
     <lb/>
     what we call a civilised country, to have a person 
     <lb/>
     with the glorified title of postmaster receiving 
     <lb/>
     $4.80 a week. We either should cut out the 
     <lb/>
     glorified title, cut out the job, or give the person 
     <lb/>
     a salary consistent with the responsibility it en<lb break="no"/>tails. Like Mr. Hollett I have dealt with certain 
     <lb/>
     cases of defaulting. I certainly can find a lot of 
     <lb/>
     excuses for postmasters and postmistresses who 
     <lb/>
     have had to dip into the till to support their 
     <lb/>
     families. You are practically driving the person 
     <lb/>
     to peculation in some form or other. We have to 
     <lb/>
     remember that this man or woman receiving 
     <lb/>
     $4.80 a week has money orders for thousands of 
     <lb/>
     dollars going through his or her office. The whole 
     <lb/>
     system is entirely wrong. You get a person to 
     <lb/>
     spend his or her time and energy, and the use of 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     his or her house, and at the same time take the 
     <lb/>
     responsibility for very considerable monies, and 
     <lb/>
     she or he receives a return of $4.80 a week! I don't 
     <lb/>
     blame the government any more than I blame 
     <lb/>
     each and every resident of this island for putting 
     <lb/>
     up with that form of slavery. For that's all it is. I 
     <lb/>
     think you were proper to bring out the salaries as 
     <lb/>
     you did, and I believe that the general assembly 
     <lb/>
     here today agrees with the idea set forth by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Hollett, that that $4.80 is the worst badge of 
     <lb/>
     slavery imposed by any government of the 
     <lb/>
     civilised world on their fellow citizens. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Burry ....Now just why a department can 
     <lb/>show such a fine surplus without giving better 
     <lb/>service is beyond my ability to understand. Of 
     <lb/>course I do know the conditions that exist in 
     <lb/>Newfoundland, but I know the conditions in 
     <lb/>Labrador better. They have not been given very 
     <lb/>clearly in the report, although mention has been 
     <lb/>made of them. $12 per person was what the 38 
     <lb/>postmasters in Labrador received, and this is just 
     <lb/>one clear case for members getting up to say that 
     <lb/>the figures are ridiculous. But the services of the 
     <lb/>mail system, for instance in Labrador, are any<lb break="no"/>thing but a credit to any government or any 
     <lb/>department. It is an isolated region, and we do not 
     <lb/>expect the public service that we would like to 
     <lb/>have, but there are some things that could be 
     <lb/>improved, and the mail system is one of them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Just a few days ago I was talking to Mr. J.D. 
     <lb/>Williams of the Labrador Development Com<lb break="no"/>pany,<ref target="#fn_14">[1]</ref> and he is worried about his people down 
     <lb/>there on Labrador getting no mail for all these 
     <lb/>months. He has a right to be distressed about it, 
     <lb/>and something could be done about getting some 
     <lb/>mail into that coast. Where I come from, in the 
     <lb/>Hamilton Inlet area, they are still waiting for their 
     <lb/>first mail since the first of October, and they will 
     <lb/>have to wait yet. We do get our mail by air now, 
     <lb/>because planes are going in from Halifax three 
     <lb/>times a week to Goose Bay, and distributed along 
     <lb/>that immediate vicinity; but regularly it is done 
     <lb/>by dog team, and that is a very poor system, and 
     <lb/>the eight carriers are very poorly paid I can assure 
     <lb/>you. They have long distances to go, over dif<lb break="no"/>ficult and rough terrain, and I know because I 
     <lb/>have travelled with them time and again. I have 
     <lb/>helped them over the hills and have known the 
     <lb/>hardships that they have to go through. I am able 
     <lb/>to sympathise with their long journeys, and know 
     <lb/>
         
   
           
<note xml:id="fn_14">The Labrador Development Co. carried on logging operations in southern Labrador. </note>
           
            <pb n="256"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0256.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">256</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
       
     they are not properly paid for that kind of work. 
     <lb/>
     No figures occur here, and I am not able to give 
     <lb/>
     all the figures, but I know one case where a carrier 
     <lb/>
     had to go over 175 miles by dog team and he got 
     <lb/>
     $20 a trip. I feel that when a department is able 
     <lb/>
     to show a surplus, and we are able to give instan<lb break="no"/>ces such as this, there is something wrong some<lb break="no"/>where. Why not put some of this surplus into 
     <lb/>
     paying better wages and giving better service?.... 
     <lb/>
    
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Fudge The Committee made no reference 
     <lb/>to the recent contract for mail bags supplied to 
     <lb/>the Department of Posts and Telegraphs by, I 
     <lb/>understand, a Canadian firm. According to 
     <lb/>rumours this contract was valued at $75,000. I 
     <lb/>think we should find out the facts about this 
     <lb/>rumour. If it is correct, then why are local sail- 
     <lb break="yes"/>makers here in the city of St. John's left out?.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood ....It may be that in Canada they 
     <lb/>turn out these mailbags by the millions, and they 
     <lb/>can be imported at very great savings. I don't 
     <lb/>know, but unless it is a very considerable saving, 
     <lb/>I don't see why the order could not be placed with 
     <lb/>a local sailmaker. But I do know that as far back 
     <lb/>as I can remember the mailbags have been im<lb break="no"/>ported. I remember there was a terrific uproar, 10 
     <lb/>or 15 or maybe 18 years ago, when it was learned 
     <lb/>that the mailbags, hampers, etc., had been made 
     <lb/>by prison labour in Canada or the States.... I am 
     <lb/>not protectionist by any means, but in a matter 
     <lb/>like this the whole thing is relatively small, and 
     <lb/>the difference on $75,000 is not going to be so 
     <lb/>wonderfully great.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Fudge ....I am at a loss to know why you 
     <lb/>
     did not mention that in the report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood The members of the Commit<lb break="no"/>tee did not consider it to be their duty to go into 
     <lb/>
     relatively small details. We are dealing with a 
     <lb/>
     department that deals with $1.5 million a year. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Fudge $75,000 is not a small detail. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood ....Anyway, to be quite frank 
     <lb/>
     the Committee did not take it up. The report of 
     <lb/>
     the Committee was mimeographed and tabled in 
     <lb/>
     this House before the matter came up at all. As a 
     <lb/>
     matter of fact it was brought up by me personally. 
     <lb/>
     I would like to see the matter settled. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Reddy If a local company is able to do the 
     <lb/>
     work I don't think it should be sent to Canada. I 
     <lb/>
     wish to concur with the previous speakers about 
     <lb/>
     the low salaries of the employees in the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment of Posts and Telegraphs. I think there are 
     <lb/>
     some local phone offices where the person 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
         
     employed does not get any salary at all. That's a 
     <lb/>
     shade worse. I go on record as protesting against 
     <lb/>
     those low salaries. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Bailey I hardly know where to begin in this 
     <lb/>thing here. I was not aware of the fact that mail<lb break="no"/>bags are being imported from Canada, or else I 
     <lb/>certainly would have dug into it. I believe one 
     <lb/>time in this country mailbags were made in our 
     <lb/>own penitentiary. I don't think those things 
     <lb/>should be allowed whatever the saving. That is 
     <lb/>not what I got to my feet to speak about, however. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I want to stand alongside Rev. Mr. Hurry in 
     <lb/>the matter of the service given to the country. I 
     <lb/>believe, in fact I am sure, that never in our history 
     <lb/>has this country had the equipment that was fit 
     <lb/>for the country that we are in, thatcould save lives 
     <lb/>and give us service.... If we had a government that 
     <lb/>had been removed a little from the ox-cart age, 
     <lb/>this was a time when we could have got flying 
     <lb/>boats that could have handled our mail system on 
     <lb/>the Labrador in a matter of hours, and boats that 
     <lb/>would be on hand in case of sickness in any part 
     <lb/>of the island where a case wanted to be rushed to 
     <lb/>the hospital ... and when there is ice we could 
     <lb/>have amphibian planes. I did not intend to bring 
     <lb/>this up until the matter of health and welfare came 
     <lb/>in. Somebody would say it is a big expense, but 
     <lb/>it is not as big an expense as a cottage hospital, 
     <lb/>and we could save lives.... I believe that when the 
     <lb/>war was over and those flying boats that I spoke 
     <lb/>about were scrapped we could have had two or 
     <lb/>three of those for practically nothing, and 
     <lb/>amongst our airforce boys we had plenty of good 
     <lb/>pilots. The Labrador could have been looked 
     <lb/>after, whereas now it takes six to eight months to 
     <lb/>get a letter, and I know what that means. There is 
     <lb/>not much that we can say today except to draw 
     <lb/>their attention to it.... There is plenty of work for 
     <lb/>50 of these flying boats, mail, freight, and mercy 
     <lb/>trips, and in places where men have to be moved 
     <lb/>from one part of the island to another, I think 
     <lb/>those boats would pay without any cost to the 
     <lb/>country. I believe in this way our posts and 
     <lb/>telegraphs service could be extended, and that 
     <lb/>our hospitals could be extended and brought to 
     <lb/>the doors of the people.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Newell Mr. Chairman, it seems to me that a 
     <lb/>discussion of this report would be utterly incom<lb break="no"/>plete if we allowed it to pass from our hands 
     <lb/>without making some attempt to correlate the 
     <lb/>various sections of the report. Perhaps self<lb break="yes"/>
            
            <pb n="257"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0257.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">257</fw>
            
     criticism may be good for us — let's indulge for 
     <lb/>
     a little. I think there is a definite correlation 
     <lb/>
     between the various parts of this Transportation 
     <lb/>
     and Communications Report. Take for instance 
     <lb/>
     the sections on tourists and Gander. Surely they 
     <lb/>
     must have something in common. We have been 
     <lb/>
     criticised not a little because with one boot we 
     <lb/>
     kick people for spending a million a year on 
     <lb/>
     Gander, and at the same time urge them to spend 
     <lb/>
     many millions of dollars on roads to open up the 
     <lb/>
     country for the tourist trade. Somebody outside 
     <lb/>
     the Convention asked me if I did not think that 
     <lb/>
     Gander is doing a little to open up the country too. 
     <lb/>
     Things like that tend to give us an appearance off 
     <lb/>
     colour to the public. I don't care if the public are 
     <lb/>
     listening at the moment. That's one point. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then there is a definite relationship between 
     <lb/>
     posts and telegraphs and broadcasting which has 
     <lb/>
     supplemented posts and telegraphs to a great 
     <lb/>
     degree in this country. You have only to listen to 
     <lb/>
     Gerald S. Doyle's News Bulletin<ref target="#fn_15">[1]</ref> to realise that 
     <lb/>
     any day in the week. They spend five minutes 
     <lb/>
     broadcasting telegrams for people, which, if they 
     <lb/>
     had to follow the usual channels, would never 
     <lb/>
     arrive, because there are sections in this country 
     <lb/>
     where you cannot get a telegram through with 
     <lb/>
     any speed at all, not even, as Mr. Crosbie said, if 
     <lb/>
     you are willing to pay wholesale for it. They just 
     <lb/>
     don't go through. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then again roads and railways should be con<lb break="no"/>sidered in conjunction with each other. The ques<lb break="no"/>tion has been asked is it right to definitely endorse 
     <lb/>
     a policy of building a transinsular highway, for 
     <lb/>
     instance, when you have a transinsular railway, 
     <lb/>
     rather than concentrating on linking up some of 
     <lb/>
     the isolated settlements that need roads more? If 
     <lb/>
     we look about these settlements we can do so 
     <lb/>
     without any district consciousness or insular at<lb break="no"/>titude at all, because they are parts of the greater 
     <lb/>
     problem. I feel that we must consider roads and 
     <lb/>
     railways in conjunction with each other.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The other thing that I intended to speak about 
     <lb/>
     was this: after we have read the report and dis<lb break="no"/>cussed it, what profit has it brought us in our 
     <lb/>
     deliberation? In other words what does the report 
     <lb/>
     add to this general fact-finding job that we have 
     <lb/>
     to do? Now as far as Transportation and Com<lb break="no"/>munications are concerned, it seems to me that 
     <lb/>
     there are at least four questions we must answer: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. What are these services costing? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
<p>
     2. Are they adequate? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. If not, what should we be prepared to ex<lb break="no"/>pend on them? And I suppose you might ask the 
     <lb/>
     question, why spend anything on them? Which 
     <lb/>
     leaves the fourth question, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. What part have these services to play in the 
     <lb/>
     economic development of the country? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We must give a great deal of thought and 
     <lb/>
     attention to this matter — the economic potential 
     <lb/>
     value of the country, which we have not yet 
     <lb/>
     attempted to assess. I suppose when the other 
     <lb/>
     reports come in we will be getting down to that 
     <lb/>
     phrase of the discussion. These questions are 
     <lb/>
     important to me. If we are to make any intelligent 
     <lb/>
     estimate let's take a look at the answers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     First, what are these services costing? The 
     <lb/>
     figures I am quoting are from the report, and I am 
     <lb/>
     quoting from memory. Gander, about which we 
     <lb/>
     have a great many mental reservations, we think 
     <lb/>
     may cost up to $1 million.... Posts and telegraphs 
     <lb/>
     and broadcasting are negligible. One may have a 
     <lb/>
     slight deficit or small surplus. In order to retain 
     <lb/>
     our road system we will have to spend $1 million 
     <lb/>
     on highroads, and on local roads roughly 
     <lb/>
     $250,000. Tourists: the luscious plum was left to 
     <lb/>
     the last, because there seems to be some doubt 
     <lb/>
     about that one. We will call that X — the un<lb break="no"/>known quantity. As far as I am concerned that 
     <lb/>
     whole thing is an unknown quantity anyway. X 
     <lb/>
     plus $2.25 million to maintain our services in 
     <lb/>
     transportation and communications. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood The Railway? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Newell Well you can work in another 
     <lb/>
     $750,000 for the Railway, which brings it up to 
     <lb/>
     $3 million. Now as a projected transinsular high<lb break="no"/>way would cost $6 million, and something for the 
     <lb/>
     tourists, which is unknown as yet, the question is, 
     <lb/>
     are these services adequate? It seems that Gander 
     <lb/>
     is more than adequate. Posts and telegraphs are 
     <lb/>
     wholly inadequate. Roads, we are all agreed that 
     <lb/>
     the present road system of the country is utterly 
     <lb/>
     inadequate. Now what should we be prepared to 
     <lb/>
     spend? There we are running into considerable 
     <lb/>
     difficulty. Why should we be prepared to expend 
     <lb/>
     anything? Well, there are only two reasons as far 
     <lb/>
     as I am concerned, one is that these services such 
     <lb/>
     as the railway and roads and the others have a part 
     <lb/>
     to play in the economic development of this 
     <lb/>
     country, which is at the present time un<lb break="no"/>developed. I don't think we should look at these 
     <lb/>
          
     
<note xml:id="fn_15">A radio programme conststing of news and public servtce announcements.</note>

            <pb n="258"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0258.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">258</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
           
     services with an eye to what we can afford, or 
     <lb/>
     with the idea of cutting our garment according to 
     <lb/>
     the cloth, but with a view to finding a little more 
     <lb/>
     cloth somewhere. In other words, developing our 
     <lb/>
     economic resources so that we can fulfill the 
     <lb/>
     needs and provide a special service for the 
     <lb/>
     country. I am not prepared to carry the debate any 
     <lb/>
     further, but I do suggest that throughout a discus<lb break="no"/>sion of this sort we must keep in mind the prime 
     <lb/>
     purpose of this assembly, and I suggest that we 
     <lb/>
     look at the whole question of transportation and 
     <lb/>
     communications bearing these four simple ques<lb break="no"/>tions in mind.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett Mr. Chairman, after that rather 
     <lb/>
     lengthy homily on the duties of this Convention 
     <lb/>
     I feel disposed to say a word. I feel that nearly 
     <lb/>
     every member has the same idea in mind, that all 
     <lb/>
     these reports are to be taken and criticised and 
     <lb/>
     torn apart, in order to give us some idea what the 
     <lb/>
     services are costing the treasury, and that is ex<lb break="no"/>actly what we came here for.... I agree with Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Newell entirely, but I do feel that we have to find 
     <lb/>
     out what we can with regard to these reports, and 
     <lb/>
     if there is something we don't like, and if there is 
     <lb/>
     something that should be added, I don't know 
     <lb/>
     why we should not do something about it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Newell I do not know when these questions 
     <lb/>
     have to be answered — sometime, certainly, they 
     <lb/>
     must. Perhaps now is not the opportune moment 
     <lb/>
     to go too deeply into that phase of it.... I do not 
     <lb/>
     want anybody to infer we should not criticise 
     <lb/>
     anything in these reports... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood There is another side to it all. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Newell is dealing with the Convention itself 
     <lb/>
     — what the Convention ought to do, and with him 
     <lb/>
     we all agree. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Education Committee brought in its 
     <lb/>
     report and we debated it here for a day. Perhaps 
     <lb/>
     we ought to have debated it longer. The Forestry 
     <lb/>
     Committee report we debated a day, or part of a 
     <lb/>
     day and they are bringing in a supplementary 
     <lb/>
     report. It deals with one of the basic resources of 
     <lb/>
     the country. Now in comes the Transportation 
     <lb/>
     Committee's report. It deals not with basic 
     <lb/>
     productive industries at all, but with one of the 
     <lb/>
     big spending departments of the government. As 
     <lb/>
     these three have come in, and as the other six will 
     <lb/>
     come in and are read out, the country hears them. 
     <lb/>
     The country as a whole has no opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     knowing what is in a report except when they 
     <lb/>
     hear it read on the air. Most of us, just by hearing 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     figures and statistics read are unable to grasp 
     <lb/>
     them, and that is the purpose of the debate, among 
     <lb/>
     other things, to bring home to the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     people — our masters, whose servants we are — <lb/> information to pass on to them. One of the pur<lb break="no"/>poses of the debate is to bring out the information 
     <lb/>
     that is in the reports, cold-blooded and with no 
     <lb/>
     adjectives — for instance, note the model of 
     <lb/>
     restraint in "scandalously low salaries paid." In 
     <lb/>
     the main the reports are just factual; it is the 
     <lb/>
     debate which makes them live, that makes the 
     <lb/>
     facts and figures get up and dance. Suppose we 
     <lb/>
     adopt another method, suppose we brought in all 
     <lb/>
     nine reports and debated them; suppose we ap<lb break="no"/>pointed a new committee — a report consolida<lb break="no"/>tion committee — to knock all reports into one. 
     <lb/>
     Suppose we slapped that at the country — there 
     <lb/>
     would be a lot of mental indigestion. If we give 
     <lb/>
     it report by report, the country and ourselves will 
     <lb/>
     understand it better. So when we make our 
     <lb/>
     recommendations at last, it will not hit the 
     <lb/>
     country between the eyes as a surprise: they will 
     <lb/>
     have foreseen it, they will have anticipated it. I 
     <lb/>
     know if you were to ask the average New<lb break="no"/>foundlander to give you a one-minute description 
     <lb/>
     of the posts and telegraphs, not one could do it — <lb/> they do not realise what a monumental thing it is. 
     <lb/>
     We are educating the people of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     while educating ourselves. We must always 
     <lb/>
     remember not to get lost in a forest of facts and 
     <lb/>
     statistics — always bearing in mind that what we 
     <lb/>
     want to know is this: what is it going to cost the 
     <lb/>
     future government of Newfoundland, and where 
     <lb/>
     are we going to find it? We do not want people 
     <lb/>
     to think we are bogged down in the forest of 
     <lb/>
     information we have gathered. We are doing it 
     <lb/>
     bit by bit and thrashing it out as we go along. 
     <lb/>
    
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Higgins Before we get too far in the woods, 
     <lb/>and if Mr. Smallwood is out of them, I wonder if 
     <lb/>he would revert to a question I asked earlier. I 
     <lb/>wanted to know the Committee's opinion of the 
     <lb/>usefulness of the radio-telegraph as against the 
     <lb/>old land line and the comparative cost of both 
     <lb/>services. My own impression is that the present 
     <lb/>radio-telegraph service is very much slower, so 
     <lb/>far as individuals getting messages is concerned. 
     <lb/>It does not appear to have been gone into in the 
     <lb/>report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I am not evading that question. 
     <lb/>
     It is one that is going to cost the country a million 
     <lb/>
     dollars. It is dealt with in this rather voluminous 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="259"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-14_Page_0259.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">259</fw>
           
     report of the Secretary. We are no authorities on 
     <lb/>
     radio-telegraph; we cannot form much of an 
     <lb/>
     opinion as to whether land line or radio-telegraph 
     <lb/>
     is best, but the department has. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins Since that is a million dollar ques<lb break="no"/>tion, and my recollection of the report is that it is 
     <lb/>
     not very clear, and since I do not wish Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood to answer a question he does not 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     know, we will let the question drop. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[There was further discussion, touching on<lb/>telegrams, mail couriers, casual employees,<lb/>capital expenditures, mail contracts with the rail<lb break="no"/>way and steamers, and service in general. The<lb/>committee of the whale then rose and reported<lb/>progress, and the Convention adjourned]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

    
   <!-- GL, 2017-03-03, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p>
     January 15, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Transportation and Communications Committee:¹ 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Mr. Chairman, before we go 
     <lb/>
     into the appendix to the report on posts and 
     <lb/>
     telegraphs, there is an item that I think I ought to 
     <lb/>
     pass on to the Convention Yesterday we were 
     <lb/>
     talking about the subsidy paid by the Department 
     <lb/>
     of Posts and Telegraphs for the conveyance of 
     <lb/>
     mail, paid to the Railway. At that time I was not 
     <lb/>
     informed of the tme situation. I said the amount 
     <lb/>
     was $150,000. It was $150,000 from 1934 on. 
     <lb/>
     Before that for two or three years it was $217,000 
     <lb/>
     a year, and before that for quite a number of years 
     <lb/>
     it was $500,000. Well, on September 1, 1946, a 
     <lb/>
     new agreement was made between the Post Of<lb break="no"/>fice and Railway, setting up an entirely new basis 
     <lb/>
     for postal subsidy. Up to that time it was a flat 
     <lb/>
     rate of $150,000, but since September 1 the new 
     <lb/>
     agreement is, to the Railway 30 cents per mile, 
     <lb/>
     and to the coastal boats 50 cents per mile. It works 
     <lb/>
     out, as far as the Post Office can estimate it, at 
     <lb/>
     about $101,000 a year to the Railway, and to the 
     <lb/>
     coastal boats about $92,000. Then, over and 
     <lb/>
     above that the Post Office has agreed to pay the 
     <lb/>
     Railway a flat amount of$15,000 a year to handle 
     <lb/>
     mail in North Sydney and Port-aux-Basques, so 
     <lb/>
     that the total would be around $210,000 a year. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>We only have the appendix of the report on 
     <lb/>the posts and telegraphs which consists of a report 
     <lb/>from the Secretary of the department. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Job I was just going to allude to the fact that 
     <lb/>is there not another $100,000 in addition to the 
     <lb/>$210,000 provided by the Finance Department 
     <lb/>for the Railway? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood We are dealing only with posts 
     <lb/>and telegraphs, and there is only this $210,000 
     <lb/>now from that department. Mr. Cashin says, 
     <lb/>"Yes, there is another $100,000 paid the Railway 
     <lb/>by Finance Department." He was former Finance 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Minister, and is also chairman of the committee 
     <lb/>
     for public finance, and I would say that he would 
     <lb/>
     be the man to give the answer to that. Mr. Cashin 
     <lb/>
     nods his head and says, "Yes, they do pay that 
     <lb/>
     extra amount." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The Assistant Secretary read the report] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins What is the date of that report of 
     <lb/>
     the Secretary of posts and telegraphs? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood This is not a report made for us; 
     <lb/>
     it is made for the Commission of Government, 
     <lb/>
     and the Secretary, when he appeared before us, 
     <lb/>
     brought it and read it out, and we asked if there 
     <lb/>
     was any objection to our having copies made. It 
     <lb/>
     is a report submitted by the department to the 
     <lb/>
     government about a year ago. Some of the things 
     <lb/>
     mentioned, as things they intend to do, they have 
     <lb/>
     since done. They have introduced the ship-to- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     shore and coast-to-coast radio-telegraph system 
     <lb/>
     on the southwest coast. In Gander they have done 
     <lb/>
     some of the things they said they were going to 
     <lb/>
     do. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins How do you reconcile the second 
     <lb/>
     last sentence in the report, "Up to the present no 
     <lb/>
     sums have been allocated for reconstruction 
     <lb/>
     work", with Table 3 in the Chadwick-Jones 
     <lb/>
     report, where it says $300,000 was allocated 
     <lb/>
     1946-47? Is there any explanation? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood The Chadwick-Jones report 
     <lb/>
     was prepared about a year ago. This report of the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary was probably written a bit after that. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Higgins That is not an answer to the ques<lb break="no"/>tion. Your information may be perfectly correct 
     <lb/>and this report may be wrong; but that report 
     <lb/>stated $300,000 was allocated for reconstruction 
     <lb/>that is probably incorrect. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood You mean the Chadwickdones 
     <lb/>
     report? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>¹Volume II:75.<lb/>
            </p>-->
     </div>    </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>