<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-12-11" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-12-11">11 December 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="200"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0189.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0190.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0191.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0192.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0193.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0194.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0195.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0196.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0197.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0198.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0199.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0200.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-08">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0189">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0189.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0190">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0190.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0191">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0191.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0192">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0192.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0193">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0193.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0194">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0194.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0195">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0195.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0196">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0196.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0197">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0197.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0198">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0198.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0199">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0199.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0200">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0200.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="189" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0189.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">189</fw>
            
<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">December 11, 1946</head>

</div>
<div type="section">

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the commission appointing<lb/>Mr. Bradley Chairman of the Convention (6<lb/>December 1946), and a letter from Mrs. C. Fax]</hi></p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Mr. Chairman, before proceeding 
     <lb/>
     with the regular business of the Convention, I, as 
     <lb/>
     senior member of what was once the House of 
     <lb/>
     Assembly, feel it is my duty, on behalf of myself 
     <lb/>
     and the other delegates, to say a few words 
     <lb/>
     regarding your appointment as Chairman of this 
     <lb/>
     Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When it was indicated to us some three weeks 
     <lb/>
    ago that the Commission government were 
     <lb/>prepared to change the Convention Act to enable 
     <lb/>us to select and recommend our own Chairman, 
     <lb/>I felt you would be the logical person for such a 
     <lb/>position, and at our informal meeting held at that 
     <lb/>time, I took the opportunity of nominating you 
     <lb/>for this important post, to which you were elected 
     <lb/>unanimously by your fellow delegates. I realise 
     <lb/>that you have taken upon yourself a most difficult 
     <lb/>task, as from now on you will be called upon at 
     <lb/>times to make important and possibly far-reach<lb break="no"/>ing decisions. I feel confident you will prove 
     <lb/>equal to the task, and I am equally confident that 
     <lb/>any decisions you make will be fair and just. You 
     <lb/>are like all of us. a man of the people, and having 
     <lb/>known you for over 20 years in the political life 
     <lb/>of this country, I am sure you have the necessary 
     <lb/>parliamentary and legal knowledge to perform 
     <lb/>the duties of this important office with dignity 
     <lb/>and honour. Again, Mr. Chairman, I extend to 
     <lb/>you our most sincere congratulations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Gentlemen of the Convention, I 
     <lb/>appreciate very deeply the very laudatory 
     <lb/>remarks to which Mr. Cashin has just given ut<lb break="no"/>terance. I appreciate the honour which has been 
     <lb/>conferred in elevating me to the Chair of this 
     <lb/>Convention. I am all the more appreciative of it 
     <lb/>when I realise that it has arisen out of the wish of 
     <lb/>the members of the Convention, they being the 
     <lb/>representatives of the people, for this is a people's 
     <lb/>house. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     I realise also that this act does not arise only 
     <lb/>
     out of mere good will towards myself. I feel it is 
     <lb/>
     based upon some confidence you have in my 
     <lb/>
     ability to perform the duties of the office, and that 
     

            <cb/>
         

     fact in itself increases my sense of responsibility. 
     <lb/>
     It impresses upon me the absolute need of bend<lb break="no"/>ing all my energies to two things, first the main<lb break="no"/>tenance of the dignity of this assembly, and 
     <lb/>
     second, the necessity for an absolutely impartial 
     <lb/>
     conduct of the debates. I do not mean that it is my 
     <lb/>
     intention to apply the rules of this House purely 
     <lb/>
     in their letter, but that there must accompany any 
     <lb/>
     such interpretation a sense of the spirit of the rule 
     <lb/>
     as well. I assure you I thoroughly appreciate the 
     <lb/>
     task which lies ahead, and hope I shall measure 
     <lb/>
     up to it as you expect me to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am very pleased to be able to welcome back 
     <lb/>
     two members who have been unable to be present 
     <lb/>
     with us for some time. Mr. Jackman has had a 
     <lb/>
     very bad illness, and I am glad to welcome him 
     <lb/>
     back, and Mr. Hollett also has been unable to be 
     <lb/>
     with us for two or three weeks. I regret to an<lb break="no"/>nounce that Mr. Kennedy has had to enter hospi<lb break="no"/>tal, and is suffering from some trouble which I 
     <lb/>
     hope will soon be cleared up, and I hope he will 
     <lb/>
     be back with us again when we meet in January. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Some of you are aware that Mr. Brown, who 
     <lb/>
     was stricken so very dramatically here over a 
     <lb/>
     month ago, has now returned to his home at 
     <lb/>
     King's Cove. I was at the boat when he left on 
     <lb/>
     Saturday afternoon, and he is much improved, 
     <lb/>
     and we all hope his improvement will continue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There are one or two things that I wish to draw 
     <lb/>
     to the attention of the members. The first is that 
     <lb/>
     before the members leave town for the Christmas 
     <lb/>
     vacation I would like to see each individually; the 
     <lb/>
     second is in connection with the debates. I have 
     <lb/>
     heard complaints from the public that at times 
     <lb/>
     they do not know who is speaking. That, I fear, 
     <lb/>
     has been to some extent our own fault. I believe 
     <lb/>
     I have been an offender myself. When a member 
     <lb/>
     rises to speak I suggest that he should address the 
     <lb/>
     Chair and then remain silent until he is named by 
     <lb/>
     the Chairman. That immediately places the 
     <lb/>
     public in possession of the name of the man 
     <lb/>
     speaking. Otherwise they will be confused. If you 
     <lb/>
     will follow my instructions in this respect it will 
     <lb/>
     be better for the members themselves and for the 
     <lb/>
     public. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="190" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0190.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">190</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
 
</div>
<div type="section">          
<head>
     Report of the Transportation and Communications Committee<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
    
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Orders of the day. Mr. Small- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     wood to table a report of the Transportation and 
     <lb/>
     Communications Committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName><ref target="#fn_02">[2]</ref> Mr. Chairman, the members 
     <lb/>
     will find the copies of the report on their desks, 
     <lb/>
     and I believe that I am supposed only to give 
     <lb/>
     notice of the motion that the report be received 
     <lb/>
     tomorrow. However the day is still young, and I 
     <lb/>
     wonder, Mr. Chairman, if the gentlemen would 
     <lb/>
     be agreeable to the idea of proceeding this after<lb break="no"/>noon with the consideration of at leastone section 
     <lb/>
     of the report, and whether they would be willing 
     <lb/>
     to waive the rule requiring notice of motion.... 
     <lb/>
     What I would like to do is to move the house into 
     <lb/>
     a committee of the whole to consider the report 
     <lb/>
     of the Committee on Transportation and Com<lb break="no"/>munications, on the understanding that only one 
     <lb/>
     section, namely that on Gander, be considered 
     <lb/>
     this afternoon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention resolved into a committee of the<lb/>whole]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood The report is a pretty bulky 
     <lb/>
     document of 143 foolscap pages, covering the 
     <lb/>
     railway, the coastal steamer system, posts and 
     <lb/>
     telegraphs, roads and bridges, Gander airport, 
     <lb/>
     broadcasting, and the tourist trade. The commit<lb break="no"/>tee has worked hard, every member. Mr. Mac<lb break="no"/>Donald, Mr. Figary and Mr. Northcott were 
     <lb/>
     especially valuable members of the Committee 
     <lb/>
     in connection with its work in investigating the 
     <lb/>
     railway. Mr. Hannon was especially valuable in 
     <lb/>
     investigating posts and telegraphs, Mr. Butt and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Ryan were able to give us a lot of information 
     <lb/>
     on roads and bridges, Mr. Bailey an endless fund 
     <lb/>
     of knowledge on shipping, and Mr. Watton, who 
     <lb/>
     acted as secretary, I hope will never have to work 
     <lb/>
     as hard again as in the last two weeks. We were 
     <lb/>
     very sorry to lose you, sir, from the Committee 
     <lb/>
     but very glad to see you so signally honoured by 
     <lb/>
     being appointed Chairman of the National Con<lb break="no"/>vention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With your permission I propose for just a few 
     <lb/>
     minutes to review the report as a whole. We find 
     <lb/>
     that Gander cost $4 million to build up to the 
     <lb/>
     outbreak of the war. In 1941 the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government spent $25 million, and the 
     <lb/>
     RAF spent $3 million, so that the total cost of the 
     <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
         

     airport was $32 million. Then Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     bought out Canada's interest for $1 million. 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, since then, has spent $300,000 to 
     <lb/>
     reconvert the airport to civilian purposes, and 
     <lb/>
     will yet have to spend another $300,000 to pur<lb break="no"/>chase new equipment.... We find in the report that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Neill, Commissioner for Public Utilities, es<lb break="no"/>timates the probable operating loss at around 
     <lb/>
     $500,000 a year; while Squadron Leader Pattison 
     <lb/>
     estimates the probable operating loss at around 
     <lb/>
     $1 million a year. Roads and bridges. We have in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland today 94 miles of paved highway, 
     <lb/>
     1,500 miles of gravel highway. Secondary roads, 
     <lb/>
     442 miles motorable, 154 miles non-motorable. 
     <lb/>
     Thus 2,000 miles motorable, 3,000 miles local, 
     <lb/>
     total, 5,000 miles. Of the 5,000 miles in the 
     <lb/>
     country now, 264 miles were built since Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government came. That government 
     <lb/>
     has spent on new road construction $2 million; 
     <lb/>
     on reconditioning $1 million; on paving roads 
     <lb/>
     $1.3 million; on bridge construction, $1 million; 
     <lb/>
     on snow clearing $132,000; and on road main<lb break="no"/>tenance, $4 million — total, $11 million. Since 
     <lb/>
     they came they have spent $781,000 on the pur<lb break="no"/>chase of road machinery and equipment, and they 
     <lb/>
     need now to spend a $¹/₂ million on the purchase 
     <lb/>
     of new road machinery and equipment. We find 
     <lb/>
     that the government is spending $2¹/₂ million a 
     <lb/>
     year under the heading of "Roads and Bridges." 
     <lb/>
     We find in our report that the future expenditure 
     <lb/>
     under the heading of roads may be $1 million a 
     <lb/>
     year, and it should be $2 million and probably 
     <lb/>
     $2 1/2 million 
     <lb/> </p>


            <p>Under the heading of "Posts and Telegraphs" 
     <lb/>we find that in the last seven years there has been 
     <lb/>an average surplus of $180,000 a year and from 
     <lb/>this it would appear that the Department of Posts 
     <lb/>and Telegraphs is self-supporting. We find this 
     <lb/>has been done at the cost of letting the system 
     <lb/>itself run down; and of underpaying the staff, 
     <lb/>especially the outport staff. I cannot at this point 
     <lb/>resist the temptation to quote from one of a num<lb break="no"/>ber of letters that I have received from outport 
     <lb/>postmasters and operators. This one says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
          <p>For 25 years I have been one of those 
     <lb/>outport operators (we are everything now, 
     <lb/>postmasters, operators, bank managers, mes<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_01">[1] Volume II:75. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

<note xml:id="fn_02">[2] Mr. Smallwood became convenor of the Transportation and Communications Committee in place of Mr.<lb/>Bradley, when the latter became Chairman of the Convention.</note>

            <pb n="191" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0191.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">191</fw>
         
     sengers, all in one) whose living has been and 
     <lb/>
     still is a mere existence. During that time I 
     <lb/>
     have taught a dozen students, some of whom 
     <lb/>
     are now working with the department, others 
     <lb/>
     having had to resign and go away to the States 
     <lb/>
     and Canada to get a decent living. I have a 
     <lb/>
     wife and family. My present wage, including 
     <lb/>
     bonus and all, totals $17.50 per week, or 
     <lb/>
     approximately 32 cents per hour. This office 
     <lb/>
     is central and serves the following places 
     <lb/>
     (here he names seven settlements) with over 
     <lb/>
     2,200 people. Formerly this was the work of 
     <lb/>
     five different post offices. Amongst these 
     <lb/>
     eight settlements we have five churches with 
     <lb/>
     five clergymen, eight schools with twelve 
     <lb/>
     teachers, 22 businesses large and small, three 
     <lb/>
     garages, doctors, nurses, police, etc. An 
     <lb/>
     average of over 1,000 items of ordinary mail 
     <lb/>
     is handled daily. The general increase of 
     <lb/>
     business for the past 12 years has averaged 
     <lb/>
     over 500%. All this has been pointed out to 
     <lb/>
     the authorities and repeated requests have 
     <lb/>
     been made for adjustment of salary. I was 
     <lb/>
     told to make application. It is now November 
     <lb/>
     and no favourable reply has yet been 
     <lb/>
     forthcoming, but it is rumoured that the out<lb break="no"/>port post offices are being reviewed and their 
     <lb/>
     salaries revised. It is rumoured that the 
     <lb/>
     amount of increase for some of us married 
     <lb/>
     men will be $2.20 per month or 50 cents per 
     <lb/>
     week or 1 cent per hour. This will probably 
     <lb/>
     be termed 'substantial' and will be supposed 
     <lb/>
     to take care of present living conditions. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Small-wood, this is applicable to 75% of the 
     <lb/>
     outport officials of the Postal Telegraph Of<lb break="yes"/>fices. 
     <lb/>
      </p></quote>


            <p>This is only one of a number of similar letters 
     <lb/>received from various parts of the island, along 
     <lb/>the same lines. There are nearly 900 full-time 
     <lb/>staff employed at a cost of $750,000. There are 
     <lb/>in Newfoundland and Labrador 630 post offices. 
     <lb/>In Newfoundland. in summer, there are 159 
     <lb/>courier routes covering 167,000 miles; in winter, 
     <lb/>
          

            <cb/>


     160 courier routes covering 116,000 miles. In 
     <lb/>
     Labrador, in summer, there are two courier routes 
     <lb/>
     covering 1,340 miles; in winter, eight courier 
     <lb/>
     routes covering 7,300 miles. The increases in 
     <lb/>
     numbers of letters, telegrams and money orders 
     <lb/>
     since 1939 have been striking:<ref target="#fn_03">*</ref>
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now we find in our report that it is utterly neces<lb break="no"/>sary that $1 million be spent by the Department 
     <lb/>
     of Posts and Telegraphs to prevent its utter col<lb break="no"/>lapse. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Under the heading of "Railway", we find that 
     <lb/>
     from 1904-1946 earnings amounted to $129 mil<lb break="no"/>lion and expenses to $142 million. The operating 
     <lb/>
     loss has been $13 million. In the last 26 years 
     <lb/>
     since the government took over<ref target="#fn_04">[1]</ref>, the operating 
     <lb/>
     loss has been $7 1/2 million, an average over 
     <lb/>
     $250,000 every year. In the last ten years the 
     <lb/>
     operating surplus was $300,000, or $30,000 a 
     <lb/>
     year. This period includes the war years, the 
     <lb/>
     richest in our history. In the past 44 years there 
     <lb/>
     were only five years with a surplus; four of these 
     <lb/>
     during the recent war and the other, 1937, with a 
     <lb/>
     surplus of $32,000. In 1944-45 the operating loss 
     <lb/>
     was over $500,000; in 1945-46 it was $1 million. 
     <lb/>
     This does not tell the whole story. For there has 
     <lb/>
     been no mark-down for depreciation, and the 
     <lb/>
     government had to give the Railway $1 1 million 
     <lb/>
     for capital improvements. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Since 1923, $7 1/2 million has been given by 
     <lb/>
     the government to the Railway to pay losses; $11 
     <lb/>
     million for capital improvement. A total of $18 
     <lb/>
     million, or $700,000 a year from the public chest. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In the future, the main line has got to be 
     <lb/>
     re-railed within a very few years at a cost of 
     <lb/>
     $3 1/2 million; new rolling stock has to be pur<lb break="no"/>chased at a cost of $750,000 — total $4 million 
     <lb/>
     to be spent for capital improvement, if it is to be 
     <lb/>
     kept operating.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In connection with the Broadcasting Corpora<lb break="no"/>tion, the capital cost of land, buildings, masts, 
     <lb/>
     transmitter, and studio equipment spent by the 
     <lb/>
     government was $84,000. This amount is payable 
     <lb/>

    to the government by the Broadcasting Corpora<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_03"><table><row><cell>*</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:underline">1939</hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:underline">1945</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Letters and post cards</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$9 million</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$13 million</cell></row><row><cell>Telegraphs</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$500,000</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$ 1 million</cell></row><row><cell>Money Orders issued</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$ 250,000 </cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$ 400,000 </cell></row><row><cell>Total </cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$2,700,000 </cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$ 7,000,000 </cell></row></table></note><note xml:id="fn_04">[1] The Newfoundland government took over the railway from the Reid Newfoundland Company in 1923.</note><pb n="192" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0192.jpg"/><fw type="num">192</fw><fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw><fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>tion in 25 yearly installments at 3 1/2%. The in<lb break="no"/>come of the Corporation consists of two 
     <lb/>
     things: sale of time to broadcasters, and license 
     <lb/>
     fee received from the public on their receiving 
     <lb/>
     sets.<ref target="#fn_05">*</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     By the end of 1945 the Corporation had in<lb break="no"/>creased its fixed assets from the original $84,000 
     <lb/>
     up to $96,000, after paying the government 
     <lb/>
     $30,000 on account of capital liability, and its 
     <lb/>
     current assets stood at $75,000, of which $68,000 
     <lb/>
     was in cash. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We find the plans for the future are to build in 
     <lb/>
     St. John's a broadcasting house; in Corner Brook 
     <lb/>
     to increase VOWN from 250 to 1,000 watts and 
     <lb/>
     to erect a new building to house it; at Gander to 
     <lb/>
     take over and renovate the former RCAF radio 
     <lb/>
     station; at Grand Falls to erect a new 1,000 watt 
     <lb/>
     station. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     You will find in the report a discussion of the 
     <lb/>
     question of free speech on the government sta<lb break="no"/>tion; and a discussion of the repeated request of 
     <lb/>
     VOCM<ref target="#fn_06">[1]</ref> for the right to increase the power and 
     <lb/>
     install other stations as well. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The final section is the tourist business. You 
     <lb/>
     will find the report to be fairly comprehensive. 
     <lb/>
     The Committee reports of the pleasure it found 
     <lb/>
     on turning from the other three or four things on 
     <lb/>
     which a lot of public money is going to be lost, 
     <lb/>
     to something in which there seems an excellent 
     <lb/>
     prospect of getting money into the country in the 
     <lb/>
     shape of profits. The Committee has been im<lb break="no"/>pressed by what they have learned about the 
     <lb/>
     magnitude and value of tourist trade in North 
     <lb/>
     America and have wondered strongly what share 
     <lb/>
     our country can get of it. It has every possibility. 
     <lb/>
     I regard the tourist business as the most hopeful 
     <lb/>
     possibility economically before this country 
     <lb/>
     today. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Recapitulating the sections, the country is 
     <lb/>
     faced with annual operating loss on Gander of 
     <lb/>
     $500,000 to $1 million; on the Railway, $1 mil<lb break="no"/>lion and up. A total of a $2 1/2-3 million loss on 
    

            <cb/>
           
     operating just these two public utilities. We find 
     <lb/>
     the country is faced with the need to spend a lot 
     <lb/>
     of money on capital outlays.... Summing it up, we 
     <lb/>
     shall have to find between $3.75 and $4 million 
     <lb/>
     a year for the Railway, Gander and roads; and we 
     <lb/>
     shall have to spend around $5 million on capital 
     <lb/>
     account on these three utilities within the next 
     <lb/>
     very few years 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That is a brief outline of the 140 odd pages of 
     <lb/>
     the six sections of this report. The understanding 
     <lb/>
     is we deal merely with Gander, and I suggest that 
     <lb/>
     the report be read section by section, with any 
     <lb/>
     gentleman wishing to intervene doing so. 
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The section of the report dealing with Gander<lb/>airport was read]</hi><ref target="#fn_07">[2]</ref><lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I was hoping the members 
     <lb/>would interrupt Mr. Secretary while he was read<lb break="no"/>ing that report to take it up bit by bit, but they did 
     <lb/>not. I hope that we do not infer from that they do 
     <lb/>not intend to deal with it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> The entire operating loss that you 
     <lb/>estimate as $500,000 to $1 million, does that 
     <lb/>include the value of the landing fees or not? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That's including all income.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> According to that, the country has 
     <lb/>spent $2.5 million for the airport, it pays out $1 
     <lb/>million for salaries and that is recoverable, our 
     <lb/>own people are getting the $1 million back again, 
     <lb/>and all the other companies are paying $1 million 
     <lb/>in salaries. By the way, you made a comment 
     <lb/>about why the plane companies were not ap<lb break="no"/>proached to take over this airport themselves. Did 
     <lb/>your Committee discuss the feasibility of ap<lb break="no"/>proaching the airlines on that matter? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No. Airlines have got some 
     <lb/>kind of contractual agreement with the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and for the Committee on Transportation 
     <lb/>to approach those airline companies and interfere 
     <lb/>in any way or degree in the question of landing 
     <lb/>fees would have been an inexcusable interference 
     <lb/>with the function of government, It was not our 
     <lb/>duty, or within the rights of this Convention to 
     <lb/>
  

        
     <note xml:id="fn_05">*<table>

<row><cell/><cell><hi rendition="simple:underline">1943</hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:underline">1944</hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:underline">1945</hi></cell></row> 
     
<row><cell>Station time sold    </cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$31,000 </cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$ 45,000</cell> <cell rendition="simple:centre">$ 50,000 </cell></row>
     
<row><cell>Licenses taken in   </cell><cell rendition="simple:centre"><hi rendition="simple:underline">44,000</hi></cell><cell rendition="simple:centre"><hi rendition="simple:underline">49,000</hi> </cell><cell rendition="simple:centre"><hi rendition="simple:underline">45,000</hi></cell></row>
     
<row><cell/><cell rendition="simple:centre">$82,000</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$103,000</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$112,000</cell></row> 

<row><cell>Profit             </cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$15,000 </cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$ 11,000 </cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">$ 26,000</cell></row></table> 
  
     </note>
 

     <note xml:id="fn_06">[1] VOCM, a privately owned and operated radio station in St. John's.</note> 
     <lb/>
        
<note xml:id="fn_07">[2] Volume II:75. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
        

            <pb n="193" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0193.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">193</fw> 
 

     deal with a firm having a contract with the 
     <lb/>
     government, raising the question of landing char<lb break="no"/>ges. Mr. Higgins will agree. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Yes, but it is important. I think 
     <lb/>
     your Committee were in agreement to leasing the 
     <lb/>
     airport to the airline companies? 
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I prefer not to speak for the 
     <lb/>whole Committee on that. We stand by the report 
     <lb/>as a whole. We say it was suggested to Mr. Neill 
     <lb/>that such an attitude might have been chosen by 
     <lb/>the government in the first place. Knowing that 
     <lb/>these foreign airlines were more eager to use 
     <lb/>Gander than the government was or could be, all 
     <lb/>they had to do was to sit tight and wait for the 
     <lb/>airlines to come to them. They can't make their 
     <lb/>airlines pay, so far as the North Atlantic traffic is 
     <lb/>concerned, without Gander; it's an impossibility 
     <lb/>to make it pay, and the government might have 
     <lb/>stood pat and waited for the airlines to come to 
     <lb/>them, and then said "All right, we have no use for 
     <lb/>Gander, we have no aircraft and we don't intend 
     <lb/>to use it, but if you want to use it you can, on our 
     <lb/>conditions, and these are (1) that you pay all 
     <lb/>charges of operating the port, and (2) that you 
     <lb/>follow the conditions and standards of payment 
     <lb/>of wages, and the fact that Newfoundlanders 
     <lb/>must be employed. We lay down the standards 
     <lb/>and you follow them and pay all costs." It was 
     <lb/>suggested to Mr. Neill that should have been the 
     <lb/>attitude of the government His answer was to 
     <lb/>shrug his shoulders and not vouchsafe a word of 
     <lb/>comment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As for the Transportation Committee, in reply 
     <lb/>
     to Mr. Higgins, I still don't see for a moment that 
     <lb/>
     it would have been profitable, or that the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee would have got anywhere if it had gone to 
     <lb/>
     Pan-American, Trans-World Airways, BOAC, 
     <lb/>
     TCA, etc., and even if it had been practical to 
     <lb/>
     meet them, I don't see that it would be quite 
     <lb/>
     proper. Maybe I am misunderstanding Mr. Hig<lb break="no"/>gins. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Yes, I did mean it that way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> I would like to ask a question, 
     <lb/>
     but first I would like to make a few comments on 
     <lb/>
     the report. To my mind the way Gander is being 
     <lb/>
     operated now is a public scandal. I have ex<lb break="no"/>pressed myself on this whenever I could get an 
     <lb/>
     opportunity. The most reasonable thing to do 
     <lb/>
     would be to close down Gander. It is like a man 
     <lb/>
     with $3,000 a year trying to operate a 50 car 
     <lb/>
                        <cb/>
           

     garage for the benefit of his neighbours. It is a 
     <lb/>
     disgrace. As for the question, I see here that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood, in the preamble, page 2, says, 
     <lb/>
     "We have to record that with one exception we 
     <lb/>
     have secured all the information we wanted." 
     <lb/>
     That exception is Gander, Has that been refused? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In reply to Mr. Harrington, the 
     <lb/>House will recall that the very first question 
     <lb/>tabled in this Convention was the one I tabled in 
     <lb/>connection with Gander. It was rather a long 
     <lb/>question, asking for details of expenditure, etc. I 
     <lb/>understand that a very honest attempt is being 
     <lb/>made to get out that information, but as yet we 
     <lb/>have not received it. It has not been refused. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> It seems to me that, in expressing its 
     <lb/>
     views on the omissions, the Committee has over<lb break="no"/>looked the fact that not only should the airport 
     <lb/>
     have been run without loss to the colony, but the 
     <lb/>
     colony should have gotten something out of it. 
     <lb/>
     We have a strategic position, but it seems to have 
     <lb/>
     been given away, and a heavy loss incurred. 
     <lb/>
     There should have been something obtained for 
     <lb/>
     the colony in return for the concessions given. 
     <lb/>
     Early in February this year the surviving mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the old Legislative Council issued a 
     <lb/>
     protest through the newspapers here on the leases 
     <lb/>
     of airfields, and the lack of general information 
     <lb/>
     given to the public. In his reply Mr. Neill stated, 
     <lb/>
     as an excuse, that it was a rule between the 
     <lb/>
     nations concerned that only exchanges in air 
     <lb/>
     rights should be given. This report rightly points 
     <lb/>
     out that we were not in the same position of other 
     <lb/>
     countries because we did not want to run an air 
     <lb/>
     service, therefore we were entitled to something 
     <lb/>
     else in addition in exchange for use of our air<lb break="no"/>fields. We were a member of this organisation 
     <lb/>
     and the excuse was that we were not able to 
     <lb/>
     bargain. The answer would seem to be that we 
     <lb/>
     should never have been a member of PICAO<ref target="#fn_08">[1]</ref> s 
     <lb/>
     it is called. I thought I would like to draw the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the members to the fact that this had 
     <lb/>
     been protested against. This is exactly what 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Neill wrote us: "Strategic positions on air 
     <lb/>
     routes are not a bargaining factor against any 
     <lb/>
     other concessions. 'Air rights for air rights' is the 
     <lb/>
     accepted international principle, and any sugges<lb break="no"/>tion that air rights should be a bargaining factor 
     <lb/>
     for other concessions would not be entertained." 
     <lb/>
     That is where we fell down at the start, in agree<lb break="no"/>ing to abide by the decision of an organisation to 
   

     <note xml:id="fn_08">Provisional International Civil Aviation Organisation.</note>
 

            <pb n="194" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0194.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">194</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
  

     which it was not suitable for us to belong. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I hope this report is not a forerun<lb break="no"/>ner of some more expenditure reports coming in. 
     <lb/>
     I would like to go a little further and, as Mr. Job 
     <lb/>
     just said, I think we should have refused to 
     <lb/>
     operate this airport. It should have been operated 
     <lb/>
     by the joint airlines, and we should have had a 
     <lb/>
     rental for it of at least $500,000 a year. Instead 
     <lb/>
     we have a deficit estimated to run for at least five 
     <lb/>
     years, and only a slim hope of breaking even. I 
     <lb/>
     don't know what the expansion of aviation will 
     <lb/>
     be, but if it keeps on Gander may be by-passed, 
     <lb/>
     and Newfoundland will wind up with big deficits 
     <lb/>
     until it is finally decided to close it. How the 
     <lb/>
     government could make an agreement like that is 
     <lb/>
     beyond my comprehension. At the end of each 
     <lb/>
     statement it says that Mr. Neill has no comment. 
     <lb/>
     That is not satisfactory, but I don't see how he 
     <lb/>
     could make any comment after making the deal 
     <lb/>
     he did.... They were told what to do just the same 
     <lb/>
     as in the bases deal. The findings of this report, 
     <lb/>
     sir, are a disgrace. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> I want to compliment the members 
     <lb/>
     of the Transportation Committee for bringing in 
     <lb/>
     such a fine report, giving us the history of Gander 
     <lb/>
     and its Operation. The subject has been clear to 
     <lb/>
     me ever since we had the privilege of having 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Mr. Neill with us for a meeting of the 
     <lb/>
     Finance Committee. In talking about the Gander 
     <lb/>
     airport operation at that time he told us it was 
     <lb/>
     mnning in the red to the tune of $750,000 and the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland Railway $1 million a year. I 
     <lb/>
     remarked it was not a very satisfactory picture, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Neill remarked he hoped it would be better 
     <lb/>
     next year, and I answered that I was sure the 
     <lb/>
     people of Newfoundland hoped that it would be 
     <lb/>
     better next year. The overall picture I have from 
     <lb/>
     your report, read and explained, is that we are 
     <lb/>
     running in the red to the tune of $500,000 a year 
     <lb/>
     on the operation of Gander airport. That opera<lb break="no"/>tion, is chiefly for the convenience and benefit of 
     <lb/>
     the great powers of the world, and how New<lb break="no"/>foundland came to be forced into a deal that 
     <lb/>
     would put our poor little country in that position, 
     <lb/>
     to finance an airport for the great powers of the 
     <lb/>
     world, I can't understand. It surely is not much 
     <lb/>
     credit to them. I think businessmen, if they were 
     <lb/>
     considering the future of Newfoundland, should 
     <lb/>
     consider the matter of leasing the airport to those 
     <lb/>
     great powers, so that Newfoundland would have 
     <lb/>
                     <cb/>
          

     gotten at least something out of it for the use of 
     <lb/>
     its territory, and the people of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     should get something out of it also for its operation. 
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Mr. Chairman, I wish to call Mr. 
     <lb/>Smallwood's attention to page 2, the second 
     <lb/>paragraph, wherein he talks of a great number of 
     <lb/>trucks, etc. How is it, Mr. Smallwood, that you 
     <lb/>do not give us the exact number of trucks, equip<lb break="no"/>ment, etc? How many buildings are there at 
     <lb/>Gander? What is the size? Have any of these 
     <lb/>buildings been leased, and to whom? And what 
     <lb/>rentals have been paid? Did you inquire into the 
     <lb/>cost of running the bakery, which I understand is 
     <lb/>operated by the government? Those are the things 
     <lb/>that we should have had in this report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In reply to Mr. Fudge, the 
     <lb/>
     report says that for the $1 million that the govern<lb break="no"/>ment paid, they got the hangers and other erec<lb break="no"/>tions the Canadians have put there, as well as 
     <lb/>
     whatever equipment they left there. This equip<lb break="no"/>ment consisted of a large number of trucks, cars, 
     <lb/>
     bulldozers, tractors, snow plows, etc. The report 
     <lb/>
     might go on to add at least 1,000 other items, 
     <lb/>
     because it is just beyond counting. I doubt 
     <lb/>
     whether a complete inventory has been made by 
     <lb/>
     the Division of Civil Aviation of the whole of the 
     <lb/>
     equipment. It is something staggering. I suppose 
     <lb/>
     in connection with blankets alone there were 
     <lb/>
     easily 50,000 blankets.... The report says that if 
     <lb/>
     the government had to buy all these buildings and 
     <lb/>
     equipment new it would mean an outlay of noth<lb break="no"/>ing less than $5 million and probably much more. 
     <lb/>
     The buildings the Canadians put on Gander and 
     <lb/>
     the enlarging of the runways ran to $25 million 
     <lb/>
     capital expenditure. The government of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, for $1 million, got the enlargements 
     <lb/>
     that had been made in the runways, the new 
     <lb/>
     hangers, and dozens of great barrack buildings, 
     <lb/>
     not counting the almost uncountable number of 
     <lb/>
     pieces of equipment of every conceivable 
     <lb/>
     description... We can get the number of build<lb break="no"/>ings, and we can get the blueprints. The number 
     <lb/>
     must run into a couple of hundred buildings. It is 
     <lb/>
     a vast airport. Mr. Fudge's third question was 
     <lb/>
     what buildings have been rented out. Some build<lb break="no"/>ings have been rented to Goodyear and House....<ref target="#fn_09">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     The main question was what is the airport costing 
     <lb/>
     the country from the capital standpoint, and 
     <lb/>
     second, is the government going to make any 
     <lb/>
     money on it? The Newfoundland people have to 
    

     <note xml:id="fn_09">[1] Roland Goodyear and A.J. House opened the Goodyear Humber Stores Ltd, in Gander in 1936/37.</note>
  

            <pb n="195" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0195.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
     <fw type="num">195</fw>

          
     foot that bill. I would say in connection with this 
     <lb/>
     report that I feel anything but happy. If you look 
     <lb/>
     at the Gander section you will see "the decision 
     <lb/>
     of the Government to take over the operation of 
     <lb/>
     Gander is to us incomprehensible." You will note 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Neill was asked why the government 
     <lb/>
     made that decision cold-bloodedly, knowing it 
     <lb/>
     was going to cost $500,000 to $1 million loss 
     <lb/>
     merely to operate it; not counting the million for 
     <lb/>
     buying the installations; not counting the 
     <lb/>
     $300,000 for converting buildings to civilian use. 
     <lb/> </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I did not ask for that information. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I know. I was going to deal 
     <lb/>with it, if you have no objection. In addition to 
     <lb/>another $300,000 to buy still further equipment 
     <lb/>— that is $1,600,000 on capital account since the 
     <lb/>war ended — on top of that to lose up to $1 
     <lb/>million a year; frankly I do not believe that the 
     <lb/>Newfoundland government decided that in cold 
     <lb/>blood — to saddle the people of this country with 
     <lb/>a loss of $1 million a year. At the last session one 
     <lb/>of the gentlemen proposed that the privilege 
     <lb/>should be accorded members of this Convention, 
     <lb/>that they should have the right that former Houses 
     <lb/>of Assembly had, not to be sued in court for 
     <lb/>anything said on the floor of the House. We have 
     <lb/>not that right — I wish we had. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Why does not Mr. Smallwood go 
     <lb/>
     ahead and take a chance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I would like to remind Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood that indulging in personalities is not 
     <lb/>
     permitted here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I do not intend to indulge in 
     <lb/>
     personalities with anyone, but Mr. Neill said 
     <lb/>
     categorically it was the first he heard of it. It was 
     <lb/>
     suggested to him that the proposition that the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland government operate Gander, 
     <lb/>
     even at a loss, was made to the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     government by the British; and he said it was the 
     <lb/>
     first he heard of it. When it was suggested to him 
     <lb/>
     that the British government was, in fact, footing 
     <lb/>
     the bills and paying the operating losses, he said 
     <lb/>
     it was the first he heard of it. I say this, that I am 
     <lb/>
     very sorry we have not that privilege which 
     <lb/>
     former Houses of Assembly had.... Cast your 
     <lb/>
     mind back to a year ago. The war was just about 
     <lb/>
     over, and the United States with a vast aircraft 
     <lb/>
     industry was ready to hurl a vast armada of pas<lb break="no"/>senger planes in the air, ready to seize control of 
     <lb/>
     the air traffic of the world. Great Britain was not 
     <lb/>
     ready; we had no aircraft; she is not ready yet. 
   

            <cb/>
          

     This is now December, 1946. If one year ago the 
     <lb/>
     United States had enough planes ready to capture 
     <lb/>
     the air traffic of the air. there was only one thing 
     <lb/>
     that could stop that. That was Gander. Because 
     <lb/>
     the United States airlines must have Gander.... By 
     <lb/>
     being able to land at Gander, an aircraft does not 
     <lb/>
     have to carry fuel load from New York. The 
     <lb/>
     landing fees are $85 each way, $170 a trip.... $170 
     <lb/>
     comes to the government for the privilege of 
     <lb/>
     saving them what? Thousands of dollars. There 
     <lb/>
     is the blunder that has been made. It was given to 
     <lb/>
     me this spring on absolutely high-class authority 
     <lb/>
     (I wish I could mention the name), that it would 
     <lb/>
     pay them to pay anything up to $1,000 per return 
     <lb/>
     flight rather than not have the use of Gander. 
     <lb/>
     Let's work that down. That means that control 
     <lb/>
     over Gander was the great trump someone had up 
     <lb/>
     his sleeve when dealing with the Americans... I 
     <lb/>
     say this deliberately, if Great Britain paid out $5 
     <lb/>
     million cold cash to the Government of New<lb break="no"/>foundland in return for giving Britain control 
     <lb/>
     over Gander, it would be money well spent — a 
     <lb/>
     bargain which Britain would be getting. There is 
     <lb/>
     the scandal. 1 find it not only incomprehensible, 
     <lb/>
     but beyond my power to believe. Now we find 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Neill said he had just recently, just a matter 
     <lb/>
     of days before, written a letter to the British 
     <lb/>
     government stating that, in his opinion. it was 
     <lb/>
     unthinkable that Newfoundland should be sad<lb break="no"/>dled with the operating losses of Gander. He had 
     <lb/>
     not gotten an answer. He was asked, "How long 
     <lb/>
     ago did you send it?" "Recently", he said; and he 
     <lb/>
     added, "I made it a strong letter." He still has not 
     <lb/>
     gotten an answer.... If they have saddled this 
     <lb/>
     country with a $1 million operating loss for the 
     <lb/>
     convenience of wealthy foreign airlines who 
     <lb/>
     operate up into millions a year — I find it un<lb break="no"/>believable — I do not believe it happened. If it 
     <lb/>
     did happen, instead of waiting for this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion to end sometime next year, before waiting 
     <lb/>
     for that, we ought to fire out the government who 
     <lb/>
     did it, if they did. I am remembering I have no 
     <lb/>
     privilege — remembering it vividly. I find it 
     <lb/>
     impossible to believe that we are saddled with it. 
     <lb/>
     Out in Gander they have a trade union with 900 
     <lb/>
     members; another trade union with 100 members 
     <lb/>
     — 1000 Newfoundlanders. They cannot live — 
     <lb/>
     the cost of living is prohibitive. They got 10% 
     <lb/>
     increases, and since then the cost of living has 
     <lb/>
     eaten it up. Why? What is the game? Is it they 
     <lb/>
     cannot give more wages because we are saddled 
   

            <pb n="196" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0196.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">196</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
          

     with $1 million operating loss?.... We have not 
     <lb/>
     got the whole story on Gander, it is just as well 
     <lb/>
     to face it. We have written in our report all we 
     <lb/>
     may fairly write, because there is not a fact in it 
     <lb/>
     that is not a fact, but all the facts are not there. 
     <lb/>
      </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Iwould like to ask Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>— not meaning to be personal, it strikes me it is 
     <lb/>very fortunate that he has not jet propulsion or we 
     <lb/>would have a job to hold him — I would like to 
     <lb/>ask him to explain where he gets the authority for 
     <lb/>the statement that the operating costs will be 
     <lb/>repaid and that it will be retroactive. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Neill said he had recently 
     <lb/>
     written a very strongly worded letter, "as strongly 
     <lb/>
     as any one of you would word it. I have just 
     <lb/>
     written that letter to the British government." In 
     <lb/>
     view of that, I am expecting an announcement 
     <lb/>
     before this Convention closes to the effect that 
     <lb/>
     the British government has generously agreed to 
     <lb/>
     relieve the Newfoundland people of that burden. 
     <lb/>
     And I believe it will be retroactive. From April I 
     <lb/>
     in my belief, the cost of the losses of operating 
     <lb/>
     Gander will not have cost the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     people anything and the people of Gander who 
     <lb/>
     are demanding increases in pay should not be 
     <lb/>
     blocked in getting them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> On page 4 of the report, "Mr. Neill, 
     <lb/>
     the Commissioner for Public Utilities, was asked 
     <lb/>
     why the Commission of Government had made 
     <lb/>
     this decision. His reply was that it was because 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland was a member of the Provisional 
     <lb/>
     International Civil Aviation Organization 
     <lb/>
     (PICAO) which organisation decided that 
     <lb/>
     Gander should be kept open by Newfoundland." 
     <lb/>
     Where did you get the idea that the Government 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland decided it should be kept open? 
     <lb/>
     On page 1 it says the British government paid 
     <lb/>
     five-sixths of the cost of the airport and paid 
     <lb/>
     $100,000 a year operating expenses prior to the 
     <lb/>
     war; the British government surely had some 
     <lb/>
     equity there, how has the equity been liquidated, 
     <lb/>
     or has it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> PICAO is the name of the 
     <lb/>
     group of nations interested in civil aviation — 
     <lb/>
     Canada, United States, Great Britain and New<lb break="no"/>foundland are members of PICAO. I intended to 
     <lb/>
     find out whether Newfoundland has a vote in it. 
     <lb/>
     As to the equity, it was understood and agreed 
     <lb/>
     from the beginning that the British government 
     <lb/>
     would build Gander at their expense up to five- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     sixths of the cost. One-sixth of the cost to be 
    

            <cb/>
            
     borne by Newfoundland, but the ownership of the 
     <lb/>
     airport was to be Newfoundland's. I do not think 
     <lb/>
     they had any equity, or have now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I would like to ask Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
     if he knows anything about a meeting that was 
     <lb/>
     held by this PICAO in Chicago. I think such a 
     <lb/>
     meeting was held and one of our commissioners 
     <lb/>
     was present. That may have been at the same time 
     <lb/>
     this transaction was on. There is no mention in 
     <lb/>
     the report about it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The Chicago meeting was the 
     <lb/>
     one at which the dispute occurred between 
     <lb/>
     Canada, United States and Great Britain; New<lb break="no"/>foundland had very little part in that, except to 
     <lb/>
     listen. I believe PICAO is the subsequent 
     <lb/>
     development of the Chicago conference. It was 
     <lb/>
     at that conference that the lst, 2nd, 3rd, 4th and 
     <lb/>
     5th freedoms were enunciated — the right to fly 
     <lb/>
     over territory, right to land passengers, right to 
     <lb/>
     pick up passengers. They have had conferences 
     <lb/>
     since and have sub-committees meeting from 
     <lb/>
     time to time. There was one recently in Ireland. 
     <lb/>
     Squadron Leader McGrath attended that, but he 
     <lb/>
     was merely a technical observer in the British 
     <lb/>
     delegation. No one attended as a full-fledged 
     <lb/>
     representative of Newfoundland. Very few men 
     <lb/>
     attended who had more technical knowledge than 
     <lb/>
     Squadron Leader McGrath, but he was not repre<lb break="no"/>senting Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> It was pointed out that New<lb break="no"/>foundland was a member of PICAO and PICAO 
     <lb/>
     decided Newfoundland should operate the 
     <lb/>
     Gander. We do not have sufficient information 
     <lb/>
     on it and I think the Committee should go into it. 
     <lb/>
     If we could get the information on that, we might 
     <lb/>
     be getting at the root of the trouble. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> You must remember that it was 
     <lb/>
     PICAO or the Commission of Government who 
     <lb/>
     made the deal, not the Committee. The Commit<lb break="no"/>tee has opposed it every step of the way. I would 
     <lb/>
     say that if the Committee had to make the deal 
     <lb/>
     the mark-up would be $1 million profit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> What would be the landing char<lb break="no"/>ges made by airports outside? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> it would be simple for the 
     <lb/>
     Committee to have gotten landing charges in 
     <lb/>
     various airports around the world. The Commit<lb break="no"/>tee did not do that. Landing charges in airports in 
     <lb/>
     any other part of the world are immaterial and 
     <lb/>
     have nothing whatever to do with charges in 
     <lb/>
     Gander. Gander is the only airport in the world 
     

            <pb n="197" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0197.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">197</fw>
     

     of its size, it is one which cannot be done 
     <lb/>
     without.... I say forget the landing charges and 
     <lb/>
     charge all the traffic will bear, without driving the 
     <lb/>
     traffic away. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Do you think it would have been 
     <lb/>
     feasible for the airlines to operate the airport at 
     <lb/>
     the start? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes. They wanted to do that. I 
     <lb/>
     know that in February or March some people 
     <lb/>
     were down here from the States and held a num<lb break="no"/>ber of conferences. That took place at Gander 
     <lb/>
     with the Commissioner, Mr. Neill, the Director, 
     <lb/>
     Squadron Leader Pattison, and a number of 
     <lb/>
     others. I may say, Mr. Chairman, as each session 
     <lb/>
     of that conference ended I knew within an hour 
     <lb/>
     exactly what happened at it, and I learned in that 
     <lb/>
     way a lot of information about Gander. I believe 
     <lb/>
     if the airlines were running Gander at their own 
     <lb/>
     expense today they would be paying much better 
     <lb/>
     wages than the Newfoundland government is 
     <lb/>
     paying.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Would Mr. Smallwood tell us if 
     <lb/>
     there is any possibility of making such a deal 
     <lb/>
     now? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I don't know that. I would say 
     <lb/>
     the airlines would be very silly and simple if they 
     <lb/>
     did, seeing they are now getting a good airfield 
     <lb/>
     for nothing. The chance was there in the spring, 
     <lb/>
     but I don't know now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> Those figures of wages, did you 
     <lb/>
     get these from the civil airlines in Gander? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> From Squadron Leader Pat<lb break="no"/>tison, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> Would he know these figures? 
     <lb/></p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, he is Director of Civil 
     <lb/>Aviation. The wages paid in Gander are still 
     <lb/>pretty low. All the boys working with the airlines 
     <lb/>are boys who used to be down with the RAF, and 
     <lb/>former Newfoundlanders from the RAF and 
     <lb/>RCAF. They are employing Newfoundlanders 
     <lb/>wherever they can. The Americans are paying 
     <lb/>roughly $1 million in wages, along with the oil 
     <lb/>companies and other employers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I am not quite content with that 
     <lb/>
     explanation. What I want to know is, did you get 
     <lb/>
     any actual figures from the four airlines operating 
     <lb/>
     in Gander? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, we did not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> Well then, the figures are not 
     <lb/>
     worth the paper they are written on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Chairman, can Mr. Small<lb break="no"/>
                     <cb/>
           wood tell us did the Newfoundland government 
     <lb/>
     pay any fee to join PICAO or not? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I'm afraid I don't know. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, will Mr. Small- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     wood undertake to find out the countries repre<lb break="no"/>sented on PICAO at the time the decision was 
     <lb/>
     made that Newfoundland should operate 
     <lb/>
     Gander? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I would undertake to recom<lb break="no"/>mend to the Committee on Transportation and 
     <lb/>
     Communications that they should try to find out. 
     <lb/>
     I think frankly that any further inquiries on 
     <lb/>
     Gander had better come from the Convention as 
     <lb/>
     a whole.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> As a member of this Trans<lb break="no"/>portation Committee I fully agree with all in this 
     <lb/>
     report, but with regard to Mr. Hollett's question 
     <lb/>
    as to who was on PICAO and whether 
     <lb/>PICAO did compel the Newfoundland govern<lb break="no"/>ment to purchase Gander, I would like to know 
     <lb/>where we are going to get that information. There 
     <lb/>is only one person I know of, the Commissioner 
     <lb/>of Public Utilities, and he has said that it was on 
     <lb/>the instructions of PICAO that they had bought 
     <lb/>Gander. A little later he said that he had written 
     <lb/>to the British government saying that the New<lb break="no"/>foundland government could not hear the ex<lb break="no"/>pense of Gander. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I don't think Mr. Neill said that 
     <lb/>
     PICAO had instructed Newfoundland to pur<lb break="no"/>chase and operate Gander. I don't think that was 
     <lb/>
     quite the word. The word here is "decided" — 
     <lb/>
     that "PICAO decided". Mr. Neill was asked why 
     <lb/>
     the Commission of Government had made this 
     <lb/>
     decision, and his reply was that Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     was a member of PICAO, which organisation 
     <lb/>
     decided that Gander should be kept open by 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. But Newfoundland could have 
     <lb/>
     disagreed, but rather than back out of that or<lb break="no"/>ganisation altogether — to this Mr. Neill made 
     <lb/>
     no comment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Newfoundland is not a member of 
     <lb/>
     PICAO as far as I can make out. Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     attended the PICAO meeting in Chicago as part 
     <lb/>
     of the British delegation, it was not separate.... 
     <lb/>
     </p>
            

<p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> This million dollars... Have they 
     <lb/>actually paid the million dollars over to Canada 
     <lb/>yet, and if so from what fund? Is it from the 
     <lb/>general revenue of the country this year, or from 
     <lb/>the surpluses that have accumulated? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am afraid I don't know I 


            <pb n="198" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0198.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">198</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
         

     remember reading or hearing that it was being 
     <lb/>
     paid in installments, but from what fund I don't 
     <lb/>
     know.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I think we will have to get Mr. Neill 
     <lb/>
     on the carpet again. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Smallwood, what is the mean<lb break="no"/>ing of the third paragraph on page 2? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, there was a formal taking 
     <lb/>
     over of Gander on April 1 by the Division of Civil 
     <lb/>
     Aviation. You see the Canadian government, on 
     <lb/>
     April 17, 1941, took over Gander to operate it as 
     <lb/>
     a war airport, and on April 1, 1946, the govern<lb break="no"/>ment took back formal possession of Gander, the 
     <lb/>
     operation and control of it, and housekeeping 
     <lb/>
     there was assumed by the Division of Civil Avia<lb break="no"/>tion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> They began from the first of April? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Actually the Division was 
     <lb/>operating there before that and controlling parts 
     <lb/>of Gander during the winter. They began taking 
     <lb/>men on in February or March, but it was on April 
     <lb/>1 that they formally and officially took over and 
     <lb/>began to operate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> It was merely the wording that I 
     <lb/>
     was questioning. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I still don't get you. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:STAR1">Mr. Starkes</persName> If Newfoundland was represented 
     <lb/>
     at this convention in making this deal in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with the Gander, would they not be entitled 
     <lb/>
     to have a copy of the minutes of that meeting to 
     <lb/>
     bring back to their country, and could not this 
     <lb/>
     Committee get a copy of those minutes for the 
     <lb/>
     Convention? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> They could certainly try to get 
     <lb/>
     those minutes, but guaranteeing to get them is a 
     <lb/>
     horse of another colour. I would suggest that 
     <lb/>
     anything of that nature now come from the Con<lb break="no"/>vention as a whole. Major Cashin is chairman of 
     <lb/>
     the Finance Committee and he might be able to 
     <lb/>
     dig up a lot of that stuff better than we could. 
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Mr. Chairman, I move that the 
     <lb/>committee receive this report now, and take up 
     <lb/>the other one to-morrow. I think we have gone 
     <lb/>pretty thoroughly into it, there is a lot of informa<lb break="no"/>tion that we can't get, but it may be forthcoming 
     <lb/>later when the Finance Report comes in. 
     <lb/>Mr. Neill will certainly have to come before us 
     <lb/>again. We can't let him get away with the fact 
     <lb/>that we can't get the cost of operating up to date. 
     <lb/>I move therefore that we receive this report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashboume</persName> Mr. Chairman, does that mo<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>

          tion need a seconder? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It is not essential. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> Well, I would like to make a 
     <lb/>
     few remarks. I feel, sir, that too frequently con<lb break="no"/>cessions have been made to outside companies, 
     <lb/>
     and also too sweeping concessions. I believe that 
     <lb/>
     the vast majority of the people of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     have thought that the airports on our soil would 
     <lb/>
     have been real assets to this country, and not, as 
     <lb/>
     we find out today, a liability, I rather regret that 
     <lb/>
     I see no reference in this report to Goose airport, 
     <lb/>
     because I believe that when the lease of that was 
     <lb/>
     made to Canada there was quite a spirited com<lb break="no"/>ment in the public press. The government should 
     <lb/>
     certainly have asked the people of this country 
     <lb/>
     for their views through the press before these 
     <lb/>
     terms were agreed upon. I would like to know 
     <lb/>
     whether these agreements are covered by leases, 
     <lb/>
     and how long these leases run? I would also like 
     <lb/>
     to have a copy of these leases if we could secure 
     <lb/>
     them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I also note that between the estimate of the 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Commissioner of Public Utilities and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Pattison there is half a million dollars dis<lb break="no"/>parity, and furthermore I would like to see these 
     <lb/>
     figures broken down in both cases, so that we 
     <lb/>
     may know why there should be this disparity. 
     <lb/>
     Regarding a point that has already been men<lb break="no"/>tioned I would like to see the corresponding 
     <lb/>
     scales of landing charges elsewhere I think 
     <lb/>
     that we would be wise in not railroading an 
     <lb/>
     important matterlike this through. I feel that there 
     <lb/>
     is quite a bit more information this Convention 
     <lb/>
     could demand before this report is finally ac<lb break="no"/>cepted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I don't want to 
     <lb/>
     delay the House, but I am glad Mr. Ashboume 
     <lb/>
     referred to the estimates. I remember the excite<lb break="no"/>ment in Gander the night that Mr. Wild delivered 
     <lb/>
     his last budget. It was generally believed in 
     <lb/>
     Gander that Britain was footing the bills on the 
     <lb/>
     operating losses of the airport, so on the night that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Wild delivered his budget, it was broadcast 
     <lb/>
     and everyone who could get to a radio was there, 
     <lb/>
     and I remember very vividly the sentence that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Wild used. It was this: "Newfoundland is 
     <lb/>
     primarily responsible for the operation of 
     <lb/>
     Gander". The word "primarily" struck me be« 
     <lb/>
     tween the eyes. Why did he not say "New<lb break="no"/>foundland is responsible", why "primarily 
     <lb/>
     responsible"? I knew the government did not 
  

            <pb n="199" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0199.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">199</fw>
         

     want any talk to be going on to the effect that the 
     <lb/>
     British government was footing the bills. It was 
     <lb/>
     put over in the most beautiful way. It could only 
     <lb/>
     mean that Newfoundland is, in the first instance, 
     <lb/>
     responsible, but will be recouped, and so they 
     <lb/>
     voted $750,000 in the estimate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir William Hillman was in Gander, he was 
     <lb/>
     the Director General of Civil Aviation of the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom at that time, on his way through 
     <lb/>
     to the Bermuda Conference, and he made the 
     <lb/>
     statement that "they were fed up with repeated 
     <lb/>
     requests coming to them from Newfoundland in 
     <lb/>
     connection with Gander, authorising this, that 
     <lb/>
     and the other for amounts of $50,000 here, 
     <lb/>
     $70,000 there and $100,000 somewhere else." 
     <lb/>
     His complaint was that instead of putting them to 
     <lb/>
     the necessity of running to their superiors with so 
     <lb/>
     many requests for authorisation, they should 
     <lb/>
     come in and say they wanted $1 million or $2 
     <lb/>
     million, and it would only occur once, and there 
     <lb/>
     would be a row, but they would pass it and there 
     <lb/>
     would be no more trouble for a year. There was 
     <lb/>
     another point that Mr. Ashboume raised — 
     <lb/>
     Goose Bay and Torbay. We thought that as the 
     <lb/>
     operation of Goose and Torbay do not come 
     <lb/>
     within the realm of public finance we would 
     <lb/>
     ignore them. The contracts for the lease of Goose 
     <lb/>
     and Torbay have been published in the press and 
     <lb/>
     are public property, and certainly the exchequer 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland is not involved in the expenses 
     <lb/>
     of either of those airports.... If we made a mistake 
     <lb/>
     and if the House orders us to get further informa<lb break="no"/>tion regarding Goose and Torbay, we will be 
     <lb/>
     happy to carry out their orders. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> My point about Goose was that 
     <lb/>
     on account of its proximity to Newfoundland it 
     <lb/>
     might have a prejudical effect on our bargaining 
     <lb/>
     powers about Gander airport. I believe that might 
     <lb/>
     have been recognised by the people who effected 
     <lb/>
     the lease of the Goose airport.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, Gander is the 
     <lb/>
     only airport designated by the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     government as a port of call for transatlantic 
     <lb/>
     aircraft. The Division of Civil Aviation has the 
     <lb/>
     authority to divert an aircraft from Gander either 
     <lb/>
     to Torbay or Goose or Stephenville in case 
     <lb/>
     Gander is closed in, but Gander is the airport, the 
     <lb/>
     others are only alternates in case of bad 
     <lb/>
     weather.... The CAA<ref target="#fn_10">[1]</ref> of the United States 
     <lb/>
     government had also designated Gander as the 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
           

     only airport on the North Atlantic which may be 
     <lb/>
     used by American aircraft flying the North Atlan<lb break="no"/>tic. That means an aircraft leaving the US to cross 
     <lb/>
     the Atlantic, or leaving Europe for the US, must 
     <lb/>
     clear for Gander. If, having cleared for Gander 
     <lb/>
     she learns that Gander is closed in, then that does 
     <lb/>
     not mean that she has to turn back, for Gander 
     <lb/>
     tells them, "You may land at Stephenville, or 
     <lb/>
     Torbay, or Goose", but Gander is the only desig<lb break="no"/>nated airport, and further, from the standpoint of 
     <lb/>
     the CAA it is the only designated airport for 
     <lb/>
     American aircraft. There have been rumours 
     <lb/>
     going around from time to time that the 
     <lb/>
     Americans want the right to use Stephenville, but 
     <lb/>
     I don't think there is anything to it. I don't think 
     <lb/>
     our government would be so insane as to permit 
     <lb/>
     the civilian use of any other airport except 
     <lb/>
     Gander. I think we can dismiss that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BURR2">Mr. Burry</persName> Mr. Chairman, I understand that as 
     <lb/>
     far as Goose airport is concerned it does not enter 
     <lb/>
     into the civilian aviation picture. That is because 
     <lb/>
     it is considered to be a permanent military base 
     <lb/>
     to be operated as such.... Mr. Smallwood is per<lb break="no"/>fectly right in saying that planes coming across 
     <lb/>
     the Atlantic have the right to land at Goose at the 
     <lb/>
     rate of three or four a day when Gander is closed 
     <lb/>
     in, or any other airport that they cannot reach.... 
     <lb/></p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That is the case, but I don't 
     <lb/>think Mr. Burry means to say that an airplane 
     <lb/>approaching Gander has a choice of landing 
     <lb/>where it likes, it has to do so on the instructions 
     <lb/>of the Newfoundland government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> I would like to second Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin's motion and in doing so I wish I could 
     <lb/>
     know of some correct way to limit the time of 
     <lb/>
     speakers' addresses to l5 minutes or so at a time. 
     <lb/>
     It would facilitate the work of this Convention. 
     <lb/>
     </p>


            <p><persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I would like to support Major 
     <lb/>Cashin's motion. I think we should accept the 
     <lb/>various reports coming in after reasonable 
     <lb/>debate, by sections, and when the whole report 
     <lb/>has been formally received, if there are any criti<lb break="no"/>cal points on which we need further explanations, 
     <lb/>l feel they should come from the convention of 
     <lb/>the whole. If we start throwing reports back on 
     <lb/>the hands of the committees, it is going to take a 
     <lb/>long time. We have a number of reports coming 
     <lb/>in and we have fairly well covered the ground. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It has been moved and seconded 
     <lb/>that the section of the report of Transportation 
 

        
     <note xml:id="fn_10">[1] Civil Aviation Authority. </note>
  

            <pb n="200" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-11_Page_0200.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">200</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
         

     and Communications Committee, entitled 
     <lb/>
     "Gander Airport" be received. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried. The committee of the whole<lb/>rose, and the Convention adjourned]</hi></p>

<!-- GL, 2017-06-08, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
           <!-- <p>
     December 12, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Transportation and Communications Committee:¹ 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I suggest to the House that this 
     <lb/>
     afternoon we take up the section of the report 
     <lb/>
     dealing with broadcasting. Perhaps Mr. Secretary 
     <lb/>
     would read the section on broadcasting 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>[The report was read as far as the second para<lb break="no"/>graph on page 4]<lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Mr. Cashirt I cannot let that go. That statement, 
     <lb/>
     "We are aware also of the existence, at least 
     <lb/>
     amongst some members of the public, of a belief 
     <lb/>
     that free speech is limited on the Corporation's 
     <lb/>
     stations, and that censorship is exercised over 
     <lb/>
     broadcasting by the Corporation. The point was 
     <lb/>
     put bluntly to the Chairman and General 
     <lb/>
     Manager of the Corporation, and in denying 
     <lb/>
     categorically the existence of any limitation of 
     <lb/>
     free speech or of censorship they explained the 
     <lb/>
     Corporation's policy fully and answered freely 
     <lb/>
     any questions we cared to put." That statement is 
     <lb/>
     a deliberate falsehood. In denying that there is 
     <lb/>
     censorship, the Chairman of the Corporation was 
     <lb/>
     lying and lying deliberately. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman You must not indulge in per<lb break="no"/>sonalities. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin He was making a false statement. I 
     <lb/>
     want to tell the Chairman of the Broadcasting 
     <lb/>
     Corporation that manuscripts were taken out of 
     <lb/>
     the broadcasting house to be censored. I have 
     <lb/>
     proof. I am sorry I did not bring a manuscript to 
     <lb/>
     show where certain things were cut out which 
     <lb/>
     they claimed were libelous because they 
     <lb/>
     reflected on the Commission of Government. 
     <lb/>
     The Railway would not take an action against the 
     <lb/>
     Broadcasting Corporation, which is owned and 
     <lb/>
     controlled by the government. If a statement was 
     <lb/>
     made regarding certain things that went on in the 
     <lb/>
     Railway which the Broadcasting Corporation 
     <lb/>
     said was libelous, well then, if they allowed it to 
     <lb/>
     go over the air would the Railway take an action 
     <lb/>
     against the Broadcasting Corporation? Certainly 
     <lb/>
     not. They would be going to law with themselves, 
     <lb/>
     and that is not sensible. But the Chairman of the 
     <lb/>
     Broadcasting Corporation has had a man ready to 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     go on the air and has censored his speech and cut 
     <lb/>
     out half of it and brought it back to him half an 
     <lb/>
     hour before he had to go on the air. That same 
     <lb/>
     statement that they cut out has been made over 
     <lb/>
     VOCM and there was no libel action taken 
     <lb/>
     against them. The broadcasting station is a tool 
     <lb/>
     of the Commission of Government, and they 
     <lb/>
     have been using it as such for the past 18 months. 
     <lb/>
     I know whereof I speak and I could not let this 
     <lb/>
     thing go without expressing an opinion.... 
     <lb/>
     Anyway it will have to come before the Finance 
     <lb/>
     Committee and we will have to bring Mr. Wiln 
     <lb/>
     liams² up and he can say it to my face, because 
     <lb/>
     he knows it is false. I told him so in the broad<lb break="no"/>casting house, and I had to chase him all around 
     <lb/>
     the town to do it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>[The Secretary continued reading the report]<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     
     Mr. Cashin May I be permitted to turn back to 
     <lb/>
     page 3, subsection 1, where it says: "To erect a 
     <lb/>
     suitable building etc." Where are they going to 
     <lb/>
     find that building, and how much will it cost? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood A little further up on the same 
     <lb/>page you will see that at the end of 1945 the 
     <lb/>Corporation's current assets amounted to 
     <lb/>$75,000, consisting of $68,000 cash, which 
     <lb/>amount included $9,800 accounts receivable, 
     <lb/>which have since been collected. In other words, 
     <lb/>at the end of 1945 they had cash on hand of 
     <lb/>roughly $68,000. You will notice a little further 
     <lb/>on in this report, they have been making $10,000 
     <lb/>to $20,000 a year, in fact it was up around 
     <lb/>$26,000 last year. I suppose what they intended 
     <lb/>to build the broadcasting house out of is their 
     <lb/>current assets, perhaps even getting a loan for the 
     <lb/>balance from the government. We did not ask 
     <lb/>what it was going to cost or exactly where it was 
     <lb/>to come from. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin They also say they are going to 
     <lb/>
     build a broadcasting station at Grand Falls, and 
     <lb/>
     take over the RCAF station at Gander, In my 
     <lb/>
     opinion they won't get far unless they go to the 
     <lb/>
     government for the balance of the money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     ¹Volume II:119. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>² George Williams, Chairman of Board of Governors of the Broadcasting Corporation of Newfoundland.<lb/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>