<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-12-12" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-12-12">12 December 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          
         
          <biblScope unit="page" from="200" to="208"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0200.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0201.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0202.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0203.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0204.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0205.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0206.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0207.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0208.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-03">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-03">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0200">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0200.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0201">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0201.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0202">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0202.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0203">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0203.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0204">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0204.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0205">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0205.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0206">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0206.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0207">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0207.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0208">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0208.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="200" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0200.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">200</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-03-03, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 


<!--<p>
     and Communications Committee, entitled 
     <lb/>
     "Gander Airport" be received. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>[The motion carried. The committee of the whole<lb/>rose, and the Convention adjourned]<lb/>
            </p>-->

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     December 12, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">Report of the Transportation and Communications Committee:<ref target="#fn_x1">[1]</ref>

     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole</head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I suggest to the House that this <lb/>
                  afternoon we take up the section of the report <lb/> dealing with broadcasting.
                  Perhaps Mr. Secretary <lb/> would read the section on broadcasting <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The report was read as far as the second para<lb break="no"/>graph on page 4]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I cannot let that go. That statement, <lb/> "We
                  are aware also of the existence, at least <lb/> amongst some members of the
                  public, of a belief <lb/> that free speech is limited on the Corporation's <lb/>
                  stations, and that censorship is exercised over <lb/> broadcasting by the
                  Corporation. The point was <lb/> put bluntly to the Chairman and General <lb/>
                  Manager of the Corporation, and in denying <lb/> categorically the existence of
                  any limitation of <lb/> free speech or of censorship they explained the <lb/>
                  Corporation's policy fully and answered freely <lb/> any questions we cared to
                  put." That statement is <lb/> a deliberate falsehood. In denying that there is
                  <lb/> censorship, the Chairman of the Corporation was <lb/> lying and lying
                  deliberately. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You must not indulge in per<lb break="no"/>sonalities. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> He was making a false statement. I <lb/> want to
                  tell the Chairman of the Broadcasting <lb/> Corporation that manuscripts were
                  taken out of <lb/> the broadcasting house to be censored. I have <lb/> proof. I am
                  sorry I did not bring a manuscript to <lb/> show where certain things were cut out
                  which <lb/> they claimed were libelous because they <lb/> reflected on the
                  Commission of Government. <lb/> The Railway would not take an action against the
                  <lb/> Broadcasting Corporation, which is owned and <lb/> controlled by the
                  government. If a statement was <lb/> made regarding certain things that went on in
                  the <lb/> Railway which the Broadcasting Corporation <lb/> said was libelous, well
                  then, if they allowed it to <lb/> go over the air would the Railway take an action
                  <lb/> against the Broadcasting Corporation? Certainly <lb/> not. They would be
                  going to law with themselves, <lb/> and that is not sensible. But the Chairman of
                  the <lb/> Broadcasting Corporation has had a man ready to <lb/>
                  <cb/> go on the air and has censored his speech and cut <lb/> out half of it and
                  brought it back to him half an <lb/> hour before he had to go on the air. That
                  same <lb/> statement that they cut out has been made over <lb/> VOCM and there was
                  no libel action taken <lb/> against them. The broadcasting station is a tool <lb/>
                  of the Commission of Government, and they <lb/> have been using it as such for the
                  past 18 months. <lb/> I know whereof I speak and I could not let this <lb/> thing
                  go without expressing an opinion.... <lb/> Anyway it will have to come before the
                  Finance <lb/> Committee and we will have to bring Mr. Wil<lb break="no"/>liams<ref target="#fn_01">[2]</ref> up and he can say it to my face, because <lb/> he
                  knows it is false. I told him so in the broad<lb break="no"/>casting house, and I
                  had to chase him all around <lb/> the town to do it. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary continued reading the report]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> May I be permitted to turn back to <lb/> page 3,
                  subsection 1, where it says: "To erect a <lb/> suitable building etc." Where are
                  they going to <lb/> find that building, and how much will it cost? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> A little further up on the same <lb/>page you will
                  see that at the end of 1945 the <lb/>Corporation's current assets amounted to
                  <lb/>$75,000, consisting of $68,000 cash, which <lb/>amount included $9,800
                  accounts receivable, <lb/>which have since been collected. In other words, <lb/>at
                  the end of 1945 they had cash on hand of <lb/>roughly $68,000. You will notice a
                  little further <lb/>on in this report, they have been making $10,000 <lb/>to
                  $20,000 a year, in fact it was up around <lb/>$26,000 last year. I suppose what
                  they intended <lb/>to build the broadcasting house out of is their <lb/>current
                  assets, perhaps even getting a loan for the <lb/>balance from the government. We
                  did not ask <lb/>what it was going to cost or exactly where it was <lb/>to come
                  from. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> They also say they are going to <lb/> build a
                  broadcasting station at Grand Falls, and <lb/> take over the RCAF station at
                  Gander, In my <lb/> opinion they won't get far unless they go to the <lb/>
                  government for the balance of the money. <lb/>
               </p>
            
<note xml:id="fn_x1">[1] Volume II:119. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

            <note xml:id="fn_01">[2] George Williams, Chairman of Board of Governors of the Broadcasting Corporation of Newfoundland.</note>

            <pb n="201" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0201.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">201</fw>
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am sure Major Cashin will <lb/> admit that
                  apart from any quarrelling on the mat<lb break="no"/>ter of censorship they do
                  seem to be flourishing, <lb/> and they should not have any trouble in borrow<lb break="no"/>ing from the government or anyone. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I don't suppose they will have any <lb/> trouble
                  as long as the surplus lasts! <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> That's absolutely apart from the <lb/> government, it
                  is a public corporation? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> The people of Newfoundland have a <lb/> share of it,
                  I suppose? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> What happens at the end of 25 <lb/> years. When
                  the capital is paid off, where does <lb/> the ownership lie then? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The unpaid balance of that <lb/> original
                  advance of $84,000? They are paying <lb/> that off regularly and at the end of 25
                  years it will <lb/> be all paid off and they will still own it. It may <lb/> not
                  be the same Board of Governors, but they will <lb/> own it as they own it now, as
                  the trustees of the <lb/> Newfoundland people. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary continued reading the report]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, the only appen<lb break="no"/>dix
                  to this report gives the number of radio receiv<lb break="no"/>ing sets in the
                  country, reasonably supposed to be <lb/> in operation in Newfoundland and Labrador
                  from <lb/> January 1, 1937 to December 31, 1945. And then <lb/> secondly a table
                  showing the number of sets upon <lb/> which the licence fees were paid from
                  January 1, <lb/> 1937 to December 31, 1945. There is quite a <lb/> difference in
                  the figures, showing that there have <lb/> been quite a number of owners of radio
                  sets not <lb/> paying their licenses.... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I would like to underline the paragraph on 
     <lb/>
     page 5, which reads as follows: "There is one 
     <lb/>
     matter upon which the committee feels that it 
     <lb/>
     must express its disappointment etc." You 
     <lb/>
     have in St. John's and in Corner Brook and Grand 
     <lb/>
     Falls (where there are to be stations) and also 
     <lb/>
     Gander, various organizations, not government 
     <lb/>
     departments, but the MCLI,<ref target="#fn_02">[1]</ref> the Patricians and 
     <lb/>
     Holy Cross, the Llewellyn Club,<ref target="#fn_03">[2]</ref> trade unions 
     <lb/>
     and the co-operative movement (that movement 
     <lb/>
     is making good use of the Corporation), but there 
     <lb/>
     are a lot of other corporations, and they are open 
     <lb/>
     to give free the use of their facilities for forums 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
          
     and round table conferences for formulating 
     <lb/>
     public opinion. I think that too much publicity 
     <lb/>
     cannot be given to that fact. We were informed 
     <lb/>
     that their rules down there (in the paragraph on 
     <lb/>
     page 4) are as follows, it says: "However the 
     <lb/>
     Corporation is prepared to give free time, on the 
     <lb/>
     basis of equality, to reputable persons who wish 
     <lb/>
     to discuss etc." I think that refers to individuals, 
     <lb/>
     not organisations, and I believe the rule is this: 
     <lb/>
     former cabinet ministers, and, I believe, former 
     <lb/>
     members of the Legislative Council, are, accord<lb break="no"/>ing to the rule laid down by the Corporation, 
     <lb/>
     permitted to have one and a half hours, or three 
     <lb/>
     half-hour broadcasts, no charge made, subject to 
     <lb/>
     the right of the Corporation to edit the contents 
     <lb/>
     of the broadcast. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> The censorship by Mr. Williams! <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am speaking strictly to the <lb/>report. Their
                  right is to edit the script, also to <lb/>submit it to their solicitor for his
                  opinion on any <lb/>statement which may appear to be libelous or <lb/>defamatory.
                  Former cabinet ministers and mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the House of Assembly can
                  have ap<lb break="no"/>parently equal time. And the same with members <lb/>of the
                  upper house. I want to emphasise for the <lb/>benefit of people who may be
                  listening in to-night <lb/>(if anyone does listen to these broadcasts) that the
                  <lb/>Corporation is there to give the use of their station <lb/>free for the
                  discussion of public affairs. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Is that true of VOCM? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It is general knowledge that <lb/> VOCM has
                  been very generous also in the use of <lb/> its time and in the latitude it allows
                  speakers on <lb/> public affairs. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Are they prepared to give <lb/> VOCM the same
                  facilities as VONF, on educa<lb break="no"/>tional matters? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am sure that Mr. Jackman <lb/> does not
                  suppose that the Broadcasting Corpora<lb break="no"/>tion has anything to do with
                  broadcasts on <lb/> VOCM, or with the personnel of that station. I <lb/> don't
                  think they interfere at all. The dispute with <lb/> VOCM and the Broadcasting
                  Corporation has to <lb/> do only with VOCM's request to increase their <lb/> power
                  and stations, it is not with regard to what <lb/> they shall or shall not
                  broadcast. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> I cannot agree with the excuse <lb/> given by the
                  government for turning down the 
         
     <note xml:id="fn_02">[1] Methodist College Literary Institute.</note>
          
            <note xml:id="fn_03">[2] MCLI, Patricians, Holy Cross Literary Association and the Llewellyn Club were St. John's societies that 
     <lb/>
           
            sponsored debates, lectures and discussions. </note>
     
            <pb n="202" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0202.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">202</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
          
     request for VOCM to enlarge its
                  broadcasting <lb/> facilities. It is an excuse for dictatorship. VOCM <lb/> today
                  is the most popular radio station in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. If we could
                  take a poll we would find <lb/> 90% of our people listen in to VOCM more so <lb/>
                  than VONF, and in the report it says the govern<lb break="no"/>ment is not going
                  to give VOCM a chance to <lb/> expand. I do not think it is right. It is about all
                  we <lb/> have left in our country —- the air. Now they are <lb/> trying to take
                  that away. They are going to set up <lb/> a station in Grand Falls, and possibly
                  one in Bell <lb/> Island. What sort of propaganda are they going <lb/> to give us?
                  This country owes a tribute to VOCM; <lb/> if we did not have VOCM, we would not
                  have <lb/> this National Convention today. I think this Con<lb break="no"/>vention
                  should protest against the dictatorial at<lb break="no"/>titude of the government
                  in trying to take all we <lb/> have left. There should be some public policy to
                  <lb/> make the government give VOCM a chance to <lb/> expand; it is what the
                  people want — the facts <lb/> and truth. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I come from a part of this country <lb/> where we
                  rarely hear VOCM and it is only since <lb/> I have been in St. John's I have been
                  privileged <lb/> to listen in to it, and I am thoroughly in accord <lb/> with Mr.
                  Jackrnan. I cannot swallow the excuse <lb/> given by the Broadcasting Corporation
                  for not <lb/> allowing VOCM to increase power from 250 to <lb/> 1000 watts in view
                  of the fact that the Broadcast<lb break="no"/>ing Corporation are planning to
                  increase the <lb/> power of their station here in St. John's and erect <lb/>
                  another station in Grand Falls (1000 watts) and <lb/> another in Corner Brook
                  (1000 watts). I believe <lb/> there is something more in this refusal than first
                  <lb/> strikes the eye. I would ask Mr. Smallwood if the <lb/> Committee enquired
                  as to what manner this in<lb break="no"/>creasing of VOCM from 250 to 1000 watts
                  would <lb/> contaminate or obliterate the air waves over this <lb/> country? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The report says the Committee <lb/> felt
                  considerable sympathy for VOCM and for <lb/> Mr. Butler. Whether strict observance
                  of that <lb/> ruling has the effect of making it impossible for <lb/> VOCM power
                  to be increased is a matter upon <lb/> which I am not competent to pass judgement. <lb/>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Did you enquire? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> We did, as far as our own com<lb break="no"/>petence allowed us. When you get into a techni<lb break="no"/>cal matter, you
                  have to know what kind of <lb/>
                  <cb/> questions to ask, to have the knowledge to tell <lb/> you whether the answer
                  is scientifically correct. <lb/> If the Convention will retain the services of a
                  <lb/> high—class radio technician, he could give you the <lb/> answer. We cannot.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I whole-heartedly agree with the <lb/>
                  Broadcasting Corporation and I think the time <lb/> has come to get the
                  broadcasting station back <lb/> under the people. I was in hospital for a month
                  <lb/> and in the next bed to me was one of the leading <lb/> radio technicians in
                  the world — Mr. Galgay — <lb/> he explained the whole thing to me and I followed
                  <lb/> closely. The Broadcasting Corporation is all <lb/> right.... The only thing
                  we have to do is get <lb/> control of the country, and of the broadcasting <lb/>
                  and own one valuable thing. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I would like to pay tribute to <lb/> those who
                  compile, at no doubt considerable <lb/> expense, and furnish to the broadcasting
                     com<lb break="no"/>panies the various news bulletins given to the <lb/> public
                  free of charge. These bulletins are ap<lb break="no"/>preciated in the city of St.
                  John's and especially <lb/> in those outports where no daily newspapers are <lb/>
                  immediately available. I mention the Gerald <lb/> S. Doyle news bulletin<ref target="#fn_04">[1]</ref> and the bulletin supplied <lb/> by Messrs Harvey and
                     Co.<ref target="#fn_05">[2]</ref> VOCM is not very <lb/> much heard in
                  Twillingate, probably on account <lb/> of lower power. I see no reason why they
                  should <lb/> not receive permission to increase their power. <lb/> The weather
                  forecasts, news regarding steamer <lb/> movements, railway freights, are of great
                     mo<lb break="no"/>ment to the people who live in the outports. In <lb/> St.
                  John's we can buy a newspaper twice a day <lb/> and see when various steamers are
                  accepting <lb/> freight; when trains are leaving; get weather <lb/> forecasts; but
                  to the fisherman who has to get up <lb/> early in the morning and go out it is a
                  great <lb/> satisfaction to have some idea as to what the <lb/> weather is likely
                  to be on the following day. I <lb/> would like to bring to the attention of the
                     govern<lb break="no"/>ment, the matter of considering that radio bat<lb break="no"/>teries be admitted into Newfoundland duty free. <lb/> All you have
                  to do in St. John's is plug in the <lb/> socket by which the electric light is
                  given. Very <lb/> few people in the outports enjoy that privilege. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> When this report was being read I <lb/>was like Major
                  Cashin, but I decided to hold on <lb/>until it was fully read. In 1937 I prepared
                  a <lb/>half-hour talk to deliver, and went to the best
           
     <note xml:id="fn_04">[1] This radio programme, consisting of news and public service announcements, commenced in 1932.</note>

<note xml:id="fn_05">[2] Harvey and Co., one of Newfoundland's oldest merchant houses.</note>
             
            <pb n="203" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0203.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">203</fw>
          
    legal talent and submitted my manuscript to be <lb/>
                  scrutinised. I contacted the manager of VONF <lb/> and told him I wanted to
                  deliver a talk. He told <lb/> me it depended on the topic and nature of the talk,
                  <lb/> whether or not I would be allowed to speak. I was <lb/> advised four or five
                  days afterwards that he <lb/> regretted that after consulting the Board he could
                  <lb/> not allow me to deliver the address. He said I was <lb/> far too critical of
                  Commission of Government. In <lb/> view of that, I cannot accept the second
                  paragraph <lb/> on page 4 as a statement of fact. I congratulate <lb/> those
                  responsible for this report. I move that the <lb/> report be received. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> Before the report is received, I <lb/> would
                  like to make a few comments. I have been <lb/> broadcasting quite a while and I
                  feel I would be <lb/> remiss if I had not something to say. I have no <lb/>
                  quarrel with the Broadcasting Corporation. 1 <lb/> have said a few hard things
                  about Commission of <lb/> Government and I have not been rapped over the <lb/>
                  knuckles The comments I would like to make are <lb/> in connection with the staff.
                  On page 1 — 1 chief <lb/> operator; 1 operator. These are employed at the <lb/>
                  studio, and as far as I know they are at Mount <lb/> Pearl. It had struck me for
                  quite a while that the <lb/> Corporation is understaffed. A broadcasting sta<lb break="no"/>tion is not like a government department where <lb/> you go in and
                  see a lot of staff. Some people get <lb/> the idea there is not much work to be
                  done. Take, <lb/> for instance, Mr. House, he is chief operator and <lb/> is at
                  this moment recording this broadcast. When <lb/> it is all worked out on the basis
                  of time, they really <lb/> have a lot of work to do. We should particularly <lb/>
                  pay tribute for the way in which it is covering the <lb/> Convention and it takes
                  a lot of their time, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly the operators. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I would like to say, as Mr. Har<lb break="no"/>rington has done, that we should at this time pay <lb/> a little tribute to the
                  Broadcasting Corporation. I <lb/> agree with Mr. Jackman, if it could be done, we
                  <lb/> on the west coast would like to see VOCM's <lb/> output increased. We do not
                  get them and very <lb/> seldom VONF. We are fortunate in having <lb/> VOWN; the
                  service they are giving is good. I <lb/> understand from the report that they are
                     increas<lb break="no"/>ing the wattage in Corner Brook, and you people <lb/> in
                  here might have the opportunity of listening to <lb/> us. I agree we should offer
                  a vote of thanks to the <lb/> broadcasting station. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> My main reason for rising was to <lb/> refer to
                  the paragraph under discussion. It is <lb/>
                  <cb/> refreshing that for the first time since the House <lb/> opened, Mr.
                  Smallwood admitted there is some<lb break="no"/>thing he is not fully competent to
                  discuss. I do not <lb/> intend to give an opinion, because it might be <lb/>
                  suggested that it might be biased due to my <lb/> association with one of the
                  Board of Governors. <lb/> As the opinion is held by some members that <lb/> VOCM
                  is entitled to more power for their station, <lb/> why not have the Committee make
                  enquiries <lb/> outside as to the rightness or wrongness of the <lb/> explanation
                  given by the Broadcasting Corpora<lb break="no"/>tion? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The first thing we did was to <lb/> ask Mr.
                  Butler to appear. He stated his case <lb/> before the Broadcasting Corporation
                  stated <lb/> theirs. We knew nowhere else to go. We would <lb/> need technical
                  information in order to be able to <lb/> assess the technical explanation that the
                     Broad<lb break="no"/>casting Corporation gave us. I would like to join <lb/>
                  with Mr. Harrington and Mr. Ballam in the words <lb/> they have uttered about the
                  gratitude of this Con<lb break="no"/>vention to the Corporation, for broadcasting
                  the <lb/> debates; not only to going to considerable ex<lb break="no"/>pense,
                  because it does cost money, but re-arrang<lb break="no"/>ing their whole time from
                  9.15 each night until <lb/> around midnight. I know the whole country is <lb/>
                  listening and that is giving value to the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion deliberations
                  and debates, a value it could not <lb/> possibly have otherwise. Tens of thousands
                  who <lb/> have to vote on the kind of government they want, <lb/> would have no
                  way of knowing the facts upon <lb/> which we are basing our recommendations, and
                  <lb/> upon which they perhaps will base their voting <lb/> for the referendum. The
                  Corporation should <lb/> know how grateful we feel to them and I am <lb/>
                  disappointed we have not been hearing it from all <lb/> sides of the house.... A
                  feeling has grown up that <lb/> the Convention is lying on its oars and loafing.
                  <lb/> There are nine committees; three of them have so <lb/> far reported; six
                  others have yet to report. Here is <lb/> one of 143 pages foolscap and I am sure
                  the <lb/> Finance Committee will bring in 200 to 300 <lb/> pages. That is not done
                  without hard work.... <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I wonder if the Committee asked the <lb/>Broadcasting
                  Corporation how far they were <lb/>prepared to go in cutting commercial
                  advertising <lb/>in order to arrange their time to give individuals <lb/>or other
                  bodies the opportunity to broadcast. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The answer is simple. A broad<lb break="no"/>casting station arranges some of its programmes <lb/>as much as a year in
                  advance... In connection
          
            <pb n="204" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0204.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">204</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
           
    with this broadcasting of these
                  proceedings, they <lb/> have cancelled everything after 9.15 at night. Not <lb/>
                  only are we grateful to the Corporation but also <lb/> to the commercial firms
                  whose programmes have <lb/> got to be cancelled in order to make way for what
                  <lb/> we think is more important — the discussion of <lb/> public affairs. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> If you have commercial advertising <lb/> there is a
                  certain rigidity about those programmes <lb/> which cannot be offset, unless you
                  ask the people <lb/> who control them and they are pleased to do it <lb/> (and I
                  am not doubting that they are). I want to <lb/> know how far the Broadcasting
                  Corporation are <lb/> prepared to go in lessening revenue from com<lb break="no"/>mercial purposes so that they can facilitate the <lb/> broadcasting of other
                  affairs... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It seems strange for Mr. Butt to <lb/> be
                  directing that question at me, because he is as <lb/> well able to answer that
                  question as I am.... In <lb/> connection with the large number of radio sets on
                  <lb/> which no payment was made in 1944, the answer <lb/> is that during the war
                  it became just about impos<lb break="no"/>sible to get radio sets, and in many
                  cases radio <lb/> tubes and other spare parts, the result was that <lb/>
                  throughout the country there came, by the end of <lb/> the war, to be a very large
                  number of radio sets <lb/> which actually were not in use and so I suppose, <lb/>
                  with some degree of humanity, postmasters <lb/> throughout the island did not
                  collect the fees on <lb/> unused radio sets. I think that's the explanation. <lb/>
                  Mr. Miller I am somewhat disappointed about <lb/> the manner in which this report
                  is being covered <lb/> by the House. Very good points have been over<lb break="no"/>looked, and we are making useless remarks. Our <lb/> business today is as
                  serious as it will be later on. <lb/> There was a good point made by Major Cashin,
                  <lb/> concerning the erection of broadcasting stations <lb/> at St. John's, Corner
                  Brook, Gander, and Grand <lb/> Falls. I can't guess the amount these outlays <lb/>
                  might total. I might say a quarter of a million <lb/> dollars. Not worth our
                  consideration this after<lb break="no"/>noon? We may be asked to spend that in
                  three or <lb/> four years time. It is well worth our considera<lb break="no"/>tion, and further this report should deal with the <lb/> business basis of the
                  Broadcasting Corporation. <lb/> I think it is incomplete because it has not got it
                  <lb/> here. I cannot form an opinion whether the <lb/> Broadcasting Corporation
                  will be an asset or a <lb/> liability to the future of Newfoundland. I want to
                  <lb/> know. That's what I am here for — more about <lb/> the assets and
                  liabilities of the future. This report <lb/>
                  <cb/> has not got it and I am disappointed. The Com<lb break="no"/>mittee ought to
                  have investigated the rates we <lb/> charge compared with the rates they charge in
                  <lb/> Canada, find out if there are any privileges given <lb/> on this
                  broadcasting station, whether some <lb/> people are getting special rates, etc.
                  General <lb/> routine work, but it is not in the report. I do agree <lb/> with Mr.
                  Hollett and others who made mention <lb/> of VOCM. That station is not heard in my
                  district, <lb/> or very rarely, and that is only 84 miles away. I <lb/> cannot
                  take Mr. Smallwood's explanation when <lb/> he says that VOCM could find no place
                  on the <lb/> air. Has the air, that is the channels of broad, <lb/> casting,
                  reached a saturation point? Must we <lb/> think that the United States and Canada
                  will have <lb/> to go down to these lower frequencies and less <lb/> power? We are
                  not driving a hard enough bar<lb break="no"/>gain, and VOCM is getting a raw deal.
                  At the <lb/> same time I am not so greatly concerned over <lb/> that, but I am
                  that we have not got the facts in <lb/> dollars and cents. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> As the report states, the <lb/> balance sheet
                  of the Broadcasting Corporation is <lb/> published annually in the public
                  accounts, the <lb/> report of the Auditor General, and in consider<lb break="no"/>able detail. I brought along the balance sheet for <lb/> each of the last three
                  years, but we have them <lb/> running back 14 or 15 years. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr Cashin</persName> 16 years. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> For each of these 16 years the <lb/> annual
                  balance sheet was published in considerv <lb/> able detail. It is fairly simple,
                  and it seems they <lb/> have been making from $12,000 to $25,000 a <lb/> year
                  profit. It does not look like they would ever <lb/> be a liability. If the number
                  of people with radio <lb/> sets and licence fees and the sale of time on the <lb/>
                  air should fall off, then their income will fall, and <lb/> they might have a
                  deficit. I don't think we need <lb/> to look upon them as a liability in the
                  future. The <lb/> other point is one that I have so much sympathy <lb/> for myself
                  that I don't want to be jockeyed into <lb/> the position of standing here
                  defending the <lb/> Broadcasting Corporation. I am not responsible <lb/> for the
                  explanation of this, we are only repeating <lb/> honestly the explanation given to
                  us by the <lb/> Broadcasting Corporation, admitting our in<lb break="no"/>ability
                  to assess its validity. It sounds genuine and <lb/> we are not competent to
                  question it. Mr, Miller, <lb/> please don't blame us for that explanation. <lb/>
                  Mr. Chairman if all the gentlemen are through <lb/> and there is no further
                  comment I move that the 
           
            <pb n="205" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0205.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">205</fw>
            
    Committee rise, report progress, and beg leave to <lb/>
                  sit again tomorrow. <lb/>
               </p>

<cb/>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee of the whole rose and reported 
     <lb/>
    progress]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Motion to Prevent Disposal of Assets by the Government 
     <lb/>
     until a Decision has been made on a Future Form of Government. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
</div>
<div type="section">

             <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Mr. Crosbie to move that this <lb/> Convention
                  is of the opinion that until the people <lb/> of Newfoundland have decided what
                  form of <lb/> government they wish to have in the future, there <lb/> should be no
                  further negotiations in connection <lb/> with any disposal of any assets of
                  Newfoundland, <lb/> either in Newfoundland or Labrador. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> ....Some five or six weeks ago we <lb/> had the
                  Forestry Report submitted and there was <lb/> considerable debate regarding the
                  value of timber <lb/> on Labrador. I am afraid many people here spoke <lb/> of
                  Labrador not knowing of what they spoke. I <lb/> felt it was rather a pity for us
                  to discuss in public <lb/> something we did not know about. That report <lb/> was
                  passed and sent back to the committee for <lb/> consideration. I have taken some
                  trouble to ascer<lb break="no"/>tain what was the position of timber on Labrador.
                  <lb/> I had an idea that Bowaters, one of the large paper <lb/> companies, had
                  made surveys there in 1937 and <lb/> 1938, both ground and aerial. I have been in
                  <lb/> Comer Brook and asked Mr. Lewin, and he told <lb/> me that he had no
                  objection to getting the surveys <lb/> and giving them to the Committee. To his
                  <lb/> knowledge, where we said 2 million cords of <lb/> wood, there are 20 million
                  cords of wood easily <lb/> accessible. At that time the cost would have been <lb/>
                  extremely heavy and they had the opportunity of <lb/> making this other deal at
                  Gander, which they <lb/> took. He said it was good timber and there is no <lb/>
                  reason why it should not be made into pulpwood <lb/> or paper. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Bearing that in mind I was somewhat worried 
     <lb/>
     about a letter I received from Saint John, N,B., 
     <lb/>
     Canada. We did hear rumours on the street about 
     <lb/>
     certain parties negotiating with the Department 
     <lb/>
     of Natural Resources for timber rights. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood may have had the idea that some 
     <lb/>
     delegates in the Convention were mixed up in the 
     <lb/>
     movement. I am sorry I forgot to bring that letter 
     <lb/>
     here, but that party went on to say that "myself 
     <lb/>
     and my association can procure ten or eleven 
     <lb/>
     thousand miles of timber on Labrador and can get 
     <lb/>
     them for you on favourable terms." It is getting 
     <lb/>
     pretty rough when a Newfoundlander has to be 
     <lb/>
     offered part of his own country from an outsider. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Flinn told us that negotiations had been com<lb break="no"/><cb/>menced, and since that nothing had been done. I 
     <lb/>
     am prepared to believe that, but I believe this 
     <lb/>
     resolution should go through this Convention. I 
     <lb/>
     also feel, since yesterday, that it is more neces<lb break="no"/>sary. We heard of the Gander agreement, and I 
     <lb/>
     don't think any man who had the interest of the 
     <lb/>
     country at heart would make such an agreement. 
     <lb/>
     The British government are only trustees of this 
     <lb/>
     country, and that's all. They have been the last 12 
     <lb/>
     years, and they feel by setting up this National 
     <lb/>
     Convention they would like to pass back their 
     <lb/>
     trust to us. That being so I don't think Commis<lb break="no"/>sion of Government has any right to bargain away 
     <lb/>
     any more assets of this country in Labrador. We 
     <lb/>
     don't know the value of Labrador. I mentioned 
     <lb/>
     timber, but in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Magazine Digest</hi> of last month 
     <lb/>
     there is an article that interested me. It said 
     <lb/>
     "Labrador Iron Ore Saves United States Steel 
     <lb/>
     Mills". That staggered me and I read the article. 
     <lb/>
     It finished up by saying that in the not far distant 
     <lb/>
     future the United States will be taking from 
     <lb/>
     Labrador $350 million worth of iron ore a year, 
     <lb/>
     and that's not chicken feed. I understand that one 
     <lb/>
     of the companies is negotiating a power agree<lb break="no"/>ment on Labrador. The British government 
     <lb/>
     should be very cautious about any further agree<lb break="no"/>ments they make until the people have an oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity to say something about the future of this 
     <lb/>
     country. With that in mind I beg to move this 
     <lb/>
     resolution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> I second the motion proposed by <lb/>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName>, and may I say that it looks like we <lb/> have
                  uncovered things during our fact-finding <lb/> investigations that many of us
                  thought unbeliev<lb break="no"/>able. It is time to cry halt to further dickering
                  with <lb/> the assets of Newfoundland and Labrador by a <lb/> caretaker government
                  — yesterday's revelations <lb/> on the Gander airport deal for example — and <lb/>
                  there are others to come — so that in this motion, <lb/> even though it may not be
                  heeded, we do never<lb break="no"/>theless consider it our duty to try and save
                  the <lb/> remnants of our heritage for the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland,
                  as well as let them know what is <lb/> happening. I strongly support Mr. Crosbie's
                     mo<lb break="no"/>tion.... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The motion has been moved by
           
            <pb n="206" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0206.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">206</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
     


     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> and seconded by <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName>.
                  The <lb/> matter is open for discussion. Each member has <lb/> the right to speak
                  once, Mr. Crosbie having the <lb/> right to reply. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I support Mr. Crosbie's motion. I <lb/> feel from
                  what ground we have covered we <lb/> realise with deep concern the serious inroads
                  <lb/> which have been made on our national wealth <lb/> during the term of
                  Commission of Government. <lb/> Many of their unscrupulous acts are beyond <lb/>
                  repair, more will be headaches for some future <lb/> government; but at least and
                  during the remainder <lb/> of their tenure of office I would suggest that <lb/>
                  "what we have we hold." This is not the time to <lb/> encourage any lengthy debate
                  on the matter; but <lb/> we will all agree, in view of the startling facts <lb/>
                  already before us, this urgent matter demands our <lb/> immediate consideration.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     If they as the trustees and guardians of our 
     <lb/>
     country's resources refuse our request, an appeal 
     <lb/>
     should be addressed from this Convention, 
     <lb/>
     through His Excellency the Governor, to the ap<lb break="no"/>propriate authorities in London. Some may inter<lb break="no"/>pret this as being beyond our terms of reference. 
     <lb/>
     If so, it is certainly not beyond our rights as 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlanders, who are at this time more than 
     <lb/>
     ever concerned over the fate of what little is left 
     <lb/>
     of our natural resources. If nothing more is done, 
     <lb/>
     a unanimous petition from the individual mem<lb break="no"/>bers outside the official scope of the Convention 
     <lb/>
     should be addressed to the government on this 
     <lb/>
     important matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MILL1">Mr. Miller</persName> Take the second last line — "nor any <lb/>
                  disposal of any assets of Newfoundland or <lb/> Labrador." Does "assets" cover the
                  whole thing? <lb/> I feel it should be all-embracing. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It would be scandalous if the <lb/> motion were
                  to pass with practically no discus<lb break="no"/>sion. I do not think the
                  government or the country <lb/> would consider that this Convention was taking
                  <lb/> it seriously if it went through in a perfunctory <lb/> manner. It is one of
                  the most vital things to come <lb/> before the Convention. The point made by <lb/>
                  Mr. Miller is that it does not go far enough; it <lb/> seems to me, technically,
                  that it goes a little too <lb/> far. I think I know what is in the mind of the
                  <lb/> mover and those who seconded it; they have in <lb/> mind the public domain,
                  the natural resources, <lb/> waterpowers, timber and territorial areas; but <lb/>
                  what is mentioned there is the word "assets" <lb/> which goes way beyond physical
                  assets. As <lb/>
                  <cb/> worded, if that were adopted by us and accepted <lb/> it would preclude the
                  government from adding to <lb/> the national assets. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> You are wrong. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> According to the motion there <lb/> should be
                  no further negotiations in connection <lb/> with any assets of Newfoundland, even
                  to in<lb break="no"/>crease those assets. I know Mr. Crosbie means <lb/> the
                  natural resources of this country that might <lb/> still be bartered away, and
                  that is what we all have <lb/> in mind. If some of the rumours are true — what
                  <lb/> about this business of further bases? Mr. Job has <lb/> been concerned that
                  we have leased those bases <lb/> for 99 years in return for nothing. Even the land
                  <lb/> they built on, the Americans did not pay for — <lb/> not a single cent. It
                  was paid for by the British <lb/> government. First the Newfoundland govern<lb break="no"/>ment paid for it and the British government paid <lb/> them back.
                  One thing I will say for Mr. Crosbie, <lb/> if anything is to happen, he is the
                  first to hear of <lb/> it. If our territory is to be further bartered away, <lb/>
                  if we do get our own government back again in <lb/> the future we will not be able
                  to do much with it. <lb/> Maybe Mr. Crosbie would tell us about the 20 <lb/>
                  million cords of good merchantable timber dis<lb break="no"/>covered by Bowaters.
                  ls that on Crown land or is <lb/> it among the grants? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> As far as I know it still belongs to <lb/>
                  Newfoundland. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That makes it more important. <lb/> If we have
                  20 million cords in Labrador and if <lb/> people are here from Canada and the
                  United <lb/> States trying to get concessions; and if a private <lb/> company can
                  write Mr. Crosbie from Saint John <lb/> and offer him 10,000 square miles of
                  timberland <lb/> in Labrador, there must be some reason on their <lb/> part for
                  the man to be able to think they can get <lb/> it. Every member of this Convention
                  would not <lb/> be a Newfoundlander if he did not feel as <lb/> Mr. Crosbie does,
                  who is determined to do every<lb break="no"/>thing in his power to prevent any
                  more of this <lb/> going on for the next 12 months. There is room <lb/> there for
                  a first-class row. I am sure the whole <lb/> Convention, and the public, will back
                  him; and if <lb/> he wants a parade or march, we will follow <lb/> behind... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I agree with Mr. Miller. If our <lb/> reading is
                  correct, I agree that Mr. Crosbie means <lb/> assets as being in toto. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[It was moved by Mr. Smallwood, seconded by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Higgins and carried, that Mr. Crosbie be 
           
            <pb n="207" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0207.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">207</fw>
         
     aallowed to speak again]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I did not expect to get into this this <lb/>
                  afternoon. By the word "assets" 1 mean every<lb break="no"/>thing — the water that
                  runs; power taken from <lb/> that water; trees; fish around the shores we con<lb break="no"/>trol; timber; anything that is under New<lb break="no"/>foundland
                  domain. I used the word "natural <lb/> resources" today. You do not have to go
                  back <lb/> very far to find $8 million loaned free of interest; <lb/> $2 million
                  borrowed at interest. It does not make <lb/> sense. That is why I deliberately
                  used the word <lb/> "asset". Mr. Smallwood thinks it might mean that <lb/> they
                  can increase our assets; I do not think the <lb/>government can. They have not the
                  ability. If you <lb/>. read further you will see "any disposal"; it is
                  <lb/>"disposal" with which I am concerned. We are <lb/>elected here by the
                  different districts, we have <lb/>had a lot of criticism because we have had no
                  <lb/>public sessions; if we had had public sessions, <lb/>there would not have
                  been much assets left to play <lb/>with. What we have left, for goodness' sake let
                  <lb/>us hold on to. I will head a parade, sure, but it may <lb/>be worse than a
                  parade. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I rise to support the motion made by <lb/>Mr.
                  Crosbie. Mr. Smallwood thinks we are <lb/>taking it in a lukewarm manner. I think
                  it is <lb/>because each of us agrees that it should have been <lb/>on the carpet
                  long ago. I feel the hopelessness of <lb/>the situation. All we can do is pass our
                  opinion <lb/>on the disposal of assets. The Commission of <lb/>Government, and I
                  probably should say the <lb/>Dominions Office, will take no more note of our
                  <lb/>opinion than throw it in the wastepaper basket. <lb/>Those absentee landlords
                  have disposed of prac<lb break="no"/>tically all we did have at the time we lost
                     respon<lb break="no"/>sible government, without consultation of the <lb/>people
                  of this country; more than that, they dis<lb break="no"/>pose of territory, giving
                  mineral rights on the <lb/>Labrador; giving timber leases, and doing any<lb break="no"/>thing which came to their minds to dispose of the <lb/>public
                  domain of this Dominion — and it is a <lb/>Dominion. "Dominions Office" — I am
                  sick of <lb/>it. It puts me in mind of a stanza from Milton, this <lb/>corrupt
                  practice. <lb/>
               </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Enough of such as for their bellies' sake, 
     <lb/>Creep and intrude and climb into the fold? 
     <lb/>Of other care they little reckining make, 
     <lb/>Than how to scramble at the shearers' feast, 
     <lb/>And shove away the worthy bidden guest; 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     Blind mouths! (that is the mouths of State) 
     <lb/>
    that scarce themselves know how to hold 
     <lb/>A sheep-hook, or have learn'd aught else the 
     <lb/>least 
     <lb/>That to the faithful Herdman's art belongs! 
     <lb/>What recks it them? What need they? Thay 
     <lb/>are sped; 
     <lb/>And when they list, their lean and flashy 
     <lb/>songs 
     <lb/>Grate on their scrannel Pipes of wretched 
     <lb/>straw. 
     <lb/>The hungry Sheep (the starving people of this 
     <lb/>country from 1933-39) look up, and are not 
     <lb/>fed, 
     <lb/>But swoln with wind and the rank mist they 
     <lb/>draw, 
     <lb/>Rot inwardly, and foul contagion spread: 
     <lb/>Besides what the grim wolf with privy paw 
     <lb/>Daily devours apace, and nothing said; 
     <lb/>But that two-handed engine at the door 
     <lb/>Stands ready to smite once, and smite no 
     <lb/>more.<ref target="#fn_06">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>That is the Dominions Office described by Mil<lb break="no"/>ton in the 17th century, that little back room in 
     <lb/>some place in Downing Street where the destinies 
     <lb/>of colonies are decided; where they think they 
     <lb/>have the right to sell Newfoundland or give it 
     <lb/>away as they have been doing. I speak thus be<lb break="no"/>cause I realise the hopelessness of the situation. 
     <lb/>We saw what happened at Gander. One to two 
     <lb/>million is to come out of the pockets of the people 
     <lb/>annually and they ask us to decide if the country 
     <lb/>is self-supporting. It is the worst treatment any 
     <lb/>country in the world ever got from the mother 
     <lb/>country... I support the motion of Mr. Crosbie. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I support the motion which I think <lb/>should have
                  been brought in long ago. I do not <lb/>agree with Mr. Hollett that the Dominions
                  Office <lb/>will not take note of it; we should see to it that <lb/>they do. We
                  are elected by the people of this <lb/>country and we should be the voice of
                  freedom. <lb/>The time has come for us to start fighting and to <lb/>let Great
                  Britain and certain elements know the <lb/>way we have been treated in the past,
                  and I <lb/>believe from today we should get going on this. <lb/>The people of this
                  country criticised us for doing, <lb/>as they thought, nothing, when we were
                  getting <lb/>$15 a day. They lost interest because we had no <lb/>public sessions.
                  As Mr. Crosbie says, if we had
           
   
          
     <note xml:id="fn_06">[1] An excerpt from "Lycidas" by John Milton. See Menitt Y. Hughes (ed), John Milton: Complete Poems 
     <lb/>
     and Major Prose (New York, 1957), p. 120. 
     </note>
            
            <pb n="208" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-12_Page_0208.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">208</fw>
            <fw type="num">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
           

    been having public sessions we would not
                  have <lb/> found out the things we did. I believe each and <lb/> every one in this
                  House should forget all differen<lb break="no"/>ces and get this country back to
                  the people to <lb/> whom it belongs. We are here because our people <lb/> love
                  this country. Why should they give away the <lb/> assets our forebears fought so
                  hard to get? The <lb/> Commission government intends to spend that <lb/> $30
                  million surplus before they get out. Then they <lb/> will turn the government over
                  to us. We waited <lb/> too long. How much longer are we going to put <lb/> up with
                  it? We are not going to get anything <lb/> without fighting for it. The average
                  Briton does <lb/> not understand anything but a fight. I risked my <lb/> life for
                  this country and I would do it again. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VINC1">Mr. Vincent</persName> However there is no need to <lb/>elaborate on why
                  this motion should, and doubt<lb break="no"/>less will command the unanimous
                  approval of <lb/>this House. To me it would be most extraordinary <lb/>indeed
                  should a dissenting voice be heard. I make <lb/>no apologies for saying that any
                  delegates raising <lb/>their voice against this should be deemed un<lb break="no"/>patriotic indeed. Let's back the resolution with <lb/>concerted action, and do
                  it right away. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I don't think there will be any <lb/> notice
                  taken of the motion, but to be critically <lb/> correct I think that the motion
                  will have to be <lb/> amended, and for that reason I move the follow<lb break="no"/>ing amendment: that the word "assets" be deleted <lb/> and the following words
                  substituted: "any of the <lb/> natural resources or liquid assets of New<lb break="no"/>foundland at present under the control of the <lb/> Commission of
                  Government, other than already <lb/> contracted for, either in Newfoundland or
                  <lb/> Labrador". Otherwise it will mean that High<lb break="no"/>roads cannot even
                  sell a tractor. The waterpower <lb/> situation is already covered by one of the
                  acts in <lb/> 1938 and 1944, giving the Labrador Mining and <lb/> Exploration
                  Company full power to acquire what <lb/> waterpower they require as soon as mining
                  leases <lb/> are taken out by them. We have no control over <lb/> that. That's why
                  I move that amendment. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I would second that if Mr. Hig<lb break="no"/>gins would assure me that they can't pay their <lb/> bills! <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Does that mean rum at the Control<lb break="no"/>lers? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It is not that kind of liquid that <lb/> Mr.
                  Higgins is dealing with. Does that mean that <lb/>
                  <cb/> they could not pay their bills? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> We will say "their liquid assets <lb/>other than
                  current". I think the whole lot of it is <lb/>really a lot of nonsense. I am sure
                  there won't be <lb/>any notice taken of it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That's a little bit complicated, <lb/> and I
                  think you had better put that in writing and <lb/> submit it to the clerk, please.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention agreed to accept the proposed 
     <lb/>
     change to the motion without debate]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Five years ago I wrote a letter to <lb/> the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Daily News</hi>. In the final paragraph l pointed
                  <lb/> out that since the beginning of Commission <lb/> government we, the people
                  of Newfoundland, <lb/> stood by silently and had our possessions and our <lb/>
                  assets given to outsiders without having any <lb/> voice in the matter whatever. I
                  congratulate <lb/> Mr. Crosbie; I am strongly in favour of this mo<lb break="no"/>tion, and will do anything I can to see that the <lb/> motion will have teeth in
                  it. I realise that we as a <lb/> Convention are not in a position to demand the
                  <lb/> Commission of Government do anything, but we <lb/> have an opportunity if we
                  wish to take it on <lb/> ourselves, that each delegate when he goes back <lb/> to
                  his district should call a public meeting <lb/> throughout the whole country to
                  deal with <lb/> Mr. Crosbie's motion from a public standpoint, <lb/> and, while
                  the Dominions Office is inclined prac<lb break="no"/>tically at all times to
                  ignore things, I think some <lb/> public agitation at least may open their eyes...
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> I would like to take up where <lb/>Mr. Bailey
                  left off... I certainly agree with him. <lb/>I don't think that Mr. Bailey was
                  being radical in <lb/>what he said, neither do I think that Mr. Hollett <lb/>is a
                  defeatist, but a realist. However I have my <lb/>doubts. I think this motion may
                  do something. <lb/>The stronger we make it the more chance we have <lb/>of doing
                  something. Mr. Bailey made a little <lb/>excursion into our history, a matter
                  which <lb/>Mr. Bailey and I have made numerous excur<lb break="no"/>sions into the
                  past few years. When people say, <lb/>"That's 50 or lOO years ago, forget that",
                  well the <lb/>same thing is happening today, and what are we <lb/>going to do
                  about it? I want to support Mr. <lb/>Bailey's stand that it is time for fighting,
                  and if <lb/>this is the beginning of the tight, I am all for it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[ The motion as amended carried unanimously, 
     <lb/>
     and the Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
    </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>