<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-12-11" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-12-11">11 December 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1000" to="1017"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1000.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1002.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1003.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1004.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1005.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1006.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1007.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1008.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1009.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1010.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1011.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1012.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1013.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1014.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1015.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1016.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1017.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-08-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-08-09">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1000">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1000.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1001">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1002">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1002.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1003">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1003.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1004">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1004.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1005">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1005.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1006">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1006.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1007">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1007.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1008">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1008.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1009">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1009.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1010">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1010.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1011">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1011.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1012">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1012.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1013">
         <graphic url="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1013.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1014">
         <graphic url="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1014.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1015">
         <graphic url="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1015.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1016">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1016.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1017">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1017.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1000" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1000.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1000</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-08-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->

<!--<p>
     because how can I decide anything on pure 
     <lb/>
     hypothesis or conjecture, and the debate, as far as 
     <lb/>
     I am concerned for the last l5 minutes, has had 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     anything but a factual foundation. 
     <lb/>
     [The committee rose and reported progress, and 
     <lb/>
     the Convention adjourned.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     December 11, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">Report of the Ottawa Delegation 
<lb/>
     Proposed Arrangements for the Entry of Newfoundland into Confederation 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole</head>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> Mr. Chairman... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Mr. Reddy, Mr. Bailey was oc<lb break="no"/>cupying the floor, if you don't mind deferring it. 
     <lb/>
     
    </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> Mr. Chairman, as regards to this dis<lb break="no"/>cussion we were in yesterday evening when the 
     <lb/>question probably went outside of the scope of 
     <lb/>the clause discussed, I assure you that I did not 
     <lb/>intentionally do it; I was just trying to make it 
     <lb/>clear for the Convention and the people to under<lb break="no"/>stand. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Iam sure we all appreciate that, 
     <lb/>
     Captain Bailey. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I would like you to turn to page 4 of 
     <lb/>
     the Grey Book, where I intended to follow on 
     <lb/>
     when I left off yesterday evening when brought 
     <lb/>
     to order - Transitional Grants: 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     In order to facilitate the adjustment of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland to the status of a province and 
     <lb/>
     the development by Newfoundland of 
     <lb/>
     revenue-producing services, Canada will pay 
     <lb/>
     to Newfoundland each year during the first 
     <lb/>
     twelve years of union a diminishing Transi<lb break="no"/>tional Grant payable as follows... 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Now each and every one of us will note that 
     <lb/>
     after the first three years there has to be found a 
     <lb/>
     certain portion from taxation different from what 
     <lb/>
     we have got today. I want it made clear just what 
     <lb/>
     we have to expect, I believe in the quotation 
     <lb/>
     which was, I think, made in this House by some 
     <lb/>
     member, that the wrong way to tax a people is for 
     <lb/>
     one body to collect the taxes and another body to 
     <lb/>
     spend it. So I believe that When we get closer to 
     <lb/>
     the crux of the matter and find out what we are 
     <lb/>
     being taxed for, I believe we will have a better 
     <lb/>
     form of government. I think this clause we have 
     <lb/>
     before us points that out very strongly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I find, and I am worried about it, that there has 
     <lb/>
     been no effort made for any adjustment in what 
     <lb/>
     we have before us. We know what we are going 
     <lb/>
     to get, it has been pointed out very strongly, 
     <lb/>
     everything that is coming to us; but nobody has 
     <lb/>
     taken the trouble so far to point out what we are 
    

            <cb/>
       

     going to pay and how it is going to be paid. I tried 
     <lb/>
     yesterday in my humble and probably illiterate 
     <lb/>
     manner to bring to your attention the difference 
     <lb/>
     in the direct taxation that must come upon us if 
     <lb/>
     and when we come into confederation. We must 
     <lb/>
     adjust ourselves, and l not only see that 12 years 
     <lb/>
     to the day we will have to find this amount that 
     <lb/>
     is brought before us, but also another $1.5 mil<lb break="no"/>lion. I cannot see for the life of me how this 
     <lb/>
     country can have the very least in services under 
     <lb/>
     $5 million taxation. Now that's the point I would 
     <lb/>
     like to make clear today. and I don't see, looking 
     <lb/>
     at it from every angle. after the federal and 
     <lb/>
     provincial governments take their cuts. where the 
     <lb/>
     cut is going to come from for municipal purposes 
     <lb/>
     and for our schools. You will find out that the 
     <lb/>
     578,062 people of Nova Scotia are collecting 
     <lb/>
     $9,941,058 for their schools. I say we have got 
     <lb/>
     twice the territory to service, because we can't go 
     <lb/>
     on leaving the Labrador in the place it is into; I 
     <lb/>
     am sure it is the greatest disgrace in the world, 
     <lb/>
     the way that Newfoundland has left the people of 
     <lb/>
     Labrador. If there is one body of people in our 
     <lb/>
     country that has raised themselves by the boot<lb break="no"/>straps, against odds that you can hardly under<lb break="no"/>stand, it's the people of Labrador. I believe that 
     <lb/>
     they should have the same as everybody else. 
     <lb/>
     There isn't any doubt that there's an immense 
     <lb/>
     amount of wealth in the country, and our people 
     <lb/>
     in Labrador should not be left like the natives. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I tried yesterday to explain in my simple way 
     <lb/>
     how these people are raising this money. I can't 
     <lb/>
     quote the districts in the Province ofNova Scotia, 
     <lb/>
     that's the municipal statistics, the clause here 
     <lb/>
     would be too deep to go into. I think we have got 
     <lb/>
     about 33 pounds of data on this Convention Act, 
     <lb/>
     and I slogged through most of it, and I believe if 
     <lb/>
     we were to make an impartial survey of Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia we would have to have 30-odd pounds of 
     <lb/>
     that... I am not satisfied that this country is going 
     <lb/>
     to get all it needs for $75 per capita, It can't be 
     <lb/>
     done, and if we had $120 per capita, including 
  

            <pb n="1001" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1001.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>  <fw type="num">1001</fw>
          

     our federal taxes, we will have to find another $5 
     <lb/>
     million to give the service to the country that the 
     <lb/>
     people require. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When we look around we know what we have 
     <lb/>
     to have. Take just Public Health and Welfare. We 
     <lb/>
     will go through the villages of Newfoundland. It 
     <lb/>
     is not because it can't be done, or should not be 
     <lb/>
     done, but because the people don't understand. 
     <lb/>
     You want a staff of people going through this 
     <lb/>
     country just to educate people. If you don't, it will 
     <lb/>
     cost money just to prevent ill-health in many 
     <lb/>
     cases. There are hundreds and thousands more 
     <lb/>
     items that I could think about if I had the time, 
     <lb/>
     but I don't want to keep this Convention too long, 
     <lb/>
     I just want to emphasise the fact that those taxes 
     <lb/>
     have to be raised, and yesterday I brought it down 
     <lb/>
     to two localities; I did no harm in what I was 
     <lb/>
     trying to do, I wanted to show the responsibility 
     <lb/>
     that would fall on the people of the different 
     <lb/>
     villages and settlements and towns throughout 
     <lb/>
     this country if we have got to put those services 
     <lb/>
     in. I believe they should be put in if we have 
     <lb/>
     responsible government or Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government. I am sure it should be done if we 
     <lb/>
     have Commission government. And then we will 
     <lb/>
     have our people saying, "I don't know how much 
     <lb/>
     taxes I am paying". Nobody knows. Canadians 
     <lb/>
     know, yes the Canadians know. Why does the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian and Nova Scotia man know? Because 
     <lb/>
     the Nova Scotia man collects the taxes, and not 
     <lb/>
     only collects the taxes, but he employs an army 
     <lb/>
     — six councillors here and six there and 12 
     <lb/>
     somewhere else to see if those taxes are used 
     <lb/>
     right. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That's all I am going to say on this, and I 
     <lb/>
     believe there are others wanting to get the floor. 
     <lb/>
     I want to emphasise this fact to our people that 
     <lb/>
     we cannot go on, and we are not going to go on 
     <lb/>
     getting a handout from the federal government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada to run this country. Now that's all we 
     <lb/>
     talked of so far — handouts. When that time 
     <lb/>
     comes we will have a royal commission and what 
     <lb/>
     will we find? Perhaps $100,000 or $200,000, 
     <lb/>
     perhaps $500,000 being collected for municipal 
     <lb/>
     services outside St. John's. What is the royal 
     <lb/>
     commission going to say? "Why you are not 
     <lb/>
     taxing your people at all — look what our people 
     <lb/>
     are paying. You have got to bring it up." And that 
     <lb/>
     is the question before us today. Now whether our 
     <lb/>
     people are going to have that royal commission 
     <lb/>
     down is none of my business, they have got the 
 

            <cb/>
         

     vote and let them use it, but for everyone's sake 
     <lb/>
     let us realise that they are going to come in and 
     <lb/>
     they don't promise anything else. This Grey 
     <lb/>
     Book doesn't promise us anything else, and com<lb break="no"/>mon sense doesn't promise us. That is all I am 
     <lb/>
     going to say on this question today. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> Mr. Chairman, during the past 
     <lb/>
     several days l've asked myself often if I were 
     <lb/>
     dreaming. Everyone of us hears some strange and 
     <lb/>
     funny things as we go through life, but a story as 
     <lb/>
     fantastic as any I've listened to has been 
     <lb/>
     delivered in this house during recent days by the 
     <lb/>
     member from Bonavista Centre, Mr. Smallwood, 
     <lb/>
     with a straight and solemn face, and up to this 
     <lb/>
     moment I am not sure whether or not the member 
     <lb/>
     for Bonavista has been playing one of his practi<lb break="no"/>caljokes and poking fun at us all the time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, a point of of 
     <lb/>
     order. Mr, Reddy is imputing motives to me, and 
     <lb/>
     he is out of order in doing so, and every time he 
     <lb/>
     does I am going to rise to a point of order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Just a moment now, gentlemen, 
     <lb/>
     please. Your point of order is predicated upon the 
     <lb/>
     assumption that Mr. Reddy is imputing motives 
     <lb/>
     to you, Mr. Smallwood. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, sir. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> No, I hold that that is just what 
     <lb/>
     he has cleverly avoided doing, by virtue of that 
     <lb/>
     expression, he says, "I don't know whether or not 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood is playing one of his practical 
     <lb/>
     jokes upon us." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That itself is a definite imputa<lb break="no"/>tion. It is casting doubt upon my bonafideness. It 
     <lb/>
     is casting doubt upon my honesty and sincerity. 
     <lb/>
     He definitely casts doubt. He does not know 
     <lb/>
     whether I am doing such and such or not. If that's 
     <lb/>
     not an implication. if that's not casting doubt 
     <lb/>
     upon my integrity as a member of this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion, and as one piloting this report, if that's not 
     <lb/>
     casting doubt, I don't know what is. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> No, I am afraid 1 can't sustain 
     <lb/>
     you on that point. In effect he says he can't plumb 
     <lb/>
     the psychological depths of your mind to know 
     <lb/>
     exactly what you are doing. I can't see that he has 
     <lb/>
     imputed bad faith or anything else, because he 
     <lb/>
     says he does not know. He says. "I don't know 
     <lb/>
     whether or not Mr. Smallwood is playing a prac<lb break="no"/>tical joke." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> But isn't be bound to assume 
     <lb/>
     that I am a man of integrity? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I rise to a point of order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="1002" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1002.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1002</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>  <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
           

 <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am on my point of order. 
     <lb/>
     There is one still before the Chair. Am I not 
     <lb/>
     entitled, as a member of this Convention, to have 
     <lb/>
     it assumed, unless it can be proved to be other<lb break="no"/>wise, that I am a man of integrity and sincerity? 
     <lb/>
     And here is a man who says he does not know 
     <lb/>
     whether I am a man of integrity or not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> No, he does not say that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> He has doubt about it. He does 
     <lb/>
     not know. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> He does not know whether you 
     <lb/>
     are playing a practical joke or not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In other words he does not 
     <lb/>
     know whether l am honest or not, whether I have 
     <lb/>
     introduced this sincerely and honestly, or 
     <lb/>
     whether I am just playing a joke. If that's not 
     <lb/>
     imputing... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I am sony, Mr. Smallwood, I 
     <lb/>
     have to hold that the statement made by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Reddy is not capable, in my judgement, of 
     <lb/>
     the interpretation you have placed upon it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> OK, Mr. Chairman? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> I know we are living in a mad world, 
     <lb/>
     and I have thought recently that we here have 
     <lb/>
     ringside seats, and are participants in propagating 
     <lb/>
     some of this madness. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName>, about three or four weeks ago 
     <lb/>
     the Economic Committee delivered through 
     <lb/>
     Major Cashin its Economic Report. As a supple<lb break="no"/>ment to this report, the Committee made a 
     <lb/>
     serious, and I believe sincere attempt, to give an 
     <lb/>
     estimate of our probable revenue for the next 
     <lb/>
     three years, which period they called the foresee<lb break="no"/>able future. They were careful to say that they 
     <lb/>
     were guessing, but that this guess was based on 
     <lb/>
     present day facts, as they saw them; and as they 
     <lb/>
     were all intelligent men, they made what they 
     <lb/>
     said was an estimate of what our economic con<lb break="no"/>dition might be for the next three years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When Major Cashin sat down the member for 
     <lb/>
     Bonavista Centre rose to his feet, and launched 
     <lb/>
     forth on perhaps the most devasting, violent and 
     <lb/>
     bitter speech I have listened to since I came here 
     <lb/>
     15 months ago. Mr. Smallwood ridiculed the idea 
     <lb/>
     of this Economic Committee attempting to give 
     <lb/>
     the people a problematical budget for three years 
     <lb/>
     ahead. Mr. Smallwood used his bitterest sarcasm 
     <lb/>
     to discredit the Economic Report in general, and 
     <lb/>
     the three—year budget in particular.... Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood said, in effect, that for the Economic 
  

            <cb/>
      

     Committee to estimate our revenue three years in 
     <lb/>
     advance was nonsense and worse. When he had 
     <lb/>
     delivered his solar plexus punch I felt that, ir<lb break="no"/>respective of the merits or demerits of the case, 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Smallwood was sincerely convinced that 
     <lb/>
     the future could not be seen, and our probable 
     <lb/>
     revenue could not be essayed, and we could not 
     <lb/>
     count our chickens before they were hatched; and 
     <lb/>
     that this was the honest and sincere conviction of 
     <lb/>
     the member for Bonavista Centre. So much for 
     <lb/>
     that; but as they say, "time marches on". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     For the past three or four days I have been 
     <lb/>
     sitting, listening to the same member from 
     <lb/>
     Bonavista Centre stand up and deliver his es<lb break="no"/>timate of our revenue and expenditure if we be<lb break="no"/>came a province of Canada, not for a foreseeable 
     <lb/>
     future of a paltry three years, or four years, or five 
     <lb/>
     years, or six years or seven years. No, nothing 
     <lb/>
     less than a period of eight years in the future is 
     <lb/>
     worthy of the attention of Mr. Smallwood, and 
     <lb/>
     equipped with his own particular spyglass, and 
     <lb/>
     all by himself, he projects himself and all of us 
     <lb/>
     eight years ahead, up to 1956. He then divides the 
     <lb/>
     eight years into two four-year periods, and 
     <lb/>
     proceeds with serene self-confidence to read our 
     <lb/>
     economic future for the next eight years — and 
     <lb/>
     in three days composes a budget covering from 
     <lb/>
     now till 1956, and brings it to this House and 
     <lb/>
     delivers it for our appreciation. And I have no 
     <lb/>
     doubt if the gentleman from Bonavista Centre 
     <lb/>
     had been requested to prepare a budget taking us 
     <lb/>
     further into the stratosphere, he would have done 
     <lb/>
     so with equal facility. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now Mr. Chairman, I may not have the best 
     <lb/>
     of understanding, but as I see it the member for 
     <lb/>
     Bonavista Centre has said in effect to Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin and his associates of the Economic Com<lb break="no"/>mittee. "How dare you attempt to look into the 
     <lb/>
     future. That is not <hi rendition="simple:italic">your</hi> province — that is just 
     <lb/>
     another of <hi rendition="simple:italic">my</hi> provinces. and it is only I who am 
     <lb/>
     permitted to see the shape of things to come. It is 
     <lb/>
     all right for me to estimate eight years ahead, but 
     <lb/>
     it is nonsensical for you, Major Cashin, to attempt 
     <lb/>
     any such thing!" Mr. Chairman, may I be par<lb break="no"/>doned if I ask in all seriousness if there be some 
     <lb/>
     direct ray oflight giving the member for Bonavis<lb break="no"/>ta Centre prophetic vision, and leaving the other 
     <lb/>
     members of this House in darkness? If so, I wish 
     <lb/>
     to raise a point of order, so that this ray of light 
     <lb/>
     be made available to the other members also. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman, the humble members of the 


            <pb n="1003" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1003.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1003</fw>
          

     Economic Committee said that they were stick<lb break="no"/>ing their collective necks out when they at<lb break="no"/>tempted to guess the economic future of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland — three years ahead. if so, what 
     <lb/>
     can be said for the gentleman who so bravely tells 
     <lb/>
     the people of Newfoundland that by following his 
     <lb/>
     programmes their economic welfare is assured, 
     <lb/>
     not for just a day, not for just three years, not, not 
     <lb/>
     for just eight years, but always. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I want to reply 
     <lb/>
     to Mr. Reddy, but there is lots of time if Mr. Hol<lb break="no"/>lett wants to reply to the witty speech which 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Reddy has just delivered, and whose author 
     <lb/>
     I congratulate very sincerely upon his wit and 
     <lb/>
     humour. The point, the one point in the speech 
     <lb/>
     sir, which I think demands a reply is this: that I 
     <lb/>
     quarrelled with Major Cashin, the chairman of 
     <lb/>
     the Finance Committee, and with the members of 
     <lb/>
     the Finance Committee, for having brought in a 
     <lb/>
     budget looking three years ahead, and that I then 
     <lb/>
     am so inconsistent as to bring in one for eight 
     <lb/>
     years ahead. Now that's the point of that speech. 
     <lb/>
     Sir, there is no point in it. There is not a good 
     <lb/>
     point. What the Economic Committee did was 
     <lb/>
     bring in a firm budget for three years. I have not 
     <lb/>
     done any such thing. What they said was that each 
     <lb/>
     year for three years the Government of New 
     <lb/>
     foundland under responsible government would 
     <lb/>
     collect... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Mr. Chairman, I rise to a point of 
     <lb/>
     order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> State your point. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> We stated no such thing, that a 
     <lb/>
     government of Newfoundland under responsible 
     <lb/>
     government — I don't think the words "respon<lb break="no"/>sible government" appear in the Economic 
     <lb/>
     Report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I must sustain you on that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> All right, the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, whether responsible, or Com<lb break="no"/>mission or what. I don't think the Economic 
     <lb/>
     Report could have meant the government of the 
     <lb/>
     Province of Newfoundland. I think they meant 
     <lb/>
     the Government of Newfoundland for each of the 
     <lb/>
     three years foreseeable in the future would collect 
     <lb/>
     roughly $30 million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have said that if we become a province there 
     <lb/>
     are certain fixed assets that we know we will get. 
     <lb/>
     There is no guesswork about it. We <hi rendition="simple:italic">know</hi> the 
     <lb/>
     provincial government will get $6,820,000 a year 
     <lb/>
     in subsidies. We know we will get $35 million a 
    

            <cb/>
          

     year for the first three years, $22 million in eight 
     <lb/>
     years. We know we can, or will get $666,000 paid 
     <lb/>
     back to the provincial government for Gander; 
     <lb/>
     we know we will get $1.8 million or whatever it 
     <lb/>
     is paid back to the government for the two Rail<lb break="no"/>way boats — that's $2 million. Now I have mere<lb break="no"/>ly added up the income for the first eight years 
     <lb/>
     that we know we will get. I have added that up, 
     <lb/>
     and it comes to $80 million. Sir, that is not 
     <lb/>
     guesswork, just ordinary addition and multiplica<lb break="no"/>tion of known facts: $80 million will come to the 
     <lb/>
     provincial government of Newfoundland, leav<lb break="no"/>ing $40 million to collect in taxes, that is $5 
     <lb/>
     million a year. Now sir, for any man in this 
     <lb/>
     Convention or out of it to get up and say that in 
     <lb/>
     the coming eight years the government of the 
     <lb/>
     Province of Newfoundland could collect, on an 
     <lb/>
     average, $5 million a year revenue, $40 million 
     <lb/>
     in eight years, through taxation, is surely, surely, 
     <lb/>
     not to be put in the same class as forecasting $30 
     <lb/>
     million by taxation, $30 million for the next three 
     <lb/>
     years. Surely there is all the difference in the 
     <lb/>
     world. I estimate that the Government of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, if we become a province. would need 
     <lb/>
     to spend in the first eight years $120 million; $80 
     <lb/>
     million of that would come in from sources that 
     <lb/>
     we know about, that are in the Grey Book. That 
     <lb/>
     leaves $40 million to get by taxation in eight 
     <lb/>
     years, an average of $5 million a year. You don't 
     <lb/>
     have to be a prophet or a financier to be quite 
     <lb/>
     firmly convinced that we as a province can col<lb break="no"/>lect in taxes $5 million a year. So that the speech 
     <lb/>
     which Mr. Reddy has just read out is really quite 
     <lb/>
     without point. it is comparing two things that are 
     <lb/>
     not actually comparable. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> First I would like to make a remark 
     <lb/>
     or two with regard to the statement made by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood yesterday relative to the interest 
     <lb/>
     on the 1950-52 loans. You will rememberthat the 
     <lb/>
     day before yesterday I pointed out to 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood that I thought he had erred in 
     <lb/>
     some way, and that he and his budget makers had 
     <lb/>
     failed to provide for $123,000 in his accounts. 
     <lb/>
     that is to say $80,000 and some hundreds from 
     <lb/>
     1947-50, and some $40,000-odd from 1947-52. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood replied to me that he would 
     <lb/>
     answer me yesterday, after consulting with the 
     <lb/>
     Finance Department. Now I feel quite sure that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood did not have to consult the 
     <lb/>
     Finance Department. I am also certain that he did 
     <lb/>
     not consult them at all... 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <pb n="1004" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1004.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1004</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
            

<p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> You are wrong then. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> And if he did, he did not get any 
     <lb/>
     satisfaction 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I did. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Well, in that case there must be 
     <lb/>
     something wrong with the Finance Department, 
     <lb/>
     because they have made a ruling that they will 
     <lb/>
     not answer any questions from this Convention 
     <lb/>
     unless it comes through the proper channels. I 
     <lb/>
     wonder therefore why Mr. Smallwood has the 
     <lb/>
     privilege of going to the Finance Department and 
     <lb/>
     getting the information. He can go to his little 
     <lb/>
     friend who helped him make up the budget,<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> and 
     <lb/>
     he probably did. Anyway I discover that he and 
     <lb/>
     his budgetmakers were $123,000 short in 1947- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     48, 1949-50, and $40,000-odd short for 1951-52, 
     <lb/>
     That was the first thing that should have gone into 
     <lb/>
     that budget. That was left out, and as I go through 
     <lb/>
     it I find there were many other things left out, 
     <lb/>
     many other things not accurate there; but having 
     <lb/>
     found that first error I studied it very carefully, 
     <lb/>
     because i was indeed surprised. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now Mr. Chairman, first I have a reply to one 
     <lb/>
     of the first things stated in this House, one given 
     <lb/>
     in connection with the statement made by 
     <lb/>
     Premier Duplessis, wherein he stated that formal 
     <lb/>
     notice had been given to the Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government that he was not satisfied, and did not 
     <lb/>
     intend to remain satisfied with the judgement of 
     <lb/>
     the Privy Council, 1927, relative to the Labrador. 
     <lb/>
     I am just in receipt of a reply to that question 
     <lb/>
     which was tabled here from the government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p rendition="simple:right">
     December 5, 1947. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Dear Sir:   
     <lb/></p>

<p>
     In reply to question asked by Mr. M.M. 
     <lb/>
     Hollett, M.A., as to whether the Premier of 
     <lb/>
     Quebec had served formal notice upon the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Newfoundland that the 
     <lb/>
     Province of Quebec does not consider that 
     <lb/>
     the judgement of the Privy Council in 1927 
     <lb/>
     relative to the boundary between Quebec 
     <lb/>
     Labrador and Newfoundland Labrador is the 
     <lb/>
     final settlement of this issue, I am directed to 
     <lb/>
     inform you that no such formal notice has 
     <lb/>
     been received by the Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/></p>

<p rendition="simple:right">
     Yours faithfully, 
     <lb/>
     W.J. Carew 
     <lb/>
     Secretary. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p></quote>

            <p>So up to December 5, 1947, Mr. Duplessis had 

   
           
            <cb/>
          

     not made good his statement. 
     <lb/>
     
    </p>

            <p>Then I have another reply to a question which 
     <lb/>I made on the December 2. and this one is so 
     <lb/>important that I will read you the notice of ques<lb break="no"/>tion first: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>I give notice that I will on tomorrow ask 
     <lb/>His Excellency the Governor of New<lb break="no"/>foundland to seek clarification from the 
     <lb/>Government of the United Kingdom for the 
     <lb/>benefit of this Convention on the following 
     <lb/>point: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>That is to say, that whereas under the 
     <lb/>Lease Bases Agreement 1941 it was stipu<lb break="no"/>lated that upon the resumption by New<lb break="no"/>foundland of the constitutional status held by 
     <lb/>it prior to the 16 February, 1934. the contract<lb break="no"/>ing parties to said Agreement would be the 
     <lb/>Government of the United States ofAmerica 
     <lb/>and the Government of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore, what would be the posi<lb break="no"/>tion should Newfoundland enter into con<lb break="no"/>federation with Canada? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Would the contracting parties under said 
     <lb/>Agreement be the Government of the United 
     <lb/>States of America and the provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Newfoundland, or otherwise, and if 
     <lb/>otherwise, to inform this Convention as to the 
     <lb/>real position which will exist. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>And to that question this is the reply signed by 
     <lb/>Mr. Carew, Secretary of the Commission of 
     <lb/>Government. I take it that the Commission had 
     <lb/>made inquiry from the Commonwealth Relations 
     <lb/>Office, otherwise they would not have replied to 
     <lb/>it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p>
     Dear Sir: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With regard to the question submitted by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Hollett on December 2, the reply is as 
     <lb/>
     follows: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is assumed that the question is based on 
     <lb/>
     the text of notes exchanged between 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Churchill and Mr. Winant at the time of 
     <lb/>
     the signature of the Leased Bases Agreement 
     <lb/>
     of 1941 (Cmd. 6259). It was then agreed 
     <lb/>
     between the United Kingdom and United 
     <lb/>
     States governments that "upon resumption 
     <lb/>
     by Newfoundland of the constitutional status 
     <lb/>
     held by it prior to February 16, 1934, the 
     <lb/>
     words "the Government of the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom wherever they occur in relation to 
     <lb/>
     a provision applicable to Newfoundland in 
     



<note xml:id="fn_01">[1] Probably a reference to Mr. Nimshi Crewe.</note> 


            <pb n="1005" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1005.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>  <fw type="num">1005</fw>
        

     the said Agreement shall be taken to mean, 
     <lb/>
     so far as Newfoundland is concerned, the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Newfoundland and the 
     <lb/>
     Agreement shall then be construed accord<lb break="no"/>ingly". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The wording of this note did not cover the 
     <lb/>
     position which would arise in the event of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland entering into the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     confederation, but in that event the present 
     <lb/>
     function of the United Kingdom government 
     <lb/>
     in relation to Newfoundland under the terms 
     <lb/>
     of the Agreement would devolve upon the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>
     From that I read that upon confederation the 
     <lb/>
     contracting parties to that base agreement will be 
     <lb/>
     the governments of the United States and the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion of Canada. In other words New<lb break="no"/>foundland is out of the picture. Entering con<lb break="no"/>federation you give up all claim to the bases. 
     <lb/>
     Remember they are only leased grants for 99 
     <lb/>
     years, and while some of us may not be here, 
     <lb/>
     some of our offspring may be, and these lease 
     <lb/>
     agreements, whereby part of Newfoundland was 
     <lb/>
     given away by Great Britain for a few destroyers, 
     <lb/>
     upon confederation we pass over the whole 
     <lb/>
     leased territory, the lease goes over and the agree<lb break="no"/>ment is between the USA and Canada. That looks 
     <lb/>
     very much to me like the alienation of the public 
     <lb/>
     domain of this little country of ours. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I asked that question because I see the serious<lb break="no"/>ness of it. I see Canada taking over these bases 
     <lb/>
     and being a party to the agreement with the 
     <lb/>
     United States, and under the defence pact which 
     <lb/>
     Canada today has with the United States it is 
     <lb/>
     simple for Canada to man these bases, put her 
     <lb/>
     own men in here for a while, a skeleton crew if 
     <lb/>
     you like, and deprive 3,500 Newfoundlanders of 
     <lb/>
     jobs which they are now working at, and for 
     <lb/>
     which I understand they are getting very good 
     <lb/>
     pay. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I don't know whether I am as 
     <lb/>
     clear on that as you are, that the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland shall be taken to mean the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada in the event of our going 
     <lb/>
     into confederation; by virtue of the fact that under 
     <lb/>
     section 92, sub-clause 13, of the BNA Act, the 
     <lb/>
     civil rights of the province will fall upon the 
     <lb/>
     province, so whether they mean the provincial 
     <lb/>
     government, in the event of entering confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, or the federal government of Canada, does 
     <lb/>
     not appear to me to be quite clear. But if they 


            <cb/>
         

     mean the federal government of Canada I would 
     <lb/>
     be interested in knowing how they arrived at that 
     <lb/>
     conclusion.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> In my opinion it would be highly 
     <lb/>
     unconstitutional, but we have been the subject of 
     <lb/>
     so much unconstitutionalism (if that is the word, 
     <lb/>
     sir) since 1933, that I never expect to see con<lb break="no"/>stitutionalism applied here again. I will read that 
     <lb/>
     again: "But in that event the present function of 
     <lb/>
     the United Kingdom government..." What is their 
     <lb/>
     function now? They are party to the agreement 
     <lb/>
     with the United States of America, "But in that 
     <lb/>
     event the present function of the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     government in relation to Newfoundland under 
     <lb/>
     the terms of the Agreement would devolve upon 
     <lb/>
     the Government of Canada." That's plain 
     <lb/>
     enough. I want you gentlemen to think that over. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman "Upon the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada." As a matter of interest. Mr, Hollett, I 
     <lb/>
     would like to know the manner in which that 
     <lb/>
     conclusion has been arrived at. It would be very 
     <lb/>
     interesting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Yes, I think it is about time our 
     <lb/>
     people did know and ask about it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> It is a very serious position if that 
     <lb/>
     is so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> All I can say is that I don't know 
     <lb/>
     how you get around it in the event of our becom<lb break="no"/>ing a province, because civilian property rights 
     <lb/>
     within the province of course come within the 
     <lb/>
     domain of the provincial government. How then 
     <lb/>
     can the Canadian government, as such, abrogate 
     <lb/>
     to itself the rights which are reserved to provin<lb break="no"/>cial governments under section 92? l am not 
     <lb/>
     trying to obstruct you, but it is a very far-reaching 
     <lb/>
     conclusion, and I would like to know how it is 
     <lb/>
     reached. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I just want to suggest to you that it may 
     <lb/>
     be a question of defence, you know, which is 
     <lb/>
     purely federal government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That's true, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I put it to you that this is not a 
     <lb/>
     question of defence. I am talking about the base 
     <lb/>
     agreement. it is a question of Newfoundland ter<lb break="no"/>ritory. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The point is this... that while the 
     <lb/>
     reversion under the lease would ordinarily come 
     <lb/>
     to the province under section 92, we would un<lb break="no"/>derstand that defence, being a matter concerning 
     <lb/>
     the bases and the Government of Canada, would 
     <lb/>
     naturally come within the purview of section 91, 
 

            <pb n="1006" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1006.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1006</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
          

     therefore in matters of defence the bases might, 
     <lb/>
     as defence, come within the jurisdiction of the 
     <lb/>
     federal government. Still the point made by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Hollett is this: how can they abrogate to 
     <lb/>
     themselves the rights which would pass to the 
     <lb/>
     province, the right to the reversions under the 
     <lb/>
     lease, which would be transferred to the province 
     <lb/>
     under section 92? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> The logic of it is that it would revert to 
     <lb/>
     the federal government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> As defence, but as a matter of 
     <lb/>
     civil and property rights, no. Mr. Hollett, if I may 
     <lb/>
     interrupt you at this, I would like to declare a brief 
     <lb/>
     recess. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Short recess]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> ....Now Mr. Chairman, in looking 
     <lb/>
     at this whole matter of this information which has 
     <lb/>
     been brought back to us from Canada by the 
     <lb/>
     delegation which went from this Convention to 
     <lb/>
     find out if there were any equitable basis for 
     <lb/>
     union between Newfoundland and Canada, and 
     <lb/>
     in studying these books which have been brought 
     <lb/>
     back, and all this information, I feel that it would 
     <lb/>
     be wise if we pause for a little while in our 
     <lb/>
     deliberation and take a look at Canada, relative 
     <lb/>
     particularly to these agreements which the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government is endeavouring to make, 
     <lb/>
     and which they have made with some of the 
     <lb/>
     provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As we know, these tax agreements have not 
     <lb/>
     been signed by Ontario, Quebec and Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>
     as yet, and I want, before I go on to that, to give 
     <lb/>
     the delegates a sort of refresher on this business 
     <lb/>
     of confederation. To that end I want us to remem<lb break="no"/>ber that in 1864 British North America was just 
     <lb/>
     a number of inconsiderable colonies dispersed 
     <lb/>
     along a narrow belt of territory from the Atlantic 
     <lb/>
     to the Pacific. In the centre was the Province of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, stretching 1,000 miles from Gaspé to the 
     <lb/>
     Detroit River, linked together commercially by 
     <lb/>
     the St Lawrence River system and the Grand 
     <lb/>
     Trunk Railway built in 1850, and consisting of a 
     <lb/>
     million French Canadians and a million and a half 
     <lb/>
     English, Irish and Scotch settlers, whose chief 
     <lb/>
     industries were agriculture, lumbering, ship<lb break="no"/>building, fishing and considerable manufactur<lb break="no"/>ing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Britain had adopted a free trade policy, and the 
     <lb/>
     Reciprocity Treaty with the United States was not 
     <lb/>
     to be renewed. The St. Lawrence was frozen up 
     <lb/>
     for six months of the year, and the northern 
    

            <cb/>
      

     United States were not too friendly at that time. 
     <lb/>
     On the Atlantic seaboard there were the colonies 
     <lb/>
     of Nova Scotia, New Brunswick and Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island, as well as Newfoundland, with a 
     <lb/>
     total population of 800,000 in 1864. Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>
     was still prosperous, her prosperity based on the 
     <lb/>
     era of wooden ships and the high prices following 
     <lb/>
     the American Civil War. It was a colony of 
     <lb/>
     fishermen, sailors and traders. Nova Scotia had 
     <lb/>
     enjoyed representative government for 100 
     <lb/>
     years, and had a culture all her own. She had fish, 
     <lb/>
     lumber, agriculture and coal, and traded with 
     <lb/>
     New England, the West Indies, Europe, and in<lb break="no"/>deed the whole world all seasons of the year. New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick, the home of United Empire 
     <lb/>
     Loyalists, had much the same natural resources 
     <lb/>
     as Nova Scotia. Prince Edward Island had 
     <lb/>
     agriculture, fishing and shipbuilding. All three 
     <lb/>
     were prosperous on account of the demand for 
     <lb/>
     their products by the United States and the high 
     <lb/>
     prices then existing. Then in the centre was the 
     <lb/>
     Red River District (now Manitoba), with 10,000 
     <lb/>
     souls, mostly half-breeds. In the west were two 
     <lb/>
     separate colonies, one on Vancouver Island, and 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia on the mainland. They united 
     <lb/>
     in 1866 to form one colony, but not more than 
     <lb/>
     10,000 people lived there. Such was British 
     <lb/>
     North America in 1864, or just before the idea of 
     <lb/>
     confederation was mooted. Between all these 
     <lb/>
     colonies there were no commercial dealings 
     <lb/>
     whatsoever. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There were various causes for the desire of 
     <lb/>
     confederation: there were conflicting interests, 
     <lb/>
     personal ambitions of some statesmen, and there 
     <lb/>
     was the question of commercial greed between 
     <lb/>
     the various colonies; most of all there was fear of 
     <lb/>
     the American empire. Confederation as finally 
     <lb/>
     consummated was only a compromise, for it was 
     <lb/>
     the hope and wish of Sir John A. Macdonald and 
     <lb/>
     most of the Fathers of Confederation that a real 
     <lb/>
     legislative union could be brought about, and not 
     <lb/>
     merely a <hi rendition="simple:italic">loosely</hi> bound number of autonomous 
     <lb/>
     provinces. "I have always contended", said Mac<lb break="no"/>donald in one of the debates, "that if we could 
     <lb/>
     agree to have one government and one parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, it would be the best, the cheapest, the most 
     <lb/>
     vigorous and the strongest system of government 
     <lb/>
     we could adopt." Lower Canada (Quebec), New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick and Nova Scotia, however, were 
     <lb/>
     against such an idea for various reasons, and so 
     <lb/>
     Macdonald, Sir Charles Tupper and others who 


            <pb n="1007" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1007.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1007</fw>
       


     favoured the idea of one government for the 
     <lb/>
     whole of Canada, had to be satisfied with what 
     <lb/>
     we know as confederation or no union at all. 
     <lb/>
     However, confederation as consummated in 
     <lb/>
     1867 left no doubt as to where the sovereignty of 
     <lb/>
     Canada lay, and as Sir Wilfred Laurier stated, 
     <lb/>
     "Every reasonable precaution seems to have been 
     <lb/>
     taken against leaving behind us any reversionary 
     <lb/>
     legacies of sovereign state rights as they have in 
     <lb/>
     the United States to stir up strife and discord 
     <lb/>
     among our children." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The relationships between the provincial 
     <lb/>
     legislatures and the Dominion government were 
     <lb/>
     defined by the division of powers actually written 
     <lb/>
     into the British North America Act and later 
     <lb/>
     modified by what the courts have since said, the 
     <lb/>
     words which describe what those powers really 
     <lb/>
     mean. The strength or weakness of the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government relative to the provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ments has depended in large measure upon politi<lb break="no"/>cal, fiscal, economic and social considerations. 
     <lb/>
     The powers of the Dominion government as laid 
     <lb/>
     down in the British North America Act include 
     <lb/>
     these high functions and sovereign powers by 
     <lb/>
     which general principles and uniformity of legis<lb break="no"/>lation may be secured in those questions that are 
     <lb/>
     of common import to all the provinces, to quote 
     <lb/>
     Lord Carnarvon when he introduced the act in the 
     <lb/>
     House of Lords. In other words, power was given 
     <lb/>
     to deal with all matters of a public and general 
     <lb/>
     character, as for example the making of treaties 
     <lb/>
     or the making of war, and laws relative to taxation 
     <lb/>
     in general. And to the provinces was given those 
     <lb/>
     powers which allowed then to deal with all mat<lb break="no"/>ters of a merely local or private nature in the 
     <lb/>
     province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If you have had the opportunity, gentlemen, to 
     <lb/>
     read the British North America Act you will find 
     <lb/>
     in one section that the Dominion government is 
     <lb/>
     given the power to raise money <hi rendition="simple:italic">by any</hi> mode or 
     <lb/>
     system of taxation. And, if you turn to another 
     <lb/>
     section you will find that the provinces are given 
     <lb/>
     the exclusive right to make laws in relation to 
     <lb/>
     direct taxation within the province in order to 
     <lb/>
     raise revenue for provincial purposes. This is 
     <lb/>
     very important to remember, for it is these two 
     <lb/>
     sections which all down through the past 82 years 
     <lb/>
     have caused so much friction in dominion- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     provincial relationships, and which on more than 
     <lb/>
     one occasion have nearly wrecked the union. In 
     <lb/>
     other words, during all these years the proper 
  

            <cb/>
          

     division of power as between the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     government and the provincial legislatures has 
     <lb/>
     been a continuous source of haggling, and caused 
     <lb/>
     a breakdown in the whole federal system around 
     <lb/>
     1937. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A province which hitherto has run and 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">financed</hi> its own affairs, on entering into such a 
     <lb/>
     union must of necessity lose some of its tax 
     <lb/>
     sources to the central. or in this case the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion govemment, just as also it will be able 
     <lb/>
     to rid itself of some of the costs of government. 
     <lb/>
     Take ourselves, for example; if we entered into 
     <lb/>
     confederation tomorrow our treasury would lose 
     <lb/>
     $10.5 million on account of income tax and about 
     <lb/>
     $18 million in customs and excise. On the other 
     <lb/>
     hand, we might rid ourselves of the railway 
     <lb/>
     deficits, the servicing of our deficit, and a few 
     <lb/>
     other charges In other words, by relinquishing 
     <lb/>
     $28.5 million we no longer have to worry about 
     <lb/>
     these services as a government. But as in<lb break="no"/>dividuals we would still have to contribute to 
     <lb/>
     their costs. For instance, on all those articles we 
     <lb/>
     import, other than from Canada, we shall still be 
     <lb/>
     charged duty, and the Dominion government 
     <lb/>
     would collect from us about $15 million in in<lb break="no"/>come tax instead of the $10 million we now pay. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But let us get back to Nova Scotia in 1865. 
     <lb/>
     Whilst still a separate province in 1864, Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia had a revenue of $1.3 million and an 
     <lb/>
     expenditure of $1,222,355. leaving a surplus of 
     <lb/>
     $77,645. The question was how much of the $1.3 
     <lb/>
     million revenue would still remain to the local 
     <lb/>
     legislature after confederation. At that time over 
     <lb/>
     90% of Nova Scotia's taxation revenue came 
     <lb/>
     from customs duties, and this, on going into 
     <lb/>
     confederation, she would have to turn over to the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion government. Acutally it was found 
     <lb/>
     that if Nova Scotia entered confederation only 
     <lb/>
     $107,000 could he expected to be collected by 
     <lb/>
     her from the local revenue sources still reserved. 
     <lb/>
     It was found that after she would go into con<lb break="no"/>federation her local expenditures would be 
     <lb/>
     $667,000, Now this would leave a deficit of 
     <lb/>
     $560,000. How was the deficit to be made up? 
     <lb/>
     There were various methods devised: (1) the use 
     <lb/>
     of the power of direct taxation; (2) concession of 
     <lb/>
     the right of the province to use indirect taxation; 
     <lb/>
     (3) divide Nova Scotia into municipalities and let 
     <lb/>
     them hear much of the burden with regard to 
     <lb/>
     government roads, health, etc. Up to this time 
     <lb/>
     town councils were almost unknown in Nova 


            <pb n="1008" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1008.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1008</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> 


     Scotia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     What was finally decided was the form of a 
     <lb/>
     subsidy from the Dominion treasury. The dif<lb break="no"/>ficulty however was to decide on a method of 
     <lb/>
     subsidy which would not appear unfair. For in<lb break="no"/>stance, to make up Nova Scotia's deficit on ac<lb break="no"/>count of loss of revenue, it would require $1.70 
     <lb/>
     per capita, $1.33 for New Brunswick, and but 38 
     <lb/>
     cents for Quebec and Ontario. They argued that 
     <lb/>
     if Nova Scotia was to receive $1.70 per head of 
     <lb/>
     population so should the other provinces. The 
     <lb/>
     Quebec Conference very nearly broke up over 
     <lb/>
     this matter. That was the Quebec Conference in 
     <lb/>
     1865, I think it was. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> 1864. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Thank you. What really saved the 
     <lb/>
     day was that Nova Scotia, through Dr. Charles 
     <lb/>
     Tupper, undertook to try to carry on with 
     <lb/>
     $371,000 instead of the $667,000, the actual cost 
     <lb/>
     estimated in 1864, a reduction of 40%; Prince 
     <lb/>
     Edward Island cut 27%, and New Brunswick 
     <lb/>
     12.5%. Thus, Nova Scotia's position after con<lb break="no"/>federation would be as follows: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<table>
<row><cell>Revenue</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">$ 107,000</cell></row> 
<row><cell>Expenditure</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">371,000</hi></cell> </row>
<row><cell>Deficit</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">$264,000</cell> </row>
</table>

            <p>
     This deficit amounted to 80 cents per head of 
     <lb/>
     population, and this was made the basic subsidy 
     <lb/>
     rate for all the provinces, and if you look at your 
     <lb/>
     tax agreement you will find that that is still exist<lb break="no"/>ing in the tax agreement which is offered us 
     <lb/>
     today. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now how the finance ministers of Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>
     and New Brunswick ever hoped to carry on under 
     <lb/>
     this static financial arrangement is anybody's 
     <lb/>
     guess. The proof that this financial arrangement 
     <lb/>
     was a hopeless one is to be found in the fact that 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia ran a heavy deficit almost immedi<lb break="no"/>ately, and had to seek better terms from the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion government within a year. By 1874 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia was expending $755,000 on neces<lb break="no"/>sary services, and could hardly be expected to 
     <lb/>
     carry on with $371,000 as agreed in 1867. Hence 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia, as well as the other provinces, had 
     <lb/>
     to go repeatedly to the Dominion government to 
     <lb/>
     beg for an adjustment, and they have been doing 
     <lb/>
     that ever since. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     No provision seems to have been made for any 
     <lb/>
     expected form of economic or social evolution. 
     <lb/>
     Nor is any made today under the various agree<lb break="no"/>ments which the provinces have with the 
 

            <cb/>
       

     Dominion government. There is no flexibility in 
     <lb/>
     the system of subsidy per capita per year, or as 
     <lb/>
     some provinces have agreed upon now, for a 
     <lb/>
     period of five years. For instance, the economic 
     <lb/>
     and social revolution in Canada during the 70 
     <lb/>
     years from 1867 to 1937 is indicated most 
     <lb/>
     pointedly by the fact that whereas in 1867 the 
     <lb/>
     total Dominion, provincial and municipal expen<lb break="no"/>diture was $25 million, in 1937 it was $1,000 
     <lb/>
     million. And it is interesting to note that in 1930. 
     <lb/>
     the provinces and their municipalities or town 
     <lb/>
     councils were providing 70% of the total outlay 
     <lb/>
     on the primary functions of government in 
     <lb/>
     Canada. The municipal system of government 
     <lb/>
     along with the provincial governments bears 
     <lb/>
     most of the burden, so much so that the 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Charles Dunning was able to say. "The 
     <lb/>
     Dominion government does not render to the 
     <lb/>
     people of Canada anything like the volume and 
     <lb/>
     value of services performed by the provincial and 
     <lb/>
     municipal bodies of Canada". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, the sources of revenue left to the 
     <lb/>
     province after confederation were mainly four in 
     <lb/>
     number: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. Revenues from fees, licenses and permits. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. Revenues from lands, forests and mines. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. Revenues from direct taxation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. The annual subsidy from the Dominion 
     <lb/>
    government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The first of these in the provinces, as in New<lb break="no"/>foundland, amounts to very little. The second 
     <lb/>yields but a very modest revenue. The fourth was 
     <lb/>to be a fixed amount. And it was upon the third 
     <lb/>— direct taxation — that both the province and 
     <lb/>the town councils had to rely. The unfortunate 
     <lb/>circumstances were, however, that the Dominion 
     <lb/>government also has had to invade the field of 
     <lb/>direct taxation. Thus it comes about that in 
     <lb/>Canada we have both the provincial government, 
     <lb/>Dominion government and town councils, under 
     <lb/>the provisions of the British North America Act, 
     <lb/>all resorting in the past in large measure for their 
     <lb/>revenues, to some means of direct taxation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Prior to the war, the Dominion and provincial 
     <lb/>
     governments were taxing incomes, and the 
     <lb/>
     provinces were collecting succession duties; for 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion government, as before stated, can 
     <lb/>
     raise money by any mode or system of taxation 
     <lb/>
     whatever, in spite of the fact that the provinces, 
     <lb/>
     under the British North America Act were given 
     <lb/>
     the exclusive right to direct taxation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="1009" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1009.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1009</fw>
            

<p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Not exclusive. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> What method was left for the 
     <lb/>
     municipalities or town councils? It has to be 
     <lb/>
     remembered that 93% of all people in Canada 
     <lb/>
     live in incorporated areas. Their main method of 
     <lb/>
     direct taxation is the tax on property and tax on 
     <lb/>
     business. Prior to 1942, Nova Scotia and New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick also taxed income, but now and for 
     <lb/>
     the next five years the Dominion government 
     <lb/>
     alone will tax income in all provinces except 
     <lb/>
     Ontario, Quebec and Nova Scotia, who still retain 
     <lb/>
     the right to tax incomes as well. Under confed<lb break="no"/>eration the town councils have the right to tax all 
     <lb/>
     real property, that is to say your house and land, 
     <lb/>
     your boats and nets, your barn and farming equip<lb break="no"/>ment, or any other kind of property, as also any 
     <lb/>
     improvements which you may make on these 
     <lb/>
     properties. If you are unable to pay these taxes on 
     <lb/>
     your property, the municipality or town council 
     <lb/>
     has the right to take it and sell it or rent it, and as 
     <lb/>
     a matter of actual fact the total amount of property 
     <lb/>
     taken from the individual property holders in 
     <lb/>
     Canada by town councils up to the year 1943, by 
     <lb/>
     reason of the fact that the owners or householders 
     <lb/>
     could not pay their taxes, was $88,484,188. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     However, you cannot have roads and educa<lb break="no"/>tion and public welfare unless you pay for it by 
     <lb/>
     way of taxation, and since the provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ments of New Brunswick and Nova Scotia and 
     <lb/>
     the others have surrendered most of their taxing 
     <lb/>
     powers to the Dominion government under the 
     <lb/>
     present system of confederation, the burden of 
     <lb/>
     the maintenance of said roads, education and 
     <lb/>
     public welfare must be borne by the municipality 
     <lb/>
     or town council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The trend today in Canada is to nullify the 
     <lb/>
     usefulness of the provincial governments and 
     <lb/>
     concentrate all power and authority at Ottawa, so 
     <lb/>
     that eventually they may have just one govern<lb break="no"/>ment at Ottawa, and the municipal authorities 
     <lb/>
     throughout Canada, constituting the Government 
     <lb/>
     of Canada. It is <hi rendition="simple:italic">just this</hi> that all the provinces of 
     <lb/>
     Canada last year fought out bitterly with the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion government, and against which only 
     <lb/>
     Ontario, Quebec and Nova Scotia were strong 
     <lb/>
     enough financially and morally to successfully 
     <lb/>
     contend. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To fairly understand the position, sir, of 
     <lb/>
     Canadian finance at the present time, we have to 
     <lb/>
     remember that during the period 1930-1937 the 
     <lb/>
     combined revenues of provinces and 
   

            <cb/>
      

     municipalities fell short of total relief and current 
     <lb/>
     expenditures by over $750 million; and this in 
     <lb/>
     spite of ruthless cuts on account of education and 
     <lb/>
     health services, and the restriction of relief pay<lb break="no"/>ments in many areas to little more than the barest 
     <lb/>
     needs for existence. By 1937 the whole provin<lb break="no"/>cial financial structure was falling about the 
     <lb/>
     govemment's ears, so much so that the various 
     <lb/>
     provincial bodies were unable to issue securities 
     <lb/>
     on the New York stock market when they had 
     <lb/>
     obligations falling due. Temporary assistance 
     <lb/>
     was given by the Dominion government and on 
     <lb/>
     the recommendation of the Governor of the Bank 
     <lb/>
     of Canada, a royal commission was set up on 
     <lb/>
     August 1, 1937. After three years this Rowell- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Sirois Commission made its report and recom<lb break="no"/>mendations, but 1 need not go into that. The plan 
     <lb/>
     was endorsed by the Dominion government, and 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">this</hi> was the plan which subsequently was 
     <lb/>
     employed as a basis for discussion at the con<lb break="no"/>ference of January, 1941 — which as you will 
     <lb/>
     remember, proved a dismal failure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hepburn of Ontario thought the publication of 
     <lb/>
     the report and the conference ill-timed and com<lb break="no"/>plained of the $500,000 cost of the report. He held 
     <lb/>
     that great financial concerns and wealthy in<lb break="no"/>dividuals who were holders of provincial bonds 
     <lb/>
     had engineered the report. He also objected to the 
     <lb/>
     surrender to a central authority of rights and 
     <lb/>
     privileges granted under the British North 
     <lb/>
     America Act. Most of the premiers spoke against 
     <lb/>
     the Sirois recommendations, and refused to sit in 
     <lb/>
     further conferences. Said Hepburn, "I will not 
     <lb/>
     sell my province down the river for all time to 
     <lb/>
     come and allow our social services to remain a 
     <lb/>
     victim of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">dictatorial methods of a 
     <lb/>
     bureaucracy to be set up in Ottawa</hi>." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     However, although three provincial premiers 
     <lb/>
     had refused to even sit down to discuss the 
     <lb/>
     Rowell-Sirois Report, they all agreed to sur<lb break="no"/>render income tax collection to the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     government for the duration of the war and for 
     <lb/>
     one year thereafter, as did also the municipalities. 
     <lb/>
     As a result the municipalities were compensated 
     <lb/>
     yearly to the amount of $86 million, Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>
     receiving less than $3 million. What would we 
     <lb/>
     have got, I wonder? The Dominion finance min<lb break="no"/>ister then proceeded to step up rates on personal 
     <lb/>
     and corporation incomes to the highest possible 
     <lb/>
     point, collecting nearly $1,000 million in 1943 
     <lb/>
     from these sources alone as against $123 million 


            <pb n="1010" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1010.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1010</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
         

     collected by the government and municipalities 
     <lb/>
     in 1940. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     So great was the opposition to the Rowell- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Sirois Report in 1941, that the recommendations 
     <lb/>
     used as a basis for discussion at the conference of 
     <lb/>
     provincial premiers in 1945-46 were a new and 
     <lb/>
     fresh approach to the problem of Dominion- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     provincial relations. The agenda was to em<lb break="no"/>phasise full employment and high national in<lb break="no"/>come. If, it said, employment and income can be 
     <lb/>
     maintained at a high level all our problems are 
     <lb/>
     manageable: if we fall seriously short they may 
     <lb/>
     be overwhelming. Previous Dominion-provin<lb break="no"/>cial conferences had been called when most of 
     <lb/>
     the provinces were in financial difficulties. The 
     <lb/>
     1945-46 conference, however, was assembled 
     <lb/>
     when each and all could balance their budgets. 
     <lb/>
     The Dominion government, however, was carry<lb break="no"/>ing a staggering burden of debt. In 1940 its na<lb break="no"/>tional debt was only $4 billion. in 1945 it was $13 
     <lb/>
     billion and mounting; the interest on the national 
     <lb/>
     debt would exceed the entire current expenditure 
     <lb/>
     on all services before the war. On top of this there 
     <lb/>
     was the matter of civil re-establishment of her 
     <lb/>
     soldiers, which would run into many billions. I 
     <lb/>
     want to point out now the disunity between the 
     <lb/>
     provinces, because I think Newfoundland should 
     <lb/>
     know the relationships between the various 
     <lb/>
     provinces in the Dominion of Canada before 
     <lb/>
     herself making the plunge. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The conference of Dominion and provincial 
     <lb/>
     premiers met in the House of Commons on the 
     <lb/>
     morning of August 6, 1945. The Rt. Hon. W.L. 
     <lb/>
     Mackenzie King occupied the Chair. The person<lb break="no"/>nel of the premiers had changed considerably 
     <lb/>
     since the conference of 1941, and it was hoped 
     <lb/>
     that some real settlement of Dominion — provin<lb break="no"/>cial differences could be accomplished. In spite 
     <lb/>
     of the almost superhuman efforts of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion prime minister, it was doomed to 
     <lb/>
     failure. No comprehensive plan for the whole of 
     <lb/>
     Canada could be arrived at, and after nine months 
     <lb/>
     the whole conference came to an abrupt end, 
     <lb/>
     Prime Minister King in his opening address on 
     <lb/>
     August 6 said that 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     an effort is being made to ensure the maxi<lb break="no"/>mum of co-operation between the federal 
     <lb/>
     government and the governments of the 
     <lb/>
     provinces, in order that the Canadian people, 
     <lb/>
     working together, may achieve the construc<lb break="no"/>tive goal of peace as effectively as they have 
  

            <cb/>
        

     carried on the essential though inevitable 
     <lb/>
     destructive talk of war. Further. just as our 
     <lb/>
     fighting men have assured our freedom, so 
     <lb/>
     may we use that freedom to win the victories 
     <lb/>
     over depression, over unemployment. over 
     <lb/>
     insecurity and over want, victories over 
     <lb/>
     prejudice, over intolerance and over disunity. 
            </p>

</quote>

<p>
     Brave words these, Mr. Chairman. Let me see 
     <lb/>
     how difficult of accomplishment they were. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The matter of taxation was the great stumbling 
     <lb/>
     block. Said Premier Drew of Ontario, "If the 
     <lb/>
     provincial legislatures were to continue as free 
     <lb/>
     and responsible legislative bodies within the con<lb break="no"/>ception of the British North America Act, then it 
     <lb/>
     would seem clear that the provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ments must have authority over their own taxa<lb break="no"/>tion within clearly defined fields". He pointed to 
     <lb/>
     what he termed "the fundamental weakness of 
     <lb/>
     the British North America Act, the restriction of 
     <lb/>
     the provinces to direct taxation and the authority 
     <lb/>
     given the Dominion government to raise money 
     <lb/>
     in any form of taxation". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Premier Duplessis said, "We are opposed to 
     <lb/>
     centralisation of power. We are here to col<lb break="no"/>laborate and co-operate. Co-operation and 
     <lb/>
     collaboration can never exist where solemn 
     <lb/>
     pledges are disregarded and pacts are violated. 
     <lb/>
     An accumulation of powers leads to autonomy. 
     <lb/>
     Centralisation leads to Hitlerism." He said he 
     <lb/>
     regarded the British North America Act as a 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">solemn contract</hi>. They had been granted certain 
     <lb/>
     taxing powers under the Act, and unless they 
     <lb/>
     were allowed to exercise these powers they could 
     <lb/>
     not carry out their legislative duties to their 
     <lb/>
     people in the provinces and municipalities. Now 
     <lb/>
     Ontario and Quebec are the wealthy provinces, 
     <lb/>
     88% of all invested capital in Canada is con<lb break="no"/>centrated in these two provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Nova Scotia premier was a bit more con<lb break="no"/>ciliatory. Premier McNair of New Brunswick 
     <lb/>
     spoke of the economic plight of his province, to 
     <lb/>
     which geography, national policy and monopo<lb break="no"/>listic competition from other parts of Canada had 
     <lb/>
     been basic contributing factors. New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick's per capita income was just about the 
     <lb/>
     lowest in Canada. The remedy, he said, lay with 
     <lb/>
     the federal authorities through their exclusive 
     <lb/>
     control of tariffs, trades, freight rates, credit and 
     <lb/>
     monetary policy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Premier Hart of British Columbia expressed 
     <lb/>
     the belief that it was still an indispensable feature 
    

            <pb n="1011" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1011.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1011</fw>
        

     of responsible government that the provinces 
     <lb/>
     should raise their own revenues by their own tax 
     <lb/>
     laws, and not have to depend on handouts from 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Premier Jones painted a gloomy picture of his 
     <lb/>
     province. "Prince Edward Island", he said, "had 
     <lb/>
     not sought to enter into confederation. It was 
     <lb/>
     Canada that had sought to bring PEI into con<lb break="no"/>federation. At that time they were relatively well- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     off. That had now changed, and they had 
     <lb/>
     gradually been reduced to a rather unprosperous 
     <lb/>
     state." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Premier Manning of Alberta wanted a definite 
     <lb/>
     understanding about respective fields of 
     <lb/>
     Dominion and provincial jurisdiction, a fair and 
     <lb/>
     equal adjustment of such burdens as freight rates 
     <lb/>
     and tariffs, a settlement of taxation and monetary 
     <lb/>
     issues in which Dominion policy has an adverse 
     <lb/>
     effect on the provinces. He reviewed the fiscal 
     <lb/>
     experience of the province from confederation 
     <lb/>
     until their situation became acute with the depres<lb break="no"/>sion of 1930. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And so it was in this spirit that the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     proposals were formally placed before the con<lb break="no"/>ference. The proposals of the Dominion govern<lb break="no"/>ment were in three sections: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. There was an outline of the philosophy 
     <lb/>
     with which they proposed to attack Canada's 
     <lb/>
     post-war problems. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. There was a summary of the plans which 
     <lb/>
     the government hoped to adopt for an orderly 
     <lb/>
     transition from war to peace. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. This consisted of the actual proposals for 
     <lb/>
     the post-war years. It was this third section of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion proposals which the provincial 
     <lb/>
     premiers generally would have none of. It offered 
     <lb/>
     substantial grants to each of the provinces, on 
     <lb/>
     condition that they withdrew completely from the 
     <lb/>
     fields of personal and corporation income taxes 
     <lb/>
     and succession duties, leaving these taxes solely 
     <lb/>
     for collection by the Dominion government. In 
     <lb/>
     return the Dominion government offered: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. A public investment policy whereby the 
     <lb/>
     central government would pay 20% of the cost of 
     <lb/>
     provincial and municipal public works, provided 
     <lb/>
     they were executed within a period named by the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. A social security programme, embracing a 
     <lb/>
     national health programme, a national old age 
     <lb/>
     pension scheme at age 70, Dominion-provincial 
     <lb/>
     old age assistance at age 65 - 69, unemployment 


            <cb/>
          

     assistance for unemployed employables. That 
     <lb/>
     would be in our country fishermen, unemployed 
     <lb/>
     employable, at certain times of the year. I think 
     <lb/>
     it would also include not only fishermen, but 
     <lb/>
     agriculture, forestry, lumbering, logging, 
     <lb/>
     transportation, and various other things. Further, 
     <lb/>
     in view of the fact that succession duties also 
     <lb/>
     would be given up by the provinces, the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion government would make a grant of 
     <lb/>
     $12 per head of population. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the first presentation of these proposals all 
     <lb/>
     the premiers merely accepted them as a basis of 
     <lb/>
     argument. Premier Jones of PEI spoke of the very 
     <lb/>
     unsatisfactory economic history of his province 
     <lb/>
     under confederation. The revenues were not 
     <lb/>
     capable of much expansion. The deficits grew 
     <lb/>
     year by year. "The intention of confederation", 
     <lb/>
     he said, "was for each province to have a fair 
     <lb/>
     share of the commercial benefits. The federal 
     <lb/>
     parliament has failed to function as intended, and 
     <lb/>
     as the Maritimes were promised it would func<lb break="no"/>tion. The conditions are blighting the native 
     <lb/>
     genius of our people." The premiers of the other 
     <lb/>
     eight provinces had further caustic remarks to 
     <lb/>
     make with regard to the Dominion government's 
     <lb/>
     plan. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A committee then was formed consisting of 
     <lb/>
     Mr. King, three Dominion ministers and nine 
     <lb/>
     provincial premiers to study the plan. They met 
     <lb/>
     in private session on August 9, 1945, but imme<lb break="no"/>diately adjourned until November 26. It sat until 
     <lb/>
     November 30, then adjourned until January 28, 
     <lb/>
     1946, when it sat for a further five days and 
     <lb/>
     adjourned again until April 25. It then was 
     <lb/>
     decided to meet in public session on April 29. 
     <lb/>
     These public sessions lasted four days, when the 
     <lb/>
     premier of Quebec left for his home in disgust. I 
     <lb/>
     give you, sir, this brief account of the period of 
     <lb/>
     sessions to show how deep-seated is the rift in 
     <lb/>
     Dominion-provincial relations and how far they 
     <lb/>
     are from agreement on any policy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let us see what happened at this public session 
     <lb/>
     which began on April 29, 1946, after nine months 
     <lb/>
     of study by the provincial governments. Each 
     <lb/>
     province prior to April 29 had made written 
     <lb/>
     replies, criticisms and counter-proposals. It was 
     <lb/>
     found that eight provinces attacked the proposals 
     <lb/>
     and the ninth province rejected the whole plan 
     <lb/>
     even as a basis of negotiations. Five of the nine 
     <lb/>
     provinces suggested that certain tax fields should 
     <lb/>
     be left to the provinces. Three provinces 
   

            <pb n="1012" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1012.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1012</fw>
         

     criticised the inadequacy of the provisions for 
     <lb/>
     unemployment relief since the "self-employed", 
     <lb/>
     such as fishermen, who in certain economic areas 
     <lb/>
     might far exceed the number of wage earners, 
     <lb/>
     were left as a local responsibility. You can see 
     <lb/>
     how much that would affect us here in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. Three of the provinces disclaimed the 
     <lb/>
     entire philosophy of the Dominion plan in that it 
     <lb/>
     would eventually destroy the autonomy of the 
     <lb/>
     provinces and hence the whole idea of federation. 
     <lb/>
     Many other objections were brought forward by 
     <lb/>
     individual provinces. All their objections gave an 
     <lb/>
     advance idea of what was to happen at the public 
     <lb/>
     sessions of April 29 to May 3 when the con<lb break="no"/>ference broke up. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When later the per capita rate of grant was 
     <lb/>
     raised which brought the Prince Edward Island 
     <lb/>
     grant from the Dominion government up to $22 
     <lb/>
     per capita, Premier J. Walter Jones of that 
     <lb/>
     province insisted that it would still leave the 
     <lb/>
     province $1 million short of what it would need. 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia said also that such a per capita grant 
     <lb/>
     would be far from sufficient. Premier Drew 
     <lb/>
     stated that its acceptance by the Province of On<lb break="no"/>tario would result in a $15 million deficit per 
     <lb/>
     year. Premier Duplessis compared the small sum 
     <lb/>
     which Quebec would receive with the large sums 
     <lb/>
     collected out of the province by Dominion taxa<lb break="no"/>tion in recent years. Douglas of Saskatchewan 
     <lb/>
     stated that a subsidy based on population was 
     <lb/>
     unscientific and that there was no relationship 
     <lb/>
     between population and needs — and so it was 
     <lb/>
     with all the provinces. Said Ontario's premier, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     If the provinces were to abandon their 
     <lb/>
     most important sources of direct taxation in 
     <lb/>
     return for an annual payment on a fixed basis, 
     <lb/>
     they would place themselves in a legislative 
     <lb/>
     strait-jacket from which they could only es<lb break="no"/>cape by abandoning still further powers in 
     <lb/>
     return for added payments at some future 
     <lb/>
     date. They would become little more than 
     <lb/>
     local administrative commissions of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion government, which would ul<lb break="no"/>timately mean the abandonment of the basic 
     <lb/>
     idea of federation and the British North 
     <lb/>
     America Act, and the eventual result would 
     <lb/>
     be despotism. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>
     Premier Duplessis voiced the same idea when he 
     <lb/>
     said that 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>The evils of centralisation mean totali<lb break="no"/>tarianism in the end.... The exclusive rights 
    

            <cb/>
           

     of the provinces in matters of social legisla<lb break="no"/>tion, education, civil law, etc., should be 
     <lb/>
     conserved one by one and safeguarded, if 
     <lb/>
     confederation is to survive. The federal 
     <lb/>
     proposals would destroy the inalienable 
     <lb/>
     rights of all the provinces: then tend to estab<lb break="no"/>lish and increase the growth of bureaucracy 
     <lb/>
     which does not suit and can never suit either 
     <lb/>
     a democracy or a country ruled by parliamen<lb break="no"/>tary institutions. 
     <lb/>
   </p>
</quote>

            <p>It was evident to the Dominion government that 
     <lb/>their proposals would not be acceptable, and so 
     <lb/>they made other offers to the premiers. They were 
     <lb/>briefly as follows. In return for specified pay<lb break="no"/>ments to the provinces the Dominion government 
     <lb/>proposed that the provinces undertake, for the 
     <lb/>next three years, not to levy income, corporation 
     <lb/>and succession duties taxation. The annual pay<lb break="no"/>ment was a guaranteed minimum of not less than 
     <lb/>$15 per capita based on the population either in 
     <lb/>1941 or 1942 as the provinces might elect. It was 
     <lb/>to rise with national income and population. I 
     <lb/>want you to know that under this tax agreement 
     <lb/>the subsidy which we shall get depends on two 
     <lb/>variable things. It depends on increase in popula<lb break="no"/>tion, and it depends on the gross national product 
     <lb/>of Canada — two variables, and I shall point out 
     <lb/>to you later just how they did vary. Under this 
     <lb/>proposal PEI was to receive $2 million in 1947, 
     <lb/>Nova Scotia $10 million and New Brunswick 
     <lb/>$7.5 million. The Dominion government was 
     <lb/>also prepared to allow the provinces to make tax 
     <lb/>levies on mining and logging operations. Further, 
     <lb/>the Dominion government was prepared to seek 
     <lb/>an amendment to the constitution so as to enable 
     <lb/>the provinces to levy an <hi rendition="simple:italic">indirect tax on retail 
     <lb/>sales</hi>. It also would allow the provinces to tax 
     <lb/>property. They also were prepared to pay part of 
     <lb/>the burden of health services, to the extent of 40 
     <lb/>cents per head of population. Assuming that we 
     <lb/>were a province that would amount to about 
     <lb/>$120,000. When we remember that our health 
     <lb/>estimates for this year are approximately $6 mil<lb break="no"/>lion we can see how insignificant such help 
     <lb/>would be to us. They would take care of old age 
     <lb/>pensions and grant some unemployment assis<lb break="no"/>tance. Altogether this was a much better offer, but 
     <lb/>still the provincial premiers decided they could 
     <lb/>not agree. Nor <hi rendition="simple:italic">did</hi> they agree. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <p>The Premier of Ontario claimed that in 1945 
     <lb/>the Dominion government had collected over 


            <pb n="1013" facs="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1013.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1013</fw>
          

     $700 million from the people of that province 
     <lb/>
     alone on account of income and corporation 
     <lb/>
     taxes, and yet in return for the complete 
     <lb/>
     withdrawal not only from these fields, but also 
     <lb/>
     succession duties, the Dominion government 
     <lb/>
     now proposed to pay to the Government of On<lb break="no"/>tario $64 million. Premier Duplessis of Quebec 
     <lb/>
     also spoke strongly against the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     government plan, and described it as "the scut<lb break="no"/>tling of confederation". MacDonald of Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia pointed out that the provinces were left 
     <lb/>
     with "great and growing obligations" to their 
     <lb/>
     people, but to meet them the only exclusive fiels 
     <lb/>
     of taxation proposed to be left to the provinces 
     <lb/>
     are real estate and automobiles in the hands of 
     <lb/>
     their owners. He expressed the view that the 
     <lb/>
     provinces had made a bad bargain in confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. He predicted, and these are his words, that 
     <lb/>
     "Provincial autonomy will be gone, provincial 
     <lb/>
     independence will vanish, provincial dignity will 
     <lb/>
     disappear, provincial governments will become 
     <lb/>
     mere annuitants of Ottawa, provincial public life 
     <lb/>
     — and I do not think these words are too strong 
     <lb/>
     — will be debased and degraded". Premier Mc<lb break="no"/>Nair of New Brunswick spoke like MacDonald 
     <lb/>
     of Nova Scotia against the proposals. Premier 
     <lb/>
     Garson of Manitoba in his address made remarks 
     <lb/>
     which show only too clearly the differences be<lb break="no"/>tween the provinces, particularly between the 
     <lb/>
     provinces of Ontario and Québec and the com<lb break="no"/>paratively poor provinces, as did also Premier 
     <lb/>
     Hart of British Columbia. Premier Jones said that 
     <lb/>
     PEI had entered confederation upon the under<lb break="no"/>standing that it would receive from the federal 
     <lb/>
     government such subsidies as would enable it to 
     <lb/>
     carry on the public services allotted to the provin<lb break="no"/>cial government without resorting to direct taxa<lb break="no"/>tion. "The subsidies paid in the past to Prince 
     <lb/>
     Edward Island", he said, "and the amount now 
     <lb/>
     offered are totally inadequate." Premier Douglas 
     <lb/>
     of Saskatchewan expressed great disappointment 
     <lb/>
     over the Dominion government's proposals and 
     <lb/>
     stressed the need for an emergency grant to meet 
     <lb/>
     such crises as drought, crop failure and agricul<lb break="no"/>ture relief. Premier Manning of Alberta stated 
     <lb/>
     that the proposals failed to meet the conditions 
     <lb/>
     which his government thought necessary for a 
     <lb/>
     remedy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The conference then adjourned until May 1, 
     <lb/>
     1946, and then the Minister of Finance, next day, 
     <lb/>
     in a speech which lasted for 1 3/4 hours, stressed 
  

            <cb/>
        

     that in spite of the objections raised by the nine 
     <lb/>
     provincial premiers, the Dominion government 
     <lb/>
     would stand firm and had no intention of modify<lb break="no"/>ing the proposals. I would ask you to look at your 
     <lb/>
     Grey Book again, and see what Premier King 
     <lb/>
     says about the proposals: "it is the best we can 
     <lb/>
     offer". His speech only served to increase the 
     <lb/>
     anger of the premiers, and particularly so of those 
     <lb/>
     of Ontario and Quebec. Said Mr. Duplessis, "if 
     <lb/>
     the Ottawa proposals are in the nature of a 'take 
     <lb/>
     it or leave it', I will leave it and take my train back 
     <lb/>
     to Quebec." You will find that he did do that. 
     <lb/>
     Premiers MacDonald, Manning and Douglas also 
     <lb/>
     spoke that day, as also did Premier Drew of 
     <lb/>
     Ontario; and when the conference adjourned, the 
     <lb/>
     word "failure" could be written across the whole 
     <lb/>
     proceedings. Manning attacked what he called 
     <lb/>
     "the uncompromising rigidity" of the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     government. Their attitude, he said, was "in<lb break="no"/>defensible" and he laid the responsibility for 
     <lb/>
     failure on the doorstep of the Dominion govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Drew of Ontario complained, as had 
     <lb/>
     Duplessis, of the 'take it or leave it' attitude of 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian government. He commended to 
     <lb/>
     Finance Minister Ilsley the careful reading "of a 
     <lb/>
     book called Mein Kampf." He said he would find 
     <lb/>
     there clearly set out the formula that the authority 
     <lb/>
     of small individual states ought to be diminished 
     <lb/>
     and their power invested in a central government. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Ilsley, he said, had spoken of a "heavy 
     <lb/>
     obligation" involved in carrying health in<lb break="no"/>surance, baby bonuses and old age pensions, <hi rendition="simple:italic">but 
     <lb/>
     it happens, he said, that there were to be financed 
     <lb/>
     by new levies upon the taxpayers</hi>. He, Mr. Drew, 
     <lb/>
     was certainly opposed to double taxation in any 
     <lb/>
     and every field. Subsidies, repeated Mr. Duples<lb break="no"/>sis, cannot compensate for permanent rights. 
     <lb/>
     Centralisation gave birth to bureaucracy, and 
     <lb/>
     bureaucracy was the enemy of democracy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The rest of that day, sir, was spent in a wran<lb break="no"/>gling spirit of angry speechmaking, something 
     <lb/>
     like we get here sometimes, and the sitting ad<lb break="no"/>journed until next morning, May 3, when Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Ilsley endeavoured to show how utterly impos<lb break="no"/>sible for the Dominion was the counter-proposal 
     <lb/>
     of the Ontario premier. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     More speeches in the same tone as on the day 
     <lb/>
     before were made. "Ontario has gone the limit", 
     <lb/>
     said Drew. Duplessis said, "Dominion proposals 
     <lb/>
     were not acceptable to Quebec." He again quoted 
     <lb/>
     Sir Wilfred Laurier as saying that, "A policy of 
  

            <pb n="1014" facs="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1014.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1014</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> 
   

     federal subsidies was wrong, and always led to 
     <lb/>
     extravagance." He quoted Mackenzie King him<lb break="no"/>self as saying in 1930, "that it was a vicious 
     <lb/>
     principle to have one body raise the taxes and 
     <lb/>
     another body spend the people's money thus 
     <lb/>
     raised." When the conference resumed its sitting 
     <lb/>
     after lunch Premier Duplessis was not present. 
     <lb/>
     He had gone back to Quebec City as he had 
     <lb/>
     threatened, and after another 1 3/4 hours, the 
     <lb/>
     conference adjourned and it has not again been 
     <lb/>
     reconvened. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Certain provinces have since made five-year 
     <lb/>
     agreements with the Dominion government, 
     <lb/>
     whilst others have refused to do so, that is to say, 
     <lb/>
     Ontario, Quebec and Nova Scotia. This, very 
     <lb/>
     briefly, is the story of a Canada united in war, but 
     <lb/>
     greatly divided in peace. This is the Canada 
     <lb/>
     which we, as Newfoundlanders are asked to 
     <lb/>
     pledge our word to unite with. I ask you 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen to consider it well. You have heard the 
     <lb/>
     opinions of the prime ministers of the various 
     <lb/>
     provinces of Canada. I take it they are the best 
     <lb/>
     men that Canada can produce. These are their 
     <lb/>
     reflections on the tax agreement which has been 
     <lb/>
     offered to Newfoundland today. We have no 
     <lb/>
     prime minister, we have no parliament, we have 
     <lb/>
     no place where men can get together with a 
     <lb/>
     mandate from the people, as did Duplessis and 
     <lb/>
     Drew and all the others. These men came 
     <lb/>
     together and consulted and they came to the 
     <lb/>
     conclusions as I have just quoted, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There are certain things, sir, which stand out 
     <lb/>
     very clearly: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. All provincial premiers agree that the 
     <lb/>
     provincial governments can best look after the 
     <lb/>
     welfare of their own people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. To do this they must have money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. To get the money they should be able to 
     <lb/>
     adjust their own taxes in certain fields, and not be 
     <lb/>
     in the position of beggars to the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     government.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. In a changing world both economically and 
     <lb/>
     with regard to social services, a govern-ment's 
     <lb/>
     revenue must also change from year to year. It 
     <lb/>
     cannot be bound by fixed subsidies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. A people's welfare is subject to the hazards 
     <lb/>
     of their occupations, and the hazards of the 
     <lb/>
     fisheries, mining, lumbering, manufacturing, 
     <lb/>
     etc., are all different, and consequently the 
     <lb/>
     elected government in every area, whose duty is 
     <lb/>
     towards the people's well-being, cannot have its 
  

            <cb/>
        

     hands tied. There must be a certain flexibility. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     What of us in Newfoundland? Shall we rush 
     <lb/>
     blindly into something upon which the nine 
     <lb/>
     provinces of Canada, after many months of 
     <lb/>
     deliberation, themselves cannot agree? Now 
     <lb/>
     having the picture of Canada under confederation 
     <lb/>
     before us, let us take a look at what Mr. Macken<lb break="no"/>zie King and his Dominion government have to 
     <lb/>
     offer Newfoundlanders. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Short recess]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, I come now to a 
     <lb/>
     consideration of the terms which have been 
     <lb/>
     brought back from Canada. I will try to be as brief 
     <lb/>
     as I can, but I do not expect to be able to finish 
     <lb/>
     this by the time we conclude. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now when we look at these documents which 
     <lb/>
     have been brought back from Canada by the 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa delegation, it will be well for us first to 
     <lb/>
     refer to the letter of Prime Minister King, in 
     <lb/>
     which he says that he was of the opinion that the 
     <lb/>
     questions to be discussed with the delegation are 
     <lb/>
     of such complexity and of such significance for 
     <lb/>
     both countries that it is essential to have a com<lb break="no"/>plete and comprehensive exchange of informa<lb break="no"/>tion, and a full and careful exploration by both 
     <lb/>
     parties of the issues involved, so that an accurate 
     <lb/>
     appreciation of the position may be guaranteed 
     <lb/>
     on each side. There was one gentleman who fully 
     <lb/>
     appreciated the significance of Newfoundland's 
     <lb/>
     entering into union with Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Well, what did our delegation do? We have 
     <lb/>
     some idea now of what they did. They got 
     <lb/>
     together certain facts and figures here before they 
     <lb/>
     went to Ottawa, put them together and went off 
     <lb/>
     to Ottawa, only to discover that these things 
     <lb/>
     which were brought back to us from Canada had 
     <lb/>
     been prepared months before they went up there. 
     <lb/>
     That to me looks very funny. The proposed ar<lb break="no"/>rangements, as I stated before, are set forth in the 
     <lb/>
     document, the Grey Book, and Mr. King, Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister King again says, "I feel I must em<lb break="no"/>phasise that as far as the financial aspects of the 
     <lb/>
     proposed arrangements for union are concerned, 
     <lb/>
     the Government of Canada believes that the ar<lb break="no"/>rangements go as far as the government can go 
     <lb/>
     under the circumstances." The government could 
     <lb/>
     not readily contemplate any change in those ar<lb break="no"/>rangements, so what you have, you have in the 
     <lb/>
     Grey Book, and Prime Minister King says there 
     <lb/>
     is to be, as far as he can see, no change what<lb break="no"/>soever there. 
  

            <pb n="1015" facs="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1015.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1015</fw>
     

     Now let's take a look first at the services 
     <lb/>
     which will be taken over by Canada. You will 
     <lb/>
     find those in section 5. You have all read it, and 
     <lb/>
     I don't need to go over it.... Now let's look at the 
     <lb/>
     financial arrangements, and first as to the public 
     <lb/>
     debt, let's take a squint at that. Canada, as you 
     <lb/>
     know, will assume and provide for the servicing 
     <lb/>
     of the debt now guaranteed by the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom, that is $63,569,074. Now what hap<lb break="no"/>pens really is this, gentlemen, that the guarantee 
     <lb/>
     of our debt would simply change hands from the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Britain to the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, for mark you, our Newfoundland people 
     <lb/>
     would still raise the money to pay the interest. 
     <lb/>
     Don't forget that. Don't let us have our people 
     <lb/>
     think that Canada is wiping out the debt. She is 
     <lb/>
     just putting herself in the same position that Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain is today, as a guarantor of our debt, but 
     <lb/>
     don't forget that she will see to it that we people 
     <lb/>
     in Newfoundland will service that debt by the 
     <lb/>
     taxes which she will impose upon us. And 
     <lb/>
     another point, if I were a bondholder under that 
     <lb/>
     debt I would as soon have the guarantee of Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain as I would that of Canada. Be that as it 
     <lb/>
     may, I want you to note that Canada, in taking 
     <lb/>
     over our debt does nothing to help us along these 
     <lb/>
     lines whatsoever. We would pay for the servicing 
     <lb/>
     of the debt under confederation as we pay it now, 
     <lb/>
     through taxes, only it will be administered by the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion government. Well, let's say that dis<lb break="no"/>poses of the sterling debt, but remember that we 
     <lb/>
     would still be left, as a new province of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     with a total debt of $10,465,593, besides interest 
     <lb/>
     at from 3.75% to 3%. Canada does not guarantee 
     <lb/>
     this interest for us. This interest, with our local 
     <lb/>
     dollar debt of $10 million, is at the present time 
     <lb/>
     practically $500,000, when you add on the 
     <lb/>
     $123,000 which our friend from Bonavista 
     <lb/>
     Centre forgot. You will find that the interest on 
     <lb/>
     our national debt is $499,000 and some odd 
     <lb/>
     hundred dollars, practically $500,000, and that is 
     <lb/>
     the first charge on the new province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now let us take a look at where our revenue 
     <lb/>
     came from this year— I think that 1947-48 would 
     <lb/>
     be as good a guide as any other. The Customs 
     <lb/>
     Department gave us $19.5 million. As a province 
     <lb/>
     we give that up completely. Posts and Telegraphs 
     <lb/>
     gave us $1.7 million. That too, we surrender to 
     <lb/>
     Canada. The Assessor's Office yielded $10.5 
     <lb/>
     million. That too Canada takes over, only more 
     <lb/>
     so on account of higher taxes in Canada. Home 


            <cb/>
        

     Affairs gave us $194,000, and that's out, practi<lb break="no"/>cally. Education will yield the provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ment nothing. Last year the Justice Department 
     <lb/>
     was supposed to yield $47,000. Natural Resour<lb break="no"/>ces and Public Health and Welfare yield precious 
     <lb/>
     small amounts as we know. In other words, prac<lb break="no"/>tically all revenue producing sources are handed 
     <lb/>
     over to Canada. Now let us assume, and I am not 
     <lb/>
     talking about the latest budget brought in, but the 
     <lb/>
     budget prepared by the Ottawa delegation in 
     <lb/>
     these books, let us assume that these figures of 
     <lb/>
     revenue as a province are correct, or practically 
     <lb/>
     so. They say the yield will be $1.25 million. On 
     <lb/>
     that they added, for a large profit, $1 million, and 
     <lb/>
     that makes a total provincial revenue of $2.25 
     <lb/>
     million. Now what monies do we get from 
     <lb/>
     Canada? You have it outlined there in your Grey 
     <lb/>
     Book. They give you $6.8 million. I think it is. 
     <lb/>
     But remember that's their estimate, based upon 
     <lb/>
     the irreducible minimum and the adjusted sub<lb break="no"/>sidy, which, as I already pointed out, depends on 
     <lb/>
     two variables: the increase in your population, 
     <lb/>
     and the increase or otherwise in the gross national 
     <lb/>
     product of Canada. The gross national product I 
     <lb/>
     think you all understand. Now I want you to look 
     <lb/>
     at page 148, book 1, and turn over to the next 
     <lb/>
     page, and see what I have taken. Instead of taking, 
     <lb/>
     as the Ottawa delegation did, the adjusted figure 
     <lb/>
     of $6.8 million, I have taken the irreducible min<lb break="no"/>imum, and that is $15 per head of the population, 
     <lb/>
     and the statutory subsidies, the irreducible mini<lb break="no"/>mum. I want you to look at this particular list of 
     <lb/>
     figures here, and you will find that the minimum, 
     <lb/>
     for instance in Nova Scotia in 1944, was 
     <lb/>
     $12,524,000, and the next year it was 
     <lb/>
     $12,244,000, and the next year, 1946, it was 
     <lb/>
     $11,521,000. Then they take a three year average, 
     <lb/>
     and they say, "For 1947 the Nova Scotia subsidy 
     <lb/>
     will be $12,096,000." Well, if you look back to 
     <lb/>
     1944 you will see that it was $12,544,000, prac<lb break="no"/>tically $500,000 less than the estimated figure for 
     <lb/>
     1947. Then you can look all along these figures 
     <lb/>
     and you will find that in every one of these 
     <lb/>
     provinces, the estimate for 1947 under this tax 
     <lb/>
     agreement is far, in some cases $1 million, below 
     <lb/>
     that which it was in 1944. Why? Why was it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Which it would have been... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Why was it? Why say, "It would 
     <lb/>
     have been"? It is immaterial. Why should it have 
     <lb/>
     been? Simply because there was a change in the 
     <lb/>
     population of the province, and there was a 
   
            <pb n="1016" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1016.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1016</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
       

     change in the gross national product of Canada. 
     <lb/>
     Therefore I say this which the Ottawa delegation 
     <lb/>
     has brought in — $6.8 million — is something 
     <lb/>
     which we cannot take for granted. We don't 
     <lb/>
     know what the gross national product is going to 
     <lb/>
     be this year, or next year, or the year after. The 
     <lb/>
     gross national product in Canada in 1944 and 
     <lb/>
     earlier was tremendous. Why? Because they 
     <lb/>
     were working and turning out guns, ammunition 
     <lb/>
     and ships, and all sorts of war material to send 
     <lb/>
     across to win this war. That in itself gave employ<lb break="no"/>ment to people and put up the gross national 
     <lb/>
     product as never before in the history of Canada. 
     <lb/>
     The war ends, and as soon as the war ends all that 
     <lb/>
     industry has to cease, and has to be changed over 
     <lb/>
     to peace time industry, and it is inconceivable to 
     <lb/>
     think that Canada could, in such a few years, get 
     <lb/>
     back to the high peak of gross national product 
     <lb/>
     as it was in the war years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That figure of $6 million, I put the irreducible 
     <lb/>
     minimum in the books, and that's official — 
     <lb/>
     $6,211,000, and that is the only figure that we can 
     <lb/>
     take. You cannot take the $6.8 million, because 
     <lb/>
     by the time we, if we do, go into confederation, 
     <lb/>
     the gross national product of Canada may have 
     <lb/>
     changed to such an extent that we would not get 
     <lb/>
     any more than our gross irreducible minimum. 
     <lb/>
     To prove that, on the same page on which you are 
     <lb/>
     looking, you go to Saskatchewan. In 1944 Sas<lb break="no"/>katchewan received by way of subsidy, or would 
     <lb/>
     have received, $16,525,000. Now you notice in 
     <lb/>
     1946 they got $15,291,000, and you will notice 
     <lb/>
     Note D: "The adjusted figure being less than the 
     <lb/>
     guaranteed minimum, the guaranteed minimum 
     <lb/>
     is substituted." In other words, the population of 
     <lb/>
     Saskatchewan had changed, and if you go back 
     <lb/>
     to the population at the top of the page, you will 
     <lb/>
     find that the population in Saskatchewan in 1941 
     <lb/>
     was 895,000, in 1942 it was 883,000, in 1944 — 
     <lb/>
     858,000, in 1945 — 845,000 and still coming 
     <lb/>
     down. In 1946 it was 832,000, as against 895,992, 
     <lb/>
     so you see that change in the population in Sas<lb break="no"/>katchewan over that brief four of five years made 
     <lb/>
     such a difference in the amount that you would 
     <lb/>
     have been glad the irreducible minimum was put 
     <lb/>
     in there, so the federal government gave Sas<lb break="no"/>katchewan the irreducible minimum. So I take 
     <lb/>
     that figure. Yes, you will get that much, which is 
     <lb/>
     guaranteed, but anything more you cannot bank 
     <lb/>
     on. Now! Adding that and the revenues which I 
     <lb/>
     have already mentioned, this gives us a total 


            <cb/>
    

     revenue, more or less assured, of $8,461,756. 
     <lb/>
     From this we must take the amount before men<lb break="no"/>tioned for interest payment on our debt of 
     <lb/>
     $499,628, leaving $7,962,000, and that, 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen, is the amount of hard cash which you 
     <lb/>
     will have to run your province under confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, unless you are prepared to impose new 
     <lb/>
     taxation on the people. The Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada however, realises how hopeless that 
     <lb/>
     would be, save that in the first three years (this is 
     <lb/>
     a sop, now) they will give us an amount of $3.5 
     <lb/>
     million, or a transitional grant, in order to facili<lb break="no"/>tate the adjustment of Newfoundland to the status 
     <lb/>
     of a province, and note, "the development in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland of further revenue producing ser<lb break="no"/>vice". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In other words then, your revenue in the first 
     <lb/>
     three years of confederation will be, after paying 
     <lb/>
     the interest on your debt, $11,462.128. After the 
     <lb/>
     first three years this amount of transitional grants 
     <lb/>
     is reduced each year by $350,000, until at the end 
     <lb/>
     of the twelfth year you are back where you 
     <lb/>
     started, and the amount is $7.9 million, or practi<lb break="no"/>cally $8 million, unless you increase taxation, 
     <lb/>
     and we understood that we have to. We must 
     <lb/>
     increase taxation if we are to partake of the 
     <lb/>
     glories of confederation. Mark that down. You 
     <lb/>
     have to increase taxation in this country if you 
     <lb/>
     want to go into confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Somebody will say, "Oh yes, but you won't 
     <lb/>
     have any customs duties to pay." Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
     will tell you. Gentlemen, I put it to you, if we 
     <lb/>
     enter into confederation it is the plan of Canada 
     <lb/>
     that we shall buy all the goods that she can make 
     <lb/>
     us buy. We are going to buy from Canada, don't 
     <lb/>
     worry about that, and isn't it reasonable to expect 
     <lb/>
     that the manufacturers will take advantage of 
     <lb/>
     that, and put the prices up to such an extent that 
     <lb/>
     the amounts which our people will pay for the 
     <lb/>
     things which they will buy from Canada will be 
     <lb/>
     about on a par with those which the people have 
     <lb/>
     to pay today under our customs duties. I don't 
     <lb/>
     think there is any question of that. I think, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood, you will agree with that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> All that's very sound, you 
     <lb/>
     could not deny that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> No question about it at all. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, not at all. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> There is no question about that at 
     <lb/>
     all, but your provincial government — 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood will probably be prime minister 
   

            <pb n="1017" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-11_Page_1017.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1017</fw>
         

     — will not be so stupid as to allow that, because 
     <lb/>
     by that time they will have employed some or all 
     <lb/>
     of their multitudinous forms of taxation now 
     <lb/>
     known in Canada, such as taxes for your lands.... 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Cod traps. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Oh yes, on your cod traps — I 
     <lb/>
     would not think you would tax Labrador cod 
     <lb/>
     traps, at any rate — taxes on your trees if you like, 
     <lb/>
     or in other words stumpage rates, sales tax, tax on 
     <lb/>
     amusements, education tax, poll tax or head tax, 
     <lb/>
     a poor tax and dozens of others. Mr. Chairman, 
     <lb/>
     if anybody in this House says you are not going 
     <lb/>
     to have a land tax, a county rate and a school rate 
     <lb/>
     and a poor rate, they don't know what they are 
     <lb/>
     talking about. I hold here in my hand a tax notice 
     <lb/>
     issued by the municipality of Cape Breton Coun<lb break="no"/>ty to a poor man who is deceased, and the tax 
     <lb/>
     notice has come to the trustee or administrator of 
     <lb/>
     the estate. He had a piece of land when he died in 
     <lb/>
     Cape Breton County, valued at $100 — no house 
     <lb/>
     or anything on it. His assessment on that $100 
     <lb/>
     piece of land: county rate $4.12, school rate 


            <cb/>
    

     $2.75, poor rate 30 cents, total $7.17. The man, 
     <lb/>
     being sick and dying, did not pay it from 1944 to 
     <lb/>
     1946, when this final notice was received, and the 
     <lb/>
     administrator of the estate received this bill for 
     <lb/>
     $28.62 for four years, taxes on a piece of land 
     <lb/>
     valued at $ 100 in Cape Breton County — over a 
     <lb/>
     quarter of the value of the land. 
     <lb/></p>
            

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIGA1">Mr. Figary</persName> Taxed by the provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ment? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> It was the municipality of Cape 
     <lb/>
     Breton, under the Province of Nova Scotia. So 
     <lb/>
     don't anybody dispute the fact that you will be 
     <lb/>
     taxed. You have to be, you have to get the money 
     <lb/>
     from somewhere. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now Mr. Chairman, I understand that as far as 
     <lb/>
     the Broadcasting Company are concerned we 
     <lb/>
     can't carry on any further, so I move that the 
     <lb/>
     committee rise and report progess and ask leave 
     <lb/>
     to sit again tomorrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee rose and reported progress, and 
     <lb/>
     the Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-08-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

     <!--December 12, 1947<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, I am sure we have 
     <lb/>all learned with deep regret the tragedy which has 
     <lb/>recently happened at Goose Bay, and touches 
     <lb/>every person in Newfoundland. I refer of course 
     <lb/>to the tragic loss of life of 23 American neigh<lb break="no"/>bours of ours here. In this connection, sir, I wish 
     <lb/>to make the following motion: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whereas this house and the people of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland have learnt with profound 
     <lb/>
     regret of the recent tragic loss of life to the 
     <lb/>
     American army personnel on duty in this 
     <lb/>
     country; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And whereas many of these men of the 23 
     <lb/>
     who have lost their lives in this heartbreaking 
     <lb/>
     disaster were neighbours of ours living at 
     <lb/>
     Fort Pepperrell with their families; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Therefore be it resolved that we of this 
     <lb/>
     house do tender our heartfelt sympathy to the 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
           
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Commanding General of Fort Pepperrell and 
     <lb/>
     through him to the bereaved families of the 
     <lb/>
     deceased; and that a copy of this resolution 
     <lb/>
     be forwarded to the said Commanding 
     <lb/>
     General accordingly. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I would like to second 
     <lb/>Mr. Hollett's motion. I am personally acquainted 
     <lb/>with some of those who were lost. I think it is a 
     <lb/>kind gesture, and I have much pleasure in second<lb break="no"/>ing the resolution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You have heard the motion of 
     <lb/>condolence, gentlemen. Are you ready for the 
     <lb/>question? I think that when the motion is carried 
     <lb/>we might stand for a period of a minute to show 
     <lb/>our respect. 
     <lb/>[The motion carried and the Convention stood in 
     <lb/>Silence]  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Ottawa Delegation 
     <lb/>
     Proposed Arrangements for the Entry of Newfoundland into Confederation 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Mr. Chairman, I presume that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Hollett has the floor this afternoon? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> He has, Major Cashin, for two 
     <lb/>reasons. First he did not finish yesterday; and 
     <lb/>second he was the first to catch my eye. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> If Mr. Hollett was not going to 
     <lb/>
     speak, I presume I could speak, and if not, I would 
     <lb/>
     follow him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, that is a little 
     <lb/>
     irregular. I propose to comment on Mr. Hollett's 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>