<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-02-03"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-02-03">3 February 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="268" to="280"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0268.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0269.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0270.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0271.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0272.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0273.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0274.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0275.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0276.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0277.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0278.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0279.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0280.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-08">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0268">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0268.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0269">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0269.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0270">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0270.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0271">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0271.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0272">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0272.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0273">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0273.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0274">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0274.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0275">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0275.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0276">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0276.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0277">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0277.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0278">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0278.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0279">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0279.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0280">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0280.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="268"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0268.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">268</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
       
<div type="section">   

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     February 3, 1947</head>

</div>

<div type="section">

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Orders of the day Notice of 
     <lb/>
     motion. Mr. Higgins to give notice that on tomor<lb break="no"/>row he will move the following amendments to 
     <lb/>
     the rules of procedure of the Convention....<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref>
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Chairman, gentlemen, the 
     <lb/>proposed amendment is for the purpose of bring<lb break="no"/>ing the rules of procedure into line with the 
     <lb/>amended act with respect to the National Con<lb break="no"/>vention. As you know, when the present Chair<lb break="no"/>man was appointed, the not had to be amended. 
     <lb/>It gives the Chairman his right to vote, but does 
     <lb/>not confer on him any second or casting vote as 
     <lb/>Chairman. The proposed amendment gives the 
     <lb/>Chairman of the Convention his right to vote. It's 
     <lb/>merely to regularise the rules of procedure in 
     <lb/>accordance with the amended act. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Mr. Chairman, I wish to give notice of 
     <lb/>
     motion. lhereby give notice that] will, on tomor<lb break="no"/>row, move the following resolution: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Whereas it is the duty of this National 
     <lb/>
     Convention to ascertain all important facts 
     <lb/>
     bearing upon the financial and economic 
     <lb/>
     position of this country, and upon all possible 
     <lb/>
     and suitable forms of government to be laid 
     <lb/>
     before the people: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Be it therefore resolved that it is essential 
     <lb/>
     that this Convention take immediate steps to 
     <lb/>
     ascertain 
     <lb/>
      </p>

            <p>1. What steps, if any, can be taken for estab<lb break="no"/>lishing improved economic or fiscal relation<lb break="no"/>ships between the United States of America 
     <lb/>and Newfoundland, particularly bearing in 
     <lb/>mind the present occupation of certain New<lb break="no"/>foundland territory by the said United States 
     <lb/>of America, and the fact that free entry is 
     <lb/>accorded to the United States for its importa<lb break="no"/>tion into Newfoundland; 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     2. What financial and fiscal relationships 
     <lb/>
     could be expected between the Government 
     <lb/>
     of the United Kingdom and Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (1) Under a continuation of Commission 
     <lb/>
     government in its present form, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (2) Under a revised form of Commission 
     <lb/>
     government with elected representatives there<lb break="no"/>on, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (3) Under responsible government in ap<lb break="no"/>proximately its previous form, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (4) Under any other suitable form of 
     <lb/>
    government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>3. What would be a fair and equitable basis 
     <lb/>for federal union of the Dominion of Canada 
     <lb/>and Newfoundland, or what other fiscal, 
     <lb/>political or economic arrangements may be 
     <lb/>possible. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Be it further resolved that His Excellency 
     <lb/>
     the Governor in Commission be informed 
     <lb/>
     that this National Convention desires to ap<lb break="no"/>point a committee of its members to confer 
     <lb/>
     with His Excellency the Governor in Com<lb break="no"/>mission on ways and means of determining 
     <lb/>
     the matters herein before enumerated, and 
     <lb/>
     that in the event of His Excellency the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor in Commission being agreeable to con<lb break="no"/>ferring with such a committee, the Chairman 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention in consultation with the 
     <lb/>
     Steering Committee shall thereupon select a 
     <lb/>
     delegation of members of this Convention 
     <lb/>
     which, with the Chairman ofthe Convention, 
     <lb/>
     shall constitute the committee referred to in 
     <lb/>
    this resolution and which shall report to this 
     <lb/>Convention the results of their conferences 
     <lb/>before being in any way committed to the 
     <lb/>despatch of any delegation outside of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the Transportation and Communications Committee:<ref target="#fn_02">[2]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, the only addi<lb break="no"/>tional information that this Committee has to 
     <lb/>
     bring before the committee of the whole today is 
     <lb/>
     the supplementary report on Gander,<ref target="#fn_03">[3]</ref> consisting 
     <lb/>
     of a verbatim shorthand account of the interview 
     <lb/>
     held with the Commissioner of Public Utilities, 
     <lb/>
                        <cb/>
           

     Mr. Neill, by a Committee appointed by the Con<lb break="no"/>vention, and i think perhaps that the best thing 
     <lb/>
     would be to ask the Secretary to read the verbatim 
     <lb/>
     account of that interview. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the verbatim report]</hi> 
      </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Mr. Chairman, some of my friends 
    

   
    
     <note xml:id="fn_01">1 Volume II:53. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
<note xml:id="fn_02">2 Volume II:75. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
<note xml:id="fn_03">3 Volume II:79. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
   
            <pb n="269"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0269.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">269</fw>
         

     have been commenting on the fact that, for the 
     <lb/>
     past few weeks, I have not been taking a very 
     <lb/>
     active part in the debates of this assembly. My 
     <lb/>
     explanation to them and to the public, is that, first, 
     <lb/>
     I felt the carefully prepared reports which the 
     <lb/>
     several committees have presented were in them<lb break="no"/>selves sufficiently informative and factual for the 
     <lb/>
     basic purposes of this Convention. And second, 
     <lb/>
     wishing to expedite the work, I did not desire to 
     <lb/>
     enter into any analysis of endless details, which, 
     <lb/>
     if encouraged, could only develop into idle dis<lb break="no"/>cussions, with a consequent cost of the people's 
     <lb/>
     money and the delegates' time. For these reasons, 
     <lb/>
     I have been content to adopt the role of a more or 
     <lb/>
     less silent spectator. But on the present occasion 
     <lb/>
     I rise to what I regard as a state of political 
     <lb/>
     emergency, with the object of placing before this 
     <lb/>
     Convention my impression of things as I see them 
     <lb/>
     today, and with the hope that what I shall have to 
     <lb/>
     say may be of some assistance to my fellow 
     <lb/>
     delegates and to the public at large. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On September 18 last, just a week after this 
     <lb/>
     Convention had assembled, I made a speech in<lb break="no"/>troducing the Chadwick-Jones report. I referred 
     <lb/>
     to this Convention in terms which, to some of 
     <lb/>
     you, may have seemed unduly harsh — perhaps 
     <lb/>
     shocking. I pointed out my lack of faith in this 
     <lb/>
     Convention, referred to it as being ethically 
     <lb/>
     improper, in View of the agreement which was 
     <lb/>
     made between the last Newfoundland parliament 
     <lb/>
     and the British government, wherein self-govern<lb break="no"/>ment was promised this country upon its becom<lb break="no"/>ing self-supporting. I pointed out how that 
     <lb/>
     agreement had been deliberately avoided and 
     <lb/>
     ignored by the wholly unauthorised substitution 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention set-up. I said that as time went 
     <lb/>
     on, and the true nature of this Convention 
     <lb/>
     emerged, many delegates would endorse my sen<lb break="no"/>timents. I concluded with the statement that it 
     <lb/>
     would become clear that in its dealings with us, 
     <lb/>
     the Dominions Office had stolen the vocabulary 
     <lb/>
     of democracy, but had ignored both its spirit and 
     <lb/>
     substance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Over four months have elapsed since I made 
     <lb/>
     that speech, and today the things that I said then 
     <lb/>
     seem to have proved too dismally true. In one 
     <lb/>
     respect, perhaps, I might change my views. At 
     <lb/>
     that time I referred to the Convention as a 
     <lb/>
     glorified stall. Today I do not regard it in any such 
     <lb/>
     light manner. Rather I see in its characteristics 
     <lb/>
     something far more sinister and even tragic. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     Today I see it as a premeditated design to keep us 
     <lb/>
     out of control of our own country, so that time 
     <lb/>
     may be afforded those in power to complete their 
     <lb/>
     campaign of sabotage. And so, I see this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion and its activities as something in the nature 
     <lb/>
     of fiddling while Rome burns. Now, let me say, 
     <lb/>
     that in speaking in this strain, I cast no reflection 
     <lb/>
     whatever on the personnel of this body, I simply 
     <lb/>
     speak of the Convention as a political entity — 
     <lb/>
     as being part of the costly and cumbersome 
     <lb/>
     machinery, consisting of plebiscites and referen<lb break="no"/>dums, which have been foisted on us to confuse 
     <lb/>
     our thoughts and efforts, until the plans of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominions Office have been completed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As for the personnel in the months that we 
     <lb/>
     have been together, I have come to know most of 
     <lb/>
     the delegates intimately and have made many 
     <lb/>
     warm friends. I have been greatly impressed with 
     <lb/>
     the sound reasoning and sincere utterances 
     <lb/>
     shown in their speeches. Many of them may not 
     <lb/>
     have been blessed with college education, and 
     <lb/>
     have had to get their learning in the university of 
     <lb/>
     hard knocks, but new as some of them may be to 
     <lb/>
     the political atmosphere, they have proven that 
     <lb/>
     they can measure up to their jobs in a manner 
     <lb/>
     reflecting credit on themselves and the people 
     <lb/>
     they represent. We have in this assembly repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of all Newfoundland, including 
     <lb/>
     Labrador. From the great forests of the west to 
     <lb/>
     the stormy coastlines of the north — merchants 
     <lb/>
     and miners, lawyers and lumbermen, fishermen 
     <lb/>
     and farmers, teachers and teamsters; the rich and 
     <lb/>
     the poor, the classes and the masses — all are 
     <lb/>
     represented here. And because of this wide rep<lb break="no"/>resentation, I feel that I am speaking, not so much 
     <lb/>
     to the delegates themselves, as to the 300,000 odd 
     <lb/>
     people who are depending on us to safeguard 
     <lb/>
     their interests. I speak on behalf of no particular 
     <lb/>
     district, nor as the advocate of any political party 
     <lb/>
     or belief, but just as an ordinary Newfoundlander 
     <lb/>
     to his fellow men and women, on a matter of 
     <lb/>
     national interest. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I said that I rose to an emergency, and perhaps 
     <lb/>
     I should explain myself a little more clearly. Let 
     <lb/>
     me say, then, that I am seriously alarmed, at the 
     <lb/>
     state of things in this country today. I am dis<lb break="no"/>turbed at the things which have come to my 
     <lb/>
     notice as an ordinary citizen and as a member of 
     <lb/>
     this Convention. I have seen things which I think 
     <lb/>
     the people should know, because in the final 
     <lb/>
     analysis they are our masters. They are the people 
     <lb/>
   

            <pb n="270"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0270.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">270</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
      

     who own this country, and who are most directly 
     <lb/>
     concerned in what happens to it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Firstly I am not satisfied, and have never been 
     <lb/>
     satisfied, with the method adopted for the solu<lb break="no"/>tion of our political position. I have always 
     <lb/>
     regarded the setting up of a Convention such as 
     <lb/>
     this as not being the proper method of solving the 
     <lb/>
     problem which confronts us, and every day that 
     <lb/>
     passes further confirms these beliefs. I have slow<lb break="no"/>ly seen emerge into the light of day the duplicity 
     <lb/>
     and bad faith which underlies this whole busi<lb break="no"/>ness. I have seen proof that our country is being 
     <lb/>
     deliberately sidetracked from the democratic 
     <lb/>
     highway that we thought we were on into a blind 
     <lb/>
     alley, where we can spend our time groping for 
     <lb/>
     progress and getting nowhere. As a result, I say 
     <lb/>
     that if we do not become aware of these things, 
     <lb/>
     and turn around on a new course, we are headed 
     <lb/>
     for danger. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let us review things. This country was 
     <lb/>
     promised self-government when she became 
     <lb/>
     self-supporting. On December 12, 1945, in the 
     <lb/>
     House of Lords, the Dominions Secretary 
     <lb/>
     declared that Newfoundland was then self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting, and had been since 1941; and coming 
     <lb/>
     nearer home, we find that no less an authority 
     <lb/>
     than former Commissioner for Finance Wild told 
     <lb/>
     this Convention four months ago that we were 
     <lb/>
     self-supporting. All right then, we are self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting. These men say we are, and they should 
     <lb/>
     know. Now then, the first question we ask is, why 
     <lb/>
     was not this international contract carried out? It 
     <lb/>
     is a serious thing to break an international agree<lb break="no"/>ment, Mr. Chairman. Yet not alone was this done, 
     <lb/>
     but no reason was given us for such default. What 
     <lb/>
     does this mean and what impression must we, as 
     <lb/>
     sensible men, gather from this? I submit there is 
     <lb/>
     only one deduction we can make, and this is that 
     <lb/>
     the British government has not kept faith with us; 
     <lb/>
     that it was not in their interest that we should have 
     <lb/>
     control of our own country. And so determined 
     <lb/>
     were they to carry out their plan, that they did not 
     <lb/>
     hesitate to treat an international agreement as just 
     <lb/>
     another scrap of paper. Is this the situation which 
     <lb/>
     confronts us today? Must we look for duplicity 
     <lb/>
     where we should look for straightforward deal<lb break="no"/>ing? But let us go on and study the character of 
     <lb/>
     the thing further. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     You will remember when, on the request of 
     <lb/>
     the Convention, Commissioner for Finance Wild 
     <lb/>
     was asked to appear before us, his point-blank 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
          

     refusal to answer certain questions. Does this 
     <lb/>
     indicate a wholesome co-operation with our ef<lb break="no"/>forts, or does it indicate another example of the 
     <lb/>
     bad faith to which I have referred? Does it not 
     <lb/>
     indicate that both Mr. Wild and the Commission 
     <lb/>
     government, as well as the Dominions Office, 
     <lb/>
     have regarded us as an opposition rather than a 
     <lb/>
     friendly body — that they did not care whether 
     <lb/>
     we got facts or not; that they had no sympathy for 
     <lb/>
     either ourselves or the work which we had under<lb break="no"/>taken? For myself, as a member of a committee 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention, 1 have been time and time 
     <lb/>
     again unable to get the information I requested. I 
     <lb/>
     have been refused information, sometimes al<lb break="no"/>most insolently refused. Other committees have 
     <lb/>
     indicated that they have been greeted with the 
     <lb/>
     same hostility and lack of co-operation. I remem<lb break="no"/>ber one extraordinary instance, when the govern<lb break="no"/>ment refused information on confidential 
     <lb/>
     grounds, and shortly after I saw the whole thing 
     <lb/>
     published in pamphlet form in the Dominion of 
     <lb/>
     Canada. Could there be anything more farcical? 
     <lb/>
     Here they tell us we are an assembly appointed 
     <lb/>
     and authorised to get facts, and yet when we go 
     <lb/>
     to the very people who so appointed us — when 
     <lb/>
     we go to the normal source — we are, in so many 
     <lb/>
     words told to go about our business. I say again, 
     <lb/>
     does this conduct indicate anything? Does it not 
     <lb/>
     indicate beyond all reasonable doubt, that the 
     <lb/>
     Commission government and the Dominions Of<lb break="no"/>fice do not want us to get all the facts — do not 
     <lb/>
     want us to know what the true state of this country 
     <lb/>
     is today, and how our affairs are being managed? 
     <lb/>
     Does it not clearly show that we are regarded as 
     <lb/>
     a body without either importance or standing; 
     <lb/>
     that we are not being taken seriously; that they 
     <lb/>
     have given us the glory, but that the power 
     <lb/>
     remains with themselves? What would you say, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman, if you were doing business with a 
     <lb/>
     man and he treated you that way? You would say 
     <lb/>
     that he was a trickster and a deceiver; refuse to 
     <lb/>
     have anything to do with him any longer. You 
     <lb/>
     would cease to put faith in him. But let us see if 
     <lb/>
     we cannot also prove what 1 have said in a dif<lb break="no"/>ferent manner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let us suppose that we have none of this 
     <lb/>
     evidence of bad faith on the part of the Commis<lb break="no"/>sion government and the Dominions Office. Let 
     <lb/>
     us forget all this, and take up a single instance 
     <lb/>
     where the British government comes to us, in all 
     <lb/>
     good faith, and asks us to find out the facts 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="271"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0271.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">271</fw> 
    

           

     relating to the financial and economic position of 
     <lb/>
     this country. Would not the first question that 
     <lb/>
     would come to mind be this: why should the 
     <lb/>
     British government have to ask us to undertake 
     <lb/>
     such a task now? Do you think they would need 
     <lb/>
     to call on 45 men, living in all parts of this country 
     <lb/>
     with no particular training in such matters, to do 
     <lb/>
     this work for them? Don't you think they have all 
     <lb/>
     the answers themselves? They with their 4,000 
     <lb/>
     civil servants, with their $10,000 salaried 
     <lb/>
     departmental heads, with their highly-paid im<lb break="no"/>ported financial experts, with their agents scat<lb break="no"/>tered all over the island, with their great numbers 
     <lb/>
     of bureaux and offices — do you think in the face 
     <lb/>
     of this, they can ask us to believe that they must 
     <lb/>
     send out an invitation to us, and ask us to please 
     <lb/>
     come to St. John's, and add up their accounts for 
     <lb/>
     them and tell them whether the country is self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     supporting or not? Why the whole thing is so 
     <lb/>
     wildly absurd, so obviously a thing of sending the 
     <lb/>
     fool further, that I am amazed that this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion has not long ago refused to have any part of 
     <lb/>
     this political game of hide the button. I say that 
     <lb/>
     we are being trifled with, that the country is being 
     <lb/>
     trifled with, that this Convention is being treated 
     <lb/>
     as so many children, to whom this political toy is 
     <lb/>
     given to distract their attention to play this mock 
     <lb/>
     parliament business according to a book of in<lb break="no"/>structions furnished by those two jokers, Messrs. 
     <lb/>
     Chadwick and Jones. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On behalf of the people whom I represent and 
     <lb/>
     myself, I wish to record my strong resentment at 
     <lb/>
     the derogatory and insulting manner in which we 
     <lb/>
     have been treated by the Dominions Office, and 
     <lb/>
     in the interests of all Newfoundland I say that, 
     <lb/>
     being aware of this position, it is high time that 
     <lb/>
     we did something about it. To use the words of 
     <lb/>
     Winston Churchill, "What kind of people do they 
     <lb/>
     think we are anyhow?" Do they think we have no 
     <lb/>
     intelligence? Do they think we have no national 
     <lb/>
     pride? Do they think we do not resent such un<lb break="no"/>called-for treatment? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Some months ago in a radio address, I ex<lb break="no"/>pressed myself to the effect that if New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders did not soon take over their country, 
     <lb/>
     there would be nothing left to take over. I have 
     <lb/>
     that same feeling today. It is an old story now, 
     <lb/>
     about the bartering away of our national assets. 
     <lb/>
     But the thing still goes on, and the tragedy of it is 
     <lb/>
     we are doing nothing to stop it. Sometime ago this 
     <lb/>
     Convention unanimously passed a resolution re<lb break="no"/>
         
            <cb/>
questing the Commission that no further commit<lb break="no"/>ments or charges should be made upon our na<lb break="no"/>tional resources, until such time as it was decided 
     <lb/>
     what form of government would administer our 
     <lb/>
     affairs in the future. But do you think there will 
     <lb/>
     be any attention paid to such a request? I tell you, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman, not the slightest. Indeed, I doubt 
     <lb/>
     if this Convention has been given the courtesy of 
     <lb/>
     a reply to their request. It was only a few days ago 
     <lb/>
     that a further act was passed giving further con<lb break="no"/>cessions on the Labrador to outside parties, and 
     <lb/>
     we have no doubt that as time goes on further 
     <lb/>
     contractual obligations will be made involving us 
     <lb/>
     to the tune of many millions of dollars of the 
     <lb/>
     people's money, further compromising our fu<lb break="no"/>ture in adeeper bondage. You will remember that 
     <lb/>
     at the beginning of this Convention we were 
     <lb/>
     furnished with a ten-year programme for the ex<lb break="no"/>penditure of some $60 million. This programme 
     <lb/>
     is actually being carried out today by the Com<lb break="no"/>mission government itself, without any notice 
     <lb/>
     being taken of this Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am aware there are those amongst us who 
     <lb/>
     seem obsessed with the peculiar idea that the 
     <lb/>
     problem of Newfoundland can be dealt with as 
     <lb/>
     one would a problem in mathematics; that it is 
     <lb/>
     something which can be worked out by the rule 
     <lb/>
     of three. They seem to want somebody to come 
     <lb/>
     and show as a mathematical certainty that New<lb break="no"/>foundland will never know another bad day. 
     <lb/>
     They want a gilt-edged guarantee that there will 
     <lb/>
     be no more depressions in the world, that there 
     <lb/>
     will be no more wars, no more bombs, no more 
     <lb/>
     ups or downs in either politics or commerce. 
     <lb/>
     They want to be assured of the exact number of 
     <lb/>
     fish we are going to catch ten years from now, the 
     <lb/>
     number of trees we are going to cut, the number 
     <lb/>
     of tons of ore we are going to extract from our 
     <lb/>
     mines. And if we can't perform this miracle of 
     <lb/>
     exactly prophesying all these things, they will say 
     <lb/>
     that we are not self-supporting ―   that we had 
     <lb/>
     better not take a chance, there may be a depres<lb break="no"/>sion in 1950 or even 1960, and we had better go 
     <lb/>
     in with some other country that has no depres<lb break="no"/>sions, no wars, and no business cycles. Why the 
     <lb/>
     thing is so absurd, so hopelessly impractical, that 
     <lb/>
     I would not mention it at all but for the reason that 
     <lb/>
     there are people who actually think this way. I 
     <lb/>
     ask, what country, what individual, what 
     <lb/>
     businessman expects to be able to have a 
     <lb/>
     blueprint of his condition five or ten years from 
     

            <pb n="272"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0272.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">272</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
          

     now? If a prosperous firm in good standing today 
     <lb/>
     cannot tell how things are going to he say five 
     <lb/>
     years hence, do they throw up their hands in 
     <lb/>
     despair, close their doors and beg someone else 
     <lb/>
     to come and take over their business? When 
     <lb/>
     Canada, the United States and Great Britain her<lb break="no"/>self were in the depths of the depression, did they 
     <lb/>
     do it? Of course they didn't. They kept on — they 
     <lb/>
     took the good with the bad, and they won their 
     <lb/>
     fight, just as our ancestors did when we had a bad 
     <lb/>
     fishery. I repeat, no man and no nation knows 
     <lb/>
     what the future holds. But they don't show the 
     <lb/>
     white feathers, they know that uncertainty is the 
     <lb/>
     unavoidable law of life. And their pride, their 
     <lb/>
     courage, and their patriotism bids them fight on. 
     <lb/>
     They know well that any other course is the 
     <lb/>
     course of cowardice and dishonour. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But why, I ask, should any one in New<lb break="no"/>foundland talk of giving up, or talk of selling out? 
     <lb/>
     For what is the actual position? We are faced with 
     <lb/>
     no financial or economic emergency. On the 
     <lb/>
     contrary, we are richer than we ever were before, 
     <lb/>
     than we ever expected to be. And as for our future 
     <lb/>
     prospects, I tell you they were never brighter. I 
     <lb/>
     know something of the economic and financial 
     <lb/>
     structures of other countries, and I also know 
     <lb/>
     something about the position of Newfoundland, 
     <lb/>
     and I place myself on record as saying that I know 
     <lb/>
     of no other people in the world who can today 
     <lb/>
     face their future with more confidence and as<lb break="no"/>surance, than Newfoundland. I see no shadow on 
     <lb/>
     the road ahead. Rather do I see continued bright<lb break="no"/>ness and prosperity. And when the final reports 
     <lb/>
     are presented to this Convention, I will prove 
     <lb/>
     what I say by the evidence of hard facts and 
     <lb/>
     figures. I know that there are with us today the 
     <lb/>
     prophets of doom and disaster, and they in their 
     <lb/>
     way are bad enough. But worse still are those 
     <lb/>
     whom I honestly believe are disappointed at 
     <lb/>
     every new sign and proof of our country's 
     <lb/>
     prosperity, which the investigations of this Con<lb break="no"/>vention are steadily producing. I cannot find 
     <lb/>
     words to express my utter contempt for this latter 
     <lb/>
     class. All I can say is that they disgrace the very 
     <lb/>
     name when they claim to be Newfoundlanders. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then there is another class of individual, who 
     <lb/>
     give evidence of a truly strange form of political 
     <lb/>
     thinking — who say give us food, not votes. Feed 
     <lb/>
     us, and we care not what you do with us. Why, 
     <lb/>
     sir, one can be well fed in a gaol. And Hitler, I 
     <lb/>
     believe, fed his people very well. But is that an 
     <lb/>
           

            <cb/>
      

     argument for us going to gaol, or setting up a 
     <lb/>
     tyrannical dictatorship? I agree we must have 
     <lb/>
     food, but let us see that we eat that food as free 
     <lb/>
     men, and not as a dishonoured people, lest the 
     <lb/>
     food we seek turn sour in our months. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I know something of what people called graft 
     <lb/>
     in the old days, and I know something also of the 
     <lb/>
     things which are going on today. If you want 
     <lb/>
     evidence of this, I refer you to that section of the 
     <lb/>
     Auditor General's report which deals with the 
     <lb/>
     Department of Public Health and Welfare, and 
     <lb/>
     also the Railway Department, and you will get an 
     <lb/>
     indication of what I mean. I assure you that if the 
     <lb/>
     whole story of the things which are taking place 
     <lb/>
     today under the present regime were exposed, the 
     <lb/>
     people of this country would be shocked as they 
     <lb/>
     have never been before. Why, Mr. Chairman, 
     <lb/>
     there is at present on the table of this house the 
     <lb/>
     report of the Transportation Committee, and in 
     <lb/>
     this instance alone we find that a sum of no less 
     <lb/>
     than $1 million per year is being sacrificed, or 
     <lb/>
     should I say sabotaged, with no more considera<lb break="no"/>tion or foresight than if it were so many cents. In 
     <lb/>
     a recent interview with the Commissioner for 
     <lb/>
     Public Utilities we were coolly informed that this 
     <lb/>
     obligation had been fastened on the necks of the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland people solely by the decision of 
     <lb/>
     the local Commissioners without any reference 
     <lb/>
     to the British government. What an example of 
     <lb/>
     spendthrift dictatorship, what an abuse of a 
     <lb/>
     people's interests, what a breach of the sacred 
     <lb/>
     obligations of trusteeship. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Is it not high time that we did something about 
     <lb/>
     all this, that we took some steps to prevent this 
     <lb/>
     country being kicked around in this manner, of 
     <lb/>
     having the British government use us and all that 
     <lb/>
     is ours for her advantage and to our detriment? is 
     <lb/>
     it not time that this Convention did something 
     <lb/>
     about saving the country itself? I say, sir, that 
     <lb/>
     there was never a time in our national life when 
     <lb/>
     the motto "Delays are dangerous" was more ap<lb break="no"/>plicable. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The great need of this country today is unity 
     <lb/>
     — unity of thought and purpose in doing the job 
     <lb/>
     which lies before us. I am too well aware of the 
     <lb/>
     fact that there are many circumstances which 
     <lb/>
     mitigate against this sense of unity, and which at 
     <lb/>
     the same time render more easy the task of those 
     <lb/>
     who would disunite us. There is our far-flung 
     <lb/>
     coastline, our isolated settlements, our lack of 
     <lb/>
     communications — all these things militate 
     
  
            <pb n="273"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0273.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">273</fw>
           

     against unity of thought and ideas. Indeed, our 
     <lb/>
     very origin is rooted in disunity. With us, the 
     <lb/>
     melting-pot of nationalism has worked very 
     <lb/>
     slowly. Hundreds of years ago our country was 
     <lb/>
     peopled with English, Irish and Scotch, and even 
     <lb/>
     today their assimilation into a national unity is 
     <lb/>
     not complete. We proclaim public holidays in 
     <lb/>
     honour of England, Ireland and Scotland, but 
     <lb/>
     where is our Newfoundland day? Why, even our 
     <lb/>
     very national ode was composed by one who was 
     <lb/>
     not a Newfoundlander. We boast of our English, 
     <lb/>
     Irish and Scotch descent, but who boasts that he 
     <lb/>
     is a Newfoundlander? Is not all this wrong? 
     <lb/>
     Should not the state of things be rectified? Is it 
     <lb/>
     not time that we awoke to the fact that we are first 
     <lb/>
     of all Newfoundlanders and not the citizens of 
     <lb/>
     any country thousands of miles across the seas? 
     <lb/>
     Let us acknowledge our national obligations, 
     <lb/>
     take pride in the fact that we are New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders, and acknowledge the duty we owe 
     <lb/>
     this land. And the first duty — the first obligation 
     <lb/>
     — is the duty of unity; the duty of joining our 
     <lb/>
     strength and our numbers in the common inter<lb break="no"/>ests of our common country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I know there are members of this Convention 
     <lb/>
     who entertain ideas of merging our individuality 
     <lb/>
     with other countries, of absorbing our nationhood 
     <lb/>
     with other peoples. Such things, in view of the 
     <lb/>
     great vital issue which now faces us, I regard as 
     <lb/>
     being of secondary importance — things that 
     <lb/>
     properly belong not to the present, but to the 
     <lb/>
     future — things for the people of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     to consider as a self-governing dominion I regard 
     <lb/>
     them as issues which should not be allowed to 
     <lb/>
     destroy the unity, or enervate the thoughts of the 
     <lb/>
     people at this juncture. But let me add, that I deny 
     <lb/>
     to no man his right to advocate any form of 
     <lb/>
     government he may choose, and if a general 
     <lb/>
     election were called in this country, there is a free 
     <lb/>
     scope for the confederate, the unionist, the 
     <lb/>
     labourer, the socialist, and all those who wish to 
     <lb/>
     present their belief for the endorsement of the 
     <lb/>
     people. All such things come within the sphere of 
     <lb/>
     a free democracy. But I emphasise, that the issue 
     <lb/>
     today is not a party issue, it is a national issue, an 
     <lb/>
     issue of emergency, of saving the country, of 
     <lb/>
     saving the treasury, of saving the resources of the 
     <lb/>
     people while there is yet time. It is a situation 
     <lb/>
     where we must put Newfoundland first, before all 
     <lb/>
     else, before the aims of this Convention, before 
     <lb/>
     the designs of the Commission government, 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           

     before the wishes of the Dominions Office or the 
     <lb/>
     British government. We must put first things first. 
     <lb/>
     All else must be brushed aside in the interest of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. If that interest demands that we 
     <lb/>
     should convert this assembly into a purely New<lb break="no"/>foundland assembly, that should be done. If it 
     <lb/>
     demands that we ignore the rules and constitution 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention that should be done. If it 
     <lb/>
     demands we should send a delegation to London, 
     <lb/>
     demanding a general election in the spring of 
     <lb/>
     I947, that should be done. Anything and every<lb break="no"/>thing should be done to ensure that there is no 
     <lb/>
     delay, that there is no time lost in restoring the 
     <lb/>
     control of our destinies to the hands of our own 
     <lb/>
     people. If we have any rights at all in our own 
     <lb/>
     country, the right of free action or free speech, 
     <lb/>
     then these rights should be exercised to obtain for 
     <lb/>
     us the right of responsible government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now we come to this matter of confederation 
     <lb/>
     with Canada. Propaganda, inspired right here in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, has been appearing in certain 
     <lb/>
     sections of the Canadian press, specially 
     <lb/>
     designed to injure Newfoundland by mis<lb break="no"/>representation of facts. There is a lot of talk about 
     <lb/>
     this affair of submerging our century-old nation<lb break="no"/>hood with another country, and I expect we shall 
     <lb/>
     hear more, much more of it in the future. For the 
     <lb/>
     present I merely say this: if Canada is prepared 
     <lb/>
     to accept us in confederation, then be assured it 
     <lb/>
     is only because she wants something we have, 
     <lb/>
     and that she wants it very much. If she wants us, 
     <lb/>
     she wants us for her benefit, not for ours. And if 
     <lb/>
     she offers us one dollar, you can be certain that 
     <lb/>
     she counts on getting two or three of ours in 
     <lb/>
     return. Remember this, to any such deal Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain must be a party, and so it would all boil 
     <lb/>
     down to a clever game between Canada and Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain in which they would take the winnings 
     <lb/>
     and Newfoundland would be the pawn. As com<lb break="no"/>monsense people, I ask you to remember this 
     <lb/>
     when you are being deluged with the gilded story 
     <lb/>
     of the lovely things Canada is going to do for us, 
     <lb/>
     of how grand we will live with two chickens in 
     <lb/>
     every pot and every man a millionaire. Let us 
     <lb/>
     remember that this is simply a repetition of the 
     <lb/>
     siren song that has lured many an unlucky 
     <lb/>
     country to its doom. It is the sugar on the pill, the 
     <lb/>
     bait in the trap. Such was the method used in 
     <lb/>
     luring us into Commission government and the 
     <lb/>
     valley of the dole in l933. The little countries of 
     <lb/>
     Europe have heard that song, the Maritime 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="274"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0274.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">274</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
          

     provinces heard it and to their grief heeded it. I 
     <lb/>
     expect to hear it sung in this very chamber before 
     <lb/>
     long. For a change I should like someone to tell 
     <lb/>
     us not why we should go to Canada, but why 
     <lb/>
     Canada should want us at all. Is anyone within 
     <lb/>
     the reach of my voice, I wonder, so innocent as 
     <lb/>
     to think that a big country ever yet cared a hoot 
     <lb/>
     about the welfare of a little country. Such in brief 
     <lb/>
     is all I want to say about this confederation busi<lb break="no"/>ness at the present time. I have faith in our people, 
     <lb/>
     and I firmly believe that the people will see 
     <lb/>
     through the sham and skulduggery which lies 
     <lb/>
     behind this whole confederation issue. And I 
     <lb/>
     know they will stand by Newfoundland when the 
     <lb/>
     call goes forth. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I do not know what the other delegates may 
     <lb/>
     think, but as for myself, I express it as my sincere 
     <lb/>
     conviction that a general election under respon<lb break="no"/>sible government should be held in this country 
     <lb/>
     in the spring of 1947. I further say that if this is 
     <lb/>
     not done, we shall live to deeply regret it. Let us 
     <lb/>
     remember that we cannot escape the verdict of 
     <lb/>
     history and that today we are on trial. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I do not propose to further take up the time of 
     <lb/>
     this Convention, and in closing I would like to 
     <lb/>
     briefly sum up the message I would leave with 
     <lb/>
     you. That message is that there are grave reasons, 
     <lb/>
     why we should not delay in taking some steps to 
     <lb/>
     forestall the disaster which looms ahead. To the 
     <lb/>
     best of my ability I have given you these reasons. 
     <lb/>
     I do not make any specific motion at the present 
     <lb/>
     time, because I wish to give this Convention time 
     <lb/>
     for full consideration of the things which I have 
     <lb/>
     stated. I give a challenge and the challenge I 
     <lb/>
     present is one for action. I do this because of my 
     <lb/>
     sense of duty to the people who sent me here; to 
     <lb/>
     my conceptions of those things which I feel are 
     <lb/>
     just and decent; and above all, for the love which 
     <lb/>
     I share with you all for the greatest and finest little 
     <lb/>
     country in the world ― Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> ....Mr. Chairman, many of the 
     <lb/>
     delegates stressed the great need of roads in their 
     <lb/>
     districts. I think it is my duty to do likewise in 
     <lb/>
     fairness of the district I represent. Whatever the 
     <lb/>
     form of government is in we must have roads 
     <lb/>
     and more roads. Roads should be, sir, foremost 
     <lb/>
     in any form of government. I would like to see a 
     <lb/>
     trunk road across this country, but the big ques<lb break="no"/>tion is just where is the money coming from. 
     <lb/>
     Gentlemen, I really and truly think it would come 
     <lb/>
     if we had more faith in ourselves and our country, 
    

            <cb/>
           

     but then "Faith without works is dead". The 
     <lb/>
     delegates have not all agreed or approved of the 
     <lb/>
     idea of a trunk road across the country, but I think, 
     <lb/>
     sir, we have all agreed on this one point, and that 
     <lb/>
     is, the great, and urgent need for more and better 
     <lb/>
     roads in the outport settlements. I would like to 
     <lb/>
     see all our local roads connected from settlement 
     <lb/>
     to settlement, and connecting up to the railway. 
     <lb/>
     Then we can live, move and have our being, and 
     <lb/>
     do business with one another, which is essential 
     <lb/>
     to the well-being of any country or community. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, I want now to refer briefly to 
     <lb/>
     a small settlement in Lewisporte district, known 
     <lb/>
     as Laurenceton, where no train, no steamer calls. 
     <lb/>
     There are approximately 80 or 90 families living 
     <lb/>
     there, without any government transportation, 
     <lb/>
     yet these same people always pay their taxes, and 
     <lb/>
     are all independent, and further they do not know 
     <lb/>
     the meaning of dole. To get their supplies, or 
     <lb/>
     freight, these people have to go all the way to 
     <lb/>
     Botwood, a distance of 12 or 14 miles, blow high 
     <lb/>
     or blow low. All you gentlemen know where 
     <lb/>
     Botwood is, as usually every November month 
     <lb/>
     the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Kyle</hi> is ordered there by the Railway to keep 
     <lb/>
     the port of Botwood open so that the AND Co. 
     <lb/>
     can load their paper and ship it, while the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Kyle</hi> 
     <lb/>
     keeps the channel free of ise. This same channel 
     <lb/>
     the Laurenceton people must use to get their 
     <lb/>
     freight along in the late fall. This is not good 
     <lb/>
     enough, and provision should be made for them. 
     <lb/>
     I may say, sir, these same people are only four or 
     <lb/>
     five miles away from the Lewisporte — Brown's 
     <lb/>
     Arm road, and if these people could be connected 
     <lb/>
     to that road it would eliminate all this unneces<lb break="no"/>sary risk and hardship. When once joined to the 
     <lb/>
     road they would get their freight by way of 
     <lb/>
     Lewisporte in half an hour by truck. Those people 
     <lb/>
     also are the salt of the earth, and are entitled to 
     <lb/>
     better treatment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Some 18 or 20 years ago the Lewisporte -<lb/>
Boyd's Cove road was surveyed, or partly sur<lb break="no"/>veyed, and not a great deal more has been done 
     <lb/>
     to it since, although some settlements have been 
     <lb/>
     extended a little here and there. This road is of 
     <lb/>
     paramount importance, not only to Lewisporte 
     <lb/>
     district, but to Twillingate district, Fogo district, 
     <lb/>
     and Bonavista North to Weslcyville. This road, 
     <lb/>
     therefore, when completed, can and will serve 
     <lb/>
     more than 30,000 people.... Freight then can be 
     <lb/>
     landed at Lewisporte or Wesleyville, and trucked 
     <lb/>
     from either end of the road as the need arises. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="275"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0275.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">275</fw>
            
<p>
     Then there would be no need of the steamers 
     <lb/>
     being jammed in the ice in December. I am sure 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Ashbourne and Mr. Watton will support 
     <lb/>
     me on this very worthy and urgent road project. 
     <lb/>
     By this road will travel lumbermen, fishermen, 
     <lb/>
     farmers, and tourists.... 
     <lb/>
      </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I listened with 
     <lb/>very great interest indeed to what Major Cashin 
     <lb/>had to say, and nothing would give me more 
     <lb/>pleasure than to be in a position at this moment 
     <lb/>to take up in discussion some of the matters he 
     <lb/>discussed. I am positively itching to discuss the 
     <lb/>matters touched on by Major Cashin. Perhaps the 
     <lb/>opportunity will come my way to do that before 
     <lb/>the Convention ends. Unfortunately, however, I 
     <lb/>have a duty this afternoon that I must perform, 
     <lb/>namely to deal briefly with this supplementary 
     <lb/>report on the operation of Gander airport.... Now, 
     <lb/>Mr. Chairman, when the original report on 
     <lb/>Gander was brought in, I said as plainly as I could 
     <lb/>— well, perhaps I did not exactly say, but I 
     <lb/>certainly hinted very broadly — that in my 
     <lb/>opinion the people and Government of New<lb break="no"/>foundland would not have to pay a dollar of the 
     <lb/>losses that would be run up in operating Gander. 
     <lb/>I was the only one, I believe, who did say that, 
     <lb/>because I had information, gathered at Gander 
     <lb/>and here, that led me strongly to believe it.... Now 
     <lb/>today we have a little more knowledge about it, 
     <lb/>given to the Committee by Mr. Neill, the Com<lb break="no"/>missioner for Public Utilities, who is the final 
     <lb/>boss, in Newfoundland at any rate, over Gander. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I am convinced that this interview that we had 
     <lb/>with Mr. Neill is very strong evidence that my 
     <lb/>original contention was correct. Major Cashin 
     <lb/>put this question to Mr. Neill. Major Cashin said, 
     <lb/>"The government agreed to operate, knowing 
     <lb/>there was going to be a loss, primarily for the 
     <lb/>purpose of helping these air companies?" Mr. 
     <lb/>Neill said, "I go with you except to say that we 
     <lb/>never contemplated there would be a loss on the 
     <lb/>Newfoundland exchequer". Then Major Cashin 
     <lb/>said to him, "You must have some reason for 
     <lb/>that?", and Mr. Neill replied, "Yes". Then Major 
     <lb/>Cashin said, with a question mark in his voice, 
     <lb/>"Great Britain half-indicated they would pay the 
     <lb/>deficit?", and Mr. Neill said, "Well, in brief 
     <lb/>words, we have put up the case to them and they 
     <lb/>have not yet finalised it" (page 3 of the report). 
     <lb/>Major Cashin said again, "Why should New<lb break="no"/>
           

            <cb/>
        foundland be burdened with this expenditure of 
     <lb/>
     $750,000," and Mr. Neill replied, "I am hoping 
     <lb/>
     we will rectify that." I said to him, "When you 
     <lb/>
     did it (that is, took over Gander), did you have 
     <lb/>
     any knowledge or belief that Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     would not have to pay that operating deficit on 
     <lb/>
     Gander?", and he replied, "We always put up the 
     <lb/>
     position that we would require assistance for the 
     <lb/>
     operation of Gander." I said, "To whom?", and 
     <lb/>
     he said, "To the British government." Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin said, "They did not say 'yes' or 'no' they 
     <lb/>
     would pay this deficit?", and he said "Not yet." I 
     <lb/>
     said to him, "Is this the position: you took over 
     <lb/>
     the operation of Gander, believing there would 
     <lb/>
     be a deficit in its operation, and hoping only that 
     <lb/>
     the British government might help Newfound<lb break="no"/>land in paying the deficit?" He said, "I would not 
     <lb/>
     go so far as to say that. We have placed the 
     <lb/>
     position before the British government, stating 
     <lb/>
     that we expect assistance in the operation of 
     <lb/>
     Gander." I asked him, "When did you put that 
     <lb/>
     before them?", and he said, "Several times." I 
     <lb/>
     said, "When was the earliest time? Did you put it 
     <lb/>
     to them before you decided to take over the 
     <lb/>
     airport?", and he replied, "I think it was always 
     <lb/>
     known." It was an understood thing between the 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government and the British 
     <lb/>
     government that if Newfoundland were to take 
     <lb/>
     over the operation of Gander, and if there was to 
     <lb/>
     be a loss each year that Britain, or PICAO,<ref target="#fn_04">[1]</ref> or 
     <lb/>
     someone would have to pay it, but not New<lb break="no"/>foundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is important, extremely important, to know 
     <lb/>
     where we stand on Gander. I won't go so far as 
     <lb/>
     to say that we now know definitely, beyond all 
     <lb/>
     doubt, that the loss in running Gander will not 
     <lb/>
     have to come out of our pockets; we do not know 
     <lb/>
     definitely and finally, and we will not know it 
     <lb/>
     until the government here gets a final official 
     <lb/>
     reply from the British government, but we are 
     <lb/>
     going to get it.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The last thing I have in mind is to defend the 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government. Except for the first 
     <lb/>
     year they were in the country, I have always been 
     <lb/>
     against them.... At the same time, if they have a 
     <lb/>
     word of credit coming to them I see no reason 
     <lb/>
     why I should refuse to give them that word of 
     <lb/>
     credit. If I had thought when l piloted the Gander 
     <lb/>
     report through this Convention just before 
     <lb/>
     Christmas, that the Commission of Government 
    

   
       <note xml:id="fn_04">1 Provisional International Civil Aviation Organisation.</note>
 
 
            <pb n="276"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0276.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">276</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
          

     had agreed to pay the loss, I would have said so.... 
     <lb/>
     But I had to speak the truth as I knew it.... I don't 
     <lb/>
     think the loss on Gander will cost the public chest 
     <lb/>
     of this country a single dollar. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I hope I don't embarrass Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood in the question — I would be rather 
     <lb/>
     surprised if I did, but nevertheless this is a report 
     <lb/>
     brought in by his Committee, and the intimation 
     <lb/>
     that we have from anything brought in is that it 
     <lb/>
     is public, I take it.... We gather that Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood, or his Committee, were advised by 
     <lb/>
     some person, maybe Mr. Pattison, that he advised 
     <lb/>
     the government that the fee for landing should be 
     <lb/>
     $300.... Do you know if that is a fact or not, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood? It is very important. Did the Direc<lb break="no"/>tor say that we should get $300 for a landing fee? 
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I would like very much indeed 
     <lb/>to be able to answer Mr. Higgins frankly; how<lb break="no"/>ever, I can do no more than repeat what is in this 
     <lb/>last page of our report. I asked if $300 for landing 
     <lb/>should be charged, and he said, "I am not going 
     <lb/>to answer that question because it might interfere 
     <lb/>with Pattison." I thought he meant Squadron 
     <lb/>Leader Pattison, who is the Director of Civil 
     <lb/>Aviation. Then I said, "Would you say whether 
     <lb/>or not that it is the opinion of the Director and 
     <lb/>other officials of the Department of Civil Avia<lb break="no"/>tion that it ought to be $300 per landing?", and 
     <lb/>Mr. Neill, said "I certainly will not." Mr. Job said, 
     <lb/>"Would you say they expressed that opinion?" 
     <lb/>He said, "Minutes between Gander and myself 
     <lb/>are privileged." That's all I can say to Mr. Hig<lb break="no"/>gins. I will, however, say this, that a man who is 
     <lb/>an outstanding authority on aviation, and I do not 
     <lb/>refer to Squadron Leader Pattison now, stated to 
     <lb/>me that any amount up to $1 ,000 per landing, that 
     <lb/>is $2,000 per round trip, would be still an 
     <lb/>economic figure to charge the international air 
     <lb/>lines for the use of Gander.... I have a copy of that 
     <lb/>statement, and I delivered it to a Commissioner 
     <lb/>who delivered it to Mr. Neill, or at least he told 
     <lb/>me he did. Anything up to $1,000 per landing 
     <lb/>would be an economic figurel Now when I asked 
     <lb/>him if he had been advised by the Director of 
     <lb/>Civil Aviation, or anyone, if a figure of $300 
     <lb/>would be all right, he would not reply. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I am asking him that.... Did you 
     <lb/>
     have $300 per landing fee as a fishing question, 
     <lb/>
     or it is based on facts? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It was based on knowledge. I 
     <lb/>
     know that the Commissioner for Public Utilities 
    

            <cb/>
           

     was advised officially that $300 ought to be 
     <lb/>
     charged. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> You know that the Commissioner 
     <lb/>
     was advised officially, by, I take it, some member 
     <lb/>
     or the Director of Civil Aviation? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am sorry, I won't say by 
     <lb/>
     whom. Mr. Higgins will appreciate that I cannot, 
     <lb/>
     in honour, repeat information given to me unless 
     <lb/>
     I am permitted to do it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Then I don't think the shorthand 
     <lb/>
     script should have been submitted to the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion. We are not sure if Mr. Smallwood's man of 
     <lb/>
     honour can't tell us, or what it is. We are trying 
     <lb/>
     to figure out why Mr. Smallwood thinks we 
     <lb/>
     should get $300 instead of $85 as a landing fee, 
     <lb/>
     and we are allowed to use that information. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I think we are getting a little 
     <lb/>
     away from the mark. If Gander is costing $1 
     <lb/>
     million a year operating loss, the first question is 
     <lb/>
     who is to pay that loss. It was to find that out , if 
     <lb/>
     we could, that this delegation was appointed to 
     <lb/>
     go and interview the Commissioner for Public 
     <lb/>
     Utilities. We did not exactly find out, but I think 
     <lb/>
     that we are satisfied that whoever does pay, it will 
     <lb/>
     not be Newfoundland. The rest are minor details 
     <lb/>
     compared with who pays the loss.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> ....The point that I rise to mention is 
     <lb/>
     found on page 4 of the repon of the Transporta<lb break="no"/>tion and Communications Committee in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with Gander, wherein it states as follows: 
     <lb/>
     "Mr. Neill, the Commissioner for Public 
     <lb/>
     Utilities, was asked why the Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government had made this decision. His reply 
     <lb/>
     was that it was because Newfoundland was a 
     <lb/>
     member of the Provisional International Civil 
     <lb/>
     Aviation Organisation (PICAO) which organisa<lb break="no"/>tion decided that Gander should be kept upon by 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland." On that point you will remem<lb break="no"/>ber that I tabled a question to the Hon. Mr. Neill, 
     <lb/>
     and he writes me to say that he is in doubt as to 
     <lb/>
     exactly what I meant by that question, which I 
     <lb/>
     thought was obvious and clear to any person, but 
     <lb/>
     he said, "I have my office copy of the minutes of 
     <lb/>
     the meeting of PICAO. I cannot recollect any 
     <lb/>
     reference to Gander." He goes on to say they 
     <lb/>
     attended as part of the British delegation. In the 
     <lb/>
     sixth paragraph he says, "I do not understand the 
     <lb/>
     reference to PICAO — that Gander should be left 
     <lb/>
     open." This report is excellent but this definitely 
     <lb/>
     must be an error. It is important that we have this 
     <lb/>
     definitely decided, because Mr. Neill said he does 


            <pb n="277"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0277.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">277</fw>
          

     not understand that PICAO decided that Gander 
     <lb/>
     should be kept open, and, on the other hand, the 
     <lb/>
     Committee says that PICAO was the organisation 
     <lb/>
     that decided that Gander should be kept open. 
     <lb/>
     Referring to the supplementary report, I notice 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Neill denies that he ever said that. Is he 
     <lb/>
     hedging, or is the Committee in error in the 
     <lb/>
     original document? I wonder if Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
     would say anything about that? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It was at the meeting of the 
     <lb/>
     Finance Committee that Mr. Neill made the state<lb break="no"/>ment, so I still believe that the reason New<lb break="no"/>foundland took it over was that we are a member 
     <lb/>
     of PICAO.... However, in our interview the other 
     <lb/>
     day he said that he did not say it. I don't think 
     <lb/>
     there was a stenographer present at the meeting 
     <lb/>
     of the Finance Committee at which Mr. Neill 
     <lb/>
     made the statement in the first place, but there are 
     <lb/>
     many members of the Finance Committee here 
     <lb/>
     today, and they can easily say whether, according 
     <lb/>
     to their recollection, he made that statement or 
     <lb/>
     not.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> Again on that $300 landing charge. 
     <lb/>
     I wonder could Mr. Smallwood tell us whether 
     <lb/>
     the Director of Civil Aviation came before the 
     <lb/>
     Committee and if he did, what he thought the 
     <lb/>
     landing charge should be? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, Mr. Chairman, when 
     <lb/>
     Squadron Leader Pattison appeared before us, in 
     <lb/>
     view of the fact that he is in a subordinate position 
     <lb/>
     I did not feel that I should embarrass him by 
     <lb/>
     asking him questions on which a decision had 
     <lb/>
     actually been reached by the government as a 
     <lb/>
     whole, on landing fees. I did not ask him, and 
     <lb/>
     neither did any other member of the Committee. 
     <lb/>
     As a matter of fact, when Mr. Pattison appeared 
     <lb/>
     before us the information we sought was more or 
     <lb/>
     less of a background nature.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, could Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood tell us anything about this Canada, 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, United Kingdom agreement? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I think that refers to other bases 
     <lb/>altogether — Torbay, Goose, Stephenville, Har<lb break="no"/>mon Field, etc. Does it refer to Gander? I don't 
     <lb/>think so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Mr. Chairman, sometime ago in this 
     <lb/>
     house I felt that the Committee should have as<lb break="no"/>certained what equipment was in Gander.... That 
     <lb/>
     was all, I understand, belonging to the $1 million 
     <lb/>
     deal. Rumours have been coming out from 
     <lb/>
     Gander that there is a certain amount of equip<lb break="no"/>
                       <cb/>
         ment being removed, some by the Americans to 
     <lb/>
     Harmon Field, and some by the Canadians to 
     <lb/>
     Goose Bay.... I am wondering if that is our 
     <lb/>
     property, Newfoundland's property? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, the million dol<lb break="no"/>lars that Newfoundland is to pay Canada for what 
     <lb/>
     Canada had at Gander does not include any 
     <lb/>
     American equipment, so the Americans could do 
     <lb/>
     what they liked with their own equipment. The 
     <lb/>
     great bulk of it they moved to St. John's. They 
     <lb/>
     formed a pool of equipment they intended to sell, 
     <lb/>
     and to it they brought the equipment they owned 
     <lb/>
     in Gander. The buildings were not owned by 
     <lb/>
     them but by the Canadians. The $25 million that 
     <lb/>
     the Canadians spent on capital account included 
     <lb/>
     the buildings they built to be occupied by the 
     <lb/>
     Americans. They now belong to the Department 
     <lb/>
     of Civil Aviation of the Newfoundland govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     So far as equipment is concerned the vast bulk 
     <lb/>
     of it was included in that purchase price. That 
     <lb/>
     which was not included was shipped back to 
     <lb/>
     Canada or in here to War Assets Corporation for 
     <lb/>
     sale, or, to a limited extent, remains at Gander. 
     <lb/>
     Now so far as the tremendous quantity of equip<lb break="no"/>ment owned by Newfoundland is concerned, the 
     <lb/>
     government has disposed of some of it.... There 
     <lb/>
     is a tremendous surplus of certain things at 
     <lb/>
     Gander, and I suppose one day they will be offer<lb break="no"/>ing a lot of it for sale.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Mr. Chairman, I am wondering 
     <lb/>
     whether or not the government actually knows 
     <lb/>
     what equipment was there when it was taken 
     <lb/>
     over. We don't know, therefore, in my opinion, 
     <lb/>
     they could move a lot of things that we did not 
     <lb/>
     know were there, and that is why I say surely the 
     <lb/>
     government should make an inventory.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> They have an inventory, and 
     <lb/>
     when I was at Gander at Christmas I saw it. It is 
     <lb/>
     a huge thing — I suppose a thousand sheets.... 
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I don't want to stop Mr. Fudge on 
     <lb/>this matter, but I would like to direct Mr. 
     <lb/>Smallwood's attention to this $300 matter once 
     <lb/>more. The importance of it is that from your 
     <lb/>report we understand that we are losing half a 
     <lb/>million a year at Gander. In the letter from 
     <lb/>Squadron Leader Pattison to your Committee he 
     <lb/>states that by mid-I947 we might expect 1,000 
     <lb/>planes a month. The normal fee is less than $100. 
     <lb/>That would mean that we would have $200 more 
     <lb/>per plane, which would give us $2.4 million a 
     

            <pb n="278"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0278.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">278</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
         
     year, or $1 million over the deficit.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I think that I will unbutton a 
     <lb/>
     little. Here's the position: Newfoundland is under 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government, therefore New<lb break="no"/>foundland is under the Parliament of Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain and the government of Great Britain, and 
     <lb/>
     the Dominions Office of Great Britain, and will 
     <lb/>
     so remain so long as we have Commission 
     <lb/>
     government. We are virtually a branch of the 
     <lb/>
     British government. Now the British government 
     <lb/>
     has a tremendous stake in post-war civil aviation. 
     <lb/>
     Civil aviation is becoming as important in world 
     <lb/>
     trade as the merchant marine used to be before 
     <lb/>
     the war. If Britain is to have her place in the sun 
     <lb/>
     commercially speaking in the world, she must 
     <lb/>
     have a great part to play in civil aviation. One of 
     <lb/>
     the biggest trumps that Britain had was virtually 
     <lb/>
     control over Gander. We here in Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     look at Gander as our airport — we New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders who say that Gander should be 
     <lb/>
     made to fit into the scheme of things in such a 
     <lb/>
     way as to be the greatest possible benefit to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. But you could not expect the 
     <lb/>
     British government to look at Gander in that light 
     <lb/>
     at all. If I were in the government of Great Britain, 
     <lb/>
     as Minister of Civil Aviation, I would have on the 
     <lb/>
     wall in my office a great map of the world, and I 
     <lb/>
     would have drawn on the map in red lines the 
     <lb/>
     British airways and air routes, and show on that 
     <lb/>
     map the airports that Britain controlled,' and 
     <lb/>
     could look at it and say, "Here is what we have; 
     <lb/>
     these are our bargaining weapons in dealing with 
     <lb/>
     the Americans", and amongst them I would place 
     <lb/>
     Gander. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As a Newfoundlander I would look at it in an 
     <lb/>
     entirely different light. Great Britain, God 
     <lb/>
     knows, needed some weapons to fight the 
     <lb/>
     Americans in civil aviation. Before the war ended 
     <lb/>
     the Americans had thousands of planes ready to 
     <lb/>
     fly, and tens of thousands of personnel ready to 
     <lb/>
     fly them, millions of money. The American 
     <lb/>
     policy was for each nation to be on its own, act 
     <lb/>
     unilaterally, grab all the airways and air traffic of 
     <lb/>
     the world, and if America had been able to do that 
     <lb/>
     now, in 1947 she would dominate the airways of 
     <lb/>
     the world. Britain, on the other hand, had no 
     <lb/>
     planes, not even yet has she got her new models 
     <lb/>
     ready to fly. If America had been able to go ahead 
     <lb/>
     on her own today Britain would be out of the 
     <lb/>
     picture, but Britain is not out of the picture, and 
     <lb/>
     one of the reasons is that Britain virtually control<lb break="no"/>
            
            <cb/>
         led Gander, because they could say to America, 
     <lb/>
     "Look here, you think you can do as you like, 
     <lb/>
     charge as little as you like, etc., but you can't 
     <lb/>
     because you can't use Gander without our con<lb break="no"/>sent, neither can you use that other big airport in 
     <lb/>
     Africa, or the one in India; and if you want to use 
     <lb/>
     them you are going to play ball with us, or agree 
     <lb/>
     to our policy of multilateral action, agreeing on 
     <lb/>
     policy and all doing the same thing. That's what 
     <lb/>
     you have to agree to or you won't have the use of 
     <lb/>
     the airports that we control." That was a perfectly 
     <lb/>
     reasonable attitude for Britain to take, thinking of 
     <lb/>
     her own interests. If I had been prime minister of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland and if the British government had 
     <lb/>
     come to me and said, "Look here, Smallwood, 
     <lb/>
     you have an airport at Gander, and it is very 
     <lb/>
     important to us that we should control that air<lb break="no"/>port. We are on the broad of our back, we have 
     <lb/>
     been blitzed and beaten to pieces, and the 
     <lb/>
     Americans have been untouched, and if we don't 
     <lb/>
     do something about it inside a year the Americans 
     <lb/>
     will own all the airports of the world, will you 
     <lb/>
     help us? Will you let us control Gander so that 
     <lb/>
     we can use it for a bargaining weapon in talking 
     <lb/>
     with the Americans?" I would say, "How?", and 
     <lb/>
     they would say, "If we don't allow them to use it 
     <lb/>
     that finishes them for the North Atlantic air 
     <lb/>
     routes." I would say, "Well, I hate to say 'no' to 
     <lb/>
     you, but what is it going to cost us?" They would 
     <lb/>
     say, "Well, we can't ask $300 per landing, be<lb break="no"/>cause if we do that the Americans are going to 
     <lb/>
     demand $300 for our planes crossing the 
     <lb/>
     Pacific." I would say, "But if you are only going 
     <lb/>
     to charge $85 a plane we will lose $l million a 
     <lb/>
     year. We are willing to help you, sure, but what 
     <lb/>
     does Newfoundland get out of it?" Now if they 
     <lb/>
     said, "Look, we will employ all New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders out there, and let you have the 
     <lb/>
     general running of the airport, and we will foot 
     <lb/>
     the bills", I would say, "OK, take it with my 
     <lb/>
     blessing." Now that's the rock bottom position. 
     <lb/>
     Gander has been used up to now not for the 
     <lb/>
     interest of Newfoundland, but for the interest of 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain. I am not saying a word against that, 
     <lb/>
     but I don't want it to cost Newfoundland any<lb break="no"/>thing. We need every dollar we can lay our hands 
     <lb/>
     on in the next 20 years. We can't afford to pay 
     <lb/>
     the loss of Gander. If Britain will pay it, and all 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlanders are employed out there (in<lb break="no"/>cluding those American airlines, and they are 
     <lb/>
     employing men that are not Newfoundlanders), 
    

            <pb n="279"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0279.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">279</fw>
       
     and they get decent pay and decent working 
     <lb/>
     conditions, and it does not cost us anything, then 
     <lb/>
     it is a bargain for us to let Britain dominate 
     <lb/>
     Gander in the international field. That's the 
     <lb/>
     thought as I see it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Thank you very much for your 
     <lb/>
     short answer, Mr. Smallwood. I move that we 
     <lb/>
     increase the landing fees of Mr. Smallwood in the 
     <lb/>
     future! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> I can only infer from Mr. Small<lb break="no"/>wood's remarks that the British government ex<lb break="no"/>ploited us, and that the British government were 
     <lb/>
     traitors to us. I won't say any more on that, but if 
     <lb/>
     I think that Mr. Smallwood is bound, as a New<lb break="no"/>foundlander, to incorporate this in the general 
     <lb/>
     report that he has given.... Gander as was and as 
     <lb/>
     is are two different things. It was necessary to 
     <lb/>
     spend more money to change over to a peace<lb break="no"/>time basis. Who is to find that money? New<lb break="no"/>foundland. Who is to find it next year? 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. Who is to get the accommoda<lb break="no"/>tion? The British government. I am quite sure that 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain will recover her economic security 
     <lb/>
     in the near future, and I don't see why we should 
     <lb/>
     go on year after year spending money to keep 
     <lb/>
     Gander alive. What is more, it is still a big ques<lb break="no"/>tion as to whether Gander will be a success or not. 
     <lb/>
     Are we going to pay for the experiment? If it is a 
     <lb/>
     flop, we are a flop with it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am very much in sympathy 
     <lb/>
     with what Mr. Miller says, but I don't think he 
     <lb/>
     quoted me right. I did not say that the British 
     <lb/>
     government exploited us. I did not say that, be<lb break="no"/>cause I did not think it. If the British government 
     <lb/>
     is footing the bills, and if 1,000 or 1,200 New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders are getting work and decent wages, 
     <lb/>
     that is not exploitation. If it is, God send a lot 
     <lb/>
     more like it. If we get work at Gander under 
     <lb/>
     decent conditions, and there is a loss of a million 
     <lb/>
     a year to do it, and Britain pays that loss, not 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, that is not exploitation.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I am still in doubt if he really feels 
     <lb/>
     that we can get $300 as a landing fee or not. 
     <lb/></p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I will say this very briefly. If we 
     <lb/>had our own government, responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and I am opposed to it just as much as 
     <lb/>Major Cashin is for it, but if we had it, we could 
     <lb/>charge what we liked to land at Gander. We could 
     <lb/>charge $5,000, or $5 million or $300. If we 
     <lb/>charged $300, the airlines would pay it and use 
     <lb/>Gander, but we would only break even, and we 
     

            <cb/>
            

     break even now if Britain pays the difference. 
     <lb/>
      </p>

            <p>Mr. Higgins I follow you, but there are too 
     <lb/>many "ifs" in it as far as I am concerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, it is not my fault that we 
     <lb/>
     have no responsible government is it? ... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> To get down to tin tacks. Will you 
     <lb/>
     get any plane company to pay those fees? If not 
     <lb/>
     why talk about it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> If it would pay them to skip 
     <lb/>
     Gander they would skip it, but how could they do 
     <lb/>
     it? It's a question of gas, from New York to 
     <lb/>
     Gander, the number of extra passengers that a 
     <lb/>
     plane can take on knowing that she can refuel at 
     <lb/>
     Gander. Up to $300 would pay any plane. It is 
     <lb/>
     true that in December, you may remember, some 
     <lb/>
     planes overflew Gander, nonstop from New York 
     <lb/>
     to Ireland, which they did because they only had 
     <lb/>
     a part load of passengers. They are always filled 
     <lb/>
     coming from Europe to America, but sometimes 
     <lb/>
     they are only half full going from America to 
     <lb/>
     Europe.... Under ordinary conditions, for years to 
     <lb/>
     come, planes must land at Gander.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I can't understand Mr. Small<lb break="no"/>wood's figuring. On $85 per flight for landing the 
     <lb/>
     loss would be approximately $1 million a year. If 
     <lb/>
     we charge $300, that is increase the landing fee 
     <lb/>
     almost four times, according to Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
     we are still only breaking even. That does not 
     <lb/>
     make sense to me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, Mr. Chairman. it is all 
     <lb/>
     very hypothetical. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I can't understand why the British 
     <lb/>
     government, if they are going to pay this dif<lb break="no"/>ference, can't tell us and let us stop this hackling. 
     <lb/>
     I think until they say they are going to pay us, we 
     <lb/>
     have got to pay it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I move that the report be received. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Any further discussion? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I am afraid that I am unable to 
     <lb/>
     venture any opinion this afternoon as to what 
     <lb/>
     would be a just and equitable charge for these 
     <lb/>
     airplanes that have to use our soil, but one thing 
     <lb/>
     I know is that when they land on Gander they are 
     <lb/>
     landing on Newfoundland soil. and I think the 
     <lb/>
     time will have to come when we shall have to 
     <lb/>
     protect our natural resources and our assets for 
     <lb/>
    the benefit of the people of Newfoundland. Now 
     <lb/>I can understand why the British government and 
     <lb/>the Dominions Office are in a dual capacity when 
     <lb/>they are protecting the interests of the air routes 
     <lb/>of the British Empire and the people of New<lb break="no"/>
           
            <pb n="280"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-03_Page_0280.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">280</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>

          
     foundland. It is not an easy thing to try and see 
     <lb/>
     two sides of an argument, but it is the right thing 
     <lb/>
     to try and see both sides of the argument. If, and 
     <lb/>
     I do not mean to say that it has been done, but if 
     <lb/>
     we on this side of the Atlantic have been used in 
     <lb/>
     order that favourable treatment might be ac<lb break="no"/>corded to the British in the air routes of the 
     <lb/>
     Pacific, if that has been done, and if New<lb break="no"/>foundland is suffering by having to receive a 
     <lb/>
     lower amount of landing fees, then I think it is 
     <lb/>
     only right that the people who are benefitting 
     <lb/>
     from it should see that Newfoundland is reim<lb break="no"/>bursed, and I am of the opinion and belief that 
     <lb/>
     when this thing is straightened out that it will be 
     <lb/>
     done. I don't see how you can have peace and 
     <lb/>
     concord and goodwill and harmony unless these 
     <lb/>
     things are done on an equitable basis. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We have assets in Newfoundland, be it those 
     <lb/>
     of our forests, fisheries, or minerals (which are a 
     <lb/>
     diminishing asset, for every ton of ore out of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland is one less to come). By reaffores<lb break="no"/>tation we may be able to protect our forests, but 
     <lb/>
     unless we get the full amount of labour that these 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
           

     things will give us, how can Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     prosper? I am of the opinion that in the past 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland has suffered when it has come to 
     <lb/>
     the matter of signing agreements with big com<lb break="no"/>panies. The government should have had the best 
     <lb/>
     possible technical advisers, and if necessary, 
     <lb/>
     should have employed them to see that the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of Newfoundland were fully protected. Now 
     <lb/>
     maybe we should be satisfied if we get the run<lb break="no"/>ning expenses of Gander. I would not be prepared 
     <lb/>
     at this time to give a snap judgement on the 
     <lb/>
     matter. I believe that all our assets should be 
     <lb/>
     turning in something to this country, whether it 
     <lb/>
     be the dry dock or the railway, or our fisheries, 
     <lb/>
     or mines, or the airfields, let them all contribute 
     <lb/>
     their fair share to the up-keep and necessary 
     <lb/>
     expenses of the government.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, it is 5.30, and I 
     <lb/>
     move that the committee rise and report having 
     <lb/>
     considered the matter to them referred and passed 
     <lb/>
     same with some amendment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried]</hi> 
    </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head>
     Forestry Committee: Supplementary Report<ref target="#fn_05">[1]</ref>
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Mr. Chairman, all members, I think, 
     <lb/>
     have a copy of this supplementary report on 
     <lb/>
     Forestry, and I now move that this report be 
     <lb/>
     received.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention agreed to proceed with the<lb/>report immediately, and resolved into a commit<lb break="no"/>tee of the whole]</hi>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Some months ago when the 
     <lb/>
     Forestry Report was originally introduced, we 
     <lb/>
     moved to accept the report subject to further 
     <lb/>
     information. We made some further investiga<lb break="no"/>tions in the Department of Natural Resources 
     <lb/>
     with regard to timber resources on the Labrador. 
     <lb/>
     We could not get any, and finally we contacted 
     <lb/>
     the Bowater people at Comer Brook, and a week 
     <lb/>
     ago Mr. Lewin, General Manager of the Bowater 
     <lb/>
     Paper Corporation, came before the Committee 
     <lb/>
     and gave us his views and brought a copy of the 
     <lb/>
     survey which Bowaters made in 1937, showing 
     <lb/>
     approximately 25 million cords of commercial 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
            
     timber situated in the Hamilton Inlet area of 
     <lb/>
     Labrador. Of this 6,000 square miles, some 350 
     <lb/>
     square miles are under lease and the balance is 
     <lb/>
     retained by the Crown. We have 5,500 square 
     <lb/>
     miles of available timber lands on Labrador, on 
     <lb/>
     which is carried around 20 to 25 million cords of 
     <lb/>
     timber. Also if I remember correctly, the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Convention were doubtful as regards 
     <lb/>
     what the earning power from our timber resour<lb break="no"/>ces would be now, and in the near future. I think 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Lewin has confirmed that in his report, and I 
     <lb/>
     would now ask the Secretary to read this sup<lb break="no"/>plementary report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the supplementary report]</hi> 
   </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> In view of the fact that there is only 
     <lb/>one reporter here today, I move that the commit<lb break="no"/>tee, rise, report progress, and ask leave to sit again 
     <lb/>tomorrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried, and the Convention ad<lb break="no"/>journed]</hi> 
     </p>
   
      
     <note xml:id="fn_05">1 Volume II:63. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note> 
     <lb/>
            
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>