<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-04-14"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-04-14">14 April 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="491" to="493"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0491.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0492.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0493.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-23">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0491">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0491.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0492">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0492.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0493">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0493.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="491"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0491.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">491</fw>
           
<!-- GL, 2017-06-23, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

 <!--  p>
     section do pass as read. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>[The motion carried. The section on coal was 
     <lb/>read and passed, and the section on copper read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     The committee then rose and reported progress, 
     <lb/>
     and the Convention adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     April 14, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
    <emph> Report of the Mining Committee:<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I would suggest that to summarise<lb/>the paragraph on copper read on Saturday that the<lb/>table marked Table l, at the end of the section on<lb/>copper be read. That will summarise the report...<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee briefly discussed the sections on 
     <lb/>copper, gold, lead, asbestos, chrome, salt, 
     <lb/>petroleum, pyrophyllite, limestone, barite, nick<lb break="no"/>el, mica, and marble. The Secretary read the 
     <lb/>section on cement.]</hi>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> When the report of the Local<lb/>Industries Committee was brought in here, that<lb/>report quoted a special memorandum prepared<lb/>for the Committee by the Industrial Development<lb/>Board, and I was particularly struck at the time<lb/>by the reference to cement. The Industrial<lb/>Development Board pointed out what a great pity<lb/>it was that the two main ingredients necessary to<lb/>make cement were separated from each other by<lb/>roughly the width of the country. One was on the<lb/>eastern side of the country, and the other on the<lb/>western. The cost of bringing the two together<lb/>was what caused it to be dropped. Now the Min<lb break="no"/>ing Committee brings a different light on the<lb/>matter. I remember after the remarks I made<lb/>when the Local Industries Report was being<lb/>debated I ran into the Mayor of St. John's, who<lb/>was very enthusiastic about the matter. He told<lb/>me that the St. John's Municipal Council uses<lb/>50,000 bags a year.... That's only one case. If you<lb/>could get cement in this country at reasonable<lb/>price there would be thousands of people using it<lb/>for foundations of their homes and for the erec<lb break="no"/>tion of buildings of all kinds, with remarkable<lb/>progress in construction and industry. This is<lb/>evidently one of the most important sections of<lb/>this report. It absolutely contradicts the report of<lb/>the Industrial Development Board.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>According to this, in the Port-au-Port area<lb/>there are very extensive deposits of gypsum,<lb/>limestone, and silica clay. These are the articles<lb/>necessary for the manufacture of cement. They<lb/>are all within a radius of two miles. The only thing

            <cb/>

      is, you have to import coal to create the heat for<lb/>dehydrating it, or else use hydro-electric power,<lb/>and we understand there is sufficient power in<lb/>that vicinity for this industry. I wonder if<lb/>Mr. Higgins could tell us if anyone is interested,<lb/>and if there is any move on foot to start a cement<lb/>industry, and could he throw a little light on this:<lb/>"The main question is, of course, whether or not<lb/>cement could be produced at a cost comparable<lb/>to the cost of the imported article." What is meant<lb/>by that? What would be the cost? There would be<lb/>the cost of mining and bringing them together to<lb/>the point of the hydro-electric development, etc.,<lb/>all which, surely, should not cost any more,<lb/>speaking generally, than anywhere else. Labour<lb/>is certainly no better paid in this country than in<lb/>Canada, generally speaking, and certainly no bet<lb break="no"/>ter than in the States. You can develop hydro<lb break="no"/>electric energy in this country as cheaply as<lb/>anywhere. What are the prospects of making<lb/>cement? Is there anything doing?<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I don't know if I can enlighten you<lb/>more than I have on this matter. The last sentence<lb/>would be the cost of the finished product, that is<lb/>the selling price compared to the finished article.<lb/>With respect to our contradiction of the Local<lb/>Industries Report, we are satisfied that the infor<lb break="no"/>mation we have given you is correct as far as our<lb/>information goes....<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Why not develop cement out<lb/>there on a worldwide scale? Why not develop it<lb/>for export all over the world? In terms of that kind<lb/>we have to think. I have been watching, looking<lb/>for possibilities of using up our own raw mater<lb break="no"/>ials. I know cement is used all over the world.<lb/>When Mr. Higgins, Major Cashin and I form a<lb/>government, we must see what we can do with<lb/>that.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I think Mr. Smallwood answered his<lb/>own question. There is too big a cement plant in<lb/>Canada and the United States for us to have one.<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> If the cost is too high, it is no use


<note xml:id="fn_01">1 Volume II:313. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
          

    
            <pb n="492"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0492.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">492</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
         

     talking about it.... 
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee then discussed the sections on<lb/>slate, molybdenum, gypsum, manganese, an<lb break="no"/>timony and bismuth. The Secretary read the sec<lb break="no"/>tion on brick-making]</hi></p>


            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, it is quite an 
     <lb/>eye-opener — two plants in Trinity Bay making 
     <lb/>600,000 bricks each, 1,200,000 bricks, and 
     <lb/>Mr. Dawe over at Makinsons, over 2 million 
     <lb/>bricks a year. It's amazing. That's an eye-opener 
     <lb/>to the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I believe that this Section was 
     <lb/>prepared by Mr. Vardy, and he may have some 
     <lb/>comments to add. He will have to be the one to 
     <lb/>answer any comments. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VINC1">Mr. Vincent</persName> Those Trinity Bay plants have 
     <lb/>modern methods — has Mr. Dawe's plant? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I worked on this with the other 
     <lb/>members of the Committee, but the plant at 
     <lb/>Snooks Harbour, Mr. Smith's plant, has some 
     <lb/>modern machinery, but they agree that it is not as 
     <lb/>modern as it should be. They tried to get in some 
     <lb/>machinery duty free but did not succeed, though 
     <lb/>finally they did get in one machine. It is quite an 
     <lb/>old industry, and naturally the people are very 
     <lb/>proud to find that the tests of the shale showed an 
     <lb/>abundant quantity, and it has proved very suc<lb break="no"/>cessful. We believe that the time is not far distant 
     <lb/>when the people owning the two brickyards over 
     <lb/>there will amalgamate. The chances are they will 
     <lb/>do that, and there will be a large company formed 
     <lb/>to manufacture brick out of this shale. In conver<lb break="no"/>sation with Professor Hayes, he informed us that 
     <lb/>this shale was of a very high quality, and the brick 
     <lb/>made from that will stand up against the very best 
     <lb/>imported article, and he could not see why there 
     <lb/>should not be an industry there employing from 
     <lb/>100 to 200 men. One thing I would like to say for 
     <lb/>that brick industry over there, is that it has gone 
     <lb/>on continuously over a period of 40 or 50 years. 
     <lb/>One of the older brickyards closed down, but 
     <lb/>these other two yards have employed workers 
     <lb/>right through. They paid reasonable wages, and 
     <lb/>although the owners did not earn very much 
     <lb/>profit, yet, at the same time, those employed 
     <lb/>made a comfortable living and the owners of the 
     <lb/>yards have always come through If there is any 
     <lb/>further information I can give I will. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I may say I was responsible for the section on 
     <lb/>
     slate. I have been through the slate mines in 
     <lb/>
     England and Wales, and worked in a slate quarry 


            <cb/>
          

     when I was so young, that when a Welshman sent 
     <lb/>
     me in to see what time it was, I went in and looked 
     <lb/>
     up at the steam guage and told him it was quarter 
     <lb/>
     past 90. I remember that quite well. I did not even 
     <lb/>
     know the time. Those quarries were worked for 
     <lb/>
     the period given in the report, and finally they 
     <lb/>
     found that owing to the very great cost of 
     <lb/>
     transportation in moving the slate from here to 
     <lb/>
     England, they could not compete with the Welsh 
     <lb/>
     quarries. The last that was sent over, they finished 
     <lb/>
     up loading the ship with cod oil in common casks. 
     <lb/>
     The ship got out and met rough weather, and by 
     <lb/>
     the time they got over there the whole thing was 
     <lb/>
     slate dust. That finished it for Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     There is some talk of having the quarries opened 
     <lb/>
     to manufacture slate dust for mineralised roofing, 
     <lb/>
     but the smooth roofing seems to have taken the 
     <lb/>
     place of it, and there is not much hope of doing 
     <lb/>
     anything about it, but the brick industry has a 
     <lb/>
     future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:STAR1">Mr. Starkes</persName> In connection with this report here 
     <lb/>
     about Mr. Dawe operating near Brigus, it says the 
     <lb/>
     quality is equal to the imported, and they have 
     <lb/>
     also got a lot of machinery coming in. Further on 
     <lb/>
     in the report is this, "We understand the company 
     <lb/>
     is operating without any concessions with regard 
     <lb/>
     to duty". Does not that machinery come in duty 
     <lb/>
     free as far as all local industries are concerned? 
     <lb/>
     Don't they get their machinery duty free? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> No, you must be a large company to 
     <lb/>
     get anything in duty free. A small industry does 
     <lb/>
     not have a chance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> And it has got to be foreign. 
 </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> Yes, If you are a large company, 
     <lb/>sure, you can comera few politicians and you are 
     <lb/>OK for getting machinery in. I was for years with 
     <lb/>the present government trying to bring in wire 
     <lb/>netting free to dry fish on. A large American 
     <lb/>concern offered to give it free to the fishermen, 
     <lb/>the Philadelphia bankers guaranteed this firm and 
     <lb/>they offered to ship it, but the government would 
     <lb/>not consent to let the wire netting in duty free, 
     <lb/>with the result that the company withdrew. 
     <lb/>Samples were sent away, 900 bags by the Shaw 
     <lb/>Steamship Co., and the company would have 
     <lb/>done a large business in this country, but it was 
     <lb/>turned down because the material which they 
     <lb/>wanted to give away to the fishermen was not 
     <lb/>allowed in duty free. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VINC1">Mr. Vincent</persName> If they had modern methods at 
     <lb/>
     George's Brook and Snooks Harbour, would 


            <pb n="493"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-14_Page_0493.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">493</fw>
        

     production he stepped up? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> It is more or less the old crude way. 
     <lb/>
     The clay is taken from the pits by wheelbarrow, 
     <lb/>
     and goes to elevators and into the crusher, and 
     <lb/>
     down into the moulds, and the bricks are cut off 
     <lb/>
     by a string of wires passing through the moulds. 
     <lb/>
     Afterwards they are taken out and pass to the kiln, 
     <lb/>
     then they are sun dried. It's the old crude 
     <lb/>
     methods, and I believe if they had more modern 
     <lb/>
     methods the production would be stepped up, but 
     <lb/>
     then again you are up against the imported article 
     <lb/>
     being superior, and in order to make the industry 
     <lb/>
     worthwhile you will have to condemn the clay 
     <lb/>
     pits and use the shale. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Chairman, the duty on 
     <lb/>
     machinery coming in for brick is free. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Won't Mr. Vardy confirm the 
     <lb/>
     fact that one of the gentlemen making brick down 
     <lb/>
     his way went away recently to the States and 
     <lb/>
     visited a number of up-to-date brick factories, 
     <lb/>
     and has plans to improve his plant in Trinity Bay? 
     <lb/>
     Isn't that true? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> Yes, I understand it is true. They 
     <lb/>
     have plans in mind to get together on it over there 
     <lb/>
     and try to use the shale. There is an unlimited 
     <lb/>
     quantity of shale. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:STAR1">Mr. Starkes</persName> The machinery for making brick is 
     <lb/>
     duty free, and your Committee must have made 
     <lb/>
     a mistake. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I have not consulted the tariff on this 
     <lb/>
     myself. That was always my knowledge, and I 
     <lb/>
     know Mr. Smith had trouble on that. Is that a 
     <lb/>
     recent tariff? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Well this tariff is issued by the 
     <lb/>
     Customs in June, 1946, and included quite a lot 
     <lb/>
     of machinery for various purposes, including 
     <lb/>
     machinery for making brick, and it's duty free the 
     <lb/>
     same as cordage machinery for making twine, 
     <lb/>
     that's duty free. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Its nice to know the Mining Com<lb break="no"/>mittee made one slip! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> All those bricks that are made, 
     <lb/>
     are they used locally? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I don't know of any local made brick 
     <lb/>
     being exported. I know we are importing a lot of 
     <lb/>
     brick, but I don't know of any being exported. It 
     <lb/>
     has been stated that the main complaint against 
     <lb/>
     our local brick is that it is very coarse and absorbs 
     <lb/>
     too much moisture. It can't stand up over a period 
     <lb/>
     of years against the hard brick. Of course, there 
     <lb/>
     is the hard and soft, I may say they use the hard 
     <lb/>
     brick for chimneys, but I think that's the main 
     <lb/>
     complaint. The brick manufactured from clay has 
     <lb/>
     been very porous, but the brick manufactured 
     <lb/>
     from this shale can be hardened up so that, as the 
     <lb/>
     report says, "it will be like steel". The opinion is 
     <lb/>
     that an industry should be started immediately. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I don't want to disagree with 
     <lb/>Mr. Vardy again, but there has been some brick 
     <lb/>exported. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I said "to my knowledge"; I did not 
     <lb/>
     say there was not any exported. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The section was adopted. The committee began<lb/>discussion of the section on water-power, and<lb/>then rose and reported progress. The Convention<lb/>adjourned]</hi>
            </p>

    

<!-- GL, 2017-06-23, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
   
            <!--<p>
     April 15, 1947 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>[The Report of the Finance Committee was read by Mr. Cashin.¹ The Convention adjourned. ]<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     April 16, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Mining Committee:² 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> When we adjourned this report we 
     <lb/>
     were dealing with water-power.³ The table has 
     <lb/>
     been read, and Mr. Banfield was to give us some 
     <lb/>
     figures of estimated horsepower. I would ask you 
     <lb/>
     to mark on the tables the figures which Mr. Ban- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     field will read out. I would like to say we cannot 
     <lb/>
     vouch for the accuracy of these figures. We are 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     giving them to you as we got them. We are 
     <lb/>
     informed they are only an estimate. They will 
     <lb/>
     give you some idea, though not very accurate, of 
     <lb/>
     the potential horsepower in the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Banfield Mobile River 3,000 hp 
     <lb/>
     Petty Harbour 1,800 
     <lb/>
     Tors Cove &amp; Rocky River 4,493 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     ¹Volume II:369.<lb/>²Volume II:313.<lb/>³Volume II:354. The editors were unable to find the table on water-power. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
    </div>     </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>