<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-04-01"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-04-01">1 April 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.

          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="450" to="465"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0450.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0451.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0452.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0453.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0454.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0455.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0456.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0457.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0458.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0459.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0460.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0461.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0462.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0463.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0464.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0465.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-23">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0450">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0450.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0451">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0451.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0452">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0452.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0453">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0453.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0454">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0454.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0455">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0455.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0456">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0456.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0457">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0457.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0458">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0458.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0459">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0459.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0460">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0460.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0461">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0461.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0462">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0462.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0463">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0463.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0464">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0464.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0465">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0465.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="450"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0450.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">450</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
         
<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     April 1, 1947 
</head>

            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>Election of the Ottawa Delegatio</emph>n 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I have this afternoon received 
     <lb/>
     the following communication from His Excellen<lb break="no"/>cy the Governor, which I will ask the Secretary 
     <lb/>
     to read to the Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p>
     His Excellency the Governor has been 
     <lb/>
     informed by the High Commissioner for 
     <lb/>
     Canada in Newfoundland that the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government will be happy to receive a 
     <lb/>
     delegation from the National Convention of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland at a mutually convenient 
     <lb/>
     date. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Canadian government is of the 
     <lb/>
     opinion that the questions to be discussed 
     <lb/>
     with the delegation are of such complexity 
     <lb/>
     and of such significance for both countries 
     <lb/>
     that it is essential to have a complete and 
     <lb/>
     comprehensive exchange of information and 
     <lb/>
     a full and careful argument of both panics of 
     <lb/>
     all issues involved, so that an accurate ap<lb break="no"/>preciation of the position may be gained on 
     <lb/>
     each side. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Canadian government is confident 
     <lb/>
     that the friendship and co-operation which 
     <lb/>
     have marked the relations of our two 
     <lb/>
     countries should provide a firm basis for our 
     <lb/>
     discussions. The delegation from the Nation<lb break="no"/>al Convention will be warmly welcomed in 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Government House, St. John's, Nfld. April 1, 
     <lb/>1947. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     I take it that following the precedent of a few 
     <lb/>
     weeks ago, the next matter is to resolve the Con<lb break="no"/>vention into a committee of the whole for the 
     <lb/>
     purpose of electing this delegation, if someone 
     <lb/>
     will now make a motion to that effect. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> Mr. Chairman, in my opinion, 
     <lb/>
     before any such delegation is elected we should 
     <lb/>
     have the findings of the delegation to London 
     <lb/>
     first, in order to get a complete picture of the 
     <lb/>
     whole set-up. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The matter is entirely in the 
     <lb/>
     hands of the Convention, but I suggest that this 
     <lb/>
     delegation has a very substantial amount of work 
     <lb/>
     to do before they can leave to discuss the question 
     <lb/>
     of confederation with the Canadian government. 
     <lb/>
     It is not our desire to unduly prolong the length 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention, and in all probability the 
     <lb/>
     delegation to London will have returned by the 


            <cb/>
        

     middle of May, around which time the delegation 
     <lb/>
     to Ottawa should be ready to leave. In the mean<lb break="no"/>time it is perfectly obvious they will have a 
     <lb/>
     tremendous amount of work to do. We have 
     <lb/>
     asked the Canadian government to receive a 
     <lb/>
     delegation, and they have accepted the idea. It is 
     <lb/>
     obvious now that we must get ready for that 
     <lb/>
     delegation to go. I am not going into any details 
     <lb/>
     now, but I suggest there is a tremendous amount 
     <lb/>
     of work to do locally. They have to take up the 
     <lb/>
     possible repercussion of the change from the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland to the Canadian tariff, the amount 
     <lb/>
     of the revenue that will be left to us, what amount 
     <lb/>
     would be required to run a provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ment, where these monies will have to come 
     <lb/>
     from, how much of our money will have to be 
     <lb/>
     taken over by the Canadian government, etc. All 
     <lb/>
     these questions require considerable figuring, in 
     <lb/>
     the course of which deliberations the delegation 
     <lb/>
     will have to have the assistance of some of the 
     <lb/>
     financial advisers of the government, the Asses<lb break="no"/>sor of Taxes and others. In fairness to whoever 
     <lb/>
     the delegation should be, I suggest that they 
     <lb/>
     should be appointed immediately, but it is for you 
     <lb/>
     to decide. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> There may be something in what 
     <lb/>
     you say, and there may be something for them to 
     <lb/>
     do before they go, but I don't see any immediate 
     <lb/>
     rush to do it today. I would like to see this report 
     <lb/>
     cleaned up first, and with that in view I will make 
     <lb/>
     a motion that the election of the delegation to 
     <lb/>
     Canada be postponed until we finish this Public 
     <lb/>
     Health report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I have much pleasure in seconding 
     <lb/>
     that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You have heard the motion. Is 
     <lb/>
     there any further discussion? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I see no objection to electing the 
     <lb/>
     delegation to Canada immediately, but I also see 
     <lb/>
     no objection to delaying it until this report is 
     <lb/>
     finished. Seeing it has been moved and seconded 
     <lb/>
     I am prepared to accept it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Is the Convention ready for the 
     <lb/>
     question? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Suppose the report finishes 
     <lb/>
     today, according to the motion the election will 
     <lb/>
     follow the completion of the debate on the report. 
     <lb/>
     Is that what you have in mind? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="451"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0451.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">451</fw>
            
<p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> The motion I made was that the 
     <lb/>
     question of the election should come up after the 
     <lb/>
     completion of this report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Do you mean its adoption, be<lb break="no"/>cause you recall Major Cashin's motion of 
     <lb/>
     yesterday, which he withdrew to bring up again 
     <lb/>
     on the motion of the adoption of this report? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> That might take us another three 
     <lb/>weeks. No, I mean the completion of our debate 
     <lb/>on it, Major Cashin's motion might keep us a 
     <lb/>month. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> May I suggest that your motion 
     <lb/>
     should be that the election be deferred until the 
     <lb/>
     orders of the day are completed? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I am not up on parliamentary 
     <lb/>
     procedure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That will follow the report of the 
     <lb/>
     Committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Supposing we don't finish today, 
     <lb/>
     it might be necessary to continue tomorrow? 
     <lb/>
 </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I can't see why we should not go ahead 
     <lb/>now, it has to be done sometime. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Well, I thought if we finish 
     <lb/>
     tonight we can go ahead with the election. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> I am entirely in accord with the 
     <lb/>
     sentiments of Mr. Job. Sometime ago we decided 
     <lb/>
     we would send a couple of delegations, and when 
     <lb/>
     the letter was brought in here informing us that 
     <lb/>
     one such delegation would be received we went 
     <lb/>
     ahead and elected it. I don't see why we should 
     <lb/>
     waste any further time. We have known that we 
     <lb/>
     were going to send a delegation to Ottawa, and 
     <lb/>
     frankly I did not know that today might be the day 
     <lb/>
     of the election, but I have known that we would 
     <lb/>
     be sending a delegation, and I have in mind who 
     <lb/>
     I should like to see on that delegation. I don't 
     <lb/>
     need any further consideration or advice, and I 
     <lb/>
     don't see why the matter should not be disposed 
     <lb/>
     of and then get on with our regular business. 
     <lb/>
     There has been altogether too much pussy-foot<lb break="no"/>ing around here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCA7">Mr. McCarthy</persName> I was going to say much the 
     <lb/>
     same as Mr. Nowell. It is only a matter of 20 
     <lb/>
     minutes or so. We all knew for some time that 
     <lb/>
     there would be a delegation to Ottawa, and there 
     <lb/>
     was no comment last time when the delegation 
     <lb/>
     was elected to go to London. According to the 
     <lb/>
     motion that the delegation should proceed to 
     <lb/>
     London and the other should proceed to Ottawa 
     <lb/>
     there was nothing in that motion to say that the 
     <lb/>
     delegation could not be elected before the other 
 

            <cb/>
           

     one had returned; so I don't see why we should 
     <lb/>
     delay. Let's get it over with 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I think Mr. Hickman's motion 
     <lb/>
     is reasonable. If we finish this report tonight, we 
     <lb/>
     can then get on with the election. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I am perfectly satisfied to 
     <lb/>
     withdraw it. I thought we would clean up one 
     <lb/>
     thing first, but I am perfectly satisfied to 
     <lb/>
     withdraw it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I don't want to hold up the thing at 
     <lb/>
     all, but the orders of the day were to continue with 
     <lb/>
     the Report of Public Health and Welfare and I 
     <lb/>
     don't see why we should inject anything into the 
     <lb/>
     orders of the day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> This is a communication from 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency the Governor and that's why it 
     <lb/>
     was introduced at the beginning of the session. I 
     <lb/>
     received this communication since lunch, no one 
     <lb/>
     knew I had it, but I felt it was my duty to bring it 
     <lb/>
     before the Convention immediately. What the 
     <lb/>
     Convention does with it is for the Convention to 
     <lb/>
     decide. It seems to me that we are only following 
     <lb/>
     the precedent that we set a few weeks ago when 
     <lb/>
     we elected the delegation to London. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Vote on the question and let the 
     <lb/>
     house decide. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I seconded that motion, but I am 
     <lb/>
     willing to let it go as you wish. I don't like Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Newell's saying that we are pussy-footing 
     <lb/>
     around. Any delegation that goes from this Con<lb break="no"/>vention is important and there is no nonsense 
     <lb/>
     about it. I don't know what is going on, because 
     <lb/>
     there is so much inside and outside stuff going 
     <lb/>
     on, and it's time we got down to rock bottom, It 
     <lb/>
     seems to me there are some who are bent on 
     <lb/>
     selling the country or tying its hands. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> If you will excuse me, please, no 
     <lb/>
     delegation from this Convention can possibly sell 
     <lb/>
     this country, or in any way tie the country's 
     <lb/>
     hands. I want that to be distinctly understood. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I will withdraw that, sir. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> I find that Mr. Ballam and I are very 
     <lb/>
     much in accord, and it was precisely for some of 
     <lb/>
     the things he hinted at that I would like to have 
     <lb/>
     the election now. Let's have it — now is the time. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> That's what you think! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> I am with Mr. Ballam on Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Hickman's motion, for the reason that I have not 
     <lb/>
     given any thought to it, and I am not prepared to 
     <lb/>
     select members of this Convention at this mo<lb break="no"/>ment; but if we proceed with the business before 
  

            <pb n="452"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0452.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">452</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
        

     the Chair, I would have time to think it over. I 
     <lb/>
     would not like to think that there is going to be 
     <lb/>
     anything rigged in the way of selecting delegates 
     <lb/>
     to go to Ottawa. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I can assure you, Mr. Penney, 
     <lb/>
     that there has been nothing rigged. No one in the 
     <lb/>
     world knew of this except myself and His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency until this afternoon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> I know that, but there was whisper<lb break="no"/>ing going around after the delegation for England 
     <lb/>
     was elected that there was a kind of a selection 
     <lb/>
     made or agreed upon. Whether that was so or not 
     <lb/>
     I don't know; I did not have any part in it and I 
     <lb/>
     voted for the delegates I thought best. I don't 
     <lb/>
     agree that we are wasting time if we proceed with 
     <lb/>
     the business where we left off last night, and then 
     <lb/>
     select the delegates and give us all a fair chance. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FOWL2">Mr. Fowler</persName> I would like to support Mr. 
     <lb/>Hickman's motion simply because on looking 
     <lb/>around here I see six or seven seats vacant, and 
     <lb/>possibly by the time we have this disposed of the 
     <lb/>members may be here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Let me be quite sure what your 
     <lb/>
     motion is, or have you withdrawn it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I suggest that we put the motion 
     <lb/>
     which is that the election be deferred until this 
     <lb/>
     report is finished and adopted, except for the 
     <lb/>
     proviso of Major Cashin, but until the debate is 
     <lb/>
     concluded, and immediately after that proceed 
     <lb/>
     with the election. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The debate of the committee of 
     <lb/>
     the whole. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The motion is then that the elec<lb break="no"/>tion take place after the completed report of the 
     <lb/>
     committee of the whole has been received. Does 
     <lb/>
     everybody understand that clearly? When the 
     <lb/>
     committee of the whole on the Public Health and 
     <lb/>
     Welfare Report has reported that they have con<lb break="no"/>sidered the matter and passed it and recommend 
     <lb/>
     that it be received and laid on the table of the 
     <lb/>
     House, after that the election takes place. Is that 
     <lb/>
     it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> It strikes me that if you are going 
     <lb/>
     to wait until the report is adopted, and there is talk 
     <lb/>
     of adjouming until after the Easter recess, in that 
     <lb/>
     case it could very well be that the election would 
     <lb/>
     not take place until after the Easter recess. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I thought that it would be com<lb break="no"/>pleted today. I had no intention of delaying it till 
     <lb/>
     after Easter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> We decided here a little while ago to 
     <lb/>
     send two delegations, and it was the under<lb break="no"/>standing that the delegation would be chosen for 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa immediately we learnt from that country 
     <lb/>
     that they would receive that delegation. I think 
     <lb/>
     we should all be big and broad enough to face the 
     <lb/>
     issue now and then get on with the report. None 
     <lb/>
     of us knew this was coming up, but I think we 
     <lb/>
     should face up to it now. We are all in the same 
     <lb/>
     boat, and then we won't be accused of gauging 
     <lb/>
     up on anyone. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I would suggest that in any event 
     <lb/>
     it would be the last business before the Easter 
     <lb/>
     recess. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The motion is that the election 
     <lb/>
     of the delegation to Canada be the last business 
     <lb/>
     before the Easter recess. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I am not trying to obstruct the 
     <lb/>
     progress of the House, but I understand that it was 
     <lb/>
     something of a similar nature to the last one and 
     <lb/>
     it was acted upon immediately. Is this going to be 
     <lb/>
     regarded as discourteous or not? This is merely a 
     <lb/>
     thought, not that it matters to me much, but it 
     <lb/>
     would look a little discourteous. I would like the 
     <lb/>
     members to think that over before they make a 
     <lb/>
     decision. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> May I point out that there was 
     <lb/>
     no other business before the House at the time? 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I ask you to consider the point 
     <lb/>that has been suggested by Mr. Higgins. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HANN1">Mr. Hannon</persName> I would like to also suggest that 
     <lb/>
     previous to the election of the delegation to Lon<lb break="no"/>don every member of this Convention was fully 
     <lb/>
     aware of the fact that the election was to take 
     <lb/>
     place, I am not sure, but I think at least two days 
     <lb/>
     previous. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I don't think that is correct, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Harmon. I gave nobody any information about it 
     <lb/>
     until I brought the document into this chamber. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> If you remember, I came in a little 
     <lb/>late and those who refused to be nominated were 
     <lb/>sitting at the table and I did not know what they 
     <lb/>were sitting there for then. I did not know what it 
     <lb/>was all about. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HANN1">Mr. Hannon</persName> I must admit I did not get it from 
     <lb/>
     you, sir, but from hearsay. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I believe there were some 
     <lb/>
     suspicions, and that was because the House was 
     <lb/>
     called together when there was apparently no 
     <lb/>
     business to go ahead with. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> It is my opinion that we are wast<lb break="no"/>
         

            <pb n="453"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0453.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">453</fw>
          

     ing time and playing petty politics. Let's clean 
     <lb/>
     this up and be done with it now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> I am agreeable to anything, but I am 
     <lb/>
     not very diplomatic about it, and I am not going 
     <lb/>
     to try to be. I believe Mr. Penney said there has 
     <lb/>
     been a lot of talk about the previous delegation. I 
     <lb/>
     feel, personally, that if we, without any precon<lb break="no"/>ceived notions or knowledge of this thing, have 
     <lb/>
     this election now that there will be no excuse for 
     <lb/>
     talk whatever, and I am heartily sick of even 
     <lb/>
     hearing politics. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Is the House ready for the ques<lb break="no"/>tion? The motion is that the election of the delega<lb break="no"/>tion to Canada be deferred until the Report of the 
     <lb/>
     Committee on Public Health and Welfare has 
     <lb/>
     been received, and in any case to be the last 
     <lb/>
     business of the house prior to the Easter recess. 
     <lb/>
     Those who are in favour of that motion please say 
     <lb/>
     "aye," contrary "nay". I think the "nays" have it. 
     <lb/>
     I declare the motion lost. Now, gentlemen, we 
     <lb/>
     have this document before us. Is it your pleasure 
     <lb/>
     that we do now resolve ourselves into a commit<lb break="no"/>tee of the whole for the purpose of holding this 
     <lb/>
     election? If so I will receive a motion for that. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I move that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCA7">Mr. McCarthy</persName> I second that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It has been moved and seconded 
     <lb/>
     that this House do now resolve itself into a com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the whole to elect the delegation to 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa. The motion is that I do now leave the 
     <lb/>
     Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried and the Convention resolved<lb/>into a committee of the whole]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Now, there are six delegates to 
     <lb/>
     be elected. Each member can vote for six mem<lb break="no"/>bers. If he votes for five, or four or three, his ballot 
     <lb/>
     is a perfectly good one, but if he votes for seven 
     <lb/>
     his ballot must be rejected. Possibly there are 
     <lb/>
     some members who are not desirous of being 
     <lb/>
     members of that delegation, if so would they 
     <lb/>
     please come and sit in the center of the room. 
     <lb/>
     Those who can't sit at the table will please sit in 
     <lb/>
     the easy chairs at the back of the room. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Newell, Major Cashin, and Mr. Hickman, I want 
     <lb/>
     you to help in the scrutinising, and also Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Penney; these will be enough, with the Secretary. 
     <lb/>
     Before you cast your ballots is there any further 
     <lb/>
     information that any member requires? If so, I 
     <lb/>
     will be glad to furnish it if it is in my power. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> When we elected the delega<lb break="no"/>tion to London there was some talk about the fact 


            <cb/>
          

     that the newspaper reporters were excluded and 
     <lb/>
     the radio represented. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> We can't allow any but the offi<lb break="no"/>cials of the House here. The radio operators are 
     <lb/>
     officials of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> Another matter, it is definitely un<lb break="no"/>derstood that the delegation from England will 
     <lb/>
     return before this delegation goes to Canada? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That is the resolution, Mr. Pen<lb break="no"/>ney, there is no question about that. Now, will the 
     <lb/>secretaries please count the members present. 
     <lb/>There are 37. Call off the names to be sure. Will 
     <lb/>you all please sit down somewhere and remain 
     <lb/>there until your names are called.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Now, will you take a list of the 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen who are in the running? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> May I ask a question? There 
     <lb/>
     are six appointed to go to England, can any of 
     <lb/>
     these six go to Canada too? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I know of no rule under which 
     <lb/>
     they can be excluded. I understand that there will 
     <lb/>
     be two alternates; they will be the seventh and 
     <lb/>
     eighth candidates on the ballot, but you only vote 
     <lb/>
     for six, remember. Now check off the members 
     <lb/>
     who are eligible. The members who are in their 
     <lb/>
     seats are the members who are eligible, I under<lb break="no"/>stand. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the names of the members to<lb/>be voted on: Messrs. MacDonald, Starker,<lb/>Jones, Ballam, Penney, Roddy, Vincent, Higgins,<lb/>Smallwood, Crummey, Burry, Miller, Fogwill,<lb/>McCormack, Ashbourne, Bailey, Vardy, Job]</hi>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Has anybody been left out? 
     <lb/>Very well. When you complete your ballots, 
     <lb/>gentlemen, please hand them in. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[After the ballots were counted, the Chairman<lb/>announced the result]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Gentlemen, there are five 
     <lb/>
     elected: Messrs. Higgins, Ashboume, Small- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     wood, Job and Burry. Messrs. Ballam and Crum<lb break="no"/>mey have tied for sixth place. The eighth place 
     <lb/>
     has been secured by Mr. Starkes, so he will be the 
     <lb/>
     second alternate. You will now ballot on Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Ballam and Mr. Crummey, that is to say who will 
     <lb/>
     be the sixth of the delegation and who will be the 
     <lb/>
     first alternate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The result of the ballot was that Mr. Ballam took<lb/>sixth place on the delegation and Mr. Crummey<lb/>became first alternate]</hi>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Moved and seconded that the 
     <lb/>
     delegation to Ottawa do consist of Messrs. Hig<lb break="no"/>
   
            <pb n="454"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0454.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">454</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
           

     gins, Ashbourne, Smallwood, Job, Burry and 
     <lb/>
     Ballam as members of the delegation, with 
     <lb/>
     Messrs. Crumrney and Starkes as first and second 
     <lb/>
     alternates. Those in favour please say "aye", con<lb break="no"/>
      
            <cb/>
        trary "nay" — motion carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee of the whole rose and reported<lb/>the election of the delegation. The Convention<lb/>adopted the report]</hi>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
    
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the Public Health and Welfare Committee:<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:STAR1">Mr. Starkes</persName> ....I would like to make it plain to 
     <lb/>
     the people of this country about the old age 
     <lb/>
     pension of fishermen. They are entitled to an old 
     <lb/>
     age pension when they get to 75 years even if they 
     <lb/>
     are earning up to $25 a month, and even if they 
     <lb/>
     have up to $400 in the bank. That is something I 
     <lb/>
     don't think the majority of the people in this 
     <lb/>
     country realised before, at least in our region. I 
     <lb/>
     am speaking from experience because there are 
     <lb/>
     several in that district who applied for the pension 
     <lb/>
     and have been turned down on that account. I 
     <lb/>
     would like them to understand that they can legal<lb break="no"/>ly get it. 
    
   </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I am in the same boat as Mr. Starkes. 
     <lb/>I mentioned quite recently that I had a letter from 
     <lb/>my district — Lamaline — on the old age pen<lb break="no"/>sions, and by reason of the fact that this man had 
     <lb/>a small amount of money through selling some 
     <lb/>property he was denied that pension. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VINC1">Mr. Vincent</persName> I would refer you for a moment to 
     <lb/>page 22 of the report: "To be eligible for the 
     <lb/>pension a man must have passed the age of 75. 
     <lb/>On his death his widow receives $18 per quarter 
     <lb/>if she has reached the age of 65 years." I submit 
     <lb/>that this old age pension scheme needs revision. 
     <lb/>I regret that no practical recommendations to this 
     <lb/>effect are to be found in this otherwise very fine 
     <lb/>report. It seems just tragic that so little considera<lb break="no"/>tion is given the honest, hard-working fisherman 
     <lb/>and his wife, who for years have toiled and slaved 
     <lb/>at their calling to give us this heritage of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I am not proud, I feel ashamed that 
     <lb/>these fishermen who have spent 30 or 40 years at 
     <lb/>the cod fishery, and somenmes years at the seal 
     <lb/>fishery as well, should derive so little from their 
     <lb/>labour. Something is wrong, something should be 
     <lb/>done by the people that legislate in this country. 
     <lb/>I submit that your Committee would have been 
     <lb/>justified in bringing in, and I am sure this Con<lb break="no"/>vention would have approved of it, a recommen<lb break="no"/>dation to lower the age limit to 65 or at least 70 
     <lb/>years, and augment the pension, or double it from 
     <lb/>the amount it is now. My friends have no bank 
  

            <cb/>
      

     accounts, and very little life insurance, but by the 
     <lb/>
     grace of God and the apparent hardihood of your 
     <lb/>
     race, if you live to be 75 then your very grateful 
     <lb/>
     country may recognise your years of service and 
     <lb/>
     hardship and patriotism, and you will get for the 
     <lb/>
     rest of your days the magnificent sum of 19 and 
     <lb/>
     3/4 cents per day! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JONE5">Mr. Jones</persName> Mr. Chairman, I have not spoken to 
     <lb/>
     this report because I would rather listen to the 
     <lb/>
     next fellow and get his ideas. I see that $1 million 
     <lb/>
     has been spent for dole this year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It was stated here yesterday that a man in need 
     <lb/>
     did not have as much trouble in some districts as 
     <lb/>
     he did in others to get relief. I wonder why? In 
     <lb/>
     speaking of relieving officers I know they have 
     <lb/>
     instructions from the Department of Public 
     <lb/>
     Health and Welfare to keep down expenses, and 
     <lb/>
     I also know they have instructions to see that no 
     <lb/>
     man starves. I wonder how far on that road of 
     <lb/>
     starvation does a man have to go before he can 
     <lb/>
     get a note from the officer to relieve him from 
     <lb/>
     that starvation? I think that there should be some<lb break="no"/>thing definite about it. All relieving officers 
     <lb/>
     should have their instructions and should treat the 
     <lb/>
     people in the same way. I know there are people 
     <lb/>
     here who are fasting since this is the Lenten 
     <lb/>
     season, but they are not fasting because the 
     <lb/>
     Church tells them it is right, but because they 
     <lb/>
     have not the food. I know instances of that, and I 
     <lb/>
     think there should be something tangible in order 
     <lb/>
     that people may get relief. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In speaking of sick people, I wonder what a 
     <lb/>
     man has to do when he is sick before he can get 
     <lb/>
     relief? I suppose he has to get a note from the 
     <lb/>
     doctor, and then when that man recovers how is 
     <lb/>
     the relieving officer to know that he is fit to work 
     <lb/>
     to cut off the funds? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> In reply to Mr. Jones, the 
     <lb/>
     department has set up outport representatives 
     <lb/>
     known as relieving officers, to whom any man 
     <lb/>
     who is in need can apply. When these men, 
     <lb/>
     whether sick or poor or destitute, apply to the 
     <lb/>
     relieving officer he gets in touch with the depart<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_01">[1] Volume II:251. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

   
            <pb n="455"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0455.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">455</fw>
    
     ment in St. John's and gets his instructions from 
     <lb/>
     the department. They have certain standing or<lb break="no"/>ders from the department, and I have always 
     <lb/>
     maintained that a relieving officer should have 
     <lb/>
     not only some initiative on his own part, but some 
     <lb/>
     power to grant relief in cases of destitution. It 
     <lb/>
     might be, perhaps, that in certain cases it might 
     <lb/>
     be abused, but certainly the department could 
     <lb/>
     check on the relieving officer; but naturally this 
     <lb/>
     relief has to be given out, as in the past, in larger 
     <lb/>
     quantities in certain sections to a great number of 
     <lb/>
     people, and they have to have certain other rather 
     <lb/>
     stringent rules and regulations. That is the set-up 
     <lb/>
     in the outports, any man can approach a relieving 
     <lb/>
     officer in his district; and I know some cases 
     <lb/>
     where the relieving officers are Rangers, and they 
     <lb/>
     forward on to the department the applications and 
     <lb/>
     need for relief as it arises. As you can see from 
     <lb/>
     the figures given there has not been much relief 
     <lb/>
     up until quite recently in the outports, but as the 
     <lb/>
     winter months move along the people become 
     <lb/>
     destitute, they have no money, no credit, and no 
     <lb/>
     means of providing themselves with food, and 
     <lb/>
     they have to apply to the relieving officer; and, 
     <lb/>
     as was pointed out last night, in certain sections, 
     <lb/>
     in White Bay for instance, where the trap fishery 
     <lb/>
     has failed for two years following, these people 
     <lb/>
     have just carried themselves along as far as they 
     <lb/>
     can. I think that the department is sympathetic 
     <lb/>
     towards these applications and, while each ap<lb break="no"/>plication has to be studied on its merits, the 
     <lb/>
     amount of earning power that a man has during 
     <lb/>
     the summertime and what avenues he has tried to 
     <lb/>
     secure employment, all these factors have to be 
     <lb/>
     ascertained and studied. As far as I know they are 
     <lb/>
     submitted to the department in St. John's and they 
     <lb/>
     get their orders from the official here who looks 
     <lb/>
     after outport relief and deals with the cases as 
     <lb/>
     they come up. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> ... If a male is receiving a pension 
     <lb/>
     and he has a wife, on his decease the whole thing 
     <lb/>
     is forgotten unless she goes through the whole 
     <lb/>
     rigamarole all over again and has the relieving 
     <lb/>
     officer and the doctor state that she is eligible for 
     <lb/>
     the pension, and then she has to wait six months 
     <lb/>
     after his death. In nine cases out of ten the people 
     <lb/>
     are too old or too poor to bother about it. They 
     <lb/>
     don't get it until the whole thing is gone over. We 
     <lb/>
     should recommend that this should be automatic. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> That has been my experience in 
     <lb/>the past. I have filled out quite a few applications 
 

            <cb/>
          

     for old age pensions, etc. They can certainly find 
     <lb/>
     out by sending out a questionnaire to every old 
     <lb/>
     age pensioner who is married and ascertain the 
     <lb/>
     age of his wife; when the man dies, the cheque is 
     <lb/>
     immediately returned to the department and, as 
     <lb/>
     has been said, application has to be made. As 
     <lb/>
     soon as the application is made the cheque is sent 
     <lb/>
     forward, and if it happens to miss a quarter the 
     <lb/>
     past quarter is included with the next one. That's 
     <lb/>
     been my experience.... These old age pensions 
     <lb/>
     are marked "payable in advance" whatever that 
     <lb/>
     means. I know of a case or two where people have 
     <lb/>
     died after the beginning of the quarter, and have 
     <lb/>
     been alive at the 1st of April when the cheque is 
     <lb/>
     supposed to be issued. If the person is in St. 
     <lb/>
     John's and alive on the 1st of April he gets a 
     <lb/>
     cheque, and if he happens to die when the cheque 
     <lb/>
     was received in the outports, on the 4th or 5th, the 
     <lb/>
     cheque is sent back to the department; and I have 
     <lb/>
     had one or two cases where they have paid that 
     <lb/>
     cheque in order to give the benefit of the money 
     <lb/>
     for burial purposes. I quite agree with that point, 
     <lb/>
     and I don't see why a better plan could not be 
     <lb/>
     worked out as regards the age of the widow. It is 
     <lb/>
     the practice of the department to send out once or 
     <lb/>
     twice a year for a certificate showing that the old 
     <lb/>
     age pensioner and his wife are still alive. That's 
     <lb/>
     done so that nobody else would be getting the 
     <lb/>
     cheques.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That age limit of 65 is strictly adhered to, and 
     <lb/>
    there are cases where the widow may be 62 or 63 
     <lb/>and has had to have her name entered on the 
     <lb/>widow's list instead of becoming eligible for the 
     <lb/>old age pension, and is therefore looked after by 
     <lb/>the fund for widows, orphans and the infirm. I 
     <lb/>don't know if that answers your question. I am in 
     <lb/>full sympathy with the idea that the pension age 
     <lb/>should be lowered. When I was introducing this 
     <lb/>report I mentioned that in my remarks. We have 
     <lb/>no authority to make any change in this age limit, 
     <lb/>it is a matter for the government. I know that to 
     <lb/>these elderly people, particularly the fishermen 
     <lb/>and others who have helped build up the 
     <lb/>economy of Newfoundland throughout the years, 
     <lb/>this amount, even if very small, is a help to them, 
     <lb/>and I am in sympathy with the remarks of Mr. 
     <lb/>Ballam. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VINC1">Mr. Vincent</persName> Thank you very much for that ex<lb break="no"/>planation. Are the relieving inspectors making 
     <lb/>periodic visits to the outport districts? If so how 
     <lb/>many are there? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
            <pb n="456"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0456.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">456</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
           

 <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I can't answer offhand how 
     <lb/>
     many there are. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CRUM1">Mr. Crummey</persName> Two. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am not going to delay you at 
     <lb/>
     all, but a minute ago Mr. Jones referred to that 
     <lb/>
     amount of $1.1 million as being dole. That's not 
     <lb/>
     quite the case. It is $1.1 million for this year, but 
     <lb/>
     it is not all able-bodied relief or dole; it is for the 
     <lb/>
     sick poor, for widows, children, for special food 
     <lb/>
     orders, extra nourishment that is, and coal and 
     <lb/>
     clothing. That $1.1 million is for this year to the 
     <lb/>
     end of March. Now if you take the report and add 
     <lb/>
     up the different things under the different head<lb break="no"/>ings it is astonishing, and I am sure if Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin has not already done it he will be 
     <lb/>
     astonished when he sees what the total comes to 
     <lb/>
     — $1.1 million for those items I have just men<lb break="no"/>tioned. Widows and orphans, including board 
     <lb/>
     and lodging, is another $450,000; old age pen<lb break="no"/>sions $250,000; grants to orphanages $40,000 
     <lb/>
     odd; aged and infirm $78,000 — that's a total of 
     <lb/>
     $2 million this very year for relief of one kind and 
     <lb/>
     another —if you can call old age pensions relief, 
     <lb/>
     and perhaps you should not, but it is in that 
     <lb/>
     general classification — $2 million a year. Now 
     <lb/>
     in the old days the sick poor and widows and 
     <lb/>
     children of widows and special food orders, coal 
     <lb/>
     and clothing, that was all called dole. You take 
     <lb/>
     the figures today and you can find there are only 
     <lb/>
     300-400 people on the dole. That seems to com<lb break="no"/>pare very well with six or eight years ago, but the 
     <lb/>
     reason is this, that they have changed the system. 
     <lb/>
     What is now called dole is only able-bodied 
     <lb/>
     relief, but in the old days up to the war everything 
     <lb/>
     was called dole, and if you included everything 
     <lb/>
     today in the year that ended yesterday the govern<lb break="no"/>ment spent $2 million on public relief. It is an 
     <lb/>
     astonishing figure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I have had some experience in get<lb break="no"/>ting applications forwarded to the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Public Health and Welfare, especially with the 
     <lb/>
     relieving officer. As I see it this widow that was 
     <lb/>
     referred to here is entitled to the $18 per quarter, 
     <lb/>
     provided that she is not one that in the opinion of 
     <lb/>
     the relieving officer can support herself. I 
     <lb/>
     remember a case or two where the widow has 
     <lb/>
     been living with the son, and the son has a large 
     <lb/>
     family, and in the opinion of the relieving officer 
     <lb/>
     the son could very well look after the mother as 
     <lb/>
     well as his wife and children, and the OK from 
     <lb/>
     the relieving officer did not go on the form. If 
 

            <cb/>
          

     that's the principle of the Department of Public 
     <lb/>
     Health and Welfare, that this poor old soul must 
     <lb/>
     go over with the son, and he has to support his 
     <lb/>
     mother along with his family, I am wondering if 
     <lb/>
     that principle should not apply even to the official 
     <lb/>
     of the department. If I am correctly informed 
     <lb/>
     there are officials of this department who have 
     <lb/>
     been recommended for a pension. I wonder 
     <lb/>
     whether any investigation was made as to 
     <lb/>
     whether any of the sons of these officials are able 
     <lb/>
     to look after them, and therefore why the pen<lb break="no"/>sion? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I don't know if Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
     meant that old age pensions etc. should be called 
     <lb/>
     dole. I think it is to our discredit that the country 
     <lb/>
     is in such a shape as it is, and I don't believe it 
     <lb/>
     should go down as such, or that the country 
     <lb/>
     should get the impression that it is. If a man gets 
     <lb/>
     sick the government has a fund for that, which is 
     <lb/>
     called social security. Dole should be able- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     bodied relief and nothing else — for the man who 
     <lb/>
     can work, but can't get work to do. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I did not call the old age pen<lb break="no"/>sion dole, I said that generally under the heading 
     <lb/>
     of relief we might include old age pensions. I 
     <lb/>
     expressed some doubt as to whether old age 
     <lb/>
     pensions could even be included under relief, I 
     <lb/>
     was not even talking of dole at that moment. I 
     <lb/>
     think that you can almost measure the civilisation 
     <lb/>
     of a country by the extent to which that country 
     <lb/>
     looks after its womout toilers. They say you can 
     <lb/>
     measure the standards of a country by the way in 
     <lb/>
     which we bury our dead, but you can certainly 
     <lb/>
     measure it by the way in which the womout 
     <lb/>
     toilers are treated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> Well, we have called relief dole in 
     <lb/>
     the past, and dole relief, but I would like to see in 
     <lb/>
     this the amount that the people received who 
     <lb/>
     would have worked, but could not on account of 
     <lb/>
     sickness, and I would like to see it classified as 
     <lb/>
     social security. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> Referring to that matter 
     <lb/>
     brought up by Mr. Fudge, was that widow you 
     <lb/>
     mentioned the widow of an old age pensioner? I 
     <lb/>
     can't understand how they can grant a man and 
     <lb/>
     his wife a pension, and then take away the pen<lb break="no"/>sion from the wife after the man who was her sole 
     <lb/>
     support was taken away. I think that calls for 
     <lb/>
     special investigation with the department. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:STAR1">Mr. Starkes</persName> I think his wife was living, but 
     <lb/>
     instead of getting $30 a quarter he was only 


            <pb n="457"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0457.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">457</fw>
           

     getting $18 and if his widow did not apply for the 
     <lb/>
     old age pension within six months she did not get 
     <lb/>
     it. She has to apply within six months from the 
     <lb/>
     death of her husband to get it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> In the case to which I referred, this 
     <lb/>
     widow, I don't think her husband had a pension, 
     <lb/>
     was seeking the widow's mite, but because in the 
     <lb/>
     opinion of the relieving officer her son could 
     <lb/>
     support her, which I think was incorrect, I took 
     <lb/>
     the matter up myself here in St. John's, and 
     <lb/>
     settled the matter satisfactorily for the lady, but 
     <lb/>
     no thanks to the relieving officer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the next section on Child<lb/>Welfare and War Pensions. The committee then<lb/>adjourned until 8 pm]</hi>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BURR2">Mr. Burry</persName> Before the debate begins, I would 
     <lb/>
     like to point out an error in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Daily News</hi> report 
     <lb/>
     of yesterday aftemoon's debate. I refer to what 
     <lb/>
     was said by Mr. Smallwood when he was speak<lb break="no"/>ing of the infant mortality rate in Labrador. As 
     <lb/>
     you will recall he pointed out that there were 
     <lb/>
     several districts in Newfoundland and Labrador 
     <lb/>
     which had a high rate, other districts had a low 
     <lb/>
     rate. He mentioned one district where medical 
     <lb/>
     services were not up to the highest and yet that 
     <lb/>
     district had a very low infant mortality. He said 
     <lb/>
     there was a member in the Convention repre<lb break="no"/>senting that district. Apparently the reporter con<lb break="no"/>cluded that that district was Labrador. He refers 
     <lb/>
     to it in the write-up: "In Labrador where the infant 
     <lb/>
     mortality is lowest, medical facilities are almost 
     <lb/>
     nil." There are two errors. The district where the 
     <lb/>
     infant mortality rate is lowest is not Labrador — 
     <lb/>
     I wish it were. Also, describing the medical ser<lb break="no"/>vices in Labrador as almost nil is just not the way 
     <lb/>
     to describe them. I do not want to give you the 
     <lb/>
     impression that we are satisfied in Labrador with 
     <lb/>
     the medical services we have. I do not suppose 
     <lb/>
     any part of the island is satisfied. But we do have 
     <lb/>
     medical services. As you will recall, it was 
     <lb/>
     pointed out that there are three hospitals; we have 
     <lb/>
     a motor ship travelling up and down the coast 
     <lb/>
     during the summer. We have a nursing station at 
     <lb/>
     Forteau, there was a new institution put up there 
     <lb/>
     last year. Some of our people are also in close 
     <lb/>
     proximity to the RCAF in Goose Bay and we get 
     <lb/>
     medical services from these people, and supplies 
     <lb/>
     too. Missionaries in the north, while not graduate 
     <lb/>
     doctors, have some training along those lines and 
     <lb/>
     have given good service. All in all, our medical 
     <lb/>
     services are not too bad in Labrador. I would like 
 

            <cb/>
           

     to point that out because I am sure that the 
     <lb/>
     reporter probably misunderstood Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
     when he made that statement. I am sure he will 
     <lb/>
     be happy to make a correction in the interest of 
     <lb/>
     keeping the record straight. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The sections read this afternoon 
     <lb/>
     are now open for debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The only business is the debate 
     <lb/>
     of the report? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> Mr. Chairman, as a member who 
     <lb/>
     signed this report, and more particularly as chair<lb break="no"/>man of the sub-committee responsible for the 
     <lb/>
     welfare section, I can do no other than agree that 
     <lb/>
     this gives you the picture as presented to us, and 
     <lb/>
     we have endeavoured to make the comments 
     <lb/>
     necessary to give the country our unbiased views 
     <lb/>
     regarding whether or not many of these huge 
     <lb/>
     expenditures are fairly or equally made, con<lb break="no"/>sidering not only the peculiar wishes of the ex- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     serviceman or other applicant, but the ability of 
     <lb/>
     our purse to undertake such lavish commitments 
     <lb/>
     on these doubtful schemes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let us take the report section by section. In the 
     <lb/>
     health section we find the department has done 
     <lb/>
     an enormous amount of good by bringing the 
     <lb/>
     total number of hospitals in this country to 39 plus 
     <lb/>
     nine nursing stations. The General Hospital is 
     <lb/>
     now one of the best in North America, both as to 
     <lb/>
     building, equipment and skill. There is a shortage 
     <lb/>
     of nurses, due partly to so many of our girls 
     <lb/>
     joining the Canadian services or obtaining more 
     <lb/>
     remunerative employment elsewhere, but in the 
     <lb/>
     main because of the refusal of the department to 
     <lb/>
     step up the beginner's salary in proportion to the 
     <lb/>
     trained personnel or the higher income brackets. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It means a real sacrifice today for a girl to 
     <lb/>
     spend three years in training, which in reality is 
     <lb/>
     three years hard work and not going to school as 
     <lb/>
     some would suggest. Owing to the serious dearth 
     <lb/>
     of trained nurses, instead of being in a lecture- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     room they are almost continually doing full-time 
     <lb/>
     duty for 12 hours a day or night. They are trying 
     <lb/>
     to study when they should be resting. I realise this 
     <lb/>
     is unavoidable for the present, and will be for 
     <lb/>
     many years to come unless those responsible 
     <lb/>
     learn the definition of justice, and face the un<lb break="no"/>deniable realisation that we are living in an age 
     <lb/>
     of social reform when every labourer is worthy 
     <lb/>
     of his or her just and reasonable hire. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The cottage hospitals are a grand thing if we 
 

            <pb n="458"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0458.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">458</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
           

     had a population of five or ten million people to 
     <lb/>
     support them. They are giving splendid service. 
     <lb/>
     I will say reasonably commensurate with the cost 
     <lb/>
     of operating, in some respects inadequate but in 
     <lb/>
     every way out of proportion to our capacity to 
     <lb/>
     pay. We have them now and are building more, 
     <lb/>
     but with our very scattered population the most 
     <lb/>
     we can afford for many years to come is an 
     <lb/>
     increase in our doctors and nursing services 
     <lb/>
     throughout the country. What we need most is a 
     <lb/>
     sound consciousness of the basic factors of our 
     <lb/>
     real problem. Spend half the money we are 
     <lb/>
     spending on hospitals, Markiands, boglands, 
     <lb/>
     Humber Valley projects and other crazy 
     <lb/>
     schemes, on subsidising boat building, a bonus to 
     <lb/>
     men who are farm-minded for clearing their own 
     <lb/>
     land, of say $100 an acre, and in two years the 
     <lb/>
     country will have several thousand more engaged 
     <lb/>
     in each of these occupations and will be $4 mil<lb break="no"/>lion better off than we are today, instead of spend<lb break="no"/>ing to create huge insurmountable problems for 
     <lb/>
     future governments and generations unborn. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The "Impact Upon Disease" has been tackled 
     <lb/>
     seriously and the department deserves commen<lb break="no"/>dations for their efforts in this direction. But the 
     <lb/>
     lack of statistics is inexcusable when the whole 
     <lb/>
     country knows this division was amply staffed to 
     <lb/>
     keep them. It is a hopeful sign to find that tuber<lb break="no"/>culosis is on the decrease and it is common 
     <lb/>
     knowledge that the Dominions Office has always 
     <lb/>
     taken a serious View of the effect of this dread 
     <lb/>
     disease upon our people. The noteworthy con<lb break="no"/>tribution of the TB Association<ref target="#fn_02">[1]</ref> is evi-dence of 
     <lb/>
     our deep consciousness of our responsibility as 
     <lb/>
     citizens. The work of the Division of Visual 
     <lb/>
     Education as a means of combating this silent 
     <lb/>
     menace will contribute in no small way toward 
     <lb/>
     checking at the source the unnecessary spreading 
     <lb/>
     of the disease. We have given due credit for what 
     <lb/>
     has been done but we cannot overlook the cost. 
     <lb/>
     The amount of $6 million plus the Public Works 
     <lb/>
     expenditure for the department is a terrific burden 
     <lb/>
     for this little country to carry. In fact under nor<lb break="no"/>mal conditions we cannot hope to survive under 
     <lb/>
     such a load. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In spite of what has been said on the 
     <lb/>
     favourable side of the balance sheet, the question 
     <lb/>
     the whole country is asking is, "Are we getting 
     <lb/>
     fair value for the money spent? And can we get 
     <lb/>
     as good or better value for the same or less 
   

            <cb/>
            

     money?" In my checking of the various statistics, 
     <lb/>
     and observations through the various depart<lb break="no"/>ments and institutions, my conclusions are that 
     <lb/>
     this can be done, but not while under the control 
     <lb/>
     of unscrupulous individuals whose political 
     <lb/>
     records are black chapters in this country and 
     <lb/>
     who should never have been put in positions of 
     <lb/>
     trust, but who in my opinion acquired the position 
     <lb/>
     through a betrayal of the people's trust. Any 
     <lb/>
     Commissioner who would knowingly withhold 
     <lb/>
     four days pension or any part of it belonging to 
     <lb/>
     the war veterans of this country is not fit to hold 
     <lb/>
     this office, and in my opinion, and I have good 
     <lb/>
     evidence on this, it would never have been paid 
     <lb/>
     had it not been for pressure brought upon him 
     <lb/>
     from the Auditor-General. It has been stated that 
     <lb/>
     certain investigations are in progress; these have 
     <lb/>
     been in progress for several years, and in my 
     <lb/>
     opinion will still be in progress when the Con<lb break="no"/>vention dies, and in the interval between then and 
     <lb/>
     a general election they will have a grand oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity to cover up their dirty tracks. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If the Dominions Office had wanted a fair, true 
     <lb/>
     picture of what has been happening in this 
     <lb/>
     country they should have recalled the Commis<lb break="no"/>sion, and appointed a provisional government 
     <lb/>
     with the understanding that it held office only 
     <lb/>
     until Newfoundland decided on her future form 
     <lb/>
     of government. It is no use denying we have been 
     <lb/>
     handicapped for information from some quarters, 
     <lb/>
     and that some received has not been authentic. 
     <lb/>
     When we rechecked we found the figures were 
     <lb/>
     questionable. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The veterans' section of the report gives the 
     <lb/>
     people of this country the most disgraceful pic<lb break="no"/>ture they were ever asked to view. Those respon<lb break="no"/>sible for the first scheme, which I am informed 
     <lb/>
     has been changed six times, must be mentally 
     <lb/>
     unbalanced and in any case cannot know the 
     <lb/>
     definition of justice. The figures before you are 
     <lb/>
     self-explanatory and speak for themselves. I feel 
     <lb/>
     it my bounden duty to appeal to the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner for Home Affairs to cease further action 
     <lb/>
     under this senseless scheme at once, and if it has 
     <lb/>
     been modified or changed six times, in the name 
     <lb/>
     of justice and the veterans frame a scheme imme<lb break="no"/>diately on true democratic principles of equal 
     <lb/>
     rights to all and special privileges to none. We 
     <lb/>
     did not expect any special privileges when we 
     <lb/>
     went over, we would all have been satisfied if we 


<note xml:id="fn_02">[1] Newfoundland Tuberculosis Association founded by St, John's Rotary Club, 1942. </note>


            <pb n="459"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0459.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">459</fw>
      

     had not received any on return. There may be 
     <lb/>
     extenuating circumstances where compassionate 
     <lb/>
     allowances would have had to be made, but the 
     <lb/>
     whole ex-serviceman's school of thought is 
     <lb/>
     broad along these lines and no unjust criticisms 
     <lb/>
     would have been offered for any such action. 
     <lb/>
     
      </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am not going to delay the 
     <lb/>House, but before this report passes the commit<lb break="no"/>tee of the whole, I think it is only fair to say a 
     <lb/>word or two about it. I think it is also only fair to 
     <lb/>say a word or two about the business of the 
     <lb/>Department of Public Health and Welfare. This 
     <lb/>Convention cannot possibly do its work without 
     <lb/>taking very close account of this department. 
     <lb/>They are spending $6 million a year. The Com<lb break="no"/>mittee is of the unanimous opinion that in the 
     <lb/>years to come they will have to go on spending 
     <lb/>$6 million a year, at least. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is pointed out by the Committee that al<lb break="no"/>though certain items of expense in the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment of Public Health and Welfare may come 
     <lb/>
     down because the value of the dollar may go up 
     <lb/>
     — the same amount of money will buy more — 
     <lb/>
     on that account the cost of running the depart<lb break="no"/>ment may fall. Although that is true on the one 
     <lb/>
     hand, on the other hand the new extensions and 
     <lb/>
     new institutions that the department is putting in 
     <lb/>
     for the next year or two will drive the cost of 
     <lb/>
     running these institutions up again. The addition<lb break="no"/>al cost will equal the saving they may make on 
     <lb/>
     the purchases of supplies and materials in the 
     <lb/>
     public institutions. So for that reason, the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee is unanimous in the opinion that the future 
     <lb/>
     government of Newfoundland, whatever that 
     <lb/>
     government may be, had just as well face up to it 
     <lb/>
     that itis going to require at least $6 million dollars 
     <lb/>
     a year to run the Department of Public Health and 
     <lb/>
     Welfare, not counting what used to be called dole 
     <lb/>
     in this country, but is now known as able-bodied 
     <lb/>
     relief; we have today practically none — none 
     <lb/>
     worth speaking of. If we should have it in the next 
     <lb/>
     few years, then the cost of able-bodied relief must 
     <lb/>
     be tacked on to that $6 million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, Mr. Chairman, speaking for myself and 
     <lb/>
     not for the Committee, I have to say that the 
     <lb/>
     growth of the public services of this country 
     <lb/>
     insofar as they have to do with social and welfare 
     <lb/>
     services is a thing that needed to be done. I feel 
     <lb/>
     like giving the Commission of Government 
     <lb/>
     praise.... In health and welfare, especially in 
     <lb/>
     health, they do deserve praise. I think the people 
  
            <cb/>
       

     will think better of us if we give them the credit 
     <lb/>
     due them and the people will then be more likely 
     <lb/>
     to pay attention when we knock them where they 
     <lb/>
     should be knocked. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As Major Cashin has said, they have gone 
     <lb/>
     from 500 employees of all kinds 12 years ago to 
     <lb/>
     1,400 today. They have gone from $2.75 million 
     <lb/>
     a year to $6 million today. Since 1934 they have 
     <lb/>
     spent $45 million in that one department. $18 
     <lb/>
     million of that was spent on public relief — not 
     <lb/>
     dole, not able-bodied relief, but all forms of 
     <lb/>
     public relief. The second largest item of expendi<lb break="no"/>ture since 1934 is $7.5 million in salaries; the 
     <lb/>
     third largest was pensions, principally for World 
     <lb/>
     War I — $7.5 millions in 13 years. Fourth is the 
     <lb/>
     same amount and is for maintenance of their own 
     <lb/>
     hospitals — $6 million, not counting salaries. 
     <lb/>
     That was for drugs, food and equipment. Then 
     <lb/>
     they spent $1 million since 1934 to help out 
     <lb/>
     privately-owned hospitals. Then they spent 
     <lb/>
     $500,000 in those 13 years to help out the or<lb break="no"/>phanages. That brings you up to $33 million. The 
     <lb/>
     remainder comes under various headings. On top 
     <lb/>
     of that they are going to spend $65 million in the 
     <lb/>
     next year or two: $250,000 on the General Hospi<lb break="no"/>tal; $2.5 million to build a practically new mental 
     <lb/>
     hospital; $200,000 for a new home for nurses; 
     <lb/>
     $750,000 to build a home for the aged and infirm; 
     <lb/>
     $500,000 to build seven new cottage hospitals; 
     <lb/>
     $2.5 million to build a new sanatorium on the 
     <lb/>
     west coast. When the new west coast sanatorium 
     <lb/>
     is built, even though they have the old one on 
     <lb/>
     Topsail Road and the new one is opened, all the 
     <lb/>
     doctors who are authorities on TB who came 
     <lb/>
     before us agreed that there will still be a need for 
     <lb/>
     more. When these new institutions are built, it is 
     <lb/>
     going to run it up $1.25 million extra expenditure 
     <lb/>
     over and above the $6 million a year they are 
     <lb/>
     spending today. Let the Committee say, and I 
     <lb/>
     agree, that the government is doing right in intro<lb break="no"/>ducing and expanding these social services and 
     <lb/>
     they must go further. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I suggest to Major Cashin, who has one of the 
     <lb/>
     most onerous and responsible jobs as chairman 
     <lb/>
     of the Finance Committee, that if I were here in 
     <lb/>
     opposition and Major Cashin was standing over 
     <lb/>
     there as Minister of Finance, I would plead with 
     <lb/>
     him to put down at least $6 million dollars for this 
     <lb/>
     social service and social welfare vote in that 
     <lb/>
     department; not counting what he would have to 
     <lb/>
     put down for dole, if, God forbid, there should be 


            <pb n="460"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0460.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">460</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
           

     any dole in the next few years. When Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin brings in the Finance Report showing the 
     <lb/>
     prospective expenditure, let him start off by 
     <lb/>
     saying that $6 million a year is the amount the 
     <lb/>
     government has to spend, and not a cent less, on 
     <lb/>
     social welfare. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Referring to this section "Impact on Disease" 
     <lb/>
     — we are talking only to Newfoundland people 
     <lb/>
     and let us face it. It was only in the second last 
     <lb/>
     government (of which Major Cashin was a mem<lb break="no"/>ber) that they brought in the Health and Welfare 
     <lb/>
     Act. In the next government — the Alderdice 
     <lb/>
     government — that was acted upon a little fur<lb break="no"/>ther. When the Commission came in with some 
     <lb/>
     money from the British Treasury they went fur<lb break="no"/>ther. This has started in the last 15 or 16 years 
     <lb/>
     only, and since that attention has been paid to 
     <lb/>
     social services and social welfare. Because it is 
     <lb/>
     new we have a lot of leeway to make up before 
     <lb/>
     we catch up with other countries in the standard 
     <lb/>
     of social services. There is not a man here who 
     <lb/>
     would suggest it is wrong for the government to 
     <lb/>
     give more and more attention to social welfare. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I do honestly and sincerely congratulate the 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government upon expanding — 
     <lb/>
     not starting — what the Squires government 
     <lb/>
     began, and what the Alderdice government con<lb break="no"/>tinued. We in Newfoundland have become more 
     <lb/>
     prosperous in the last five or six years thanks to 
     <lb/>
     the war, when the money began to flow in, and 
     <lb/>
     we began to give the Commission of Government 
     <lb/>
     more money in taxes. I congratulate them for 
     <lb/>
     spending more on public health. It is a trend in 
     <lb/>
     the right direction.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> As we had some discussion on the 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lady Anderson</hi> about the justification for the 
     <lb/>
     money spent on her, I would like to ask just one 
     <lb/>
     more question, has the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lady Anderson</hi> any X-ray 
     <lb/>
     equipment? I am thinking of TB and the pos<lb break="no"/>sibility of doing an enormous amount of good if 
     <lb/>
     the X-ray equipment were installed on that <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lady 
     <lb/>
     Anderson</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> In replying to Mr. Butt's ques<lb break="no"/>tion, I might say there is no X-ray equipment on 
     <lb/>
     the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lady Anderson</hi>. I quite appreciate the fact that 
     <lb/>
     it would be a good idea to equip this vessel with 
     <lb/>
     an X-ray.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> When we were discussing the opening 
     <lb/>
     of the new sanatorium on Topsail Road there 
     <lb/>
     seemed to be some doubt as to whether there were 
     <lb/>
     any more patients in the hospital since the new 
    

            <cb/>
           

     building has been opened. Is there any difficulty 
     <lb/>
     in the way? Why are there not more patients? 
    </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I have here a letter from Dr. 
     <lb/>Bennett. There are now 350 patients at the 
     <lb/>Sanatorium; 250 of these are in the new naval 
     <lb/>hospital; 150 patients were transferred out of the 
     <lb/>former sanatorium and 100 new patients have 
     <lb/>been admitted There are still 100 patients in the 
     <lb/>old hospital, making a total of 350 now left. The 
     <lb/>new hospital, which was taken over from the 
     <lb/>Canadian naval authorities, will hold 35 more 
     <lb/>and these will be admitted soon, making a total 
     <lb/>of 285. These new patients will be admitted as 
     <lb/>soon as staff is available. There are 100 patients 
     <lb/>now in the former sanatorium and 130 will be 
     <lb/>admitted after renovation; which will then give 
     <lb/>capacity to the old sanatorium of 230 — which 
     <lb/>added to the 285 capacity of the naval hospital, 
     <lb/>will give a grand total of 515 patients. Further 
     <lb/>accommodation above this figure will need new 
     <lb/>construction of the wings of the naval hospital.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <p>One point as regards the Sanatorium, it seems 
     <lb/>to me that they have only a skeleton crew of 
     <lb/>nurses. It is a sad affair. lt seems to me there is 
     <lb/>great danger of some of these nurses being run 
     <lb/>off their feet. Some of the patients I spoke to there 
     <lb/>had been in the nursing service, and picked up the 
     <lb/>germ and have become victims and naturally they 
     <lb/>require hospitalisation. There is a big shortage of 
     <lb/>nurses.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I wonder if the Committee gave con<lb break="no"/>sideration to the question of care or follow-up 
     <lb/>treatment of people who have been in the 
     <lb/>Sanatorium?.... In my opinion one of the most 
     <lb/>hopeful signs that I have seen as far as welfare is 
     <lb/>concerned in the last few years is the organisation 
     <lb/>of the TB Association, for the reason that it has 
     <lb/>grown out of the people of Newfoundland and is 
     <lb/>not a purely governmental organisation. It invol<lb break="no"/>ves a principle which to me is of the utmost 
     <lb/>importance, that it is out of the people themselves 
     <lb/>must grow all the institutions which will make 
     <lb/>Newfoundland better and increase her social wel<lb break="no"/>fare developments. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I do not know definitely what 
     <lb/>follow-up treatment the doctors have as regards 
     <lb/>the patients, but I would take it that in these 
     <lb/>institutions they have some such plan. In the 
     <lb/>Notre Dame Bay Memorial Hospital at Twillin<lb break="no"/>gate, every patient who leaves that institution is 
     <lb/>given a slip signed by Dr. Olds advising what that 


            <pb n="461"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0461.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">461</fw>
          

     patient should do for a certain period.... I take it 
     <lb/>
     that is the standard practice in any up-to-date 
     <lb/>
     hospital and I presume the same thing is done in 
     <lb/>
     the Sanatorium. There is a need to follow up these 
     <lb/>
     cases, to find out how they are getting on. Unless 
     <lb/>
     we have these statistics with regard to the number 
     <lb/>
     of active TB cases and the number of cures ef<lb break="no"/>fected and of people who can enter into profitable 
     <lb/>
     employment, how do we know what progress we 
     <lb/>
     are making? I hope and trust that Public Health 
     <lb/>
     and Welfare will in future make an annual report, 
     <lb/>
     so that the people would have a clear and 
     <lb/>
     thorough picture of the activities of the depart<lb break="no"/>ment and the inroads it is making upon disease... 
     <lb/>
     I believe that the work of the Committee on 
     <lb/>
     Public Health and Welfare would have been 
     <lb/>
     greatly helped if we had had annual reports. It is 
     <lb/>
     a practice of certain sub-divisions of government 
     <lb/>
     to make annual reports to the Commissioner in 
     <lb/>
     charge. I strongly suggest that this matter should 
     <lb/>
     be taken up.... We are laymen when it comes to 
     <lb/>
     making reports on these things We do the best 
     <lb/>
     we can. But when it comes to medical terms and 
     <lb/>
     disease terms, it is the doctors themselves who 
     <lb/>
     can put in black and white the facts of the inroads 
     <lb/>
     on disease. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> I wonder if that is entirely what Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Butt had in mind I take it he was not referring to 
     <lb/>
     people coming back to the hospital to get sub<lb break="no"/>sequent treatment. I wonder if he had in mind the 
     <lb/>
     economic condition — the means of earning a 
     <lb/>
     living. An arrested case of TB has to go back to 
     <lb/>
     engage in a type of work not conducive to the 
     <lb/>
     good health of persons who have just come out 
     <lb/>
     of TB hospital. I do not think it is done in this 
     <lb/>
     country along these lines. In one or two cases I 
     <lb/>
     know they have been provided employment, but 
     <lb/>
     that has been done on their behalf by other or 
     <lb/>
     ganisations in the north. This is another case 
     <lb/>
     where the whole public health and welfare sys<lb break="no"/>tem ties up with the economic position. I think 
     <lb/>
     we have the wrong outlook towards the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture of public monies. Take cottage hospitals — 
     <lb/>
     if they do cost $20,000 to $25,000 a year, what is 
     <lb/>
     that? I suppose there are households, not to men<lb break="no"/>tion hospitals, who get through that amount of 
     <lb/>
     money a year. The question we have to face, and 
     <lb/>
     very soon, is why do we have so much TB? Why 
     <lb/>
     do we have relief? And somebody says it is partly 
     <lb/>
     attributable to the standard of living. The stand<lb break="no"/>ard of living is low, why? Is that something that 


            <cb/>
           

     is going to be dependent on a particular form of 
     <lb/>
     government or is it dependent on us, the people? 
     <lb/>
     Who do we have to blame?  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> The labour crowd? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> Perhaps we can blame them. I think 
     <lb/>
     it goes even deeper than that. Our whole 
     <lb/>
     economic system is antiquated and whenever you 
     <lb/>
     suggest a minor alteration somebody thinks you 
     <lb/>
     are crazy. Unless we can check the economic 
     <lb/>
     problem we are not going to make any great 
     <lb/>
     strides in public health and welfare and we will 
     <lb/>
     always need to spend huge sums on both. I sug<lb break="no"/>gest that whether or not we can afford it, if we are 
     <lb/>
     not prepared to get to work and change the 
     <lb/>
     economic position of this country, at least the 
     <lb/>
     economic system, if we are not prepared to do 
     <lb/>
     something drastic. then we had better make up 
     <lb/>
     our minds that we have to afford these expendi<lb break="no"/>tures. The people do not want anybody's sym<lb break="no"/>pathy, but we have to tackle this problem from a 
     <lb/>
     realistic point of view. When we can provide an 
     <lb/>
     economic system that will give a decent standard 
     <lb/>
     of living we may be able to look forward to lower 
     <lb/>
     expenditures on public health and welfare. Until 
     <lb/>
     we do that, we have to make up our minds that it 
     <lb/>
     must come from somewhere; even if we have to 
     <lb/>
     do without some things to provide $6 million, it 
     <lb/>
     has to be provided. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> Speaking of TB, we have to get 
     <lb/>
     at the root of it. First, the government should see 
     <lb/>
     that every hotel, boarding house and restaurant 
     <lb/>
     has hot and cold water. Where there are no toilets 
     <lb/>
     inside, the ones outside should be treated with 
     <lb/>
     chlorine which will kill flies which carry the 
     <lb/>
     germs. I think if the chairman of the Committee 
     <lb/>
     would stress that point to the Public Health and 
     <lb/>
     Welfare Department, they will have done some<lb break="no"/>thing worthwhile. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> raised a very important point when 
     <lb/>
     he mentioned the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Northern Ranger</hi> carrying sick 
     <lb/>
     people. Sick people should be segregated from 
     <lb/>
     other passengers, especially if a patient is carry<lb break="no"/>ing the germ of TB. It is a terrible thing to have 
     <lb/>
     those patients among two or three others.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Speaking of the report, it is a mass of figures 
     <lb/>
     and a few hours' job to grasp them, so I would 
     <lb/>
     more or less leave them as they are. I congratulate 
     <lb/>
     the members on the report. I am sure they put a 
     <lb/>
     lot of time and energy into it. Going back to the 
     <lb/>
     able-bodied relief which was spoken about — 
     <lb/>
     this $100,000 spent on fuel for the sick relief, 
   

            <pb n="462"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0462.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">462</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
          

     $50,000 in St. John's and $50,000 in the outports. 
     <lb/>
     I wonder if the chairman could give us some idea 
     <lb/>
     of what districts this $50,000 was spent in? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I am unable to give that break<lb break="no"/>down this evening, but we may be able to get 
     <lb/>
     those figures. As regards the inspection of hotels 
     <lb/>
     and restaurants, the department has supervision 
     <lb/>
     over restaurants and the people who work in 
     <lb/>
     them. As regards isolation wards on steamers, I 
     <lb/>
     think that is an excellent point. I think there is a 
     <lb/>
     sick bay on the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Kyle</hi>.<ref target="#fn_03">[1]</ref> I think in the construction 
     <lb/>
     of the new boats now in process of being built it 
     <lb/>
     would be a good idea to have places on them for 
     <lb/>
     sick people. We are a maritime country — lots of 
     <lb/>
     people cannot get to a doctor in hospital without 
     <lb/>
     taking passage by boat and it is sometimes very 
     <lb/>
     necessary for them to try and reach hospital to see 
     <lb/>
     whether or not they can be cured. They have no 
     <lb/>
     way of travelling, oftentimes, except by these 
     <lb/>
     boats. As pointed out by Mr. Miller, it is certainly 
     <lb/>
     too bad when these people who are going to seek 
     <lb/>
     hospitalisation are, through no fault of their own, 
     <lb/>
     forced to occupy staterooms with other pas<lb break="no"/>sengers who are travelling. When I see the 
     <lb/>
     manager of the Railway, Mr. Russell, I will make 
     <lb/>
     that suggestion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> Page 27 of this report — Vet<lb break="no"/>erans' Affairs — something struck me very for<lb break="no"/>cibly: "With regard to the men of the merchant 
     <lb/>
     navy, they appear to have been discriminated 
     <lb/>
     against. Those who were not recruited through 
     <lb/>
     the agents of the Ministry of Shipping received 
     <lb/>
     no consideration whatsoever, while those who 
     <lb/>
     were so enlisted for foreign service for the dura<lb break="no"/>tion, unless disabled, received only a small frac<lb break="no"/>tion of the benefits of other units, many of them 
     <lb/>
     as low as one fifth of the lowest amounts given 
     <lb/>
     other members of the forces...." It just shows 
     <lb/>
     what short memories governments have. Here 
     <lb/>
     you have a body of men whose help was largely 
     <lb/>
     instrumental in the winning of the war. These 
     <lb/>
     men carried quantities of munitions, food, etc. 
     <lb/>
     without which no war could have been won. I do 
     <lb/>
     not think any member of any other service will 
     <lb/>
     deny that they took exceptional risks in doing this 
     <lb/>
     work. Yet when the war is all over, they are 
     <lb/>
     forgotten. I wonder if the Committee asked why 
     <lb/>
     the men of the merchant navy were discriminated 
     <lb/>
     against? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCA7">Mr. McCarthy</persName> I would like to say I was going 
   

            <cb/>
           

     to make that point. I would like to add further, we 
     <lb/>
     find in this report—Civil Re-establishment plan, 
     <lb/>
     under Veterans' Affairs — under plan A, $4,000 
     <lb/>
     to $6,000 is being Spent for higher education; 
     <lb/>
     under plan B, ex-servicemen who want to settle 
     <lb/>
     in their own areas on a farm are entitled to ap<lb break="no"/>proximately $2,500; we find a man starting a 
     <lb/>
     small business and he gets about $500. I am not 
     <lb/>
     supporting all the accusations made by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Vardy, but we also find fishermen who stay home 
     <lb/>
     and want to go fishing will get $500, and if he 
     <lb/>
     needs an engine, for instance, he will possibly get 
     <lb/>
     $700. We find in the Fisheries Report that our 
     <lb/>
     fisheries are still the economy of our country. 
     <lb/>
     Yet, as Mr. Vardy stated, these men wore the 
     <lb/>
     same uniform, they fought on the same front and 
     <lb/>
     still they are only entitled to $500 to $700. I 
     <lb/>
     wonder if your Committee enquired as to why 
     <lb/>
     that decision was made as regards these different 
     <lb/>
     rates? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I would ask Mr. Vardy to 
     <lb/>
     answer that question. He was a member of the 
     <lb/>
     merchant navy during the war and was chairman 
     <lb/>
     of the sub-committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I think Mr. Ashbourne will agree 
     <lb/>
     that it is simple for me to answer these questions. 
     <lb/>
     From the very start I kept up my interviews and 
     <lb/>
     consultations with various men in connection 
     <lb/>
     with this scheme. As far as the merchant navy 
     <lb/>
     men are concerned, Mr. MacDonald will be 
     <lb/>
     surprised to know that out of 3,000 men, only 
     <lb/>
     about 60 received anything, and some of them as 
     <lb/>
     low as $20. We have that evidence from no less 
     <lb/>
     a person than the Director of Civil Re-estab<lb break="no"/>lishment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Sixty? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> Yes, 60. Now they have the scheme 
     <lb/>
     changed. They give these men, if they are on 
     <lb/>
     relief, a limited amount of unemployment 
     <lb/>
     benefit. The limited of these men can get, if they 
     <lb/>
     served from 1939-45, is $700. That is the top 
     <lb/>
     limit. These men signed the same articles that 
     <lb/>
     men signed in the Royal Navy, the RAF or the 
     <lb/>
     Royal Artillery. They had to sign in triplicate up 
     <lb/>
     here at the Newfoundland Railway office or at 
     <lb/>
     Bowring's office — forms to the effect they were 
     <lb/>
     volunteering for the duration, unless disabled. I 
     <lb/>
     have these forms, I signed them myself. The men 
     <lb/>
     of the merchant navy did a good job and the men 
     <lb/>
     of the tug service did a good job and are deprived 


<note xml:id="fn_03">[1] Newfoundland Railway coastal steamer serving Labrador.</note> 


            <pb n="463"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0463.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">463</fw>
    

     now of any benefits. Finally they were informed 
     <lb/>
     the scheme had been changed and they were 
     <lb/>
     going to be given benefits under the land clearing 
     <lb/>
     scheme. I know a number of men in the merchant 
     <lb/>
     navy who, with this understanding, spent the last 
     <lb/>
     cent they had cutting down brush, made prepara<lb break="no"/>tions for tractors to come in and clear the land; 
     <lb/>
     and during the time they were doing this work, 
     <lb/>
     trying to take advantage of these benefits, the 
     <lb/>
     scheme was changed and the merchant navy men 
     <lb/>
     and the tug service men who landed the troops in 
     <lb/>
     France for the invasion, these men were deprived 
     <lb/>
     of all benefits except under the fishery assistance 
     <lb/>
     scheme. Some of these men got as low as $100 
     <lb/>
     to $140. One man told me he could qualify for 
     <lb/>
     $140, and he was a married man who left his 
     <lb/>
     family to go over there to serve. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The unemployment scheme is made to suit 
     <lb/>
     each individual case. I was told they regarded it 
     <lb/>
     as compassionate allowance. If a person happens 
     <lb/>
     to come in and is hard up they will give him the 
     <lb/>
     amount of unemployment benefit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In reference to the questions asked by Mr. Butt 
     <lb/>
     and Mr. Newell in connection with the 
     <lb/>
     Sanatorium, I do know for a fact that when each 
     <lb/>
     case is regarded as cured and the patient returns 
     <lb/>
     home, they give the patient a form to report 
     <lb/>
     periodically, and they make a special effort to get 
     <lb/>
     these people to come in at certain intervals for 
     <lb/>
     X-ray or check up. Eventually when cured, they 
     <lb/>
     give them a certificate to that effect. They do try 
     <lb/>
     to keep contact with each case as it is discharged 
     <lb/>
     from the institution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCA7">Mr. McCarthy</persName> In spite of all that Mr. Vardy has 
     <lb/>
     said he has not answered my question, which was 
     <lb/>
     if the Committee had inquired as to why the 
     <lb/>
     government should make the decision. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> We did make numerous inquiries 
     <lb/>
     We objected from the beginning and the Commit<lb break="no"/>tee knows I was strong on it. The only answer to 
     <lb/>
     these enquiries was that this scheme was framed 
     <lb/>
     by the Commissioner for Finance and the Com<lb break="no"/>missioner for Home Affairs. The Director of 
     <lb/>
     Civil Re-establishment has the duty to carry out 
     <lb/>
     the scheme as far as possible. They have no 
     <lb/>
     excuse except that was the decision made by the 
     <lb/>
     two Commissioners and they are powerless to 
     <lb/>
     change it. We made enquiries in every detail in 
     <lb/>
     connection with the scheme. I may say that the 
     <lb/>
     Humber Valley scheme started from $4,000 to 
     <lb/>
     $6,000. I do not think $4,000 is mentioned in our 
  

            <cb/>
           

     report. The first information we had was that it 
     <lb/>
     was $5,000; our final information, which was 
     <lb/>
     given to the Agricultural Committee as well, was 
     <lb/>
     that it was $6,000. I am informed on good 
     <lb/>
     authority that $6,000 will not go near re-estab<lb break="no"/>lishing these men. The vote is $1.3 million for 
     <lb/>
     300 men. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCA7">Mr. McCarthy</persName> That includes road building, 
     <lb/>
     etc.? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> The delegate from St. John's West 
     <lb/>
     Extern made reference to the TB Association. In 
     <lb/>
     doing so he intimated we had solved some of our 
     <lb/>
     own problems. How many branches of the TB 
     <lb/>
     Association are in Newfoundland at the present 
     <lb/>
     time? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I believe that two branches 
     <lb/>
     have already been organised — a branch at Chan<lb break="no"/>nel and another at Comer Brook. I believe that 
     <lb/>
     the formation of a branch at Grand Falls is being 
     <lb/>
     proceeded with. These are the only three 
     <lb/>
     branches I know of at the moment. At the meeting 
     <lb/>
     of the directors of the TB Association, of which 
     <lb/>
     I am a director, the matter was discussed and I 
     <lb/>
     think that in a great many of the larger outports 
     <lb/>
     they would like to have branches and for those 
     <lb/>
     who want them there will be a chance for a branch 
     <lb/>
     to be formed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I think that a branch properly or<lb break="no"/>ganised and active would solve some of the TB 
     <lb/>
     problem. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> In fairness to myself, there would 
     <lb/>
     seem to be implied that I was criticising the work 
     <lb/>
     done at the Sanatorium. I was thinking of the 
     <lb/>
     thing pointed out by Mr. Newell, and that is the 
     <lb/>
     supplying of proper kinds of work for patients 
     <lb/>
     afterwards. That is important.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> Speaking briefly on the report I 
     <lb/>
     would call attention to page 36, wherein the cost 
     <lb/>
     of living index is given from 1 October 1938 to 
     <lb/>
     1 March, 1947, beginning at 100 and ending up 
     <lb/>
     167.6. I would like to know if this cost of living 
     <lb/>
     index is really an index of the lift in prices or the 
     <lb/>
     cost of things from 1938-47. Many people think 
     <lb/>
     costs have lifted three times or more. I was 
     <lb/>
     wondering if we could get any information on 
     <lb/>
     how the index is made up; and in asking that 
     <lb/>
     question I would like to say I agree with other 
     <lb/>
     members regarding the very informative report 
     <lb/>
     of this Public Health and Welfare Committee.... 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> Every detail covering the cost of 
    

            <pb n="464"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0464.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">464</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
          
     living index is somewhere here in the files, but 
     <lb/>
     owing to the report's being limited there were 
     <lb/>
     several details we felt compelled to leave out. 
   </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I must refer back to something Mr. 
     <lb/>Butt said with regard to TB patients and what 
     <lb/>happens to them. I had occasion to go into the 
     <lb/>Sanatorium early last fall, and I happened to meet 
     <lb/>a gentleman there, whom I understand has since 
     <lb/>deceased. I refer to Mr. Conrad Fitzgerald. He 
     <lb/>edited a magazine called <hi rendition="simple:italic">Sunbeams</hi>. It was most 
     <lb/>interesting and informative Mr. Fitzgerald told 
     <lb/>me that one of the big factors in the recurrence of 
     <lb/>TB was the fact that after a patient is discharged 
     <lb/>from hospital there is no form of rehabilitation. 
     <lb/>In other words, he is to all intents and purposes 
     <lb/>cured, and if he is a fisherman he must go in a 
     <lb/>boat; if a logger, he must go in the woods. By so 
     <lb/>doing, he is losing what it took years to build up. 
     <lb/>Mr. Fitzgerald's idea was that there should be 
     <lb/>some form of rehabilitation whereby those fisher<lb break="no"/>men coming out of hospital could be looked after 
     <lb/>until they could rehabilitate themselves to the 
     <lb/>extent where they could follow their usual voca<lb break="no"/>tion.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I agree entirely with Mr. Bal<lb break="no"/>lam. This problem should be tied in with our 
     <lb/>
     health system. The problem of rehabilitation is 
     <lb/>
     one which must be tackled because when a man 
     <lb/>
     has suffered from such a disease as TB naturally 
     <lb/>
     the whole body is impaired, and it stands to 
     <lb/>
     reason that a man cannot undertake strenuous 
     <lb/>
     work. I believe such a scheme would be money 
     <lb/>
     well spent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In reply to Mr. Penney, I wish to thank him for 
     <lb/>
     his remarks on the report. I would like to say that 
     <lb/>
     this matter of arriving at the monthly cost of 
     <lb/>
     living index in St. John's is a rather complicated 
     <lb/>
     matter as I see it. There has been a discussion on 
     <lb/>
     this matter going on; you see letters in the papers. 
     <lb/>
     It seems that when the index was started it was 
     <lb/>
     set at 100. Staple articles, food and clothing, were 
     <lb/>
     placed at certain values and when they advanced 
     <lb/>
     other articles were placed on the list. When prices 
     <lb/>
     advanced in grocery stores the prices were 
     <lb/>
     entered and different calculations were arrived at. 
     <lb/>
     They took October 1, 1938 as 100 for these 
     <lb/>
     commodities as listed and eventually these 
     <lb/>
     figures were arrived at. I have not changed the 
     <lb/>
     figures myself.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> Do you not believe that the cost of 
     <lb/>
     living over the last decade has been lifted a great 
 

            <cb/>
          

     deal more? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> Certain items no doubt have. 
     <lb/>
     
  </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> It is made up for St. John's; I do not 
     <lb/>know if the department inquired into the cost of 
     <lb/>living in the outports. I see nothing about it. I take 
     <lb/>it for granted that the cost of living may be higher 
     <lb/>in St. John's than in the outports. I suppose that 
     <lb/>is the reason for giving able-bodied relief in St. 
     <lb/>John's at $1 1.25 per head and in the outports at 
     <lb/>$5 per head. I suppose the cost is not so high? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> What is the Federation of 
     <lb/>Labour index? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> 210.7. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCA7">Mr. McCarthy</persName> I think it is 215 now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The government figures are 
     <lb/>
     notoriously wrong, everyone knows that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> In answer to Mr. Fudge, I do 
     <lb/>
     not think they have the cost of living compiled 
     <lb/>
     for any outports. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> The people on poor or sick relief are 
     <lb/>
     expected to live on $5 — they must think the cost 
     <lb/>
     of living is lower in the outports. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I would say it is not because the cost 
     <lb/>
     of living is lower, but because the outports are far 
     <lb/>
     away from the source of government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I have been paying close attention 
     <lb/>
     here tonight to what the members have been 
     <lb/>
     talking about and I have also noticed the amounts 
     <lb/>
     paid to the different returned men. I wondered 
     <lb/>
     about it. I wondered why such a difference was 
     <lb/>
     made in the different classes. All the men took a 
     <lb/>
     chance on going over there. I do not know who 
     <lb/>
     is responsible for these pensions. I have before 
     <lb/>
     me a letter which I received from a returned man 
     <lb/>
     and which I shall read: "At the age of 35 I enlisted 
     <lb/>
     in 1939 with the Forestry Unit, later transferring 
     <lb/>
     to the Royal Air Force with air sea rescue and air 
     <lb/>
     crew, Bomber Command. In June, 1940, I took 
     <lb/>
     part in evacuating troops from Dunkirk and 
     <lb/>
     France by small boats. During the Battle of 
     <lb/>
     Britain I flew as air-crew, also made 49 trips over 
     <lb/>
     occupied territory up to February 7, 1945, when 
     <lb/>
     we were shot down by enemy aircraft and I 
     <lb/>
     received a fractured spine and fractured ribs. I 
     <lb/>
     spent six months in hospital in Holland and 
     <lb/>
     England and upon arrival in this country in Sep<lb break="no"/>tember, 1945, I was again hospitalised for 
     <lb/>
     removal of parts of ribs. My pension has been 
     <lb/>
     reduced to 20% — $28 per month — for wife and 
     <lb/>
     family of three in spite of the fact that I have spent 
     <lb/>
     about three months in bed with medical attention 
    

            <pb n="465"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-01_Page_0465.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">465</fw>
         

     for injuries since my return. I was promoted to 
     <lb/>
     commissioned rank in 1944 attaining the rank of 
     <lb/>
     Flying Officer upon my release in 1945. In an 
     <lb/>
     effort to supplement my pension since my return, 
     <lb/>
     I made application for 32 government positions 
     <lb/>
     advertised and was called for nine interviews on 
     <lb/>
     selection boards for junior government positions, 
     <lb/>
     but was unsuccessful. The other 23 positions I 
     <lb/>
     was ignored. I was successful in obtaining a 
     <lb/>
     temporary position with the Tourist Board with a 
     <lb/>
     small salary in the hope that some other position 
     <lb/>
     would open and under present circumstances this 
     <lb/>
     job will soon end. I obtained my Junior Associate 
     <lb/>
     Grade at Trinity East and have three years' train<lb break="no"/>ing at the Baptist Theological College of Mis<lb break="no"/>souri, USA. My war record speaks for itself and 
     <lb/>
     my civilian character can be ascertained from any 
     <lb/>
     of my past employers. I was the oldest person 
     <lb/>
     from Newfoundland who served in air operations 
     <lb/>
     and took part in all major conflicts from the 
     <lb/>
     evacuation of Dunkirk to the crossing of the 
     <lb/>
     Rhine." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am not going to say much about this because 
     <lb/>
     I do not know the set-up but I believe if ever we 
     <lb/>
     get a government of the people for the people, this 
     <lb/>
     is something that should not happen.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I suggest that Mr. Bailey take 
     <lb/>
     that case up with the pensions officer of the 
     <lb/>
     department. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would like to answer some of the points 
     <lb/>
     brought up in the debate yesterday afternoon and 
     <lb/>
     last night. Major Cashin asked about the amount 
     <lb/>
     given for special food orders. The department 
     <lb/>
     does not give the cost of those food orders per 
     <lb/>
     district. It is in accounts rendered by supplying 
     <lb/>
     merchants and they are issued on recommenda<lb break="no"/>tion of the doctor or nurse. The question was 
     <lb/>
     asked regarding cottage hospitals, whether a doc<lb break="no"/>
       

            <cb/>
         
tor not attached to a cottage hospital and who is 
     <lb/>
     working in the area has a right to send a patient 
     <lb/>
     into the cottage hospital. It is understood that the 
     <lb/>
     doctor in charge will treat the patients; they 
     <lb/>
     charge $4 for services for hospital outside the 
     <lb/>
     area. Some member asked regarding salaries of 
     <lb/>
     district nurses for Harbour Breton, I believe. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEN3">Mr. Spencer</persName> I did not ask for any particular 
     <lb/>section. I asked if there were two nurses, why 
     <lb/>were the amounts different. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> The $4,866.73 charged up for 
     <lb/>
     Harbour Breton is the salaries of the district nur<lb break="no"/>ses of the area, and not in the cottage hospital 
     <lb/>
     alone. The district nurse looks after the area, of 
     <lb/>
     which the hospital is the head. In regard to Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Penney's question, the answer is not yet avail<lb break="no"/>able. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The section was adopted, and the committee<lb/>then adopted the report as a whole. The commit<lb break="no"/>tee rose and so reporled to the Convention]</hi>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> In deference to Major Cashin 
     <lb/>
     who raised the question in connection with this 
     <lb/>
     report, its further consideration should be 
     <lb/>
     deferred. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I move that this report be not 
     <lb/>
     adopted or received until the Convention and the 
     <lb/>
     public have received the full report regarding a 
     <lb/>
     secret and confidential report<ref target="#fn_04">[1]</ref> given the mem<lb break="no"/>bers in private session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> If I may offer you a suggestion, 
     <lb/>
     the best thing to do is to defer it until tomorrow. 
     <lb/>
     That keeps it before the House and we can always 
     <lb/>
     defer it from day to day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I second that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Moved and seconded that this 
     <lb/>
     report be deferred until tomorrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried, and the Convention ad<lb break="no"/>journed]</hi>
            </p>


<note xml:id="fn_04">[1] Above, p. 445.</note>

   <!-- GL, 2017-06-23, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day --> 
   
            <!--<p>
     April 10, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Jackman I give notice that I will on tomor<lb break="no"/>row move the following: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whereas it is desirable that the National 
     <lb/>
     Convention and the people of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     should be fully informed, so far as possible, 
     <lb/>
     of all the facts having any bearing upon forms 
     <lb/>
     of government that might be submitted to the 
     <lb/>
     people in a national referendum; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Therefore be it resolved that the ap<lb break="no"/>propriate authorities be advised that the Con<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>vention desires to inform the Government of 
     <lb/>
     the United States of America of the 
     <lb/>
     Convention's wish to learn that govern<lb break="no"/>ment's attitude on the question of the federal 
     <lb/>
     union of Newfoundland with the United 
     <lb/>
     States of America: and further wishes to as<lb break="no"/>certain the terms and conditions on the basis 
     <lb/>
     of which the Government of the United 
     <lb/>
     States of America consider that such federal 
     <lb/>
     union might be effected, for which purpose 
     <lb/></p>-->


            
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>