<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-10-15" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-10-15">15 October 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:YU1">Thomson Yu</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
          
          
          <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1995"/>. 
          
          
          <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="594"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0591.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0592.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0593.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0594.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-07-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="YuTom" when="2017-07-05"> Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0591">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0591.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0592">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0592.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0593">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0593.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0594">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0594.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="591" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0591.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1947 </fw> <fw type="running"> NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">591</fw>



<!-- TY, 2017-07-05, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day-->
         <!--   <p>
     Chair. You are out of order. You have to get a <lb/>Chairman. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Secretary Order! Gentlemen, remember 
     <lb/>
     where you are. The Chairman has resigned and I 
     <lb/>
     think the best expedient would be if you were to 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     adjourn immediately. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Ballam I move we adjourn to the call of the 
     <lb/>
     Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Ryan I second that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The Convention adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
<div type="section">
   
<head rendition="simple:centre">October 15, 1947</head> </div>
            
            
            
<div type="section">
   
   <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Acting Chairman<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> read a commission ap<lb break="no"/>pointing John Bernard McEvoy as Chairman]</hi><lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     
     
     <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> Mr. Secretary, may I avail myself 
     <lb/>
     of this, the first opportunity, to publicly convey 
     <lb/>
     my congratulations to my very good friend, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McEvoy, our new Chairman, on his appointment 
     <lb/>
     to this most important office. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I do not think that I am unduly egotistic when 
     <lb/>
     I say there is no one in this Convention more 
     <lb/>
     qualified to appreciate the problems and the dif<lb break="no"/>ficulties which at times beset the Chairman than 
     <lb/>
     myself, for I occupied the post for a period of 
     <lb/>
     nearly 12 months and I had particular opportunity 
     <lb/>
     to observe those errors which contribute so large<lb break="no"/>ly to the Chairman's problems. One of the very 
     <lb/>
     greatest of our errors has been a casual assump<lb break="no"/>tion that we are a political body, even a partly 
     <lb/>
     political body. The method of our election by the 
     <lb/>
     people has tended to foster that illusion and our 
     <lb/>
     adoption of a parliamentary framework for our 
     <lb/>
     deliberations has tended to confirm it. There is a 
     <lb/>
     tendency to assume that we may speak for the 
     <lb/>
     people in a representative capacity, where no 
     <lb/>
     such right exists. And that for two reasons: the 
     <lb/>
     first, in its nature double, I suppose, has to do with 
     <lb/>
     our election to the seats which we now occupy. 
     <lb/>
     A substantial number of us are here by acclama<lb break="no"/>tion and received no votes. Many others of us 
     <lb/>
     received votes and hold our seats by the franchise 
     <lb/>
     of somewhere in the neighbourhood of 25% of 
     <lb/>
     the electorate of our particular district. We can 
     <lb/>
     hardly then claim to have been sent here as a body 
     <lb/>
     by a majority of the electors of this country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But there is an even greater reason for this. We 
     <lb/>
     were not elected to carry out any particular 
     <lb/>
     policy, for no such policy could properly exist. 
     <lb/>
     Far from pledging allegiance to any form of 
     <lb/>
     government or policy, our duty under the act 
     <lb/>
     which created us was nothing more or less than 
     <lb/>
     that of investigating and recommending, as a 
     <lb/>
     result of our investigations, to the Crown. We 
     <lb/>
     were and are in the nature of somewhat numerous 
     <lb/>
     royal commissions charged with duties as inves<lb break="no"/>
            
            <cb/>
   tigators of facts, and obligated to make recom<lb break="no"/>mendations to the Crown just as a royal commis<lb break="no"/>sion does. It is fair to say that in reality the only 
     <lb/>
     difference between this Convention and a royal 
     <lb/>
     commission is the method of our selection. Quite 
     <lb/>
     clearly, it is outside our province to advocate 
     <lb/>
     particular forms of government. It is quite 
     <lb/>
     human, of course, that we should have opinions 
     <lb/>
     as to forms of government. I think l am not going 
     <lb/>
     too far if I say that any man who has not got 
     <lb/>
     personal opinions about forms of government is 
     <lb/>
     not a man fitted to be in this Convention at all. 
     <lb/>
     But those views should not be allowed to obtrude 
     <lb/>
     themselves into our deliberations. Our duty is not 
     <lb/>
     to advocate, but simply and objectively to recom<lb break="no"/>mend, not the particular form of government 
     <lb/>
     which appeals to us, but those forms of govern<lb break="no"/>ment which may be suitable in the circumstances. 
     <lb/>
     Ours is not the right to decide; we have nothing 
     <lb/>
     to do with decisions. It is ours to recommend 
     <lb/>
     forms upon which the people themselves will 
     <lb/>
     decide. Theirs is the duty, theirs alone the right to 
     <lb/>
     make the ultimate selection. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Speaking for myself, as I see the position 
     <lb/>
     today, I shall have to recommend to His 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's Government, insofar as my vote in this 
     <lb/>
     Convention goes, one form of government which 
     <lb/>
     I do not altogether like, and another which I shall 
     <lb/>
     definitely vote against at the plebiscite. I must 
     <lb/>
     recommend them notwithstanding that I do not 
     <lb/>
     like them — I do not like the one and I am 
     <lb/>
     opposed to the other — because they are forms 
     <lb/>
     which might be suitable and which the people 
     <lb/>
     might select; and I have no right whatever to 
     <lb/>
     debar the people from the right to vote for or 
     <lb/>
     against any form of government which might be 
     <lb/>
     suitable. If we could have kept that one point in 
     <lb/>
     view, many of our difficulties could not have 
     <lb/>
     arisen and much of the ill-will which has 
     <lb/>
     developed could have been avoided. Unfortu<lb break="no"/>nately it was not so. Political ideologies were 
     <lb/>adopted and fought for — sincerely enough, per<lb break="no"/>haps, but definitely erroneous. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <note xml:id="fn_01">[1] Captain W. Gordon Warren.</note> 
     
            
            <pb n="592" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0592.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">592</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">October 1947</fw> 
     
     
     
     
            <p>
     We are now drawing to the close of the ac<lb break="no"/>tivities of this Convention. Our work is for the 
     <lb/>
     most part completed. And yet the part which 
     <lb/>
     remains is the most important part. The decision 
     <lb/>
     has still to be made on the question of forms of 
     <lb/>
     government which we shall recommend to His 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Can we not for the remainder of our life as a 
     <lb/>
     Convention, forget our political leanings? Can 
     <lb/>
     we not realise, as I have already said, that we are 
     <lb/>
     not a body of partisans, but rather in the position 
     <lb/>
     of a bench of judges? That we are not a House of 
     <lb/>
     Assembly, but rather in the nature of a royal 
     <lb/>
     commission? If we can do this, we shall recover 
     <lb/>
     that public respect which I fear we have done 
     <lb/>
     much to destroy, we shall remove unnecessary 
     <lb/>
     and improper problems and difficulties from the 
     <lb/>
     path of the Chairman, and we shall have done a 
     <lb/>
     real service to this country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In our new Chairman I have full confidence. 
     <lb/>
     His ability is great. He is adequate to the task. For 
     <lb/>
     myself, I offer him my fullest co-operation and 
     <lb/>
     support and I trust that all members will feel as I 
     <lb/>
     do on this subject. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir, I move that our new Chairman do now 
     <lb/>
    take the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> In rising to second the motion so ably 
     <lb/>proposed by our ex-Chairman, which I may call 
     <lb/>a motion of welcome to you as our new Chair<lb break="no"/>man, I cannot add very much to the encomium 
     <lb/>expressed by the proposer of the motion. I feel 
     <lb/>sure that your expert knowledge and well-known 
     <lb/>diplomacy fit you well for the office you have 
     <lb/>accepted at no small sacrifice to yourself. I think, 
     <lb/>moreover, that the government can be congratu<lb break="no"/>lated upon the promptness with which they dealt 
     <lb/>with the crisis calling for a new appointment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     I do not intend to discuss those regrettable 
     <lb/>
     events which occurred in this chamber a few days 
     <lb/>
     ago, as I feel that in the public interest it will be 
     <lb/>
     best to entirely forget and overlook them. Never<lb break="no"/>theless, I cannot refrain from saying, without the 
     <lb/>
     slightest equivocation, that in my opinion our 
     <lb/>
     ex-Chm'iman performed his difficult duties at all 
     <lb/>
     times in a fair and unbiased manner, and that he 
     <lb/>
     at no time allowed his personal leanings towards 
     <lb/>
     any particular ideology to interfere with the per<lb break="no"/>formance of those duties. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Unfortunately there seem to be many mem<lb break="no"/>bers who have already formed definite opinions 
     <lb/>
     as to the recommendations to be made in connec<lb break="no"/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     tion with the forthcoming referendum without 
     <lb/>
     having heard all the evidence or waiting for the 
     <lb/>
     end of the discussions. This is indeed an unfortu<lb break="no"/>nate state of affairs, as our plain duty is to proceed 
     <lb/>
     with the presentation of facts, and not to utilise 
     <lb/>
     this National Convention as a jumping-off place 
     <lb/>
     for future political partisanship. If we cannot help 
     <lb/>
     forming a definite bias towards one or more 
     <lb/>
     forms of government, we can restrain ourselves 
     <lb/>
     from preventing a hearing for those other forms 
     <lb/>
     of which, at the present time, we may not ap<lb break="no"/>prove. 
     <lb/></p>

   <p>
     Our duties as regards the gathering of facts 
     <lb/>
     have almost reached their objective, and if we 
     <lb/>
     now decide to concentrate our attention on per<lb break="no"/>haps three phases of our deliberations which 
     <lb/>
     seem to me necessary before we wind up our 
     <lb/>
     work, we shall be acting wisely. The first of these 
     <lb/>
     seems to be to declare whether the country is at 
     <lb/>
     the present time self-supporting, a decision 
     <lb/>
     which should not be difficult to reach. The 
     <lb/>
     second is to decide whether we have a reasonable 
     <lb/>
     expectation of being able to maintain a self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting position in the foreseeable future, and I 
     <lb/>
     submit that we cannot be expected to prophesy 
     <lb/>
     for any lengthy period, and indeed under present 
     <lb/>
     world conditions it may be dangerous to 
     <lb/>
     prophesy at all. The third phase, it seems to me, 
     <lb/>
     is to debate and definitely decide upon the forms 
     <lb/>
     of government which we consider should be 
     <lb/>
     placed on the referendum paper, taking each form 
     <lb/>
     separately. Perhaps I should add a fourth item, 
     <lb/>
     namely, the drafting of a report covering our 
     <lb/>
     findings and recommendations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I feel sure, sir, that if you can assist in keeping 
     <lb/>
     the minds of the delegates of this Convention on 
     <lb/>
     these definite objectives you will be doing us a 
     <lb/>
     good service, and we shall be able to wind up our 
     <lb/>
     operations within a comparatively short period. I 
     <lb/>
     believe you will receive the respect and support 
     <lb/>
     of all the delegates. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. McEvoy</persName> Members of the National Conven<lb break="no"/>tion of Newfoundland, before assuming the Chair 
     <lb/>
     I should like, first of all, to express to you my very 
     <lb/>
     deep appreciation and sincere thanks for the 
     <lb/>
     warmth and kindness of your welcome and to 
     <lb/>
     assure you I regard your kindness in this respect 
     <lb/>
     as a very great and pleasing compliment. In par<lb break="no"/>ticular would I address my thanks to my distin<lb break="no"/>guished and learned friend, Mr. Bradley, former 
     
            
            <pb n="593" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0593.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
     October 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">593</fw> 


            
     Chairman of this Convention, for his kind 
     <lb/>
     remarks; and to the Hon. R. B. Job who so gra<lb break="no"/>ciously consented to second the motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I feel I should trespass upon your time and 
     <lb/>
     patience in order that I may, at the outset, leave 
     <lb/>
     with you my conceptions of my sworn duty. As I 
     <lb/>
     see it, my position is similar to that of a judge of 
     <lb/>
     the Supreme Court. I come to this chamber under 
     <lb/>
     a Royal Commission issued by His Excellency 
     <lb/>
     the Governor in Commission, and I have sworn 
     <lb/>
     that I will do the duties expected of me, "so help 
     <lb/>
     me God." The extent to which I shall be success<lb break="no"/>ful, must, in the last analysis depend upon the 
     <lb/>
     sympathy, co-operation and support that I receive 
     <lb/>
     from you as members. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I want to make it clear that I regard my sworn 
     <lb/>
     duties in a three-fold way. Firstly, that I must 
     <lb/>
     impartially and fairly discharge my duties to His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency the Governor in Commission who has 
     <lb/>
     entrusted the discharge of the duties of this office 
     <lb/>
     to me. I have, secondly, to fairly, impartially, and 
     <lb/>
     without fear and prejudice discharge my duties to 
     <lb/>
     the people who sent you here; and thirdly, I have 
     <lb/>
     my sworn duty to you as the representatives of 
     <lb/>
     the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     My task is none too easy. It was a duty I did 
     <lb/>
     not seek and I doubt very much if anybody other 
     <lb/>
     than His Excellency the Governor could have 
     <lb/>
     persuaded me to accept it. But, like the thousands 
     <lb/>
     of people throughout this country who know our 
     <lb/>
     Governor, I think it is a fair statement to make 
     <lb/>
     that he is a great man in the most literal sense of 
     <lb/>
     the term. He is a wise man and what perhaps is 
     <lb/>
     the most important of all, he is a good man. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am not underestimating the extent of my 
     <lb/>
     duties. May I remind members that the lamented 
     <lb/>
     late Hon. Mr. Justice Fox, because of the exacti<lb break="no"/>tudes of his office, in the opinion of many of us 
     <lb/>
     who were close to him, laid down the burdens and 
     <lb/>
     cares of this life at the untimely age of 54 because 
     <lb/>
     he had accepted the office which I am now about 
     <lb/>
     to assume. I feel duty bound to say that Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Justice Fox sacrificed his life for his country just 
     <lb/>
     as truly as if he had laid it down on the battlefields 
     <lb/>
     of Europe. This country is under an irreparable 
     <lb/>
     debt to him and to his family. Then again, as a 
     <lb/>
     great lawyer, and a judge of the Supreme Court, 
     <lb/>
     his wide parliamentary experience pre-eminently 
     <lb/>
     fitted him to discharge his duties as Chairman. 
     <lb/>
     The high standards set by the Hon. Mr. Justice 
     <lb/>
     Fox will indeed be very difficult for me to attain, 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     if I ever do attain them. But certain it is, by and 
     <lb/>
     with your sympathy and co-operation, I shall 
     <lb/>
     strive to the best of my ability to maintain the very 
     <lb/>
     high traditions set by him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I feel, however members may be divided in 
     <lb/>
     their opinions on this subject, that the high stand<lb break="no"/>ards set by the late Mr. Justice Fox were quite 
     <lb/>
     definitely maintained by my distinguished and 
     <lb/>
     learned friend Mr. Bradley, K.C. His wide par<lb break="no"/>liamentary experience, his brilliantly analytical 
     <lb/>
     mind, and his great facility for promptly and 
     <lb/>
     concisely expressing that brilliance of mind, 
     <lb/>
     quite properly entitled him to the respect and 
     <lb/>
     admiration of all who know him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I come in at a very awkward time. I take over 
     <lb/>
     where one Chairman laid down the burdens and 
     <lb/>
     cares of this life, and the other, because of the 
     <lb/>
     exactitudes of the office, saw fit to resign. I must 
     <lb/>
     therefore appeal to members to remember the 
     <lb/>
     unenviable place in which I find myself. Idid not 
     <lb/>
     seek this office. I agreed to accept it only at the 
     <lb/>
     request and persuasion of His Excellency, but, 
     <lb/>
     having accepted it, it is my intention to discharge 
     <lb/>
     literally the requirements and dictates of my oath 
     <lb/>
     by presiding impartially and without fear or 
     <lb/>
     favour.... I shall expect members of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion to obey any rulings that I may be called upon 
     <lb/>
     from time to time to make, unless and until such 
     <lb/>
     rulings are appealed to and reversed by the whole 
     <lb/>
     House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I should like to conclude by again expressing 
     <lb/>
    my very deep appreciation and thanks for the 
     <lb/>warmth and kindness of your welcome, and to ask 
     <lb/>you to accord to me in some measure the respect, 
     <lb/>co-operation and support that I certainly intend 
     <lb/>to give you, so that together we may walk forward 
     <lb/>with dignity, decorum and businesslike ex<lb break="no"/>pediency, in the colossal task of preparing our 
     <lb/>beloved country to shortly meet its fateful ren<lb break="no"/>dezvous with destiny. Gentlemen, thank you very 
     <lb/>much.</p>
            
 
   <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName>
 Mr. Chairman, I have no inten<lb break="no"/>tion whatever of making any lengthy remarks. I 
     <lb/>want merely to assure you of my deep admiration 
     <lb/>of you, my respect, and my intention to co<lb break="no"/>operate with you to the fullest possible extent. I 
     <lb/>believe that for the remaining few weeks that the 
     <lb/>Convention will last the members will conduct 
     <lb/>the affairs of the Convention in a manner that will 
     <lb/>deserve the respect of the whole country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     If I cannot speak for the members I can speak 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="594" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-10-15_Page_0594.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="num">594</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">October 1947</fw> 
     <lb/>
            
            
     for myself, and I promise you that, as far as it lies 
     <lb/>
     in my ability at least, while you are in the Chair 
     <lb/>
     and for the remainder of this Convention's life, I 
     <lb/>
     for one will be an absolute model of parliamen<lb break="no"/>tary propriety, dignity and decorum. If the mem<lb break="no"/>bers who smile are inclined to doubt the sincerity 
     <lb/>
     of what I say, I will give you at this moment an 
     <lb/>
     earnest of the sincerity of my statement and in<lb break="no"/>tentions, when I offer, through you, to a member 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention about whom at the last sitting 
     <lb/>
     on Friday last, in the heat of debate and in a state 
     <lb/>
     of anger, I made a remark which now I wish to 
     <lb/>
     withdraw. I refer to the remark I made about my 
     <lb/>
     good and learned friend behind me, Mr. Hollett. 
     <lb/>
     I withdraw the remark. I apologise sincerely to 
     <lb/>
     him, and promise him sincerely that he will have 
     <lb/>
     to provoke me much more than he has ever done 
     <lb/>
     in the past, before I will make another insulting 
     <lb/>
     remark about him.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName>, I wish you every success in 
     <lb/>
     your office, and I believe you will be a success. I 
     <lb/>
     look upon you as one Newfoundlander, amongst 
     <lb/>
     others, who has come up from the ranks by hard 
     <lb/>
     work, great study and brilliance of mind. I ac<lb break="no"/>claim you as a Newfoundlander of whom we 
     <lb/>
     always can be proud. You have my respect, and 
     <lb/>
     you will have my co-operation to the dying hour 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, I don't propose to 
     <lb/>
     make any extended remarks in reply to my friend 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood. I think probably he has the right 
     <lb/>
     to lose his temper once in a while, the same as the 
     <lb/>
     rest of us, and I can say frankly that I do very 
               
               <cb/>
            
     heartily accept his apology for the words which 
     <lb/>
     he used towards me the other day, but, as I said, 
     <lb/>
     these words were spoken in the heat of debate and 
     <lb/>
     I am quite sure that he probably did not mean 
     <lb/>
     what he said, and if he did, he has recanted now. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood and myself have got along very 
     <lb/>
     peaceably in the past 12 months. We have fallen 
     <lb/>
     out once in a while, but it was always in the 
     <lb/>
     course of debate when we were trying to decide 
     <lb/>
     something which we each believed to be for the 
     <lb/>
     benefit, or otherwise, of our country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am rather appalled at the attitude taken by 
     <lb/>
     some of the daily papers in connection with the 
     <lb/>
     little episode which happened here on Friday. 
     <lb/>
     Speaking for myself, I remember being in the 
     <lb/>
     British House of Commons last May at question 
     <lb/>
     time, and there were more cat-calls across the 
     <lb/>
     floors of that assembly than we have cast at each 
     <lb/>
     other in the whole 12 months. There were cat<lb break="no"/>calls and cries of "sit down" and "get out"; and 
     <lb/>
     nobody seemed to worry about that, it was in the 
     <lb/>
     ordinary course of debate.... I accept this apology 
     <lb/>
     from Mr. Smallwood, and l would like, sir, in 
     <lb/>
     accepting it, to offer to you my heartiest con<lb break="no"/>gratulations on this office which you have as<lb break="no"/>sumed, and which I know will tax even you; at 
     <lb/>
     times you will be taxed probably as to the correct 
     <lb/>
     decision to give, but I feel quite sure that I can 
     <lb/>
     add my words to Mr. Smallwood in offering you 
     <lb/>
     my whole-hearted support in this strenuous job 
     <lb/>
     which you have undertaken for your country. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<!-- TY, 2017-07-05, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
<!--   <p>
     October 17, 1947¹ 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Finance Committee:² 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Keough Before I present myself to the sub- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ject matter which is before us, I should like, sir, 
     <lb/>
     seeing that this is the first occasion on which I 
     <lb/>
     have spoken since your advent to our midst, to 
     <lb/>
     say a word of welcome to yourself.... It was a wise 
     <lb/>
     choice that led to your selection, and it is with 
     <lb/>
     considerable reassurance that we welcome you to 
     <lb/>
     the Chair of this assembly. It is to a most impor- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tant undertaking that you are committed, to 
     <lb/>
     preside with impartiality and with wisdom over 
     <lb/>
     the deliberations of this House. The task to which 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     this assembly is committed is of much moment 
     <lb/>
     to all the people. We are all little men sent here 
     <lb/>
     to serve a great purpose. But because the purpose 
     <lb/>
     is great, if we serve it worthily, some of the 
     <lb/>
     greatness will descend upon us. But if we serve 
     <lb/>
     this purpose unworthily, our names will stand 
     <lb/>
     forever cursed, and our posterity will point to us 
     <lb/>
     as men of little soul, who could not face the 
     <lb/>
     supreme power of our faith when its challenge 
     <lb/>
     came. I am quite confident that your guidance. 
     <lb/>
     sir, will increase the measure of the illustrious- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     ¹The proceedings for October 17, 1947, were taken from the recording of the debate. 
     <lb/>
    ²Volume II:369. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
         </div>
      </div></body>
   </text>
</TEI>