<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-10-11"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-10-11">11 October 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

          <date when="1995"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="86"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0075.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0076.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0077.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0078.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0079.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0080.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0081.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0082.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0083.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0084.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0085.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0086.hocr.html"/>
               </item>


            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-16">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-02-16">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-04">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0075">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0075.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0076">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0076.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0077">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0077.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0078">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0078.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0079">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0079.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0080">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0080.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0081">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0081.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0082">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0082.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0083">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0083.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0084">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0084.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0085">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0085.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0086">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0086.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="75"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0075.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">75</fw>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-02-16, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
<!--<p>
     refused information regarding the disposition of 
     <lb/>
     some timber areas on Labrador. We have been 
     <lb/>
     told that the government was not going to give 
     <lb/>
     that information. I am taking this opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     telling the Information Committee. I would like 
     <lb/>
     to back up what Mr. Bradley has said — we are 
     <lb/>
     here to find out facts as to the assets of the country 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     and those very assets may be given away. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Bradley It would be better if we had it in 
     <lb/>
     writing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin I shall put it in writing after ad<lb break="no"/>journment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The Convention adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->


<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     October 11, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> At the request of the Fisheries Committee, Mr.
                  Keough has been added to that <lb/>committee.<lb/>
               </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
           
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Interim Report of the Fisheries Committee:<ref target="#fn_x1">[1]</ref>

     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read pages 1 and 2 of the report]</hi> 
     <lb/></p>

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That might be termed the first <lb/> section of
                  the report, gentlemen. Any member <lb/> wishing to debate on the report may now
                  speak. <lb/> If you do not desire to discuss that section of the <lb/> report,
                  gentlemen. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> I acknowledge there is a fish plant in <lb/> Long
                  Harbour, Placentia Bay. I wonder if the <lb/> government inspected that too, as it
                  is not men<lb break="no"/>tioned here. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> The bait depots are not included. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> With regard to the amount of capital <lb/>
                  invested, did the committee arrive at the amount <lb/> invested by the government
                  or did they not? <lb/>
               </p>
           
 <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I don't know of any money invested by <lb/>the government. That has
                  certainly not been <lb/>taken into account. There may be in one or two <lb/>places
                  advances made by the government which <lb/>have been paid or partly repaid, but
                  they have not <lb/>been taken into account. These figures are rough <lb/>I must
                  confess, but they are the nearest we can <lb/>get. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I saw in the estimates where a cer<lb break="no"
                  />tain amount of money had been subsidised by the <lb/> government for advances to
                  possible corpora<lb break="no"/>tions. I understood also that a certain amount had
                  <lb/> been put out, and it might be suggested that the <lb/> committee arrive at
                  the true situation. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The committee will make in<lb break="no"
                  />quiries into that point, Mr. Hollett. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> Mr. Chairman. in the fourth para<lb break="no"
                  />graph the wording is a little ambiguous. It reads: <lb/> "The frozen blueberry
                  industry was also a very <lb/> substantial business and of very definite value to
                  <lb/> the country owing to the fact that the cost of <lb/> picking was very little
                  ...." As it reads it might <lb/>
                 
                  <cb/> seem as if the value was of small return to the <lb/> pickers, but I am sure
                  that is not the thought of <lb/> the Fishery Committee, or is it? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I think that the idea was that the cost of <lb/> the
                  picking was small comparatively, and it was <lb/> a very worthwhile return to the
                  pickers. I think it <lb/> was because the price paid to the pickers was <lb/>
                  small in past years. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> There is another question about bait <lb/> sold
                  to fishermen. The report states that "The bait <lb/> frozen (squid and herring)
                  was substantial, but <lb/> nothing like the present-day volume because the <lb/>
                  fishermen were not generally so accustomed to <lb/> using the frozen bait as they
                  are now." I don't <lb/> believe that, because years ago the only reason <lb/> why
                  fishermen did not use frozen bait very <lb/> generally was because of the cost,
                  which was <lb/> almost prohibitive in view of the amount of <lb/> money they
                  received for the fish caught. I was <lb/> wondering if the committee would be good
                  <lb/> enough to look into the present cost of bait as <lb/> supplied to first, our
                  shore fishermen, and second, <lb/> our bank fishermen. It is absolutely essential
                  if <lb/> our fishermen are to use frozen bait that some <lb/> means be found to
                  supply that bait at the least <lb/> possible cost. The committee might be able to
                  get <lb/> some figures with regard to that.... It is several <lb/> years since I
                  had anything to do with fishery <lb/> conditions, but in those old days there were
                  a <lb/> good many cases of the fall fishing being given <lb/> up merely because
                  for that fishery it became <lb/> necessary for the banking fleet to procure frozen
                  <lb/> bait, and after trying it for a number of years they <lb/> discovered that
                  the returns which the individual <lb/> fisherman made on that trip were absolutely
                  nil <lb/> when they took into consideration the cost of <lb/>

<note xml:id="fn_x1">1 Volume II:21 1. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

                  <pb n="76" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0076.jpg"/>
                  outfitting for that fall trip, which is much more <lb/> than for a trip in the
                  summer or spring, and that <lb/> cost was largely brought about by the money <lb/>
                  which fishermen were charged up with on ac<lb break="no"/>count of bait. I think
                  it is important for us to know <lb/> just how the supply of bait now would apply
                  to <lb/> the possibility of fishermen prosecuting the bank <lb/> fishery in the
                  late fall, and whether or not we <lb/> might not come to the conclusion that the
                     fisher<lb break="no"/>men are perfectly right. It is senseless for a man <lb/>
                  to go out on the last trip in the fall if they find <lb/> when they come in with a
                  loaded ship that they <lb/> still have nothing coming to them towards their <lb/>
                  income for the winter... I would suggest that it <lb/> would be wise if we knew
                  just what it would cost <lb/> a banker, or the individual member of a crew, to
                  <lb/> get sufficient bait to enable him to proceed on the <lb/> fall trip. <lb/>
               </p>
          
  <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> That's an interesting point. I really <lb/>don't know, but we
                  could take it up. I should have <lb/>thought that there would be no question at
                  all that <lb/>they would make a good deal of money on it, but <lb/>I can't say
                  definitely. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I am referring to the salt fishery <lb/>more than to
                  the fresh. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I was thinking of the fresh fish. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> Mr. Chairman, might I ask the <lb/>committee if
                  they can tell us by whom these ships <lb/>are owned or who operates them? Another
                  heavy <lb/>investment is the draggers. Is that investment by <lb/>private
                  enterprise or is the government going to <lb/>bill us for new draggers? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BURR2">Mr. Burry</persName> Mr Chairman, there is a small item <lb/>here regarding
                  the smelt fishery. l have no doubt <lb/>there will be more said about that, but I
                  wonder <lb/>if there is any idea of continuing this industry to <lb/>any extent,
                  of if it means anything to New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I know there is a lot of
                  smelt on the <lb/>Labrador, and I was wondering if there was any <lb/>possibility
                  of the fresh freezing process being <lb/>continued, as I think we might have some
                  frozen <lb/>and sent to the markets. I know the committee <lb/>will be dealing
                  with this further and they might <lb/>go into that. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I think it is gradually increasing. <lb/>
               </p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Any further comment on that<lb/> section, gentlemen? Are you
                  ready for the ques<lb break="no"/>tions? Moved that section 1 be adopted.<lb/></p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The section was adopted. The Secretary read
   
          
            <cb/>
          
     pages 3, 4 and 5 of the report]</hi><ref target="#fn_x2">[1]</ref>
 
     <lb/></p>

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> I wonder if the committee could <lb/> tell this
                  Convention just what is Newfoundland's <lb/> quota on fillets, etc., under the
                  preferential rate <lb/> of l-7/8 cents. <lb/>
               </p>
            
<p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> We are really operating under a joint <lb/>quota and it is to this
                  country's advantage to get <lb/>as many pounds as possible in under this quota at
                  <lb/>the earliest possible date. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> Any duty on fresh salmon and <lb/>lobster? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I cannot touch that question. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Is there a race to get in that 18 <lb/>million
                  pound quota? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> We produce as much as we can and get <lb/>it in as soon
                  as we can. There is no actual race. <lb/>We want to get a quota of our own, and a
                  special <lb/>one, if we can. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> With the total quota for New<lb break="no"
                  />foundland and Canada being 18 million pounds, <lb/>is the situation now that the
                  one who gets there <lb/>first gets the larger share of the total quota? Might
                  <lb/>it not be a little dangerous to get a quota of our <lb/>own? Our share of the
                  18 million pounds was 5 <lb/>million, and unless the quota was increased might
                  <lb/>it not be dangerous? Last year we got 5 of the 18 <lb/>millions; we succeeded
                  to that extent but if a <lb/>definite quota is obtained is not the position that
                  <lb/>it might be less than the amount we got last year? <lb/>I have in mind the
                  pitifully small volume of <lb/>fishery exports of Newfoundland as compared
                  <lb/>with those of Canada. I am not in the trade and <lb/>many of the members of
                  the Fishery Committee <lb/>are and undoubtedly they know of what is in the
                  <lb/>minds of the Fisheries Board and in Mr. Gushue's <lb/>mind, but to me it does
                  seem that there is a certain <lb/>amount of danger. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I think there is a very great danger <lb/>if we do
                  not have a quota, in view of the fact that <lb/>today you have a joint quota and
                  this new plant <lb/>is starting in Louisbourg.... <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> That is why I referred to the necessity <lb/>of making
                  some special arrangements direct with <lb/>the United States on this matter.
                  Unless we do get <lb/>some special arrangements we may not get any <lb/>thing. We
                  want to get a good quota but it will <lb/>depend on ourselves. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> There is one paragraph to which I <lb/>would like to
                  refer. On page 4: "The codfish sold <lb/>

<note xml:id="fn_x2">Volume II:212-213. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note> 

                  <pb n="77" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0077.jpg"/>
                 

 <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">77</fw> to the cold storage plants will certainly, in the <lb/>
                  long run, give the fishermen much better returns <lb/> than those from saltfish."
                  I wonder how long that <lb/> run is going to be? We are trying to think of some
                  <lb/> way by which we can raise the standard of the <lb/> people, and the only way
                  is to raise the standard <lb/> of the primary producer. I am afraid the price for
                  <lb/> fresh fish paid to the man who goes out in the <lb/> morning and comes back
                  in the evening, will <lb/> largely depend on the amount of money that that <lb/>
                  man would get if he had salted the fish, provided <lb/> there was no fish plant
                  there. I have all honour <lb/> and respect for the men who have been building
                  <lb/> up this fresh fish industry. The progress made <lb/> over the last few years
                  is marvellous — tremen<lb break="no"/>dous.... But the point is this: if the fresh
                  fish <lb/> industry is going to be of real benefit to this <lb/> country, it must,
                  primarily, be of a real benefit to <lb/> the primary producer — the man who goes
                  out <lb/> and risks his life... At the moment a man goes out <lb/> and catches
                  fish and comes in hoping to sell in <lb/> cold storage. He may be unable to do
                  that; there<lb break="no"/>fore he has to salt it, make it and dry it. How are
                  <lb/> we going to prevent some unscrupulous fresh fish <lb/> man from taking
                  advantage of that situation? He <lb/> has, in a real sense, a gun which he can put
                  to that <lb/> man's head by saying, "All right, go salt your <lb/> fish, you will
                  get only $5 or $10. You do not have <lb/> to work; you do not have to run the risk
                  of <lb/> weather." How are we going to prevent this? If <lb/> this Convention is
                  going to back the fresh fish <lb/> industry, we have to be careful about that
                  point. <lb/> Fresh fish is all right — a lot of fortunes have <lb/> been made out
                  of it. You may say, "How am I <lb/> going to gain by it? I will not have to get
                  down <lb/> on the flake and spread it? How much more is it <lb/> going to raise
                  the standard of living?" The answer <lb/> to that is to unite. Unless the fresh
                  fish trade <lb/> endeavours to work up some sort of co—operation <lb/> between
                  themselves, the fishermen and the pack<lb break="no"/>ers, then I am afraid the
                  fresh fish industry will <lb/> go the way of saltfish. I put it through you to the
                  <lb/> Fisheries Board that is something that has to be <lb/> taken into account.
                  We have first to raise the <lb/> standard of living of the people; from the fresh
                  <lb/> fish industry as well as the lumbering industries <lb/> and everything else,
                  and I suggest that one of the <lb/> first things the promoters of the fresh fish
                     in<lb break="no"/>dustry have to do is to gain the confidence of the <lb/> men
                  who produce the raw material. How it is <lb/>
                  <cb/>
                 
 going to be done is
                  not for me to say, but unless <lb/> it is done, the fresh fish industry is ruined
                  from <lb/> the start. Any man interested in the fresh fish <lb/> industry must
                  take care to see that the price paid <lb/> to fishermen for fresh fish is not
                  going to be <lb/> governed by the price for salt fish. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> In replying to that, it is stated in the <lb/> same
                  paragraph, "one of the objectives of the cold <lb/> storage operators is to pay as
                  high a price as <lb/> possible to the fishermen." But there is a lot of <lb/>
                  money invested and unless the operator can do <lb/> well in the first few years of
                  the industry, it is <lb/> going to be a bad job... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> It is my opinion and the opinion of <lb/> many
                  others, that the objective of the cold storage <lb/> operators is to pay as low a
                  price as possible, and <lb/> that sentence should not be embodied in the <lb/>
                  report. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> I was going to make somewhat the <lb/> same
                  remark. I would like to know just what <lb/> evidence the Fisheries Committee has
                  at its dis<lb break="no"/>posal on which it based this assertion? I am <lb/>
                  prepared to accept it on evidence from the com<lb break="no"/>mittee, otherwise I
                  am not prepared to accept it.... <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> We have no evidence other than the <lb/>statements of
                  the cold storage plants. You could <lb/>put the word 'alleged' or 'declared' in
                  there. <lb/>
               </p>
            
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The section was amended accordingly]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I see the old suspicion still exists, that <lb/> the
                  operators of all commercial concerns are after <lb/> one thing. In my experience
                  the merchants have <lb/> done a good job in the past and in the most part <lb/>
                  have the country's interest at heart. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> It is not a case of suspicion. I am of <lb/> the
                  opinion that business is business and I am <lb/> sorry to have to raise the point,
                  but I could not <lb/> accept the statement as it stood. I want to have as <lb/>
                  little to say as possible on the subject, but I am in <lb/> possession of certain
                  knowledge with regard to <lb/> the operation of fresh fish plants which made it
                  <lb/> impossible for me to accept that as it stood... <lb/> Mr. Northcott On page
                  5, paragraph
                  5<ref target="#fn_x3">[1]</ref>
                  it says, <lb/> "There are only four or five large exporters to the <lb/> USA
                  market..." Who knows that in ten years' <lb/> time there will not be 20 such
                  plants? I would like <lb/> the Committee to bear that in mind. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I suggest that be amended to read <lb/> "There are
                     <hi rendition="simple:italic">at present</hi> only four or five large <lb/>
                  exporters." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The sentence was amended]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

 <note xml:id="fn_x3">1 Volume 11:212. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note> 
    
            <pb n="78"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0078.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">78</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I hope Mr. Job did not think I was <lb/> laying
                  any charges against the merchants. I agree <lb/> that merchants have many times
                  done a good job. <lb/> Our resources are of mushroom growth and <lb/> mushrooms do
                  not grow except under favourable <lb/> circumstances. Our natural resources are
                  our <lb/> producers and unless co-operation is kept be<lb break="no"/>tween the
                  fresh fish industry and the producer it <lb/> will go the way of the saltfish
                  industry. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> In the past the cake has not been large <lb/> enough
                  to divide. In the fresh fish industry we are <lb/> trying to enlarge the cake so
                  that there will be <lb/> enough to provide for the primary producer. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> If he believes that, why does he say <lb/>the men
                  who put up the money must be paid, must <lb/>have their money back, must pay off
                  capital <lb/>expenditure? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I did not say "pay off" capital expendi<lb break="no"
                  />ture, but I do say "reduce" the expenditure. The <lb/> plants will cost twice as
                  much in say five years <lb/> time. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> In regard to merchants, we could <lb/> leave them
                  to organised labour. What we want to <lb/> get at is the market. Have we any
                  figures on the <lb/> consumption of frozen fish in the United States? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> We have figures. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> How do they compare? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> What we could supply is a mere drop <lb/> in the
                  bucket. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> I think this mere drop in the buck<lb break="no"
                  />et should be supplied in return for what we have <lb/> given them in the past. I
                  am referring to markets <lb/> and prices. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> In trying to get tariff conces<lb break="no"
                  />sions, I would suggest all fish produced in New<lb break="no"/>foundland be
                  embodied in this report. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> There is a very interesting item on <lb/> page
                  6<ref target="#fn_x4">[1]</ref>
                  showing the comparative years 1943 to <lb/> 1946 — labour. In connection with
                  operating <lb/> plants, I wonder if the committee could make it <lb/> even more
                  illuminating. We might be able to <lb/> obtain figures of how much fish was
                  produced <lb/> and what was the overhead and operating cost, <lb/> and we might be
                  optimistic enough to find out <lb/> what the gross production was in dollars.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> These figures were given us confiden<lb break="no"
                  />tially, and if it became necessary to ask for more <lb/> information we could
                  try to get it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> You notice that the amount paid to <lb/>
                  <cb/>
                  
                  the fishermen in 1946 is practically four times the <lb/> amount paid for 1943,
                  whilst that for labour has <lb/> just doubled; either the fishermen must have done
                  <lb/> exceptionally well or the labourers were very <lb/> poorly paid. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> This is an interim report as I <lb/>
                  understand, and so far we have had a reasonably <lb/> illuminating discussion on
                  the various points <lb/> contained in it, but there is a great deal of talk <lb/>
                  about fishermen versus the merchants, etc, and <lb/> the real purpose of this
                  aftemoon's meeting was <lb/> to get to the summary of the report, Mr. Small<lb
                     break="no"/>wood has been very quiet, and I am sure that he <lb/> has something
                  to say, and would suggest we <lb/> waive the rest of this discussion as time is
                     pass<lb break="no"/>ing. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Moved that the second section <lb/> of the
                  interim report as read and amended be <lb/> adopted. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The second section was adopted, and the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary read the summary]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Any comments on this conclud<lb break="no"/>ing
                  section of the report? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> Mr. Chairman and gentlemen, in <lb/> speaking on
                  the interim report of the Fisheries <lb/> Committee, the main object of which is
                  the cold <lb/> storage industry, may I first congratulate the <lb/> committee on
                  the excellence of their report, and <lb/> the thoroughness with which they have
                  reviewed <lb/> the situation, in regard to the future of the in<lb break="no"
                  />dustry, and the possibilities of its expansion. <lb/> Mr. Job has given us an
                  excellent resumé of <lb/> conditions under which our fisheries will have to <lb/>
                  function, and stressed the necessity of markets, <lb/> with favourable tariffs and
                  trade relations, <lb/> primarily with the United States. We feel that the <lb/>
                  concessions granted to the United States in the <lb/> way of leases of
                  Newfoundland territory for 99 <lb/> years, together with free importations for use
                  at <lb/> their bases, use of roads, etc., should justify some <lb/> adequate
                  returns, and I concur with the report as <lb/> presented in its entirety, but will
                  add that more <lb/> stress should be placed on other phases of the <lb/> industry,
                  particularly the herring industry. <lb/>
               </p>
<p>
In section 5, page 8<ref target="#fn_x5">[2]</ref>, you do mention herring<lb/>
and its by-products such as oil and meal.... Com<lb break="no"/>ing from the home of the herring, I would be<lb/>
remiss in my duty if I did not point out a few facts<lb/>
that are peculiar to the industry, and of great<lb/> 

<note xml:id="fn_x4">1 Volume 11:213. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note> 

<note xml:id="fn_x5">2 Volume 11:214. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
     
    
            <pb n="79"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0079.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">79</fw>
           
     importance when speaking of markets. The in<lb break="no"/>dustry has grown from an export value of 
     <lb/>
     $236,000 in the year 1934-35 to $2,071,000 in 
     <lb/>
     the year 1944-45, and to a much greater amount 
     <lb/>
     in the last year. We know that herring are avail<lb break="no"/>able in vast quantities, and amounts already 
     <lb/>
     procured can be maintained and probably aug<lb break="no"/>mented if we find the markets. The greater bulk 
     <lb/>
     of the herring exported in this last year or two 
     <lb/>
     went to contracts placed by UNRRA, and al<lb break="no"/>though we hope this will be maintained there is 
     <lb/>
     no guarantee. It is obvious, in order to keep this 
     <lb/>
     growing industry at its present level, new markets 
     <lb/>
     must be found. I did not hear Mr. Gushue's 
     <lb/>
     speech on this subject at Rotary<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref>, and also mislaid 
     <lb/>
     the paper containing his speech. I will say that he 
     <lb/>
     and his board have done a good job in respect to 
     <lb/>
     the herring industry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Getting back to the cold storage industry, you 
     <lb/>
     will note that there is not a cold storage or quick- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     freezing plant on the west coast, north of Port- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     aux-Basques or Isle-aux-Morts. It would seem 
     <lb/>
     that where the herring are in abundance, as in the 
     <lb/>
     Bay of Islands, would be the most logical place 
     <lb/>
     to have such a plant, since bait could be obtained 
     <lb/>
     not only for our own fisheries, but exported for 
     <lb/>
     the same purpose. We do, during the winter 
     <lb/>
     months export quite a lot of herring to Canada, 
     <lb/>
     frozen by natural process. It is probable these 
     <lb/>
     matters have been gone into by the Fisheries 
     <lb/>
     Committee, or will be looked into at future meet<lb break="no"/>ings. I am not forgetting when speaking of her<lb break="no"/>ring to mention the importance of fish meal 
     <lb/>
     plants, and am happy to say we have one of the 
     <lb/>
     finest in the country owned by our mutual friend 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chesley Crosbie, in Bay of Islands. I think 
     <lb/>
     that this phase of the herring industry can be 
     <lb/>
     developed on a far greater scale if given aid and 
     <lb/>
     encouragement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When speaking of the herring industry, and I 
     <lb/>
     have mentioned Bay of Island particularly, I do 
     <lb/>
     not want to sectionalise the debate. I speak of it 
     <lb/>
     as it affects the country as a whole, not one 
     <lb/>
     particular part thereof, but, I do say, that in Bay 
     <lb/>
     of Islands we have been, and will probably con<lb break="no"/>tinue to be, sadly neglected in our efforts to 
     <lb/>
     promote this great and coming industry. We have 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
       
    
            
          
           
     always had and will probably continue to have a 
     <lb/>
     shortage of nets and gear. Also, due to the fact 
     <lb/>
     that shipping closes at an early date due to ice, 
     <lb/>
     much of the produce must be shipped by rail. 
     <lb/>
     Incidentally, all of these products so shipped 
     <lb/>
     must be hauled from the waterfront to the railroad 
     <lb/>
     station, and we have only an abused cowpath on 
     <lb/>
     which to do this most important work.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     At the present time in Bay of Islands quite a<lb/>large processing plant is being constructed by a<lb/>Canadian firm which will in all probability in<lb break="no"/>clude refrigeration. Does it not seem strange that<lb/>outside interests have to come and do a job which<lb/>should be done by our own government or local<lb/>interests?....<lb/> 
               <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Mr. Chairman, when the Fisheries <lb/>Committee
                  presented the report which we now <lb/>have before us it raised a question which
                  is more <lb/>important than the apparent subject matter of the <lb/>report proper.
                  I feel sure that as it was listened to <lb/>by the majority of the members of the
                     Conven<lb break="no"/>tion, and since that time by the public generally,
                  <lb/>there arose in the minds of the majority some<lb break="no"/>thing of the
                  past history of Newfoundland... <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>If we go back into Newfoundland's history far 
     <lb/>enough we have, on the authority of McLintock<ref target="#fn_02">[2]</ref> 
     <lb/>in particular, a clear picture of how in her struggle 
     <lb/>to establish herself, Newfoundland had to grow 
     <lb/>up in an atmosphere where the whole power of 
     <lb/>great nations tended to depress the struggling 
     <lb/>colony. Newfoundland, and the potential and ac<lb break="no"/>tual wealth of her fisheries, were treated as just 
     <lb/>another source of producing wealth for the 
     <lb/>mother country as well as a training ground for 
     <lb/>the defence of Britain, which at that time was 
     <lb/>looked upon as the chief preoccupation of 
     <lb/>government. In our studies of the problem of 
     <lb/>governing Newfoundland we are almost in<lb break="no"/>variably faced with the fact that the greatest prob<lb break="no"/>lem of government is the dispersal of our people. 
     <lb/>People may vary in their interpretation of the 
     <lb/>reasons for our having settled so far apart from 
     <lb/>each other, but if my reading of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>history is correct the repressive measures taken 
     <lb/>against settlement in the island were the main 
     <lb/>cause of our having to hide away in places where 
     <lb/>we could not be found. In addition, and because 
     <lb/>
            

     <note xml:id="fn_01">1 R. Gushue, speech at St. John's Rotary Club, 12 September 1946, as reported in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Evening Telegram</hi>, 13 
     <lb/>September 1946, p. 2.</note>
<note xml:id="fn_02">2 Alexander H. McLintock, <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Establishment of Constitutional Government in Newfoundland, 1783—1832. A <lb/>
               <lb/>Study of Retarded Colonization</hi> (London, 1941).</note>

            <pb n="80"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0080.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">80</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
          
     of our settlement in isolated places and our preoc<lb break="no"/>cupation with the fisheries, there came down 
     <lb/>
     through the years a feeling that agriculture, which 
     <lb/>
     in most countries formed the basis of a stable 
     <lb/>
     economy, should not be pushed so far as it could. 
     <lb/>
     These facts helped it to form an economy which 
     <lb/>
     has never in our history made for stability, and 
     <lb/>
     has given us almost without regard to economic 
     <lb/>
     conditions in the outside world a long series of 
     <lb/>
     recurrent depressions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In a world in which industries were organised 
     <lb/>
     more or less on an individualistic basis, New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders were able to extract a tolerable 
     <lb/>
     though relatively poor living. When in more 
     <lb/>
     recent times the emphasis in industry changed 
     <lb/>
     from individual to mass production, the in<lb break="no"/>stability of the Newfoundland economy showed 
     <lb/>
     up, as ours was then an economy out of keeping 
     <lb/>
     with world progress In addition there were oc<lb break="no"/>casions when our own statesmen should have 
     <lb/>
     been able to alleviate conditions by reciprocity 
     <lb/>
     treaties with other countries, but there appeared 
     <lb/>
     always to be the interests of some power standing 
     <lb/>
     in the way. Witness the Bond-Blaine Treaty.<ref target="#fn_03">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Carrying on this sketchy remembrance of past 
     <lb/>
     history we see weaknesses which may or may not 
     <lb/>
     have been caused by circumstances in our own 
     <lb/>
     handling of the situation: for example, a too great 
     <lb/>
     contribution to World War I on the financial side 
     <lb/>
     — not that Newfoundland should not have given 
     <lb/>
     her utmost, but that she had no right to give far 
     <lb/>
     beyond her capacity; and afterwards, a complete 
     <lb/>
     lack of disinterested self-interest in handling the 
     <lb/>
     burden of debt at a time of world crisis; and 
     <lb/>
     further an apparent unwillingness or inertia on 
     <lb/>
     the part of Newfoundlanders to accept full re<lb break="no"/>sponsibility for thinking out our own problems and 
     <lb/>
     carrying them through Arising out of this later 
     <lb/>
     weakness, and bringing ourselves down to the 
     <lb/>
     present day, we allowed ourselves to be put in a 
     <lb/>
     position where again we have found that the little 
     <lb/>
     margin between abject poverty and an ordinary 
     <lb/>
     decent standard of living has been jeopardised. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With these thoughts in mind I suggested 
     <lb/>
     yesterday the adjournment of the debate on the 
     <lb/>
     Fisheries interim report which was obviously 
     <lb/>
     designed to bring together a protest on behalf of 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
            
     
     what, I believe, is a majority of Newfoundlanders 
     <lb/>
     against concessions given at Newfoundland's ex<lb break="no"/>pense and over such a long period. Coming 
     <lb/>
     straight to the point of the proposal, I must say 
     <lb/>
     that I realise that in the end governmental and 
     <lb/>
     economic influence lies where power resides. In 
     <lb/>
     other words, if a small population in a small 
     <lb/>
     island happens to get in the way of larger and 
     <lb/>
     more powerful interests, inevitably — in the 
     <lb/>
     world as it has been constituted in the past — that 
     <lb/>
     island is dealt with as the powers decide. I am not 
     <lb/>
     concerned at the moment with whether binding 
     <lb/>
     contracts or legal technicalities may be used as 
     <lb/>
     an argument for a fatalistic attitude on our part. I 
     <lb/>
     am concerned with a new world which places 
     <lb/>
     emphasis on the welfare of small countries as 
     <lb/>
     well as great.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I suggest, therefore, that this problem of ap<lb break="no"/>pealing to great powers on a humanitarian basis 
     <lb/>
     should be pushed to the limit of our ability. I 
     <lb/>
     would not have any of my listeners feel that I 
     <lb/>
     subscribe to a begging attitude. I suggest the 
     <lb/>
     problem be approached with dignity and on the 
     <lb/>
     basis that Newfoundlanders have something to 
     <lb/>
     offer which should command a reasonable return 
     <lb/>
     from fellow human beings — a position of 
     <lb/>
     strategic and geographical importance which 
     <lb/>
     should be as much shared by us as the position of 
     <lb/>
     wealth and purchasing power might be shared by 
     <lb/>
     other countries in the interests of all. It may be 
     <lb/>
     argued that Newfoundland has already been paid 
     <lb/>
     for concessions which have been given to other 
     <lb/>
     countries in the form of a prosperity which we 
     <lb/>
     never before enjoyed, but I would point out that 
     <lb/>
     the prosperity came not so much by design as by 
     <lb/>
     accident and our concern is not with the tem<lb break="no"/>porary present as with the continuing future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     You will note that the Fisheries Committee 
     <lb/>
     left their recommendations as it were in mid-air, 
     <lb/>
     in that they suggested that negotiations should be 
     <lb/>
     initiated at once: they did not say by whom. I 
     <lb/>
     appreciate the committee's difficulties in this 
     <lb/>
     respect because their only appeal could be to a 
     <lb/>
     government which committed this country to the 
     <lb/>
     bases deal without making reservations for a 
     <lb/>
     reconsideration of the position after the stress of 
     <lb/>
     war passed. And at our stage of political in<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_03">[1]A reciprocity treaty negotiated between Colonial Secretary Robert Bond and the American Secretary of 
     <lb/>State, James Blaine, in 1890. It would have allowed free access to the US market for Newfoundland products<lb/>in exchange for allowing Americans to obtain bait in Newfoundland waters. As a result of Canadian protests,<lb/>the treaty was not ratified.</note><pb n="81"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0081.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">81</fw>decision, it would appear futile to ask that 
     <lb/>
     government to initiate new proposals. Further, as 
     <lb/>
     a Convention we have not yet clearly defined our 
     <lb/>
     own status, I must confess that I read into our 
     <lb/>
     terms of reference wider powers than we as a 
     <lb/>
     body have yet assumed. This, although it has an 
     <lb/>
     important bearing on the question now before us, 
     <lb/>
     is a problem which will take more definite shape. 
     <lb/>
     In the meantime, I suggest that the committee's 
     <lb/>
     proposal be accepted unanimously and that we 
     <lb/>
     ought in the days before us clarify our minds as 
     <lb/>
     to how Newfoundland should proceed with the 
     <lb/>
     important question of seeking adequate returns 
     <lb/>
     for benefits shared. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> This first report presented to the <lb/>
                  Convention is perhaps one of the most important <lb/> on which debate will take
                  place. I am not directly <lb/> interested in the fishing industry myself, but am
                  <lb/> vitally concerned with the contents of this report <lb/> inasmuch as it
                  affects the welfare of this country <lb/> as a whole. I have studied the report
                  with interest <lb/> and find that we have made some great strides in <lb/>
                  advancement in this particular phase of the fish<lb break="no"/>ing industry. From
                  the original start, which <lb/> covered only items such as salmon, blueberries
                  <lb/> and smelts, we have in a very short while through <lb/> keen progressiveness
                  reached the worthwhile fig<lb break="no"/>ure of approximately 30 million pounds
                  of fresh <lb/> cod frozen in its various forms of fillets. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     For this country to be economically sound and 
     <lb/>
     to continue as such, the economic welfare of the 
     <lb/>
     people and particularly of the primary producer 
     <lb/>
     must also be sound. This can only be in fact when 
     <lb/>
     we can have these dependent upon our first and 
     <lb/>
     largest industry earning an economic living 
     <lb/>
     wage. While the paper and mining industries may 
     <lb/>
     be the largest in certain respects, yet the fishing 
     <lb/>
     industry with its various types of production is 
     <lb/>
     the mainstay of the majority of the people in this 
     <lb/>
     island. While these larger industries provide 
     <lb/>
     employment and other sources of revenue, yet it 
     <lb/>
     is the primary producer who is the backbone of 
     <lb/>
     this country, even though there may be yet un<lb break="no"/>developed mines and other natural resources 
     <lb/>
     which may come into operation within the next 
     <lb/>
     few years. There are approximately 25,000 
     <lb/>
     fishermen directly employed in the production of 
     <lb/>
     fish and by-products, and if we allow them an 
     <lb/>
     average of four dependents to a family, that 
     <lb/>
     would give us approximately half of our popula<lb break="no"/>tion. We must not forget that in addition to these 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     producers there are many who derive their living 
     <lb/>
     from the necessary work involved in conjunction 
     <lb/>
     with the handling, packaging and exporting of 
     <lb/>
     our production, such as coopers, truckmen, 
     <lb/>
     longshoremen and other intermediary workers. 
     <lb/>
     These, together with the fishermen and their de<lb break="no"/>pendents give us an estimated half of our popula<lb break="no"/>tion who are directly dependent upon the various 
     <lb/>
     phases of our productive economy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Although great strides have been made in 
     <lb/>
     recent years it is obvious that our production must 
     <lb/>
     not only include codfish, but other types of fish 
     <lb/>
     as well. I cannot give an accurate estimate of what 
     <lb/>
     the country's total production need be to produce 
     <lb/>
     a secure standard of living. But I imagine it would 
     <lb/>
     have to be raised to something over one million, 
     <lb/>
     to possibly two million pounds a year, so that a 
     <lb/>
     lower cost could be gained, and at the same time 
     <lb/>
     give the maximum return and benefit to the 
     <lb/>
     producer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The most important point of the interim report 
     <lb/>
     is contained in the introductory remarks of Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Job. He reported that "The United States market 
     <lb/>
     is our main hope for the future." I consider that a 
     <lb/>
     very pertinent point. Tariff arrangements should 
     <lb/>
     be concluded with the United States that will 
     <lb/>
     assure us of being able to dispose of our fish 
     <lb/>
     products on a fair competitive basis, and I feel 
     <lb/>
     that an assurance or arrangement must be con<lb break="no"/>cluded for a length of time that will give us a 
     <lb/>
     source of security for the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     producer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It may not be within the rights of this National 
     <lb/>
     Convention to recommend or suggest policy to 
     <lb/>
     our present government, but I do feel that our 
     <lb/>
     point, if unanimously adopted by this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion, should be brought as strongly as possible to 
     <lb/>
     the attention of both our present government and 
     <lb/>
     that of the United States, as well as our Canadian 
     <lb/>
     friends. In the event of any negotiations coming 
     <lb/>
     from this recommendation it might be wise to 
     <lb/>
     point out to our Canadian friends that in this 
     <lb/>
     instance we would not wish to have any repetition 
     <lb/>
     of interference or blocking, as occurred with the 
     <lb/>
     Bond-Blaine treaty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The whole future of this country depends upon 
     <lb/>
     this great industry and we cannot be too strong in 
     <lb/>
     our efforts to obtain security for the future. The 
     <lb/>
     decision of this Convention as to the form or 
     <lb/>
     forms of government which should be recom<lb break="no"/>mended to the people of Newfoundland must 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="82"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0082.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">82</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
      
     have a bearing on the future prospects and nation<lb break="no"/>al welfare and economy of the country as a whole. 
     <lb/>
     I can do no more than support very strongly the 
     <lb/>
     remarks of my friend Mr. Job when he presented 
     <lb/>
     this report. 
     <lb/>
    </p>
           
 <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I have very genuine admiration <lb/>for the work of the
                  Fisheries Committee in the <lb/>preparation of this interim report. I am always
                  <lb/>filled with admiration by evidence of work done, <lb/>particularly work of
                  research, and the report, <lb/>insofar as it is factual, statistical, insofar as
                  it <lb/>reviews something of the history and present <lb/>dimensions of the fresh
                  fish industry, is a very <lb/>fine piece of work. I know that Mr. Job for many
                  <lb/>years has been something of a pioneer in the <lb/>fisheries of this country
                  and we find him now one <lb/>of the pioneers in the fresh fish developments. I
                  <lb/>have often wondered whether it was a good thing <lb/>for Newfoundland to turn
                  away from her cen<lb break="no"/>turies-old method of fishing. I do not refer
                  merely <lb/>to the technical methods of fishing, but to the <lb/>social or
                  sociological; we have had 30, 40 and <lb/>50,000 petty capitalists — whether it is
                  a good <lb/>thing to turn away from that and to industrialise <lb/>the fishing and
                  increase the units of production; <lb/>to increase mechanical processing; turn the
                  <lb/>fishery from what it has so long been, an adven<lb break="no"/>ture, a highly
                  individualistic adventure, develop<lb break="no"/>ing certain sturdy independence
                  and individualism <lb/>in our fishermen; turning from that into what can <lb/>only
                  be called industrialism in the fishery, reaching <lb/>perhaps ultimately some day
                  to the fishery <lb/>proletariat — men engaged for wages as they might <lb/>be in a
                  clothing factory, in a mine or paper mill or <lb/>any other industrial
                  enterprise.... My head tells me <lb/>we must change; we must become
                  industrialised; <lb/>we must go ahead or go under; yet I will watch this
                  <lb/>trend to industrialism in the fisheries with a great <lb/>deal of interest in
                  the next ten, 20 or 30 years, if I <lb/>live that long. I know it must come; it is
                  inevitable <lb/>and indeed it may be regrettable. Mr. Bradley has <lb/>told me of
                  the developments in Bonavista in the last <lb/>four or five years. I lived in
                  Bonavista at a time of <lb/>desperate privation; he has lived there latterly in
                  the <lb/>
                  <cb/> time of a partially industrialised fishery. He tells <lb/> me that a social
                  revolution has occurred there in <lb/> living conditions and standards since the
                  fresh <lb/> fish freezing plant has been established. So, I <lb/> have a great
                  deal of sympathy for and a great deal <lb/> of appreciation of the importance of
                  this new <lb/> development and also a great deal of concern. I <lb/> am sure Mr.
                  Crosbie will recall my expressions <lb/> of concern and worry about future markets
                  for <lb/> fresh fish. I felt that in times of shortages of food, <lb/> especially
                  protein foods, we could ship fish into <lb/> the United States and get our prices;
                  leap over the <lb/> duty and not feel it.... But what of the day when <lb/> there
                  will not be a world food shortage, when in <lb/> the United States itself perhaps
                  they will once <lb/> again be ploughing under every third furrow of <lb/> cotton,
                  and the farmers will be paid by the <lb/> government to destroy their pigs and
                  their crops, <lb/> or perhaps not to plant at all; when the coffee of <lb/> Brazil
                  will be used experimentally as fuel to run <lb/> railways; when the trawlers dump
                  their fish rather <lb/> than block a market already glutted? What of the <lb/> day
                  when shortages will have disappeared, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly the shortage of
                  protein foods? What then <lb/> about our fishery? What then of our fresh fish
                  <lb/> industry, whose markets have been in the Untied <lb/> States of America?
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I went this forenoon to the office of the 
     <lb/>
     American Consul General to ask him if he had 
     <lb/>
     statistics showing the quantities of fish imported 
     <lb/>
     into the United States. I brought back a statistical 
     <lb/>
     abstract of the published figures. The figures 
     <lb/>
     come up to as late as March past and in the short 
     <lb/>
     time I had I took up the figures from September 
     <lb/>
     last — 7 months. The figures are given in pounds 
     <lb/>
     and they sound astronomical. For the past seven 
     <lb/>
     months the figures are: <ref target="#fn_04">*</ref>
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Total of 250,000 pounds of fish, or 420 million 
     <lb/>
     pounds per year. I looked back over the period 
     <lb/>
     before the war when there was no shortage of 
     <lb/>
     protein food, and I find that in 1937-1940 the 
     <lb/>
     average imports of fish into the United States 
     <lb/>
     amounted to 328 million pounds or something 
     <lb/>
     like 100 million pounds less than what it is now 
     <lb/>
          
      <note xml:id="fn_04">   
           <table>
     <row><cell>* Imported from Canada</cell><cell>:</cell> <cell>177 million pounds of fish</cell></row> 
<row><cell>" Newfoundland</cell><cell>:</cell> <cell>33 million " " " </cell></row>
<row><cell>" Mexico</cell><cell>:</cell> <cell>20 million " " " </cell></row> 
<row><cell> " Portugal</cell><cell>:</cell> <cell>11 million " " " </cell></row>
<row><cell>" Iceland</cell><cell>:</cell> <cell>7.5 million " " " </cell></row>
<row><cell>" Norway</cell><cell>:</cell> <cell>6.5 million " " "</cell></row>
           </table></note> 
     
            <pb n="83"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0083.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">83</fw>
          
     averaging.... I was interested to discover the 
     <lb/>
     production of fish in the United States, and I 
     <lb/>
     found that besides importing 425 million pounds 
     <lb/>
     a year, she is producing herself something over 4 
     <lb/>
     billion pounds a year — 12 times as much fish as 
     <lb/>
     she imports. The American consumption of fish 
     <lb/>
     is 32 pounds per year per capita. Of the 32 pounds 
     <lb/>
     consumed she imports three and produces 29 
     <lb/>
     pounds. I wonder seriously, as I have done for 
     <lb/>
     more than a year, what is the future of the fresh 
     <lb/>
     fish industry of Newfoundland in the United 
     <lb/>
     States when times come back to normal, which 
     <lb/>
     we hope they some day will? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, this business of approaching America 
     <lb/>
     for special consideration for the admission of our 
     <lb/>
     fish... I wonder honestly and sincerely what can 
     <lb/>
     we do with the United States. I ask the question 
     <lb/>
     sincerely, because I wonder sincerely what we 
     <lb/>
     can do. If they have indeed a multilateral policy, 
     <lb/>
     tariff action and trade agreements and trade 
     <lb/>
     treaties, and if it is a fact that they are trying to 
     <lb/>
     make up an international trade organisation, and 
     <lb/>
     if it is their policy not to deal in bilateral trade 
     <lb/>
     agreements, what can be done by this Convention 
     <lb/>
     or by the Commission of Government or by the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Great Britain or any other 
     <lb/>
     country? By all means let us try, but we have 
     <lb/>
     imposed on us in this Convention a very solemn 
     <lb/>
     and very important duty. We must face facts. It 
     <lb/>
     is because we did not that we lost self-govern<lb break="no"/>ment in 1934. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Whatever we can get out of the United States, <lb/> I am all for it. I am all for
                                          having this Convention <lb/> send a delegate there if they
                                          will receive us and <lb/> if they are prepared to talk
                                          business with us.... I <lb/> am as much concerned as any
                                          man for the future <lb/> of this country, for the standard
                                          of our people's <lb/> lives. I know that our people have
                                          never had a <lb/> square deal, and I know they are not
                                          getting a <lb/> square deal now, I know they are being
                                          looted and <lb/> plundered. My own family, working class
                                          <lb/> people, my father and mother and my brothers, <lb/>
                                          are being looted. I happen to have been a bit <lb/>
                                          luckier than the rest because a rich uncle educated <lb/>
                                          me (after looting the people to get the money, and <lb/>I
                                          happened to benefit from part of that loot<lb break="no"
                                          />ing), but I am still of the blood and guts of
                                          the<lb/> class I spring from. If it becomes necessary to
                                          tell<lb/> some of the truth I am quite prepared to tell it,
                                          but<lb/> I do want facts to be faced. I don't want
                                          this<lb/> Convention to be led down a blind alley, but
                                          let<lb/> <cb/> us try with our eyes open, knowing where we
                                          are <lb/>likely to land before we begin. <lb/> </p>
   
    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Mr. Smallwood gave a lot of figures <lb/> on the
                  fish imports into the United States, and <lb/> from the facts shown they are
                  importing an extra <lb/> million pounds per year. Do you mean to say we <lb/> will
                  not be able to sell any more fish in the United <lb/> States? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, I did say that from 1937 to <lb/> 1940
                  imports into the United States then as com<lb break="no"/>pared with now showed
                  the present level is one <lb/> hundred million pounds a year higher than before
                  <lb/> the war, the increase being accounted for, I sup<lb break="no"/>pose, by the
                  world shortage of food, and par<lb break="no"/>ticularly of protein- containing
                  foods, but when <lb/> that shortage disappears, and with American <lb/> fishermen
                  producing 12 times as much fish as <lb/> they are importing from abroad, it will
                  come back <lb/> to the normal figure which is a lot less. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> The imports today are of frozen and <lb/> fresh fish,
                  and frozen fish a few years ago was not <lb/> in existence. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> You left the impression that we should <lb/> get out
                  of the fish business. It seems as if there <lb/> would be no object in our staying
                  in the business <lb/> under these conditions. You did not mean that, <lb/> did
                  you? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, I did not mean that. I am <lb/> wondering
                  what will happen to our fish market in <lb/> the States when the food situation
                  returns to <lb/> normal. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I have been listening very atten<lb break="no"
                  />tively to my learned friend Mr. Smallwood and <lb/> he has had me practically
                  hypnotized for the past <lb/> half hour, but the salient facts are these. If
                     New<lb break="no"/>foundland is going to go ahead we have to look <lb/> to the
                  fish industry for the future. Because, from <lb/> that much discussed
                  Chadwick-Jones report the <lb/> fact emerges that the greatest number of people
                  <lb/> gainfully employed in the country come from the <lb/> fishing industry. That
                  being so, it is to increase <lb/> the earnings of our people in the fishing
                  industry <lb/> that we have to look to. The suggestion contained <lb/> in this
                  report, and in the address of Mr. Hazen <lb/> Russell given yesterday before the
                  Rotary Club <lb/> is that the pickup of the fish industry in New<lb break="no"
                  />foundland must come from the sale of fresh <lb/> frozen fish, and the people
                  that run this industry, <lb/> the pioneers and the people who are now putting
                  <lb/> their money into it, and in particular a man like <lb/> Mr. Russell, seem to
                  have an unbounded faith in <lb/>
                  <pb n="84" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0084.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">84</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw> the future of this fresh fish industry. In
                  reading <lb/> his report and the report of the Fishery Commit<lb break="no"/>tee
                  the things that stand out seem to be that there <lb/> will be necessary plant
                  extension and there will <lb/> have to be subsidising of the industry to the
                  extent <lb/> that the fishermen will be paid more money. By <lb/> that I gather
                  that we will have to keep in line with <lb/> the other countries such as Canada
                  and Iceland. <lb/> But the whole point of this debate is the <lb/> US market. If
                  we don't have a United States <lb/> market we are not going to have a fresh fish
                  <lb/> industry. Now that being granted, and I hope I am <lb/> not going to be
                  accused by Mr. Butt of being a <lb/> fatalist, we have got this to face with the
                  United <lb/> States of America. They have a very large fishing <lb/> population,
                  and are very interested in the same <lb/> industry that we ourselves are trying to
                  increase <lb/> in production. We all remember what happened <lb/> here in 1938.
                  That big General Seafoods Cor<lb break="no"/>poration<ref target="#fn_05"
                     >[1]</ref> came in here and concluded an agree<lb break="no"/>ment with the
                  government that would have been <lb/> of immense benefit to the people of this
                  country, <lb/> and I don't know whether any local industrialist <lb/> in the
                  fishing industry had anything to do with it <lb/> or not, but when the deal was
                  practically through <lb/> the American House of Congress, the American <lb/>
                  Senate, the fishing industries of New England <lb/> were organised to such an
                  extent that a prohibi<lb break="no"/>tive tariff was raised against that deal and
                  that big <lb/> industry was dropped and the General Sea Foods <lb/> people went
                  out of the picture. What power has <lb/> that same New England bloc today? We know
                  <lb/> they are vitally interested, and they are watching <lb/> this new Louisbourg
                  proposition in Canada, and <lb/> even the debates in this house. We saw yesterday
                  <lb/> one of the representatives of the US government <lb/> present here and
                  everything that goes on is going <lb/> to be of interest. Now the point is, is the
                  western <lb/> bloc referred to by Mr. Russell, namely the <lb/> western states, of
                  sufficient power to overcome <lb/> the lobbying effect of the New England fish
                  bloc? <lb/> If not, then we might as well forget our fresh fish <lb/> industry. If
                  only a 1% increase on the present <lb/> tariff went on the fresh frozen fillets
                  going in it <lb/> would not pay the industry to operate. How are <lb/> we going to
                  block that? I would certainly try but <lb/> the bases are here, that's an
                  accomplished fact. <lb/> We can't tomorrow or the next day say, "Give us <lb/>
                  these concessions or we will turn you out." We <lb/>
                  <cb/> might as well forget that. The only thing we can <lb/> do is trust to the
                  humanitarian principles of the <lb/> people we are going to sell our fish to, and
                  that's <lb/> why I am a bit sorry that all this debate had to <lb/> happen in
                  public. The Government of the United <lb/> States might know about it, and the
                  people of the <lb/> United States may know what we are going to do, <lb/> but if
                  the American interests know that we are <lb/> going into this industry in a big
                  way they may <lb/> take the steps necessary to see that we are <lb/> squashed....
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I have been listening to what I <lb/> consider to
                  be an awful lot of pessimism. We <lb/> have the finest fishing ledge known in the
                  world. <lb/> One American fish man told me the time would <lb/> come when the US
                  would have to come to New<lb break="no"/>foundland waters to get her fish. Before
                  the war, <lb/> in the midwestem states very little fish was con<lb break="no"
                  />sumed. The methods of freezing and keeping <lb/> frozen fish have changed
                  entirely in the last ten <lb/> years. The cost of a freezing unit is very small
                  <lb/>today compared to ten years ago. One town in the <lb/>midwestem states did
                  not consume one pound of <lb/>fish per year. They put in a Birdseye freezer there,
                  <lb/>and they increased their consumption of fish in a <lb/>few months from none
                  to 15 lb. per person. We <lb/>have no reason to be pessimistic. Why should we
                  <lb/>not ask for tariff concessions? We can ask, and if <lb/>we don't get them,
                  well, we can't be blamed. We <lb/>can fight anyway. It is true there is a tariff
                  on fresh <lb/>fish in the United States, but that does not say that <lb/>it can't
                  be changed. I don't expect this govern<lb break="no"/>ment to go back and ask for
                  a change in the base <lb/>agreement. They can't — they signed it. The
                  <lb/>American market is not the only market for fresh <lb/>fish. The methods of
                  processing fish are changed <lb/>entirely. You can take and consume huge quan<lb
                     break="no"/>tities in this country year in and year out. Within <lb/>the last
                  couple of months I have had inquiries for <lb/>a fairly large tonnage of frozen
                  fish from Brazil, <lb/>which now takes hardly any saltfish at all. We <lb/>can't
                  send it down because we have not the <lb/>cold-storage ships and facilities, and
                  they have <lb/>not the facilities to handle it either, but I believe <lb/>that
                  will change in a year or two and we may have <lb/>a market in Brazil or other
                  countries. I say let's <lb/>find out what procedure we have got to use, We
                  <lb/>have heard a lot about procedure lately. "Proce<lb break="no"/>dure" is a
                  lovely word. You are told you can't do <lb/>

                  <note xml:id="fn_05">1 The General Sea Foods Corporation wanted to establish a
                     multi-purpose fish plant that would freeze fresh <lb/> fish, use offal to make
                     fertilizer, and provide bait for fishermen. </note>

                  <pb n="85" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0085.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">85</fw> this or that. Who are you afraid you will disturb, <lb/>
                  the United States, the Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, the Dominions
                  Office in Great Britain? We <lb/> have rather to ask and try to get some
                     arrange<lb break="no"/>ment with the American government, and if we <lb/> can't
                  get markets in the US, let's go somewhere <lb/> else. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I don't want to be misunderstood. <lb/> I did not
                  suggest no action be taken, but I do think <lb/> it should be taken in such a
                  manner as will be <lb/> proper, and not belligerently. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am saying this for the benefit <lb/> of the
                  House and not Mr. Crosbie, and I don't <lb/> want him to misunderstand me. Let us
                  do some<lb break="no"/>thing if possible, but not through the government <lb/>
                  that has betrayed this country for the past 13 <lb/> years, let this Convention
                  make the approach. <lb/> Mr. Crosbie Now if you could tell me how to <lb/> get
                  over the question of procedure, I might be <lb/> able to tell you how to get over
                  the American <lb/> tariff. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> I think this question of trade should <lb/> be
                  brought into this. We import from Canada $19 <lb/> million worth of trade; could
                  we not inject it in <lb/> the report. We keep 16 or 19 factories going on a <lb/>
                  million dollars each. I think that should be gone <lb/> into thoroughly. The
                  question of trade may help <lb/> soften the Americans. I would like to see them
                  <lb/> more familiar with our trade. If Canada wanted <lb/> to block it as she did
                  in other industries, we could <lb/> put up the question of trade. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I take it it will be seen by the Commis<lb break="no"
                  />sion of Government in some form or other. I do <lb/> not think We ought to take
                  a pessimistic attitude. <lb/> I listened to Mr. Smallwood and think he took a
                  <lb/> defeatist attitude. He referred to imports which <lb/> America had from
                  Iceland, but surely in the case <lb/> of Newfoundland which has given 99 year
                  leases <lb/> of valuable concessions, we ought to have trade <lb/> concessions
                  different from Iceland. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Who is going to do it? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> It is a matter for development. I do not <lb/> know.
                  I hope it will be done by our own govern<lb break="no"/>ment, the British
                  government and the Canadian <lb/> government and that something may come of it.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I hope so. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> There are other points apart from <lb/> actual
                  tariff concessions which a good many <lb/> gentlemen would like to speak about and
                  I would <lb/> suggest we adjourn until after dinner. I move the <lb/> adjournment
                  of the debate. <lb/>
               </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I did not propose to say anything on <lb/> this
                  matter because we are passing this interim <lb/> report through the committee
                  stage and it asks <lb/> that the Commission of Government or the <lb/> Dominions
                  Office to do something with regard to <lb/> getting for our fish favourable
                  concessions into <lb/> the United States. We have been working on this, <lb/>
                  reading it section by section — one would think <lb/> it was a bill being
                  introduced into Parliament, <lb/> whereas it is an interim report of the Fisheries
                  <lb/> Committee, suggesting we do something about <lb/> our fish. Whether we can
                  get the concessions or <lb/> not we have to try, and we should pass this report
                  <lb/> without debate. We should be as one and forget <lb/> whether the merchant or
                  the fisherman is going <lb/> to get gypped. We have to get the concessions <lb/>
                  from the United States if we can, if not, we have <lb/> to do something else about
                  it. I suggest the debate <lb/> be finished and let us be as one in this
                  connection. <lb/>
               </p>
            
<p><persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I agree with Major Cashin but I am <lb/>not content that we
                  should, in dealing with fresh <lb/>fish, leave the other fisheries out. The report
                  says <lb/>"Herring and its by-products may be mentioned", <lb/>it is not "may be"
                  it <hi rendition="simple:italic">must</hi> be. They have a right to <lb/>a place
                  just as much as fresh frozen fish. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I agree. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> They must be mentioned on a com<lb break="no"/>mon
                  basis. The herring industry is just as impor<lb break="no"/>tant as the fresh fish
                  industry and there is a <lb/> possibility of losing the market because of <lb/>
                  UNRRA'S going out and we do not want to lose <lb/> it; we want to get more, not
                  less. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I take it all stages of the fishery will <lb/> be
                  considered in the same way. One kind of fish <lb/> is just as essential as the
                  other. I believe we may <lb/> be able to get our fresh fish onto a firm footing. I
                  <lb/> am sure this report is good and we should back it <lb/> and try and get
                  something. One of the hardest <lb/> things we have to face is selling in a cheap
                  market <lb/> and buying in a dear market. We have to buy <lb/> where we sell and
                  if we cannot sell, we should <lb/> not buy. We are the largest customer per capita
                  <lb/> the United States has and we are the best cus<lb break="no"/>tomer of
                  Canada. They have to make way for us. <lb/> In 1922 we imported goods to the value
                  of $287 <lb/> million and they took goods to the value of <lb/> $270,000 from us.
                  How can we live like that? I <lb/> do not believe anyone is fighting for our
                  markets. <lb/> We just want to swop. I say to the men processing <lb/> fresh fish,
                  go ahead, and I say to this Convention, <lb/> let us go ahead. Let us vote anyway.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <pb n="86"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-11_Page_0086.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">86</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
            
<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I move that this report be adopted. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> Does it mean that these re<lb break="no"
                  />commendations will be carried out? If it does, I <lb/>hope that we are going to
                  deal with the United <lb/>States on reduction of tariffs, they will also con<lb
                     break="no"/>sider other industries, such as paper, etc. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Pulp and paper have free entry into <lb/> the
                  United States. The Americans do not manu<lb break="no"/>facture. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> What is meant by "adopting the <lb/> report".
                  There are several points to be brought up. <lb/> If we adopt the report, what
                  follows? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The Convention resolved itself <lb/> into a
                  committee of the whole to consider the <lb/> report. Before that happened the
                  report had to be <lb/> read. Now the duty of the committee is to con<lb break="no"
                  />sider the report and having considered it, to rise <lb/> and recommend that it
                  be adopted by the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion. After the committee rises that will
                  be done. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I move that we adjourn the debate <lb/>until Monday.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There is a motion before the <lb/> Chair that
                  the report be adopted. <lb/>
               </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I do not want to press mat if the Con<lb break="no"
                  />vention thinks it should be further debated. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There is a motion before the <lb/> Chair that we
                  rise and resume at 8 o'clock. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Before I can vote for the adoption <lb/> of this
                  report, I want to know why requests are <lb/> made for action to be taken to get
                  tariff conces<lb break="no"/>sions from the United States? I want to know <lb/>
                  why. Is it that the fresh fish industry cannot carry <lb/> on longer at the
                  present rates? If that is so, I would <lb/> say adopt the report. But surely it
                  must have some <lb/> facts and figures to show that the fresh fish in<lb
                     break="no"/>dustry is in danger of extinction by reason of <lb/> tariffs placed
                  on it by the United States. They <lb/> must bring figures to show that. We are
                  told that <lb/> Canada, who has hitherto blocked our efforts, is <lb/> anxious to
                  help, the United States is anxious to <lb/> help, other countries are anxious to
                  help, but <lb/> these things have to be debated before I am <lb/> prepared to
                  adopt this report. I am not in favour <lb/> of the motion to adopt the report.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee of the whole rose and reported 
     <lb/>
     progress. The Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-02-16, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


<!--<milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     October 14, 1946. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Gentlemen, I feel sure that I 
     <lb/>
     echo your thoughts when I say how pleased we 
     <lb/>
     are to have Mr. K.M. Brown back again and we 
     <lb/>
     hope his condition has improved, permanently 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     so; and that Mr. Fudge is back with us again. I 
     <lb/>
     have to report that Mr. Figary will not be able to 
     <lb/>
     attend.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Interim Report of the Fisheries Committee: 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Job I have been acting chairman of the 
     <lb/>
     Fisheries Committee during the absence of Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Brown. He has now returned, and as there have 
     <lb/>
     been various comment on this report, I move that 
     <lb/>
     it be referred back to the Fisheries Committee for 
     <lb/>
     further consideration. I ask therefore that the 
     <lb/>
     committee rise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The committee rose and reported progress] 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Chairman This completes the orders of the 
     <lb/>day. I have to inform you that Mr. Hollett and Mr. 
     <lb/>Newell on behalf of the Education Committee 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     informed me this afternoon that the work of the 
     <lb/>
     committee is completed and that presently its 
     <lb/>
     report will be printed and placed before the Steer<lb break="no"/>ing Committee, and will come with the least 
     <lb/>
     possible delay before the Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Is there any other matter you wish to discuss? 
     <lb/>
     If not, I will accept a motion to adjourn until such 
     <lb/>
     time as the Steering Committee is in a position to 
     <lb/>
     tell us when we may meet. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>[The Convention adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     October 28, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Chairman I received a telegram from 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Thompson, President of the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     Lumbermen's Association now in annual con<lb break="no"/>vention at Grand Falls, extending greetings to 
     <lb/>
     this Convention and I would ask the Secretary to 
     <lb/>
     kindly read the telegram to which I replied on 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     your behalf. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. Justice Fox 
     <lb/>Chairman of the National Convention, 
     <lb/>St. John's. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Newfoundland Lumbermen's As<lb break="no"/>sociation now in Annual Convention at 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
     </div>    </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>