<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-04-18" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-04-18">18 April 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="508"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0499.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0500.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0501.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0502.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0503.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0504.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0505.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0506.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0507.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0508.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-27">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-27">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0499">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0499.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0500">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0500.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0501">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0501.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0502">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0502.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0503">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0503.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0504">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0504.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0505">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0505.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0506">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0506.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0507">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0507.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0508">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0508.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="499" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0499.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">499</fw>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-06-27, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
<!--<p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The company is in another 
     <lb/>
     country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I know. If the iron ore was valued 
     <lb/>
     at $2, and if the selling price was $6 a ton, do you 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     mean to tell me that Mr. Allen is going to let that 
     <lb/>
     crowd get away with that? 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>[The committee rose and reported progress, and<lb/>the Convention adjourned]<lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     April 18, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I have just received a com<lb break="no"/>munication from the Newfoundland Broadcast<lb break="no"/>ing Corporation, which the Secretary will now 
     <lb/>
     read to you. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Broadcasting Corporation of Newfoundland 
     <lb/></p>

<p rendition="simple:right">
    April 18, 1947. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     F.G. Bradley, K.C., LL.B., 
     <lb/>
    Chairman, National Convention. 
     <lb/>Honourable Sir, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     In view of certain statements made by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. P.J. Cashin, a member of the National 
     <lb/>
     Convention, during the proceedings at a 
     <lb/>
     recent case in the Supreme Court, the Broad<lb break="no"/>casting Corporation feels it should have some 
     <lb/>
     assurance from the Convention on its attitude 
     <lb/>
     towards the recording and subsequent broad<lb break="no"/>casting of proceedings of the sessions of the 
     <lb/>
     Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Would you please ascertain the wishes of 
     <lb/>
     the Convention in this respect and advise us 
     <lb/>
     accordingly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="tccd:textIndent">
     Yours faithfully, 
     <lb/>
    The Broadcasting Corporation of Nfld., 
     <lb/>W.F. Galgay, Manager. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> This communication is now 
     <lb/>before you, gentlemen. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I presume the intention of this let<lb break="no"/>ter is that the Corporation wishes to know the 
     <lb/>feelings of the Convention with respect to broad<lb break="no"/>casting — whether it is our direct wish that the 
     <lb/>broadcasting of the debates be continued or not. 
     <lb/>Speaking for myself, I am sorry that it happened 
     <lb/>at the beginning, butnow that it is here and people 
     <lb/>have been listening in as fully as we feel they 
     <lb/>have been, it might be rather regrettable if it were 
     <lb/>discontinued at this stage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> I concur with Mr. Higgins. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STAR1">Mr. Starkes</persName> I agree with Mr. Higgins. The 
     <lb/>people in the outports have no chance whatever 
     <lb/>to hear the proceedings of the Convention as far 
     <lb/>as newspapers are concerned. The people in 
     <lb/>St. John's have the daily papers, but the people 
     <lb/>in the outports, if they can't listen in, have no 
     <lb/>means of hearing it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> In the district I come from, the 



    

    
            <cb/>
          

     people look to the radio for the broadcasting of 
     <lb/>
     what the Convention is doing. I agree with 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Higgins too, that I would have voted against 
     <lb/>
     it had it been put to the question, but since it is in 
     <lb/>
     the House I feel it should be continued. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I feel that I would prefer to keep 
     <lb/>
     them in, so that there would be no implication 
     <lb/>
     with respect to a certain case arising out of the 
     <lb/>
     use of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> Our duty here is to survey 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland's position. Now in doing that we 
     <lb/>
     must sometimes be ruthless. We must go without 
     <lb/>
     regard to the law. We are not always going to be 
     <lb/>
     free of libel. Are we going to forfeit the right to 
     <lb/>
     give the public this information, or are we going 
     <lb/>
     to forfeit half the issue as far as Newfoundland is 
     <lb/>
     concerned? Fifty years hence, will it be better that 
     <lb/>
     the people will have gotten our chatter here, 
     <lb/>
     limited and restricted, or will it be better that we 
     <lb/>
     disregard that? We will be at a loss, too, if we 
     <lb/>
     don't get out and talk to our districts, and the 
     <lb/>
     people will be at a loss, but won't we do a better 
     <lb/>
     job if we disregard that and go into the situation 
     <lb/>
     deeply and having fully explored it all, then give 
     <lb/>
     our just opinion on the whole thing? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I notice some remarks have been 
     <lb/>
     made about one of the remarks of a certain mem<lb break="no"/>ber of this Convention yesterday. I don't exactly 
     <lb/>
     know what these references were, but I do know 
     <lb/>
     this: that this Convention was definitely referred 
     <lb/>
     to yesterday as a debating society. If we are 
     <lb/>
     purely and simply a debating society, I think there 
     <lb/>
     is very little room for these microphones here. 
     <lb/>
     That came up, as I remember, in a discussion on 
     <lb/>
     the matter of privilege. We were compared to a 
     <lb/>
     debating society, and had no more privilege than 
     <lb/>
     that. I feel that the presence of the microphones 
     <lb/>
     very certainly informs the general public as to the 
     <lb/>
     proceedings that have taken place. I do feel, 
     <lb/>
     however, that there are occasions when it would 
     <lb/>
     be wise that the prior discussion of certain mat<lb break="no"/>ters, at any rate, should not go out over the air, 
     <lb/>
     but merely the decision arrived at by the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion by a discussion which, in some cases, might 
     <lb/>
     possibly be heated. I don't think that is conducive 


            <pb n="500" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0500.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">500</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
       

     to the well-being of the public. It also retards the 
     <lb/>
     full expression of the individual members of the 
     <lb/>
     Convention as to their ideas on certain things. I 
     <lb/>
     do believe there are occasions when this long- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     suffering public, which was referred to yesterday 
     <lb/>
     by a certain member of the Bar, might be spared 
     <lb/>
     arguments. I do say, as far as a certain member 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention is concerned yesterday, he 
     <lb/>
     said nothing more derogatory about the 
     <lb/>
     microphones than were said by anyone else. I do 
     <lb/>
     think they are serving their purpose provided they 
     <lb/>
     are not monopolised by one or two or a few. I do 
     <lb/>
     think it should be your prerogative to cutout the 
     <lb/>
     broadcasting at certain times. 
     <lb/>
     
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I agree with Mr. Hollett. I may say 
     <lb/>that this is the first time I heard of anything 
     <lb/>coming in to find out if we wanted this broadcast<lb break="no"/>ing. It has been here for a long time, and now we 
     <lb/>have a letter asking if we wish to keep it. They 
     <lb/>did not ask us first, and now, as far as I am 
     <lb/>concerned, it can stay here.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I support Mr. Higgins in what he 
     <lb/>said. As the microphones have been here practi<lb break="no"/>cally the full time for every session, I see no 
     <lb/>reason why they should be removed. I think they 
     <lb/>can serve a useful purpose if we, on our part, keep 
     <lb/>as near to the point as possible. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> To bring the matter to a head, I move 
     <lb/>that we request the Broadcasting Corporation, from 
     <lb/>today, to have the microphones in this chamber. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> I would like to second that motion. 
     <lb/>If I might speak briefly, there are one or two 
     <lb/>things I would like to point out. First of all, we 
     <lb/>should look at this logically, and not be carried 
     <lb/>away by anything that anyone says here or some<lb break="no"/>where else. If people want to exercise their 
     <lb/>freedom of speech, let them go ahead and do it. 
     <lb/>There are one or two things that appear to me, and 
     <lb/>the first is that broadcasting is about the only 
     <lb/>means of having accurate reporting of what goes 
     <lb/>on here. If we do not broadcast proceedings, the 
     <lb/>only reporting we can rely on is newspaper 
     <lb/>reporting, and they, not being machines, cannot 
     <lb/>give full reports of what transpires here, and the 
     <lb/>people on the outside have to rely on secondhand 
     <lb/>information of what somebody else heard, and 
     <lb/>will not really get a full and accurate report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The other point is this: I feel that if we have 
     <lb/>any reason for refusing to broadcast our proceed<lb break="no"/>ings, in other words if we put the microphones 


            <cb/>
          

     out, I don't see why we should let the public 
     <lb/>
     occupy the galleries. I don't think there is any 
     <lb/>
     necessity for the Convention being conducted in 
     <lb/>
     secret. If it is not being conducted in secret, and 
     <lb/>
     if people care to exercise the privilege of coming 
     <lb/>
     here in person, then I think everybody should be 
     <lb/>
     allowed in through the microphones and broad<lb break="no"/>casting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Finally, whether or not we express ourselves 
     <lb/>
     too fully (it has been argued that some of us do 
     <lb/>
     express ourselves too fully because of the 
     <lb/>
     microphones, and its also been argued that we 
     <lb/>
     don't express ourselves as fully as if they were 
     <lb/>
     not here), I don't think the presence of the 
     <lb/>
     microphones should affect in any way at all the 
     <lb/>
     orderly conducting ofour business. and if we, as 
     <lb/>
     a body of 45 people, are not capable of conduct<lb break="no"/>ing our business in an orderly way in the presence 
     <lb/>
     of the microphones, I don't think we would be 
     <lb/>
     capable of doing it if the microphones were out.... 
     
</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I wish to support the motion, and 
     <lb/>frankly I do not see any other way that we can 
     <lb/>impart the knowledge that we glean here on the 
     <lb/>affairs of the country to the people, except over 
     <lb/>the radio. I fail to see in what way it excuses us 
     <lb/>from making any fair, full or frank statement in 
     <lb/>this Convention. It definitely does not save us in 
     <lb/>any way, because if we make a libelous state<lb break="no"/>ment, it is still libelous whether the microphones 
     <lb/>are here or not, and the only way that we could 
     <lb/>come out in the open and make statements not for 
     <lb/>the public would be for the Chairman to call a 
     <lb/>secret meeting. I know that the Convention was 
     <lb/>referred to yesterday in a very low manner, but I 
     <lb/>say that the public of Newfoundland can be the 
     <lb/>best judges of that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I would like, while we are at it, 
     <lb/>
     to say a word that l have been threatening now 
     <lb/>
     for some time to say, a word of praise for the 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen who sit here each day in the press box. 
     <lb/>
     I am myself an old newspaper man, and I covered 
     <lb/>
     sessions of this chamber for many many years 
     <lb/>
     and for various governments, and sat in that same 
     <lb/>
     press box, and I know something about the job of 
     <lb/>
     sitting in here, and reporting for the public the 
     <lb/>
     proceedings that go on. I am full of admiration 
     <lb/>
     and respect for the gentlemen who sit in the press 
     <lb/>
     box daily, representing the newspapers and the 
     <lb/>
     radio stations. To my mind the job that the Doyle 
     <lb/>
     News Bulletin<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> does each night is masterly — a 


<note xml:id="fn_01">[1] A news programme Sponsored by Gerald S. Doyle Ltd. on VONF, the government radio station. </note>


            <pb n="501" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0501.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">501</fw>
         

     complete, comprehensive and intelligent com<lb break="no"/>pilation of the news of each aftemoon's proceed<lb break="no"/>ings — a masterly job. The job done by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Jamieson, not exactly as a newscast but as a 
     <lb/>
     commentary, is a job of which all of us as New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders ought to be proud, proud that we 
     <lb/>
     have a Newfoundlander who turns in a first-class, 
     <lb/>
     finished, professional job of commentary each 
     <lb/>
     night. The gentleman who prepares a broadcast 
     <lb/>
     for VOCM each day, again deserves commenda<lb break="no"/>tion. The same of the men representing the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Eve<lb break="no"/>ning Telegram</hi> and the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Daily News</hi> — fair, 
     <lb/>
     impartial and competent. I think our satisfaction 
     <lb/>
     with the Broadcasting Corporation itself, broad<lb break="no"/>casting the actual proceedings, and our satisfac<lb break="no"/>tion at that being done, ought not to overlook the 
     <lb/>
     splendid service rendered to the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland by the gentlemen who sit in the press 
     <lb/>
     box.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have been accused of talking too much. Like 
     <lb/>
     my friend Major Cashin and Mr. Hollett and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Bailey and Mr. Fudge and other gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     here, perhaps I talk too much. As a matter of fact 
     <lb/>
     I doubt it. I think that's what we were sent here 
     <lb/>
     for — to talk, and think, and study, and carry on 
     <lb/>
     research, and then talk, so that the people of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland can hear. Not just talk nonsense, 
     <lb/>
     but talk about our reports. Ten gentlemen here 
     <lb/>
     were appointed as a Finance Committee They 
     <lb/>
     have spent months digging up the facts about this 
     <lb/>
     country's finances for many year past. Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin turned in a splendid job here the other day, 
     <lb/>
     reading that report. What is the good of doing all 
     <lb/>
     that work, if it is not debated and broadcast for 
     <lb/>
     the people of Newfoundland? Take this mag<lb break="no"/>nificent report of the Mining Committee. The like 
     <lb/>
     of it has never before been assembled in the 
     <lb/>
     history of this country, and I have readjust about 
     <lb/>
     everything published on mining in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. What is the good of it, if the people 
     <lb/>
     can't hear the debate? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     While I am at it, Mr. Chairman, I don't think 
     <lb/>
     the people of this country owe any gratitude to 
     <lb/>
     the half dozen people, maybe nine, in the last five 
     <lb/>
     or six months mostly hiding behind a <hi rendition="simple:italic">nom de 
     <lb/>
     plume</hi>, who have written letters to the papers 
     <lb/>
     sneering at the Convention. We talk too much, 
     <lb/>
     etc., and they have not got the brains to know that 
     <lb/>
     that's what we are here for. If they were elected, 
     <lb/>
     and had to come in here, they would have to hold 


            <cb/>
         

     their mouths because they have no brains. That's 
     <lb/>
     all we <hi rendition="simple:italic">can</hi> do — talk. We can't order anybody to 
     <lb/>
     do anything. We can only study out our reports 
     <lb/>
     and come in here and debate them. We debate the 
     <lb/>
     reports so that the people of Newfoundland will 
     <lb/>
     know what is going on. There is one other thing. 
     <lb/>
     An old friend of mine in Elliston, Simeon Tucker, 
     <lb/>
     a fisherman since he was born almost, was in 
     <lb/>
     town the other day, and he said, "Mr. Smallwood, 
     <lb/>
     what we can't understand in Elliston is this: the 
     <lb/>
     way you fellows there in the Convention cross- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     hackle<ref target="#fn_02">[1]</ref> each other." That's an outport expres<lb break="no"/>sion, but they forget two things, first that the 
     <lb/>
     Governor, the day he opened this Convention, 
     <lb/>
     prophesied for us as an old-timer himself in the 
     <lb/>
     House of Commons, he said this, "Now, 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen, you will do your work and make your 
     <lb/>
     studies, and your feelings will run high some<lb break="no"/>times, and when men's feelings run deep their 
     <lb/>
     language will sometimes become a bit heated, 
     <lb/>
     and they will be a bit excited". Save me from the 
     <lb/>
     cold-blooded brute whose feelings can't get 
     <lb/>
     worked up, and a man who can't express himself, 
     <lb/>
     or does not express himself with heat and en<lb break="no"/>thusiasm. I would not trust him. Give me a man 
     <lb/>
     like Major Cashin or Mr. Higgins, or Mr. Bailey 
     <lb/>
     or myself, a man that feels a thing in his heart and 
     <lb/>
     gets up and says it. But now the people of the 
     <lb/>
     country are not used to that. What do they think 
     <lb/>
     the House of Assembly was — a Sunday school, 
     <lb/>
     where everybody got up and bowed and scraped 
     <lb/>
     and never lost their tempers? Oh no! Is the House 
     <lb/>
     of Commons a Sunday school? Oh no! A man 
     <lb/>
     whose name commands respect in this world, the 
     <lb/>
     Rt. Hon. Winston Churchill, I myself saw 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Churchill in the House of Commons take up 
     <lb/>
     a book in a row that was going on, take up a book 
     <lb/>
     and fling it across the floor at another man. He 
     <lb/>
     was good and excited.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     For the first time in their lives, our people have 
     <lb/>
     heard the proceedings of the House broadcast. If 
     <lb/>
     our people could compare our proceedings with 
     <lb/>
     those in the houses of parliament in other 
     <lb/>
     countries, they would say how decent and simple 
     <lb/>
     our debates are. We are a crowd of ordinary 
     <lb/>
     people trying to find out what we can. "Why is it 
     <lb/>
     taking so long?" some say. The Amulree Royal 
     <lb/>
     Commission came'out here and it took them six 
     <lb/>
     months, and they had all kinds of help and ex<lb break="no"/>perts. Their job was not one hundredth as big as 


<note xml:id="fn_02">[1] To cross-examine, to argue, to question (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Dictionary of Newfoundland English</hi>, p, 123).</note> 
   

            <pb n="502" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0502.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">502</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
          

     this Convention's. It took six months to produce 
     <lb/>
     a report not as big as one of our nine reports.... 
     <lb/>
     What is it we are doing? We are doing the biggest 
     <lb/>
     job so far as digging into, finding out and passing 
     <lb/>
     on, ever done in this country. People who ask that 
     <lb/>
     question have not the brains to get out of their 
     <lb/>
     own way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> When this Convention opened 
     <lb/>
     on September 11 the microphones were here, and 
     <lb/>
     I for one would not like to debar any person from 
     <lb/>
     hearing what was going on in this chamber. If 
     <lb/>
     there is anybody who does not wish to listen to 
     <lb/>
     the broadcasts, all they have to do is switch their 
     <lb/>
     radio over and listen to another programme. 
   </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> I was one of the delegates who said 
     <lb/>I would like to see the microphones thrown out 
     <lb/>of the room.... At the time I made the statement 
     <lb/>in this House, I think we were all kind of upset 
     <lb/>with long-winded speeches and I blamed it on the 
     <lb/>microphones. I would not want the people of this 
     <lb/>country to think I would be a party to depriving 
     <lb/>them of information regarding this Convention. I 
     <lb/>am just as fully for the obtaining of public infor<lb break="no"/>mation for the people of the outports as any other 
     <lb/>delegate in this Convention. One thing, I would 
     <lb/>like to see addresses confined to 15 minutes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Butt</persName> I think the people of this country are 
     <lb/>just as much a part of this Convention as the 
     <lb/>actual members sitting here and they are entitled 
     <lb/>to every bit of information they possibly can get. 
     <lb/>The radio was made for this country, as isolated 
     <lb/>as we are.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I had a feeling from the letter that there was 
     <lb/>
     an implication that we ought to soft-pedal our 
     <lb/>
     language. I do not know if that was intended. I 
     <lb/>
     agree with Mr. Smallwood, who already has said 
     <lb/>
     it is up to each individual member, in accordance 
     <lb/>
     with his ability, to say anything he believes and 
     <lb/>
     it is up to each individual to take the risk after<lb break="no"/>wards, if it be treated as not proper. I do feel that 
     <lb/>
     we ought to get a little harder, and consequently 
  

            <cb/>
     

     to speak of the things on our minds regardless of 
     <lb/>
     who likes it or who does not like it. If we get into 
     <lb/>
     a jam, let us take the rap. The sooner the people 
     <lb/>
     get that attitude, the better for the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> I want to go on record as agree<lb break="no"/>ing heartily with Mr, Butt. When I made my 
     <lb/>
     initial speech in support of Mr. Job's motion, I 
     <lb/>
     felt we should speak our minds with due regard 
     <lb/>
     for the rules of procedure and respect for the 
     <lb/>
     Chair, and we should not be awed in any way by 
     <lb/>
     anyone in the House or outside. In broadcasting 
     <lb/>
     at Christmas I said I had no intention of making 
     <lb/>
     an apology for anything said here. We could not 
     <lb/>
     be expected to turn into Roosevelts or Churchills 
     <lb/>
     overnight. Fourteen years we have been without 
     <lb/>
     taking part in politics and it takes time to become 
     <lb/>
     reueducated. I would like to pay tribute to the 
     <lb/>
     various speakers. As for the microphones, I for 
     <lb/>
     one would like to see them stay, particularly as it 
     <lb/>
     would be a wrong time, now as we will soon be 
     <lb/>
     coming to the forms of government, to have them 
     <lb/>
     removed.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> I wish to clear up a misunderstand<lb break="no"/>ing that perhaps I wanted to have the 
     <lb/>
     microphones removed. I asked the Convention to 
     <lb/>
     think of two things: one was the removal of the 
     <lb/>
     microphones; the other was just what it would 
     <lb/>
     mean. We may this afternoon be required to 
     <lb/>
     discuss a paragraph of the Mining Report already 
     <lb/>
     read which may be embarrassing to us, to others 
     <lb/>
     or to the country. If we are to do a thorough job 
     <lb/>
     we have to speak fairly and frankly.... There are 
     <lb/>
     things crippling Newfoundland's economic posi<lb break="no"/>tion. If we are going to get up and make pretty 
     <lb/>
     speeches we are not going to get at it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> I wish to support Mr. Higgins' 
     <lb/>
     motion. The people of Newfoundland are paying 
     <lb/>
     to keep the microphones here. I wish Mr. Higgins 
     <lb/>
     had included VOCM.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the Mining Committee:<ref target="#fn_03">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Before we go into the report 
     <lb/>
     proper, there are a couple of questions I am going 
     <lb/>
     to try to answer. A question was asked with 
     <lb/>
     respect to the 15 cents tax on horsepower to be 
     <lb/>
     developed at Grand Falls. We cannot give all the 
     <lb/>
     information regarding the taxed horsepower. In 


            <cb/>
          

     Quebec the price is $l on installed horsepower. 
     <lb/>
     We do not know the meaning of "installed horse<lb break="no"/>power." We are going to try and find out from the 
     <lb/>
     hydroelectric engineer. It may be the term "in<lb break="no"/>stalled" would mean "capable of producing." 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>With respect to Mr. Harrington's question 


<note xml:id="fn_03">[1] Volume II:313. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
  

            <pb n="503" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0503.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">503</fw>
         

     dealing with water-power, and the possibility of 
     <lb/>
     taking away rights from these people who have 
     <lb/>
     not complied with the requirements of the act.... 
     <lb/>
     With respect to the taking of property from 
     <lb/>
     people who have not complied with the necessary 
     <lb/>
     requirements under which they got them, and 
     <lb/>
     reference to which was made in the portion on the 
     <lb/>
     table on water-power, the position is this. Some 
     <lb/>
     years ago there were timber leases on which the 
     <lb/>
     people who had rights had to erect mills. They 
     <lb/>
     did not erect mills, and the government took 
     <lb/>
     action for cancellation of licenses. But the 
     <lb/>
     government had accepted rentals. Upon action 
     <lb/>
     being taken it was ultimately decided by the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council on appeal in the case of the New<lb break="no"/>foundland Government vs. Jardine ... that the 
     <lb/>
     condition had been broken, but if after the breach 
     <lb/>
     the government had accepted the rent, then the 
     <lb/>
     government had waived its right to cancel the 
     <lb/>
     leases, and the licenses must continue on that 
     <lb/>
     understanding as long as the rents were paid and 
     <lb/>
     in good standing.<ref target="#fn_04">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In respect to expropriation of property, I am 
     <lb/>
     answering from the judgement in Dillon and 
     <lb/>
     others vs. the St. John's Housing Corporation.<ref target="#fn_05">[2]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     That judgement traces the history and powers of 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government; it is excellent reading.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The judgement is very long, gentlemen, but 
     <lb/>
     you understand the situation At that time it was 
     <lb/>
     being argued by counsel for the plaintiffs that the 
     <lb/>
     Housing Corporation had no right to expropriate 
     <lb/>
     the land where the Housing Corporation develop<lb break="no"/>ment is now situated without the consent of the 
     <lb/>
     British Parliament through one of the Secretaries 
     <lb/>
     of State, as the property being expropriated was 
     <lb/>
     not the property of British subjects residing in the 
     <lb/>
     colony. I trust, Mr. Harrington, that makes the 
     <lb/>
     point clear? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> It does and it does not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I wonder if Mr. Higgins could 
     <lb/>tell us were there royal instructions to the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor of that same kind under the old Letters 
     <lb/>Patent? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I believe there were. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> You mean that even under the 
    

            <cb/>
   

     kind of government we had before Commission 
     <lb/>
     of Government, the Governor had his instruc<lb break="no"/>tions from the King as to what he might and might 
     <lb/>
     not do? He was instructed that he was not to sign 
     <lb/>
     or agree to any act of the government that would 
     <lb/>
     confiscate the property of any person in New<lb break="no"/>foundland? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That is my impression. I will let 
     <lb/>
     you know the proper answer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Sitting beside you is the Chair<lb break="no"/>man of the National Convention, who was once 
     <lb/>
     Solicitor General of Newfoundland, and as such 
     <lb/>
     once instrumental in serving quite a number of 
     <lb/>
     writs on the owners of timber lands, who had 
     <lb/>
     been granted those timber lands on condition that 
     <lb/>
     they would develop them. They had not 
     <lb/>
     developed them, I believe, and they had not met 
     <lb/>
     the conditions, and he issued writs running up to 
     <lb/>
     a value of millions of dollars, one of the biggest 
     <lb/>
     actions ever taken in the history of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I was wondering if we could provoke 
     <lb/>
     him — it was a case where a lot of natural 
     <lb/>
     resources had been granted to certain individuals 
     <lb/>
     on certain conditions. They did not develop them, 
     <lb/>
     and he decided to get them back for the Crown. 
     <lb/>
     The government backed him and their licenses 
     <lb/>
     were cancelled.<ref target="#fn_06">[3]</ref> It may not be quite the same 
     <lb/>
     kind of case, but if it were, there is a case where 
     <lb/>
     the government could get them back, and here's 
     <lb/>
     another case where we could not get them back. 
 </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I can only speak from memory 
     <lb/>and my recollection is that the owner of the 
     <lb/>property was a limited company which was 
     <lb/>domiciled in Newfoundland. I believe it was the 
     <lb/>Reid Newfoundland Company, so that any Let<lb break="no"/>ters Patent or Instructions to the Governor would 
     <lb/>have no application. I have also to add that while 
     <lb/>those writs were in fact issued the leases were not 
     <lb/>cancelled. That was prior to the case which went 
     <lb/>to the Privy Council. Beyond that I cannot go, 
     <lb/>because I would be talking politics, and I cannot 
     <lb/>talk politics in this Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I trust, Mr. Smallwood, that is suf<lb break="no"/>ficient answer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> Regarding the matter of water<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_04">[1] Attorney General and Minister of Agriculture and Mines vs. Jardine and Martin, 1930, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Decisions of the 
     <lb/>
     Supreme Court of Newfoundland, 1927-1931</hi>, pp. 446-484.</note> 

<note xml:id="fn_05">[2] Dillon vs. Canning and the St. John's Housing Corporation, 1946, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Decisions of the Supreme Court of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, 1941-1946</hi>, pp. 386-416. </note>

<note xml:id="fn_06">[3] Attorney General and Minister of Agriculture and Mines vs. Mines and Forests (Newfoundland) Ltd. et al., 
     <lb/>July 1931. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Decisions of the Supreme Court of Newfoundland, 1927-1931</hi>, pp. 446-484. </note>


            <pb n="504" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0504.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">504</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
      

     power, would Mr. Higgins be able to tell us about 
     <lb/>
     the scope and cost of the survey which the 
     <lb/>
     government intends to make here, having this 
     <lb/>
     engineer come in for a short time? 
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I am afraid the Mining Committee 
     <lb/>knows very little as to the scope of his work. I 
     <lb/>assume he is not far enough advanced to tell us 
     <lb/>what he proposes to do, but from what little 
     <lb/>information we have, he is going to assess the 
     <lb/>horsepower of each of the rivers in Newfound<lb break="no"/>land, whether they are granted or ungranted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> Do you know the cost? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> No. He is on a regular salary, and 
     <lb/>I presume whatever help he is going to require, 
     <lb/>plus his salary, will be the cost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I think it is a very pertinent 
     <lb/>question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I agree with you, and as you know 
     <lb/>from our report, we comment that we approve of 
     <lb/>such an appointment, and we think it should have 
     <lb/>been made many years ago. Unfortunately, prac<lb break="no"/>tically all the water-power in the country has been 
     <lb/>given away, and in a good many cases for that 
     <lb/>very valuable article, a peppercom, whatever that 
     <lb/>is. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Do I understand that the counsel for 
     <lb/>the plaintiff lost the case or won it? Some person 
     <lb/>owning property sued the Housing Corporation 
     <lb/>for expropriating their property? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Yes, they were suing the Housing 
     <lb/>Corporation on the grounds that they no powers 
     <lb/>to expropriate their land. Judgement was given 
     <lb/>against the plaintiff. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> On the grounds that the plain<lb break="no"/>tiff was local and not foreign? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That does not come into it. The 
     <lb/>judge ruled that the act had been properly 
     <lb/>negotiated and the assentof the Secretary of State 
     <lb/>had been obtained.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Is that all on that particular point? 
     <lb/>If so, we will go on to the next part of the report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>There is one section of the Mining Report that 
     <lb/>we started the other day, with respect to the 
     <lb/>Committee's findings on the question of the 
     <lb/>change in the 1938 act and the 1944 act.<ref target="#fn_07">[1]</ref> The 
     <lb/>explanation that was given us for the change in 
  

            <cb/>
        

     the 10 cents per ton of iron ore to the present 
     <lb/>
     arrangement under the 1944 act of 5% of the net 
     <lb/>
     proceeds. Now you will note the comment of the 
     <lb/>
     Committee on page 5 with respect to that ex<lb break="no"/>planation, and so that there will be no doubt I 
     <lb/>
     would like to read that. "Iron ore is the cheapest 
     <lb/>
     metal commodity in the world ore deposits on 
     <lb/>
     the Quebec side of the border." The Committee's 
     <lb/>
     comment on that explanation was this: "Your 
     <lb/>
     Committee does not find itself in a position to 
     <lb/>
     accept this explanation, as we are of the opinion 
     <lb/>
     that even though the company operating the iron 
     <lb/>
     ore deposits may not be actually showing a sub<lb break="no"/>stantial profit, the parent company, that is, the 
     <lb/>
     steel manufacturing company, is actually making 
     <lb/>
     real profit. As far as we can gather, the companies 
     <lb/>
     operating the deposits are merely holding com<lb break="no"/>panies of some large steel manufacturing cor<lb break="no"/>porations."<ref target="#fn_08">[2]</ref> With respect to that comment of the 
     <lb/>
     Mining Committee, I have to inform you that the 
     <lb/>
     members of the Committee are not in full agree<lb break="no"/>ment, consequently it was decided that they 
     <lb/>
     should bring up the matter and, having heard all 
     <lb/>
     the comments and the reasons, you could either 
     <lb/>
     order that section deleted or otherwise. However, 
     <lb/>
     we are not able to go into the full argument on 
     <lb/>
     that right now. When this section was put in we 
     <lb/>
     did not have the Quebec act, which is before you 
     <lb/>
     now. This morning, we had a meeting with the 
     <lb/>
     solicitor of the company, Mr. Eric Cook, K.C., 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Claude Howse and Mr. George Allen. I want 
     <lb/>
     to have the minutes of that meeting before I 
     <lb/>
     debate this particular aspect. I would suggest that 
     <lb/>
     we let it stand at that point till I get the minutes, 
     <lb/>
     and in the meantime the Secretary will continue 
     <lb/>
     reading the report, if that's satisfactory to the 
     <lb/>
     members. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Is that satisfactory, gentlemen? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>[The Secretary continued reading the report]<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Gentlemen, at that point I would 
     <lb/>suggest to you that we might read the speech of 
     <lb/>Hon. Mr. Hugessen, who introduced the bill for 
     <lb/>that railway in the Canadian Senate. I understand 
     <lb/>it has been passed now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the Labrador Railway bill<lb/>attached to the report</hi><ref target="#fn_09">[3]</ref><hi rendition="simple:italic">]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

    
   
<note xml:id="fn_07">[1] An Act for the Confirmation of An Agreement Between the Government and Labrador Mining and Explora<lb break="no"/>tion Company, Limited, 2 Geo. Vl c40 (1938). An Act further to Amend the Act No. 41 of 1938 Entitled "An 
     <lb/>Act for the Confirmation of an Agreement Between the Government and Labrador," 8 Geo. Vl c47 (1944).</note> 

<note xml:id="fn_08">[2] Volume II:355. Most of this sentence was deleted in the final report. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

<note xml:id="fn_09">[3] An Act to Incorporate Quebec North Shore and Labrador Railway Company, l l Geo. Vl c80, (1947).</note> 

    
            <pb n="505" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0505.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">505</fw>
            

<p>
     I would prefer that if there are any questions 
     <lb/>
     dealing with the second part of the report we take 
     <lb/>
     those and let the rest stand over, as I have still not 
     <lb/>
     got the full minutes of the meeting this morning. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VINC1">Mr. Vincent</persName> In connection with the 350 mile 
     <lb/>railway may I refer you to page 8 of the report, in 
     <lb/>the letter: "To justify the railway and to justify 
     <lb/>commitments of the large sums involved, there 
     <lb/>must be a known quantity of at least 300 million 
     <lb/>tons of commercial ore".... Does this mean that 
     <lb/>before the undertaking starts that must be ascer<lb break="no"/>tained? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Before development of the mine is 
     <lb/>
     begun they have to be sure they have in sight 300 
     <lb/>
     million tons of commercial ore. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> When will that be? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> They hope that will be found by the 
     <lb/>
     end of this present year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I notice it says on page 8: 
     <lb/>
     "Owing to the short working season, it will take 
     <lb/>
     not less than three years to detemtine the iron ore 
     <lb/>
     tonnage available and, until a reasonable estimate 
     <lb/>
     can be made, it is impossible to state when 
     <lb/>
     production will begin." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> You must remember the date of 
     <lb/>
     that letter, October 28. The situation changed at 
     <lb/>
     the end of the year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> As a result they hope to know 
     <lb/>
     this year? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> It's not by any means definite, but 
     <lb/>
     they hope to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> On page 11 ... what do you 
     <lb/>
     mean by "standard price"? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Howse told us that was the 
     <lb/>
     price fixed by the iron ore producers association, 
     <lb/>
     and it was the price of ore laid down at Lake 
     <lb/>
     Superior ports, unless of course there are any 
     <lb/>
     deductions for sulphur, phosphorus, moisture, 
     <lb/>
     etc. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> When was that agreement 
     <lb/>
     made as to the standard price? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I understand it was sometime ago, 
     <lb/>
     I should think years ago. It was not as a result of 
     <lb/>
     Labrador. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, but I was wondering if it is 
     <lb/>
     the result of the war. How permanent or how 
     <lb/>
     standard is it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> If you will give me five minutes to 
     <lb/>
     inquire I will let you know... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VINC1">Mr. Vincent</persName> Mr. Chairman, in Professor 
     <lb/>
     MacKay's very excellent book<ref target="#fn_10">[1]</ref> on Newfound<lb break="no"/>land he has this to say: "As soon as the new 
     <lb/>
     discovery is developed it might have important 
     <lb/>
     effects for Newfoundland On the one hand it 
     <lb/>
     might provide an important outlet for employ<lb break="no"/>ment on the other hand it may mean reduced 
     <lb/>
     markets for Wabana." On page 11 your report 
     <lb/>
     says that it is your opinion that it won't. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> We got that opinion from Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Howse, and also from the General Manager of the 
     <lb/>
     Bell Island mines, Mr. Anson. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I wonder if the chairman of the Min<lb break="no"/>ing Committee could enlighten me on the mean<lb break="no"/>ing of this on page 12'? "Negotiations over the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland-Canada boundary between 
     <lb/>
     Labrador and Quebec have begun between the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian and Newfoundland governments and it 
     <lb/>
     is possible that the actual delimiting of the bound<lb break="no"/>ary on the ground may begin in 1947." What is 
     <lb/>
     the meaning of that word "delimiting"? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> The boundary has been generally 
     <lb/>
     determined by that famous decision of the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council in 1927. The position is that the actual 
     <lb/>
     boundary runs through this big ore deposit, so 
     <lb/>
     that we have to have it accurately determined, and 
     <lb/>
     this will be done this year. "Delimiting" means 
     <lb/>
     marking out on the ground the actual boundary. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> In other words they are going to 
     <lb/>stake it off. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That would be the height of 
     <lb/>
     land, just determine what is the height of land. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> A mile one way or the other might 
     <lb/>make a great difference. It is a watershed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In this letter from Mr. Timmins 
     <lb/>
     to Mr. Cook, paragraph two: "Preliminary sur<lb break="no"/>veys are now being made with a view to locating 
     <lb/>
     a railway, with suitable grades to an all-year port, 
     <lb/>
    but until a survey is completed no definite loca<lb break="no"/>tion and terminals can be stated. The company 
     <lb/>proposes applying for a charter for a railway 
     <lb/>company with authority to construct a railway 
     <lb/>running generally north and south through the 
     <lb/>western portion of Labrador." Does that mean 
     <lb/>that an entirely separate company altogether, one 
     <lb/>separate from the Labrador Mining and Explora<lb break="no"/>tion CO., and the North Shore Mining and Ex<lb break="no"/>ploration Co.,<ref target="#fn_11">[2]</ref> that an entirely different company 
     <lb/>is going to build and operate the railway? Or just 
 

<note xml:id="fn_10">[1] R.A. MacKay, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Newfoundland: Economic, Diplomatic, and Strategic Studies</hi> (Toronto, 1946). </note>

<note xml:id="fn_11">[2] The Hollinger North Shore Company. Volume II:355-6. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
  

            <pb n="506" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0506.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">506</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
         

     build the railway, or operate it, or both? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> It will be a separate company as far 
     <lb/>
     as the legal entity is concerned, but obviously it 
     <lb/>
     will be only for sewing these two companies. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> How will that company be af<lb break="no"/>fected insofar as it operates in Newfoundland 
     <lb/>Labrador? How would it be affected by the 1944 
     <lb/>act? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> It is not in any way affected. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> What rights have they? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> They have no rights under the 
     <lb/>
     1938 or 1944 act to export power for this railway. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> But have they got permission 
     <lb/>to develop it? Can they use that water-power, 
     <lb/>without any more legislation, on the railway 
     <lb/>within Newfoundland Labrador? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I believe that for the railway in 
     <lb/>
     Labrador they would have the power to use it, 
     <lb/>
     provided they develop the mine sufficiently to 
     <lb/>
     warrant it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> They can only develop the 
     <lb/>
     water-power if they start mining. But if they 
     <lb/>
     develop the mine they can use the water-power 
     <lb/>
     on the part of the railway in Newfoundland- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Labrador, but to use it on the rest of the railway 
     <lb/>
     they have to get a special act? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That's right. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Suppose a separate company is 
     <lb/>
     formed, a railway company, is it true that it will 
     <lb/>
     be owned by those two mining companies? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I should imagine. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> But although it is owned by 
     <lb/>
     them, it is a separate company.... I was thinking 
     <lb/>
     of taxation. Often the franchise to run a railway 
     <lb/>
     is worth something to the government that carries 
     <lb/>
     the franchise. Would there be any possibility of 
     <lb/>
     getting out of that railway company taxes that we 
     <lb/>
     cannot get out of the 1938 act and the 1944 act in 
     <lb/>
     regard to mining? Let us suppose, for the sake of 
     <lb/>
     argument, that the government has made a 
     <lb/>
     serious mistake and that where they mighthave 
     <lb/>
     got something out of the 1938 act, under the 1944 
     <lb/>
     act they will get nothing. Now along they come 
     <lb/>
     looking for a franchise to run a railway; would 
     <lb/>
     the government be in a position to re-open the 
     <lb/>
     whole matter of taxation — use the application 
     <lb/>
     for the railway to remedy any mistake they made 
     <lb/>
     in abolishing that 10 cents per ton royalty? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Not in my opinion. Remember we 
     <lb/>
     have no knowledge except insofar as Mr. Cook 
     <lb/>
     had told us. I assume that the application is with 


            <cb/>
        

     respect to the export of power to be used on the 
     <lb/>
     balance of the railway not in Labrador. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Have they the right to use a 
     <lb/>
     railway in Labrador? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> In my opinion they have the right 
     <lb/>
     to use it in Labrador. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> They can start a railway now 
     <lb/>
     and no one can stop them, is that the position? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That's the particular part that has 
     <lb/>met with a lot of non-agreement among the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Committee. That's part of it. My 
     <lb/>recollection is that they can now run the railway 
     <lb/>on the power of Grand Falls, the railway that's in 
     <lb/>Labrador, but not in Quebec, provided they 
     <lb/>develop the mine enough to haul the ore over the 
     <lb/>railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> But you must first establish the 
     <lb/>
     fact that they have the power to run a railway 
     <lb/>
     there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I am glad Mr. Smallwood raised 
     <lb/>
     that question, because i was going to raise it too, 
     <lb/>
     with a definite object in mind. If this railway is 
     <lb/>
     going to be a transportation company owned by 
     <lb/>
     the mining company and hauling their ore out, the 
     <lb/>
     haulage charges could be very great indeed with 
     <lb/>
     a consequent loss, or very little profit out of the 
     <lb/>
     mining end of it, and our 5% on that might be very 
     <lb/>
     little. I can appreciate that any company going 
     <lb/>
     into an investment or gamble such as this must be 
     <lb/>
     assured of a certain profit but it strikes me that 
     <lb/>
     this quotation referring to Lake Superior was six 
     <lb/>
     cents, which was the low. I notice they don't give 
     <lb/>
     what the high would be. The way it seems it might 
     <lb/>
     be a bit of a red herring drawn across the deal. 
     <lb/>
     The inference that I get from the report is that the 
     <lb/>
     present company could not possibly operate 
     <lb/>
     under the agreement, and they would have to 
     <lb/>
     withdraw if a different form of royalty could not 
     <lb/>
     be worked out. The inference is that they would 
     <lb/>
     not be making the 10 cents profit. Let us assume 
     <lb/>
     that they were going to make 6 cents on it. Further 
     <lb/>
     on, in the letter Mr. Timmins states that there 
     <lb/>
     should be a known quantity of at least 300 million 
     <lb/>
     tons, of which they will take out a minimum of 5 
     <lb/>
     million tons a year. If they take out 30 million 
     <lb/>
     tons they will make a profit of $l8 million over 
     <lb/>
     a period of six years. That, on the original invest<lb break="no"/>ment, would bring it about 1¹/₂% profit per year 
     <lb/>
     as a return on their investment. I can't believe 
     <lb/>
     they are going into it with that profit. They have 
     <lb/>
     got to see a return on their investment, and I can't 


            <pb n="507" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0507.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">507</fw>
         

     be persuaded that it will be 1 1/2%. If they made 
     <lb/>
     that $18 million profit based on 6 cents per ton 
     <lb/>
     profit, our portion that would accrue to the New<lb break="no"/>foundland treasury on 5% of the net profit, would 
     <lb/>
     be $900,000 over six years, whereas we would 
     <lb/>
     have got $30 million with 10 cents per ton.... I 
     <lb/>
     don't know what advice the government had at 
     <lb/>
     that time, or whether they could not see far 
     <lb/>
     enough. They made an error of judgement, I 
     <lb/>
     would say, in changing over from that l0 cents 
     <lb/>
     per ton to the 5% basis... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The point is that this transportation company 
     <lb/>
     can be put in a position whereby they can haul the 
     <lb/>
     profits out, and leave the producing company 
     <lb/>
     showing a very small balance and this country 
     <lb/>
     won't benefit from it.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> In answering that I would refer you 
     <lb/>
     to the 1938 act, paragraph 39, which you have 
     <lb/>
     before you. I will read it for your benefit... That 
     <lb/>
     answers your question. They have the right to 
     <lb/>
     apply, but subject to such conditions and terms as 
     <lb/>
     to rental, etc., as the government may fix. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That's in 1938? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That section of the 1938 act is still 
     <lb/>
     in force. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Clause 7 of the 1944 act. Does 
     <lb/>
     that seem to bear on it? Section I. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> ....That's only over private proper<lb break="no"/>ties, it has nothing to do with obtaining the rights. 
     <lb/>
     That would be where there would be properties 
     <lb/>
     and land over which they put the railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> How do we stand then? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> They have the tight to apply to the 
     <lb/>
     government for the right-of-way for a railway, 
     <lb/>
     and the government will grant it on such terms 
     <lb/>
     and conditions as may seem reasonable and equi<lb break="no"/>table. Their application has been made, and I 
     <lb/>
     presume the government is forging what will be 
     <lb/>
     reasonable and equitable terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In the 1944 act, page 5, it 
     <lb/>
     speaks of things on which they are exempt from 
     <lb/>
     customs duty, and the things on which they have 
     <lb/>
     to pay it. Have they got to pay duty on the 
     <lb/>
     railway? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That would be one of its opera<lb break="no"/>tions. In the 1938 act, page 19: "The operations 
     <lb/>
     of the Company referred to shall include only the 
     <lb/>
     following ... transportation of such minerals." 
     <lb/>
     That would be one of the operations of the com<lb break="no"/>pany, and would come under a deduction. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> "They shall be exempt for a 
 

            <cb/>
          

     period of 20 years ... in Labrador." All duty free. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> It includes railway too if you follow 
     <lb/>on, Mr. Smallwood. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> On replacements they can only get 
     <lb/>
     up to 20% of the value. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I am going to ask the chairman of the 
     <lb/>
     Committee if he could tell me whether the royalty 
     <lb/>
     on Bell Island ore of 10 cents has been paid all 
     <lb/>
     along and is being paid? My reason for asking is 
     <lb/>
     that it would seem that if Bell Island with its ore, 
     <lb/>
     which is 52%, can stand a royalty, surely this 
     <lb/>
     other ore, which is 62%, can stand it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> There is a limit in Bell Island as to 
     <lb/>
     how much royalty they must pay. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> That's an interesting point, but no 
     <lb/>
     doubt a better basis from a Newfoundland point 
     <lb/>
     of view, would be a definite royalty per ton rather 
     <lb/>
     than a very indefinite 5% on the profit It seems 
     <lb/>
     a pity we don't know where we are. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Obviously the 1944 act from the 
     <lb/>
     point of view of the company is very much better 
     <lb/>
     than the 1938 act. They had the best advice they 
     <lb/>
     could get both times. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> On the face of it it seems not very 
     <lb/>
     satisfactory. We don't know what Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     is going to make out of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That's the point the Mining Com<lb break="no"/>mittee did not agree about. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Can you tell us where the disagreement 
     <lb/>
     comes in? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> They are not satisfied that New<lb break="no"/>foundland is getting a good deal on it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> That was the point I was going to 
     <lb/>
     raise, Mr. Chairman. I wonder could you tell us, 
     <lb/>
     do you believe Newfoundland has proper protec<lb break="no"/>tion in the agreement with the Labrador Mining 
     <lb/>
     Company? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I would much prefer to wait until I 
     <lb/>
     can give you all the facts. I am afraid I will not 
     <lb/>
     be able to answer the question. We will either 
     <lb/>
     have to have another session, or we will put it in 
     <lb/>
     a supplementary report. I would not like to give 
     <lb/>
     you my own opinion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> I did not think you would. I have 
     <lb/>
     been listening to the debate this last several days, 
     <lb/>
     and the impression I have is that Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     has not got proper protection in the agreement. 
     <lb/>
     The Grand Falls of Labrador is situated in the 
     <lb/>
     heart of unexplored territory believed to contain 
     <lb/>
     precious mineral deposits as well as timber areas, 
     <lb/>
     and is therefore the key to future development. 
    

            <pb n="508" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-18_Page_0508.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">508</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
        

     To tie up that great potential asset at this time for 
     <lb/>
     a fee of 15 cent per kilowatt hour cannot be 
     <lb/>
     regarded as in the best interests of Newfound<lb break="no"/>land, more especially when that great water<lb break="no"/>power may be used to develop the Quebec side 
     <lb/>
     of the Labrador boundary, giving Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     benefit through labour returns only. It is my belief 
     <lb/>
     that the delegates of the National Convention 
     <lb/>
     should register protest, or demand the agreement 
     <lb/>
     be re-written or changed so as to protect New<lb break="no"/>foundland in greater measure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Going back to the 15 cents per 
     <lb/>
     horsepower, if my memory serves me correct, on 
     <lb/>
     Wednesday one of the delegates and a member 
     <lb/>
     of the Committee, the representative for 
     <lb/>
     Labrador, said when the question was put to him, 
     <lb/>
     that the Commission of Government did not want 
     <lb/>
     to commit themselves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I must disagree with you there. 
     <lb/>
     Another member of the Convention made that 
     <lb/>
     statement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> He replied. I realised some of the 
     <lb/>
     solicitors putting through the deals were New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders and I was a bit sore; but after hear<lb break="no"/>ing that, we will have to pat him on the back, 
     <lb/>
     because if the Commission did not know what to 
     <lb/>
     charge, the solicitors would have said 5 cents a 
     <lb/>
     horsepower. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> We have nothing to show that the 
   

            <cb/>
            

     Commission did not know what price to fix. 
  
</p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I did not intend to have anything to 
     <lb/>say on this. I appreciate the point brought out by 
     <lb/>Mr. Hickman, Mr. Job and Mr. Smallwood, that 
     <lb/>the Mining Committee are not all as one on 
     <lb/>certain particular sections. Some of us realise the 
     <lb/>act is not so hot as far as Newfoundland is con<lb break="no"/>cerned. We may be wrong. We are trying to find 
     <lb/>out. We ought to have no further debate until the 
     <lb/>chairman of the Mining Committee is prepared 
     <lb/>to bring in a supplementary report. I appreciate 
     <lb/>the point brought out by Mr. Hickman: if we have 
     <lb/>made a bad deal so far, and any water-power they 
     <lb/>want is to be exported, and we have to issue a 
     <lb/>permit for the railway, there may be something 
     <lb/>to save out of the wreck. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> I agree with Mr. Hollett's remarks. 
     <lb/>
     Maybe we can do justice to this after we get the 
     <lb/>
     minutes of the meeting. It is well for every man 
     <lb/>
     in this house to be thoroughly acquainted with it 
     <lb/>
     all. This 10 cents per ton is objected to, and the 
     <lb/>
     company hopes to pay Newfoundland substan<lb break="no"/>tially well! I will give you a comparison: up to 
     <lb/>
     recently the Newfoundland fishermen were 
     <lb/>
     charged an export tax of $10 per ton on codfish. 
     <lb/>
     How does it compare with 10 cents on iron ore?
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee rose and reported progress, and<lb/>the Convention adjourned]</hi>
            </p>
   

<!-- GL, 2017-06-27, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
            <!--<p>
     April 21, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Mining Committee:¹ 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I propose at this time to give you a 
     <lb/>
     picture of the territory that these particular acts² 
     <lb/>
     refer to, and with which the second part of our 
     <lb/>
     report deals. As you realise, in the introduction to 
     <lb/>
     the railway bill by Mr. Hugessen of Quebec,³ he 
     <lb/>
     gave a picture of that area. With your permission 
     <lb/>
     I was going to ask our own senator from Labrador 
     <lb/>
     who was in that area, who was over Grand Falls 
     <lb/>
     and into the mines, if he would give us an account 
     <lb/>
     of the area as he knows it, and any other com- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     merits he would care to give us, so we would be 
     <lb/>
     in a better position to understand it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Mr. Barry ....There are one or two comments I 
     <lb/>
     would like to make before giving that word pic<lb break="no"/>ture. With the rest of the Committee, I took a 
     <lb/>
     serious view of the change that was made from 
     <lb/>
     10 cents per ton royalty to 5% of the net income. 
     <lb/>
     We thought with 10 cents royalty we would cer<lb break="no"/>tainly get a considerable amount. We found they 
     <lb/>
     changed to 5% of net profits, and there are so 
     <lb/>
     many suspicions of how big companies have a 
     <lb/>
     way of manipulating their profits to avoid taxes. 
     <lb/>
     We thought the 5% of the net profits they would 
     <lb/>
     declare would not give us much revenue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     ¹Volume II:313.<lb/>²Refers to: An Act for the Confirmation of an Agreement Between the Government and Labrador Mining 
     <lb/>
     and Exploration Company, Limited, 2 Geo. VI c40 (1938). An Act further to Amend the Act No. 4! of l938 
     <lb/>
     Between the Government and Labrador Mining and Exploration Company, Ltd, 8 Geo. Vl c47 (1944). 
     <lb/>
    ³An Act to Incorporate Quebec North Shore and Labrador Railway Company. 1l Geo. Vl c80 (1947). 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>