<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-01-08"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-01-08">8 January 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          
        
          <biblScope unit="page" from="222" to="229"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0222.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0223.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0224.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0225.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0226.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0227.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0228.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0229.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-03">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-03">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0222">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0222.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0223">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0223.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0224">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0224.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0225">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0225.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0226">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0226.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0227">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0227.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0228">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0228.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0229">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0229.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="222"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0222.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">222</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            
<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     January 8, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>


            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>Report of the Transportation and Communications Committee:<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I suggest that the Secretary 
     <lb/>
     read the report on the Railway.<ref target="#fn_02">[2]</ref>
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hickman We have all had this report for 
     <lb/>
     three or four weeks and have had an opportunity 
     <lb/>
     to read through it. I move that it be taken as read. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Reddy I would like to see the report read. 
     <lb/>It is going to the outports and they are interested. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Job I second Mr. Hickman's motion. This 
     <lb/>has been published in the newspapers and to read 
     <lb/>it would be a waste of time. There are other 
     <lb/>reports to be brought in and some of them may 
     <lb/>take a whole day to read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood It is true that this report has 
     <lb/>
     been published in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Daily News</hi> and in the 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Evening Telegram</hi>. I do not think it has been 
     <lb/>
     published in the weekly newspapers; and even if 
     <lb/>
     it had been in all the papers put together they do 
     <lb/>
     not reach more than a certain fraction of the 
     <lb/>
     population of Newfoundland. On the other hand, 
     <lb/>
     the radio does. It seems to me that all the people 
     <lb/>
     in Newfoundland and Labrador are entitled to all 
     <lb/>
     the information in this report and in all the other 
     <lb/>
     reports that may come before this Convention. It 
     <lb/>
     seems to me, not only desirable, but necessary, 
     <lb/>
     that it should come before the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I know of no other way it could be 
     <lb/>
     done. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[After some discussion, Mr. Hickman withdrew<lb/>his motion, and the Secretary continued reading<lb/>the report]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins I note that Mr. Smallwood is 
     <lb/>
     making some allowance for customs duties and 
     <lb/>
     wages; did the Committee take into account the 
     <lb/>
     income tax paid by employees? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Perhaps the Committee made a 
     <lb/>
     mistake even in mentioning the customs duties 
     <lb/>
     that the Railway paid the government if it raises 
     <lb/>
     an awkward question such as the income tax paid 
     <lb/>
     the government by employees. We did not con<lb break="no"/>sider the income tax paid by the Railway employ<lb break="no"/>ees to the government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins What would the average wages of 
     <lb/>
     monthly employees be? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood The Railway employs 4,000 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
       
     men. We did not break them down into different 
     <lb/>
     classes of wages and salaries. We took the total 
     <lb/>
     amount paid. Wages was one item of the Railway 
     <lb/>
     expenses. We showed the total forevery year. We 
     <lb/>
     have shown the total cost of the Railway and the 
     <lb/>
     total income, the total loss and total profit in each 
     <lb/>
     year. If the report is full of statistics now, it would 
     <lb/>
     be more complicated if we had gone into the costs 
     <lb/>
     in detail. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins I am not trying to be difficult. We 
     <lb/>
     have a picture of the net operating loss — it is 
     <lb/>
     costing so much money a year; is it not fair to 
     <lb/>
     assess duty and income tax also? That would 
     <lb/>
     reduce that loss. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Yes, in a certain sense; but the 
     <lb/>
     same argument applies to every department of the 
     <lb/>
     government. Public Health and Welfare, for in<lb break="no"/>stance is spending $4.5 million; you might find 
     <lb/>
     how many employees they have, what income tax 
     <lb/>
     they paid, and then if you like, subtract that and 
     <lb/>
     say the cost is that much less. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins Is that not the real position though? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood It may be the real position 
     <lb/>when you take the nine reports and find out what 
     <lb/>is going back to the government in taxes out of 
     <lb/>the wages they pay. But why do it in a particular 
     <lb/>case if you do not do it in all cases? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job I think Mr. Higgins is right. We know 
     <lb/>
     that the Railway is costing us money, but it is not 
     <lb/>
     costing us as much as we imagine it is. It would 
     <lb/>
     be of benefit if we could find what it is costing 
     <lb/>
     the country in an absolutely net way. It may be 
     <lb/>
     difficult for the Committee to get all details. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood If you do that, if you draw up 
     <lb/>an account and on the left hand side you show the 
     <lb/>total amount of money the government spent on 
     <lb/>wages, and on the right side you show the total 
     <lb/>income, if you show in that total income the part 
     <lb/>that is paid by their own employees in taxes, 
     <lb/>surely you would have to reduce it on the other 
     <lb/>side. Where would you end? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett On page 4 of this report, paragraph 
     <lb/>
     3, it says "It will be noted...." Has the Committee 
     <lb/>
     tried to find out why this sudden change? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<note xml:id="fn_01">1 Volume II:75. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

 <note xml:id="fn_02">2 Volume II:103. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
          
            <pb n="223"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0223.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">223</fw>
            
<p>
     Mr. Smallwood We did and it is worse than that. 
     <lb/>
     In 1944-45 they had a loss of $500,000. In 1945- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     46 they had a loss of $1 million, and in this year, 
     <lb/>
     which will end March 31, 1947, it will be $1.5 
     <lb/>
     million. The operating loss is definitely on the 
     <lb/>
     increase. It applies to railways all over the world. 
     <lb/>
     There is an upward trend in operating rates, the 
     <lb/>
     cost of coal, of supplies of all kinds. For example, 
     <lb/>
     the cost of coal has increased to the railway by 
     <lb/>
     100%. The cost of wages has increased, so the 
     <lb/>
     Railway informs us, by 70%. That does not mean 
     <lb/>
     a 70% increase in the pay of the railroaders, but 
     <lb/>
     the number of employees has had to be increased. 
     <lb/>
     The reason is that there are more trains of all 
     <lb/>
     kinds, more runs made, and more staff engaged 
     <lb/>
     to do more work and put in more time, and 
     <lb/>
     additional freight handlers here and along the 
     <lb/>
     line. More freight handlers are handling coastal 
     <lb/>
     boat freight, which in turn calls for more over<lb break="no"/>head staff at headquarters, accounting, auditing, 
     <lb/>
     etc. There was a time this year when the total 
     <lb/>
     number employed was 4,300. That was largely 
     <lb/>
     seasonal staff. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The loss jumped from $500,000 the year 
     <lb/>
     before last to $1 million last year and $1.5 million 
     <lb/>
     this year, and the reason is that the cost of operat<lb break="no"/>ing is going up faster than their income is going 
     <lb/>
     up. That is a situation that applies to every rail<lb break="no"/>way in North America today, so the Railway 
     <lb/>
     informed me. There is not a railway in Canada or 
     <lb/>
     the States, I am told, that is today even meeting 
     <lb/>
     its operating costs. Our railway is doing the same 
     <lb/>
     thing and is going to do so even more in the future 
     <lb/>
     than it has done up to now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett I just asked the question so that it 
     <lb/>
     might be brought to the attention of the public. I 
     <lb/>
     think some mention of that should be made in the 
     <lb/>
     report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood That is not in the report proper, 
     <lb/>
     but the appendix contains a reference to it by the 
     <lb/>
     General Manager of the Railway himself, signed 
     <lb/>
     by his own name. He deals with that very 
     <lb/>
     thoroughly. He speaks of the mounting cost of 
     <lb/>
     supplies, coal, number of employees, etc. There 
     <lb/>
     was a small increase given to railway men, but it 
     <lb/>
     was mostly due to the increased number of men 
     <lb/>
     employed. It is only fair to say that on behalf of 
     <lb/>
     the railwaymen.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job I don't want to be too persistent, but I 
     <lb/>
      
            <cb/>
          
     would like to draw attention to that section on 
     <lb/>
     page 5, "All the modifying factors having been 
     <lb/>
     taken into consideration....etc."<ref target="#fn_03">[1]</ref> Now is that cor<lb break="no"/>rect? I don't think it is, because on page 4 the 
     <lb/>
     report says $702,325, that is before the modifying 
     <lb/>
     factors have been taken into account. The 
     <lb/>
     modifying factors show duties to be deducted, so 
     <lb/>
     surely it cannot be correct that the loss is still 
     <lb/>
     $700,000. Is that section wrong? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood No, sir, but for the 26 years that 
     <lb/>
     the government has been operating this Railway, 
     <lb/>
     which ended on the 31st of March last, the 
     <lb/>
     government has had to pay the Railway a total 
     <lb/>
     amount of $18,250,000. Now if you take that $18 
     <lb/>
     million that the government had to pay the Rail<lb break="no"/>way — first of all to meet their losses and then to 
     <lb/>
     buy new equipment, and for capital and main<lb break="no"/>tenance account, and divide it by the 26 years it 
     <lb/>
     comes to an average of $702,000 a year. It is true 
     <lb/>
     that at the bottom of the next page we put it in 
     <lb/>
     round figures, but when we say that all the factors 
     <lb/>
     have been taken into consideration, we do not 
     <lb/>
     mean as a matter of accountancy — the customs 
     <lb/>
     duties, income tax paid by railwaymen, etc. We 
     <lb/>
     do not take it into account as a matter of book<lb break="no"/>keeping, but into consideration. The position is 
     <lb/>
     not quite as bad as it sounds. We know it is not a 
     <lb/>
     dead loss of $700,000. We have got the railway 
     <lb/>
     and the services performed, 4,000 men get their 
     <lb/>
     living and they pay income tax, which does help 
     <lb/>
     the revenue. But I fail completely to understand 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Job. Does he really mean that we ought to 
     <lb/>
     have found out exactly how much income tax is 
     <lb/>
     paid to the government by railroaders, or if we 
     <lb/>
     were to find it out, how could we deduct it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job I am talking about the customs duties. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood All right, take the customs 
     <lb/>duties and purchases. How are you going to find 
     <lb/>that out? Some of the goods they bought and paid 
     <lb/>duty on them, some of them they imported and 
     <lb/>they were duty free. If they got flour for their 
     <lb/>dining cars they paid no duty. Are we expected, 
     <lb/>as a Committee, to find out every detail of what 
     <lb/>the Railway spent, who got it and what it was 
     <lb/>spent on, and follow it through and see what duty 
     <lb/>was paid on all these articles, and then deduct it 
     <lb/>from that $700,000 a year? I don't think the 
     <lb/>Committee would consider it. If it was to be done 
     <lb/>it would have to be a job for high class auditors. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<note xml:id="fn_03">1 Volume II:106. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

            <pb n="224"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0224.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">224</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>

            <p>
     If it has to be done for the Railway it will have to 
     <lb/>
     be done for every other department. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job They state definitely here that the duty 
     <lb/>
     paid by the Railway was $213,915 in one year, 
     <lb/>
     and in another year it was $167,636, so that if that 
     <lb/>
     was deducted from $700,000, it would be more 
     <lb/>
     like $500,000. The loss is considerably less than 
     <lb/>
     $700,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I want to know why that 
     <lb/>
     amount should be deducted. Why should you 
     <lb/>
     deduct what the government pays back to the 
     <lb/>
     country on what they import? If a firm on water 
     <lb/>
     Street pays so much to the government in cus<lb break="no"/>toms duties, and if that firm pays income tax and 
     <lb/>
     profits tax, how is that any different from the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland Railway paying customs duties to 
     <lb/>
     the government? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job One is a public utility. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood The government pays 
     <lb/>
     $700,000 a year for the past 30 years, but the 
     <lb/>
     Railway being an importer of certain goods pays 
     <lb/>
     duty on these goods the same as a commercial 
     <lb/>
     firm. Mr. Job wants to know why that should not 
     <lb/>
     be deducted, but the point is not what the Railway 
     <lb/>
     is costing the country, but what the Railway is 
     <lb/>
     costing the government. We are dealing with 
     <lb/>
     public finance. What the Railway is costing New<lb break="no"/>foundland is this: what is paid out by the Railway 
     <lb/>
     is paid by Newfoundland. Now the government 
     <lb/>
     pays out so much more; in addition Newfound<lb break="no"/>land is supporting the Railway by travelling on it 
     <lb/>
     and paying fares, sending freight, etc. The 
     <lb/>
     general economy of Newfoundland is doing that, 
     <lb/>
     but the government is making up the difference. 
     <lb/>
     Between the public and the government the Rail<lb break="no"/>way gets a certain amount of money — enough 
     <lb/>
     to pay their expenses. They don't get enough to 
     <lb/>
     pay their expenses from the public. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job I don't want to take any part in that 
     <lb/>
     suggestion at all. I just want to say what is the 
     <lb/>
     meaning of that sentence, "All the modifying 
     <lb/>
     factors being taken into consideration." But you 
     <lb/>
     have not deducted them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood No, we are taking them into 
     <lb/>
     consideration, but we are not deducting them. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Job Then, you have not taken them into 
     <lb/>consideration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett Would that reply be suitable or 
     <lb/>
     satisfactory for the years 1922-23 and 1923-24? 
     <lb/>
     1922-23 showed a loss of practically $600,000. 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
           
     The next year showed a loss of only $6,000. 
     <lb/>
     Would the same reply be given? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Yes. In 1922-23 the Railway 
     <lb/>
     lost $593,000. Next year the loss was only 
     <lb/>
     $6,500. The reason is exactly the same. In that 
     <lb/>
     year the Humber<ref target="#fn_04">[1]</ref> began, and a tremendous 
     <lb/>
     amount of tonnage was hauled on the railway, 
     <lb/>
     which gave them a sudden increase in their 
     <lb/>
     revenue, and that was not offset by an increase in 
     <lb/>
     their expenditures or costs of operating, because 
     <lb/>
     they did not have to take on additional 
     <lb/>
     employees, and they did not have to pay large 
     <lb/>
     amounts of additional money for coal.... Pass on 
     <lb/>
     to the next year, 1924-25 — they lost $328,000, 
     <lb/>
     because that big heavy traffic in connection with 
     <lb/>
     the starting of Humber had more or less passed 
     <lb/>
     away, and their costs did begin to creep up again. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Hollett Why did they creep up again in that 
     <lb/>second year? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I am sure Mr. Hollett does not 
     <lb/>
     expect me to know the details of all these years. 
     <lb/>
     We all remember the Humber, but exactly why 
     <lb/>
     in detail their costs rose each year, I do not 
     <lb/>
     remember. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett At least one thing you can remem<lb break="no"/>ber? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Reddy Did it ever occur to your Committee 
     <lb/>
     that the Railway is overstaffed at present? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I can't say whether it occurred 
     <lb/>
     to the Committee. I can only say it never occurred 
     <lb/>
     to me that the Railway is overpaid, and it still 
     <lb/>
     does not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Reddy To my mind, sir, the country 
     <lb/>
     believes that the Railway is overstaffed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Figary I want to assure Mr. Reddy that the 
     <lb/>
     Railway is not overstaffed. In Argentia a few 
     <lb/>
     days ago there were two boats at the dock, and 
     <lb/>
     they had 30 men there in order to get those two 
     <lb/>
     boats ready for the southwest coast. Not only at 
     <lb/>
     Argentia, but at other places along the railway 
     <lb/>
     there should be more staff. I have been working 
     <lb/>
     with the Railway since 1914, and I can say that 
     <lb/>
     the Railway is not overstaffed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Fogwill I wish to support Mr. Figary. I don't 
     <lb/>
     think they are overstaffed. Sometimes the men 
     <lb/>
     may have more to do than at other times, but I 
     <lb/>
     have worked there since 1924 and I know that 
     <lb/>
     often we have had to put in too much overtime. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood Mr. Reddy ought to give us 
     <lb/>some indication of where and in what particular 
     <lb/>
         
   
<note xml:id="fn_04">The Humber project — the building of the Corner Brook newsprint mill.</note>

            <pb n="225"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0225.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">225</fw>
          
     departments or branches of the railway system 
     <lb/>
     there is overstaffing. I have been along the rail<lb break="no"/>way many times, and in every single individual 
     <lb/>
     railway station from here to Port-aux-Basques. I 
     <lb/>
     can assure you that so far as Gander station is 
     <lb/>
     concerned they are not overstaffed. When a man 
     <lb/>
     is paid for ten hours work, and then has to come 
     <lb/>
     back for two or three hours overtime, with no pay 
     <lb/>
     at all, for six days a week for months and months 
     <lb/>
     on end to keep up with the work, I don't think 
     <lb/>
     there is any overstaffmg. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins I may be anticipating parts of the 
     <lb/>
     report, but I note that the only reduction in operat<lb break="no"/>ing costs that Mr. Smallwood's Committee has 
     <lb/>
     suggested might be caused by increasing these 
     <lb/>
     companies that have special rates. What is the 
     <lb/>
     real trouble with the Railway that they are losing 
     <lb/>
     money? Has the Committee any real reasons to 
     <lb/>
     give? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I thought that I had one. He will 
     <lb/>
     recall I said that every railway in North America 
     <lb/>
     is losing money, ... unless they increase their 
     <lb/>
     freight rates, which the railways in America and 
     <lb/>
     Canada are desiring right now to do.... If we 
     <lb/>
     increase the freight rates the general public will 
     <lb/>
     have to bear the cost of operating the railway. If 
     <lb/>
     we do not, the government has to pay the loss. 
     <lb/>
     Whether the people pay it or the government pay 
     <lb/>
     it, the people of Newfoundland in general have 
     <lb/>
     to stand the loss.... As for the other point he 
     <lb/>
     raised. Early this afternoon there was a memoran<lb break="no"/>dum laid on your desks from the management of 
     <lb/>
     the Railway replying to the Committee's 
     <lb/>
     criticisms of these special rates that are given to 
     <lb/>
     the paper companies, the Buchans Mining Com<lb break="no"/>pany, Imperial Oil Ltd, and Shell Oil. We will 
     <lb/>
     come to that; perhaps Mr. Higgins will be willing 
     <lb/>
     to wait until we come to that in the report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins I am quite willing.... I would like 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood to explain whether there is any 
     <lb/>
     difference between the subsidy that is paid by the 
     <lb/>
     government now, and what used to be paid. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Yes, I believe there is. Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin, who, as Finance Minister, used to pay it 
     <lb/>
     once, will probably tell us about that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin In connection with that, prior to the 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government the Railway 
     <lb/>
     received $500,000 a year in subsidy. When the 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government came in they 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     received $250,000. That was $250,000 dif<lb break="no"/>ference as regards Commission of Government 
     <lb/>
     and the days prior to that. The $250,000 was out 
     <lb/>
     of one pocket into another, and the Railway 
     <lb/>
     would have been much better off if it had got that 
     <lb/>
     extra quarter of a million dollars. No one brought 
     <lb/>
     up the fact that the government advanced $18 
     <lb/>
     million since 1920-21.... I feel the boats should 
     <lb/>
     continue to get subsidies, particularly since war<lb break="no"/>time, because the cost of operations have gone 
     <lb/>
     up. The cost of coal has gone up 100%. I under<lb break="no"/>stand there is a plan on now to convert the railway 
     <lb/>
     to oil. Coal costs $1.5 to $2 million a year — $18 
     <lb/>
     a ton. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Coal — 70,000 tons costing 
     <lb/>
     $18.50. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin That is $1,300,000 — an additional 
     <lb/>
     charge of $600,000. Now I understand they are 
     <lb/>
     going to convert to fuel oil and hope to save 
     <lb/>
     $500,000 a year. Under present circumstances 
     <lb/>
     and business conditions, it is going to cost 
     <lb/>
     $750,000 a year from the treasury unless they cut 
     <lb/>
     expenses to the bone. Those Clarenville ships<ref target="#fn_05">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     should be segregated from the Railway. All boats 
     <lb/>
     not connecting with the railway system should be 
     <lb/>
     clear of the Railway. They will find the Auditor 
     <lb/>
     General condemning the whole accounting sys<lb break="no"/>tem of the Railway. You will find an $80,000 
     <lb/>
     mistake, even if it is shown over. That is caused 
     <lb/>
     by subsidiaries — the dock is making money, 
     <lb/>
     shipping losing money. The dock is kept up by 
     <lb/>
     the ships. If they put a ship on the dock they credit 
     <lb/>
     it to the dock. If they put a locomotive in the 
     <lb/>
     machine shop, they credit it to the machine shop. 
     <lb/>
     It is all one pool. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Another point, in 1939-40, shortly after the 
     <lb/>
     outbreak of war, the government gave the Rail<lb break="no"/>way $500,000 out of the Colonial Development 
     <lb/>
     Fund to build a dock at Port-aux-Basques and a 
     <lb/>
     dock at St. John's. The balance of the Colonial 
     <lb/>
     Development Fund still owing was wiped out by 
     <lb/>
     the British government, yet I notice the Railway 
     <lb/>
     is being charged with interest on a debt that has 
     <lb/>
     been cancelled. I presume there is some explana<lb break="no"/>tion for it. I think the Railway situation today has   
     <lb/>
     to be handled with care. Let us look at it this way; 
     <lb/>
     they paid $5,400,000 in wages, and 30% of that 
     <lb/>
     comes back in customs duties — $1.5 million. 
     <lb/>
     The Railway costs $1.75 million, therefore the 
     <lb/>
         
   
<note xml:id="fn_05">1 A class of wooden motor vessels built during the war, 1939—1945, at a government shipyard at Clarenville, 
     <lb/>
     Trinity Bay.</note>

            <pb n="226"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0226.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">226</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
          

     $700,000 is wiped out. It is a net value to the 
     <lb/>
     treasury of $1 million. If you take off the customs 
     <lb/>
     duties you have to take off the $700,000. I think 
     <lb/>
     that $700,000 is conservative. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Commenting on Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin's remarks, I would like to point out that 
     <lb/>
     this $700,000 is only the average amount that the 
     <lb/>
     government has had to pay to the Railway each 
     <lb/>
     year since 1923. It is not the actual losses of the 
     <lb/>
     Railway at all. The loss last year was $1 million; 
     <lb/>
     this year it is going to be $1.5 million. Comment<lb break="no"/>ing on another point raised by Major Cashin, he 
     <lb/>
     is right. In 1940 the government owed the 
     <lb/>
     Colonial Development Fund $2,794,000 of the 
     <lb/>
     $4.5 million they borrowed. In 1940 the Colonial 
     <lb/>
     Development Fund cancelled that debt. Included 
     <lb/>
     in that was an amount of $600,000 that the 
     <lb/>
     government borrowed from the Fund to give to 
     <lb/>
     the Railway to build a paper shed and pier at 
     <lb/>
     Port-aux-Basques ($300,000) and one at St. 
     <lb/>
     John's ($300,000). That was included in the 
     <lb/>
     $2.75 million cancelled in 1940. Yet, since 1940, 
     <lb/>
     the Finance Department has been collecting from 
     <lb/>
     the Railway the interest on that loan. It is only an 
     <lb/>
     amount of between $3,000 and $4,000 and as 
     <lb/>
     they have been dealing in millions, I suppose they 
     <lb/>
     have not paid much attention to it. With regard to 
     <lb/>
     the additional cost, during the war years they did 
     <lb/>
     make a profit each year. Their costs now begin to 
     <lb/>
     rise and today we find the cost of wages has 
     <lb/>
     increased 60%, steel, coal and other purchases 
     <lb/>
     have advanced close to 100%. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Jackman Have the freight rates been ad<lb break="no"/>justed to meet the rising costs? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Not in late years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Jackman How can you have a profit if you 
     <lb/>
     do not match your rates to meet the increased 
     <lb/>
     costs? If you are going to have increased costs, 
     <lb/>
     you must have increased freight rates and in<lb break="no"/>creased passenger rates. My opinion is that there 
     <lb/>
     is a deliberate policy to foist the Railway on us 
     <lb/>
     as a white elephant, and it is going to be used as 
     <lb/>
     a political issue either for confederation with 
     <lb/>
     Canada or Commission of Government. If this 
     <lb/>
     Convention is going to resolve itself into a dollars 
     <lb/>
     and cents Convention, I am going to fight it. 
     <lb/>
     Remember the human element is important. It 
     <lb/>
     was not dollars and cents that won the war. We 
     <lb/>
     won the war but we have lost the peace. I suggest 
     <lb/>
     freight rates and passenger rates be increased to 
     <lb/>
     meet the cost. The people will pay. They are 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
           
     paying the excess profit tax. We must remember 
     <lb/>
     it is not dollars and cents which count, it is the 
     <lb/>
     credit of the country. If the Railway is losing 
     <lb/>
     money, and losing it through not raising freight 
     <lb/>
     rates and passenger rates they should raise them. 
     <lb/>
     People are going to pay, anyway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hillier I did not happen to be here at the 
     <lb/>
     opening of this debate, but I have listened with 
     <lb/>
     great interest to the various speakers and I find 
     <lb/>
     figures are very interesting things, but I feel as 
     <lb/>
     we have a lot of reports yet to consider and if we 
     <lb/>
     spend so much time debating each report, we will 
     <lb/>
     get through in the New Year of 1948.... The 
     <lb/>
     question is, what has the government to con<lb break="no"/>tribute to the Railway to keep it going? It is 
     <lb/>
     earning something. The Railway is a necessity. 
     <lb/>
     We have to consider income and expenses, but 
     <lb/>
     we should be as brief as possible in debating. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Northcott I think Mr. Jackman struck the 
     <lb/>nail on the head. If I have 100 pounds of freight 
     <lb/>landed at Lewisporte it will cost 78 cents; if I have 
     <lb/>a carload lot, I will get it for 39 cents. If the AND 
     <lb/>Co. has a carload lot, they get it for 16 cents per 
     <lb/>l00 lbs. I have no money; they have. Same thing 
     <lb/>applies to Bowaters. We are giving them too big 
     <lb/>a concession. We can pick up a lot of money 
     <lb/>there, maybe $30,000 or $40,000 a year. The time 
     <lb/>has come when we should. It is true they own 
     <lb/>their cars; it is also true that they pay 16 cents per 
     <lb/>100 lbs. I think the same concession applies to 
     <lb/>Bowaters and I think Imperial Oil are getting 
     <lb/>their cars hauled back from Gander without 
     <lb/>charge. I do not think it is fair. There is need of 
     <lb/>an adjustment there, and a large one. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job Do these figures of the cost include the 
     <lb/>
     profits derived from the dry dock, which must 
     <lb/>
     have been considerable, and from the number of 
     <lb/>
     chartered steamers? We know these profits from 
     <lb/>
     the dry dock and from chartered steamers are 
     <lb/>
     going to be reduced to almost nothing in the 
     <lb/>
     future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood For every year, 1940-45-46, 
     <lb/>
     earnings means earnings from every conceivable 
     <lb/>
     source.... Actually during the war $600,000 profit 
     <lb/>
     was made in the chartering of outside steamers. 
     <lb/>
     So far as the dock is concerned the figures are 
     <lb/>
     here. In normal times the dock comes pretty close 
     <lb/>
     to breaking even. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job There, again, they pay duty on imports 
     <lb/>
     of plating. ldo not see how they expect to be able 
     <lb/>
     to compete with other places. With that extra cost 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="227"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0227.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">227</fw>
          
     of repairs a ship will go on to Halifax for repairs 
     <lb/>
     instead. It seems a very wrong system, charging 
     <lb/>
     on that plating. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood They charge duty only on small 
     <lb/>
     things and also on ordinary maintenance 
     <lb/>
     materials, not on locomotives, rolling stock or 
     <lb/>
     steel rails. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary continued reading the report]</hi> 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Higgins What does the re-railing mean? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood Mr. Russell informs us that the 
     <lb/>main line of railway has got to be re-railed — not 
     <lb/>the branch lines. But the rails which are taken up 
     <lb/>from the main line could be used on the branch 
     <lb/>lines. Estimated cost replacement of rail (for six 
     <lb/>years) $600,000.<ref target="#fn_06">[1]</ref> It was suggested to me, not by 
     <lb/>the Railway, but by others, that this was on the 
     <lb/>optimistic side, and that it might cost more than 
     <lb/>that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To convert to oil will cost $1 million. They 
     <lb/>
     hope to have it done before 1947 is over.... I may 
     <lb/>
     say the government has not yet made any appro<lb break="no"/>priation for this outlay, but it is a definite policy 
     <lb/>
     adopted by the Railway and approved by the 
     <lb/>
     government.... Similarly with the steamers. They 
     <lb/>
     have ordered the steamers — that's a definite 
     <lb/>
     commitment, but nothing has been paid on them 
     <lb/>
     as yet, and the total cost is to be $2.5 million. 
     <lb/>
     Then they have to buy seven new locomotive 
     <lb/>
     engines, and that will run to $445,000; freight 
     <lb/>
     equipment, another $250,000; $4.2 million and 
     <lb/>
     $3.6 million for rail relaying is roughly $8 mil<lb break="no"/>lion. That's capital outlay to be made on the 
     <lb/>
     railway in the course of the next two to six years. 
     <lb/>
     I think perhaps that covers the section we just 
     <lb/>
     read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins You say also that operating losses 
     <lb/>
     are likely to increase rather than decline. Is that a 
     <lb/>
     definite understanding? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Yes, because costs of materials 
     <lb/>
     are still rising. Take, for instance, shipping. I 
     <lb/>
     understand all controls on shipping in Canada 
     <lb/>
     and the United States are abolished. During the 
     <lb/>
     war the shipping boards controlled all shipping, 
     <lb/>
     and now it has become more difficult than ever.... 
     <lb/>
     The costs are still going up, and other costs are 
     <lb/>
     climbing steadily. So long as they do, the losses 
     <lb/>
     in the operation of the Railway must go on in<lb break="no"/>creasing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins Have you any estimate of what the 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     increase is likely to be? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood No, it would be a pretty dif<lb break="no"/>ficult thing to do. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett That point raised by Mr. Higgins 
     <lb/>
     interests me very much too. The Committee say, 
     <lb/>
     "Apart from capital expenditures we are im<lb break="no"/>pressed by the probability that operating costs are 
     <lb/>
     likely to increase rather than decline".<ref target="#fn_07">[2]</ref> I under<lb break="no"/>stood the idea of these improvements was to cut 
     <lb/>
     down on the operating expense. In view of that, 
     <lb/>
     why are they impressed that we are liable to get 
     <lb/>
     greater operating expense in the future? I want 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood to understand that I am not get<lb break="no"/>ting up in any critical way at all. I think your 
     <lb/>
     report is excellent, but there are certain things I 
     <lb/>
     cannot understand, and this is one of them. Why 
     <lb/>
     should the Committee say that we are headed for 
     <lb/>
     increased operating expenses? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I appreciate what Mr. Hollett 
     <lb/>
     says, and believe he does not rise in any critical 
     <lb/>
     spirit, and I am grateful to him for his words about 
     <lb/>
     our report. I am acting merely as spokesman for 
     <lb/>
     a Committee of ten gentlemen, one of whom is 
     <lb/>
     no longer a member of the Committee, namely 
     <lb/>
     our Chairman, Mr. Bradley. We did work hard, 
     <lb/>
     there is no question of that, and there is a tremen<lb break="no"/>dous amount of knowledge here which we our<lb break="no"/>selves may not have digested properly.... The 
     <lb/>
     particular question is in paragraph 4, "Apart from 
     <lb/>
     Capital Expenditure, etc." I tell you one thing, for 
     <lb/>
     example. We have 4,000 men working on that 
     <lb/>
     railway. I am convinced that the standard of life 
     <lb/>
     of these 4,000 railroad men must go up, not down, 
     <lb/>
     and that will give you greater operating costs. I 
     <lb/>
     am not a railroad man, but 4,000 of our people 
     <lb/>
     are operating that railway for the benefit of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, and I contend that it should not be 
     <lb/>
     operated at the expense of these men or their 
     <lb/>
     families. Their first charge should be a living 
     <lb/>
     wage, and a decent standard of life for everyone 
     <lb/>
     who is working on it, and if we agree to that, 
     <lb/>
     wages must go up or the cost of living must go 
     <lb/>
     down. The main point is that these men, as the 
     <lb/>
     men in the mills in Grand Falls and Corner Brook 
     <lb/>
     and the mines at Buchans and Bell Island, work<lb break="no"/>ing the public utilities for the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, are just as much entitled to a decent 
     <lb/>
     standard of life as anyone else. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett I think that is the only reason. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<note xml:id="fn_06">1 Volume II: 118. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

<note xml:id="fn_07">2 Volume II:106. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

            <pb n="228"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0228.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">228</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
           
 <p>
     Mr. Smallwood No, that's not the reason. As I 
     <lb/>
     have said ad nauseam, the cost of material is still 
     <lb/>
     rising. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Bailey As a member of that Committee, as 
     <lb/>
     far as I can find out there will be a sharp rise 
     <lb/>
     during the coming year, but after that I have not 
     <lb/>
     the least doubt that there will be an easing of the 
     <lb/>
     situation. Of course, while we were with the 
     <lb/>
     railroad, the negotiations for the increased wages 
     <lb/>
     were not on, although we were informed that 
     <lb/>
     there were rumours that it probably would come. 
     <lb/>
     I could not see myself where they could keep 
     <lb/>
     within the bounds of what they showed us.... I 
     <lb/>
     know it is very difficult to arrive at it in dollars 
     <lb/>
     and cents, but we could not get along without it, 
     <lb/>
     and from facts and figures we received, I believe 
     <lb/>
     that if something turned up along the line of 
     <lb/>
     railroad that would give us another Corner Brook 
     <lb/>
     or Grand Falls, it would cease being a liability 
     <lb/>
     and balance its books.... The bulk of the earnings 
     <lb/>
     are from here to Corner Brook and Grand Falls, 
     <lb/>
     and from Port-aux-Basques to Corner Brook. The 
     <lb/>
     rest of the railroad is a liability to the country.... 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Fudge Getting back to the Railway expen<lb break="no"/>diture, I see nothing in the report as to the amount 
     <lb/>of money being paid out by the government in the 
     <lb/>way of claims and losses. I think that there is quite 
     <lb/>a considerable amount paid in claims, and what 
     <lb/>are the causes of these claims? Is the property 
     <lb/>being rough-handled?.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Does Mr. Fudge direct that 
     <lb/>
     question at me? In the matter of claims, this is one 
     <lb/>
     out of 17,598 other items. We only examined one 
     <lb/>
     or two items, and that was not one of them. The 
     <lb/>
     total expense is $12 million, and included in that 
     <lb/>
     is what they paid out in claims. That is as near as 
     <lb/>
     I can go to answering Mr. Fudge. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Fudge The point I am getting at, is that if 
     <lb/>
     we knew the amount paid in claims, we could 
     <lb/>
     deduct that from the total and perhaps find out 
     <lb/>
     why that amount is being paid out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I would undertake to get the 
     <lb/>
     total figure of claims in any particular year in 
     <lb/>
     which they have figured... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Fudge It costs somebody something. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood It costs the Railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Figary As far as that is concerned, it is only 
     <lb/>
     a few days ago we had a conference with the 
     <lb/>
     management of the Railway, and they told us that 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     $80,000 was paid out on one terminal only of the 
     <lb/>
     railway last year. Mr. Russell believes that this is 
     <lb/>
     due to pilfering, and he impressed on us the 
     <lb/>
     necessity of having this cut out. If this is the 
     <lb/>
     amount for one terminal, then what about the 
     <lb/>
     rest? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Fudge In View of that can you wonder that 
     <lb/>
     the Railway is in debt? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Reddy Mr. Fudge's idea there about the 
     <lb/>
     claims on the Railway and what it is costing is a 
     <lb/>
     very important question. As Mr. Figary says, it is 
     <lb/>
     pilfering and I think the Railway management 
     <lb/>
     should stop it. Not only pilfering, but careless 
     <lb/>
     management on the part of the Railway is causing 
     <lb/>
     these claims. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett Mr. Chairman, on page 8 of the first 
     <lb/>
     appendix, which you say has been furnished you 
     <lb/>
     by the Railway, paragraph 3, there is reference 
     <lb/>
     made to the special rates paid by certain com<lb break="no"/>panies....<ref target="#fn_08">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood If Mr. Hollett will excuse me, 
     <lb/>
     that is in the section we are going to read now. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Hollett Certainly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read from page 7, Special Obser<lb break="no"/>vations]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Mr. Chairman, there is very 
     <lb/>
     little that need be said by us about that because 
     <lb/>
     there is a memorandum which you will find on 
     <lb/>
     your desks, sent to the Committee today by the 
     <lb/>
     management of the Railway, which I think ex<lb break="no"/>plains it. I would like here to pay tribute to Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Watton, the Secretary of the Committee, who 
     <lb/>
     went to enormous trouble and labour to obtain 
     <lb/>
     these figures from the Railway. We were in<lb break="no"/>formed that the Buchans Mining Co., the AND 
     <lb/>
     Co., Shell Oil and Imperial Oil were getting 
     <lb/>
     special rates for hauling their wood, paper, ore 
     <lb/>
     and oil, and we went to special pains to get these 
     <lb/>
     figures. We got the special rates, but where we 
     <lb/>
     did fall into an error was in this respect: they gave 
     <lb/>
     us the special carload rates, and what we did was 
     <lb/>
     compare the rates that these companies get with 
     <lb/>
     the carload rate. What we ought to have done was 
     <lb/>
     to compare their special rates not with the carload 
     <lb/>
     rate but with the trainload rate. If a man gets 
     <lb/>
     carload rate, the practice is for him to load and 
     <lb/>
     unload the car himself, but in the case of a train<lb break="no"/>load you have a different situation altogether. Or 
     <lb/>
     maybe it is the other way around, anyway the 
     <lb/>
           
   
<note xml:id="fn_08">1 Volume II:106. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
     
            <pb n="229"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0229.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">229</fw>

           point I am trying to make is that we compared <lb/>two things that were not comparable...<lb/>

<hi rendition="simple:italic">[There followed a lengthy discussion of the spe<lb break="no"/><cb/>cial freight rates charged to certain companies. 
     <lb/>
     The committee rose and reported progress and 
     <lb/>
     the Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

   <!-- GL, 2017-03-03, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


            <!--<p>
     January 9, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. Chairman Orders of the day. Mr. <lb/>Smallwood to move that the Commissioner for<lb/>Public Utilities be invited to appear before the<lb/>Convention, in public or private session as he<lb/>shall prefer, to present an account of the facts of<lb/>the financing of Gander, and to be interrogated<lb/>thereon.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Mr. Smallwood Mr. Chairman, I feel that the<lb/>motion is self-explanatory and it does not need<lb/>any Verbal defence whatever. I think we all are<lb/>agreed that we are not satisfied that we have the<lb/>complete story of Gander. We do not know who<lb/>is responsible for the debt to be incurred, and for<lb/>that reason I move the motion.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Fowler I feel very much in favour of Mr.<lb/>Smallwood's motion and take pleasure in<lb/>seconding it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Job Mr. Chairman, I support the resolution <lb/>proposed by Mr. Smallwood, and take the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity to make a few remarks on the subject which<lb/>I think is allied to the resolution. My view for<lb/>some time has been that we shall not make serious<lb/>progress in helping to remedy certain existing<lb/>defects in the economic position of New<lb break="no"/>foundland until we, as Newfoundlanders, are able<lb/>to sit down at a round table conference with<lb/>appointed representatives of Great Britain,<lb/>Canada and the United States of America, to<lb/>discuss not only the question of operation of<lb/>airports, and the concessions already given and<lb/>asked for in connection with defence bases, but<lb/>also our general economic position. As you are<lb/>probably aware by this time, I am of the opinion<lb/>that we should on every possible occasion stress<lb/>the fact that our valuable strategic position is<lb/>being utilised by Canada, the USA and Great<lb/>Britain for defence and other purposes, without<lb/>any material return to Newfoundland for its use,<lb/>and without any consultation with the people of<lb/>Newfoundland.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>At a round table conference, at which real<lb/>representatives of Newfoundland should be<lb/>present, these questions could be thrashed out and<lb/>the case for Newfoundland could be properly<lb/>presented. Our position is such a strong one, that<lb/>if properly impressed it could not fail to appeal<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>to our American and Canadian friends, who are<lb/>anxious to continue to utilise to the utmost for<lb/>their own important purposes, the valuable<lb/>facilities arising from our strategic position.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The ace card we hold for negotiations in con<lb break="no"/>nection with the future prosperity of New<lb break="no"/>foundland consists of her strategic position. Our<lb/>problem is in my opinion an economic one, and<lb/>not as some people seem to imagine, mainly a<lb/>political one. The sooner an attempt is made to<lb/>secure such a joint conference the better, and its<lb/>object should be to discuss the degree of assis<lb break="no"/>tance, by tariff concessions or otherwise, to<lb/>which Newfoundland is entitled, in exchange for<lb/>utilisation of her strategic position for the benefit<lb/>mainly of Canada, USA and Great Britain. I make<lb/>no apology for repeatedly stressing this view<lb break="no"/>point, and on some suitable occasion hope to<lb/>place before the Convention some definite plan<lb/>of action to secure such a conference as that<lb/>proposed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Ashbourne I am in favour of this motion<lb/>and I support it, but it has occurred to me that<lb/>there may be other matters which the members<lb/>might want to take up with the Commissioner for<lb/>Public Utilities. According to the motion as<lb/>worded this interview would relate to Gander<lb/>airport and would, unless amended, debar the<lb/>consideration of other matters; possibly Mr.<lb/>Smallwood could enlarge the motion to include<lb/>any other matters of public concern any member<lb/>might wish to bring before him at this time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. SmallwoodI am prepared to accede to Mr.<lb/>Ashboume's suggestion. The only thing is we<lb/>ought to be specific. We ask the Commissioner<lb/>to come and give a certain explanation about one<lb/>particular thing; we cannot add "such other mat<lb break="no"/>ters as we would wish to discuss." We would<lb/>have to be specific so that he could bring along<lb/>other data on the matters to be discussed. If the<lb/>house wants to add any other topic to be discussed<lb/>with the Commissioner, I am agreeable to that.<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>Mr. Chairman If Mr. Ashbourne wishes to<lb/>make an amendment, that would be in order, but<lb/>as Mr. Smallwood has pointed out, we cannot<lb/>obviously invite the Commissioner here and <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>