<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-12-01"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-12-01">1 December 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="899" to="915"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0899.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0900.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0901.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0902.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0903.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0904.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0905.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0906.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0907.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0908.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0909.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0910.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0911.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0912.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0913.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0914.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0915.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-08-02">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-08-02">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0899">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0899.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0900">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0900.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0901">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0901.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0902">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0902.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0903">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0903.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0904">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0904.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0905">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0905.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0906">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0906.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0907">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0907.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0908">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0908.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0909">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0909.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0910">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0910.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0911">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0911.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0912">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0912.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0913">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0913.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0914">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0914.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0915">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0915.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="899"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0899.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">899</fw>
            
<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">December 1, 1947</head>
</div>

<div type="section">
<p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I give notice that I will on 
     <lb/>
     tomorrow ask His Excellency the Governor in 
     <lb/>
     Commission to ask the Government of Canada to 
     <lb/>
     state whether, in the event of union and the con<lb break="no"/>sequent operation of the Newfoundland railway 
     <lb/>
     and steamship system by Canada, it would be the 
     <lb/>
     policy of the Government of Canada to continue 
     <lb/>
     in their employment all the employees of the 
     <lb/>
     system at the time of union, with the rights and 
     <lb/>
     privileges with respect to continuity of employ<lb break="no"/>ment that are accorded to employees of the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian National Railways. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Mr. Chairman, I should like to bring 
     <lb/>
     to the attention of the delegates and to the country 
     <lb/>
     an article which appeared in a local newspaper 
     <lb/>
     on Saturday last, November 29. It reads as fol<lb break="no"/>lows and is captioned: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Duplessis is to Challenge Decision 
     <lb/>
     by Privy Council</hi> 

            </p>

            <p>
     Quebec, November 29: Formal notice has 
     <lb/>
     been served upon Ottawa, Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     and the Privy Council that this province ap<lb break="no"/>parently does not consider that the judgment 
     <lb/>
     rendered by the Council about twenty years 
     <lb/>
     ago, taking part of Labrador away from 
     <lb/>
     Quebec and awarding it to Newfoundland, 
     <lb/>
     constitutes a final settlement of this highly 
     <lb/>
     controversial issue. Quebec's newsy 
     <lb/>
     premier, Hon. Maurice Duplessis revealed 
     <lb/>
     this at a press conference yesterday after<lb break="no"/>noon, when he referred to the mineral pos<lb break="no"/>sibilities and probabilities of Ungava, or New 
     <lb/>
     Quebec, much of which is located in 
     <lb/>
     Labrador. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "This great mineral wealth uncovered is 
     <lb/>
     particularly important, and we are pleased to 
     <lb/>
     say that two-thirds of this vast territory incon<lb break="no"/>testably is located in the Province of 
     <lb/>
     Quebec," said Mr. Duplessis, who then went 
     <lb/>
     on to make an unusually important statement, 
     <lb/>
     when he declared that "One-third is a ter<lb break="no"/>ritory upon which we consider that we have 
     <lb/>
     rights." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     He referred to this one-third in question at 
     <lb/>
     another point as "One third which was at<lb break="no"/>tributed by a judgment of the Privy Council 
     <lb/>
     and by the present federal government to the 
     <lb/>
     colony of Newfoundland." The whole matter 
     <lb/>
     came up when the premier told reporters that 
     <lb/>
     he had just received a visit from J. I. Rankin, 
    

            <cb/>
    

     the managing director of N.A. Timmins, 
     <lb/>
     Regd., the Timmins Interests, and those con<lb break="no"/>trolling the Hollinger North Shore Explora<lb break="no"/>tion Co. Ltd., which firm is doing the mineral 
     <lb/>
     exploration and exploitation work in Un<lb break="no"/>gava. Mr. Duplessis goes on, "The first 
     <lb/>
     reports of the work which I have just received 
     <lb/>
     indicate that tons of unsurpassable mineral 
     <lb/>
     wealth was found and this is only the result 
     <lb/>
     of the investigation which relatively speak<lb break="no"/>ing was a most incomplete one...." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Asked exactly what minerals had been 
     <lb/>
    uncovered, the premier replied, "Vast quan<lb break="no"/>tities of mineral ore, iron most definitely and 
     <lb/>I think gold and possibly other minerals too. 
     <lb/>I did not get detailed information to any 
     <lb/>extent." He goes on, "The results to date are 
     <lb/>all the more remarkable and the future pos<lb break="no"/>sibilities and probabilities extraordinary", he 
     <lb/>pointed out, "when it is considered that the 
     <lb/>Hollinger interests are working only a por<lb break="no"/>tion of a section of 1,500 square miles out of 
     <lb/>the entire New Quebec or Ungava Territory, 
     <lb/>which has an area of more than 311,000 
     <lb/>square miles." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. Duplessis</persName> recalled that all this vast 
     <lb/>
     and exceptionally rich territory of more than 
     <lb/>
     300,000 square miles had remained absolute<lb break="no"/>ly unproductive until the National Union as<lb break="no"/>sumed office for a second time in 1944.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     He terminated his statement by reiterat<lb break="no"/>ing, "Quebec intends remaining the mistress 
     <lb/>
     in her own home and running her own affairs, 
     <lb/>
     and with the vast industrial expansion which 
     <lb/>
     this province definitely established, you can 
     <lb/>
     see how important it is to this province in 
     <lb/>
     particular but to Canada as a whole also, that 
     <lb/>
     we remain masters in our own house and 
     <lb/>
     continue to administer our own affairs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>


            <p>
     I cannot say what my fellow delegates may 
     <lb/>
     think of this, but to me it seems a most extraordi<lb break="no"/>nary statement for the Prime Minister of Quebec 
     <lb/>
     to make. Goodness knows, this whole Conven<lb break="no"/>tion set-up is bewildering enough. The political 
     <lb/>
     fog in which our people are enshrouded today is 
     <lb/>
     dense enough, without adding to our confusion 
     <lb/>
     by the injection of this sort of thing. At the very 
     <lb/>
     beginning of these so-called terms from Ottawa, 
     <lb/>
     as contained in the Grey Book, we find in section 
     <lb/>
     2 the following: "The province of Newfoundland 


            <pb n="900"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0900.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">900</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
          

     will include the territory of Labrador defined by 
     <lb/>
     the award of the Judicial Committee of the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council in 1927 as Newfoundland territory." 
     <lb/>
     There we have a definite, clear-cut statement by 
     <lb/>
     the Ottawa government. Yet here we have at the 
     <lb/>
     same time the Quebec provincial government, 
     <lb/>
     representative, mind you, of approximately one- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     third of the population of Canada, and repre<lb break="no"/>senting a political balance of power in the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian Parliament, saying that they deny this 
     <lb/>
     statement — that they refuse to acknowledge 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland as being the legal owner of this 
     <lb/>
     territory, and that they are going to do everything 
     <lb/>
     in their power to take it from us. If the cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances were different, my first impulse 
     <lb/>
     would be to ask the Commission government 
     <lb/>
     what this whole thing means. But I know that I 
     <lb/>
     would be only wasting my time, because they 
     <lb/>
     would not tell me. Only a few days ago, they were 
     <lb/>
     asked whether we could regard the agreement 
     <lb/>
     made between the Government of Great Britain 
     <lb/>
     and our own government in 1933 as being at 
     <lb/>
     present valid and effective, and if it were to be 
     <lb/>
     followed out, and they came back with the reply 
     <lb/>
     that in effect it was none of our business. Here we 
     <lb/>
     have a solemn agreement made between two 
     <lb/>
     governments, whereby we surrendered our 
     <lb/>
     sovereignty upon certain specific terms and 
     <lb/>
     which provided for the return of our lost political 
     <lb/>
     life; and we are told that we should not talk about 
     <lb/>
     it, that it is not within the province of us repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of the Newfoundland people even to 
     <lb/>
     discuss it. Using the words of Winston Churchill, 
     <lb/>
     "What kind of people do they think we are?" Do 
     <lb/>
     they think we are so many children to be trifled 
     <lb/>
     with? Do they think we do not know the nature 
     <lb/>
     of a contract, and the sacred moral and legal 
     <lb/>
     obligations which it entails and which are im<lb break="no"/>posed upon the parties? It seems to me that it is 
     <lb/>
     time we ceased to allow ourselves, or our people, 
     <lb/>
     to be used for the foolish purposes of this debat<lb break="no"/>ing society. It is time that we realised that we have 
     <lb/>
     greater duties, greater responsibilities, greater 
     <lb/>
     obligations than those which have been imposed 
     <lb/>
     upon us by this narrow, farcical Convention and 
     <lb/>
     its narrower terms of reference. How can we 
     <lb/>
     place any dependence, any faith upon any agree<lb break="no"/>ment or promise made to us by any government 
     <lb/>
     of Canada or, for that matter any other country, 
     <lb/>
     when we see an attempt being made, as in this 
     <lb/>
     case, to tear these terms of reference to bits before 


            <cb/>
          

     we have even finished reading them? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But the point I wish to make is this: it is 
     <lb/>
     impossible for us to blind our eyes to the fact that 
     <lb/>
     we are obviously holding discussions with a 
     <lb/>
     country a third of whose people openly and 
     <lb/>
     brazenly declare they will refuse to honour the 
     <lb/>
     terms now before the Chair — who openly tell 
     <lb/>
     the world that they are going to spare no effort to 
     <lb/>
     rob us of our rich Labrador territory. I ask my 
     <lb/>
     fellow delegates: are they prepared to consider 
     <lb/>
     doing business on that basis? Are they prepared 
     <lb/>
     to discuss terms with a people who have openly 
     <lb/>
     shown their unfriendliness — who declare that 
     <lb/>
     regardless of all laws, their purpose is to wrest 
     <lb/>
     from us that which is ours? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Under the circumstances, if we have respect 
     <lb/>
     for ourselves, if we are sincere in our desire to 
     <lb/>
     faithfully protect the interests of the people who 
     <lb/>
     sent us here, we must seriously consider the 
     <lb/>
     matter of throwing this confederation business 
     <lb/>
     out of this chamber, and to have no more parley 
     <lb/>
     with a people who threaten our well-being — 
     <lb/>
     who in effect are set on a campaign to steal away 
     <lb/>
     our people's wealth.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are witnessing a spectacle which has been 
     <lb/>
     repeated many times in the history of small 
     <lb/>
     countries. It is the old story of the covetous eyes 
     <lb/>
     and the greedy hands of bigger and more power<lb break="no"/>ful countries coveting the wealth and the assets 
     <lb/>
     of the smaller country. Sometimes the big fellow 
     <lb/>
     gets what he wants by political trickery, some<lb break="no"/>times he gets it by threats and pressure; and 
     <lb/>
     failing these, he takes it by brute force. In our 
     <lb/>
     Labrador possession, through the goodness of 
     <lb/>
     Providence, we have been given a source of 
     <lb/>
     untold wealth, a means by which this country can 
     <lb/>
     obtain and hold a continued prosperity. How 
     <lb/>
     long, I ask you, do you think this wealth will be 
     <lb/>
     ours if we once found ourselves in the hands of 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian government? I tell you that it would 
     <lb/>
     be only so long as they could rig up the necessary 
     <lb/>
     legal machinery to euchre us out of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is all too clear now that the key to this whole 
     <lb/>
     mystery is the desire of Canada to take from us 
     <lb/>
     our Labrador wealth. It explains everything — 
     <lb/>
     baby bonuses, old age pensions and all the rest of 
     <lb/>
     it. It is a cheap enough bribe.... I make the state<lb break="no"/>ment now, and I am convinced that time will bear 
     <lb/>
     me out, that this entire business — referendums, 
     <lb/>
     conventions and all the rest of it, has but one main 
     <lb/>
     object, and that is a deliberate and preconceived 
  

            <pb n="901"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0901.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">901</fw>
          

     plot to rob this country of the unexpected wealth 
     <lb/>
     of our Labrador. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I do not think you are entitled to 
     <lb/>
     express that opinion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I will go further and say that the 
     <lb/>
     parties to this plot are the Government of Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain, Canada and our own local Commission, 
     <lb/>
     and to show how recklessly eager they are to see 
     <lb/>
     this plot succeed, we find that they do not hesitate 
     <lb/>
     in throwing overboard the agreement of 1933. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Unless you can lay the founda<lb break="no"/>tion for that statement, I do not think you ought 
     <lb/>to go that far. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I make the statement, and I am 
     <lb/>
     convinced that time will bear me out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That may be. None of us is 
     <lb/>
     omniscient; we cannot say whether time will bear 
     <lb/>
     you out or not. You are making a statement of 
     <lb/>
     fact. I do not think you are justified in doing that 
     <lb/>
     at this time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I want to make it clear that I am not 
     <lb/>
     in the least afraid of discussing these so-called 
     <lb/>
     Canadian terms, for the simple reason that I am 
     <lb/>
     confident that when the people have been shown 
     <lb/>
     how worthless they really are, they will feel about 
     <lb/>
     them as I do. My principal objection to them is 
     <lb/>
     that I see in them only a camouflage, a deceit and 
     <lb/>
     a bait that is being used by those who plot against 
     <lb/>
     our country, to entrap and destroy us. I will show 
     <lb/>
     this Convention, and I will back it with the neces<lb break="no"/>sary proof, that this whole thing had its origin 
     <lb/>
     several years ago. And when the story is told, it 
     <lb/>
     will be a most inglorious one for all parties con<lb break="no"/>cerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName>, it is not my intention to go 
     <lb/>
     further into this matter at the present time. Nor do 
     <lb/>
     I intend to make any motion at the moment. My 
     <lb/>
     object is simply to impress on delegates the hid<lb break="no"/>den significance of this latest move on the part of 
     <lb/>
     the premier of French Canada and to ask my 
     <lb/>
     fellow delegates to give the matter their serious 
     <lb/>
     consideration. Vigilance, it is said, is the price of 
     <lb/>
     safety. Let that then be our watchword. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I have read and studied that ar<lb break="no"/>ticle, Major Cashin. I cannot help expressing the 
     <lb/>
     feeling that for Premier Duplessis it might be 
     <lb/>
     good politics; but in my judgement it is pretty bad 
     <lb/>
     law. How he or anybody else can depart from a 
     <lb/>
     judgement delivered by the Privy Council 20 
     <lb/>
     years ago, I cannot begin to understand. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I agree from the legal standpoint, 
 

            <cb/>
     

     but as I said a few minutes ago, "time will bear 
     <lb/>
     me out". You or I may not be here, but you will 
     <lb/>
     find if we go into confederation with Canada, that 
     <lb/>
     within five years Labrador will be taken from 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I do not know if I am in order 
     <lb/>
     in speaking at this moment any more than Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin was in order. If he was in order, I take it 
     <lb/>
     I am in order. I do not know what business is 
     <lb/>
     before the House. I do not know if there is any 
     <lb/>
     motion before the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There is no motion before the 
     <lb/>
     House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I take it that Major Cashin was 
     <lb/>
     out of order and I am equally out of order, not 
     <lb/>
     more so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I allowed Major Cashin the 
     <lb/>
     latitude of going on; I must allow you the same 
     <lb/>
     latitude, out of order or otherwise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> We were all interested on 
     <lb/>
     Saturday to read in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Evening Telegram</hi> a spe<lb break="no"/>cial despatch from its own correspondent in 
     <lb/>
     Quebec; and to read again this morning in the 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Daily News</hi> a Canadian Press despatch about the 
     <lb/>
     same matter, but with a significant difference. 
     <lb/>
     The story on Saturday said that Duplessis had 
     <lb/>
     declared that he had served notice on the govern<lb break="no"/>ments of Canada and Newfoundland, and on the 
     <lb/>
     Privy Council, of intending to make a move to 
     <lb/>
     offset the judgement of the Privy Council 20 
     <lb/>
     years ago. Whereas in the Canadian Press 
     <lb/>
     despatch in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Daily News</hi> not a single word is 
     <lb/>
     said about Quebec serving notice on the govern<lb break="no"/>ments of Canada and Newfoundland and on the 
     <lb/>
     Privy Council. We do not know Quebec in this 
     <lb/>
     matter. Quebec has nothing to do with it, never 
     <lb/>
     did. We never had any dispute with the Province 
     <lb/>
     of Quebec.... This is a contemptible, completely 
     <lb/>
     contemptible effort, an effort beneath contempt, 
     <lb/>
     beyond contempt, to drag a red herring across the 
     <lb/>
     trail; to create a stink so heavy, so strong — that 
     <lb/>
     is what it is. We in Newfoundland have never had 
     <lb/>
     anything to do with the Province of Quebec or the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Quebec or the premier of Quebec 
     <lb/>
     in the Labrador boundary question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Even if we did, they have been 
     <lb/>
     sleeping 20 years on their rights. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> ....There was a dispute between 
     <lb/>
     the governments of Canada and Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     as to where the boundary of Labrador should lie. 
     <lb/>
     There was the dispute. That dispute came up 40 
 

            <pb n="902"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0902.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="num">902</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> 


     odd years ago — 50 years ago, in the first place... 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Do not go into detail. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am doing this to take the stink, 
     <lb/>
     the smear out of it, to put it in its true perspective. 
     <lb/>
     It came to the point where it could be submitted 
     <lb/>
     to a court.... Finally the governments of New<lb break="no"/>foundland and Canada agreed to submit the mat<lb break="no"/>ter to the highest court in the whole world insofar 
     <lb/>
     as the British Empire and the British Common<lb break="no"/>wealth of Nations is concerned, ... namely the 
     <lb/>
     judicial division of the Privy Council itself.... 
     <lb/>
     Quebec was not in it; she had nothing to do with 
     <lb/>
     it. The Government of Canada engaged its 
     <lb/>
     lawyers and the Government of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     engaged its lawyers. I have read every word of 
     <lb/>
     that evidence. The Judicial Committee handed 
     <lb/>
     down its verdict 20 years ago. What was the 
     <lb/>
     verdict? They could see exactly where the bound<lb break="no"/>ary lay in some respects ... but there was one part 
     <lb/>
     they could not see where the point was, and they 
     <lb/>
     said, "The height of land: find that height of land 
     <lb/>
     and you have the boundary." The Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada accepted that verdict. They had no 
     <lb/>
     choice... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> The House knows that just as well 
     <lb/>
     as you do. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> ....The matter is closed. There 
     <lb/>
     is no one on this earth who could reopen it; it is 
     <lb/>
     settled, finished and finalised. And now we have 
     <lb/>
     it dragged in here, and why? There is an election 
     <lb/>
     on in Quebec. He is not an officer of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada, this slimy politician, this fascist, 
     <lb/>
     this Nazi, this vote-getter. He wants to be re<lb break="no"/>elected, and he has dragged this in as an election 
     <lb/>
     tactic. We know all about election tactics, and we 
     <lb/>
     are asked by Major Cashin to accept what Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Duplessis says as being important when the cold 
     <lb/>
     truth of the matter is the Government of Canada 
     <lb/>
     says, the Province of Newfoundland will include 
     <lb/>
     the territory of Labrador. What territory of 
     <lb/>
     Labrador? The territory of Labrador defined by 
     <lb/>
     the award of the Judicial Committee. Now this 
     <lb/>
     dark, dismal plot that Major Cashin throws at us; 
     <lb/>
     we are not surprised, because Major Cashin can 
     <lb/>
     see plots where no one else can see them...  
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There is no motion before the 
     <lb/>Chair. I was prepared to allow Major Cashin the 
     <lb/>right to express himself on the point, but you are 
     <lb/>not arguing it before the Privy Council. If you 
     <lb/>want to comment on it briefly, I will be glad to 
     <lb/>allow you the right; but as far as I am concerned 
    

            <cb/>
         

     Mr. Duplessis is wasting his time since the party 
     <lb/>
     concerned is the Dominion of Canada, not the 
     <lb/>
     Province of Quebec. The only way in which Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Duplessis could take over Labrador is by forcibly 
     <lb/>
     invading it.... I don't think we ought to waste very 
     <lb/>
     much further time on this. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There will be an awful lot of 
     <lb/>
     time wasted between now and the referendum 
     <lb/>
     about Premier Duplessis and the territory belong<lb break="no"/>ing to our government in Labrador. Our people 
     <lb/>
     are going to hear an awful lot about this because 
     <lb/>
     there has been a grievance there and this is a good 
     <lb/>
     time to ventilate it, as has been done so many 
     <lb/>
     times in the past by politicians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Newspaper reports are of no 
     <lb/>
     concern to me at all. They have no official stand<lb break="no"/>ing. It is true that I did allow Major Cashin to read 
     <lb/>
     it, but from the purely parliamentary standpoint 
     <lb/>
     he had no right to refer to it. After all, a newspaper 
     <lb/>
     report is simply the reporter's conception of what 
     <lb/>
     the thing is. When Major Cashin referred to it I 
     <lb/>
     did not know his purpose, but I think I should 
     <lb/>
     have allowed him a certain amount of latitude by 
     <lb/>
     virtue of the fact that it did headline the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Evening 
     <lb/>
     Telegram</hi> on Saturday afternoon.... I don't think 
     <lb/>
     it is incumbent upon you to try to make out an 
     <lb/>
     indictment against Premier Duplessis. A lot of us 
     <lb/>
     know all about Premier Duplessis. We know his 
     <lb/>
     antipathy to English-speaking people, and he 
     <lb/>
     would cut off if he could, for no other reason, the 
     <lb/>
     entry of Newfoundland, or the United States or 
     <lb/>
     any English-speaking body, so as to allow his 
     <lb/>
     French-Canadians to have all he thinks they 
     <lb/>
     should have. As far as I am concerned, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood, I don't think there is any point in 
     <lb/>
     belabouring the point.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I won't labour the point any 
     <lb/>
     more. I give notice that I will on tomorrow ask 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency the Governor in Commission to 
     <lb/>
     ask the Government of Canada whether the 
     <lb/>
     recently published statements of the Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Duplessis — the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Honourable</hi> Mr. Duplessis... 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Yes, go on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> God help us, God help us. To 
     <lb/>
     ask the Government of Canada whether the 
     <lb/>
     recently published statements of the Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Duplessis, Premier of Quebec, on the Labrador 
     <lb/>
     boundary, modify in any particular the letter and 
     <lb/>
     enclosure of October 29, 1947, of the Right 
     <lb/>
     Honourable the Prime Minister of Canada, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly in clause 2 of the enclosure, which reads 
    

            <pb n="903"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0903.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">903</fw>
         

     as follows: "The Province of Newfoundland will 
     <lb/>
     include the territory of Labrador, defined by the 
     <lb/>
     award of the Judicial Committee of the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council in 1927 as Newfoundland territory." 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There is no motion before the 
     <lb/>
     Chair, Mr. Hollett. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I was about to give notice of ques<lb break="no"/>tion, but I wanted to say a few words about the 
     <lb/>
     question that has been raised 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I am not going to listen to much 
     <lb/>
     more on it, Mr. Hollett. It is decidedly out of 
     <lb/>
     order, although I did allow Mr. Cashin to quote 
     <lb/>
     from a newspaper, which I am not bound to 
     <lb/>
     recognise at all. I am not bound to take notice of 
     <lb/>
     any newspaper reports or anything which is ap<lb break="no"/>parently or allegedly happening in Canada or 
     <lb/>
     anywhere else, but if you are going to be brief, I 
     <lb/>
     suppose... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I will be very brief, sir. I too was 
     <lb/>
     very much perturbed when I saw the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Telegram</hi> on 
     <lb/>
     Saturday.... I immediately prepared a question to 
     <lb/>
     be laid on the table. There is just one other thing 
     <lb/>
     that I want to draw to the attention of this House, 
     <lb/>
     and that is the British North America Act, 1871, 
     <lb/>
     which reads as follows: "Alteration of Limits of 
     <lb/>
     Province", section III: "The Parliament of 
     <lb/>
     Canada may from time to time with the consent 
     <lb/>
     of the Legislature of any Province of the said 
     <lb/>
     Dominion, increase, diminish, or otherwise alter 
     <lb/>
     the limits of such Province, upon such terms and 
     <lb/>
     conditions as may be agreed to by the said Legis<lb break="no"/>lature; and may, with the like consent, make 
     <lb/>
     provision respecting the effect and operation of 
     <lb/>
     any such increase or diminution or alteration of 
     <lb/>
     territory in relation to any province effected 
     <lb/>
     thereby." Which simply means this: if we become 
     <lb/>
     a province of the Dominion of Canada, the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government could alter the limits of the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I know that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> The Canadian government could 
     <lb/>
     alter the limits of the Newfoundland province 
     <lb/>
     with the consent of the Newfoundland legisla<lb break="no"/>ture. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I prefer to put it this way, and it 
     <lb/>
     is the way I was always taught to put it: that the 
     <lb/>
     areas that any province might bring with it into 
     <lb/>
     confederation cannot in any way be abrogated or 
     <lb/>
     taken away by the Parliament of Canada, except 
     <lb/>
     by and with the express consent of the legislature. 
     <lb/>
 </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> That is exactly what I said, and I just 
     <lb/>want to add one further remark before I put my 
     <lb/>question, and that is this: having studied very 
     <lb/>carefully the two Black Books which have been 
     <lb/>brought back by the delegation to Canada, I 
     <lb/>foresee that within the next eight years the finan<lb break="no"/>ces of this country will be in such a rotten state 
     <lb/>that the legislature of Newfoundland will be 
     <lb/>prepared to make any change in the limitation of 
     <lb/>the province. Now this is the question which I 
     <lb/>wish to lay on the table: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Whereas certain statements have ap<lb break="no"/>peared in the press of this country, as well as 
     <lb/>
     in the press of the Province of Quebec, to the 
     <lb/>
     effect that the premier of Quebec has served 
     <lb/>
     formal notice upon the Government of New<lb break="no"/>foundland that the province of Quebec does 
     <lb/>
     not consider that the judgement of the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council in 1927 relative to the boundary 
     <lb/>
     between Quebec-Labrador and Newfound<lb break="no"/>land-Labrador is the final settlement of this 
     <lb/>
     issue, and whereas such statements may have 
     <lb/>
     a considerable bearing upon the deliberations 
     <lb/>
     and recommendations to be made by this 
     <lb/>
     National Convention, I give notice that I will 
     <lb/>
     on tomorrow ask the Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to lay on the table a factual statement as 
     <lb/>
     to whether such formal notice from the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec government has been or has not 
     <lb/>
     received by the said Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the Ottawa Delegation 
     <lb/>
     Proposed Arrangements for the Entry of Newfoundland into Confederation 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, when we rose 
     <lb/>
     on Friday we were at clause 22. I had got about 
     <lb/>
     half way through my explanation of the clause 
     <lb/>
     when the House rose, and so I do not intend now 
     <lb/>
     to take very much time although, as I said then, 
     <lb/>
     this is the most important clause in the entire 


            <cb/>
      

     document. It is no harm to read it again, sir? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I think it would be very ad<lb break="no"/>visable. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Clause 22, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Economic Survey</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Should the government of the province 
     <lb/>institute an economic survey of New<lb break="no"/>
          
            <pb n="904"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0904.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">904</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
         
     foundland with a view to determining what 
     <lb/>
     resources may profitably be developed and 
     <lb/>
     what new industries may be established or 
     <lb/>
     existing industries expanded, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada will make available the ser<lb break="no"/>vices of technical personnel and agencies to 
     <lb/>
     assist in the work. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As soon as may be practicable after union 
     <lb/>
     the Government of Canada will make a spe<lb break="no"/>cial effort to collect and make available 
     <lb/>
     statistical and scientific data about the 
     <lb/>
     natural resources and economy of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, in order to bring such information 
     <lb/>
     up to the standard attained for existing 
     <lb/>
     provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>
     There is a story behind that clause, which the 
     <lb/>
     members no doubt might like to hear. We had got 
     <lb/>
     fairly well along in our talks when I raised what 
     <lb/>
     I thought was a matter of fundamental impor<lb break="no"/>tance to Newfoundland. I said, "Mr. St. Laurent, 
     <lb/>
     as long as I remember I have been hearing a 
     <lb/>
     certain phrase used by people, and that is about 
     <lb/>
     opening the country up — opening up New<lb break="no"/>foundland. That is a sort of old-fashioned, home<lb break="no"/>ly way of saying that we would like to have 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland developed — expanded and 
     <lb/>
     developed. Now", I said, "what would confedera<lb break="no"/>tion do to open up Newfoundland, to open up her 
     <lb/>
     resources, to develop her resources and expand 
     <lb/>
     her economy?" I did not get very far at that first 
     <lb/>
     meeting. One member only of the conference 
     <lb/>
     supported me, and that was the Hon. Brooke 
     <lb/>
     Claxton. I said it again, and still did not get very 
     <lb/>
     far, but at the third one they agreed to insert a 
     <lb/>
     clause covering the situation, and that clause is 
     <lb/>
     here: the Government of Canada would provide 
     <lb/>
     the services of technical personnel and agencies 
     <lb/>
     to assist in the work. In what work? In the work 
     <lb/>
     of making an economic survey of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     to see what resources may be developed, and 
     <lb/>
     what new industries may be established, or exist<lb break="no"/>ing industries expanded, and then it says: "As 
     <lb/>
     soon as may be practicable after union the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada will make a special effort 
     <lb/>
     to collect and make available statistical and 
     <lb/>
     scientific data about the natural resources and 
     <lb/>
     economy of Newfoundland, in order to bring 
     <lb/>
     such information up to the standard attained for 
     <lb/>
     existing provinces." Wherever in these terms the 
     <lb/>
     word "Newfoundland" occurs, that word in<lb break="no"/>cludes Labrador, so that an economic survey of 


            <cb/>
         

     Newfoundland means an economic survey of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland and Newfoundland-Labrador, 
     <lb/>
     and that kind of survey is going to take many 
     <lb/>
     millions of dollars to conduct. It cannot be done, 
     <lb/>
     you cannot scour and scrape the island of New<lb break="no"/>foundland and the 100,000 square miles we own 
     <lb/>
     down there in Labrador, for minerals and water- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     powers and timber and other natural resources 
     <lb/>
     without it taking several years and many millions 
     <lb/>
     of dollars. And that, not family allowances, im<lb break="no"/>portant as they are, not old age pensions, not the 
     <lb/>
     various social security payments that will come 
     <lb/>
     into Newfoundland, and not the subsidies that 
     <lb/>
     will be paid to the government of the province of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. not these things, but this clause 
     <lb/>
     — the economic survey of Newfoundland — is 
     <lb/>
     in my opinion the most important thing in this 
     <lb/>
     entire document. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, I would like to make 
     <lb/>
     a few comments with regard to that particular 
     <lb/>
     section. The first thing I notice is the phrase 
     <lb/>
     "Should the government of the province institute 
     <lb/>
     an economic survey" — "should they". It is 
     <lb/>
     problematical. I go on further: "As soon as may 
     <lb/>
     be practicable" — God only knows when that 
     <lb/>
     will be — "As soon as may be practicable after 
     <lb/>
     union the Government of Canada will make a 
     <lb/>
     special effort to collect and make available statis<lb break="no"/>tical and scientific data about the natural resour<lb break="no"/>ces and economy of Newfoundland, in order to 
     <lb/>
     bring such information up to the standard attained 
     <lb/>
     for existing provinces." Now, I ask members to 
     <lb/>
     fix in their minds the provinces of Nova Scotia, 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick, and Prince Edward Island. They 
     <lb/>
     are existing provinces. they have been there, most 
     <lb/>
     of them, for 70 years. I wonder if Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
     could tell me if this economic survey, which is 
     <lb/>
     the standard for all the provinces in Canada, has 
     <lb/>
     in any way affected the prosperity or otherwise 
     <lb/>
     of, say, Prince Edward Island. Usually, if you 
     <lb/>
     improve the economy of a country the population 
     <lb/>
     of that country increases. Take Prince Edward 
     <lb/>
     Island — the population has hovered around 
     <lb/>
     90,000 for the last 70 years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     One more point, we have had economists in 
     <lb/>
     this country galore. We have had people 
     <lb/>
     prospecting for ore. All the wood we have is now 
     <lb/>
     being exploited, we are catching as much fish as 
     <lb/>
     we can. Did these Ottawa people indicate what 
     <lb/>
     other prospects there might be in this country ... ? 
     <lb/>
     I just raise the point because I don't want anyone 
   

            <pb n="905"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0905.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">905</fw>
          

     to hold out a hope that should the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government decide to make an economic survey 
     <lb/>
     they would do it as soon as practicable. I wonder 
     <lb/>
     if Mr. Smallwood will say a word on that? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Hollett is, whether inten<lb break="no"/>tionally or unintentionally, confusing the two 
     <lb/>
     paragraphs; the first paragraph deals with an 
     <lb/>
     economic survey, and the second paragraph deals 
     <lb/>
     only with a special effort of the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada to collect and make available scientific 
     <lb/>
     data. It is that which is to be done as soon as 
     <lb/>
     practicable after union. The other thing is done 
     <lb/>
     when the provincial government institutes the 
     <lb/>
     survey. The reason is this: ... that if it were not 
     <lb/>
     left to the Government of Newfoundland to in<lb break="no"/>stitute and initiate the economic survey, and the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada stepped in on its own, 
     <lb/>
     immediately what we would be hearing would 
     <lb/>
     be, "Oh, I see, so without a by your leave the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada is going to walk in and 
     <lb/>
     begin surveying your resources". Should the 
     <lb/>
     government of the province start it, then the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada will step in and do the 
     <lb/>
     job, so that no one can say they will ride in here 
     <lb/>
     roughshod, or without permission. It's up to the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Newfoundland.... The other point 
     <lb/>
     is as to Prince Edward Island. We have said a lot 
     <lb/>
     about PEI in the Convention in the last few days. 
     <lb/>
     Is there any need for me to say once more that 
     <lb/>
     PEI, although it is a province, is a little island of 
     <lb/>
     2,000 square miles, one-twentieth the size of the 
     <lb/>
     island of Newfoundland. It is only a large farm. 
     <lb/>
     It has no industries, no natural resources apart 
     <lb/>
     from the soil and the fish in the water. It has no 
     <lb/>
     minerals, no oil, no timber, has no natural resour<lb break="no"/>ces except its very fine soil and the fish surround<lb break="no"/>ing its coast. Therefore, what happens is this: a 
     <lb/>
     man who had a farm in PEI of 50 acres 30 or 40 
     <lb/>
     years ago, inherited it from his father who had 
     <lb/>
     owned 300 acres, and the various sons took 50 
     <lb/>
     acres each. Now he is married and has sons, and 
     <lb/>
     there is not enough land for four or five sons to 
     <lb/>
     live on, so what happens is the oldest sons stay 
     <lb/>
     on, and the younger ones have to get off. When 
     <lb/>
     the population grows to the point where the land 
     <lb/>
     cannot support them, they emigrate to other parts 
     <lb/>
     of Canada, and a good thing it is that they have 
     <lb/>
     other parts to immigrate to. Let's hear no more 
     <lb/>
     about this tiny little Island of Prince Edward's.... 
     <lb/>
     Now one other point Mr. Hollett raised on this 
     <lb/>
     clause. Take the second paragraph: "As soon as 
    

            <cb/>
            

     may be practicable after union". Any member of 
     <lb/>
     the Convention, or any member of the public may 
     <lb/>
     care to think that the Government of Canada is 
     <lb/>
     just putting up a big bluff, only a cod, that they 
     <lb/>
     are a crowd of cheapskates who are trying to bluff 
     <lb/>
     this country; if anyone wishes to believe that he 
     <lb/>
     has a perfect right to believe it. If Mr. Hollett 
     <lb/>
     wishes to believe it, he has a perfect right to, and 
     <lb/>
     if he says that the words, "As soon as practicable 
     <lb/>
     after union the Government of Canada will do 
     <lb/>
     such and such" are not worth the paper they are 
     <lb/>
     written on, he is entitled so to believe. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> What do you think? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am convinced of this, and it 
     <lb/>
     seems to me a very reasonable belief: New<lb break="no"/>foundland as a province of Canada is either going 
     <lb/>
     to be a drag on the Dominion of Canada, or she 
     <lb/>
     is going to pay her way. One or the other. Which 
     <lb/>
     would Canada want?... She would want to step in 
     <lb/>
     and give us a lifting hand that would help us stand 
     <lb/>
     on our own feet and be independent financially 
     <lb/>
     and otherwise. That is what I believe. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I only asked you a question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well that's my answer, and I 
     <lb/>
     stand by it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I would like to make a short com<lb break="no"/>ment on that paragraph, particularly with respect 
     <lb/>
     to the first part. I am a little disappointed in the 
     <lb/>
     wording, and in the interpretation that we were 
     <lb/>
     given in Ottawa, and the interpretation that Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood has given today. In reading the first 
     <lb/>
     part of the first paragraph, it is clearly stated that 
     <lb/>
     should the Government of Newfoundland in<lb break="no"/>stitute an economic survey and request the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada, then the latter will make 
     <lb/>
     available technical personnel or agencies to assist 
     <lb/>
     in the work. It does not say, as I was led to believe, 
     <lb/>
     that the Government of Canada would pay for the 
     <lb/>
     work. It merely says to assist in the work. Now 
     <lb/>
     how much assistance it is going to be, and who is 
     <lb/>
     going to pay for it, is questionable — very ques<lb break="no"/>tionable. They may merely provide the personnel 
     <lb/>
     and the agencies, and we will have to pay for it. 
     <lb/>
     That is the meaning of the paragraph, and I would 
     <lb/>
     challenge Mr. Smallwood to interpret it other<lb break="no"/>wise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I will very gladly do that. If Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Higgins can point to one single solitary case in 
     <lb/>
     the 80 years of Canadian history where the 
     <lb/>
     federal government surveyed a province and 
     <lb/>
     charged that province for doing it... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="906"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0906.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">906</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
           

 <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That is not the point. The point 
     <lb/>
     is... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Charged for the services of its 
     <lb/>
     personnel that it loaned to that province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The point taken by Mr. Higgins 
     <lb/>
     arises out of his interpretation of the expression 
     <lb/>
     "The Government of Canada will make available 
     <lb/>
     the services of technical personnel and agencies 
     <lb/>
     to assist in the, work." It is not a case of what they 
     <lb/>
     have done in the past for other provinces. The 
     <lb/>
     question that Mr. Higgins has directed is the 
     <lb/>
     interpretation to be placed upon the phrase that I 
     <lb/>
     have just read, and he says it is an open question 
     <lb/>
     as to how much technical personnel and agencies 
     <lb/>
     are to be provided by the Dominion government, 
     <lb/>
     and if and when provided, by whom and to what 
     <lb/>
     extent the services are to be paid. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It was to that point exactly that 
     <lb/>
     I was addressing myself, and I said in reply, 
     <lb/>
     would Mr. Higgins show me one case in the 80 
     <lb/>
     years of confederation, where the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada has conducted any survey of minerals or 
     <lb/>
     water-powerm or fish or soil, for any province and 
     <lb/>
     charged that province for doing it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That is not the point, it is not what 
     <lb/>
     they did in the past. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That's exactly what it is.... ls it 
     <lb/>
     its practice, when it does work for various provin<lb break="no"/>ces, to charge the provinces for doing it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> What the Dominion has done 
     <lb/>
     for the provinces in similar circumstances, in<lb break="no"/>sofar as a uniform policy may be found, may 
     <lb/>
     assist in the interpretation of this clause, but has 
     <lb/>
     no direct bearing upon an interpretation of the 
     <lb/>
     phrase. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> We don't know officially what has 
     <lb/>
     been done by the Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Well, that's another matter. 
     <lb/>
      </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> You don't want me to take up 
     <lb/>the Black Book and read again the technological 
     <lb/>and scientific services of the Government of 
     <lb/>Canada... There they are, we read them out the 
     <lb/>other day, these great federal departments 
     <lb/>employing thousands of men, expert technical 
     <lb/>men at work all the year around. Where do they 
     <lb/>work? Throughout the provinces of Canada 
     <lb/>doing this survey work. They do not charge any 
     <lb/>provincial government for the work they do. It is 
     <lb/>borne in full by the Government of Canada, and 
     <lb/>there is no reason in the world to suppose that in 
     <lb/>doing that kind of survey in Newfoundland they 


            <cb/>
           

     are going to charge for it. Where did that sugges<lb break="no"/>tion come from? Mr. Higgins said, "How do we 
     <lb/>
     know but they will charge us for it?" 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> No. Mr. Higgins is asking. Now 
     <lb/>
     is your reply this: that the nature and extent of the 
     <lb/>
     services to be rendered by the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada under the concluding words of the first 
     <lb/>
     paragraph of clause 22. Mr. Smallwood, has to 
     <lb/>
     be resolved in the light of the technical and other 
     <lb/>
     services which were mimeographed by you the 
     <lb/>
     other day, and delivered to members of the 
     <lb/>
     House? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In part, sir, because remember 
     <lb/>
     that that list is merely the names of the divisions, 
     <lb/>
     it is not a description of their work, It is merely a 
     <lb/>
     pan list ofthe various departments of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Let me go further then, as 
     <lb/>
     detailed in the Black Book. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes sir, and applied in New<lb break="no"/>foundland with particular pressure in point of 
     <lb/>
     time. These great federal departments of Canada 
     <lb/>
     have come to Newfoundland to scour the island 
     <lb/>
     and scour Labrador in an effort... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Chairman, I don't want to in<lb break="no"/>terrupt... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, Mr. Higgins had better 
     <lb/>
     not interrupt, unless he is on a point of order or 
     <lb/>
     privilege. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Well, l am on a point of order. I am 
     <lb/>
     asking for the interpretation of the paragraph. I 
     <lb/>
     am not asking for an oration on the services 
     <lb/>
     provided by the Government of Canada. How do 
     <lb/>
     you sir, interpret the wording of that section? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It might not mean very much 
     <lb/>and it might mean a great deal. Perhaps at this 
     <lb/>time, Mr. Smallwood, however embarrassing it 
     <lb/>might be, I will allow you to refer to the details 
     <lb/>as given in the Black Book, and to which I now 
     <lb/>direct your attention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I thank you for permission to 
     <lb/>
     do that. In doing that, in view of the discussion 
     <lb/>
     we had earlier today, and in view of the time, to 
     <lb/>
     spare the House and the country the ordeal of 
     <lb/>
     reading a description of these great federal 
     <lb/>
     departments... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You might take a midway posi<lb break="no"/>tion, Mr. Higgins has addressed himself to me, 
     <lb/>
     but I am afraid I cannot do anything without the 
     <lb/>
     assistance of somebody. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> It is only the wording, the inter<lb break="no"/>
            

            <pb n="907"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0907.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">907</fw> 
 

     pretation, I am asking you. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The nature and extent of the 
     <lb/>
     services envisaged by the phrase is in question, 
     <lb/>
     and for that I would refer you to the volume of 
     <lb/>
     the Black Book where this is referred to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I ask you again how you interpret 
     <lb/>
     the words "to assist in the work." Does it mean to 
     <lb/>
     complete the work or merely to assist in the 
     <lb/>
     work? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I construe this clause to mean 
     <lb/>
     that the work envisaged and contemplated by the 
     <lb/>
     section in question will be facilitated by the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada by providing the techni<lb break="no"/>cal personnel and agents. I constnte the word 
     <lb/>
     "agents" to mean technical personnel and techni<lb break="no"/>cal agents to assist. How I constme that is this: 
     <lb/>
     there is a certainjob to be done which will require 
     <lb/>
     certain technical advice and technical skill, that 
     <lb/>
     technical personnel will be provided by the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Should not the word "assist" be left 
     <lb/>
     out? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> No. If, for example, you are 
     <lb/>
     going to build a paper mill tomorrow, you may 
     <lb/>
     have 15,000 employees; but of that number, only 
     <lb/>
     maybe 5% or 10% provide the technical help and 
     <lb/>
     assistance. I regard this as meaning pretty well 
     <lb/>
     the same thing. They will provide the technical 
     <lb/>
     help and assistance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> The province will have to provide 
     <lb/>
     the other services? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I think it is merely an undertak<lb break="no"/>ing on the part of the Canadian government to 
     <lb/>
     facilitate, not to "do", by providing the technical 
     <lb/>
     personnel and assistance to bring about the com<lb break="no"/>pletion of the work; the rest and residue falls on 
     <lb/>
     the province, That is my interpretation for what 
     <lb/>
     it is worth. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Here are some of the things the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada does... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Could we not ask the government 
     <lb/>
     a straight question? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> He is quite welcome to do that. 
     <lb/>
     I am about to read, at your request, sir, a descrip<lb break="no"/>tion of some of the things the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada does. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I was asked a question about the 
     <lb/>
     nature of the technical services, if the answer is 
     <lb/>
     in the Black Book, you may read it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Smallwood then read sections of the Black 
     <lb/>
     Book, Volume I, dealing with the Canadian 


            <cb/>
        

     departments of Mines and Resources and Public 
     <lb/>
     Works] </hi>

            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> ...After this survey is carried out, 
     <lb/>
     what is to be done then? Our people. even the 
     <lb/>
     most ardent confederates, are looking forward in 
     <lb/>
     terms of dollars and cents; what our people want 
     <lb/>
     to know is how quick can all those scientific 
     <lb/>
     terms be turned into cash. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I do not think anyone alive can 
     <lb/>
     answer that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I do not believe that if we went into 
     <lb/>
     confederation all those scientific terms would 
     <lb/>
     bring one barrel of flour into the pantry or one 
     <lb/>
     piece of pork into the barrel. To my mind that is 
     <lb/>
     not worth the paper it is written on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The clause simply says they un<lb break="no"/>dertake to conduct an economic survey with the 
     <lb/>
     idea of determining the resources that may be 
     <lb/>
     properly developed and to provide, if you will, 
     <lb/>
     the necessary technical help and assistance in 
     <lb/>
     determination of that. The establishment of in<lb break="no"/>dustry after that takes place is something entirely 
     <lb/>
     different, depending on world conditions, the 
     <lb/>
     ability to raise money and other factors. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> We have been referring to PEI pretty 
     <lb/>
     often recently. I believe the population of that 
     <lb/>
     Island when they went into confederation was 
     <lb/>
     110,000, and today it is 92,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> 94,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I wonder why the people cannot get 
     <lb/>
     as good a living there now as they got 70 or 80 
     <lb/>
     years ago. I have here a quotation from the 
     <lb/>
     Department of Reconstruction of Prince Edward 
     <lb/>
     Island where it gives the wage earnings. 1 think 
     <lb/>
     our people should know of it. In the borough of 
     <lb/>
     Queens, 4,045 wage earners. average yearly 
     <lb/>
     earnings each, $720. County of Kings, 1,41l 
     <lb/>
     wage earners, average earnings $419. The point 
     <lb/>
     I want to press home is that apparently confedera<lb break="no"/>tion has not increased wage earnings on the Is<lb break="no"/>land. Take the fishermen and loggers and average 
     <lb/>
     it up, very few people in Newfoundland, except 
     <lb/>
     those unfortunate enough to have a bad voyage, 
     <lb/>
     make below $419. I know on our part of the coast 
     <lb/>
     the ships' wages for four months in Bay de Verde 
     <lb/>
     and Grates Cove is somewhere around $300, and 
     <lb/>
     the same thing applies to many ships that go to 
     <lb/>
     the Labrador. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You are as far from the point as 
     <lb/>
     the sun is from the earth. We are debating section 
     <lb/>
     22. You are telling us about PEI. What possible 


            <pb n="908"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0908.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">908</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
         

     connection is there between that and section 22? 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> Mr. Smallwood brought up the mat<lb break="no"/>ter of PEI. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You have gone astray from the 
     <lb/>
     point. PEI entered into the picture in connection 
     <lb/>
     with communications under section 4. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> On that point, we were talking about 
     <lb/>
     the surveys of the natural resources of the 
     <lb/>
     province. I take it the whole standard of any 
     <lb/>
     country or any province will depend on the 
     <lb/>
     amount of natural resources? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> And the development which 
     <lb/>
     takes place. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> And the living standard. For in<lb break="no"/>stance, the salaries of teachers would depend on 
     <lb/>
     the natural resources of the country. I put it to you 
     <lb/>
     that with all these surveys that have been made, 
     <lb/>
     say in PEI, they have not yet been able to raise 
     <lb/>
     the salaries of their teachers to the standard which 
     <lb/>
     we have in Newfoundland now. I was wondering 
     <lb/>
     if that was why the delegation to Ottawa cut 
     <lb/>
     $500,000 off the amount of the teachers, so that 
     <lb/>
     we could get down to the standard of Prince 
     <lb/>
     Edward Island. We are talking about natural 
     <lb/>
     resources. We must relate everything else to 
     <lb/>
     these natural resources. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Did I understand you to make 
     <lb/>
     the statement that the educational standard, the 
     <lb/>
     salaries of teachers generally in eastern Canada, 
     <lb/>
     are lower than Newfoundland? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> The salaries of teachers in PEI are 
     <lb/>
     very much lower than they are in Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     If you wish me to prove it, I can. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I am not interested in the dif<lb break="no"/>ficulties of the teaching profession in PEI; I am 
     <lb/>
     interested in PEI only insofar as it may have a 
     <lb/>
     bearing on the correct interpretation of section 22 
     <lb/>
     which is now before the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> This economic survey which we are 
     <lb/>
     to get from the experts of Canada is not likely to 
     <lb/>
     tend to raise the standard of living of our people, 
     <lb/>
     if we are to judge by the provinces now existing 
     <lb/>
     in Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I quite agree with that. The point 
     <lb/>
     is this, industrially this country may have great 
     <lb/>
     potentialities. Mr. Smallwood tells us PEI never 
     <lb/>
     had any. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Did Mr. Smallwood say PEI never 
     <lb/>
     had any? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I understood him to say it should 
     <lb/>
     be regarded as a million dollar farm. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I did not say PEI had no in<lb break="no"/>dustry; I said there were no natural resources 
     <lb/>
     except soil and fish 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Before Prince Edward Island went 
     <lb/>
     into confederation she was one of the richest little 
     <lb/>
     countries in the world. She had a huge ship-build<lb break="no"/>ing industry; a good deal of forestry: good fish<lb break="no"/>ing; a splendid farming trade with the USA — the 
     <lb/>
     most prosperous little country on the Atlantic 
     <lb/>
     seaboard 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Bailey said, and I am 
     <lb/>
     paraphrasing him, this survey, those experts 
     <lb/>
     scouring the island to find out what we have in 
     <lb/>
     the way of natural resources, would that put a 
     <lb/>
     piece of pork in the barrel? Would that create 
     <lb/>
     work and employment? Surely the answer is 
     <lb/>
     simple. How long back in his life can Mr. Bailey 
     <lb/>
     remember hearing stories of our inexhaustible 
     <lb/>
     wealth, our vast natural resources? And it is only 
     <lb/>
     this year, 1947, that any government in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland's history has ever brought in a 
     <lb/>
     man to begin to measure how much water-power 
     <lb/>
     we have; there is no known check of our 
     <lb/>
     minerals; no known check of our timber re<lb break="no"/>sources.... It is time we found out just what we 
     <lb/>
     have got. When we have found it out, will that 
     <lb/>
     put an extra pound of pork in the barrel? Yes, for 
     <lb/>
     this reason. We have gone beyond the day when 
     <lb/>
     someone could start a little company with 
     <lb/>
     $10,000 or $15,000, get a grant of a piece of land 
     <lb/>
     supposed to contain a mine, and then go out and 
     <lb/>
     sell the mine for a million dollars. Today you 
     <lb/>
     have to know exactly what you have before capi<lb break="no"/>tal will show any interest. Let someone show 
     <lb/>
     what Newfoundland has, and if we are a province 
     <lb/>
     of Canada, and it is found out officially, definite 
     <lb/>
     data can be printed and published as to what we 
     <lb/>
     have, and there is capital in Canada, the United 
     <lb/>
     States and even in Britain to capitalise every last 
     <lb/>
     little ounce of the natural resources we have. That 
     <lb/>
     is why we need this economic survey. Let us find 
     <lb/>
     out what resources we have here.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> In connection with mining in 
     <lb/>
     Canada, Mr. Smallwood, was it through the ef<lb break="no"/>forts of the Canadian government that the out<lb break="no"/>standing gold mines of Canada were brought 
     <lb/>
     about? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I will answer in my own way. 
     <lb/>
     I will not answer "yes" or "no". I will not be 
     <lb/>
     forced into it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Let us take the Lakeshore. That was 


            <pb n="909"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0909.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">909</fw>
          

     discovered by Harry Oakes, a gold mining 
     <lb/>
     prospector who came up from the States many 
     <lb/>
     years ago. He prospected in Alaska, came into 
     <lb/>
     Ontario and what happened? He was trying to 
     <lb/>
     beat his way from Toronto to Montreal and was 
     <lb/>
     thrown off the train by the conductor. He fell in 
     <lb/>
     with a Chinaman and he discovered the 
     <lb/>
     Lakeshore. That is one of them. It was the 
     <lb/>
     pioneers in Canada who discovered its wealth. 
     <lb/>
     The government probably assisted them later on. 
     <lb/>
     They did it here. They do it everywhere. Let us 
     <lb/>
     look at Hollinger mine — the one that is owned 
     <lb/>
     by Timmins. What happened? Hollinger controls 
     <lb/>
     probably the biggest gold mine in the world, 
     <lb/>
     founded by Benny Hollinger, staked by Mc<lb break="no"/>Martin. The government had nothing to do with 
     <lb/>
     that. As far as mining is concerned, you have to 
     <lb/>
     have the pioneer spirit, the men to go out in the 
     <lb/>
     wilds. Someone went to the Labrador and found 
     <lb/>
     the ore, the government did not find it. The same 
     <lb/>
     thing applies to forestry. The government did not 
     <lb/>
     know what timber was on Crown lands. They 
     <lb/>
     give us some idea. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It was only a guess. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> In Canada they do not know what 
     <lb/>
     they have. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, they do. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Go down to Quebec, and they can<lb break="no"/>not tell you, or to British Columbia. In Van<lb break="no"/>couver, I was there 40 years ago, they do not 
     <lb/>
     know what they have there yet. It is being dis<lb break="no"/>covered every day.... As far as the Government 
     <lb/>
     of Canada coming down here is concerned, our 
     <lb/>
     people have to do it themselves. We have to get 
     <lb/>
     over the idea, whether we have confederation, or 
     <lb/>
     under Commission government or under respon<lb break="no"/>sible government or any other form of govern<lb break="no"/>ment, that if we are not prepared to pioneer and 
     <lb/>
     work ourselves, no government is going to feed 
     <lb/>
     us. Someone has to pay for it and it is generally 
     <lb/>
     the taxpayer. Whilst we appreciate the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government's proposals — that is why I have 
     <lb/>
     sympathy with Mr. Smallwood here and it is 
     <lb/>
     unusual for me to say that — he is acting on 
     <lb/>
     behalf of the Canadian government. He is telling 
     <lb/>
     us what the Canadian government says — he has 
     <lb/>
     no more idea than I have.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That is not quite fair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> If I am unfair, that is the unfortunate 
     <lb/>
     position he is in; he is answering questions on 
     <lb/>
     behalf of the Canadian government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> He has been repeatedly under 
     <lb/>
     fire answering questions and giving interpreta<lb break="no"/>tions. He has given interpretations as best he can; 
     <lb/>
     you may or may not accept his interpretations but 
     <lb/>
     that does not alter the fact that he gives an honest 
     <lb/>
     interpretation and in many cases he has been 
     <lb/>
     supported. For example, if I am in a courtroom 
     <lb/>
     giving an interpretation of some act, it is not fair 
     <lb/>
     to say I am the lawful agent of that legislature 
     <lb/>
     because I am giving an interpretation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> We are wasting a lot of time. The 
     <lb/>
     same thing has applied to every chairman of 
     <lb/>
     every committee; he automatically became a 
     <lb/>
     minister of the Crown. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Which is highly improper. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> As chairman of the Finance Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, I became finance minister overnight; 
     <lb/>
     same thing with the Economic Report and the 
     <lb/>
     other reports. We had questions fired at us, all of 
     <lb/>
     us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You have been chairman of two 
     <lb/>
     reports since I have occupied this office, and I 
     <lb/>
     agree with what you say. But I suggest it is not 
     <lb/>
     only highly improper, but highly unfair. If you as 
     <lb/>
     a minister of the Crown had access to the infor<lb break="no"/>mation required, then there would be every 
     <lb/>
     reason to ask those questions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> That is why I say we are wasting a 
     <lb/>
     lot of time and not trying to finish up. I am not 
     <lb/>
     trying to close off the debate. We know the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government may or may not come 
     <lb/>
     down; they have not given us any undertaking 
     <lb/>
     they will. It is not in the terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> They say that automatically 
     <lb/>
     they will come, if we go into confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I would like to repeat that the 
     <lb/>
     procedure employed by Mr. Smallwood was or<lb break="no"/>dained by this House before we went into com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the whole at all. He was a member of 
     <lb/>
     the Ottawa delegation. He has been requested, 
     <lb/>
     and it becomes his duty while he remains as he 
     <lb/>
     is, to read and interpret the clause, and to answer 
     <lb/>
     any questions on the clause. It is the right of 
     <lb/>
     members to be satisfied or dissatisfied with his 
     <lb/>
     interpretation or any answers on questions ad<lb break="no"/>dressed to him arising out of his interpretation. 
     <lb/>
     But I do not think, in fairness to him, it is fair to 
     <lb/>
     say because he is simply discharging a duty. he 
     <lb/>
     is acting as an agent.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> Mr. Chairman, in regards to this 
     <lb/>
     fairness probably I did not make myself clear.... 


            <pb n="910"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0910.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">910</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
         

     We don't want to put a fancy picture before our 
     <lb/>
     people of what is going to be, because our people 
     <lb/>
     are looking to this. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It is not a question of a fancy 
     <lb/>
     picture at all. It is important or relatively unim<lb break="no"/>portant as far as members are concerned, and 
     <lb/>
     every man is entitled to draw his own con<lb break="no"/>clusions. Mr. Smallwood thinks it is important, 
     <lb/>
     other members think otherwise, and I am not 
     <lb/>
     prepared to say who is right and who is wrong. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> Mr. Chairman, I think it <hi rendition="simple:italic">is</hi> important. 
     <lb/>If we were in a position tomorrow to spend $50 
     <lb/>million on the survey of this country, I think it 
     <lb/>would be one of the most important things in our 
     <lb/>history.... If we got the money, go ahead, but let 
     <lb/>our people understand that it is the province that 
     <lb/>would be going ahead, and these people are going 
     <lb/>to help. Now if the federal government promised 
     <lb/>to come down here and put in a survey, then we 
     <lb/>know what we are talking about. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That's what it is. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I don't see it. I don't see where the 
     <lb/>
     federal government is going to pay a dollar on 
     <lb/>
     this...  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There is no point in arguing it. 
     <lb/>
     It is a question of interpretation... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> If they intend to do it why don't they 
     <lb/>
     say, "We will bear the cost"? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Well, they do say it, in my 
     <lb/>
     opinion; but you are entitled to your own opinion. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The reporter was unable to record the next 
     <lb/>passage of the debate, since the Chairman, Mr. 
     <lb/>Bailey and Mr. Smallwood were all talking at 
     <lb/>once.]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> ....There is one simple little 
     <lb/>
     thing Canada could do, and if we could afford it 
     <lb/>
     we could do it for ourselves, and that's this survey 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Bailey spoke about. And this method 
     <lb/>
     which I have never heard of before, of two ships 
     <lb/>
     with a wire strung between them, scraping the 
     <lb/>
     bottom with other wires, and showing where the 
     <lb/>
     shoals and fishing grounds are; that might be 
     <lb/>
     worth untold millions of dollars to New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I am sure that Mr. Bailey will agree 
     <lb/>
     with that. That is included in this economic sur<lb break="no"/>vey. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> That has been done long ago. I don't 
     <lb/>
     believe there is a fisherman who does not know 
     <lb/>
     where every shoal that exists is situated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Within three miles, or four 
     <lb/>
     miles. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Yes, and including the Grand 
     <lb/>
     Banks. 
    </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, Captain Bailey knows. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I am not sure that Captain Bailey 
     <lb/>knows much about deep-sea fishing around New<lb break="no"/>foundland. The only reason I am saying a few 
     <lb/>words on this clause is this: Mr. Smallwood said 
     <lb/>that in his opinion this was the most important 
     <lb/>section in this Grey Book, and I want to point out 
     <lb/>that survey has been in operation in Canada for 
     <lb/>70 or less years, and we know the results in 
     <lb/>Canada. What can we expect from this idea of 
     <lb/>confederation if this is the most important sec<lb break="no"/>tion? lf nothing better has been done in PEI if you 
     <lb/>like, or Nova Scotia, Saskatchewan, if nothing 
     <lb/>better has restulted from these surveys, then why 
     <lb/>is this the most important section in this book? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It is the most important section 
     <lb/>because Mr. Smallwood says so, but it may have 
     <lb/>no importance at all so far as you or I are con<lb break="no"/>cerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> On the question of an economic sur<lb break="no"/>vey, I certainly agree with Mr. Smallwood. What 
     <lb/>I was trying to find out from reading section 22 
     <lb/>is how far the public services of Canada would 
     <lb/>be of assistance in bringing about a proper 
     <lb/>economic and financial survey of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>as well. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> They don't mention a financial 
     <lb/>survey. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> No, I know they don't, but I think that 
     <lb/>is something necessary to be done. I raised some 
     <lb/>doubt the time before when the public services 
     <lb/>sections were read, those public services which 
     <lb/>would apply to Newfoundland. I am sorry this 
     <lb/>debate came up this afternoon because I have 
     <lb/>been making a survey of these services, and this 
     <lb/>afternoon I am only going to refer to one section, 
     <lb/>and that comes under the Public Health and Wel<lb break="no"/>fare Department. There are 17 services 
     <lb/>enumerated there. Four of those are treated here 
     <lb/>separately, all of them relating to financial 
     <lb/>benefits of one kind or other. They are: the treat<lb break="no"/>ment of sick and injured mariners; old age pen<lb break="no"/>sions; pensions for the blind; family allowances. 
     <lb/>Eight of these services are purely consulting ser<lb break="no"/>vices. Eight of them. The balance are like this: 
     <lb/>food and drug standards; investigation and re<lb break="no"/>search; industrial health; national physical fitness 
     <lb/>programme. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now the point that I would like to make, and 


            <pb n="911"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0911.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">911</fw>
         

     I would like to see this gone into very carefully, 
     <lb/>
     is this: ... that out of these 17 services, four are 
     <lb/>
     referred to here because they will affect the 
     <lb/>
     province in a financial way. Eight of them are, as 
     <lb/>
     the Director of Medical Services knows, consult<lb break="no"/>ing services. We have never been refused any 
     <lb/>
     information of any kind that any of the civil 
     <lb/>
     service departments wanted from the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     government at any time, and that service is avail<lb break="no"/>able to Newfoundland. I make this as a flat state<lb break="no"/>ment, and if anyone can correct that, then I will 
     <lb/>
     apologise, but I think I am on fairly safe ground, 
     <lb/>
     because I have made a fairly reliable survey of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, Mr. Smallwood wanted to know 
     <lb/>
     whether the province had paid anything under 
     <lb/>
     any one of these services. The National Physical 
     <lb/>
     Fitness Programme. There is some incongruity in 
     <lb/>
     talking of a physical fitness programme when we 
     <lb/>
     are talking about an economic survey, but I am 
     <lb/>
     giving this as an example. You will find on page 
     <lb/>
     93 of the Black Book: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The National Physical Fitness Programme 
     <lb/>
     provides for the establishment of a National 
     <lb/>
     Council on Physical Fitness, on which the 
     <lb/>
     provincial governments have repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives. Financial assistance is given to 
     <lb/>
     any province that has signed an agreement 
     <lb/>
     with the Dominion Government as provided 
     <lb/>
     in the Act. Within the limits of the National 
     <lb/>
     Physical Fitness Fund, set up in the con<lb break="no"/>solidated Revenue Fund for the purpose, the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Government undertakes to pay 
     <lb/>
     one dollar for every dollar a province spends 
     <lb/>
     on its program ... etc., etc. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>
     Now this is one case in which the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     government only assists in carrying out one of the 
     <lb/>
     services mentioned, and what is worrying me is 
     <lb/>
     just how far these public services, and this par<lb break="no"/>ticular survey, will mean something to New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I believe that we will make progress 
     <lb/>
     by the things which are found, as Major Cashin 
     <lb/>
     has pointed out, and by the things which are 
     <lb/>
     deliberately organised by a government or by a 
     <lb/>
     great concern; but I express this as a matter of 
     <lb/>
     opinion. Having said that I believe firmly in an 
     <lb/>
     economic survey, I question if that survey of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland should not be done by people 
     <lb/>
     partly from Newfoundland, Canada, the United 
     <lb/>
     States, one at least from New Zealand, and from 
     <lb/>
     the Scandinavian countries. In that way I think 
     <lb/>
     we would get a much better idea of the economic 
  

            <cb/>
           

     potentialities of Newfoundland than by having it 
     <lb/>
     done by the ordinary administrative servants of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> If it is the pleasure of the House 
     <lb/>
     we shall proceed to read the next section. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Clause 23 — <hi rendition="simple:italic">General</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Suitable provision will be made in the 
     <lb/>
     formal instrument of union or in other ap<lb break="no"/>propriate legislation for the following: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (1) The extension of Canadian citizen<lb break="no"/>ship to the people of Newfoundland; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (2) The continuation of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     laws, courts, commissions, authorities, etc., 
     <lb/>
     until altered by the appropriate authority: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (3) The first constitution of the Province 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland, in accordance with the 
     <lb/>
     wishes of the appropriate Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     authorities and subject to the provisions of 
     <lb/>
     the British North America Acts, 1867 to 
     <lb/>
     1946, which are applicable to provincial con<lb break="no"/>stitutions generally; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (4) The retention by Newfoundland of its 
     <lb/>
     natural resources on the same basis as other 
     <lb/>
     provinces; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (5) The application to the Province of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland of the British North America 
     <lb/>
     Acts, 1867 to 1946 (except as otherwise 
     <lb/>
     provided in the terms of union), and of the 
     <lb/>
     federal laws of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Sir, on these five paragraphs I have not much 
     <lb/>
     to say. The extension of Canadian citizenship to 
     <lb/>
     the people of Newfoundland is not a matter of 
     <lb/>
     utmost importance. You know the very recent 
     <lb/>
     trend within the British Commonwealth. The 
     <lb/>
     people of Australia are becoming Australian 
     <lb/>
     citizens, of South Africa, South African citizens, 
     <lb/>
     and of Canada, Canadian citizens. One of the 
     <lb/>
     reasons is that up to now we have all been British 
     <lb/>
     subjects. Of course we have been and we will 
     <lb/>
     always be British subjects; but in addition we 
     <lb/>
     become citizens of England, or Canada, or 
     <lb/>
     Australia; citizens of the dominion in which we 
     <lb/>
     live. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the second one, Newfoundland laws, 
     <lb/>
     courts, etc. .... I don't think that there is anything 
     <lb/>
     much that calls for comment in that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "The first constitution of the Province of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, in accordance with the wishes of the 
     <lb/>
     appropriate Newfoundland authorities...ap<lb break="no"/>plicable to provincial constitutions generally." 
     <lb/>
     Now on that I think I ought to point out that the 
  

            <pb n="912"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0912.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">912</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
           

     constitution of a province is a matter for that 
     <lb/>
     province. We often hear the question, "Under 
     <lb/>
     confederation, how many members would New<lb break="no"/>foundland elect to the House of Assembly?" You 
     <lb/>
     often hear the question, "Would there be two 
     <lb/>
     houses?" "Would it be 'bicameral', or 
     <lb/>
     'unicameral'?" "Would there be a lower house 
     <lb/>
     and an upper house?" Then again you often hear, 
     <lb/>
     "How many districts would there be?" All these 
     <lb/>
     matters are in the provincial constitution of New<lb break="no"/>foundland if we become a province, and we are 
     <lb/>
     the masters. We decide for ourselves whether our 
     <lb/>
     general elections shall be every four years, or five 
     <lb/>
     or six; whether our House of Assembly shall 
     <lb/>
     consist of 15 members of 50, or anything be<lb break="no"/>tween. We decide whether we shall have an upper 
     <lb/>
     house or just an elected house. All these matters 
     <lb/>
     are our own business.... The only thing is that 
     <lb/>
     those portions of the BNA Act which are com<lb break="no"/>mon to the provinces generally would also be 
     <lb/>
     common to the Province of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On no. 4 there is not much to say. New<lb break="no"/>foundland would hold on to its own natural 
     <lb/>
     resources. On no.5, the BNA Act would apply to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland as it does to all provinces, except 
     <lb/>
     that there are certain places in these terms where 
     <lb/>
     we are exempted from particular provisions of 
     <lb/>
     the act.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> "The extension of Canadian 
     <lb/>
     citizenship to the people of Newfoundland." I 
     <lb/>
     take it now we change our name from New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders to Canadians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, no, any more than the 
     <lb/>
     people of Prince Edward Island will ever cease 
     <lb/>
     to be Islanders. The people of Nova Scotia are 
     <lb/>
     Canadians, yes, but also Nova Scotians. We will 
     <lb/>
     always be Newfoundlanders, not only in name 
     <lb/>
     but in truth, even if we are Canadians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> We have several agreements with 
     <lb/>
     various corporations. For instance we have one 
     <lb/>
     agreement with the Newfoundland-Labrador 
     <lb/>
     Mining and Development and Exploration Com<lb break="no"/>pany, which states that Newfoundlanders will be 
     <lb/>
     given preference in employment. The same ap<lb break="no"/>plies at Corner Brook and Grand Falls, Buchans, 
     <lb/>
     etc. Once we become a province of Canada there 
     <lb/>
     is nothing to stop what we call, at the present 
     <lb/>
     time, a Canadian coming in and getting work 
     <lb/>
     there just on the same basis as a Newfound<lb break="no"/>lander. Would there? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, the contracts made be<lb break="no"/>
           

            <cb/>
         tween the Government of Newfoundland and any 
     <lb/>
     corporations bearing on taxation, or bearing on 
     <lb/>
     conditions under which they were given any con<lb break="no"/>cessions or contracts, those would stand. Even 
     <lb/>
     Bowaters will still only pay $150,000 a year 
     <lb/>
     income tax, although other corporations will pay 
     <lb/>
     according to the Canadian corporation income 
     <lb/>
     tax. Any contracts which the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     government has made up to the moment we be<lb break="no"/>come a province will stand. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I quite appreciate that question of 
     <lb/>
     taxation, but in connection with those who are to 
     <lb/>
     be employed — there is nothing in here to say it 
     <lb/>
     will apply. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> No. but under Section 92... 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> But if I am living in Quebec there 
     <lb/>is nothing to stop me from going up in Ontario, 
     <lb/>and I have just as much right to get a job up there 
     <lb/>as any fellow that lives in Toronto. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Certainly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Well, there would be nothing to 
     <lb/>
     prevent a man who lived in the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     end of Labrador now, even though we have legis<lb break="no"/>lation to give Newfoundlanders preference for 
     <lb/>
     the work that's there. When we become a 
     <lb/>
     province of Canada men from British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     for that matter, can come in on our own bases. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No ... Newfoundlanders had a 
     <lb/>government since 1825. Ever since then New<lb break="no"/>foundland has had a government under various 
     <lb/>forms. We have one now, and we will have one 
     <lb/>up to the day we become a province, if we be<lb break="no"/>come a province. These various governments 
     <lb/>have made various contracts, and these contracts 
     <lb/>stand. If you like to put a question to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada, and are not prepared to take my 
     <lb/>word, put a question to the Government of 
     <lb/>Canada. That will settle it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Major Cashin's point is wheth<lb break="no"/>er or not there are any immigration restrictions 
     <lb/>
     between provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Immigration is a concurrent 
     <lb/>
     jurisdiction. It is both federal and provincial. It is 
     <lb/>
     concurrent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> There's nothing to stop me, if I am 
     <lb/>
     living in Montreal, from going to British Colum<lb break="no"/>bia if I want to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well no, there is not, but there 
     <lb/>
     could be. It is concurrent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> "The continuation of New<lb break="no"/>foundland laws...until altered by the appropriate 
  

            <pb n="913"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0913.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">913</fw>
         

     authority." Who is that going to be? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> How could the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada say that?.... That's for us to determine, 
     <lb/>
     not them. They can't name the authority. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Well, who are we going to name? 
     <lb/>
     That's up to the future government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The government that you and I 
     <lb/>
     are going to be in next year together. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> You mean the provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The constitution of courts both 
     <lb/>
     civil and criminal, and the regulation of civil 
     <lb/>
     procedure is a matter entirely for the province, 
     <lb/>
     but the matter of criminal law, which is reflected 
     <lb/>
     in the criminal code of Canada is decided by the 
     <lb/>
     federal government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I must apologise, Mr. Chairman. I 
     <lb/>
     was not there the first couple of days that this thing 
     <lb/>
     was being discussed, but assuming that tomorrow 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland voted to go into confederation 
     <lb/>
     who is going to finalise that deal? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> We mean to do that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Who is going to finalise it, is it the 
     <lb/>
     British government, or who is it? I want to know. 
     <lb/>
     
 </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am itching to answer that, but 
     <lb/>I won't. It is getting a little late, and we have 
     <lb/>another clause. We have to go back to veterans 
     <lb/>and merchant seamen, you see, and we should 
     <lb/>finish that, it is only a matter of reading it. But 
     <lb/>this matter that Major Cashin raises did come up 
     <lb/>and we had quite a little discussion on it here on 
     <lb/>the second or third day. He was not in the House. 
     <lb/>I would suggest that he hold that over until we 
     <lb/>come to it. We will come back to it again. It is a 
     <lb/>very interesting subject and quite important, and 
     <lb/>we should come back to it again. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Would the Quebec fishermen be 
     <lb/>
     permitted to fish on the French Shore or 
     <lb/>
     Labrador? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That is a matter for future 
     <lb/>
     decision. Immigration is concurrent. Both the 
     <lb/>
     federal government and each provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ment has ideas on that. We would be a province, 
     <lb/>
     with a provincial government. That provincial 
     <lb/>
     government would have authority for that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Getting back to those contracts 
     <lb/>
     which Mr. Smallwood refers to, namely 
     <lb/>
     Bowaters, which he claims pays $150,000 a year 
     <lb/>
     in taxes, which is correct we are told. This will 
     <lb/>
     not be changed. I presume that many other con<lb break="no"/>tracts that exist at the present time, if we should 
  

            <cb/>
        

     go into confederation, will also not be changed. 
     <lb/>
     That is what I understood him to say. Then isn't 
     <lb/>
     it reasonable to assume that the contracts made 
     <lb/>
     on behalf of the British government and the 
     <lb/>
     Americans in connection with their bases will 
     <lb/>
     remain also? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You are getting into very deep 
     <lb/>
     water there, Mr. Fudge. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Well, if one is a contract so is the 
     <lb/>
     other. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It all depends, I don't want to 
     <lb/>
     express an opinion on that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I did not hear quite what Mr. Fudge 
     <lb/>
     said. I gathered it was something about the bases 
     <lb/>
     deal. Is that right? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> ....Mr. Smallwood tells us the 
     <lb/>
     Bowater contract would remain the same if we 
     <lb/>
     went into confederation, and the point I raised 
     <lb/>
     was that I presume the contracts made between 
     <lb/>
     the British government for the base deals with the 
     <lb/>
     United States would remain also. It's a contract. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> That is a very important point, and 
     <lb/>one I was going to raise myself. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> For whom? You are raising the 
     <lb/>
     point to be dealt with by whom? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> The point is this: the British govern<lb break="no"/>ment signed a contract. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I am not interested in that at all. 
     <lb/>
     It is not competent for this House to even deal 
     <lb/>
     with it. The whole thing is <hi rendition="simple:italic">ultra vires</hi>, and I don't 
     <lb/>
     want to hear anything about it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, I shall mention 
     <lb/>
     something which is not <hi rendition="simple:italic">ultra vires</hi>, which is a 
     <lb/>
     letter written by Winston Churchill in which he 
     <lb/>
     stated... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> In connection with what? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> With parts of this country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You are not to mention it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> But it is my country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I am ruling on a point of law, 
     <lb/>
     and there is no appeal from this Chair on a point 
     <lb/>
     of law, and I rule that the terms of the Convention 
     <lb/>
     Act do not require us to go into that, and I defy 
     <lb/>
     anybody in this chamber or out of it, anybody in 
     <lb/>
     this country, to show me anything in section 3, 
     <lb/>
     which defines and sets forth your duty, which 
     <lb/>
     allows you to review these base deals. Show me 
     <lb/>
     how it becomes <hi rendition="simple:italic">intra vires</hi> to this House, and I 
     <lb/>
     will allow you to go on with it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I must take exception, if you don't 
     <lb/>
     mind. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="914"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0914.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">914</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
            

<p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There is no debate on this point. 
     <lb/>
     I am not ruling on a question of procedure, I am 
     <lb/>
     ruling on a point of law. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, I did not ask you to 
     <lb/>
     rule on a point of law. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I have ruled this as being <hi rendition="simple:italic">ultra 
     <lb/>
     vires</hi>, and I hope I won't have to do it again. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> There is a point of law here. Com<lb break="no"/>ing back to the Labrador Exploration thing again. 
     <lb/>It says the company shall employ Newfoundland 
     <lb/>workmen, provided they shall be available. If 
     <lb/>Newfoundland enters union with Canada, and 
     <lb/>Newfoundlanders become Canadians, does this 
     <lb/>point stand in law? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> To whom do you address this 
     <lb/>
     question? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> To the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> If the House ... of course, I am 
     <lb/>
     not going to be here when you decide it. I am not 
     <lb/>
     prepared to recognise this House as a court of 
     <lb/>
     judicature, or having any jurisdiction whatever to 
     <lb/>
     pronounce upon a point of law. Why the whole 
     <lb/>
     thing is becoming absurd — too ridiculous for 
     <lb/>
     anything. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> You just decided on a point of law. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I decided this point of law: it is 
     <lb/>for me to decide as a Chairman whether any man 
     <lb/>is <hi rendition="simple:italic">intra vires</hi> or <hi rendition="simple:italic">ultra vires</hi>.... I am not sitting here 
     <lb/>as a senior partner of McEvoy and Lewis, I am 
     <lb/>sitting here as Chairman of this Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Well, I will ask Mr. Smallwood. 
     <lb/>Does this proviso stand in law? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am not a lawyer, and it is a bit 
     <lb/>
     ridiculous for me to give an opinion on a matter 
     <lb/>
     of law, but I will give you an opinion for what it 
     <lb/>
     is worth — a cent and a half, and the cent is 
     <lb/>
     plugged. It is not even worth a cent and a half, 
     <lb/>
     but I will say this: the contracts we have with 
     <lb/>
     corporations stand. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Yes, as far as the corporations are 
     <lb/>
     concerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, as far as the Government 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland is concerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Well, Mr. Chairman. in order to get 
     <lb/>
     an answer to this question I will have to address 
     <lb/>
     a question to the Department of Justice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I am afraid you will. That is the 
     <lb/>
     proper procedure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Excuse me, Mr. Chairman. I will 
     <lb/>
     probably be told it is none of my business. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I am sorry. I don't defend the 

<cb/>

Department of Justice. I am not the Department 
     <lb/>of Justice. If you will table your question we will 
     <lb/>endeavour to have it answered. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, it is now 5.30, 
     <lb/>
     and if the House has indulgence enough we could 
     <lb/>
     finish this final clause. Would that be all right? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> Regarding Labrador. If New<lb break="no"/>foundland-Labrador develops into such a great 
     <lb/>mine as we think it will be, is there anything to 
     <lb/>prevent Newfoundland being flooded by French 
     <lb/>Canadians, taking the work from Newfound<lb break="no"/>landers? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> We just answered that question 
     <lb/>
     twice, once to Mr. Cashin and once to Mr. Jack<lb break="no"/>man. If Mr. Reddy does not agree with my answer 
     <lb/>
     I can't help it. The answer is, "No". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> That is not true. There is nothing in 
     <lb/>
     God's world to prevent French Canadians from 
     <lb/>
     entering Labrador if there is work there, if we 
     <lb/>
     become a province of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Would Mr. Reddy be kind 
     <lb/>
     enough to give his reasons. That's a very 
     <lb/>
     categorical statement.... Mr. Reddy says there is 
     <lb/>
     nothing to stop the French Canadians, millions of 
     <lb/>
     them, from flocking into Labrador if we become 
     <lb/>
     a province. He ought to have some reason for that 
     <lb/>
     statement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> Mr. Chairman, is there anything to 
     <lb/>
     prevent a man from Sydney going to work in 
     <lb/>
     Saskatchewan? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I have no knowledge of it 
     <lb/>
     myself. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> Well then, why can't they come in 
     <lb/>
     here? It will be all the same if we become a 
     <lb/>
     province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Your opinion is predicated upon 
     <lb/>
     the ease with which people can move from one 
     <lb/>
     province to another now, so that if we become a 
     <lb/>
     province you said... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I have been in every province in 
     <lb/>
     Canada, from the Atlantic to the Pacific and there 
     <lb/>
     is no bar on the borderline, anyone can go right 
     <lb/>
     through. I have been from Vancouver Island to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, not once but many times. They 
     <lb/>
     never even question it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> But here you are up against the 
     <lb/>
     position where Newfoundland, as a province, 
     <lb/>
     enters with its contracts made with corporations, 
     <lb/>
     including the Labrador Mining and Exploration 
     <lb/>
     Company. That contract either stands or it does 
     <lb/>
     not. Now, why not direct a question to the 
   

            <pb n="915"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-01_Page_0915.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">915</fw>
        

     Government of Canada? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I have had to rule my friend Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Hollett out of order, and I have had to do the same 
     <lb/>
     thing with Major Cashin, but you are getting 
     <lb/>
     pretty far afield now, as to whether or not, for 
     <lb/>
     example, Bowaters or the AND Company would 
     <lb/>
     have the right to take in residents from some part 
     <lb/>
     of Canada in lieu of Newfoundlanders, bearing in 
     <lb/>
     mind the fact that in becoming the tenth province 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland becomes a part of Canada. I want 
     <lb/>
     to say ... that we are getting very far afield. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> It is a very important point. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> This Convention should not be 
     <lb/>
     improperly placed in the position where it has to 
     <lb/>
     make pronouncements upon far-reaching points 
     <lb/>
     of law, or where I am called upon to express an 
     <lb/>
     opinion upon a point of law; which I don't have 
     <lb/>
     to do, except insofar as it concerns the interpreta<lb break="no"/>tion of the Convention Act.... I think, Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin, the point by you is well taken, that is, 
     <lb/>
     address your questions on legal points to the 
     <lb/>
     Department of Justice in this country or in 
     <lb/>
     Canada, consistent with our practice in submit<lb break="no"/>ting various other questions to various other 
     <lb/>
     departments of government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> ....As far as this employment of 
     <lb/>
     French Canadians on the Labrador — I have 
     <lb/>
     asked in a good many cases, where we have 
     <lb/>
     signed agreements with employers, that 
     <lb/>
     preference be given to people who reside in the 
     <lb/>
     area. However, before we get the number of 
     <lb/>
     employees required, people from all over the 


            <cb/>
         

     island have flocked in and have been hired. 
     <lb/>
     Similarly, if there is work down there, the 
     <lb/>
     Canadians will have their men there before we 
     <lb/>
     get the message. It is a waste of time to discuss 
     <lb/>
     it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> To get a clear-cut answer to the 
     <lb/>
     questions raised by Major Cashin, which I con<lb break="no"/>sider to be of far-reaching importance, the only 
     <lb/>
     thing to do is to address a series of questions 
     <lb/>
     calculated to determine whether there are exist<lb break="no"/>ing contracts, and whether Newfoundlanders are 
     <lb/>
     to be employed in the event of the constitutional 
     <lb/>
     status of the country being altered. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> If we take measures to keep these 
     <lb/>
     workmen out of Labrador, it would be a poor 
     <lb/>
     basis to start off on. All the other provinces might 
     <lb/>
     set up laws to keep Newfoundlanders out of the 
     <lb/>
     other parts of Canada. If we start out by saying, 
     <lb/>
     "You cannot work in our province — keep out". 
     <lb/>
     they can put up a poster in any other province to 
     <lb/>
     the same effect. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Discrimination almost invariab<lb break="no"/>ly and inevitably provokes retaliation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I do not believe any law or anything 
     <lb/>
     else can keep them out. If we have confederation, 
     <lb/>
     we are Canadians and they are Canadians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> In view of the fact that Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin is going to table a question on that point, 
     <lb/>
     we are putting the cart before the horse. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee rose and reported progress, and 
     <lb/>
     the Convention adjourned]</hi>  
     <lb/>
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2017-08-02, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
            <!--<milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     December 2, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I give notice that I will on tomorrow 
     <lb/>
     ask His Excellency the Governor to obtain from 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian government the following informa<lb break="no"/>tion: 
     <lb/>
     (1) The annual revenues and expenditures of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion of Canada each year from the 
     <lb/>
     year 1931-32 to the year 1946-47, both years 
     <lb/>
     inclusive. 
     <lb/>
     (2) The total amount of loans raised each 
     <lb/>
     year from 193l -32 to 1946-47, showing 
     <lb/>
     where such loans were raised and what inter<lb break="no"/>est is being paid. 
     <lb/>
     (3) The annual revenues and expenditures of 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian National Railways and its sub<lb break="no"/>sidiaries from 193l-32 to 1946-47. 
     <lb/>
     (4) The total advances made each year from 
     <lb/>
     1931-32 to 1946-47 by the Canadian treasury 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     to the Canadian National Railways on ac<lb break="no"/>count of deficits incurred, or in the way of 
     <lb/>
     loans. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (5) The amounts of money paid by the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government for each of the railway 
     <lb/>
     systems: the Grand Trunk, the Grand Trunk 
     <lb/>
     Pacific, and the Canadian Northern, all three 
     <lb/>
     of which are now included in the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     National Railway System. What was the total 
     <lb/>
     amount in dispute and defaulted on by the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government in respect of the Grand 
     <lb/>
     Trunk bonds held by English financial in<lb break="no"/>stitutions? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (6) Did the Canadian treasury guarantee any 
     <lb/>
     loan to the Canadian Pacific Railway prior to 
     <lb/>
     1940, and if so what was the amount? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I give notice that I will on tomorrow ask the 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>