<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-02-07" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-02-07">7 February 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="303"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0295.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0296.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0297.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0298.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0299.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0300.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0301.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0302.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0303.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-09">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0295">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0295.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0296">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0296.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0297">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0297.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0298">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0298.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0299">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0299.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0300">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0300.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0301">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0301.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0302">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0302.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0303">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0303.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="295" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0295.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">295</fw>
           
<!-- GL, 2017-06-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

 <!--<p>
     there in the end of the report that they are now 
     <lb/>
     considering having a survey made on Labrador. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>[The committee of the whole rose and reported 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     that it had passed the report. The Convention 
     <lb/>
     adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     February 7, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">Report of the Local Industries Committee:<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref>
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole</head>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Mr. Chairman, before the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary reads the report I would like to say that 
     <lb/>
     I do not intend to introduce it with a long talk, 
     <lb/>
     because after it has been read it will be only a 
     <lb/>
     matter of duplication. I would like to point out 
     <lb/>
     that, with respect to local industries, pulp and 
     <lb/>
     paper, mining, fisheries and forestry have their 
     <lb/>
     own committees, so consequently we could not 
     <lb/>
     touch on those and had to confine ourselves to the 
     <lb/>
     smaller or secondary industries. We did not have 
     <lb/>
     any statistics or sources of information whatever. 
     <lb/>
     We tried several channels but could not get any<lb break="no"/>thing on which to base our report. That presented 
     <lb/>
     quite a difficulty with the result that the report is 
     <lb/>
     not as complete as if there had been a statistical 
     <lb/>
     department of the government which had kept 
     <lb/>
     these figures over a number of years, and which 
     <lb/>
     could have given us comparative figures. This is 
     <lb/>
     a disappointment to the Committee, and perhaps 
     <lb/>
     to you too. The Committee worked very hard, and 
     <lb/>
     everything possible was done. You will see now 
     <lb/>
     that we have had a job in collecting a lot of that. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read part of the report]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> May I ask Mr. Hickman to turn back 
     <lb/>
     to page 3. I notice here that tobacco and cordage 
     <lb/>
     are grouped as one. Was it not possible to have 
     <lb/>
     them separate? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> No. The questionnaire was sent 
     <lb/>
     out separately and we received one reply from the 
     <lb/>
     industries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> They came together and ganged up? 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I appreciate there are many mem<lb break="no"/>bers in this Convention who may not understand 
     <lb/>
     protective tariffs, and that is why I asked Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Hickman why these three things were put 
     <lb/>
     together. You will probably remember 22 years 
     <lb/>
     ago I made my House of Assembly debut on 
     <lb/>
     protective tariffs, and one of these industries was 
     <lb/>
     tobacco. That's one particular fault I find with 
     <lb/>
     this report; it does not show the protective tariff 
     <lb/>
     these industries have. I agree in principle they 
   

            <cb/>
       
     should have a certain amount of protection, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly when they are local, but here is one now 
     <lb/>
     that says it will not give full particulars, the 
     <lb/>
     Imperial Tobacco Co. Over 60% of the stock of 
     <lb/>
     that company is held outside the country, ap<lb break="no"/>proximately 60% on watered stock, and they 
     <lb/>
     have a protection of.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Would you explain watering 
     <lb/>
     stock? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> When the company started we will 
     <lb/>
     assume that they have so many shares, I am 
     <lb/>
     bringing my mind back 20 years, and at that time 
     <lb/>
     they had watered their stock several times. That 
     <lb/>
     means that if they put in $100 and they were 
     <lb/>
     getting 15% on it, then the next year, if they 
     <lb/>
     watered it and made those shares worth $200, that 
     <lb/>
     would mean that they were getting 30% on their 
     <lb/>
     original investment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> What is "watering"? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> If they have a good year, and they 
     <lb/>
     pay a 20% dividend on their common stock, they 
     <lb/>
     would "water" that and give two shares for one. 
     <lb/>
     I am not particularly opposed to protective tariffs, 
     <lb/>
     but this company has $550,000 a year in protec<lb break="no"/>tive tariffs, and I think the people of this country 
     <lb/>
     should know, and also the members of this Con<lb break="no"/>vention. What is the use of this Convention if we 
     <lb/>
     can't get these facts? Here we have it borne out 
     <lb/>
     — three companies gang up and say, "We won't 
     <lb/>
     give the facts". I did not intend to speak on this, 
     <lb/>
     but I saw here that they had 218 employees 
     <lb/>
     between the three of them, and they pay $400,000 
     <lb/>
     wages that is about $1,700 on average. Now some 
     <lb/>
     of our other industries that belong to New<lb break="no"/>foundland and have protection, pay much more 
     <lb/>
     on an average than these people do to their 
     <lb/>
     employees. They are also paying 45% dividends 
     <lb/>
     on theirstock. This is fact and it should be known. 
     <lb/>
     The protection has been increased by the Com<lb break="no"/>mission govemment. I am sorry that we have not 
     <lb/>
     got a copy of the tariff here, so that we could work 
     <lb/>
     it out. I think I gave some statistics to some 


   
<note xml:id="fn_01">[1] Volume II:54. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
    

            <pb n="296" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0296.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">296</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
          
     gentlemen of that Committee to show the tariff 
     <lb/>
     protection There is an excise tariff and an import 
     <lb/>
     duty, and the difference between the two is the 
     <lb/>
     protection they get. If you look up the blue book 
     <lb/>
     of the Customs you will see how much is 
     <lb/>
     manufactured in the year and how much is im<lb break="no"/>ported, and work out the protection by that. Here 
     <lb/>
     is an industry controlled by the British American 
     <lb/>
     Tobacco Co., one of the largest tobacco com<lb break="no"/>panies in the world, and it has a protection tariff 
     <lb/>
     of $550,000 a year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I intended to discuss the very 
     <lb/>
     matter Major Cashin has raised, but not to do it 
     <lb/>
     until the report was finished reading. I guess how 
     <lb/>
     is the time to go into it. I have a great deal of 
     <lb/>
     admiration for the work that the Committee has 
     <lb/>
     done. Any of us can see they put in a lot of work. 
     <lb/>
     I know the terrible difficulty they must have had 
     <lb/>
     because I have been doing that kind of thing 
     <lb/>
     myself, trying to get the same figures. It is one of 
     <lb/>
     the complaints that I have against this govern<lb break="no"/>ment that they have not got, after 13 years, any 
     <lb/>
     department to gather together just the ordinary 
     <lb/>
     facts and figures and statistics to show what the 
     <lb/>
     country is worth, the value of the goods 
     <lb/>
     produced, and of the manufactures. We and the 
     <lb/>
     government and Mr. Hickman's committee do 
     <lb/>
     not know, because there is no one to tell them. 
     <lb/>
     This matter of protective tariff, I can't agree with 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Cashin, or with the Committee, in drawing 
     <lb/>
     too sharp a line between those local industries 
     <lb/>
     whose capital is owned outside the country, and 
     <lb/>
     those whose capital is owned inside the country. 
     <lb/>
     So far as the consumers of Newfoundland are 
     <lb/>
     concerned it does not make much difference who 
     <lb/>
     owns the capital, if the effect of a high protective 
     <lb/>
     tariff or a high customs tariff is to drive up the 
     <lb/>
     cost of living.... Why draw the line? The enquiry 
     <lb/>
     that has to be made is on the effect of the tariff on 
     <lb/>
     all local industries. That's the enquiry that ought 
     <lb/>
     to be made. It is true the Committee goes on to 
     <lb/>
     say that it would require investigation by ac<lb break="no"/>countants and economists in order to determine 
     <lb/>
     the degree of protection these local companies 
     <lb/>
     get. If it is so it is a pity that the Local Industries 
     <lb/>
     Committee did not make an effort to get an ac<lb break="no"/>countant and economist to do that job. We are 
     <lb/>
     down now to one of the most fundamental things 
     <lb/>
     that we have to face. I heard Major Cashin in this 
     <lb/>
     very chamber stand up 20 years ago, and I heard 
     <lb/>
     him say that if he had his way he would take every 
    

            <cb/>
           
     local industry in this country and burn it to the 
     <lb/>
     ground. Now he did not mean that I know, but 
     <lb/>
     what he was getting at then, and also this after<lb break="no"/>noon, and what I am trying to get at, is this: taking 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland as a whole, we know that in a 
     <lb/>
     local industry the employees get their living and 
     <lb/>
     the owners get their dividends, so a local industry 
     <lb/>
     is certainly good for those who are employed in 
     <lb/>
     it and for those who own it, but is that local 
     <lb/>
     industry good for Newfoundland? Industries are 
     <lb/>
     good, but I would point out this fact, and it is the 
     <lb/>
     thing that we have to keep in our minds, and if 
     <lb/>
     we run into the danger of forgetting it we are 
     <lb/>
     going wrong. Every man, woman and child in this 
     <lb/>
     building and in this country today, is eating food 
     <lb/>
     and wearing clothes, footwear, etc, bought from 
     <lb/>
     the money that comes back into Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     for the fish, the paper and the minerals we ship 
     <lb/>
     out. That's the only money we have, what we get 
     <lb/>
     back for these three things. That's all we have to 
     <lb/>
     live on — how we divide it up is another matter.... 
     <lb/>
     There is no other money, except during the war 
     <lb/>
     when we had a lot of Canadian and American 
     <lb/>
     money for base construction. There is a little 
     <lb/>
     dribble still coming in. The only money that we 
     <lb/>
     live on is what comes into Newfoundland from 
     <lb/>
     Spain, Portugal, Italy, the West Indies, etc. for 
     <lb/>
     fish, and from Canada and England for iron ore 
     <lb/>
     and paper, not what is produced in these local 
     <lb/>
     industries. They don't produce a single cent of 
     <lb/>
     new money, they only have their share of the fish, 
     <lb/>
     paper and mineral money. What follows from 
     <lb/>
     this? That it is absolutely necessary for this 
     <lb/>
     country to make the cost of fishing, of manufac<lb break="no"/>turing paper, of mining, as cheap as we can make 
     <lb/>
     it. Are we doing that? Yes, I am afraid we are. 
     <lb/>
     How? Down through the years whenever we 
     <lb/>
     wanted to cut down the cost of producing fish we 
     <lb/>
     cut down the price we gave the fishermen. How 
     <lb/>
     did we cut down the cost of producing iron ore? 
     <lb/>
     By cutting the wages of the miners. And how did 
     <lb/>
     we cut down the price of paper? By cutting the 
     <lb/>
     wages of the men in the mills. But that is not the 
     <lb/>
     way to do it. One way is to cut down the cost of 
     <lb/>
     living, and these local factories are not cutting it 
     <lb/>
     down, they are making it higher. That's what is 
     <lb/>
     meant in this paragraph here. What does it say? 
     <lb/>
     They received 39 replies, which in their case 
     <lb/>
     showed a yearly total of wages, salaries, etc. of 
     <lb/>
     $3,981,000, and a yearly total of taxes, including 
     <lb/>
     customs, taxes, excise, etc. of $4,800,000. Where 
    

            <pb n="297" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0297.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">297</fw>
         
     did that $4,800,000 come from? It came from the 
     <lb/>
     fishermen, the paper makers and forest workers 
     <lb/>
     and from the miners in Bell Island and Buchans 
     <lb/>
     by making the cost of living higher. That's what 
     <lb/>
     the local industries mean. I am far from satisfied 
     <lb/>
     with what this report shows, but I don't blame the 
     <lb/>
     Committee. It is one of the things that we have 
     <lb/>
     kept hidden in this country. I only know a few 
     <lb/>
     men, some in this house today, who are very 
     <lb/>
     much alive to the effect of the protective tariff. 
     <lb/>
     Here it says, "It can be clearly understood that the 
     <lb/>
     tariff in effect today is a revenue tariff." Who says 
     <lb/>
     it is? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> The Committee disagrees with 
     <lb/>
     that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> They have a perfect right to do 
     <lb/>
     so, just as I have a perfect right to disagree with 
     <lb/>
     the Committee. You can't say that our tariff in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland today is a protective tariff, or a 
     <lb/>
     revenue tariff, it is both, and the people pay it all. 
     <lb/>
     Every cent of it comes out of the fish and the 
     <lb/>
     paper and the minerals, and drives up the cost of 
     <lb/>
     living. Some day someone has got to get down to 
     <lb/>
     brass tacks and find out once and for all just how 
     <lb/>
     far these local industries are justified, just how far 
     <lb/>
     it pays the 315,000 of our population to have this 
     <lb/>
     protection on these local industries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I believe in local industries. I would be a 
     <lb/>
     terrible fool if I did not, but what industries? I 
     <lb/>
     believe in the industries that are natural to the 
     <lb/>
     country, eg. fish.... We have the raw material 
     <lb/>
     right here, and it is only a matter of hauling it out 
     <lb/>
     of the water and curing it, tinning or bottling or 
     <lb/>
     freezing it. Let's encourage the industry in every 
     <lb/>
     way. What else is natural? Paper making, because 
     <lb/>
     we have the timber and the waterpower. 
     <lb/>
     Minerals, because we have the minerals. Furring, 
     <lb/>
     because we have the animals, and gaming be<lb break="no"/>cause we have the game. These are the industries 
     <lb/>
     we ought to foster and protect. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     You have it summed up magnificently by the 
     <lb/>
     Industrial Development Board, if I can anticipate 
     <lb/>
     just for a moment. "The local Industrial Board 
     <lb/>
     have done a fine job ... considered the possibility 
     <lb/>
     of making cement". That's all right because we 
     <lb/>
     have the raw material to make cement. They sent 
     <lb/>
     away samples and had them analysed and the 
     <lb/>
     report came back that it would make a first-class 
     <lb/>
     Portland cement. But why could they not go 
     <lb/>
     ahead with a cement industry? Because some of 
     <lb/>
     the raw materials are on one side of the island, 
   

            <cb/>
            
     and the rest on the other side, and it would be too 
     <lb/>
     expensive to bring them together to manufacture 
     <lb/>
     them into cement. All you have to do is put a high 
     <lb/>
     tariff on imported cement. Make out the cost of 
     <lb/>
     bringing the raw materials together from east and 
     <lb/>
     west and the cost of manufacturing them, and it 
     <lb/>
     comes to $5 a bag to produce it here in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. Well, make the price $5.60 for the 
     <lb/>
     imported cement by putting on a high tariff. If 
     <lb/>
     you can do it for other things why not do it for 
     <lb/>
     cement? Putting a protective tariff on an imported 
     <lb/>
     article makes it more expensive then the local 
     <lb/>
     article and drives up the cost ofliving. It was said 
     <lb/>
     by Major Cashin 20 years ago, and it is a wonder<lb break="no"/>ful thing how Major Cashin and l are growing to 
     <lb/>
     agree with each other, I hope to convert him 
     <lb/>
     before I am finished! Some day we have got to 
     <lb/>
     go into this question of our tariff, above all our 
     <lb/>
     protective tariff.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I don't want to say too much because the man 
     <lb/>
     who will stand up and express any doubt that 
     <lb/>
     these local factories are divinely blessed is likely 
     <lb/>
     to be hounded out of the island. I agree they are 
     <lb/>
     an imposition, and the people of the country will 
     <lb/>
     never live while these duties are on, and they have 
     <lb/>
     got to come off. I had better sit down before I say 
     <lb/>
     too much. I am not saying a word against Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Hickman's committee, or against him. The 
     <lb/>
     figures are not here, and the government have not 
     <lb/>
     got them. If they had a royal commission they 
     <lb/>
     would not get them. You can't blame the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee for not bringing in information that the 
     <lb/>
     government has not got. I had to get this off my 
     <lb/>
     chest or burst. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Now that Mr. Smallwood has not 
     <lb/>
     completely burst, I want to make a comment that 
     <lb/>
     I am sure he will answer. I am a little upset about 
     <lb/>
     this unholy alliance of Mr. Smallwood and Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin, but I suppose these things are bound to 
     <lb/>
     happen! The thing that puzzles me is that we have 
     <lb/>
     30 manufacturers making returns, and in these 
     <lb/>
     concerns there are 2,300 employees. And if these 
     <lb/>
     are burned or closed down what would be the 
     <lb/>
     position of these employees of all those con<lb break="no"/>cerns? What would they do? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Let us take any given article, 
     <lb/>
     say a microphone (a very favourite article of 
     <lb/>
     mine); say there is a factory manufacturing them 
     <lb/>
     in St. John's. The materials have to be imported, 
     <lb/>
     so the government puts a duty on the raw material 
     <lb/>
     used to make these microphones of say 30%, but 
  

            <pb n="298" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0298.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">298</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
          

     on the completed microphone that might be im<lb break="no"/>ported into the country they put a duty of 40% or 
     <lb/>
     50%, which is aprotection of 10% or 20%. I don't 
     <lb/>
     say close down the manufacturers, I say take off 
     <lb/>
     the 30% duty on the raw materials, and all the 
     <lb/>
     duty on the finished article, wipe out the duty 
     <lb/>
     completely. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> What is the real difference then so 
     <lb/>
     far as profits to these manufacturers are con<lb break="no"/>cerned? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am not worried about the 
     <lb/>
     profits, I am worried about the cost of living — I 
     <lb/>
     have to pay more, like all of us. I am not a 
     <lb/>
     shareholder in a local factory, if I were — I am 
     <lb/>
     big enough to know what human nature is like — 
     <lb/>
     no doubt I would like a high protective tariff, no 
     <lb/>
     duty at all on the raw material, but say 50% or 
     <lb/>
     60% on the finished article, so that I would have 
     <lb/>
     a protective tariff of 40% or 50%. That's if I were 
     <lb/>
     a shareholder. I am a consumer, and so are all of 
     <lb/>
     us, and I am interested only in the cost of living. 
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Whilst I don't disagree with you, 
     <lb/>how is the government going to make up the 
     <lb/>difference in their duties under your scheme? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, Mr. Cashin told us a few 
     <lb/>minutes ago what he said 20 years ago, and I will 
     <lb/>remind you of what I said 20 years ago in the 
     <lb/>MCLI<ref target="#fn_02">[1]</ref> in a debate they had up there. I said the 
     <lb/>day would come in Newfoundland when there 
     <lb/>would be a political party and on their banner 
     <lb/>they would inscribe two words "Direct Taxa<lb break="no"/>tion", not indirect taxation as you have today in 
     <lb/>our customs tariff. The Chadwick-Jones report 
     <lb/>tells us that in the last year they report the per<lb break="no"/>centage of the total revenue was risen to 30% — 
     <lb/>30 cents out of every dollar they took in direct 
     <lb/>taxation, but that still left you 70 cents to the 
     <lb/>dollar that was taken in by indirect taxation. I 
     <lb/>would say it ought to be the other way about — 
     <lb/>70% by direct taxation and not more than 30% by 
     <lb/>indirect taxation. That is what is crucifying the 
     <lb/>people of this country and always did.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There was a time in Newfoundland when the 
     <lb/>
     tariff amounted to 8% or 10%. Go back 20 or 30 
     <lb/>
     years ago, when you got a duty of 20% it was 
     <lb/>
     something unusual. It was the same as it is in 
     <lb/>
     Canada today, about 10%. You take all our im<lb break="no"/>ports into Newfoundland last year, you will find 
     <lb/>
     it in the Chadwick-Jones report, lump them all 
     <lb/>
     together and what was the average rate of duty? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     25%. It would be much higher than that if we took 
     <lb/>
     out the free list, the flour and beef, etc., that pays 
     <lb/>
     no duty. It would probably be 40% or more. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We wonder why the cost of living is so high, 
     <lb/>
     and we blame the merchants and the shop<lb break="no"/>keepers. Maybe some do deserve it, I think there 
     <lb/>
     is some profiteering, but the real trouble is the 
     <lb/>
     tariff: $19 million we paid the government last 
     <lb/>
     year in duty, and on it $10 million profit, that's 
     <lb/>
     $29 million our tariff tacked on to the cost of 
     <lb/>
     living. There is only one cure for it, to cut the duty 
     <lb/>
     out altogether. A few may be hurt, but I don't 
     <lb/>
     think there is any need to burn down the factories 
     <lb/>
     or shut them down. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> You don't agree with Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin then? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> He did not really mean that, but 
     <lb/>
     he meant that if you took every employee and 
     <lb/>
     gave them their present wages it would be a 
     <lb/>
     couple of million dollars.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> About $4 million a year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, it would pay this country, 
     <lb/>
     it would pay them well, first to shut down the 
     <lb/>
     factories; second to pay out that $4 million from 
     <lb/>
     the treasury in wages and let them go idle, doing 
     <lb/>
     nothing (we could not do that I know, but it would 
     <lb/>
     pay them); and third to take the duty off and let 
     <lb/>
     the cost of living come down. As Major Cashin 
     <lb/>
     says, cut out these tariffs and let the people live 
     <lb/>
     and breathe which they have never been able to 
     <lb/>
     do. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> A few of the remarks Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood has made we have pointed out in the 
     <lb/>
     report. He has not taken them into account. I refer 
     <lb/>
     to one remark on page 8, this $4,800,000 which 
     <lb/>
     he implied, and rightly so, came out of the pock<lb break="no"/>ets of the people who made the money. He im<lb break="no"/>plied that if those local industries were not there 
     <lb/>
     the people would not have had to pay that money. 
     <lb/>
     They still would have had to pay it, and perhaps 
     <lb/>
     more. There are certain local industries that do 
     <lb/>
     make things cheaper than the imported articles. 
     <lb/>
     Another thing he said was that local industries are 
     <lb/>
     driving up the cost of goods. We have found that 
     <lb/>
     in many cases the tariff has been reduced since 
     <lb/>
     these companies have been in business. There is 
     <lb/>
     one, clothing, which ran to 65% duty, and is down 
     <lb/>
     today to 35% in spite of local industries being 
     <lb/>
     here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Was the duty on raw material 
     

    <note xml:id="fn_02">The Methodist College Literary Institute; a St. John's debating society. </note>
     

            <pb n="299" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0299.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">299</fw> 
   

     reduced also? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Not that I know of. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Do you mean they are still 
     <lb/>
     paying the same duty on the raw materials? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> To my knowledge. Here again 
     <lb/>
     there is one case brought up in the Committee. 
     <lb/>
     Some years ago the question of biscuits was 
     <lb/>
     brought up and we discovered that the fancy 
     <lb/>
     biscuits brought in here sold for 85 cents a pound. 
     <lb/>
     The local people bought them out and the im<lb break="no"/>ported ones were reduced to 45 cents a pound 
     <lb/>
     immediately. There are certain instances like that 
     <lb/>
     that we recommend there be a thorough study on. 
     <lb/>
     I think that the sweeping statement you made 
     <lb/>
     should be left until the true picture is brought out. 
     <lb/>
      </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am trying to bring a plea to 
     <lb/>have the facts brought out. I don't say the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee can do it, but I am only pleading that it be 
     <lb/>done, and let us know where we stand. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> I have served on the Local In<lb break="no"/>dustries Board, and I did not intend to have a 
     <lb/>
     word to say. I prefer to sit back and listen until 
     <lb/>
     the report at least is read; but I have listened to 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood bawling until our eardrums are 
     <lb/>
     ready to burst, and if I had my way I would have 
     <lb/>
     the microphones fired out of this room today and 
     <lb/>
     save the people from having to listen to all this. 
     <lb/>
     Local industries made the United States and 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and are helping to make Newfoundland; 
     <lb/>
     and in the town where I come from they help 
     <lb/>
     support a good number of people, and no man 
     <lb/>
     should attack them. The tariff question is another 
     <lb/>
     matter altogether, and in our report, where we had 
     <lb/>
     doubt about the question of tariff we asked the 
     <lb/>
     Convention to investigate. Common courtesy 
     <lb/>
     would expect members to listen to the whole 
     <lb/>
     report before they make any loud attacks on 
     <lb/>
     industries as a whole. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am sorry if I have offended 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Penney. I hope that on reflection he will agree 
     <lb/>
     that I have not attacked local industries. I have 
     <lb/>
     not done so. I have attacked tariff protection of 
     <lb/>
     them. In the very fine and historic town from 
     <lb/>
     which Mr. Penney comes, Carbonear, they have 
     <lb/>
     a very fine industry over there, but it is not 
     <lb/>
     protected. It is a magnificent wood industry, and 
     <lb/>
     is one of the industries that are natural to the 
     <lb/>
     country. The raw material is here and you don't 
     <lb/>
     need any tariff protection. Take for instance your 
     <lb/>
     paper industry, that is not protected, on the con<lb break="no"/>trary there is a customs duty on many things that 
   

            <cb/>
           

     go into it, which are helping to hurt it. They have 
     <lb/>
     no protective tariff, but they have to pay duty on 
     <lb/>
     the things that go into it. The industry Mr. Penney 
     <lb/>
     refers to is not only not protected, but it is hurt 
     <lb/>
     because they have to pay duty on some of their 
     <lb/>
     raw material. I say take off the duty and give that 
     <lb/>
     industry a better chance than it has. I am sorry 
     <lb/>
     that I bawled. I can't change my voice any more 
     <lb/>
     than Mr. Penney can change the shape of his nose. 
     <lb/>
     I can't help it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> I believe Mr. Smallwood is ad<lb break="no"/>vocating free trade. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Would you expect a little country 
     <lb/>
     like Newfoundland to take off the duty, when 
     <lb/>
     only a few days ago one of our industries is up 
     <lb/>
     for a higher tariff? They want to put 50% more 
     <lb/>
     on our fish, and you advocate free trade when the 
     <lb/>
     United States is advocating a higher rate of duty 
     <lb/>
     on our fish going in there? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I hope no one jumps on me, but 
     <lb/>
     maybe the cure is along the lines that Mr. Job is 
     <lb/>
     suggesting. Maybe we can let their goods come 
     <lb/>
     in here duty free and they will let our goods go in 
     <lb/>
     there duty free. You might have complete free 
     <lb/>
     trade between the USA and Newfoundland. Why 
     <lb/>
     not? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Where are the employees 
     <lb/>
     depending on local industries going to get off? 
     <lb/>
     There is also Norway and Sweden and other 
     <lb/>
     places competing with us for our fish, and where 
     <lb/>
     could we get off? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Might I ask the convenor of the 
     <lb/>
     Committee, and Mr. Smallwood, whether or not 
     <lb/>
     the protective tariff is a thing unknown in any 
     <lb/>
     other part of the world, or is it just here? Are there 
     <lb/>
     protective tariffs in Canada? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Yes, there are... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> May I correct Mr. Smallwood? He 
     <lb/>
     said there was no duty on lumber coming into this 
     <lb/>
     country. There is a duty on lumber coming into 
     <lb/>
     this country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There might as well not be. If 
     <lb/>
     there is a local tariff for local lumber it is a pure 
     <lb/>
     waste of printer's ink... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I agree with Mr. Penney that it is a 
     <lb/>
     pity that we started this argument before the thing 
     <lb/>
     has been read, however I would refer to the 
     <lb/>
     returns of the tobacco and cordage companies, 
     <lb/>
     where the totals are grouped as one. Why is that 
     <lb/>
     done? I note that these three items pay wages, 
   

            <pb n="300" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0300.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">300</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
         
     salaries, commissions, etc., of $480,000. Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin has told us that tobacco alone has a pro<lb break="no"/>tection of $552,000. If they are, we are paying 
     <lb/>
     protection of that amount in order to pay out 
     <lb/>
     much less than $480,000 in wages 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am a little bit disturbed by the Committee's 
     <lb/>
     report that they were unable to get the facts from 
     <lb/>
     the manufacturers. When people hesitate to dis<lb break="no"/>close certain matters, especially when these mat<lb break="no"/>ters are essential to us here, I am concerned about 
     <lb/>
     it. I don't want them to disclose their dead secrets, 
     <lb/>
     but they should be able to give us something that 
     <lb/>
     would be of assistance to us in coming to a full 
     <lb/>
     appraisal. Iagree in a good many ways with what 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood has said. There is no question 
     <lb/>
     that he has something here into which he can get 
     <lb/>
     his teeth, and he certainly got them in. I expect 
     <lb/>
     we shall hear more from other members of this 
     <lb/>
     Convention with regard to this report. I predict 
     <lb/>
     for it a very stormy passage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On page 4 of the report, after telling us how 
     <lb/>
     difficult it was for you to find the facts, you say 
     <lb/>
     there is an Industrial Statistics Act. Why was it 
     <lb/>
     not possible for you to go to that department of 
     <lb/>
     the government and ask them, under that act, to 
     <lb/>
     get the necessary information for you? If the act 
     <lb/>
     is there it is their duty to find it. Did you approach 
     <lb/>
     any person in that department and ask if they 
     <lb/>
     could get the information under that act? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> We approached the department 
     <lb/>
     that was handling that, and were told that that act 
     <lb/>
     was put on the books in 1938, and that the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment of Public Health and Welfare used it for 
     <lb/>
     acquiring statistics covering the number of 
     <lb/>
     employees in the various manufacturing con<lb break="no"/>cerns and businesses and their wages. At that time 
     <lb/>
     there were people on relief, and it was used to 
     <lb/>
     check the earning and the number of people 
     <lb/>
     employed. After that period it was not found 
     <lb/>
     necessary for the department to have those 
     <lb/>
     figures, as unemployment became unknown due 
     <lb/>
     to the bases, etc. We asked the department if we 
     <lb/>
     could have this information obtained through the 
     <lb/>
     act. We were advised that it had been transferred 
     <lb/>
     to the Department of Public Utilities, and it 
     <lb/>
     would be in the hands of the Labour Relations 
     <lb/>
     Office. On making inquiries of that department 
     <lb/>
     we found that they did not know it had been 
     <lb/>
     cancelled. After a while we found it would be 
     <lb/>
     under Public Utilities and the Labour Relations 
     <lb/>
     Officer, and we then found that it only covered 
     

            <cb/>
           
     employees and wages, and did not cover the great 
     <lb/>
     majority of questions that we wanted. We then 
     <lb/>
     found that to get those particulars which the act 
     <lb/>
     was empowered to obtain would take so long that 
     <lb/>
     it would delay us for months.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary continued reading the report]</hi> 
     <lb/>
     
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I wonder if Mr. Hickman 
     <lb/>would explain column 5 on page 3. It says "Pur<lb break="no"/>chases of Local Raw Materials and Expenses". 
     <lb/>What would the local raw materials amounting to 
     <lb/>$2.25 million? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Without looking up any actual 
     <lb/>
     returns, we did not ask the firms to specify, it 
     <lb/>
     would include packages, wood, shucks, barrels, 
     <lb/>
     berries, and local produce manufactured locally, 
     <lb/>
     bottles, etc. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Milk? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Yes, milk that would go into but<lb break="no"/>ter and ice-cream. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> In computing the value of 
     <lb/>
     these local industries it strikes me that we should 
     <lb/>
     have some idea of the amount that these com<lb break="no"/>panies pay in corporation taxes. I don't see any<lb break="no"/>thing here concerning that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> You mean profit taxes? Well, 
     <lb/>
     that was a question that, after consideration, we 
     <lb/>
     did not like to put in the questionnaire. We did 
     <lb/>
     not expect to get any replies if we asked what 
     <lb/>
     profit taxes were paid. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> That is an asset to the country, 
     <lb/>
     the amount of taxes that the country is paid. 
     <lb/>
     
 </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I agree with Mr. MacDonald that 
     <lb/>we ought to know what we ought to expect in 
     <lb/>connection with that. In the Mining Committee 
     <lb/>we approached the big companies and asked 
     <lb/>them that, and they had no hesitation in giving us 
     <lb/>the information. Why should your Committee be 
     <lb/>careful of asking those local corporations for that 
     <lb/>information? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> In the case of a large corporation 
     <lb/>
     their balance sheet is probably published 
     <lb/>
     anyway, but in the case of local small companies 
     <lb/>
     we felt that if we asked the question we would 
     <lb/>
     not have any answer given us as to income tax, 
     <lb/>
     and they might not have answered a lot of the 
     <lb/>
     questionnaires, with the result that we would not 
     <lb/>
     have as much information as we did get. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> We asked the Assessor of Taxes if 
     <lb/>
     we could have that information and he said no, 
     <lb/>
     but the corporations themselves did give it to us. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> I think with Mr. Hollett that these 
     
            <pb n="301" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0301.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">301</fw>
          

     large companies did give their figures and we 
     <lb/>
     were given permission to use these figures as a 
     <lb/>
     gross total. There is one other point that I would 
     <lb/>
     have liked to have seen in this report, and that is 
     <lb/>
     on the protective tariff, the duties as they would 
     <lb/>
     have regularly been, provided we did not have 
     <lb/>
     that industry here at all. As I see it, this discussion 
     <lb/>
     got a bit away from that, we got down to drawing 
     <lb/>
     examples on the basis of no duties at all. I don't 
     <lb/>
     think that situation has any relation at all when 
     <lb/>
     we are dealing with protective tariffs. I think that 
     <lb/>
     had these tariffs in relation to the different matters 
     <lb/>
     as we found them been figured out, and if we had 
     <lb/>
     a tabulation on these things, that a few figures 
     <lb/>
     there might speak more than a lot of words.... 
     <lb/>
      </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> On page 8, the last paragraph, 
     <lb/>I wonder if Mr. Hickman would mention that. It 
     <lb/>says: "It can therefore be seen rather than 
     <lb/>season work which might be directly or indirectly 
     <lb/>dependent on that fisheries...." It that means any<lb break="no"/>thing, it means that there should be local in<lb break="no"/>dustries to provide wages, but which would not 
     <lb/>be either directly or indirectly dependent on the 
     <lb/>fisheries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> It would be dependent on them as 
     <lb/>
     far as the money would derive from these basic 
     <lb/>
     industries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> What do you mean by secon<lb break="no"/>dary industries? You don't mean that Corner 
     <lb/>
     Brook and Buchans and Grand Falls are secon<lb break="no"/>dary do you? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> No, they are basic industries. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, what kind of industry 
     <lb/>could you have that would not be directly or 
     <lb/>indirectly dependent on these? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> That means not dependent on the 
     <lb/>
     fisheries as a cooper, or a longshoreman or any<lb break="no"/>thing of that sort. Someone who is making some<lb break="no"/>thing that can be sold to the consumer, and which 
     <lb/>
     would provide employment to people who are 
     <lb/>
     today getting employment in the United States or 
     <lb/>
     elsewhere. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> You should have left out that 
     <lb/>
     word "indirectly", because it is almost impos<lb break="no"/>sible to get an industry which is not indirectly 
     <lb/>
     dependent on the fisheries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Again on page 8, you consulted the 
     <lb/>
     Board of Trade committee and you say that they 
     <lb/>
     supplied to us figures that they had received in 
     <lb/>
     reply to their questionnaire. Are these figures in 
     <lb/>
     the report? I don't see them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Only what is contained in that 
     <lb/>
     paragraph. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Mr. Chairman, I wonder would the 
     <lb/>
     chairman of the Local Industries Committee say 
     <lb/>
     whether or not they had written W.J. Lundrigan 
     <lb/>
     of Corner Brook in connection with his plant 
     <lb/>
     there, as there are a number of men employed 
     <lb/>
     there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> We sent out to all known 
     <lb/>
     manufacturers or local industries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Did you get a reply from him? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Yes, but we stated that their reply 
     <lb/>
     would be kept confidential and only used in the 
     <lb/>
     total of the category referred to. It was on that 
     <lb/>
     basis that they submitted it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Would you mind stating whether he 
     <lb/>
     said what the number of employees was that he 
     <lb/>
     had there? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I think he did. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I have some knowledge of that firm, 
     <lb/>
     because our organisation has an agreement with 
     <lb/>
     that man, and I am prepared to state here that the 
     <lb/>
     rate of wages paid in this wood working plant is 
     <lb/>
     far better than anything else paid anywhere in the 
     <lb/>
     island for local wages. The great bulk of that is 
     <lb/>
     from this particular wood working plant to which 
     <lb/>
     I refer.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I see here under boots and shoes, 102 
     <lb/>
     employees, $13,000 duty and excise, $150,000 
     <lb/>
     volume of business, $120,000 capital. For once I 
     <lb/>
     am going to agree with Mr. Smallwood on one 
     <lb/>
     thing. I wonder at what cost to this country that 
     <lb/>
     local industry is carried on. At the end of the last 
     <lb/>
     war I came in contact with quite a bunch of men 
     <lb/>
     who were interested in changing the map of 
     <lb/>
     Europe. One of those rose to a pretty prominent 
     <lb/>
     position in the Czechoslovakian government, and 
     <lb/>
     he explained to me what was going to take place 
     <lb/>
     and what was going to be put into the boot and 
     <lb/>
     shoe industry there. He spoke also of the good 
     <lb/>
     quality of our herring. I suppose today the 
     <lb/>
     country has got an idea of the consumption of 
     <lb/>
     herring in Middle Europe, as they call it. The 
     <lb/>
     humble herring may be nothing at all in this 
     <lb/>
     country, but in those countries it is a luxury. I was 
     <lb/>
     interested, and at that time we had a big export of 
     <lb/>
     herring from this country, but unfortunately, due 
     <lb/>
     to the depression and not being handled right, we 
     <lb/>
     lost that market.... Those chaps, apparently they 
     <lb/>
     were very intelligent and well educated. I 
     <lb/>
     thought, if he banks on going into that position it 
  

            <pb n="302" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0302.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">302</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
         

     might be all right to get together, and, I do not 
     <lb/>
     understand much about it, but there is a trade 
     <lb/>
     agreement — you buy your stuff from me and I 
     <lb/>
     will buy from you. I supported Sir Richard 
     <lb/>
     Squires and went down with him. I said to him 
     <lb/>
     once, "I don't know much about what can be 
     <lb/>
     done, I am not in the government, but I believe if 
     <lb/>
     this was gone into right we could get the thin edge 
     <lb/>
     of the wedge into Middle Europe". He said, 
     <lb/>
     "What has Czechoslovakia got?" I said, "Boots 
     <lb/>
     and shoes", and he said, "We have a local in<lb break="no"/>dustry". "Well," I said, "we can't produce shoes 
     <lb/>
     as cheap as we can herring, and if we don't 
     <lb/>
     produce herring we can't buy shoes whether we 
     <lb/>
     buy them here or not." That's the position. The 
     <lb/>
     first man in this country that you have got to look 
     <lb/>
     to is the primary producer — the fisherman. We 
     <lb/>
     had only a small pulp and paper industry at that 
     <lb/>
     time, and there was lots of talk of the Humber, 
     <lb/>
     and things were pretty tough when fish dropped 
     <lb/>
     from $19 a quintal to around $8. Things were 
     <lb/>
     hitting the fishermen pretty hard. Well, he said he 
     <lb/>
     would take it up and see whatcould be done about 
     <lb/>
     it. He went into it and a month or so afterwards I 
     <lb/>
     happened to go down to Mr. Halfyard's and Sir 
     <lb/>
     Richard was there, and he told me there was 
     <lb/>
     nothing could be done about it because of the 
     <lb/>
     local industries.... We could have been putting 
     <lb/>
     one million barrels of herring into Europe. Now 
     <lb/>
     suppose that one million barrels only gave the 
     <lb/>
     fishermen perhaps $5 a barrel, what would it have 
     <lb/>
     meant to this country during the depression? Ac<lb break="no"/>cording to Sir Richard — I won't malign the man 
     <lb/>
     — the local shoe industry meant more to this 
     <lb/>
     country, but according to what I have heard there 
     <lb/>
     were some boots and shoes imported into this 
     <lb/>
     country from Czechoslovakia; and children's 
     <lb/>
     shoes could have been laid down here for 80 cents 
     <lb/>
     a pair, women's for $1 and men's for $1.20. 
     <lb/>
     There was a tariff, I forget what it was called.... 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Anti-dumping clause. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I don't care who it hurts or who is 
     <lb/>
     responsible for it, whether they are dead or alive 
     <lb/>
     today, these men went a long way towards bring<lb break="no"/>ing on this country what we had in 1936. I made 
     <lb/>
     a census in 1939 in every village from Lead Cove 
     <lb/>
     to Summerside, Trinity Bay, and the number of 
     <lb/>
     people who died from TB between 1920 and 
     <lb/>
     1930, and between 1930 and 1939 trebled. 
     <lb/>
     Whoever is responsible for this sort of legislation 
     <lb/>
     in this country is responsible for the deaths of 
    

            <cb/>
            
     those people, or a part of it, because you can 
     <lb/>
     understand what it would have meant to this 
     <lb/>
     country if there had been $5 million, or only half 
     <lb/>
     that amount during those years. A few people 
     <lb/>
     have been enabled to go ahead and have a profit 
     <lb/>
     at the expense of the health and wealth of the 
     <lb/>
     primary producer of this country.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are not ashamed of anything we have done 
     <lb/>
     since we came here. If a royal commission came 
     <lb/>
     here they would have the power to find out the 
     <lb/>
     facts, but we have no power at all. I believe the 
     <lb/>
     words that Major Cashin said, "We are a glorified 
     <lb/>
     mock parliament", and that's all. We are not in a 
     <lb/>
     position to do anything. If the responsible 
     <lb/>
     government and Commission of Government 
     <lb/>
     had been up to their jobs, we could have walked 
     <lb/>
     into a certain office and got the information right 
     <lb/>
     away, and certainly they have enough offices, 
     <lb/>
     they are the biggest real estate owners in the 
     <lb/>
     country. We find out that this country has been 
     <lb/>
     run worse than anything I have ever seen in my 
     <lb/>
     life. I don't know who is responsible for it. It 
     <lb/>
     looks to me that we were never intended to find 
     <lb/>
     out the truth about this country.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Referring to the tobacco factory. I was here in 
     <lb/>
     St. John's in 1942 when one of the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioners came back from overseas and spoke for 
     <lb/>
     the boys, and asked people to give money to send 
     <lb/>
     them smokes. At the price we were paying for 
     <lb/>
     cigarettes it looked all right. I had been used to 
     <lb/>
     going to St. Pierre to buy Gem cigarettes for 60 
     <lb/>
     cents a carton, but this gentleman appealing for 
     <lb/>
     smokes for the boys — Wings, one of the 
     <lb/>
     cheapest cigarettes in the world — says, "You 
     <lb/>
     can buy these cigarettes for $1 .20 a carton", when 
     <lb/>
     the merchant in St. Pierre could buy them here 
     <lb/>
     and freight them to St. Pierre and sell them for 60 
     <lb/>
     cents a carton. I am wondering if the honourable 
     <lb/>
     gentleman had shares in the tobacco factory. This 
     <lb/>
     is one of the reason why the cost of living is as it 
     <lb/>
     is. I am not going to take up any more time on 
     <lb/>
     this. I am not against local industries, I believe 
     <lb/>
     we should have more, but let us produce what we 
     <lb/>
     can produce cheapest, and sell to the people who 
     <lb/>
     can manufacture cheapest, so that the cost of 
     <lb/>
     living can be kept down.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whatever government comes in, the first thing 
     <lb/>
     we have to do is find out who in this world can 
     <lb/>
     take our stuff from us that we can produce and 
     <lb/>
     sell, and take from them what they can produce 
     <lb/>
     the cheapest, and give our people a chance to live. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="303" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-07_Page_0303.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">303</fw>

            <p>
     Let us see that our men going to the fisheries get 
     <lb/>
     a square deal so that we can live as a country 
     <lb/>
     should live. 
     <lb/> </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Committee rose and reported progress.]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Gentlemen, I have to report to 
     <lb/>you that in pursuance of the plan adopted a couple 
     <lb/>of days ago at an informal session of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion, the following were elected to be members 
     <lb/>of the committee to interview His Excellency the 
     <lb/>Governor in Commission. These are the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the committee: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Hon. R.B. Job 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     Mr. C.A. Crosbie 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. G.F. Higgins, K.C. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. T.W. Ashbourne 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. J.R. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. I. Newell 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. F.T. Fogwill 
     <lb/>
     
      </p></quote>


            <p>It is necessary that we have a motion formally to 
     <lb/>confirm this election I will accept a motion now 
     <lb/>from any member of the Convention confirming 
     <lb/>the appointment of these gentlemen. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion was put and carried, and the Con<lb break="no"/>vention adjourned]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-06-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
   
            <!--<p>
     February 10, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Local Industries Committee:¹ 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I think perhaps it might be best if 
     <lb/>
     the Secretary would finish reading the report, and 
     <lb/>
     we could then take it all and debate it.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>[The Secretary read the second part of the report,<lb/>and Mr. Hickman answered a number of ques<lb break="no"/>tions]<lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Let us consider the appendix 
     <lb/>
     compiled by the Industrial Development Board, 
     <lb/>
     which strikes me as a constructive. report. They 
     <lb/>
     seem to have the same idea I have — to use up 
     <lb/>
     the raw materials we have here in the country 
     <lb/>
     rather than import. I do not think sealskins are 
     <lb/>
     mentioned, but that is an important item. They are 
     <lb/>
     exported raw. Why are they not manufactured 
     <lb/>
     here? Then the birch. What possibilities are there 
     <lb/>
     for manufacturing that here? Then, limestone. It 
     <lb/>
     seems from this report that limestone is sub- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sidised in Canada. To encourage agriculture, the 
     <lb/>
     government subsidises limestone to make it 
     <lb/>
     cheaper for farmers. Fish offal — perhaps Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Crosbie can tell us something about that. I was 
     <lb/>
     into a place in Labrador where there was 
     <lb/>
     machinery for turning fish guts, sound bones, and 
     <lb/>
     heads into fish meal. Then we come to seaweed. 
     <lb/>
     What do we find? "Processing firms in the USA 
     <lb/>
     when contacted re the establishment of branch 
     <lb/>
     plants in this country immediately asked for data 
     <lb/>
     on the quantities of the various species of 
     <lb/>
     seaweed available. This information, unfor<lb break="no"/>tunately, has never been compiled." Why not? 
     <lb/>
     They make blancmange out of seaweed. 
     <lb/>
     Blancmange is the usual Sunday dessert in New<lb break="no"/>foundland; and here we are importing 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     blancmange. Then wallboard, If they can make 
     <lb/>
     wallboard out of sawdust, why can't we put up a 
     <lb/>
     place to make wallboard? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> They are doing experimental 
     <lb/>
     work on that now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I know the Anglo-New- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     foundland Development Co. have been ex<lb break="no"/>perimenting with it. We have the raw materials 
     <lb/>
     for all those things. I know of one local factory in 
     <lb/>
     St. John's — it is true they are importing raw 
     <lb/>
     material — they are milking that factory to put 
     <lb/>
     the profits into another industry of the country. I 
     <lb/>
     like that very much.... I hope Mr. Job will tell us 
     <lb/>
     about sealskins and Mr. Crosbie about fish offal. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Job I take this opportunity of making a few 
     <lb/>remarks about Mr. Smallwood's ideas in regard 
     <lb/>to different industries. I am in accord with some 
     <lb/>of his ideas but I am not in accord with the drastic 
     <lb/>way in which he thinks local industries should be 
     <lb/>dealt with. Any local industry must have a small 
     <lb/>amount of protection and the most important 
     <lb/>thing about local industries is the employment. 
     <lb/>There are 3-4,000 men employed in local in<lb break="no"/>dustries, what would be the position if they were 
     <lb/>out of employment now? It is serious. I think it is 
     <lb/>helpful to the country generally. The other point 
     <lb/>is the enormous government revenue from those 
     <lb/>industries. I do not know how much. I do say that 
     <lb/>if any industry is receiving excessive protection, 
     <lb/>it should be remedied. Now, with regard to 
     <lb/>sealskins. The answer is simple. It has been tried 
     <lb/>on various occasions. The main trouble is foreign 
     <lb/>tariffs. Our sealskins go into the United States 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     ¹Volume II:54. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>