<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-12-13" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-12-13">13 December 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="221"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0209.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0210.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0211.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0212.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0213.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0214.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0215.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0216.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0217.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0218.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0219.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0220.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0209">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0209.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0210">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0210.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0211">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0211.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0212">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0212.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0213">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0213.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0214">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0214.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0215">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0215.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0216">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0216.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0217">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0217.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0218">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0218.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0219">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0219.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0220">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0220.jpg"/>
      </surface>
<surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0221">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0221.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="209" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0209.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> 

            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">209</fw>
    
<div type="section">    

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     December 13, 1946 
  </head>

            <head rendition="simple:centre">Report of the Transportation and Communications Committee:<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole</head>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman I would suggest 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Secretary might read the report on the 
     <lb/>
     tourist trade.<ref target="#fn_02">[2]</ref> There are two very long appen<lb break="no"/>dices attached to the report, and another not quite 
     <lb/>
     so long, three in all. It might not perhaps be 
     <lb/>
     necessary for these appendices to be read, al<lb break="no"/>though members would no doubt like to refer to 
     <lb/>
     them throughout the debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the report on the tourist 
     <lb/>
     trade]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOWL2">Mr. Fowler</persName> I would like all the members 
     <lb/>
     present to know that my knowledge of the Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board<ref target="#fn_03">[3]</ref> is comparatively new, and chiefly con<lb break="no"/>fined to this report, and the correspondence I have 
     <lb/>
     lately read in the press as a result of the resigna<lb break="no"/>tion of the Tourist Board. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The opening remarks of the Committee sug<lb break="no"/>gested that the Tourist Board's work was one of 
     <lb/>
     the bright spots in the country's affairs. It has 
     <lb/>
     been demonstrated quite clearly that the Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board has more than given good returns for the 
     <lb/>
     money they expended. It is incomprehensible 
     <lb/>
     that the work of the Board has been treated in 
     <lb/>
     such a careless fashion by the Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government. The mind of a government that will 
     <lb/>
     look at the work of the Tourist Board, that has 
     <lb/>
     worked voluntarily over a period of 20 years, and 
     <lb/>
     dismiss their labours in such a summary fashion, 
     <lb/>
     is beyond my comprehension. I can only assume 
     <lb/>
     that the gentlemen handling our affairs are not 
     <lb/>
     only utterly callous to the future of our country, 
     <lb/>
     but actually do not want to see this country 
     <lb/>
     prosper. It is apparent that tourist traffic can be a 
     <lb/>
     major industry but for reasons best known to 
     <lb/>
     themselves the Commission of Government are 
     <lb/>
     not going to see this industry properly developed. 
     <lb/>
     If we had the power I would like to move a vote 
     <lb/>
     of censure on the Commission of Government for 
     <lb/>
     their attitude towards the most important industry 
     <lb/>
     of the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The future of the tourist industry cannot be too 
     <lb/>
     strongly stressed. I am firmly convinced that with 
     <lb/>
     a proper approach it can be a wonderful asset to 
  
   
    
            <cb/>
         

     us. We have seen what the tourist industry in 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia has meant — why, in the last year 
     <lb/>
     alone the sum of $22 million was realised, Even 
     <lb/>
     with the very conservative figure of $50 per 
     <lb/>
     tourist in Newfoundland in the last year before 
     <lb/>
     the war, the sum of $346,500 was realised. I am 
     <lb/>
     certain that $50 is too conservative and at least 
     <lb/>
     the sum of $ 10 per day is spent by tourists coming 
     <lb/>
     to Newfoundland. This would mean that 
     <lb/>
     $750,000 came to the revenue in 1939. 
</p>

            <p>Newfoundland is the least explored country in 
     <lb/>the world as far as tourist traffic is concerned. It 
     <lb/>has a real attraction for tourists, and if we proper<lb break="no"/>ly develop the traffic Newfoundland is assured of 
     <lb/>a definite income that will increase as the years 
     <lb/>come. When we realise that for salmon fishing 
     <lb/>alone we have over 200 fishing streams, we can 
     <lb/>be sure that our country's possibilities are of 
     <lb/>immense value. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I heartily endorse everything Mr. 
     <lb/>Fowler has said. I agree with his condemnation 
     <lb/>of the powers that be over our tourist trade. I 
     <lb/>congratulate the Committee on a very fine and 
     <lb/>full report, because I see tremendous possibilities 
     <lb/>in the future for our tourist traffic. I, like a good 
     <lb/>number of you here, have gone over a great part 
     <lb/>of the country. I have observed it particularly 
     <lb/>from the tourist standpoint, because most of my 
     <lb/>wanderings have been for sport-fishing or shoot<lb break="no"/>ing. I am convinced it is a factor in the economy 
     <lb/>of our country. All we have to do is look nextdoor 
     <lb/>to our immediate neighbour, Canada and Nova 
     <lb/>Scotia alone, where the attractions are not a patch 
     <lb/>on our own, in spite of any ideas some people 
     <lb/>may have. We look at our own and we see that in 
     <lb/>1939, 6,900 tourists came here and spent an es<lb break="no"/>timated $346,500, and that for an expenditure by 
     <lb/>this government of $34,932. I am sure the figure 
     <lb/>of $50 spent by each tourist is very conservative 
     <lb/>and this $346,000 coming into the country can 
     <lb/>easily be doubled, or possibly trebled. In the past 
     <lb/>three years the Tourist Board's grant from the 
     <lb/>government has been $26,000, and we have seen 
   

       
<note xml:id="fn_01">[1] Volume 11:75. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>  

<note xml:id="fn_02">[2] Volume 11:123. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note> 

<note xml:id="fn_03">[3] The Tourist Development Board was a voluntary board staffed with a paid director operating under the 
     <lb/>Department of Public Works.</note>
 
            <pb n="210" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0210.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">210</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
         

     the returns. We saw the crowds of tourists in the 
     <lb/>
     country this year, even though no preparations 
     <lb/>
     had been made for their accommodation. We 
     <lb/>
     have seen all during the war years the potential 
     <lb/>
     visitors we will have, even if members of the 
     <lb/>
     forces and their relatives only came here once. 
     <lb/>
     All that goodwill that has been built up is in grave 
     <lb/>
     jeopardy by a government which, rightly or 
     <lb/>
     wrongly, is pursuing a most extraordinary policy. 
     <lb/>
     I have criticised Major Cashin in this House 
     <lb/>
     earlier in the debates about remarks made about 
     <lb/>
     this government. I am beginning to wonder if he 
     <lb/>
     is not right and I am wrong. Because the attitude 
     <lb/>
     of this government today is utterly incomprehen<lb break="no"/>sible; and your report, Mr. Smallwood, is the 
     <lb/>
     same thing. All we have to do is look at the 
     <lb/>
     correspondence between the Tourist Board and 
     <lb/>
     the Commissioner for Public Utilities leading up 
     <lb/>
     to the resignation, the most discourteous treat<lb break="no"/>ment any body of citizens was ever handed in this 
     <lb/>
     country by any government. It is hard to realise 
     <lb/>
     that in the Commission of Government are three 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlanders who subscribed to the letters 
     <lb/>
     shown in this correspondence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The correspondence began September, 1945, 
     <lb/>
     urging on the government the necessity of taking 
     <lb/>
     action about the tourist policy. After a lot of 
     <lb/>
     cajoling they finally agreed to have two experts, 
     <lb/>
     one at a time — the Mathes agency was the first 
     <lb/>
     one, they came down and made a survey in 1945, 
     <lb/>
     and they made their report.<ref target="#fn_04">[1]</ref> On page I you will 
     <lb/>
     note: "Has Newfoundland a tourism potential 
     <lb/>
     worth developing? Our answer is most emphati<lb break="no"/>cally YES." They give reasons why. You have 
     <lb/>
     the report of Oliver<ref target="#fn_05">[2]</ref> who comes back in his report 
     <lb/>
     this year entirely agreeing with the Mathes agen<lb break="no"/>cy. On page 1 Oliver says, "Newfoundland <hi rendition="simple:italic">has</hi> a 
     <lb/>
     very considerable tourist potential, and there 
     <lb/>
     should be no doubt of that. I have not attempted 
     <lb/>
     to detail it, because Mathes' presentation to your 
     <lb/>
     Board has already done so in comprehensive 
     <lb/>
     fashion." These two reports were all any govern<lb break="no"/>ment should need to be quite certain they were on 
     <lb/>
     the right track. They had their own Board's 
     <lb/>
     recommendation for years before that; their con<lb break="no"/>stant urging on the govemment for action; and 

            <cb/>
           

     then to bolster that position that had these two 
     <lb/>
     agencies make these very valuable reports. And 
     <lb/>
     what do they do? All we have to do is refer 
     <lb/>
     ourselves to the correspondence and we will see 
     <lb/>
     the most discouneous letter ever written by a 
     <lb/>
     government department to a semi-govemment 
     <lb/>
     agency. and written to nine men who comprise 
     <lb/>
     this Tourist Board — nine unpaid citizens who 
     <lb/>
     have given, some of them, 20 odd years of service 
     <lb/>
     to the country. Their names alone will tell you 
     <lb/>
     who they are and what their work means: 
     <lb/>
     W.A. Reid, J.F. Meehan, J.W. Allan, C.E.A. Jef<lb break="no"/>frey, A.B. Perlin, Leonard C. Outerbridge, Cyril 
     <lb/>
     Duley, A.W. Bentley, And, I believe, Herbert 
     <lb/>
     Russell, who did not sign the letter because he is 
     <lb/>
     an employee of the government and could not 
     <lb/>
     very well do so. They write the Commissioner for 
     <lb/>
     Public Utilities urging the implementing of these 
     <lb/>
     reports. The various letters show how they went 
     <lb/>
     about it. Mr. Reid wrote on 6 June to J.S. Neill, 
     <lb/>
     the Commissioner, and I want to read part of it: 
     <lb/>
     </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>With reference to the report on the tourist 
     <lb/>possibilities of Newfoundland, made by 
     <lb/>Mr. Douglas R. Oliver of Toronto, copy of 
     <lb/>which was forwarded to you on April 16th, I 
     <lb/>have to inform you that the Board has given 
     <lb/>careful consideration to this report, and con<lb break="no"/>siders it to be a sound and conservative ap<lb break="no"/>preciation of the situation, and is generally in 
     <lb/>accord with the recommendations and sug<lb break="no"/>gestions contained therein. If you will refer 
     <lb/>to my letter to the Hon. Sir George London 
     <lb/>of September 19, 1945, copy of which is 
     <lb/>enclosed. which sets forth very clearly the 
     <lb/>Board's views regarding what steps should 
     <lb/>be taken in this matter, you will see that the 
     <lb/>strong recommendation was made that im<lb break="no"/>mediate steps be taken to procure from the 
     <lb/>Canadian National Railways or some like 
     <lb/>source, the services of a thoroughly trained 
     <lb/>and competent executive from their tourist 
     <lb/>department. This man should come here 
     <lb/>without delay to study the situation and to 
     <lb/>make recommendations to the government as 
     <lb/>to the best form of organization which should 
     <lb/>set up for the development of the tourist 



<note xml:id="fn_04">[1] J.M. Mathes, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Tourism Potential in Newfoundland; an Investigation carried out by J.M. Mathes Inc.</hi> (New 
     <lb/>
     York, 1945). This survey was made on the request of the Nfld. Tourist Development Board. Volume II: 140. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note> 
 
<note xml:id="fn_05">[2] Douglas R. Oliver, <hi rendition="simple:italic">A Report on Newfoundland's Tourist Trade Position</hi> (Toronto, 1946). Volume 11:128. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>


            <pb n="211" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0211.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">211</fw>
        
     industry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As a result of this recommendation, 
     <lb/>
     authority was eventually given for Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Oliver's visit, which culminated in the report 
     <lb/>
     above referred to, and which confirms the 
     <lb/>
     contention of the Board and the opinions 
     <lb/>
     expressed by all those whose advice has been 
     <lb/>
     sought and who, it is believed, are in a posi<lb break="no"/>tion to speak with some authority on the 
     <lb/>
     subject, namely, that the tourist industry in 
     <lb/>
     this country is capable of successful develop<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is now the urgent request of the Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board that the recommendations contained 
     <lb/>
     in the report should be implemented as quick<lb break="no"/>ly as possible, particularly with regard to the 
     <lb/>
     setting up of a new government tourist or<lb break="no"/>ganization. Here let me say that it is the 
     <lb/>feeling of the Board that the head of this<lb/>organization should occupy a position<lb/>analogous to that of the chairman of the<lb/>Fisheries Board, or the manager of the New<lb break="no"/>foundland Railway.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I have been requested by the members of<lb/>the Board ... to set forth their position with<lb/>regard to the future of the Board's activities.<lb/>Just prior to the outbreak of the recent war,<lb/>the matter of the appointment of a full-time<lb/>director, and the general expansion of the<lb/>activities of the Board were under active<lb/>discussion with the Hon. Sir Wilfred Woods<lb/>who was at that time Commissioner for<lb/>Public Utilities. When the war intervened it<lb/>was agreed that for the duration of hostilities<lb/>tourist expenditure should be kept to a mini<lb break="no"/>mum ... but that the organizations in<lb/>St. John's and New York should be kept<lb/>together with a view to expansion to take<lb/>advantage of the anticipated post-war travel<lb/>demand. Two years ago the opportunity oc<lb break="no"/>curred to secure the services as director of<lb/>Mr. C.C. Duley, who has been associated<lb/>with the Board since its inception....<lb/>Mr. Duley became the Board's director, and<lb/>since that time, largely due to his efforts, an<lb/>intensive study of tourist possibilities in<lb/>selected localities has been made and various<lb/>recommendations forwarded to the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner. However, no indication of the government's attitude towards tourist development has been forthcoming, and no<lb/>
          
            <cb/>
            
     policy in this connection has been an<lb break="no"/>nounced. The members of the Board, some 
     <lb/>
     of whom have served for 20 years, now feel 
     <lb/>
     that they are entitled to a definite pronounce<lb break="no"/>ment from the government as to its policy 
     <lb/>
     with regard to the development of the tourist 
     <lb/>
     industry.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As you know, the members of the Board 
     <lb/>
     are all engaged in businesses of various kinds 
     <lb/>
     and it is therefore impossible for them to 
     <lb/>
     devote more than a certain portion of their 
     <lb/>
     time to this work. If, however, the develop<lb break="no"/>ment which we hope to see takes place, we 
     <lb/>
     are all prepared to do anything we can to be 
     <lb/>
     of assistance to the Government in this un<lb break="no"/>dertaking. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (signed) W.A. Reid, Chairman 
     <lb/>
     
            </p></quote>


            <p>That is the letter and I make no excuse for <lb/>
reading it at this length because the answer is all <lb/>
the more worthy of condemnation.... The answer <lb/>
to the letter was in this form. </p>

  
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>I should be glad if you would refer to your<lb/>letter of the 6th June, concerning the report<lb/>made by Mr. Douglas R. Oliver upon tourist<lb/>possibilities in Newfoundland.<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Your letter and Mr. Oliver's report were 
     <lb/>
     considered at a recent meeting of the Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government and 1 have been 
     <lb/>
     directed to inform you that, while the govern<lb break="no"/>ment believes the tourist industry in New<lb break="no"/>foundland is capable of development, it does 
     <lb/>
     not propose to incur expenditure in the erec<lb break="no"/>tion of accommodation for tourists, as it is 
     <lb/>
     felt that this is a matter for private enterprise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The need for additional roads is ap<lb break="no"/>preciated and progress is being made in this 
     <lb/>
     direction as quickly as circumstances will 
     <lb/>
     permit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As you are aware, the government is al<lb break="no"/>ready making a grant of $26,000 per annum 
     <lb/>
     to the Newfoundland Tourist Development 
     <lb/>
     Board. No doubt the sums so made available 
     <lb/>
     will continue to be expended to the best ad<lb break="no"/>vantage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The government is not prepared to estab<lb break="no"/>lish a new tourist and travel authority. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (signed) J.S. Neill. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>(for) Secretary for Public Works. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>We look at this programme — this expendi<lb break="no"/>ture of $59 million — and there was not one cent 
     <lb/>allocated to tourist traffic. It would definitely 
    

            <pb n="212" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0212.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">212</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
         

     indicate that the "Big 6" have made no allocation 
     <lb/>
     for anything in the way of tourist development. 
     <lb/>
     In spite of all the advice they have had, in spite 
     <lb/>
     of experts going over the country, they come 
     <lb/>
     back and say, "No, we have no interest." That is 
     <lb/>
     the only department of the government which 
     <lb/>
     produces money — big money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This Board has resigned and the next thing we 
     <lb/>
     will have is the paid personnel of the Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board receiving their notices at the end of the 
     <lb/>
     year. I do not think we should let the opportunity 
     <lb/>
     pass without at least expressing our opinion on 
     <lb/>
     the utterly ruthless policy of the government. It 
     <lb/>
     is the one department putting in time and effort 
     <lb/>
     and getting returns. But it does not meet with the 
     <lb/>
     approval of our rulers! It leads to the belief that 
     <lb/>
     has been expressed that the government does not 
     <lb/>
     want this country to become wealthy, for reasons 
     <lb/>
     best known to themselves. We have got to be kept 
     <lb/>
     in the condition of servitude so that we will not 
     <lb/>
     get too independent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If we refer to the paid personnel of the Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board, I know the work that has been done by 
     <lb/>
     them. They are not paid for working nights, Sun<lb break="no"/>days or holidays; but the Board has been there 
     <lb/>
     nights, Sundays and holidays. Even the voluntary 
     <lb/>
     workers have been there on such occasions. It has 
     <lb/>
     not cost the country anything, because the Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board and the paid personnel have been 
     <lb/>
     crusaders for their ideas rather than merely earn<lb break="no"/>ing government money. Some departments know 
     <lb/>
     what work has been done by that Board and their 
     <lb/>
     value; and the government expresses its thanks in 
     <lb/>
     three paragraphs. We have this letter addressed 
     <lb/>
     to Mr. Reid: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p rendition="simple:right">
     26 November 1946. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. I have the honour to acknowledge the 
     <lb/>
     receipt of the letter of the 15th November, 
     <lb/>
     addressed to His Excellency the Governor in 
     <lb/>
     Commission, signed by you and other mem<lb break="no"/>bers, tendering your resignation from the 
     <lb/>
     Board. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. I am directed to accept the resigna<lb break="no"/>tions. In doing so I am to express the thanks 
     <lb/>
     of the government for the services you have 
     <lb/>
     rendered and to express our regret that you 
     <lb/>
     have found it necessary to sever your connec<lb break="no"/>tion with the Board. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. I have sent a copy of this letter to the 
     <lb/>
     other signatories under reference. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     (signed) J.S. Neill 
   </p>
</quote>


            <p>After 20 years service, that is what the govern<lb break="no"/>ment thinks of our fellow countrymen. I think I 
     <lb/>have gone further than I intended to in this matter. 
     <lb/>That is such a rank injustice that I could not let it 
     <lb/>pass without giving you my comments as I feel 
     <lb/>them and as I believe a good many members felt 
     <lb/>today. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There are several points about 
     <lb/>tourist travel business that ought to be brought 
     <lb/>out. If an American or Canadian concern comes 
     <lb/>to Newfoundland to start a paper mill or a mine, 
     <lb/>we are all very glad. It means they employ New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders and pay out wages, it circulates 
     <lb/>money. But a paper mill or mine uses up some of 
     <lb/>this country's natural resources. There is this 
     <lb/>about the tourist trade; money is brought into 
     <lb/>Newfoundland by tourists who come here and 
     <lb/>spend and do not use up any of the natural resour<lb break="no"/>ces. You might also say it is money for not 
     <lb/>exactly nothing; they get pleasure out of our 
     <lb/>climate, our air, out of meeting our people and by 
     <lb/>knocking around the country. Some of them do 
     <lb/>take some salmon and other fish — that is a very 
     <lb/>small diminution of the resources. This Tourist 
     <lb/>Board, as Mr. Higgins said, has been working for 
     <lb/>something like 20 years, absolutely free. When 
     <lb/>the Tourist Board appeared before the Transpor<lb break="no"/>tation Committee I am sure all the members were 
     <lb/>deeply impressed.... These hard-headed, practi<lb break="no"/>cal businessmen are not easily impressed with the 
     <lb/>financial possibilities of anything. We were im<lb break="no"/>pressed by the great faith these men had in the 
     <lb/>tourist possibilities of Newfoundland. I have 
     <lb/>been a firm believer that the tourist trade con<lb break="no"/>stitutes the most promising thing we have in this 
     <lb/>country today. If Newfoundland in 1946 had 
     <lb/>been ready to receive them, Newfoundland could 
     <lb/>have got many, many thousands of the tourists 
     <lb/>who, in this present year, were spending $4 bil<lb break="no"/>lion on the North American continent. It would 
     <lb/>not take a great many million dollars to bring into 
     <lb/>Newfoundland each year 40,000 - 50,000 
     <lb/>tourists. If 100,000 tourists can be brought into 
     <lb/>Nova Scotia in one year, I feel quite confident 
     <lb/>that we can bring that number of tourists into 
     <lb/>Newfoundland for a fortnight or a month or six 
     <lb/>weeks and some even longer, every summer, it 
     <lb/>can mean $10 million or $15 million of new 
     <lb/>money coming in without costing the country 
     <lb/>anything in the way of its natural resources. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="213" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0213.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">213</fw>
            
<p>
     We have got to get away from the idea that the 
     <lb/>
     only tourists who can be brought in here are the 
     <lb/>
     men who come in for salmon fishing. That's the 
     <lb/>
     old idea, but this Mathes advertising agency of 
     <lb/>
     New York, a large and important American con<lb break="no"/>cern, who have specialised in the travel trade, 
     <lb/>
     representing many hotels and other tourist cater<lb break="no"/>ing organisations in the US, when they surveyed 
     <lb/>
     the tourist possibilities of Newfoundland they 
     <lb/>
     pointed out that this idea is entirely wrong. You 
     <lb/>
     will see listed one thing after another which to 
     <lb/>
     other people, Canadians and Americans, are 
     <lb/>
     quaint, unusual, appealing and interesting. When 
     <lb/>
     they spend three or four weeks here they go back 
     <lb/>
     thrilled and interested by the different accents 
     <lb/>
     they find, and the different scenery we have. 
     <lb/>
     These things have a cash value, and it does not 
     <lb/>
     cost anything for American or Canadian tourists 
     <lb/>
     to have a look at us. What stands in the way? This 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Douglas R. Oliver who submitted his report, 
     <lb/>
     spent five years as director of the Ontario 
     <lb/>
     government's   Trade and Tourist Bureau. Ontario 
     <lb/>
     gets most of the tourists who come into Canada, 
     <lb/>
     over one million tourists in a year.... So they bring 
     <lb/>
     this Mr. Oliver. He comes down and makes a 
     <lb/>
     study and looks over the various plans that the 
     <lb/>
     Board had drawn up, takes them back and sub<lb break="no"/>mits these plans to another man in Ontario, who 
     <lb/>
     is the manager of a firm which is catering to 
     <lb/>
     tourists, and operating a number of hotels, who 
     <lb/>
     looks over them with his expert eye and points 
     <lb/>
     out some weaknesses. For instance, the plan for 
     <lb/>
     Stephenville area.... There they propose that a 
     <lb/>
     tourist hotel should be built. Their original idea 
     <lb/>
     was that it would be one large building but 
     <lb/>
     when Mr. Oliver submitted that plan to that 
     <lb/>
     tourist hotel manager in Ontario, up in Muskoka 
     <lb/>
     Lakes, he said, "Look, all the experience we have 
     <lb/>
     shows that it would be a mistake to have one 
     <lb/>
     building to house all your tourists. Instead of that 
     <lb/>
     have one building, and a series of small cabins 
     <lb/>
     scattered through the trees around that large 
     <lb/>
     building. They can sleep in the cabins and eat in 
     <lb/>
     the hotel. You cut down the cost of accommoda<lb break="no"/>tion, heating, etc." Finally they got this report and 
     <lb/>
     presented it to the government. What are they 
     <lb/>
     asking the government to do — put up a lot of 
     <lb/>
     tourist hotels? No. They are asking for one only, 
     <lb/>
     in the west, centering around Stephenville, be<lb break="no"/>cause you have magnificient fishing and scenery 
     <lb/>
     there, and also Corner Brook. Hook up that by 
    

            <cb/>
      
     road, and your tourist can land by boat at Corner 
     <lb/>
     Brook and later on by air at Stephenville or 
     <lb/>
     Harmon Field, and coming east and west by road 
     <lb/>
     they can center around this Stephenville area. 
     <lb/>
     They have taken that as a seeding ground. Now, 
     <lb/>
     they said that if the government would build that 
     <lb/>
     hotel as an example, then if it worked out private 
     <lb/>
     capital would be encouraged to build the same 
     <lb/>
     kind of accomodation centres in the other areas.... 
     <lb/>
     If only the government would spend a few dol<lb break="no"/>lars. They have $30 million belonging to us ac<lb break="no"/>cumulated over these rich war years, and if they 
     <lb/>
     would build just one, beginning at Stephenville, 
     <lb/>
     as an encouragement and an example to other 
     <lb/>
     people, then in the course of a few years we might 
     <lb/>
     end up by having a magnificent tourist trade. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The government had no faith, belief, no inter<lb break="no"/>est in it, being just coldly indifferent to the whole 
     <lb/>
     thing, and you have the future of these eight or 
     <lb/>
     nine men of whom Mr. Higgins speaks, working 
     <lb/>
     their hearts out, giving their time and work, you 
     <lb/>
     would not know but the fate of the country 
     <lb/>
     depended on the way they have been working, 
     <lb/>
     and the government are completely indifferent to 
     <lb/>
     it. They have given them $180,000 in all those 
     <lb/>
     years, and for that in these same years the Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board hands back $4 million. If they can find a 
     <lb/>
     better proposition than that I would like them to 
     <lb/>
     lead me to it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If the people of Newfoundland only knew the 
     <lb/>
     possibilities there are for the tourist travel trade, 
     <lb/>
     if they could see the millions of dollars that could 
     <lb/>
     be brought into this country by merely spending 
     <lb/>
     a bit of money. What have they spent on land 
     <lb/>
     settlement schemes? Gone down the drain a lot 
     <lb/>
     of it. They have spent millions in the last ll years 
     <lb/>
     and what have they got to show for it? Here is a 
     <lb/>
     chance for them to spend one or two million and 
     <lb/>
     bring in perhaps a million a year.... We can only 
     <lb/>
     try to let the country know. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I think this matter has been 
     <lb/>
     well covered by previous speakers. I feel sorry 
     <lb/>
     that the Tourist Board has decided to retire. I 
     <lb/>
     guess they felt it was about the only thing that 
     <lb/>
     they could do — probably as a matter of protest. 
     <lb/>
     It is a natural consequence, after being no doubt 
     <lb/>
     greatly disappointed at the lack of encourage<lb break="no"/>ment, that they should feel as they do. We are 
     <lb/>
     situated on an island, and probably there was a 
     <lb/>
     time when people who perhaps had a certain fear 
     <lb/>
     of the sea hesitated to leave the mainland; but 


            <pb n="214" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0214.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">214</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>             <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
   
          

     today, with the advance and progress of air 
     <lb/>
     transport, we are in another and different situa<lb break="no"/>tion altogether... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As Mr. Smallwood said, we know we need 
     <lb/>
     accommodation in Newfoundland to look after 
     <lb/>
     tourists. We certainly want more road extensions, 
     <lb/>
     so that the roads will come to the piers and these 
     <lb/>
     people will have outlets so that they can come, 
     <lb/>
     see and enjoy our trout and salmon fishing, and 
     <lb/>
     also take in the beautiful scenery. Faith and a 
     <lb/>
     breadth of vision are essential in this matter, and 
     <lb/>
     I can only hope the resignation of this Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board will bring the matter to a head, and that the 
     <lb/>
     government will change its attitude so that this 
     <lb/>
     country can come in on this mine of potential 
     <lb/>
     income. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> I too agree with the various 
     <lb/>
     speakers in connection with the tourist trade. It is 
     <lb/>
     nothing short of a crime that the government has 
     <lb/>
     not assisted in every possible way the tourist 
     <lb/>
     trade in Newfoundland. The possibilities are 
     <lb/>
     beyond all comprehension, and should be pushed 
     <lb/>
     to the limit, especially when the government had 
     <lb/>
     the men at its disposal to do the job. The figures 
     <lb/>
     of $50 per person quoted in the Amulree Report 
     <lb/>
     are very conservative... If we go over the tourist 
     <lb/>
     trade in the right way and make it worthwhile I 
     <lb/>
     am convinced that it would be the second or third 
     <lb/>
     largest industry in this country today. I fail to see 
     <lb/>
     why the government has not taken a greater in<lb break="no"/>terest in this all-important issue. If it were outside 
     <lb/>
     interests looking for concessions the chances are 
     <lb/>
     they would have been given, but unfortunately 
     <lb/>
     the people asking for these concessions happened 
     <lb/>
     to be Newfoundlanders, and that is why I think 
     <lb/>
     they were not granted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Mr. Chairman, I am wondering 
     <lb/>
     if Mr. Smallwood could tell us, in relation to 
     <lb/>
     these figures covering the number of tourists 
     <lb/>
     from 1929 up to 1939, do they include those 
     <lb/>
     people who travelled here by the S.S. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Fort Am<lb break="no"/>herst</hi> and <hi rendition="simple:italic">Fort Townshend</hi> and <hi rendition="simple:italic">Fort St. George</hi>, 
     <lb/>
     arriving here on Thursday and leaving Saturday, 
     <lb/>
     or are they people who have come in for a definite 
     <lb/>
     stay? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The figures given are strictly 
     <lb/>
     tourists. They are not travellers or businessmen 
     <lb/>
     or returning natives, but people who come in here 
     <lb/>
     on pleasure bound. It would include some round 
     <lb/>
     trippers. The round tripper in any country is 
     <lb/>
     regarded as the poorest result of the tourist trade. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     That is the person who with a fortnight's holidays 
     <lb/>
     with pay, the round trip, canjust afford to perhaps 
     <lb/>
     buy a book or two and take snapshots and a few 
     <lb/>
     souvenirs, but they are the small minority. The 
     <lb/>
     big majority — well, Mr. Hickman will have 
     <lb/>
     noticed in one of the appendices the exact ac<lb break="no"/>count of the money spent. The Tourist Board 
     <lb/>
     estimates the money that a handful of tourists 
     <lb/>
     spent this year, 1946. They counted the number 
     <lb/>
     of tourists that visited a few rivers this year, and 
     <lb/>
     got an exact count of what they spent, and it was 
     <lb/>
     I think $80,000 or $90,000, an average of $400- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     500 per tourist. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There are cases well known to the Board of 
     <lb/>
     tourists coming and spending from $1,000 to 
     <lb/>
     $1,500 or $2,000. We have all known of cases 
     <lb/>
     where the wealthy tourists have actually adopted 
     <lb/>
     the families of their guide for instance, and send 
     <lb/>
     money down to these families each year. Many 
     <lb/>
     of them are extremely wealthy men, some in 
     <lb/>
     Canada and the States whose income runs up to 
     <lb/>
     from $100,000 to $1 million a year, and they 
     <lb/>
     don't mind spending $4-5,000 a year. It is a 
     <lb/>
     country they don't know, unusual and different, 
     <lb/>
     and these round trippers are so insignificant in 
     <lb/>
     number that it's hardly worthwhile mentioning 
     <lb/>
     them at all. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Incidentally, here is a table just brought in, for 
     <lb/>
     the first nine months of this year, 1946. In the first 
     <lb/>
     nine months of 1946, 700,000 US automobiles 
     <lb/>
     entered the Maritimes with tourists. Incidentally, 
     <lb/>
     the house will be interested to know that 2,000 
     <lb/>
     motor cars arrived at North Sydney for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of coming over to Newfoundland, thinking 
     <lb/>
     there was a ferry service on the boat, as there is 
     <lb/>
     on PE Island. The federal government has a ferry 
     <lb/>
     which takes 60 motor cars aboard. They do not 
     <lb/>
     need to get out of their motor ears. 2,000 arrived 
     <lb/>
     in Sydney thinking they were going to get to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, in addition to the 700,000 who 
     <lb/>
     entered the Maritimes. We have no conception of 
     <lb/>
     what a monumental trade this travel is. 
     <lb/>
     Americans have itchy feet —they get in their cars 
     <lb/>
     and go all over the American continent. We want 
     <lb/>
     to get a batch of them here where they will spend 
     <lb/>
     American money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I thoroughly endorse the statements 
     <lb/>
     of Mr. Fowler, Mr. Higgins and others, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly in regard to the Tourist Board, and the 
     <lb/>
     frightful discourtesy handed out to them by some 
     <lb/>
     junior clerk in that department —- at least he was 
  

            <pb n="215" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0215.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">215</fw>
          
     ordered to do it.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In dealing with this report of the Tourist Com<lb break="no"/>mittee I hope I am not going to throw cold water 
     <lb/>
     on the enthusiasm expressed by other members. 
     <lb/>
     I note 1 1/2 pages are taken up with tourist trade in 
     <lb/>
     Canada, which gives us some interesting facts I 
     <lb/>
     cannot find in the rest of the report about New<lb break="no"/>foundland. In looking at the tourist traffic as it 
     <lb/>
     applies to Canada, and looking at it as it applies 
     <lb/>
     to Newfoundland, we are looking at two different 
     <lb/>
     propositions. In the United States a man gets in 
     <lb/>
     his car, takes his family, and drives to some place 
     <lb/>
     in Canada with little or no inconvenience.... In 
     <lb/>
     this country, there are 90 miles separating us from 
     <lb/>
     the mainland, absolutely no ferry service. When 
     <lb/>
     you get to Port-aux-Basques you get on a train 
     <lb/>
     which is slow moving and you eventually arrive 
     <lb/>
     at Glenwood. I have been there and I have seen 
     <lb/>
     tourists coming to Glenwood. At one time I heard 
     <lb/>
     a lot of curses from four tourists who came up 
     <lb/>
     from the Gander River and had to stand outside 
     <lb/>
     the station, the waiting room was locked, waiting 
     <lb/>
     for the car, a train coming up from Grand Falls. 
     <lb/>
     They did not like the trip very much. The type of 
     <lb/>
     tourist we will get will be sportsmen, people who 
     <lb/>
     want to get away from it all, get clear of the office 
     <lb/>
     and into the wilds where no one can get at them; 
     <lb/>
     men who do not mind roughing it. They will go 
     <lb/>
     to the Humber and the Gander and other lakes. 
     <lb/>
     That is the type we have been getting in the past. 
     <lb/>
     In the report I think the Committee envisages 
     <lb/>
     what Oliver and Mathes envisaged; that is, that 
     <lb/>
     the government should construct a road; that they 
     <lb/>
     should build a first-class hotel at Stephenville 
     <lb/>
     with several cabins; that hotels be built in other 
     <lb/>
     places, and so on. I do not see that the Committee 
     <lb/>
     has brought in any figures to show just what this 
     <lb/>
     scheme is going to cost the government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It is in the appendix. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> That is only a small part in a large 
     <lb/>
     scheme. I would say the Committee has not been 
     <lb/>
     able to get facts or figures from the Tourist Board 
     <lb/>
     as to the possible outlay of money it will cost the 
     <lb/>
     country. I am not speaking against the tourist 
     <lb/>
     traffic; it has possibilities I feel that there is little 
     <lb/>
     possibility of making much money as a private 
     <lb/>
     concern until we get a road through the country, 
     <lb/>
     and until we get a few landing places for small 
     <lb/>
     planes where people with lots of money can come 
     <lb/>
     in and drop down near the lakes or rivers where 
     <lb/>
     they want to fish. Such a plan as that brought forth 
    

            <cb/>
         
     by Oliver and Mathes would have to be presented 
     <lb/>
     to Dominions Office, and when you say the Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government tumed down the sugges<lb break="no"/>tions of the Tourist Board, simply say Dominions 
     <lb/>
     Office. They, in their wisdom, cannot see any 
     <lb/>
     possibilities in this country for tourist traffic. If 
     <lb/>
     we can ever get to the point where we get tran<lb break="no"/>sinsular road, I do not think we will have to ask 
     <lb/>
     the government to start business. 
     <lb/>
     
      </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In the Mathes' Report the very 
     <lb/>point which Mr. Hollett raised is dealt with: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:centre">C. Accommodations 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>We must be extremely frank and say that 
     <lb/>here is Newfoundland's first great weakness. 
     <lb/>But it is not one that cannot be quickly 
     <lb/>remedied. As the Bank of Montreal plainly 
     <lb/>stated in their recent report on tourism in 
     <lb/>Canada, the American sportsman and tourist 
     <lb/>wants first class accommodations. This 
     <lb/>means attractive location, distinctive ap<lb break="no"/>pearance, good beds and mattresses, hot and 
     <lb/>cold running water, showers and private 
     <lb/>toilets, cleanliness and paint. That is not their 
     <lb/>idea of luxury — just comfort. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

    

            <p>
     Section three of the report covers the other 
     <lb/>
     points raised. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mathes and Oliver do not say there <hi rendition="simple:italic">must</hi> be a 
     <lb/>
     transinsular road. At the point where tourists 
     <lb/>
     land, whether it be Port-aux-Basques, Corner 
     <lb/>
     Brook, St. John's, Lewisporte or wherever, there 
     <lb/>
     ought to be roads leading out; that does not in<lb break="no"/>volve a transinsular highway. If they land in 
     <lb/>
     Port-aux-Basques, where are they going to go 
     <lb/>
     then, when there is no road leading out of Port- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     aux-Basques? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Where did the 2,000 think they 
     <lb/>
     were going? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> They were on four wheels and 
     <lb/>
     probably thought they would wander around 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland and go back by way of Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia. But if there had been a ferry across the 
     <lb/>
     Gulf even, there still would be no place to go 
     <lb/>
     when they got in Port-aux-Basques. They would 
     <lb/>
     just have to go back across the Gulf. That is the 
     <lb/>
     problem to be solved. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I have listened with a great deal of 
     <lb/>
     interest to Mr. Smallwood's report on the tourist 
     <lb/>
     trade, and one thing strikes me as outstanding. 
     <lb/>
     You will remember that Mr. Smallwood was able 
     <lb/>
     to give the exact number of tourists entering 
     <lb/>
     Canada during 1945, even the exact number of 
  

            <pb n="216" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0216.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">216</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
      

     dollars spent there. I wonder if Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
     would be good enough to tell us where he got this 
     <lb/>
     information and from whom? When it came to 
     <lb/>
     the question of the exact number of items com<lb break="no"/>prising the purchase by the government of the 
     <lb/>
     equipment at Gander this fine detail was not 
     <lb/>
     available. Surely some sort of inventory was 
     <lb/>
     made and that self same inventory must now be 
     <lb/>
     in the possession of the Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Further, it appears to me that if Mr. Small<lb break="no"/>wood had taken the same pains to obtain this 
     <lb/>
     inventory as he did to get the figures of the tourist 
     <lb/>
     trade in Canada, this information would now be 
     <lb/>
     in our hands. The purpose of this Convention is 
     <lb/>
     to enquire into the position of this country, and 
     <lb/>
     no doubt by his figures he intends to show what 
     <lb/>
     the tourist trade will mean here. That depends on 
     <lb/>
     the future form of government we may have, as 
     <lb/>
     the Commission of Government, I understand, 
     <lb/>
     has already turned thumbs-down on the tourist 
     <lb/>
     trade. However, Mr. Smallwood's figures on the 
     <lb/>
     value of the tourist trade to Newfoundland 1929- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     1939 are small in comparison with Canadian 
     <lb/>
     figures. I cannot understand why our Commis<lb break="no"/>sion of Government turned down the aggressive 
     <lb/>
     policy to encourage this trade. Certainly an ex<lb break="no"/>planation should be forthcoming. It is a question 
     <lb/>
     of vital public importance. I feel hot under the 
     <lb/>
     collar when I am reminded of the Gander deal 
     <lb/>
     whereby the Commission saddled us with $1 
     <lb/>
     million a year operating cost and then turned 
     <lb/>
     down a profitable tourist trade. I can only come 
     <lb/>
     to one conclusion and that is that their only inter<lb break="no"/>est is to run us in the hole. Perhaps we cannot 
     <lb/>
     expect the Dominions Office to display great 
     <lb/>
     interest in our welfare, but we should expect and 
     <lb/>
     demand from the Newfoundland representatives 
     <lb/>
     their sense of duty to the people of our country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Fudge asks the question as 
     <lb/>
     to where the Transportation Committee got its 
     <lb/>
     figures on tourism in Canada. We did not need to 
     <lb/>
     look for it; the Bank of Canada in one of its 
     <lb/>
     monthly circulars gives an article on that very 
     <lb/>
     topic, and the Tourist Board considered it part of 
     <lb/>
     their job to know the movement of tourism in 
     <lb/>
     Canada, so that they had figures and they kindly 
     <lb/>
     provided the Transportation Committee with a 
     <lb/>
     copy. As to the inventory of the equipment at 
     <lb/>
     Gander, I said before, and I repeat, I doubt if the 
     <lb/>
     government has a complete list of the endless 
     <lb/>
     variety of things they bought from the 
   

            <cb/>
           
     RCAF when they took over Gander. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> I am in accord with everyone 
     <lb/>
     else who condemned the present regime for their 
     <lb/>
     utter disregard of the possibilities of the tourist 
     <lb/>
     trade. It is one of the things I always believed in, 
     <lb/>
     and I believe in it more now because I see the 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government does not. It seems, 
     <lb/>
     as Mr. Fudge says, that anything that costs 
     <lb/>
     money, they are all for it — Gander for example; 
     <lb/>
     any way we can make money, that is out. Page 
     <lb/>
     10 of the Oliver report says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     So many Newfoundlanders with whom I 
     <lb/>
     discussed travel trade, and its chances of 
     <lb/>
     expansion, talked in terms of, "But we have 
     <lb/>
     only three months of a season here", or, "Yes, 
     <lb/>
     but we never see any tourist money," or 
     <lb/>
     "Tourists won't come, our summers are too 
     <lb/>
     chilly", or, "Why would we let tourists spoil 
     <lb/>
     our fishing for us?" 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This is not defeatist talk. it springs from 
     <lb/>
     lack of appreciation and understanding of the 
     <lb/>
     industry, and is a natural argument for people 
     <lb/>
     who have still to rub shoulders, so to speak, 
     <lb/>
     with tourist traffic in great volume. These 
     <lb/>
     people are not aware that in the province of 
     <lb/>
     Ontario, which annually takes approximately 
     <lb/>
     70% of Canada's total tourist revenue, most 
     <lb/>
     of the first-class summer resort hotels operate 
     <lb/>
     most profitably on a two and one half 
     <lb/>
     month's basis. These people are not aware, 
     <lb/>
     either, that the tourist dollar, no matter how 
     <lb/>
     or where spent, eventually to some extent and 
     <lb/>
     in some form touches every person's pocket. 
     <lb/>
     Nor do they know that long before Ontario 
     <lb/>
     had any main roads, or even before there 
     <lb/>
     were motor cars, Americans came tremen<lb break="no"/>dous distances by train and boat, to locate 
     <lb/>
     summer cottages, fish and hunt, and general<lb break="no"/>ly relax and rest. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Not realising that what can be accomplished 
     <lb/>
     elsewhere can be accomplished in substantial 
     <lb/>
     degree in Newfoundland, the average New<lb break="no"/>foundlander talks of tourism without thinking, 
     <lb/>
     and unconsciously builds, within himself at least, 
     <lb/>
     an unwarranted prejudice against your travel 
     <lb/>
     trade cause. It is important that we get tourist 
     <lb/>
     consciousness. As a matter of fact I was talking 
     <lb/>
     with a gentleman on this tourist business and one 
     <lb/>
     point he mentioned interested me, it would only 
     <lb/>
     be a small part of the overall scheme, but he spoke 
     <lb/>
     of Harbour Grace and the possibilities of making 
 

            <pb n="217" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0217.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">217</fw>
        

     that town a convention town with the possibility 
     <lb/>
     of clubs and societies in the States coming here 
     <lb/>
     to hold their conventions — for example the 
     <lb/>
     Rotary Club, and other societies. This whole 
     <lb/>
     tourist business is a splendid opportunity. I would 
     <lb/>
     like to go on record as being thoroughly disgusted 
     <lb/>
     with the regime in its dealings with the Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> Before I get too indignant over this 
     <lb/>
     Tourist Board business, I think it essential for us 
     <lb/>
     to have the cost of the proposed programme We 
     <lb/>
     have what it cost under different headings — we 
     <lb/>
     know we must have better roads, but at $50,000 
     <lb/>
     a mile, how many of these can we afford? We also 
     <lb/>
     must have cabins; we must have ferry service on 
     <lb/>
     the Gulf; but we do not know what all this is going 
     <lb/>
     to cost, and that is the essential information. We 
     <lb/>
     have a surplus of $27 million — this programme 
     <lb/>
     looks extensive — would it cost $27 million? I 
     <lb/>
     do not think it would be justified. If it cost $2 
     <lb/>
     million, yes. I do not know how far this 
     <lb/>
     programme was recommended to the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, I do not know what it will cost. If some<lb break="no"/>thing better than a guess should have been made 
     <lb/>
     and should have been presented here, then I could 
     <lb/>
     really feel that the Tourist Board were handed out 
     <lb/>
     an injustice. It is essential for us to have that. It is 
     <lb/>
     an important point and one to which we will, 
     <lb/>
     possibly, have to look to in the future when the 
     <lb/>
     thing is considered again. With regard to the 
     <lb/>
     government's setting up of cabins, I disagree, I 
     <lb/>
     think that should be done by private enterprise. 
     <lb/>
     The government should find the roads and 
     <lb/>
     facilities Sometime the highway will be inevit<lb break="no"/>able. But the cabins should be done by private 
     <lb/>
     enterprise — the least we get the government into 
     <lb/>
     business, the better for Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There were three points raised. 
     <lb/>
     In one of these reports the amount of money 
     <lb/>
     which the Tourist Board proposed to be spent was 
     <lb/>
     stated. It is not even $2 million. As to the point 
     <lb/>
     about this being the job for private enterprise — 
     <lb/>
     yes, the reports all say that it should be done by 
     <lb/>
     private enterprise, but they point out that this is a 
     <lb/>
     country in which businessmen who have money 
     <lb/>
     to invest don't seem to have great deal of faith in 
     <lb/>
     it, and the pioneer work should be done by the 
     <lb/>
     government. The government should build just 
     <lb/>
     one to test it out and see if it works. If the 
     <lb/>
     government built them all it would cost about $2 
     <lb/>
     million, but for one it would cost $100,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     The other point that Mr. Miller raises is also 
     <lb/>
    dealt with in one of these reports He ventures to 
     <lb/>assume that roads for tourists must be paved. It 
     <lb/>says in the Mathes report that a paved road is 
     <lb/>better than gravel, nevertheless tourists coming 
     <lb/>to Newfoundland would not be expecting to find 
     <lb/>paved roads, but a half-decent gravel road over 
     <lb/>which they could travel at 25 or 30 miles an hour. 
     <lb/>The fact that a road is not paved, but gravel, is 
     <lb/>rather quaint and different to tourists 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> With the spirit and principle of the 
     <lb/>Tourist Board before us I am in sympathy and 
     <lb/>appreciate the services of the very fine men who 
     <lb/>served on that Board for so many years without 
     <lb/>any pay, but sitting here this afternoon and listen<lb break="no"/>ing, Mr. Smallwood made me a little nervous in 
     <lb/>talking about the development of the tourist traf<lb break="no"/>fic, where he envisaged thousands of motor cars 
     <lb/>up there in North Sydney trying to get across and 
     <lb/>come down this way. I felt very nervous over it, 
     <lb/>because they will drive to the right, and half the 
     <lb/>people around Conception Bay might be wiped 
     <lb/>out. Then again they are going to catch our sal<lb break="no"/>mon and sea trout, our partridge and snipe, and 
     <lb/>take away our venison, and even if we have lots 
     <lb/>of money we won't have so much fish. Insofar as 
     <lb/>the principle of the tourist traffic is concerned, I 
     <lb/>humbly step in with the rest of the men who have 
     <lb/>spoken regarding the members of the Tourist 
     <lb/>Board, but if we left our natural resources open 
     <lb/>to a great multitude of tourists we will hardly 
     <lb/>have anything left but money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I agree with the previous speakers. 
     <lb/>We are all too conscious of the fact that almost 
     <lb/>every bit of advertising that Newfoundland has 
     <lb/>had has been usually had, apan from the little bit 
     <lb/>of favourable publicity given us by the New<lb break="no"/>foundland Tourist Board. We who have travelled 
     <lb/>on the various continents know that. I have seen 
     <lb/>five of the seven seas. In view of my knowledge 
     <lb/>of what little has been done in the way of adver<lb break="no"/>tising our country abroad, I was not surprised to 
     <lb/>find that so little is known of Newfoundland. A 
     <lb/>few days ago I received a letter from New 
     <lb/>Zealand, addressed to "Newfoundland, Canada". 
     <lb/>Not long ago I received a letter from a friend in 
     <lb/>Australia addressed "Newfoundland, North 
     <lb/>America". He was probably correct! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     In reviewing the action of the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     Tourist Board, I fail to see, in view of the 
     <lb/>
     government's insane attitude, how the Board 
 

            <pb n="218" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0218.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">218</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
           

     could do anything else but resign.... In one sec<lb break="no"/>tion of our report we find that they willingly 
     <lb/>
     throw away $1 million a year, chiefly for the 
     <lb/>
     benefit of foreigners, and in the same report we 
     <lb/>
     find them bickering over a few thousand dollars 
     <lb/>
     which could be wisely spent to promote the best 
     <lb/>
     interests of this country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> Shortly after this Convention 
     <lb/>
     met I put through a question before committees 
     <lb/>
     were appointed, on this very subject of tourist 
     <lb/>
     development. The question was divided into five 
     <lb/>
     parts. I have never received a direct answer to 
     <lb/>
     those questions, but in this report those questions 
     <lb/>
     are all answered.... I have met a lot of tourists in 
     <lb/>
     my time, and found out that they enjoyed it very 
     <lb/>
     much here.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I did not think that we were all 
     <lb/>
     going over the question before the House, that is 
     <lb/>
     individually making speeches on it.... The tourist 
     <lb/>
     traffic is probably of more interest over on the 
     <lb/>
     west coast than in this part of the country, simply 
     <lb/>
     because we have bigger fishing rivers, we have 
     <lb/>
     steamship routes in Corner Brook, and there 
     <lb/>
     seems to be a desire amongst the people who 
     <lb/>
     come to visit primarily that part of the coast, so 
     <lb/>
     that the action of the government in not support<lb break="no"/>ing this movement of the Tourist Board is, in my 
     <lb/>
     opinion, very bad. I know that next summer it is 
     <lb/>
     anticipated by a certain fraternal organisation 
     <lb/>
     that they will have a conference in Corner Brook, 
     <lb/>
     and that might mean a thousand people coming 
     <lb/>
     in there for a start, and much potential income. If 
     <lb/>
     the country had any encouragement from the 
     <lb/>
     government along these lines similar excursions 
     <lb/>
     would be made, and we would materially benefit 
     <lb/>
     from it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Mr. Chairman, there is a point on 
     <lb/>
     which I am not satisfied. That point is the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of broadcasting. I would like to know from 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood, if he does know, the frequency 
     <lb/>
     and power of radio station VOUS, and on whose 
     <lb/>
     authority they operate. Perhaps this may come 
     <lb/>
     under the 99-year lease of Fort Pepperell, but I 
     <lb/>
     would like to know anyhow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In dealing with broadcasting we 
     <lb/>
     did not go into the question of VOUS at Fort 
     <lb/>
     Pepperell or the other station at Argentia, or the 
     <lb/>
     one at Stephenville. These are not in New<lb break="no"/>foundland, they are in the USA, on American 
     <lb/>
     bases, and we did not feel our authority extended 
     <lb/>
     that far. However, if Mr. Fudge would bring a 
 

            <cb/>
         
     motion that a delegation be appointed to go to 
     <lb/>
     these bases, I have no doubt that delegation 
     <lb/>
     would get that information. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I would prefer to make a motion that 
     <lb/>
     we go over and capture those places. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I am not satisfied with the answer 
     <lb/>
     you gave Mr. Fudge, Mr. Smallwood. Yesterday 
     <lb/>
     we heard a lot about VOCM, about frequency and 
     <lb/>
     channels of the air. Who gave VOUS the chan<lb break="no"/>nel? Certainly if they got it VOCM should have 
     <lb/>
     it, they were here before the others. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That does sound like a very 
     <lb/>
     valid argument. If VOUS are over the 250 watts 
     <lb/>
     that VOCM has. and authorised by the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment of Posts and Telegraphs that makes a very 
     <lb/>
     strong case for allowing VOCM to increase their 
     <lb/>
     power to the same extent. If the House wants the 
     <lb/>
     Transportation Committee to go into that I am 
     <lb/>
     satisfied to make a motion to that effect.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I imagine that the postal telegraph 
     <lb/>
     authorities here gave permission to VOUS to 
     <lb/>
     operate and they would have the necessary infor<lb break="no"/>mation. I think it would be a simple matter for 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood to get this information. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> ldon't want to interrupt, but are we 
     <lb/>
     not supposed to be discussing the tourist traffic? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That's perfectly true. I allowed 
     <lb/>some latitude in the hope that some information 
     <lb/>would be brought out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> We are discussing the whole report 
     <lb/>
     of the Communications and Transportation Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, and I think this is a matter that effects the 
     <lb/>
     general public. We have heard how appreciative 
     <lb/>
     the general public are of the services given by 
     <lb/>
     VOCM. I would like to make a motion that we 
     <lb/>
     ask the Committee on Transportation and Com<lb break="no"/>munications to inquire into the authority under 
     <lb/>
     which they act and the frequency they have, that 
     <lb/>
     is the watt power, if I am in order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I second that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The motion is that, through 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood, the Transportation and Com<lb break="no"/>munications Committee do inquire into the 
     <lb/>
     authority under which VOUS operates in this 
     <lb/>
     country, and also the power which has been al<lb break="no"/>lotted to them by the Department of Posts and 
     <lb/>
     Telegraphs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I move that the report be received. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I don't know just how we should 
     <lb/>take this. It seems we must be in the right and the 
 

            <pb n="219" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0219.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">219</fw>
          
     whole world in the wrong. Whatever part of the 
     <lb/>
     world I have been in there is one thing a govern<lb break="no"/>ment is interested in and it's the tourist trade. If 
     <lb/>
     the government of Switzerland had left out the 
     <lb/>
     possibility of the tourist trade that country would 
     <lb/>
     be in a lot worse condition than she is in today. 
     <lb/>
     In fact it's the one thing that makes that country 
     <lb/>
     one of the best living countries in the world with 
     <lb/>
     the assets that she has got. It's only valleys and 
     <lb/>
     mountains, snow and ice, and farming land is at 
     <lb/>
     a premium.... There are other countries in the 
     <lb/>
     world in the same position... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I think some men on the Committee lifted their 
     <lb/>
     eyebrows when I asked Squadron Leader Pat<lb break="no"/>tison the potentialities of travelling in Gander, 
     <lb/>
     and he said, "I think we don't want them, we have 
     <lb/>
     got nothing for them to come to, even people who 
     <lb/>
     want to stay over we don't want, because they are 
     <lb/>
     something we can't manage because we have no 
     <lb/>
     facilities for them." So I don't know, we acquired 
     <lb/>
     the Gander very cheaply, but for a country like 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland we acquired the Gander at a 
     <lb/>
     sacrifice. Having acquired Gander at a sacrifice, 
     <lb/>
     if there was any way it could be made pay, why 
     <lb/>
     should they turn their thumbs down on it? I 
     <lb/>
     believe people travelling from the old country to 
     <lb/>
     the west would stop over for a day or two and 
     <lb/>
     have a look at it if the country was interested in 
     <lb/>
     it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I don't hold with Mr. Miller about private 
     <lb/>
     capitalisation because I don't believe hotels in 
     <lb/>
     this country are going to flourish. It is not the 
     <lb/>
     hotel that you have got to look at, it is the dollars 
     <lb/>
     that are left behind in the country, and in that way 
     <lb/>
     the government has to take hold of it. Perhaps in 
     <lb/>
     time, when the country comes up to expectations, 
     <lb/>
     people who have come here and had a good time 
     <lb/>
     will go back and talk about it, and it may pay just 
     <lb/>
     as well as St. Petersburg or Key West. The 
     <lb/>
     Government of the United States came in at Key 
     <lb/>
     West and took a hold there and built up the road 
     <lb/>
     and helped the people. They did not build any 
     <lb/>
     hotels, but they came in and helped the people get 
     <lb/>
     on their feet, and paid the unemployed people 
     <lb/>
     who were starving, fixed the roads and fixed the 
     <lb/>
     golf course I believe that the government should 
     <lb/>
     at least spend $1 million on this. I don't believe 
     <lb/>
     it would be lost to the country. When the dollar 
     <lb/>
     is spent everybody gets the good of it, in fact one 
     <lb/>
     of the reasons that our whole economic system 
     <lb/>
     was so bad was that our dollars were not turned 
   

            <cb/>
           
     over. All our earnings we received in a chit 
     <lb/>
     around the table or an IOU. Anything which 
     <lb/>
     takes money out of the country, the Commission 
     <lb/>
     of Government is interested in it. They had their 
     <lb/>
     concentration camps, or land settlements, yet 
     <lb/>
     they could not get a bulldozer to go around and 
     <lb/>
     plow up five or six acres of land. Now they have 
     <lb/>
     other plans. That has been the policy all through. 
     <lb/>
     The Commission of Government wants to stay 
     <lb/>
     here while there is a chance. Apparently the 
     <lb/>
     country is on its feet now, but by the time they 
     <lb/>
     are through with it, perhaps another commission 
     <lb/>
     will want to come in. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Higgins properly con<lb break="no"/>demned the discourtesy of the government in the 
     <lb/>
     way they treated the Tourist Board, but it would 
     <lb/>
     be a pity if the net result of the debate were to 
     <lb/>
     concentrate on that side of the matter. The Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board is merely an incident — the thing that 
     <lb/>
     matters is tourism; bringing people to New<lb break="no"/>foundland and having them spend money. We are 
     <lb/>
     hoping the tourist trade will develop in this 
     <lb/>
     country. I would like the people to see it as a 
     <lb/>
     chance to help the country. Up to the outbreak of 
     <lb/>
     war, everything Newfoundland needed she had 
     <lb/>
     to import; she paid for everything she received 
     <lb/>
     with the money she got from the things she ex<lb break="no"/>ported. But when the war came, a new element 
     <lb/>
     came into the picture. We were not dependent 
     <lb/>
     during the war on the money we got from the 
     <lb/>
     things we exported to foreign markets; we had 
     <lb/>
     new money which the Canadians and Americans 
     <lb/>
     paid us for work in building defense bases. That 
     <lb/>
     construction has stopped and very little money is 
     <lb/>
     coming to Newfoundland today from work on the 
     <lb/>
     bases. We are back again to where we were 
     <lb/>
     before the war. The big thing about the tourist 
     <lb/>
     trade is that it will bring into the country new 
     <lb/>
     money. The Commission of Government has this 
     <lb/>
     chance of bringing new money into the country, 
     <lb/>
     dangling before their very eyes, and they have 
     <lb/>
     done nothing about it. So far as they are con<lb break="no"/>cerned the tourist trade does not exist. They are 
     <lb/>
     not interested in a thing which is going to bring 
     <lb/>
     money into Newfoundland. If this report does not 
     <lb/>
     put that thought across to the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, then it is just a waste of words. It is 
     <lb/>
     not enough to feel sympathy for the Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board for the way the government has treated 
     <lb/>
     them; the thing to be disgusted with is that the 
     <lb/>
     government has neglected what is going to be a 
   

            <pb n="220" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0220.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">220</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw>
         

     big source of revenue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> There is no need to attempt to refute 
     <lb/>
     anything said about the Tourist Board. We are all 
     <lb/>
     in perfect agreement about that. What I am con<lb break="no"/>cerned about is the subject matter of this report. 
     <lb/>
     I feel in some cases it is a bit vague. Apart from 
     <lb/>
     registering our indignation at certain things, I 
     <lb/>
     find myself listening to this motion that we rise 
     <lb/>
     and report progress and I ask myself, how much 
     <lb/>
     progress? I feel it is not even open to debate that 
     <lb/>
     tourist trade is an economic value to the country. 
     <lb/>
     We must assume that everyone knows that. I 
     <lb/>
     think it is pertinent to enquire how much money 
     <lb/>
     should we spend on it. What do we find in the 
     <lb/>
     report? To use their own words, "We are con<lb break="no"/>vinced that the travel trade has within it the 
     <lb/>
     possibility of becoming one of this country's 
     <lb/>
     most profitable and most considerable economic 
     <lb/>
     resources." It is too vague. I hope when we con<lb break="no"/>sider this report again some consideration will be 
     <lb/>
     given to the financial side of it. How much do we 
     <lb/>
     want any government to undertake, and how 
     <lb/>
     much should we leave for private enterprise? Is 
     <lb/>
     it going to be private enterprise or free enterprise 
     <lb/>
     or social enterprise? That is the question we have 
     <lb/>
     to decide. It is a serious question and we should 
     <lb/>
     give it some thought. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Apart from that I have no cause to disagree 
     <lb/>
     with anything that has been said, except in this 
     <lb/>
     one other instance The report does not say on 
     <lb/>
     whose authority they based their information. I 
     <lb/>
     am not trying to compare the attitude of the 
     <lb/>
     government as against the attitude of the Tourist 
     <lb/>
     Board, but I wondered if the government was 
     <lb/>
     asked their viewpoint on the matter. I am not 
     <lb/>
     particularly concerned about their viewpoint, but 
     <lb/>
     reverting back to something you said, Mr. Chair<lb break="no"/>man, before you became Chairman, about our 
     <lb/>
     sitting here as a bench of judges, it seems to me 
     <lb/>
     necessary that before we pass judgement on any 
     <lb/>
     matter of policy we should get both sides of the 
     <lb/>
     story; maybe the Committee satisfied itself on 
     <lb/>
     that point, but I would like to know.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am inclined to disagree with Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
     when he says that we should try and get certain 
     <lb/>
     things or thoughts across to the people of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. I think the presence of 
     <lb/>
     microphones may incline him to that thought. 
     <lb/>
     WhatI am concerned is with facts that will aid us 
     <lb/>
     in our deliberations a little later on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I hate to disagree with Mr. 
 

            <cb/>
          

     Newell on anything because usually I agree with 
     <lb/>
     what he says. The point about getting information 
     <lb/>
     across to the people — I feel strongly about that. 
     <lb/>
     We are 45 men whose job it is to gather all the 
     <lb/>
     information we can get and on the basis of that 
     <lb/>
     information make up our minds on what kind of 
     <lb/>
     government we will recommend. But when we 
     <lb/>
     have done that, a much bigger choice has got to 
     <lb/>
     be made, and that is by the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I feel that the people are even much 
     <lb/>
     more entitled to get this information than we are 
     <lb/>
     — they need it more than we do. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> I was not criticising our putting in<lb break="no"/>formation over to the public. I am sorry if you 
     <lb/>
     misunderstood me there. I understood your 
     <lb/>
     remark to be in connection with making the 
     <lb/>
     people tourist conscious, and I do not think that 
     <lb/>
     is necessary as the people are already tourist 
     <lb/>
     conscious. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> It must be shown that we have to spend 
     <lb/>
     money in order to get money. That is of primary 
     <lb/>
     importance. I do not want to put myself in the 
     <lb/>
     position of defending the government, but by 
     <lb/>
     having Gander, people are getting value in dol<lb break="no"/>lars and cents. If we spend $500,000 as a deficit, 
     <lb/>
     we get back $1 million in wages; therefore the 
     <lb/>
     country has benefited by $500,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> If it costs one million and we 
     <lb/>
     get one million, are we then square? Does one 
     <lb/>
     cancel out the other? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> How much money have we got out 
     <lb/>
     and how much do we hope to get back? That is 
     <lb/>
     of primary importance. We should find out what 
     <lb/>
     money they are going to have to find and what 
     <lb/>
     they are going to get back to make themselves 
     <lb/>
     more self-supporting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> I think the amount asked for was 
     <lb/>
     $2 million — $200,000 a year over a period of 
     <lb/>
     ten years. After a year or two if it worked, it 
     <lb/>
     would be increased. If they had gotten that when 
     <lb/>
     they asked for it, we would have a big tourist 
     <lb/>
     trade in Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I do not see the logic of Mr. Butt's 
     <lb/>
     argument with regard to Gander — paying $1 
     <lb/>
     million to civil servants and going in the hole 
     <lb/>
     another million! Getting back to the other point 
     <lb/>
     under discussion — the information which 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Newell wanted — I do not see how the 
     <lb/>
     Committee could have gotten all the facts in 
     <lb/>
     regard to possible expenditure; and as to making 
     <lb/>
     an estimate as to cost, the most it could have been 
    

<pb n="221" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-12-13_Page_0221.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">221</fw>

would be a guess. Mathes speaks of a casino, <lb/>
resorts, etc. Tourist trade <hi rendition="simple:italic">is</hi> a gamble, but it is a<lb/>
gamble worthwhile.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I move that the committee rise,
<cb/>

report progress and ask leave to sit again on <lb/>
tomorrow.</p>

<p>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried. The committee rose, and the
Convention adjourned until January 8, 1947]</hi></p>

       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>