<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-09-16"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-09-16">16 September 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
      
         
          <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="15"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0013.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0014.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0015.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-08">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0013">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0013.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0014">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0014.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0015">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0015.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="13"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0013.jpg"/>
           <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">13</fw>
     
<!-- GL, 2017-02-09 Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

           <!-- <p>
     Mr. Chairman There is one difficulty that ap<lb break="no"/>pears to me — difficulty of getting in touch with 
     <lb/>
     the members and it would be better to know now 
     <lb/>
     the date, then we would know exactly when we 
     <lb/>
     were to re-assemble. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. HollettI fail to see how it can adjourn in<lb break="no"/>definitely. It may take some time for the commit<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>tee to draft the rules but we should meet every<lb/>day; we were not sent here for indefinite adjourn<lb break="no"/>ments. Another thing, I do not think the public<lb/>should be admitted where rules and regulations<lb/>are being made relative to the business. I do agree<lb/>that the committee should be allowed time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>[The Convention adjourned until September 16]<lb/>
            </p>-->

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     September 16, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
</div>
<div type="section">

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The questions asked by <lb/> Mr. Smallwood at
                  the last sitting have been trans<lb break="no"/>mitted to the department
                  concerned, but as yet no <lb/> reply has been received. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> As it is commonly reported that during <lb/> the
                  deliberations between a deputation of the <lb/> Commission of Government and the
                  Dominions <lb/> Secretary in London during the summer of 1944, <lb/> the then
                  Dominions Secretary, speaking with the <lb/> approval of the Cabinet, offered to
                  cancel the <lb/> Newfoundland sterling debt, or alternatively to <lb/>make annual
                  grant for several years that would in <lb/>total be the equivalent of this debt, I
                  give notice <lb/>that I will at the next meeting request the Com<lb break="no"
                  />missioner for Finance or the department con<lb break="no"/>cerned to table the
                  following information: <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p>1. Is this report accurate in part or in full? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>2. If so, has the decision or proposal then 
     <lb/>made been altered, amended or rescinded? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. If it has been rescinded, has the commis<lb break="no"/>sioner any knowledge that it is the inten<lb break="no"/>tion of the British government to make 
     <lb/>an alternative offer or financial or eco<lb break="no"/>nomic assistance to Newfoundland in 
     <lb/>any shape or form? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. If any offer of assistance is to be made, 
     <lb/>
    what is its nature? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Information on a variety of topics was requested 
     <lb/>
     by Mr. Bradley, Mr. Cashin, Mr. Vincent and Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> In the absence of the Hon. Mr. <lb/> Job, I
                  have to make a report of the work of the <lb/> select committee appointed at the
                  last sitting to <lb/> draft an address of loyalty to His Majesty the <lb/> King,
                  and of thanks to His Excellency the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The select committee appointed on Thursday, 
     <lb/>
     September 12, 1946, to draft an address of loyalty 
     <lb/>
     to His Majesty the King, begs to submit the 
     <lb/>
     accompanying draft address for your approval, 
     <lb/>
     and if thought fit, adoption: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     To His Excellency Sir Gordon Mac<cb/>donald, K.C.M.G. Governor and Com<lb break="no"/>mander-in-Chief in and over the Island of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland and its dependencies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     May it please Your Excellency: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We, the duly elected representatives of the 
     <lb/>
     people of Newfoundland in National Con<lb break="no"/>vention assembled do hereby desire to con<lb break="no"/>vey through you, as our first official act, an 
     <lb/>
     affirmation of our deepest loyalty to His 
     <lb/>
     Most Gracious Majesty King George VI, and 
     <lb/>
     our complete and lasting allegiance to the 
     <lb/>
     Crown. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     The select committee appointed on Thursday, 
     <lb/>
     September 12, 1946 to draft an address of thanks 
     <lb/>
     to His Excellency the Governor, begs to submit 
     <lb/>
     the accompanying draft address for your up 
     <lb/>
     proval, and if thought fit, adoption: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     To His Excellency Sir Gordon Mac<lb break="no"/>donald, K.C.M.G., Governor and Com<lb break="no"/>mander-in-Chief in and over the Island of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland and its dependencies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     May it please your Excellency: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We, the delegates of the National Conven<lb break="no"/>tion in session assembled beg to thank Your 
     <lb/>
     Excellency for the gracious speech which 
     <lb/>
     you have been pleased to deliver at the open<lb break="no"/>ing session of the National Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I would accept a motion for the <lb/> adoption
                  of these reports. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> I move that these reports he <lb/> adopted.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I second that motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried unanimously]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Apropos of that, His Excellency <lb/> is not in
                  town at the moment. In the old days the <lb/> procedure was for a delegation to
                  proceed to <lb/> Government House and to present to His Excel~ <lb/> lency the
                  address in reply. Similar procedure <lb/> might be followed in regard to the
                  address of <lb/> loyalty and the address of thanks; but as the <lb/> Governor will
                  not return for a fortnight, do you <lb/> wish that the delegation should go to
                  Government <lb/>
                  <pb n="14" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0014.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">14</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> House and present it to the Administrator,
                  who is <lb/> Hon. Mr. Winter, or would you rather you waited <lb/> until His
                  Excellency's return and deliver it to him <lb/> in person? That would be about the
                  second of <lb/> October. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> It seems to me that it would be <lb/> more
                  appropriate to wait until the return of His <lb/> Excellency, and if in order, I
                  make that as a <lb/> motion. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> I second that motion.<lb/>
               </p>

    
            <cb/>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Proposed by Mr. Bradley and<lb/> seconded by Mr.
                  Reddy that the address of loyal<lb break="no"/>ty to the King and the address of
                  thanks to His<lb/> Excellency the Governor as received and adopted<lb/> be
                  presented to His Excellency on his return to<lb/> the city. Carried.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p>When His Excellency comes I will ascertain<lb/> what time will be convenient to him, and acquaint<lb/> you accordingly.<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the Committee on Rules and Procedure<ref target="#fn_x1">[1]</ref>
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> The committee met on Friday <lb/> morning and the
                  report of the committee itself <lb/> you will find on the second page which the
                     mem<lb break="no"/>bers have before them now, and which is signed <lb/> by the
                  chairman. This is a motion to receive and <lb/> adopt the report <hi
                     rendition="simple:italic">seriatim</hi>. I don't know whether <lb/> the members
                  of the Convention desire to have a <lb/> chance to look over these, and for that
                  reason I <lb/> think I should confine the motion to the reception <lb/> of the
                  report for the moment. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I second the motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Is the Convention ready? <lb/> Proposed by Mr.
                  Bradley and seconded by <lb/> Mr. Crosbie that the rules of procedure be <lb/>
                  received. Carried.... I think the appropriate plan <lb/> would be to have the
                  Convention resolve itself <lb/> into a committee of the whole... Carried.
                  <lb/></p>

<p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Sections 1-48 of this report approved]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Would it not be a good point to <lb/> repeat to
                  the committee the whole statement you <lb/> made at the meeting of the committee
                  on Friday <lb/> morning? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I am instructed to inform you <lb/> that in so
                  far as the Commission of Government <lb/> is concerned, the members of the
                  Commission <lb/> and high officials, that they are most willing that <lb/> the
                  Convention should have all possible informa<lb break="no"/>tion that we should
                  require, and that they are most <lb/> willing that that information should be
                  placed <lb/> before the Convention. They are not willing to <lb/> come before the
                  Convention in public, but they <lb/> offer to come before you at any of the
                  committee <lb/> meetings in private. However, there may be oc<lb break="no"
                  />casions when it may be more practical, because <lb/> of the readiness with which
                  they can get informa<lb break="no"/>tion from their departments, to call upon
                  them. <lb/> But in all other respects they will be happy and <lb/>
                  <cb/> willing to give all possible information. It was <lb/> never intended by the
                  government here, or by the <lb/> Dominions Office or the Secretary of State that
                  <lb/> this Convention should have power to subpoena <lb/> the members of the
                  Commission of Government <lb/> or high officials. That I am also instructed to
                  <lb/> convey to you. You will understand that the <lb/> absence of any rule or
                  authority to subpoena <lb/>witnesses does not apply merely to the officials
                  <lb/>of the government, but to anybody. We have no <lb/>right at all, gentlemen,
                  to compel any person to <lb/>come forward. That was the right which the old
                  <lb/>House of Assembly had by statute in the statutory <lb/>rules, but it is a
                  right which we have not got. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In regard to their willingness to <lb/>appear
                  before committees of the House, I think <lb/>on Friday you made it clear that that
                  might be a <lb/>committee of the whole, so that instead of a <lb/>commissioner, or
                  anyone else who had been in<lb break="no"/>vited to come to be interrogated,
                  attending only <lb/>a small committee and at that committee giving <lb/>certain
                  information which would then sub<lb break="no"/>sequently be passed on to the
                  whole Convention <lb/>by the members of that committee, leaving the <lb/>members
                  of the Convention depending upon a <lb/>second-hand report, all members of the
                     Conven<lb break="no"/>tion could hear it at the same time by forming
                  <lb/>themselves into a committee of the whole. <lb/>
               </p>
   
    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I don't think there is any objec<lb break="no"
                  />tion to the size of the committee, because it would <lb/> be held in private.
                  There are occasions when it <lb/> may not be possible for you to find out all the
                  <lb/> information you want, no matter how specific <lb/> your intentions are. l
                  have been instructed to tell <lb/> you that it may not be possible to get the
                     infor<lb break="no"/>mation by specific questions, but it may be neces<lb
                     break="no"/>sary to have a personal interview with a <lb/>
                  <note xml:id="fn_x1">[1] Volume II:53. [Volume II is not in <hi
                        rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
                  <pb n="15" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-16_Page_0015.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">15</fw> commissioner, in which case the commissioners <lb/> are not
                  only willing but anxious to convenience <lb/> you, subject to the conditions which
                  I have been <lb/> instructed to set before you. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FOWL2">Mr. Fowler</persName> Mr. Chairman, who gave members <lb/> of the old
                  House of Assembly the power to sub<lb break="no"/>poena people? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Parliament. It was the old right <lb/> of
                  Parliament itself, that came down through the <lb/> ages, and it was also a
                  straight act. We have <lb/> neither executive or legislative power to compel <lb/>
                  anybody to come before us. All our power is <lb/> contained in the section of the
                  act to which refer<lb break="no"/>ence is being made in the National Convention.
                  <lb/> Well, gentlemen, shall we proceed? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Sections 49 to 53 approved. The committee rose 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
      
     and reported progress. On the motion of Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Cashin the order of the day was deferred] </hi>
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BURR2">Mr. Burry</persName> In reference to the questions tabled <lb/> — the
                  word "Newfoundland" occurred all <lb/> through in reference to our great
                  territory. Would <lb/> that also — in the questions of Major Cashin, <lb/> Mr.
                  Smallwood and others — apply to Labrador? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Technically or specifically? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BURR2">Mr. Burry</persName> Will we get information regarding <lb/>Labrador from
                  these questions? I want to be clear <lb/>on that. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> It provides for that, and in future it <lb/> will
                  apply to Labrador all the time. There is one <lb/> that refers to Labrador
                  specifically, <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<!-- GL, 2017-02-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p>
     September 17, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Chairman The questions tabled at the last 
     <lb/>
     sitting were sent immediately to the various 
     <lb/>
     departments and answers have not yet been 
     <lb/>
     received. In connection with questions, it is 
     <lb/>
     natural to suppose that at the commencement of 
     <lb/>
     proceedings, all members may not be conversant 
     <lb/>
     with the rules of procedure as to the form and 
     <lb/>
     relevancy of the question Some of these ques<lb break="no"/>tions will have to be re~worded; and I feel I should 
     <lb/>
     advise with the members privately, rather than in 
     <lb/>
     public, because I feel sure that if a member wants 
     <lb/>
     to ask questions in the required scope, attention 
     <lb/>
     being paid to the rules, he will want to confine 
     <lb/>
     himself strictly to relevancy. Therefore, with 
     <lb/>
     your permission, we might have a private word 
     <lb/>
     at an appropriate occasion when I can outline the 
     <lb/>
     rules in regard to questions. Whatever informa<lb break="no"/>tion is required by the Convention will not alone 
     <lb/>
     be obtained, but questions in respect thereof will 
     <lb/>
     be in the prescribed form. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [Requests for information on a variety of topics 
     <lb/>
     were tabled by Mr. Smallwood, Mr. Hollett, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Hickman, Mr. Vincent and Mr. Newell] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood lf I might be permitted, under 
     <lb/>
     the heading of "Questions", some newspapermen 
     <lb/>
     and radiomen asked me to make the point that in 
     <lb/>
     addition to the three copies of questions and 
     <lb/>
     motions tabled, it would be convenient if addi<lb break="no"/>tional copies were made available to them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Perhaps it might be better to 
     <lb/>
     have these questions available to the press on the 
     <lb/>
     day when they are asked in the House. The pro<lb break="no"/>cedure requires that the member give notice of 
     <lb/>
     the question and on the following day asks it 
     <lb/>
     formally. One of the reasons for the 24-hour 
     <lb/>
     interval between notice and asking of questions 
     <lb/>
     is that in certain cases the question has to be 
     <lb/>
     reviewed by the Chairman, to take care that the 
     <lb/>
     question is in the correct form and is relevant. The 
     <lb/>
     day following, the chamber hears the question 
     <lb/>
     formally, that is, brought forward on the order 
     <lb/>
     paper. If copies were then available, as they ap<lb break="no"/>pear on the order paper, it might be the ap<lb break="no"/>propriate occasion, as being the subject of 
     <lb/>
     interrogation on the following day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>