<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-11-12"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-11-12">12 November 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="703" to="714"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0703.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0704.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0705.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0706.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0707.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0708.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0709.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0710.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0711.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0712.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0713.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0714.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-07-24">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-07-24">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0703">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0703.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0704">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0704.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0705">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0705.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0706">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0706.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0707">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0707.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0708">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0708.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0709">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0709.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0710">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0710.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0711">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0711.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0712">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0712.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0713">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0713.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0714">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0714.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="703"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0703.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">703</fw>
            
<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     November 12, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Before proceeding to the busi<lb break="no"/>ness of the day, may I advise the House that I have 
     <lb/>
     just received the following communication from 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency the Governor: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     12 November, 1947. 
     <lb/></p>
<p>
     Dear Mr. Chairman, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have received a communication from the 
     <lb/>
     High Commissioner for Canada directing my 
     <lb/>
     attention to a typographical error in the last 
     <lb/>
     paragraph on page 10 of the document out<lb break="no"/>lining the "Proposed Arrangements for the 
     <lb/>
     Entry of Newfoundland into Confederation." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     The word "not" needs to be deleted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whilst this does not of course affect the 
     <lb/>
     appointment of the debt or the retention of the 
     <lb/>
     surplus by Newfoundland and is immaterial 
     <lb/>
     from the standpoint of the general effect of 
     <lb/>
     the proposed arrangements, the High 
     <lb/>
     Commissioner feels that, for the sake of ac<lb break="no"/>curacy, he should mention the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="simple:right">
     Yours sincerely, 
     <lb/>
     Gordon Macdonald 
     <lb/>
     Governor. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

</div>

<div type="section">
           
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the Finance Committee: Economic Report<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> Mr. Chairman, I am not going to 
     <lb/>
     enter into any petty discussions or sandbag 
     <lb/>
     anyone. I have heard too much of this; have 
     <lb/>
     listened to too much doom and disaster and 
     <lb/>
     sundry roaring and reckon our listeners suffered 
     <lb/>
     the same, although not at the same time. 
            </p>

<p>
     Newfoundlanders are not infallible, neither 
     <lb/>
     are other people, and to prove this I would like to 
     <lb/>
     take you back to the time Japan declared war on 
     <lb/>
     China. We were told by the political economists 
     <lb/>
     of the United States and other countries, includ<lb break="no"/>ing Great Britain, that Japan could not carry on 
     <lb/>
     war with China without going financially broke, 
     <lb/>
     yet she did continue this war for several years. 
     <lb/>
     Then in March 1933, we were told by the political 
     <lb/>
     economists of Great Britain and the United States 
     <lb/>
     that Hitler, who had come to power in Germany, 
     <lb/>
     could not last six months, yet in fact he lasted 
     <lb/>
     until 1939 when he declared war on Great Britain 
     <lb/>
     and later the United States, and for six years he 
     <lb/>
     waged war against these two great nations and 
     <lb/>
     their allies. Japan later attacked the United States 
     <lb/>
     and helped Hitler for at least two or three years 
     <lb/>
     of war against these two great countries. Hitler 
     <lb/>
     lasted long enough to bring untold hardship and 
     <lb/>
     starvation to millions, and millions are still suf<lb break="no"/>fering, yet we are told here in this chamber that 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlanders are foolish, because they bring 
     <lb/>
     in a report and make estimates that may not 
     <lb/>
     finally turn out. I have seen budgets and estimates 
     <lb/>
     made of other countries with the same result. It is 
     <lb/>
     true that the report of your Committee may be 
     <lb/>
     changed in places, that is why it is brought in 
     <lb/>
     here; to be treated the same as other reports — 


   
          
            <cb/>
       

     some things added, some things taken away; but 
     <lb/>
     as a member of that Committee I am satisfied it 
     <lb/>
     is as clear a picture of the conditions of this 
     <lb/>
     country today and for the near future as is pos<lb break="no"/>sible. I am sure we are self-supporting at the 
     <lb/>
     moment, and will be for some time to come. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would like to review once more our fisheries. 
     <lb/>
     As we know it is from our fisheries that the 
     <lb/>
     greatest number of our people obtain their 
     <lb/>
     livelihood. If our fisheries are prosperous, our 
     <lb/>
     country is prosperous... It may come as a surprise 
     <lb/>
     to some of you to know that we are the second 
     <lb/>
     largest exporter of frozen fish and fishery 
     <lb/>
     products to the United States. Canada comes first, 
     <lb/>
     but some day I hope we will come first. You 
     <lb/>
     know that there has been a meeting of many 
     <lb/>
     countries to discuss the reduction of tariffs and 
     <lb/>
     inter-trade; it may be possible there will be a 
     <lb/>
     reduction on certain tariffs and then New<lb break="no"/>foundland will benefit, we cannot expect better 
     <lb/>
     treatment than other countries, but at least we 
     <lb/>
     may expect the same. We have been told that this 
     <lb/>
     country is in a very strategic position. This is 
     <lb/>
     perfectly true. But I do not mean a strategic 
     <lb/>
     position with regard to war, but with regard to our 
     <lb/>
     fishing banks, the water around and near our 
     <lb/>
     shores. We are known to have one of the largest 
     <lb/>
     continental fishing ledges in the world, one of the 
     <lb/>
     best. I have been told by presidents of large 
     <lb/>
     fishing companies of the United States that some 
     <lb/>
     day in the near future they will have to come to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland for their raw materials. This 
     <lb/>
     paints a nice picture in my mind of what our 
     <lb/>
     fisheries may be in the future. In 1934-35 we 




<note xml:id="fn_01">[1] Volume 11:425. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

            <pb n="704"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0704.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">704</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1947</fw>
          

     exported very little frozen or fresh fish. It was 
     <lb/>
     only in 1937-38 that some of our people had 
     <lb/>
     sufficient courage to go ahead. In 1940-45 it took 
     <lb/>
     great strides. Due to the necessity of more food 
     <lb/>
     because of war conditions a great many people 
     <lb/>
     ate fish who never ate fish before, and who will 
     <lb/>
     continue to eat fish for years to come. The war 
     <lb/>
     gave our exporters an opportunity to get more or 
     <lb/>
     less established and today they are still enlarging 
     <lb/>
     and are still very optimistic over the future of our 
     <lb/>
     fresh fish industry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Within a very few weeks you will have here 
     <lb/>
     in St. John's, operating from Job Brothers, two 
     <lb/>
     new up-to date trawlers which will permit this 
     <lb/>
     firm to operate all year round. This will give 
     <lb/>
     employment to many Newfoundlanders and will 
     <lb/>
     help change entirely the outlook of our fisheries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is true that our salt codlish for 1934-35 was 
     <lb/>
     only worth $5 million and in 1945 it was some 
     <lb/>
     $17 millions — quite a gap. It is also true we can 
     <lb/>
     expect reduced prices in our salt codfish over the 
     <lb/>
     course of the next few years, but I do not expect 
     <lb/>
     to see our salt codfish drop in price as low as it 
     <lb/>
     did in 1934-35. If you say, "Why?", my answer 
     <lb/>
     is this: during recent years there has been a 
     <lb/>
     greater spirit of cooperation all over this country 
     <lb/>
     and our marketing system for salt codfish has 
     <lb/>
     improved tremendously. There will be no throat- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     cutting, no loss because of shipping on consign<lb break="no"/>ment; more co-operation in every direction, 
     <lb/>
     which means a steadier, firmer market and better 
     <lb/>
     returns. Like every other industry, the salt cod- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     fishery has certain branches and phases that are 
     <lb/>
     uneconomic, and one of these branches is the 
     <lb/>
     Labrador fishery. This fishery costs a lot to fit out 
     <lb/>
     and continues only for three to four months; 
     <lb/>
     further, during these three or four months, only 
     <lb/>
     six weeks of fishing may be done. We had men 
     <lb/>
     come home from Labrador last year and this year 
     <lb/>
     with no voyages, men who have to go through 
     <lb/>
     hardship because they have caught no fish. For 
     <lb/>
     these men I have deepest sympathy and greatest 
     <lb/>
     admiration; it is not their fault, the country's 
     <lb/>
     fault, but nature's. I feel it is our duty, knowing 
     <lb/>
     that these fisheries are uneconornical, to wake up, 
     <lb/>
     get together, try and find the cure for these un<lb break="no"/>economical fisheries. I would suggest centralisa<lb break="no"/>tion, intense fishing of certain areas, more 
     <lb/>
     versatile boats, better equipment. You may say, 
     <lb/>
     "Where is this money coming from?" I say, if 
     <lb/>
     necessary the state should put it up. They have 


            <cb/>
         

     guaranteed bonds to our paper companies to the 
     <lb/>
     extent of $15 to $20 million. Why cannot the 
     <lb/>
     same thing be done for our fisheries? I am sure 
     <lb/>
     that if our men go to the Labrador, properly 
     <lb/>
     equipped with the right vessels, they can come 
     <lb/>
     back and later prosecute other fisheries, even the 
     <lb/>
     seal fishery, which are now on the verge of being 
     <lb/>
     developed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then we have in this country our herring 
     <lb/>
     fishery. I have been in touch with this fishery 
     <lb/>
     from an angle entirely different from the pattern 
     <lb/>
     of the old days, from the angle of mass produc<lb break="no"/>tion, the production of protein meals that are 
     <lb/>
     badly needed all over the world, and will be 
     <lb/>
     needed for many years to come, Fishmeal is only 
     <lb/>
     in its infancy. It is only in the last 15 or 20 years, 
     <lb/>
     that the value of these fish meals have been 
     <lb/>
     realised for the purpose of feeding cattle, poultry 
     <lb/>
     and many other purposes. It is true, as some of 
     <lb/>
     you have said, since 1940 I have been in this 
     <lb/>
     business, had hardship and it is true I have made 
     <lb/>
     no money. But I would like to assure you my faith 
     <lb/>
     in this industry is greater than ever, and I am sure 
     <lb/>
     some day I will be rewarded or at least repaid for 
     <lb/>
     the trouble I have taken. We have today, which 
     <lb/>
     we never had before, the filletting of herring, the 
     <lb/>
     canning of herring by a large Canadian company, 
     <lb/>
     that has invested close to half a million dollars in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland for the handling of herring, a firm 
     <lb/>
     that has been for years in the herring fishery of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, who know their markets and have faith 
     <lb/>
     in herring as a product. There are many people in 
     <lb/>
     this country who would doubt that these in<lb break="no"/>dustries can be developed. To them I say, have 
     <lb/>
     faith, encourage the people who are trying to run 
     <lb/>
     them, do not knock — just encourage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We have a whale fishery which has gradually 
     <lb/>
     been built up because ofnewer methods and more 
     <lb/>
     things being found to save waste in the plants, 
     <lb/>
     and to decrease the cost of production which will 
     <lb/>
     under normal times permit this industry to meet 
     <lb/>
     the prices which may be prevailing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The seal fishery will again come into its own. 
     <lb/>
     We have the opportunity of developing this in<lb break="no"/>dustry and making it much more valuable than in 
     <lb/>
     the past. Today the seal fishery has changed 
     <lb/>
     somewhat, we have smaller boats going to the 
     <lb/>
     ice, with smaller crews and it appears to me that 
     <lb/>
     these boats and smaller crews may be the answer 
     <lb/>
     to a larger and most beneficent fishery in the 
     <lb/>
     future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="705"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0705.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1947</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">705</fw>
            

<p>
     There are many varieties of fish which I can<lb break="no"/>not take time to discuss with you. I would like to 
     <lb/>
     discuss, however, our lobster fishery. At one time 
     <lb/>
     we only canned lobster, but today the greater part 
     <lb/>
     of our lobsters are being shipped alive. I am sure 
     <lb/>
     that the co-operative men in this Convention will 
     <lb/>
     agree that, through the shipment of live lobster 
     <lb/>
     by the co-operatives and private firms, the fisher<lb break="no"/>men are much better off than they ever were. I am 
     <lb/>
     glad that the co-operative movement has taken 
     <lb/>
     over such work, and I wish them luck in the 
     <lb/>
     future. Now then, we come to the product about 
     <lb/>
     which many people are sceptical and that is the 
     <lb/>
     value of our waste. When we first started in 
     <lb/>
     Corner Brook to manufacture herring oil and 
     <lb/>
     meal after extracting the oil from the water, we 
     <lb/>
     had water left. During the last two years we have 
     <lb/>
     found this water valuable and today there is not 
     <lb/>
     a thing which cannot be used, including the 
     <lb/>
     water. This also applies to the whaling industry, 
     <lb/>
     and I am sure we are going to find the same in all 
     <lb/>
     the other branches of our fishery. In Iceland and 
     <lb/>
     other countries, all this waste is utilised, running 
     <lb/>
     into millions of dollars; and waste can be utilised 
     <lb/>
     in this country as well. I am sure that in centres 
     <lb/>
     such as Bonavista where they are handling large 
     <lb/>
     quantities of frozen fish, fish waste plants could 
     <lb/>
     be established and the fishermen will get more 
     <lb/>
     money per quintal for their fish and get rid of the 
     <lb/>
     dirt and the filth around their harbours. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The value of our fisheries in 1946 was some<lb break="no"/>where in the neighbourhood of $34 million. The 
     <lb/>
     Fishery Committee valued the fisheries at $25 
     <lb/>
     million. I think they can be valued at more if we 
     <lb/>
     have faith and courage enough to go ahead, to 
     <lb/>
     move forward, to push and strive for greater 
     <lb/>
     developments. I feel that if our fisheries go below 
     <lb/>
     $25-30 million, it is because we are lacking 
     <lb/>
     foresight and vision, something which most 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlanders find in other countries, and 
     <lb/>
     which we seem to lack in our own. I have every 
     <lb/>
     reason, the country has every reason, to feel 
     <lb/>
     optimistic over the future of fisheries. We have 
     <lb/>
     unlimited resources and raw materials; we have 
     <lb/>
     the fishermen; we have everything that anyone 
     <lb/>
     needs to develop the fisheries in this country and 
     <lb/>
     push them forward. We may need assistance, 
     <lb/>
     more research information, more biological in<lb break="no"/>formation and a better laboratory than the one we 
     <lb/>
     now have, but these are things we can have if we 
     <lb/>
     want to fight for them, push for them and insist 
 

            <cb/>
          

     on them. There is very little more I can say on the 
     <lb/>
     Economic Report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This country and this Convention is facing 
     <lb/>
    very momentous weeksjust ahead. We are going 
     <lb/>to discuss forms of government. We are going to 
     <lb/>discuss many different things, but I would like to 
     <lb/>say to you all, let us remember it is a fine country 
     <lb/>that we live in, that we fought for and that we will 
     <lb/>fight for again. During those weeks let us forget 
     <lb/>our political passion, let us argue out those things 
     <lb/>sensibly, reasonably and intelligently. Let us give 
     <lb/>the public of this country the facts that we can 
     <lb/>give them without being hot, personal and 
     <lb/>abusive. We can do it if we wish, and l for one 
     <lb/>intend to follow those lines, and I hope and trust 
     <lb/>that we can prove to our country and our people 
     <lb/>that we are sensible, reasonable and willing to 
     <lb/>co-operate and work together. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> ....Mr. Hickman, in a very fair 
     <lb/>speech calmly made here two or three days ago, 
     <lb/>gave me the impression that he was a bit disap<lb break="no"/>pointed in connection with Convention proceed<lb break="no"/>ings. If that is so, I can quite understand it. I too 
     <lb/>have been somewhat disappointed, because the 
     <lb/>mental picture I had built up of this work has been 
     <lb/>dashed to pieces. I have no desire to prolong this 
     <lb/>Convention one hour longer than is strictly neces<lb break="no"/>sary, so my remarks will not be lengthy. I am not 
     <lb/>aspiring to a place in any future government 
     <lb/>Newfoundland may have, so like Mr. Hickman, 
     <lb/>I have no axe to grind. My only wish is that 
     <lb/>whatever our political set-up, it proves to be 
     <lb/>productive of the most good for the most people 
     <lb/>and in the general interest of all. I do not look on 
     <lb/>the dark side of life, even when clouds are heavy 
     <lb/>and dark I look beyond them in hope. I believe 
     <lb/>that we have somewhere resources as yet un<lb break="no"/>touched which can be profitably developed, and 
     <lb/>that those we have can be further developed; but 
     <lb/>capital, labour and government must work 
     <lb/>together. A government must not be expected to 
     <lb/>shoulder all the responsibility in making a 
     <lb/>country progress. We, the people, have to bear 
     <lb/>our share, and blame ourselves to the proper 
     <lb/>extent for lack of progress. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     With a long pull and a strong pull all together, 
     <lb/>
     I see no reason why matters in this country could 
     <lb/>
     not be considerably improved. I fear in the past 
     <lb/>
     there has been a little too much of self and not 
     <lb/>
     enough of the realisation of the necessity of pull<lb break="no"/>ing together. What are the hopes of mending our 
   

            <pb n="706"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0706.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">706</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1947</fw>
         

     ways? Has our attitude shown that we are moving 
     <lb/>
     along that road? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This report has come in for considerable 
     <lb/>
     debate. Some members have gone all out in sup<lb break="no"/>port, others have taken a contrary view. In some 
     <lb/>
     cases the debate has been a bit on the stormy side. 
     <lb/>
     I wonder what our listeners all over the country 
     <lb/>
     think. Are they in agreement that the task as<lb break="no"/>signed us is being handled properly? Are they 
     <lb/>
     acquiring such knowledge as will enable them to 
     <lb/>
     decide more easily the great question which must 
     <lb/>
     in due time be given serious thought? An artist 
     <lb/>
     may paint a beautiful picture, but it may not 
     <lb/>
     appeal to every one in the same way. The same 
     <lb/>
     applies to the picture this Economic Report gives. 
     <lb/>
     There is no just reason why one man should 
     <lb/>
     become aggrieved simply because the other fel<lb break="no"/>low cannot see in that picture the same thing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I do not see much in this report to disturb my 
     <lb/>
     peace of mind, neither am I going to quarrel over 
     <lb/>
     it. There are many listeners all over New<lb break="no"/>foundland quite capable of judging the merits or 
     <lb/>
     otherwise of this report.... I leave it to them.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Economics is the science that treats of produc<lb break="no"/>tion, and use of wealth, so its meaning has two 
     <lb/>
     sides. Faith in the possibilities of production is 
     <lb/>
     one thing, getting down to business and pro<lb break="no"/>ducing is another thing. Nature may provide 
     <lb/>
     wealth in the land, but she does not dig it out. The 
     <lb/>
     four factors are land, labour, capital and organisa<lb break="no"/>tion, and capital is very important. The report 
     <lb/>
     does give an encouraging picture. I hope it works 
     <lb/>
     out along these lines in the years which lie 
     <lb/>
     ahead.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Fishery. I note the government laboratory 
     <lb/>
     motor vessel has found a variety of fish off our 
     <lb/>
     coast which might become a source of wealth 
     <lb/>
     some day; but it is of little value to know that 
     <lb/>
     wealth exists if we don't go after it. I am more 
     <lb/>
     familiar with the shore codfishery than any other, 
     <lb/>
     and agree with Mr. Reddy that the shore fishery 
     <lb/>
     is too short to enable our fishermen to earn a 
     <lb/>
     decent living. On some parts of the Burin Penin<lb break="no"/>sula it has, because of shortage of bait, been but 
     <lb/>
     a two months fishery for some years. Prospects 
     <lb/>
     are better now by reason of the erection of bait 
     <lb/>
     depots. One member made reference to failure of 
     <lb/>
     the fishery in his area, another brought to notice 
     <lb/>
     the high earnings of a banking vessel at Grand 
     <lb/>
     Bank. To get a true picture of the average earn<lb break="no"/>ings of our fishermen the whole rather than the 


            <cb/>
         

     part is to be considered. The earnings of fisher<lb break="no"/>men are very irregular depending upon quantity 
     <lb/>
     secured and price received, and the value of 
     <lb/>
     earnings is based on cost of fishery outfit and the 
     <lb/>
     general necessities of life. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Revenue is affected by earnings. The fisher<lb break="no"/>man is no eight-hour-a-day-man with a regular 
     <lb/>
     income. He too often cannot cut the garment 
     <lb/>
     according to the cloth. When he cannot provide 
     <lb/>
     from the fishery, too often he finds there is no 
     <lb/>
     employment elsewhere, which places him in a 
     <lb/>
     fairly tight spot; and this because of lack of 
     <lb/>
     industries. The problem is the establishing of 
     <lb/>
     more industries. Give our people adequate 
     <lb/>
     employment at a living wage and one of our 
     <lb/>
     greatest problems is solved. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The report suggests an increased grant for old 
     <lb/>
     age pensions. Fishermen who, having spent prac<lb break="no"/>tically a lifetime at that trade, and for reasons over 
     <lb/>
     which they have no control, had been unable to 
     <lb/>
     save from their earnings sufficient money to pro<lb break="no"/>vide even moderate comforts for the evening of 
     <lb/>
     life, would greatly appreciate augmentation to 
     <lb/>
     that paid at present. The present pension is too 
     <lb/>
     low, and the age should be 65 instead of 75 years. 
     <lb/>
     I am not satisfied that pensions should be paid 
     <lb/>
     from the general revenue. I believe an export tax 
     <lb/>
     on all our fish and fishery products to provide the 
     <lb/>
     wherewithal to pay fishermen pensions would be 
     <lb/>
     the better way.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Committee does not definitely say that 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland is in every particular self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting. If we accept the interpretation that when 
     <lb/>
     a government has funds sufficient to meet the 
     <lb/>
     cost of public services that country is self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting, then I agree that Newfoundland is self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     supporting. I take it that was what the Committee 
     <lb/>
     meant, and that was what the British government 
     <lb/>
     meant by being self-supporting. I prefer to class 
     <lb/>
     it as the government being self-supporting. If we 
     <lb/>
     had sufficient industries to assure adequate 
     <lb/>
     employment at a living wage, then providing for 
     <lb/>
     meeting the cost of public services would cease 
     <lb/>
     to be a problem. It is a matter of just how we look 
     <lb/>
     at it and of interpretations, so we won't quarrel 
     <lb/>
     over that... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I feel that the revenue received during the past 
     <lb/>
     two years has to a considerable extent been the 
     <lb/>
     result of high earnings during the period of war, 
     <lb/>
     and the augmentation of the purchasing power of 
     <lb/>
     many of our people, particularly business people 


            <pb n="707"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0707.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">707</fw>
          

     who ventured to increase their imports when 
     <lb/>
     more shipping space was available, and the risk 
     <lb/>
     of loss was not so great as during the war. I do 
     <lb/>
     not think the increase in revenue has been al<lb break="no"/>together the outcome of industrial growth. There 
     <lb/>
     has been an increase in exports of iron and paper 
     <lb/>
     by reason of more shipping available during the 
     <lb/>
     past two years, which directly or indirectly, quite 
     <lb/>
     likely has in some way been responsible for in<lb break="no"/>crease in revenue. Suffice it to know that we had 
     <lb/>
     an increase in revenue, though we all may not 
     <lb/>
     quite agree as to the power which brought it to 
     <lb/>
     us.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCO4">Mr. McCormack</persName> Mr. Chairman, ... I propose to 
     <lb/>
     deal but briefly with this report, as it has been 
     <lb/>
     thoroughly covered by previous speakers. I am 
     <lb/>
     sure that the members as well as the listening 
     <lb/>
     public have satisfied themselves by this time as 
     <lb/>
     to its merits or demerits. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Since it has been held up to ridicule, though 
     <lb/>
     only by a small minority of speakers, I should like 
     <lb/>
     to say that in my opinion Major Cashin and the 
     <lb/>
     members of his Committee have done an ad<lb break="no"/>mirable job. The task of estimating the economic 
     <lb/>
     prospects of the country really requires experts 
     <lb/>
     with full authority to probe into every department 
     <lb/>
     of government, and yet in spite of many draw<lb break="no"/>backs the Committee has given us a body of solid 
     <lb/>
     facts, arrived at by a co-ordination of reports 
     <lb/>
     prepared by the various committees, and on the 
     <lb/>
     basis of these facts, has estimated our prospects 
     <lb/>
     for the immediate future.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are expected to determine on the basis of 
     <lb/>
     the committee reports, and bearing in mind the 
     <lb/>
     effect the war had on our economy, whether we 
     <lb/>
     are and can reasonably hope to remain self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting. We are all aware that no country, no 
     <lb/>
     people, is self-sufficient. A country must depend 
     <lb/>
     on its productive economy and on its ability to 
     <lb/>
     trade on a remunerative basis in order to attain 
     <lb/>
     any measure of success in giving its people a 
     <lb/>
     reasonably high standard of living. It is super<lb break="no"/>fluous to say that most people in this country are 
     <lb/>
     living more comfortably today than they did say 
     <lb/>
     in 1930, and with the indisputable facts of this 
     <lb/>
     report on our ever-increasing productive 
     <lb/>
     enterprises, our improved facilities for trade 
     <lb/>
     negotiations, our favourable position by reason 
     <lb/>
     of our strategic importance, we must honestly 
     <lb/>
     admit that we are definitely self-supporting, and 
     <lb/>
     without being unduly optimistic, can look for<lb break="no"/>
            

            <cb/>
          
ward to a continuation of this prosperity. The fact 
     <lb/>
     that hard-headed and successful businessmen 
     <lb/>
     have invested large sums and are continuing to 
     <lb/>
     expand their business ventures is an undeniable 
     <lb/>
     proof of their confidence in future progress. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We could not hope for more than this report 
     <lb/>
     contains. It proves the country is enjoying the 
     <lb/>
     greatest prosperity in its history, and gives 
     <lb/>
     evidence that this prosperity is not ephemeral but 
     <lb/>
     permanent. It gives a fair estimate of ordinary 
     <lb/>
     requirements of government over a period of 
     <lb/>
     three years, and of revenue anticipated for the 
     <lb/>
     same period, with facts on which to base such 
     <lb/>
     estimates. It shows good prospects for our main 
     <lb/>
     industries with demand for pulp and paper and 
     <lb/>
     minerals reasonably stable. It evaluates our local 
     <lb/>
     industries and takes into account the considerable 
     <lb/>
     employment at the bases and at Gander. It advises 
     <lb/>
     conservation of our surplus, and points out that 
     <lb/>
     only very necessary public works should be un<lb break="no"/>dertaken at the present time. Referring to the 
     <lb/>
     Marshall Plan it wisely observes that our future 
     <lb/>
     prosperity, like that of all other countries, is de<lb break="no"/>pendent on general world conditions and on the 
     <lb/>
     quantity and quality of what we produce and 
     <lb/>
     export. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> has dealt with the value of 
     <lb/>
     agriculture to the economy of this country. I 
     <lb/>
     could and would like to go into this more fully, 
     <lb/>
     but I will not take more of your time. Suffice to 
     <lb/>
     say that agriculture in this country should be 
     <lb/>
     given much more consideration and assistance 
     <lb/>
     than in the past. I accept this report as being fair 
     <lb/>
     and equitable and am satisfied that the country is 
     <lb/>
     at the present time, and can remain self-support<lb break="no"/>ing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KEOU1">Mr. Keough</persName> ....In between now and when we 
     <lb/>
     first did meet there has been much application of 
     <lb/>
     honest effort and sincerity of purpose to the task 
     <lb/>
     in hand — and there has been some application 
     <lb/>
     of effort to the serving of political purposes. We 
     <lb/>
     have been to London and to Ottawa. We have 
     <lb/>
     examined with such competence as was ours into 
     <lb/>
     the financial and economic changes that have 
     <lb/>
     taken place in the island since 1934. And we are 
     <lb/>
     come now, at long last, to the drawing of the first 
     <lb/>
     of the great conclusions — as to whether or not 
     <lb/>
     we are self-supporting; in other words, to the 
     <lb/>
     drawing of a conclusion which in the strict letter 
     <lb/>
     of the law might well be held to be none of our 
     <lb/>
     business. It was as far back as last January that I 


            <pb n="708"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0708.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">708</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1947</fw>
           

     first gave it as my opinion that it was not the 
     <lb/>
     assigned task of the Convention to seek a con<lb break="no"/>clusion as to whether or not we are self-support<lb break="no"/>ing. I am still of that opinion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I grant you that the Letters Patent of 1934 did 
     <lb/>
     provide for the administration of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     until such time as it became self-supporting 
     <lb/>
     again. But those Letters Patent were issued under 
     <lb/>
     the Great Seal at Westminster. And that locates 
     <lb/>
     the headache at Westminster. The burden of 
     <lb/>
     proof of self-support — at any rate the decision 
     <lb/>
     in the matter — lies with Westminster. And if the 
     <lb/>
     British Parliament had decided to foist the 
     <lb/>
     responsibility for determination of the question 
     <lb/>
     of self-support upon this Convention it would 
     <lb/>
     have been written in the Convention Act. No  such 
     <lb/>
     thing was written into the Convention Act. What 
     <lb/>
     we were told to do was examine into the financial 
     <lb/>
     and economic changes that have taken place 
     <lb/>
     since 1934. The Economic Report before us, 
     <lb/>
     undoubtedly not without good reason, has seen 
     <lb/>
     fit to go beyond that commitment and bring the 
     <lb/>
     matter of whether or not the island is again self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     supporting before this assembly. It has gone fur<lb break="no"/>ther and suggests that we are self-supporting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     During the deliberations of the Finance Com<lb break="no"/>mittee in preparation of the Economic Report, I, 
     <lb/>
     together with another member of the Committee, 
     <lb/>
     did resign therefrom. By that time it was evident 
     <lb/>
     that the other members of the Committee were of 
     <lb/>
     one mind upon an approach to the matter in hand 
     <lb/>
     with which I was not in accord. Reappointed to 
     <lb/>
     the Committee by you, Mr. Chairman, I thought 
     <lb/>
     that the Committee would make more rapid 
     <lb/>
     progress if I did not attend further meetings. It 
     <lb/>
     was just as well that I did not. For to this report 
     <lb/>
     in its entirety I would not have been able to 
     <lb/>
     subscribe, and my presence at meetings at which 
     <lb/>
     it was prepared could only have led to further 
     <lb/>
     delays — at a cost to the country of $1,000 a 
     <lb/>
     day....  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I see it this way. The proper function of the 
     <lb/>
     Economic Report, as is self-evident from the 
     <lb/>
     terms of reference of the Convention, is to indi<lb break="no"/>cate the economic changes that have taken place 
     <lb/>
     in the island since 1934, and as is implicit in those 
     <lb/>
     terms of reference, to make such forecast for the 
     <lb/>
     foreseeable future as the financial and economic 
     <lb/>
     data to hand and the competence of the talent 
     <lb/>
     applied to its interpretation make possible. There 
     <lb/>
     is a line of demarcation between such an 
 

            <cb/>
           

     enterprise and taking a decision as to whether or 
     <lb/>
     not we are self-supporting. The Economic Report 
     <lb/>
     has crossed that line. It was not wrong for the 
     <lb/>
     report to do so. But in doing so the report put a 
     <lb/>
     chip on its shoulder and went hunting trouble — 
     <lb/>
    perhaps without as much purpose as may have 
     <lb/>been supposed. The British Parliament has not 
     <lb/>asked for a decision on the specific question of 
     <lb/>self-support. That is a decision that it will make 
     <lb/>for itself — for it has made that condition for 
     <lb/>itself. To be fair, it must be said that the report 
     <lb/>did have some justification for addressing itself 
     <lb/>to the question, in that it was popularly expected 
     <lb/>to make a pronouncement. Rightly or wrongly, 
     <lb/>the people have been led to expect this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion to pronounce upon the matter of self-sup<lb break="no"/>port... And I do think that that makes the matter 
     <lb/>of self-support legitimate for our concern. In that 
     <lb/>belief I have already discussed the matter in 
     <lb/>Convention. And in that belief, now that this 
     <lb/>report has formally brought the matter before this 
     <lb/>Convention, I intend to discuss it further today. 
     <lb/>However, I cannot see that any useful purpose is 
     <lb/>served by the estimate of revenue and expendi<lb break="no"/>ture for the next three years. For such an estimate 
     <lb/>to have any credibility it would have to be predi<lb break="no"/>cated upon a more accurate measure of our 
     <lb/>economy than was possible. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     To begin with, there is not in the Convention 
     <lb/>
     anyone equipped with the specialised knowledge 
     <lb/>
     necessary for making a conclusive evaluation of 
     <lb/>
     the present condition and the potential of our 
     <lb/>
     economy. And even if there had been elected a 
     <lb/>
     composite financial wizard and mathematical 
     <lb/>
     genius, it is an open question just how far he 
     <lb/>
     could have gone in that direction. For he would 
     <lb/>
     have had available to him few reliable statistical 
     <lb/>
     indices, no reliable figure of national income, 
     <lb/>
     hardly any basis aggregates upon which to predi<lb break="no"/>cate a conclusion that would be much more than 
     <lb/>
     a good guess. One of the most urgent needs is for 
     <lb/>
     an efficient bureau of statistics. If we had had 
     <lb/>
     such a bureau to turn to this Convention would 
     <lb/>
     have been over in half the time. Even if we had 
     <lb/>
     had foresight enough at the beginning to call in a 
     <lb/>
     competent statistician-economist, I am con<lb break="no"/>vinced that we should have achieved more ac— 
     <lb/>
     curate results sooner.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In the absence of conclusive statistical infor<lb break="no"/>mation and special talent skilled in interpretation 
     <lb/>
     of the same, I cannot see where any special value 
  

            <pb n="709"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0709.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">709</fw>
         

     attaches to the putting together of probabilities to 
     <lb/>
     achieve a budget for tomorrow. Under such cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, an estimate of the immediate future 
     <lb/>
     in broad terms is the most that should be at<lb break="no"/>tempted. To provide for the morrow on paper 
     <lb/>
     down almost to the last million dollar — I'm 
     <lb/>
     afraid I have to view that as counting the chickens 
     <lb/>
     before even the eggs are laid. The way ahead is 
     <lb/>
     loaded with imponderables that do not lend them<lb break="no"/>selves to reduction into round figures of probable 
     <lb/>
     revenue and expenditure. Under these circum<lb break="no"/>stances any attempt to forecast the shape of things 
     <lb/>
     to come in terms of millions of dollars could at 
     <lb/>
     its best result in a good guess, a guess susceptible 
     <lb/>
     to challenge by any other guess held to be just as 
     <lb/>
     good.... All of which is not to suggest, mind you, 
     <lb/>
     that the Finance Committee has deliberately 
     <lb/>
     prepared anything like a political document. Far 
     <lb/>
     from it. I am quite prepared to accept this report 
     <lb/>
     as an honest effort to make an objective appraisal 
     <lb/>
     of our economic position — and an effort which 
     <lb/>
     is, after its own fashion, monumental. But I am 
     <lb/>
     not prepared to go along with it all the way. And 
     <lb/>
     if I must give reasons, they are these: 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     1. The spirit in which the report is written 
     <lb/>
     is more optimistic than I can find cause to 
     <lb/>
     feel. I do not contend that the Committee set 
     <lb/>
     out deliberately to achieve an optimistic 
     <lb/>
     report, or that they have achieved such a 
     <lb/>
     result. But I do not note that the report notes 
     <lb/>
     that there is any dark side to the future. And 
     <lb/>
     as far as I am concerned there is a dark side 
     <lb/>
     to the future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. I can see no particular value that at<lb break="no"/>taches to the forecast of revenue and expen<lb break="no"/>diture for the next three years.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. ....The way I read it, the report says we 
     <lb/>
     are self-supporting, and as far as can be 
     <lb/>
     foreseen we are going to stay self-supporting. 
     <lb/>
    I have to record that I cannot subscribe to that 
     <lb/>position without qualification. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

    

            <p>
     To my mind the Convention is not competent 
     <lb/>
     to do much more than generalise about the 
     <lb/>
     present condition of our economy and its poten<lb break="no"/>tials.... For the record, then, I should like to make 
     <lb/>
     a few generalisations about the economic chan<lb break="no"/>ges that have come upon us since 1934, and on 
     <lb/>
     our chances for the future. This will be my final 
     <lb/>
     word upon these matters. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The economy in 1934 was in a state of col<lb break="no"/>lapse. The Depression was the immediate cause 
  

            <cb/>
         

     that induced this condition. And indeed the 
     <lb/>
     Depression occasioned more havoc within the 
     <lb/>
     economy of Newfoundland than it did within the 
     <lb/>
     economies of most countries. But the Depression 
     <lb/>
     was able to do that because of other causes 
     <lb/>
     making for fundamental weaknesses in the 
     <lb/>
     economy. Of such causes the more notable were 
     <lb/>
     these: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p>
     1. Newfoundland's economy was an ex<lb break="no"/>port economy. The national income was for 
     <lb/>
     the most part derived from the sale of staple 
     <lb/>
     commodities abroad. In consequence, our 
     <lb/>
     economy was extremely vulnerable and col<lb break="no"/>lapsed with the collapse of world trade. Col<lb break="no"/>lapse was very nearly complete.... Such a 
     <lb/>
     disastrous deterioration in our export trade 
     <lb/>
     naturally resulted in wage cuts and lay-offs 
     <lb/>
     and in the reduction of fishermen's incomes 
     <lb/>
     to sub-subsistence levels. The coincidence of 
     <lb/>
     these conditions in their turn precipitated 
     <lb/>
     wage reductions and unemployment in local 
     <lb/>
     secondary industry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. Newfoundland's economy was based 
     <lb/>
     upon but few natural resources — for the 
     <lb/>
     most part fish, wood and some minerals. Ex<lb break="no"/>cept in the instance of fish the quantity of the 
     <lb/>
     natural resources was meager. And in the 
     <lb/>
     instance of fish we were geared to the 
     <lb/>
     production of a greater quantity than the 
     <lb/>
     market at that time could absorb. This lack of 
     <lb/>
     diversification was a fundamental fault. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. Newfoundland's economy was crip<lb break="no"/>pled by the great burden of servicing the 
     <lb/>
     public debt. Had the public debt been inter<lb break="no"/>nally contained, the national income would 
     <lb/>
     have been at the advantage of what it cost to 
     <lb/>
     service it. But the public debt was 
     <lb/>
     preponderantly an external debt and this in<lb break="no"/>volved the export of a sizeable proportion of 
     <lb/>
     the increment from production to service it.... 
     <lb/>
     By 1933 the ratio of service cost to revenue 
     <lb/>
     had become such as would in any case have 
     <lb/>
     led to the eventual wreck of the island's 
     <lb/>
     economy even without benefit of a world 
     <lb/>
     depression.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. The Newfoundland people were 
     <lb/>
     without adequate reserves to fall back upon. 
     <lb/>
     In many countries the Depression did not 
     <lb/>
     bear so heavily as it otherwise might have 
     <lb/>
     upon many people, because in the past they 
     <lb/>
     had been able to make some provision 
    

            <pb n="710"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0710.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">710</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1947</fw>
           

     against just such an emergency. But the 
     <lb/>
     economy of Newfoundland had never been 
     <lb/>
     such as to permit more than a handful to put 
     <lb/>
     aside a little against a rainy day. At the time 
     <lb/>
     the Newfoundland people had some meager 
     <lb/>
     reserves. And all during the Depression they 
     <lb/>
     hung on to them for dear life. People with a 
     <lb/>
     little money in the bank or in the sock went 
     <lb/>
     on dole, but would not part with their little 
     <lb/>
     accumulated store. I have never been able to 
     <lb/>
     bring myself to blame them.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Finally, there must also be taken into ac<lb break="no"/>count the fact that the national income had 
     <lb/>
     long been at the advantage of increment from 
     <lb/>
     seasonal employment on the American main<lb break="no"/>land and from emigrant remittances, and that 
     <lb/>
     the former ceased and the latter were cur<lb break="no"/>tailed by about 75% in the early 1930s. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>
     Not since 1919-20 had the taxable capacity of 
     <lb/>
     our economy been such as would enable us to 
     <lb/>
     defray the normal costs of government and ser<lb break="no"/>vice the public debt without borrowing. By 1933 
     <lb/>
     world depression had played such havoc with our 
     <lb/>
     economy as to have reduced it to where it could 
     <lb/>
     no longer provide many with the opportunity to 
     <lb/>
     make a living, and in consequence a quarter of 
     <lb/>
     the population came to be on relief. Such then 
     <lb/>
     was the fix in which we found ourselves in 1934 
     <lb/>
     — up to our necks in a depressed economy which 
     <lb/>
     was unequal to the task of supporting one quarter 
     <lb/>
     of the population. In between then and now have 
     <lb/>
     come Commission of Government and World 
     <lb/>
     War II and a new virility to our economy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In a speech delivered about two weeks ago — 
     <lb/>
     and which appears to have been misunderstood 
     <lb/>
     in some respects — I analysed the present condi<lb break="no"/>tion of our economy and drew the following three 
     <lb/>
     conclusions: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     1. That no man of fair mind can deny that 
     <lb/>
     our finances and economy are in much 
     <lb/>
     sounder condition than they were in 1934 — 
     <lb/>
     and perhaps in sounder condition than they 
     <lb/>
     have ever been. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. That in consequence, no man may 
     <lb/>
     deny the possibility of a precarious condition 
     <lb/>
     of self-support. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. That no man can speak with con<lb break="no"/>fidence of the future.... 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>
     I wish to add a comment or two with reference 
     <lb/>
     to this possibility of a precarious self-support. I 
     <lb/>
     know that in using that phrase I shall be thought 
   

            <cb/>
         

     of as playing politics. It does not matter. But for 
     <lb/>
     the life of me, I cannot see what other conclusion 
     <lb/>
     there is to come to. To admit of more would 
     <lb/>
     involve gratuitous assumption. Not to admit to so 
     <lb/>
     much would involve downright evasion. And so 
     <lb/>
     I say that a fair man must admit to the possibility 
     <lb/>
     of a precarious self-support However, if it be a 
     <lb/>
     condition of self-support we have come to, we 
     <lb/>
     have to hold that the condition is precarious, 
     <lb/>
     because even the immediate future offers no 
     <lb/>
     surety that the basis upon which our improved 
     <lb/>
     condition rests will not be disestablished over<lb break="no"/>night.... If this be a condition of self-support we 
     <lb/>
     have arrived at, it is a meager enough thing. At 
     <lb/>
     its best, it is a condition of self-support at the level 
     <lb/>
     of what we were used to — perhaps even a little 
     <lb/>
     better than what we were used to. But that is not 
     <lb/>
     enough. It may well be that, for the most part, the 
     <lb/>
     standard of living is higher today than it ever was. 
     <lb/>
     But that is not all that is to be taken into con<lb break="no"/>sideration. The important consideration is — is it 
     <lb/>
     high enough? In the issue that confronts this 
     <lb/>
     nation, are we to be satisfied with that which is 
     <lb/>
     as good as what we were used to, or are we going 
     <lb/>
     to seek for the most that may be had? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If anyone feels that the condition of our 
     <lb/>
     economy is sound and satisfactory, then the 
     <lb/>
     reason must be that he feels that our economy is 
     <lb/>
     adequate to provide us with as good as what we 
     <lb/>
     have been used to. That is one way of looking at 
     <lb/>
     it. Yet we may well find the average fisherman 
     <lb/>
     taking another view. The average fisherman has 
     <lb/>
     always had his own cost of living index, which 
     <lb/>
     he has historically applied to determine the satis<lb break="no"/>factory condition or otherwise of our economy. 
     <lb/>
     That index has been this — a barrel of flour for a 
     <lb/>
     quintal of fish. In times when fishermen have 
     <lb/>
     been able to get a barrel of flour for a quintal of 
     <lb/>
     fish, they have been able to cope adequately with 
     <lb/>
     their family economies, and enjoy some measure 
     <lb/>
     of temporary security. In times when our fisher<lb break="no"/>men have been unable to get a barrel of flour for 
     <lb/>
     a quintal of fish, they have found the national 
     <lb/>
     economy out of focus with their best interests, 
     <lb/>
     and have lived with their fingers crossed against 
     <lb/>
     adversity. Today it takes two quintals of fish to 
     <lb/>
     pay for a barrel of flour — and it is just possible 
     <lb/>
     that my last forgotten fisherman on the bill of 
     <lb/>
     Cape St. George is not so happy over the condi<lb break="no"/>tion of our economy as is the Finance Committee. 
     <lb/>
     He may not at this moment be wondering about 
    

            <pb n="711"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0711.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">711</fw>
          

     where his next meal is coming from. But he may 
     <lb/>
     well be wondering where his next barrel of flour 
     <lb/>
     is coming from. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have to insist upon relating any conclusion 
     <lb/>
     as to the sound and satisfactory character of our 
     <lb/>
     economy to the minimum that I am prepared to 
     <lb/>
     be satisfied with. I have made the point before 
     <lb/>
     that we are a western people, a North American 
     <lb/>
     people. We have but to look across the Gulf to 
     <lb/>
     the North American mainland to observe the 
     <lb/>
     standard of civilisation that such a people are 
     <lb/>
     entitled to enjoy in this day and generation. If 
     <lb/>
     there are any means that we can employ to come 
     <lb/>
     by such standard, then we have every right to use 
     <lb/>
     those means, provided they are not in conflict 
     <lb/>
     with Christian principles and the democratic 
     <lb/>
     tradition. For a little while I had almost become 
     <lb/>
     uncertain of that. So much emphasis had come to 
     <lb/>
     be put upon our duty not to sell that rather amor<lb break="no"/>phous something called "our sacred heritage" for 
     <lb/>
     a mess of pottage, that I had almost come to think 
     <lb/>
     that a mess of pottage was something intrinsically 
     <lb/>
     evil. However, in the meantime I have had the 
     <lb/>
     opportunity of talking again with people to whom 
     <lb/>
     a mess of pottage has meant the difference almost 
     <lb/>
     between life and death at times — and I have 
     <lb/>
     consequently been confirmed in my belief that in 
     <lb/>
     its rightful place a mess of pottage is something 
     <lb/>
     of considerable moment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In the most recent years we have come upon 
     <lb/>
     a new ability to supply ourselves with some of 
     <lb/>
     the public and social services of a western people. 
     <lb/>
     It is but little enough we have come by — and 
     <lb/>
     what we have come by we have come upon the 
     <lb/>
     hard way. We have been a long time in this island. 
     <lb/>
     Our history is as long as the history of any others 
     <lb/>
     who live in this hemisphere. We are as old in the 
     <lb/>
     New World as any men of our race. We have 
     <lb/>
     worked hard in this island — we and our fathers 
     <lb/>
     before us, and their fathers before them. The men 
     <lb/>
     who pushed around the capstans to stump the first 
     <lb/>
     fields, and their sons after them who laboured so 
     <lb/>
     mightily to make those fields produce the little 
     <lb/>
     that they have; the men who decade after decade 
     <lb/>
     have wrenched from the ice floes their wealth of 
     <lb/>
     seals and from the surrounding sea its wealth of 
     <lb/>
     fish; the men who have trapped and logged and 
     <lb/>
     mined and done all such others things as men 
     <lb/>
     have done in this island to make a living; they 
     <lb/>
     have all had to work for that living mightily 
     <lb/>
     indeed. From the wolf at the door they have 
 

            <cb/>
       

     received no quarter. Sometimes even to stay alive 
     <lb/>
     has required effort monumental in its propor<lb break="no"/>tions.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In June past we came to the end of 450 years 
     <lb/>
     of history — for the most part years of grim 
     <lb/>
     endeavour to make both ends meet, years of just 
     <lb/>
     managing to keep body and soul together, years 
     <lb/>
     of doing without. And at the end of four and a half 
     <lb/>
     centuries we have not very much to show for all 
     <lb/>
     our years and all our efforts. Three or four 
     <lb/>
     cathedrals, a few hundred churches, a thousand 
     <lb/>
     or so schools, a narrow gauge railroad that swirls 
     <lb/>
     across the island in a reiteration of fantastic 
     <lb/>
     scrolls, a few ribbons of road and an airport at 
     <lb/>
     Gander and in the red. Once upon a time we even 
     <lb/>
     had a house of parliament and a museum. These 
     <lb/>
     latter years, it is true, many more of our people 
     <lb/>
     have come to know the benefits of what are called 
     <lb/>
     modern conveniences. But as far as a great many 
     <lb/>
     are concerned, the intimate institutions of their 
     <lb/>
     daily lives still are outdoor latrines, wood stoves, 
     <lb/>
     kerosene oil lamps, and carry in your drinking 
     <lb/>
     water from the well back of the house. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have often wondered why it is that after four 
     <lb/>
     and a half centuries we have so little to show for 
     <lb/>
     all our efforts. It is true we live in a gaunt land 
     <lb/>
     that maybe has not had the capacity to produce a 
     <lb/>
     higher standard of living than we have known. 
     <lb/>
     But I have often wondered if that is not too simple 
     <lb/>
     an explanation. There is a saying that they built 
     <lb/>
     New England out of hard times and codfish. 
     <lb/>
     Well, we too have had the codfish. It will also be 
     <lb/>
     conceded that we have had the hard times. There 
     <lb/>
     is another saying about the fault being not in our 
     <lb/>
     stars but in ourselves. But there again the ex<lb break="no"/>planation is too simple. There have been things 
     <lb/>
     in our history that have been beyond ourselves to 
     <lb/>
     effect, that have contributed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In any case, it would appear that we have 
     <lb/>
     lately come to enjoy a somewhat greater portion 
     <lb/>
     than has been our historic portion.... Some of us 
     <lb/>
     have come to be a bit better off than ever before. 
     <lb/>
     As a people, we have come to be able to supply 
     <lb/>
     ourselves with a few of the public amenities and 
     <lb/>
     social services of a North American civilisation. 
     <lb/>
     I am not prepared to accept as conclusive 
     <lb/>
     evidence of a condition of self-support less than 
     <lb/>
     reason to believe that we shall be able to maintain 
     <lb/>
     such personal and national standards for the nor<lb break="no"/>mal times of the future. No person of fair mind 
     <lb/>
     will seek to deny that there is some hope that we 
    

            <pb n="712"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0712.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">712</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1947</fw>
          

     can maintain such standards. And reasons can be 
     <lb/>
     given for such hope. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Take the matter of the fundamental character 
     <lb/>
     of our economy. It is still preponderantly an 
     <lb/>
     export economy. The national income is still for 
     <lb/>
     the most part derived from the sale of staple 
     <lb/>
     commodities abroad. But it so happens that the 
     <lb/>
     world today is temporarily more congenial to the 
     <lb/>
     well-being of an export economy than it has been 
     <lb/>
     for a long time. With the reconstruction of Europe 
     <lb/>
     to be accomplished, and a world-wide shortage 
     <lb/>
     of consumer goods to be filled, one would im<lb break="no"/>agine that world demand for staple products will 
     <lb/>
     not be satisfied in a short time. So for the future 
     <lb/>
     there is some consolation in that. There is con<lb break="no"/>solation too in the strengthening of our economy 
     <lb/>
     through the diversification that has been 
     <lb/>
     achieved in the fishing industry and in a lesser 
     <lb/>
     dependence upon that industry; in the reduction 
     <lb/>
     of the burden of the public debt; in the increment 
     <lb/>
     to the national income derived from services 
     <lb/>
     rendered at the military installations; and in the 
     <lb/>
     accumulation of not insignificant national reser<lb break="no"/>ves. These are the major factors that urge us to 
     <lb/>
     look with hope to the future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But if there is reason to be hopeful there is also 
     <lb/>
     room for doubt. And I am not prepared to avoid 
     <lb/>
     this just because it may be held to be the proper 
     <lb/>
     thing to accent the optimistic view. You see, I 
     <lb/>
     belong to the generation that has never voted. We 
     <lb/>
     have grown up and come to our maturity without 
     <lb/>
     benefit of all the tender ministrations of shib<lb break="no"/>boleth and political poppycock that other genera<lb break="no"/>tions have enjoyed. In consequence, we are far 
     <lb/>
     less likely than were our fathers to give our 
     <lb/>
     allegiance to a cause for purely sentimental 
     <lb/>
     reasons. The mere injunction that we should have 
     <lb/>
     faith in our country is not enough to scare us away 
     <lb/>
     from insisting that there is a dark side to the future 
     <lb/>
     too. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Two years ago you could hardly get a man in 
     <lb/>
     this island to do an odd job. There was full 
     <lb/>
     employment. Wartime construction and the 
     <lb/>
     withdrawal of men from the economy to enter the 
     <lb/>
     fighting services were what led to that condition. 
     <lb/>
     It was not a matter of a sudden competency 
     <lb/>
     having come upon the economy to find a niche 
     <lb/>
     and a living for all. Now the war jobs are over, 
     <lb/>
     and those who fought are returned. I doubt that 
     <lb/>
     all returned men have found employment — and 
     <lb/>
     there are certainly others now without jobs. Our 
   

            <cb/>
          

     economy has not been able to absorb the twin 
     <lb/>
     flow of manpower from the armed services and 
     <lb/>
     from the schools. And it is no answer to say that 
     <lb/>
     nobody need be without work these days, the 
     <lb/>
     unemployed can go to the lumberwoods. It so 
     <lb/>
     happens that not all of them can. Not all of them 
     <lb/>
     are suited for that sort of work. Technique with a 
     <lb/>
     bucksaw does not come naturally. 1n the last 
     <lb/>
     analysis there is no such thing as unskilled labour. 
     <lb/>
     If you don't believe that, you might try putting 
     <lb/>
     your average professor of psychology in a ditch 
     <lb/>
     with your average road labourer and see who digs 
     <lb/>
     the mostest ditch in the shortest time. In any case, 
     <lb/>
     the Christian position is that it is an inherent right 
     <lb/>
     of man to be free to earn a living at work of his 
     <lb/>
     own choosing and for which he is suited. Am I to 
     <lb/>
     understand that we must be satisfied to have 
     <lb/>
     self-support mean less than that? For it would 
     <lb/>
     seem that we are headed for more of less than 
     <lb/>
     that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Economic Report is hopeful of a continu<lb break="no"/>ing annual revenue for the future of $30 million 
     <lb/>
     because this year we shall have a revenue of $40 
     <lb/>
     million. A pious hope, a goodly hope, but never<lb break="no"/>theless a figure pulled out of thin air. And it might 
     <lb/>
     just as well have been $20 million or $50 million. 
     <lb/>
     And if I prefer to contend that the year after next 
     <lb/>
     our revenue will amount to $50 million, I'd like 
     <lb/>
     to see anyone in this Convention undertake to 
     <lb/>
     prove to me that it could not be. It would be a 
     <lb/>
     most interesting manoeuvre to observe.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Apropos of that revenue, there are two things 
     <lb/>
     worthy of mention. One is that it derives in part 
     <lb/>
     from not-so-efficient business management. 
     <lb/>
     During the war, goods were in such short supply 
     <lb/>
     that business firms began booking orders for this, 
     <lb/>
     that and the other thing over half the world. 
     <lb/>
     Orders were duplicated and triplicated and never 
     <lb/>
     cancelled. This year there has been a flood of 
     <lb/>
     goods emanating from these orders that should 
     <lb/>
     have been cancelled but were not. The revenue 
     <lb/>
     originating from this source may hardly be con<lb break="no"/>strued to have arisen from the normal needs of 
     <lb/>
     the people. Also there is a great deal of importing 
     <lb/>
     to satisfy what may be called an abnormal re<lb break="no"/>placement demand. Many things wore out during 
     <lb/>
     the war years, which due to shortages could not 
     <lb/>
     be replaced. Indeed, in this island many things 
     <lb/>
     wore out during the Depression which people 
     <lb/>
     have only lately come to be in a financial position 
     <lb/>
     to replace. Much current importing is being done 
  

            <pb n="713"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0713.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">713</fw>
          

     to satisfy such abnormal replacement demand. It 
     <lb/>
     so happens then, that significant proportions of 
     <lb/>
     the $40 million we shall likely realise this year 
     <lb/>
     derive from extraordinary rather than the ordi<lb break="no"/>nary needs of the people. Since such is the case, 
     <lb/>
     it could be that $30 million would be a more 
     <lb/>
     appropriate figure from which to begin to fig<lb break="no"/>ure.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     However, my major concern for the immedi<lb break="no"/>ate future is rooted in the uncertainty that hangs 
     <lb/>
     over the whole world. If everything goes just 
     <lb/>
     right with the world everything will go all right 
     <lb/>
     with us. If it doesn't, I prefer not to think of the 
     <lb/>
     consequences. Two months ago something did 
     <lb/>
     not go right — England froze the convertibility 
     <lb/>
     of sterling. Overnight we were no longer so cer<lb break="no"/>tain that we were self-supporting. We needed $7 
     <lb/>
     million to tide us over the crisis and the winter. 
     <lb/>
     Such was the meager measure of our much- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     vaunted self-support. And had it happened that 
     <lb/>
     we were not able to dig down in our own pocket 
     <lb/>
     for that, a great many of our fishermen would be 
     <lb/>
     finding little evidence of self-support in their 
     <lb/>
     open receipts. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     For the future, of this much only can we be 
     <lb/>
     certain — that if everything goes just right in the 
     <lb/>
     world we will manage to get along. If the Mar<lb break="no"/>shall Plan goes into effect; if the world's ex<lb break="no"/>change problems can be solved; if the Geneva 
     <lb/>
     multilateral trade arrangements come to be 
     <lb/>
     ratified and extended; if the US won't up the tariff 
     <lb/>
     on our fresh fish; if the world price of newsprint 
     <lb/>
     stays put; if a hundred and one things go just right, 
     <lb/>
     then all will go all right with us — if at home the 
     <lb/>
     fishery doesn't fail. For the fishery is still impor<lb break="no"/>tant, and a fishery failure will still mean hungry 
     <lb/>
     people. And will the nations of the world take 
     <lb/>
     care to conduct their affairs so as to serve our best 
     <lb/>
     interests? What is your guess? And don't forget 
     <lb/>
     that my guess is as good as yours. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I do regret it if my attitude appears unreason<lb break="no"/>able, as I know that it must to some. But resolu<lb break="no"/>tion of the question of self-support at the national 
     <lb/>
     level in terms of present and anticipated revenues 
     <lb/>
     in excess of expenditures appears to me too 
     <lb/>
     simple a solution. I keep seeking a conclusion in 
     <lb/>
     terms of the ability of the little fellow to carry on 
     <lb/>
     — the little fellow who hasn't got a Cadillac to 
     <lb/>
     his name, and who never gets to attend a com<lb break="no"/>munity concert, but who nevertheless makes up 
     <lb/>
     the fibre and sinew of the nation. And I am not so 
  

            <cb/>
        

     certain that right at this moment this little fellow 
     <lb/>
     enjoys as great a measure of security as he did 
     <lb/>
     during the normal times of the past. He has, it is 
     <lb/>
     true, a higher income. But it is a question if it 
     <lb/>
     means as much to him in terms of the necessities 
     <lb/>
     of life as his incomes in the normal times of the 
     <lb/>
     past have meant. He has an enormously increased 
     <lb/>
     cost of living to contend with. And in that respect, 
     <lb/>
     please don't remind me that his salt pork comes 
     <lb/>
     in duty free. He also has to have a shirt for his 
     <lb/>
     back on which he must pay 40% duty — plus 
     <lb/>
     profit, plus profit on the duty. And incidentally 
     <lb/>
     who wants to eat salt pork all the year round? I 
     <lb/>
     grant you that he may have come to enjoy a 
     <lb/>
     measure of precarious self-support. But whether 
     <lb/>
     or not he can continue to enjoy in the normal 
     <lb/>
     times of the future such meager-enough stand<lb break="no"/>ards of living and social services as he now 
     <lb/>
     knows, is not something on which we can pass 
     <lb/>
     judgement at this moment. It is something at 
     <lb/>
     which we can but guess. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As has already been pointed out by several 
     <lb/>
     speakers it is not our business here to take the 
     <lb/>
     optimistic view of the future. It is not our business 
     <lb/>
     to take the pessimistic view. It is our business to 
     <lb/>
     take the realistic view. And the realistic view is 
     <lb/>
     this: if all goes just right with the world we will 
     <lb/>
     manage to get along. If not — the deluge. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am not prepared to accept as conclusive 
     <lb/>
     evidence of self-support less than satisfactory 
     <lb/>
     evidence that we can hope to see the paltry stand<lb break="no"/>ards of living and public and social services we 
     <lb/>
     now know, maintained for the normal times of 
     <lb/>
     the future. And there are far too many im<lb break="no"/>ponderables in between now and even this time 
     <lb/>
     next year, for anybody to give me categoric as<lb break="no"/>surance of any such thing. I am consequently 
     <lb/>
     compelled to an attitude of economic agnos<lb break="no"/>ticism. I am convinced that the only thing of 
     <lb/>
     which we can be certain is that we cannot be 
     <lb/>
     certain. So I cannot join in a categoric assurance 
     <lb/>
     to the Newfoundland people that we are self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting. The possibility of a precarious self-sup<lb break="no"/>port I am prepared to admit. But I cannot join in 
     <lb/>
     such an assurance as sees no shadows on the road 
     <lb/>
     ahead. If others can, be it upon their own con<lb break="no"/>science. It is a matter of conscience since it can<lb break="no"/>not be shown to be a matter of fact. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I note that the Economic Report quotes for our 
     <lb/>
     edification the late President Roosevelt's famous 
     <lb/>
     dictum — "We have nothing to fear but fear 


            <pb n="714"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-12_Page_0714.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
     714 NATIONAL CONVENTION November 1947 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
           

     itself." Might I point out that Roosevelt was 
     <lb/>
     addressing those words to 130 million people 
     <lb/>
     living in one of the richest lands of the earth and 
     <lb/>
     with all the mighty forces of a highly in<lb break="no"/>dustrialised civilization theirs to command. The 
     <lb/>
     Economic Report is addressing 320,000 people 
     <lb/>
     living in one of the poorest lands of the earth, and 
     <lb/>
     with but a $30 million national surplus to pull and 
     <lb/>
     haul on if the going gets rough. There just hap<lb break="no"/>pens to be a slight difference. But now that 
     <lb/>
     Roosevelt's name has come up, I remember that 
     <lb/>
     he had a formula for the re-establishment of the 
     <lb/>
     lives of men at a level of not less than the most 
     <lb/>
    that might be had for all men. He wanted all men  
     <lb/>everywhere to enjoy freedom from fear, freedom 


            <cb/>
           

     from want, freedom from the fear of want. And I 
     <lb/>
     like to think that he wanted that not only for the 
     <lb/>
     butcher and baker and candlestick-maker he 
     <lb/>
     knew, but for my last forgotten fisherman on the 
     <lb/>
     bill of Cape St. George as well. And if in the 
     <lb/>
     decision that confronts this nation there shall be 
     <lb/>
     any way of coming by such economic security, 
     <lb/>
     and yet retaining the full measure of our political 
     <lb/>
     liberty, then we should not turn our backs on that 
     <lb/>
     way to a more spacious destiny for purely sen<lb break="no"/>timental reasons. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee rose and reported progress. A 
     <lb/>
     number of items on the order paper were 
     <lb/>
     deferred]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>


</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Motion to Amend National Convention Act to Permit Voting by Proxy 
     <lb/>
            </head></div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I move: 
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>
     That this Convention request His Excellency 
     <lb/>
     the Governor in Commission that Paragraph 
     <lb/>
     2 of the National Convention Act, 1946, be 
     <lb/>
     amended, whereby provision may be made 
     <lb/>
     that any member or members of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion incapacitated by reason of illness from 
     <lb/>
     attending sessions of the Convention may 
     <lb/>
     have his or their vote recorded in his or their 
     <lb/>
     absence provided he or they have signed and 
     <lb/>
     executed the proper instrument to give effect 
     <lb/>
     to this purpose. Such right to vote by proxy 
     <lb/>
     shall be exercised only during the debate on 
     <lb/>
     forms of government and the recommenda<lb break="no"/>tions to the United Kingdom government 
     <lb/>
     arising therefrom to be put before the people 
    

            <cb/>
       

     at a national referendum. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     If the motion is carried, and if the Commission 
     <lb/>
     of Government accede to the request, it will be 
     <lb/>
     necessary to amend article 39 of our own con<lb break="no"/>stitution, but that could wait until after amend<lb break="no"/>ment is made by the Commission of Government, 
     <lb/>
     if the amendment is passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
       <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It is to permit members in<lb break="no"/>capacitated by illness from attending to express 
     <lb/>
     by proxy his or their vote or votes on forms of 
     <lb/>
     government, when that business comes before 
     <lb/>
     the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I wish to second that motion. 
            </p>

<p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried, and the Convention ad<lb break="no"/>journed]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2017-07-24, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     November 13, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I give notice thatI will on tomorrow 
     <lb/>
     ask the Honourable the Commissioner for Home 
     <lb/>
     Affairs to obtain as soon as possible from the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom government the answers to the 
     <lb/>
     following questions: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (a) Does the United Kingdom govern<lb break="no"/>ment regard the legislation known as the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland Act, 1933, whereby the con<lb break="no"/>stitution of Newfoundland was suspended, as 
     <lb/>
     being at present valid, subsisting and legally 
     <lb/>
     effective? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (b) If the said legislation of 1933 is at 
     <lb/>
     present regarded by the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     government as valid and effective, is the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom government prepared to 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     comply with the provisions as set forth in the 
     <lb/>
     annex to the said act, wherein it states in 
     <lb/>
     section 4, subsection (g), "it would be under<lb break="no"/>stood that, as soon as the Island's difficulties 
     <lb/>
     are overcome, and the country is again self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     supporting, responsible government on the 
     <lb/>
     request of the people of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     would be restored?" 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (c) If the United Kingdom government 
     <lb/>
     intends to carry out the provisions set forth in 
     <lb/>
     the annex to the 1933 legislation, sub-section 
     <lb/>
     (g), what manner and what methods do they 
     <lb/>
     propose using to obtain the wishes of the 
     <lb/>
     people? 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>