<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-10-30" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-10-30">30 October 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
  
         
           <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

          <date when="1995"/>.   
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="125"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0120.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0121.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0122.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0123.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0124.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0125.hocr.html"/>
               </item>

            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-02-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-04">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0120">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0120.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0121">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0121.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0122">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0122.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0123">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0123.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0124">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0124.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0125">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0125.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="120" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0120.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">120</fw> <fw type="num">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">October 30, 1946</head>

</div>
<div type="section">
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Before proceeding to the orders <lb/> of the
                  day, I should like to clarify a situation to <lb/> which I referred yesterday
                  afternoon in dealing <lb/> with the motion before the Chair relative to the <lb/>
                  sending of a delegation to Ottawa and the amend<lb break="no"/>ment proposed by
                  Mr. Penney. I said I would put <lb/> the motion and then put the amendment — what
                  <lb/> I meant was this; that when the debate on the <lb/> motion has terminated
                  and when all the members <lb/> who wish to speak have spoken thereto, I shall <lb/>
                  <cb/> then read the question and then announce that to <lb/> that question an
                  amendment has been proposed <lb/> and seconded so that you gentlemen may then
                  <lb/> understand that you will have the right to speak <lb/> to the amendment as a
                  new question. You quite <lb/> understand? Then when the debate on both is <lb/>
                  over, I shall, of course, pursuant to the ordinary <lb/> practice, put the
                  amendment first, and from that <lb/> the consideration of the motion will follow
                  in due <lb/> course. <lb/>
               </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Motion to send a Delegation to Canada<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Before the debate is proceed with, <lb/> I would
                  like to take up a matter of procedure. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Certainly. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> If I understand your ruling correct<lb break="no"/>ly, this Convention has power to send a delega<lb break="no"/>tion, and that
                  ruling was confirmed by Mr. <lb/>Wheare. I am not competent to contest your
                  <lb/>ruling, there are others more capable of doing <lb/>that, yet I would like to
                  draw your attention to an <lb/>extract from His Excellency the Govemor's ad<lb break="no"/>dress<ref target="#fn_02">[2]</ref> given before the Convention,
                  and I quote: <lb/>
               </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>These forty-six Newfoundlanders gather 
     <lb/>together to consider, and here in the interest 
     <lb/>of accuracy quote from the official terms of 
     <lb/>reference "to consider and discuss amongst 
     <lb/>themselves as elected representatives of the 
     <lb/>Newfoundland people, the changes that have 
     <lb/>taken place in the financial and economic 
     <lb/>situation of the Island since 1934, and bear<lb break="no"/>ing in mind the extent to which the high 
     <lb/>revenue of recent years have been due to 
     <lb/>wartime conditions, to examine the position 
     <lb/>of the country, and to make recommenda<lb break="no"/>tions to His Majesty's Government as to pos<lb break="no"/>sible forms of future Government to be put 
     <lb/>before the people at a national referendum. 
     <lb/>Though these terms of reference do not per<lb break="no"/>mit of a roving commission, they do provide 
     <lb/>ample scope for the members of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion to ventilate their views on the possible 
     <lb/>forms of future Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>He says the terms of reference do not permit of a 
     <lb/>roving commission. I do not know whether we 
     <lb/>consider a delegation to Ottawa or anywhere else 
     <lb/>as a roving commission; I would like a ruling on 
     <lb/>that... 
     <lb/></p>
            
            <cb/>
       
<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I do not think, Major Cashin, <lb/> that His
                  Excellency had in mind when he used <lb/> that expression, the competency or
                  otherwise of <lb/> the Convention in sending a delegation to Ot<lb break="no"/>tawa; nor do I consider that the expression which <lb/> you have quoted is
                  germane to the ruling which <lb/> I gave yesterday. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> The point I am making, His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency
                  says, "the terms of reference do not permit <lb/>a roving commission." <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You want an interpretation of <lb/>"roving
                  commission"? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Yes. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I do not think you want to con<lb break="no"/>strue
                  that expression too literally. It means what <lb/>it says. I would say what His
                  Excellency perhaps <lb/>had in mind was that we were confined within <lb/>certain
                  definite limits by virtue of the terms of <lb/>reference. We have to regard those
                  terms of ref<lb break="no"/>erence in ascertaining what our powers are... I
                  <lb/>confirm my ruling of yesterday, that I think it is <lb/>perfectly competent
                  for this Convention, if it so <lb/>desires, to send a delegation to Ottawa, if the
                  <lb/>Canadian government is prepared to receive such <lb/>a delegation, to
                  ascertain the terms and the basis <lb/>of which the Canadian government would be
                  <lb/>prepared to consider federal union with Canada; <lb/>in the same way, it is
                  perfectly competent for this <lb/>Convention to ascertain any other fact. It
                  really <lb/>amounts to the eliciting of information, and one <lb/>of the primary
                  duties as well as the patent <lb/>authority and right of this Convention is to
                  elicit <lb/>information on basic facts. Is that clear, Major <lb/>Cashin? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Quite clear, but I have not gotten <lb/>the
                  definition of a "roving commission" yet. As <lb/>
                  <note xml:id="fn_01">[1] See pp. 93, 104. [Debate Day: 1946-10-28]</note>
                  <note xml:id="fn_02">[2] See p. 3. [Debate Day: 1946-09-11]</note>
                  <pb n="121" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0121.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">121</fw> I understand it, a roving commission is one meant <lb/> to
                  go around and get facts. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I am not saying what His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency meant; that would be impertinence on my <lb/> part. All I can do is to
                  construe the words. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> That is a point that has also been <lb/>
                  troubling me. It has been insinuated here that we <lb/> might possibly send a
                  delegation to Timbuctoo. <lb/> Where are we going to draw the line about this
                  <lb/> roving commission? I would like to refer you to <lb/> paragraph 2 of this
                  White Paper: <lb/>
               </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     Accordingly, His Majesty's Government 
     <lb/>
     in the United Kingdom, having considered 
     <lb/>
     the changed financial and economic position 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland, it was announced by the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs in 
     <lb/>
     the House of Lords on the 11th December, 
     <lb/>
     1945, that steps would be taken as soon as 
     <lb/>
     possible to provide machinery whereby the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland people would be enabled to 
     <lb/>
     examine the future of the Island and to ex<lb break="no"/>press their considered views as to the form of 
     <lb/>
     Government they desire, having regard to the 
     <lb/>
     financial and economic conditions prevailing 
     <lb/>
     at the time. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>

            <p>
     In <hi rendition="simple:italic">Newfoundland</hi>, not in Canada or Timbuc<lb break="no"/>too. Whilst I am not in a position of disputing 
     <lb/>
     your ruling, sir, or the distinguished constitution<lb break="no"/>al historian who has been sent out here by the 
     <lb/>
     Dominions Office, yet my mind is not satisfied 
     <lb/>
     that we, as a Convention, have the right to send a 
     <lb/>
     delegation to Canada, to England or even to 
     <lb/>
     Timbuctoo; and I would like to have that position 
     <lb/>
     fully clarified, at least as far as my mind is con<lb break="no"/>cerned, and I would like to have clarification on 
     <lb/>
     the point which Major Cashin raised. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I confirm my ruling. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WATT1">Mr. Watton</persName> Mr. Chairman, I have listened with <lb/> varying
                  emotions to the several speakers on the <lb/> resolution now before this House.
                  Some with <lb/> profound interest, to others with disgust. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     As I have stated before in this House, I came 
     <lb/>
     to this Convention with an open mind, and I want 
     <lb/>
     to make it clear that no one either inside or outside 
     <lb/>
     this Convention has succeeded in altering my 
     <lb/>
     opinion. I have not been offered any senatorships, 
     <lb/>
     neither have I been offered a trip to Ottawa; I also 
     <lb/>
     want it to be understood that I am not a con<lb break="no"/>federate, not that it will make any difference to 
     <lb/>
     me what people think of me. As far as this motion 
     <lb/>
     now before the Chair is concerned I am going to 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
            
     support it. The people of this country, whom we 
     <lb/>
     represent, the people of Fogo district, whom I 
     <lb/>
     personally represent, expect when the time 
     <lb/>
     comes to be given the real facts, they want to 
     <lb/>
     know if this country is self-supporting at this 
     <lb/>
     moment, if it is likely to be so in the future. In 
     <lb/>
     short they want to know just where we stand as a 
     <lb/>
     country. They also want to know about forms of 
     <lb/>
     government, whether it be Commission govern<lb break="no"/>ment, responsible government, confederation or 
     <lb/>
     any other form, and we have got to give it to them. 
     <lb/>
     Whether we like it or not, there are thousands of 
     <lb/>
     people who think that confederation is the best 
     <lb/>
     thing that could ever happen in this country. 
     <lb/>
     Perhaps it is, I don't know, nobody knows, and I 
     <lb/>
     therefore consider it our duty to find out. When 
     <lb/>
     the terms of confederation are made known those 
     <lb/>
     who are now favouring it may be turned against 
     <lb/>
     it; on the other hand, the terms may be such that 
     <lb/>
     every man and woman in this country may 
     <lb/>
     demand it. Who are we to dictate to these people 
     <lb/>
     whose servants we are? There are people who say 
     <lb/>
     they are Newfoundlanders and will not be a party 
     <lb/>
     to selling this country up the St. Lawrence River. 
     <lb/>
     It's not a question of selling the country to 
     <lb/>
     anyone, it's just a matter of doing a job we were 
     <lb/>
     sent here to do. I am also a Newfoundlander, and 
     <lb/>
     when I say that, I am proud of it — I mean it. 
     <lb/>
     Together with thousands of others I freely gave 
     <lb/>
     six of the best years of my life in the service of 
     <lb/>
     my country. I am not going to lower myself by 
     <lb/>
     asking somebody where they were in the last war 
     <lb/>
     or any other war; it's none of my business, I leave 
     <lb/>
     that to the dictates of their own consciences. But 
     <lb/>
     that is beside the point. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It has been stated that there is some ulterior 
     <lb/>
     motive in bringing in this resolution. Be that as it 
     <lb/>
     may, I am beginning to believe that there is some 
     <lb/>
     ulterior motive behind those opposing it. Is it 
     <lb/>
     possible that those who are opposing the seeking 
     <lb/>
     of the terms of confederation are afraid that the 
     <lb/>
     terms are going to be so good it will upset their 
     <lb/>
     political castle of dreams and bring it tumbling 
     <lb/>
     around their ears? The people of this country 
     <lb/>
     have been bluffed and hoodwinked long enough, 
     <lb/>
     it's about time they were given some of the cold 
     <lb/>
     hard facts, whether it suits our own personal, 
     <lb/>
     selfish desires or not. The people have never had 
     <lb/>
     a chance to live half-decent lives, but in spite of 
     <lb/>
     that there are those who would have us believe 
     <lb/>
     that we are living in prosperous times, that we are 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="122" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0122.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">122</fw>
           
     self-supporting. I would like to take these 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen to some of the little outports, to the 
     <lb/>
     little fishing villages to see how the fisherman 
     <lb/>
     and his family lives. Even in these so-called 
     <lb/>
     prosperous times he and his family have half 
     <lb/>
     enough to eat, half enough to wear, and they may 
     <lb/>
     have a tight roof over their heads and they may 
     <lb/>
     not. Are we, this National Convention, sent here 
     <lb/>
     by these very people who are at this moment 
     <lb/>
     suffering untold hardships, are we going to deny 
     <lb/>
     them the facts concerning confederation, or any<lb break="no"/>thing else for that matter? If I did such a thing I 
     <lb/>
     would consider myself a traitor to the cause I 
     <lb/>
     have taken up. If I became a party to such a 
     <lb/>
     dishonourable act, could I in all sincerity still 
     <lb/>
     stand on my feel and call myself a true New<lb break="no"/>foundlander? I think not. At this time we have to 
     <lb/>
     be realistic, we have to face the facts, however 
     <lb/>
     distasteful they may appear. We have to acquit 
     <lb/>
     ourselves like men, and be strong; we must not 
     <lb/>
     allow our own petty desires and selfish interests 
     <lb/>
     to have an overriding influence over our better 
     <lb/>
     judgement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am not a politician, and I don't know that I 
     <lb/>
    have any desire to be. But I do say I have the 
     <lb/>interest of this country really and truly at heart; 
     <lb/>not from any selfish motives, but from an intense 
     <lb/>desire to see that this land of ours has a fighting 
     <lb/>chance, that our people have a chance to live 
     <lb/>decent lives. And in that spirit, I support the 
     <lb/>motion now before the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> Mr. Chairman, I am in accord with <lb/>the principle
                  embodied in this resolution al<lb break="no"/>though I am not in accord with the
                  method, that <lb/>of sending a delegation to Ottawa. What could a <lb/>delegation
                  possibly accomplish except to confer <lb/>with the government officials of that
                  country? <lb/>Whatever is done will have to be reduced to <lb/>writing and
                  presented to this Convention. Could <lb/>not the terms of confederation be
                  ascertained in <lb/>another way? Is it not possible for this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion to find out those terms by transmitting its <lb/>enquiry to the Canadian
                  government through the <lb/>regular diplomatic channels which exist between
                  <lb/>the governments of both countries? If that is <lb/>possible then, why send a
                  delegation at all? <lb/>
               </p>

    

            <p>
     As regards the time of ascertaining the terms, 
     <lb/>
     in my opinion it does not matter whether those 
     <lb/>
     terms arrive now or in January. We have the 
     <lb/>
     ruling of the Chair that it is within the scope of 
     <lb/>
     this Convention to find out those terms. But we 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
            
           
     have yet to decide whether confederation could 
     <lb/>
     be a recommendation of this Convention or not. 
     <lb/>
     So it really does not matter when we receive 
     <lb/>
     them, the question can be laid aside until we are 
     <lb/>
     ready to deal with any form of government which 
     <lb/>
     may be introduced in this assembly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I did not come here with a definite opinion in 
     <lb/>
     support of any particular form of government. 
     <lb/>
     But I did come here with the opinion that Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government must go and an elected 
     <lb/>
     government be restored; we should never have 
     <lb/>
     lost the rights of responsible government. Before 
     <lb/>
     I close l would like to make an observation. Since 
     <lb/>
     I sat in this House I have not said very much, but 
     <lb/>
     a couple of weeks ago I did object to some words 
     <lb/>
     which were embodied in a report that was 
     <lb/>
     presented here, and for my objection I was as<lb break="no"/>sociated with radicalism by someone who 
     <lb/>
     probably does not know the meaning of the word 
     <lb/>
     "radical". I was born and reared in New<lb break="no"/>foundland and have lived all my life in the City 
     <lb/>
     of St. John's, and during that time I have worked 
     <lb/>
     for the period of 29 years, and in that 29 years I 
     <lb/>
     have been fortunate to enjoy six weeks vacation 
     <lb/>
     with pay. If that is a definition of a radical then I 
     <lb/>
     should be proud to be a radical, and I would think 
     <lb/>
     that there are many more people of the same 
     <lb/>
     category in this country who would think in the 
     <lb/>
     same terms as I. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In conclusion, and I hope I am right in saying 
     <lb/>
     this, I believe the question of federating with the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion of Canada is a question that must be 
     <lb/>
     left to a duly elected government of this country, 
     <lb/>
     and they should have a clear mandate from the 
     <lb/>
     people of Newfoundland before any steps are 
     <lb/>
     taken to implement any terms of union that may 
     <lb/>
     be considered. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JONE5">Mr. Jones</persName> Mr. Chairman, in the opening days <lb/> of this
                  Convention when the Chadwick-Jones <lb/> report was up for discussion, I said that
                  all forms <lb/> of government should be set aside until the <lb/> desired facts
                  had been collected and examined. I <lb/> am sorry that suggestion has not been
                  adhered to. <lb/> I saw then, as some of us see now, that it was bad <lb/> policy
                  to introduce a discussion on the different <lb/> forms of government before the
                  facts had been <lb/> ascertained. At the present time we know very <lb/> little of
                  the economic conditions of this country, <lb/> and I think it is a mistake to send
                  a delegation to <lb/> Ottawa from this Convention until we know its <lb/>
                  financial condition. I would not wish to be one of <lb/>
                  <pb n="123" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0123.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="num">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">123</fw> the delegates to approach the Canadian govern<lb break="no"/>ment with what little information we have at <lb/> present in this
                  Convention on our economic and <lb/> financial life. I am not a confederate, never
                  was, <lb/> and have never given it five minutes considera<lb break="no"/>tion. I
                  believe in my own country — New<lb break="no"/>foundland for Newfoundlanders -
                  until I am <lb/> convinced otherwise. Nevertheless, Mr. Chair<lb break="no"/>man,
                  I am in favour of finding out what the <lb/> Canadian government has to offer us,
                  should <lb/> confederation become a live question in this <lb/> country. Many of
                  the previous speakers have <lb/> already said that we owe it to the people of this
                  <lb/> country, no difference what our own individual <lb/> views may be. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     This Convention is only in its infancy; it has 
     <lb/>
     not yet emerged from its committee stage. Until 
     <lb/>
     we have passed that milestone let the different 
     <lb/>
     forms of government sleep peacefully, and when 
     <lb/>
     we are strong enough, wake them up, and then we 
     <lb/>
     shall see what we shall see. Mr. Chairman, we are 
     <lb/>
     growing up too fast; let us get back to our com 
     <lb/>
     mittee stage and finish that job first. When that 
     <lb/>
     work has been completed and discussed we shall 
     <lb/>
     be in a much better position to talk about the 
     <lb/>
     different forms of government most suitable for 
     <lb/>
     this country. We may find that our own house, 
     <lb/>
     with a little window cleaning, may not be so bad 
     <lb/>
     to live in after all. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have listened to the previous speakers for and 
     <lb/>
    against the motion now under fire, and I find that 
     <lb/>a big majority of the members is in favour of 
     <lb/>finding out what terms Canada would offer this 
     <lb/>country should confederation become a live 
     <lb/>issue. The chief obstacle seems to be the time of 
     <lb/>approach. I too think that the motion is a bit 
     <lb/>premature, and therefore favour the amendment 
     <lb/>brought in by Mr. Penny on Monday afternoon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Mr. Fudge was interrupted in <lb/>his address the
                  other afternoon and unwittingly <lb/>sat down. I feel quite sure that none of us
                  wants <lb/>to deprive Mr. Fudge of his liberty of completing <lb/>his remarks.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> On the introduction of these resolu<lb break="no"/>tions before the House, I rose and objected to the <lb/>statement made by Mr.
                  Smallwood, wherein he <lb/>stated that Newfoundland was 50 to 100 years
                  <lb/>behind the times. I want to say that I did not <lb/>believe it then and do
                  not believe it now. <lb/>
               </p>

    

            <p>
     It appears to me that the sole aim of the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion at this stage of our proceedings was to divide 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
          
     us, so that we may not be able to enquire and to 
     <lb/>
     examine the condition of our country, being the 
     <lb/>
     first order and may I add the first duty to do so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have listened to the debate on this question 
     <lb/>
     and I recall the introduction of the Chadwick- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Jones report by Major Cashin. You will remem<lb break="no"/>ber also that in later addresses made by other 
     <lb/>
     delegates Major Cashin was attacked viciously. 
     <lb/>
     No point was raised then regarding personalities, 
     <lb/>
     or that attack was not the proper procedure. But 
     <lb/>
     during discussion on this resolution, which in my 
     <lb/>
     opinion came before it was sent for, Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin, in my opinion at any rate, was not treated 
     <lb/>
     fairly. And it appears to me that the whole thing 
     <lb/>
     was unfair. Mr. Cashin merely asked for an ex<lb break="no"/>planation from the introducer of these resolutions 
     <lb/>
     on whose authority he was suggesting the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment of senators and delegates to Ottawa. 
     <lb/>
     This I certainly would have asked myself, and I 
     <lb/>
     want to ask it now and to go on record that I have 
     <lb/>
     asked, not only for my own information but for 
     <lb/>
     the information of the people who comprise the 
     <lb/>
     second-largest district in the country. I feel that 
     <lb/>
     we are entitled to such information. I consider 
     <lb/>
     that if the statements made by Mr. Hollett and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Harrington are not denied, then there is noth<lb break="no"/>ing else left for us to do but accept them as the 
     <lb/>
     truth. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Right at this particular moment, one of the 
     <lb/>
     most important reports was to be discussed, 
     <lb/>
     namely the Forestry Report, which was full of 
     <lb/>
     hope and encouragement and would have had an 
     <lb/>
     important bearing on the final findings of this 
     <lb/>
     Convention. This report in my opinion was too 
     <lb/>
     optimistic for the advocates of confederation. 
     <lb/>
     They only want the dark and gloomy picture to 
     <lb/>
     come before the people of our country. I am sick 
     <lb/>
     and tired of hearing some of our delegates stating 
     <lb/>
     that we have not got the men in our country 
     <lb/>
     capable of looking after our own affairs. Let me 
     <lb/>
     recall one of the most important boards set up in 
     <lb/>
     this country during the war. I refer to the Woods 
     <lb/>
     Labour Board, and I am not alone in this when I 
     <lb/>
     say that the members on that board from its very 
     <lb/>
     beginning were highly capable of looking after 
     <lb/>
     their own affairs. The results show this and they 
     <lb/>
     were Newfoundlanders. And I further state, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Chairman, that at the head of that board was 
     <lb/>
     another Newfoundlander, namely yourself, who 
     <lb/>
     succeeded the late Judge Higgins. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I want to put myself definitely on record as 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="124" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0124.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">124</fw>
 <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
         

     supporting the amendment to this resolution, and 
     <lb/>
     I do so feeling that I am carrying out the duties 
     <lb/>
     entrusted to me to defend with all the power at 
     <lb/>
     my command the rights and liberties of our 
     <lb/>
     people. I am one who has confidence in the future 
     <lb/>
     of our country and our people, and I do not 
     <lb/>
     believe for a moment that this good old ship of 
     <lb/>
     state is at all leaky, and I am not prepared to send 
     <lb/>
     out an SOS to the Canadian rescue tug. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BROW7">Mr. Brown</persName>   A few days ago I spoke briefly in <lb/>
                  connection with the resolution now before this <lb/> house. I felt at that time,
                  as I do today, that that <lb/> resolution was premature. It was brought in <lb/>
                  before the receipt of committee reports which <lb/> would show just what the
                  financial and economic <lb/> position of this country is. I have been wondering
                  <lb/> to myself the reason why Canada has not sent a <lb/> delegation here,
                  instead of this Convention send<lb break="no"/>ing a delegation to Canada, if
                  Canada wants <lb/> Newfoundland, and there is no doubt she does <lb/> want to
                  annex Newfoundland... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I remember quite well, sir, and so do you when 
     <lb/>
     members from the government of the day went 
     <lb/>
     to Quebec, trying to sell the Labrador to the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec government. I can name the men if 
     <lb/>
     necessary; I think the Prime Minister was one of 
     <lb/>
     them, and they, in the final analysis, offered to 
     <lb/>
     sell Labrador to the Quebec government for $15 
     <lb/>
     million, and the Quebec government turned it 
     <lb/>
     down, thinking that in the final analysis the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council of England would award Labrador to 
     <lb/>
     Quebec, or to Canada. They would not take over 
     <lb/>
     Labrador, or what we claimed we owned of it, for 
     <lb/>
     $15 million. Now we have a resolution before 
     <lb/>
     this House asking us to send a delegation to 
     <lb/>
     Canada to get the terms, and I presume if neces<lb break="no"/>sary become part and parcel of Canada. Canada 
     <lb/>
     wants Labrador, and she wants Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     Perhaps the Dominion government is not so in<lb break="no"/>terested, or the people at Ottawa, but the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     government is, and wants Newfoundland, and 
     <lb/>
     thinks today, Mr. Chairman, that Labrador 
     <lb/>
     should never have been ceded to Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     I have seen a lot happen in this assembly, and so 
     <lb/>
     have you, sir, and I don't know today who is the 
     <lb/>
     father of this House, whether it is you or myself. 
     <lb/>
     You were elected in 1919, 1923, 1924, and I was 
     <lb/>
     elected in 1923, 1924, 1928, 1932 and 1946 
     <lb/>
     without a defeat, and I have seen many hard and 
     <lb/>
     rough times in this House. This is a famous 
     <lb/>
     chamber. Famous sometimes for what it did not 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
            
     do, and famous for what it did do as well. I was 
     <lb/>
     in the House and saw some of the hardest fights 
     <lb/>
     across this floor and took part of it myself. I have 
     <lb/>
     been here till 7 o'clock in the morning in an 
     <lb/>
     all-night session, and my friend Mr. Cashin was 
     <lb/>
     here as well, and also Mr. Bradley. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There is so much said about crooked poli<lb break="no"/>ticians and graft and everything else, but I want 
     <lb/>
     to tell this House that I was not one of them. I left 
     <lb/>
     politics after all these years associated with the 
     <lb/>
     public life of the country a shade worse off than 
     <lb/>
     when I entered it. I defy any department of the 
     <lb/>
     government in Newfoundland to turn up a piece 
     <lb/>
     of paper that I had black-leaded in my name and 
     <lb/>
     to say that I spent a dollar in my life of govern<lb break="no"/>ment money. I never have, although I had 
     <lb/>
     authority to spend up to $40,000 and got licked 
     <lb/>
     after all. I have never done it, Mr. Speaker, and I 
     <lb/>
     feel that I have been a fairly honourable member 
     <lb/>
     of this House. At times I was unruly and had to 
     <lb/>
     take my seat. I submitted to your ruling, sir, but 
     <lb/>
     once I remember distinctly when I balked for a 
     <lb/>
     little while and you told me you would have me 
     <lb/>
     removed from the House, and I asked you, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, what man in the House could remove 
     <lb/>
     me, and you told me you would have me re<lb break="no"/>moved. I looked down at my old friend the late 
     <lb/>
     Robert Walsh, and he was about 90 years old, and 
     <lb/>
     I said, "Would you like to take that job on Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Walsh?", and he said, "No". I have seen times in 
     <lb/>
     this House when men could have got money and 
     <lb/>
     plenty of it, and I distinctly remember on one 
     <lb/>
     occasion when there was a bill on the table before 
     <lb/>
     this House, and I, with three others, when all the 
     <lb/>
     other members of the opposition were against us, 
     <lb/>
     we stood our ground and defied this House on 
     <lb/>
     every corner, and three of these members are here 
     <lb/>
     today. Mr. Bradley, Mr. Ashbourne and myself, 
     <lb/>
     and another man that's not in this House today. 
     <lb/>
     Am I right or wrong, Mr. Bradley? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then some of us have been called political 
     <lb/>
     grafters. I defy any man in this country to call me 
     <lb/>
     one. There is no one here who can call me such, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman. We have before this House a 
     <lb/>
     resolution. It is a different resolution from what 
     <lb/>
     was brought before the Steering Committee, sir, 
     <lb/>
     and you know it, and we passed this resolution, 
     <lb/>
     but when brought into this House it was a dif<lb break="no"/>ferent resolution entirely. It may have meant the 
     <lb/>
     same thing, but the wording was different entire<lb break="no"/>ly. I am not against getting terms from Canada, 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="125" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-30_Page_0125.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">125</fw>
           
     and seeing what these terms are, but it is prema<lb break="no"/>ture, sir. We have not yet got for the people of this 
     <lb/>
     country what we were sent here to get. Therefore 
     <lb/>
     I am in duty bound to vote against the resolution 
     <lb/>
     and to vote for the amendment. Nobody, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood or anybody else, has ever ap<lb break="no"/>proached me or offered me a senatorship or a trip 
     <lb/>
     to Ottawa or anything else. As perhaps the oldest 
     <lb/>
     member here I say here that nobody apart from 
     <lb/>
     God Almighty directs my course. I have a mind 
     <lb/>
     of my own. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     While men in this House today may come to 
     <lb/>
     the chamber for the first time, I know even more 
     <lb/>
     about what I speak than people whose fathers 
     <lb/>
     before them have spent their lifetime in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with the fisheries of this country. I am not 
     <lb/>
     one of those. I feel that we came here to do a duty 
     <lb/>
     to the people. I don't feel as Mr. Watton felt this 
     <lb/>
     afternoon that some are here with an ulterior 
     <lb/>
     motive. I have no ulterior motive. I was elected 
     <lb/>
     by acclamation. I was called out by the people in 
     <lb/>
     my own district, and not only one crowd but 
     <lb/>
     several. I never intended to run as a delegate to 
     <lb/>
     this Convention, but I did intend, if I was spared, 
     <lb/>
     to run in whatever election might come forward 
     <lb/>
     at a later date. I was called by my people, like it 
     <lb/>
     was said of me one time when I was called for 
     <lb/>
     another district. My reply was that it was not that 
     <lb/>
     I can't go there, I was not afraid to go there. I have 
     <lb/>
     never feared a political election or a political 
     <lb/>
     fight. I loved it, and I love it today. Therefore, 
     <lb/>
     when we come down to supporting this motion I 
     <lb/>
     feel that I can't do it in sincerity. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> I have been practically 30 years representing <lb/> labour in this country. My
                  younger days were <lb/> spent in the Pacific coast fishery business in <lb/>
                  Alaska. I know all about fishing — more than <lb/> many who have had so much prate
                  on it. I was <lb/> there with frozen fingers, on the Banks and in the <lb/> dory.
                  I have gone through the mill as much as the <lb/> average man in this House has
                  gone. Yet I don't <lb/> come here pretending that I know it all. I have <lb/>
                  handled labour in this country for 29 years. I have <lb/> led strikes and settled
                  strikes, and got wages <lb/> increased, and I have done many things for the <lb/>
                  people of this country, and I am not ashamed of <lb/> it today. <lb/>
                  <cb/>
                  <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> referred to the Woods Labour <lb/> Board. I am a
                  member of that Woods Labour <lb/> Board, and it has done a lot for this country,
                  and <lb/> is still doing it. That Woods Labour Board is <lb/> showing to this
                  country that we don't want <lb/> anybody else to come in and run our own affairs.
                  <lb/> That Woods Labour Board, under the chairman<lb break="no"/>ship of the late
                  revered and honoured Judge Hig<lb break="no"/>gins, and of the present Mr. Justice
                  Fox, has done <lb/> work that perhaps few others could do. We have <lb/>
                  experienced people on that board, and it has done <lb/> a good job; therefore I
                  join with my friend, <lb/> Mr. Fudge, in saying that we can handle our own <lb/>
                  affairs and we don't have to go to Canada. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     You will find today in Canada places where 
     <lb/>
     people are just as backward as they are in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I have a piece of paper in my pocket 
     <lb/>
     now, I won't read it, but if I did I doubt if there 
     <lb/>
     would be ten men in this House who would vote 
     <lb/>
     for this resolution. Let it go. I will not read it now, 
     <lb/>
     I will leave it to some other time. I am not jumping 
     <lb/>
     to any conclusions, I know where I stand. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Some get up and make flowery speeches, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman. I have never read a speech in this 
     <lb/>
     assembly from the first day up to the present day, 
     <lb/>
     and you know sir, that the rules of the House of 
     <lb/>
     Assembly would not allow members to read their 
     <lb/>
     speeches. You had to get up and spit it out of you 
     <lb/>
     and have no hesitation in doing it. I have done it 
     <lb/>
     for years, and I hope I am doing it now. In the 
     <lb/>
     meantime, Mr. Chairman, I am not sorry to see 
     <lb/>
     that this is allowed now to the new members in 
     <lb/>
     this House. The only thing about it, are the 
     <lb/>
     speeches that the members read all written by 
     <lb/>
     themselves or by someone else? I don't have to 
     <lb/>
     write a speech to get up and express my opinion, 
     <lb/>
     I can get up and speak my mind without a written 
     <lb/>
     speech. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have never met Mr. Penney before coming 
     <lb/>
     here to this Convention, and I have not spoken 20 
     <lb/>
     words to you since you have been here, but I hold 
     <lb/>
     you in the highest esteem. Thank you for seeing 
     <lb/>
     fit to bring in this amendment. I think that in 
     <lb/>
     doing so you are doing no injustice... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Brown collapsed at this point. The Conven<lb break="no"/>tion adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-02-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


          <!--  <p>
     October 31, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Cashin I would like to make the motion that 
     <lb/>
     this House adjourn until Monday afternoon at 3 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     o'clock, in respect for one of our delegates, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Brown, who dropped here yesterday after<lb break="no"/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>