<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-11-06"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-11-06">6 November 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="663" to="671"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0663.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0664.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0665.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0666.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0667.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0668.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0669.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0670.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0671.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-07-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-07-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0663">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0663.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0664">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0664.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0665">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0665.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0666">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0666.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0667">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0667.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0668">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0668.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0669">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0669.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0670">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0670.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0671">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0671.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="663"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0663.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
     November 1947 NATIONAL CONVENTION 663 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     November 6, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Gentlemen, I have just received 
     <lb/>
    a letter from His Excellency the Governor: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Government House, St. John's. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     November 6, 1947. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     J. B. McEvoy, Esq., K.C., LL.B., 
     <lb/>
    Chairman, National Convention, 
     <lb/>St. John's, Nfld. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     Dear Mr. Chairman: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In response to a request by the Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Canada, the Right Hon. W. L. 
     <lb/>
     Mackenzie King, I wish to ask you to kindly 
     <lb/>
     bring to the immediate attention of the Na<lb break="no"/>tional Convention the enclosed copy of a 
     <lb/>
     letter I have received, together with the 
     <lb/>
     enclosure attached thereto. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Have you enough copies? I think they might be 
     <lb/>
     distributed. I propose to have the enclosure read 
     <lb/>
     by the Secretary when copies have been dis<lb break="no"/>tributed.... Quite obviously there can be no 
     <lb/>
     discussion. Immediately after it is read we will 
     <lb/>
     proceed with the business of the day as indicated 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     by the order paper. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett Mr. Chairman, may I ask if the 
     <lb/>
     communication from the Rt. Hon. Mackenzie 
     <lb/>
     King is to be read too? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman I don't know if that is included 
     <lb/>
     or not. In my copy it is. If you would be so good, 
     <lb/>
     Captain Warren, would you proceed with the 
     <lb/>
     reading of the document? I propose releasing the 
     <lb/>
     copies to the press. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The Secretary read the document]¹ 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Bradley Mr. Chairman, I do not know how 
     <lb/>
     you intend to deal with this communication, but 
     <lb/>
     I suggest that because of the importance of the 
     <lb/>
     document itself, if for no other reason, the proper 
     <lb/>
     procedure would be to receive it now, and to refer 
     <lb/>
     it to a committee of the whole tomorrow.... I give 
     <lb/>
     notice that I will on tomorrow move that the 
     <lb/>
     communication from the Government of Canada 
     <lb/>
     be received, and referred to a committee of the 
     <lb/>
     whole. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Finance Committee: Economic Report² 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Job Mr. Chairman, I want to make a few 
     <lb/>
     remarks on this Economic Report, and I dare say 
     <lb/>
     that people will be curious to know why my 
     <lb/>
     signature is not appended to it. Perhaps they will 
     <lb/>
     be disappointed when I tell them that, in the main, 
     <lb/>
     I was in favOur of the winding-up part of the 
     <lb/>
     report. I believe that the country is self-support- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ing. I did not sign the report for two or three 
     <lb/>
     reasons. The first was that I thought it was not 
     <lb/>
     necessary to introduce a budget. One can quite 
     <lb/>
     understand the inclination of Major Cashin to 
     <lb/>
     introduce this report on the basis of a budget, and 
     <lb/>
     as any finance minister would have introduced it 
     <lb/>
     in a house of parliament. I think we can also 
     <lb/>
     understand why Mr. Smallwood, who might be 
     <lb/>
     termed "the Leader of the Opposition", thought 
     <lb/>
     it his duty to tear it to pieces. His tearing of it to 
     <lb/>
     pieces was a matter of opinion, whether it was 
     <lb/>
     effective or not. I don't think it was very effec<lb break="no"/>tive. I would like to express my approval of the 
     <lb/>
     conclusions of the report, and I don't want to 
     <lb/>
     enter into a discussion of the details. I think the 
     <lb/>
     report was written in a very racy, very readable 
     <lb/>
     way, and presented in a very interesting form. On 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     the other hand I don't hesitate to say that the 
     <lb/>
     estimates can be only regarded as guesswork. 
     <lb/>
     Estimates generally are. There is no reason, in my 
     <lb/>
     opinion, why $35 million or $25 million, or $40 
     <lb/>
     million should not have been taken as the prob<lb break="no"/>able revenue, instead of $30 million. However, 
     <lb/>
     the figures as they are in the report are pretty 
     <lb/>
     good, and it is the interpretation that counts. 
     <lb/>
     There is only one discrepancy that I can really 
     <lb/>
     point to in the figures, and it is not done with a 
     <lb/>
     view to criticism, because I don't think it matters 
     <lb/>
     very much. Life insurance values are put down as 
     <lb/>
     $30 million as the surrender value. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Chairman That is the estimated cash sur<lb break="no"/>render value. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Job Yes, Now 1 would like to hand to the 
     <lb/>chairman of the Committee the actual report from 
     <lb/>the office of the Assessor of Taxes which shows 
     <lb/>the actual liability to policy holders as at 31 
     <lb/>December as $22,237,464. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Cashin What year? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Job Last year, l946. I don't think it matters. 
     <lb/>That $8 million will not make a shadow of dif<lb break="no"/>ference to me in my opinion as to the life in<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <pb n="664"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0664.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">664 NATIONAL CONVENTION November 1947 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     surance. If the value has increased, as this shows 
     <lb/>
     it has ... the effect is very important on our 
     <lb/>
     economy as I consider it. When I was a member 
     <lb/>
     of this Finance Committee considering this 
     <lb/>
     Economic Report I stated at the start that I did not 
     <lb/>
     think it necessary to introduce a budget. I was 
     <lb/>
     asked to draft a report, which I did — a very short 
     <lb/>
     report. It took me two days to do, but I produced 
     <lb/>
     this report at the Committee and Major Cashin 
     <lb/>
     said that he did not want to introduce it. He said 
     <lb/>
     that he wanted to make up this report and produce 
     <lb/>
     it. I did not blame him a bit, but I could not agree 
     <lb/>
     with what was going into it, and I simply 
     <lb/>
     withdrew. I thought it was read very well, was 
     <lb/>
     well prepared, and the only objection I have is 
     <lb/>
     that it may mislead people. In the short report that 
     <lb/>
     I prepared there were one or two things that are 
     <lb/>
     not in Major Cashin's report, and I would like to 
     <lb/>
     call your attention to them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would like to read first of all my reasons for 
     <lb/>
     leaving out the estimates. My suggestion was that 
     <lb/>
     the difficulty of furnishing really valuable figures 
     <lb/>
     was so great under present world conditions that 
     <lb/>
     any forecast might be considered a waste of 
     <lb/>
     time.... We know what the present situation is, 
     <lb/>
     and we know that the situation we can see imme<lb break="no"/>diately ahead is very good, but I don't think we 
     <lb/>
     can really forecast actual figures. One of the 
     <lb/>
     things that makes it clear, one of the points of 
     <lb/>
     difference, is what has recently occurred in con<lb break="no"/>nection with the saltfish trade — the difficulty of 
     <lb/>
     getting exchange. A few months ago, before there 
     <lb/>
     was any question of the exchange, we all felt very 
     <lb/>
     happy about the situation. That situation has been 
     <lb/>
     temporarily solved by the government advancing 
     <lb/>
     the money themselves, but that is only a temper- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ary cure. I am not, however, at all pessimistic 
     <lb/>
     about the future of the fishery; and I believe that 
     <lb/>
     the fresh fish plants and the possibility of central 
     <lb/>
     curing stations, will make a great difference in 
     <lb/>
     our fish situation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     ....One of the points that I thought should have 
     <lb/>
     been brought out very strongly was that the stand<lb break="no"/>ard of living of our people today is a very dif<lb break="no"/>ferent thing to what it was in 1934, or 1944 rather. 
     <lb/>
     Today we find the average Newfoundlander en<lb break="no"/>joying undoubtedly a much higher standard of 
     <lb/>
     living than ever before. My friend Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood over there read a letter from an in<lb break="no"/>dividual fisherman, and Mr. Hollett rightly 
     <lb/>
     pointed out, I think, that we always have some 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     people in trouble. It will always be so. You can 
     <lb/>
     find the same thing in any city, but I think the 
     <lb/>
     general condition of our people today is very 
     <lb/>
     much improved. I think the people are becoming 
     <lb/>
     more accustomed to thinking for themselves, and 
     <lb/>
     this is largely due to factors such as the circulat<lb break="no"/>ing regional libraries, the adult education move<lb break="no"/>ment, the co-operative committees, the 
     <lb/>
     agricultural societies. the Jubilee Guilds, the 
     <lb/>
     Junior Red Cross Association, and our Memorial 
     <lb/>
     University College, and I should not fail to men<lb break="no"/>tion the increased intelligence and diligence of 
     <lb/>
     the various unions all over the country. It is 
     <lb/>
     making people think more than they used to do, 
     <lb/>
     and that is one of our chief assets, a sign of 
     <lb/>
     improvement for the future. I think it helps us to 
     <lb/>
     look at the future in a more hopeful way than we 
     <lb/>
     have done in the past. Undoubtedly the taxable 
     <lb/>
     capacity of the economy has been increased to 
     <lb/>
     where it can produce revenues which, in addition 
     <lb/>
     to being able to defray the normal costs of 
     <lb/>
     government, can support more public and social 
     <lb/>
     services than we have ever hitherto had, and yet 
     <lb/>
     leave a surplus of perhaps a million or so to spare 
     <lb/>
     at the end. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     ...I would like to refer to the comment in this 
     <lb/>
     report on the question of trade with the USA. This 
     <lb/>
     to my mind is the vital question in connection 
     <lb/>
     with our future economy unless we can do 
     <lb/>
     without the fish trade, but it is the vital point in 
     <lb/>
     connection with all the future of the fish trade.... 
     <lb/>
     I have had the idea for a very long time that if we 
     <lb/>
     could get some round table conferences between 
     <lb/>
     representatives of Canada, Great Britain and the 
     <lb/>
     United States, we would get somewhere. Now 
     <lb/>
     this report indicates that would have to be done 
     <lb/>
     by a government of our own, and it might be so; 
     <lb/>
     but supposing for the sake of argument that the 
     <lb/>
     country did elect to continue Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government, I don't see any reason why, if there 
     <lb/>
     is a proper agitation, Commission could not have 
     <lb/>
     such a conference. But this report indicates that 
     <lb/>
     it would have to be done by a constitutional 
     <lb/>
     government. That might not be necessary. Of 
     <lb/>
     course in case of confederation the thing would 
     <lb/>
     simply fall through. It would be impossible. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would like to wind up by saying I have great 
     <lb/>
     pleasure in supporting the concluding paragraphs 
     <lb/>
     of the report, as I believe that we are self-support- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ing, and that we will continue to be self-support- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ing for very many years ahead.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="665"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0665.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
     November 1947 NATIONAL CONVENTION 665 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     Mr. Vincent ....There are a few observations I 
     <lb/>
     would make, and I trust you will bear with me in 
     <lb/>
     my rather inadequate presentation of them. Two 
     <lb/>
     very able speakers have so far clashed swords, 
     <lb/>
     both occupying long periods in the vindication of 
     <lb/>
     their pet arguments, and in my opinion with good 
     <lb/>
     advantage. I can assure you that I have no inten<lb break="no"/>tion of carrying the argument so far, for after all 
     <lb/>
     I am only the junior lieutenant in the heretofore 
     <lb/>
     styled "B", or "Bonavista Block", and with such 
     <lb/>
     powerful Sidekicks as the member for Bonavista 
     <lb/>
     Centre, and my esteemed and learned friend, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Bradley, K.C., I need have no worries but that the 
     <lb/>
     so-called "B Block" will contribute its pen<lb break="no"/>nyworth to this debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, I trust you will pardon me if I 
     <lb/>
     confine the greater part of my talk to a discussion 
     <lb/>
     of that industry which census statistics tell us 
     <lb/>
     employs 62% of our people, for isn't it true that 
     <lb/>
     the success of the 62% contributes in a large way 
     <lb/>
     to the success of the 38%? In this I know that very 
     <lb/>
     fine gambling Newfoundlander, my personal 
     <lb/>
     friend Mr. Crosbie, will support me, for his 
     <lb/>
     record at the fisheries is told in deeds not in 
     <lb/>
     words, and however much our proposed plans for 
     <lb/>
     the future of that industry may differ, we both 
     <lb/>
     believe in Newfoundland as principally a fishing 
     <lb/>
     country. I put codfish first; he, I believe, puts 
     <lb/>
     herring and whales. I am going to talk about fish, 
     <lb/>
     the soundness of the economy of the fishery ... 
     <lb/>
     and if being called a defeatist means the revela<lb break="no"/>tion here of cold facts pertaining to that industry, 
     <lb/>
     then by all means call me a defeatist. I live with 
     <lb/>
     fishing folk, I own Labrador schooners, I supply 
     <lb/>
     inshore fishermen, and if this Committee has 
     <lb/>
     something practical and constructive to offer, 
     <lb/>
     something that will contribute to the future well- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     being and success of every Joe Killick fisherman, 
     <lb/>
     not only in my hard-hit Bonavista North, but to 
     <lb/>
     every last fisherman in this island, then count on 
     <lb/>
     my unqualified support. I very much regret, how<lb break="no"/>ever, that in this report I find a lot of well-mean- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ing platitudes. Of that more later on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Economic Report, combining as it does 
     <lb/>
     the sum total of the findings of the several reports 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention, is of first importance. It does 
     <lb/>
     seem to me, however, that the real question to be 
     <lb/>
     determined is just this: what is the relation of the 
     <lb/>
     actual economic position of this island to the 
     <lb/>
     constitutional issue? I presume that will be borne 
     <lb/>
     out later. For the moment we are to concern 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     ourselves with the subject matter before the 
     <lb/>
     Chair. The question to which each delegate must 
     <lb/>
     give his considered opinion is simply: can I ac<lb break="no"/>cept the report of the Economic Committee as 
     <lb/>
     being in my opinion a true and accurate picture 
     <lb/>
     of the island's economy? Or, to put it shorter, 
     <lb/>
     what is my interpretation of the term "self-suf- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ficiency"? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It does seem dangerous to talk about experts, 
     <lb/>
     but I hold to the opinion expressed by several 
     <lb/>
     others, that the Committee, lacking the services 
     <lb/>
     of an economist-statistician, were greatly hand<lb break="no"/>icapped in that they had no reliable, authoritative 
     <lb/>
     statistics at their command, to enable them to 
     <lb/>
     even remotely indicate the basic soundness of our 
     <lb/>
     economy. By way of clarification, there is in this 
     <lb/>
     report an assumption based on the estimates 
     <lb/>
     given the Ottawa delegation by the Railway 
     <lb/>
     management that our Railway is worth $72 mil<lb break="no"/>lion, and the question naturally arises, is this a fair 
     <lb/>
     and proper estimate?.... The Report of the 
     <lb/>
     Forestry Committee, on which committee I ac<lb break="no"/>tively served with Major Cashin, made a 
     <lb/>
     provisional estimate of the earnings of our forest 
     <lb/>
     resources as not less than $30 million. Can this 
     <lb/>
     evaluation be safely projected into the future? 
     <lb/>
     And in this respect, have we or have we not 
     <lb/>
     reached our productive peak? Fisheries valued at 
     <lb/>
     $30 million; isn't it true that the vagaries of this 
     <lb/>
     industry, the many uncertainties surrounding it, 
     <lb/>
     are of such a nature that not even a prophet could 
     <lb/>
     predict as to whether the product of this industry 
     <lb/>
     will have even a nominal market value say five 
     <lb/>
     years from now? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are self-supporting. Time was when such 
     <lb/>
     a revelation would make the man in the fishing 
     <lb/>
     boat, the man in the street toss his hat into the air 
     <lb/>
     and cheer. It might even have been heralded by a 
     <lb/>
     roll of drums. Yes, Mr. Chairman, a budgetary 
     <lb/>
     surplus, propped up by a healthy looking balance 
     <lb/>
     sheet, does show a very promising, rosy picture 
     <lb/>
     for the faithful, who do not require an absolute 
     <lb/>
     gilt-edged guarantee of our solvency. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let's talk about the economy of the fishery, in 
     <lb/>
     particular the codfishery, for that phase of the 
     <lb/>
     industry employs many more men than do the 
     <lb/>
     other branches. I believe in our fisheries so much 
     <lb/>
     that for the past two years I have been investing, 
     <lb/>
     when l was told by a big business friend of mine, 
     <lb/>
     a Water Street financier, lam looking at him now, 
     <lb/>
     that it was dangerous going, and maybe he was 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="666"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0666.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
     666 NATIONAL CONVENTION November 1947 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     right. So now I am going to give you first-hand 
     <lb/>
     information as to just how sound the Labrador 
     <lb/>
     branch of the codfishery is at the moment — I 
     <lb/>
     shall call the play exactly as I find it, November 
     <lb/>
     1947 edition. With the past I have little concern, 
     <lb/>
     rather I am concerned with what we shall eat and 
     <lb/>
     wear in the years that lie immediately ahead. So, 
     <lb/>
     with the indulgence of this House, I'll get district- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     minded and talk of things as they really are in my 
     <lb/>
     constituency of Bonavista North, and I under<lb break="no"/>stand this goes for all of the northeast coast, for, 
     <lb/>
     as said a gentleman speaking yesterday, "A 
     <lb/>
     country is as self-sufficient as its people." Now 
     <lb/>
     permit me to refer you to the Economic Report, 
     <lb/>
     page 30: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Summarising what we have said with 
     <lb/>
     regard to our fishing industry, it would seem 
     <lb/>
     that the outlook for the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     fisheries is anything but discouraging. In<lb break="no"/>deed, judging from the evidence available 
     <lb/>
     and the opinion of those qualified to speak, it 
     <lb/>
     would seem that we have entered upon a new 
     <lb/>
     era-the era of modernised methods, faster 
     <lb/>
     production and more profitable markets. And 
     <lb/>
     it is not unreasonable to say that the adoption 
     <lb/>
     of methods which have brought prosperity to 
     <lb/>
     such a country as Iceland, cannot fail but 
     <lb/>
     bring similar results to the 30,000 of our 
     <lb/>
     people engaged in the fishing industry of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now the junior member for "B Block" will 
     <lb/>
     have the temerity to give his frank opinion, based 
     <lb/>
     on first-hand knowledge of this phase of the 
     <lb/>
     industry. The economy of the Labrador cod- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     fishery is so shot to pieces that the individual 
     <lb/>
     fisherman at this moment is just one shortjump 
     <lb/>
     ahead of the dole, and if there is to be any 
     <lb/>
     Labrador fishery next season, if the Labrador 
     <lb/>
     fisherman sails up the coast in a schooner, he will 
     <lb/>
     go only with a guarantee of his security, or, to put 
     <lb/>
     it plainer, he will go only with a guaranteed 
     <lb/>
     minimum salary at the end of the voyage. I have 
     <lb/>
     an interest in three schooners which this year 
     <lb/>
     prosecuted the fishery, and the 30 men on board 
     <lb/>
     these schooners each one declared the day he 
     <lb/>
     arrived home, "Not again brother, my last trip", 
     <lb/>
     and do you wonder? The season coming as the 
     <lb/>
     smashing climax to a cycle of three bad years, the 
     <lb/>
     fisherman is fed up. Schooners are being put on 
     <lb/>
     the block, codtraps are being auctioned. Is this 
     <lb/>
     encouraging? I'll pause here for a moment and 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     ask that question of my hard-boiled, industrious 
     <lb/>
     old friend, fishing master Capt. Billy Winsor of 
     <lb/>
     Wesleyville. He gave up the fight discouraged, 
     <lb/>
     after 40 years up coast, and he's as good a fisher<lb break="no"/>man as ever trod a deck. I'll pause and ask that 
     <lb/>
     question of hard-driving fishing skippers, Capt. 
     <lb/>
     Malcolm, and Charles Rodgers of Fair Island; I'll 
     <lb/>
     ask that question of the shoremen in Cape Freels 
     <lb/>
     and at Musgrave Harbour, who wondered what 
     <lb/>
     they'd do with the fish when they told them about 
     <lb/>
     the convertibility of sterling. I'll ask the chap in 
     <lb/>
     Newtown with whom I talked ten days ago, who 
     <lb/>
     told me his summer's catch of fish was in his 
     <lb/>
     store, and he wanted flour and couldn't get it. 
     <lb/>
     Yes, Mr. Chairman, I'll ask them the question, 
     <lb/>
     and am well content to await their replies, and 
     <lb/>
     quite satisfied to abide by their decisions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am not suggesting that government or vested 
     <lb/>
     interest can make fish swim at specific periods in 
     <lb/>
     specific harbours, so that our schooners may 
     <lb/>
     secure substantial loads; but I do want to point 
     <lb/>
     out that the Labrador phase of the industry 
     <lb/>
     employs a lot of our people, and 1 am not satisfied 
     <lb/>
     in my own mind that the fishery generally is 
     <lb/>
     anything but discouraging. The Labrador fishery 
     <lb/>
     at the moment is flat on its back; some fishing 
     <lb/>
     skippers have lost everything, and sharemen- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     fishermen have given up all plans of going back 
     <lb/>
     to the coast. This is not exaggerated. Look up 
     <lb/>
     your papers and read the schooners advertised for 
     <lb/>
     sale. I am conversant with every angle of this 
     <lb/>
     industry, and if this house, or the Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government wants some corroboration, they 
     <lb/>
     have only to have a look-see around the northeast 
     <lb/>
     coast ofBonavista Bay, and it will be put to them 
     <lb/>
     in very strong terms. Modernise your methods, 
     <lb/>
     centralise your fisheries, establish dollar credits, 
     <lb/>
     invoke the Marshall Plan, transform and 
     <lb/>
     refashion, my prayers go with your petitions in 
     <lb/>
     this respect, gentlemen of the Economic Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, but your vested interests, or your govern<lb break="no"/>ment had better bestir themselves, for it is later 
     <lb/>
     than you think. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Allow me to summarise; 1947 finds thousands 
     <lb/>
     of our fishermen with an average seasonal catch 
     <lb/>
     of 30 quintals per man, valued at less than $11 
     <lb/>
     per quintal; 1947 finds our fishermen, all fine 
     <lb/>
     adaptable fellows, seeking employment in the 
     <lb/>
     woods, to try to augment their meager earnings; 
     <lb/>
     and the last straw that breaks the camel's back, 
     <lb/>
     this past week I talked with Labrador fishermen 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="667"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0667.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
     November 1947 NATIONAL CONVENTION 667 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     coming back from the camps to destitute families, 
     <lb/>
     told, "Sorry, no work, our camps are filled." 
     <lb/>
     Moreover last Saturday I was told by a respon<lb break="no"/>sible official of one of the large paper companies, 
     <lb/>
     "We have reduced our cut this year", and tragi<lb break="no"/>cally enough, one of the reductions was in the 
     <lb/>
     Bonavista Bay area. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The value of our total productive economy is 
     <lb/>
     entirely dependent on the economy of countries 
     <lb/>
     thousands of miles away. The welfare of my last 
     <lb/>
     fisherman friend down on stormy Cape Freels is 
     <lb/>
     entirely dependent on the economic standing of 
     <lb/>
     the Italian, the Greek, the Spaniard, living in 
     <lb/>
     continental Europe. We have no internal markets 
     <lb/>
     for our products, and if we did, what could 
     <lb/>
     300,000 people eat anyhow? Thus I submit that 
     <lb/>
     our economic set-up has no similarity in the 
     <lb/>
     western hemisphere. I don't know the solution to 
     <lb/>
     this big problem of our fisheries. Probably my 
     <lb/>
     able friend Mr. Crosbie has something to offer, 
     <lb/>
     but this I do know, that solving the problem will 
     <lb/>
     require capital expenditure on a large scale, be 
     <lb/>
     the source the vested interests or the state. Other<lb break="no"/>wise, the poor forgotten fishermen, every last 
     <lb/>
     man of them, must just patiently endure and 
     <lb/>
     quietly wait, till chance or somebody else comes 
     <lb/>
     along to redeem their fortunes. I'm finished with 
     <lb/>
     the fisheries Mr. Chairman and gentlemen, but 
     <lb/>
     before closing, I want to say without any hesita<lb break="no"/>tion, that I advocate state control, or government 
     <lb/>
     subsidy for this industry, and I am not a com<lb break="no"/>munist. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I shall briefly touch on this budgetary 
     <lb/>
     proposed expenditure — page 10 of the report — 
     <lb/>
     and here I note the figures "Public Health and 
     <lb/>
     Welfare—$6,250,000." A lot of money, but with 
     <lb/>
     our expanding health service is this enough? 
     <lb/>
     What of the actual needs of the far-flung com<lb break="no"/>munities remote from the modern capital of St. 
     <lb/>
     John's? You can't provide a hospital for every 
     <lb/>
     settlement, but they should have at least a nurse 
     <lb/>
     for every ten, and if you think we have that you 
     <lb/>
     had better look up your statistics. What about 
     <lb/>
     those hundreds of known cases of TB vainly 
     <lb/>
     awaiting admission to our sanatorium? Are these 
     <lb/>
     unfortunate young people to be refused a chance 
     <lb/>
     to lead useful lives again? At the moment there 
     <lb/>
     is lack of space, and lack of nursing personnel. 
     <lb/>
     Have we enough cottage hospitals, have we 
     <lb/>
     enough doctors? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Education — proposed expenditure, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     $3,750,000. What of this? Is it a fact that there 
     <lb/>
     was a shortage of teachers this year? Are there 
     <lb/>
     still many ungraded teachers occupying positions 
     <lb/>
     in our schools, and what of the teachers them<lb break="no"/>selves, overworked and underpaid? Is the com<lb break="no"/>pensation they receive adequate to their needs or 
     <lb/>
     in keeping with the standards of their profession? 
     <lb/>
     I'll pause here and ask that branch of the civil 
     <lb/>
     service just how much longer they will have to 
     <lb/>
     endure this injustice. The Finance Committee did 
     <lb/>
     increase the grant a little, subject, of course, to 
     <lb/>
     their resuming the administration of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment in the future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Public works, proposed expenditure $4 mil<lb break="no"/>lion. I agree with the member for Bonavista East 
     <lb/>
     that this is very inadequate. What of the people 
     <lb/>
     between Hare Bay and Musgrave Harbour, some 
     <lb/>
     20,000 of them? They have been walking 40 
     <lb/>
     miles to reach civilisation for the past 50 years, 
     <lb/>
     and they recently signed a petition begging the 
     <lb/>
     powers that be to consider their request for a road. 
     <lb/>
     Must they go on for the next 50 years still beating 
     <lb/>
     through the 40 miles of wasteland to hear the puff 
     <lb/>
     of a train? I shall not touch on the economy of a 
     <lb/>
     merchant marine fleet, as proposed by this Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, I leave that to the member for Trinity 
     <lb/>
     South, my good friend Captain Bailey. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Economic Report is no unworkmanlike 
     <lb/>
     muddle. Coupled with a very businesslike finan<lb break="no"/>cial statement, it reveals in the opinion of its chief 
     <lb/>
     sponsor and the signatories, a balance sheet 
     <lb/>
     which shows unmistakably that this country is 
     <lb/>
     self-supporting. But after a close examination of 
     <lb/>
     both reports, and applying an altogether different 
     <lb/>
     interpretation to the term "self-sufficient", I can<lb break="no"/>not agree that this country is self-supporting. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Higgins Mr. Chairman, referring to the 
     <lb/>remarks of the last speaker, when he described 
     <lb/>his membership in the "B Block" I wonder if that 
     <lb/>should not be "P Block" or "Pessimistic Block", 
     <lb/>because all we have heard from that block so far 
     <lb/>has been pessimism about the future of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I don't know whether the other mem<lb break="no"/>bers of that same block are going to speak in that 
     <lb/>same manner, but if they do, to me it is not a fair 
     <lb/>criticism of the facts we have had put before us 
     <lb/>in the report and the facts we know ourselves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I propose to deal briefly with the report as we 
     <lb/>
     have it.... It is relatively unimportant, at least it is 
     <lb/>
     to me, whether capital expenditures are put in 
     <lb/>
     ordinary expenditures, or whether ordinary ex<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <pb n="668"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0668.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">668 NATIONAL CONVENTION November 1947 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     penditure are put in capital expenditures; and 
     <lb/>
     may I say again it is relatively unimportant 
     <lb/>
     whether Major Cashin, as the former finance 
     <lb/>
     minister, made an error in his budget, and under<lb break="no"/>estimated or overestimated his expenditure, or 
     <lb/>
     whether his predecessors or his successors did the 
     <lb/>
     same thing. I suggest, with all due respect to the 
     <lb/>
     Finance Committee, what is important is what 
     <lb/>
     was our position in 1934, and what is it today? 
     <lb/>
     Because, as you know, the terms of reference ask 
     <lb/>
     us to go back to 1934, and study the changes that 
     <lb/>
     have taken place in the economy and bearing in 
     <lb/>
     mind the extent to which the revenues of recent 
     <lb/>
     years have been due to wartime conditions, to 
     <lb/>
     examine the position of the country from that 
     <lb/>
     time on. That is what I propose to do very briefly. 
     <lb/>
     I presume that nearly every member is going to 
     <lb/>
     have something to say. We have had two very 
     <lb/>
     long, very well-delivered speeches — one ex<lb break="no"/>tremely pessimistic, and one extremely realistic, 
     <lb/>
     in my opinion. But these points come to me in the 
     <lb/>
     survey of the 1934 - 1947 period. In 1934 I 
     <lb/>
     believe we owed $100 million.... And today we 
     <lb/>
     owe, deducting our liquid assets, $35 million. In 
     <lb/>
     1934 the people had $25 million in the Savings 
     <lb/>
     Bank, today they have $80 million. In 1934 our 
     <lb/>
     people had insurance worth $52 million, today 
     <lb/>
     they have insurance worth $100 million. The 
     <lb/>
     cash surrender value of this insurance in 1934 
     <lb/>
     was worth $9 million, today it is worth about $22 
     <lb/>
     million. Today we have fixed government assets 
     <lb/>
     of something in the vicinity of $140 million. Now 
     <lb/>
     the Finance Committee gives our fixed assets in 
     <lb/>
     the vicinity of $110 million. I believe they have 
     <lb/>
     not added in the value of Gander airport, and the 
     <lb/>
     cost of it should be the value of it. We may not 
     <lb/>
     be able to put it on the block and sell it for that, 
     <lb/>
     but I am putting in the cost of it as the value of 
     <lb/>
     it.... Included in that, of course, is the $72 million 
     <lb/>
     value that has been put on the Railway. That 
     <lb/>
     value has been put on by the management of the 
     <lb/>
     Railway. I don't know where you could get any 
     <lb/>
     better value for the Railway than by going to the 
     <lb/>
     Manager and asking him, and I must say that I 
     <lb/>
     think it very unethical of Mr. Smallwood to sug<lb break="no"/>gest that we, as the Ottawa delegation, gave 
     <lb/>
     figures to the Canadian government which we 
     <lb/>
     knew to be incorrect. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Point of order. I did not say, and 
     <lb/>
     I did not suggest that the Ottawa delegation had 
     <lb/>
     given the Government of Canada any figures or 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     any information knowing them to be incorrect, 
     <lb/>
     and I ask Mr. Higgins to withdraw that remark. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Chairman That is so. The figure of $72 
     <lb/>million, so stated Mr. Smallwood, had been 
     <lb/>handed to the Ottawa delegation, because it was 
     <lb/>received from the Railway management. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins Mr. Smallwood did say that we 
     <lb/>
     knew we were fooling them when we gave it to 
     <lb/>
     them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I did not, and I ask Mr. Higgins 
     <lb/>
     to withdraw both remarks, this one and the one 
     <lb/>
     before. I' will read my comment to you if you 
     <lb/>
     don't. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins If you don't like it, or if you don't 
     <lb/>
     prefer to take my word for it, you can have the 
     <lb/>
     stenographer read it back. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I will have the stenographer 
     <lb/>
     read it, or the recording that went over the air, or 
     <lb/>
     anything you like. I hope, Mr. Chairman, when 
     <lb/>
     he finds that I did not say them he will withdraw 
     <lb/>
     them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p/>

            <p>[In the absence of a transcript, the Chairman was<lb/>unable to rule on Mr. Smallwood's point of order.<lb/>Mr. Higgins agreed to withdraw the remarks so<lb/>that debate might continue]<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I thank Mr. Higgins, Mr. Chair<lb break="no"/>man. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins You need not thank me, Mr. Small- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     wood. To revert to our figures from 1934 on, our 
     <lb/>
     revenue from 1934-35 was $9,624,000. Our 
     <lb/>
     revenue in 1946-47 was $37,250,000. Our expen<lb break="no"/>diture in 1934-35 was $10 million, and our ex<lb break="no"/>penditure in 1946-47 was $25 million. We have 
     <lb/>
     had a surplus of revenue over expenditure now 
     <lb/>
     since 1941, and you all know that expenditure has 
     <lb/>
     not been curtailed. Therefore there can be no 
     <lb/>
     doubt whatsoever that at the present time at least 
     <lb/>
     this country is self-supporting, and we have been 
     <lb/>
     self-supporting since 1941. I say also that I am 
     <lb/>
     satisfied that our present high expenditure, our 
     <lb/>
     present high revenue, is due in a large measure to 
     <lb/>
     war expenditures. I think we must all agree to 
     <lb/>
     that, but I am prepared to agree with the Finance 
     <lb/>
     Committee's contention that our continuing high 
     <lb/>
     revenues are, in a large measure, due to the 
     <lb/>
     growth of our main industries and general world 
     <lb/>
     conditions. I am satisfied that if, as it must, the 
     <lb/>
     exchange problem can be handled, that these 
     <lb/>
     revenues will continue comparatively high. I am 
     <lb/>
     prepared to agree with the Committee's figure of 
     <lb/>
     $30 million as a fair revenue for the foreseeable 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="669"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0669.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
     November 1947 NATIONAL CONVENTION 669 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     What of the future? The best forecast that can 
     <lb/>
     be made is only an opinion. I am prepared to 
     <lb/>
     accept the opinion of the Committee as to the 
     <lb/>
     future. They have given us what was described, I 
     <lb/>
     believe in one of our documents at Ottawa, as an 
     <lb/>
     educated "guesstimate", and I believe today in 
     <lb/>
     the letter we have had from the Hon. Mr. King he 
     <lb/>
     describes it as an "informed guess." Whether it is 
     <lb/>
     an "educated guesstimate" or an "informed 
     <lb/>
     guess", it is as good as any statistician-economist 
     <lb/>
     can do for us at the present time. However, to go 
     <lb/>
     back to this "guesstimate". Let us look at what 
     <lb/>
     the businessmen think of the future, because 
     <lb/>
     that's the only way we in this country can gauge 
     <lb/>
     what the future is likely to be. If the businessmen 
     <lb/>
     of the country are willing to put money into their 
     <lb/>
     businesses, backing the future of the country, 
     <lb/>
     then we can be fairly safe in saying, "These men 
     <lb/>
     do not take chances with their money unless they 
     <lb/>
     have a fairly good idea of what they are doing." 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Hickman There could be a philanthropic 
     <lb/>side to it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins Yes, Mr. Hickman, I agree you are 
     <lb/>
     a philanthropist in a big way. You are building 
     <lb/>
     that big service station in the west end, and that 
     <lb/>
     big garage in Corner Brook just because you are 
     <lb/>
     a philanthropist. Also in the fish industry there 
     <lb/>
     continues to be a lot of money and equipment put 
     <lb/>
     into it in the last two years. You realise there are 
     <lb/>
     today 18 modern plants in operation. Is that cor<lb break="no"/>rect, Mr. Chairman? I am not quite sure if it is 18 
     <lb/>
     or more modern fish plants. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Fourteen, Mr. Hollett says. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Higgins Compared with five in 1939 and 
     <lb/>two in 1934. Do you see the new herring plant 
     <lb/>being built by Connors Brothers at Petries, as 
     <lb/>well as a garage? Do you see that hard-headed 
     <lb/>businessman Mr. Crosbie blowing his money 
     <lb/>into the fishery for fun, into the herring and the 
     <lb/>whale fishery? How do you View these new 
     <lb/>fishery corporations that are being incorporated 
     <lb/>all over the place? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then we go to the other of our main industries, 
     <lb/>
     mining. The Committee says that the future ap<lb break="no"/>pears to be good. As far as we can gauge that is 
     <lb/>
     a fairly correct assumption. The present market 
     <lb/>
     for Bell Island ore is good, and if the apparent 
     <lb/>
     rapid depletion of the Spanish ores is correct, and 
     <lb/>
     assuming continuous large scale production by 
     <lb/>
     British industries, then we can look for a more 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     extensive market in the United Kingdom than 
     <lb/>
     before the war. Also you know Germany was one 
     <lb/>
     of our biggest customers before the war, and it is 
     <lb/>
     not outside the realm of possibility that she may 
     <lb/>
     not be a good customer again. The known deposit 
     <lb/>
     at Buchans is good, I believe, until at least 1956, 
     <lb/>
     and possibly more, but that is apparently the last 
     <lb/>
     word we have had. But as you know that mine 
     <lb/>
     was supposed to have been closed any time 
     <lb/>
     within the last ten or twelve years, closed per<lb break="no"/>manently, and they have found new bodies of ore 
     <lb/>
     constantly. The operations at St. Lawrence have 
     <lb/>
     demonstrated that the area is one of the biggest 
     <lb/>
     fluorspar fields in the world. The Asbestos Cor<lb break="no"/>poration of Canada has recently been investing 
     <lb/>
     their money in our deposits here. All I intend to 
     <lb/>
     say with respect to the ore deposits of Labrador 
     <lb/>
     is that they may very well profoundly alter the 
     <lb/>
     whole economic position, as the Bell Island and 
     <lb/>
     Buchans mines have already done. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With respect to agriculture it is most hearten<lb break="no"/>ing to know that the Director of Agriculture es<lb break="no"/>timated our products this year are worth $14-15 
     <lb/>
     million. The Finance Committee, in my opinion, 
     <lb/>
     has been most conservative in estimating die 
     <lb/>
     value of the tourist industry. When on my holiday 
     <lb/>
     in Canada the past three months, I made a par<lb break="no"/>ticular study of the tourist possibilities of the 
     <lb/>
     island, and I am quite convinced, as was my 
     <lb/>
     friend Mr. Smallwood as well, that the tourist 
     <lb/>
     possibilities of Newfoundland really have a 
     <lb/>
     wonderful future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Hear, hear! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins As 1 said earlier, the Committee's 
     <lb/>
     "guesstimate" of the future appears to me to have 
     <lb/>
     a good background. I am prepared to accept the 
     <lb/>
     report as presented, and I submit that we are now 
     <lb/>
     in a sound, satisfactory financial position, and we 
     <lb/>
     have every reason to believe that we will continue 
     <lb/>
     to remain in that position in the foreseeable fu<lb break="no"/>ture. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Butt Mr. Chairman, there is one point in this 
     <lb/>
     report which I don't think Mr. Higgins quite 
     <lb/>
     stressed enough, one particular section of it. Ac<lb break="no"/>cording to the Amulree Report in 1934 the gross 
     <lb/>
     public debt was $101 million, and the gross 
     <lb/>
     public debt at March 31, 1947, was roughly 
     <lb/>
     $83,993,000, but here's the solid fact that could 
     <lb/>
     have made a great deal of difference to us. The 
     <lb/>
     interest payment on our public debt in 1934, I 
     <lb/>
     believe, was $5,200,000. It did not include any 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="670"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0670.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
     670 NATIONAL CONVENTION November 1947 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     provision for sinking fund. In 1947, as at 31 
     <lb/>
     March, the interest payment was $3,545,000, and 
     <lb/>
     it included a sinking fund provision of $903,380. 
     <lb/>
     The point I am making is that there is a permanent 
     <lb/>
     and continuous benefit as at today of over $2 
     <lb/>
     million, the amount that we will not have to pay 
     <lb/>
     out for interest. If we had had that $2 million 
     <lb/>
     which we were paying out prior to that time it 
     <lb/>
     would have made a very great difference to the 
     <lb/>
     future of this country. I suggest that on that point 
     <lb/>
     alone we ought to watch very carefully, because 
     <lb/>
     we now have a continuous benefit of something 
     <lb/>
     like $2-2.5 million, and it is being reduced all the 
     <lb/>
     time. Further than that, it looks as if the sinking 
     <lb/>
     fund payment can be kept up for the foreseeable 
     <lb/>
     future. I am not going to try to define the foresee<lb break="no"/>able future, but we are reducing our debt by 
     <lb/>
     $8-900,000 a year, and we only have to find, as 
     <lb/>
     at March 31, $2.6 million against $5 million in 
     <lb/>
     1934.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett Major Cashin, may I ask a question 
     <lb/>
     through you to Mr. Butt? What was the sinking 
     <lb/>
     fund provision in 1947? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Butt The sinking fund provision for 1947 
     <lb/>
     was $903,000.... The real point is that we have a 
     <lb/>
     continuing benefit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin I think I ought to further explain this 
     <lb/>
     sinking fund. When the Financial Act was passed 
     <lb/>
     in 1933 the sinking fund was to be paid in 1937, 
     <lb/>
     amounting to 1% of the total sterling indebted<lb break="no"/>ness. The total sterling indebtedness is 
     <lb/>
     £17,790,000, therefore the annual sinking fund 
     <lb/>
     amounted to £177,950, or in dollar exchange (at 
     <lb/>
     that time it was $4.80) it amounts to $854,160, 
     <lb/>
     but the point I am trying to make is this, that each 
     <lb/>
     year the sinking fund went across to Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain. It was invested, as we are told in the 
     <lb/>
     Auditor General's report at any rate, in the actual 
     <lb/>
     payment of the debt. In other words they got it in, 
     <lb/>
     but the following year that amount was not taken 
     <lb/>
     off the principal. I agree with that to a point, but 
     <lb/>
     the following year we sent over more money 
     <lb/>
     paying interest on the debt we had redeemed, and 
     <lb/>
     what is the result? Today I estimate, sometimes I 
     <lb/>
     make mistakes, but I estimate that Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     has lost $1 million on that sinking fund loan 
     <lb/>
     during the past ten years, because if you take 
     <lb/>
     £177,000 and compound it annually at 3% you 
     <lb/>
     will find that if you work it out at present dollar 
     <lb/>
     exchange it will go over $9 million.... In all, we 
     <lb/>
     have paid in sinking fund approximately $l0 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     million, that is if you include interest on it, but 
     <lb/>
     we have only got the benefit today of$8.5 million 
     <lb/>
     on the other side, consequently Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     has lost by the handling of that sinking fund $1.5 
     <lb/>
     million since 1937. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Would you take that step by 
     <lb/>
     step and explain, if that is so? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Take down £177,000 yourself and 
     <lb/>
     figure it out for yourself, because you don't 
     <lb/>
     believe what I tell you. Somebody take it down. 
     <lb/>
     £177,000 at 3% annually, and compound it for 
     <lb/>
     ten years, and find out what it is and check it with 
     <lb/>
     the present sinking fund in London, and see 
     <lb/>
     where you are. I have gone to the trouble to do it, 
     <lb/>
     and I have had it checked by the bank, and I think 
     <lb/>
     I am fairly accurate. I state now that we have lost 
     <lb/>
     $1.5 million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Not the mathematical total of 
     <lb/>
     it, but in principle, how did we lose $1.5 million? 
     <lb/>
     1f we have, it sounds like a crime firm has been 
     <lb/>
     committed against the country. Has this country 
     <lb/>
     been robbed? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin I don't say it has been robbed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood But it has been done out of $l.5 
     <lb/>
     million. Will you explain it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin All right, I will explain it to you. 
     <lb/>
     You have a note agreement for $1,000 and at the 
     <lb/>
     end of the month you pay $100 and you renew it 
     <lb/>
     for another month. Is the bank going to charge 
     <lb/>
     you interest on $1,000 when you go to pay it the 
     <lb/>
     next time? No, on $900, but we have been paying 
     <lb/>
     it out, sending the actual interest on the sinking 
     <lb/>
     fund overto England. I will explain in my opinion 
     <lb/>
     what is happening: the money was sent across to 
     <lb/>
     England and it bought in our principal; when it 
     <lb/>
     went over the next time they were not able to buy 
     <lb/>
     it in, and they did not invest the sinking fund to 
     <lb/>
     bear interest, and that's where we lost money, and 
     <lb/>
     they did not reduce it from the principal. You can 
     <lb/>
     take these estimates for the last ten years and 
     <lb/>
     under the consolidated fund services you will 
     <lb/>
     find that the 3% guaranteed stock for this 
     <lb/>
     amounts to £17,790 to date.... I hold that when 
     <lb/>
     that stock was bought in, that the next year when 
     <lb/>
     we bought in £177,950 worth, it should have been 
     <lb/>
     deducted off here, and that's where 1 say we lost 
     <lb/>
     $1 million at least. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Well, is this the picture? To put 
     <lb/>
     it very simply, we will say I owe $1,000, say I 
     <lb/>
     borrowed $1,000 from you... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin You couldn't. I haven't got it! 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="671"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-11-06_Page_0671.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
     November 1947 NATIONAL CONVENTION 671 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Neither have I, but say you 
     <lb/>
     loaned me $1,000 and I agreed to pay you 3% 
     <lb/>
     interest on that $1,000 every year, so the first year 
     <lb/>
     comes around and I pay you the interest. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin $30. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Besides that, I am supposed to 
     <lb/>
     put aside so much in the bank to meet that prin<lb break="no"/>cipal of$1,000 in say ten years, so that is $100 a 
     <lb/>
     year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood The first year rolls around and 
     <lb/>
     I put in $100 for sinking fund, and I pay you the 
     <lb/>
     interest of $30. Is this what you mean, that at the 
     <lb/>
     end of the second year I have put another amount 
     <lb/>
     into the sinking fund, which reduces it by what? 
     <lb/>
     Say the sinking fund is another $100, all right that 
     <lb/>
     reduces it to $800, but I am still paying you 
     <lb/>
     interest on the $1,000? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Oh no, you are not, you don't owe 
     <lb/>
     me $1,000 now, you only owe me $800. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Exactly, well where have I lost 
     <lb/>
     money? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin You have not, but the country has. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood Well, I am the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Well, you are not the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Well, in this illustration 1 am 
     <lb/>
     the country, and you are the bondholders in 
     <lb/>
     England. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Well, the bondholders don't get the 
     <lb/>
     money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Well, I owe you $1,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin You don't understand it, and your 
     <lb/>
     talk is driving me crazy. You don't understand it, 
     <lb/>
     and it is impossible to drive it into your head. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood I am very thick-headed and 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     very dumb, but I am trying to get this straightened 
     <lb/>
     out. Where has Newfoundland lost it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin She has lot it in interest I tell you, 
     <lb/>
     by the trustees of the sinking fund not investing 
     <lb/>
     it when it went over there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood They did not invest it in our 
     <lb/>
     bonds? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin They did not invest it at all, and we 
     <lb/>
     have lost interest on it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood And they lost interest on it? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Cashin Sure. When they bought it in the 
     <lb/>interest was £177,950. The next year when we 
     <lb/>sent over interest, the interest was paid into the 
     <lb/>sinking fund. The next year they sent over 
     <lb/>another £177,950, and they might not have been 
     <lb/>able to buy it in, and consequently they got on 
     <lb/>interest on it, but you are sending interest over. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood We are sending interest over, 
     <lb/>not on the sinking fund, but on the portion of the 
     <lb/>debt that they did not buy in. Is that because they 
     <lb/>could not buy it in? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin I don't know, because here's the 
     <lb/>
     position. We have asked for a statement of ac<lb break="no"/>count, and the sinking fund, and all you can get 
     <lb/>
     is two lines in the Auditor' General's report. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Hickman I don't think the reporter can go 
     <lb/>on any longer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Is it the pleasure of the House to 
     <lb/>
     adjourn? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin I move that the committee rise, we 
     <lb/>
     are getting tangled up in a lot of figures here, and 
     <lb/>
     report progress, and ask leave to sit again tomor<lb break="no"/>row. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>[The committee rose and reported progress, and<lb/>the Convention adjourned]<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     November 7, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Before calling on Major Cashin, 
     <lb/>
     with the indulgence of the House, I would like to 
     <lb/>
     direct the attention of members to the fact that my 
     <lb/>
     attention has been drawn to the second matter on 
     <lb/>
     the order paper, which isn't quite correct, and 
     <lb/>
     therefore, by and with your indulgence, I would 
     <lb/>
     ask the consent of the House that item two be 
     <lb/>
     amended so that it will read: 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>To move that the communication from the 
     <lb/>Government of Canada be received, and that 
     <lb/>the Convention resolve itself into a commit<lb break="no"/>tee of the whole on tomorrow to consider the 
     <lb/>said communication. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>....If you have no objection to that I will put the 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins Is it intended to be two separate 
     <lb/>
     motions or what? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr Chairman It could be two separate motions, 
     <lb/>
     but by that change it is immaterial.... One is just 
     <lb/>
     that you do now receive, and the other is that on 
     <lb/>
     tomorrow the motion will be made to resolve the 
     <lb/>
     Convention into a committee of the whole. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins I suggest that it might be better to 
     <lb/>
     have two separate motions in the matter, rather 
     <lb/>
     than have this in the double-barrelled form that it 
     <lb/>
     is now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Bradley I don't see that there could be any 
     <lb/>
     particular objection to that change, although I 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>