<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-01-09" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-01-09">9 January 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          
          
         
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
                    

          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="236"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0229.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0230.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0231.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0232.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0233.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0234.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0235.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0236.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-03">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-03">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0229">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0229.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0230">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0230.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0231">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0231.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0232">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0232.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0233">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0233.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0234">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0234.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0235">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0235.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-08_Page_0236">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0236.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="229" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0229.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">229</fw>

<!-- GL, 2017-03-03, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

           <!-- <p>point I am trying to make is that we compared <lb/>two things that were not comparable...<lb/>[There followed a lengthy discussion of the spe-<lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     cial freight rates charged to certain companies. 
     <lb/>
     The committee rose and reported progress and 
     <lb/>
     the Convention adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     January 9, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Orders of the day. Mr. <lb/>Smallwood to move that
                  the Commissioner for<lb/>Public Utilities be invited to appear before
                  the<lb/>Convention, in public or private session as he<lb/>shall prefer, to
                  present an account of the facts of<lb/>the financing of Gander, and to be
                  interrogated<lb/>thereon.<lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I feel that the<lb/>motion is
                  self-explanatory and it does not need<lb/>any Verbal defence whatever. I think we
                  all are<lb/>agreed that we are not satisfied that we have the<lb/>complete story
                  of Gander. We do not know who<lb/>is responsible for the debt to be incurred, and
                  for<lb/>that reason I move the motion.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FOWL2">Mr. Fowler</persName> I feel very much in favour of Mr.<lb/>Smallwood's
                  motion and take pleasure in<lb/>seconding it.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Mr. Chairman, I support the resolution <lb/>proposed by
                  Mr. Smallwood, and take the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity to make a few remarks on
                  the subject which<lb/>I think is allied to the resolution. My view for<lb/>some
                  time has been that we shall not make serious<lb/>progress in helping to remedy
                  certain existing<lb/>defects in the economic position of New<lb break="no"/>foundland until we, as Newfoundlanders, are able<lb/>to sit down at a round
                  table conference with<lb/>appointed representatives of Great Britain,<lb/>Canada
                  and the United States of America, to<lb/>discuss not only the question of
                  operation of<lb/>airports, and the concessions already given and<lb/>asked for in
                  connection with defence bases, but<lb/>also our general economic position. As you
                  are<lb/>probably aware by this time, I am of the opinion<lb/>that we should on
                  every possible occasion stress<lb/>the fact that our valuable strategic position
                  is<lb/>being utilised by Canada, the USA and Great<lb/>Britain for defence and
                  other purposes, without<lb/>any material return to Newfoundland for its
                  use,<lb/>and without any consultation with the people of<lb/>Newfoundland.<lb/>
               </p>

    

    

            <p>At a round table conference, at which <hi rendition="simple:italic">real</hi><lb/> representatives of Newfoundland should be<lb/>present, these questions could be thrashed out and<lb/>the case for Newfoundland could be properly<lb/>presented. Our position is such a strong one, that<lb/>if properly impressed it could not fail to appeal<lb/>
           
            <cb/>
            
to our American and Canadian friends, who are<lb/>anxious to continue to utilise to the utmost for<lb/>their own important purposes, the valuable<lb/>facilities arising from our strategic position.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The ace card we hold for negotiations in con<lb break="no"/>nection with the future prosperity of New<lb break="no"/>foundland consists of her strategic position. Our<lb/>problem is in my opinion an economic one, and<lb/>not as some people seem to imagine, mainly a<lb/>political one. The sooner an attempt is made to<lb/>secure such a joint conference the better, and its<lb/>object should be to discuss the degree of assis<lb break="no"/>tance, by tariff concessions or otherwise, to<lb/>which Newfoundland is entitled, in exchange for<lb/>utilisation of her strategic position for the benefit<lb/>mainly of Canada, USA and Great Britain. I make<lb/>no apology for repeatedly stressing this view<lb break="no"/>point, and on some suitable occasion hope to<lb/>place before the Convention some definite plan<lb/>of action to secure such a conference as that<lb/>proposed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I am in favour of this motion<lb/>and I support
                  it, but it has occurred to me that<lb/>there may be other matters which the
                  members<lb/>might want to take up with the Commissioner for<lb/>Public Utilities.
                  According to the motion as<lb/>worded this interview would relate to
                  Gander<lb/>airport and would, unless amended, debar the<lb/>consideration of other
                  matters; possibly Mr.<lb/>Smallwood could enlarge the motion to include<lb/>any
                  other matters of public concern any member<lb/>might wish to bring before him at
                  this time.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am prepared to accede to Mr.<lb/>Ashboume's
                  suggestion. The only thing is we<lb/>ought to be specific. We ask the
                  Commissioner<lb/>to come and give a certain explanation about one<lb/>particular
                  thing; we cannot add "such other mat<lb break="no"/>ters as we would wish to
                  discuss." We would<lb/>have to be specific so that he could bring along<lb/>other
                  data on the matters to be discussed. If the<lb/>house wants to add any other topic
                  to be discussed<lb/>with the Commissioner, I am agreeable to that.<lb/>
                  <lb/>
               </p>

    

    

            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> If Mr. Ashbourne wishes to<lb/>make an amendment,
                  that would be in order, but<lb/>as Mr. Smallwood has pointed out, we
                  cannot<lb/>obviously invite the Commissioner here and
            
            <pb n="230" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0230.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">230</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
           

     adopt the attitude of a roving commission to
                  go <lb/> into any subject under the sun, and deal with <lb/> things he was not
                  prepared to deal with. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> We know that the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner
                  for Finance, Mr. Wild, appeared before the <lb/> Convention before he left and
                  seemed quite ready <lb/> to answer any questions put to him by the mem<lb break="no"/>bers. If the Commissioner did not have all the <lb/> information
                  available at the time, he could submit <lb/> it at a later date. That would do
                  away with the <lb/> necessity of having him appear a second time. <lb/> Personally
                  I would not want to bring in an amend<lb break="no"/>ment unless I feel other
                  members might wish to <lb/> ask for certain other information. Since no other
                  <lb/> members have spoken, I do not feel like amend<lb break="no"/>ing the motion.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I am inclined to agree with Mr. <lb/> Ashbourne,
                  but as Mr. Smallwood says, we <lb/> should be specific. He is responsible only for
                  his <lb/> department; perhaps if we add the words "public <lb/> works, roads and
                  railway." I make that as an <lb/> amendment. <lb/>
               </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I do not wish to dictate to the <lb/>
                  Convention, but may I suggest to the mover and <lb/> seconderthat we add these
                  words: "and to discuss <lb/> any other public matter with which the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner may be prepared to deal." That in itself <lb/> leaves open
                  the possibility and probability should <lb/> the occasion arise that you may have
                  another <lb/> session with the Commissioner. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Would that take in our strategic <lb/> position
                  as well? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> If he is not prepared to deal with <lb/> any
                  matter, we have no authority to compel him. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> About two years ago in New <lb/>York a prominent
                  member of the Republican <lb/>party said, "We should turn our eyes towards
                  <lb/>Newfoundland, and if we cannot get it by peace<lb break="no"/>ful means, we
                  will have to do it by other means." <lb/>Since then, six months ago, a very
                  prominent <lb/>member of the Quebec legislature said they were <lb/>going in and
                  take Labrador regardless of who is <lb/>going to try and stop them. Probably Mr.
                  Neill <lb/>might be able to tell us something about that.<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref>
                  <lb/>
               </p>


</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the on Transportation and Communications Committee:<ref target="#fn_02">[2]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
           <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I would suggest that this after<lb break="no"/>noon we deal with the section on roads and <lb/> bridges.<ref target="#fn_03">[3]</ref> I would ask the Secretary to read that <lb/> section. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the report]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There is only one appendix to <lb/> this
                     report,<ref target="#fn_04">[4]</ref> and that was prepared bythe depart<lb break="no"/>ment dealing with local roads and bridges, <lb/> describing the
                  system the government has of <lb/> helping the maintaining of local roads. In view
                  of <lb/> the fact that we are on the air it ought to be read, <lb/> not at the
                  present moment, but the information in <lb/> it is so important to the whole
                  country, it ought <lb/> to be read before the debate is over. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> What is intended by the comparison <lb/> of
                  Newfoundland (1943) with Prince Edward <lb/> Island? It looks to me, as far as
                  road revenue is <lb/> concerned, we received much more revenue from <lb/> fewer
                  cars. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That is an important point. The <lb/>
                  <cb/> table is given to show the possibilities that exist, <lb/> in Newfoundland,
                  at least in theory, of getting <lb/> revenue from roads. We have therefore shown
                  <lb/> what the actual revenue is in such nearby places <lb/> as Prince Edward
                  Island, Nova Scotia and New <lb/> Brunswick. Road revenue in Canada and the <lb/>
                  United States is a clearly defined thing. In New<lb break="no"/>foundland it is
                  not. You cannot say exactly how <lb/> much revenue Newfoundland is now getting
                  <lb/> from roads. You can only add up what they get <lb/> from motor car and
                  drivers' licenses. That <lb/> revenue would not exist if there were no roads,
                  <lb/> What we have done is add in the customs duties <lb/> received on gasoline.
                  Unfortunately, there is no <lb/> separation made between the revenue received
                  <lb/> from gasoline used by motor cars on the one <lb/> hand, and customs duties
                  received on gasoline <lb/> used by fishermen, mills, farms, on the other <lb/>
                  hand. We took the total amount received on all <lb/> gasoline; added that to what
                  was received on
            
   
<note xml:id="fn_01">The Commissioner never appeared before the Convention, though he did meet with the Committee on 
     <lb/>Transportation and Communications.</note>

<note xml:id="fn_02">[2] Volume II:75. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

<note xml:id="fn_03">[3] Volume II:85. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

<note xml:id="fn_04">[4] Volume II:91. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
           
            <pb n="231" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0231.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">231</fw>
       

     motor car and drivers' licenses. That is where we <lb/>
                  get the total for 1945-46 of $634,000. We took <lb/> the year 1943 as a basis of
                  comparison. The <lb/> amount in Newfoundland for 1943 was <lb/> $664,492. We did
                  not actually get that from <lb/> roads; we got it from gasoline duties collected
                  <lb/> and also motor car and drivers' licenses. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Why call it "road revenue"? It is out <lb/> of
                  place there. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It is not.... In 1943 we had <lb/> 6,700 motor
                  vehicles and only 5,100 miles of <lb/> road. Nova Scotia had 59,000 vehicles and
                  <lb/> 15,000 miles of road. If we had had 15,000 miles <lb/> of road then our
                  revenue would have been the <lb/> same as Nova Scotia. It is aimed at showing that
                  <lb/> the construction of roads in Newfoundland can <lb/> be used as a means of
                  bringing revenue into the <lb/> govemment, and to prove it we have given the <lb/>
                  cases of these other countries. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> It says here that gasoline was strin<lb break="no"/>gently rationed in Prince Edward Island, New <lb/> Brunswick and
                  Nova Scotia; you must remember <lb/> you cannot run without tires either. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In 1943, their revenue was <lb/> below normal.
                  If they had been able to get all the <lb/> gasoline they wanted, the gasoline tax
                  would <lb/> have brought in more money. If they had been <lb/> able to get more
                  cars and trucks, their revenue <lb/> instead of being $4.5 million would have been
                  <lb/> $55 million as compared with Newfoundland's <lb/> $600,000. And not even
                  $600,000, actually, be<lb break="no"/>cause that includes gasoline to fishermen
                  and <lb/> sawmills <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> 1 cannot remember if we made this up <lb/> on a
                  basis of comparable rates against other <lb/> places or whether we took into
                  account the actual <lb/> duty collected as between one country and <lb/> another.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Road revenue in Canada does <lb/> not include
                  customs duties. No province in <lb/> Canada collects customs duties; these are
                     col<lb break="no"/>lected by the federal government. The $4.5 mil<lb break="no"/>lion collected does not include customs duties. <lb/> That includes the gasoline
                  tax ... and the money <lb/> collected from licences on vehicles and licences <lb/>
                  paid by drivers. The bulk of the revenue in <lb/> Canada and United States is
                  received from <lb/> gasoline tax and not... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> What is the licence fee? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That varies in the provinces <lb/> and in the
                  states. I do not know what a driver has <lb/>
                  <cb/> to pay for a licence in Canada or in the United <lb/>States. I do know the
                  bulk of the road revenue is <lb/>obtained through gasoline tax. <lb/>
               </p>
   
    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> This is misleading. You added <lb/> vehicular
                  licences and customs duties; yet you <lb/> fail to mention what the gasoline tax
                  is in Canada. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The gasoline tax in Nova <lb/>Scotia is, I think,
                  10 cents a gallon That is a direct <lb/>tax collected by the provincial
                  government. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> What is the duty in this country? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> 14 cents. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> 16 cents on the Avalon Peninsula. That <lb/> takes
                  care of something extra spent on the roads. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> If the duty on gasoline coming <lb/>into this
                  country is 14 cents, I do not think the 2 <lb/>cents extra paid on the Avalon
                  Peninsula takes <lb/>care of the extra government money spent on <lb/>roads in the
                  Avalon Peninsula. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I did not say that. It takes care of <lb/> something
                  extra being spent on roads. We do <lb/> collect something extra, and I say that in
                  view of <lb/> the fact that others are saying the Avalon Penin<lb break="no"/>sula
                  is getting more than it should get. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> For years the fishermen got a rebate <lb/> on gas
                  of 13 cents; in the Avalon Peninsula they <lb/> got 11 cents. That was on Acto. We
                  have to <lb/> remember the price the Imperial Oil Co. charges <lb/> — in 1929, in
                  Newfoundland, the price was $98 <lb/> for ten barrels of gasoline to the consumer;
                  the <lb/> price for the same barrels in Nova Scotia was $57; <lb/> the price to
                  the fishermen, and we paid tax or <lb/> duties, was $35. These are three different
                  prices. <lb/> In Bermuda they paid the same price as in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. The freight on crude oil was $2.40 a <lb/> ton. Yet you could not buy
                  a gallon of gas here <lb/> under 18 cents. The Newfoundland fishermen <lb/> have
                  been bringing into the coffers of the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Oil Co. $400,000 a
                  year on gasoline. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> As a member of the Transporta<lb break="no"/>tion Committee, I think the time is opportune <lb/> when I should make a few
                  remarks regarding <lb/> roads and transportation, and what they can and <lb/> will
                  do for this country, if we go at it the right <lb/> way. So, sir, in rising to
                  offer a suggestion, I want <lb/> it to be distinctly understood that ideals are
                  not <lb/> attained at a single bound, but only through hard <lb/> work and
                  perseverance. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName>, some of the delegates men<lb break="no"/>tioned
                  about getting three square meals a day. I, <lb/> too, pray that each and every
                  member will see to <lb/> it that we get for our people three square meals a
       
            <pb n="232" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0232.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">232</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
          
     day and also for our children's children.
                  But in <lb/> order to be sure of getting three meals a day, we <lb/> must first
                  put forward some form of constructive <lb/> or workable plan or plans; and,
                  further we must <lb/> try and bring into being some kind of insurance <lb/> scheme
                  whereby, when the labourer can no <lb/> longer work, there will be a little
                  nest-egg to tide <lb/> him or her over when nearing the eventide of life. <lb/>
                  Therefore, we must, of necessity, have some <lb/> definite fixed plan or plans so
                  that our people can <lb/> earn their daily bread. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     We must have economic security and resour<lb break="no"/>ces, in order to ensure security for our people, and 
     <lb/>
     we have that security on land and sea, especially 
     <lb/>
     in the sea and around our coastline; but so far we 
     <lb/>
     have not as yet developed or exploited our resour<lb break="no"/>ces. Why? Because we have no highway running 
     <lb/>
     across our country! Mr. Chairman, when east has 
     <lb/>
     met west by highway then, as follows night the 
     <lb/>
     day, so will follow in large quantities from the 
     <lb/>
     various harbours, bays or districts of this country, 
     <lb/>
     great quantities of live lobster, fresh salmon, 
     <lb/>
     fillets, smelts and blueberries, etc. to the Gander 
     <lb/>
     airport to be flown to the great, unlimited western 
     <lb/>
     markets of the world in a matter of only hours, 
     <lb/>
     not days. All we want is to give that great 
     <lb/>
     republic, America, the products they ask for and 
     <lb/>
     in the way they should be delivered — strictly 
     <lb/>
     fresh quality stock guaranteed number 1. Then it 
     <lb/>
     will not be a matter of price, but, "How much can 
     <lb/>
     you sell us?" 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Therein lies a great deal of prosperity. When 
     <lb/>
     once a highroad through this country is com<lb break="no"/>pleted and the important settlements connected 
     <lb/>
     to it, there will be sold by the thousands, cars and 
     <lb/>
     trucks and the like, not to mention the extra 
     <lb/>
     millions of barrels of gas; all of which will turn 
     <lb/>
     into this country a tremendous amount of 
     <lb/>
     revenue. Then will follow machine shops, 
     <lb/>
     garages, restaurants, hotels, log cabins, fuelling 
     <lb/>
     stations, farms and many other unknown things 
     <lb/>
     and the Industrial Development Board and 
     <lb/>
     Tourist Board will more than be repaid and have 
     <lb/>
     its hands full catering to the many and various 
     <lb/>
     requests and demands made upon it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     So this is a step in the right direction, and we 
     <lb/>
     should give it very careful consideration, as roads 
     <lb/>
     are the life of any country. Let us go forward 
     <lb/>
     together to build a new Newfoundland that can, 
     <lb/>
     and will stand up against the many, many storms 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
          
     that will beat against and around our shores, and 
     <lb/>
     may it be further said of this Convention and of 
     <lb/>
     our children, that we have built a firm and solid 
     <lb/>
     foundation; and may it bring lasting peace, con<lb break="no"/>tentment and prosperity to our shores for all time. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> I refer to page 4,<ref target="#fn_05">[1]</ref>
                  "The Depart<lb break="no"/>ment estimates that some proportion between <lb/>70%
                  and 80% of the annual road maintenance <lb/>expenditure consists of wages paid to
                  highroads <lb/>employees." I ask the Committee if the depart<lb break="no"/>ment
                  has a minimum wage rate? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I think the smartest thing I <lb/> could do is
                  to ask Mr. Fudge — he is the president <lb/> of the West Coast Labourers' Union
                  and was <lb/> involved in the wage rates. I think labourers' rates <lb/> were
                  brought up, and maybe Mr. Fudge can give <lb/> us the rates in pay on highroads
                  during last year? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I might say I am not here to give <lb/>away any
                  secrets from the organisation which I <lb/>represent. This is not a secret now,
                  but it may be <lb/>valuable information to someone seeking further <lb/>increases
                  for labour. Last year, the organisation I <lb/>represent took up the matter of low
                  rates paid to <lb/>workmen, which was 40 cents an hour. Our union <lb/>secured 58
                  cents an hour for labourers, and 61 <lb/>cents or 64 cents for truck drivers. The
                  labour rate <lb/>is 58 cents in the Humber district. Of course we <lb/>have good
                  men over there, who may be worth a <lb/>little more. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> That is not answering my ques<lb break="no"/>tion. Has the government a minimum basic rate <lb/> for labourers throughout
                  Newfoundland? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No statutory minimum. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Are they paying an equal rate <lb/> throughout
                  the country? I happen to know some <lb/> of the men are getting only 20 cents an
                  hour. A <lb/> highroads labourer in Bell Island gets 40 cents. <lb/> The
                  government issues a cost of living index for <lb/> a family of five at $34.80 a
                  week. How can a man <lb/> earning $24 a week live, when the government <lb/>
                  itself says it costs $34.80 a week? There is dis<lb break="no"/>crimination. I do
                  not see why in one section <lb/> common labour should be given preference over
                  <lb/> another part. I congratulate Mr. Fudge in getting <lb/> this increase for
                  labourers in his section. Why <lb/> should any government discriminate against its
                  <lb/> own employees? That is not government, it is <lb/> mis-government. There
                  should be equal <lb/> privileges for all. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[There followed a brief discussion of snow clear<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_05">[1] Volume II:87. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note><pb n="233" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0233.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">233</fw>ing expenses]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am disappointed. Here is a <lb/> report which
                  deals with the Spending of many <lb/> millions of dollars. The Committee felt it
                  wanted <lb/> this information to help the Convention deter<lb break="no"/>mine the
                  status of the country economically and <lb/> financially. So far the report has
                  not been debated <lb/> from that standpoint. We have not said one word <lb/> on
                  what the future is likely to be. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> In order to alleviate Mr. Small<lb break="no"/>wood's disappointment, I would like to say I find <lb/> the report very
                  interesting and instructive, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly to those of us who can
                  hardly remember <lb/> when we saw a road last. The question of com<lb break="no"/>munication is an important one. It is a fine thing <lb/> to open up this country
                  by a transinsular road; but <lb/> we should also give thought to opening up the
                  <lb/> country inside Newfoundland as well. There are <lb/> vast stretches being
                  impaired economically due <lb/> to the lack of communications. There are parts of
                  <lb/> this country where fishermen are impaired in <lb/> getting bait because on a
                  day that is too stormy to <lb/> go in a boat, there is no other way to get it.
                  Large <lb/> sections have practically no roads. The section I <lb/> know best has
                  nothing but barely community <lb/> roads, you have to stretch the imagination to
                  call <lb/> some of them roads. There are no inter-com<lb break="no"/>munity
                  connections.... I would like for us to give <lb/> some thought to that. Another
                  thing is the miles <lb/> of road privately owned, but yet used by the <lb/>
                  public. For instance the Bowater company has <lb/> built a considerable number of
                  miles of road and <lb/> done a great deal to open up the remoter parts of <lb/>
                  the country. They deserve a great deal of credit <lb/> for it. Our road policy
                  should dovetail into the <lb/> policy of these companies in such a way that one
                  <lb/> might augment the other. It does not come within <lb/> the scope of this
                  Convention to discuss these <lb/> things. But the economic policy of the future of
                  <lb/> roads whether public or private is a very impor<lb break="no"/>tant
                  consideration. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> On page 2<ref target="#fn_06">[1]</ref> — "It
                  will thus be seen <lb/> that there are 1,063.3 miles of motorable road on <lb/>
                  the Avalon Peninsula, and 978.8 miles in the <lb/> remainder of the Island." I can
                  understand why <lb/> my friends across the way should hang their <lb/> heads. When
                  I think of the millions of dollars <lb/> spent on the Avalon Peninsula, I should
                  have <lb/> expected the Commission of Government, since <lb/> they started road
                  building, would have built more <lb/>
                  <cb/> outside. I come from the beating heart of the <lb/> country. We have very
                  few roads — 42 miles to <lb/> Botwood; four miles of paved road to the golf <lb/>
                  course, a few other miles to Badger; that is all <lb/> apart from the track
                  leading to Halls Bay. I am <lb/> thinking of that part of the country. The
                     govern<lb break="no"/>ment did think of it. They actually started out to <lb/>
                  build a road, four miles to the golf course — they <lb/> left off there. The next
                  year they decided to pave <lb/> the road from Grand Falls to Botwood. They <lb/>
                  spent one whole year renovating and recondition<lb break="no"/>ing, spent
                  thousands of dollars making it ready to <lb/> pave next year. The next year they
                  forgot about <lb/> it. If they did start now, they would have to spend <lb/>
                  hundreds of thousands of dollars to recondition it <lb/> again. That is the kind
                  of treatment we got. Not <lb/> that by talking about it I expect it is going to
                  mean <lb/> anything. I think if the $20,000 spent on roads <lb/> were spent on the
                  welfare of the country general<lb break="no"/>ly, it would have been better.
                  Speaking of roads <lb/> (and I am going to be called a heretic for saying <lb/>
                  this) I am wondering if we are not barking up the <lb/> wrong tree when we prate
                  about roads. For the <lb/> last 40 years we have heard what would happen <lb/> if
                  we had a system of roads throughout. I am <lb/> beginning to doubt it, because if
                  there was any <lb/> truth in it, surely the people by now would have <lb/> had the
                  roads. What do we get if we do get <lb/> transinsular roads? I was wondering if it
                  would <lb/> help any if we put the road there, although it is <lb/> bound to come
                  some day. Who will use it? Where <lb/> will they go? What shall they carry? Would
                  it be <lb/> much cheaper to use the railway? When I think <lb/> of the waste of
                  public money on roads — money <lb/> just dug into the earth! If half the money
                  used on <lb/> roads had been used to help the fishermen catch <lb/> their fish,
                  then we would have been much better <lb/> off. I do say the report is, factually,
                  an excellent <lb/> one; but as to the future, it is in the air. They plan <lb/> on
                  putting a road to Port-aux-Basques; all I can <lb/> say is, God help the surplus
                  if they do it by the <lb/> method they are spending now. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> We have to admit that there has <lb/> been a lot
                  of money spent around the Avalon <lb/> Peninsula, and I see every justification
                  for it. We <lb/> say, as far as the island is concerned, "Avalon <lb/> first; the
                  rest of the country afterwards." I have to <lb/> admit that the money might have
                  been better <lb/> spent if the amount spent on paving roads, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly this year, had been employed joining up
      
  <note xml:id="fn_06">[1] Volume II:85. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
     
            <pb n="234" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0234.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">234</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            
     smaller sections outside St. John's, with
                  the idea <lb/> of a transinsular highway. I disagree with the <lb/> defeatest
                  ideas of Mr. Hollett. I am convinced we <lb/> have to have a cross-country road.
                  Whatever the <lb/> cost it will be well spent. We know the cost to <lb/> maintain
                  it will be high, but while we will not <lb/> have it open in winter, we will have
                  a road across <lb/> the country in summer when produce would be <lb/> made
                  available throughout the country, and when <lb/> people would be able to move more
                  freely. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I notice Governor Macdonald in his year-end 
     <lb/>
     talk, spoke of the transinsular highway. The plans 
     <lb/>
     have been delayed too long. If it is going to take 
     <lb/>
     from the railway, then that is just too bad. The 
     <lb/>
     only way a country can be developed is by roads. 
     <lb/>
     As far as St. John's is concerned, we do not 
     <lb/>
     apologise for the money spent; our population is 
     <lb/>
     greater and the roads were here before the rest of 
     <lb/>
     the country was heard of. I recommend to any 
     <lb/>
     future form of government that roads, and par<lb break="no"/>ticularly transinsular roads, should have a very 
     <lb/>
     prominent part in their programme. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> What has surprised me most is <lb/> the
                  complete silence of members who do' not <lb/> come from the Avalon Peninsula.
                  There is one <lb/> paragraph of three lines:<ref target="#fn_07">[1]</ref>
                  "Included in this is an <lb/> amount of $529,464.61 spent in the past two <lb/>
                  years on the 9.2 miles between St. John's and <lb/> Topsail, to reconstruct,
                  recondition and pave the <lb/> Conception Bay highroad." Perhaps the districts
                  <lb/> the other members represent have not got condi<lb break="no"/>tions such as
                  they have in the parts I represent. In <lb/> Gambo, the cemetery is a mile from
                  the settle<lb break="no"/>ment. I have walked over that mile — it is bog to <lb/>
                  your ankles. There are places where you have to <lb/> leave the road altogether. I
                  wonder what the <lb/> people of Gambo will think when they hear that <lb/> in the
                  past two years $500,000 has been spent <lb/> from St. John's to Woodstock?<ref target="#fn_08">[2]</ref> What for? I do <lb/> not know a great deal aboutthe
                  area, butmy guess <lb/> is that that was done for a few people who have <lb/>
                  country houses out around Topsail, so that they <lb/> can get in their cars and
                  get out there easier. I <lb/> cannot imagine what other reason there could be.
                  <lb/> And the rest of the country is up to its shins in <lb/> bog. I am thinking
                  of the islands down there also <lb/>
                  <cb/> — Silver Hare Island<ref target="#fn_09">[3]</ref> — where there is a cove
                  <lb/> on one side where there is a school, and in order <lb/> to get to that
                  school the children have to climb <lb/> over a cliff of some 30 to 40 feet in
                  heightbecause <lb/> the road is broken. There was a bridge there and <lb/> it gave
                  way. Yet the government spends <lb/> $500,000 to recondition and pave nine miles
                  of <lb/> road from here to Woodstock, $60,000 a mile. <lb/> And in the future they
                  intend to spend "in Con<lb break="no"/>ception Bay, to re-pave a section of the
                  highroad <lb/> west of Topsail," $420,000. When they have <lb/> spent that
                  $420,000, plus $529,000, that is $1 <lb/> million to re-pave roughly 15 miles of
                  road. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> That is what I meant by waste. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> A certain proportion is wasted, <lb/>but it is
                  surprising to me — this report is full of <lb/>dynamite, and we are passing it
                  over talking <lb/>about details. Does the House agree with the <lb/>Committee's
                  report? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBE2">Mr. Roberts</persName> Before any of the St. John's mem<lb break="no"/>bers reply, I would like to refer to page 9 in <lb/> connection with the
                  transinsular highway, a nice <lb/> scheme, providing we have the money to build
                  it. <lb/> I am very disappointed that no money is to be <lb/> spent on the
                  Northern Peninsula. For 40 years we <lb/> have been wanting roads. We are very
                  isolated. <lb/> Instead of a transinsular road they should link up <lb/> the
                  isolated places. In the Bonne Bay area we <lb/> have fared fairly well. During the
                  past ten years <lb/> we have been linked up with Deer Lake and <lb/> Corner Brook.
                  The distance from Bonne Bay <lb/> north is 125 miles, and 75 miles of that is
                  without <lb/> a harbour. I sent freight out of St. John's the first <lb/> week in
                  November and where is it? At Corner <lb/> Brook. In Clarenville there is a lot of
                  freight for <lb/> that part of the northeast Coast. What are the <lb/> people
                  going to do this winter? We are 40 years <lb/> asking for a road. Do they want the
                  people to <lb/> starve? I have been asked, "What have you got <lb/> there?" We
                  have some of the best salmon rivers. <lb/> I was interested in the tourist trade.
                  One tourist <lb/> came down to Lomond<ref target="#fn_10">[4]</ref> to do some
                  fishing and <lb/> had to wait a day to get to the rivers. He was <lb/> paying $25
                  a day besides other expenses. We <lb/> have some of the best lobster fishing
                  grounds on <lb/> that coast, but there is no way of getting out to it. <lb/>
               </p>
   
<note xml:id="fn_07">[1] Volume II:89. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

<note xml:id="fn_08">[2] A small community near Topsail, Conception Bay. </note>
 
<note xml:id="fn_09">[3] Bonavista Bay. </note>

<note xml:id="fn_10">[4] A logging settlement in Bonne Bay. </note>


            <pb n="235" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0235.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">235</fw>
            
<p>
     Last year there were 6,000 pounds of beef waiting 
     <lb/>
     in Clarenville to be taken out. People were wait<lb break="no"/>ing for their money to get supplies for the winter. 
     <lb/>
     When I look at the money spent on the Avalon, 
     <lb/>
     it gets under my skin. Instead of a transinsular 
     <lb/>
     road, give us the roads to isolated places so that 
     <lb/>
     the people can live. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> The section of the country I repre<lb break="no"/>sent has received no attention. I would like to take <lb/> you all over the road
                  from Burin to St. Lawrence. <lb/> One thing I would advise is that you have your
                  <lb/> life insured, another thing is to bring a nice, soft <lb/> cushion. The
                  roads are very narrow and very little <lb/> money has been spent in that area. I
                  agree that <lb/> vast sums of money are necessary for roads <lb/> throughout the
                  country, but I do not think it is in <lb/> order for so much money to be spent on
                  one <lb/> section. In the Lamaline area the roads are eight <lb/> feet wide and
                  the soil is soft. There has been <lb/> nothing done in that area, apart from a man
                  going <lb/> over it with a horse and scraper. You can imagine <lb/> what he can
                  accomplish. These places should <lb/> have closer attention. Mr. Reddy of Burin
                  East <lb/> could tell a similar story of the road problem in <lb/> his section.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I think every district in the country <lb/> has a
                  road problem, and people throughout the <lb/> country will hear of this ridiculous
                  expenditure <lb/> of $500,000 on this road de luxe. But talking of <lb/> it for
                  weeks will not bring back that $500,000. It <lb/> is not our duty to define
                  government policy on <lb/> roads. It is something we can recommend to <lb/>
                  whatever form of government we might have in <lb/> future. Iknow we have very poor
                  road conditions <lb/> in the Humber area. We are trying to do some<lb break="no"/>thing about it ourselves. That is the only thing we <lb/> can do at the moment.
                  That is why I have not <lb/> spoken about this report. We are all aware that <lb/>
                  the only thing we can do is recommend. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> I am a firm believer in the building <lb/> of
                  roads, but the Avalon Peninsula has been very <lb/> well favoured in road
                  expenditure over the last <lb/> few years. I note with satisfaction from the
                  report <lb/> that the Burin Peninsula road is to be undertaken <lb/> next year. I
                  assure you the people of Burin Penin<lb break="no"/>sula will be very interested
                  in this road, which <lb/> will touch four districts; so I am not speaking for
                  <lb/> my district alone. It is essential to the fisheries, <lb/> especially to the
                  fresh fish industry carried on in <lb/> Burin by Fishery Products.... As to the
                  local roads <lb/> in St. Lawrence, they are in a desperate condition. <lb/>
               </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     Children, in many cases. cannot get to school 
     <lb/>
     because the roads are too bad. I hope the govern<lb break="no"/>ment will do more than they have done in the past 
     <lb/>
     to make better local roads for the people in the 
     <lb/>
     outports. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> I feel just as strongly as Mr. <lb/> Hollett
                  does about the expenditure on the Avalon <lb/> Peninsula, but as a member of St.
                  John's West, I <lb/> do not feel like hanging my head. After all, we <lb/> are not
                  here as part of a House of Assembly which <lb/> is responsible for the outlay. I
                  think if we were, <lb/> we would be re-elected. One thing that has oc<lb break="no"/>curred to me as I read the report is that since 1934 <lb/> the
                  average mileage of roads constructed has <lb/> been something in the neighbourhood
                  of 22 miles <lb/> a year. Before we get on to the future aspects, I <lb/> would
                  like to take a look at the past. From 1832 <lb/> to 1934, the average has been 50
                  miles a year. In <lb/> the very beginning, in the day of Sir Thomas <lb/>
                  Cochrane, 1835, the first roads were built around <lb/> Conception Bay. 1 do not
                  imagine a great deal of <lb/> roads were built in the first 20 years of repre<lb break="no"/>sentative government, so the annual average <lb/> would be 50 or 60
                  miles. If we consider that was <lb/> done by pick and shovel, it stands up very
                  well in <lb/> contrast with the last 14 years with all types of <lb/> modern
                  machinery. The amount of money spent <lb/> in these recent years did not get
                  maximum results <lb/> — the paving of Topsail Road at $60,000 a mile <lb/> is
                  proof of that. That point should be brought to <lb/> light. I would like to hear
                  the other inhabitants of <lb/> the Avalon Peninsula — Mr. Penney, Mr. Crum<lb break="no"/>mey and Mr. Jackman on that point. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Mr. Harrington referred to me as <lb/> an
                  inhabitant of the Avalon Peninsula. I do not <lb/> know if I am or not; the fact
                  remains that as far <lb/> as Bell Island is concerned very little was spent <lb/>
                  on roads there.... We have on Bell Island one <lb/> public road leading from the
                  upper level of the <lb/> island to the beach. We have 9,000 people. We <lb/> have
                  not a hospital. We have had many emergen<lb break="no"/>cy cases during the last
                  35 or 40 years. It is <lb/> through luck and God's help that these people <lb/>
                  reached a hospital. There have been cases where <lb/> lives were lost.... This
                  road has been neglected for <lb/> years. It is a deliberate action on the part of
                  the <lb/> Commission of Government, because the people <lb/> are urging for it and
                  the government does not <lb/> want it to be rammed down their throats. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It does not come within the pur<lb break="no"/>view of this Convention to make any attack upon
           
            <pb n="236" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-09_Page_0236.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">236</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
          
     Commission of Government or upon its
                  motives. <lb/> You can only refer to its suitability as a system, <lb/> but not in
                  such a way as to make reference to <lb/> individuals. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> The point I want to make is that <lb/> it is
                  important the road to the beach be attended <lb/> to, and for quite a number of
                  years it has not been <lb/> kept open. If the report shows $529,000 spent on <lb/>
                  nine miles of road, I fail to see how we can have <lb/> a transinsular road if it
                  is going to cost $60,000 a <lb/> mile. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BURR2">Mr. Burry</persName> I have not spoken in this debate, not <lb/> because
                  I am not interested, but because <lb/> Labrador was not mentioned in it. I do not
                  feel <lb/> that there has been discrimination against <lb/> Labrador. We do not
                  want to claim any money to <lb/> be spent on opening up the various communities.
                  <lb/> We have no roads in Labrador. There are at least <lb/> 35 miles of good
                  motorable roads in the area of <lb/> Goose Bay — Canadian and American — but <lb/>
                  apart from that, no roads, as such. We should <lb/> spend money to open up the
                  country, but we <lb/> should be careful how we apportion the money. <lb/> For so
                  small a country to spend a lot of money on <lb/> roads, that will not mean very
                  much in opening <lb/> up the country, would seem an unwise expendi<lb break="no"/>ture, when we need it so much to develop our <lb/> resources and bring
                  prosperity. I am wondering, <lb/> when we have spent all those millions of dollars
                  <lb/> on roads, how is it going to compare with the <lb/> amount the government
                  has spent on fisheries <lb/> which are so important to Newfoundland and <lb/>
                  Labrador.... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I do not think Mr. Smallwood or <lb/> anyone else
                  on the Transportation Committee <lb/> need worry because there has been so little
                  <lb/> criticism. The report is so complete that there is <lb/> little room for
                  criticism. I read it during the <lb/> Christmas recess, and on the whole their
                  work has <lb/>
                  <cb/> been really excellent.... 0n the question of roads, <lb/> I am sure we all
                  agree that we should offer <lb/> criticism on the amount spent on Avalon Penin<lb break="no"/>sula; it is out of proportion to the amount spent in <lb/> other
                  parts of the country. I am thinking of a <lb/> funeral I attended at Ireland's
                     Eye<ref target="#fn_11">[1]</ref> during the <lb/> summer, when Mr. Toope was
                  buried; they had <lb/> to rest the casket on seven different occasions in <lb/>
                  order to get across holes where bridges once <lb/> were. There has not been a cent
                  spent there in 14 <lb/> years, If they can spend $500,000 on nine miles, <lb/>
                  they should spend money on isolated parts of the <lb/> country. Local road
                  committees have done a <lb/> great deal, and I agree that the department, on the
                  <lb/> whole, has been reasonably liberal to those on the <lb/> various committees
                  who are prepared, to some <lb/> extent, to help themselves. It is not easy to
                     be<lb break="no"/>come so public-spirited, to take such a com<lb break="no"/>munity interest as to neglect the fishing and <lb/> logging in orderto get work
                  done on a 50-50 basis <lb/> on the roads. When the government brought in <lb/>
                  that policy of spending the money through road <lb/> committees, they were
                  thinking in terms of town <lb/> councils. They put the cart before the horse. They
                  <lb/> should continue to pay the people the rate of $4 <lb/> a day. I am not
                  complaining because our friend <lb/> here says the rate is 58 cents an hour; we
                  have not <lb/> been dissatisfied. The people are willing to work <lb/> for 40
                  cents an hour.... I do not think Trinity has <lb/> been mentioned. We have been
                  petitioning the <lb/> government for the past 25 or 30 years to put a <lb/> bridge
                  across the Sound so that Random Island <lb/> will become part of Newfoundland
                  also. With <lb/> regard to this $6 million for a transinsular road, I <lb/> think
                  it will cost at least $10 to $12 million at die <lb/> lowest.... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee rose and reported progress, and 
     <lb/>
     the Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<note xml:id="fn_11">[1] In Trinity Bay.</note>
            

<!-- GL, 2017-03-03, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p>
     January 10, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Transportation and Communication Committee:² 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Mr. Chairman, yesterday after<lb break="no"/>noon we completed all of the report on roads and 
     <lb/>
     bridges up to but not including the section here 
     <lb/>
     given as an appendix,³ on local roads, and I 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     would suggest that the Secretary be asked to read 
     <lb/>
     the appendix on local roads before we have any 
     <lb/>
     discussion on it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The Secretary read from the report] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
           
    </div>     </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>