<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-09-11" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-09-11">11 September 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
          
         
          <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

          <date when="1995"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0002.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0003.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0004.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-02-09">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-08">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0001">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0002">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0002.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0003">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0003.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0004">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0004.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0001.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1</fw>
            
<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     PROCEEDINGS 
     <lb/>
     OF 
     <lb/>
     THE FIRST SESSION OF THE NATIONAL CONVENTION OF NEWFOUNDLAND 
     <lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">

            <p>
     Begun and holden at St. John's in the said 
     <lb/>
     Island on Wednesday, the 11th day of September, 
     <lb/>
     Anno Domini nineteen hundred and forty-six, 
     <lb/>
     being in the tenth year of the Reign of His Majes<lb break="no"/>ty, our Sovereign Lord George, by the Grace of 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
           
     God, of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and 
     <lb/>
     Ireland, and of the British Dominions beyond the 
     <lb/>
     Seas, King, Defender of the Faith, Emperor of 
     <lb/>
     India. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     September 11, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     Pursuant to the proclamation of His Excellen<lb break="no"/>cy the Governor, Sir Gordon Macdonald, 
     <lb/>
     K.C.M.G., issued on August 2, 1946, the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the National Convention met at 1 1.45 am, 
     <lb/>
     September 11, 1946, and at noon, the Chairman, 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Mr. Justice Fox, K.C., met the assembled 
     <lb/>
     members in the former House of Assembly 
     <lb/>
     chambers, Colonial Building. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The proclamation was read by the Secretary, 
     <lb/>
     Captain W. Gordon Warren, RA. The commis<lb break="no"/>sion of Hon. Mr. Justice Fox, KC. was read by 
     <lb/>
     the Secretary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman then took the chair and ad<lb break="no"/>dressed the members of the National Convention 
     <lb/>
     as follows: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Gentlemen of the National Convention: It is 
     <lb/>
     not my intention to address you at any length this 
     <lb/>
     morning, butI do wish to avail of this opportunity 
     <lb/>
     — an occasion unprecedented in the annals of 
     <lb/>
     this colony, of great, perhaps fateful, moment in 
     <lb/>
     all our lives, and as future generations may con<lb break="no"/>sider it, of equally great historic importance and 
     <lb/>
     of far reaching consequence in the national life 
     <lb/>
     of this beloved Newfoundland of ours — to ex<lb break="no"/>press to you, and to publicly acknowledge my 
     <lb/>
     profound sense of appreciation of the honour 
     <lb/>
     conferred upon me in being appointed Chairman 
     <lb/>
     of this National Convention. In that spirit I 
     <lb/>
     solemnly and unreservedly affirm to you, with a 
     <lb/>
     single~minded purpose and deeply cherished 
     <lb/>
     hope, my fervent desire to serve you faithfully 
     <lb/>
     and well, and, to the utmost of my ability, to 
     <lb/>
     co-operate with you and to assist you in your 
     <lb/>
     all-important work and in the performance of the 
     <lb/>
     responsible duties — nay, sacred trust — which 
     <lb/>
     you have undertaken, in the name and on behalf 
     <lb/>
     of our country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I cordially greet and welcome you, and most 
     <lb/>
     heartily congratulate you upon your election by 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
          
     the free voice of our people as their repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives to this Convention; and I unite with 
     <lb/>
     them in the confidence which you so well deserve 
     <lb/>
     and which they thus have manifested, in your 
     <lb/>
     capacity and competence successfully to ac<lb break="no"/>complish the tasks which lie ahead, and in your 
     <lb/>
     integrity and honour worthily to uphold the lofty 
     <lb/>
     traditions of which you are today the proud cus<lb break="no"/>todians and I am sure always will be the fearless 
     <lb/>
     exponents, to the end that under Providence this 
     <lb/>
     dear land may prosper and progress, and her 
     <lb/>
     people find true peace and lasting happiness and 
     <lb/>
     contentment. May God assist and direct you in 
     <lb/>
     your deliberations and decisions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The main purpose of our assembling here this 
     <lb/>
     morning, gentlemen, is to have the members sign 
     <lb/>
     the roll. As your names are called, will you please 
     <lb/>
     come to the desk, in twos, and sign your names. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
          
            <p>In the following order the names were called by 
     <lb/>the Secretary and the members signed the roll: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Crummey, (District of Bay de Verde) 
     <lb/>
    Mr. Dawe (District of Bay Roberts) 
     <lb/>Mr. Jackman (District of Bell island) 
     <lb/>Mr. Smallwood (District of Bonavista Centre) 
     <lb/>Mr. Bradley (District of Bonavista East) 
     <lb/>Mr. Vincent (District of Bonavista North) 
     <lb/>Mr. Brown (District of Bonavista South) 
     <lb/>Mr. Figary (District of Burgeo) 
     <lb/>Mr. Reddy (District of Burin East) 
     <lb/>Mr. Hillier (District of Burin West) 
     <lb/>Mr. Penney (District of Carbonear) 
     <lb/>Mr. Goodridge (District of Ferryland) 
     <lb/>Mr. Watton (District of Pogo) 
     <lb/>Mr. Banfield (District of Fortune Bay) 
     <lb/>Mr. Hollett,M.A. (District of Grand Falls) 
     <lb/>Mr. MacDonald (District of Grand Falls) 
     <lb/>Mr. Starkes (District of Green Bay) 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="2" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0002.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>
      
     Mr. Jones (District of Harbour Grace) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Kennedy (District of Harbour Main) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Harmon (District of Harbour Main) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Spencer (District of Hermitage) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Fudge (District of Humber) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Ballam (District of Humber) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Northeott (District of Lewisporte) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Miller (District of Placentia East) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Ryan (District of Placentia West) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. McCarthy (District of Port-au~Port) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Fowler (District of Port de Grave) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Roberts (District of St. Barbe) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Keough (District of St. George's) 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Fogwill (District of St. John's 
     <lb/>
                        East Extem) 
     <lb/>Mr. Butt (District of St. John's 
     <lb/>                   West Extern) 
     <lb/>Mr. McCormack (District of St. Mary's) 
     <lb/>Mr. Higgins (District of St. John's City 
     <lb/>                   East) 
     <lb/>Mr. Hickman (District of St. John's City 
     <lb/>                       East) 
     <lb/>Mr. Job (District of St. John's City 
     <lb/>                  East) 
     <lb/>Mr. Crosbie (District of St. John's City 
     <lb/>                West) 
     <lb/>Mr. Cashin (District of St. John's City 
     <lb/>                West) 
     <lb/>Mr. Harrington (District of St. John's City 
     <lb/>               West) 
     <lb/>Mr. Cranford (District of Trinity Centre) 
     <lb/>Mr. Vardy (District of Trinity North) 
     <lb/>Mr. Bailey (District of Trinity South) 
     <lb/>Mr. Ashboume (District of Twillingate) 
     <lb/>Mr. Newell (District of White Bay) 
     <lb/>Rev. Burry (District of Labrador) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. Justice Fox, K.C. signed as Chair<lb break="no"/>man and was followed by Professor K.C.<lb/>Wheare, Mr. W. Gordon Warren, as Secretary<lb/>and Mr. Francis Ryan as Assistant Secretary.<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>

    

    
            <cb/>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Now, gentlemen, I wish to in<lb break="no"/>troduce
                  the following officials: first, a distin<lb break="no"/>guished scholar, Professor
                  K.C. Wheare,<lb/>Professor of Government at Oxford University,<lb/>whose services
                  have been made available as ex<lb break="no"/>pert adviser to this Convention.
                  Next, Captain<lb/>W. Gordon Warren, R.A. Secretary of this Con<lb break="no"/>vention, and Mr. Francis Ryan, Assistant<lb/>Secretary.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p>That concludes this morning's session, but I<lb/>might briefly refer to the proposed procedure for<lb/>this afternoon. The members will kindly as<lb break="no"/>semble in this chamber at a quarter to three to<lb/>await the arrival of His Excellency the Governor<lb/>at 3' o'clock. His Excellency has graciously con<lb break="no"/>sented to open the Convention. That being done,<lb/>following His Excellency's address, the Con<lb break="no"/>vention will remain seated until I return to the<lb/>Chair; and then, possibly, we shall take an ad<lb break="no"/>journment until tomorrow afternoon, or other<lb/>such time as you desire, when an address of<lb/>loyalty to His Majesty the King, and thanks to His<lb/>Excellency the Governor, will be proposed by<lb/>Hon. Mr. Job and seconded by Mr. Harrington,<lb/>and, doubtless, supported by the various mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Convention. Then will follow the<lb/>appointment of a committee to draft the address<lb/>of loyalty to His Majesty and thanks to His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency. Then, I suggest we might appoint a<lb/>committee on rules and procedures; and as I shall<lb/>mention to you then — I shall not delay you now<lb/>— we should propose a resolution making ap<lb break="no"/>plicable to the proceedings of the Convention<lb/>parliamentary procedure in so far as it can be<lb/>applied, pending the report of the committee on<lb/>rules and procedure, which may take a week or<lb/>ten days. But we must have rules to pursue our<lb/>deliberations and I make that suggestion for your<lb/>thought in the meantime. We shall now take<lb/>recess until this afternoon at 2.45.<lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">Afternoon Session, September 11, 1946<lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">

            <p>At 2.45 pm the members of the Convention as<lb break="no"/>sembled in the chambers to await the arrival of<lb/>His Excellency the Governor and party. At 2.55<lb/>the Chairman took the chair. At 2.58 Captain<lb/> W. Gordon Warren as A.D.C. announced to the<lb/>Chairman the arrival of His Excellency the<lb/>Governor.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I have the very great honour to <lb/> present
                  His Excellency the Governor Sir Gordon <lb/> Macdonald, K.C.M.G., who very
                  graciously has <lb/> consented to open this Convention. His Excellen<lb break="no"/>cy the Governor. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Sir Gordon Macdonald</persName>, K.C.M.G. We are <lb/> meeting today in
                  a building where the giants of <lb/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0003.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">3</fw> former days engaged in wordy warfare to further <lb/> the
                  interest of their native country: men who <lb/> played a noble part in the public
                  affairs of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, who served their day and generation <lb/>
                  with wisdom and devotion, men to whom the <lb/> country is heavily indebted. We
                  are meeting to <lb/> welcome another body of men, who are the <lb/> elected
                  representatives of the different districts in <lb/> Newfoundland as members of the
                  National Con<lb break="no"/>vention: men confronted with a task as difficult,
                  <lb/> and shouldering a responsibility as heavy as any <lb/> of their
                  predecessors; men called upon to give of <lb/> their best. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     In the long and honoured history of New<lb break="no"/>foundland there are many notable and outstand<lb break="no"/>ing dates, which her people can remember with 
     <lb/>
     pardonable and justifiable pride. Dates which, as 
     <lb/>
     it were, leap to the mind when one only thinks of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland — 1497, 1739, 1832, 1845 and 
     <lb/>
     many others. It is now over 217 years since the 
     <lb/>
     first governor of Newfoundland was appointed, 
     <lb/>
     114 years since representative government was 
     <lb/>
     granted and 91 years since responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment was first introduced. There are many 
     <lb/>
     memorable dates in the history of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     Amongst those dates, in the days to come, will 
     <lb/>
     figure with no less lustre September 11, 1946. 
     <lb/>
     That date will not be omitted by the future his<lb break="no"/>torian of Newfoundland, since it is that on which 
     <lb/>
     the elected representatives of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     gathered together as a National Convention, 
     <lb/>
     presided over by a fellow countryman of theirs 
     <lb/>
     whose name has a deservedly honoured place in 
     <lb/>
     the counsels of the nation. These 46 New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders gather together to consider, and 
     <lb/>
     here in the interest of accuracy I quote from the 
     <lb/>
     official terms of reference, "to consider and dis<lb break="no"/>cuss amongst themselves as elected repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of the Newfoundland people, the 
     <lb/>
     changes that have taken place in the financial and 
     <lb/>
     economic situation of the island since 1934, and 
     <lb/>
     bearing in mind the extent to which the high 
     <lb/>
     revenues of recent years have been due to war<lb break="no"/>time conditions, to examine the position of the 
     <lb/>
     country, and to make recommendations to His 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's Government as to possible forms of 
     <lb/>
     future government to be put before the people at 
     <lb/>
     a national referendum." Though these terms of 
     <lb/>
     reference do not permit of a roving commission, 
     <lb/>
     they do provide ample scope for the members of 
     <lb/>
     the Convention to ventilate their views on the 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
          
     possible forms of future government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To consider and discuss the financial and 
     <lb/>
     economic changes that have taken place in New<lb break="no"/>foundland during the past 12 years is no small 
     <lb/>
     undertaking. To examine the position of the 
     <lb/>
     country calls for much thought and keen obser<lb break="no"/>vation, and then in the light of all the knowledge 
     <lb/>
     gained and all the information placed before you, 
     <lb/>
     to make recommendations as to possible forms of 
     <lb/>
     future government. Such terms of reference will 
     <lb/>
     make it possible for every member of the Con<lb break="no"/>vention to do his duty by his people and the task 
     <lb/>
     of the Chairman should not be too onerous. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Nevertheless, it is true to state that at no time 
     <lb/>
     have a body of representatives in Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     been called upon to deal with a more difficult 
     <lb/>
     task, nor to shoulder heavier responsibilities. To 
     <lb/>
     be entrusted with the obligation of recommend<lb break="no"/>ing what forms of government are deserving of 
     <lb/>
     consideration by the people of any country is a 
     <lb/>
     great honour and a great responsibility. But to be 
     <lb/>
     entrusted with such a task in a crucial period of 
     <lb/>
     transition in the world's history, at a time of much 
     <lb/>
     uncertainty, adds distinction to the honour 
     <lb/>
     without in any way lessening the responsibility. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      Gentlemen, you are certainly entitled to use 
     <lb/>
     the words of Oliver Cromwell, words he wrote 
     <lb/>
     when in a most precarious and perilous position, 
     <lb/>
     surrounded by superior forces, "We are upon an 
     <lb/>
     engagement very difficult" — an engagement 
     <lb/>
     which will demand the highest and the best from 
     <lb/>
     every member of the Convention; which will 
     <lb/>
     demand not only intelligence and knowledge, but 
     <lb/>
     also wisdom and sagacity, tolerance and mag<lb break="no"/>nanimity; a task which will call for a high degree 
     <lb/>
     of selflessness, the noblest form of patriotism. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This in no way means there will not be dif<lb break="no"/>ferences of opinion; it in no way means that those 
     <lb/>
     differences will not be expressed with vigour and 
     <lb/>
     maybe passion. Persons who feel strongly, some 
     <lb/>
     times speak strongly. But what it does mean is 
     <lb/>
     that when a member does intervene, he will do so 
     <lb/>
     in the highest interest of the Convention and of 
     <lb/>
     the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Few questions have roused more feeling, have 
     <lb/>
     disturbed the emotions to a greater degree in 
     <lb/>
     nearly all countries, than questions relating to the 
     <lb/>
     possible forms of government. They raise not 
     <lb/>
     only political and constitutional issues but also 
     <lb/>
     issues of immense moral and social significance, 
     <lb/>
     questions to which the warm heart may be as safe 
     <lb/>
         
            <pb n="4" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-11_Page_0004.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">4</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>
           
     a guide as a cool head. But the cool head, the 
     <lb/>
     analytical mind, the wide vision, all will be 
     <lb/>
     necessary. I realised this clearer than ever the 
     <lb/>
     other day. When re-reading that classic on repre<lb break="no"/>sentative govemmentby John Stuart Mill, I came 
     <lb/>
     across a passage not inappropriate to this oc<lb break="no"/>casion, apassage worthy of serious consideration 
     <lb/>
     by each member of the Convention. It reads as 
     <lb/>
     follows: "To determine the form of government 
     <lb/>
     most suitable to any particular people", says Mill, 
     <lb/>
     "we must be able, among the defects and 
     <lb/>
     shortcomings which belong to that people, to 
     <lb/>
     distinguish those that are the immediate impedi<lb break="no"/>ment to progress; to discover what it is which, as 
     <lb/>
     it were, stops the way. The best government for 
     <lb/>
     them is the one which tends most to give them 
     <lb/>
     that for want of which they cannot advance, or 
     <lb/>
     advance only in a lame and lopsided manner. We 
     <lb/>
     must not, however, forget", John Stuart Mill con<lb break="no"/>tinues, "the reservation necessary in all things 
     <lb/>
     which have for their object improvement, or 
     <lb/>
     progress; namely that in seeking the good which 
     <lb/>
     is needed, no damage, or as little as possible, be 
     <lb/>
     done to that already possessed." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Those are wise words; they were written some 
     <lb/>
     85 years ago, but they are very much up to date. 
     <lb/>
     I would commend them to the earnest consider<lb break="no"/>ation of every member of the Convention. They 
     <lb/>
     will help you in your deliberations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Gentlemen, you are honoured men. Your fel<lb break="no"/>low countrymen have called you to a very big job. 
     <lb/>
     You have their confidence. They trust you. They 
     <lb/>
     are expecting great things ofyou. When you have 
     <lb/>
     fulfilled your task as members of the National 
     <lb/>
     Convention, they know that they will be called 
     <lb/>
     upon to exercise their civic responsibilities. Then 
     <lb/>
     one of, if not the most important election in the 
     <lb/>
     history of Newfoundland will take place. Your 
     <lb/>
     fellow countrymen look to you for guidance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     They look to you for guidance during your 
     <lb/>
     deliberations. They hope for your guidance when 
     <lb/>
     you return to your homes. They know you will be 
     <lb/>
     fully informed on all the aspects of all the 
     <lb/>
     problems confronting Newfoundland. They 
     <lb/>
     know that on the next occasion they go to the 
     <lb/>
     polling, they will have the destiny of the rising 
     <lb/>
     generation and following generations in their 
     <lb/>
     hands. They are relying on you in a very special 
     <lb/>
     manner to help them in every way to discharge 
     <lb/>
     that great responsibility. It is an aspect of your 
     <lb/>
     work which I know you are not likely to overlook. 
     <lb/>
     The whole of your work is preliminary but very 
     <lb/>
     closely associated with that forthcoming elec<lb break="no"/>tion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But your fellow countrymen will not by any 
     <lb/>
     means he the only people interested in your ac<lb break="no"/>tivities. I do not think it is an exaggeration to say 
     <lb/>
     that the whole civilised world is keenly inter<lb break="no"/>ested, I feel sure that you will be fortified in your 
     <lb/>
     work in the knowledge that you have millions of 
     <lb/>
     well-wishers beyond the long and rugged 
     <lb/>
     coastline of your native land. You have the good 
     <lb/>
     wishes of all your fellow countrymen. It is with 
     <lb/>
     that knowledge thatI would have you go on your 
     <lb/>
     way, and in declaring the National Convention 
     <lb/>
     open, I trust that unborn generations of New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders will rise to sing your praises for the 
     <lb/>
     grand job you did. That God's richest blessings 
     <lb/>
     will rest on all your labours is my earnest prayer. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Gentlemen of the National Con<lb break="no"/>vention, if it pleases you I should accept a motion <lb/>for the adjournment of
                  the Convention until 3 <lb/>o'clock tomorrow afternoon when a motion for <lb/>the
                  presenting an address of loyalty to His Majes<lb break="no"/>ty and thanks to His
                  Excellency will be presented <lb/>to the Convention. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-02-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
            <!--<milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     September 12, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Job Mr. Chairman, 1 rise with much 
     <lb/>
     pleasure to move a vote of thanks to His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency the Governor for his very fine opening 
     <lb/>
     address yesterday to the National Convention, a 
     <lb/>
     momentous occasion in the history of our 
     <lb/>
     beloved country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are now passing a landmark which I sin~ 
     <lb/>
     cerely hope and believe will be the commence<lb break="no"/>ment of a period in which the people of all classes 
     <lb/>
     and denominations in Newfoundland will make 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     a new start. Where this journey will end no one 
     <lb/>
     can at the moment forecast, but at any rate it 
     <lb/>
     would seem likely to eventuate at some not far 
     <lb/>
     distant date in an encouragement to every in<lb break="no"/>dividual of voting age to take a much wider and 
     <lb/>
     deeper interest than they have done in the past in 
     <lb/>
     the management of their country's affairs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1 am not going to review our past errors of 
     <lb/>
     omission and commission at this juncture; but it 
     <lb/>
     will be necessary during our deliberations to refer 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>