<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-02-04"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-02-04">4 February 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="285"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0281.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0282.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0283.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0284.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0285.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-08">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0281">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0281.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0282">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0282.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0283">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0283.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0284">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0284.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0285">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0285.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="281"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0281.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">281</fw>
 
<div type="section">         
<head rendition="simple:centre">
     February 4, 1947 </head>
  
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>Amendments to the Rules of Procedure</emph><ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
    </p>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Orders of the day. Mr. Higgins 
     <lb/>
     K.C. to move the following amendments to the 
     <lb/>
     Rules of Procedures of the Convention.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Chairman and gentlemen, as I 
     <lb/>
     told you yesterday this is merely a formal motion 
     <lb/>
     to bring the rules of procedure in line with the 
     <lb/>
     amended act. It requires, of course, a two-thirds 
     <lb/>
     vote of the Convention, but I can assure you it is 
     <lb/>
     purely of a formal nature, and there is nothing that 
  

            <cb/>
           

     should give you cause to worry in the matter. I 
     <lb/>
     move it, sir. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Moved and seconded by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Ashboume that the rules of the Convention be 
     <lb/>
     amended in accordance with the motion just 
     <lb/>
     made by Mr. Higgins. Are you ready for the 
     <lb/>
     question? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[After some debate, the motion carried]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Motion to Enquire into Future Forms of Government 
     <lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Mr. Job will move the following 
     <lb/>
     resolution. Mr. Secretary, will you read it please? 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the motion]</hi> 
              </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Whereas it is the duty of this National 
     <lb/>
     Convention to ascertain all important facts 
     <lb/>
     bearing upon the financial and economic 
     <lb/>
     position of this country, and upon all possible 
     <lb/>
     and suitable forms of government to be laid 
     <lb/>
     before the people 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Be it therefore resolved that it is essential 
     <lb/>
     that this Convention take immediate steps to 
     <lb/>
     ascertain 
     </p>

            <p>1. What steps, if any, can be taken for estab<lb break="no"/>lishing improved economic or fiscal relation<lb break="no"/>ships between the United States of America 
     <lb/>and Newfoundland particularly bearing in 
     <lb/>mind the present occupation of certain New<lb break="no"/>foundland territory by the said United States 
     <lb/>of America and the fact that free entry is 
     <lb/>accorded to the United States for its importa<lb break="no"/>tions into Newfoundland; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. What financial and fiscal relationships 
     <lb/>
     could be expected between the Government 
     <lb/>
     of the United Kingdom and Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (1) Under a continuation of Commission 
     <lb/>
     government in its present form, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (2) Under a revised form of Commission 
     <lb/>
     go-vernment with elected representatives 
     <lb/>
     thereon, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (3) Under responsible government in ap<lb break="no"/>proximately its previous form, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (4) Under any other suitable form of 
     <lb/>
     government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. What would be a fair and equitable basis 
     <lb/>
     for federal union of the Dominion of Canada 
     <lb/>
     and Newfoundland, or what other fiscal, 
    

            <cb/>
     
     political or economic arrangements may be 
     <lb/>
     possible. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Be it further resolved that His Excellency 
     <lb/>
     the Governor in Commission be informed 
     <lb/>
     that this National Convention desires to ap<lb break="no"/>point a committee of its members to confer 
     <lb/>
     with His Excellency the Governor in Com<lb break="no"/>mission on ways and means of determining 
     <lb/>
     the matters hereinbefore enumerated, and 
     <lb/>
     that in the event of His Excellency the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor in Commission being agreeable to con<lb break="no"/>ferring with such a committee, the Chairman 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention in consultation with the 
     <lb/>
     Steering Committee shall thereupon select a 
     <lb/>
     delegation of members of this Convention 
     <lb/>
     which, with the Chairman of the Convention, 
     <lb/>
     shall constitute the committee referred to in 
     <lb/>
     this resolution and which shall report to this 
     <lb/>
     Convention the results of their conferences 
     <lb/>
     before being in any way committed to the 
     <lb/>
     despatch of any delegation outside of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Mr. Chairman, my intention was at one 
     <lb/>
     time to ask for this motion to be deferred for 
     <lb/>
     another day, because the members have only just 
     <lb/>
     got the copy of the resolution placed on their 
     <lb/>
     desks, but I thought that the same purpose would 
     <lb/>
     be served if I introduced the resolution and per<lb break="no"/>haps got a seconder, and then the matter might be 
     <lb/>
     laid over until tomorrow for debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In moving this resolution I feel that there is no 
     <lb/>
     need to take up the time of the Convention with 
     <lb/>
     a very lengthy explanation. The motion is self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     explanatory and in my opinion non-controver<lb break="no"/>sial. If it is adopted it will enable the Convention 
     <lb/>
     to start the machinery at once for securing certain 

<note xml:id="fn_01">1 Volume II:53. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>


            <pb n="282"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0282.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">282</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
           

     information which, in my opinion, is essential 
     <lb/>
     before we can intelligently recommend any form 
     <lb/>
     of future government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     You will notice that section 1 deals with the 
     <lb/>
     very important question of improved, or perhaps 
     <lb/>
     I should say stable, fiscal relationships with the 
     <lb/>
     United States of America. I propose in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with this subject, to issue soon a short 
     <lb/>
     pamphlet<ref target="#fn_02">[1]</ref> making clear what is in my mind for 
     <lb/>
     the information of members, or of anyone else 
     <lb/>
     interested in the question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Section 2 deals with a point that has been 
     <lb/>
     raised once or twice as to whether, under certain 
     <lb/>
     circumstances, we can or can not expect any 
     <lb/>
     continuation of assistance from Great Britain, 
     <lb/>
     and it also leaves open for discussion general 
     <lb/>
     questions of finance and exchange between the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom and Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Section 3 is the section that may be com<lb break="no"/>mented upon controversially, but which I hope 
     <lb/>
     will be accepted in the spirit in which it is offered. 
     <lb/>
     In my opinion we were elected to this Convention 
     <lb/>
     to deal in a fair and broad way with our problems, 
     <lb/>
     and to make recommendations for their solution. 
     <lb/>
     It may be that some think that the confederation 
     <lb/>
     issue would be better left alone altogether, and 
     <lb/>
     that it is not our business even to discuss it, but 
     <lb/>
     in view of the ruling of our late respected Chair<lb break="no"/>man, Mr. Justice Fox, concurred in by Professor 
     <lb/>
     Wheare, and I think I am right in saying by our 
     <lb/>
     present Chairman, that confederation with 
     <lb/>
     Canada is one of the issues open for debate, we 
     <lb/>
     would in my opinion be wrong in not facing this 
     <lb/>
     fact now, and making some preparations for its 
     <lb/>
     discussion at a future date. The inclusion of the 
     <lb/>
     confederation issue in this resolution is made 
     <lb/>
     only so that our deliberations and recommenda<lb break="no"/>tions can come to an end as soon as possible. I 
     <lb/>
     think that a discussion of the pros and cons of 
     <lb/>
     confederation or of any other form of government 
     <lb/>
     at the present juncture would be a great mistake, 
     <lb/>
     but I cannot agree that we would be unwise in 
     <lb/>
     seeking to gather now certain details which must 
     <lb/>
     have a bearing on the forms of government which 
     <lb/>
     it is clear to me we must debate if we are to 
     <lb/>
     accomplish the duties for which we were elected. 
     <lb/>
     However, the gathering of such information is the 
     <lb/>
     sole object of the resolution, which in its present 
     <lb/>
     form provides for reporting back to the whole 
     <lb/>
     Convention prior to the despatch of any delega<lb break="no"/>
      
            <cb/>
           tion. 
  </p>

            <p>
     I would like to add that it is my firm belief that 
     <lb/>
     confederation with Canada would not be a satis<lb break="no"/>factory solution to our problems, but it is also 
     <lb/>
     evident to me that a considerable number of the 
     <lb/>
     people who have elected this Convention will 
     <lb/>
     expect a fair and free discussion of the subject. 
     <lb/>
     The main point I want to stress is that this is in no 
     <lb/>
     way a resolution favouring confederation or any 
     <lb/>
     other form of government, and that I have worded 
     <lb/>
     it as broadly as possible in the hope that it will be 
     <lb/>
     accepted as a non-controversial motion. There is 
     <lb/>
     only one other remark I would like to make, and 
     <lb/>
     that is that this whole resolution has been drafted 
     <lb/>
     by myself without any influence from any other 
     <lb/>
     member of the Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I should like to second the motion, 
     <lb/>
     and to say that I agree entirely with the reasoning 
     <lb/>
     of Mr. Job in introducing the resolution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I would like to 
     <lb/>
     say that I support the motion, that I agree with all 
     <lb/>
     three sections in it, and that I think the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion would be well advised to send a committee 
     <lb/>
     of its members to the Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and seek their advice as to the proper steps 
     <lb/>
     for the Convention to take in securing the 
     <lb/>
     answers to these three questions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Is the House ready for the ques<lb break="no"/>tion? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, this is a very impor<lb break="no"/>tant resolution, and one which I think we should 
     <lb/>
     study very carefully and think about before we 
     <lb/>
     vote. The first section of the resolution ... invol<lb break="no"/>ves quite a lot. In the first place, I would say 
     <lb/>
     "what steps, if any, are to be taken for the estab<lb break="no"/>lishing of improved economic or fiscal relation<lb break="no"/>ships" is a matter which is wholly and solely for 
     <lb/>
     the government of the day, or for the business 
     <lb/>
     people of the time. I can find nothing in the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland Act, or the Convention Act, 
     <lb/>
     which authorises us to set ourselves up as a body 
     <lb/>
     to deal with other nations.... I wonder what at<lb break="no"/>titude the Commission of Government would 
     <lb/>
     take if we attempted to interfere in their preroga<lb break="no"/>tive, which they undoubtedly possess as the 
     <lb/>
     government of the day. It is surely their duty, and 
     <lb/>
     theirs only, to approach the United States with 
     <lb/>
     regard to concessions in tariff and other matters. 
     <lb/>
     On that point alone I think we are sticking our 
     <lb/>
     noses into something which at the moment is 
    

   
  
<note xml:id="fn_02">1 Robert B. Job, <hi rendition="simple:italic">A Pamphlet on the Idea of a "Partly Internationalized" Newfoundland</hi> (St. John's, 1947).</note>

            <pb n="283"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0283.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">283</fw>
         

     none of our business whatsoever. Why should we 
     <lb/>
     not go and endeavour to interview the govern<lb break="no"/>ments of a dozen countries who take our 
     <lb/>
     products? If we are going to deal with the United 
     <lb/>
     States, why not with Portugal, Spain, Italy, 
     <lb/>
     Greece and the West Indies? .... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The second part of that section — "Bearing in 
     <lb/>
     mind ... free entry etc... — we have gone into 
     <lb/>
     this before, and I think we all agreed that we did 
     <lb/>
     not give any territory of ours to the United States, 
     <lb/>
     therefore in what way can we use that as a bar<lb break="no"/>gaining power in order to get our fish into the 
     <lb/>
     USA duty free or with concessions? That part of 
     <lb/>
     our territory which has been stolen from us and 
     <lb/>
     given away, was taken from us by Great Britain. 
     <lb/>
     If we look for concessions on account of that, we 
     <lb/>
     must look to Great Britain, who sliced it off this 
     <lb/>
     little island and gave it away. I can imagine the 
     <lb/>
     answer any delegation would get if we ap<lb break="no"/>proached the United States saying, "Look here, 
     <lb/>
     you have got some of our territory, what are you 
     <lb/>
     going to do about it?" That's a signed and sealed 
     <lb/>
     bargain, by which Great Britain gave away for 99 
     <lb/>
     years, which means forever, those bases, and for 
     <lb/>
     which they got 40 or 50 old destroyers. That I 
     <lb/>
     think is something which we have to think about 
     <lb/>
     in dealing with that particular section... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Hollett read Section 2]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In other words we are expected to communi<lb break="no"/>cate with the Commission of Government, and in 
     <lb/>
     conjunction with them set up a committee to say, 
     <lb/>
     "Well now, if we have responsible government, 
     <lb/>
     what will you do for us?"; "If we continue your 
     <lb/>
     puppet government as it is, or slightly reformed, 
     <lb/>
     what will you do to help us?"; or, "If we take 
     <lb/>
     some other form of Government, what is your 
     <lb/>
     attitude then?" I think that's the most ridiculous 
     <lb/>
     section of the lot. In other words we have to 
     <lb/>
     decide what form of Government we will recom<lb break="no"/>mend to the people. Can you conceive of the 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government sitting down and 
     <lb/>
     talking to asses who would ask them questions of 
     <lb/>
     that sort? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then we come to clause three. A nice little 
     <lb/>
     parcel tied up with a neat little string. The same 
     <lb/>
     parcel which we had several months ago, and 
     <lb/>
     which we spent a week or ten days arguing about, 
     <lb/>
     nicely disguised and designed to fool people, 
     <lb/>
     there is no question about it. Mind you, I have no 
     <lb/>
     objection to our knowing the terms under which 
     <lb/>
     We might go into union with Canada, but I am 
    

            <cb/>
        
     reminded of the fact, when I think of it, that the 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa government is unable to come to terms 
     <lb/>
     with the various provinces at the present time.... 
     <lb/>
     In spite of that we consider sending a delegation 
     <lb/>
     to Ottawa to find out the terms. I admit that is not 
     <lb/>
     the exact wording, but that is the point of the 
     <lb/>
     section.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am not very strongly against this motion. It 
     <lb/>
     commits us to very little except that it asks us to 
     <lb/>
     approach the Commission of Government. I 
     <lb/>
     don't know if they will receive us. There is noth<lb break="no"/>ing to get us into serious trouble at the moment, 
     <lb/>
     but it is a pity that we can't get on with the job 
     <lb/>
     for which we were sent here and then, according 
     <lb/>
     to our own poor judgement, make up our minds 
     <lb/>
     as to whether we are self-supporting. Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin told us yesterday that we were self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting since 1941, but we have not decided that 
     <lb/>
     in our wisdom. I think we ought to get to work 
     <lb/>
     and finish our business, and find out just where 
     <lb/>
     we are, and let the government talk fiscal matters 
     <lb/>
     with the United States, and with Canada for that 
     <lb/>
     matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> May I make a few remarks of explana<lb break="no"/>tion? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Anything that you have said you 
     <lb/>
     may explain, Mr. Job, if it has been misinter<lb break="no"/>preted. In addition you have your right of reply 
     <lb/>
     at the end of the debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I don't want a long debate, but there is 
     <lb/>
     nothing in this resolution calling for an approach 
     <lb/>
     to any foreign government at all. You said we 
     <lb/>
     might as well approach Spain or Italy or Greece 
     <lb/>
     or the United States, but this motion is not for 
     <lb/>
     approaching the United States, but our own 
     <lb/>
     government, for information which I think it is 
     <lb/>
     necessary for us to have in doing this job here. 
     <lb/>
     There is nothing in this resolution which calls for 
     <lb/>
     the sending of a delegation anywhere outside of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Is the Convention ready for the 
     <lb/>
     question? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> Mr. Chairman, the last paragraph 
     <lb/>
     of the resolution, I wish to move an amendment 
     <lb/>
     to delete the words from line six "the Chairman 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention in consultation with the Steer<lb break="no"/>ing Committee shall thereupon select a delega<lb break="no"/>tion of members of this Convention", and insert 
     <lb/>
     these words: "the Convention shall elect from 
     <lb/>
     amongst its members a delegation which, with 
     <lb/>
     the Chairman of the Convention, shall constitute 
    

            <pb n="284"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0284.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">284</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
          

     the Committee referred to in this Resolution 
     <lb/>
     etc." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> There is one point I would like to make, 
     <lb/>
     if I may intervene for a moment. The rules pro<lb break="no"/>vide that the Chairman shall appoint all commit<lb break="no"/>tees.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That is the rule, gentlemen. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCA7">Mr. McCarthy</persName> Would this be a committee or a 
     <lb/>delegation? The resolution reads "delegation". 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It is referred to as a "delegation" 
     <lb/>in one place and a "committee" in another place. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Can you not agree to suspend the 
     <lb/>rules? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You can by a two-thirds 
     <lb/>
     majority motion, of which I think notice will have 
     <lb/>
     to be given. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> You can suspend it if it is unani<lb break="no"/>mous. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There has been an amendment 
     <lb/>
     moved which has not been seconded, and of 
     <lb/>
     which I have not the exact words. I have no desire 
     <lb/>
     to restrict the right of any member, but I must 
     <lb/>
     have that in writing before I can submit it to the 
     <lb/>
     body. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Chairman left the Chair for ten minutes]</hi> 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Mr. Fogwill, have you your 
     <lb/>proposed amendment in writing now? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> Yes, sir. The amendment to the 
     <lb/>
     resolution is as follows: to delete the words from 
     <lb/>
     line six "the Chairman of this Convention in 
     <lb/>
     consultation with the Steering Committee shall 
     <lb/>
     thereupon select a delegation of members of this 
     <lb/>
     Convention", and insert these words: "elected by 
     <lb/>
     the National Convention from its own members". 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I have no objection to that change. I 
     <lb/>think it is quite proper and probably democratic 
     <lb/>if the Convention should elect its own commit<lb break="no"/>tees. The only reason I put it in was that the rules 
     <lb/>provided for it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I second the motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It has been moved by Mr. Fog- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     will and seconded by Mr. Bailey that the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion be amended.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Mr. Chairman, speaking to the 
     <lb/>
     resolution, I am somewhat of the same mind as 
     <lb/>
     my friend Mr. Hollett. l have no particular objec<lb break="no"/>tion to a committee of the Convention interview<lb break="no"/>ing the Commission of Government with regard 
     <lb/>
     to any matter, but with all due respect to Mr. Job 
     <lb/>
     and Mr. Higgins, I think that in many cases we 
     <lb/>
     are going to askthem things which we as sensible 


            <cb/>
          
     people should not ask. For instance, "What steps, 
     <lb/>
     if any, can be taken for establishing improved 
     <lb/>
     economic or fiscal relationships between the 
     <lb/>
     United States of America and New<lb break="no"/>foundland....?" Surely to goodness, every mem<lb break="no"/>ber of this Convention knows that the only step 
     <lb/>
     which can be taken is that the government itself 
     <lb/>
     get in touch with the United States government 
     <lb/>
     and ask them these questions. They won't tell us 
     <lb/>
     to appoint a delegation to go to Washington, 
     <lb/>
     because I think it's been proved that we have no 
     <lb/>
     power to do that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And then the second part, "What financial and 
     <lb/>
     fiscal relationships could be expected between 
     <lb/>
     the Government of the United Kingdom and 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland etc." First when this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion met there was a ten year programme placed 
     <lb/>
     on the table of the house, which is now being 
     <lb/>
     carried out. That $59 million program, of which 
     <lb/>
     in this fiscal year so far about $8-9 million have 
     <lb/>
     been spent, they have been carrying it out and 
     <lb/>
     have never asked us whether they would or not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The government has power to go to the United 
     <lb/>
     States and talk paper, mines or anything else. I 
     <lb/>
     would also like to point out that, at the present 
     <lb/>
     time, the fishing interests of Gloucester are put<lb break="no"/>ting on a campaign looking for increased tariff 
     <lb/>
     protection for their fish. In my opinion we have 
     <lb/>
     no power, it is up to the government to do that, 
     <lb/>
     and they would be falling down on their job if 
     <lb/>
     they are not trying to do it. Now, I would be 
     <lb/>
     perfectly willing to support this part of the ques<lb break="no"/>tion: "What steps, if any, are you taking", is the 
     <lb/>
     government taking. But what steps can be taken, 
     <lb/>
     or what steps are the government trying to take? 
     <lb/>
     They should be taking some. The British govern<lb break="no"/>ment should be taking some steps in our interests, 
     <lb/>
     but are they doing that? They know what can be 
     <lb/>
     done if they will only do it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The next thing: "What would be a fair and 
     <lb/>
     equitable basis for federal union....!" We are as<lb break="no"/>king them to tell us what they think is fair. It's 
     <lb/>
     our job to decide what is fair, not theirs, and 
     <lb/>
     furthermore, Mr. Chairman, we had this matter 
     <lb/>
     up some three or four months ago and there was 
     <lb/>
     an amendment moved by Mr. Penney and passed 
     <lb/>
     in this House, whereby this confederation issue 
     <lb/>
     was to be left over until such time as our reports 
     <lb/>
     were finished. I think Mr. Penney will agree that 
     <lb/>
     that was the idea of his amendment, and now we 
     <lb/>
     find it in here. I have no objection to a delegation 
     <lb/>
        

            <pb n="285"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-04_Page_0285.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">285</fw>
          

     going down and talking to the Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government in the next three months, but I want 
     <lb/>
     them to go down somewhat sensibly; to ask them 
     <lb/>
     what can be done is a lot of foolishness. As a 
     <lb/>
     former minister of the Crown I have to state that 
     <lb/>
     that looks silly to me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I would like to point out to the 
     <lb/>
     Convention before the debate goes any further, 
     <lb/>
     that this amendment can only be put with the 
     <lb/>
     consent of the whole House, because it is, in my 
     <lb/>
     opinion, contrary to the rules. Is there any further 
     <lb/>
     discussion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, may I ask under 
     <lb/>
     what particular rule the amendment is a con<lb break="no"/>tradiction? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Yes, Mr. Hollett. Rule 42 says, 
    

            <cb/>
          

     "The Chairman of the Convention shall appoint 
     <lb/>
     all committees." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Did not that refer to committees in 
     <lb/>
     connection with the working of this Convention? 
     <lb/>
     It should not apply to the idea of appointing a 
     <lb/>
     committee to go elsewhere.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The rule says "all committees". 
     <lb/>
     Nevertheless, that can be overridden by the Con<lb break="no"/>vention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[After some debate, and with the consent of the<lb/>Convention, the Chairman put Mr. Fogwill's<lb/>amendment to the vote. It was carried. The Con<lb break="no"/>vention then debated and passed Mr. Job's mo<lb break="no"/>tion as amended (30-7), and adjourned. There<lb/>followed an informal session]</hi></p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Informal Session of Convention 
     <lb/>
     Tuesday, February 4th, 1947 
     <lb/>
     at 4.50 pm 
     <lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     Pursuant to adjournment of the public session at 
     <lb/>
     430 pm the Convention assembled in the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Council Chamber to consider the im<lb break="no"/>plementing of the motion of Hon. R.B. Job. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> asked that the committee referred 
     <lb/>
     to in Hon. Mr. Job's motion be elected in open 
     <lb/>
     session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName>, K.C. moved and <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> 
     <lb/>
     seconded that a nominating committee be elected 
     <lb/>
     for the purpose of recommending and nominating 
     <lb/>
     a committee to interview the Governor in Com<lb break="no"/>mission. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Ater some discussion <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName>, K.C,, with 
    

            <cb/>
          
     the consent of <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> and the Convention 
     <lb/>
     withdrew his motion and moved that the electing 
     <lb/>
     of that committee be effected forthwith by secret 
     <lb/>
     ballot. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The motion was seconded by <persName ref="pers:BURR2">Rev. Mr. Burry</persName> 
     <lb/>
     and carried, whereupon the following were 
     <lb/>
     elected members of the committee with the 
     <lb/>
     Chairman: Hon. R.B. Job, Messrs. CA. Crosbie, 
     <lb/>
     G.F. Higgins, K.C,, T.G.W. Ashbourne, J.R. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood, I. Newell and F.D. Fogwill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There being no further business the meeting 
     <lb/>
     then adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-06-08, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
   
           <!-- <p>
     February 6, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Forestry Committee:¹ 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Mr. Chairman, when we adjourned 
     <lb/>
     the other afternoon I suggested to you that we had 
     <lb/>
     something additional to the supplementary 
     <lb/>
     report, and I will now read that additional supple<lb break="no"/>ment.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Committee has recently received 
     <lb/>
     numerous representations from certain sec<lb break="no"/>tions of the country requesting that certain 
     <lb/>
     timber areas now held by private corpora<lb break="no"/>tions either under lease or free simply should 
     <lb/>
     revert to the Crown. These particular areas 
     <lb/>
     carry the only available timber in these ter<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>ritories that could be of benefit to the people 
     <lb/>
     generally, either for fuel or the manufacture 
     <lb/>
     of lumber for local consumption. The 
     <lb/>
     Forestry Committee feels that the Commis<lb break="no"/>sion government might make an effort to 
     <lb/>
     negotiate with the companies concerned for 
     <lb/>
     an exchange of properties by mutual en- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     couragment and if possible try and effect a 
     <lb/>
     settlement that would be equitably fair. A 
     <lb/>
     settlement along these lines would be of 
     <lb/>
     material assistance to the people concerned. 
     <lb/>
     The whole supplementary report is now 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>¹Volume II:56.<lb/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>