<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-04-11"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-04-11">11 April 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="482"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0473.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0474.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0475.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0476.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0477.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0478.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0479.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0480.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0481.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0482.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-23">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0473">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0473.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0474">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0474.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0475">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0475.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0476">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0476.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0477">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0477.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0478">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0478.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0479">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0479.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0480">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0480.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0481">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0481.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0482">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0482.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="473"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0473.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">473</fw>
            

<!-- GL, 2017-06-23, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

<!--<p>
     as read. Motion carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> We have one more page on the La 
     <lb/>
     Manche mine. I don't know if you wish to have 
     <lb/>
     that now, or if you wish to adjourn. With your 
     <lb/>
     consent I was going to ask that we adjourn until 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     tomorrow, rather than have another session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>[The Secretary read the section on La Manche.<lb/>The committee rose and reported progress, and<lb/>the Convention adjourned]<lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">

            <head rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     April 11, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Orders of the day. Mr. Jackman 
     <lb/>
     to move the following resolution: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Whereas it is desirable that the National 
     <lb/>
     Convention and the people of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     should be fully informed, so far as possible, 
     <lb/>
     of all the facts having any bearing upon forms 
     <lb/>
     of government that might be submitted to the 
     <lb/>
     people in a national referendum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Therefore be it resolved that the ap<lb break="no"/>propriate authorities he advised that the Con<lb break="no"/>vention desires to inform the Government of 
     <lb/>
     the United States of America of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion's wish to learn that government's at<lb break="no"/>titude on the question of the federal union of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland with the United States of 
     <lb/>
     America: and further wishes to ascertain the 
     <lb/>
     terms and conditions on the basis of which 
     <lb/>
     the Government of the United States of 
     <lb/>
     America consider that such federal union 
     <lb/>
     might be effected, for which purpose this 
     <lb/>
     Convention desires to send a delegation to 
     <lb/>
     Washington, D.C. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Be it further resolved that the delegation 
     <lb/>
     shall have no authority whatsoever to nego<lb break="no"/>tiate or conclude any agreement or in any 
     <lb/>
     manner to bind the Convention or the people 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Mr. Chairman, in rising to move 
     <lb/>
     this resolution I do not do so with any undue 
     <lb/>
     enthusiasm. I feel very sad about the whole situa<lb break="no"/>tion. I am a Newfoundlander and I am very proud 
     <lb/>
     of my birth. I lost in the first world war the only 
     <lb/>
     brother in the world I could have as a companion, 
     <lb/>
     who laid down his life at Beaumont Hamel in 
     <lb/>
     1916, for the rights of all people to choose their 
     <lb/>
     own way of living. But I do recognise, sir, a 
     <lb/>
     certain subtle line of propaganda which we fell 
     <lb/>
     for in 1933, and which we are beginning to fall 
     <lb/>
    for again today. Mr. Chairman, I have your last 
     <lb/>speech that you gave in this House when you 
     <lb/>were the Leader of the Opposition. I have it home 
     <lb/>on file, I have kept it for years. I just want to note 
     <lb/>one part of it, when you said that the government 
     <lb/>was making serfs of the people of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     Now Mr. Chairman, my idea in moving this 
     <lb/>
     resolution is only to satisfy a number of my 
     <lb/>
     constituents who are in favour of this. I have 
     <lb/>
     listened to a number of people apart from my 
     <lb/>
     constituency talking about the same thing. Per<lb break="no"/>sonally, whilst I move this, I do not agree with it. 
     <lb/>
     It sounds inconsistent but nevertheless I cannot 
     <lb/>
     help it. I believe that if we as a people want to get 
     <lb/>
     down to brass tacks, that there is only one way 
     <lb/>
     we can do it, and that is by standing on our own 
     <lb/>
     feet. I do not believe in getting everything from 
     <lb/>
     a government. As John Stuart Mill says, "The 
     <lb/>
     worth of a nation is the worth of the individual." 
     <lb/>
     We have been subjected, not only lately, but for 
     <lb/>
     a number of years, to this line of propaganda: 
     <lb/>
     "Give me your mind, and I will give you some<lb break="no"/>thing to eat." I think it is appropriate to recall a 
     <lb/>
     warning from one of the greatest philosophers of 
     <lb/>
     modern times — by the way he was a German — 
     <lb/>
     Hegel. He told the German people over 100 years 
     <lb/>
     ago, "Men are not free when they are not think<lb break="no"/>ing." Of course the logical follow-up is this: there 
     <lb/>
     is only one way to bring it into action, and that is 
     <lb/>
     by the ballot, a secret weapon which all of us 
     <lb/>
     fought for, and it is sad to think that the battle of 
     <lb/>
     Runnymede, which was fought so long ago, 
     <lb/>
     should have been sabotaged in 1933. I do not 
     <lb/>
     wish to hold up the investigations of this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion, in fact I am very anxious to get it concluded 
     <lb/>
     as quickly as possible, because as I have said 
     <lb/>
     before, it is the common people who are paying 
     <lb/>
     for it and I don't want to take anything off of 
     <lb/>
     anyone. Now at this time I think it would be very 
     <lb/>
     appropriate to quote a reference from the Bible, 
     <lb/>
     very appropriate. This is it: "For verily I say unto 
     <lb/>
     you that whosoever shall say unto this mountain: 
     <lb/>
     'Be thou removed and be thou cast into the sea 
     <lb/>
     and shall not doubt in his heart, but shall believe 
     <lb/>
     that those things which he saith shall come to 
     <lb/>
     pass, he shall have whatsoever he saith." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Shakespeare says, "Our doubts are traitors, 
     <lb/>
     and make us lose the good we oft might win by 
     <lb/>
     fearing to attempt." Mr. Chairman, in moving 
     <lb/>
     this resolution I do it in this way: I have faith in 
   

            <pb n="474"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0474.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">474</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
          

     our people, I have faith in Newfoundland and 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlanders. We fought in two wars and we 
     <lb/>
     came out on top, and not only on top, but we got 
     <lb/>
     from the highest rank and authorities in England 
     <lb/>
     these continents. Lord Haig said in the last war, 
     <lb/>
     "Newfoundlanders are better than the best." 
     <lb/>
     Montgomery said, "Give me a million New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders and we will clean up all the Ger<lb break="no"/>mans in the world." Here is what I say: I have 
     <lb/>
     faith in my country, and I have faith in our people, 
     <lb/>
     and I do not like the idea of sending delegations 
     <lb/>
     anywhere. I do, however, agree with the delega<lb break="no"/>tion going to England, and that's one of the 
     <lb/>
     reasons why I move this resolution, because 
     <lb/>
     when our delegation goes to England they are 
     <lb/>
     going to be asked, "Well, what do the people in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland think?" The answer is, "Some say 
     <lb/>
     responsible government, and some confedera<lb break="no"/>tion", and it stops there. Now if this resolution is 
     <lb/>
     passed today, they will be fully aware of this as 
     <lb/>
     well, when the Dominions Secretary asks, "What 
     <lb/>
     do you think of the USA?" Well, we also want to 
     <lb/>
     know what about that. I move this resolution first 
     <lb/>
     of all because I know there are a number of 
     <lb/>
     people in Newfoundland who would vote for 
     <lb/>
     amalgamation with the USA, and secondly be<lb break="no"/>cause I want our delegation when they go to 
     <lb/>
     England to let the British government know that 
     <lb/>
     we are beginning to get pretty itchy — in other 
     <lb/>
     words we are willing to go in with anyone. I 
     <lb/>
     personally do not agree with it. I am a New<lb break="no"/>foundlander, and I want Newfoundland for New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders, but as I see it you are having a 
     <lb/>
     delegation sent to England and one to Canada, 
     <lb/>
     and in order to give the people what they want, 
     <lb/>
     and in accordance with our terms of reference and 
     <lb/>
     what Professor Wheare told us, I move that this 
     <lb/>
     delegation be also included. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I allow the resolution, but in 
     <lb/>
     doing so I feel that it is my duty to point out 
     <lb/>
     clearly to the Convention that this proposal 
     <lb/>
     directly and essentially involves a secession from 
     <lb/>
     the British Commonwealth of Nations, and the 
     <lb/>
     incorporation of Newfoundland into a foreign 
     <lb/>
     power, under a foreign flag. Does anyone second 
     <lb/>
     the motion? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIGA1">Mr. Figary</persName> I rise to second the motion made by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Jackman. I am not going to make any com<lb break="no"/>ments because I think it has been well covered by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Jackman. I want to say that I am not al<lb break="no"/>together in favour of it, but there are a lot of 
   

            <cb/>
       

     people in this country and in the district which I 
     <lb/>
     represent, and in many other districts, expecting 
     <lb/>
     this resolution to come up, and if it did not I 
     <lb/>
     believe these people would be very disappointed. 
     <lb/>
     I do not see anything wrong with it. I think we 
     <lb/>
     should have all the facts and information that we 
     <lb/>
     can get. I am not so much concerned about federal 
     <lb/>
     union with the USA, but I think we should get 
     <lb/>
     some information with regards to trade between 
     <lb/>
     the USA and Newfoundland, and I believe there 
     <lb/>
     is a lot of information that can be obtained. On 
     <lb/>
     these grounds I have much pleasure in supporting 
     <lb/>
     this motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BANF1">Mr. Banfield</persName> I am much opposed to this Con<lb break="no"/>vention sending a delegation to the USA, and I 
     <lb/>
     will vote against it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> With regard to the resolution before 
     <lb/>
     us, I feel we all have to have the greatest respect 
     <lb/>
     for the USA and its people, and we wish to be 
     <lb/>
     forever on good terms with them, but despite that 
     <lb/>
     I am not able to support this motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Is there any further discussion? 
   </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I feel we have had too little time to 
     <lb/>consider a question which to me is of great im<lb break="no"/>portance. I realise that I may be considered rather 
     <lb/>crazy and unpatriotic, but sometime or other 
     <lb/>somebody has got to say it. I am as interested in 
     <lb/>the welfare of Newfoundland as anyone else. All 
     <lb/>my people came from England, and for three 
     <lb/>generations we have been born and brought up in 
     <lb/>Newfoundland, but we have had the terms of 
     <lb/>reference interpreted to include all forms of 
     <lb/>government. There are a number of people who 
     <lb/>feel that the time has come when we, as New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders, ought to make a decision for our<lb break="no"/>selves as to what we want to do. Now that's the 
     <lb/>question. We ought to make a decision for our<lb break="no"/>selves as to what we ought to do. There are, so 
     <lb/>far as I canjudge, quite a number of people who 
     <lb/>would consider it. I have people of my own in the 
     <lb/>United States, and I know that they look upon 
     <lb/>themselves as blood brothers to Britishers. Now 
     <lb/>I don't want to go into consideration of the 
     <lb/>reasons why we should or should not debate this 
     <lb/>question. I think it is the wrong time for us to do 
     <lb/>it, and i want to move that the whole question be 
     <lb/>deferred to a later date so that we can have time 
     <lb/>to think about it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> If that's an amendment, I 
     <lb/>
     second it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It has been moved by Mr. Butt 
  

            <pb n="475"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0475.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">475</fw>
         

     and seconded by Mr. Harrington in amendment 
     <lb/>
     that the consideration of this matter be deferred 
     <lb/>
     to a later date. 
    </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Is it in order for me to speak? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It is in order for you to speak on 
     <lb/>the amendment once. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> My point in moving this resolu<lb break="no"/>tion was that I felt that when our delegation goes 
     <lb/>to England, it should be fully armed with all the 
     <lb/>facts regarding forms of government in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. That is the only reason why I moved 
     <lb/>it. I am not in favour of federation with anyone. 
     <lb/>I am a Newfoundlander, and I believe in New<lb break="no"/>foundland and Newfoundlanders, but my whole 
     <lb/>object in moving this motion was this: that when 
     <lb/>the delegation would go to England, they would 
     <lb/>be able to tell the British people that there is 
     <lb/>sentiment here in Newfoundland favouring amal<lb break="no"/>gamation or federation with the United States. 
     <lb/>That is the only reason I put it, and I think it is 
     <lb/>only fair that this Convention should vote on it 
     <lb/>now, and give this delegation the full facts. What 
     <lb/>are we holding back for? I was told yesterday 
     <lb/>when I decided to bring this resolution in, "Don't 
     <lb/>do that, it is political suicide." I am not a 
     <lb/>politician, and I am not looking for anything in 
     <lb/>that respect. The only way you can classify me as 
     <lb/>a politician is that I will fight and die for the right 
     <lb/>to bring my family up as decent human beings, 
     <lb/>and my next door neighbours' children as well. 
     <lb/>If the delegation goes to England and is asked, 
     <lb/>"What is the sentiment in Newfoundland?", they 
     <lb/>can say, "Well, some want Commission govern<lb break="no"/>ment, some responsible government, and some 
     <lb/>confederation with Canada." Then they might 
     <lb/>say, "What about the United States, how do they 
     <lb/>think about that?" Now here's what I look at, by 
     <lb/>giving this resolution passage, when the 
     <lb/>Dominions Secretary asks them that question 
     <lb/>they can pass it on. There is a lot of sentiment 
     <lb/>regarding the United States. Personally I do not 
     <lb/>want to see my country put out on hook to 
     <lb/>anybody, but seeing it is going to go that way, and 
     <lb/>there are so many wishing to let it go that way, 
     <lb/>my argument is let it go to the highest bidder. I 
     <lb/>want to put myself on record, and I think there is 
     <lb/>as much British blood in me as any man in this 
     <lb/>Convention, that I admire the British people and 
     <lb/>what they fought and died for. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We have been told that if we go into con<lb break="no"/>federation that we will get baby bonuses and 


            <cb/>
        

     family allowances, and that if we go in with the 
     <lb/>
     Americans everything will he "hunky dory". 
     <lb/>
     What did Churchill tell the people in 1940? Here 
     <lb/>
     is what he told them, and here's what I tell the 
     <lb/>
     people of Newfoundland, regardless of what 
     <lb/>
     form of government they take up. He said, "I have 
     <lb/>
     only one thing to offer you — blood, sweat and 
     <lb/>
     tears." He did not say, "Give me your mind and 
     <lb/>
     let me do your thinking for you, and we will give 
     <lb/>
     you baby bonuses." Well, I have six children and 
     <lb/>
     I can figure out quickly $48 a month — very fine. 
     <lb/>
     He told them blood, sweat and tears, and I tell 
     <lb/>
     them the same. I am used to hard times all my life, 
     <lb/>
     and I know what hunger is, and what it is to stand 
     <lb/>
     in the breadline, and what it is to wake up in the 
     <lb/>
     morning and wonder how in God's name are you 
     <lb/>
     going to raise your children up. I know all these 
     <lb/>
     things, and I am not looking for it from con<lb break="no"/>federation with Canada or the United States or 
     <lb/>
     anyone else, but I am looking for it in one way 
     <lb/>
     only — through ourselves, and we can do it. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman, I am sorry if I am out of order, but 
     <lb/>
     I can't help it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now as I see it as far as our country is con<lb break="no"/>cerned, we are Split wide open. But the people 
     <lb/>
     have the final choice and believe it or not the 
     <lb/>
     ordinary man, even if he does not know his 
     <lb/>
     ABCs, is pretty commonsense after all. Now we 
     <lb/>
     are here, sent here by our people to explore, 
     <lb/>
     investigate and find out what is best for New<lb break="no"/>foundland. We have different personal ideas. My 
     <lb/>
     idea from the beginning is only one thing, respon<lb break="no"/>sible government, but it is not for me or you or 
     <lb/>
     anyone else to say what form of government we 
     <lb/>
     should have. All we can do is give our opinion, 
     <lb/>
     and it is up to the people to decide. But I do say 
     <lb/>
     this, give them the chance anyway. If I could get 
     <lb/>
     up with the ability of Mr. Smallwood, with his 
     <lb/>
     oratorical power, I would talk here for the next 
     <lb/>
     ten weeks if I were allowed on responsible 
     <lb/>
     government, but, as I was saying, it is not me or 
     <lb/>
     you, but what the people think. However, I think 
     <lb/>
     that if we are going to send delegations to Ottawa 
     <lb/>
     and to England why not, as many of our people 
     <lb/>
     want to know, why not send a delegation to the 
     <lb/>
     United States as well? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Pardon me, but you should con<lb break="no"/>fine your remarks to the amendment. You have 
     <lb/>
     already spoken on the main question. The amend<lb break="no"/>ment is that of deferring the resolution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> I just wanted to make it clear that 


            <pb n="476"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0476.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">476</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
      

     in moving this resolution I do so with no en<lb break="no"/>thusiasm. I am a Newfoundlander and a British 
     <lb/>
     subject, and I believe the only country in the 
     <lb/>
     world today that is doing anything towards the 
     <lb/>
     welfare of the common man is the British govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and I don't want anyone to think for a 
     <lb/>
     moment that I am, by moving this resolution, 
     <lb/>
     disloyal to what I think is the best we have, but I 
     <lb/>
     do say that a lot of people want a delegation to 
     <lb/>
     the USA and why should we not send one there? 
     <lb/>
     Possibly the United States won't have it, and I 
     <lb/>
     hope they won't, but when the time comes for our 
     <lb/>
     delegation to go over to England, let them go with 
     <lb/>
     the thought that there is a sentiment in New<lb break="no"/>foundland on this line. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I had no intention of indulging in 
     <lb/>
     this debate myself. In fact I felt very much like 
     <lb/>
     adopting Mr. Butt's attitude, but as this debate 
     <lb/>
     has gone so far I would much prefer now to have 
     <lb/>
     the motion on the main question put.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     What I want to say is this. There's a lot of parts 
     <lb/>
     of the British Empire today where they are be<lb break="no"/>having like rats trying to leave a ship that they 
     <lb/>
     believe is in trouble. This is the oldest colony of 
     <lb/>
     Britain, the oldest colony and the first colony, and 
     <lb/>
     I want to say this to you: is the oldest colony, even 
     <lb/>
     by words, going to stab a Britain that's now 
     <lb/>
     practically on her back, going to stab her in that 
     <lb/>
     recumbent back today, even if it is only by 
     <lb/>
     words? I have got as much, not British but Irish 
     <lb/>
     blood as anyone, and I would be the last to 
     <lb/>
     support this motion. You ask how I am being 
     <lb/>
     consistent by uttering words like that. Well, 
     <lb/>
     Canada is part of the Empire, and if this country 
     <lb/>
     decides, if we as a people decide, to join Canada, 
     <lb/>
     we will not be getting out of the British Empire; 
     <lb/>
     but once we adopt such a motion, or the country 
     <lb/>
     adopts what would follow such a motion, we 
     <lb/>
     would lose our nationality, we would be no 
     <lb/>
     longer British. I don't think there is a possibility 
     <lb/>
     of this happening, but I don't like to see such a 
     <lb/>
     motion brought into the House like this. I want to 
     <lb/>
     raise every objection to this motion. Mr Jackman 
     <lb/>
     says, "What about India?" India is becoming a 
     <lb/>
     rat, are we going to become another rat? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Order, Mr. Jackman. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Gentlemen, I don't intend to make 
     <lb/>
     any speech, because I know I would lose my 
     <lb/>
     temper, but I shall vote against the amendment, 
     <lb/>
     and I shall vote against the motion. I have faith 
     <lb/>
     enough in the men of this Convention that if the 


            <cb/>
         

     question is put now we shall get the correct 
     <lb/>
     verdict. If I am in order, I beg to move that the 
     <lb/>
     amendment and motion be now put. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I beg to second the motion just 
     <lb/>
     made by Mr. Hollett, and I intend to vote against 
     <lb/>
     the amendment and also against the motion. 
 </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The motion is that the previous 
     <lb/>question be now put. The motion is carried. I shall 
     <lb/>now put the previous question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The motion is that the consideration of this 
     <lb/>
    resolution be deferred to a later date. I declare the 
     <lb/>amendment lost. The original motion is of ex<lb break="no"/>treme importance. I shall permit other speakers 
     <lb/>to this question if there are any who desire to 
     <lb/>address the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> Mr. Chairman, while I believe the 
     <lb/>resolution now before the House has been badly 
     <lb/>timed, still I consider it my duty in fairness to the 
     <lb/>people who sent me here to entertain the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     England so far has promised us nothing. 
     <lb/>
     Canada will only offer us just barely what she 
     <lb/>
     thinks would convince us that confederation 
     <lb/>
     would be the best thing for us. Canada is not a 
     <lb/>
     market for our fish. This resolution would be a 
     <lb/>
     means of helping the English delegation. It would 
     <lb/>
     greatly strengthen the delegation to Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If it were possible for this country to associate 
     <lb/>
     itself with the USA our fishery problem, which 
     <lb/>
     is the greatest problem in this country, would be 
     <lb/>
     solved by giving us free access to the greatest fish 
     <lb/>
     market of the world and assuring our fishermen 
     <lb/>
     of a higher standard of living never before en<lb break="no"/>joyed by them, and removing forever the awful 
     <lb/>
     Spectre of poverty always hovering over our fish<lb break="no"/>ing population. Hundreds of thousands of our 
     <lb/>
     fellow Newfoundlanders are residing in the 
     <lb/>
     United States. They are longing for the day when 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland will perhaps become part and par<lb break="no"/>cel of that great republic. It is too important a 
     <lb/>
     matter to be slighted in any way. If any delegate 
     <lb/>
     here objects to this resolution, he will be depriv<lb break="no"/>ing his people of an opportunity to obtain real 
     <lb/>
     facts so vital to the country's welfare. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> Mr. Chairman, I am sure we are all 
     <lb/>
     very conscious of the fact that this is a very 
     <lb/>
     delicate subject. We are also conscious that we 
     <lb/>
     are British subjects. Now it is a changing world, 
     <lb/>
     and all down through these several hundred years 
     <lb/>
     since Newfoundland was colonised we have not 
     <lb/>
     seen eye to eye with the mother country, but out 
 

            <pb n="477"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0477.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">477</fw>


     of all our little petty differences, when the mother 
     <lb/>
     country was in trouble we immediately donned 
     <lb/>
     our uniforms and rushed to the colours. We are 
     <lb/>
     also conscious of our very close friendship with 
     <lb/>
     the United States. That is an undeniable fact. In 
     <lb/>
     fact we see Canada, Newfoundland and the 
     <lb/>
     USA flirting so closely that many times we feel 
     <lb/>
     perhaps that they should get married; yet down 
     <lb/>
     deep in our inner consciousness is that longing 
     <lb/>
     for freedom, the longing to cement even closer 
     <lb/>
     our relationship with Great Britain. I cannot see 
     <lb/>
     eye to eye with many of the things that have been 
     <lb/>
     said. I spent, during the two wars, something over 
     <lb/>
     seven years in the Pacific, around the British 
     <lb/>
     coast and in various parts of Britain. I have never 
     <lb/>
     yet been able to find a word that I could say in 
     <lb/>
     disrespect of the British people. I know that our 
     <lb/>
     treatment in 1932-33-34 was not really the wish 
     <lb/>
     of the British people.... It was not the people, but 
     <lb/>
     the Dominions Office who gave us that treatment. 
     <lb/>
     It was a handful like that who betrayed Belgium 
     <lb/>
     and France.... I want to see this National Conven<lb break="no"/>tion uphold the principle that the mother country 
     <lb/>
     and the Union Jack have stood for for so long.... 
     <lb/>
     Since I have come in here today I have worded 
     <lb/>
     an amendment to the motion. It is along the lines 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Butt suggested in the early part of the 
     <lb/>
     debate: "That, in view of the fact that a delegation 
     <lb/>
     is about to proceed to the United Kingdom to 
     <lb/>
     ascertain what the mother country is prepared to 
     <lb/>
     do, no further discussion should take place on this 
     <lb/>
     resolution until the delegation returns and its 
     <lb/>
     results are discussed." I think that in all fairness, 
     <lb/>
     with that consciousness in our hearts that the 
     <lb/>
     mother country has stood up for us at all times, 
     <lb/>
     that we should give her the last chance of giving 
     <lb/>
     our delegation the proper information and proof 
     <lb/>
     in realistic terms, that they still stand behind 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, as Britain's oldest colony, and 
     <lb/>
     that they are prepared to liquidate our national 
     <lb/>
     debt for the blood we have given to protect the 
     <lb/>
     British Isles. We were told repeatedly over there 
     <lb/>
     that if it had not been for the colonial troops the 
     <lb/>
     mother country would have gone under.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I know there is an element who would wel<lb break="no"/>come the idea of annexation with the USA. I have 
     <lb/>
     a lot of friends in the USA, and I know that they 
     <lb/>
     are a fine people, but I don't think that those in 
     <lb/>
     authority in the United States would give it one 
     <lb/>
     moment's consideration at the present time, be<lb break="no"/>cause there are bigger factors than New<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
           
foundland, this tiny island of rock. When you 
     <lb/>
     start to come north and look at the chart on the 
     <lb/>
     bridge and look at this island, you think of our 
     <lb/>
     300,000-odd people, and you think of the people 
     <lb/>
     you left in their millions, and you then become 
     <lb/>
     very conscious that as far as the rest of the world 
     <lb/>
     is concerned, we are very unimportant, and that 
     <lb/>
     our only hope is to stick to Britain until she shows 
     <lb/>
     definite signs of forsaking us. I am not going to 
     <lb/>
     deny the fact that it was Englishmen, the Pilgrim 
     <lb/>
     Fathers, who founded the United States, and 
     <lb/>
     eventually Great Britain herself will be only too 
     <lb/>
     happy to see all the western hemisphere come 
     <lb/>
     together as one I am sorry, but while I have a lot 
     <lb/>
     of respect for the motion, and for the courage 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Jackman has shown by bringing it in, I can<lb break="no"/>not really suppon it, but I would have it discussed 
     <lb/>
     later on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> Mr. Chairman, I am emphati<lb break="no"/>cally and irrevocably against it. I think it should 
     <lb/>
     be at once put before the Convention to get the 
     <lb/>
     treatment it deserves — to be thrown out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> May I speak once more? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> No, sir. Is the House ready for 
     <lb/>
     the question? Well, Mr. Jackman, you may close 
     <lb/>
     the debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> It is not my idea at all. I did not 
     <lb/>
     bring in this resolution because I believe in it. I 
     <lb/>
     believe in Newfoundland for Newfoundlanders, 
     <lb/>
     and I think we are going to be absolutely wrong. 
     <lb/>
     After all, who are we? Are we masters or ser<lb break="no"/>vants? I was sent here to this Convention to find 
     <lb/>
     out what I could do for my country. As far as I 
     <lb/>
     can see, we have been given instructions in this 
     <lb/>
     respect according to our terms of reference. 
     <lb/>
     Professor Wheare ruled that we can recommend 
     <lb/>
     any form of government. Now here's my posi<lb break="no"/>tion, and I hope I make myself clear; it's not for 
     <lb/>
     me or for you to decide, it's up to the people of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland to decide, and we have been told 
     <lb/>
     by a constitutional expert from Great Britain that 
     <lb/>
     it is in order to put the United States on our ballot 
     <lb/>
     paper in the referendum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I have to correct you there. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Wheare never made any such statement. 

 </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Well, Mr. Chairman, I think 
     <lb/>Mr. Butt put the question, and as I understood it 
     <lb/>he did say so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I can assure you that he never 
     <lb/>
     made any such statement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Well, sir, if I had known that I 
    

            <pb n="478"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0478.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">478</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
      

     would never have attempted to bring it in. The 
     <lb/>
     only reason was that I felt that there are a certain 
     <lb/>
     number of people in Newfoundland who would 
     <lb/>
     want to be given a chance to vote for union with 
     <lb/>
     the United States. I quote the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Sunday Herald</hi>. I 
     <lb/>
     like that paper, you get a lot of news out of that, 
     <lb/>
     I have seen in that paper where the United States, 
     <lb/>
     in a straw ballot, topped all other forms of 
     <lb/>
     government. Have we the right to turn around and 
     <lb/>
     be dictators and say: "No, you are not going to 
     <lb/>
     have any chance whatever to vote for the United 
     <lb/>
     States, you are not going to have any chance to 
     <lb/>
     vote for confederation, or any chance to vote any 
     <lb/>
     way"? Is that what we say — we 45 delegates? 
     <lb/>
     Who are we? Are we dictators? If this is turned 
     <lb/>
     down, we are dictators. We are telling people that 
     <lb/>
     as far as we are concerned they have no right to 
     <lb/>
     vote for federal union with the United States. I 
     <lb/>
     protest in fairness as a democratic citizen, as a 
     <lb/>
     true blooded Britisher. Possibly there is a great 
     <lb/>
     deal more British blood in my veins than in a 
     <lb/>
     good many here. I protest in the name of Run<lb break="no"/>nymede and the Bill of Rights. After all, when the 
     <lb/>
     Convention is over and we discuss forms of 
     <lb/>
     government, it is all finished. Are we the 
     <lb/>
     masters? No, we are only the servants. The 
     <lb/>
     people of Newfoundland, as far as my experience 
     <lb/>
     is concerned, and I have been a working man 
     <lb/>
     always associated with labour, I know they are 
     <lb/>
     pretty good. They might not know the three Rs, 
     <lb/>
     but they know the difference between a codfish 
     <lb/>
     and a herring. Let us give them the final say. I 
     <lb/>
     protest with all my power against this dictatorial 
     <lb/>
     attitude, against the attitude of this Convention in 
     <lb/>
     saying to the people of Newfoundland, "You 
     <lb/>
     can't put you name on the ballot paper for the 
     <lb/>
     United States." I think we should consider it very 
     <lb/>
     carefully. I challenge any member as far as my 
     <lb/>
     loyalty is concerned. I believe in Britain, she is 
     <lb/>
     the cradle of democracy. It was there that trade 
     <lb/>
     unions started, out of which I get my living today. 
     <lb/>
     Hitler's first move was to bust the trade and 
     <lb/>
     labour unions wide open, but thanks be to God 
  

            <cb/>
          

     the trade and labour movement in England stood 
     <lb/>
     by when the blackshirts and everyone else.... 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I must ask you to confine your<lb break="no"/>self to the question. We are not concerned with 
     <lb/>Hitler. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Well, no, I don't want to talk 
     <lb/>
     about Hitler, he is not worth talking about, but in 
     <lb/>
     my opinion it is quite possible the people will turn 
     <lb/>
     it down. I wish they would, but my argument is 
     <lb/>
     that we have no right to take it off the ballot paper. 
     <lb/>
     If we do we are dictators. It is the people who 
     <lb/>
     have the last say on this matter. Why not put it on 
     <lb/>
     the ballot paper and give them a chance? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     One of our men said last September, after the 
     <lb/>
     ruling of the late Judge Fox, he did say, and 
     <lb/>
     Professor Wheare ruled on it, "You can send a 
     <lb/>
     delegation to Timbuctoo if you want to." We 
     <lb/>
     have got one going to England and one to 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and there's a lot of people in New<lb break="no"/>foundland who want one to go to the United 
     <lb/>
     States. Give the people the chance. If we turn 
     <lb/>
     down that amendment we are putting ourselves 
     <lb/>
     in a position where we are 45 people who have 
     <lb/>
     decided that we are going to take the destiny of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland in our own hands. You can do 
     <lb/>
     what you like, but I will vote to give the people 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland what they want. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Gentlemen, you have heard the 
     <lb/>
     question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Standing vote sir? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I will put it in the ordinary way 
     <lb/>
     first. The motion is that this resolution, which has 
     <lb/>
     been read twice already, do pass. Those in favour 
     <lb/>
     please say "aye", contrary "nay". I think the 
     <lb/>
     "nays" have it. Those who are in favour of the 
     <lb/>
     resolution please stand — two. Those who are 
     <lb/>
     against it please stand. Mr. Clerk, I have not 
     <lb/>
     recorded my vote on any resolution. I intend to 
     <lb/>
     record it today with the "nays". You will please 
     <lb/>
     record it accordingly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Well, it's a dictatorship. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Order, please. I declare the 
     <lb/>
     resolution lost by a vote of 34 to 3. 
     <lb/>
            </p></div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the Mining Committee:<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head></div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The section dealing with the La 
     <lb/>
     Manche mine has been read and is now open for 
     <lb/>
     discussion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Before proceeding I would like to 
   

            <cb/>
           

     correct an error which I made in a statement 
     <lb/>
     yesterday. It has been pointed out to me. Yester<lb break="no"/>day when I was referring to the Buchans Mining 
     <lb/>
     Co. railway cars which were made up at Bishop's 
   

   
<note xml:id="fn_01">1 Volume II:313. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note> 


            <pb n="479"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0479.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">479</fw>
           

     Falls and taken to Buchans, I said the AND 
     <lb/>
     Co. had made them up and put them on. I meant 
     <lb/>
     of course the Newfoundland Railway. I would 
     <lb/>
     like to get that straight now. 
    
 </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[There followed a brief discussion of the section<lb/>on the La Manche mine. The Secretary then read<lb/>the section on Bell Island, and Mr. Higgins<lb/>answered questions on points of detail]</hi>
            </p>


            <p><persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> I am beginning to get at home 
     <lb/>now, and I welcome this opportunity to explain 
     <lb/>the economic relationship which exists on Bell 
     <lb/>Island today. You will note on page 4 that there 
     <lb/>was a closedown of the mine in 1943 due to 
     <lb/>labour trouble. The workers at Bell Island 
     <lb/>decided that things were not as we would like 
     <lb/>them to be. We could not live.... We decided we 
     <lb/>wanted more money for our work. Well, the 
     <lb/>thought was to throw us out of work, but we came 
     <lb/>back and got things adjusted between us, but not 
     <lb/>as we wanted them. All around that time, 1943- 
     <lb break="yes"/>44-45, the relationship between labour and 
     <lb/>management on Bell Island was a dog-eat-dog 
     <lb/>relationship, but early in the year we negotiated 
     <lb/>a new contract. I believe that if the same relation<lb break="no"/>ship between capital and labour which exists on 
     <lb/>Bell Island today could be brought into effect 
     <lb/>throughout Newfoundland, we would not have 
     <lb/>any worry about how we are going to live. We 
     <lb/>would be self-supporting. Here is the exact posi<lb break="no"/>tion. In order for our people to live we must have 
     <lb/>an outside market for our output. The only per<lb break="no"/>manent market we had before was the Sydney 
     <lb/>market, and that would only give us about two 
     <lb/>days a week. I must give the Commission of 
     <lb/>Government credit for helping in this matter, 
     <lb/>especially Commissioner Neill. We were very 
     <lb/>anxious to obtain an English market to absorb our 
     <lb/>extra output. In order to do so we had to get 
     <lb/>around the table, not with chips on our shoulders, 
     <lb/>but get down to work it out between ourselves 
     <lb/>and find out how we could get at it. Anyway, the 
     <lb/>management told us that they could break in on 
     <lb/>an English market for 750,000 tons of ore, but the 
     <lb/>question was the matter of price. We decided that 
     <lb/>this market would be a benefit the whole com<lb break="no"/>munity and the whole country, so we decided we 
     <lb/>would get out and get this market. The manage<lb break="no"/>ment were very fair and very frank and put their 
     <lb/>cards on the table. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now I know there are certain men over on Bell 
     <lb/>
     Island listening to me now, and it is quite possible 
  

            <cb/>
         

     that they would knock my head off if they could 
     <lb/>
     get it. They are reactionaries and don't want to do 
     <lb/>
     anything for the common good. Anyway, the 
     <lb/>
     company put their cards on the table and so did 
     <lb/>
     we. We wanted to live and so did they. This 
     <lb/>
     market meant 750,000 tons of ore, so we forgot 
     <lb/>
     our differences in 1943 and got down and shook 
     <lb/>
     hands and decided that we were going out to get 
     <lb/>
     this market. Now the reason I bring this up is 
     <lb/>
     because I feel regardless of what our people 
     <lb/>
     decide on later with regard to forms of govern<lb break="no"/>ment, that it is not the forms of government that 
     <lb/>
     count but the effect they have.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now as I said a moment ago, there are a few 
     <lb/>
     who would knock my head off because I am 
     <lb/>
     standing with the company. I am not standing 
     <lb/>
     with the company or anyone, but we got together 
     <lb/>
     and in order to get that market it took co-opera<lb break="no"/>tion on both sides. Labour and management are 
     <lb/>
     working hand in hand, and if you will notice here 
     <lb/>
     anything over 5,000 tons of ore we all share in 
     <lb/>
     the profit. We have a general bonus for everyone, 
     <lb/>
     but when we get above 5,000 tons everyone gets 
     <lb/>
     his share. For example, our basic rate of pay is 58 
     <lb/>
     cents an hour, but after we got this working, the 
     <lb/>
     very first week every man on this job got 3 cents 
     <lb/>
     an hour extra because of production.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Jackman is assistant chairman 
     <lb/>
     of the subcommittee on Bell Island, as well as 
     <lb/>
     chairman of the Mineworkers on Bell Island. 
     <lb/>
     That's why he is talking at such length. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> I would like to know if in order 
     <lb/>
     to get 65 cents per hour the men overwork them<lb break="no"/>selves? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> ....What happened over our way, 
     <lb/>
     we were trying to get the worth of our labour. We 
     <lb/>
     had to fight to get it, but the equipment is there 
     <lb/>
     and this schedule can be easily taken care of by 
     <lb/>
     the equipment. We have a certain type of labour 
     <lb/>
     which I would call "enforced labour", but the 
     <lb/>
     company did promise us that as soon as it is 
     <lb/>
     possible to get equipment to take the place of 
     <lb/>
     hand labour they would institute it.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> This table shows that in 1934 
     <lb/>
     we exported to Great Britain an amount of 22,000 
     <lb/>
     tons, and the next year 24,000 tons. I am curious 
     <lb/>
     to know why that much ore was exported over 
     <lb/>
     there.... Why would there be any ore going to 
     <lb/>
     Britain if there was not a quantity of a quarter of 
     <lb/>
     a million tons or around there? Can you explain 
     <lb/>
     that? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="480"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0480.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">480</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
           

 <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I think that they took that amount to 
     <lb/>
     test it out on certain furnaces. That's what I heard 
     <lb/>
     when I happened to be there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I remember in 1925 in London 
     <lb/>
     talking with Major General Sir Newton Moore, 
     <lb/>
     who was the European representative of the Bell 
     <lb/>
     Island company, and he had been contacting the 
     <lb/>
     smelters in England, and they claimed that our 
     <lb/>
     Bell Island ore was not suitable for use in 
     <lb/>
     England because it had too much silica, phos<lb break="no"/>phorus, etc.... Has the Committee any further 
     <lb/>
     information on the prospects of selling ore in 
     <lb/>
     Britain this year? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> You will remember sometime last 
     <lb/>
     year there was a big announcement stating that 
     <lb/>
     Bell Island ore had been sold for some ten years 
     <lb/>
     ahead, some 750,000 tons a year. We questioned 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Anson and Mr. Archibald and they told us 
     <lb/>
     that this is not so; but they did feel that if they 
     <lb/>
     could compete with the prices of ore from Spain 
     <lb/>
     and the other places, Sweden, etc., that the market 
     <lb/>
     could be maintained. It is all a question of com<lb break="no"/>petitive prices. They feel if they can continue to 
     <lb/>
     sell at the market price, that they would get their 
     <lb/>
     fair share, or their quote. That's as far as the 
     <lb/>
     Committee could go. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Have they got an order this 
     <lb/>
     year? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Not up to the time we talked to 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Anson, sometime in February, but they had 
     <lb/>
     good hopes of getting the order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Assuming they get the order, 
     <lb/>
     700,000 tons would run to how much money 
     <lb/>
     roughly? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I could not tell you. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> How much would that be 
     <lb/>
     today, Major Cashin? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> About $4 million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Did the General Manager say 
     <lb/>
     anything about spending money in Britain from 
     <lb/>
     the standpoint of dollars? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> He did not seem to worry about 
     <lb/>
     that at all. If they could meet the price of their 
     <lb/>
     competitors he felt they could secure the order. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> In our last meeting with the com<lb break="no"/>pany they notified us that they have an order for 
     <lb/>one million tons.... The impression we got from 
     <lb/>the company is that if we keep our production up 
     <lb/>above 500,000 tons of ore, we can compete in the 
     <lb/>British market or any market in price, but we 
     <lb/>must keep it up to 500,000 tons.... Some of the 
   

            <cb/>
           

     men are working a bit harder than they should on 
     <lb/>
     account of lack of equipment, but our position is 
     <lb/>
     that we are in the British market and we are going 
     <lb/>
     to stay there. The workers will see to that. The 
     <lb/>
     workers say, "That's our business, not the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Iron and Steel Company's, but ours. 
     <lb/>
     We want to live and work, and if we want to do 
     <lb/>
     that we must produce." Mr. Bullen told me — he 
     <lb/>
     is the purchasing agent in England — that if we 
     <lb/>
     can keep within that figure there is no worry for 
     <lb/>
     the next five years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I take it that the Island has now 
     <lb/>
     got a firm contract signed with Great Britain for 
     <lb/>
     the sale of one million tons of ore in 1947, and 
     <lb/>
     that if the men on the Island keep the daily 
     <lb/>
     production up and the cost of production down to 
     <lb/>
     the present level they can sell more ore in the next 
     <lb/>
     five years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> The system on Bell Island today 
     <lb/>
     is a profit-sharing system between capital and 
     <lb/>
     labour.... I wish the rest of Newfoundland would 
     <lb/>
     do likewise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Jackman is a wonderful 
     <lb/>
     man, and I guess the crowd over there knew what 
     <lb/>
     they were doing when they sent him over here. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Forget the bouquets. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> On page 8, showing the num<lb break="no"/>ber of employees on Bell Island for each year, is 
     <lb/>
     that the correct number for the year or the average 
     <lb/>
     number? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That's the actual number. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> But they would not be employ<lb break="no"/>ed all the year round, would they? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That's the largest number, is that 
     <lb/>
     not so Mr. Watton? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WATT1">Mr. Watton</persName> Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> An average of l,575 for each 
     <lb/>
     year in that period. On page 9, "In the schedule 
     <lb/>
     to this act, etc.", I am asking this before we pass 
     <lb/>
     on from Bell Island, can we get Major Cashin, 
     <lb/>
     who I believe was Minister of Finance in 1930, 
     <lb/>
     and who would have some first hand knowledge 
     <lb/>
     of that act of 1930, which expires in 1949.... 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> It came into effect January 1, 1929. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It says 1930 here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> It came into effect January l, 1929. 
     <lb/>
     I introduced the act. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It was probably brought into 
     <lb/>
     the House when it opened that winter. In that act 
     <lb/>
     it says: "The Company is not liable for customs 
     <lb/>
     duties on coal, explosives, and such equipment 
 

            <pb n="481"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0481.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">481</fw>
         

     (not including hand tools) as shall be used in the 
     <lb/>
     mining, transportation and shipping of ore and 
     <lb/>
     the generation of power in connection there<lb break="no"/>with." On the other hand, they have to "pay duty 
     <lb/>
     on spare parts, articles and materials required for 
     <lb/>
     renewals, replacements, and repairs in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with the Company's equipment for the min<lb break="no"/>ing, transportation, and shipping of ore and the 
     <lb/>
     generation of power for the purposes in connec<lb break="no"/>tion therewith, but in no case is the duty to exceed 
     <lb/>
     25 percent." How does that compare with the 
     <lb/>
     other mining and industrial companies in the 
     <lb/>
     country? Does that apply to St. Lawrence, 
     <lb/>
     Buchans, etc.? 
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> St. Lawrence has no concessions. 
     <lb/>They come under the 1930 act, so they informed 
     <lb/>us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In the next paragraph it goes on 
     <lb/>to say what the tax is, expiring in 1949. Maybe 
     <lb/>there will be changing that and making a new 
     <lb/>contract. Let me read it out: "The Company pays 
     <lb/>no royalties but instead pays an export tax, and 
     <lb/>under the above mentioned act for the 20 year 
     <lb/>period the export tax payable is (a) on the first 
     <lb/>1,000,000 tons or part thereof exported by said 
     <lb/>Company during any one year, 10 cents per ton; 
     <lb/>(b) on iron ore exported by the Company during 
     <lb/>one year in excess of 1,000,000 tons and not 
     <lb/>exceeding a further 500,000, tons the sum of 3 
     <lb/>cents per ton." ' 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <p>Now I remember after the general election of 
     <lb/>1928, when Major Cashin was Minister of 
     <lb/>Finance. I remember the great joy, his voice 
     <lb/>literally rang with pleasure, when he got up and 
     <lb/>announced that he had managed to collect 
     <lb/>$48,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> You are wrong. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, what was it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> $136,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I think my memory is very 
     <lb/>good. Well, that he had collected $136,000 from 
     <lb/>the Bell Island company in taxes that they ought 
     <lb/>to have paid and had not paid, arrears of taxes that 
     <lb/>the outgoing government had never bothered to 
     <lb/>collect. Major Cashin got it, and then in the fall 
     <lb/>of 1929 and the spring of 1930 they got this new 
     <lb/>act collecting 10 cents a ton on the first million 
     <lb/>tons, and 3 cents a ton thereover up to 1.5 million. 
     <lb/>I was not in that government, but I have been 
     <lb/>hearing since 1920 about taxing Bell Island, and 
     <lb/>I know it has been a filthy story, one of the 
    

            <cb/>
          

     filthiest in the history of this country. If it were 
     <lb/>
     written it would be pretty rotten reading. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There were unions, I remember leading a 
     <lb/>
     delegation of the very union you are referring to 
     <lb/>
     in 1926 before the Monroe cabinet. I was the 
     <lb/>
     spokesman for the entire afternoon, and I remem<lb break="no"/>ber that Chairman Bradley of the Convention 
     <lb/>
     here today was chairman of that meeting, and the 
     <lb/>
     father of Mr. Higgins was Attorney General, and 
     <lb/>
     he supported me from beginning to end that after<lb break="no"/>noon, and as a result they changed the 
     <lb/>
     Workrnen's Compensation Act. It was a bone of 
     <lb/>
     contention with the government from 1920 down 
     <lb/>
     to a very short while ago, that the tax ought to be 
     <lb/>
     50 cents a ton, and there was also a contention 
     <lb/>
     that it ought to be $1 a ton. Now I see it is down 
     <lb/>
     to 10 cents a ton on their first million, and 3 cents 
     <lb/>
     a ton over that to 1.5 million. What happens then? 
     <lb/>
     Free? Lovely. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> The highest is $115,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No income tax? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> No. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> They don't make the money, how 
     <lb/>
     can they pay the taxes? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I hope as president of that 
     <lb/>
     union you are not deluded and deceived by the 
     <lb/>
     accounts and talks of mining companies when 
     <lb/>
     they talk about profits. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> I don't want to get into an argu<lb break="no"/>ment, but here is the position. Mr. Smallwood is 
     <lb/>
     not right. I do feel that the tax, insofar as royalty 
     <lb/>
     is concerned on the export of our ore, is not 
     <lb/>
     sufficient — it could be more, but here is what 
     <lb/>
     we get. It is the workers get it now and not the 
     <lb/>
     government. We get the full extent of what they 
     <lb/>
     can pay, and we don't pass it to the government. 
     <lb/>
     The less we pay to the government the more we 
     <lb/>
     will have for ourselves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> With regard to this Bell Island situa<lb break="no"/>tion, and the criticism of them for not paying a 
     <lb/>
     higher royalty, or export tax on ore. In order to 
     <lb/>
     get to the bottom of this we have to go back to 
     <lb/>
     before 1919, when there were two companies 
     <lb/>
     operating. I think around 1920 they came 
     <lb/>
     together and called themselves the British Em<lb break="no"/>pire Steel Company — BESCO. They operated 
     <lb/>
     for a year or two and were always in financial 
     <lb/>
     difficulties. They cannot operate without Bell 
     <lb/>
     Island. Up to 1919 they were paying some profits 
     <lb/>
     taxes. There was a new government in 1920, and 
     <lb/>
     another in 1924, and when we came into office in 


            <pb n="482"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-04-11_Page_0482.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">482</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 1947</fw>
           

     1928 I found that they had not paid any royalties 
     <lb/>
     or profits taxes for a number of years. They are 
     <lb/>
     in financial difficulties today and if the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government foreclosed on them tomorrow they 
     <lb/>
     would be out of business. They owe the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government many millions of dollars. I am not 
     <lb/>
     defending the company, but it is bankrupt in a 
     <lb/>
     sense today. They are not making any money. 
     <lb/>
     The common stockholders in that company have 
     <lb/>
     not had a dividend for years. I forget what they 
     <lb/>
     owed the treasury — $2-300,000, They sent 
     <lb/>
     down representatives every spring looking for 
     <lb/>
     free export tax for the coming year, and the first 
     <lb/>
     year we were in office we objected, and finally 
     <lb/>
     made a deal whereby they paid 10 cents royalty 
     <lb/>
     up to one million tons and 3 cents up to 1.5 
     <lb/>
     million tons, and in addition they paid us 
     <lb/>
     $136,000 in settlement of back taxes. They paid 
     <lb/>
     $100,000 down and $12,000 each year till it was 
     <lb/>
     paid. The company has been struggling. In this 
     <lb/>
     report you will notice a letter signed by Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister Baldwin, wherein he indicated to the 
     <lb/>
     Prime Minister of that day that they were going 
     <lb/>
     to try to get some business for the Dominion Steel 
     <lb/>
     Company. They never got it. That 20,000 odd 
 

            <cb/>
        

     tons was all. They made certain promises to us 
     <lb/>
     but they did not carry them out. That is the 
     <lb/>
     position. I am glad to see now that Bell Island is 
     <lb/>
     going along well, but it cannot go along unless 
     <lb/>
     you have a prosperous Corporation. They have to 
     <lb/>
     produce at least 1.5 million tons a year in order 
     <lb/>
     to make it prosperous. Up to a month before die 
     <lb/>
     war started the Germans were buying one million 
     <lb/>
     tons a year. Great Britain bought none, Sydney 
     <lb/>
     from 6-700,000 tons, and if she continues to use 
     <lb/>
     that amount and Great Britain takes 750,000 tons 
     <lb/>
     it will be fine.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am glad Bell Island is going well, and I am 
     <lb/>
     glad Mr. Jackman is making such a good thing of 
     <lb/>
     the union on Bell Island. I hope Great Britain 
     <lb/>
     continues to take ore from us instead of going 
     <lb/>
     back to Sweden. If she can take 750,000 tons of 
     <lb/>
     ore a year to mix with that high grade ore which 
     <lb/>
     will suit the furnaces, it would be a great thing. 
     <lb/>
     One of their greatest excuses was that the docks 
     <lb/>
     could not take the big ships for ore, but suddenly 
     <lb/>
     all this changes, therefore they were kidding us 
     <lb/>
     in the past. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee of the whole rose and reported<lb/>progress, and the Convention adjourned]</hi>
            </p>

    <!-- GL, 2017-06-23, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
   
           <!-- <p>
     April 12, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Mining Committee:¹ 
     <lb/>
     Committee of Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Chairman, when we ad<lb break="no"/>journed yesterday afternoon the section on Bell 
     <lb/>
     Island had been read and there had been some 
     <lb/>
     discussion on it. I don't know if the discussion 
     <lb/>
     was completed or not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Ashbonme Has the Committee any figures 
     <lb/>
     on the 1946 production of ore at Bell Island? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> The Committee have only the 
     <lb/>figures in the report. I don't know if Mr. Jackman 
     <lb/>can give us any further information. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> The production for this year will 
     <lb/>
     be about the same as last year — roughly around 
     <lb/>
     1.5 million tons.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I mentioned this because 
     <lb/>
     yesterday the figure of $4 per ton was mentioned, 
     <lb/>
     and I see from the I945 figures that the same 
     <lb/>
     value for export was about $2.50 per ton. I was 
     <lb/>
     wondering if that $150 increase was brought 
     <lb/>
     about by the Canadian market paying a higher 
     <lb/>
     price than the English market, and if the English 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     market is prepared to pay a higher price. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> These are Major Cashin's figures, 
     <lb/>
     not mine. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> There is quite a difference be<lb break="no"/>tween $2.50 and $4, sir. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I quite realise that, but they are not 
     <lb/>
     the Committee's figures. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I was wondering if it was a 
     <lb/>
     matter of price, or if it is just quantity.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Possibly Major Cashin could ex<lb break="no"/>plain it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Those figures were given over two 
     <lb/>
     years. If my memory serves me correctly the 
     <lb/>
     amount exported in l945 would be much higher 
     <lb/>
     than in 1946 because the miners have since got 
     <lb/>
     an increase in pay and that would drive up the 
     <lb/>
     cost. The officials on Bell Island told me that the 
     <lb/>
     payroll would be approximately $4 million a 
     <lb/>
     year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That's when they have full produc- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     ¹Volume II:313. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
     </div>    </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>