<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-02-26"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-02-26">26 February 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="326"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0313.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0314.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0315.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0316.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0317.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0318.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0319.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0320.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0321.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0322.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0323.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0324.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0325.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0326.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-09">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0313">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0313.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0314">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0314.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0315">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0315.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0316">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0316.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0317">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0317.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0318">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0318.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0319">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0319.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0320">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0320.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0321">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0321.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0322">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0322.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0323">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0323.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0324">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0324.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0325">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0325.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0326">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0326.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="313"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0313.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">313</fw>
           
<!-- GL, 2017-06-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
 <!--<p>
     cial results to the people of the country as a 
     <lb/>
     whole. I endorse the work of the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     Industrial Development Board and recommend 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     that they receive all the encouragement possible. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>[The committee rose and reported that it had<lb/>passed the report. The Convention adjourned]<lb/>
            </p>-->
   

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     February 26, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   

            <p rendition="simple:centre">
  <emph>   Report of the Committee of the Convention which interviewed 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency the Governor in Commission<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref></emph>
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I did not know that I was to make this 
     <lb/>
     motion, and unfortunately I have not prepared 
     <lb/>
     any remarks. I simply move that this report be 
     <lb/>
     received and suggest that it be read to the House. 
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I second that motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried, and the report of the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee was read by the Assistant Secretary]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Mr. Chairman, when this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion decided to send a committee to confer with 
     <lb/>the Governor in Commission with the object of 
     <lb/>obtaining information relating to the sending of 
     <lb/>delegates to discuss the affairs of our country 
     <lb/>with the governments of Great Britain, Canada 
     <lb/>and the United States, I was one of those who 
     <lb/>voted against such a measure on the grounds that 
     <lb/>such a committee could not obtain any tangible 
     <lb/>results. Today, that Committee has presented its 
     <lb/>report and its nature is such as I anticipated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Over and over, I have given expression of my 
     <lb/>opinion that it is futile to entertain any notion that 
     <lb/>we can expect sincere co-operation from either 
     <lb/>the Dominions Office or its local agents, the 
     <lb/>Commission of Government. I have given 
     <lb/>definite instances of the obvious intention of our 
     <lb/>rulers to thwart and circumscribe the activities of 
     <lb/>this Convention — of their intention to divert and 
     <lb/>keep our thoughts and actions in the harmless and 
     <lb/>ineffectual channel of petty discussion. I have 
     <lb/>pointed out that as a country and a people we are 
     <lb/>being trifled with, that our rulers do not intend to 
     <lb/>allow us to interfere with the plans they have laid 
     <lb/>down. Time goes by, the treasury of our country 
     <lb/>is being squandered, and future generations are 
     <lb/>being harnessed with huge financial commit<lb break="no"/>ments... I say that under the present set-up, this 
     <lb/>Convention can do nothing to help our people or 
     <lb/>our country. If the doors of this Convention were 
     <lb/>closed tomorrow it would make no appreciable 
     <lb/>difference or have any effect on the already 
     <lb/>prepared plans of the Dominions Office. The 
     <lb/>future of this country has been planned out long 
     <lb/>ago in an office thousands of miles away. And if 
     <lb/>
      

            <cb/>
         

     Mr. Attlee can do it, he is going to see that we 
     <lb/>
     follow out his plans to the letter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The fate of this country does not rest with this 
     <lb/>
     Convention, but in the hands of the common 
     <lb/>
     people. We have been given the glory, but Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Attlee has kept the power. If there are any 
     <lb/>
     amongst us who cling to the vain hope that this 
     <lb/>
     Convention might be able to protect and 
     <lb/>
     safeguard the financial and political interests of 
     <lb/>
     this country, they should be long disillusioned. 
     <lb/>
     We have only to examine the report before us 
     <lb/>
     today, to obtain ample confirmation of what I say. 
     <lb/>
     We have the position where the members of this 
     <lb/>
     Convention, representing over 300,000 people, 
     <lb/>
     decide to ascertain the possibility of establishing 
     <lb/>
     economic relations with other countries, and in 
     <lb/>
     particular the United States. To quote the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion: "bearing in mind the present occupation of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland territory by the United States of 
     <lb/>
     America and the fact that free entry is accorded 
     <lb/>
     the USA for its imports into Newfoundland." 
     <lb/>
     Arising out of this resolution, a committee of the 
     <lb/>
     Convention asked the government if they can 
     <lb/>
     approach the USA with a view to making some 
     <lb/>
     profitable-arrangements in the interests of the 
     <lb/>
     country, and the answer to their request is a clear 
     <lb/>
     and definite refusal. We, the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, are told that the Dominions Office 
     <lb/>
     will not allow us to make any attempt to better 
     <lb/>
     our national conditions by opening negotiations 
     <lb/>
     with the United States. When the people of this 
     <lb/>
     country, through their appointed representatives 
     <lb/>
     are prevented from exercising the ordinary 
     <lb/>
     freedom of bargaining with another country, 
     <lb/>
     what name are we to put on this sort of thing? 
     <lb/>
     Could there ever be presented to us a stronger 
     <lb/>
     justification for having control of our own 
     <lb/>
     country? Imagine the position, if the British 
     <lb/>
     government tried to prevent Canada or Australia 
     <lb/>
     or any other colony or dominion from doing 
     <lb/>
     business with the United States. Would not the 
     <lb/>
     thing be regarded as so outrageous and improper 
  

<note xml:id="fn_01">1 Volume II:446. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
   

            <pb n="314"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0314.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">314</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
          

     as to be outside the realm of possibility? Yet this 
     <lb/>
     is the very outrageous procedure which is taking 
     <lb/>
     place in this oldest dominion today. But, in spite 
     <lb/>
     of even this, some people do not yet recognise the 
     <lb/>
     rough hand of dictatorship even when it is thrust 
     <lb/>
     in their face. As every man and woman in this 
     <lb/>
     island knows, if we could make some arrange<lb break="no"/>ments with the United States for the free entry of 
     <lb/>
     our fish into the great markets of that country, 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland could become unbelievably 
     <lb/>
     prosperous. Will any person disagree that this is 
     <lb/>
     a matter which should have been dealt with by 
     <lb/>
     the United Kingdom government on our behalf 
     <lb/>
     when these base deals were first discussed? But 
     <lb/>
     it is evident that the interests of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     were not even a secondary consideration. This is 
     <lb/>
     the error we would now like to correct, the 
     <lb/>
     blunder we would try to rectify, the national loss 
     <lb/>
     which we would attempt to make good. But when 
     <lb/>
     we try to make our future brighter and more 
     <lb/>
     prosperous, what do we meet? We come up 
     <lb/>
     against a wall of opposition and a denial of our 
     <lb/>
     rights to make any such effort on behalf of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Incidentally, there is another matter which 
     <lb/>
     comes to my mind at this point. If my memory 
     <lb/>
     serves me right, in the early days of this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion, the Chairman was asked if the Convention 
     <lb/>
     had the power to send a delegation from its mem<lb break="no"/>bership to the United States. On that question 
     <lb/>
     being directed by the Chairman to Professor 
     <lb/>
     Wheare, that gentleman stated that this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion had such powers. But today the Convention 
     <lb/>
     is informed through this report that we have no 
     <lb/>
     such power. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I have to correct you there. The 
     <lb/>
     ruling of the late Chairman and of Professor 
     <lb/>
     Wheare was that this Convention had a perfect 
     <lb/>
     right to send a delegation to the United States to 
     <lb/>
     consider the possibilities of joining up with that 
     <lb/>
     country, should the United States be so minded 
     <lb/>
     to receive any such delegation, but he gave no 
     <lb/>
     ruling on the question as to whether trade 
     <lb/>
     negotiations would be on the same basis. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> If we have power to send a delega<lb break="no"/>tion to the United States to discuss our political 
     <lb/>
     and economic future, it would certainly involve 
     <lb/>
     tariff arrangements concerning our fish. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That is a question upon which I 
     <lb/>
     do not feel called upon to give a ruling at the 
     <lb/>
     moment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I can understand that. I am sure if 
     <lb/>
     we sent a delegation to the United States, one of 
     <lb/>
     the first things we would discuss would be so 
     <lb/>
     much of our fish going into the market annually. 
     <lb/>
     However, what is the meaning of this divergent 
     <lb/>
     opinion? What lies behind these two contradic<lb break="no"/>tory statements? ls Professor Wheare right when 
     <lb/>
     he made that statement, or is the Commission 
     <lb/>
     right in denying his statement? What is the jus<lb break="no"/>tification for subjecting this Convention to two 
     <lb/>
     such conflicting opinions? If Professor Wheare 
     <lb/>
     is right; and I am inclined to believe he is, then 
     <lb/>
     the Commission is guilty of an inexcusable act in 
     <lb/>
     ignoring his findings. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In the matter of all these proposed negotia<lb break="no"/>tions with outside countries, we are simply told 
     <lb/>
     that we cannot move unless and until we get the 
     <lb/>
     permission of the Dominions Office, If it suits the 
     <lb/>
     Dominions Office and the interests of the British 
     <lb/>
     government to let us bargain, they will do so. But, 
     <lb/>
     if our doing so interferes with their own bargain<lb break="no"/>ing, then we are out of luck. This is an extraordi<lb break="no"/>nary situation, above ail in the country which 
     <lb/>
     witnessed the birth of the Atlantic Charter. We 
     <lb/>
     may be too close to the picture to see the full 
     <lb/>
     significance of this thing at the present time. But 
     <lb/>
     when our people look back and consider its 
     <lb/>
     implications, they will find it bears the same 
     <lb/>
     sinister marks as those things which killed the 
     <lb/>
     Bond-Blaine treaty, which gave the French the 
     <lb/>
     rights to our shorelines, which sacrificed our 
     <lb/>
     bases in the last decade. One thing these events 
     <lb/>
     have in common. In none of them were the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of Newfoundland put first. In none of them 
     <lb/>
     did she get a square deal. And she is not getting 
     <lb/>
     a square deal now. I go further and say that she 
     <lb/>
     will never get a square deal. She will never know 
     <lb/>
     liberty, never know a real freedom, never know 
     <lb/>
     either happiness or prosperity until such time as 
     <lb/>
     she has her own free government appointed by 
     <lb/>
     her own free people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Consider how different things would be today 
     <lb/>
     if we did have our own Newfoundland govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Would we, the representatives of the 
     <lb/>
     people, have to go on our knees and say, "Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Attlee, may we have your kind permission to do 
     <lb/>
     business on behalf of our country with the United 
     <lb/>
     States? May we ask this great country to give us 
     <lb/>
     some monetary return for the things which they 
     <lb/>
     got for nothing from you, the most precious asset 
     <lb/>
     in the keeping of any country — the sacred 
     

            <pb n="315"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0315.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">315</fw>
         

     sovereignty of our native soil?" Would New<lb break="no"/>foundland have to go like a slave approaching its 
     <lb/>
     master, and ask for permission to exercise the 
     <lb/>
     normal, God-given rights of a free people? Of 
     <lb/>
     course not Today, under a people's government, 
     <lb/>
     we would be in a position to fight tooth and nail 
     <lb/>
     for the protection of our country's interest. We 
     <lb/>
     would not have to beg — we would be able to 
     <lb/>
     demand.... We would be in a position to help our 
     <lb/>
     country in a tangible manner. We would be able 
     <lb/>
     to safeguard and further our trading interests. We 
     <lb/>
     could control the present squandermania which 
     <lb/>
     envisages in this one year the expenditure of the 
     <lb/>
     outrageous sum of nearly $40 million. We would 
     <lb/>
     be able to throw in the wastepaper basket, where 
     <lb/>
     it properly belongs, this Attlee reconstruction 
     <lb/>
     programme, which indicates spending some $60 
     <lb/>
     million other than current expenditure in the next 
     <lb/>
     ten years. These are only some of the rights we 
     <lb/>
     could exercise if we today possessed the priceless 
     <lb/>
     asset of independence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Speaking on the matter of expenditure I can<lb break="no"/>not help referring to a matter which properly 
     <lb/>
     belongs to the Financial Report, the evidence 
     <lb/>
     which has come before me and our Committee, 
     <lb/>
     which indicates beyond doubt that the financial 
     <lb/>
     policy of the present government is to dissipate 
     <lb/>
     the treasury wealth of this country in a manner so 
     <lb/>
     reckless and so unexplainable as to defy the un<lb break="no"/>derstanding of the ordinary Newfoundlander. 
     <lb/>
     Take the matter of the proposed expenditure for 
     <lb/>
     the present fiscal year ending on March 31, 1947, 
     <lb/>
     we find that it is the intention of the government 
     <lb/>
     to run our expenditure up to the colossal unheard- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     of total of nearly $40 million, more than half our 
     <lb/>
     total national debt; or if we deduct from that debt 
     <lb/>
     all our available cash surpluses, the sum of the 
     <lb/>
     national debt itself. I defy anybody else to find 
     <lb/>
     any logical or sane reason for this wild rampage 
     <lb/>
     and dissipation of a country's treasury, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly a country such as ours, and am forced to 
     <lb/>
     come to one conclusion: that it is part of a callous 
     <lb/>
     and deliberately planned campaign to bleed the 
     <lb/>
     finances of this country to such an extent that it 
     <lb/>
     will be impossible for us ever to stand on our own 
     <lb/>
     feet; to so weaken us, that we will have no other 
     <lb/>
     recourse, but to remain forever at subservient and 
     <lb/>
     penurious people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now if, in view of this extraordinary spending, 
     <lb/>
     there was any commensurate arrangements to 
     <lb/>
     increase our revenues, or if such expenditure 
 

            <cb/>
   
     were made with the assurance that there would 
     <lb/>
     be a corresponding increase in our revenues, one 
     <lb/>
     might be able to find some method in this ap<lb break="no"/>parent madness. But in our case it is clear there 
     <lb/>
     is no such justification. Another thing I would 
     <lb/>
     like to point out is that the proposed expenditure 
     <lb/>
     would, on the face of it, appear as the ordinary 
     <lb/>
     and necessary expenditure incidental to the 
     <lb/>
     proper operation of government, but such is not 
     <lb/>
     the case. Because out of this $40 million the sum 
     <lb/>
     of only $23 million is required for the administra<lb break="no"/>tion of our affairs. The balance is what I regard 
     <lb/>
     as a creative, an artificial expenditure, and to that 
     <lb/>
     extent the budget of the Commission is both false 
     <lb/>
     and misleading: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In a previous address on September 18, 1946, 
     <lb/>
     in commenting on the statement of Prime Mini<lb break="no"/>ster Attlee delivered in the House of Commons 
     <lb/>
     on December 11, 1945, I pointed out that he had 
     <lb/>
     indicated that the Commission government had a 
     <lb/>
     programme mapped out for Newfoundland, the 
     <lb/>
     working out of which would take two or three 
     <lb/>
     years, and would be pushed forward without in<lb break="no"/>terruption. Some of my listeners disagreed with 
     <lb/>
     the construction which 1 put on Mr. Attlee's 
     <lb/>
     remarks, which 1 said meant nothing more or less 
     <lb/>
     than that the Commission of Government in<lb break="no"/>tended to stay here several more years, regardless 
     <lb/>
     of such things as conventions or referendums. It 
     <lb/>
     was only a few days ago that I had my opinion 
     <lb/>
     confirmed by no less an authority than the present 
     <lb/>
     Commissioner for Finance, the Hon. Mr. James. 
     <lb/>
     When I reminded him of Mr. Attlee's remarks, 
     <lb/>
     he stated that was the programme at present in 
     <lb/>
     effect in Newfoundland and that it would be 
     <lb/>
     carried out in accordance with the statement.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName>, I may have possibly wandered 
     <lb/>
     slightly from my original intention of comment<lb break="no"/>ing on the report of this Committee, but I feel that 
     <lb/>
     the urgency of informing this Convention and the 
     <lb/>
     country of the matters to which I have referred is 
     <lb/>
     in itself a sufficient apology for any digression. 
     <lb/>
     As I see it, the only service we can be to the 
     <lb/>
     people of this country is to inform them of the 
     <lb/>
     political situation and the critical condition which 
     <lb/>
     faces us today. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> ....Mr. Chairman, I desire to make a 
     <lb/>
     few remarks with regards to this report follow<lb break="no"/>ing a motion made by the Hon. Mr. Job and duly 
     <lb/>
     passed. I spoke against that motion, particularly 
     <lb/>
     with regard to the method of seeking tariff con<lb break="no"/>
         
            <pb n="316"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0316.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">316</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
          
     cessions from the United States of America, and 
     <lb/>
     also against the part relating to the basis for 
     <lb/>
     federal union with the Dominion of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Careful consideration of this report must indi<lb break="no"/>cate that those who voted against the passing of 
     <lb/>
     said motion were far from wrong in the criticisms 
     <lb/>
     we directed at it. I can well understand Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Job' s endeavour to get tariff concessions from the 
     <lb/>
     USA for our fish and fish products, and can 
     <lb/>
     assure Mr. Job that every member of this Con<lb break="no"/>vention is just as anxious as he is, albeit, some of 
     <lb/>
     us must agree with the attitude taken by the 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government, that the question is 
     <lb/>
     the active concern of the government of the day; 
     <lb/>
     who further point out and rightly so, that since in 
     <lb/>
     April of this year representatives of the majority 
     <lb/>
     of states forming the United Nations will meet at 
     <lb/>
     Geneva to discuss the formation of an interna<lb break="no"/>tional trade organisation, with a view to agree<lb break="no"/>ment on tariff and trade questions, it is scarcely 
     <lb/>
     likely that at this time a participating state would 
     <lb/>
     entertain proposals for separate tariff arrange<lb break="no"/>ments. Furthermore we understand from this 
     <lb/>
     report that representatives from Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     will be present at this conference 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Turning now to clause three of the resolution 
     <lb/>
     and report thereon, it appears that the Commis<lb break="no"/>sion of Government would be prepared to find 
     <lb/>
     out from the Government of Canada whether the 
     <lb/>
     said government would receive a delegation from 
     <lb/>
     the Convention to consider what would be a fair 
     <lb/>
     and equitable basis for federal union. You will 
     <lb/>
     note they are careful to point out that the words 
     <lb/>
     "or what other fiscal, political or economic arran<lb break="no"/>gements may be possible" should notbe included 
     <lb/>
     in any inquiry, or in the terms of reference of any 
     <lb/>
     delegation to Canada, as they say, and rightly so, 
     <lb/>
     that these are matters entirely for discussion be<lb break="no"/>tween governments. If these arrangements can<lb break="no"/>not be discussed by a delegation from this 
     <lb/>
     Convention with the Government of Canada, I 
     <lb/>
     fail to see how any fair and equitable basis for 
     <lb/>
     union can be arrived at by any other consult<lb break="no"/>ations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When I ask myself why this third section 
     <lb/>
     relative to Canada was introduced in Mr. Job's 
     <lb/>
     motion, I must seek out the grounds on which 
     <lb/>
     such an effort on our part should be based and we 
     <lb/>
     ought all to do some right thinking in the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Why are we here? The answer is, "the Con<lb break="no"/>
           
            <cb/>
        vention Act". To this act we must go to get the 
     <lb/>
     terms of reference. We are told there to consider 
     <lb/>
     and discuss amongst ourselves the financial and 
     <lb/>
     economic conditions of our country, having due 
     <lb/>
     regard to the degree which the wartime prosperity 
     <lb/>
     has affected same. Then based on our findings as 
     <lb/>
     to whether or not the country is self-supporting, 
     <lb/>
     to consider and recommend forms of government 
     <lb/>
     to be recommended to the Dominions Office, any 
     <lb/>
     one of which might be suitable to our apparently 
     <lb/>
     peculiar needs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     They, then, in their omniscient wisdom, are to 
     <lb/>
     decide which forms of government they will 
     <lb/>
     place on the ballot paper at a referendum to be 
     <lb/>
     held at some time in the hazy future. If the Con<lb break="no"/>vention Act means anything, it means that and 
     <lb/>
     that only. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let us go back to the Amulrec report.<ref target="#fn_02">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Everyone in this country is familiar by now with 
     <lb/>
     the implications of his several recommendations. 
     <lb/>
     We have had a dozen years under their benign 
     <lb/>
     influence. But the recommendation to which I 
     <lb/>
     chiefly wish to refer will be found in section 634, 
     <lb/>
     subsection 4(g) and it reads as follows: "It would 
     <lb/>
     be understood that, as soon as the Island's dif<lb break="no"/>ficulties are overcome and the country is again 
     <lb/>
     self-supporting, responsible government <hi rendition="simple:italic">on re<lb break="no"/>quest from the people of Newfoundland</hi>, would 
     <lb/>
     be restored". Up to a year or so ago, few people 
     <lb/>
     if any in this country ever doubted that promise. 
     <lb/>
     On the 17 February, 1934, the new Letters Patent 
     <lb/>
     under the then new system of government were 
     <lb/>
     read in the ballroom of the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     Hotel.... These Letters Patent of 1934, which 
     <lb/>
     suspended the Letters Patent of 1876 and 1905, 
     <lb/>
     were granted to us by His Majesty George V. 
     <lb/>
     Paragraph four promised the highest dignitaries 
     <lb/>
     of this land that "We are graciously pleased to 
     <lb/>
     suspend the aforesaid Letters Patent which will 
     <lb/>
     provide for the administration of the said Island, 
     <lb/>
     until such time as it may become self-supporting 
     <lb/>
     again, on the basis of the recommendations 
     <lb/>
     which are contained in the report of the Royal 
     <lb/>
     Commission, appointed by us on the 17th of 
     <lb/>
     February 1933". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     You will remember that a year ago, the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary of State for the Dominions, in the 
     <lb/>
     House of Lords, stated that machinery was being 
     <lb/>
     set up to find out the will of the people of this 
     <lb/>
     country, and that they would be given an oppor<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_02">1 <hi rendition="simple:italic">Newfoundland Royal Commission 1933, Report</hi> (Cmd. 4480, 1933).</note> 

            <pb n="317"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0317.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">317</fw>
     

     tunity to select a form of government suitable to 
     <lb/>
     their needs. I do not believe that up to that time 
     <lb/>
     there was ever any thought in the mind of the 
     <lb/>
     British House of Commons of any other form of 
     <lb/>
     government than the form which we now enjoy, 
     <lb/>
     that is Commission of Government, or respon<lb break="no"/>sible government 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I take you back to September 2, 1940: France 
     <lb/>
     had fallen in June, and Great Britain stood alone 
     <lb/>
     against the might of Hitler's Germany. The 
     <lb/>
     people of North America realised their danger, 
     <lb/>
     should Britain fall; they consulted the British 
     <lb/>
     government and began to look to their own defen<lb break="no"/>ses. On the above-mentioned date, the Marquis 
     <lb/>
     of Lothian wrote to Mr. Cordell Hull, and told 
     <lb/>
     him that in View of the interest of His Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     Government in the national security of the United 
     <lb/>
     States, and their desire to strengthen the ability of 
     <lb/>
     the United States to co-operate with the other 
     <lb/>
     nations of the Americas in the defense of the 
     <lb/>
     western hemisphere, that His Majesty's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would secure the grant to the United States 
     <lb/>
     freely and without consideration for the lease of 
     <lb/>
     naval and air bases on the Avalon Peninsula and 
     <lb/>
     the southern coast of Newfoundland. The agree<lb break="no"/>ment for this lease was signed on 27 March l94l, 
     <lb/>
     and accompanying this agreement, and forming 
     <lb/>
     part of it was a letter from Mr. Winston Churchill 
     <lb/>
     to Mr. Winant. It has such significance that I give 
     <lb/>
     it in full to refresh your memories: "...it is the 
     <lb/>
     intention of the Government of the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom that, upon the resumption by New<lb break="no"/>foundland of the constitutional status held by it 
     <lb/>
     prior to the 16th February 1934, the words 'the 
     <lb/>
     government of the United Kingdom', wherever 
     <lb/>
     they occur in relation to a provision applicable to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland in the said agreement, shall be 
     <lb/>
     taken to mean, so far as Newfoundland is con<lb break="no"/>cerned, the government of Newfoundland, and 
     <lb/>
     the agreement shall then be construed according<lb break="no"/>ly..." I ask you, was there any idea in Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Churchill's mind, at that date, but that we would 
     <lb/>
     eventually resume our former status?.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The wording of the Convention Act, the spas<lb break="no"/>modic and well-timed despatches from across the 
     <lb/>
     Cabot Strait, and the almost demoniacal fury of 
     <lb/>
     some of the protagonists of confederation in this 
     <lb/>
     country, will have convinced you that there is 
     <lb/>
     more in this thing than first strikes the eye. It is 
     <lb/>
     international and not a local issue. The war ended 
     <lb/>
     in 1945; the Americans are at Fort Pepperell, 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
        
     Argentia and Stephenville; the Canadians are at 
     <lb/>
     Goose Bay. The diplomats of the world are writ<lb break="no"/>ing the peace terms. Great Britain has had her 
     <lb/>
     economy disrupted, she seeks a loan of $3.5 
     <lb/>
     million from the United States and gets it. Canada 
     <lb/>
     lends her $1,250 million. Great Britain financial<lb break="no"/>ly is deeply obligated. The Big Four are en<lb break="no"/>deavouring to write the peace treaties; Russia and 
     <lb/>
     the United States have not often been in accord, 
     <lb/>
     neither on the peace treaties, in the United Na<lb break="no"/>tions effort, nor with regard to disarmament; so 
     <lb/>
     much so that the United States and Canada start 
     <lb/>
     negotiations for a mutual defence pact. What 
     <lb/>
     more natural, than that the future status of New<lb break="no"/>foundland should be taken into consideration. 
     <lb/>
     "Would it not be better", some might say, in view 
     <lb/>
     of this mutual defence pact which, by the way, 
     <lb/>
     was signed a few days ago, "if Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     was completely under the control of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada?" I say again that our status is 
     <lb/>
     now an international issue; hence the Convention 
     <lb/>
     Act as is, and hence the bait which is being 
     <lb/>
     constantly held out to us by emissaries from 
     <lb/>
     across the water. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But Britain has pledged her word to us by the 
     <lb/>
     Letters Patent, 1934, and we demand that if we 
     <lb/>
     are to go into confederation with Canada, we 
     <lb/>
     shall go only at the instance of a duly elected 
     <lb/>
     government of our own with a clearly defined 
     <lb/>
     directive from the people of this country. We 
     <lb/>
     know that there has grown up in England, and 
     <lb/>
     hence in the dominions, what is known as the 
     <lb/>
     doctrine of mandate, which has been sanctioned 
     <lb/>
     by. the highest authority. That doctrine is that 
     <lb/>
     parliament cannot legislate on a new question of 
     <lb/>
     vital importance without a mandate from the 
     <lb/>
     people. It was the breach of this mandate which 
     <lb/>
     gave us Commission of Government. Mr. Alder<lb break="no"/>dice assured the people, when seeking election, 
     <lb/>
     that his government would seek from the British 
     <lb/>
     government some way out of our difficulties, but 
     <lb/>
     he further assured the people there would be no 
     <lb/>
     change in our constitutional status until the ques<lb break="no"/>tion had been submitted to them by way of 
     <lb/>
     referendum; that was not done. But was not the 
     <lb/>
     question of the suspension of our dominion status 
     <lb/>
     of vital importance to Newfoundland? Was it not 
     <lb/>
     a question of vital importance to the British 
     <lb/>
     people? And yet we know that neither the British 
     <lb/>
     government nor our own referred the matter to 
     <lb/>
     their people, nor did they have any mandate from 
   

            <pb n="318"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0318.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">318</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
         

     them before taking such a drastic step. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It was tragedy enough that we could not raise 
     <lb/>
     by means of revenue $8-10 million to carry on, 
     <lb/>
     especially when $5 million would have to be 
     <lb/>
     ear-marked for the bondholders of our debt; but 
     <lb/>
     was it not an ignominy when Britain said, "Yes, 
     <lb/>
     allow us to suspend your constitution, and we will 
     <lb/>
     feed your people on six cents a day; but you will 
     <lb/>
     have it restored when you become self-support<lb break="no"/>ing again, if you ask for it". How were we meant 
     <lb/>
     to ask for it? "Oh, you may elect a national 
     <lb/>
     convention. They will find out if you are self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting." But did they say to our people, "If your 
     <lb/>
     convention finds you self-supporting, they will 
     <lb/>
     have authority from you to request the restoration 
     <lb/>
     of your former constitution". No, they say, "If 
     <lb/>
     they find your country self-supporting, they may 
     <lb/>
     suggest to the Dominions Office forms of 
     <lb/>
     government suitable to your needs". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Would it be pertinent to ask Great Britain what 
     <lb/>
     she understands by the words "self-supporting"? 
     <lb/>
     I am sorry to raise this point, for I am as loyal to 
     <lb/>
     my king and empire as any man in Britain today. 
     <lb/>
     Who are we, gentlemen, to recommend forms of 
     <lb/>
     government? Do the men who framed the Con<lb break="no"/>vention Act know of any better form than that in 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain today? We could recommend Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government; that's the latest experi<lb break="no"/>ment in our great British Empire. We could 
     <lb/>
     recommend representative government, were it 
     <lb/>
     not for the fact that it has been tried and failed 
     <lb/>
     miserably the world over. We could recommend 
     <lb/>
     that we might come up a peg from where we are 
     <lb/>
     today and suggest a crown colony; and we could 
     <lb/>
     recommend any one or more of the 2,000 dif<lb break="no"/>ferent known forms of government that have 
     <lb/>
     been tried and failed through the ages. We can do 
     <lb/>
     all that, but do we not know that the British 
     <lb/>
     system so far has no equal, or why try to force it 
     <lb/>
     on India or Burma? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Some people have concurred that this Con<lb break="no"/>vention may even send a delegation to Canada; 
     <lb/>
     in fact, it seems to be the idea embodied in the 
     <lb/>
     motion and report. Let me quote you section 146 
     <lb/>
     of the British North America Act, 1867: "It shall 
     <lb/>
     be lawful for the Queen on addresses from the 
     <lb/>
     Houses of the Parliament of Canada, and from the 
     <lb/>
     Houses of the respective Legislatures of the 
     <lb/>
     Colonies or Provinces of Newfoundland, Prince 
     <lb/>
     Edward Island, and British Columbia to admit 
   

            <cb/>
      
     those Colonies or Provinces, or any of them into 
     <lb/>
     the Union on such terms and conditions in each 
     <lb/>
     case as are in the addresses expressed and as the 
     <lb/>
     Queen thinks fit to approve, subject to the 
     <lb/>
     Provisions of this Act..."<ref target="#fn_03">[1]</ref> You will note that it is 
     <lb/>
     only lawful for the Queen to admit us into union 
     <lb/>
     after receiving an address from the House of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature. And yet there are some people who 
     <lb/>
     want to get "the terms". What terms? Are they 
     <lb/>
     already drawn up? Or are they to be unpigeon- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     holed from the closets of 1895 and 1867? Are 
     <lb/>
     there no terms on our side? Not in the minds of 
     <lb/>
     some people who wanted to hike off to Canada 
     <lb/>
     before we had even started our investigations.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Says the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Ottawa Journal</hi>: "Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     owes $100 million, she is facing bankruptcy, and 
     <lb/>
     wants to get in out of the wet; she cannot take it, 
     <lb/>
     she cannot face the future". And yet "the terms" 
     <lb/>
     will be so good, I'm told. I tell you there are no 
     <lb/>
     terms; confederation must essentially be a ques<lb break="no"/>tion of bargaining on both sides.... If we are to 
     <lb/>
     unite with Canada, we must do it like men who 
     <lb/>
     believe we have something to contribute to the 
     <lb/>
     partnership and, mind you, we have confeder<lb break="no"/>ation if the people of this country say so, <hi rendition="simple:italic">and only 
     <lb/>
     if they say so</hi>. How may they say so? I submit 
     <lb/>
     there is only one way, and that is under section 
     <lb/>
     146 of the BNA Act and the doctrine of mandate 
     <lb/>
     and that is embodied in the truth that Parliament 
     <lb/>
     ought not to adopt any far-reaching measure 
     <lb/>
     without a mandate from the country. But you say, 
     <lb/>
     "We have no parliament." Ah yes, we have, for 
     <lb/>
     as soon as our constitution comes out of its state 
     <lb/>
     of suspended animation, the voice of the people 
     <lb/>
     can be heard on the issue.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The process of entering into federal union is 
     <lb/>
     clear cut. First you have to have two self-govern<lb break="no"/>ing entities; second they must have much in com<lb break="no"/>mon, and each must have something to offer the 
     <lb/>
     other. One may be wealthy, but lacking some<lb break="no"/>thing which she needs and which the other, who 
     <lb/>
     may not be so wealthy, possesses. Third, the 
     <lb/>
     people of both countries must he made duly 
     <lb/>
     aware of the situation. In the fourth place, the 
     <lb/>
     people of both countries must authorise their 
     <lb/>
     respective governments to explore the pos<lb break="no"/>sibilities of a fair partnership. Fifth, each govern<lb break="no"/>ment must then report back to its people and get 
     <lb/>
     their final approval, by way of the referendum or 
     <lb/>
     otherwise. There is no other way, except by coer<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_03">1 Great Britain. <hi rendition="simple:italic">British North America Act</hi>, (30 &amp; 31 Victoria, c3, 1867).</note> 
 

            <pb n="319"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0319.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">319</fw>
           

     cion or trickery. Either of these latter methods is 
     <lb/>
     likely to prove disastrous Witness the case of 
     <lb/>
     PEI, a separate geographical unit like ourselves, 
     <lb/>
     whose prime minister, 72 years after union with 
     <lb/>
     Canada, publicly declared a few years ago, "The 
     <lb/>
     real trouble is, we shouldn't be part of Canada at 
     <lb/>
     all". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am quite aware that there are a number of 
     <lb/>
     people in favour of union with Canada; so there 
     <lb/>
     were in 1867 and in 1895, and I am in no way 
     <lb/>
     trying to prevent those people, who are undoub<lb break="no"/>tedly loyal Newfoundlanders, from getting what 
     <lb/>
     has been called "the terms", but I do contend that 
     <lb/>
     these terms must be obtained by the proper con<lb break="no"/>stitutional means. I am also aware that there are 
     <lb/>
     more people who would prefer a closer associa<lb break="no"/>tion with the USA. There are also constitutional 
     <lb/>
     means to attain that end. We know, too, that a 
     <lb/>
     great number of our people are not anxious to get 
     <lb/>
     farther away from the mother country, and par<lb break="no"/>ticularly so when that mother country, having 
     <lb/>
     sacrificed her resources to save the civilisation 
     <lb/>
     which we enjoy is for the moment in dire distress. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There is much more that could be said about 
     <lb/>
     this issue, but I shall content myself with once 
     <lb/>
     again registering a continuing opposition to the 
     <lb/>
     idea of this Convention sending any delegation 
     <lb/>
     to Canada at this or any future time on the follow<lb break="no"/>ing grounds. First, our terms of reference give us 
     <lb/>
     no such authority. Second, the people who sent 
     <lb/>
     us here gave us no such authority. Third, as 
     <lb/>
     "terms" always envisage bargaining, that bar<lb break="no"/>gaining must be done by duly appointed repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives with the mandatory power of the 
     <lb/>
     people behind them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We come now to the question of sending a 
     <lb/>
     delegation to the United Kingdom. Against this 
     <lb/>
     idea there can be no objection because there are 
     <lb/>
     many matters about which the Convention should 
     <lb/>
     have a clearer picture than we have. To that end, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman, I beg leave to lay on the table a 
     <lb/>
     notice of motion relative thereto: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Whereas it has been intimated to this Con<lb break="no"/>vention by His Excellency the Governor in 
     <lb/>
     Commission, that he is prepared to forward 
     <lb/>
     to the Government of the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     any enquiries from this Convention respect<lb break="no"/>ing financial and fiscal relationships which 
     <lb/>
     may be expected in the event that the people 
     <lb/>
     of this country at the proposed forthcoming 
     <lb/>
     referendum to be held in Newfoundland, 
    

            <cb/>
          
     should decide on any of the following forms 
     <lb/>
     of government: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. Commission of Government in its 
     <lb/>
     present form; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. A revised form of Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. Responsible government; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. Any other suitable form of government; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And Whereas His Excellency has further 
     <lb/>
     informed us that should the Convention re<lb break="no"/>quest discussion of these questions with the 
     <lb/>
     Government of the United Kingdom by a 
     <lb/>
     delegation from the Convention members, 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency will enquire and inform the 
     <lb/>
     Convention whether such a delegation would 
     <lb/>
     be received; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And Whereas in the event that such a 
     <lb/>
     delegation shall proceed to England for the 
     <lb/>
     purpose aforesaid the Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government has undertaken to give all pos<lb break="no"/>sible assistance in making transport and other 
     <lb/>
     arrangements for the delegates; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And Whereas this Convention, in view of 
     <lb/>
     the importance of the matters hereunder out<lb break="no"/>lined are of opinion that such a delegation 
     <lb/>
     should be despatched; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now Therefore Be It Resolved that this 
     <lb/>
     Convention request His Excellency the 
     <lb/>
     Governor in Commission to acquaint His 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's Government in the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom of their desire to send a delegation 
     <lb/>
     consisting of the Chairman and six of its 
     <lb/>
     members to the United Kingdom at the ear<lb break="no"/>liest possible moment to discuss with the said 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom government the various 
     <lb/>
     matters set forth hereunder; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Be It Further Resolved that as soon as His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency the Governor in Commission in<lb break="no"/>forms us of the willingness of His Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     Government in the United Kingdom to ac<lb break="no"/>cede to our request said delegation shall be 
     <lb/>
     elected by secret ballot; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And Be It Finally Resolved that the Steer<lb break="no"/>ing Committee be requested to prepare a 
     <lb/>
     detailed statement of the questions to be sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to His Majesty's Government in the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom; such statement of ques<lb break="no"/>tions to be submitted to the National Conven<lb break="no"/>tion for confirmation before being delivered 
     <lb/>
     to His Excellency the Governor in Commis<lb break="no"/>sion for transmission to the United Kingdom. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="320"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0320.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">320</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
            
<p>
     Matters to be Discussed by the Delegation with 
     <lb/>
     the United Kingdom Government 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. National debt; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. Military, naval and air bases in this 
     <lb/>
     country; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. Gander airport; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. Interest-free loans; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. Any matters relating to the future eco<lb break="no"/>nomic position of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     </p></quote>


            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That portion of your address 
     <lb/>which contains, apparently, notice of motion can<lb break="no"/>not be included on the record at this stage. A 
     <lb/>notice of motion must be given at another time. 
     <lb/>You may renew your notice of motion before the 
     <lb/>House rises. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There are one or two things I 
     <lb/>would like to say in reply to Major Cashin and 
     <lb/>Mr. Hollett. With one thing Major Cashin said, I 
     <lb/>am in the deepest and profoundest agreement. I 
     <lb/>jotted down his words: "The fate of this country 
     <lb/>does not rest with this Convention, but with the 
     <lb/>common people.".... The fate of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>will be decided by the people of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>when they vote in the national referendum some<lb break="no"/>time this present year, and not in the dim, hazy 
     <lb/>future that Mr. Hollett has referred to. All this 
     <lb/>Convention can do is what the law gives it 
     <lb/>authority to do; and the authority is the National 
     <lb/>Convention Act under which we were all elected. 
     <lb/>Two pieces of authority we got when elected — 
     <lb/>one, to look into the condition of the country, 
     <lb/>economically and financially. How is she likely 
     <lb/>to shape up in the next 15 or 20 years? The second 
     <lb/>piece of authority was this; that having taken as 
     <lb/>good a look as we know how, to suggest and 
     <lb/>recommend to the Dominions Office a number of 
     <lb/>forms of government to be laid before the New<lb break="no"/>foundland people; so that they will be able to 
     <lb/>decide for themselves, what form of government 
     <lb/>they think they want. That is quite a lot of 
     <lb/>authority.... In connection with the forms of 
     <lb/>government that we may recommend, Mr. Job 
     <lb/>very wisely and in the spirit of statesmanship, 
     <lb/>brought into this house a couple of weeks ago a 
     <lb/>motion. And what did that motion say? That it is 
     <lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">essential</hi> that this National Convention take im<lb break="no"/>mediate steps to find out what Britain might be 
     <lb/>prepared to do for us if we went on under Com<lb break="no"/>mission government or if we went back to 
     <lb/>responsible government or if we had some other 
     <lb/>kind of government. And it was essential for us 
   

            <cb/>
           
     to find out also what fair and equitable basis there 
     <lb/>
     might be for any federal union of Canada and 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland.... Mr. Job's motion went on to 
     <lb/>
     say that we should appoint a committee to go and 
     <lb/>
     meet the Governor and the Commission to get 
     <lb/>
     their advice as to what steps we can take to get 
     <lb/>
     that information. The Committee met the govern<lb break="no"/>ment and they gave us their advice. Their advice 
     <lb/>
     was, "Send over and ask the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Britain what they are prepared to do; with regard 
     <lb/>
     to finding out what fair and equitable basis there 
     <lb/>
     may be for a union of Newfoundland and Canada, 
     <lb/>
     send to the Government of Canada and ask 
     <lb/>
     them." They went further and said, "If you want 
     <lb/>
     to send a delegation to London and a delegation 
     <lb/>
     to Ottawa, the Convention should ask us to find 
     <lb/>
     out whether the British government and the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government would receive such 
     <lb/>
     delegations, If they say they will, we will pay the 
     <lb/>
     expenses of those two delegations." That is the 
     <lb/>
     report that has come in here. Major Cashin pays 
     <lb/>
     little attention to the advice of the government. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Hollett pays even less. Mr. Hollett is 
     <lb/>
     prepared to send one to London, but not to send 
     <lb/>
     one to Ottawa. Major Cashin has not made it clear 
     <lb/>
     whether he is in favour of sending one delegation 
     <lb/>
     or another. This Convention has gone on record, 
     <lb/>
     with a small number of us voting against it, not 
     <lb/>
     including myself, in adopting Mr. Job's motion, 
     <lb/>
     to say we consider it essential that immediate 
     <lb/>
     steps be taken to secure this information; also, 
     <lb/>
     whether it is possible to take up discussions with 
     <lb/>
     the United States. In justice to the Commission 
     <lb/>
     of Government, I must refer to what Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin said about that. He states the government 
     <lb/>
     says this business of tariffs, trade treaties and 
     <lb/>
     trade are matters for government and govern<lb break="no"/>ment, they should be handled through diplomatic 
     <lb/>
     channels. Then he says the late Chairman and 
     <lb/>
     Professor Wheare both said that you can send a 
     <lb/>
     delegation to Washington. Then you, sir, inter<lb break="no"/>rupted him and pointed out that what the late 
     <lb/>
     Chairman and Professor Wheare referred to was 
     <lb/>
     a delegation going to the States, not to deal with 
     <lb/>
     customs or trade matters, but to deal with the 
     <lb/>
     federal union of Newfoundland and the United 
     <lb/>
     States. He acknowledged this, then went straight 
     <lb/>
     on and argued it was inconsistent. Professor 
     <lb/>
     Wheare, he continued, said we could and the 
     <lb/>
     government says we cannot. Two entirely dif<lb break="no"/>ferent kinds of delegations were referred to; one 
    

            <pb n="321"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0321.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> 
  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">321</fw>
          

     to deal with trade and tariffs and the other pos<lb break="no"/>sible federal union. Of course the government is 
     <lb/>
     right! When we come to talk about making a tariff 
     <lb/>
     deal with the United States, that is a matter for 
     <lb/>
     the Government of Newfoundland, whatever that 
     <lb/>
     may be, not the Convention. We were not elected 
     <lb/>
     as a government to do the job of the government; 
     <lb/>
     not elected to make a trade treaty or get tariff 
     <lb/>
     concessions with the United States.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Suppose we had responsible government in 
     <lb/>
     office today and we wanted to take up with the 
     <lb/>
     United States this question of trade tariffs and 
     <lb/>
     concessions, could our responsible government 
     <lb/>
     do it? Yes! On two conditions. First, if Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain were willing. Up to the last minute we had 
     <lb/>
     responsible government in 1934, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Newfoundland could not go gallivanting 
     <lb/>
     up to make trade treaties on its own. If we had 
     <lb/>
     signed the Statute of Westminster we would be 
     <lb/>
     able to do it. But we never signed that. In 1920 
     <lb/>
     when Sir Richard Squires wanted a treaty with 
     <lb/>
     Spain and when Sir Robert Bond wanted a treaty 
     <lb/>
     with the United States, they had to do it through 
     <lb/>
     diplomatic channels, that is the British ambas<lb break="no"/>sador, and the British foreign minister. That is 
     <lb/>
     how we would have to deal today if we had 
     <lb/>
     responsible government, only if the US were 
     <lb/>
     willing to discuss the matter. Why will they not 
     <lb/>
     discuss it? Because in April they are having an 
     <lb/>
     international conference and until that is held, 
     <lb/>
     they have no intention whatever of making any 
     <lb/>
     separate deals with individual nations.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     So the government gave us this advice, and 
     <lb/>
     you have to give credit where credit is due. They 
     <lb/>
     said this matter of trade concessions, allowing 
     <lb/>
     our fish to go in at a lower rate of duty, ought to 
     <lb/>
     be dealt with between government and govern<lb break="no"/>ment; not between the Convention and the 
     <lb/>
     Government of the United States.... I do not like 
     <lb/>
     the Commission of Government. At least, if 
     <lb/>
     anyone comes in here to paint them as a pack of 
     <lb/>
     scoundrels, let us have proof! Then Major Cashin 
     <lb/>
     read out something Mr. Attlee said, adding 
     <lb/>
     "when I made that statement a lot of the members 
     <lb/>
     did not agree with my interpretation of it." The 
     <lb/>
     interpretation was this: Mr. Attlee said and could 
     <lb/>
     mean only that they were here for another three 
     <lb/>
     years. You can hold your Convention and 
     <lb/>
     referendum; they are going to be here for another 
     <lb/>
     three years.... Where is there a scrap of evidence 
     <lb/>
     that the Commission is going to be here another 
   
<cb/>

     three years? This year, 1947, there will be a 
     <lb/>
     national referendum, no doubt about it. There is 
     <lb/>
     not a man here but in his heart knows that in 1947 
     <lb/>
     there is going to be a referendum. We do not 
     <lb/>
     know when it will be. If we can get the job 
     <lb/>
     finished in the next two or three months.... I say 
     <lb/>
     here and now that some month this year there is 
     <lb/>
     going to be a referendum and the people will 
     <lb/>
     decide what kind of government we will have. 
     <lb/>
     "Oh!" they say, "you may have the referendum 
     <lb/>
     but what guarantee have we that Dominions Of<lb break="no"/>fice, this evil genius of Newfoundland, this oc<lb break="no"/>topus on the back of the world, will put on the 
     <lb/>
     ballot what we recommend?" Trash and nonv 
     <lb/>
     sense! Whatever we recommend within reason, 
     <lb/>
     unless it is some cockeyed foolish thing, they will 
     <lb/>
     put on the ballot and the people will get their 
     <lb/>
     chance to vote it down or up. They are the bosses. 
     <lb/>
     Then someone says, "What guarantee have we 
     <lb/>
     that the Government of Britain will give us the 
     <lb/>
     kind of government we vote for?" We have this 
     <lb/>
     guarantee.... They have said categorically that the 
     <lb/>
     kind of government the people vote for they will 
     <lb/>
     have. What is all this nonsense about? Finally, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Hollett... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I rise to a point of order. Was it not 
     <lb/>
     decided here that the use of a person's name was 
     <lb/>
     not to be tolerated? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You are right. It is improper, 
     <lb/>
     strictly speaking, to use a person's name. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I shall refer to him as the junior 
     <lb/>
     member for Grand Falls. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That would be in order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I would like to know where you get 
     <lb/>
     your authority to refer to me as the junior member 
     <lb/>
     for Grand Falls? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I thought I was paying you a 
     <lb/>
     compliment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I wish to advise the present speaker 
     <lb/>
     who has the floor that if my name is bandied 
     <lb/>
     about as was Major Cashin's, i have no privileges 
     <lb/>
     in this House, but I have privileges outside. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I do not wish to hear anything 
     <lb/>
     outside this House. I repeat, in your objection to 
     <lb/>
     the use of your name, you are correct. I have told 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood he must not name you by name, 
     <lb/>
     but he must identify you. Proceed, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The member for Grand Falls 
     <lb/>
     who just sat down. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> Is this a mock parliament? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="322"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0322.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">322</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Do you rise to a point in order? 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Fudge Yes, there is too much laughing and 
     <lb/>
     noise going on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That is true. Will the people in 
     <lb/>
     the gallery please remember that there is no dis<lb break="no"/>order permitted in this House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The member for Grand Falls 
     <lb/>
     gave us the benefit of his researches into the 
     <lb/>
     British North America Act, which is the constitu<lb break="no"/>tion of Canada. He quotes section 146.... It is 
     <lb/>
     surprising to me, the keen interest he has been 
     <lb/>
     showing in this matter of confederation... Per<lb break="no"/>haps he wants us to join the union. Let us take 
     <lb/>
     him at his word. Let us admit that is the way to 
     <lb/>
     join. I see the second senior member for St. 
     <lb/>
     J ohn's West looking at me — I may not mention 
     <lb/>
     his name — I think in the back of his mind he is 
     <lb/>
     hoping strongly we will have our own elected 
     <lb/>
     government in this country. So am I. Let us trace 
     <lb/>
     it. The delegation goes over to the British govern<lb break="no"/>ment and asks them to state what they are 
     <lb/>
     prepared to do for us if anything. They will tell 
     <lb/>
     us. We send a delegation to Ottawa and ask them 
     <lb/>
     what they are prepared to offer. We have both 
     <lb/>
     these pieces of information and we get down to 
     <lb/>
     talking about forms of government. Let us say we 
     <lb/>
     recommend this: ...(a) that Commission govern<lb break="no"/>ment be continued; (b) that we go back to respon<lb break="no"/>sible government; (c) that we have responsible 
     <lb/>
     government in union with Canada according to 
     <lb/>
     the terms handed to the National Convention by 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian government on such and such a 
     <lb/>
     date. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The referendum is held. You cannot go any 
     <lb/>
     higher than the people of Newfoundland. The 
     <lb/>
     gentleman from St. John's West agreed on that. 
     <lb/>
     They are our bosses. I like to think that when they 
     <lb/>
     see those terms, they will say, "That looks pretty 
     <lb/>
     good, we will vote for it." What are we up 
     <lb/>
     against? You have Commission of Government. 
     <lb/>
     They are here. But the referendum is held and the 
     <lb/>
     people have voted for confederation. Where do 
     <lb/>
     we- go from here? That is what is worrying the 
     <lb/>
     gentleman from Grand Falls. You have your elec<lb break="no"/>tion. Why not? The people have voted for respon<lb break="no"/>sible... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> It is on your mind. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Does that surprise you? For 
     <lb/>
     seven years I scarcely missed a night advocating 
     <lb/>
     responsible government. Do not look too pleased 
     <lb/>
     over that. I am worried about whether we can 

<cb/>

     afford it or not. I would like to have responsible 
     <lb/>
     government, because I believe in it. The 
     <lb/>
     gentleman from Grand Falls said, "Are you going 
     <lb/>
     to have a better system of government than they 
     <lb/>
     have in the mother country?" I agree, they have 
     <lb/>
     responsible government in the old country, and I 
     <lb/>
     would like to see it here too. i hope they can 
     <lb/>
     afford it over there. It looks a bit doubtful just 
     <lb/>
     now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> We have been helping them out! 
     <lb/>
     
      </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The point is this: responsible 
     <lb/>government by all means if it does not put too 
     <lb/>great a burden on our people and keep up the cost 
     <lb/>of living. If union with Canada would help us to 
     <lb/>make it pay, let's have it. That's whatl want to 
     <lb/>find out, what have they got to offer us. Maybe if 
     <lb/>these terms are brought back I will stand up in 
     <lb/>this house, and show you a lot of fancy talking 
     <lb/>against those terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We will say the people vote for confederation, 
     <lb/>
     what is the next step after the referendum? 
     <lb/>
     Simple enough. Call for a general election, issue 
     <lb/>
     your new Letters Patent, call the houses together, 
     <lb/>
     the upper house and the lower house and we 
     <lb/>
     will have our two houses of parliament. I can see 
     <lb/>
     the Major (is it against the rules to say that Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Chairman?), I can see him bringing it in next 
     <lb/>
     January in this house, which would be the House 
     <lb/>
     of Assembly, "Whereas in the National Referen<lb break="no"/>dum the people of Newfoundland by a majority 
     <lb/>
     decided to accept union with Canada, therefore 
     <lb/>
     be it resolved that we now address a petition to 
     <lb/>
     His Majesty the King, praying that His Majesty 
     <lb/>
     may be graciously pleased to legislate New<lb break="no"/>foundland into confederation with Canada." I can 
     <lb/>
     see myself scconding it.... It is legal and constitu<lb break="no"/>tional, and this is the nice thing about it, that if 
     <lb/>
     the decision is made it will be made by the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland people. I am sure if the gentleman 
     <lb/>
     from Grand Falls were given a chance to decide 
     <lb/>
     for the people of Newfoundland, he would say, 
     <lb/>
     "Oh no, let the people decide that." Well; if the 
     <lb/>
     people decide it, what is wrong with it? Let the 
     <lb/>
     people's will be done if the heavens fall, if they 
     <lb/>
     vote for it that's the end of it. All we have to do 
     <lb/>
     is call our parliament, get both houses elected and 
     <lb/>
     send our address to the king. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There may be other points that the Major 
     <lb/>
     brought in that I ought to deal with, but I don't 
     <lb/>
     want to get him angry, I am so anxious that the 
     <lb/>
     Major and I should be good friends. There are 
     

            <pb n="323"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0323.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">323</fw>
        

     tens of thousands of people around the island that 
     <lb/>
     like him, and some of them like me too. I would 
     <lb/>
     like to show him some letters I get saying, "Get 
     <lb/>
     together with Cashin, you ought to be friends". 
     <lb/>
     That finance business looks bad, I can't under<lb break="no"/>stand that game, but don't forget this — if they 
     <lb/>
     have stuck in a couple of million dollars to pay 
     <lb/>
     for these steamers in their budget, if they don't 
     <lb/>
     pay it this year they must pay it next year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Tell where that money is coming 
     <lb/>
     from. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I rise to a point of order. Is this a 
     <lb/>
     conversation between this member and the mem<lb break="no"/>ber from St. John's West? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Major Cashin, strictly speaking, 
     <lb/>
     is our of order, but I will let it go. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Don't let's get too formal Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Chairman, or we will be thinking that we are the 
     <lb/>
     Government. I agree with Major Cashin in this. I 
     <lb/>
     hope they are not going to dip into our surplus of 
     <lb/>
     $28 million. We have got that nest egg, and that's 
     <lb/>
     all we have to show for the war and I hope they 
     <lb/>
     are not dipping into that.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> Mr. Chairman, before you proceed 
     <lb/>
     with notice of motion there is one point I would 
     <lb/>
     like to be satisfied on. Since it seems necessary 
     <lb/>
     to be known by certain names I suggest that I be 
     <lb/>
     known as "the very brief speaker." There are only 
     <lb/>
     two things necessary here and that is clarity and 
     <lb/>
     consistency. My friend from Bonavista stated last 
     <lb/>
     fall and reiterated today, and very emphatically, 
     <lb/>
     that we could not approach the United States on 
     <lb/>
     this tariff question. I am not doubting his word at 
     <lb/>
     all, but I am going to refer you to the fifth line in 
     <lb/>
     the paragraph that deals with clause one,<ref target="#fn_04">[1]</ref> which 
     <lb/>
     was in reference to the tariff question.... Now 
     <lb/>
     that's a report back to us from the Commission 
     <lb/>
     of Government. Am I to believe that the Commis<lb break="no"/>sion would not hazard an opinion as to whether 
     <lb/>
     or not we could do this? Why don't they give us 
     <lb/>
     a clear understandable answer that it could or 
     <lb/>
     could not be done? This is a masterpiece of 
     <lb/>
     discreetness. I would accept it with better grace 
     <lb/>
     if I did not think it was in part subscribed to by 
     <lb/>
     our own Committee. The whole thing has been 
     <lb/>
     passed over very lightly. They went to confer 
     <lb/>
     with the Commission of Government with a 
     <lb/>
     resolution that contained three important clauses. 
     <lb/>
     Somewhere along the way they forgot about one 
     <lb/>
     clause, and they come back with this answer, 
     
            <cb/>
       

     "that it was doubtful whether the subject matter 
     <lb/>
     of the clause was within the terms of reference of 
     <lb/>
     the Convention or not." I think in the discussion 
     <lb/>
     of any matter the first essential is the estab<lb break="no"/>lishment of facts. That was not done. The Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government did not give an opinion, 
     <lb/>
     and the Committee did not give an opinion. The 
     <lb/>
     word "doubtful" stays here, despite the fact that 
     <lb/>
     we have the opinion of the member from 
     <lb/>
     Bonavista, expressed twice, that we cannot do it. 
     <lb/>
     I want to know can we do it or can't we? If we 
     <lb/>
     can't, then I think it should be stated definitely 
     <lb/>
     and in understandable language in this report, and 
     <lb/>
     until such time as this paragraph dealing with 
     <lb/>
     clause one is corrected I certainly will not vote 
     <lb/>
     for the adoption of the report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> There is no need for me to go into 
     <lb/>
     the details of the purpose behind sending a com<lb break="no"/>mittee to interview the government which arose 
     <lb/>
     out of the Hon. Mr. Job's resolution. However, I 
     <lb/>
     would like to point out I did not vote for this 
     <lb/>
     action on the part of the Convention, and I still 
     <lb/>
     do not agree with it. It has been my contention all 
     <lb/>
     along that the first duty of this Convention is to 
     <lb/>
     enquire into and determine the present financial 
     <lb/>
     state of our country and to gauge if possible what 
     <lb/>
     our future prospects are. Until we know what we 
     <lb/>
     have, and when we will get what we own, we will 
     <lb/>
     only prejudice our possibilities of the best 
     <lb/>
     proposition from the countries we may approach. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I regret that thus far there has been nothing or 
     <lb/>
     very little said of an encouraging nature as far as 
     <lb/>
     our country is concerned. We have been sub<lb break="no"/>jected to a steady flow of hot air which has tended 
     <lb/>
     to hold our little country up to the ridicule of the 
     <lb/>
     outside world. Sometime ago we were given 
     <lb/>
     good advice by our fellow member when he said 
     <lb/>
     if we had any dirty linen to wash, why not wash 
     <lb/>
     it in private? I feel very strongly about the time 
     <lb/>
     which is being wasted. In the early days we had 
     <lb/>
     a resolution to send a delegation to Ottawa and 
     <lb/>
     we are still talking about delegations outside of 
     <lb/>
     our own country when we do not know what is in 
     <lb/>
     our own warehouse. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName>, if any delegation goes from 
     <lb/>
     this country they should know what stock is in 
     <lb/>
     our own warehouse and then find out what the 
     <lb/>
     British government intends to do about the base 
     <lb/>
     deals, as they did not have the consent of the 
     <lb/>
     people when our territory was bartered away. I 


<note xml:id="fn_04">1 Volume II:447. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
    
            <pb n="324"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0324.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">324</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
       
     had an interview with Mr. Attlee when he was 
     <lb/>
     here; I told him we were 100% loyal and British, 
     <lb/>
     that we have given and we will give our best, but 
     <lb/>
     we are jealous of what we own. I told him we 
     <lb/>
     must have a voice in what is done with our 
     <lb/>
     property. The war is now over and the people 
     <lb/>
     expect to get back what is theirs or get adequate 
     <lb/>
     compensation for it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When we finally take stock I would be in 
     <lb/>
     favour of a delegation to England, because I am 
     <lb/>
     convinced there are many things over there 
     <lb/>
     which should be in our stock sheet. I am not 
     <lb/>
     concerned any more about fish than about land 
     <lb/>
     and money on loan and landlease deals, it's all 
     <lb/>
     ours and our people need it all. This Convention, 
     <lb/>
     is an elected body from the people, let's forget 
     <lb/>
     this "asking" and "if you please" business. Let us 
     <lb/>
     stand on our feet and demand. My attitude may 
     <lb/>
     be termed radical, but I belong to the same stock 
     <lb/>
     from across the ocean and I have the same 
     <lb/>
     bulldog spirit and determination to have and to 
     <lb/>
     hold what is ours, regardless of who likes it. 
     <lb/>
      </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> I was particularly interested in sec<lb break="no"/>tion one of Mr. Job's resolution, in respect to 
     <lb/>establishing improved economic or fiscal 
     <lb/>relationships between the USA and this country, 
     <lb/>which was one of my real reasons for voting for 
     <lb/>the resolution as a whole. I was keenly disap<lb break="no"/>pointed on discovering how lightly this all-im<lb break="no"/>portant question, was brushed aside by our 
     <lb/>Committee. If there is the least shred of hope of 
     <lb/>improving our relationship with the USA, which 
     <lb/>is the greatest country on earth, where thousands 
     <lb/>of our own blood relations reside, no stone must 
     <lb/>be left unturned to achieve this important objec<lb break="no"/>tive. Any movement in this direction, will receive 
     <lb/>the support of 80% of our population. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If it were possible, for instance, to effect a 
     <lb/>
     reduction in the tariff of a couple of cents per 
     <lb/>
     pound on our fresh fish entering the USA this 
     <lb/>
     would mean the difference between prosperity 
     <lb/>
     and poverty to a large number of our fishermen. 
     <lb/>
     Therefore I am not at all satisfied with the attitude 
     <lb/>
     of the Commission of Government or our Com<lb break="no"/>mittee on this question. And I hope at some future 
     <lb/>
     date this whole question will receive the attention 
     <lb/>
     from this Convention it fully deserves. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> There is plenty of food for thought 
     <lb/>in the pamphlet published by Mr. Job and it is 
     <lb/>well worthy of study in view of the hold that 
     
         

            <cb/>
          
     Great Britain, the United States and Canada have 
     <lb/>
     on our country as far as our foreign policy and 
     <lb/>
     defence are concerned. This, like forms of 
     <lb/>
     government, is something which must be decided 
     <lb/>
     by the people of Newfoundland, and our 
     <lb/>
     authority is limited to recommendation only. I 
     <lb/>
     have every sympathy with our unfortunate posi<lb break="no"/>tion which prompted the spirit and substance of 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Job's resolution but we are not the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and it is strictly outside the terms of refer<lb break="no"/>ence. It is correct that Professor Wheare stated 
     <lb/>
     we have got the power to send a delegation to the 
     <lb/>
     USA to discuss terms of union, and we must 
     <lb/>
     admit that the treatment accorded Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     in 1933 has not been conducive to the promoting 
     <lb/>
     of the cordial relationship so much desired be<lb break="no"/>tween the mother country and her oldest colony. 
     <lb/>
     It was the old Conservative Churchill govern<lb break="no"/>ment which set up the machinery for the National 
     <lb/>
     Convention and the newly elected Labour 
     <lb/>
     government merely took it over as a going con<lb break="no"/>cern, and being favourable toward New<lb break="no"/>foundland getting some form of responsible 
     <lb/>
     government, they naturally set the machinery in 
     <lb/>
     motion as soon as it was expedient to do so. 
     <lb/>
     Despite what the first paragraph on page 2<ref target="#fn_05">[1]</ref> in<lb break="no"/>fers, I am of the opinion that should a delegation 
     <lb/>
     go to London on any business pertaining to the 
     <lb/>
     welfare of Newfoundland, they will get a hearing 
     <lb/>
     on any matter affecting this country, even though 
     <lb/>
     it may not be strictly speaking within the terms 
     <lb/>
     of reference. It is also worth noting that the 
     <lb/>
     Governor was a member of the Opposition when 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland lost her franchise and His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency himself voted against the suspension of 
     <lb/>
     democratic government. 
     <lb/>
      </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Speaking of delegations next year 
     <lb/>we have the Olympic Games on, and I think we 
     <lb/>could send a very fine delegation from this House 
     <lb/>to the Olympic Games! I feel certain that if we 
     <lb/>could get them to put on a contest for long dis<lb break="no"/>tance talking we could make a good showing. 
     <lb/>We are hired, or retained by the people to do 
     <lb/>a job as a committee of enquiry, and any man who 
     <lb/>consented to be hired must put his own thoughts 
     <lb/>and ideas beside the point as a member of the 
     <lb/>committee. I may feel equally as strongly about 
     <lb/>responsible government as Major Cashin and Mr. 
     <lb/>Hollett, But even though I feel as I do, as a 
     <lb/>member of this committee of enquiry I still must 


<note xml:id="fn_05">Volume II:447. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note> 
    

            <pb n="325"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0325.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw> 
   
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">325</fw>
        

     go about doing the job as it should be done. That 
     <lb/>
     should be the feeling of each member. It is not 
     <lb/>
     because we have our own feeling for various 
     <lb/>
     forms of government, not because the honourable 
     <lb/>
     member for Bonavista Centre, has his own ideas 
     <lb/>
     about the form of government best suited to our 
     <lb/>
     needs; he and the other two gentlemen must 
     <lb/>
     realise that the only thing that concerns us is to 
     <lb/>
     get the facts. The interpretation to be put on these 
     <lb/>
     facts is for the country as a whole. Why not stop 
     <lb/>
     trying to colour the business with our own per<lb break="no"/>sonal wishes? Why not get the facts, whether we 
     <lb/>
     like them or not? Why not get the terms from 
     <lb/>
     Canada if we can? Why not send a delegation to 
     <lb/>
     England and find out what they are prepared to 
     <lb/>
     do? We should not care what the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada will offer us, or what the Government of 
     <lb/>
     the United Kingdom will offer us. As a commis<lb break="no"/>sion of enquiry we are hired to get these facts, or 
     <lb/>
     we fail in our duty. For that reason I feel that 
     <lb/>
     motion should be put through this afternoon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> I rise to a point of information. It is 
     <lb/>
     definitely stated here, "it was doubtful whether 
     <lb/>
     the subject matter of the clause was within the 
     <lb/>
     terms of reference of the Convention or not". I 
     <lb/>
     am not trying to put any hard questions, I just 
     <lb/>
     want plain information on it. If the Committee 
     <lb/>
     can't back up that word "doubtful" then I think it 
     <lb/>
     should be removed. I think it's time we moved in 
     <lb/>
     definite fashion, understood each other and what 
     <lb/>
     we have got to do. I feel quite sure that if we can't 
     <lb/>
     establish certain facts as we go along, we are not 
   
<cb/>

     going to do the best for our country's interest. 
     <lb/>
     Once again I must say that the answer to clause 
     <lb/>
     1, which is based on doubt, is not an answer at 
     <lb/>
     all. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> For your information, that is the 
     <lb/>
     answer given by His Excellency the Governor in 
     <lb/>
     Commission. Whether that advice is right or not 
     <lb/>
     is another matter, but that is the advice they gave 
     <lb/>
     us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Might I just add that the Committee as 
     <lb/>
     a whole adopted this resolution unanimously, and 
     <lb/>
     thought it was a correct statement of the inter<lb break="no"/>view, and it did therefore mean that they accepted 
     <lb/>
     that advice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Exactly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I support Mr. Higgins. The people 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland are looking for facts, and we 
     <lb/>
     have no right to deny them, and they want all the 
     <lb/>
     information that we can give them and they must 
     <lb/>
     have it; otherwise how can we expect them even<lb break="no"/>tually to make a decision on matters with which 
     <lb/>
    they are not thoroughly familiar. I am most 
     <lb/>anxious that our people be well informed, not 
     <lb/>only with regard to the financial and economic 
     <lb/>position but with the general make up and pos<lb break="no"/>sibilities of the various forms of government 
     <lb/>considered by this Convention based on facts. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Is the House ready for the ques<lb break="no"/>tion? The motion is that this report be received. 
     <lb/>All those in favour say "aye", contrary "nay". 
     <lb/>The motion is carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the Committee on Agriculture:<ref target="#fn_06">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   </div>

<div type="section">
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> In presenting this Agricultural Report, 
     <lb/>
     I do not intend to make a speech. I hope the report 
     <lb/>
     speaks for itself. There are one or two observa<lb break="no"/>tions, however, that I would like to make. The 
     <lb/>
     report is not a treatise on agriculture. It is rather 
     <lb/>
     an attempt to survey the national aspects of 
     <lb/>
     agriculture in Newfoundland in the round. You 
     <lb/>
     will note the report is divided into five parts. One 
     <lb/>
     is a slight introduction not intended to be a history 
     <lb/>
     of agriculture in Newfoundland, but the idea of 
     <lb/>
     the Committee as to some of the reasons why 
     <lb/>
     agriculture has not taken the part in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland's economy that it should have. 
     <lb/>
     The second part we hope is a close approximation 
   
<cb/>

     of the value of agriculture as a unit in our national 
     <lb/>
     production. The third pan is an examination of 
     <lb/>
     government expenditures which involved an ex<lb break="no"/>amination of the policy of the Agricultural 
     <lb/>
     Division of the Department of Natural Resour<lb break="no"/>ces. The fourth part is the extraordinary or 
     <lb/>
     reconstruction expenditure which involves more 
     <lb/>
     expenditure than any part of the agricultural 
     <lb/>
     programme of the government. Finally we have 
     <lb/>
     a summary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Committee proceeded in this way. First 
     <lb/>
     we had a memorandum from the Director of 
     <lb/>
     Agriculture. This excellent document contained 
     <lb/>
     no figures of any kind, but gave us an insight into 


<note xml:id="fn_06">1 Volume II: 167. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
    

            <pb n="326"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-02-26_Page_0326.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">326</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 1947</fw>
          

     the minds and policies of the people looking after 
     <lb/>
     the agricultural industry in so far as the govern<lb break="no"/>ment is concerned. Where you find quotation 
     <lb/>
     marks in the report, they are nearly always from 
     <lb/>
     that memorandum. Before we start to discuss the 
     <lb/>
     report, I would like to pay tribute to Mr. Gillis for 
     <lb/>
     I know he wished, at times, that the Dickens had 
     <lb/>
     us. Having examined this document we 
     <lb/>
     proceeded to get certain facts about imports and 
     <lb/>
     local production. We then got government ex<lb break="no"/>penditure figures, and when we thought we had 
     <lb/>
     a rough picture of agriculture in Newfoundland, 
     <lb/>
     we then got from government officials and out<lb break="no"/>side sources, evidence; and this evidence we used 
     <lb/>
     for checking and cross-checking our own 
     <lb/>
     opinion. The result you will find in the report 
     <lb/>
     before you. The Committee was careful not to 
     <lb/>
     make the value of agriculture either too much or 
     <lb/>
     too little. It would be fair to say we viewed the 
     <lb/>
     prospects in agriculture in the future with much 
     <lb/>
     greater enthusiasm than would appear from the 
     <lb/>
     report itself. There is one section on the 
     <lb/>
     demonstration farm which may suggest that the 
     <lb/>
     Committee did not put much value on the farm. 
     <lb/>
     That would be incorrect. All we wished to convey 
     <lb/>
     was the fact that for one reason or another, the 
     <lb/>
     farm did not appear to us to be used as much as 
     <lb/>
     it should, in the interests of agriculture as a 
     <lb/>
     whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That is all I have to say. except that the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee will answer all the questions we possibly 
     <lb/>
     can; we will be happy to go back and find out 
     <lb/>
     anything that will help the members make up 
     <lb/>
     their minds as to whether Newfoundland is self-<lb break="yes"/>
          

            <cb/>
          

supporting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the report. The committee 
     <lb/>
     then rose and reported progress]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I beg to give 
     <lb/>
     notice that I will on tomorrow move the follow<lb break="no"/>ing resolution: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Resolved that the National Convention 
     <lb/>
     desires to send a delegation consisting of the 
     <lb/>
     Chairman and six other of its members to 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa to ascertain from the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada what fair and equitable basis may 
     <lb/>
     exist for federal union of Newfoundland and 
     <lb/>
     Canada; and 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Resolved that the National Convention 
     <lb/>
     requests His Excellency the Governor in 
     <lb/>
     Commission to ascertain whether the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada will receive such a 
     <lb/>
     delegation for the purpose stated; and 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Resolved that should the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada be willing to receive such a delega<lb break="no"/>tion, then the said delegation shall be elected 
     <lb/>
     forthwith by secret ballot, and shall proceed 
     <lb/>
     to Ottawa as soon as possible after the Con<lb break="no"/>vention shall have received from His 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's Government in the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom that Govemment's replies to the 
     <lb/>
     questions adopted by the Convention pur<lb break="no"/>suant to Mr. Hollett's resolution of even date, 
     <lb/>
     but not before. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I rise to give notice of a motion or 
     <lb/>
     resolution to be placed on the table tomorrow.... 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[ The text of Mr. Hollett's motion is given above, 
     <lb/>pp. 319-320. The Convention adjourned]</hi> 
   
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2017-06-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
   
            <!--<p>
     February 27, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Committee on Agriculture:1 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     [ The Secretary continued reading the report. ] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Butt Mr. Chairman, I skipped one small 
     <lb/>
     detail yesterday. We have the recapitulation of 
     <lb/>
     imports in detail, so if anyone wants any par<lb break="no"/>ticular item you can have it. Further, you will find 
     <lb/>
     on your desks a memo on the feed pool situation. 
     <lb/>
     We did not look upon this as part of our report, 
     <lb/>
     because it was more or less an emergency 
     <lb/>
     measure about the distribution of feeds. I 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     apologise because we only got it on February 25, 
     <lb/>
     and I barely read it myself, and some of you have 
     <lb/>
     not even seen it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The Secretary read the feed pool report. 2] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I wonder if Mr. Crosbie would 
     <lb/>
     tell us, how serious is it to take 5,000 sacks of fish 
     <lb/>
     meal and export it? Does it leave enough to meet 
     <lb/>
     local needs? There is a shortage of high protein 
     <lb/>
     fish meals. Have our local dairy and pig men 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>lVolume 11:167.<lb/>2Volume 11:179.<lb/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>