<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-09-20"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-09-20">20 September 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
          <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

           <date when="1995"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="58"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0045.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0046.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0047.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0048.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0049.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0050.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0051.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0052.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0053.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0054.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0055.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0056.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0057.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0058.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-02-14">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-08">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0045">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0045.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0046">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0046.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0047">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0047.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0048">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0048.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0049">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0049.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0050">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0050.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0051">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0051.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0052">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0052.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0053">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0053.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0054">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0054.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0055">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0055.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0056">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0056.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0057">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0057.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0058">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0058.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="45"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0045.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">45</fw>
           
<!-- GL, 2017-02-14 Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

 <!--<p>
     that additional advances in respect of similar 
     <lb/>
     agency services, have been made by the bank on 
     <lb/>
     a guaranteed overdraft basis, instead of being the 
     <lb/>
     subject of issues from the exchequer. The amount 
     <lb/>
     of such outstanding advances at the present time 
     <lb/>
     is approximately $1.2 million. They will be 
     <lb/>
     cleared as soon as audited accounts are rendered 
     <lb/>
     by the Newfoundland departments concerned to 
     <lb/>
     the service departments in the United Kingdom, 
     <lb/>
     who, I might add, have been pressing for these 
     <lb/>
     accounts as they are anxious to clear them as soon 
     <lb/>
     as possible. This matter is well in hand and I am 
     <lb/>
     informed that a large batch of audited accounts 
     <lb/>
     has been despatched to the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     during the past week. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I understand that the Convention wishes to 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     have further information regarding the 1% sink<lb break="no"/>ing fund on the 3% guaranteed stock. The annual 
     <lb/>
     payment, as shown in the published estimates, is 
     <lb/>
     the figure of £177,950 which I have already 
     <lb/>
     quoted. It has been paid every June since 1938, 
     <lb/>
     when the first payment became due, to the trus<lb break="no"/>tees to invest the sinking fund contributions in the 
     <lb/>
     guaranteed stock, as well as the interest which 
     <lb/>
     they receive on the sinking fund investments. In 
     <lb/>
     addition to the statement in the white paper, you 
     <lb/>
     will find this information in the accounts publish<lb break="no"/>ed with the Comptroller and Auditor General's 
     <lb/>
     report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [It was agreed that Mr. Wild would be requested 
     <lb/>
     to meet the Convention again on September 24. 
     <lb/>
     The Convention adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>-->

<div type="section">
            <head>
     September 20, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Requests for information were tabled by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Northcott, Mr. Hickman, Mr. Higgins, Mr. Fog<lb break="no"/>will, Mr. Walton, Mr. Jackman, Mr. Fowler, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McCormack, and Mr. Cashin]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Arising out of the minutes and <lb/> pursuant to
                  your resolution, an invitation was <lb/> extended to the Hon. the Commissioner for
                  <lb/> Finance to attend before you in private session on <lb/> Tuesday at 4
                  o'clock. Further, I received an in<lb break="no"/>timation from His Excellency
                  that he will be <lb/> pleased to receive a delegation from the National <lb/>
                  Convention at 11 o'clock on tomorrow at <lb/> Government House for the purpose of
                  presenting <lb/>
                  <cb/> to His Excellency addresses of loyalty to His <lb/> Majesty the King and of
                  thanks to His Excellen<lb break="no"/>cy. I submit that you might appoint a
                  delegation <lb/> at once. I think that perhaps Mr. Job as convenor <lb/> of that
                  committee might suggest a delegation. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I do not suppose it is possible for the <lb/>whole of
                  the Convention to be received, and in <lb/>that event I would suggest the
                  committee that <lb/>drafted the addresses would be appointed. I make <lb/>that as
                  a motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I second that motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried unanimously]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     Report of the Steering Committee<ref target="#fn_x1">[1]</ref>
 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> Copies of this report are on the <lb/> desks of
                  the members and I presume you have <lb/> read them. It will be unnecessary for me
                  to read <lb/> them formally. I would draw your attention to <lb/> section 2. It is
                  recommended that the work of the <lb/> Convention be divided up into nine
                  committees, <lb/> each consisting of ten men. We have en<lb break="no"/>deavoured
                  to apportion the work of the members <lb/> as best we could in order to balance
                  them. These <lb/> committees will be appointed by the Chairman in <lb/> accordance
                  with the schedule which is attached <lb/> to this report and which sets out the
                  various <lb/> committees and members of each. As each mem<lb break="no"/>ber of
                  the Convention sits on two committees, we <lb/> suggested a schedule which
                  provides that each <lb/> committee meets three times a week. That does <lb/> not
                  mean that the committees cannot meet of<lb break="no"/><cb/>tener. They may meet
                  at night. Section 4 provides <lb/> that the chairman of each committee is to be
                  one <lb/> of the members of the Steering Committee, in <lb/> order that there
                  might be a connection between <lb/> the Steering Committee and each sub-committee.
                  <lb/> As there are only seven members on the Steering <lb/> Committee and there
                  are nine committees, it is <lb/> obvious, at present, that two chairmen are not
                  <lb/> members of the Steering Committee. It has there<lb break="no"/>fore been
                  suggested we should ask your leave to <lb/> add to the Steering Committee
                  accordingly. It is <lb/> proposed that the work begin at once. It will be <lb/>
                  apparent that very little in the form of formal <lb/> meetings of the Convention
                  will take place, and <lb/> it was thought advisable that after we meet the <lb/>
                  Commissioner for Finance on Tuesday there <lb/> should be an adjournment taken,
                  and that we <lb/>
                  <note xml:id="fn_x1">1 Volume II:445. [Volume II is not in <hi
                        rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
                  <pb n="46" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0046.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">46</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> should meet at the call of the Chairman.
                  Section <lb/> 6 is very important. It is one thing to ask ques<lb break="no"
                  />tions; another thing to get information. In order <lb/> that this be done as
                  speedily as possible we have <lb/> asked the Commission of Government to provide
                  <lb/> an official in each department to assist the com<lb break="no"/>mittees and
                  in that way will facilitate the obtain<lb break="no"/>ing of information and save
                  valuable time. You <lb/> will notice that there has been considerable over<lb
                     break="no"/>lapping in connection with the asking of ques<lb break="no"/>tions.
                  In order that this may be avoided it is <lb/> proposed to set up a 'Questions
                  Committee' to <lb/> which all questions will first be handed. It is not <lb/>
                  intended to restrict rights to ask questions. We <lb/> may advise you as to how to
                  change the questions <lb/> and there may be questions eliminated where <lb/> there
                  is overlapping, and your questions <lb/> amplified in order to get the information
                  with <lb/> greater exactitude. The Commission has agreed <lb/> and is anxious to
                  facilitate us in every way. I <lb/> move that this report be received. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I second that motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried unanimously. The Conven<lb break="no"/>tion resolved into a committee of the whole. Sec<lb break="no"/>tions 2, 3 and 4 of the report were approved. 
     <lb/>
     Section 5 was read]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, in 1934 the <lb/> Commission of
                  Government system came into <lb/> Newfoundland, and since then in this country
                  <lb/> there has been no political action of any kind <lb/> whatsoever until the
                  holding of the National Con<lb break="no"/>vention election. For 12 or 13 years
                  there hap<lb break="no"/>pened in this country exactly what Mr. Bradley, <lb/>
                  sitting in this House at the time as leader of the <lb/> Opposition, forecast
                  would happen. I remember <lb/> his forecast that one effect of Commission <lb/>
                  government would be the death of whatever <lb/> public opinion had existed. For 12
                  or 13 years in <lb/> Newfoundland there has been no political action, <lb/> no
                  political agitation, no political propaganda. <lb/> That has been a grand thing.
                  At that time I dis<lb break="no"/>agreed with Mr. Bradley in private conversation
                  <lb/> and in my own mind. I thought that what we <lb/> needed was a political
                  holiday or armistice. We <lb/> have had it, but we have also had what he forecast
                  <lb/> — the death of public sentiment. Now that was <lb/> reflected very
                  considerably in the number of our <lb/> citizens throughout the island who did not
                  bother <lb/> to vote on the 21st of June. Sir, this Convention <lb/> opened on
                  Wednesday a week ago, and I have <lb/> followed, as I am sure we have all done,
                  the <lb/>
                  <cb/> reports appearing in the daily newspapers and the <lb/> weeklies, and the
                  nightly broadcasts on the two <lb/> stations, of the meetings of this Convention;
                  and, <lb/> as others have done, I have tried to visualise what <lb/> was happening
                  throughout the island. I was <lb/> trying to picture in my mind hundreds of
                  families <lb/> around the island sitting in their homes listening <lb/> to the
                  broadcasts of the events of the Convention <lb/> of that day. That has gone on now
                  for a week and <lb/> two days, and it has been good stuff, it has been <lb/>
                  suggestive and informative, but it has all had to <lb/> do with public affairs and
                  that is to the good. <lb/> What is needed in this country is a great revival <lb/>
                  of interest in public affairs, and I do not mean <lb/> politics. God forbid. This
                  section 5 would have <lb/> the effect of closing down the general assembly <lb/>
                  of the Convention, and setting up as its only <lb/> substitute very valuable work
                  on the part of nine <lb/> committees. A practical idea, a useful idea, and a <lb/>
                  necessary idea that these nine committees should <lb/> be set up, entirely right
                  that these practical topics <lb/> should be tackled in that way, and I agree
                     com<lb break="no"/>pletely; but it seems to me, and it means no more <lb/> to
                  me than it does to the members of the Steering <lb/> Committee or to any member of
                  the Convention, <lb/> a pity that after seven or eight nights only of <lb/>
                  practical, informative and even brilliant broad<lb break="no"/>casts, reaching
                  perhaps 200,000 of our people <lb/> nightly for eight nights, arousing the public
                     inter<lb break="no"/>est in public affairs, that after eight nights it <lb/>
                  should thus be abruptly cut off and for three or <lb/> four weeks they should hear
                  no more about the <lb/> National Convention. The suggestion was made, <lb/> but I
                  don't see it in this section, I think, sir, by <lb/> you, the thought of meeting
                  once a week in <lb/> general assembly. That is not mentioned here. It <lb/> is
                  intended that the Cenvention should adjourn <lb/> until called together by the
                  Chairman at the in<lb break="no"/>stance of the Steering Committee, except that on
                  <lb/> Tuesday we do meet in private session to meet <lb/> the commissioner. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I think you rather misapprehend <lb/> the effect
                  of this inquiry. It is not the intention of <lb/> the Steering Committee to
                  recommend that the <lb/> Convention adjourn indefinitely, but while mem<lb
                     break="no"/>bers are at work it is impossible to have a session <lb/> of the
                  Convention; but as the work progresses and <lb/> they are in a condition to report
                  to the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion, the Convention will immediately re-as<lb
                     break="no"/>semble. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The work of these committees <lb/>
                  <pb n="47" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0047.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">47</fw> is going to take time, a week or two, or maybe <lb/> three,
                  at least in the case of some of the nine <lb/> committees. Some may be able to
                  report back <lb/> tentatively within a week. The whole point is that <lb/> it
                  seems to me regrettable, unless there can be <lb/> provided in some way to the
                  reporters, who are <lb/> the eyes and ears of the Newfoundland public, a <lb/>
                  daily statement to keep the interest of the public <lb/> continuously alert. I
                  fear that a good beginning <lb/> made at interesting the people of Newfoundland
                  <lb/> will be stopped abruptly for a week or two and <lb/> then, let's picture it,
                  a committee reports to the <lb/> Steering Committee that it has done a certain
                  <lb/> amount of work and is able to report, tentatively <lb/> at least; the report
                  is brought in and tabled and the <lb/> whole Convention receives it and it goes to
                  the <lb/> individual men to study. It is a case of the whole <lb/> house meeting
                  merely to receive these reports <lb/> and I fear that there is not only a
                  possibility, but <lb/> a probability, that for the next two to four weeks <lb/>
                  the general assembly of the Convention will dis<lb break="no"/>appear with that
                  amount of time lost completely, <lb/> from this one standpoint of keeping the
                     New<lb break="no"/>foundland public interested and informed.... <lb/> There is
                  nothing personal in it, but I am terribly <lb/> impressed by the need to arouse in
                  our New<lb break="no"/>foundland people a continuous and increasing <lb/> interest
                  in pubic affairs. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> Mr. Chairman, I appreciate to the <lb/> full all
                  my friend Mr. Smallwood has said.... I am <lb/> not quite sure that an
                  adjournment, even for a <lb/> month, will so kill public opinion that it cannot
                  <lb/> be immediately revived when we have something <lb/> to lay before them. The
                  brutal fact is that it is not <lb/> physically possible for the whole Convention
                  and <lb/> the nine committees to meet at the same time. <lb/> Obviously we cannot
                  be in two places at once, <lb/> and if we are to obtain some continuity of <lb/>
                  publicity it must be at the expense of the work of <lb/> the various committees,
                  and that must delay the <lb/> completion of that work. Now if the Convention <lb/>
                  thinks that the value of that continuous publicity <lb/> outweighs the value of
                  speed in the working of <lb/> the committees, why of course that is up to them.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> I agree with Mr. Smallwood, not <lb/>altogether but
                  to some extent, but as Mr. Bradley <lb/>says we must not do anything to keep us
                  here <lb/>longer than necessary. Anything that we can do <lb/>to expedite matters
                  I believe it is our duty to do. <lb/>I was wondering, at the 3 o'clock meeting of
                  the <lb/>committees, if the session could not meet here, as <lb/>
                  <cb/> there may be some other people who would like <lb/> to place questions, and
                  the longer these are <lb/> delayed naturally the longer we will be waiting <lb/>
                  for the answers. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That is in the next two sections, <lb/> Mr.
                  Ballam. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> It is just merely a suggestion.... <lb/>
               </p>
           
 <p><persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> The people of Newfoundland <lb/>have waited for almost 14
                  years, and I feel that <lb/>what they want now is cold, hard facts. Reporting
                  <lb/>over the air and to the newspapers is all right, but <lb/>I feel that what
                  they want is nothing sensational <lb/>at all, just the facts. I feel this is a
                  good move, <lb/>because I don't see how we are going to get <lb/>anywhere if we
                  are going to meet in full session <lb/>every day like this. I don't think any of
                  us want <lb/>to be here longer than necessary, I think we <lb/>should get the work
                  done and put the information <lb/>before the members. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I am somewhat in accord with the <lb/> sentiments
                  of Mr. Smallwood, that it is not pos<lb break="no"/>sible to keep the interest of
                  the public alive if we <lb/> adjourn the assembly for a considerable period, <lb/>
                  and I am wondering if we could compromise a <lb/> little on this plan and have the
                  committees meet <lb/> on Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, <lb/> and then
                  have the Convention meet on Friday. In <lb/> some instances these committees are
                  going to <lb/> extend over a somewhat long drawn out time, and <lb/> I feel that
                  if we knew that the Convention would <lb/> come in session once a week, it might
                  make up <lb/> for the lack of continuity. I think Mr. Smallwood <lb/> and all of
                  us would consider this a compromise. <lb/>
               </p>
            
<p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Mr. Chairman, I agree with the <lb/>remarks of Mr. Jackman. If this
                  Convention ad<lb break="no"/>journs, and meets, say once or twice a week, it
                  <lb/>adjoums in order to give the different committees <lb/>time to get the
                  information that our constituents <lb/>are asking for and need, and I feel sure,
                  sir, <lb/>regardless of the Convention adjourning for a <lb/>week or two, the
                  people are not going to lose <lb/>interest. The people will be informed that the
                  <lb/>Convention is adjourned for a purpose, and that <lb/>the representative they
                  sent to this Convention is <lb/>seeking information for them, and that the
                     infor<lb break="no"/>mation cannot be gotten together while this Con<lb
                     break="no"/>vention sits daily. There must be adjournment, <lb/>and time given
                  the members of the committees in <lb/>order to seek this information which is so
                  vitally <lb/>important to this Convention. I fail to see where <lb/>the citizens
                  of this country can object when they <lb/>
                  <pb n="48" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0048.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">48</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> know, that the Convention was adjourned
                  for a <lb/> purpose, and that every member of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion was
                  doing his job in their interest, and seek <lb/> ing the information that they sent
                  us here to get.... <lb/></p>
            

<p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In line with Mr. Butt, my point <lb/>is not that the public
                  would condemn us for not <lb/>meeting daily, they would just lose interest. Now
                  <lb/>on a given night 200,000 people, let us assume, <lb/>are listening in. On
                  that one occasion, in one <lb/>sentence or two, it is said in a broadcast that the
                  <lb/>Convention has adjourned to go into committee <lb/>work. I will agree that if
                  that were said each night <lb/>for a week on the air that fact would then become
                  <lb/>public property in Newfoundland. I am sure that <lb/>my friend Mr. Harrington
                  will agree on that. You <lb/>have got to say the same thing in a number of
                  <lb/>ways at least five times over that many days <lb/>before it becomes public
                  property. I am afraid <lb/>that the reaction would be, "What's happened to
                  <lb/>the Convention? I have not heard a word from <lb/>them for some days." The
                  fact that they divided <lb/>into nine committees, and that they are working
                  <lb/>like nailers to get certain information would not <lb/>be appreciated. My
                  point was not as to whether <lb/>the constituents would blame us or not, my fear
                  <lb/>is that they will not even know that we have <lb/>adjourned or why, and they
                  will think we are <lb/>trying to stretch it out as long as possible. Already
                  <lb/>lots of people have said, "Oh they meet at 3 <lb/>o'clock and adjourn at 5
                  o'clock - $15 gone to <lb/>wing!" They don't know how we are working - <lb/> that
                  does not make good copy for our friends in <lb/>the press box, and the bare fact
                  that there was a <lb/>committee meeting is not copy at all.... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BROW7">Mr. Brown</persName> Mr. Chairman, what is the radio and <lb/> the press
                  for? Surely, the press and the radio can <lb/> inform the general public what is
                  happening. <lb/> Well, if the general public don't want us to get <lb/> the
                  information that we are seeking today and <lb/> going to seek, how can we reach
                  any decision in <lb/> this Convention? Surely there must be a time for <lb/> the
                  obtaining of this information, and we can't <lb/> get that information and have
                  this house sit every <lb/> day. Some of us have been sitting on some com<lb
                     break="no"/>mittee every day, except Sunday, up to the <lb/> present time, and
                  I don't see how this House can <lb/> sit daily and obtain the information we want
                  to <lb/> give the general public. I think this is only <lb/> prolonging the debate
                  and losing time discussing <lb/> the matter. As far as what my friend Mr. Small<lb
                     break="no"/>wood says about us getting $15 a day, there will <lb/>
                  <cb/> be some of us who go out of St. John's and our <lb/> $15 a day won't cover
                  our expenses, Mr. Chair<lb break="no"/>man. I hope we can get through by
                  Christmas, and <lb/> I know many others in this Convention who are <lb/> of the
                  same opinion. Let us get down to business <lb/> in the right way and get through
                  this Convention <lb/> just as quickly as we possibly can, in the mean<lb
                     break="no"/>time obtaining all possible information and <lb/> giving it to the
                  public. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Just one last word. I hope the <lb/> newspaper
                  men and radio men present have <lb/> received enough copy so that they can drive
                  it <lb/> home to the public. That's my idea, to give them <lb/> enough copy to
                  make them say more than one line <lb/> that we are going to adjourn. If they
                  report this <lb/> little scrap that we have had, it may serve the <lb/> purpose
                  for which it was intended. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I agree entirely with Mr. Butt, <lb/> and if the
                  people have had nothing for 12 years I <lb/> think another week or two won't hurt.
                  I think the <lb/> quicker we get down to the actual work the better. <lb/>I would
                  like to make a motion that the motion be <lb/>put. <lb/>
               </p>
   
    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I second that motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Moved that section 5 as read be <lb/> agreed.
                  Motion carried unanimously. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[Section 6 read]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There is a slight correction <lb/> there,
                  gentlemen. The officials of a department <lb/> will not come here and take part in
                  the committee <lb/> meetings, but it is meant that an official from the <lb/>
                  department will be there and his first duty will be <lb/> to give this task his
                  first attention. That section <lb/> will read: "It is proposed that each committee
                  <lb/> shall have the assistance of an official of the <lb/> appropriate government
                  department to assist it in <lb/> its task of obtaining the necessary information
                  <lb/> from that department. The Commission of <lb/> Government have assured the
                  Chairman of their <lb/> fullest co-operation in this respect." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Sections 6 and 7 approved]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It is proposed that each member <lb/>of the
                  Convention sit on two committees, and the <lb/>schedule for the time of sitting
                  has been so ar<lb break="no"/>ranged that they will not overlap. If it is so
                  <lb/>approved, gentlemen, I shall appoint the members <lb/>of the Convention to
                  the committees accordingly. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[Moved and carried that this suggestion be ap<lb break="no"/>proved. The committee of the whole rose, and the 
     <lb/>Convention adopted the Report of the Steering 
     <lb/>Committee]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
            <pb n="49"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0049.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">49</fw>
</div>

<div type="section">         

<head>
     Report on the Financial and Economic Position of Newfoundland<ref target="#fn_x2">[1]</ref>
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I wish to make the following remarks <lb/> on the
                  subject of this Chadwick and Jones report, <lb/> which perhaps for short I may
                  call the white <lb/> paper. I hope there will be many other oppor<lb break="no"
                  />tunities of referring to it, and on this assumption <lb/> I do not intend to
                  speak at length on it today. It <lb/> has been prepared from our own government
                  <lb/> department records, with a view to giving us a <lb/> preliminary picture of
                  the economic position of <lb/> Newfoundland. This document, in my opinion, is
                  <lb/> a definite contribution to our efforts and cannot <lb/> be lightly brushed
                  aside. I believe that a careful <lb/> study of it will help the delegates to get
                  some sort <lb/> of a picture of the government's economic posi<lb break="no"
                  />tion, but it is far from providing all the informa<lb break="no"/>tion we will
                  require. A careful study of that <lb/> excellent review entitled <hi
                     rendition="simple:italic">Newfoundland. <lb/> Economic, Diplomatic and
                     Strategic Studies</hi>, <lb/> edited by R.A. MacKay, of which a copy has <lb/>
                  been furnished to every delegate, will give us a <lb/> still clearer picture. I
                  wish today to briefly call <lb/> attention to two short sentences in this white
                  <lb/> paper, one of which on page 9 reads as follows: <lb/> "The long term
                  prosperity of the Island ultimately <lb/> depends on a flourishing export trade."
                  The other <lb/> on page 21 reads: "Certain industries run by <lb/> outside
                  concerns bring into the country only suf<lb break="no"/>ficient money to run their
                  operations, but the <lb/> great bulk of earnings from the sale of fish is <lb/>
                  ploughed back into the economy." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I have emphasised, and will take every oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of again emphasising, that the happy state 
     <lb/>
     of affairs declared to he so vital and desirable by 
     <lb/>
     those two bright young delegates, Mr. Newell 
     <lb/>
     and Mr. Keough in their admirable addresses, 
     <lb/>
     will never be achieved unless and until we are 
     <lb/>
     assured of a more stable and profitable market for 
     <lb/>
     our fishery products of all sorts than has existed 
     <lb/>
     in the past. Such a market will be available only 
     <lb/>
     if we take advantage of our strategic position to 
     <lb/>
     negotiate tariff arrangements with the mother 
     <lb/>
     country, with Canada and with the United States 
     <lb/>
     of America, and the sooner some government 
     <lb/>
     with solid backing can get under way with these 
     <lb/>
     negotiations the better. There is very shortly 
     <lb/>
     going to be held an international trade convention 
     <lb/>
     for the purpose of discussing trade relations and 
     <lb/>
     tariffs, at which a delegate or delegates appointed 
     <lb/>
     by the Newfoundland Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/><cb/>ment will be present. Newfoundland's case for 
     <lb/>
     special consideration so far as trade and tariff 
     <lb/>
     relations with the United Kingdom, Canada and 
     <lb/>
     with the United States of America are concerned, 
     <lb/>
     should be based not only upon the question of 
     <lb/>
     reciprocity on tariff concessions, but also upon 
     <lb/>
     the fact that these three countries will be utilising 
     <lb/>
     our strategic position for the safety of their mil<lb break="no"/>lions of people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This country has never received anything, ex<lb break="no"/>cept the temporary benefit of certain expendi<lb break="no"/>tures during the war, which were necessary for 
     <lb/>
     the safety of these millions of people, in return 
     <lb/>
     for the 99-year leases of Newfoundland territory 
     <lb/>
     granted to the United States, and the special air<lb break="no"/>port facilities granted to Canada. We do not want 
     <lb/>
     to be subsidised by outside people to enable us to 
     <lb/>
     maintain that fair standard of living to which 
     <lb/>
     reference has been made, but we do want to be 
     <lb/>
     assisted by tariff arrangements. It is useless to 
     <lb/>
     develop our production of fish products without 
     <lb/>
     assurance of a profitable market. I make these 
     <lb/>
     present remarks on account of the urgency exist<lb break="no"/>ing, to impress upon those who will be respon<lb break="no"/>sible for the appointment of delegates to this 
     <lb/>
     forthcoming international trade convention, of 
     <lb/>
     not overlooking our grounds for special con<lb break="no"/>sideration. We shall want the full weight of this 
     <lb/>
     Convention and of our people behind this idea if 
     <lb/>
     anything is to be accomplished quickly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Before closing, Mr. Chairman, I would like to 
     <lb/>
     support most strongly the views and patriotic 
     <lb/>
     sentiments so eloquently expressed by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood and also by Mr. Ken Brown upon the 
     <lb/>
     remarks of Major Cashin on introducing his mo<lb break="no"/>tion for receipt of this white paper. His address 
     <lb/>
     was more or less a repetition of some made over 
     <lb/>
     the radio for months prior to the Convention, and 
     <lb/>
     I fancy that they amused a great many people and 
     <lb/>
     perhaps even were helpful in arousing public 
     <lb/>
     interests in the political situation, but it was not 
     <lb/>
     the kind of address that should have been 
     <lb/>
     delivered at this Convention, and I fancy that 
     <lb/>
     every delegate here will agree with this viewpoint 
     <lb/>
     and resent the subtle insinuations made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VINC1">Mr. Vincent</persName> Mr. Chairman, in speaking to the <lb/> motion
                  before the Convention I did so, in the <lb/> words of Mr. Keough, "possessed with
                  a deep <lb/> conviction that this is a vital moment in the annals <lb/>
                  <note xml:id="fn_x2">1 Volume II:16. [Volume II is not in <hi
                        rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
                  <pb n="50" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0050.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">50</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> of our country." I have observed that
                  there are <lb/> those among us who are very hopeful of seeing a <lb/> sentiment
                  develop in favour of this or that form <lb/> of government. In the early stages of
                  what can <lb/> only be described as an investigating committee, <lb/> that is very
                  bad. One delegate is a proponent of <lb/> this, another an adherent of that, and
                  it would be <lb/> very unfortunate should any attempt be made by <lb/> a proponent
                  of any form to superimpose his <lb/> preconceived notions, fixed beliefs and
                     fore-or<lb break="no"/>dained opinions on this assembly. There should <lb/> be
                  no splitting into groups. Supposing your dis<lb break="no"/>trict does want
                  confederation and mine respon<lb break="no"/>sible government, what of it?
                  Districts are but the <lb/> components of what make up Newfoundland, so <lb/> let
                  us confine ourselves to factual data only. <lb/> Furthermore, any attempt to
                  narrow the issues or <lb/> restrict the choice of the people would not only <lb/>
                  be foolhardy, it would be positively dangerous. <lb/> The majority of our people
                  are not concerned <lb/> with the name of tomorrow's government, but <lb/> that the
                  administration of tomorrow should pro<lb break="no"/>vide, inasmuch as governments
                  can, more com<lb break="no"/>prehensive and higher educational standards, <lb/>
                  more and better communications, in short a <lb/> general raising of the standard
                  of living which, to <lb/> say the least, is much lower than in any English- <lb
                     break="yes"/> speaking country of the western hemisphere. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>The solution is not to be found in the political 
     <lb/>field, it will be found in the future prosperity and 
     <lb/>consequent happiness of that family over the 
     <lb/>way, for "a nation is as poor as its people." I 
     <lb/>personally do not care what name is given to their 
     <lb/>set form of government; I'll vote for it as soon as 
     <lb/>it can be shown it was in the best interest of 
     <lb/>Newfoundland. Today we are at the cross-roads. 
     <lb/>"Whence from here and whither tending?" I ask. 
     <lb/>These are important questions and it devolves 
     <lb/>upon the members to be exacting in their research 
     <lb/>and honest in their opinions, not guided by senti<lb break="no"/>ment. The economy of Newfoundland is not basi<lb break="no"/>cally different in 1946 from what it was in 1934 
     <lb/>— the influx of outside capital during the abnor<lb break="no"/>mal war years cannot in the long run have any 
     <lb/>appreciable effect upon our ability to be self-suf<lb break="no"/>ficient - the internal market for our products 
     <lb/>cannot in the foreseeable future be greatly en<lb break="no"/>larged. Newfoundland still has 42,000 square 
     <lb/>miles of territory with only a third of a million 
     <lb/>people. That confronts us with a large problem 
     <lb/>for it obviously means a too-wide diffusion of our 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     national effort, which in turn greatly weakens the 
     <lb/>
     ability of any centralised government to maintain 
     <lb/>
     anything like fair provisions for the communica<lb break="no"/>tions so essential to the people of the small towns 
     <lb/>
     and villages. I would hesitate to vote for any form 
     <lb/>
     of government before all the facts are assimi<lb break="no"/>lated. For after all, the real trouble is the age-old 
     <lb/>
     business game of trying to make enough money 
     <lb/>
     on the goods sold to enable the businessman to 
     <lb/>
     keep his personnel happy, and his stores and 
     <lb/>
     warehouses in fairly decent order. The three 
     <lb/>
     meals and tight roof argument may he basically 
     <lb/>
     sound, but it is only a half-truth, for the question 
     <lb/>
     is not how we'll eat and what we'll wear. It goes 
     <lb/>
     deeper than that, for it must not be forgotten that 
     <lb/>
     no government in itself can go on providing for 
     <lb/>
     the welfare of its people unless its resources can 
     <lb/>
     support its economy. Government of course can 
     <lb/>
     provide legislation, social and otherwise, that 
     <lb/>
     will in some measure contribute to that end, but 
     <lb/>
     the burning questions are, can we provide new 
     <lb/>
     industries, seek out and develop new resources? 
     <lb/>
     There is a dire need for newer methods in our 
     <lb/>
     saltfish industry; and our external trade, the very 
     <lb/>
     essence and life-blood of our economy, is, as it 
     <lb/>
     was 50 years ago, still contingent upon the ability 
     <lb/>
     of foreign markets to purchase our exportable 
     <lb/>
     products. These and other factors tend to make 
     <lb/>
     the task facing the Convention a case of arith<lb break="no"/>metic plus sound common sense, so let us dis<lb break="no"/>pense with our pet opinions and continue the 
     <lb/>
     investigation on our financial and economic af<lb break="no"/>fairs on the broad plane of securing facts only. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I cannot agree that the Convention is a farce 
     <lb/>
     and a fiasco. I am willing to explore every pos<lb break="no"/>sibility, analyse every issue, and without iden<lb break="no"/>tifying myself with any group or following any 
     <lb/>
     star, to measure everything by the yardstick of the 
     <lb/>
     best for Newfoundland. I would vote for the 
     <lb/>
     retention of Commission of Government, if after 
     <lb/>
     the mobilisation of all the facts I find it is best for 
     <lb/>
     the country, but I shall as readily vote against it 
     <lb/>
     if the opposite is the case. Logically I believe in 
     <lb/>
     responsible government — what free man 
     <lb/>
     doesn't — but it is not a question of what I 
     <lb/>
     believe, it's what is best for Newfoundland.... I 
     <lb/>
     do not pretend to have any notion how the 
     <lb/>
     country would vote tomorrow, but I am con<lb break="no"/>vinced that the widest publicity should be given 
     <lb/>
     to the findings and deliberations of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion. If we conduct our investigation in the proper 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="51"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0051.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">51</fw>
        
     manner, I am confident we can safely leave the 
     <lb/>
     final analysis in the hands of our fellow New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders. They will choose wisely and well. 
     <lb/>
   </p>
           
 <p><persName ref="pers:JONE5">Mr. Jones</persName> Mr. Chairman, it is with a certain <lb/>amount of intimidation I
                  rise to make a few <lb/>remarks on the report now in question. This Na<lb
                     break="no"/>tional Convention has become a reality after <lb/>much tribulation.
                  I hope its faculties will continue <lb/>to keep healthy and strong, because it
                  will need <lb/>the shoulder of an Hercules to carry the burden <lb/>of statistics
                  about to be placed upon its shoulders. <lb/>The members of this Convention have
                  been ap<lb break="no"/>pointed by our respective districts to try and find
                  <lb/>out the best form of government suitable for <lb/>Newfoundland The task is
                  going to be extremely <lb/>difficult, and will call for the best contribution
                  <lb/>each and every one of us can put into it. We shall <lb/>have to give sane and
                  unbiased considerations to <lb/>the many problems which will from time to time
                  <lb/>confront us, and there is much hard work in store <lb/>for us before we can
                  attempt to try and come to a <lb/>decision. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, since we relinquished our 
     <lb/>
     status as a self-governing people, Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     has been in the limelight, and still is. We have had 
     <lb/>
     many reverses in our economic life since then, 
     <lb/>
     yet we have survived somehow. When war was 
     <lb/>
     declared Newfoundland was at its lowest ebb, 
     <lb/>
     economically and financially, yet in spite of the 
     <lb/>
     fact that many of our young men were on the dole, 
     <lb/>
     being only half-fed and half-clothed (on six cents 
     <lb/>
     a day) they rallied round the colours, and very 
     <lb/>
     soon some 7,000 of our young men were enlisted 
     <lb/>
     in the different forces of the empire, not forget<lb break="no"/>ting thousands of our young women who offered 
     <lb/>
     their services. Mr. Chairman, let us hope New<lb break="no"/>foundland will never again experience the dif<lb break="no"/>ficult times previous to the outbreak of hostilities. 
     <lb/>
     That is where this Convention comes in, to find 
     <lb/>
     that form of government which will remove the 
     <lb/>
     spectre of want from our people. Should this 
     <lb/>
     Convention recommend such a form of govern<lb break="no"/>ment, then it will be the means of placing New<lb break="no"/>foundland on the map, and our children's 
     <lb/>
     children will look back in the years to come on 
     <lb/>
     the work of this Convention and say it was a 
     <lb/>
     masterpiece. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, as we look at the estimates for 
     <lb/>
     1946-47 we find a deficit balance of approxi<lb break="no"/>mately $4 million. How can we be self-support<lb break="no"/>ing under these conditions? If we wish to find a 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
         
     solution to our problems, we must forget this 
     <lb/>
     form or that form of government, until we have 
     <lb/>
     studied carefully all the information at our dis<lb break="no"/>posal and then come to our decision, which is the 
     <lb/>
     most suitable form of government for this sadly 
     <lb/>
     burdened country of ours. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WATT1">Mr. Watton</persName> Mr. Chairman, during the past few <lb/> days we
                  have listened to some lengthy and elo<lb break="no"/>quent speeches by several
                  members of this Con<lb break="no"/>vention and I wish to tender congratulations.
                  <lb/> What I have to say will not be lengthy nor will it <lb/> be eloquent. I am
                  not too particularly blessed with <lb/> the gift of oratory, nor do I think it is
                  necessary <lb/> at this stage of our proceedings. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The Chadwick and Jones report will he of the 
     <lb/>
     utmost value to us in our deliberations, and I do 
     <lb/>
     not think there will be any question of its adop<lb break="no"/>tion. During this debate a lot has been said for and 
     <lb/>
     against various forms of government. Mr. Chair<lb break="no"/>man, the time is not ripe, nor do I think it ap<lb break="no"/>propriate, for us to discuss the merits or demerits 
     <lb/>
     of any particular form of government. As regards 
     <lb/>
     what form of government is best for this country 
     <lb/>
     at the present, I have no idea, but as to what <hi rendition="simple:italic">kind</hi> 
     <lb/>
     of a government I want for this country, I have a 
     <lb/>
     very <hi rendition="simple:italic">fixed</hi> idea. What I, and the majority of the 
     <lb/>
     people of this country want is a government that 
     <lb/>
     will give us the greatest measure of economic and 
     <lb/>
     financial stability. A government that will see to 
     <lb/>
     it that the rising generations of this country are 
     <lb/>
     given a sound education, a chance to develop a 
     <lb/>
     healthy mind, and what is perhaps most important 
     <lb/>
     of all, a healthy body. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     During the past, Mr. Chairman, our people 
     <lb/>
     have been denied a great many, if not all of these 
     <lb/>
     privileges or shall I say <hi rendition="simple:italic">rights</hi>. I could carry on in 
     <lb/>
     this strain to come length, but if I do I shall 
     <lb/>
     probably find myself in the rather awkward posi<lb break="no"/>tion of self-contradiction. Because at the begin<lb break="no"/>ning I stated that what I had to say would not be 
     <lb/>
     lengthy.... So let us cut out the pretty speeches 
     <lb/>
     and get down to business. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> Feeling that our friends at Car<lb break="no"
                  />bonear may be thinking I am asleep on the job or <lb/> something worse because
                  we are not figuring in <lb/> the news so far, may I take this opportunity of <lb/>
                  speaking briefly, as well as to let you know at the <lb/> start that I am not a
                  past master in the field of <lb/> oratory. Yet, like all other members of this
                     Con<lb break="no"/>vention, we have our own opinions and feelings <lb/>
                  concerning the work which we are called upon to <lb/>
                  <pb n="52" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0052.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">52</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> do. I was surprisingly touched and pleased
                  with <lb/> the addresses of Mr. Newell of White Bay Dis<lb break="no"/>trict, and
                  Mr. Keough of St. George's on Wed<lb break="no"/>nesday last, because they were
                  young men <lb/> representing extern districts in Newfoundland, <lb/> and they may
                  not have been schooled in par<lb break="no"/>liamentary amenities in the same way
                  as our old <lb/> time politicians whom we have already heard <lb/> every so often.
                  Yet it could be clearly seen that <lb/> they were alive to their jobs and gave us
                  some <lb/> good stuff to think over. May they be followed <lb/> by other outport
                  members who may be classified <lb/> as unknown in this public way so far, like
                  your <lb/> humble servant. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     When Mr. Brown told us in his address that he 
     <lb/>
     came to this Convention with an open mind his 
     <lb/>
     declaration touched me closely, for I can say also 
     <lb/>
     that it is my privilege to be sailing in the same 
     <lb/>
     boat in that respect. While I am not in love with 
     <lb/>
     the dictatorial make-up of Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government, I am more concerned over the num<lb break="no"/>ber and kind of meals the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland will be able to afford in the years 
     <lb/>
     ahead, than I am in particular forms of govern<lb break="no"/>ment at this time, so to that end, and for that 
     <lb/>
     purpose I am very willing to serve with a feeling 
     <lb/>
     that there are many rivers to cross in between. 
     <lb/>
      </p>
           
 <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Chairman, I had not intended <lb/>to address this assembly
                  at the present time, and <lb/>I don't intend to do so today for more than five
                  <lb/>or six minutes. I feel it is much more fitting to <lb/>have members outside
                  St John's do the talking <lb/>at the present time, because we in St. John's who
                  <lb/>are so much closer to the seat of government have <lb/>a lot to learn from
                  the opinions of outside mem<lb break="no"/>bers. My real reason for rising in this
                  debate was <lb/>because I did not feel justified in keeping silence <lb/>any
                  longer, having listened to the remarks of the <lb/>proposer of this motion on
                  Wednesday last. I do <lb/>not feel justified for two reasons, one that silence
                  <lb/>may be considered to give consent to the views <lb/>of Major Cashin, and
                  secondly because I feel that <lb/>his remarks, whilst they may be good politics,
                  do <lb/>not lead to contentment in the minds of the <lb/>delegates. The remarks I
                  object to are these. In <lb/>referring to the undertaking by the British
                  <lb/>government to Newfoundland — "When the <lb/>country is self-supportin g we
                  would have respon<lb break="no"/>sible government given back upon the express
                  <lb/>wish of the people" — he said, speaking of this <lb/>people, "How can any
                  thinking Newfoundlander <lb/>
                  <cb/> honestly and conscientiously give his moral sup<lb break="no"/>port and
                  endorsement to a thing which is not <lb/> alone illegal but even ethically
                  improper?" <lb/> Again, in referring to a statement made by Prime <lb/> Minister
                  Attlee that the Commission have in hand <lb/> or are planning to meet our present
                  needs during <lb/> the next two or three years, Mr. Cashin read into <lb/> this
                  statement the fact that the British government <lb/> intended to enforce
                  Commission rule for two or <lb/> three years. He said again, "Our status, despite
                  <lb/> what may be said to the contrary, is simply that <lb/> of a mock parliament,
                  a discussion group, a study <lb/> club." How anybody holding opinions such as
                  <lb/> these can sit as a member of this Convention is <lb/> beyond my
                  understanding, and certainly Major <lb/> Cashin's doing so is, using his own
                  words, very <lb/> improper. The most scathing part, however, is the <lb/> excuse
                  he gave when he said he was not "a sub<lb break="no"/>servient delegate to a
                  Commission-inspired as<lb break="no"/>sembly, but rather a free and independent
                  <lb/> representative of the people whose interests I <lb/> represent." The
                  suggestion contained in these <lb/> remarks means that either some or all of us
                  are <lb/> subservient delegates to what Major Cashin <lb/> describes as "a
                  Commission-inspired assembly". <lb/> I resent that suggestion, and I am sure I
                  resent it <lb/> equally with all of you here today. There is no <lb/> man here who
                  is not a free and independent <lb/> representative of the people, and I defy Major
                  <lb/> Cashin or any other person to say otherwise. I am <lb/> not interested in
                  the background of this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion; as far as I am concerned we
                  have been <lb/> elected by the people of this country to ascertain <lb/> if we
                  have or can arrange economic security and <lb/> financial stability. Without these
                  no government <lb/> can be successful. Having ascertained these items <lb/> we
                  must look to the form of government best <lb/> suited to the country. Our fellow
                  countrymen are <lb/> looking to us with great expectations, in fact the <lb/>
                  outside world is also extremely interested in this <lb/> Convention, as we note by
                  the newspaper <lb/> coverage we are receiving. I ask you, can the <lb/> remarks of
                  Major Cashin impress our country or <lb/> outsiders with our ability to solve our
                  problems? <lb/> Let us in all future sessions refrain from all such <lb/> remarks
                  as we heard here on Wednesday last. We <lb/> must remember that the cost of this
                  Convention <lb/> is by no means inconsiderable. The sum of <lb/> $150,000 was set
                  aside to cover this assembly. <lb/> The costs amount to upwards of $800 for each
                  <lb/> day. Unless we are giving service in line with our <lb/>
                  <pb n="53" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0053.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">53</fw> terms of reference we are not playing the game <lb/> by our
                  constituents or by the country generally. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> Mr. Chairman, much has been said <lb/> on what we
                  are gathered here for. I could not help <lb/> recalling some of the speeches of
                  yesterday. I <lb/> believe we of the Convention realise the respon<lb break="no"
                  />sibility of what is an historic occasion, and it is <lb/> something, in my
                  estimation, that should not have <lb/> happened. I am learning for the first time
                  the <lb/> whole truth about what has happened in the past, <lb/> and the truth
                  still leaves me in that state of mind <lb/> that there should never have been an
                  occasion for <lb/> a National Convention. I agree with my <lb/> honourable
                  colleague, Major Cashin, that we <lb/> should never have surrendered the
                  constitution. <lb/> In that I differ from my learned colleague <lb/> Mr. Brown. At
                  that time I was out of the country. <lb/> In 1929, watching the course of events,
                  I was <lb/> talking to some of the members of the House and <lb/> the matter of
                  borrowing came up. They said we <lb/> had to borrow to get along, I asked, "What
                  are <lb/> you going to do when you can't borrow, have you <lb/> any plan? You had
                  better get one for your bor<lb break="no"/>rowing days are about over." It seems
                  like <lb/> everybody drifted along with no plan, "laissez <lb/> faire" was the
                  order of the day. That was the time <lb/> to have tried to get the house in order,
                  and when <lb/> the world got in the doldrums in the thirties, the <lb/> first
                  thing we should have done was to have <lb/> notified our debtors that until our
                  markets picked <lb/> up we would acknowledge our debt, and pay a <lb/> token
                  payment of say one third of one percent <lb/> and also tried at the time to get
                  our interest scaled <lb/> down. After all, we had spent a lot of the money <lb/>
                  fighting for democracy, it was just as well to face <lb/> it first as last. No,
                  that much was too much for <lb/> Newfoundland, where vested property has sacred
                  <lb/> rights above the call of human rights. Then the <lb/> Tory element came to
                  the fore and we had to <lb/> surrender our franchise, our birthright. Esau sold
                  <lb/> his for a mess of pottage, he made a better bargain <lb/> than us. I don't
                  know who got anything out of it. <lb/> I am sure the British government didn't,
                  for since <lb/> 1934 all liberal-minded people throughout the <lb/> world have
                  reminded her of her treatment of <lb/> Newfoundland. When serving on a great ship
                  in <lb/> 1940 and talking in the mess about the way the <lb/> democrats let the
                  Spanish republic down, one <lb/> steward who was secretary of the Barcelona <lb/>
                  Labour Party and on the run from Franco said, <lb/> "What did you expect of the
                  Tory element in <lb/>
                  <cb/> Britain, did they not take away Terra Nova's <lb/> constitution because she
                  could not pay to the <lb/> Yankee and British capitalists the interest on her
                  <lb/> debt, and that debt was only $2 a head for the <lb/> people of Britain?" So
                  you see, prestige is hard <lb/> to get and easy to lose. Then we got a Commis<lb
                     break="no"/>sion of Government, a cure for all our ills. I was <lb/> home from
                  1936 to 1939 and if ever there was a <lb/> hopeless, befuddled body of men in the
                  world's <lb/> history it was that same Commission. I'm sure <lb/> had the home
                  government given us the power to <lb/> elect our commissioners with the power the
                     com<lb break="no"/>missioners had, plus financial experts from the <lb/> old
                  country, the story would have been different <lb/> today. I doubt if we would have
                  been clamouring <lb/> for a change of government. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Let us review our country's past. With every<lb break="no"/>thing against us for the past 336 years since the 
     <lb/>
     first permanent settlers landed here, taking the 
     <lb/>
     type of country it's our lot to own, and the way 
     <lb/>
     our economic system has worked, we have made 
     <lb/>
     marvellous progress, and its because our people 
     <lb/>
     seem to be made out of different clay. The north 
     <lb/>
     breeds men, and our country bred good men - <lb/>we must never let them down, and I have great 
     <lb/>
     faith in the future. I don't think it's going to be 
     <lb/>
     easy. We don't want men of the type who sur<lb break="no"/>rendered our God-given right to vote. Personally, 
     <lb/>
     I don't think we'll get them, I think we have 
     <lb/>
     learned our lesson. Let us review our past finan<lb break="no"/>cially. The figures, if one is to believe the British 
     <lb/>
     year book from 1900 to 1930, show that with a 
     <lb/>
     population of less than 255,000, we exported 
     <lb/>
     nearly $700 million worth of goods and we im<lb break="no"/>ported just $l4 million less than we exported. Out 
     <lb/>
     of these imports we built a Grand Falls, a Corner 
     <lb/>
     Brook, Deer Lake, the dry dock, the New<lb break="no"/>foundland Hotel, hundreds of miles of railroads. 
     <lb/>
     Added to that we borrowed $70 million, added to 
     <lb/>
     the wages of a number of men who like myself 
     <lb/>
     worked outside the country and sent their money 
     <lb/>
     in, which probably in the 30 years reached nearly 
     <lb/>
     $100 million. Let us get down to the crux of the 
     <lb/>
     matter, and find out why, with this wealth in 
     <lb/>
     sight, we are in the place we are. In 1929 our 
     <lb/>
     exports totalled $40 million, or $140 per head for 
     <lb/>
     every man, woman and child in Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     That was our foreign trade. That year the foreign 
     <lb/>
     trade of the United States, the greatest in her 
     <lb/>
     history, was $42 per capita. Economists have told 
     <lb/>
     me we are the largest exporters per capita in the 
     <lb/>
         
            <pb n="54"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0054.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">54</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>
           
     British Empire, of goods taken from sea, forest, 
     <lb/>
     mines and land, and its all plain to the world that 
     <lb/>
     any country where exports exceed imports that 
     <lb/>
     country is in a healthy condition, except New<lb break="no"/>foundland. If we are going to eat, as Mr. Newell 
     <lb/>
     states, we have to find out how and where we are 
     <lb/>
     going to eat. We have got to have a plan and a 
     <lb/>
     government that will give us that freedom from 
     <lb/>
     fear and want that so many of us fought for. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I could not help thinking, when listening to 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Wild, with a revenue of $33 million, how our 
     <lb/>
     country in 1930 had exports valued at $7 million 
     <lb/>
     and a revenue of $1.25 million. Take our position 
     <lb/>
     today and then, are we not that much better off? 
     <lb/>
     If our social security and way of living would 
     <lb/>
     only increase with our expert and revenue, then 
     <lb/>
     we sure would have heaven on earth. I think in 
     <lb/>
     those days our "crooked" politicians did a good 
     <lb/>
     job, and if we get men of their stamp and manag<lb break="no"/>ing ability, plus the advanced knowledge of the 
     <lb/>
     last 46 years, it will augur well for the country. I 
     <lb/>
     am not in accord with this big plan spending. I 
     <lb/>
     believe in retrenchment with a capital "R" for the 
     <lb/>
     days that are always ahead after a war. Then plan. 
     <lb/>
     "Today" has always characterised their actions in 
     <lb/>
     the past — always the wrong thing at the wrong 
     <lb/>
     time. I believe the government is making a mis<lb break="no"/>take. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I voted against Mr. Smallwood bringing in an 
     <lb/>
     expert. I'm no BA but I don't want any expert to 
     <lb/>
     tell me why we don't eat or why we can't balance 
     <lb/>
     budgets. I have been a left wing socialist since 
     <lb/>
     1910, and have travelled to nearly every country 
     <lb/>
     with a coastline in the world. I have been for<lb break="no"/>tunate to meet folks who are trying and planning 
     <lb/>
     a better way of life. I have also taken notice of 
     <lb/>
     conditions in Newfoundland for 45 years and I'm 
     <lb/>
     not at all surprised that things are as they are, in 
     <lb/>
     fact with our laissez faire way its a wonder they 
     <lb/>
     are not worse.... I can answer Mr. Newell, before 
     <lb/>
     we eat we have to have a government "of the 
     <lb/>
     people, for the people and by the people" who 
     <lb/>
     will see that those conditions are eliminated and 
     <lb/>
     the common man is represented. I spent the six 
     <lb/>
     years of the war with 28 voyages to Europe, with 
     <lb/>
     Russia and the Mediterranean thrown in, and I 
     <lb/>
     can assure my learned colleague, Major Cashin, 
     <lb/>
     that the ports of Britain are no stranger to me. I 
     <lb/>
     detested the Commission of Government and 
     <lb/>
     would have fought it if it had been the best 
     <lb/>
     government in the world, and it was a long way 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
          
     from that, for I believe in democracy. I'm still of 
     <lb/>
     that mind. I could not get any news of what was 
     <lb/>
     going on home from this side, so I tried on the 
     <lb/>
     other. I met quite a few men who are in power 
     <lb/>
     today. I remember one of them saying, "New<lb break="no"/>foundland with nearly 20,000 of her sons and 
     <lb/>
     daughters working and fighting for democracy is 
     <lb/>
     under a dictatorship. It sounds ridiculous, but we 
     <lb/>
     don't know what to do for Newfoundland for they 
     <lb/>
     don't know what they want themselves." I'm sure 
     <lb/>
     we cannot place the blame on the Labour Party, 
     <lb/>
     for had you, Major Cashin, got 50 or 60 men 
     <lb/>
     together of sterling character and demanded self 
     <lb/>
     rule with a united populace behind you, Labour 
     <lb/>
     would have fought for us and I think the Tory 
     <lb/>
     element would have been glad to have changed 
     <lb/>
     it.... The only chance for the Labour Party to find 
     <lb/>
     out if there was really any political talent and 
     <lb/>
     interest in government was to call a National 
     <lb/>
     Convention. Take it from me, Labour is in sym<lb break="no"/>pathy with us and don't put the blame on them. I 
     <lb/>
     agree with you about our getting out a financial 
     <lb/>
     report by Newfoundlanders wholeheartedly, and 
     <lb/>
     the quicker our way; the British way in getting 
     <lb/>
     back our independence is going to be expensive 
     <lb/>
     and a long-drawn out affair, and we should peti<lb break="no"/>tion His Majesty's Government, as we are an 
     <lb/>
     elected body and heartily sick of Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government, and ask if they will turn the govern<lb break="no"/>ment over to us and let us put parties in the 
     <lb/>
     field, first for responsible government, second for 
     <lb/>
     modified Commission of Government, third for 
     <lb/>
     confederation with Canada, fourth North of 
     <lb/>
     Ireland status, and for three years educate our 
     <lb/>
     people in what they have lost, so our people will 
     <lb/>
     have full knowledge of the issues at stake. I 
     <lb/>
     believe this is the best and cheapest way, and I 
     <lb/>
     don't think it should be left to a later date. I 
     <lb/>
     believe this would be parliamentary, and no man 
     <lb/>
     could say the country was sold down the street. I 
     <lb/>
     have never thought the Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment legal. The Statute of Westminster states 
     <lb/>
     these seven self-governing nations within the 
     <lb/>
     British Commonwealth of Nations are in no way 
     <lb/>
     subordinate to each other, neither in their domes<lb break="no"/>tic or foreign policy, and as I read it that cannot 
     <lb/>
     be changed without a plebiscite of the people. 
     <lb/>
     That plebiscite was not held, the Alderdice 
     <lb/>
     government was elected to bring back prosperity 
     <lb/>
     to the country, not to sell it.... We, as the first 
     <lb/>
     elected body of Newfoundlanders, will forget the 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="55"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0055.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">55</fw>
           
     lapse of the past and hold the mother country to 
     <lb/>
     the Statute of Westminster, so let us go ahead and 
     <lb/>
     appeal to the mother country to allow us to take 
     <lb/>
     our place without a lot of beating around the bush, 
     <lb/>
     take over the job and quit ourselves as men.... So 
     <lb/>
     let us clear lower decks and face whatever our 
     <lb/>
     country calls for. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FOWL2">Mr. Fowler</persName> Mr. Chairman, if I recall correctly <lb/> some
                  speakers in the early stages of this debate <lb/> called for an end to oratory and
                  the beginning of <lb/> the real business of this Convention. I think that <lb/>
                  this was not the end but the beginning of such <lb/> oratory, and while I realize
                  that it is a great <lb/> temptation to any delegate, conscious of his <lb/>
                  ability, to burst forth in flowery speech, yet I also <lb/> contend, sir, that the
                  sooner we get down to real <lb/> business the better. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I agree that the people of this country are very 
     <lb/>
     much concerned over this business of eating in 
     <lb/>
     the future, but feel sure the great majority are also 
     <lb/>
     gravely concerned over the way they will vote, 
     <lb/>
     and as to whether they will have that precious 
     <lb/>
     right restored to them in future years. You need 
     <lb/>
     more than a full stomach in order to have a 
     <lb/>
     contented people, and history will bear out that 
     <lb/>
     statement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are about to discuss the report of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominions Office. This, I hope, will be an inter~ 
     <lb/>
     esting study, and give us a first class picture of 
     <lb/>
     our financial and economic position at the 
     <lb/>
     present. But how this Convention or any other 
     <lb/>
     body can determine whether Newfoundland will 
     <lb/>
     be self-supporting in say ten years from now, 
     <lb/>
     regardless of what form of government we adopt, 
     <lb/>
     is more than I can understand; and since the basis 
     <lb/>
     of our economy is by no means stable, a chance 
     <lb/>
     on the future must be taken in any event. There<lb break="no"/>fore, in order to justify ourselves before posterity, 
     <lb/>
     we owe it to them as well as to ourselves, to 
     <lb/>
     secure if possible a form of government which 
     <lb/>
     will embody the highest ideals of democracy and 
     <lb/>
     permit of the greatestopportunities for all. To this 
     <lb/>
     end, gentlemen, let us take up the work at hand 
     <lb/>
     in harmony and unity. Let us not strike the note 
     <lb/>
     of discord too loudly, for there are eager ears 
     <lb/>
     listening, but, in the words of Britain's wartime 
     <lb/>
     prime minister, "Let us go forward together." 
     <lb/>
     </p>
           
 <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, we have certainly <lb/>had an opportunity to hear
                  all shades of opinion. <lb/>I am amused at the idea of the open mind, and
                  <lb/>also of making sure of three meals a day. In order <lb/>
                  <cb/> to bring this thing to a close, I move that the <lb/> question he now put
                  with regard to the acceptance <lb/> of the report. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I have already spoken and I <lb/> can't speak
                  again, but may there not be other <lb/> delegates who may wish to speak? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MCCO4">Mr. McCormack</persName> Mr. Chairman, gentlemen, I <lb/> did not
                  propose to address the Convention as I am <lb/> unaccustomed to public speaking,
                  also because I <lb/> consider all this speech-making so much waste of <lb/> time
                  that could be used to better advantage. How<lb break="no"/>ever, as it seems to be
                  the order of the day and <lb/> apparently expected by many, I now ask for your
                  <lb/> tolerance. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Few of us came here with this so-called open 
     <lb/>
     mind, and as was to be expected, the proponents 
     <lb/>
     of the different forms of government are already 
     <lb/>
     showing their partiality to those whom they look 
     <lb/>
     to as leaders. I believe, however, that all are 
     <lb/>
     motivated with a sincere and honest desire to 
     <lb/>
     arrive at recommendations which will be of 
     <lb/>
     greater benefit to the many rather than to the few. 
     <lb/>
     It should be remembered meantime that each one 
     <lb/>
     of us expects to form conclusions from facts 
     <lb/>
     obtained, rather than from oratory in debate 
     <lb/>
     before these facts are obtained. The Steering 
     <lb/>
     Committee is to be complimented in this connec<lb break="no"/>tion in dividing the work between the different 
     <lb/>
     committees and we may now hope for more 
     <lb/>
     expediency in obtaining the information relative 
     <lb/>
     to our work. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Many questions have been tabled, most of 
     <lb/>
     them relevant, but not all of them absolutely 
     <lb/>
     necessary, the replies to which may be difficult 
     <lb/>
     to obtain, and, as the Hon. Mr. Wild suggested, it 
     <lb/>
     would be well to confine them to essentials, 
     <lb/>
     otherwise the compilation of replies will outlive 
     <lb/>
     the Convention itself. Surely we can arrive at an 
     <lb/>
     estimate of our national economy approximate 
     <lb/>
     enough to meet our requirements without seeking 
     <lb/>
     after minute details. With reference to our nation<lb break="no"/>al income, we cannot hope to obtain even a fairly 
     <lb/>
     approximate figure when no tabulation of in: 
     <lb/>
     dividual incomes is available from the majority, 
     <lb/>
     and even those would not contain supplementary 
     <lb/>
     income. I might refer to a large number 
     <lb/>
     throughout the island receiving monetary gifts 
     <lb/>
     regularly or otherwise from friends or relatives 
     <lb/>
     within the United States and Canada, I would 
     <lb/>
     suggest, in this connection, that Convention 
     <lb/>
     delegates, whom it may be assumed are conver<lb break="no"/><pb n="56"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0056.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">56</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>sant with the living conditions of their con<lb break="no"/>stituents, should be able to contribute towards a 
     <lb/>
     solution of this problem. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As for forms of government, in the final 
     <lb/>
     analysis no form of government can give 
     <lb/>
     economic security if our resources, when fully 
     <lb/>
     developed, are not capable of giving us a self-suf<lb break="no"/>ficient national income equitably distributed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Our chief concern, then, is to discover, not 
     <lb/>
     alone our economic position at the present time 
     <lb/>
     of abnormality, but, insofar as possible, what we 
     <lb/>
     can expect it to be in say ten years time. In 
     <lb/>
     speaking thus, I am not unmindful of our many 
     <lb/>
     neglected assets, as for example our geographic 
     <lb/>
     position, on which we should capitalise, and the 
     <lb/>
     many services supplied us at high cost by outside 
     <lb/>
     interests, which could and should be supplied by 
     <lb/>
     ourselves. We must not fail to remember that the 
     <lb/>
     government is primarily an administrative body, 
     <lb/>
     and may I quote in conclusion: "O'er forms of 
     <lb/>
     government let fools contest, That which is best 
     <lb/>
     administered is best." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Gentlemen, is it the wish that <lb/> we adjourn
                  the debate to enable any of the mem<lb break="no"/>bers who have not spoken to
                  speak on this mo<lb break="no"/>tion? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> I think that this would be a wise <lb/> move, and
                  for that reason I move the adjeumment <lb/> of the debate, because I think there
                  are many <lb/> members who have not had a chance to find their <lb/> feet, and we
                  ought to give them an opportunity to <lb/> do so, so that they can be more
                  accustomed to <lb/> speaking on the floor of the house before we get <lb/> to the
                  really serious business of this Convention. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Proposed by Mr. Bradley, <lb/>seconded by Mr.
                  Ballam that the debate on this <lb/>motion be adjourned. Carried unanimously.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Pursuant to the adoption of the Report of the 
     <lb/>
     Steering Committee, and in accordance with the 
     <lb/>
     suggestions of that committee, I appoint the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing committees: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (1) <hi rendition="simple:italic">Fisheries</hi> 
     <lb/>
     Brown (Convener) 
     <lb/>
     Job 
     <lb/>
    Goodridge 
     <lb/>Crosbie 
     <lb/>Bradley 
     <lb/>Ashboume 
     <lb/>Hillier 
     <lb/>Reddy 
     <lb/>Fudge 
     <lb/>
      
            <cb/>
           
     Figary 
     <lb/>(2) <hi rendition="simple:italic">Finance</hi> 
     <lb/>Cashin (Convener) 
     <lb/>Job 
     <lb/>Crosbie 
     <lb/>Hickman 
     <lb/>Crummey 
     <lb/>Keough 
     <lb/>Penny 
     <lb/>Goodridge 
     <lb/>Bellam 
     <lb/>Cranford <lb/>
(3) <hi rendition="simple:italic">Forestry</hi> 
     <lb/>Fudge (Convener) 
     <lb/>Cashin 
     <lb/>Dawe 
     <lb/>MacDonald 
     <lb/>Roberts 
     <lb/>Vardy 
     <lb/>Brown 
     <lb/>Vincent 
     <lb/>Northcott 
     <lb/>Bailey 
     <lb/>(4) <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mining</hi> 
     <lb/>Higgins (Convener) 
     <lb/>Hollett 
     <lb/>Banfield 
     <lb/>Miller 
     <lb/>Jackman 
     <lb/>Vardy 
     <lb/>Fowler 
     <lb/>McCarthy 
     <lb/>Watton 
     <lb/>Burry 
     <lb/>(5) <hi rendition="simple:italic">Agriculture</hi> 
     <lb/>Butt (Convener) 
     <lb/>McCormack 
     <lb/>Fogwill 
     <lb/>Keough 
     <lb/>Harmon 
     <lb/>Ballam 
     <lb/>Spencer 
     <lb/>McCarthy 
     <lb/>Jones 
     <lb/>Kennedy
     <lb/>(6) <hi rendition="simple:italic">Local Industries</hi> 
     <lb/>Hickman (Convenor) 
     <lb/>Reddy 
     <lb/>Dawe 
     <lb/>Hillier 
     <lb/>Penny 
     <lb/>
   
            <pb n="57"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0057.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">57</fw>
          
     Vincent 
     <lb/>
    McCormack 
     <lb/>Starkes 
     <lb/>Cranford 
     <lb/>Jackman 
     <lb/>(7) <hi rendition="simple:italic">Education</hi> 
     <lb/>Hollett (Convenor) 
     <lb/>Fowler 
     <lb/>Jones 
     <lb/>Fogwill 
     <lb/>Spencer 
     <lb/>Miller 
     <lb/>Harrington 
     <lb/>Smallwood 
     <lb/>Ryan 
     <lb/>Newell 
     <lb/>(8) <hi rendition="simple:italic">Public Health and Welfare</hi> 
     <lb/>Ashboume (Convener) 
     <lb/>Newell 
     <lb/>Roberts 
     <lb/>Higgins 
     <lb/>Harrington 
     <lb/>Kennedy 
     <lb/>Banfield 
     <lb/>Burry 
     <lb/>Crummey 
     <lb/>Starkes 
     <lb/>(9) <hi rendition="simple:italic">Transportation</hi> 
     <lb/>Bradley (Convener) 
     <lb/>Smallwood 
     <lb/>Hannon 
     <lb/>Figaxy 
     <lb/>Northcott 
     <lb/>Ryan 
     <lb/>Bailey 
     <lb/>Watton 
     <lb/>Butt 
     <lb/>MacDonald 
     <lb/>
            </p>
 
<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The Committee on Information<lb/> will consist of Mr. Bradley,
                  KC. and Mr. Hig<lb break="no"/>gins, K.C., in association with myself; and in<lb/>
                  view of the alteration of the procedure there will<lb/> be no necessity in the
                  future for notice of ques<lb break="no"/>tions. All requests for information will
                  now be<lb/> passed to the Committee on Information and they<lb/> will transmit
                  them forthwith to the appropriate<lb/> departments for information. Will the
                  convenors<lb/> of the various committees notify the committees<lb/> to meet in
                  accordance with the schedule. We will<lb/>
                  <cb/> now proceed with the orders of the day. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Since I tabled notice of this <lb/> motion<ref
                     target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> we have heard Mr. Wild. At the session <lb/>
                  yesterday there was some difficulty in getting the <lb/> exact figure showing the
                  gross national produc<lb break="no"/>tion of the country and it was suggested that
                  by a <lb/> process of sampling there could be arrived at <lb/> something fairly
                  accurate, approximate, at least, <lb/> of the figure asked for in this resolution.
                  You <lb/> gentlemen are quite familiar what arguments <lb/> there are in favour of
                  the general idea of knowing <lb/> the value of the gross national production of
                  the <lb/> country. It is an entirely different motion, of <lb/> course, from that
                  defeated here the other day - <lb/>the one which asked for the appointment to the
                  <lb/> Convention of a statistician-economist. This <lb/> solely asks that the
                  government should provide <lb/> us with the information. How they get it is not
                  our <lb/> business. We do not put a time limit there, but <lb/> within the next
                  couple or three months we want <lb/> some approximate idea, something more com<lb
                     break="no"/>plete than is given in Dr. McKay's book where <lb/> there is an
                  attempt at guessing the national <lb/> production. I make that motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I second that motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> I do stress the difference between <lb/> this and
                  the motion which was defeated the other <lb/> day. I think we must all agree that
                  every bit of <lb/> information possible for us to have ought to be <lb/> laid
                  before us. Just how accurate an estimate of <lb/> the gross national production of
                  this country can <lb/> be obtained by the government, I do not know. I <lb/> am
                  neither a statistician nor am I an economist; <lb/> but I think Mr. Wild indicated
                  that something <lb/> more could be done than has as yet been done, <lb/> and for
                  that reason I think we would be making a <lb/> very grave mistake if we refuse to
                  adopt this <lb/> resolution. It is an effort to get all the information <lb/> and
                  in order for us to get a basic figure. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I take it the Finance Committee <lb/> will take
                  that under consideration as one of their <lb/> first duties. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I am in favour of the proposal; it is <lb/>
                  essential that we know the gross national produc<lb break="no"/>tion, but why not
                  have it for, say, 1939 and for <lb/> 1933, otherwise it will be impossible for us
                  to <lb/> make the comparison. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I would like to have it for every <lb/> year
                  for the last 50 years, but it is a sheer impos<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_01"
                     >[1] 0n September 19, 1946, Mr. Smallwood gave notice of motion to ask the
                     government for a statement of the<lb/>gross national product, see p.
                     39.</note><pb n="58"
                     facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-20_Page_0058.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">58</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>sibility. It has never been done; it can be
                  done <lb/> only with respect to figures that can be gotten. <lb/> The original
                  data upon which the final figure <lb/> would be built are missing except
                  for'possibly <lb/> last year and this year. They exist, but not in <lb/> written
                  form — in government accounts but <lb/>
                  <cb/> never as actual written data. I wish they had. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I take the liberty of deleting the <lb/>word
                  "House" and substituting the word "Con<lb break="no"/>vention" in this resolution.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried unanimously, and the Con<lb break="no"/>vention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-02-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


            <!--<milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     September 24, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Order of the day. Presentation 
     <lb/>
     of the reply of His Excellency the Governor to 
     <lb/>
     the address of loyalty and the address of thanks. 
     <lb/>
     I beg to inform you, gentlemen, that pursuant to 
     <lb/>
     your appointing, and on the request of the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor, a delegation attended upon His Excellency, 
     <lb/>
     and presented to him the address of loyalty and 
     <lb/>
     the address of thanks for the speech with which 
     <lb/>
     he opened the Convention. The address of loyalty 
     <lb/>
     will be forwarded to His Majesty, and His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency was pleased to make the following reply to 
     <lb/>
     the address which was presented to him: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman and Gentlemen of the Na<lb break="no"/>tional Convention: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I thank you for your address in reply to the 
     <lb/>
     speech with which the Convention was 
     <lb/>
     opened on Wednesday, Sept. 11, 1946. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Gordon Macdonald 
     <lb/>
     Governor 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Government House 
     <lb/>
    St. John's, Nfld. 
     <lb/>21 Sept. 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     [The Convention resolved into a committee of the 
     <lb/>
     whole] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman I have the pleasure to bring to 
     <lb/>
     you this afternoon the Honourable the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner for Finance who has very kindly consented 
     <lb/>
     to address you today on the eve of his departure 
     <lb/>
     Gentlemen, Mr. Wild. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Wild I am not going to address you formal<lb break="no"/>ly; I hoped thatI might have a chance of speaking 
     <lb/>
     on some of the points raised by members of the 
     <lb/>
     committee who would like further information 
     <lb/>
     on some of the general topics covered at our last 
     <lb/>
     meeting. I cannot give you figures as I am not the 
     <lb/>
     type who can carry masses of figures in his head, 
     <lb/>
     but I would be glad to give your any information 
     <lb/>
     in a very broad manner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Has any member any question 
     <lb/>
     to direct to Mr. Wild? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin The first question I would like to 
     <lb/>
     ask Mr. Wild is, does he think it is good business 
     <lb/>
     to borrow money when there is money in the 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     treasury? In 1942-43 the government borrowed 
     <lb/>
     $1.5 million; from 1940-41 up to the end of 1945, 
     <lb/>
     $3 million was invested in war savings certifi<lb break="no"/>cates with interest at 3% per annum. $8.5 million 
     <lb/>
     was borrowed altogether. We did not have to 
     <lb/>
     borrow that money. What was the idea of borrow<lb break="no"/>ing that money? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Wild I would like to point out that the 
     <lb/>surplus at the end of March, 1946, was $28.5 
     <lb/>million; since then we have set aside $3 million 
     <lb/>for the redemption of two sterling loans, which 
     <lb/>leaves us a surplus of $25 million. At the moment 
     <lb/>the revenue from April I, 1946, is considerably 
     <lb/>in excess of expenditure; but that surplus at the 
     <lb/>moment is no indication that increases will be 
     <lb/>continuous. Revenue comes in more quickly 
     <lb/>from income tax in the first two months of the 
     <lb/>year. It is not a clear indication of the ultimate 
     <lb/>picture. For instance, we budgeted for a deficit 
     <lb/>this year on account of reconstruction expendi<lb break="no"/>ture. Major Cashin's question was mainly why 
     <lb/>did the government do a certain thing? I do not 
     <lb/>know that it is the intention of the committee that 
     <lb/>the reasons why should be investigated. There are 
     <lb/>certain answers that I could give, but on general 
     <lb/>principle, I would say that your main intention is 
     <lb/>to get the position as it was some years ago. If one 
     <lb/>is to give reasons for every action, I am afraid we 
     <lb/>shall not get very far. I make that as a matter of 
     <lb/>principle. Actually, there were very good 
     <lb/>grounds for the loans we raised during the war. 
     <lb/>The main reason was anti-inflation. It was not 
     <lb/>that we wanted money; we didn't. The question 
     <lb/>was what to do with it when we had it. If I had 
     <lb/>been able to dispose of the money, I would have 
     <lb/>gone out for bigger borrowing. We had the War 
     <lb/>Savings Committee most of the members were 
     <lb/>residents of St. John's, but there were also out<lb break="no"/>port members — we had a committee which used 
     <lb/>to give us advice before borrowing. It was largely 
     <lb/>for the purpose of encouraging thrift, and it had 
     <lb/>been done to a greater extent in other countries. 
     <lb/>What we did was the best thing. We borrowed in 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

</div>         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>