<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-11-05"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-11-05">5 November 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>.   
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="154"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0150.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0151.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0152.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0153.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0154.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-02-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-07">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0150">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0150.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0151">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0151.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0152">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0152.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0153">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0153.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0154">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0154.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="150"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0150.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">150</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
           
<!-- GL, 2017-02-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

 <!--<p>
     negotiate with the Canadian government in 
     <lb/>
     regard to possible federal union. There are 
     <lb/>
     thousands of Newfoundlanders tonight who have 
     <lb/>
     a strong desire for confederation and those people 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     have the right to request and receive all the facts 
     <lb/>
     pertaining to the terms of confederation. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>[The Convention adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   

<div type="section">
            <head>
     November 5, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read a report and correspon<lb break="no"/>dence from the Newfoundland Industrial 
     <lb/>
     Development Board<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> </hi>
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I give notice that I will on tomorrow <lb/>
                  <cb/> move that the report of the Industrial Develop<lb break="no"/>ment Board be
                  referred to a committee for con<lb break="no"/>sideration. <lb/>
               </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     Motion to send a Delegation to Ottawa<ref target="#fn_02">[2]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> In view of the fact that this report may <lb/> have
                  an effect upon the people's thinking, I move <lb/> that the debate be adjourned
                  until tomorrow, and <lb/> that we proceed with the other orders of the day. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Anybody second that motion? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KENN3">Mr. Kennedy</persName> I second the motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Moved by Mr. Butt and secon<lb break="no"/>ded
                  by Mr. Kennedy that the debate on the mo<lb break="no"/>tion to send a delegation
                  to Ottawa be adjourned <lb/> until tomorrow to allow the members time to <lb/>
                  study the report and the enclosure of Mr. Pratt's <lb/> address. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[After some debate, the motion to adjourn debate 
     <lb/>
     was defeated]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Chairman, since adjouming <lb/> last evening
                  I gave some thought to the matter <lb/> under discussion today with the idea of
                  trying to <lb/> reconcile the different points of view.... I sum it <lb/> up in
                  this way, in eight points: <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     1. We are all agreed that we want the terms 
     <lb/>
     of confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. The difference between us is when is the 
     <lb/>
     time to make the inquiry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. Mr. Smallwood's motion is to start the 
     <lb/>
     machinery for the approach to Canada immedi<lb break="no"/>ately. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. Mr. Penney's amendment is to defer the 
     <lb/>
     approach until we have finished the reports. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. Mr. Bradley's amendment is the same as 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood's motion, but the delegation is 
     <lb/>
     not to leave before the first of January. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6. If Mr. Bradley's amendment is passed and 
     <lb/>
     the delegates named, they can begin work imme<lb break="no"/>diately and work through the Christmas vacation. 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     7. The delegates appointed would be 
     <lb/>
     honourable men and would, I am confident, not 
     <lb/>
     be prepared to consult with the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     authorities until they are armed with the neces<lb break="no"/>sary data. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     8. So that there would be no doubt in the 
     <lb/>
     minds of the members of the Convention, I sug<lb break="no"/>gest that if the amendment suggested by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Bradley was carried, that before the delegates left 
     <lb/>
     for Canada they individually assure the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion that they were so armed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With that safeguard I cannot imagine any 
     <lb/>
     doubt in the minds of the delegates as to the 
     <lb/>
     approach being in safe hands..... With that 
     <lb/>
     safeguard, I can see no objection to having the 
     <lb/>
     amendment moved by Mr. Bradley passed im<lb break="no"/>mediately. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CRUM1">Mr. Crummey</persName> I rise for the purpose of report<lb break="no"
                  />ing my position as to the matter before the Chair. <lb/> I have listened
                  attentively to all the speeches. <lb/> Some of the discussion did not appeal to
                  me. I do <lb/> not intend to make a speech, I think time enough <lb/> has been
                  wasted. I will be as concise as I possibly <lb/> can. The motion is that a
                  delegation will be <lb/> appointed from this National Convention. The <lb/>
                  amendment is that the sending of a delegation be <lb/> deferred, and the reasons
                  offered I consider <lb/> sound. The amendment to the amendment is a <lb/> simple
                  matter of trying to befog the issue. The <lb/> sending of a delegation from this
                  Convention I <lb/> cannot agree with, because I take the position that <lb/> the
                  matter of confederation, or federation must be <lb/> negotiated by governments and
                  we are not a <lb/> govemment.... I want to state emphatically that I <lb/>
                  <note xml:id="fn_01">1 This Board was created in January 1942 to promote the
                     innovation and expansion of diversified industries in <lb/> Newfoundland. For
                     further information see Peter Neary, Newfoundland in the Atlantic World,
                     1929-1949 <lb/>(Kingston and Montreal. 1988), p. 168.</note>
                  <note xml:id="fn_02">2 Above, pp. 93, 104, 120, 128. [Debate Days: 1946- 10-28,
                     10-30, and 11-04]</note>
                  <pb n="151" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0151.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">151</fw> do not consider the question of confederation is <lb/> a
                  matter for the National Convention to decide, I <lb/> mean to negotiate, even
                  getting the terms. There <lb/> is nothing left for me to do but to support the
                  <lb/> amendment as it states definitely that the matter <lb/> may come up for
                  consideration later on. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MCCO4">Mr. McCormack</persName> Mr. Newell has said that <lb/> most delegates
                  are one up on him. I might say that <lb/> most delegates are three up on me. I
                  have not <lb/> spoken to either the motion or the amendment, or <lb/> to the
                  amendment to the amendment... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Previous to the introduction of the original 
     <lb/>
     motion the various committees were working 
     <lb/>
     harmoniously on the primary task. The motion by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood was not startling in itself, as most 
     <lb/>
     delegates seemed to take it for granted that we 
     <lb/>
     would want to know eventually the terms Canada 
     <lb/>
     was willing to offer under confederation. What 
     <lb/>
     was startling was the fact that it was brought in 
     <lb/>
     at that stage in our proceedings. Its introduction 
     <lb/>
     disrupted the work of the committees, and what 
     <lb/>
     is more, the tirade delivered by the mover tended 
     <lb/>
     to resolve the debate into an issue on confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The amendment offered by Mr. Penney 
     <lb/>
     seemed a logical thing at the time. Nothing has 
     <lb/>
     changed since, despite well-prepared speeches 
     <lb/>
     and the masterly way in which many of them 
     <lb/>
     have been presented. I must confess that I am not 
     <lb/>
     impressed with the points made, and have not 
     <lb/>
     been influenced by them to alter my original 
     <lb/>
     opinion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The fact that several delegates reiterated, too 
     <lb/>
     convincingly, that they were not confederates, 
     <lb/>
     makes one feel we would do well to exercise the 
     <lb/>
     suspicions for which we are becoming prover<lb break="no"/>bial, and look for underlying motives. Mr. Brad<lb break="no"/>ley, in a very logical address, presented with the 
     <lb/>
     ability of a master, has expressed concern over 
     <lb/>
     the time which might elapse in the setting up of 
     <lb/>
     machinery and the consequent delay in obtaining 
     <lb/>
     information. I cannot be persuaded, even by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Bradley, that the setting in motion of machinery 
     <lb/>
     would entail such delay as would warrant our 
     <lb/>
     rushing to Canada without necessary facts about 
     <lb/>
     our own country. He talks of January lst, which 
     <lb/>
     gives us a mere six weeks. What does a little time 
     <lb/>
     or the expenditure of a few thousand dollars 
     <lb/>
     amount to, when we consider the momentous task 
     <lb/>
     confronting this Convention? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If the outcome of the national referendum 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
         
     happened to be responsible government or Com<lb break="no"/>mission government we could look forward to a 
     <lb/>
     change at the wishes of the electorate, but if we 
     <lb/>
     commit ourselves as a tenth province the decision 
     <lb/>
     will be irrevocable. We have no guarantee that a 
     <lb/>
     referendum will be held before 1950, and should 
     <lb/>
     we obtain terms now, who is prophet enough to 
     <lb/>
     foretell if these terms would be official then? I 
     <lb/>
     propose to vote for the original amendment so we 
     <lb/>
     can put first things first and get on with the work 
     <lb/>
     of our committees and arrive at a solution of our 
     <lb/>
     primary task, discovering not whether we are 
     <lb/>
     self-supporting, but rather to what degree we are 
     <lb/>
     self-supporting, and for how long a period we can 
     <lb/>
     reasonably hope to remain so, keeping in mind 
     <lb/>
     the unprecedented and unpredictable condition 
     <lb/>
     of world affairs. We would then be in a position 
     <lb/>
     to seek terms of federal union and should do so 
     <lb/>
     without any feeling of inferiority, realising that 
     <lb/>
     both parties would expect to benefit thereby. It is 
     <lb/>
     my pleasure to support Mr, Penney's amendment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:KENN3">Mr. Kennedy</persName> I have listened until this stage of <lb/> the
                  National Convention with intent and interest, <lb/> but with the introduction of
                  this latest amendment <lb/> to the amendment, my patience has neared its <lb/>
                  end. Certain members of this assembly seem to <lb/> have forgotten what they were
                  put here to do. The <lb/> general attitude of these individuals has been <lb/>
                  revolting, and the presentation of their one-track<lb break="no"/>ed narrow-minded
                  outlook has revealed all too <lb/> plainly what they consider to be the main
                  object <lb/> at stake. We are here to seek information and on <lb/> the basis of
                  such information to recommend the <lb/> form of government we consider most
                  beneficial <lb/> to our beloved country and not, as some members <lb/> have
                  obviously concluded, to prattle on seeking <lb/> salve for our own wounded
                  prestige. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     If one and all of our present nine working 
     <lb/>
     committees could this week, or any other week 
     <lb/>
     for that matter, present the vital statistics to prove 
     <lb/>
     this country independent, what an utter waste of 
     <lb/>
     money, and what a world-wide laughing stock 
     <lb/>
     this Convention would become by prolonging 
     <lb/>
     such ridiculous tittle-tattle as this futile motion 
     <lb/>
     and equally futile amendment to the amendment 
     <lb/>
     have produced. Let us in the name of heaven 
     <lb/>
     stamp out this egotistical self-elevation, and as a 
     <lb/>
     team get down to the work which this motion and 
     <lb/>
     the amendment to the amendment are seeking to 
     <lb/>
     sabotage by their untimely and scheming inter<lb break="no"/>ruption. Not only I but our constituents are be<lb break="no"/><pb n="152"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0152.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">152</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>coming impatient. Can you blame them? I sug<lb break="no"/>gest that this Convention first obtain clear-cut 
     <lb/>
     national facts and so put our country, and not our 
     <lb/>
     ideological crazy whims first. In all earnestness, 
     <lb/>
     let us behave and pull together as gentlemen and 
     <lb/>
     true Newfoundlanders, and not like so many old 
     <lb/>
     women in constant discord with our neighbours 
     <lb/>
     on the other side of the fence. Take down that 
     <lb/>
     fence and in its place insert the programme which 
     <lb/>
     is planned, and which we were put here to carry 
     <lb/>
     out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> ....I want these terms, but the <lb/> time is
                  not ripe to get these terms; we must first <lb/> set our house in order, and until
                  then we should <lb/> make no attempt to get any more than the facts <lb/> that our
                  various committees are now gathering. <lb/> Surely we have many men in this
                  country and <lb/> assembly who are capable of running our affairs. <lb/> We have
                  lots of good businessmen in this house <lb/> today who could take care of
                  Newfoundland, and <lb/> do it well, if they were given the job. I think we <lb/>
                  have gone far enough with the debate, and I <lb/> suggest that we vote on this
                  issue, and see where <lb/> we arrive. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DAWE1">Mr. Dawe</persName> Mr. Chairman, I have no prepared <lb/> speech. I
                  happen to have had the honour to rep<lb break="no"/>resent Newfoundland at the
                  Imperial Ottawa <lb/> Conferences at the request of the Newfoundland <lb/> Board
                  of Trade on timber in 1932, and I have had <lb/> an office in the Ottawa House of
                  Parliament <lb/> building. I know something of the tricks of the <lb/> trade and
                  political intrigue. I have been in <lb/> England, and I know some of the senators
                  of <lb/> Canada, the late Senator Webster of the British <lb/> Coal Corporation,
                  with whom I negotiated the <lb/> first barter deal of pitprops with England for
                  300 <lb/> years, and later through Senator Webster 250,000 <lb/> tons of Wabana
                  ore. The basis of our Ottawa <lb/> agreement was contingent on Newfoundland <lb/>
                  selling 500,000 tons of Wabana ore. Baldwin and <lb/> Thomas promised Mr.
                  Alderdice they would do <lb/> their best, and I succeeded in breaking down the
                  <lb/> prejudice of the blast furnace owners in England <lb/> with the result that
                  Wabana ore is going there <lb/> today. Baldwin and Thomas did not do it, and I
                  <lb/> have the correspondence for it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I move that the question be put. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STAR1">Mr. Starkes</persName> In speaking on the amendment <lb/>made by Mr.
                  Penney, I want to be clear that I <lb/>came to this National Convention with an
                  open <lb/>mind, elected by the people in Green Bay district <lb/>
                  <cb/> for the third time in succession during the past 18 <lb/> years; and by the
                  way, no other member sitting <lb/> in this Convention can boast of that record. I
                  do <lb/> because I am confident that the people in my <lb/> district elected me,
                  feeling sure I would take a <lb/> firm stand and demand what I thought would be
                  <lb/> of the greatest importance to those people was <lb/> sent me here. In
                  supporting the resolution a few <lb/> days ago brought in by Mr. Smallwood, I made
                  <lb/> it plain I stood here opposed to confederation at <lb/> that time. I am also
                  opposed at the present time <lb/> to responsible government, and for that reason
                  <lb/> suggested when speaking on the resolution, that <lb/> we also should
                  ascertain from the British House <lb/> of Parliament what they are prepared to do
                  for us <lb/> in the way of cancelling our national debt, or any <lb/> other
                  handouts that we should be prepared to <lb/> consider valuable, having in mind our
                  very close <lb/> connections to the mother country, and the valu<lb break="no"
                  />able aid this country has rendered her. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I am definitely opposed to the present form of 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government as we had it forced 
     <lb/>
     upon us and had to endure it during the past 13 
     <lb/>
     years. I said "forced upon us", because we all 
     <lb/>
     know that the government of thatday, before they 
     <lb/>
     went to the country, made a pledge when present<lb break="no"/>ing their manifesto that before they would change 
     <lb/>
     our constitution, they would first submit the 
     <lb/>
     change to the people in a referendum. This they 
     <lb/>
     did not do, they did not stand by their pledge 
     <lb/>
     made to the electorate, but voted for and insti<lb break="no"/>tuted the present form of Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. I must confess that many of our people 
     <lb/>
     have during those years lost interest in the public 
     <lb/>
     affairs of this country, probably brought about by 
     <lb/>
     this so called prosperity that our country now 
     <lb/>
     enjoys. We are all conscious of the fact that this 
     <lb/>
     prosperity is not going to last forever, and God 
     <lb/>
     knows, everyone here must feel in their own 
     <lb/>
     hearts that we now must determine the future 
     <lb/>
     destiny of our people bearing in mind the prob<lb break="no"/>ability, almost the certainty, that hard times will 
     <lb/>
     come again. It would be all right to talk about 
     <lb/>
     responsible government, if we could feel confi<lb break="no"/>dent that the present degree of prosperity will 
     <lb/>
     hang on for the next 20 or 30 years.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The people of this country, and here I can 
     <lb/>
     speak very positively about the district of Green 
     <lb/>
     Bay, have a great dread in their hearts about the 
     <lb/>
     future that lies before them. That, sir, is why so 
     <lb/>
     many of our Newfoundland people today are so 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="153"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0153.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">153</fw>
           
     doubtful and so fearful about bringing respon<lb break="no"/>sible government back to our country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But there are those in this Convention who are 
     <lb/>
     all in favour of responsible government. I am not 
     <lb/>
     one of those, and I am not one of those with much 
     <lb/>
     faith or belief in Commission government. I do 
     <lb/>
     not deny that they have done some good things 
     <lb/>
     for this country. How could they be here for 12 
     <lb/>
     or 13 years without doing some good? I believe 
     <lb/>
     the people should have some say in the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of their country, and that is why I am willing 
     <lb/>
     and anxious to get all the facts about union with 
     <lb/>
     Canada. I do not pretend I know anything about 
     <lb/>
     such union and its benefits, or disadvantages, that 
     <lb/>
     is why I am anxious to at least hear the terms, so 
     <lb/>
     that we can discuss and debate them, and if we so 
     <lb/>
     desire have it placed on the ballot paper for the 
     <lb/>
     electorate to make the final decision. I am not a 
     <lb/>
     confederate, neither am I anti-confederate, but I 
     <lb/>
     can assure this house that if the people support 
     <lb/>
     the terms at the referendum, Newfoundlanders 
     <lb/>
     most assuredly will have their elected repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives; they would then have their elected 
     <lb/>
     prime ministers, and be given a chance to throw 
     <lb/>
     them out, and elect someone else after four years 
     <lb/>
     of their stewartship. Someone may say that 
     <lb/>
     responsible government would give us that. Yes 
     <lb/>
     it would, but how would it give it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Would responsible government have any hope 
     <lb/>
     of success when the hard times came again? Or 
     <lb/>
     would it mean that we would be on our own 
     <lb/>
     again, with nobody to come to our rescue? I think 
     <lb/>
     I know already what the outcome would be. What 
     <lb/>
     I and our people want to know is this: under 
     <lb/>
     confederation, would we have help in case of 
     <lb/>
     need? That is another reason why I am so anxious 
     <lb/>
     to get the terms and conditions of confederation 
     <lb/>
     without too much delay. Now so far as Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Penney's amendment is concerned, it's all right 
     <lb/>
     for one thing only, and that is to give the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion not two months or six months hoist, but to 
     <lb/>
     obliterate it completely.... The people are not 
     <lb/>
     going to be satisfied to have this confederation 
     <lb/>
     matter put on the shelf. They are determined to 
     <lb/>
     have the terms, as many telegrams from my dis<lb break="no"/>trict have clearly shown me these past four or five 
     <lb/>
     days, and other telegrams to other delegates have 
     <lb/>
     shown so clearly, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would like to know what is wrong with 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Bradley's amendment. It says very clearly 
     <lb/>
     that no matter when the delegation is appointed, 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     it cannot go to Canada before January 1, 1947. 
     <lb/>
     What do the opponents of this amendment want? 
     <lb/>
     Do they want it to be next February or next 
     <lb/>
     March, or next April or May? I'm one man who 
     <lb/>
     isn't willing to hang around here all through the 
     <lb/>
     winter helping to spend $1,000 a day of the 
     <lb/>
     people's money. It's all very well to pooh-pooh 
     <lb/>
     such a small matter but $1,000 a day sounds like 
     <lb/>
     a lot of money in a district where they haven't 
     <lb/>
     even got a doctor, such as Green Bay district, 
     <lb/>
     although 25 years ago they had two. To some 
     <lb/>
     people a $1,000 a day may sound like a very small 
     <lb/>
     amount. They may be willing to stay here for a 
     <lb/>
     whole year spending this money, but so far as the 
     <lb/>
     people of Green Bay are concerned I think they 
     <lb/>
     would much rather see some of this money going 
     <lb/>
     to help them with the new cottage hospital that 
     <lb/>
     they hope to have built at Springdale, the capital 
     <lb/>
     of my district, to which I hope and trust the 
     <lb/>
     government of today will give very serious con<lb break="no"/>sideration. Seeing the way things are going here, 
     <lb/>
     I feel like putting on my coat and going home. It 
     <lb/>
     looks like a certain number of people are out to 
     <lb/>
     kill the people's chance to get the terms of con<lb break="no"/>federation. And why? Is it because they want 
     <lb/>
     responsible government, that they spend half 
     <lb/>
     their time trying to think up this objection or that 
     <lb/>
     objection to this motion and amendment to get 
     <lb/>
     the terms of confederation? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Before I sit down I want to tell this Convention 
     <lb/>
     that the people are going to have the terms of 
     <lb/>
     confederation in spite of the efforts of a certain 
     <lb/>
     few to keep it from them.... I would not be doing 
     <lb/>
     my duty to my district and my country if I voted 
     <lb/>
     against getting these terms, so I will vote for the 
     <lb/>
     motion as amended by Mr. Bradley. I call upon 
     <lb/>
     every fair-minded man in this Convention to do 
     <lb/>
     likewise. It's time for us to give the people a 
     <lb/>
     chance, and not deny them the chance to get the 
     <lb/>
     truth about this matter once and for all. Can't we 
     <lb/>
     as men be true to the confidence placed in us, 
     <lb/>
     secure the facts from the Dominion of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     from the United Kingdom, and if need be and it 
     <lb/>
     is possible, secure the facts from the United 
     <lb/>
     States of America? That is what we are sent here 
     <lb/>
     for, and why not do it now? I give my whole<lb break="no"/>hearted support to the amendment made by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Bradley. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I rise to a point of order for informa<lb
                     break="no"/>tion. I would like to know whether or not we have <lb/> gotten into
                  a place where we are to discuss forms <lb/>
                  <pb n="154" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-05_Page_0154.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">154</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> of government. I would like to know,
                  because I <lb/> certainly will defend responsible government, <lb/> and I may have
                  something to say about some of <lb/> those who conducted our affairs at that
                  particular <lb/> time. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I have listened carefully to the dif<lb break="no"
                  />ferent speeches, but I have not said very much <lb/> and I think the pattern
                  seems to fall clearly. What <lb/> is wrong? We are going to find the terms under
                  <lb/> which Canada will accept us into union. I believe <lb/> we don't want to go
                  to Canada to get the terms. <lb/> The terms have been right here in St. John's for
                  <lb/> a long time. Newfoundland has been used as an <lb/> international pawn, and
                  you and I today are noth<lb break="no"/>ing, only pawns in the game. Our fate was
                  sealed <lb/> nearly two years ago. Everybody wants the terms <lb/> of union. I
                  guess nearly everybody here knows <lb/> what they are....<ref target="#fn_03"
                     >[1]</ref>
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FIGA1">Mr. Figary</persName> Mr. Chairman, I rise for the purpose <lb/>
                  <cb/> of seconding Mr. Crosbie's motion. I have lis<lb break="no"/>tened to
                  different speakers this afternoon on the <lb/> amendment to the amendment, and
                  practically <lb/> every one of them stated that there was a great <lb/> deal of
                  time wasted in the discussion on this <lb/> confederation matter. I can stop a
                  gramaphone <lb/> from talking, but to try and stop some people <lb/> from
                  continuous talking is, I am afraid, too big a <lb/> job for me to do. However. I
                  may say that my <lb/> patience is about exhausted, and I would suggest <lb/> that
                  we get down to the real business of the <lb/> Convention in a right and proper
                  manner. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Chairman then put the motion on the floor 
     <lb/>
     to a vote. The original motion was defeated 25- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     17. The Chairman then put Mr. Bradley's motion 
     <lb/>
     as an alternative amendment rather than an 
     <lb/>
     amendment to Mr. Penney's amendment. It was 
     <lb/>
     defeated 25-17. Mr. Penney's amendment was 
     <lb/>
     carried 25-18. The Convention then adjourned. ]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

     <note xml:id="fn_03">1 The rest of Mr. Bailey's speech, as reported, is muddled.</note> 
    
     
    <!-- GL, 2017-02-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->      
           <!-- <p>
     November 6, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Chairman2 I am very sorry to say that 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Mr. Justice Fox is unfortunately and un<lb break="no"/>avoidably absent because of some illness. I feel 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     sure that you will all join me in hoping he will 
     <lb/>
     have a very speedy return here to his duty as 
     <lb/>
     Chairman. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Education Committee:3 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Hollett In introducing this Report of the 
     <lb/>
     Committee on Education, I wish to state that the 
     <lb/>
     Committee consisted of Messrs. Harrington, 
     <lb/>
     Fowler, Spencer, Ryan, Fogwill, Miller, Jones, 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood, Newell and myself. Each and every 
     <lb/>
     one of these members gave full attendance to all 
     <lb/>
     sessions of the Committee and gave great aid in 
     <lb/>
     bringing it in so quickly. To mention any par<lb break="no"/>ticular names might be invidious, but I am bound 
     <lb/>
     to mention the name of Mr. Newell, the secretary 
     <lb/>
     whom we appointed; and Mr. Smallwood and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Harrington, appointed to assimilate and 
     <lb/>
     compile the facts obtained by them and by the 
     <lb/>
     whole Committee. I would also like to pay tribute 
     <lb/>
     to Mr. Hanley of the Department of Education 
     <lb/>
     who assisted us very materially in getting 
     <lb/>
     together the necessary data. These remarks also 
     <lb/>
     apply to all members of the department. You 
     <lb/>
     have had this report for some considerable time, 
     <lb/>
     and whilst in presenting it I did not read it fully, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            
            <p>2Captain W.G. Warren, the Convention's Secretary, acted as Chairman in the absence of Mr. Justice Fox. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     3Volume 11:65. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     I feel sure you have given it sufficient study to 
     <lb/>
     debate it without having it read again. If that be 
     <lb/>
     so, then on behalf of the Education Committee 
     <lb/>
     we invite now your criticism, either constructive 
     <lb/>
     or destructive. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood It seems to me that the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion may find in the report two matters for criti<lb break="no"/>cism. One is the second paragraph which 
     <lb/>
     describes the Committee's whole approach to the 
     <lb/>
     subject of its investigation; the other would be the 
     <lb/>
     final conclusions of the Committee, section 11. 
     <lb/>
     In section 2 it says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Committee decided at the outset that 
     <lb/>
     its approach to the subject of education must 
     <lb/>
     be strictly limited in character. It felt its own 
     <lb/>
     inability to discuss education philosophical<lb break="no"/>ly, or to approach it professionally. No mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the Committee felt competent to deal 
     <lb/>
     with education either as an art or as a profes<lb break="no"/>sion. It was decided at the outset to restrict 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>