<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-11-06"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-11-06">6 November 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

          <date when="1995"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="164"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0154.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0155.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0156.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0157.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0158.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0159.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0160.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0161.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0162.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0163.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0164.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-02-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-07">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0154">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0154.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0155">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0155.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0156">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0156.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0157">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0157.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0158">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0158.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0159">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0159.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0160">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0160.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0161">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0161.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0162">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0162.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0163">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0163.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0164">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0164.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="154"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0154.jpg"/>
             <fw type="num">150</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>

<!-- GL, 2017-02-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

           <!-- <p>
     of government. I would like to know, because I 
     <lb/>
     certainly will defend responsible government, 
     <lb/>
     and I may have something to say about some of 
     <lb/>
     those who conducted our affairs at that particular 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Bailey l have listened carefully to the dif<lb break="no"/>ferent speeches, but I have not said very much 
     <lb/>
     and I think the pattern seems to fall clearly. What 
     <lb/>
     is wrong? We are going to find the terms under 
     <lb/>
     which Canada will accept us into union. I believe 
     <lb/>
     we don't want to go to Canada to get the terms. 
     <lb/>
     The terms have been right here in St. John's for 
     <lb/>
     a long time. Newfoundland has been used as an 
     <lb/>
     international pawn, and you and I today are noth<lb break="no"/>ing, only pawns in the game. Our fate was sealed 
     <lb/>
     nearly two years ago. Everybody wants the terms 
     <lb/>
     of union. I guess nearly everybody here knows 
     <lb/>
     what they are....1 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Figary Mr. Chairman, I rise for the purpose 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     of seconding Mr. Crosbie's motion. I have lis<lb break="no"/>tened to different speakers this afternoon on the 
     <lb/>
     amendment to the amendment, and practically 
     <lb/>
     every one of them stated that there was a great 
     <lb/>
     deal of time wasted in the discussion on this 
     <lb/>
     confederation matter. I can stop a gramaphone 
     <lb/>
     from talking, but to try and stop some people 
     <lb/>
     from continuous talking is, I am afraid, too big a 
     <lb/>
     job for me to do. However. I may say that my 
     <lb/>
     patience is about exhausted, and I would suggest 
     <lb/>
     that we get down to the real business of the 
     <lb/>
     Convention in a right and proper manner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The Chairman then put the motion on the floor 
     <lb/>
     to a vote. The original motion was defeated 25- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     17. The Chairman then put Mr. Bradley's motion 
     <lb/>
     as an alternative amendment rather than an 
     <lb/>
     amendment to Mr. Penney's amendment. It was 
     <lb/>
     defeated 25-17. Mr. Penney's amendment was 
     <lb/>
     carried 25-18. The Convention then adjourned. ] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     November 6, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName><ref target="#fn_01">[2]</ref> I am very sorry to
                  say that <lb/> Hon. Mr. Justice Fox is unfortunately and un<lb break="no"
                  />avoidably absent because of some illness. I feel <lb/>
                  <cb/> sure that you will all join me in hoping he will <lb/> have a very speedy
                  return here to his duty as <lb/> Chairman. <lb/>
               </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the Education Committee:<ref target="#fn_x1">[3]</ref>
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> In introducing this Report of the <lb/> Committee
                  on Education, I wish to state that the <lb/> Committee consisted of Messrs.
                  Harrington, <lb/> Fowler, Spencer, Ryan, Fogwill, Miller, Jones, <lb/> Smallwood,
                  Newell and myself. Each and every <lb/> one of these members gave full attendance
                  to all <lb/> sessions of the Committee and gave great aid in <lb/> bringing it in
                  so quickly. To mention any par<lb break="no"/>ticular names might be invidious,
                  but I am bound <lb/> to mention the name of Mr. Newell, the secretary <lb/> whom
                  we appointed; and Mr. Smallwood and <lb/> Mr. Harrington, appointed to assimilate
                  and <lb/> compile the facts obtained by them and by the <lb/> whole Committee. I
                  would also like to pay tribute <lb/> to Mr. Hanley of the Department of Education
                  <lb/> who assisted us very materially in getting <lb/> together the necessary
                  data. These remarks also <lb/> apply to all members of the department. You <lb/>
                  have had this report for some considerable time, <lb/> and whilst in presenting it
                  I did not read it fully, <lb/>
                  <cb/> I feel sure you have given it sufficient study to <lb/> debate it without
                  having it read again. If that be <lb/> so, then on behalf of the Education
                  Committee <lb/> we invite now your criticism, either constructive <lb/> or
                  destructive. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It seems to me that the Conven<lb break="no"
                  />tion may find in the report two matters for criti<lb break="no"/>cism. One is
                  the second paragraph which <lb/> describes the Committee's whole approach to the
                  <lb/> subject of its investigation; the other would be the <lb/> final conclusions
                  of the Committee, section 11. <lb/> In section 2 it says: <lb/>
               </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The Committee decided at the outset that 
     <lb/>
     its approach to the subject of education must 
     <lb/>
     be strictly limited in character. It felt its own 
     <lb/>
     inability to discuss education philosophical<lb break="no"/>ly, or to approach it professionally. No mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the Committee felt competent to deal 
     <lb/>
     with education either as an art or as a profes<lb break="no"/>sion. It was decided at the outset to restrict 
     <lb/>
         

<note xml:id="fn_01">2 Captain W.G. Warren, the Convention's Secretary, acted as Chairman in the absence of Mr. Justice Fox.</note>
   
<note xml:id="fn_x1">3 Volume 11:65. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
 
            <pb n="155"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0155.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">155</fw>
           
     our approach to the economic side. What 
     <lb/>
     does education cost the treasury now, and 
     <lb/>
     what has it cost in the past? Is the country 
     <lb/>
     getting adequate results for the money spent? 
     <lb/>
     Could the same results have been got with 
     <lb/>
     less expenditure? Will the same level of ex<lb break="no"/>penditure have to be maintained in future, or 
     <lb/>
     will expenditure be higher or lower than 
     <lb/>
     now? One thing the Committee decided from 
     <lb/>
     the commencement of its approach was its 
     <lb/>
     inability to judge of the the country's 
     <lb/>
     capacity either now or in the future to meet 
     <lb/>
     the costs of education: the members felt that 
     <lb/>
     while as members of the National Conven<lb break="no"/>tion itself they would have ultimately to 
     <lb/>
     come to that judgement, as members of the 
     <lb/>
     Committee they had neither the general na<lb break="no"/>tional data, not even the mission, to consider 
     <lb/>
     the wider question of the country's ability to 
     <lb/>
     carry educational services. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     As to the final conclusions, that is a horse of 
     <lb/>
     another colour. Dealing with section 2, I have felt 
     <lb/>
     and am sure all members of the Committee felt, 
     <lb/>
     that here, perhaps, was the basis of the criticism 
     <lb/>
     that the Convention might be prepared to offer in 
     <lb/>
     connection with this whole report. If this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion or the government or the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Education or other competent authority were to 
     <lb/>
     bring to Newfoundland a man or a number of men 
     <lb/>
     for the purpose of investigating not the cost of 
     <lb/>
     education, the purely economic side, but educa<lb break="no"/>tion itself; if they were prepared to bring in men 
     <lb/>
     who might be described as professionals — not 
     <lb/>
     teachers or educators, but men who had made a 
     <lb/>
     study of education as such, men who had studied 
     <lb/>
     educational systems, the purpose and the reason; 
     <lb/>
     men who had made a comparison of the different 
     <lb/>
     types and forms and systems of education; and 
     <lb/>
     turn them loose in Newfoundland, giving them 
     <lb/>
     authority and power and a year or two in which 
     <lb/>
     to make a factual and objective study of educa<lb break="no"/>tion as such and of the educational system as such 
     <lb/>
     in this country; then, having spent about six 
     <lb/>
     months in the different departments, attending 
     <lb/>
     meetings of the Education Council; meetings of 
     <lb/>
     executive officers, the Council of Higher Educa<lb break="no"/>tion; going out to the different schools, these men 
     <lb/>
     might be able to offer to this Convention an 
     <lb/>
     opinion on the education system which would be 
     <lb/>
     worth having. Our Committee, consisting of two 
     <lb/>
     journalists (Mr. Harrington and myself), a 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
            
     returned soldier, two retired teachers — I cannot 
     <lb/>
     remember the rest — none of us trained men in 
     <lb/>
     the realm of the administration and philosophy of 
     <lb/>
     education, for that reason decided to admit to 
     <lb/>
     ourselves frankly and to the Convention that 
     <lb/>
     there was a great deal of the subject of which we 
     <lb/>
     knew nothing. We were not trained or equipped 
     <lb/>
     to make that kind of investigation. Then we dug 
     <lb/>
     into the question of what it cost since 1920-21 
     <lb/>
     down to the present time; and for that expenditure 
     <lb/>
     what have we got in the way of education? How 
     <lb/>
     many schools and how many classrooms, how 
     <lb/>
     many teachers? Has the school system from the 
     <lb/>
     plant, the physical standpoint, improved for that 
     <lb/>
     additional expenditure? Then we made a stab at 
     <lb/>
     guessing as to what the education plant would 
     <lb/>
     have to be in the years ahead. The result you will 
     <lb/>
     find in this report. I thought a frank statement of 
     <lb/>
     the spirit in which this report is presented would 
     <lb/>
     be best.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DAWE1">Mr. Dawe</persName> If you want any further information <lb/> ask Dr.
                  Barnes. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> With regard to (c): "It is apparent that <lb/>
                  education has made and is making very real <lb/> progress in Newfoundland." Is
                  that based upon <lb/> the fact that we have been, during the last few <lb/> years,
                  spending more money? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> ....The answer is, frankly, <lb/> "Yes". It is
                  safe to say, with more new schools <lb/> and classrooms, rebuilt and reconditioned
                  <lb/> schools, more equipment, more teachers, more <lb/> students, a larger
                  percentage of attendance, a <lb/> larger proportion of total expenditure going
                  into <lb/> it than before, yes, there has been an advance<lb break="no"/>ment in
                  the field of education. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Would it be possible for the Commit<lb break="no"
                  />tee to indicate to us on what lines or on what basis <lb/> they made that
                  report? Even a journalist, if he <lb/> wants to build a house, decides what he
                  wants and <lb/> then calls in an architect and says, three <lb/> bedrooms,
                  kitchen, bathroom and so on, he says, <lb/> "This is what I want." Could you tell
                  us on what <lb/> basis the Committee came to its conclusions? For <lb/> instance
                  page 203 of the official handbook, 1946, <lb/> reads "Changes in the curricula
                     during...de<lb break="no"/>mocratic citizenship and patriotism." If they con<lb
                     break="no"/>sidered the main lines on this sort of thing in the <lb/> report
                  did they feel unable to deal with a matter <lb/> of that kind? I am thinking of
                  our terms of refer<lb break="no"/>ence: "to consider facts and make recommenda<lb
                     break="no"/>tions for future forms of government." What has <lb/>
                  <pb n="156" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0156.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">156</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> happened in the last ten years to make us
                  more fit <lb/> to govern ourselves than in other years? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> That would take a great deal of <lb/> time. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I am not thinking of any one particular <lb/> thing
                  in the report. It tells us we spent half a <lb/> million dollars on those school
                  buildings; I have <lb/> no doubt that is necessary. We spent $15,000 <lb/>
                  additional in the training of teachers. Is that a <lb/> proper proportion? I do
                  not know. If you have a <lb/> good teacher you have a good school; and that <lb/>
                  does not mean it should be a good building. <lb/> During the period, while
                  spending extra amounts <lb/> of money, have we increased the grading and <lb/>
                  standard of our teachers? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> The point is one which we did con<lb break="no"
                  />sider, but we did not go into the various points <lb/> you mention. We took it
                  for granted that the <lb/> Convention knew what is being done along the <lb/>
                  lines of health and nutrition in schools. We came <lb/> to the conclusion that
                  education has made very <lb/> real progress That is something about which it is
                  <lb/> very difficult to bring in facts. As for patriotism, <lb/> that is instilled
                  into children before they read or <lb/> write. We are not saying it is like we
                  should see <lb/> it, but we realise that education is something <lb/> which cannot
                  be controlled by the thought of any <lb/> one particularindividual. Education is
                  something <lb/> which grows by the instinct and ability, both <lb/> financially
                  and morally, of the people. We will <lb/> not therefore give our personal views of
                  the term. <lb/> I don't know if that answers the question. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I don't want to be misunderstood, but <lb/> I know
                  the people in the education department <lb/> very well. I believe very strongly
                  that we have <lb/> made real progress. I feel also that these people <lb/> are
                  doing a remarkably good job, and I am im<lb break="no"/>pressed with their
                  sincerity. That is a correct <lb/> statement; but the point I want to know is, are
                  <lb/> there main lines that you could have considered? <lb/> For instance
                  teachers' grades, how far have you <lb/> gone with that? I am not interested in
                  particular <lb/> examples, I am thinking of the main lines that you <lb/> were
                  taking. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I believe it was Mr. Butt who <lb/> recently
                  was telling me of a situation in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with road building. I
                  think he cited an il<lb break="no"/>lustration of how an amateur can be fooled
                  very <lb/> easily by an engineer. Two estimates are made of <lb/> the cost of
                  building a road, one is small and the <lb/> other a much larger amount. The
                  amateur, not <lb/>
                  <cb/> being equipped with technical knowledge, is <lb/> easily fooled, and I think
                  Mr. Butt's illustration <lb/> was that $40,000 went down the drain before ever
                  <lb/> a sod was turned because of the estimates. It <lb/> appears that amongst
                  engineers around the world <lb/> the whole job is done by estimates. Well now,
                  <lb/> apply that to this matter of education. I have no <lb/> doubt that there are
                  men in the world today who <lb/> could walk into the Department of Education and
                  <lb/> say, "What's your total grant for education?" <lb/> "What's the total of
                  your administrative cost?" <lb/> "What is the total amount of your grant for <lb/>
                  teachers' salaries?" "What is your total amount <lb/> for this, that, and the
                  other, in percentages?" And <lb/> the minute they hear those percentages they
                     com<lb break="no"/>pare them with a dozen or maybe 20 countries <lb/> around
                  the world, and, if they are trained they <lb/> know if these are correct
                  percentages or not.... I <lb/> would think that, after having spent some years
                  <lb/> in the department, Mr. Butt would have a general <lb/> familiarity with that
                  kind of thing, but I don't <lb/> think the Education Committee felt competent to
                  <lb/> approach the matter in that regard. There may be <lb/> a dozen men in this
                  Convention today who can <lb/> blow holes in this report, and I know there are
                  <lb/> many men outside the Convention who can riddle <lb/> it properly, and
                  outside the country there are <lb/> educators and professional educationalists who
                  <lb/> would make it look like monkey work. Unfor<lb break="no"/>tunately we have
                  not got that kind of training. We <lb/> could only look at it as amateurs,
                  ordinary New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders, in the light of how many school <lb/>
                  buildings, how many rooms, the cost of upkeep <lb/> and the probable future cost,
                  etc. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     These matters touch me closely. I feel very 
     <lb/>
     prejudiced on it. I have a deep suspicion of any 
     <lb/>
     attempt on the part of any country or government 
     <lb/>
     to use the schools for propaganda. Hitler did that, 
     <lb/>
     and I don't want to see it done in this country. The 
     <lb/>
     government should foot the bills and then hands 
     <lb/>
     off. Least of all do I want our education system 
     <lb/>
     to be used for matters of propaganda, except 
     <lb/>
     maybe in the matter of health, and in that the 
     <lb/>
     Junior Red Cross is doing a very good job. Let us 
     <lb/>
     have confidence that our children are being 
     <lb/>
     brought up clean-minded and open-minded. 
     <lb/>
     They have a right to form their own opinions as 
     <lb/>
     they face life. Let's equip them to think, and in 
     <lb/>
     collaboration with the other agencies, churches, 
     <lb/>
     etc., let us train them morally and in matters of 
     <lb/>
     character. That's a wholly professional topic 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="157"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0157.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">157</fw>
           
     which I don't feel competent to discuss. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> ....I wonder if all the members have <lb/> had the
                  time to actually read this report. Obvious<lb break="no"/>ly Mr. Butt has, or at
                  least he read the beginning <lb/> and the end, and perhaps I am a little late in
                  <lb/> bringing this point up, but from the turn that the <lb/> discussion
                  immediately took I am led to wonder <lb/> if perhaps it would not be wise if
                  perhaps we <lb/> should find out how familiar the Convention is <lb/> with the
                  text as a whole. I hope this is not imper<lb break="no"/>tinent, but I would
                  really like to know if all the <lb/> members have had a chance to read this before
                  <lb/> we continue with the discussion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That would be very hard to get, <lb/> Mr.
                  Newell. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> If any members have not studied the <lb/> report
                  they might say so. I just wondered. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Mr. Newell, I put it to the Con<lb break="no"
                  />vention that if there were any objections they <lb/> should be brought forward.
                  I did not hear your <lb/> objection then. I don't know if there are any <lb/>
                  others. It can be read if the Convention so desires <lb/> it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> I think we ought to proceed with the <lb/>
                  discussion on the report, and, since I am on my <lb/> feet, I think I will give
                  Mr. Butt a material ex<lb break="no"/>ample of patriotism taught in the schools
                  during <lb/> the war. Unlike Mr. Smallwood, who looks on <lb/> any form of
                  patriotism with some suspicion, I <lb/> think it is a clean example, and perhaps
                  the only <lb/> reason why we did not include it was that it was <lb/> obvious that
                  every Newfoundlander should know <lb/> about it. That was the selling of war
                  savings <lb/> stamps in our schools, where our children came <lb/> and looked for
                  a dime, and the next day for <lb/> another dime, and eventually they got the price
                  <lb/> of a war savings certificate. I believe these <lb/> children knew the
                  purpose of these certificates, I <lb/> believe that was a clean way of teaching
                  <lb/> patriotism. It certainly worked, and it was <lb/> countrywide, and as it was
                  perfectly obvious and <lb/> we did not mention it; but it is a typical example.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Excuse me for getting up again. I am <lb/>not trying to
                  be like Hitler. I am not interested in <lb/>those political items, but cite them
                  as examples. <lb/>While I am on my feet, Mr. Smallwood, not <lb/>$40,000 went down
                  the drain, but $40,000 could <lb/>have gone down the drain if the estimate hap<lb
                     break="no"/>pened to be one third out. There you are. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> I would like to have education <lb/>defined and to
                  know when is a man educated. <lb/>
               </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> Never. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> There is one point Mr. Butt brought <lb/> out. He
                  mentioned that the money spent on <lb/> teacher training was $15,000, whilst that
                  for <lb/> building schools was $500,000. I think what Mr. <lb/> Butt meant was, is
                  there enough being spent for <lb/> teacher training, is it in proportion? And if
                  not do <lb/> you consider making recommendations for more <lb/> expenditures in
                  that respect? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I know that I am correct. The $15,000 <lb/> is not
                  even the correct figure, but I do want to put <lb/> the same question that you
                  did. I want to find out <lb/> if the Committee considered the main lines as <lb/>
                  distinct from the purely professional aspect of the <lb/> situation... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I don't think any member has any <lb/> right to
                  get up as often on any point. Regarding <lb/> teacher training, during the
                  sessions of the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee we did have Mr. Frecker, Secretary for
                  <lb/> Education, before us on several occasions, and <lb/> although we have not
                  embodied his talks in this <lb/> report we secured enough information from him
                  <lb/> to make us believe that the Department of Educa<lb break="no"/>tion is very
                  much alive to this matter of education, <lb/> and are now making plans for summer
                  schools in <lb/> the Memorial College and all over the island; so <lb/> they have
                  taken steps to raise the standard of our <lb/> teachers. That is a very difficult
                  problem, as <lb/> Mr. Frecker pointed out. Along these lines I am <lb/> quite sure
                  that the average standard of teachers in <lb/> the years to come is going to be
                  very much ahead <lb/> of what it is at present. We have to remember that <lb/> we
                  have I think it is over 2,000 teachers all over <lb/> the island, some of them
                  with only 12 or 14 <lb/> scholars, and it is not to be expected that the state
                  <lb/> could spend thousands of dollars to send a teacher <lb/> to each small
                  settlement. But they are endeavour<lb break="no"/>ing to raise the standard of all
                  teachers insofar as <lb/> the money allows. Mr. Frecker left no doubt in <lb/> our
                  minds that that is one of the great problems <lb/> which we will have to face, and
                  they are facing it <lb/> manfully. I cannot give you any particular facts <lb/> on
                  it.... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> This report is, in some ways, the <lb/> beginning
                  of our reports. It is the first brought in, <lb/> and we may be justified in
                  saying that we did not <lb/> know exactly what the Convention expects, and <lb/>
                  those bringing in reports after this will have the <lb/> advantage of seeing this
                  one torn to pieces and <lb/> will know better what to expect. I think the Com<lb
                     break="no"/>mittee will agree that we did not feel it was our <lb/>
                  <pb n="158" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0158.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">158</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> job to bring in a report which would answer
                  every <lb/> possible question that could be asked about <lb/> education in
                  Newfoundland. In going back to the <lb/> question of what we were sent here for, I
                  think <lb/> we were to examine and inquire into the financial <lb/> and economic
                  condition of this island. In view of <lb/> this we felt that we had to inquire
                  mostly into the <lb/> amount that was being spent on education. We <lb/> have that
                  in black and white. We have certain <lb/> supplementary facts that will come out
                  during <lb/> debate, but I don't see that it was our business to <lb/> discuss the
                  philosophy of education. Everybody <lb/> has ideas on this, and we could probably
                  have <lb/> gone on at great length discussing such things. I <lb/> have
                  supplementary information here which may <lb/> answer the question of the member
                  for St. John's <lb/> West. For the year ending June 30, 1944, there <lb/> were the
                  following teachers in the following <lb/> grades:<ref target="#fn_02">*</ref>
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> What's the total of graded and <lb/> ungraded
                  male and female teachers? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> I will give you those figures a little <lb/>
                  later. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Sometime ago when the Chadwick- <lb break="yes"/>
                  Jones report<ref target="#fn_x2">[1]</ref> was being considered, I think <lb/> Mr.
                  Miller made the suggestion that when any <lb/> report came up we might perhaps
                  consider the <lb/> findings of the Chadwick-Jones report in con <lb/> junction
                  with the new report. Mr. Newell ade<lb break="no"/>quately stated that the report
                  was based mainly <lb/> upon giving the information as to the financial <lb/>
                  standard of the education business. I noticed in <lb/> looking into these figures
                  here a rather interesting <lb/> comparison. In the Chadwick-Jones report the <lb/>
                  subsidies, grants, etc, for 1935-36 are given as <lb/> $696,000; in your report,
                  the total education grant <lb/> is given as $956,000, a difference of nearly <lb/>
                  $300,000, and the same applies to 1941 and 1942 <lb/> where the Chadwick-Jones
                  figures are <lb/>
                  <cb/> $1,094,000 and your figures are $1,532,000. The <lb/> Chadwick-Jones
                  estimate for 1946 and 1947 is <lb/> $2,350,000, yours is $3,538,000. The figures
                  are <lb/> so very far apart that I thought I would like to <lb/> draw your
                  attention to it, because there is ob<lb break="no"/>viously some mistake
                  somewhere. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That matter did come up <lb/> before. When the
                  report of the Education Com<lb break="no"/>mittee went before the Steering
                  Committee, <lb/> before being presented to this house, the Steering <lb/>
                  Committee noted these apparent discrepancies to <lb/> which Mr. Job has just
                  referred and returned the <lb/> report to the Education Committee, pointing <lb/>
                  them out. The Education Committee, in good <lb/> humour and without rancour,
                  looked at the <lb/> figures and were quite content that its own figures <lb/> were
                  accurate. It had gone to great pains to make <lb/> them accurate and was rather
                  suspicious of any <lb/> difference in the Chadwick-Jones report. Being <lb/> quite
                  confident of our figures, we felt that it was <lb/> the Chadwick-Jones figures
                  that were wrong. We <lb/> found that they deal with two entirely different <lb/>
                  amounts. Our figures include the same things as <lb/> the Chadwick-Jones report,
                  but they include <lb/> other things as well... Our figures include every<lb
                     break="no"/>thing. You may take it that the figures in this <lb/> report are
                  quite accurate. They may not be com<lb break="no"/>pared because the two tables
                  deal with different <lb/> matters. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> The figures for the graded and un<lb break="no"
                  />graded teachers are: graded teachers 1,788, un<lb break="no"/>graded teachers
                  326. All grades from third up to <lb/> university grade are lumped together in
                  graded <lb/> teachers. That would give about 20% roughly of <lb/> ungraded
                  teachers. That was at June 30, l944. I <lb/> think the situation was about as bad
                  then as it has <lb/> been for some time, due to the difficulty of get<lb
                     break="no"/>ting teachers in many parts of the country, and <lb/> the chairmen
                  of school boards not being able to <lb/>
                  <note xml:id="fn_02">* 
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell rendition="simple:centre">Grade</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Male<lb/> No. of Teachers</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Female<lb/> No. of Teachers</cell></row>
                        <row><cell rendition="simple:centre">University</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">98</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">64 </cell></row>
                        <row><cell rendition="simple:centre">Associate</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">83</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">74</cell></row>
                        <row><cell rendition="simple:centre">First Grade</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">172</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">489</cell></row>
                        <row><cell rendition="simple:centre">Second Grade</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">137</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">449</cell></row>
                        <row><cell rendition="simple:centre">Third Grade</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">47</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">175</cell></row>
                        <row>
                           <cell rendition="simple:centre">Uncertified</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">73</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">253</cell></row>
                     </table></note>
                  <note xml:id="fn_x2">1 Volume II: 16. [Volume II is not in <hi
                        rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
                  <pb n="159" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0159.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">159</fw> be too particular. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I believe that education is making real <lb/>
                  progress in Newfoundland and that our educators <lb/> are doing an excellent job,
                  but I feel that the <lb/> Convention should be made conversant with the <lb/> main
                  lines, such as the grading of teachers, etc. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> Since the report has been tabled the <lb/>Convention
                  has been busy with other matters and <lb/>I wonder how any delegates have studied
                  the <lb/>report. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Mr. Chairman, without doubt there is a <lb/> marked
                  difference between the estimate of <lb/> salaries and your estimate of the total
                  education <lb/> grant of $3,538,500. There is a difference of <lb/> about $1
                  million, and I think this should be <lb/> cleared up. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> For the present year ending <lb/> March 31,
                  1947, we got our information from the <lb/> department within the past three
                  weeks, and if <lb/> there is any difference in the figures, as referred <lb/> to
                  by Mr. Job, why should anybody worry? That <lb/> is a matter for Chadwick-Jones to
                  worry about. <lb/> After all, the Education Committee is comprised <lb/> of
                  average Newfoundlanders, and not of men <lb/> thoroughly versed in the issue. With
                  regard to <lb/> state control of schools I feel that the pupils <lb/> would be
                  subjected to propaganda. I do, however, <lb/> agree that children should be helped
                  to think for <lb/> themselves and to develop character, but I would <lb/> not
                  advocate state interference with the system. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> This subject of education is a real <lb/>problem.
                  During its sessions the Education Com<lb break="no"/>mittee was addressed by the
                  secretary of the <lb/>department and he gave sufficient information to <lb/>the
                  Committee to make us believe that the <lb/>government was definitely interested in
                  the train<lb break="no"/>ing of teachers and that it had taken steps in this
                  <lb/>respect. I feel sure that the standing of the average <lb/>teacher of the
                  future will show a decided im<lb break="no"/>provement over the past and present.
                  While on <lb/>this point I would like to remind delegates that <lb/>the government
                  could not be expected to spend <lb/>thousands of dollars towards the training of
                  <lb/>teachers for very small settlements. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> The Education Committee did not <lb/> feel it was
                  obligated to examine all aspects and <lb/> give all minute details, as the terms
                  of reference <lb/> pertained to an examination of Newfoundland's <lb/> economic
                  and financial condition. In view of this <lb/> the Committee decided to find out
                  the cost of <lb/> education and other matters along general lines <lb/>
                  <cb/> in connection therewith... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I agree with Mr. Newell that the <lb/> primary
                  job of the Convention is to collect finan<lb break="no"/>cial and economic facts.
                  I also believe we got the <lb/> estimate of the expenditure on education far too
                  <lb/> low. The majority of professional teachers <lb/> received less than $3,000
                  in 1944, and I notice in <lb/> the report also that two teachers received less
                  <lb/> than $300 salary. If they had to pay board they <lb/> were in debt. Further
                  on I notice that 31 get from <lb/> $300 to $400; 196 from $500 to $600; 285 from
                  <lb/> $600 to $699; 232 from $700 to $799; 202 from <lb/> $800 to $900; 446 from
                  $1,000 to $2,000 and 20 <lb/> over $2,000 upwards. I think this offers little
                  <lb/> encouragement to people to become professional <lb/> teachers, and I think
                  the Committee should <lb/> recommend an increase in the salaries. We are not <lb/>
                  concerned with what has been paid in the past. <lb/> We must look to the future,
                  and it is ridiculous <lb/> for anyone to think that a teacher could be ex<lb
                     break="no"/>pected to exist properly on $500 a year. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I agree with Mr. Crosbie. I know <lb/> one male
                  teacher, aged 23 or 24, who is paid $55 <lb/> a month salary and who pays $50 a
                  month board, <lb/> except that at Christmas-time he draws $150 <lb/> augmentation.
                  I also know of a female teacher <lb/> who is paid $50 a month salary and pays
                  $42.50 <lb/> a month board. She too gets the augmentation <lb/> grant. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BURR2">Mr. Burry</persName> Mr. Chairman, I feel sure we all <lb/> agree with
                  what Mr. Crosbie has said with regard <lb/> to the small salaries paid school
                  teachers. The <lb/> same laxity applies to the training of our teachers. <lb/>
                  Twenty percent of our teachers are ungraded and <lb/> yet Mr. Hollett wondered if
                  the government was <lb/> justified in spending money for the training of <lb/>
                  teachers in smaller schools. I come from a district <lb/> where we have quite a
                  number of small schools <lb/> and need teachers, and I say that the government
                  <lb/> would be amply justified. There is no reason in <lb/> the world why small
                  communities should be <lb/> deprived of the services of trained teachers, be<lb
                     break="no"/>cause perhaps it is from those schools that will be <lb/> sent
                  representatives to this house in later years. <lb/> Good trained teachers is the
                  important thing, I <lb/> think. What Mr. Smallwood has said I back it up, <lb/> we
                  have to have a larger percentage spent on the <lb/> training of teachers for all
                  of our schools both in <lb/> the city and in Labrador. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> According to the figures now put <lb/> forward by
                  the Education Committee in regard to <lb/>
                  <pb n="160" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0160.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">160</fw>
                  <fw type="num">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> teachers' salaries, the only thing I can
                  say is this: <lb/> is the government paying scab wages for one of <lb/> the most
                  important professions in the country? <lb/> After all, teachers start off when
                  they first leave <lb/> home to go to school; and schoolteachers should <lb/> be
                  considered among the most important profes<lb break="no"/>sional people we have. I
                  beg to make a motion <lb/> that this Convention go on record and recom<lb
                     break="no"/>mend to the Commission of Government that <lb/> they raise the
                  basic wages for teachers, even if we <lb/> have to bring the higher-ups down.
                  <lb/> Mr. Smallwood has mentioned that it is possible <lb/> when we get plenty of
                  goods on the market again, <lb/> prices will come down. Even if that does happen,
                  <lb/> still the teachers are not getting a decent living <lb/> wage, and by asking
                  for an increase on the basic <lb/> rate, that will give them a little further
                  increase <lb/> when the buying power of the dollar increases. I <lb/> beg that the
                  Education Committee recommend to <lb/> the Commission of Government an increase in
                  <lb/> the basic rate of pay for the teachers. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You are making this as an addi<lb break="no"
                  />tional recommendation of the report? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Yes. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The motion is, "That the com<lb break="no"
                  />mittee of the whole make a recommendation to <lb/> the Education Committee to
                  recommend to the <lb/> Commission of Government that the basic wages <lb/> of a
                  teacher he raised." Does anybody wish to <lb/> speak to that motion? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> I wish to support Mr. Jackman. I <lb/> also agree
                  that teachers' salaries are very low and <lb/> I think we should make a
                  recommendation for <lb/> further increase in their salaries. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Whilst I agree with Mr. Jackman, <lb/> I am
                  afraid the matter does not come into our <lb/> terms. Maybe Professor Wheare would
                  give us <lb/> an idea of his views on that. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> We should give credit where <lb/> credit is
                  due, and the Commission of Government <lb/> deserves credit for the increase in
                  grants.... They <lb/> have been generous in building many schools <lb/> throughout
                  the island, and it has made the <lb/> teachers much happier. The new schools are
                     bet<lb break="no"/>ter equipped and we have been able to get better <lb/>
                  results and we have been waiting for this for a <lb/> long time. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JONE5">Mr. Jones</persName> As a member of the Education Com<lb break="no"
                  />mittee, and having taught well over 30 years in <lb/> the schools of this
                  country, I support the report <lb/> now before the Convention for public
                  discussion. <lb/>
                  <cb/> I know there are many people thinking and saying <lb/> that $3.5 million is
                  a lot of money to be spending <lb/> on education in this country, and are
                  wondering <lb/> if we are getting adequate returns for such a large <lb/> sum. I
                  think every cent of this money is well <lb/> spent. Up to ten or 15 years ago many
                  of our <lb/> outport schools were scarcely fit to herd cattle in, <lb/> and in
                  such buildings we compelled our children <lb/> to spend five or six hours a day.
                  These schools, <lb/> if you can call them such, were poorly lighted, <lb/> poorly
                  ventilated, poorly furnished, and inade<lb break="no"/>quately staffed. No wonder
                  the Department of <lb/> Public Health and Welfare in its investigations <lb/>
                  found such a large percentage of our school <lb/> children's eyesight defective,
                  brought about <lb/> chiefly by eye strain. Many of these schools <lb/> contained
                  long benches, in which five or six <lb/> children sat with no support to their
                  backs, and <lb/> with chests cupped in in order to reach the desk <lb/> which was
                  either too high or too low, and in this <lb/> posture they generally sat through
                  the period. Is <lb/> it any wonder that we have such a high percent<lb break="no"
                  />age of TB in this country? I am sure we all agree <lb/> and are pleased to know
                  that the Department of <lb/> Education is taking steps to remedy this evil as
                  <lb/> quickly as possible with the grants at its disposal. <lb/> I said that the
                  schools were understaffed. I will <lb/> give you an example from my own
                  experience. I <lb/> once taught, or tried to teach, in a school with <lb/> over
                  100 pupils enrolled with no assistance. I was <lb/> not only supposed to teach the
                  lower grades, but <lb/> expected to prepare primary, preliminary, inter<lb
                     break="no"/>mediate and associate grades as well. Is it any <lb/> wonder, Mr.
                  Chairman, that I am standing here <lb/> today after going through such an ordeal
                  for three <lb/> years? I am glad to say that these conditions do <lb/> not exist
                  at the present time, thanks to increased <lb/> educational grants. It has been
                  said that all our <lb/> government departments are overstaffed, be that <lb/> as
                  it may. In my experience with the Department <lb/> of Education, I am sure this
                  does not apply. Every <lb/> person employed there is giving faithful service <lb/>
                  for the salary which he or she receives. In refer<lb break="no"/>ence to teachers,
                  it has been often said that they <lb/> have a good job, only having to work for
                  five <lb/> hours a day. I say it is a noble job, trying to mould <lb/> the minds
                  and characters of boys and girls, in <lb/> order to fit them to take their place
                  in the com<lb break="no"/>munity in which they live. It is a noble work, and <lb/>
                  teachers should be better paid for the work they <lb/> are trying to perform. But
                  if a person thinks a <lb/>
                  <pb n="161" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0161.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">161</fw> teacher's work is finished when he dismisses his <lb/>
                  pupils, he is very much at sea; he often has to <lb/> work up to late hours of the
                  night; he has the next <lb/> day's lessons to prepare, assignments to correct
                  <lb/> and many other things to do which only a teacher <lb/> can know. Owing to
                  the shortage of teachers, <lb/> which had been brought about chiefly by enlist<lb
                     break="no"/>ing in the different forces, and others taking more <lb/>
                  remunerative work, the department finds itself <lb/> compelled to accept boys or
                  girls from the high <lb/> schools who had passed grade XI, admit them to <lb/>
                  summer school for four or five weeks, and in <lb/> September place them in charge
                  of a school. This <lb/> is not as it should be, but the department finds it <lb/>
                  imperative, as experienced teachers are not avail<lb break="no"/>able. Supervisors
                  are therefore scattered through <lb/> the districts in order to help these young
                  and <lb/> inexperienced teachers in their work.... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     In conclusion, Mr. Chairman, I think that 
     <lb/>
     money spent on education is money well spent, 
     <lb/>
     because the better a community is educated the 
     <lb/>
     better it can manage its own affairs, and this 
     <lb/>
     applies to the government of a country as well. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> With regard to your motion, <lb/>Mr. J ackman, I
                  have discussed it with Professor <lb/>Wheare and we feel we cannot pass a motion
                  <lb/>making a recommendation to the government; <lb/>but you can make a
                  recommendation to the <lb/>Education Committee as to the possibility of
                  <lb/>approaching the appropriate authorities to the <lb/>basic wages of teachers
                  being raised. You cannot <lb/>go straight to the Education Committee and ask
                  <lb/>them to make a recommendation to the govern<lb break="no"/>ment; you can ask
                  that an amendment be put in <lb/>the report condemning the low wages of teachers.
                  <lb/>In those circumstances I am afraid I cannot accept <lb/>your motion as it is
                  now. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I suggest that probably Mr. Jack<lb break="no"
                  />man might draft up something tomorrow. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> That would be better; it will give <lb/> me more
                  time. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I must congratulate those respon<lb break="no"
                  />sible for such able reports on education and <lb/> forestry. I shall defer any
                  comment on the latter <lb/> until the appropriate time. I do not profess to be
                  <lb/> an authority to speak on education from a <lb/> theological or academic
                  standpoint; but rather as <lb/> one who is anxious to learn. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I am happy to find that at least someone on the 
     <lb/>
     Committee has entertained many of the hopes 
     <lb/>
     and thoughts for the immediate further extension 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
           
     of the Memorial University as I have myself. This 
     <lb/>
     splendid college has served a useful purpose to a 
     <lb/>
     point; but after 21 years as a junior college, that 
     <lb/>
     is, a college giving the first two years of arts and 
     <lb/>
     science, (three years for engineering), students 
     <lb/>
     who desire further education must go abroad to 
     <lb/>
     Canada or the USA and spend about two years to 
     <lb/>
     complete their studies for a degree in arts and 
     <lb/>
     science. Canadian colleges and universities have 
     <lb/>
     a very high regard for the quality of the work done 
     <lb/>
     by our students. This is good proof that the col<lb break="no"/>lege has so far justified its existence as a junior 
     <lb/>
     college. It is likely now that after 21 years of 
     <lb/>
     existence the college has probably reached the 
     <lb/>
     limit of its possibilities as a junior college. The 
     <lb/>
     next step should be the development to a degree- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     giving college. This appears an appropriate time, 
     <lb/>
     as the present college was a memorial to those 
     <lb/>
     who served, and more particularly those who 
     <lb/>
     died, in the cause of freedom during the great war, 
     <lb/>
     19l4-l918. What more fitting memorial could 
     <lb/>
     there be to those who died during the second great 
     <lb/>
     war than the inaugurating of a degree-conferring 
     <lb/>
     college? Newfoundland is probably the only 
     <lb/>
     dominion which cannot boast of such an institu<lb break="no"/>tion of higher learning. For reasons of prestige, 
     <lb/>
     therefore, this step is highly desirable. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The benefits from the present college have 
     <lb/>
     been felt throughout the whole island, since the 
     <lb/>
     students come from every part of Newfoundland, 
     <lb/>
     and after their studies return for the most part to 
     <lb/>
     their towns and villages. With degree status the 
     <lb/>
     college could considerably augment its contribu<lb break="no"/>tion in raising the general standard or level of 
     <lb/>
     education in this country. It is likely that over a 
     <lb/>
     period of ten years the enrollment would rise 
     <lb/>
     considerably. At present the normal enrollment 
     <lb/>
     would appear to be about 380. With degree status 
     <lb/>
     the enrollment would soon rise to an average each 
     <lb/>
     year of about 450 to 500. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It would not be the intention to attempt train<lb break="no"/>ing for medicine, engineering or other profes<lb break="no"/>sional training which would be very costly with 
     <lb/>
     our limited means; but to provide courses in 
     <lb/>
     liberal arts and science leading to the B.A. and 
     <lb/>
     B.Sc. One immediate benefit would be better 
     <lb/>
     qualified teachers throughout Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     You will find Newfoundlanders in key positions 
     <lb/>
     in almost every corner of the inhabitated globe; 
     <lb/>
     but they were mostly trained and educated in 
     <lb/>
     other countries. If this can be done with our 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="162"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0162.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">162</fw>
            <fw type="num">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
          
     material outside, it can be done here, and it would 
     <lb/>
     be only reasonable to expect that some of these 
     <lb/>
     men would stay here. We are a producing 
     <lb/>
     country, both in material and brains equal to the 
     <lb/>
     best; but in this respect we must become more 
     <lb/>
     national-minded and export more of the finished 
     <lb/>
     product in order for our country to derive any real 
     <lb/>
     benefit from our natural wealth. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Touching briefly on the question of teachers' 
     <lb/>
     salaries, I do feel the lower grade teachers are still 
     <lb/>
     underpaid and there is little inducement for 
     <lb/>
     anyone to take up the profession unless they see 
     <lb/>
     their way clear to qualify for the higher scale. In 
     <lb/>
     the matter of assisting in the building and equip<lb break="no"/>ping of new schools, I would say the department 
     <lb/>
     has done a good job and the value of this policy 
     <lb/>
     will best be proved over a period of years.... 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> ....Education, to my mind, is <lb/>one of the
                  more, if not the most important sub<lb break="no"/>jects in our study of the
                  future well-being of our <lb/>country. An educated people tends towards a
                  <lb/>prosperous and happy future, an uneducated <lb/>people the very opposite. We
                  have in the past <lb/>been woefully lacking in this very important mat<lb
                     break="no"/>ter. Progress has been made in the past few years <lb/>undoubtedly;
                  but much more needs to be done. <lb/>The question has been asked in this report:
                  "Is the <lb/>country getting adequate results for the money <lb/>spent? Could the
                  same results have been got with <lb/>less expenditure?" The Committee has answered
                  <lb/>these questions in a general way by stating they <lb/>consider the department
                  had done a good job <lb/>under the circumstances. They probably have, <lb/>but my
                  answer to the question, considering it <lb/>from a financial and social point of
                  view, is that <lb/>the same result can be obtained from a smaller <lb/>expenditure
                  and that better results could be ob<lb break="no"/>tained from the same
                  expenditure. I don't mean <lb/>by this that teachers are overpaid; they are very
                  <lb/>much underpaid. Teaching, as a profession, is <lb/>probably the lowest paid,
                  for what we expect <lb/>from them, of any class in the country. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Our set-up in the matter of education is wrong, 
     <lb/>
     and here I probably enter upon a very controver<lb break="no"/>sial subject. The system of denominational 
     <lb/>
     education which we have is antiquated and 
     <lb/>
     should be changed to a public school system, as 
     <lb/>
     in all progressive countries in the world today.In 
     <lb/>
     discussing this question I shall endeavour to ap<lb break="no"/>proach it from a purely financial and social 
     <lb/>
     aspect. The theological arguments I shall leave to 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
          
     more learned minds. I speak as an outport man, 
     <lb/>
     where the effect of the present system is probably 
     <lb/>
     more pronounced than in the city of St. John's, 
     <lb/>
     where large schools can be provided to carry out 
     <lb/>
     the provisions of this system. Financially, the 
     <lb/>
     present system is uneconomical, in that there is 
     <lb/>
     too much overlapping both of money and effort, 
     <lb/>
     and socially it tends to instill and keep alive that 
     <lb/>
     spirit of intolerance which has been a drag on our 
     <lb/>
     country from time immemorial, and which we 
     <lb/>
     could very well do without. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To illustrate what I am saying, my own town 
     <lb/>
     of Botwood might be very well used in this 
     <lb/>
     connection. Some two or three years ago, when 
     <lb/>
     compulsory education was put into effect, it was 
     <lb/>
     found that our schools would not accommodate 
     <lb/>
     all the children. The population was at that time 
     <lb/>
     about 2,700. We had five schools divided among 
     <lb/>
     three denominations; one, the largest having 
     <lb/>
     three schools, and the other two having one each. 
     <lb/>
     All these school buildings, except one, were in a 
     <lb/>
     bad state of repair and, with the exception of two, 
     <lb/>
     had no sanitary facilities. An effort was made to 
     <lb/>
     get an amalgamated school. A committee was 
     <lb/>
     formed to carry out the idea, which would have 
     <lb/>
     meant that one central school with a primary 
     <lb/>
     school on each end, or three schools in all, would 
     <lb/>
     have been sufficient to take care of the pupils, and 
     <lb/>
     give them a higher standard of education. The 
     <lb/>
     whole district of Botwood was canvassed, and it 
     <lb/>
     was found that the great majority of the people 
     <lb/>
     were in favour of such a school. We contacted the 
     <lb/>
     education department, and where did we get? Just 
     <lb/>
     nowhere. We even had a visit from the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner of Education of the day, who advised us 
     <lb/>
     that an act had been passed enabling an amal<lb break="no"/>gamated school to be started, providing that the 
     <lb/>
     various school boards would agree. What chance 
     <lb/>
     do you think we had, when the members of the 
     <lb/>
     school boards are recommended by the different 
     <lb/>
     ecclesiastical authorities, some of which were 
     <lb/>
     opposed to the idea? The final result to all this 
     <lb/>
     was that four new schools were built which, with 
     <lb/>
     the original two remaining, total six. Since then 
     <lb/>
     one more has been added, making seven in all. Is 
     <lb/>
     that economy? Does it tend to raise the standard 
     <lb/>
     of education as much as could be obtained by an 
     <lb/>
     amalgamated or public school? It has been said 
     <lb/>
     that the public or amalgamated school system is 
     <lb/>
     not workable. All we have to do to answer that 
     <lb/>
     question is to point to Grand Falls, Corner Brook, 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="163"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0163.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
            <fw type="num">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">163</fw>
           
     Millertown, Badger, Buchans and compare their 
     <lb/>
     results in examinations with other places. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The present system does not give teachers a 
     <lb/>
     chance to accomplish what they would wish. A 
     <lb/>
     teacher with four or five grades to teach cannot 
     <lb/>
     hope to attain the same result as with one grade, 
     <lb/>
     and the children cannot hope to attain that degree 
     <lb/>
     of knowledge which is their right. The teachers 
     <lb/>
     in these seven schools number 18. The largest of 
     <lb/>
     these school has six rooms, three others have 
     <lb/>
     three rooms each, the other three schools one 
     <lb/>
     room each, making a total 18 rooms — 18. Can 
     <lb/>
     you imagine anything more wasteful or un<lb break="no"/>economical when a central school of say ten or 
     <lb/>
     twelve rooms, and two schools for primary 
     <lb/>
     grades, would suffice? I might say that three of 
     <lb/>
     these school are situated within a radius of about 
     <lb/>
     200 yards. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In conclusion, it is my opinion that the present 
     <lb/>
     system is not only wasteful and uneconomical, 
     <lb/>
     but seriously retards the education of our young 
     <lb/>
     people who do not get the chance to which they 
     <lb/>
     are entitled, and to whom we look forward, at 
     <lb/>
     some time, to carry on the public affairs of this 
     <lb/>
     country. It also restricts the efforts of that under<lb break="no"/>paid, self-sacrificing body, the teachers of this 
     <lb/>
     country, to reach the goal they have set for them<lb break="no"/>selves, the education of our young people. They 
     <lb/>
     are doing a good job but would be eager and 
     <lb/>
     willing to do even a better one, without the 
     <lb/>
     present restrictions now placed upon them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Usually I am in accord with my <lb/> friend Mr.
                  MacDonald on those matters, but <lb/> frankly I can't agree with the statement, or
                  his <lb/> suggestions of a new school system such as he <lb/> has outlined. As far
                  as this country is concerned <lb/> the system of education that we have meets with
                  <lb/> the approval of the people, and unless you have <lb/> the approval of the
                  people as a whole no system <lb/> of education is going to be successful, because
                  <lb/> apparently it has worked out very well. Whilst it <lb/> does not make any
                  difference what comments we <lb/> make here, nevertheless we should express our
                  <lb/> thoughts, and I would like to say that in my <lb/> opinion our system of
                  education is entirely satis<lb break="no"/>factory, and should not be changed.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:KEOU1">Mr. Keough</persName> I would like to go on record as <lb/> concurring
                  completely with the statement made <lb/> by Mr. Higgins. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BURR2">Mr. Burry</persName> I would like to say a few words on <lb/> that
                  matter — as a member of the National Con<lb break="no"/><cb/>vention, not as a
                  member of the profession that <lb/> has much to do with the spending of this money
                  <lb/> and is part of the denominational system. It is <lb/> true, as Mr. Higgins
                  said, it is the choice of the <lb/> people and it should remain as such. I agree
                  with <lb/> him there, but I agree also with Mr. MacDonald <lb/> that it is a
                  wasteful system, not giving us the best <lb/> possible advantage of the money
                  spent, and I <lb/> wonder if we could not as a country perhaps do a <lb/> little
                  better under our denominational system. <lb/> There seems to be a tendency at the
                  present time <lb/> to greater divisions. Our school system in a little <lb/>
                  community seemed to be working very well, and <lb/> then certain denominational
                  interests stepped in <lb/> and opened another school, which results in a <lb/>
                  very wasteful system. I would like to be able to <lb/> arrange it so as to avoid
                  that happening, to <lb/> preserve that arrangement rather than to split it <lb/>
                  up again. That seems to be a thing to consider. I <lb/> regret that sometimes you
                  will find in some small <lb/> communities a fairly good system operating <lb/>
                  under our denominational system, and then, for <lb/> reasons that you all know,
                  the split is made and <lb/> the system is very inefficient. That does not apply
                  <lb/> to our work in Labrador, where I am chiefly <lb/> interested, because our
                  work there is going very <lb/> very smoothly under the denominational system,
                  <lb/> but I am afraid perhaps in the future it may suffer <lb/> because of it. I
                  will have no more to say about this <lb/> at the present time, but I would like to
                  say that in <lb/> Labrador and the northern part of Newfoundland <lb/> the work of
                  education is efficiently enhanced by <lb/> the interest the Grenfell Mission
                  people have had <lb/> in the schools and the education of the people in <lb/> the
                  north. The amalgamated school in St. An<lb break="no"/>thony is a great success
                  and is making a great <lb/> contribution to that community. Perhaps you do <lb/>
                  not know just what is being done in Labrador by <lb/> these people, and has been
                  done for some years. <lb/> There were three boarding schools in Labrador, <lb/>
                  one at Mary's River, one at Cartwright and one <lb/> at North West River. Two of
                  these are still exist<lb break="no"/>ing, one at Cartwright under Dr. and Mrs.
                     For<lb break="no"/>syth and one at North West River under <lb/> Mrs. Paddon and
                  her son. The one at North West <lb/> River is now being converted into a non<lb
                     break="no"/>denominational school. We have three teachers <lb/> there, and we
                  have plans made for the community <lb/> to set up a $15,000 building with a four
                  room <lb/> school. It will be under the board of education, <lb/> but I am glad to
                  say that the Grenfell Mission <lb/>
                  <pb n="164" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-06_Page_0164.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">164</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> people will carry on their boarding school.
                  They <lb/> take the children from the isolated villages and <lb/> families around
                  the coast and bring them into <lb/> North West River and Cartwright, board them,
                  <lb/> feed them and clothe them for $40 a year, $4 a <lb/> month, and now at North
                  West River they will be <lb/> sending them to the amalgamated school, and we <lb/>
                  are hoping that boarding school will increase. <lb/> That means that from the lone
                  villages and <lb/> families along the coast the Children have the <lb/> advantage
                  of getting their education, and being <lb/>
                  <cb/> fed and clothed for the year, and under the <lb/> denominational system the
                  Anglican Church and <lb/> the one I represent put teachers in the bigger <lb/>
                  villages along the coast, which gives us a fairly <lb/> good system of education.
                  The interest that the <lb/> Grenfell Mission has had in the north has <lb/>
                  facilitated the matter of education to a great ex<lb break="no"/>tent, and it
                  seems to function fairly well at the <lb/> present time. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee rose and reported progress and 
     <lb/>
     the Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <!-- GL, 2017-02-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->



           <!-- <p>
     November 7, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Chairman1 Before we begin, I have to 
     <lb/>
     report that the health of Hon. Mr. Justice Fox has 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     improved, as well as that of Mr. Brown and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Banfield. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Education Committee:2 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Ashbourne ....The money spent on schools 
     <lb/>
     and teacher training has been discussed. They are 
     <lb/>
     both very important and necessary, complemen<lb break="no"/>tary to each other. We cannot allow the children 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland to spend their days in 
     <lb/>
     delapidated, unhealthy and unsanitary schools, 
     <lb/>
     and the Commission of Government should be 
     <lb/>
     highly congratulated for embarking on school 
     <lb/>
     reconstruction on a big scale, as well as in the 
     <lb/>
     raising of teachers' salaries, which still need fur~ 
     <lb/>
     ther attention. Brainy people can command good 
     <lb/>
     wages, and if teaching does not offer the neces<lb break="no"/>sary pecuniary reward it is small wonder that the 
     <lb/>
     ambitious seek other employment, where their 
     <lb/>
     services are more adequately compensated. If we 
     <lb/>
     expect to have as leaders to train our youth, to 
     <lb/>
     reap the fruits of the capabilities and talents of 
     <lb/>
     those who have attained the heights of scholar<lb break="no"/>ship, we must be prepared to pay salaries to 
     <lb/>
     induce them to remain in the teaching profession. 
     <lb/>
     In some outport schools we lack teachers who can 
     <lb/>
     satisfactorily teach certain languages and 
     <lb/>
     science. Teachers who cannot give instruction in 
     <lb/>
     these subjects will be at a disadvantage and the 
     <lb/>
     pupils also.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With reference to common or amalgamated 
     <lb/>
     schools3, there is a sincere desire on the part of 
     <lb/>
     many to have these schools; but on examination 
     <lb/>
     we find different grading of teachers. Where can 
     <lb/>
     we hope to get suitable teachers for common 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     1The Secretary, Captain Warren, acted as Chairman. 
     <lb/>
     2Volume11:65. 
     <lb/>
     3That is, non-denominational schools. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     schools until we are assured that a uniform and 
     <lb/>
     standard diploma of competency is forthcoming? 
     <lb/>
     Doubt may exist regarding the qualifications of 
     <lb/>
     teachers, but I feel that more co-ordination of the 
     <lb/>
     various heads of the Department of Education 
     <lb/>
     might be a good idea. Then the matter of owner<lb break="no"/>ship of these common schools comes up, and who 
     <lb/>
     is going to be responsible for their maintenance 
     <lb/>
     and repairs? The present system in New<lb break="no"/>foundland has progressed very well, but if a 
     <lb/>
     concentration of the population were deemed 
     <lb/>
     advisable the matter would have to be solved. It 
     <lb/>
     is to be regretted that the building program has 
     <lb/>
     been temporarily halted owing to lack of nails 
     <lb/>
     and other building supplies. Another matter that 
     <lb/>
     calls for cement is school medical examination, 
     <lb/>
     which should be received by all pupils. For<lb break="no"/>tunately in Twillingate we have the Notre Dame 
     <lb/>
     Bay Memorial Hospital, and there is a clinic held 
     <lb/>
     by which each student can have a free medical 
     <lb/>
     examination. I believe this is the policy in vogue 
     <lb/>
     in St. John's also, but I would like to see it ex<lb break="no"/>tended to all the outports.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would like to pay tribute to the various school 
     <lb/>
     boards, as without their services I am afraid the 
     <lb/>
     whole plan of education could not function so 
     <lb/>
     well. I spent nine years as a member of a school 
     <lb/>
     board and in that time we had to pay 90% of our 
     <lb/>
     grant towards teachers salaries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Next there is the matter of free and compul- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>