<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-05-19" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-05-19">19 May 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="535"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0527.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0528.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0529.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0530.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0531.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0532.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0533.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0534.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0535.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-28">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-28">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0527">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0527.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0528">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0528.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0529">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0529.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0530">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0530.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0531">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0531.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0532">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0532.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0533">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0533.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0534">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0534.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0535">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0535.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="527" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0527.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">May 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">527</fw>
            
<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">
     May 19, 1947 
  
            </head>

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the London Delegation 
     
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Orders of the day. I have before 
     <lb/>
     me the replies of the Dominions Office to the 
     <lb/>
     various questions submitted by the delegation of 
     <lb/>
     the National Convention, which delegation was 
     <lb/>
     appointed pursuant to the resolution of February 
     <lb/>
     28, 1947, and which replies have been brought 
     <lb/>
     back by the delegation which went to London 
     <lb/>
     some three weeks ago.<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the questions and answers,<lb/>and the Convention resolved into a committee of<lb/>the whole]</hi>
            </p>

    

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Cashin read the resolutions passed by the<lb/>Convention on 28 February and 10 March, 1947,<lb/>and a despatch from the Dominion; Office dated<lb/>18 March, 1947]</hi>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> ....It will be seen from this 
     <lb/>
     memorandum that the Secretary of State agreed 
     <lb/>
     to meet the delegation and requested us to for<lb break="no"/>ward a more explanatory memorandum of the 
     <lb/>
     precise questions which we desired to ask. As a 
     <lb/>
     result, the following memorandum was prepared 
     <lb/>
     by the elected delegation and forwarded through 
     <lb/>
     the proper channel to the Secretary of State. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Cashin quoted from the memorandum]</hi>
            </p>

            <p>
     The delegation left St. John's by train on April 
     <lb/>
     24, arriving at Gander the following morning. We 
     <lb/>
     left Gander by BOAC on the evening of April 25 
     <lb/>
     and arrived in London around noon on Saturday, 
     <lb/>
     April 26. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the morning of April 29, the delegation 
     <lb/>
     was introduced to the Secretary of State and other 
     <lb/>
     members of the United Kingdom government. 
     <lb/>
     We were tendered a luncheon in the Savoy Hotel 
     <lb/>
     by the Secretary of State, and at 3 pm the same 
     <lb/>
     day our first meeting took place in the office of 
     <lb/>
     the Secretary of State in the House of Lords.<ref target="#fn_02">[2]</ref> The 
     <lb/>
     representatives of the British government who 
     <lb/>
     were present were Lord Addison, Secretary of 
     <lb/>
     State for Dominion Affairs; Mr. W. Glenvil Hall, 
     <lb/>
     Financial Secretary to the Treasury and a Mem<lb break="no"/>ber of Parliament; Mr. A.G. Bottomley, Par<lb break="no"/>liamentary Under-Secretary for Dominion 
     <lb/>
     Affairs; and Sir Eric Machtig, Permanent 
     <lb/>
     Secretary of State for the Dominions, and various 
     <lb/>
     other officials connected with the Dominions 
 

            <cb/>
     

     Office and the Treasury. Also there were present 
     <lb/>
     the Chairman of the Commission of Government 
     <lb/>
     and the Commissioner for Justice, both of whom 
     <lb/>
     had preceded us to England for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     sitting in on the meetings, as well as to advise the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary of State on matters which were to be 
     <lb/>
     discussed by the delegation. As the discussions 
     <lb/>
     proceeded, the impression created with some of 
     <lb/>
     us was that these two members of the Commis<lb break="no"/>sion had been summoned to London to give the 
     <lb/>
     Dominions Secretary information which he 
     <lb/>
     might not have, and for the further purpose of 
     <lb/>
     trying to influence the United Kingdom officials 
     <lb/>
     on matters of great importance to our country 
     <lb/>
     which came up for discussion. It was not uncom<lb break="no"/>mon to see considerable whispering take place 
     <lb/>
     when questions of serious importance were put 
     <lb/>
     to Lord Addison. I personally cannot but think 
     <lb/>
     that these two gentlemen, and I refer to the two 
     <lb/>
     members of the Commission government, un<lb break="no"/>doubtedly used their influence and efforts to jus<lb break="no"/>tify the actions of the Commission during the past 
     <lb/>
     six or seven years. What I have just said, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman, I believe. I would go so far as to 
     <lb/>
     say that the memorandum in reply to our ques<lb break="no"/>tions, which you have before you, had been 
     <lb/>
     prepared before our arrival in England, and that 
     <lb/>
     the two members of the Commission government 
     <lb/>
     assisted in its preparation, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You are making references to a 
     <lb/>
     representative of His Majesty the King. I must 
     <lb/>
     ask you not to do that in future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I was referring to the Chairman of 
     <lb/>
     the Commission of Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> He happens, also, to be the 
     <lb/>
     Governor of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I can understand that. Before I give 
     <lb/>
     any details of our three meetings, let me say 
     <lb/>
     definitely that the object of this delegation to 
     <lb/>
     London to discuss matters with the British 
     <lb/>
     government was not to seek financial assistance 
     <lb/>
     from the mother country. I hold, Mr. Chairman, 
     <lb/>
     that Newfoundland today needs no financial help 
     <lb/>
     from anyone. Our country is undoubtedly self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     supporting. The object of our delegation's going 


<note xml:id="fn_01">[1] Volume II:448. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

<note xml:id="fn_02">[2] Volume II:451. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
        

            <pb n="528" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0528.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">528</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">May 1947</fw>
         

     to Great Britain was for the purpose of discussing 
     <lb/>
     matters of future interest to the country. The 
     <lb/>
     object was to try and get the British government 
     <lb/>
     to see and think reasonably, as we thought we 
     <lb/>
     were thinking, and as the majority of us still 
     <lb/>
     think. Our primary object was to discuss the 
     <lb/>
     reduction of our public debt by way of refunding, 
     <lb/>
     by the use of our sinking fund, and by the applica<lb break="no"/>tion to that debt of our free-of-interest loans to 
     <lb/>
     Britain; to discuss future trade relations with the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom government; to discuss the fu<lb break="no"/>ture operation of Gander airport, and to seek the 
     <lb/>
     reason why Newfoundland has been burdened 
     <lb/>
     with any deficit on its operation; to see if we 
     <lb/>
     could in some way or other impress upon the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom government the importance to 
     <lb/>
     the future economy of our country of Britain 
     <lb/>
     purchasing a substantial quantity of our fresh and 
     <lb/>
     frozen fish, as well as the product of our iron 
     <lb/>
     mines on Bell Island. These are the matters, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman, which I contend we went to the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom for, and whilst there appears on 
     <lb/>
     our agenda a heading "Development Loans", you 
     <lb/>
     will all remember that we definitely told the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary of State that Newfoundland required 
     <lb/>
     no loans for development purposes from the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom government at the moment, and 
     <lb/>
     this matter was dropped from our discussions. 
     <lb/>
     Again, let me repeat for the benefit of the country 
     <lb/>
     as a whole, that our delegation did not go to 
     <lb/>
     London to seek any material assistance from 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain. We need no such assistance. If I 
     <lb/>
     may be permitted to say, Mr. Chairman, Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain is not in a position to give us any financial 
     <lb/>
     assistance at the present time. The fact of the 
     <lb/>
     matter is, Newfoundland has been and is still 
     <lb/>
     helping the United Kingdom government in a 
     <lb/>
     financial way, and at the expense of the New<lb break="no"/>foundland treasury. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     At this first meeting, which might be called a 
     <lb/>
     preliminary or informal meeting to discuss 
     <lb/>
     generalities, Viscount Addison took each ques<lb break="no"/>tion as outlined in our explanatory memorandum 
     <lb/>
     in sequence. And even though it is quite obvious 
     <lb/>
     that the intelligent discussion of these questions 
     <lb/>
     could only be discussed one with the other, the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary of State insisted that each question 
     <lb/>
     should be discussed separately. The firstquestion 
     <lb/>
     related to the public debt, and Viscount Addison, 
     <lb/>
     in effect, asked us what about it anyhow? In 
     <lb/>
     reply, we tried to convey that the public debt was 


            <cb/>
      

     one which certainly called for reduction as well 
     <lb/>
     as refunding. We tried to point out that our inter<lb break="no"/>est-free loans to the United Kingdom should be 
     <lb/>
     used for the purpose of reducing our sterling debt. 
     <lb/>
     In our opinion, Mr. Glenvil Hall, the Financial 
     <lb/>
     Secretary of the Treasury, was certainly 
     <lb/>
     favourably disposed to such a proposition, but the 
     <lb/>
     Dominions Secretary was not so enthusiastic in 
     <lb/>
     this respect. The latter then suggested that the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom government might convert our 
     <lb/>
     sterling debt, which amounted to approximately 
     <lb/>
     $75 million and bore interest at the rate of 3% 
     <lb/>
     annually, to 2.5%, and that such conversion 
     <lb/>
     would take place on January 1, 1948, after giving 
     <lb/>
     the necessary three months notice. He also indi<lb break="no"/>cated at this meeting that the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     government would be prepared to reduce this 
     <lb/>
     particular sterling debt by the application of the 
     <lb/>
     sinking fund, which is held in the Bank of 
     <lb/>
     England and amounts at the present time to some 
     <lb/>
     $75 million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With regard to the base deals, we were simply 
     <lb/>
     told that these bases had been given to the United 
     <lb/>
    States for a period of 99 years, with the concur<lb break="no"/>rence of the Commission government, and that in 
     <lb/>return Great Britain had received destroyers from 
     <lb/>the American government. It was admitted by the 
     <lb/>representatives of the United Kingdom govern<lb break="no"/>ment that no effort whatever had been made to 
     <lb/>get any remuneration for Newfoundland in the 
     <lb/>way of preferential tariffs on our fisher 
     <lb/>products, and that at the present time Great 
     <lb/>Britian was in no position to approach the 
     <lb/>American government on such a matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     It was pointed out to us, however, that if 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland decided to return to self-govern<lb break="no"/>ment, such a government might be in a position 
     <lb/>
     to further discuss the whole matter with the 
     <lb/>
     United States. We were unable to extract definite 
     <lb/>
     information as to whether or not the United States 
     <lb/>
     government had insisted on a 99 year lease of 
     <lb/>
     these bases, or whether any effort had been made 
     <lb/>
     to make such base deals simply for the duration 
     <lb/>
     of hostilities. On such matters the members of the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom government were most evasive 
     <lb/>
     and concentrated their arguments against us, on 
     <lb/>
     the grounds that these bases were absolutely es<lb break="no"/>sential to the winning of the war. The New<lb break="no"/>foundland delegation was not slow to point out 
     <lb/>
     that our country and our people had no objection 
     <lb/>
     whatever to granting such concessions to the 


            <pb n="529" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0529.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">May 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">529</fw>
          

     United States government for the duration of the 
     <lb/>
     war, and further, that the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland as a whole were prepared to make. and 
     <lb/>
     actually did make every sacrifice necessary for 
     <lb/>
     the winning of the war. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The matter of trade and tariffs was then taken 
     <lb/>
     up, and in particular the possibility for the sale of 
     <lb/>
     our fresh and frozen fish as well as iron ore to the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom. These specific matters were 
     <lb/>
     discussed generally at this meeting, and the 
     <lb/>
     Dominions Secretary promised to have some in<lb break="no"/>formation on these matters for the next meeting. 
     <lb/>
     It was then suggested by Mr. Glenvil Hall that at 
     <lb/>
     our next meeting we would discuss the whole 
     <lb/>
     matter of our sterling debt, base deals and inter<lb break="no"/>est-free loans as one subject, as he felt and we 
     <lb/>
     felt, that such matters were so interwoven, one 
     <lb/>
     with the other, that they should be discussed 
     <lb/>
     along such lines. I feel sure that the majority of 
     <lb/>
     the members of our delegation left that meeting 
     <lb/>
     feeling that because of Mr. Glenvil Hall's at<lb break="no"/>titude on the matter of our public debt, some 
     <lb/>
     reasonable consideration would be given to the 
     <lb/>
     readjustment, refunding and reduction of our 
     <lb/>
     sterling indebtedness. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Our next meeting<ref target="#fn_03">[1]</ref> with the Secretary of State 
     <lb/>
     and his colleagues took place on May 1, and was 
     <lb/>
     held in the office of the Secretary of State in the 
     <lb/>
     Dominions Office building. When we took our 
     <lb/>
     places around the table, the following memoran<lb break="no"/>dum was handed us by the Secretarg of State. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Cashin read the memorandum</hi><ref target="#fn_04">[2]</ref><hi rendition="simple:italic">]</hi>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Glenvil Hall did not attend this con<lb break="no"/>ference, but one of the permanent officials of the 
     <lb/>
     Treasury sat in, evidently for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     giving any information that might be required, or 
     <lb/>
     for the purpose of checking any errors which 
     <lb/>
     might be made in the discussion of financial 
     <lb/>
     matters. This gentleman never expressed any 
     <lb/>
     opinion, nor was he asked to do so. A general 
     <lb/>
     discussion took place on the contents of this 
     <lb/>
     memorandum. We were told that Mr. Glenvil 
     <lb/>
     Hall could not attend because he was busy with 
     <lb/>
     his parliamentary duties, but that he would 
     <lb/>
     probably attend our next meeting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After this very interesting, and what I may 
     <lb/>
     term heated discussion of Newfoundland affairs, 
     <lb/>
     we were advised by the Dominions Secretary that 
     <lb/>
     we could present a memorandum of our own in 
 

            <cb/>
        

     reply to the one received from the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom government. This memorandum, 
     <lb/>
     which has just been read by the Secretary of the 
     <lb/>
     Convention, has one or two matters contained in 
     <lb/>
     it with which I regret to say neither Mr. Bradley 
     <lb/>
     nor Mr. Keough could concur. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We will first deal with the public debt. This 
     <lb/>
     had been briefly discussed at our first meeting. It 
     <lb/>
     will be noticed that the British government puts 
     <lb/>
     this sterling debt under three main heads, as fol<lb break="no"/>lows: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     1. The two 3.5% sterling loans amounting 
     <lb/>
     together to about £870,000, which mature in 
     <lb/>
     1950 and 1952. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. The £400,000 temporary loan which was 
     <lb/>
     made available to Newfoundland by the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom government in 1917 for war 
     <lb/>
     purposes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. The 3% sterling debt of £17,790,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     With respect to the £870,000 loans, we were 
     <lb/>
     informed that the redemption of these two loans, 
     <lb/>
     coming due in 1950 and 1952 respectively, had 
     <lb/>
     been provided for from our interest-free loans to 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain, by the transfer to the Crown Agents 
     <lb/>
     for the Colonies of £800,000, which has been 
     <lb/>
     invested at 2.5%. The accrued interest on this 
     <lb/>
     £800,000 will be more than sufficient to meet the 
     <lb/>
     principal of these amounts as they fall due. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We had already known that no interest had 
     <lb/>
     been paid on the £400,000 temporary loan raised 
     <lb/>
     in 1917 for war purposes, and this matter was 
     <lb/>
     referred to in the report of the Finance Committee 
     <lb/>
     now before this house. The Secretary of State 
     <lb/>
     advised us that the repayment of this loan would 
     <lb/>
     not now be sought. Therefore the loan is can<lb break="no"/>celled, and it should disappear from our records. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With regard to the 3% sterling debt, which 
     <lb/>
     amounts to approximately £l7,790,000, or in 
     <lb/>
     dollar currency roughly $71.75 million, which 
     <lb/>
     amount has been guaranteed as to principal and 
     <lb/>
     interest by the United Kingdom government, it 
     <lb/>
     will be noted that it is the intention of the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom government to convert this debt to 
     <lb/>
     2.5% interest as from January 1, 1948. The 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom government through Viscount 
     <lb/>
     Addison, and on the advice of the Chairman of 
     <lb/>
     the Commission government and the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner for Justice, told us that because of the 
     <lb/>
     dollar shortage in Great Britain it would be im<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_03">[1] Volume II:474. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

<note xml:id="fn_04">[2] Memorandum in Response to Questions Raised by the Newfoundland Delegation. Volume II:471. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>


            <pb n="530" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0530.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">530</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">May 1947</fw>
         

     possible to have the British government take over 
     <lb/>
     this debt. Let me point out at this juncture that 
     <lb/>
     this debt is held in sterling funds and that the only 
     <lb/>
     benefit accruing to Great Britain with respect to 
     <lb/>
     dollars in this connection, is that the interest is 
     <lb/>
     paid to Britain in dollars, and it is for this reason 
     <lb/>
     that the United Kingdom government does not 
     <lb/>
     see its way clear to conceal the debt. They also 
     <lb/>
     told us that the matter of its conversion to a lower 
     <lb/>
     rate of interest has been under consideration by 
     <lb/>
     the Commission government for some time. Such 
     <lb/>
     a statement, in my opinion, is far from the truth, 
     <lb/>
     and I have no hesitation in saying that neither the 
     <lb/>
     Commission government nor the Dominions Of<lb break="no"/>fice had any intention of reducing our debt char<lb break="no"/>ges until the matter was brought to their attention 
     <lb/>
     through the efforts of this Convention. Again I 
     <lb/>
     repeat what I have so frequently stated before, 
     <lb/>
     that all the efforts of the Commission government 
     <lb/>
     have been devoted to increasing the expenditures 
     <lb/>
     of the country in every branch of the service. The 
     <lb/>
     policies now being adopted and put into opera<lb break="no"/>tion by the Commission can only result in the 
     <lb/>
     ultimate spending of all our treasury balances. No 
     <lb/>
     effort whatever has been made to curtail unneces<lb break="no"/>sary expenditures, and each succeeding year for 
     <lb/>
     the past six years finds the maintenance of 
     <lb/>
     government consistently rising. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Dorninions Office informed us that upon 
     <lb/>
     the conversion of our 3% sterling debt to 2.5%, 
     <lb/>
     the sinking fund now lying to our credit in the 
     <lb/>
     Bank of England would be deducted from this 
     <lb/>
     particular debt. This sinking fund amounts to 
     <lb/>
     around $7.5 million at the present time, and as 
     <lb/>
     there will be another payment made to this fund 
     <lb/>
     on July 1 next, the total amount will then be 
     <lb/>
     approximately $8.25 million. It has been stated 
     <lb/>
     definitely in the Financial Report<ref target="#fn_05">[1]</ref> presented to 
     <lb/>
     this Convention, that these annual sinking fund 
     <lb/>
     payments should have been deducted from the 
     <lb/>
     principal of our debt each year, as the monies 
     <lb/>
     were used for the purchase of our outstanding 3% 
     <lb/>
     stock. I say now, that by the manipulation of this 
     <lb/>
     sinking fund, Newfoundland has lost in the 
     <lb/>
     vicinity of half a million dollars, and that the 
     <lb/>
     decision of the United Kingdom government to 
     <lb/>
     use this sinking fund for the reduction of this 
     <lb/>
     sterling indebtedness is no concession on their 
     <lb/>
     part, but really an obligation which they should 
     <lb/>
     have carried out yearly since 1937-38. Neverthe<lb break="no"/>
   
            <cb/>
         
     less, by the conversion of this debt to 2.5% and 
     <lb/>
     the deduction of the sinking fund, the New<lb break="no"/>foundland treasury will save in the vicinity of half 
     <lb/>
     a million dollars annually, and our total sterling 
     <lb/>
     debt outstanding will then be approximately 
     <lb/>
     $635 million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It will be seen from the memorandum we sent 
     <lb/>
     the United Kingdom government, and their 
     <lb/>
     memorandum to us, that the matter of the disposi<lb break="no"/>tion of our interest-free loans to Britain was dis<lb break="no"/>cussed. It will be observed that the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom government informed us that on the 
     <lb/>
     advice of the Commission government, it would 
     <lb/>
     not be prudent to use the balance of these loans 
     <lb/>
     for the reduction of our sterling indebtedness, as 
     <lb/>
     such monies may be required for development 
     <lb/>
     purposes. Neither would the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     government undertake to pay the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     treasury any interest whatever on these loans, 
     <lb/>
     although the treasury of Newfoundland today is 
     <lb/>
     paying 3% per annum on these very loans. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Our delegation took the position that these 
     <lb/>
     loans should be used for the purpose of reducing 
     <lb/>
     our sterling debt, and we pointed out to the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom government that we could not under<lb break="no"/>stand the attitude of the Commission in this mat<lb break="no"/>ter. The Secretary of State had consistently 
     <lb/>
     pointed out to us that, owing to the shortage of 
     <lb/>
     dollars in Great Britain, they were not in a posi<lb break="no"/>tion to devote this money to the reduction of our 
     <lb/>
     debt; whilst on the other hand the Commission 
     <lb/>
     government had intimated that they might need 
     <lb/>
     the money for future development purposes. it 
     <lb/>
     can be seen how inconsistent the Commission 
     <lb/>
     government and the Secretary of State were, be<lb break="no"/>cause to be of any use for development purposes 
     <lb/>
     in Newfoundland, this money would have to be 
     <lb/>
     converted back to dollars, whilst under the 
     <lb/>
     present circumstances it would not be necessary 
     <lb/>
     to find dollars for the purpose of reducing our 
     <lb/>
     debt, as this debt is principally held in the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom and our loans are now in sterling cur<lb break="no"/>rency. The Dominions Secretary advised us that 
     <lb/>
     it would be a matter of policy for the future 
     <lb/>
     government of Newfoundland as to the disposi<lb break="no"/>tion of this money, and this was concurred in by 
     <lb/>
     both Mr. Bradley and Mr. Keough. Five of us 
     <lb/>
     delegates took the position that it would be good 
     <lb/>
     business to use this money to reduce our debt, as 
     <lb/>
     it would mean a further reduction in interest and 


<note xml:id="fn_05">[1] Volume II:369. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note> 


            <pb n="531" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0531.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">May 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">531</fw>


     sinking fund annually of $400,000 which when 
     <lb/>
     added to the half million dollar reduction in in<lb break="no"/>terest charges by the conversion of our debt to 
     <lb/>
     2.5% as well as using the sinking fund, would 
     <lb/>
     mean an annual saving all told to the New<lb break="no"/>foundland treasury of approximately $1 million, 
     <lb/>
     and a reduction of our sterling indebtedness to 
     <lb/>
     less than $54 million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We pointed out to the representatives of the 
     <lb/>
     British government that the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     delegation was deeply conscious of the condition 
     <lb/>
     of affairs generally in the mother country, but that 
     <lb/>
     at the same time we were fully aware of what the 
     <lb/>
     saving of $1 million annually would mean to the 
     <lb/>
     people of Newfoundland, who after all had suf<lb break="no"/>fered more than their share of hardship and priva<lb break="no"/>tion in the past. We took occasion to draw the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the Dominions Secretary to the ab<lb break="no"/>normal rise in our public expenditures during the 
     <lb/>
     past six or seven years, when such expenditures 
     <lb/>
     have risen from $16 million in 1940 to over $38 
     <lb/>
     million this year. We suggested that there was no 
     <lb/>
     sound reason for these excessive capital expen<lb break="no"/>ditures, and that in our opinion under no cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances should the expenditures exceed the 
     <lb/>
     revenues, and that our present cash balances 
     <lb/>
     should be conserved. We further pointed out that 
     <lb/>
     the application of this $9.25 million interest-free 
     <lb/>
     loan to Britain to the reduction of our sterling debt 
     <lb/>
     was a sound business proposition, and that such 
     <lb/>
     a disposition of this money would in no way 
     <lb/>
     effect the dollar situation in Great Britain. Our 
     <lb/>
     efforts to get any commitment in respect to this 
     <lb/>
     matter were of no avail, and as usual we were 
     <lb/>
     informed by Viscount Addison that these matters 
     <lb/>
     had already been considered by the Commission 
     <lb/>
     government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With regard to the operation of Gander airport, 
     <lb/>
     it will be seen from the interchange of memoran<lb break="no"/>da that under the new arrangement New<lb break="no"/>foundland is being held liable for a minimum of 
     <lb/>
     $250,000 a year deficit on the operation of this 
     <lb/>
     international air highway. Our delegation felt that 
     <lb/>
     because Newfoundland as a country was not in<lb break="no"/>terested in the air transport business, and par<lb break="no"/>ticularly in View of the fact that several foreign 
     <lb/>
     airlines were using the facilities of the airport, our 
     <lb/>
     country should not be called upon to pay any 
     <lb/>
     deficit that might be incurred in its operation. 
     <lb/>
     However, under the present circumstances it is 
     <lb/>
     quite evident that both the Dominions Office and 
 

            <cb/>
         

     the Commission government are satisfied that the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland treasury should bear one third of 
     <lb/>
     any deficit that might be incurred. Nevertheless, 
     <lb/>
     it was pointed out to us that in the event of the 
     <lb/>
     country deciding to return to responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment, the Newfoundland authorities will have the 
     <lb/>
     right to decide any future policy in respect to the 
     <lb/>
     administration of this particular airport. There is 
     <lb/>
     no doubt in my mind, Mr. Chairman, that the 
     <lb/>
     British government is using this airport for inter<lb break="no"/>national bargaining. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     You will observe that in our memorandum to 
     <lb/>
     the United Kingdom government, we stressed the 
     <lb/>
     importance of some effort being made by the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom to induce the Government of the 
     <lb/>
     United Statesto grant Newfoundland some <hi rendition="simple:italic">quid 
     <lb/>
     pro quo</hi> in return for the 99-year leases of certain 
     <lb/>
     military, naval and air bases in Newfoundland, 
     <lb/>
     and as already pointed out, we were informed by 
     <lb/>
     the representatives of the British government that 
     <lb/>
     under the present trying times which their 
     <lb/>
     country was experiencing, they were not in any 
     <lb/>
     position to take the matter up with the American 
     <lb/>
     authorities. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With regard to matters of trade and tariffs, we 
     <lb/>
     pressed with all our ability the importance of the 
     <lb/>
     purchase by Great Britain of substantial quan<lb break="no"/>tities of our fresh and frozen fish. We took oc<lb break="no"/>casion to point out that during the war they had 
     <lb/>
     purchased considerable quantities of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland's fishery products at much lower 
     <lb/>
     prices than we could have obtained from the 
     <lb/>
     United States. They invariably replied sym<lb break="no"/>pathetically, but stated that their great difficulty 
     <lb/>
     was the dollar exchange. When the matter of their 
     <lb/>
     buying some 12,000 tons of fish from Iceland and 
     <lb/>
     over 20 million pounds from Norway was 
     <lb/>
     brought to their attention, the Secretary of State 
     <lb/>
     informed us that he was writing the Chancellor 
     <lb/>
     of the Exchequer on the whole matter. It was 
     <lb/>
     pointed out to them that this very year New<lb break="no"/>foundland had purchased three ships from Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain at a cost of some $2.5 million and that in 
     <lb/>
     our opinion they should have taken fish in pay<lb break="no"/>ment, instead of transferring these dollars to the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom from the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     treasury, and not even buying our fish. At this 
     <lb/>
     point the representatives of the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     became somewhat indignant, because they felt 
     <lb/>
     that the people of Newfoundland would not mind 
     <lb/>
     them using our monies to their own advantage, 


            <pb n="532" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0532.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">532</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">May 1947</fw>
   

     even though they had evidently not considered 
     <lb/>
     the importance to the Newfoundland fishermen 
     <lb/>
     of keeping our fresh fish plants in operation. We 
     <lb/>
     received information that the fish which the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom is buying from both Iceland and 
     <lb/>
     Norway is being paid for at a much higher price 
     <lb/>
     than the same commodity could be purchased 
     <lb/>
     from Newfoundland. Finally, the Secretary of 
     <lb/>
     State gave us his assurance that he would go 
     <lb/>
     further into the matter, and I think we all feel that 
     <lb/>
     some effort will be made to purchase a quantity. 
     <lb/>
     of our fresh and frozen fish during the coming 
     <lb/>
     season. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The same difficulty arises with regard to the 
     <lb/>
     sale of our iron ore to Great Britain It is a 
     <lb/>
     question of being able to find dollars, and we 
     <lb/>
     were informed by Mr. Bottomley that he has been 
     <lb/>
     working assiduously in this respect and that we 
     <lb/>
     shall possibly have an order for our ore this 
     <lb/>
     season. Nevertheless, we obtained no definite 
     <lb/>
     assurance from the United Kingdom government 
     <lb/>
     that they would be in a position to guarantee any 
     <lb/>
     long-term contracts. As usual, they told us that 
     <lb/>
     the Commission government had been pressing 
     <lb/>
     for action on all these matters. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Our third and final meeting with the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of the United Kingdom government 
     <lb/>
     took place in the Dominions Office on the morn<lb break="no"/>ing of May 8. The Secretary of State, Viscount 
     <lb/>
     Addison, as usual, occupied the Chair and in 
     <lb/>
     reply to our memorandum handed us the follow<lb break="no"/>ing, which I shall now read for the information of 
     <lb/>
     the Convention and the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Cashin read the memorandum</hi><ref target="#fn_06">[1]</ref><hi rendition="simple:italic">]</hi>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     As on the occasion of our second meeting on 
     <lb/>
     May I, Mr. Glenvil Hall was not present, and I 
     <lb/>
     am convinced that the majority of the members 
     <lb/>
     of our delegation felt that because of this 
     <lb/>
     gentleman's reasonableness, and his sympathetic 
     <lb/>
     attitude towards Newfoundland in respect to the 
     <lb/>
     adjustment of our public debt, influence was 
     <lb/>
     brought to bear for the purpose of preventing him 
     <lb/>
     from attending our two meetings. In any case, the 
     <lb/>
     fact of his being absent for the second occasion 
     <lb/>
     is most significant. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After reading this final memorandum, I am 
     <lb/>
     sure that the Convention and the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland will be assured that because of our 
     <lb/>
     pressing the United Kingdom government for 
     <lb/>
     certain information and action, and because they 
    

            <cb/>
       

     realised their embarrassing position, they 
     <lb/>
     decided to cut us off short by simply telling us, 
     <lb/>
     in effect, that we had no business whatever to 
     <lb/>
     discuss with them the administration of the af<lb break="no"/>fairs of Newfoundland, that it was not for us to 
     <lb/>
     suggest policies which we, in our view, con<lb break="no"/>sidered were a benefit to the country and its future 
     <lb/>
     prosperity. So they raise the issue of our authority 
     <lb/>
     under the Convention Act. They tell us that our 
     <lb/>
     suggestions and efforts were nothing, more or less 
     <lb/>
     than a condemnation and criticism of the Com<lb break="no"/>mission government. They overlook the fact that 
     <lb/>
     they had asked us weeks before we left New<lb break="no"/>foundland what matters we desired to discuss 
     <lb/>
     with them. They forgetthat they agreed to discuss 
     <lb/>
     such matters, and now turn and in so many words 
     <lb/>
     tell us to mind our own business, and that all these 
     <lb/>
     affairs have been, and are still under considera<lb break="no"/>tion by the Commission government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When questioned on the constitutional issue, 
     <lb/>
     Viscount Addison glibly and deliberately 
     <lb/>
     avoided answering any direct questions, and I am 
     <lb/>
     sure he left every delegate with the impression 
     <lb/>
     that no matter what decisions this Convention 
     <lb/>
     might make, the United Kingdom government 
     <lb/>
     had made up its mind. They were going to control 
     <lb/>
     the Government of Newfoundland as long as 
     <lb/>
     there was a dollar left to the credit ofour treasury. 
     <lb/>
     This statement has been made by me on 
     <lb/>
     numerous occasions, and recent indications made 
     <lb/>
     in the budget speech tell us of a three-year 
     <lb/>
     programme which has been planned for New<lb break="no"/>foundland by the present Commission govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The British government has thrown overboard 
     <lb/>
     the agreement or pledge they gave to this country 
     <lb/>
     in 1933-34, and I express the personal opinion 
     <lb/>
     again this evening, that so long as our treasury 
     <lb/>
     dollar balances are available, it is their intention 
     <lb/>
     to hold on to the control of Newfoundland. They 
     <lb/>
     have intimated time and time again that they have 
     <lb/>
     plans for two or three year development program<lb break="no"/>mes as well as reconstruction programmes, and 
     <lb/>
     they have not shown on their part that they would 
     <lb/>
     agree to any change of government the people 
     <lb/>
     may decide on, even though a plebiscite be taken 
     <lb/>
     this year. They have not even committed them<lb break="no"/>selves to do so. At the present time our country 
     <lb/>
     is nothing more or less than an international 
     <lb/>
     pawn, and is being used by the United Kingdom 
   

            <pb n="533" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0533.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">May 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">533</fw>
       

     government for the purpose of making interna<lb break="no"/>tional deals with both the United States and 
     <lb/>
     Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That, gentlemen, completes the official record 
     <lb/>
     of the delegation's visit to the Dominions Office. 
     <lb/>
     And we have now passed on to you for what it is 
     <lb/>
     worth all the information which has been given 
     <lb/>
     us. You now know just as much as we members 
     <lb/>
     of the delegation, and are just as competent to 
     <lb/>
     arrive at your own conclusions. No doubt during 
     <lb/>
     the discussion members will have ample oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity to express their individual opinions. For 
     <lb/>
     myself, before concluding, I wish to express a 
     <lb/>
     few purely personal opinions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Firstly, what did the mission of this delegation 
     <lb/>
     to London accomplish? To begin with we were 
     <lb/>
     successful in having the £400,000 temporary 
     <lb/>
     loan of 1917, on which no interest had been paid, 
     <lb/>
     cancelled — it's off the books. Secondly, I con<lb break="no"/>tend that we were primarily instrumental in 
     <lb/>
     having our sterling debt which amounts to nearly 
     <lb/>
     $72 million and which now bears interest at 3%, 
     <lb/>
     converted, or rather we were promised it would 
     <lb/>
     be converted, to 2.5% on January 1 next. In 
     <lb/>
     addition, we were successful in having the British 
     <lb/>
     government use the sinking fund of this debt, 
     <lb/>
     which will amount to $8.25 million in July, for 
     <lb/>
     the purpose of reducing this particular debt. By 
     <lb/>
     this action the treasury of the country will save at 
     <lb/>
     least half a million dollars annually. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are of the opinion, or at least I am, that 
     <lb/>
     because of our representations the Dominions 
     <lb/>
     Office will probably devote our interest-free 
     <lb/>
     loans to the further reduction of our sterling debt, 
     <lb/>
     and that because of our consistent emphasis, there 
     <lb/>
     is a good possibility of the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     giving us an order for our fresh and frozen fish 
     <lb/>
     this season. They assure us that they are doing 
     <lb/>
     their best, such as it is. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To me, this whole affair simply represents a 
     <lb/>
     continuance of the policy which has been operat<lb break="no"/>ing in Newfoundland since 1934. It is just another 
     <lb/>
     piece in the jig-saw puzzle into which New<lb break="no"/>foundland has been cut up. But these pieces are 
     <lb/>
     gradually being put together, and when the last 
     <lb/>
     piece is put in place, and the puzzle solved, some 
     <lb/>
     people amongst us may be in for a surprise. 
     <lb/>
     Because, if the forces opposed to us have their 
     <lb/>
     way, it will not be a picture of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     they will see, not the Newfoundland which the 
     <lb/>
     Commission took over in 1934, but instead a part 
 

            <cb/>
  

     of the country we know as Canada. I will have 
     <lb/>
     much more to say on this matter at a later date. 
     <lb/>
     But for the present let me continue my comments 
     <lb/>
     on the delegates' visit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let me say that I do not believe that the British 
     <lb/>
     government ever wanted to see a delegation from 
     <lb/>
     this country coming to England. And why should 
     <lb/>
     they? For has not this visit shown that they had 
     <lb/>
     long ago finalised their plans concerning us? But 
     <lb/>
     this Convention decided to send a delegation, and 
     <lb/>
     faced with this request, the British government 
     <lb/>
     had no other choice but to put a good face on the 
     <lb/>
     matter. It would have been very bad politics for 
     <lb/>
     them to have done otherwise. Even so, they 
     <lb/>
     showed very little enthusiasm. Members will 
     <lb/>
     remember that before they would consider meet<lb break="no"/>ing us they demanded that we first place on paper 
     <lb/>
     the matters we wished to discuss. This was hardly 
     <lb/>
     an invitation to the open and free discussion we 
     <lb/>
     had hoped for. You know how it is when someone 
     <lb/>
     calls at your door that you don't want to see. If 
     <lb/>
     you can't say you are not at home, you tell the 
     <lb/>
     servant to ask the man what he wants to see you 
     <lb/>
     about, and so it was with us. Viscount Addison 
     <lb/>
     first wanted to know what we wanted to see him 
     <lb/>
     about to prepare himself in advance. He did not 
     <lb/>
     want to be taken by surprise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now compare this with the preliminaries of 
     <lb/>
     sending a delegation to Canada. Did they send us 
     <lb/>
     a guarded request to know what we wanted to see 
     <lb/>
     them about? Did they ask for memorandums? 
     <lb/>
     Not at all. They almost fell over themselves put<lb break="no"/>ting out the welcome hand. A delegation would 
     <lb/>
     be welcomed with a heart and a half. The joy bells 
     <lb/>
     will ring out in Ottawa when they arrive. Now 
     <lb/>
     what does all this mean? ln the first place it means 
     <lb/>
     that the British government has endorsed 
     <lb/>
     Canada's action — that she has encouraged 
     <lb/>
     Canada to give us a big hand. And if she has done 
     <lb/>
     this, it also means that the British government is 
     <lb/>
     prepared to see us go into Canada — that she 
     <lb/>
     wants us to go in with Canada. For myself I see 
     <lb/>
     in it just a further continuation of something 
     <lb/>
     which I have long expected. I have much inter<lb break="no"/>esting evidence, which I may place before this 
     <lb/>
     house at a later date, when the matter of forms of 
     <lb/>
     government eventually comes up. But for the 
     <lb/>
     present I say this, and you may think I am talking 
     <lb/>
     rashly if you wish. I say to you that there is in 
     <lb/>
     operation at the present time a conspiracy to sell, 
     <lb/>
     and I use the word "sell" advisedly, this country 


            <pb n="534" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0534.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">534</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">May 1947</fw>
        

     to the Dominion of Canada. I repeat, some people 
     <lb/>
     may think I am talking wildly, but I would ask 
     <lb/>
     them to remember that long before this I made 
     <lb/>
     statements in this house which were regarded at 
     <lb/>
     the time as wild prophecies, but time proved that 
     <lb/>
     I was right. All I ask you then to do in the present 
     <lb/>
     instance, is to watch events develOp in the com<lb break="no"/>ing two months, then pass your judgement on the 
     <lb/>
     statements I make today. Watch in particular the 
     <lb/>
     attractive bait which will be held out to lure our 
     <lb/>
     country into the Canadian mouse-trap. Listen to 
     <lb/>
     the flowery sales talk which will be offered you, 
     <lb/>
     telling Newfoundlanders they are a lost people, 
     <lb/>
     that our only hope, our only salvation, lies in 
     <lb/>
     following a new Moses into the promised land 
     <lb/>
     across the Cabot Strait. By the way, I note by 
     <lb/>
     recent papers, that there are 30,000 men un<lb break="no"/>employed in the Maritimes alone. Can it be that 
     <lb/>
     things are so wonderful in this Paradise that men 
     <lb/>
     don't need to work? Gentlemen, before leaving 
     <lb/>
     this matter I would say just this, look out for those 
     <lb/>
     amongst us who would take ourselves and our 
     <lb/>
     country on a one-way ride. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But let me again return to my comments on 
     <lb/>
     the delegation to England. Now, as I mentioned 
     <lb/>
     in the beginning, there are some people who had 
     <lb/>
     the impression that we went to England looking 
     <lb/>
     for favours and handouts from a starving and 
     <lb/>
     depressed people. Such is emphatically not the 
     <lb/>
     case. We went to investigate and discuss New<lb break="no"/>foundland affairs. We wanted to know what they 
     <lb/>
     were doing with our money. We wanted to know 
     <lb/>
     why they had given away parts of our sovereign 
     <lb/>
     territory, and we wanted to know above all else 
     <lb/>
     what they intended to do about our rights as a 
     <lb/>
     politically free people. For ten years we have 
     <lb/>
     been trying to get this information out of the local 
     <lb/>
     Commission, but in vain. And after our trip we 
     <lb/>
     are little wiser than we were before. But as for 
     <lb/>
     wanting to get any handouts from Britain — why 
     <lb/>
     nothing could be further from the truth. We did 
     <lb/>
     not ask for anything from Britain — not a dollar 
     <lb/>
     of her wealth, an ounce of her food, an inch of 
     <lb/>
     her territory. And I think the other members of 
     <lb/>
     the delegation will agree with me when I say that 
     <lb/>
     in the person of Viscount Addison we had to deal 
     <lb/>
     with a man who was quite competent in protect<lb break="no"/>ing his country's assets. Talk of giving — why 
     <lb/>
     he would not even give us an answer to many of 
     <lb/>
     our questions. And in the two weeks we were in 
     <lb/>
     England we were only granted three meetings. To 
  

            <cb/>
            

     my mind, Viscount Addison gave an example of 
     <lb/>
     political economy of the highest order. He was 
     <lb/>
     the soul of economy and political tact. Of course 
     <lb/>
     it would not be fair to place all the blame on the 
     <lb/>
     shoulders of the noble lord, because it was quite 
     <lb/>
     obvious that he was acting under strict orders, and 
     <lb/>
     these orders seemed to be, as regards the delega<lb break="no"/>tion, "Tell them nothing and give them nothing". 
     <lb/>
     We asked him plenty of questions. We showered 
     <lb/>
     him with them, but he shed them like a duck. He 
     <lb/>
     had his orders not to go beyond a certain point, 
     <lb/>
     and beyond that point he refused to budge. Some<lb break="no"/>times we thought we had him tied up, but he 
     <lb/>
     wiggled out with the ease of a Houdini. However, 
     <lb/>
     there were one or two occasions when he found 
     <lb/>
     himself out on a limb. I remember in particular 
     <lb/>
     when he was trying to justify the base deals. He 
     <lb/>
     put up his defence, that the British government 
     <lb/>
     were forced to give the United States these bases 
     <lb/>
     because they were in a hole and Great Britain 
     <lb/>
     desperately needed destroyers. He elaborated on 
     <lb/>
     this point and made much of it, saying that "lives 
     <lb/>
     had to be saved." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I could go on at great length, Mr. Chairman, 
     <lb/>
     commenting on the many phases of this visit of 
     <lb/>
     ours, but I believe it is best summed up in the 
     <lb/>
     London newspaper which refers to it as follows: 
     <lb/>
     "How cold, graceless, ungenerous and chuck<lb break="no"/>leheaded is the attitude of the Government 
     <lb/>
     towards Newfoundlanders." It goes on to say: "It 
     <lb/>
     could not, it dare not go back on Britain's pledge 
     <lb/>
     of 1934, that as soon as the Island's difficulties 
     <lb/>
     had been overcome, Responsible Government on 
     <lb/>
     the request of the people of Newfoundland would 
     <lb/>
     be restored. Yet today it talks of special difficul<lb break="no"/>ties of our financial position and tells the New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders harshly that, if they vote away the 
     <lb/>
     present Commission, Britain will no longer 
     <lb/>
     guarantee the interest on Newfoundland's loan of 
     <lb/>
     $71 million. Is this the way to talk to our kith and 
     <lb/>
     kin? When Newfoundland made Britain an inter<lb break="no"/>est free loan of £25 million for the war effort, she 
     <lb/>
     did not extract a promise in return. New<lb break="no"/>foundland sent her young men to tight alongside 
     <lb/>
     us, sent her sailors to defy the U-boats, she 
     <lb/>
     provided bases, she begrudged nothing. The 
     <lb/>
     statement made to the Newfoundland delegation 
     <lb/>
     by a government which has poured out millions 
     <lb/>
     in dollars to succour strangers from China to 
     <lb/>
     Chechoslovakia in the last two years is con<lb break="no"/>temptible". That is the summary of the London 


            <pb n="535" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-05-19_Page_0535.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">May 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">535</fw>
         

     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Daily Express</hi>. True, it is an opposition paper — 
     <lb/>
     it probably wishes to make political capital out of 
     <lb/>
     the facts. But does that dispute the existance of 
     <lb/>
     these facts? Does it prove that they are not a true 
     <lb/>
     statement of conditions? Gentlemen, it is my 
     <lb/>
     opinion that we should not waste much time on 
     <lb/>
     this report. The answers to our questions could 
     <lb/>
     have been obtained by means of a registered 
     <lb/>
     letter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I close my remarks with this message: the 
     <lb/>
     people amongst us who love freedom, who love 
     <lb/>
     the traditions of this fine land, who cherish our 
     <lb/>
     traditions, must prepare themselves to defend 
     <lb/>
     these things if they would preserve them. At this 
     <lb/>
     very moment the lines of battle are drawn up, and 
     <lb/>
     walking amongst us are those whose burning 
     <lb/>
     ambition it is to see this country passed into the 
     <lb/>
     hands of strangers; to haul down the flag of our 
     <lb/>
     fathers and replace it with an alien one; to make 
  

            <cb/>
            

     the Ode to Newfoundland a forgotten thing on the 
     <lb/>
    lips of our children, and to extinguish the torch 
     <lb/>which our liberty-loving ancestors cherished for 
     <lb/>nearly 100 years. All these things they will try to 
     <lb/>do under a banner to which they have nailed the 
     <lb/>dollar sign. But I tell them they will not succeed. 
     <lb/>Once before in our history our country had to 
     <lb/>meet such an attack. Once before there were those 
     <lb/>who sought to destroy her identity and sabotage 
     <lb/>her liberty, but a far poorer country and a less 
     <lb/>enlightened people gave them their answer. Shall 
     <lb/>we of today, blessed inhabitants of one of the 
     <lb/>most solvent countries in the world, fail where 
     <lb/>our fathers triumphed? I feel that I have the 
     <lb/>endorsement of all right-thinking New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders with me when I say that we shall 
     <lb/>not fail. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee rose and reported progress, and<lb/>the Convention adjourned]</hi>
            </p>
   
<!-- GL, 2017-06-28, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


           <!-- <p>
     May 20, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I wish to inform the House of 
     <lb/>
     the progress being made in connection with the 
     <lb/>
     matter of the arrangements for the conference 
     <lb/>
     between the delegation of this Convention and 
     <lb/>
     His Majesty's Government in Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The latter part of last week the delegation met 
     <lb/>
     and decided to advise the Government of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     through His Excellency the Governor, that the 
     <lb/>
     delegation would wish to meet with the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government as early as possible in the month of 
     <lb/>
     June. That presumably was communicated by 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency to His Majesty's Government in 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and l have here before me a letter which 
     <lb/>
     has just been handed to me by His Excellency 
     <lb/>
     which reads as follows: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I write to inform you that, owing to 
     <lb/>
     various important events that are to take 
     <lb/>
     place in Canada during the early part of June, 
     <lb/>
     the earliest date that would be convenient for 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian Government to receive the 
     <lb/>
     Delegation from the National Convention 
     <lb/>
     would be either June 25th or July 2nd. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would be glad if you would inform me 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     respecting the preference of the Delegation 
     <lb/>
     in the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Yours faithfully 
     <lb/>
    Sgd.: Gordon Macdonald 
     <lb/>Governor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>That, presumably, is the substance of a despatch 
     <lb/>from His Majesty's Government in Canada to the 
     <lb/>Governor in Newfoundland. It is a development 
     <lb/>which I may say I anticipated to some extent. 
     <lb/>Many of you are aware of the fact that President 
     <lb/>Truman of the United States is likely to visit 
     <lb/>Ottawa in the early part of June, which will 
     <lb/>doubtless take up a considerable portion of the 
     <lb/>time of the Canadian government for three or four 
     <lb/>days, and a little later there is a very large con<lb break="no"/>gress which will meet in Ottawa, and which will 
     <lb/>bring into the city I believe about 150,000 
     <lb/>pilgrims. These proceedings will occupy a con<lb break="no"/>siderable period of time, and the Canadian 
     <lb/>government will be of course engaged to some 
     <lb/>extent in them. I would ask the Canadian delega<lb break="no"/>tion to meet me in my office when the House 
     <lb/>adjoums this evening. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     Report of the London Delegation:¹ 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Mr. Chairman, I would like to 
     <lb/>
     congratulate this National Convention on its wis- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     dom in sending a delegation to London. I want to 
     <lb/>
     congratulate, very sincerely, the delegation itself, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>¹Volume II:448.<lb/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>