<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-12-08" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-12-08">8 December 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.  
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="960" to="973"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0960.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0961.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0962.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0963.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0964.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0965.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0966.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0967.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0968.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0969.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0970.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0971.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0972.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0973.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-08-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-08-09">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0960">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0960.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0961">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0961.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0962">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0962.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0963">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0963.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0964">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0964.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0965">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0965.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0966">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0966.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0967">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0967.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0968">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0968.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0969">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0969.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0970">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0970.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0971">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0971.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0972">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0972.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0973">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0973.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="960" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0960.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">960</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
            

<!-- GL, 2017-08-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
<!--<p>
     dark and gloomy side, and the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland want to hear it. I want to hear it now. 
     <lb/>
     (Cries of "Hear! Hear!") 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The motion is that the commit<lb break="no"/>tee rise and report progress, and ask leave to sit 
     <lb/>
     again tomorrow. Is the Convention ready for the 
     <lb/>
     question? Those in favour say "aye", contrary 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     "nay". I can't decide. Division of the House.... 
     <lb/>
     All those in favour of the motion, stand — 25. All 
     <lb/>
     those against the motion, stand — 6 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The committee rose and reported progress, and 
     <lb/>
     the Convention adjourned until Monday. Decem<lb break="no"/>ber 8] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     December 8, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I give notice 
     <lb/>
     that I will on tomorrow ask His Excellency the 
     <lb/>
     Governor in Commission to ask the Government 
     <lb/>
     of Canada if they would assist the National Con<lb break="no"/>vention in its consideration of the proposals for 


            <cb/>
      

     union by explaining in some detail the basis of 
     <lb/>
     computation of the table in Annex IV, showing 
     <lb/>
     probable federal revenue from Newfoundland in 
     <lb/>
     the event of union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the Ottawa Delegation 
     <lb/>
     Proposed Arrangements for the Entry of Newfoundland into Confederation 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, we adjourned 
     <lb/>
     on Thursday last with the thought that today we 
     <lb/>
     would deal with prospective expenditure and 
     <lb/>
     revenue of the government of the Province of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, should we become a province of 
     <lb/>
     Canada. It was understood that I would bring in 
     <lb/>
     today some figures and statistics that might indi<lb break="no"/>cate generally the expenditure that the provincial 
     <lb/>
     government would need to make, and also the 
     <lb/>
     revenue that it might expect to take in to meet 
     <lb/>
     those expenditures. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On their desks, members will find the first part 
     <lb/>
     of that estimate,<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> namely the probable expendi<lb break="no"/>tures of the provincial government of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. On the revenue side I have not, as yet, 
     <lb/>
     had the figures mimeographed. I have them here 
     <lb/>
     in front of me. Before we can get to a considera<lb break="no"/>tion of the revenue side they will be 
     <lb/>
     mimeographed and placed on the desks of the 
     <lb/>
     members. I ought to make one or two points clear 
     <lb/>
     before we come to an examination of the expen<lb break="no"/>diture table. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The first point is this: that confederation does 
     <lb/>
     not mean that Canada would take Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     over and run it, because Canada is a federal union 
     <lb/>
     of nine provinces — Newfoundland would make 
     <lb/>
     the tenth. A federal union, wherever it does exist 
     <lb/>
     in this world, means only a sharing or dividing of 
     <lb/>
     responsibilities and powers; so that confedera<lb break="no"/>tion would mean that the powers which our 
     <lb/>
     government now has would be divided. We 
    

            <cb/>
         

     would have some powers, and the Government 
     <lb/>
     of Canada would have some, and the respon<lb break="no"/>sibilities and burdens our government now has 
     <lb/>
     would be divided. Our government would carry 
     <lb/>
     some of the burdens and the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada would carry some. Now, confederation 
     <lb/>
     may or may not be a good thing for this country. 
     <lb/>
     One thing, however, is fairly clear, that if there 
     <lb/>
     are advantages from confederation for the people 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland, confederation is still not a 
     <lb/>
     good thing if the government of the Province of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland is not able to pay its way. Or put 
     <lb/>
     it this way: we might get many advantages from 
     <lb/>
     confederation. These advantages might be con<lb break="no"/>siderable, but they will all fall by the way if the 
     <lb/>
     government of the province is not able to collect 
     <lb/>
     enough revenue to pay the cost of those things 
     <lb/>
     which the government of the province would still 
     <lb/>
     have to do, even with confederation. Not only 
     <lb/>
     that, the government of the province must be able 
     <lb/>
     to pay its way without imposing too great a 
     <lb/>
     burden of taxation on the people; without costing 
     <lb/>
     the people too much in taxes; and again without 
     <lb/>
     stinting on those public services, which the 
     <lb/>
     government of the province would have to 
     <lb/>
     carry.... The government of the province would 
     <lb/>
     still have its public services to render to the 
     <lb/>
     people of Newfoundland. Confederation, there<lb break="no"/>fore, to be of real benefit, must not only give the 
     <lb/>
     people of Newfoundland certain advantages and 
     <lb/>
     benefits from the Government of Canada; it must 
 

     <note xml:id="fn_01">[1] The detailed projected provincial budget submitted by Mr. Smallwood could not be found. See Volume 
     <lb/>
     II:522 for a budget reconstructed from the debates and newspaper reports. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note> 

            <pb n="961" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0961.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">961</fw>
       

     also be possible for the government of the 
     <lb/>
     province to carry on provincial government ser<lb break="no"/>vices without diminishing them, without reduc<lb break="no"/>ing the level and standard of public service; and 
     <lb/>
     to do that without imposing on the people too 
     <lb/>
     heavy a burden of taxation. In other words, the 
     <lb/>
     total amount of taxation that is placed on the 
     <lb/>
     people of Newfoundland ... must be such as they 
     <lb/>
     can carry without too great a burden; and in the 
     <lb/>
     second place that burden of taxation put on them 
     <lb/>
     by the Government of Canada and the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Newfoundland together, must fall equi<lb break="no"/>tably and fairly upon them, and above all must 
     <lb/>
     not constitute too heavy a burden for our people 
     <lb/>
     to bear. Now the question is, can the Province of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, should we become a province, 
     <lb/>
     pay its way? That is what we are met today to deal 
     <lb/>
     with. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now I am not a prophet, nor am I the son of a 
     <lb/>
     prophet, and when I was born I was not given the 
     <lb/>
     gift of second sight. I cannot see through a stone 
     <lb/>
     wall more than any other man, and in these 
     <lb/>
     figures which I have tabled today I am not 
     <lb/>
     pretending that these are and must be the exact 
     <lb/>
     expenditures of the Province of Newfoundland.... 
     <lb/>
     The amount may be larger and may be smaller. I 
     <lb/>
     based these figures upon common sense, and 
     <lb/>
     upon what knowledge I have of the public ser<lb break="no"/>vices of Newfoundland as they exist today, and 
     <lb/>
     are likely to exist under confederation. With these 
     <lb/>
     criteria as a yardstick, I hold that the government 
     <lb/>
     of the province can and will pay its way, balance 
     <lb/>
     its budget, and do it without imposing too heavy 
     <lb/>
     a burden of taxation on the people, and without 
     <lb/>
     reducing the standard or level of public services. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir, what I have done is this. I have divided the 
     <lb/>
     public finances of this province, if we become a 
     <lb/>
     province, into two classes: on the one side expen<lb break="no"/>diture, and on the other hand what money the 
     <lb/>
     government is likely to take in year by year to 
     <lb/>
     meet these expenses. I have done something else. 
     <lb/>
     I have taken a period of eight years for both.... My 
     <lb/>
     reason for that is that one clause of the terms 
     <lb/>
     offered by the Government of Canada provides 
     <lb/>
     that within eight years of union that government 
     <lb/>
     will appoint, not might, or may, but <hi rendition="simple:italic">will</hi> appoint 
     <lb/>
     a royal commission for the purpose of looking 
     <lb/>
     into our financial condition; that it will examine 
     <lb/>
     and reassess our financial position to learn 
     <lb/>
     whether the subsidies from the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada are large enough or not; whether we can 


            <cb/>
            

     go on for more years into the future with the same 
     <lb/>
     subsidies, or whether these would need to be 
     <lb/>
     increased. As, therefore, our whole financial 
     <lb/>
     position would be reviewed and reassessed 
     <lb/>
     within eight years of union, I hold that at the least 
     <lb/>
     we must see our way clear to balancing our books 
     <lb/>
     and breaking even for eight years at least.... 
     <lb/>
     Therefore my figures are based upon a period of 
     <lb/>
     eight years, and I have gone a step further; I have 
     <lb/>
     taken the eight years and divided them in two, 
     <lb/>
     having therefore two periods of four years each, 
     <lb/>
     and the house will see, as we go on, the reason 
     <lb/>
     why. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I hope after that preliminary explanation that 
     <lb/>
     the members have their copies of the current 
     <lb/>
     estimates before them, because this whole docu<lb break="no"/>ment now on your desks of probable expenditures 
     <lb/>
     by the Government of Newfoundland as a 
     <lb/>
     province is based upon the actual estimates of the 
     <lb/>
     present government for the present fiscal year, 
     <lb/>
     which ends on March 31, 1948. In my memo, on 
     <lb/>
     the first page, it states, no. 1 — Mr. Chairman, I 
     <lb/>
     notice that many of the members have not got the 
     <lb/>
     current estimates before them. I believe in the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary's office there is a pile of them, and it 
     <lb/>
     might be a good idea if they were secured and 
     <lb/>
     distributed to the members so that they could 
     <lb/>
     follow the thing a little more intelligently than 
     <lb/>
     they could do otherwise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There are not enough. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> If there are not quite enough to 
     <lb/>
     go round it might be possible to share between 
     <lb/>
     two or three members, considering that some 
     <lb/>
     members already have copies of it here now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As the first page is rather simple, I will 
     <lb/>
     proceed with it even while we are waiting.... In 
     <lb/>
     the estimates you pass by everything until you 
     <lb/>
     come to item 3, namely "War loan if $1.5 million 
     <lb/>
     at 3.75% interest, $56,250 a year interest on that 
     <lb/>
     loan", "Victory loan...total interest per year 
     <lb/>
     $265,000." That of course refers to the public 
     <lb/>
     debt that would be Newfoundland's public debt 
     <lb/>
     if we became a province. The terms say that 
     <lb/>
     Canada would take over the external public debt; 
     <lb/>
     the internal public debt, that is, what the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Newfoundland owes the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, the Government of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     would hold on to, and to pay the interest on that 
     <lb/>
     each year would be $265,000. Then, "Sinking 
     <lb/>
     and redemption funds on the first war loan of $1.5  
     <lb/>
     million... grand total per year of $376,250." That 
 

            <pb n="962" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0962.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">962</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
          

     is the first item of expenditure that the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the province would have to meet. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then turn over to page 17, incidentally on 
     <lb/>
     page 16 you will see why this is not in my 
     <lb/>
     memorandum, these things are not federal. The 
     <lb/>
     federal government will pay the salaries of the 
     <lb/>
     Governor, and of the two judges of the Supreme 
     <lb/>
     Court, and the salaries of the magistrates of the 
     <lb/>
     District Court. All these would be paid by the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada, so that brings you to 
     <lb/>
     page 17, Department of Finance. You see what I 
     <lb/>
     have done there.... I ought to say, in connection 
     <lb/>
     with those items, that the Department of Finance 
     <lb/>
     would naturally be a smaller department than it 
     <lb/>
     is today, because so many things that department 
     <lb/>
     has to do now would then be done by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada.... The same thing applies to the 
     <lb/>
     Comptroller and the Auditor General. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then we pass on to the next page. "Travelling 
     <lb/>
     and miscellaneous expenses — $4,700. General 
     <lb/>
     contingencies. Rental, statistical machines — 
     <lb/>
     $4,500." The explanation of that, of course, is 
     <lb/>
     that the machines are costing more than that to 
     <lb/>
     rent, but the same machines would be used for 
     <lb/>
     both federal and provincial purposes. There 
     <lb/>
     would be no need of putting in additional 
     <lb/>
     machines, and that would cut down the cost to the 
     <lb/>
     province. "Printing and Publishing...$287,698 a 
     <lb/>
     year." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, I wonder would 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood mind if I asked him a question 
     <lb/>
     on that point? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I would appreciate, Mr. Chair<lb break="no"/>man, if Mr. Hollett, and other gentlemen in the 
     <lb/>
     Convention, would permit me to run through the 
     <lb/>
     entire lot. The members have just had it before 
     <lb/>
     them, and the longer they have it before them the 
     <lb/>
     better they will be able to follow it, and to put 
     <lb/>
     questions. For that reason, if the House would 
     <lb/>
     permit me to read through the entire document 
     <lb/>
     and members make notes as they go, I think we 
     <lb/>
     would get further ahead. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Would you mind, Mr. Hollett, 
     <lb/>
     just making a note at this time? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> In that figure of $287,000, under 
     <lb/>
     this heading of the Department of Finance, there 
     <lb/>
     is an amount of $186,698. I see what Mr. Small<lb break="no"/>wood has done. In the Black Books, he has taken 
     <lb/>
     $101,000 from provincial expenditure and 
     <lb/>
     passed over to Dominion expenditure, now he 
     <lb/>
     has passed it over to provincial expenditure 


            <cb/>
         

     again. That was the question I wanted to ask you. 
     <lb/>
     Why? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The reason is that the other 
     <lb/>
     table in the Black Book is one we drew up before 
     <lb/>
     we went to Ottawa at all, and before we knew 
     <lb/>
     what we know now. Knowing what we knew 
     <lb/>
     then, we thought that civil servants that the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government would take over, would 
     <lb/>
     have their pensions paid by the Canadian govern<lb break="no"/>ment, whereas the actual position is that civil 
     <lb/>
     servants on pension now, or up to the date of 
     <lb/>
     union, will continue to have their pensions paid 
     <lb/>
     by Newfoundland; but the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada will pay civil service pensions to its own 
     <lb/>
     employees in Newfoundland when they come to 
     <lb/>
     be pensioned, for the time that they will have 
     <lb/>
     been working for the Government of Canada, but 
     <lb/>
     for the period preceding their becoming federal 
     <lb/>
     employees the provincial government is to pay 
     <lb/>
     their pensions.... I will pass on to the Department 
     <lb/>
     of Home Affairs. Then the Department of Educa<lb break="no"/>tion. I have taken the entire vote of that depart<lb break="no"/>ment, and if you turn to page 39 you will see the 
     <lb/>
     grand total vote this year of the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Education, which is $3,622,300. That includes an 
     <lb/>
     amount of $500 in reconstruction for the... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> $500,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I beg your pardon, isn't that 
     <lb/>
     what I said? $500,000 for the erection of new 
     <lb/>
     schools, and reconditioning of old ones, is in<lb break="no"/>cluded in that $3,622,000. I have eliminated the 
     <lb/>
     half a million dollars from the vote, although it is 
     <lb/>
     not to be supposed that eliminating it in my table 
     <lb/>
     that there is any idea that the half a million dollars 
     <lb/>
     would not be spent; it would come under another 
     <lb/>
     heading... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Excuse me. under what other head<lb break="no"/>ing would that $500,000 come? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Under any heading that the 
     <lb/>
     government of the future cares to put it under. 
     <lb/>
     That is entirely a matter of government policy. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> But where will they get it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> We will deal with that when we 
     <lb/>
     come to revenue. We are dealing only with what 
     <lb/>
     the Government of Newfoundland, as a province, 
     <lb/>
     would spend. When we come to the question of 
     <lb/>
     where and how the government would get the 
     <lb/>
     money to meet these expenditures, then we will 
     <lb/>
     deal with that in whatever detail you like. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Excuse me, but it would be an ex<lb break="no"/>penditure wouldn't it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="963" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0963.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">963</fw>
            

<p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Obviously. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Why is it not included here? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Because it is not ordinary ex<lb break="no"/>penditure; even at the present time, it is 
     <lb/>
     reconstruction expenditure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I see, you have another budget for 
     <lb/>
     that have you? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It does not follow at all. Now 
     <lb/>
     the Department of Justice. "Administrative 
     <lb/>
     $48,906...Supreme Court, $27,934." That, of 
     <lb/>
     course, does not include the salaries of the judges 
     <lb/>
     of the Supreme Court, the federal government 
     <lb/>
     would pay that. These are other expenditures of 
     <lb/>
     the court which the Government of New<lb break="no"/>foundland would have to pay: "14 assistant 
     <lb/>
     magistrates — $38,374 a year." The reason for 
     <lb/>
     that is that in the estimate you will find under 
     <lb/>
     4 (1), under the heading, "Magistrates", seven 
     <lb/>
     district magistrates, and then you will find, 14 
     <lb/>
     assistant magistrates. As these seven district 
     <lb/>
     magistracies would become county courts, or 
     <lb/>
     district courts, and be paid for by the federal 
     <lb/>
     government, Newfoundland would then have to 
     <lb/>
     take care of the 14 assistant magistrates. So here 
     <lb/>
     in this table of mine, "14 asst. magistrates — 
     <lb/>
     $38,374 a year, three shorthand typists...".... The 
     <lb/>
     penitentiary is the $69,533 that we are presently 
     <lb/>
     spending, but the difference between $69,500 
     <lb/>
     and $34,500 is accounted for by the fact that the 
     <lb/>
     cost of operating the penitentiary would be 
     <lb/>
     shared by both governments, which would repre<lb break="no"/>sent a saving to the Government of Newfound<lb break="no"/>land. "Travelling Magistrates — $17,900" ... 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Excuse me, I take it the 14 magis<lb break="no"/>trates are going to do more travelling than the 21 
     <lb/>do now. Is that correct? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, that is not all travelling of 
     <lb/>
     magistrates.... The total vote is $22,900, and I 
     <lb/>
     have reduced it to $17,900, because seven of 
     <lb/>
     these magistrates would become county court 
     <lb/>
     judges, and they would do less travelling than 
     <lb/>
     assistant magistrates, because they are estab<lb break="no"/>lished mainly in the urban and industrial centers, 
     <lb/>
     whereas the assistant magistrates are stationed 
     <lb/>
     along the coast, and have much more territory to 
     <lb/>
     cover. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> What is B-5 in the estimates? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> B-5 in the estimates? $17,000, 
     <lb/>
     and that is for the travelling of magistrates, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> And isn't your $17,900 the same 
     <lb/>
     thing? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No. It is that whole vote of 
     <lb/>
     $22,900, reduced to $17,900 by the reduction of 
     <lb/>
     $5,000 to account for the travelling costs of coun<lb break="no"/>ty court judges. I have taken the whole vote in the 
     <lb/>
     estimates here and reduced it merely by $5,000.... 
     <lb/>
     "Penitentiary Supplies, etc. — $10,000." That is 
     <lb/>
     reduced from $45,000.... "Court House, 
     <lb/>
     St. John's...$1,053,409". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then next, the Department of Natural Resour<lb break="no"/>ces. This will take a little more explaining, be<lb break="no"/>cause there will be great changes under 
     <lb/>
     confederation in that department.... The total vote 
     <lb/>
     for Agriculture, that is salaries, is $76,942, but 
     <lb/>
     items A-4-8-9-10 would be federal. They would 
     <lb/>
     be for the government experimental farm, which 
     <lb/>
     would become federal, and therefore these 
     <lb/>
     salaries are to be omitted from that vote. There is 
     <lb/>
     a note here on page 4 of my memorandum which 
     <lb/>
     explains that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Division of Land Development, Ranger Ser<lb break="no"/>vice, note 2, explains that. We have, in New<lb break="no"/>foundland, 84 Rangers. Any province gets from 
     <lb/>
     the federal government numbers of Royal 
     <lb/>
     Canadian Mounted Police. The Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada charges $1,000 a year to a province for 
     <lb/>
     each Mounted Policeman, the full cost to the 
     <lb/>
     province. It costs the Government of Canada 
     <lb/>
     much more than that.... We can get 50 of them, 
     <lb/>
     but that does not mean 50 existing RCMP being 
     <lb/>
     brought into Newfoundland from Canada. It 
     <lb/>
     means that 50 of our Rangers can be enlisted in 
     <lb/>
     the RCMP, given their training and stationed in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, and they will cost $50,000. Now 
     <lb/>
     that reduces the number of Rangers from 84 to 
     <lb/>
     34, and the saving is $278 per man on 50 men, 
     <lb/>
     which brings the vote for Rangers down to 
     <lb/>
     $93,540, and you will get the same a little further 
     <lb/>
     down when it comes to supplies, etc., for 
     <lb/>
     Rangers. There is also a reduction there. 
     <lb/>
     "Division of Crown Lands and Surveys — 
     <lb/>
     $l7,090..." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Excuse me, before you go on, have 
     <lb/>
     you an item of expenditure for the training of 
     <lb/>
     these 50 men? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, it would not be a provincial 
     <lb/>
     expenditure, it would be federal. The training of 
     <lb/>
     RCMPs is done by the federal government, 
     <lb/>
     which pays for it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Smallwood, it is not very im<lb break="no"/>portant, but wouldn't it be $1,200 instead of 
     <lb/>
     $1,000 per man? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="964" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0964.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">964</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
           

 <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> My understanding is $1,000, 
     <lb/>
     but I was speaking from memory. It may be 
     <lb/>
    increased to $1,200, I have not heard that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> "...the cost would be $1,200." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, that would make a slight 
     <lb/>
     difference in this particular vote. Instead of 
     <lb/>
    $93,000 it would be something over $100,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     "Division of Crown Lands and Surveys." 
     <lb/>
     Now I have down $17,090, and in the estimates 
     <lb/>
     it is $33,000, and the reason is that items 74, 75 
     <lb/>
     and 76 and 77 would be federal. They would be 
     <lb/>
     employees of the federal government, and paid 
     <lb/>
     for by the federal government, which would 
     <lb/>
     reduce the vote to what it is here, namely 
     <lb/>
    $17,090. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     "Co-operative Division...Division of 
     <lb/>
     Fisheries, $112,442." That takes quite a bit of 
     <lb/>
     explaining, Mr. Chairman. The Division of 
     <lb/>
     Fisheries in the estimates amounts to $926,000, 
     <lb/>
     almost a million dollars, and it is reduced here to 
     <lb/>
     $112,000. Now the reason is this: many expendi<lb break="no"/>tures would be federal and not provincial. The 
     <lb/>
     cost of these services would be paid by the 
     <lb/>
     Department of Fisheries in the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Ranger Division. Now there again a saving is 
     <lb/>
     made in the vote for the Ranger Division. The 
     <lb/>
     total is $92,500. You can see what it is.... That 
     <lb/>
     total vote is for 84 Rangers. You take 50 Rangers 
     <lb/>
     off, because you don't have 50 Rangers, they 
     <lb/>
     become RCMP, and the total comes down to 
     <lb/>
     $37,500 on the province. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> While you are on that point, the 
     <lb/>provinces don't have the RCMP unless they want 
     <lb/>them? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, to begin with you are 
     <lb/>right, they do definitely put a number of RCMP 
     <lb/>into each province to fulfill certain federal police 
     <lb/>functions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> ...But that does not reduce the num<lb break="no"/>ber of Rangers does it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, but over and above the 
     <lb/>number here for federal purposes there would be 
     <lb/>a number for provincial purposes, rented or hired 
     <lb/>by the province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> You have no definite assurance 
     <lb/>that you can get them? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No difficulty at all in getting 
     <lb/>them, Mr. Ilsley assured us of that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Where did you get that assurance? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It is Canadian government 


    
            <cb/>
           

     policy. It is normal policy, there would be noth<lb break="no"/>ing new in it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> There was no assurance that I 
     <lb/>
    knew of that you could get them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It may be that Mr. Higgins has 
     <lb/>
    no knowledge of such assurance. I can't say that. 
     <lb/>I have it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     "Division of Crown Lands and Surveys, 
     <lb/>
     $26,400".... That reduces that vote from the 
     <lb/>
     $120,000 that it now costs us down to $26,400, 
     <lb/>
     because the federal government would carry the 
     <lb/>
     rest. "Expenses of Trade Commissions... ships 
     <lb/>
     built". Now it was said here in the Convention 
     <lb/>
     some days back, I think by Mr. Crosbie, that the 
     <lb/>
     federal government pays a ship building bounty. 
     <lb/>
     I confess I have no knowledge of that, and 
     <lb/>
     whether they do or not I have included here the 
     <lb/>
     full bounty on ships, which is $140,000. 
     <lb/>
     "Labrador operations..." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> Mr. Chairman, as we have only 
     <lb/>
    one stenographer we should have a few minutes 
     <lb/>recess. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, well as this is nearly com<lb break="no"/>pleted I thought we might finish. "Encourage<lb break="no"/>ment of Agriculture".... The total expenditure for 
     <lb/>the Department of Natural Resources would be 
     <lb/>$1,279,500. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Short recess]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, when we had to 
     <lb/>
     recess we had just finished the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Natural Resources. On the bottom of that same 
     <lb/>
     page is the Board of Liquor Control, $134,100, 
     <lb/>
     and then we have only two departments left, the 
     <lb/>
     Department of Public Works and the Department 
     <lb/>
     of Public Health and Welfare. "Department of 
     <lb/>
     Public Works, Administrative... Building 
     <lb/>
     Division". Note 1 at the bottom of the page 
     <lb/>
     attributes one quarter to be paid by the other 
     <lb/>
     government.... Public Buildings ... one third of 
     <lb/>
     the total vote to the federal government, leaving 
     <lb/>
     two thirds to be met by the provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ment. "Roads $1,270,000.... Printing, Stationery, 
     <lb/>
     etc." ... one third of the vote to the federal govern<lb break="no"/>ment, leaving $165,000 to the provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ment.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Department of Public Health and Welfare, 
     <lb/>
     "General Hospital, $295,446." Now you will 
     <lb/>
     notice in the estimate with regard to the General 
     <lb/>
     Hospital that they have deducted an amount of 
     <lb/>
     $50,000 from the vote for staff that they have not 
     <lb/>
     got, but I have included that $50,000, and I have 
   

            <pb n="965" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0965.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">965</fw>
        

     kept the whole vote for the General Hospital to 
     <lb/>
     the top, namely $295,000.... Sanatorium, the 
     <lb/>
     same thing applies there, in the estimates the 
     <lb/>
     government has taken off $65,928 for a staff that 
     <lb/>
     they have not got, but I have kept that in.... Public 
     <lb/>
     Health Laboratory, $32,634, and I ought to ex<lb break="no"/>plain that the scientific laboratory down in Mag<lb break="no"/>gotty Cove is paid for by two departments of the 
     <lb/>
     government, one is the Department of Public 
     <lb/>
     Health and Welfare. They spend $32,000 to 
     <lb/>
     maintain that laboratory, that is the personnel 
     <lb/>
     down there who work in the department, and the 
     <lb/>
     remainder is operated by the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Natural Resources, and as such that part of it 
     <lb/>
     would be federal, and so it was not included in 
     <lb/>
     the Department of Natural Resources, this 
     <lb/>
     amount is included under Health and Welfare.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Anti-TB service, $47,749. Well, the same 
     <lb/>
     thing applies there as in the General Hospital and 
     <lb/>
     the Sanatorium. The government, in their present 
     <lb/>
     estimate, have deducted $17,000 from the 
     <lb/>
     amount for the anti-TB service for help that they 
     <lb/>
     have not got, but I have included the full amount, 
     <lb/>
     making it $47,749.... "Assistance to Indigent Per<lb break="no"/>sons, $750,000." Now there is a note at the bot<lb break="no"/>tom. That $750,000 is one quarter less than is 
     <lb/>
     voted in the estimates of the government for the 
     <lb/>
     present year, and that is deducted because of the 
     <lb/>
     fact that when family allowances and old age 
     <lb/>
     pensions are paid to so many, many thousands of 
     <lb/>
     people in Newfoundland it is a fair assumption 
     <lb/>
     that the vote for indigent persons will not be the 
     <lb/>
     $1 million that is in the estimates this year, but 
     <lb/>
     $250,000 less than that; and I think I am being 
     <lb/>
     very, very conservative when I lop off only 
     <lb/>
     $250,000, in view of the fact that something like 
     <lb/>
     $11-12 million will be paid over to the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland people by the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada in family allowances and old age pen<lb break="no"/>sions... "Allowances to Widows", There again, I 
     <lb/>
     think we would be justified in lopping off some, 
     <lb/>
     in view of the many millions of dollars that will 
     <lb/>
     be spent by the Government of Canada in social 
     <lb/>
     welfare here in Newfoundland, but I have not 
     <lb/>
     lopped off any. "Old Age Pensions." The es<lb break="no"/>timate is 10,000 old age pensioners who would 
     <lb/>
     receive $30 a month. Of that amount $7.50 a 
     <lb/>
     month would be paid by the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     government, and $22.50 a month by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada. Well, 10,000 old age pensioners 
     <lb/>
     at the age of 70 and over at $7.50 a month by the 
 

            <cb/>
    

     Government of Newfoundland would be 
     <lb/>
     $900,000. Now, we have in Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     something over 12,000 persons of 70 and over 
     <lb/>
     who, from the standpoint of age at least, would 
     <lb/>
     be eligible for the pension, but I estimate that 
     <lb/>
     2,000 of the 12,000 would probably not be 
     <lb/>
     eligible because they would not meet the other 
     <lb/>
     tests, namely their income, so I put it at 10,000 
     <lb/>
     who would be fully eligible for old age pensions, 
     <lb/>
     and 10,000 of them at $7.50 a month from the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Newfoundland would be 
     <lb/>
     $900,000. "Hospital and other grants." There is a 
     <lb/>
     note 6 in addition. It refers to orphanage grants, 
     <lb/>
     $46,200. That's the full vote that the government 
     <lb/>
     now gives, but it is to be noted that in addition to 
     <lb/>
     that $46,000 a year that our government gives 
     <lb/>
     orphanages, that the orphans themselves would 
     <lb/>
     receive family allowances. "Maintenance and 
     <lb/>
     Equipment of Hospitals and Institutions, 
     <lb/>
     $859,000." It is now something over $1 million 
     <lb/>
     that is voted, but I have lopped off an amount 
     <lb/>
     from that, one third in fact, on account of the 
     <lb/>
     savings and economies that would result from 
     <lb/>
     confederation ..... "Ambulance and Transport 
     <lb/>
     Service...Genera1 Public Health", and from that, 
     <lb/>
     sir, I have deducted, according to note 8, 
     <lb/>
     $100,000 from L-13. The whole vote for that is 
     <lb/>
     $465,000 the government has voted this year, and 
     <lb/>
     from that I deducted $100,000, making the vote 
     <lb/>
     therefore $365,500, and the total vote according 
     <lb/>
     to this estimate, for the Department of Public 
     <lb/>
     Health and Welfare per year is $5,214,868. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And so, sir, we come to the Recapitulation. 
     <lb/>
     "Public Expenditures of the Government of New<lb break="no"/>foundland if we become a Province of Canada.... 
     <lb/>
     Grand Total, $14,188,775 a year." That is the 
     <lb/>
     expenditure of the provincial government of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland per year — $14,188,000. But if 
     <lb/>
     we were a province we would have our own 
     <lb/>
     House of Assembly, and these members of the 
     <lb/>
     House of Assembly, whatever number they 
     <lb/>
     might be.... I estimate $200,000 a year to cover 
     <lb/>
     the cost of the legislature of the Province of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland and then I add on to all that 
     <lb/>
     $750,000 to cover increased expenditure by the 
     <lb/>
     government, and to cover new services which we 
     <lb/>
     have not got yet, but which we are going to have, 
     <lb/>
     and which will cost so much a year to operate. I 
     <lb/>
     have added $750,000 for that for the first four 
     <lb/>
     years of union, and the grand total, then, is 
     <lb/>
     $15,138,000 as the amount that the provincial 
 

            <pb n="966" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0966.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">966</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
        

     government would spend each year — 
     <lb/>
     $15,138,000 a year to cover all expenses of the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Newfoundland each year for the 
     <lb/>
     first four years of confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The figures given are an estimate.... On the 
     <lb/>
     average to spend $15,138,000 a year for the first 
     <lb/>
     four years.... Now we come to the second four 
     <lb/>
     years. We start off with $15,138,000, and I add 
     <lb/>
     to that another $500,000 a year to cover increased 
     <lb/>
     expenditure and new services, so that on existing 
     <lb/>
     ordinary expenditures of the government, on 
     <lb/>
     things that would be provincial if we became a 
     <lb/>
     province, I have added for the eight years 
     <lb/>
     $1,258,000, added on per year for the first eight 
     <lb/>
     years of union, $1.25 million to cover the grow<lb break="no"/>ing public services of the country which will call, 
     <lb/>
     of course, for additional expenditures each year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     So that's the first half of the story, and the 
     <lb/>
     longest part I may say. The government of the 
     <lb/>
     Province of Newfoundland would spend, that is 
     <lb/>
     the money it's got to get to break even, for the 
     <lb/>
     first four years of union, average $15,138,000 a 
     <lb/>
     year, and for the second four years of union it has 
     <lb/>
     to get $15,600,000 a year, and if it does not get 
     <lb/>
     it, it cannot balance its budget, it cannot break 
     <lb/>
     even.... I don't need to remind you of why I have 
     <lb/>
     taken eight years, because within eight years of 
     <lb/>
     union there is to be a complete reassessment, a 
     <lb/>
     financial review, to see if the subsidies are, or are 
     <lb/>
     not, enough to enable Newfoundland to pay her 
     <lb/>
     own way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     So now we come to the revenue side, to see if 
     <lb/>
     it is possible and practicable to get that much 
     <lb/>
     money to meet the expenditures of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I am sorry that I have not been able to 
     <lb/>
     get this mimeographed. I promise you it will be 
     <lb/>
     on the table by tomorrow afternoon, and every 
     <lb/>
     member will be able to study it at his leisure, but 
     <lb/>
     I completed typing it only about half past two this 
     <lb/>
     afternoon, after being working on it since 
     <lb/>
     Thursday last week, and it is only since lunch 
     <lb/>
     today that I got it completed. Now, if you will 
     <lb/>
     turn to your estimates on the revenue side, in the 
     <lb/>
     beginning of the book. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Excuse me, is this revenue? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Couldn't we wait until we get the 
     <lb/>
     mimeographed copy? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, we have to get so much 
     <lb/>
     done and this will only take a short time... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> We want that before us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It's so short that you can write 
     <lb/>
     it down as I read it. It's so short. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> All right, you go slowly will you? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> You take it down, and I 
     <lb/>
     promise you tomorrow you will have it on your 
     <lb/>
     desks. Now, if you will turn to page 6 of the 
     <lb/>
     estimates, you will find that the present year our 
     <lb/>
     present government has estimated, under the 
     <lb/>
     Department of Finance, that they will take in a 
     <lb/>
     revenue of over $400,000. I estimate only 
     <lb/>
     $71,600 if we become a province. These items 
     <lb/>
     are: no. 1, inland revenue stamps $60,000, but I 
     <lb/>
     have only estimated $50,000, because some of 
     <lb/>
     that would be federal. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> All of it would be federal. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, I beg your pardon, I hap<lb break="no"/>pen to know what I am talking of, time will tell 
     <lb/>
     that.... It is, nearly all of it, on legal documents. 
     <lb/>
     Nearly all of it. Now some of these legal docu<lb break="no"/>ments would be federal, but most of them would 
     <lb/>
     be provincial in character. Therefore I estimate 
     <lb/>
     that $50,000 of the $60,000 would come to the 
     <lb/>
     province, and then also the $l4,000 for item no. 2 
     <lb/>
     would remain, and that gives you a total of 
     <lb/>
     $71,600 to the province from the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Finance.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> What about the interest on our ex<lb break="no"/>chequer balance? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I have that covered, but not 
     <lb/>
     under this heading; you will find it further down. 
     <lb/>
     Major Cashin will see the reason for that when 
     <lb/>
     we come to it. Then you go on to the Department 
     <lb/>
     of Posts and Telegraphs, on page 8, and from that 
     <lb/>
     department the only revenue we would get, as a 
     <lb/>
     province, would be 10 and 11, tax on cablegrams 
     <lb/>
     and code messages, and tax on land cables and 
     <lb/>
     wireless stations, $15,000 and $72,000. All the 
     <lb/>
     rest would be federal. If it were collected it would 
     <lb/>
     be by the federal government, but the provincial 
     <lb/>
     government would collect $87,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> The provincial government only 
     <lb/>
     gets nos. 10 and 11? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That's right, a total of $87,000. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> There's another tax. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> So there might be, but I am 
     <lb/>
     talking now of provincial government revenue. 
     <lb/>
     Department of the Assessor, we would get 
     <lb/>
     $20,000 out of $10.5 million, and the items would 
     <lb/>
     be nos. 4, 5 and 6, namely $1,500, and $17,000 
     <lb/>
     and $1,500; right, that is $20,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> It's $18,500 if I know how to add. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="967" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0967.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">967</fw>
           

 <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, it's $20,000 I make it. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Three amounts? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, three amounts, $17,000 
     <lb/>
     and $1,500 and $1,500, isn't that $20,000? Yes. 
     <lb/>
     Now go on to the Department of Home Affairs, 
     <lb/>
     and I make it $25,000, and that comes all from 
     <lb/>
     one item, number 6. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> You can't include that in the 
     <lb/>
     revenue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Can't you? I think the govern<lb break="no"/>ment can classify its income in any way it cares 
     <lb/>
     to do so. There is no law on that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> You can pass a law on anything. 
     <lb/>
     You can pass a law to legalise murder. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There is no law in existence 
     <lb/>
     now. In fact there is a law which says that all 
     <lb/>
     revenue of the government must go into the CRF 
     <lb/>
     — Consolidated Revenue Fund. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You are not justified in inter<lb break="no"/>rupting at this point at all. He is endeavouring to 
     <lb/>
     present his estimate of probable revenue. How<lb break="no"/>ever incorrect in your judgement he may be, I 
     <lb/>
     think it is in the interests of all concerned that he 
     <lb/>
     should continue, and then, of course, you may 
     <lb/>
     address yourselves on it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I would like to 
     <lb/>
     say that it is the law of England, Canada, and 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, and most countries in the world, 
     <lb/>
     that every last dollar and every last cent that that 
     <lb/>
     government collects... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I rise to a point of order. Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin was not allowed to press that point, and 
     <lb/>
     now Mr. Smallwood is going ahead and stressing 
     <lb/>
     that point. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That is not a point of order at all. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood is endeavouring to present cer<lb break="no"/>tain figures and explain them, and, until he 
     <lb/>
     finishes his explanation, I don't think it is right or 
     <lb/>
     proper to interrupt him at all. It is not a question 
     <lb/>
     which lends itself to a point of privilege. As a 
     <lb/>
     matter of fact, if we are going to deal with ques<lb break="no"/>tions of privileges I hold that he has a right to go 
     <lb/>
     on without interruption. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Oh, go on! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> What I am saying is, that it is 
     <lb/>
     the law of the land that every dollar and every 
     <lb/>
     cent that the government receives, let it be con<lb break="no"/>science money, let somebody die and leave them 
     <lb/>
     money, let it be taxation, a loan or interest 
     <lb/>
     received back on loans it made, whatever money 
     <lb/>
     the government receives must go into the Con<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
       
solidated Revenue Fund. When you put it into 
     <lb/>
     Consolidated Revenue Fund it is your decision as 
     <lb/>
     a government what particular sub-heading you 
     <lb/>
     will place it under. The sub-heading that the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Newfoundland has placed it 
     <lb/>
     under is the Department of Home Affairs, namely 
     <lb/>
     "Repayment of Loans", that is from the Housing 
     <lb/>
     Association, etc., and so I have done the same 
     <lb/>
     thing, and I am prepared to argue that with 
     <lb/>
     anyone on the face of this earth, that it is proper 
     <lb/>
     to include that amount as revenue of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, and the amount is $125,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Department of Education, I have taken the 
     <lb/>
     complete amount, $66,800. Department of Jus<lb break="no"/>tice, $30,000, that is all for one item, fines and 
     <lb/>
     forfeitures. The Department of Natural Resour<lb break="no"/>ces is at page 11, the first thing is Fisheries, and 
     <lb/>
     we get none of that. We skip that, that's federal. 
     <lb/>
     They pay the costs of running it, and they get 
     <lb/>
     whatever little bit of revenue comes in against it. 
     <lb/>
     Forestry. The total vote is found in item 7, Timber 
     <lb/>
     Lease Rentals, $82,000; no. 8, Timber and Saw<lb break="no"/>mill Royalties, $20,000; no. 9, Sawmill Licenses, 
     <lb/>
     $6,000; no. 10, Inland Fishery and Game Licen<lb break="no"/>ses, Fines, etc. $40,000; and no. 11, Water<lb break="no"/>power Rentals, $3,000. I have added to that 
     <lb/>
     $20,000 a year on the average for the first four 
     <lb/>
     years of union, because that is our public domain, 
     <lb/>
     timber, water-power and the like. It is necessarily 
     <lb/>
     from public domain that most provinces get a 
     <lb/>
     large part, if not most, of their revenue, and I hold 
     <lb/>
     that that should be steadily increased, not exor<lb break="no"/>bitantly, not oppressively, but that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Newfoundland should aim as a deliberate 
     <lb/>
     policy to get more and more revenue out of the 
     <lb/>
     private exploitation of the natural resources of 
     <lb/>
     our country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Under the heading of Agriculture the only 
     <lb/>
     item is $200, and that's agricultural grants and 
     <lb/>
     leased rentals under the heading of Miscel<lb break="no"/>laneous, $7,500, because most of that Miscel<lb break="no"/>laneous is federal. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Dog licenses. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, dog licenses, $2,500, and 
     <lb/> other items making up a total of $7,500. So that 
     <lb/>from the Department of Natural Resources the 
     <lb/>combined revenue to the government is 
     <lb/>$180,500. Have you got that down?.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Would you itemise them again? 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Forestry, $151,000; Agricul<lb break="no"/>ture, $2,000; and Miscellaneous, $7,500, and the 


            <pb n="968" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0968.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">968</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
       

     total for that department's revenue is $180,500. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now we come to the Department of Public 
     <lb/>
     Works, which is page 12 in the estimates. No. 1, 
     <lb/>
     Revenue, they now estimate $35,000, but that is 
     <lb/>
     for the supply of printing and office equipment, 
     <lb/>
     etc., to all departments of the government, but as 
     <lb/>
     some of these departments would not be provin<lb break="no"/>cial but would be federal, naturally our provincial 
     <lb/>
     Department of Public Works would not supply 
     <lb/>
     them, or get revenue less than it now gets because 
     <lb/>
     there would be fewer departments, so I have cut 
     <lb/>
     that in three, and made it $11,900. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     No. 2, Licenses for motor vehicles, drivers 
     <lb/>
     licenses, etc., $325,000; that calls for a little 
     <lb/>
     explanation. That is licenses for motor vehicles, 
     <lb/>cars, trucks, bikes and buses, drivers' licenses 
     <lb/>etc. In 1945-46 the actual amount of revenue that 
     <lb/>the government got under those headings was 
     <lb/>$182,000, but this year they have estimated for 
     <lb/>$200,000, and they have actually taken in over 
     <lb/>$260,000 already.... The revenue from motor 
     <lb/>licenses and drivers' licenses is shooting up as 
     <lb/>more roads are built and more motor cars and 
     <lb/>trucks and buses are coming into use. More 
     <lb/>people are driving, more licenses are paid, and 
     <lb/>revenue is going up very rapidly under that head<lb break="no"/>ing, and so, for the first four years of union, I have 
     <lb/>put it down at an average of $325,000 a year from 
     <lb/>motor vehicular and drivers' licenses. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Item no. 3 is examination fees for drivers' 
     <lb/>
     licenses. I have left it at $300. I might have put it 
     <lb/>
     up a bit, but I did not. Item no. 4 is payments from 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion Steel and Coal Corporation for 
     <lb/>
     roads on Bell Island, that's $4,000, and I have left 
     <lb/>
     it at $4,000. Number 8 is fees for inspection of 
     <lb/>
     boilers and machinery. I have increased that only 
     <lb/>
     $500 for the four years. Number 9 is rentals of 
     <lb/>
     mineral leases, royalties, etc., $90,000, and if I 
     <lb/>
     had anything to do with the Government of New<lb break="no"/>foundland I guarantee you now that by the time 
     <lb/>
     we had spent four years in union that would be 
     <lb/>
     easily a lot more than $90,000, but I am leaving 
     <lb/>
     the figure that the government gives. It is scan<lb break="no"/>dalous and it is disgraceful that it is only $90,000. 
     <lb/>
     Number 10, mining prospectors' licenses, $500. 
     <lb/>
     The grand total revenue for the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Public Works is $439,800. Has everyone got that 
     <lb/>
     down? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then we come to the Department of Public 
     <lb/>
     Health and Welfare, on page 13 of the estimates, 
     <lb/>
     and I have taken the whole revenue, $327,500, 


            <cb/>
        

     with the exception of one item, no. 6, the receipts 
     <lb/>
     from the merchant navy hospital, $15,000, which 
     <lb/>
     the province would not get. That would go to the 
     <lb/>
     federal government ... so the amount is $312,500. 
     <lb/>
     The Board of Liquor Control I have got down at 
     <lb/>
     $1 million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now the next item is gasoline tax. I don't 
     <lb/>
     know if the House is familiar with it, but some 
     <lb/>
     amazing things are happening in this country in 
     <lb/>
     connection with gasoline. I suppose it is due to 
     <lb/>
     the fact that more roads are being built, and that 
     <lb/>
     roads are being made better, but the income of 
     <lb/>
     the government from gasoline is shooting sky 
     <lb/>
     high. I will give you an example. The revenue 
     <lb/>
     from gasoline at the present time is got from 
     <lb/>
     customs duty. They collect one cent a gallon on 
     <lb/>
     fishermen's gas, 14 cents a gallon on ordinary 
     <lb/>
     gasoline off the Avalon Peninsula, and l6 cents 
     <lb/>
     a gallon on the Avalon Peninsula. and the total 
     <lb/>
     amount in 1941-42 was $600,000. Last year, it 
     <lb/>
     was getting up towards $l million. The exact 
     <lb/>
     amount was $922,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> On gasoline alone? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, on gasoline alone, not 
     <lb/>
     counting kerosene, or fuel oil and bunker oil or 
     <lb/>
     anything of that character, and it is not counting 
     <lb/>
     gasoline imported into Gander for use by trans<lb break="no"/>atlantic or any other aircraft. That is revenue 
     <lb/>
     collected in that one year just on gasoline, and so 
     <lb/>
     I have put what I claim to be a most modest 
     <lb/>
     figure.... Of course under confederation we 
     <lb/>
     would not collect any customs duties on gasoline, 
     <lb/>
     but we would substitute a gasoline tax, a direct 
     <lb/>
     gasoline tax. Now in my estimate I did not in<lb break="no"/>clude any tax whatever on fishermen's gasoline, 
     <lb/>
     or what is commonly known as "Acto". I think 
     <lb/>
     that as that gasoline enters directly and basically 
     <lb/>
     into two of the basic industries of the country, that 
     <lb/>
     that gasoline ought not to have any tax what<lb break="no"/>soever so far as customs duty is concerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Is it paying anything now? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, one cent a gallon. I think 
     <lb/>
     that should be completely free of tax by leaving 
     <lb/>
     out fishermen's gas and industrial gas, which is 
     <lb/>
     quite a lot different from the gas we have in this 
     <lb/>
     chamber, which is not very industrious or in<lb break="no"/>dustrial either, but taking ordinary gas used in 
     <lb/>
     motor cars, trucks, buses, motor cycles and the 
     <lb/>
     like, the figure for the first four years of union, 
     <lb/>
     $1 million a year revenue from gasoline is, I hold, 
     <lb/>
     a modest and conservative estimate. And the total 


            <pb n="969" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0969.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">969</fw>
        

     is $3,333,200. That is the total revenue by taxa<lb break="no"/>tion that would probably have to be imposed on 
     <lb/>
     the people of Newfoundland each year by the 
     <lb/>
     provincial government for the first four years of 
     <lb/>
     confederation. Now just hold that figure in your 
     <lb/>
     minds, gentlemen — $3,333,000 in taxes. 
     <lb/>
     Remember the word "taxes", revenue from taxa<lb break="no"/>tion put on the people of Newfoundland by the 
     <lb/>
     provincial government each year for the first four 
     <lb/>
     years of union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now we can get along and sort of draw a 
     <lb/>
     balance sheet, and I want to make it very clear 
     <lb/>
     that in the first place I am dealing with the first 
     <lb/>
     four years of union now, until I tell you, and I 
     <lb/>
     want to make it clear that these figures are 
     <lb/>
     average. I cannot see, not having the gift of 
     <lb/>
     second sight, exactly how much revenue the 
     <lb/>
     provincial government would take in in the first 
     <lb/>
     year, or the second or the third or the fourth, I can 
     <lb/>
     only estimate an average. We start off. If you 
     <lb/>
     would like to draw a balance sheet, gentlemen, 
     <lb/>
     take paper and write down: expenditure — 
     <lb/>
     $15,138,775. Now where are we going to get 
     <lb/>
     that? Now make another column — revenue — 
     <lb/>
     from taxation on our Newfoundland people, put 
     <lb/>
     on by the provincial government, $3,333,200. 
     <lb/>
     That's taxation we are now collecting. That's 
     <lb/>
     under taxes which we already have and which we 
     <lb/>
     will have still if we become a province. They will 
     <lb/>
     still be Newfoundland taxes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> The federal government collects 
     <lb/>
     taxes as well? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Of course, but today we are not 
     <lb/>
     dealing with federal government revenue, but 
     <lb/>
     only provincial. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now surplus — $600,000. That is assuming 
     <lb/>
     that we take our entire surplus, our cash surplus, 
     <lb/>
     taking it at $28 million, converting all of it to 
     <lb/>
     dollars and putting it on deposit with the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada at 2 5/8% interest, which they 
     <lb/>
     offer to do. $28 million accumulated cash surplus 
     <lb/>
     ... assuming that the provincial government drew 
     <lb/>
     out of that each year an average of $3 million for 
     <lb/>
     the purposes of the province. That would leave 
     <lb/>
     so much in the fund each year drawing interest at 
     <lb/>
     2 5/8 per cent. I have worked out the table if you 
     <lb/>
     would like to hear it.... I have called it $600,000. 
     <lb/>
     That's for the first four years of union. $600,000 
     <lb/>
     interest on our surplus at 2 5/8 percent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now the third item, refunds, $254,950. I will 
  

            <cb/>
            

     explain what that is. The Government of Canada 
     <lb/>
     will pay to Newfoundland $666,000 on account 
     <lb/>
     of Gander. The House will remember that the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland government is under contract to 
     <lb/>
     pay the Canadian government $1 million for their 
     <lb/>
     share in Gander. It cost $25 million, and we 
     <lb/>
     agreed to pay $1 million. We have paid $333,000, 
     <lb/>
     and we have to pay another $333,000 this year, 
     <lb/>
     so that is $666,000 which the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada will pay back to the province. Now you 
     <lb/>
     will also remember that the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada has agreed to pay back the cost of the two 
     <lb/>
     boats<ref target="#fn_02">[1]</ref> that are being built in Scotland now, not 
     <lb/>
     including the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Cabot Strait</hi>, and that's a total of 
     <lb/>
     $1,373,000 that these boats are costing us that the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada is going to pay back in 
     <lb/>
     cash. Now the two amounts put together, for 
     <lb/>
     Gander and for those two boats, is $2,039,600. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> What is that for, two boats you 
     <lb/>mean? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Would that be every year for four 
     <lb/>
     years? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, divide that by eight years 
     <lb/>
     and it comes to $254,950, which is what I have 
     <lb/>
     down as refunds. I could not think of a better 
     <lb/>
     name so I called it "Finance". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Frenzied finance! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, call it what you like. 
     <lb/>
     Major Cashin will have lots of opportunities to 
     <lb/>
     put all kinds of names on it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> You mean $254,950 from Gander 
     <lb/>
     and the boats, is that what you mean? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Divided by the first eight years 
     <lb/>
     of union, so that is per year $254,950. Now the 
     <lb/>
     Tax Rental Agreement, $6,820,000. Have you 
     <lb/>
     got that down? Now put down another item of 
     <lb/>
     $50,000, and I hardly know what to call it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> That's pretty dumb. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I may be pretty dumb, I have 
     <lb/>
     that reputation, but I was born that way: the name 
     <lb/>
     I have called it is "Gas and Electricity", and the 
     <lb/>
     position is this: under the Tax Rental Agreement 
     <lb/>
     the federal government, in addition to the pay<lb break="no"/>ments it makes, pays back to the province half of 
     <lb/>
     the corporation tax that the federal government 
     <lb/>
     collects from companies in Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     whose main business is the sale of electricity, gas 
     <lb/>
     or steam. Now there is no company that I know 
     <lb/>
     of in Newfoundland selling steam, but there are 


<note xml:id="fn_02">[1] The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bar Haven</hi> and the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Springdale</hi>, which were sister ships.</note> 

            <pb n="970" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0970.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">970</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
   

     companies selling electricity and gas... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> The Convention is selling steam. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, we are selling gas and 
     <lb/>steam both, but I am afraid we are not selling it, 
     <lb/>we are giving it away. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> And getting $15 a day for distribu<lb break="no"/>tion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I think, Major Cashin, if you 
     <lb/>
     don't mind you might indulge yourself less... 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It may be a joke to Major 
     <lb/>Cashin, but it is not a joke to many people in this 
     <lb/>country, which I think he will find before he is 
     <lb/>many years older. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Never mind that now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, sir, he invited that. I put 
     <lb/>
     that down as $50,000 a year, being half the cor<lb break="no"/>poration tax that the Government of Canada 
     <lb/>
     would collect from all companies in New<lb break="no"/>foundland whose main business is the sale to the 
     <lb/>
     public of electricity or gas. Now the transition 
     <lb/>
     grant is $2,843,750. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> That's the average you mean? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That's right. That's the transi<lb break="no"/>tion grant. That is got in this way: in the first eight 
     <lb/>
     years of union the Government of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     would receive from the Government of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     under that one heading $22,750,000. Divide that 
     <lb/>
     by eight, and it is an average per year of 
     <lb/>
     $2,843,746. Now, add these up, and it will come 
     <lb/>
     to $13,901,900. Now that would be, for the first 
     <lb/>
     four years of union, the revenue of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Newfoundland as a province from all 
     <lb/>
     sources, under all headings ... which leaves the 
     <lb/>
     provincial government short of balancing its 
     <lb/>
     budget, short $1,236,875. That amount, if it were 
     <lb/>
     got by the provincial government, would enable 
     <lb/>
     it, in the first four years of union, to balance its 
     <lb/>
     budget and break even; and that amount has got 
     <lb/>
     to be got, and that is the amount in fact of new 
     <lb/>
     taxation that would have to be placed on the 
     <lb/>
     people of the province, and I say "new", not 
     <lb/>
     additional. I do not say additional taxation, I say 
     <lb/>
     new taxes. $1,236,875 and you would balance 
     <lb/>
     your budget for those four years, and in doing so 
     <lb/>
     the total picture would be this: the total provincial 
     <lb/>
     taxation on the Newfoundland people: 
     <lb/>
     $4,570,075; the total non-tax revenue, total 
     <lb/>
     revenue to the provincial government not from 
     <lb/>
     taxes: $10,568,700; and the two together, added 
     <lb/>
     up is $15,138,775. That is the first four years of 
     <lb/>
     union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> If I might interupt for a moment, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood has given us a lot of information 
     <lb/>
     in connection with these figures, and there is no 
     <lb/>
     record, except the reporter here of course, and the 
     <lb/>
     only thing we have got to look at or read is the 
     <lb/>
     expenditures and revenue. There is no explana<lb break="no"/>tion on it at all. I take it he should have a set 
     <lb/>
     speech, and I think every member should have a 
     <lb/>
     copy of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, I have no set speech. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Well it's no good. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> These figures of revenue are in 
     <lb/>
     great detail, and you will receive it tomorrow on 
     <lb/>
     your desks in mimeographed form in very con<lb break="no"/>siderable detail. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, finally, I come to the second four years 
     <lb/>
     of union, and again the figures are the average 
     <lb/>
     each year for the four years. Expenditure 
     <lb/>
     $15,138,775. Now add to that expenditure, to 
     <lb/>
     cover new services and increased expenditure, 
     <lb/>
     another $500,000, and your grand total expendi<lb break="no"/>ture for the second four years, per year, is 
     <lb/>
     $15,638,775. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Now you are budgeting for four 
     <lb/>
     years from now are you? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The second four years, average 
     <lb/>
     per year. It is average per year remember. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> For eight years? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> For eight years. Only I am not 
     <lb/>
     budgeting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> He is on the fifth of the eight 
     <lb/>
     years, the second four year period. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The second four years of con<lb break="no"/>federation, so you start off needing to raise each 
     <lb/>
     year for these four years $ 15,638,775. Where are 
     <lb/>
     you going to get it? Well put down revenue, and 
     <lb/>
     under the heading of revenue put down taxation, 
     <lb/>
     $4,570,075. Now put down additional taxation, 
     <lb/>
     that is not additional taxation, but additional 
     <lb/>
     yield, additional revenue from existing taxes. 
     <lb/>
     Forestry, $200,000. Motor licenses and vehicular 
     <lb/>
     licenses, and drivers' licenses and the like, an 
     <lb/>
     additional $150,000. Liquor, additional, 
     <lb/>
     $250,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> What would that be, another 
     <lb/>
     $250,000? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That's right. Gasoline tax addi<lb break="no"/>tional, $250,000. Now, so far as motor licenses 
     <lb/>
     are concerned, that $150,000 and gasoline tax, 
     <lb/>
     that extra $250,000, and the $400,000 per year 
     <lb/>
     extra revenue from roads in the second four years 


            <pb n="971" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0971.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">971</fw>
        

     of union, by which time we should have in New<lb break="no"/>foundland a lot more miles of road than we have 
     <lb/>
     at the present time and therefore a lot more cars, 
     <lb/>
     buses, trucks, and a lot more drivers and a lot 
     <lb/>
     more gas consumed, and if we should have a 
     <lb/>
     tourist trade a very great increase under these 
     <lb/>
     headings, but I am putting them down at what I 
     <lb/>
     consider to be modest and conservative in<lb break="no"/>creases. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> May I interrupt you there, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood? You say in the second four years we 
     <lb/>
     will have much more roads than we have now... 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes, we have a road building 
     <lb/>program now. All these deal with ordinary expen<lb break="no"/>diture. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> But you have cut out... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, I have not cut out. Don't 
     <lb/>
     forget I have also pictured for you $3 million a 
     <lb/>
     year being withdrawn from accumulated surplus. 
     <lb/>
     Some of that will be spent on roads no doubt. 
     <lb/>
     However, to go on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> That would be reconstruction 
     <lb/>
     wouldn't it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That would be capital expendi<lb break="no"/>ture, or extraordinary expenditure, or reconstruc<lb break="no"/>tion. It would not be ordinary, but when a 
     <lb/>
     government sets out to build new roads you can't 
     <lb/>
     call that ordinary expenditure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> But that's an ordinary budget. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That's right, any extraordinary 
     <lb/>
     account, etc., is not in this. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Well, you have taken some from the 
     <lb/>
     surplus to build roads. What do you call that? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No, I have not taken it for any 
     <lb/>purpose. If we put $28 million on deposit I have 
     <lb/>imagined that we draw out $3 million a year. I 
     <lb/>have not said a word about what we would spend 
 

            <cb/>
          

     it on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> That, as I see it, is to balance your 
     <lb/>
     ordinary budget isn't it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> To draw the interest, not to 
     <lb/>
     draw capital account from your deposit. I have 
     <lb/>
     not said a word about what that $3 million a year 
     <lb/>
     would be drawn for, obviously for reconstruction 
     <lb/>
     and capital expenditure which does not appear in 
     <lb/>
     this at all. The total then in taxation on the people 
     <lb/>
     is $5,420,075. Now that is the total of these items 
     <lb/>
     I have just read.<ref target="#fn_03">*</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> $625 out? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Now just put this down please: 
     <lb/>
     total provincial taxation, revenue from taxation: 
     <lb/>
     $5,420,075; total revenue from non-tax sources: 
     <lb/>
     $10,218,075; and add that up. I see I have not 
     <lb/>
     added it. It is a total of $15,638,150. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, I just have one more observation to 
     <lb/>
     make. It is this: if, and I say "if," these estimates 
     <lb/>
     are reasonably correct, reasonably realistic, it 
     <lb/>
     would mean that in the first four years of union 
     <lb/>
     — no, I have got to go a step further — if these 
     <lb/>
     figures are reasonably correct and if the federal 
     <lb/>
     government's figures of their revenue are 
     <lb/>
     reasonably correct $20 million that they would 
     <lb/>
     collect from us, and $4.5 million that the provin<lb break="no"/>cial government would collect from us, would 
     <lb/>
     give us a total of $24.5 million for the first four 
     <lb/>
     years of union — per year that is — $24.5 million 
     <lb/>
     grand total taxation on the Newfoundland people, 
     <lb/>
     put on by the federal government and the provin<lb break="no"/>cial government. That would be a per head taxa<lb break="no"/>tion of $75 on the average. It does not mean that 
     <lb/>
     every child and every infant and every man and 
     <lb/>
     woman, boy and girl would pay $75, but on the 
     <lb/>
     average it would be a per capita taxation of $75 
     <lb/>
     per head. That is for the first four years of union, 


<note xml:id="fn_03">
     * 
<table>
<row><cell>Taxation</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$ 4,570,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Forestry, additional</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">200,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Motor licenses, additional</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">150,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Liquor, additional</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">250,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Gasoline tax, additional</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">250,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Total provincial taxes on the people</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$ 5,420,075</cell></row>
<row><cell>Now added to that, from your surplus</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">299,375</cell></row>
<row><cell>(See it's come down, it was $600,000 for the first four years, but for
<lb/>the second four years it is $299,375)</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"/></row>
<row><cell>and from refunds, the same amount</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">254,950</cell></row>
<row><cell>and Tax Rental Agreement</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">6,820,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>and Transition Grant</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,843,750</cell></row>
<row><cell>and grand total revenue of the government<lb/>each year for those four years is</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$6,638,150</cell></row>
</table>
</note>
       

            <pb n="972" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0972.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">972</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw>
          

     and for the second four years of union $77 per 
     <lb/>
     head. Now how does that compare? If you go 
     <lb/>
     back to the year 1943-44 in Newfoundland our 
     <lb/>
     per head taxation was $90. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Excuse me, may I interrupt you? 
     <lb/>
     You are not forgetting are you, that the federal 
     <lb/>
     government are still going to collect income tax, 
     <lb/>
     and... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I just put that in at $20 million, 
     <lb/>
     the whole of it at $20 million, prefacing my 
     <lb/>
     remark by saying that if we can assume that the 
     <lb/>
     federal government has estimated $20 million as 
     <lb/>
     the amount that they would collect in taxes, as a 
     <lb/>
     realistic estimate, a fairly correct estimate; if we 
     <lb/>
     can assume that ... for the sake of argument... 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Excuse me, what would be the taxa<lb break="no"/>tion per head then? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I have just told you, assuming 
     <lb/>
     that $20 million that the federal government 
     <lb/>
     would collect from us in the first four years of 
     <lb/>
     union, and the $4.5 million each year that the 
     <lb/>
     provincial government would collect from us, 
     <lb/>
     that is a total of $24.5 million, or $75 per head. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now I said that, but I am glad that Mr. Hollett 
     <lb/>
     made me say it again. To tell you the truth I am 
     <lb/>
     glad I had the second chance to say it. Now then, 
     <lb/>
     compare that with the per head taxation that we 
     <lb/>
     had on us in 1943-44. Our government taxed us 
     <lb/>
     in the year 1943-44, $28.5 million. Our popula<lb break="no"/>tion that year was 317,000 souls, and so our per 
     <lb/>
     capita taxation was $90, in 1943-44. Now take 
     <lb/>
     this present year. They tell us that the taxation put 
     <lb/>
     on us this year by our Newfoundland government 
     <lb/>
     is $40 million.... Our population is 327,000 souls, 
     <lb/>
     that is $122 per head. $122 per head is our taxa<lb break="no"/>tion here in Newfoundland this very year, $122 a 
     <lb/>
     head on the average, remember. We know there 
     <lb/>
     are thousands of people in Newfoundland that are 
     <lb/>
     not paying $122, and there are other thousands 
     <lb/>
     that are paying $2-3,000 a head, but on the 
     <lb/>
     average it is $122 a head today, whereas if my 
     <lb/>
     estimates are anywhere near the truth, and if the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government's estimates of what they 
     <lb/>
     will take from us are anywhere near the truth, the 
     <lb/>
     two of them together would be $75 a head from 
     <lb/>
     the Newfoundland people.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now go on for the next four years of union. In 
     <lb/>
     the next four years, every year, the provincial 
     <lb/>
     government taxation would be $5.5 million and 
     <lb/>
     the federal taxation $20 million, which is $25.5 
     <lb/>
     million altogether that the two governments 
  

            <cb/>
        

     would take from us, which is $77 a head com<lb break="no"/>pared with $122 a head this very year. Now 
     <lb/>
     somebody is going to say to me, and very fairly, 
     <lb/>
     "Aha, your provincial estimate may be some<lb break="no"/>where near the mark, but we don't agree with the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government's estimate of $20 million." 
     <lb/>
     Major Cashin thinks it is 20% out. In other words, 
     <lb/>
     if he were making it he would add another $4 
     <lb/>
     million to it, and make it $24 million that the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government would take from us. All 
     <lb/>
     right, I will go a step further and put $5 million 
     <lb/>
     on it. Then what do you get? I will stick $1 
     <lb/>
     million on provincial taxation and another $5 
     <lb/>
     million on federal taxation, and the per head 
     <lb/>
     taxation then is $93 ... compared with $122 per 
     <lb/>
     head that we are paying this very year, and I agree 
     <lb/>
     that we are paying far too much. $40 million is 
     <lb/>
     far too much to take out of these 327,000 living 
     <lb/>
     souls. Too much. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Well, sir, that's the story. I could go on and on 
     <lb/>
     and on like Tennyson's brook if there was any 
     <lb/>
     end of it. Tomorrow I will have these figures of 
     <lb/>
     revenue mimeographed, and they will be on 
     <lb/>
     every man's desk with the notes that I explained 
     <lb/>
     as I went along to explain these revenues. I hold, 
     <lb/>
     in conclusion, that if we become a province of 
     <lb/>
     Canada with our own provincial government, 
     <lb/>
     with the Government of Canada taxing us and the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Newfoundland taxing us, two 
     <lb/>
     governments taxing us where we only have one 
     <lb/>
     government taxing us now, I hold that the provin<lb break="no"/>cial government will pay its way for the first eight 
     <lb/>
     years of union, and that's all I am required to 
     <lb/>
     show. I don't have to go a day beyond the first 
     <lb/>
     eight years, because, inside of eight years there's 
     <lb/>
     to be a royal commission to assess, or reassess 
     <lb/>
     our financial position to see if we need more 
     <lb/>
     subsidies. I hold that I have shown that for the 
     <lb/>
     first eight years of confederation the provincial 
     <lb/>
     government of Newfoundland can pay its way, 
     <lb/>
     and can do so without putting burdensome taxa<lb break="no"/>tion on our people. I will take that back, all 
     <lb/>
     taxation is burdensome. Further, sir, they can pay 
     <lb/>
     their way without reducing our public services, 
     <lb/>
     but on the other hand, instead of reducing them, 
     <lb/>
     increasing them, giving our people more and 
     <lb/>
     better public services than we have now: that the 
     <lb/>
     provincial government can do that and pay its 
     <lb/>
     way for the first eight years of union, and sir, that 
     <lb/>
     being the case, I think I have shown what I was 
     <lb/>
     expected to show, and there is not much point in 
 

            <pb n="973" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-12-08_Page_0973.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">December 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">973</fw>
         

     my saying another word at this time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> On that point may I ask Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood what is the per capita tax the average 
     <lb/>
     Canadian citizen in Canada is paying today? 
     <lb/>
     Comparing our per capita tax of $122 per head, 
     <lb/>
     what is it in Canada today? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> What I was doing was to com<lb break="no"/>pare our present per capita tax with what would, 
     <lb/>
     or might be, our per capita tax under confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. I was not comparing it with taxation in 
     <lb/>
     Canada now or any other time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> That is a very good comparison to 
     <lb/>
     make. We will be Canadian citizens then, and I 
     <lb/>
     take it we would pay the same taxation as Canada 
     <lb/>
     pays now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> No. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Why? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I think, in view of the fact that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood has not been able to prepare his 
     <lb/>
     estimates of probable provincial revenues it 
     <lb/>
     would be just as well to receive the motion to rise 
     <lb/>
     the committee and ask leave to sit again tomor<lb break="no"/>row, particularly in view of the fact that members 
     <lb/>
     may be hampered in the debate until they receive 
     <lb/>
     this information. It won't be available until 
     <lb/>
     tomorrow. In addition to this, if it were agreeable 
     <lb/>
     to members, I would like to get a motion to 
     <lb/>
     adjourn until tomorrow afternoon, in view of the 
     <lb/>
     fact that there is business of a private nature that 
  

            <cb/>
          

     I would like to take up with members, and if it 
     <lb/>
     suits you and is to your convenience I would like 
     <lb/>
     to hold the meeting this evening at such time as 
     <lb/>
     may be decided upon by the Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I am prepared to move that the com<lb break="no"/>mittee rise, but before doing so, I was wondering 
     <lb/>
     if we could get copies of Mr. Smallwood's 
     <lb/>
     speech when it is done by the stenographer? 
     <lb/>
</p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It will take a week, I understand. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Even so I think we ought to make 
     <lb/>some effort to get that done, because, from my 
     <lb/>point of view, it has some of the most amazing 
     <lb/>statements I have heard in some time. Also I 
     <lb/>would like to ask one question of Mr. Small<lb break="no"/>wood, one single question. In your item of 
     <lb/>Refund, I think you counted on $666,000 from 
     <lb/>the federal government... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> We have only one reporter. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I see. I am sorry. I just point out that 
     <lb/>no payments have been made according to the 
     <lb/>Auditor General's Report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The payment will be this year 
     <lb/>
     we are in now. The first payment was this current 
     <lb/>
     year. That's why we won't see it in the accounts. 
     <lb/>
     I move that the committee rise and report 
     <lb/>
     progress and ask leave to sit again tomorrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee rose and reported progress, and 
     <lb/>
     the Convention adjourned]</hi>  
     <lb/>
            </p>
 

<!-- GL, 2017-08-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
            <!--<p>
     December 9, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Ottawa Delegation 
     <lb/>
     Proposed Arrangements for the Entry of Newfoundland into Confederation 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I have nothing 
     <lb/>
     in particular to say at the moment. The figures I 
     <lb/>
     tabled yesterday are before the House.1 I assume 
     <lb/>
     members will want to discuss them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> Mr. Chairman, as you know, we 
     <lb/>
     only went through this proposed budget of 
     <lb/>
     revenue and expenditure, as it would be under a 
     <lb/>
     province, yesterday afternoon, and it has not 
     <lb/>
     given us much time to study it. But in going 
     <lb/>
     through it there were a few notes I made, and I 
     <lb/>
     have only got a few comments on it for the time 
     <lb/>
     being. I can appreciate Mr. Smallwood's difficul<lb break="no"/>ty in bringing it in, and he did very well with what 
     <lb/>
     he had to work on. I am glad that the Finance 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Committee did not have to bring in one like it, 
     <lb/>
     because, while that was torn to shreds, I think we 
     <lb/>
     would go for years before we would be allowed 
     <lb/>
     to forget one like this. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the expenditure side there is $15.1  million, 
     <lb/>
     I think, for the first four year period. In that 
     <lb/>
     section there was an item of $3.1 million for 
     <lb/>
     Education. That is the same amount as contained 
     <lb/>
     in the Commission of Government estimates for 
     <lb/>
     1947-48. I don't think that is sufficient. I have not 
     <lb/>
     got the figures yet to give you what will exactly 
     <lb/>
     be required, but I think you will find that that will 
     <lb/>
     be increased considerably in the estimates for 
     <lb/>
     1948-49. I understand the Department of Educa- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     1Volume II:522. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>