<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-01-15"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
    
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
      
            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-01-15">15 January 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
      
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLM3">Martin Holmes</persName>
            </respStmt>
      
         </titleStmt>
    
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
        
            <bibl>
          
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
          
          
          <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1995"/>. 
          
          
          <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          
          
          
          
          <biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="267"/>.
        </bibl>
        
        
            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0259.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0260.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0261.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0262.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0263.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0264.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0265.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0266.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0267.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-04-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="pers:HOLM3" when="2017-04-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0259">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0259.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0260">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0260.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0261">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0261.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0262">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0262.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0263">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0263.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0264">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0264.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0265">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0265.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0266">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0266.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0267">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0267.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="259" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0259.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">259</fw>
            <!--<p> report of the Secretary. We are no authorities on <lb/> radio-telegraph; we cannot form much of an <lb/> opinion as to whether land line or radio-telegraph <lb/> is best, but the department has.  </p><p> Mr. Higgins Since that is a million dollar ques<lb break="no"/>tion, and my recollection of the report is that it is <lb/> not very clear, and since I do not wish Mr. <lb/> Smallwood to answer a question he does not <lb/> </p><milestone type="unknown"/><p> know, we will let the question drop.  </p><p>[There was further discussion, touching on <lb/> telegrams, mail couriers, casual employees, <lb/> capital expenditures, mail contracts with the rail<lb break="no"/>way and steamers, and service in general. The <lb/> committee of the whale then rose and reported <lb/> progress, and the Convention adjourned]<lb/> </p>-->
            <head rendition="simple:centre">January 15, 1947</head>
            <p rendition="simple:centre"><emph>Report of the Transportation and Communications Committee:<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> <lb/> Committee of the
               Whole</emph></p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, before we go <lb/> into the appendix to the report on
               posts and <lb/> telegraphs, there is an item that I think I ought to <lb/> pass on to
               the Convention Yesterday we were <lb/> talking about the subsidy paid by the
               Department <lb/> of Posts and Telegraphs for the conveyance of <lb/> mail, paid to
               the Railway. At that time I was not <lb/> informed of the tme situation. I said the
               amount <lb/> was $150,000. It was $150,000 from 1934 on. <lb/> Before that for two or
               three years it was $217,000 <lb/> a year, and before that for quite a number of years
               <lb/> it was $500,000. Well, on September 1, 1946, a <lb/> new agreement was made
               between the Post Of<lb break="no"/>fice and Railway, setting up an entirely new basis
               <lb/> for postal subsidy. Up to that time it was a flat <lb/> rate of $150,000, but
               since September 1 the new <lb/> agreement is, to the Railway 30 cents per mile, <lb/>
               and to the coastal boats 50 cents per mile. It works <lb/> out, as far as the Post
               Office can estimate it, at <lb/> about $101,000 a year to the Railway, and to the
               <lb/> coastal boats about $92,000. Then, over and <lb/> above that the Post Office
               has agreed to pay the <lb/> Railway a flat amount of$15,000 a year to handle <lb/>
               mail in North Sydney and Port-aux-Basques, so <lb/> that the total would be around
               $210,000 a year. 
            </p>
            <p>We only have the appendix of the report on <lb/>the posts and telegraphs which
               consists of a report <lb/>from the Secretary of the department. 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I was just going to allude to the fact that <lb/>is there not another
               $100,000 in addition to the <lb/>$210,000 provided by the Finance Department <lb/>for
               the Railway?
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> We are dealing only with posts <lb/>and telegraphs, and there is only
               this $210,000 <lb/>now from that department. Mr. Cashin says, <lb/>"Yes, there is
               another $100,000 paid the Railway <lb/>by Finance Department." He was former Finance
               <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
             Minister, and is also chairman of the committee <lb/> for public finance, and I
               would say that he would <lb/> be the man to give the answer to that. Mr. Cashin <lb/>
               nods his head and says, "Yes, they do pay that <lb/> extra amount."
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:italic"> [The Assistant Secretary read the report]</p>
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> What is the date of that report of <lb/> the Secretary of posts and
               telegraphs?
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> This is not a report made for us; <lb/> it is made for the Commission
               of Government, <lb/> and the Secretary, when he appeared before us, <lb/> brought it
               and read it out, and we asked if there <lb/> was any objection to our having copies
               made. It <lb/> is a report submitted by the department to the <lb/> government about
               a year ago. Some of the things <lb/> mentioned, as things they intend to do, they
               have <lb/> since done. They have introduced the ship-to- <lb/> shore
               and coast-to-coast radio-telegraph system <lb/> on the southwest coast. In Gander
               they have done <lb/> some of the things they said they were going to <lb/> do. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> How do you reconcile the second <lb/> last sentence in the report, "Up
               to the present no <lb/> sums have been allocated for reconstruction <lb/> work", with
               Table 3 in the Chadwick-Jones <lb/> report, where it says $300,000 was allocated
               <lb/> 1946-47? Is there any explanation? 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The Chadwick-Jones report <lb/> was prepared about a year ago. This
               report of the <lb/> Secretary was probably written a bit after that. 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> That is not an answer to the ques<lb break="no"/>tion. Your information
               may be perfectly correct <lb/>and this report may be wrong; but that report
               <lb/>stated $300,000 was allocated for reconstruction <lb/>that is probably
               incorrect. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> You mean the Chadwick-Jones <lb/> report? <lb/>
            </p>
            <note xml:id="fn_01">1 Volume II:75. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
            
            <pb n="260" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0260.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">260</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Yes. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I think it is in the estimates for <lb/> the current year, which means
               that this report by <lb/> the Secretary is more up to date — $299,000 for <lb/> the
               current year. I cannot be responsible for the <lb/> Chadwick-Jones report. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I thought you might. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Only to a limited extent am I <lb/> responsible for the Chadwick-Jones
               report. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> In yesterday's debate there <lb/> seemed to be a lot of
               misunderstanding in con<lb break="no"/>nection with the smaller post offices in the
               island. <lb/> On page 5 of the report you will see, "203 <lb/> postmasters — salaries
               paid $80 per year." In <lb/> these small places there are perhaps ten families. <lb/>
               They have a boat once a week. When the boat <lb/> arrives, these ten families go to
               the post office and <lb/> get their mail. On the return trip, the ten families <lb/>
               will go and post their mail. That is all the work <lb/> there is to that post office.
               Perhaps that person <lb/> spends one hour in a week in the post office; <lb/>
               therefore he or she is fairly well paid. In nine out <lb/> of ten cases the post
               office is in the person's <lb/> home. He or she gets a small rent. That will make
               <lb/> a clearer picture. Then 97 postmasters are in <lb/> places where there are 15
               or 20 families; they are <lb/> getting better salaries, $126—$240 a year. They <lb/>
               have no telegraph system; they have about 20 <lb/> families and weekly mail. And the
               same thing <lb/> applies. In the next group, at $240-$500 a year, <lb/> nine out of
               ten of these have a money order office <lb/> and perhaps a telephone. They send only
               three or <lb/> four messages a day. It is not necessary for that <lb/> person to
               spend all of his or her time in the office. <lb/> Again this office may be in the
               home, for which <lb/> rent is received. Then we find 21 getting $500- <lb
                  break="yes"/> $600 a year. There is more work there. The <lb/> person who is
               underpaid is the postmaster or <lb/> postmistress in places like Botwood, Fogo. St.
               <lb/> Anthony and Lewisporte. You have in the last <lb/> place a post office and
               telegraph office all in one <lb/> — one person doing three persons' work. The <lb/>
               Canadian army is there, the Shell Oil Co. and <lb/> other businesses. It is a centre.
               They are in the <lb/> office from nine in the morning until 12 at night. <lb/> This
               group is very much underpaid. If these <lb/> people were getting $200 a month they
               would be <lb/> getting a fair rate of wages.... Again we have 159 <lb/> mail
               couriers, these people have long, hard and <lb/> weary trips, and to them the country
               owes a great <lb/> debt of gratitude. Sometimes they travel on hor<lb break="no"/>
            
            <cb/>
            ses, sometimes on dog teams, and sometimes <lb/> they have to carry the mail on their
               backs.
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I am not so sure that that is, critically <lb/> speaking, a true picture.
               I am thinking of a place <lb/> where there are 600 people and the postal <lb/>
               operator is employed there 20 years. He is a <lb/> family man, his salary is $22 a
               month, and he gets <lb/> $2 a month rent for the post office. He collects an <lb/>
               average of $100 a month customs duties. I have <lb/> a message today from a man who
               is employed <lb/> around 30 years; his monthly salary is $11.62 <lb/> including war
               bonus, and he has four in his fami<lb break="no"/>1y. I think that this
               Convention must have some <lb/> sympathy for these people. I know this <lb/>
               postmaster to be a capable man. There are at least <lb/> three communities adjoining
               that settlement <lb/> where post offices were taken away, telegraph <lb/> and
               telephone poles chopped down, and this of<lb break="no"/>fice serves 1,200 to 1,500
               people. That man is <lb/> employed full time all the year round and he <lb/> receives
               $11.62 a month. I have every sympathy <lb/> for him.... 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> Mr. Chairman, I have but few obser<lb break="no"/>vations to make and
               shall refrain from any <lb/> detailed criticism. It appears we have today a <lb/>
               worn-out railway and a worn-out telegraph sys<lb break="no"/>tem, and we are coldly
               advised of this fact by both <lb/> of these departments. This has happened despite
               <lb/> the fact that both the railway and the telegraph <lb/> system had been building
               up pre-war in a highly <lb/> satisfactory manner and indicated an ability to <lb/>
               handle our normal needs for a long time. What, <lb/> then, was the reason for this
               overburdening and <lb/> unprofitable business? Plainly, sir, it is because <lb/> we
               have just fought a war, we have rendered <lb/> services beyond our means; whether
               willingly or <lb/> unwillingly I don't know, but certainly to a dis<lb break="no"
               />tressing effect in assisting a world interest. Are <lb/> we then satisfied to
               receive from that world a <lb/> graceful thank-you, and leave the matter there? <lb/>
               England, the US and Canada, stand together be<lb break="no"/>cause they must....
               Standing together in war they <lb/> still stand together in peace, but we stood with
               <lb/> them in war. Why then are we so quickly forgot<lb break="no"/>ten in peace? If
               I were to answer that question I <lb/> would say because we work out our deals on
               <lb/> "friendly terms" — two words to be careful of in <lb/> the future of
               Newfoundland. In a friendly manner <lb/> we have gone on in the past and accepted
               things <lb/> as we found them. We have accepted the word <lb/> and treatment of old
               England as final and live <lb/>
            <pb n="261" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0261.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">261</fw>
            
            under it or die under it, if you will. We are <lb/> deprived of any standing in any
               international <lb/> set-up. We must be humble contributors, ex<lb break="no"/>ploited
               in any and every way; and so we go on to <lb/> face the future; so we let ourselves
               forget the <lb/> sacrifice made to the railway and telegraph sys<lb break="no"/>tem;
               to the roads; we let ourselves forget the bases <lb/> deal; the free interest loans;
               all consequences of <lb/> friendly terms. Mr. Chairman, in international <lb/>
               politics there is no place for friendly terms, it is a <lb/> case of dog eat dog....
               Is it now time then that we, <lb/> as a people, cease to condone this policy, and
               <lb/> cease to be the good servant? 
            </p>
            <p> I hold that we in this Convention, emphatical<lb break="no"/>ly, man for man, should
               condemn this treatment <lb/> and take an aggressive stand; that we should go <lb/>
               beyond the Dominions Office, and ask that a <lb/> delegation from the present Labour
               government <lb/> of Great Britain be sent here to study and discuss <lb/> its
               findings with the National Convention more <lb/> particularly in respect to our
               injustices. I feel that <lb/> we should not go on alone, since the situation has
               <lb/> arisen mainly as a result of the war policy of other <lb/> countries, and those
               other countries must assist <lb/> us to mend the damage. I feel, sir, that we are
               <lb/> spending too much time discussing reports which <lb/> in the long run amount,
               as my friend Mr. Newell <lb/> said yesterday, to cutting our garment to suit the
               <lb/> cloth, without considering how we can enlarge <lb/> the cloth. Bigger matters
               vitally concerning us are <lb/> being passed by, and time goes on. We have <lb/>
               assisted these countries in their problems, we <lb/> have worked together in war —
               let us now boldly <lb/> present our demands in peace. 
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:italic">[In response to a question from Mr. Harrington, <lb/> Mr. Smallwood gave information
               concerning <lb/> telegraph lines built by the American forces]
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> ....I notice that they are going to <lb/> build a parcel post station out
               in Comer Brook. I <lb/> may say that this is very good news for people all <lb/> over
               the island. It always seemed ridiculous to us <lb/> that parcels had to be carted in
               here to St. John's <lb/> and then carted back again all over the country.... 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Mr. Chairman, I have not trespassed <lb/>too much on your time, and now that
               the cross- <lb break="yes"/>firing has practically ceased, this appears to be a
               <lb/>good time to sum up my impression of what we <lb/>have learned so far. As a
               member of the Transpor<lb break="no"/>tation and Communications Committee it would
               <lb/>not come with good grace from me to be critical <lb/>of the report.... Having
               said this it would appear <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p> that I should say no more. However, various <lb/> interpretations were put on some
               of the facts and <lb/> it is on these that I wish to offer a few comments. <lb/> My
               reason for doing this is twofold: I would like <lb/> to clarify my own thinking now
               that the debates <lb/> in committee have finished, and I would like to <lb/> pass on
               to the public and the other members of <lb/> the Convention my thoughts, in the hope
               that they <lb/> may be of some assistance in helping us all to <lb/> reach the best
               possible conclusion when we come <lb/> to make final decisions. 
            </p>
            <p> Since the Convention came into being I have <lb/> conceived of its work, in broad
               essentials, as <lb/>having to discover, first, what our yearly national <lb/>income
               is likely to be in the foreseeable future. I <lb/>visualised our getting out a sort
               of overall picture <lb/>of what is likely to be produced yearly for say the <lb/>next
               five or ten years — as the amount of wealth <lb/>which we would have to live on as a
               people.... 
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:italic">[Mr Butt went on to make an estimate of value <lb/> of fisheries, forestry,
               agriculture, investment <lb/> returns, bases, minerals of approximately
               $65 <lb/> million]
            </p>
            <p>The total fund, in other words, out of which we <lb/>all had to get a living at some
               standard. Now <lb/>having found that we should, secondly, discover <lb/>what percent
               of that yearly income we should <lb/>devote to government services. Government ser<lb
                  break="no"/>vices are divided into two parts. One part is <lb/>services that we
               wish for ourselves and for which <lb/>we do expect to pay on a specific basis, for
               <lb/>example, education. The other part is services <lb/>which are a combination of
               service and specific <lb/>business such as the Railway.... 
            </p>
            <p> Then there would be our major problem of <lb/> discovering what form of government
               would best <lb/> help us to increase our annual production, and <lb/> provide for the
               best distribution of that produc<lb break="no"/>tion. To get the information required
               for the first <lb/> two items mentioned we appointed nine commit<lb break="no"
               />tees.... So far three committee reports and one <lb/> interim report have been
               presented to the Con<lb break="no"/>vention. Two — Forestry and the Interim <lb/>
               Fisheries report — dealt with national wealth, <lb/> and the other two — Education,
               and Transporta<lb break="no"/>tion and Communications — dealt with a pos<lb
                  break="no"/>sible avenue of increasing that national wealth <lb/> insofar as it
               referred to the bases deal. The two <lb/> others, Education was one of pure service,
               and <lb/> the Transportation and Communications has <lb/> dealt with the combination
               of poor service and <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="262" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0262.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">262</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            
            <p> poor business. In these few remarks I propose to <lb/> touch on the Education Report
               only, and to <lb/> review the items discovered under Trans<lb break="no"/>portation
               and Communications The remark on <lb/> education is this: it has, Ibelieve, been
               accepted <lb/> by a majority of us that this one item of govern<lb break="no"/>ment
               expenditure must be of the order of $3 <lb/> million — $4 million.<ref target="#fn_02">[1]</ref> That is one item
               which <lb/> must go into our second table to be spent on <lb/> education. 
            </p>
            <p> Let us turn now to the report immediately <lb/> under consideration. In my view we
               can add <lb/> certain items to our projected government expen<lb break="no"/>diture
               table. First of all radio service — $25,000; <lb/> secondly, posts and telegraphs —
               $1.5 million- <lb break="yes"/> $1.75 million; roads and bridges — $2.5 million
               <lb/> $3 million; railway — $12 million-$13 million; <lb/> Gander and the tourists.
               On these last mentioned <lb/> I am unwilling to say what our expenditure will <lb/>
               have to be because, as regards Gander. I feel that <lb/> the position should not be
               allowed to remain as it <lb/> is: namely, Newfoundland is giving outside con<lb
                  break="no"/>cerns services for which these concerns are only <lb/> paying an
               estimated one-half of the cost. We have <lb/> agreed that this is a matter which will
               require <lb/> much more probing before we can say what must <lb/> go into our
               expenditure account. Again, on <lb/> tourists, we will have to make up our minds
               <lb/> where we are going and then estimate our expen<lb break="no"/>diture with its
               counterpart of the estimated return <lb/> to the total economy. Before leaving this
               short <lb/> sum-up, sir, I would ask you to note two things. <lb/> First, that
               although the items at present about <lb/> which we are able to speak definitely are
               very <lb/> few, the country ought to know that within the <lb/> next few weeks as the
               bulk of the work is done <lb/> many more items will be added quickly. I say that
               <lb/> in fairness to the members of the Convention and <lb/> because I feel that the
               public generally would like <lb/> to know that that is so. And secondly. you will
               <lb/> note that I have neglected for the moment the <lb/> form in which we are to
               cover the expenditure for <lb/> these government services — that is to say, how <lb/>
               we are going to collect the funds to pay for the <lb/> services.<ref target="#fn_03">[2]</ref> 
            </p>
            <p> As regards broadcasting, Mr. Chairman, I was <lb/> impressed with the need to get on
               with the expan<lb break="no"/>sion of our present services. In a country such as
               <lb/> ours where the people do not live in large centres, <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p> radio was discovered for our benefit. We ought <lb/> to back those in charge of
               broadcasting not only <lb/> with our most helpful criticism, but with the <lb/>
               necessary funds to get a full Newfoundland <lb/> coverage, on the same principle and
               for the same <lb/> reasons as we have satisfied ourselves that we <lb/> ought to push
               to the limit the purely formal <lb/> education of the country. 
            </p>
            <p> Our discussion of posts and telegraphs ap<lb break="no"/>peared to turn on the
               question of the adequacy of <lb/> the wages paid to postal employees, and at the
               <lb/> same time to an extension of the services. On the <lb/> question of an
               equitable distribution of wealth, I <lb/> have a closed mind. My mind cannot tolerate
               a <lb/> general position where wealth is concentrated <lb/> into the hands of a
               minority. We should be dis<lb break="no"/>covering ways and means of seeing to it
               that <lb/> everyone produces and that wealth is shared. <lb/> Howeverl say frankly
               that we ought not to go off <lb/> half-cocked. Whether wages paid in the Depart<lb
                  break="no"/>ment of Posts and Telegraphs are high, low, or <lb/> fair in relation
               to other government services, I do <lb/> not know, because I have not carefully
               studied <lb/> the position. How a postal telegraph employee's <lb/> wages in the
               various communities compare with <lb/> the average person's wages I do not know. If
               the <lb/> courier to whom Mr. Burry referred is doing a <lb/> necessary job, and that
               job takes a great deal of <lb/> his time and puts him out of production in other
               <lb/> spheres, then he should be paid a wage which will <lb/> put him in as
               favourable a position as the rest of <lb/> the people with whom he lives. However, to
               refer <lb/> to a $50 a year payment in some cases as a salary <lb/> of $4 per month,
               and as shameful, is not neces<lb break="no"/>sarily being realistic. For example, a
               community <lb/> of fishermen wants a lightkeeper at the approach <lb/> of their
               harbour. They cannot afford to pay a man <lb/> a living wage forjust doing a
               half-hour's work a <lb/> day, so they say to someone of their number who <lb/> lives
               on the point: "Keep your eye on that light, <lb/> fix it up if anything happens to
               put it out on the <lb/> odd occasion. This will take some of your time <lb/> away
               from farming, carpentry, etc, and we'll pay <lb/> you for that lost time, i.e. $50 a
               year." This <lb/> question will come up time and time again before <lb/> our
               discussions have finished. It is right that it <lb/> should. I have offered my
               comments in the hope <lb/> that they might be of some value in helping us all <lb/>
               to keep a sense of perspective. I repeat, I am all 
            </p>
            <note xml:id="fn_02">1. The following section is taken from the recording of the proceedings.</note>
            <note xml:id="fn_03">2. The section taken from the recording ends here.</note>
            
            <pb n="263" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0263.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">263</fw>
            <p> for the fairest distribution of wealth, but I have to <lb/> remember that as
               taxation is increased for ordi<lb break="no"/>nary services, the farmer and the
               fishermen pays. 
            </p>
            <p> May I now comment on our work in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with the Railway....
               There is one point which <lb/> is of particular interest to me, which has not been
               <lb/> sufficiently brought out. I put a blunt question to <lb/> the General Manager
               like this: "From the point <lb/> of view of lessened maintenance costs in the <lb/>
               future have you got today a better outfit to give <lb/> service than you have ever
               had?" His reply was, <lb/> and I ask the other members of the Committee to <lb/> hear
               me out, an unqualified "yes". He went into <lb/> details on the subject which I am
               not going to do. <lb/> Further he was expecting a number of things to <lb/> "break"
               favourably over the next few years of <lb/> operating, so that the costs of our
               service may be <lb/> lessened.<ref target="#fn_04">[1]</ref> As Mr. Smallwood said yesterday, the <lb/> General
               Manager hopes to see a gradual reduc<lb break="no"/>tion of the ordinary deficit over
               the next ten years <lb/> after we have passed the present period of terrifi<lb
                  break="no"/>cally high and abnormal costs, particularly <lb/> materials. To me,
               looking at the probable costs of <lb/> government in the forseeable future, this is
               of the <lb/> utmost importance. During the next few years, <lb/> when we have money,
               we will be able to carry on <lb/> and pay the high deficits. But after that period
               <lb/> when things get back more nearly to normal, <lb/> there will be a corresponding
               relief in the form of <lb/> reduced railway deficit. 
            </p>
            <p> I turn for a moment to roads, Mr. Chairman. It <lb/> is to my mind quite proper that
               we should have <lb/> debated the relative merits of trunk versus com<lb break="no"
               />munity roads. As a result of our work I feel that <lb/> the country has been
               reminded that there is a <lb/> direct relationship between the development of <lb/>
               the economy, or to repeat Mr. Newell's words, <lb/> the economic potential of the
               country and the <lb/> development of all necessary means of com<lb break="no"
               />munication and transportation. One point here <lb/> did not appear to me to be
               sufficiently brought <lb/> out. It is the fact that roads themselves, their <lb/>
               location, their standard, the method of building <lb/> them, is of tremendous
               importance. And further, <lb/> that there is or should be an economic basis for <lb/>
               the standard, the location, and the method of <lb/> building. For example, if it has
               been decided that <lb/> a base depot should be established in a certain <lb/>
               locality, it may be proper economy to build a <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p> third-class road leading to it. If however, that area <lb/> developed, it may be
               necessary and proper to <lb/> re-build a road to a necessary standard. Finally, <lb/>
               some time later because of the increase in traffic <lb/> on that road, it may be
               necessary to put a hard to <lb/> on it or to build it to a higher standard still.<ref target="#fn_05">[2]</ref>
               <lb/> Similarly, in thinking about the merits or <lb/> demerits of a transinsular
               bighroad, I have al<lb break="no"/>ready reduced my thoughts to writing in an article
               <lb/> in the <title level="j">Atlantic Guardian</title>, wherein I stated we <lb/> should have an overall
               design of a transinsular <lb/> road but that it should be constructed in sections
               <lb/> paralleling the development of these sections. <lb/> The sections to be
               developed first should be based <lb/> on the criterion of their adding to the
               development <lb/> of our economy or our total production. 
            </p>
            <p> Mr. Chairman, at the moment I have not <lb/> cleared my own thinking on Gander and
               the <lb/> tourist report, and therefore I will reserve my <lb/> comments to a later
               date I wish also to say that <lb/> the time taken by me today has a twofold purpose:
               <lb/> to be helpful to the Convention; and to report <lb/> particularly to that part
               of Newfoundland which <lb/> is responsible for my being in the Convention. 1 <lb/> do
               hope these purposes have been reasonably <lb/> fulfilled. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> I find it difficult to reconcile this <lb/> statement about the excellent
               condition of the <lb/> railway. We are told we need seven new locomo<lb break="no"
               />tives; we are told that due to the increased traffic <lb/> handled, the main line
               needs to be re-railed, That <lb/> will cost $600,000. It cannot be so good. The <lb/>
               report goes on to say that the present rails can be <lb/> cut and used to re-rail the
               branch lines. If we <lb/> anticipate laying new branch lines, they cannot <lb/> be so
               good either. Further there is no mention of <lb/> any money to re-rail those branch
               lines. That, I <lb/> presume, is an expenditure that has been over<lb break="no"
               />looked. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There is another item that <lb/> ought to be added to the cost of
               re-railing. Mr. <lb/> Russell's estimate is $600,000 for six years — <lb/> $3.6
               million to re-rail the main line. To that has <lb/> to be added another $1 million to
               cover labour <lb/> and other incidental expenses in connection with <lb/> the
               re-railing; which would make a total of over <lb/> $4.5 million, and as I remarked
               before, there are <lb/> those who contend that it will be extremely un<lb break="no"
               />likely to re-rail the main line at an overall cost of 
            </p>
            <note xml:id="fn_04">1. The following section IS taken from the recording of the proceedings.</note>
            <note xml:id="fn_05">The section taken from the recording ends here.</note> 
            
            <pb n="264" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0264.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">264</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            
            <p> $4.5 million.... It is true that Mr. Russell told us <lb/> that the railway is in a
               fairly good condition, <lb/> basically. When the railway was built, the con<lb
                  break="no"/>tractors were paid by the mile, and they were not <lb/> too particular
               about how they built it. For in<lb break="no"/>stance a lot of culverts were built of
               wood, and <lb/> the wood rotted and had to be replaced. Now it is <lb/> true, in
               recent years they have replaced a number <lb/> of those with concrete culverts. A
               certain amount <lb/> of ballasting was done. In other respects the <lb/> railway is
               in better condition than it has been for <lb/> years. But the main line has to be
               re-railed. That <lb/> will call for a better roadbed. That will run into <lb/> money.
               How much is any man's guess. They <lb/> have to buy seven new locomotives, and a lot
               of <lb/> new rolling stock. If the railway were good, they <lb/> would not have to
               re-rail the line, buy locomo<lb break="no"/>tives and buy rolling stock. But when the
                  Com<lb break="no"/>mittee visited the Railway and spent an afternoon <lb/> with
               Mr. Ryan, that matter was raised. It was <lb/> admitted that at the end of World War
               I they had <lb/> a completely worn-out railway. There were lives <lb/> lost and
               people maimed on account of the condi<lb break="no"/>tion of the railway, because of
               the traffic it had to <lb/> carry, and which no one anticipated it would <lb/> carry.
               The question was put to Mr. Ryan, "The <lb/> railway has been called upon to carry
               tremendous <lb/> amount of traffic during the war years, is it now <lb/> as worn-out
               as it was at the end of the last war?" <lb/> He said, "No, it is distinctly better
               now than at the <lb/> end of the last war." Because, he told us, during <lb/> the war
               years they did spend some money on the <lb/> roadbed, and some money on rolling stock
               and <lb/> some on general upkeep.... It is better than it was <lb/> but is far from
               being perfect and a lot of money <lb/> has to be spent to make it ordinarily
               efficient and <lb/> workable. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Smallwood said something <lb/> about not congratulating ourselves on
               the condi<lb break="no"/>tion of the railway. It seemed to me he was <lb/> pleased
               with the condition of the railway. Mr. <lb/> Smallwood said that at the end of World
               War I <lb/> we had an absolutely worn-out railway, would he <lb/> tell me what the
               government has done in regard <lb/> to that? 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> When the railway was worn-<lb break="yes"/> out, it was owned by the
               Reids. The Reids kept <lb/> coming to the government with this, that and the <lb/>
               other proposition and finally the government had <lb/> to step in. They appointed a
               Railway Commis<lb break="no"/>sion and they brought in railway experts. The <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p> upshot was that in 1923 the government bought <lb/> out the railway from the Reids.
               
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> What did they do with the railway? 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> When the government bought <lb/>it, they re-railed the whole line.
               
            </p>
            <p> There are always improvements going on. For <lb/> a small country, it is a mighty
               system. Naturally, <lb/> capital expenditure has had to be made — sta<lb break="no"
               />tions, sheds built and re-built, as regularly as <lb/> clockwork. 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> I think the point is now very clear <lb/>that the management of the
               Railway in the lean <lb/>years did a good job. When war came along we <lb/>had a
               railway system which might have carried <lb/>on for a long period to serve our needs,
               but an <lb/>excessive burden was thrown on it ... I cannot be <lb/>reconciled to the
               fact the Newfoundland should <lb/>be saddled with an expenditure on a railway
               <lb/>which helped fight a war, beyond our means. <lb/>Someone else should pay. 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> What I cannot understand is, one <lb/>statement says the railway is worn
               out, and <lb/>another says it is in better condition than ever. 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Basically, it is in a better condition. <lb/>They have put in new culverts;
               done a lot of <lb/>ballasting; taken off curves; have built new sheds <lb/>which will
               last for long periods; have put gravity <lb/>feed in the water system. Basically the
               railway <lb/>has an outfit better than before.... 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I wish to draw attention to this <lb/>particular report. You will note
               that everything <lb/>we have in this country is absolutely worn out and <lb/>should
               be scrapped. It is tragic. We have to throw <lb/>the postal telegraphs in the Narrows
               and get in a <lb/>new system. The railway has to be re-railed. <lb/>Everything this
               report touches has to be scrapped. <lb/>That is an important thing to remember when
               we <lb/>are discussing forms of government. What par<lb break="no"/>ticular form of
               government is able to afford that? <lb/>When we come to sum up, we will have to bear
               <lb/>that in mind. 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Are we now discussing the report, not <lb/>only on posts and telegraphs, but
               the general <lb/>report? 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Yes. 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> We have not had any general picture of <lb/>what all these six items are
               going to cost the <lb/>country. As a member of the Finance Committee, <lb/>I may say
               we are rather interested in finding out <lb/>what that is.... I take it from this
               report that the <lb/>Finance Committee will have to estimate a rise <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="265" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0265.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">265</fw>
            <p> on expenditure of $3.5 million from a revenue <lb/> point of view. They do help the
               primary in<lb break="no"/>dustries. The railway system and roads and <lb/> bridges
               help the fisheries and they help forestry. <lb/> But they are not, in themselves,
               revenue <lb/> producers, and I cannot feel there is much ad<lb break="no"/>vantage in
               debating this report until we have had <lb/> the other side of the picture. People
               have talked <lb/> about the irreducible minimum of expenditure to <lb/> carry along
               these services; but I think the ir<lb break="no"/>reducible expenditures will
               eventually be <lb/> governed by the maximum revenues.... 
            </p>
            <p> There is one other matter to which I would like <lb/> to refer. Mr. Smallwood
               replied to a question in <lb/> connection with duty on plates for the repair of <lb/>
               ships. The duty is refundable on foreign ships, but <lb/> it is not refundable on our
               own ships. I take it that <lb/> applies to the Railway — the ships run by the <lb/>
               Railway? 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Not local ships. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> They presumably pay duty and it con<lb break="no"/>sequently increases the
               cost of operation. It is the <lb/> same with our local mercantile marine. I do not
               <lb/> know how we are going to expect to compete <lb/> with other people in working
               up a mercantile <lb/> marine when that condition exists. The Railway <lb/> itself is
               the largest employer of mercantile marine <lb/> at the present time. I suppose one of
               these days <lb/> we will again be sending all our produce abroad <lb/> in foreign
               ships, because they are operating more <lb/> cheaply, and it is not right that these
               duties are <lb/> charged against our own ships when they have to <lb/> compete with
               these ships. Ninety percent of our <lb/> fish was shipped, in previous years, in
               Norwegian <lb/> ships and they gave very good service. It is a sad <lb/> thing being
               a naval people that we cannot work <lb/> up a good mercantile marine of our own and
               run <lb/> our own ships. Things like this question of duty <lb/> have something to do
               with it. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It is a pleasure indeed to find <lb/> myself in such complete
               agreement with Mr. Job. <lb/> Anything charged in the repair of local vessels on
               <lb/> the Newfoundland Dock is an imposition, a bur<lb break="no"/>den on local
               shipping. As a free trader, an anti- <lb break="yes"/> protectionist I would say that
               all our productive <lb/> industries should be exempted from customs <lb/> duty.... I
               would say sweep out the customs duty, <lb/> have free trade, and do away with this
               protection. <lb/> If our local mercantile marine has got to compete <lb/> with any
               other merchant marine, then it is neces<lb break="no"/>sary to reduce the costs of
               operation. The same <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p> thing applies to fish. We are competing today <lb/> with Canada, Iceland, and Norway
               in the market<lb break="no"/>ing of fish. That job is made hard for us because <lb/>
               the fishing industry is paying customs duty. Let's <lb/> wipe out those duties and
               lower the cost of <lb/> producing fish, while we are wiping out the cost <lb/> of
               repairs on the dock by wiping out duties al<lb break="no"/>together. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> 1 don't see why these ships <lb/> coming into Newfoundland and using
               our dock <lb/> should not pay the duty on the stuff that goes into <lb/> them. Does
               anybody think these ships would ever <lb/> come here if they did not have to pay? Why
               <lb/> should our own ships have to pay it, and foreign <lb/> ships get a rebate of
               duty? 1 must say I feel very <lb/> strongly about the matter, and while discussing
               <lb/> the dockyard I would like to ask Mr. Smallwood <lb/> the number of people on
               the payroll.... Now it <lb/> may be that you have not that at hand, butI would <lb/>
               certainly like to know how many people are on <lb/> that payroll with over $1
               million.... 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I could give the official ex<lb break="no"/>planation, not meaning
               that I agree with it all. If <lb/> Mr. Ashboume had a vessel and she needed <lb/>
               repairs, and he decided to repair her down in <lb/> Twillingate and he had to use
               materials for those <lb/> repairs he would get no rebate of the duty on the <lb/>
               material, and the government takes the stand that <lb/> whether that is done by
               himself in Twillingate or <lb/> done for him at the docks in St. John's, it is the
               <lb/> same situation as far as customs duty is con<lb break="no"/>cerned. In other
               words, all the local merchant <lb/> marine pays duty on certain things used in the
               <lb/> repair and operation of their ships. Now why <lb/> should any difference be
               made for foreign ships <lb/> going on the dock? Their answer is that by charg<lb
                  break="no"/>ing duty on material used to repair a local vessel <lb/> on the dock
               they are only doing what that vessel <lb/> has to do if it is repaired anywhere else
               in the <lb/> country, but in getting a ship from outside they <lb/> are getting
               something new, and they have to be <lb/> in a position to compete with other docks,
               and for <lb/> that reason the duty is paid back. That's clear to <lb/> me, not saying
               that I agree with it, but I can <lb/> certainly see that if you going to have duty on
               the <lb/> local you must have it off on the foreign or you <lb/> will not get any
               foreign ships to do. It's probably <lb/> a bit cheaper for a man having a local ship
               <lb/> repaired on the dock, because it reduces the over<lb break="no"/>head,
               therefore making it a little cheaper for local <lb/> vessels. <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="266" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0266.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">266</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I think I sat down a little too quickly, <lb/> before I had a chance to
               congratulate the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee on their report, because they have taken a
               <lb/> tremendous amount of trouble and done an enor<lb break="no"/>mous amount of
               work. The Railway is a great <lb/> asset to the country, and I always think that one
               <lb/> of the great assets on our Railway is the person<lb break="no"/>nel. I don't
               know any place (although I have done <lb/> a lot of travelling) where they make
               people as <lb/> much at home as on our railway, and I think it is <lb/> due to the
               courtesy of the officials from top to <lb/> bottom. I have heard that same expression
               from <lb/> people outside the country who have travelled on <lb/> the railway. They
               seem to get a more personal <lb/> touch, and it is an asset with a view to our
               possible <lb/> future tourist policy. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It's our natural Newfoundland <lb/> courtesy, I think. We have all got
               it, but it only <lb/> shows up when we are in contact with outsiders. <lb/> When we
               are alone, God only knows what we <lb/> will say to each other, but to outsiders we
               are a <lb/> very charming and polite people. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> I think it will be found that in all <lb/> parts of the world outside
               ships in foreign <lb/> shipyards pay no duty.... A man who goes to sea, <lb/> once he
               is outside the three mile limit does not <lb/> pay any duty, but when he is in port
               he pays duty. <lb/> That has been something that has grown up <lb/> throughout
               maritime history.... I took the ques<lb break="no"/>tion up with Mr. Russell, and he
               says it is impos<lb break="no"/>sible for us to compete with the docks in New <lb/>
               York and other large docks throughout the world, <lb/> so I don't think we can
               censure the government <lb/> for doing what is an old custom.... We are not in <lb/>
               a position, and very few countries in the world <lb/> are in the position, to compete
               with the United <lb/> States. Ships come from all parts of the world to <lb/> be
               dry-docked in the United States. If we were in <lb/> a position to have more ships
               come here, there <lb/> would be more surplus for the docks. But we went <lb/> into
               itextensively with Mr. Russell and apparent<lb break="no"/>ly we are not able to
               compete with the large docks <lb/> in the world. The only thing we get here is an
               <lb/> emergency job or a local job. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I feel the most serious aspect of this <lb/> matter is the fact that by us
               paying duty on our <lb/> local jobs, and foreign ships getting that duty <lb/> free,
               it prevents our local ships from competing. <lb/> The whole answer is that
               Newfoundlanders <lb/> usually treat outsiders better than their own. <lb/> Early in
               1940 I was in Oakland, California, with <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p> the old Queen of the Pacific, and there was never <lb/> any question of getting a
               rebate on any of the <lb/> plating we used at the dry dock, and I don't think <lb/>
               any Newfoundland ship could go to any dock in <lb/> the world and get a rebate of
               duty. Usually any <lb/> foreigners coming to Newfoundland get these <lb/> special
               concessions, and I don't believe they are <lb/> entitled to it. I never heard of a
               boat coming to <lb/> Newfoundland because of the special conces<lb break="no"/>sions,
               they only come to Newfoundland because <lb/> they are forced here because of weather
                  condi<lb break="no"/>tions, or because they become disabled.... 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> I would feel remiss if I let this oc<lb break="no"/>casion pass without
               deploring the awful condi<lb break="no"/>tions of first class travel on the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Home</hi> in
               Placentia <lb/> Bay. Time and time again she has left Placentia <lb/> with 120
               passengers —- sleeping on deck, and in <lb/> lifeboats, and every conceivable part of
               the ship, <lb/> food in a deplorable condition, almost beyond <lb/> description. The
               Railway is at last going to <lb/> replace the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Home</hi> with a new boat, and this very
               <lb/> good news. If the railway is in such a deplorable <lb/> condition due to the
               war, I think, as Mr. Miller <lb/> suggested, that we should ask those foreign <lb/>
               powers which militarily used Newfoundland for <lb/> some compensation to help us out
               in making our <lb/> railway a better service to our country. 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, if there are no <lb/> other cements it is getting up
               around the time <lb/> to adjourn. This completes all we have of our <lb/> report,
               but, as the House knows, we have asked <lb/> Mr. Neill to appear before the
               Convention and <lb/> give us further information on Gander, and it may <lb/>
               consequently be necessary to bring in a sup<lb break="no"/>plementary report on
               Gander.... 
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> Since Mr. Reddy has raised the point <lb/> of deplorable conditions on
               the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Home</hi>, I would <lb/> like to say that I agree with him. The ship's <lb/> company
               have given their best to make the pas<lb break="no"/>sengers comfortable as far as
               possible. It is a <lb/> deplorable state of affairs not to have better ac<lb
                  break="no"/>commodations, but I can't see how it can be <lb/> avoided at the
               present time. I know I have felt bad <lb/> to have to walk down and say, "We can't
               take any <lb/> more, we have no room for them." It is very <lb/> uncomfortalbe for
               women and children lying <lb/> around on the seats and chairs, etc. I do really <lb/>
               hope that it will be better, not only in that con<lb break="no"/>nection, but by the
               time we finish our work here <lb/> maybe you will see a ray of sunshine which at the
               <lb/> present time is not apparent. <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="267" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-01-15_Page_0267.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1947</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">267</fw>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I was wondering the past few <lb/> weeks what the four members from
               Placentia Bay <lb/> were looking so happy about. I think it may be <lb/> because
               these four gentlemen have succeeded in <lb/> getting a whole lot of things for
               Placentia Bay. <lb/> They are getting a new boat, and a new bait depot, <lb/> and a
               new cottage hospital, so that must be why <lb/> they are so happy. They have even got
               roads, a <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p> couple of million dollars will be spent on them <lb/> Mr. Chairman, I move that the
               committee rise, <lb/> report progress and ask leave to sit again. 
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:italic"> [The committee of the whole rose and reported <lb/> progress. The Convention received
               and adapted <lb/> the report of the Committee on Transportation <lb/> and Communications,
               and adjourned until the <lb/> call of the Chair] <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>