<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-09-19"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-09-19">19 September 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

           <date when="1995"/>.  
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="45"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0039.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0040.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0041.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0042.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0043.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0044.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0045.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-02-14">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0039">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0039.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0040">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0040.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0041">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0041.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0042">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0042.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0043">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0043.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0044">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0044.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0045">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0045.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="39"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0039.jpg"/>
          <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">39</fw>
   
            
   <div type="section">
            <head>
     September 19, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Requests for information were tabled by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Starkes, Mr. Reddy, Mr. Fowler, Mr. Roberts, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Hillier, Mr. Smallwood, Mr. Bailey, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Figary and Mr. Fudge. Mr. Smallwood gave 
     <lb/>
     notice of motion to ask the government for a 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
          
     statement of the gross national product]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Chairman announced that the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner for Finance would address the Convention 
     <lb/>
     later in the day]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     Report on the Financial and Economic Position of Newfoundland<!-- GL, 2017-02-14, commented this out because it does not seem useful, and footnote below: 1 -->
 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>Mr. Ashbourne I want first of all to congratu<lb break="no"/>late most heartily Mr. Newell and Mr. Keough,<lb/>two young men unknown to me until just recent<lb break="no"/>ly, on their maiden speeches. In resuming the<lb/>debate on this motion, I ask the earnest considera<lb break="no"/>tion of the members present for a few observa<lb break="no"/>tions which I shall make. I wish it to be<lb/>understood that I am regarding this report as a<lb/>valuable one. We cannot be too fully informed on<lb/>the financial and economic conditions of our<lb/>land. I came to this Convention with an open<lb/>mind, and with a firm desire to ascertain as well<lb/>as I could, for myself and for the people who sent<lb/>me here, a true picture of Newfoundland. Before<lb/>my election I was asked what form of govern<lb break="no"/>ment I favoured. My reply was that I refused to<lb/>have my hands tied. I realise, sir, that if I had my<lb/>mind made up before I came I might as well come<lb/>and cast my vote and then go home.... I would<lb/>like to approach this important Convention with<lb/>an unprejudiced mind. This is a View which I<lb/>made clear to my district, and I feel that I lost<lb/>some votes because of my association in former<lb/>days as a member of responsible government;<lb/>some of my constituents may have thought that I<lb/>still favoured responsible government. I realise<lb/>that in the north there is a very strong sentiment<lb/>in favour of Commission government. The mat<lb break="no"/>ter of selection of Commissioners has often been<lb/>debated, some people preferring a form by which<lb/>the people themselves would elect the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioners. I believe the fishermen and other<lb/>producers in the country, have realised that there<lb/>has been a certain stability and security evident<lb/>for some years, particularly in the ordinary<lb/>marketing of our staple products of the fisheries.<lb/>It is perhaps true that in other sections of New<lb break="no"/>foundland there may be decided preferences for<lb/>some other form of government, or for respon<lb break="no"/>sible government. I have no doubt, sir, that the<lb/>seeming indifference and apathy which was<lb/>reflected, particularly in some outports, in the<lb/>
             
          <!--  <p>
     [1]Volume II: 16. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            <cb/>
           
small number of votes cast in the election in June,<lb/>was perhaps because the people were not suffi<lb break="no"/>ciently informed about the matter. I had no public<lb/>meetings. I got out a manifesto and distributed it.<lb/>When it was my privilege to sit in the House of<lb/>Assembly about 20 years ago I said I had no doubt<lb/>but that half a dozen men could govern New<lb break="no"/>foundland.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>My first experience, sir, with this chamber,<lb/>was as a boy when I stood in the gallery yonder<lb/>and looked down upon this house. The one person<lb/>that I remember was Sir Robert Bond, that great<lb/>statesman that we remember with pride and af<lb break="no"/>fection, who represented the honourable and his<lb/>toric district of Twillingate, having as its chief<lb/>town the metropolis of the north. This great<lb/>leader in the political arena was one of the<lb/>greatest statesmen Newfoundland ever produced,<lb/>whose wise and stable leadership is a matter of<lb/>history. I remember well Sir Robert, and, al<lb break="no"/>though I cannot at the moment recall his exact<lb/>words, he talked about a bubble which would be<lb/>made to expand and occupy such a large space,<lb/>but which would utterly disappear when touched<lb/>by such a small thing as a pin-point. When the<lb/>people of Newfoundland decide that it is time to<lb/>take up the duties of responsible government<lb/>there should not be the shadow of a doubt about<lb/>the ability of the people to carry on successfully<lb/>the various tasks of government. It is no easy task<lb/>to govern a country wisely and well. It is an easy<lb/>matter, often times, to borrow money, and much<lb/>easier to spend it, but we all know where that<lb/>generally leads. We have suffered in the past in<lb/>Newfoundland, and I believe it is largely because<lb/>of a lack of education. I believe that we need here<lb/>in the city of St. John's a university, and we need<lb/>in our city, and also in our outports, the very best<lb/>teachers that we can procure. The monies now<lb/>being spent on education will, I hope, bring rich<lb/>rewards in the future. I have no doubt in my mind<lb/>whatever, Mr. Chairman, about the honouring of<lb/>
           
            <pb n="40"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0040.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">40</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>
         
     the pledge given us by the British government. 
     <lb/>
     The British government came to our aid 
     <lb/>
     generously and fully in our days of need, and 
     <lb/>
     advanced us $11 million, and let us show our 
     <lb/>
     appreciation of this fact. We live in a world in 
     <lb/>
     which we are interdependent. No man lives to 
     <lb/>
     himself, no country lives to itself. As the ebb and 
     <lb/>
     flow of tides continue, so a mutual world trade 
     <lb/>
     and commerce will ever be present upon the vast 
     <lb/>
     expanses of our ocean, bringing us, we hope, the 
     <lb/>
     necessary essentials of life, and also carrying our 
     <lb/>
     own products by which we live and by which we 
     <lb/>
     have flourishing industries, and to provide the 
     <lb/>
     necessities of life.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Our strategic position between the new and 
     <lb/>
     old worlds, being the Gibraltar of North America, 
     <lb/>
     gives us a wide bargaining power. We have near 
     <lb/>
     our shores vast treasuries of the deep, which 
     <lb/>
     when properly developed and effectively 
     <lb/>
     marketed will enhance our economy. We realise 
     <lb/>
     we have been fortunate in having UNRRA and 
     <lb/>
     the rehabilitation associations to help us out in 
     <lb/>
     the marketing of our produce, and as we face the 
     <lb/>
     future it gives us some concern regarding the 
     <lb/>
     competition which will soon be evident from 
     <lb/>
     fishing countries on the other side. We must see 
     <lb/>
     to it that our capital assets bring to our shores that 
     <lb/>
     necessary wealth by which our people can live 
     <lb/>
     and maintain themselves in dignity and security. 
     <lb/>
     That is why people long for freedom from want 
     <lb/>
     and a sense of security, so that they will be able 
     <lb/>
     not only to have three meals a day, but there will 
     <lb/>
     be that dignity and that prestige which we as 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlanders desire. It is unthinkable that 
     <lb/>
     we should do without the necessary amenities of 
     <lb/>
     life in order to provide and build up an expensive 
     <lb/>
     administrative form of government. We have 
     <lb/>
     many drawbacks, some of them resulting in 
     <lb/>
     unemployment. In the north, people can only 
     <lb/>
     work for a period of a few months, necessitating 
     <lb/>
     quite a bit of spare time. There is a serious cur<lb break="no"/>tailment in the earning power of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     as a result which we must try to overcome. Our 
     <lb/>
     social conditions need improving, the cost of 
     <lb/>
     living needs to be lowered. In this great task of 
     <lb/>
     building a better Newfoundland we are digging 
     <lb/>
     the foundation. Let us find the solid ground on 
     <lb/>
     which we can help to build a better New<lb break="no"/><cb/>foundland, realising that we are building and 
     <lb/>
     working together, and let us see to it that we do 
     <lb/>
     not labour in vain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The debate was adjourned, and the Convention 
     <lb/>
     resolved into a committee of the whole to hear the 
     <lb/>
     address of the Commissioner for Finance]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Wild I believe it is the wish of the members 
     <lb/>
     of the National Convention that I should this 
     <lb/>
     evening give a broad outline of the financial 
     <lb/>
     position of Newfoundland as I see it. <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Report 
     <lb/>
     on the Financial and Economic Position of New<lb break="no"/>foundland</hi>, prepared by the Secretary of State 
     <lb/>
     (which I shall refer to as the White Paper) which 
     <lb/>
     has been prepared for the assistance of the Con<lb break="no"/>vention, covers a good deal of the same ground 
     <lb/>
     and gives more detailed information than I shall 
     <lb/>
     be able to attempt today. I would also like to refer 
     <lb/>
     to the survey on Newfoundland, edited by 
     <lb/>
     Dr. MacKay<ref target="#fn_01">1</ref>, copies of which have, I believe, 
     <lb/>
     been circulated to members and which contains 
     <lb/>
     much valuable information. What I have to say 
     <lb/>
     will not be new, as I believe that most of you have 
     <lb/>
     already given a good deal of private study to these 
     <lb/>
     important questions and fully appreciate the es<lb break="no"/>sentials of the present position, but my talk will, 
     <lb/>
     I hope, be of some help in bringing these matters 
     <lb/>
     into focus. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is chiefly with government revenue and 
     <lb/>
     expenditure that, I take it, you are concerned at 
     <lb/>
     the moment, although in your present delibera<lb break="no"/>tions this must be considered in relation to the 
     <lb/>
     economic position of the country as a whole. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Perhaps it would be most convenient if I 
     <lb/>
     started by reference to government expenditure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The table on page 5<!-- GL, 2017-02-14, commented this out because it does not seem useful, and footnote below: 2 --> of the White Paper-shows 
     <lb/>
     a rise in expenditure between June, 1934, and 
     <lb/>
     March, 1946, from $11.6 millions to $29.1 mil<lb break="no"/>lions. The latter included over $6 millions of 
     <lb/>
     reconstruction expenditure, so that a figure of 
     <lb/>
     $23 millions should be taken for comparative 
     <lb/>
     purposes. The estimates for the present year 
     <lb/>
     again provide for a total of $23 millions, if we 
     <lb/>
     exclude reconstruction and special expenditure 
     <lb/>
     amounting to $11 millions to which I shall refer 
     <lb/>
     later. This increase from $1 1.6 to $23 millions in 
     <lb/>
     ordinary expenditure, i.e. the cost of maintaining 
     <lb/>
     government services at their present level, in<lb break="no"/>cluding the service of the public debt, is large - <lb/>
            
         <note xml:id="fn_01">1 R.A. MacKay was special assistant to the Canadian Under-Secretary of State for External Affairs and editor 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland: Economic, Diplomatic and Strategic Studies (Toronto, 1946).</note> 
    
   
            <!--<p>
     2Volume 11:18. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

            <pb n="41"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0041.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">41</fw>
          
     the cost has been just doubled, and you will wish 
     <lb/>
     to know the main reasons for it. As the White 
     <lb/>
     Paper shows, maintenance of social services 
     <lb/>
     (Public Health &amp; Welfare and Education) ac<lb break="no"/>count for $5 millions of the increase, and main<lb break="no"/>tenance of public services (Posts &amp; Telegraphs, 
     <lb/>
     Customs, Justice, Natural Resources, Public 
     <lb/>
     Works and grants to the Newfoundland Railway) 
     <lb/>
     for $4 millions. There have been increases of 
     <lb/>
     lesser degree under other heads. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There has, as you are aware, been a very 
     <lb/>
     considerable increase during the last 12 years in 
     <lb/>
     the scope of government services, To meet needs, 
     <lb/>
     which in the view of the Commission were ur<lb break="no"/>gent, we have increased the size of our hospitals 
     <lb/>
     and other public institutions including the erec<lb break="no"/>tion of some 14 cottage hospitals; we have ex<lb break="no"/>tended the nursing services, clinics, 
     <lb/>
     anti-TB services, etc. We have substantially in<lb break="no"/>creased the rates of assistance given to the infirm 
     <lb/>
     and aged. Sir John Puddester will be able to give 
     <lb/>
     you a fuller account of these improved social 
     <lb/>
     services. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Educational services have been very consid<lb break="no"/>erably improved, particularly the status and 
     <lb/>
     emoluments of teachers; the introduction of com<lb break="no"/>pulsory education has led to an increase in the 
     <lb/>
     number of children attending educational estab<lb break="no"/>lishments. The present maintenance vote of over 
     <lb/>
     $3 millions for education compares with a total 
     <lb/>
     of half a million dollars to which the service had 
     <lb/>
     been cut in the days preceding the period now 
     <lb/>
     under review. The increases of cost in the Depart<lb break="no"/>ments of Posts and Telegraphs and Customs are 
     <lb/>
     not so large and are counterbalanced by increased 
     <lb/>
     revenue. In the Department of Justice the strength 
     <lb/>
     of the police and fire services have been consid<lb break="no"/>erably extended. While in the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Natural Resources there have been established 
     <lb/>
     services such as the provision of bait depots, and 
     <lb/>
     substantial grants to the Newfoundland Fisheries 
     <lb/>
     Board; this department has also introduced the 
     <lb/>
     Ranger Force and inaugurated numerous 
     <lb/>
     schemes for the encouragement of agriculture 
     <lb/>
     and for rural development which did not exist 
     <lb/>
     before. In passing I might mention that an item 
     <lb/>
     of $500,000 on page 58 of the estimates for 
     <lb/>
     1946-47, representing payments to the Salt Fish 
     <lb/>
     Marketing Fund, which are counter-balanced by 
     <lb/>
     similar receipts under the head of customs, will 
     <lb/>
     in future disappear as this Fund is now being 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
          
     wound up. There have been considerable 
     <lb/>
     developments in the services rendered by the 
     <lb/>
     Department of Public Works, including the main<lb break="no"/>tenance of roads, public wharves and buildings, 
     <lb/>
     and geological surveys. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But quite apart from the widening of the scope 
     <lb/>
     of government services, we have to bear in mind 
     <lb/>
     the increased costs for salaries, supplies and 
     <lb/>
     materials which are the inevitable result of reduc<lb break="no"/>tion in the value of money through the war. 
     <lb/>
     Furthermore, we have to remember that in 1934 
     <lb/>
     government services had been pared to the bone, 
     <lb/>
     as in the case of the educational service to which 
     <lb/>
     I have referred particularly, and a considerable 
     <lb/>
     increase over the levels to which expenditure had 
     <lb/>
     been cut in the time of severe depression could 
     <lb/>
     be expected in the natural course of events. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I should point out that the provision of $23 
     <lb/>
     millions in the present year for ordinary main<lb break="no"/>tenance expenditure, including the service of our 
     <lb/>
     public debt, makes little provision for unemploy<lb break="no"/>ment relief, although the total of over $1,300,000 
     <lb/>
     actually provided for assistance to the infirm and 
     <lb/>
     aged is very much greater than it was a few years 
     <lb/>
     ago. In 1937 we spent over $1,600,000 on un<lb break="no"/>employment relief at the rates than current, and 
     <lb/>
     it is certain that, if similar unemployment condi<lb break="no"/>tions returned, we should require a very much 
     <lb/>
     larger amount to meet this need. Quite apart from 
     <lb/>
     the possibility of provision having to be made in 
     <lb/>
     the future for unemployment relief, we cannot, in 
     <lb/>
     my view, expect any reduction in the figure of 
     <lb/>
     $23 millions at present provided for maintenance 
     <lb/>
     services. Savings may be effected in certain 
     <lb/>
     directions, but they will be more than counter<lb break="no"/>balanced by normal expansion of activities, 
     <lb/>
     which is the inevitable trend in any progressive 
     <lb/>
     community. We can, indeed, expect additional 
     <lb/>
     costs of well over half a million dollars a year in 
     <lb/>
     respect of the operation and maintenance of new 
     <lb/>
     institutions, such as the new sanatorium on the 
     <lb/>
     west coast, the extension of the sanatorium in 
     <lb/>
     St. John's by the incorporation of one of the naval 
     <lb/>
     hospitals, and the operation by the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Public Health and Welfare of a former military 
     <lb/>
     hospital at Botwood, The provision of these im<lb break="no"/>proved social services has undoubtedly led to a 
     <lb/>
     better standard of living, which I am sure you will 
     <lb/>
     agree was urgently needed; it would certainly 
     <lb/>
     lead to great hardship and probably suffering if 
     <lb/>
     these benefits were not maintained. A question 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="42"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0042.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">42</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>
         
            
     you will have to consider is whether they do not 
     <lb/>
     need to be further extended. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We have also provided in 1946—47 for $11 
     <lb/>
     millions in respect of reconstruction and special 
     <lb/>
     expenditure. As I explained in my last budget 
     <lb/>
     speech, of which copies are available to members 
     <lb/>
     of the Convention, reconstruction expenditure, 
     <lb/>
     which we might alternatively call extraordinary 
     <lb/>
     expenditure, relates to important extensions of 
     <lb/>
     existing services and to new projects, mostly of 
     <lb/>
     a capital nature, such as new hospitals, public 
     <lb/>
     buildings, roads, harbour improvements, etc., 
     <lb/>
     which are essential for progressive development 
     <lb/>
     of economic and social conditions. It is expendi<lb break="no"/>ture which could be drastically reduced, even if 
     <lb/>
     not completely out off, if financial stringency 
     <lb/>
     dictated such a course, although it would mean 
     <lb/>
     leaving a number of worksunfinished and would 
     <lb/>
     be a most unfortunate happening so far as the 
     <lb/>
     development of the country is concerned. We 
     <lb/>
     have applied the term "special expenditure" to 
     <lb/>
     certain recoverable advances which we are 
     <lb/>
     making, mainly by way of loan, such as advances 
     <lb/>
     to the St. John's Housing Corporation. It might 
     <lb/>
     reasonably be argued that this is not expenditure 
     <lb/>
     at all in the true sense, but we have included it in 
     <lb/>
     the budget in order to get statutory authority and 
     <lb/>
     to show a complete picture. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The main items of reconstruction expenditure, 
     <lb/>
     which for 1946—47 amounts to $8 millions, are in 
     <lb/>
     respect of advances to the Newfoundland Rail<lb break="no"/>way for capital improvements, the cost of im<lb break="no"/>provements in the internal telegraph system, 
     <lb/>
     costs of civil re-establishment and vocational 
     <lb/>
     training, grants for the extension and improve 
     <lb/>
     ments of school buildings; schemes for the 
     <lb/>
     development of the forests, fisheries and rural 
     <lb/>
     districts under the Department of Natural 
     <lb/>
     Resources; improvement and reconstruction of 
     <lb/>
     roads and bridges and the building of new roads, 
     <lb/>
     the construction of new hospitals and other public 
     <lb/>
     buildings and of ' new harbour facilities, the 
     <lb/>
     provision of homes for indigent persons, etc., all 
     <lb/>
     under the Department of Public Health and We<lb break="no"/>fare such as that for the extension of the general 
     <lb/>
     hospital at Comer Brook, and special assistance 
     <lb/>
     to new local councils. Details of these reconstruc<lb break="no"/>tion services can be obtained by reference to the 
     <lb/>
     current estimates as well as to the memorandum 
     <lb/>
     on reconstruction and development schemes 
     <lb/>
     which has been prepared for your information. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     Members will no doubt wish to consider this 
     <lb/>
     memorandum at greater length. As is explained 
     <lb/>
     in the opening paragraphs of the memorandum, 
     <lb/>
     the schemes which are not already in hand must 
     <lb/>
     be regarded as tentative. Progress would depend 
     <lb/>
     entirely on the availability of funds and par<lb break="no"/>ticularly on the state of current revenue, out of 
     <lb/>
     which it would be hoped to meet as large a part 
     <lb/>
     as possible of such reconstruction expenditure, 
     <lb/>
     with the object of conserving the island's surplus 
     <lb/>
     balances to meet the needs for a rainy day. It is 
     <lb/>
     pointed out in the memorandum that, while a 
     <lb/>
     considerable number of the schemes would not 
     <lb/>
     involve additional recurring costs of main<lb break="no"/>tenance, in other cases such a consequence must 
     <lb/>
     be considered. This is of particular importance in 
     <lb/>
     the case of new roads, which call for heavy 
     <lb/>
     recurring expenditure in maintenance. On the 
     <lb/>
     other hand, some of the schemes should lead to 
     <lb/>
     increased revenue or the saving of expense. I 
     <lb/>
     haVe previously referred to special expenditure, 
     <lb/>
     which amounts in the estimates for this year to 
     <lb/>
     approximately $3 millions. Over $2 millions of 
     <lb/>
     this is in respect of loans for housing purposes; 
     <lb/>
     $250,000 is for loans for the development of the 
     <lb/>
     fishing industry; and the balance is required to 
     <lb/>
     finance operations at the Gander Airport, the cost 
     <lb/>
     of which we hope to recover. This is a matter 
     <lb/>
     about which the Commissioner for Public 
     <lb/>
     Utilities and Supply will be able to give you 
     <lb/>
     further information. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If you will refer again to the table on page 5 
     <lb/>
     of the White Paper, you will be able to trace the 
     <lb/>
     growth of revenue from $9.6 millions in 1934-35 
     <lb/>
     to an estimated $30 millions in the current year 
     <lb/>
     and an actual revenue of over $33 millions in 
     <lb/>
     1945-46. Present indications are that actual 
     <lb/>
     revenue in the current year will exceed the es<lb break="no"/>timate as, you will be glad to hear, actual collec<lb break="no"/>tions are in advance of the revenue which we had 
     <lb/>
     received in the corresponding months of last 
     <lb/>
     year. We are still experiencing a "boom" 
     <lb/>
     economy which has not yet begun to recede. How 
     <lb/>
     long we can expect this happy state of affairs to 
     <lb/>
     continue is a matter of conjecture. In any event, 
     <lb/>
     we can, I think, expect a considerable increase 
     <lb/>
     over the level of revenue attained in the years 
     <lb/>
     before the war. Just as the depreciation in the 
     <lb/>
     value of money has increased government expen<lb break="no"/>diture and earnings generally, so we may expect 
     <lb/>
     a corresponding increase in ad valorem customs 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="43"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0043.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">43</fw>
           
     revenue (subject, of course, to tariff adjustments), 
     <lb/>
     and also in the yield of income tax based on 
     <lb/>
     earnings and profits. To maintain ordinary ex<lb break="no"/>penditure at its present level, we shall, as I have 
     <lb/>
     already pointed out, require at least $23 millions 
     <lb/>
     a year, and the more we can raise in excess of this 
     <lb/>
     figure, the better shall we be placed to undertake 
     <lb/>
     development projects. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have been asked if I would give to the mem<lb break="no"/>bers an estimate of the total national income of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. This is, of course, an important 
     <lb/>
     index by which to measure taxable capacity and 
     <lb/>
     I have always regretted that we are not so well 
     <lb/>
     equipped in Newfoundland as in some other 
     <lb/>
     countries to measure this factor, which is being 
     <lb/>
     used to an increasing extent for taxation pur<lb break="no"/>poses. The answer to the question can best be 
     <lb/>
     obtained by reference to the appendix on page 
     <lb/>
     528 of the survey, edited by Dr. MacKay, to 
     <lb/>
     which I have already referred. It will be noted that 
     <lb/>
     lack of adequate basic information has prevented 
     <lb/>
     the writer from making more than a rough es<lb break="no"/>timate and has compelled him to make it with 
     <lb/>
     reference to a pre-war period. His estimate 
     <lb/>
     amounted to approximately $45 millions per 
     <lb/>
     annum, which he suggests had been doubled 
     <lb/>
     during the war. I do not know whether any of the 
     <lb/>
     members present are familiar with the intricacies 
     <lb/>
     of calculation of national income according to the 
     <lb/>
     formulae normally employed. It is a very compli<lb break="no"/>cated business and no statistical calculations can 
     <lb/>
     be of much value unless adequate and accurate 
     <lb/>
     basic information is available. It is certainly not 
     <lb/>
     available in Newfoundland at the present time 
     <lb/>
     and the only practical way of getting down to the 
     <lb/>
     task would probably be to take samples of in 
     <lb/>
     dividual incomes of cross-sections of the com<lb break="no"/>munity as a basis to work on. One of our greatest 
     <lb/>
     difficulties in obtaining basic statistics in New<lb break="no"/>foundland has been the reluctance and suspicion 
     <lb/>
     of the persons called upon to give the necessary 
     <lb/>
     information, and it will need something in the 
     <lb/>
     nature of an educational campaign before we can 
     <lb/>
     obtain the data which we require for the purposes 
     <lb/>
     we are considering. Our difficulties are all the 
     <lb/>
     greater because of our scattered population and 
     <lb/>
     because such a large proportion of our population 
     <lb/>
     work as individuals rather than as wage-earners 
     <lb/>
     in industrial undertakings. I might add that not<lb break="no"/>withstanding these difficulties we have been con<lb break="no"/>sidering whether we could enlist technical 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     assistance to carry out a survey of the kind which 
     <lb/>
     would be required, and I hope that it will be 
     <lb/>
     possible, in due course, to give a closer estimate, 
     <lb/>
     though I am afraid it will still be merely a rough 
     <lb/>
     estimate, of our national income. I should like to 
     <lb/>
     make it clear that, although our statistical infor<lb break="no"/>mation has not reached the standards we desire, 
     <lb/>
     it is nevertheless much more complete than it was 
     <lb/>
     a few years ago. We have indeed made consider 
     <lb/>
     able advance in this direction and, moreover, we 
     <lb/>
     have greatly improved the methods of collating 
     <lb/>
     the information obtained. Returns of imports and 
     <lb/>
     exports are, for example, now produced quarterly 
     <lb/>
     and much more promptly than formerly. I have 
     <lb/>
     brought with me a copy of those for the quarter 
     <lb/>
     ended 31 March, 1946, which members can ex<lb break="no"/>amine if they wish. I should be pleased indeed to 
     <lb/>
     arrange for any members who so wish to see the 
     <lb/>
     very modern and extremely interesting machines 
     <lb/>
     which we have installed in the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Finance for statistical and other purposes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There is no doubt that our taxable capacity has 
     <lb/>
     increased considerably since before the war. The 
     <lb/>
     country is stronger in a number of ways and a 
     <lb/>
     good deal of money has been spent in the reor<lb break="no"/>ganization and improvement of the fisheries, but 
     <lb/>
     there is still room for considerable development, 
     <lb/>
     as the chairman of the Fisheries Board pointed 
     <lb/>
     out the other day. To increase our standards of 
     <lb/>
     living we must, of course, increase our output per 
     <lb/>
     capita. Although we cannot expect the price of 
     <lb/>
     fish to continue at its present level, there are 
     <lb/>
     promising signs, such as the activities of the 
     <lb/>
     International Food Organisation, which suggest 
     <lb/>
     that a determined effort will be made to stabilise 
     <lb/>
     prices and to ensure that primary producers are 
     <lb/>
     given a fairer deal than they often were in the 
     <lb/>
     past. We have a number of promising new in<lb break="no"/>dustries, such as the canning factory which is 
     <lb/>
     being installed on the west coast, and the 
     <lb/>
     prospects of the paper and logging industries, for 
     <lb/>
     the next few years at any rate, are distinctly 
     <lb/>
     bright: the companies concerned are looking for 
     <lb/>
     additional labour. The future in regard to mining 
     <lb/>
     is not quite so clear, but work is steady at the 
     <lb/>
     present. We also have to take into account the 
     <lb/>
     several thousands of men engaged in steady 
     <lb/>
     employment at the American bases and the 
     <lb/>
     Gander and Goose airports. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In assessing, on this very broad basis, prospec<lb break="no"/>tive levels of production, to which our taxable 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="44"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0044.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">44</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw>

       capacity is closely  related, we must also bear in 
     <lb/>
     mind the stronger position of the country by 
     <lb/>
     reason of accumulated savings, both personal and 
     <lb/>
     corporate, to which reference is made in tables 4 
     <lb/>
     and 5 appended to the White Paper. These 
     <lb/>
     savings should ensure for some years to come a 
     <lb/>
     steady demand for goods and services and act as 
     <lb/>
     a most valuable buffer against the effects of pos<lb break="no"/>sible depression. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As you are aware, we have considerably in<lb break="no"/>creased direct taxation during the war, and it now 
     <lb/>
     amounts to more than half the yield from customs 
     <lb/>
     duties, on which we used mainly to depend. Some 
     <lb/>
     revision of our tariff will undoubtedly be neces<lb break="no"/>sary as the result of international trade discus<lb break="no"/>sions which have been under consideration for 
     <lb/>
     some time and which are now scheduled to start 
     <lb/>
     next month. We shall, of course, endeavour to 
     <lb/>
     secure more favoured treatment for the entry of 
     <lb/>
     our produce into other countries but, at the same 
     <lb/>
     time, we shall be expected to make concessions 
     <lb/>
     in return. Until these negotiations have reached a 
     <lb/>
     more advanced stage, it will be impossible to 
     <lb/>
     assess the effect on our yield from customs duties 
     <lb/>
     but, in any event, we must be prepared for some 
     <lb/>
     reduction in this source of revenue, as our tariff 
     <lb/>
     is undoubtedly still heavy on certain classes of 
     <lb/>
     commodity, although, as you will see from para<lb break="no"/>graph 17 of the white paper, during the last 12 
     <lb/>
     years the average rate of duty over all imports has 
     <lb/>
     been reduced from 36.5 to 25.5 per cent. We can, 
     <lb/>
     I think, expect some increase in revenue from the 
     <lb/>
     Department of Posts and Telegraphs as its 
     <lb/>
     telecommunication services are improved and 
     <lb/>
     extended. On the other hand, we must be 
     <lb/>
     prepared for some decline in the revenue from the 
     <lb/>
     Board of Liquor Control, as a falling off in con<lb break="no"/>sumption above the war time levels is already 
     <lb/>
     taking place. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I should like next to refer briefly to the public 
     <lb/>
     debt. You will find a statement of the debt and 
     <lb/>
     sinking funds as at 31 March last on page 35<!-- GL, 2017-02-14, commented this out because it does not seem useful, and footnote below: 1 --> of 
     <lb/>
     the White Paper. This includes both the sterling 
     <lb/>
     debt, and the local loans of $1,500,600 (3.75%), 
     <lb/>
     $1.5 million (3.25%) and of $2 million (3%) 
     <lb/>
     raised in 1940, 1942 and 1943, respectively. 
     <lb/>
     Since that date we have paid further annual sink<lb break="no"/>ing fund instalments of £177,950 and $41,250 on 
     <lb/>
     the sterling 3% guaranteed stock and on the dollar 
     <lb/>
    3.75% war loans, respectively, so that the net 
     <lb/>
       
            <!--<p>IVolume 11:45. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            <cb/>
         
     figure of $82,188,000 shown in the statement 
     <lb/>
     must be reduced by these amounts. If we allow 
     <lb/>
     for the recent 10% appreciation in the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     dollar and interest accrued on sinking funds since 
     <lb/>
     31 March, the net debt is now reduced to the 
     <lb/>
     equivalent of approximately $73,876,000. As is 
     <lb/>
     mentioned in the memorandum on reconstruction 
     <lb/>
     and development schemes, we have recently set 
     <lb/>
     aside, at interest, an amount of £800,000 (ap<lb break="no"/>proximately $3.2 million), to meet the repayment 
     <lb/>
     of the two remaining sterling trustee stocks which 
     <lb/>
     mature in 1950 and 1952, respectively. This sum 
     <lb/>
     was obtained from the government of the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom as the first repayment of the loans 
     <lb/>
     totalling $12.3 million which we made as a 
     <lb/>
     voluntary contribution to the war effort in the 
     <lb/>
     years 1941- 1944. The balance of these loans still 
     <lb/>
     due to us by the government of the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom is now approximately $9. 1 million, and 
     <lb/>
     applying the repayment of $3.2 million to the 
     <lb/>
     reduction of debt, the total amount of our public 
     <lb/>
     debt is reduced still further to $70.5 millions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>This figure excludes a 2.5% loan to the rail<lb break="no"/>way arranged in 1941 from the Defence Supplies 
     <lb/>Corporation of the United States for the purchase 
     <lb/>of equipment, of which the balance outstanding 
     <lb/>is now $1,493,000. It also excludes the value of 
     <lb/>unredeemed savings certificates, amounting to 
     <lb/>some $2,257,000, out of total issues of 
     <lb/>$3,103,000, since we have balances set aside to 
     <lb/>meet in full the government's liability in respect 
     <lb/>of these certificates. Out of the proceeds of 
     <lb/>savings certificates, we lent $1,800,000 to the 
     <lb/>United Kingdom (part of the $12,300,000 I have 
     <lb/>already mentioned), which will be available 
     <lb/>when we want it. The balance required to meet 
     <lb/>outstanding certificates is on deposit, at interest, 
     <lb/>at the Bank of Montreal, St. John's; this is the 
     <lb/>source from which current redemptions are met. 
     <lb/>At the end of March, 1946, we had an accumu<lb break="no"/>lated revenue surplus of $28,669,000. Of this, 
     <lb/>$10.5 million was loaned to the government of 
     <lb/>the United Kingdom (since reduced by the repay<lb break="no"/>ment of $3.2 million to provide for the redemp<lb break="no"/>tion of the two sterling securities I have 
     <lb/>mentioned). The balance, apart from some 
     <lb/>$240,000 used to finance the payment of allot<lb break="no"/>ments, etc, of men serving overseas with the 
     <lb/>imperial forces, was deposited at interest at the 
     <lb/>Bank of Montreal. I should explain, however, 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="45"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-09-19_Page_0045.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">September 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">45</fw>
           
     that additional advances in respect of similar 
     <lb/>
     agency services, have been made by the bank on 
     <lb/>
     a guaranteed overdraft basis, instead of being the 
     <lb/>
     subject of issues from the exchequer. The amount 
     <lb/>
     of such outstanding advances at the present time 
     <lb/>
     is approximately $1.2 million. They will be 
     <lb/>
     cleared as soon as audited accounts are rendered 
     <lb/>
     by the Newfoundland departments concerned to 
     <lb/>
     the service departments in the United Kingdom, 
     <lb/>
     who, I might add, have been pressing for these 
     <lb/>
     accounts as they are anxious to clear them as soon 
     <lb/>
     as possible. This matter is well in hand and I am 
     <lb/>
     informed that a large batch of audited accounts 
     <lb/>
     has been despatched to the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     during the past week. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I understand that the Convention wishes to 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
          
     have further information regarding the 1% sink<lb break="no"/>ing fund on the 3% guaranteed stock. The annual 
     <lb/>
     payment, as shown in the published estimates, is 
     <lb/>
     the figure of £177,950 which I have already 
     <lb/>
     quoted. It has been paid every June since 1938, 
     <lb/>
     when the first payment became due, to the trus<lb break="no"/>tees to invest the sinking fund contributions in the 
     <lb/>
     guaranteed stock, as well as the interest which 
     <lb/>
     they receive on the sinking fund investments. In 
     <lb/>
     addition to the statement in the white paper, you 
     <lb/>
     will find this information in the accounts publish<lb break="no"/>ed with the Comptroller and Auditor General's 
     <lb/>
     report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[It was agreed that Mr. Wild would be requested 
     <lb/>
     to meet the Convention again on September 24. 
     <lb/>
     The Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-02-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     September 20, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     [Requests for information were tabled by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Northcott, Mr. Hickman, Mr. Higgins, Mr. Fog- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     will, Mr. Walton, Mr. Jackman, Mr. Fowler, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McCormack, and Mr. Cashin] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Arising out of the minutes and 
     <lb/>
     pursuant to your resolution, an invitation was 
     <lb/>
     extended to the Hon. the Commissioner for 
     <lb/>
     Finance to attend before you in private session on 
     <lb/>
     Tuesday at 4 o'clock. Further, I received an in<lb break="no"/>timation from His Excellency that he will be 
     <lb/>
     pleased to receive a delegation from the National 
     <lb/>
     Convention at 11 o'clock on tomorrow at 
     <lb/>
     Government House for the purpose of presenting 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     to His Excellency addresses of loyalty to His 
     <lb/>
     Majesty the King and of thanks to His Excellen<lb break="no"/>cy. I submit that you might appoint a delegation 
     <lb/>
     at once. I think that perhaps Mr. Job as convenor 
     <lb/>
     of that committee might suggest a delegation. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Job I do not suppose it is possible for the 
     <lb/>whole of the Convention to be received, and in 
     <lb/>that event I would suggest the committee that 
     <lb/>drafted the addresses would be appointed. I make 
     <lb/>that as a motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Vardy I second that motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The motion carried unanimously] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Report of the Steering Committee[1] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Bradley Copies of this report are on the 
     <lb/>
     desks of the members and I presume you have 
     <lb/>
     read them. It will be unnecessary for me to read 
     <lb/>
     them formally. I would draw your attention to 
     <lb/>
     section 2. It is recommended that the work of the 
     <lb/>
     Convention be divided up into nine committees, 
     <lb/>
     each consisting of ten men. We have en<lb break="no"/>deavoured to apportion the work of the members 
     <lb/>
     as best we could in order to balance them. These 
     <lb/>
     committees will be appointed by the Chairman in 
     <lb/>
     accordance with the schedule which is attached 
     <lb/>
     to this report and which sets out the various 
     <lb/>
     committees and members of each. As each mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the Convention sits on two committees, we 
     <lb/>
     suggested a schedule which provides that each 
     <lb/>
     committee meets three times a week. That does 
     <lb/>
     not mean that the committees cannot meet of<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <p>[l]Volume II:445. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     tener. They may meet at night. Section 4 provides 
     <lb/>
     that the chairman of each committee is to be one 
     <lb/>
     of the members of the Steering Committee, in 
     <lb/>
     order that there might be a connection between 
     <lb/>
     the Steering Committee and each sub-committee. 
     <lb/>
     As there are only seven members on the Steering 
     <lb/>
     Committee and there are nine committees, it is 
     <lb/>
     obvious, at present, that two chairmen are not 
     <lb/>
     members of the Steering Committee. It has there<lb break="no"/>fore been suggested we should ask your leave to 
     <lb/>
     add to the Steering Committee accordingly. It is 
     <lb/>
     proposed that the work begin at once. It will be 
     <lb/>
     apparent that very little in the form of formal 
     <lb/>
     meetings of the Convention will take place, and 
     <lb/>
     it was thought advisable that after we meet the 
     <lb/>
     Commissioner for Finance on Tuesday there 
     <lb/>
     should be an adjournment taken, and that we 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>