<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-11-04" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-11-04">4 November 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
 
         
          <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="128" to="150"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0128.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0129.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0130.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0131.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0132.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0133.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0134.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0135.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0136.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0137.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0138.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0139.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0140.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0141.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0142.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0143.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0144.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0145.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0146.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0147.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0148.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0149.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0150.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-02-23">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-07">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0128">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0128.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0129">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0129.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0130">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0130.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0131">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0131.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0132">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0132.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0133">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0133.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0134">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0134.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0135">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0135.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0136">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0136.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0137">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0137.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0138">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0138.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0139">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0139.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0140">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0140.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0141">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0141.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0142">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0142.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0143">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0143.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0144">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0144.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0145">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0145.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0146">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0146.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0147">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0147.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0148">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0148.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0149">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0149.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0150">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0150.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="128" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0128.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">128</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
            
<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">November 4, 1946<lb/>
            </head>



            <head rendition="simple:centre">Motion to send a Delegation to Ottawa<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref></head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> I had no intention of delivering <lb/> any
                  lengthy or prepared speech upon this resolu<lb break="no"/>tion. It seemed so
                  clearly the right thing to do that <lb/> the bitter opposition which it has
                  encountered <lb/> appeared impossible. But, unfortunately, the <lb/> debate has
                  wandered far afield. It has been made <lb/> the occasion of confessions of
                  political faith and <lb/> expressions of antagonism to this and that form <lb/> of
                  government. It has even degenerated into an <lb/> orgy of indecent imputation, low
                  insinuations, <lb/> sour invective and what may perhaps be charitab<lb break="no"/>ly described as plain misrepresentation. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Some months ago, in a broadcast to the people 
     <lb/>
     of this country, I offered the opinion that this 
     <lb/>
     Convention was a bench of judges rather than a 
     <lb/>
     body of partisans. I am more confirmed today that 
     <lb/>
     my interpretation of its function was and is still 
     <lb/>
     right. There is something incongruous in the as<lb break="no"/>sociation of either eloquence or tub-thumping 
     <lb/>
     with matters and problems of finance and 
     <lb/>
     economics, of addition and subtraction, multi<lb break="no"/>plication and division. Figures do at times speak 
     <lb/>
     eloquently, but they speak quietly. We are con<lb break="no"/>cerned principally with figures. We have to as<lb break="no"/>certain the financial and economic position and 
     <lb/>
     prospects of this country, and whether under the 
     <lb/>
     tutelage of Britain, as an autonomous state, or in 
     <lb/>
     partnership with the provinces of Canada, lies the 
     <lb/>
     greatest probability of relegating the six cent dole 
     <lb/>
     of pre-war days into the realm of unpleasant and 
     <lb/>
     eventually traditional memories. In the welter of 
     <lb/>
     irrelevant and dubious eloquence the real issues 
     <lb/>
     have sometimes been wholly submerged. Can we 
     <lb/>
     not forget these confusing side-issues and con<lb break="no"/>fine ourselves strictly to the question upon which 
     <lb/>
     we have shortly to vote, bearing in mind that we 
     <lb/>
     must vote as judges, cooly, impartially, and calm<lb break="no"/>ly, and not as partisans in heat and in passion? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     What is this question? Briefly, it is a proposal 
     <lb/>
     that a delegation be sent to learn the terms and 
     <lb/>
     conditions of the confederation of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     with Canada. Obviously it is not a discussion of 
     <lb/>
     the merits or demerits of confederation; and yet 
     <lb/>
     we have been told of the allowance offered by 
     <lb/>
     Canada in respect of our public debt in 1895, and 
     <lb/>
     of a computation of what we should get in the 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
            
   
          
     same connection today. The amount mentioned 
     <lb/>
     was some $300 million. Again, we were in<lb break="no"/>formed of fabulous prices obtained for fishery 
     <lb/>
     products in Canada. Were these gentlemen un<lb break="no"/>consciously advocating confederation? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Again it has been suggested that the delega<lb break="no"/>tion might explore the question of tariffs and 
     <lb/>
     other matters affecting the general relations be<lb break="no"/>tween Canada and an independent Newfound<lb break="no"/>land. Surely it is clear that such investigations are 
     <lb/>
     wholly without the jurisdiction of this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion and obviously beyond the scope of any 
     <lb/>
     delegation's activities. None of these things has 
     <lb/>
     anything to do with the resolution before the 
     <lb/>
     Chair. The proposal is simply that this delegation 
     <lb/>
     endeavour to obtain facts, the terms or conditions 
     <lb/>
     of union which would be acceptable to the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada, if the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland approved of such union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is true that in the course of these explora<lb break="no"/>tions and inquiries much further, and valuable, 
     <lb/>
     information would be obtained — the normal 
     <lb/>
     functioning of the Canadian system, the actual 
     <lb/>
     relations existing between the federal and provin<lb break="no"/>cial authorities, and other matters of which I 
     <lb/>
     know little or nothing as yet. Nor is the delegation 
     <lb/>
     in any sense entitled or empowered to negotiate 
     <lb/>
     an agreement or in any way to bind even its own 
     <lb/>
     members, much less the Convention, and least of 
     <lb/>
     all, the people of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Today I am neither Commissionite nor anti- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Commissionite, neither friend nor foe of respon<lb break="no"/>sible government, neither confederate nor 
     <lb/>
     anti-confederate. I have not the facts upon which 
     <lb/>
     I may arrive at any reasoned and reasonable 
     <lb/>
     conclusion. The facts of one of these forms of 
     <lb/>
     government can only be obtained by sending a 
     <lb/>
     delegation to discuss the matter with the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government. I want those facts. I 
     <lb/>
     demand them. I refuse to offer any opinion on any 
     <lb/>
     form of government till I get them. And even 
     <lb/>
     more important is that the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland should have them. The people must 
     <lb/>
     within the next few months decide their destinies 
     <lb/>
     at the polls. Any recommendation we may make 
     <lb/>
     is but advisory. Their decision is final and ir<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_01">[1] See p.93, 104, 120. [Debate Days, 1946 10-28, 10-29, 10-30] </note><pb n="129" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0129.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">129</fw>revocable. It would be nothing short of a criminal 
     <lb/>
     dereliction of duty on our part to leave any 
     <lb/>
     avenue of information unexplored. And let me 
     <lb/>
     say this: that not only do I approve of the sending 
     <lb/>
     of this delegation to Canada, but that I am equally 
     <lb/>
     insistent that steps should be taken to obtain from 
     <lb/>
     the United Kingdom a statement as to what finan<lb break="no"/>cial and other assistance they would be prepared 
     <lb/>
     to offer us in case of need. I do not suggest that 
     <lb/>
     we should send a delegation to the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom. I do not think that is necessary. The 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom government is the government 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland and we can communicate with 
     <lb/>
     them either through His Excellency the Governor 
     <lb/>
     or through their agents, the Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government here. If the Government of the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom should deem it proper that we 
     <lb/>
     should then send a delegation to England, by all 
     <lb/>
     means let us send that delegation; but I want it 
     <lb/>
     clearly understood that should any resolution to 
     <lb/>
     send a delegation be brought in here, I shall not 
     <lb/>
     oppose it. I do not consider it the right way to 
     <lb/>
     initiate the acquiring of this information from the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom, but I shall take no steps to place 
     <lb/>
     anything in the way of such a delegation going 
     <lb/>
     immediately. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And now as to the timing of this delegation's 
     <lb/>
     visit. There has been much nervousness and fear 
     <lb/>
     expressed over the prematurity of this resolution. 
     <lb/>
     Whether these fears arise out of lack of 
     <lb/>
     knowledge of the real situation, or out of a panic- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     stricken desire to exclude information about any 
     <lb/>
     form of government which might endanger the 
     <lb/>
     position of that form to which their closed minds 
     <lb/>
     cling with fanatical tenacity, I do not know. But 
     <lb/>
     it is clearly their desire to delay any examination 
     <lb/>
     of confederation facts for a considerable period. 
     <lb/>
     That attitude tends to create the impression that 
     <lb/>
     the appointment of a delegation now would result 
     <lb/>
     in an immediate rush to Ottawa by such a delega<lb break="no"/>tion. If anything even remotely approaching a 
     <lb/>
     resemblance to such a proceeding exists in the 
     <lb/>
     mind of any delegate, the fact would not even be 
     <lb/>
     humorous. It would be deplorable Nothing is 
     <lb/>
     further from the truth. Conferences and discus<lb break="no"/>sions between governments and public bodies are 
     <lb/>
     not conducted in that way. Let us briefly review 
     <lb/>
     the probable course of procedure. The resolution, 
     <lb/>
     if adopted, would at once be sent to the Governor, 
     <lb/>
     or to the Commission of Government, who in turn 
     <lb/>
     would communicate with the Dominions Office. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     The latter would then get in touch with the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada. That government has 
     <lb/>
     already indicated in the House of Commons that 
     <lb/>
     it would be willing to meet a delegation of this 
     <lb/>
     Convention. In all probability, the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government would either suggest a suitable time 
     <lb/>
     or enquire what date would be agreeable to us. 
     <lb/>
     Thus the timing of the delegation's departure 
     <lb/>
     from Newfoundland would be delayed for a con<lb break="no"/>siderable period. Does anyone in this Convention 
     <lb/>
     imagine that any delegation of its members 
     <lb/>
     would have the temerity, or even the discourtesy 
     <lb/>
     to rush off to Ottawa at any time without first 
     <lb/>
     advising this body? And is anyone here under the 
     <lb/>
     impression that any sane body of delegates would 
     <lb/>
     depart upon such a mission without much pre<lb break="no"/>vious preparation right here in St. John's? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Their very method of approach to the subject 
     <lb/>
     will have to be very carefully considered, for they 
     <lb/>
     will have in their keeping the dignity of this land 
     <lb/>
     of ours. Newfoundland must not be placed in the 
     <lb/>
     position of a supplicant. They will have to com<lb break="no"/>pile a considerable amount of factual material for 
     <lb/>
     possible reference during their stay in Canada's 
     <lb/>
     capital. They will have many conferences with 
     <lb/>
     the departments of government here, for it is 
     <lb/>
     elementary that, before leaving it will be impera<lb break="no"/>tive that they prepare figures estimating closely: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. The amount of public service expenditures 
     <lb/>
     which will be lifted from our shoulders by the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion govemment's assumption of responsi<lb break="no"/>bility for the Railway and its subsidiaries, the 
     <lb/>
     postal telegraph services, and other items for 
     <lb/>
     which our revenue is now liable. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. The sources and amounts of our present 
     <lb/>
     revenue which will remain to us as a province 
     <lb/>
     when the Dominion takes over customs, income 
     <lb/>
     and other taxes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. The amount of revenue which will be re<lb break="no"/>quired to carry on the remaining public services 
     <lb/>
     which will still be our responsibility — educa<lb break="no"/>tion, public health and the like. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     These are a few subjects upon which much 
     <lb/>
     information must be carefully compiled and 
     <lb/>
     many others will occupy many days of work in 
     <lb/>
     close collaboration with the ablest officials of the 
     <lb/>
     public service, some of whom, by reason of their 
     <lb/>
     intimate knowledge of departmental affairs, will 
     <lb/>
     have to accompany the delegation to Ottawa. The 
     <lb/>
     early appointment of this delegation could not 
     <lb/>
     possibly result in their arrival at Ottawa much 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="130" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0130.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">130</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
           
     before the middle of December, and it might 
     <lb/>
     easily be early in the New Year before they could 
     <lb/>
     leave. So, it seems clear that if we are to arrive at 
     <lb/>
     sound conclusions, based upon all the facts, and 
     <lb/>
     communicate our recommendations to the 
     <lb/>
     Dominions Office in time to enable the British 
     <lb/>
     Parliament to deal with them before the Easter 
     <lb/>
     recess of next year, we must act on this resolution 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">now</hi>. There is no advantage to be gained by delay. 
     <lb/>
     There is a probability of serious harm. The 
     <lb/>
     people, whether confederate or anti-confederate 
     <lb/>
     (and there are many of the former in New<lb break="no"/>foundland today), want this information. Many 
     <lb/>
     are anxiously awaiting it. Shall we take the 
     <lb/>
     responsibility of balking that desire? Shall we 
     <lb/>
     refuse them that information, or even delay it? 
     <lb/>
     Have we the right to place any obstacles in the 
     <lb/>
     way of the disclosure of any truth to which the 
     <lb/>
     people are entitled? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In 1933 the Amulree report was concealed 
     <lb/>
     from the people until within a few days of the 
     <lb/>
     opening of the legislature which destroyed their 
     <lb/>
     freedom, and many knew little or nothing of the 
     <lb/>
     scheme to degrade them for their misfortunes 
     <lb/>
     until their liberties had passed into history. Shall 
     <lb/>
     we be parties to even a temporary suppression of 
     <lb/>
     the facts, whether of confederation or anything 
     <lb/>
     else? If we destroy this motion, or even delay it, 
     <lb/>
     we shall be guilty of just that. There are those in 
     <lb/>
     this land, and perhaps in this House, who would 
     <lb/>
     recklessly prevent the examination of every form 
     <lb/>
     of government which lies outside the limits of 
     <lb/>
     their own narrow notions, whose minds are firm<lb break="no"/>ly lashed to the chariot wheel of a single political 
     <lb/>
     system, whose judgement is impaired by the nar<lb break="no"/>rowness and restrictions of their mental horizons, 
     <lb/>
     who talk wildly that this or that form of govern<lb break="no"/>ment will only come to Newfoundland over their 
     <lb/>
     dead bodies Are these the men whose lead we 
     <lb/>
     shall follow down the blind alley of obstruction 
     <lb/>
     to the search for truth? Or shall we take the road 
     <lb/>
     which leads to the facts, the evidence, the infor<lb break="no"/>mation which we, as representatives of the 
     <lb/>
     people, are bound to lay before them without 
     <lb/>
     unnecessary delay, and upon which they must 
     <lb/>
     ponder and decide their destinies? ....
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In good faith, it has been suggested that this 
     <lb/>
     matter should be deferred until we know the 
     <lb/>
     details of our financial position. What connection 
     <lb/>
     is there between the two? How is the determina<lb break="no"/>tion of the one dependent upon the ascertainment 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     of the other? Early action upon this resolution 
     <lb/>
     will not bring the terms of confederation to the 
     <lb/>
     people before the last of January next, and that is 
     <lb/>
     delay enough. In the final analysis, even if our 
     <lb/>
     present financial position is found to be fairly 
     <lb/>
     satisfactory, is that the last word? Is it suggested 
     <lb/>
     that in such case no inquiries are to be made of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, or of the United Kingdom or of anyone? 
     <lb/>
     Are we then bound to walk this chaotic world 
     <lb/>
     alone? Are the people to have no choice? That 
     <lb/>
     would be a repetition of the vicious scheme of 
     <lb/>
     1933. It would be a clear breach of fundamental 
     <lb/>
     political morality. It would violate, nay, it would 
     <lb/>
     defeat both the spirit and the letter of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion Act of 1946. It would be an arrogant deter<lb break="no"/>mination of the people's destinies in the dark, a 
     <lb/>
     determination which would be bitterly resented 
     <lb/>
     by them, for the supporters of responsible 
     <lb/>
     government are not in an overwhelming majority 
     <lb/>
     in this country today. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But I am not without sympathy for those who 
     <lb/>
     fear precipitate action. I can understand their 
     <lb/>
     desire to avoid mistakes. These fears are ground<lb break="no"/>less. The delegation should be selected at an early 
     <lb/>
     date. Their early departure for Ottawa is definite<lb break="no"/>ly impossible. In any case it is not essential. In 
     <lb/>
     order to eliminate all uncertainty, I propose at the 
     <lb/>
     proper stage in this debate to offer another 
     <lb/>
     amendment which will ensure that the delegation 
     <lb/>
     shall not leave St. John's before the first day of 
     <lb/>
     January, 1947. That should, I think, meet the 
     <lb/>
     views of all but the irreconcilables. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In conclusion, it is my earnest wish and sin<lb break="no"/>cere hope that before voting upon this question 
     <lb/>
     every member of this Convention will bring to 
     <lb/>
     bear upon it the full strength of his intellect, 
     <lb/>
     backed by an irresistible urge to seek the truth; 
     <lb/>
     that we shall purge our minds of all passion and 
     <lb/>
     prejudice, all party and personal allegiances, all 
     <lb/>
     enthusiasms and all antagonisms. Let us dis<lb break="no"/>charge this solemn duty; let us reach a decision 
     <lb/>
     upon this, as upon all other questions, in cool, 
     <lb/>
     impartial and reasoned judgement. Let us render 
     <lb/>
     our decision upon the resolution now at our hands 
     <lb/>
     as a bench of judges, and not as a body of par<lb break="no"/>tisans. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:KENN3">Mr. Kennedy</persName> This House was resolved into <lb/> nine
                  committees with one main object in view, to <lb/> produce for Convention members,
                  and the <lb/> people, a detailed general summary of our <lb/> country's standing
                  in such form as to avoid con<lb break="no"/><pb n="131" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0131.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">131</fw>fusion, and at the same time give us a general <lb/> basis
                  on which to either form the groundwork for, <lb/> or reach our decisions. Hitherto
                  these committees <lb/> have worked both energetically and smoothly <lb/> towards
                  their goal, without which any decisions <lb/> cannot logically be even considered,
                  unless pre<lb break="no"/>vious bias exists. Surely, should the ultimate <lb/>
                  summary prove our beloved country to be finan<lb break="no"/>cially and
                  economically independent, any <lb/> delegation to anywhere would be both futile
                  and <lb/> a further source of expense to a country which <lb/> has already been
                  exploited to a disgusting extent. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Such interruption as this motion would in<lb break="no"/>evitably entail is both untimely and at the present 
     <lb/>stage of procedure more than impracticable In<lb break="no"/>deed I go so far as to say such action to my mind 
     <lb/>strongly suggests sabotage — at whose instiga<lb break="no"/>tion it is within my power to think, butnot to state. 
     <lb/>In consequence, as an ex-service New<lb break="no"/>foundlander, whose one aim is the freedom of my 
     <lb/>country for which I fought, I see no other possible 
     <lb/>outlet than to support the amendment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HANN1">Mr. Hannon</persName> My first vote in this National Con<lb break="no"/>vention is not going to be a silent one. The intro<lb break="no"/>duction of the
                  proposal brings back to my mind <lb/>the old story — confederation, a bugaboo
                  which <lb/>lies dormant in this country until rumour has it <lb/>that an election
                  is in the offing. Since our last <lb/>general election in 1932 up to 1946 the word
                  was <lb/>seldom if every heard. <lb/>
               </p>

    

            <p>
     Some delegates have made the broad state<lb break="no"/>ment that confederation is a very live issue over 
     <lb/>
     the greater part of this country. I have no 
     <lb/>
     authority to speak, except for a small section of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, the district which sent me here, 
     <lb/>
     where I may say confederation is anything but a 
     <lb/>
     live issue. However, I can speak from an ex<lb break="no"/>perience gained by me when acting as employ<lb break="no"/>ment manager at Gander from 1940 to 1944. 
     <lb/>
     During that time I passed through my hands 
     <lb/>
     thousands of men coming to work from all over 
     <lb/>
     the island, and not once did I hear one of these 
     <lb/>
     men say anything in favour of confederation. But 
     <lb/>
     after our men had lived with the Canadians and 
     <lb/>
     had exchanged opinions, I found that whatever 
     <lb/>
     sentiments they had had before, they were cer<lb break="no"/>tainly unfavourable afterwards. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am going to vote against the original motion 
     <lb/>
     and for the amendment proposed by Mr. Penney, 
     <lb/>
     for the following reasons: this is not the time to 
     <lb/>
     send a delegation to Ottawa, or anywhere else 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     — our work as a fact-finding organisation has 
     <lb/>
     only just begun. When the work which we were 
     <lb/>
     sent here to do is accomplished, and we are ready 
     <lb/>
     to submit our official reports to the country, then 
     <lb/>
     will be time enough to send envoys to outside 
     <lb/>
     nations, if indeed it is even then found necessary 
     <lb/>
     to do so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Mr. Chairman, I would like to <lb/> say that I am
                  not in favour of confederation with <lb/> Canada, nor with anyone. I am a
                     Newfound<lb break="no"/>lander, proud of my heritage, proud of my fore<lb break="no"/>bears. I believe in my country and my countrymen. <lb/> I am
                  satisfied with nothing less than that our <lb/> country should be restored to its
                  former position, <lb/> a self-governing dominion within the Common<lb break="no"/>wealth of Nations, the cornerstone of the British <lb/> Empire. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I had no intention at this time to state my mind 
     <lb/>
     here in this House. I have already done so in 
     <lb/>
     public, but because of this resolution I am forced 
     <lb/>
     to partly state what I was sent here for. I am the 
     <lb/>
     only delegate who was sent here on a definite 
     <lb/>
     policy for Newfoundland. I am not going to talk 
     <lb/>
     possible forms of government now. I merely wish 
     <lb/>
     to say that I speak for the common people.... I 
     <lb/>
     speak for a woman who came to my home shortly 
     <lb/>
     before I came on this Convention, and asked me 
     <lb/>
     to go into her house and view the circumstances 
     <lb/>
     under which she had to live — a shack of about 
     <lb/>
     18 feet by 24 feet, and there were in that shack 16 
     <lb/>
     human beings, half of them with TB, living like 
     <lb/>
     cattle. I speak for a man who worked 45 years for 
     <lb/>
     a company, and is thrown onto the scrap heap and 
     <lb/>
     has to take a net pension of $8 a month. I speak 
     <lb/>
     for the countless numbers of young children in 
     <lb/>
     my own district who are barred in from October 
     <lb/>
     until the sun shines again next spring, because 
     <lb/>
     they have not sufficient clothing to wear. These 
     <lb/>
     are the people I speak for, and I have a definite 
     <lb/>
     idea of what form of government Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     needs; but I feel Newfoundland must first get 
     <lb/>
     back her responsible government before we can 
     <lb/>
     go further. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I can continue talking on these lines, but I do 
     <lb/>
     not wish to obstruct the proceedings of this 
     <lb/>
     House. I said before I am not here to waste time, 
     <lb/>
     notwithstanding that $15 a day is big money for 
     <lb/>
     the labouring man. In conclusion I would like to 
     <lb/>
     ask the advocates of confederation with Canada 
     <lb/>
     this question, I would like to know the answer 
     <lb/>
     from them, and the country would like to know 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="132" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0132.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">132</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
          
     as well, why do 25,000 Canadians leave Canada 
     <lb/>
     yearly to go to the United States? Mr. Chairman 
     <lb/>
     and gentlemen I stand to support the amendment. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIGA1">Mr. Figary</persName> ....I have followed the debate on the <lb/>resolution
                  presented by Mr. Smallwood to this <lb/>Convention, and I do not object to the
                  principle <lb/>involved in the resolution; I feel we should have <lb/>that
                  information, and all the information we can <lb/>get on any form of government. I
                  and the people <lb/>of my district want it, and we must get it, so we <lb/>can be
                  in a position to decide what form of <lb/>government will be best so as to give
                  our people <lb/>a square deal. A government for all citizens of <lb/>this country
                  and not for a few. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     In the past a lot of our people were given a 
     <lb/>
     rotten deal, they have been hungry and cold, and 
     <lb/>
     there is no doubt about that; I have been in homes 
     <lb/>
     and seen it. I have seen children crying for bread 
     <lb/>
     and none to give them, seen children and even 
     <lb/>
     adults use flour sacks in order to cover their 
     <lb/>
     nakedness. These people did not endure this be<lb break="no"/>cause they were too lazy to work; there was no 
     <lb/>
     work to be had, and those who did work were paid 
     <lb/>
     a shamefully low wage, and the fishermen 
     <lb/>
     received next to nothing for their fish, barely 
     <lb/>
     enough for an existence. There was nothing that 
     <lb/>
     could be done about it, as at that time organised 
     <lb/>
     labour got little assistance or recognition from 
     <lb/>
     any source, indeed it was frowned upon in many 
     <lb/>
     places. Since Commission of Government has 
     <lb/>
     controlled this country there has been a lot of 
     <lb/>
     improvement as regards recognition of organised 
     <lb/>
     labour. This does not mean that the government 
     <lb/>
     has in all cases favoured the organisation of the 
     <lb/>
     workers, there have been times when they op<lb break="no"/>posed and actually fought against the right of 
     <lb/>
     workers to organise and bargain collectively. In 
     <lb/>
     the main, however, they have generally en<lb break="no"/>couraged the idea of collective bargaining and 
     <lb/>
     have set up machinery whereby employer and 
     <lb/>
     employee can meet and discuss their difficulties. 
     <lb/>
     At the present, I am somewhat in favour of the 
     <lb/>
     present form of government until we can deter<lb break="no"/>mine a better form for Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There has been considerable debate on the 
     <lb/>
     resolution and I have the feeling the majority are 
     <lb/>
     in favour of the amendment presented by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Penney.... I want to associate myself with pre<lb break="no"/>vious speakers. I too came to this Convention 
     <lb/>
     with an open mind, and I shall vote only for that 
     <lb/>
     which I know will benefit the people of our 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
            
     country. I do not intend to be carried away or 
     <lb/>
     swayed by every wind and doctrine. I will vote 
     <lb/>
     on the vital issues of this Convention according 
     <lb/>
     to what I believe to be in the best interests of our 
     <lb/>
     country. I agree with the principle of this resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, and it's really too bad that it had to come up 
     <lb/>
     at this time. When the time is opportune, this 
     <lb/>
     Convention will not overlook this matter, and 
     <lb/>
     will obtain the terms on which Canada would 
     <lb/>
     receive us, or should I say, on which we would 
     <lb/>
     be willing for Canada to join us. A lot of time has 
     <lb/>
     been wasted on this matter, and I do not see any 
     <lb/>
     advantage in discussing it further.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     No person can carry me beyond what I deem 
     <lb/>
    advisable on this question. I can decide that when 
     <lb/>we have received and studied the terms of con<lb break="no"/>federation with Canada. I do not like people 
     <lb/>asking me how I am going to vote (I mean outside 
     <lb/>of this chamber), that's my business, and I am 
     <lb/>only going to be led by my own conscience, 
     <lb/>whether it's voting for confederation or any other 
     <lb/>form of government. I see no alternative but to 
     <lb/>vote for the amendment... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CRAN1">Mr. Cranford</persName> Mr. Chairman. while listening to <lb/>the debate on
                  the motion now before the House, <lb/>it has given me cause to ask the question,
                  are we <lb/>inconsistent? In other words, do we practise what <lb/>we preach? The
                  vote now pending will decide my <lb/>question. <lb/>
               </p>

    

            <p>
     When we had responsible government, it was 
     <lb/>
     very often considered that spending money on 
     <lb/>
     trips both local and foreign, together with other 
     <lb/>
     similar acts, would lead to the financial collapse 
     <lb/>
     of our country. That collapse did come. Respon<lb break="no"/>sible government was ousted from power and 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government took its place, and 
     <lb/>
     in the opinion of some of us the Commission has 
     <lb/>
     not lived up to expectations. Hence a National 
     <lb/>
     Convention has been inaugurated to investigate 
     <lb/>
     our country's economic and financial condition, 
     <lb/>
     and before we have got anywhere we are con<lb break="no"/>fronted with a resolution to send delegates to 
     <lb/>
     Canada to seek terms of confederation. In my 
     <lb/>
     opinion we are asked to favour the pleasure of a 
     <lb/>
     few gentlemen on ajoyride at the expense of the 
     <lb/>
     taxpayers. Now why do the same thing that past 
     <lb/>
     governments had done that we did not approve 
     <lb/>
     of? And why send a delegation anywhere out of 
     <lb/>
     the country at any time? Why not let our actions 
     <lb/>
     be an example for any future government? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let the terms of confederation be sought by all 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="133" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0133.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">133</fw>
          
     means if we think it necessary, but do it in an 
     <lb/>
     economic manner consistent with the impression 
     <lb/>
     we gave our constituents when seeking election. 
     <lb/>
     Let our wishes be known to the Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government, with the request that the govern<lb break="no"/>ment open negotiations immediately with the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government with the aim of securing 
     <lb/>
     the terms of confederation. Let it be done by mail 
     <lb/>
     instead of selecting a band of globe trotters. Sup<lb break="no"/>pose some person brought in a resolution ad<lb break="no"/>vocating this country be made part of an 
     <lb/>
     international zone comprising the three greatest 
     <lb/>
     English-speaking nations of the world, namely 
     <lb/>
     England, Canada and the United States of 
     <lb/>
     America, would not that person have reason to 
     <lb/>
     demand the same right and privilege as the person 
     <lb/>
     who brought in the motion now before us? .... If 
     <lb/>
     we mean what we say, that we will support every 
     <lb/>
     movement that would be in the best interest of 
     <lb/>
     our country, may I suggest we use a postage 
     <lb/>
     stamp instead of a railway ticket when we can get 
     <lb/>
     the same result. Do not let us be deceived in 
     <lb/>
     thinking that Canada will give us any better terms 
     <lb/>
     than the Maritime provinces received when they 
     <lb/>
     threw in their lot with the federal government. 
     <lb/>
     With all due consideration I will support the 
     <lb/>
     amendment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MCCA7">Mr. McCarthy</persName> I am not going to speak at any <lb/> length to
                  the motion, and certainly not at all on <lb/> confederation, which is not the
                  issue; too much <lb/> has been said for and against that by some pre<lb break="no"/>vious speakers. I wish to make it clear that I am <lb/> not supporting
                  confederation or any other form <lb/> of government at this particular time, but
                  when <lb/> the time comes however I shall favour the form <lb/> of government
                  which I think will best serve New<lb break="no"/>foundland and its people. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I know there are some Newfoundlanders, few 
     <lb/>
     though they may be, who are favouring con<lb break="no"/>federation and we owe it to them to obtain all 
     <lb/>
     information possible on the issue. Whether this is 
     <lb/>
     sought now or later does not matter a great deal, 
     <lb/>
     as long as it is available to the Convention when 
     <lb/>
     committees are finished. Canada, knowing now 
     <lb/>
     that we do not have to accept, will I think submit 
     <lb/>
     her best offer. Then our confederates, knowing 
     <lb/>
     this, will have a better idea whether or not it 
     <lb/>
     would be wise to vote that way. Therefore, I 
     <lb/>
     support the resolution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEN3">Mr. Spencer</persName> Mr. Chairman, hitherto l have <lb/> taken no
                  verbal part in the public sessions of this <lb/>
                  <cb/> House. Being one of the younger members of this <lb/> Convention and
                  unaccustomed, as many of us <lb/> are, to gatherings of this sort, I have chosen
                  rather <lb/> to listen and learn. But having sat and listened for <lb/> the last
                  two days to the comments and debate on <lb/> the resolution now before the House,
                  I feel com<lb break="no"/>pelled to make some comment. I know, and many <lb/>
                  gentlemen here have stated, that there are people <lb/> in all the districts of
                  Newfoundland and Labrador <lb/> who are expecting that confederation will be one
                  <lb/> of the forms of government which will be <lb/> presented to them at a future
                  referendum, and for <lb/> that reason alone it was inevitable that the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of getting terms from the Canadian govern<lb break="no"/>ment
                  should at some time have to come before <lb/> this House. I think we agree on
                  that. The main <lb/> point of the argument at the present time is, it <lb/> seems
                  to me, the time of presenting the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, which some delegates
                  think was premature. <lb/> But the fact remains that the motion is before the
                  <lb/> House and we have spent three sessions in dis<lb break="no"/>puting and
                  debating it. Now what are we going to <lb/> do about it? Are we going to shelve
                  this resolution <lb/> at the present and bring it in at some future date? <lb/> I
                  have come to the conclusion that I will <lb/> support the motion, because if we
                  shelve the <lb/> question now and have it brought in again at some <lb/> future
                  date, we should have all our discussions <lb/> and debates over again which to me
                  seems a <lb/> waste of time, and l have no wish to see this <lb/> Convention
                  prolonged more than is absolutely <lb/> necessary. I would wish this Convention to
                  have <lb/> the facts when they want them and not have to <lb/> wait for them. In
                  making this decision I wish it to <lb/> be clearly understood that I have not been
                     ap<lb break="no"/>proached or influenced by any member of this <lb/>
                  Convention. Let us get the question settled as <lb/> quickly as possible and get
                  on with the real busi<lb break="no"/>ness of finding the facts about our own
                  country. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> Mr. Chairman, 1 have not spoken <lb/>on the
                  resolution before because I did not think it <lb/>necessary to have so many
                  speeches made. If <lb/>every resolution and question that is brought in is
                  <lb/>going to have 45 speeches made on it we are <lb/>going to be here for a very
                  long time yet. The <lb/>resolution now before the Convention is not <lb/>whether
                  we are going to back confederation or <lb/>not. There is nothing in it about
                  confederation <lb/>except to obtain the facts as to terms with Canada. <lb/>Those
                  who spoke on the amendment want to get <lb/>the facts too. The only point is to
                  decide whether <lb/>
                  <pb n="134" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0134.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">134</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> we should send a delegation now or in two
                  weeks <lb/> or in two months time.... I feel that too much time <lb/> has been
                  wasted on something that should have <lb/> been finished many days ago. A
                  gentleman told <lb/> me this afternoon that he was going to move an <lb/>
                  amendment to the amendment. I hope he will <lb/> soon get started and have 45
                  speeches made on it <lb/> before it is too late. Personally I think this whole
                  <lb/> thing should be shelved until January next, and <lb/> for that reason I
                  support Mr. Bradley's amend<lb break="no"/>ment.... I am not a confederate and not
                  supporting <lb/> any particular form of government; but in the <lb/> interests of
                  the whole country I would like to see <lb/> something definite done on this
                  question once <lb/> and for all. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> I would like to speak briefly on the <lb/> motion
                  introduced by Mr. Smallwood. I am <lb/> favourably impressed with the views of
                  previous <lb/> speakers. The people of my district are friendly <lb/> disposed to
                  confederation, and I would like to see <lb/> all information available brought
                  before this <lb/> house for consideration with regard to this ques<lb break="no"/>tion. Remember that upon this the destiny of our <lb/> country may depend, and
                  the weal or woe of <lb/> 300,000 people may rest. Now the people who <lb/> sent us
                  delegates here are watching us closely. I <lb/> may say that the final reports of
                  two committees <lb/> have been laid aside because of the time spent on <lb/> these
                  resolutions. Even at that it is not lost time, <lb/> because it is vitally
                  necessary to have this ques<lb break="no"/>tion explored to the fullest extent and
                  have all <lb/> information ready at the proper time. If this Con<lb break="no"/>vention takes a year to complete its work, what <lb/> is a year to the life of a
                  country and its people? I <lb/> was born in this country, lived in this country
                  and <lb/> I hope to die in this country.... Therefore, with a <lb/> sincere heart,
                  I will support the amendment. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> Mr. Chairman, when this resolu<lb break="no"/>tion
                  was introduced I was away, unfortunately. <lb/>However, I heard most of the
                  speeches over the <lb/>radio and I would like to congratulate some <lb/>people on
                  the job they did not do. I do not think <lb/>the time opportune to discuss
                  confederation <lb/>terms because we have not the facts and figures <lb/>yet
                  concerning our own country. At the moment <lb/>the idea of preparing to send a
                  delegation to <lb/>Ottawa to discuss terms is ridiculous. For <lb/>argument's
                  sake, I happen to own a business and <lb/>Mr. Smallwood happens to own a business
                  and <lb/>we are thinking of amalgamating. Then he asks <lb/>
                  <cb/> me what my assets are. My answer to him would <lb/> be that I do not know,
                  but if he would not mind <lb/> waiting a bit to discuss this thing I would let him
                  <lb/> know at a later date. The same applies to this <lb/> confederation business,
                  and I fail to see any <lb/> sound reason for going into it in a hurry. I feel the
                  <lb/> majority of delegates will view this matter in the <lb/> same light.... I am
                  not an anti-confederate neither <lb/> am I a confederate. I am not supporting any
                  <lb/> particular form of government at the present <lb/> time; but I am definitely
                  opposed to what has <lb/> taken place within the past week or so. 1 will now <lb/>
                  support the amendment. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> Mr. Chairman, at this stage I am not <lb/> going
                  to say much about sending a delegation to <lb/> Ottawa, but I am sorry that such
                  an issue <lb/> developed at this time because it smacks of old- <lb break="yes"/>
                  time politics.... I move that the resolution be put <lb/> to a vote so that the
                  Convention will be able to <lb/> move along on more important business matters.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Bradley made reference to the <lb/>sounding of
                  the British government. That is a <lb/>point I would like to be clear on, and
                  would you, <lb/>sir, explain what possible effect that would have <lb/>on a spring
                  referendum? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I will get the exact words used <lb/> later, and
                  until then you might let the matter stand <lb/> over. Is there any other member
                  who wishes to <lb/> speak before the reply is made by the original <lb/> mover of
                  the question? If not, the debate on the <lb/> original question will finish with
                  the reply by the <lb/> mover of the original question. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, before coming <lb/> to the main
                  part of my remarks I would like to say <lb/> how deeply grateful I am for the very
                  many words <lb/> of encouragement I have received since I moved <lb/> this
                  resolution on Monday last. By word of <lb/> mouth, by telephone and by telegraph
                  from many <lb/> parts of the country these encouraging messages <lb/> have come,
                  enough to show me, if I had not <lb/> known before, that this country wants the
                     resolu<lb break="no"/>tion to pass. And now 1 reply to my friend Mr. <lb/>
                  Harrington. I am deeply sorry to find that we are <lb/> on opposite sides. I did
                  hope it would be other<lb break="no"/>wise. As he said himself, I was expecting
                  his <lb/> support of this motion, for months ago he <lb/> declared to me his
                  intention to do so. From the <lb/> moment I first met him — that was when he <lb/>
                  worked with me on the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Book of Newfoundland</hi><ref target="#fn_02">[1]</ref>
                  <lb/> — I liked and admired him. I have followed his <lb/>
                  <note xml:id="fn_02">[1] J.R. Smallwood, (ed), The Book a Newfoundland (2 volumes,
                     St. John's, 1937).</note>
                  <pb n="135" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0135.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">135</fw> career ever since, especially as my successor in <lb/> the
                  Barrelman radio programme. I believe he is a <lb/> patriot, and I believe he loves
                  this country every <lb/> bit as much as I do. I am all the more sorry, <lb/>
                  therefore, that he has marred his political career, <lb/> which I thought was a
                  rather promising one, by <lb/> his remarks aimed at me on Monday. I thought at
                  <lb/> first that I should put them down to naivety, to <lb/> lack of experience in
                  everyday affairs. I felt sorry <lb/> that he should make such an almost
                     unforgive<lb break="no"/>able break. Yes, I told Mr. Harrington that I <lb/>
                  thought he would make a very good member of <lb/> any delegation that might go to
                  Canada to get the <lb/> terms of confederation. I did not promise a seat <lb/> on
                  any such delegation from this Convention to <lb/> Ottawa. 1 shall not appoint it I
                  suppose I would <lb/> be lucky to be on it myself. I did tell Mr. Har<lb break="no"/>rington that he would make a good member of the <lb/> delegation,
                  and I would say now again that he <lb/> would make a good member, if I could feel
                  sure <lb/> that it was only an unfortunate break he made <lb/> here on Monday
                  last, and not a deliberate piece <lb/> of double-crossing treachery, if it was not
                  an <lb/> unscrupulous attempt at political throat-cutting. <lb/> Some day, I
                  trust, Mr. Harrington will learn that <lb/> in the circles in which men move and
                  work and <lb/> deliberate there is a line drawn, a well-known and <lb/>
                  well-established line, which men do not cross. <lb/> It's simply not done to rush
                  into a public assemb<lb break="no"/>ly and blurt out what is said in private
                     conversa<lb break="no"/>tion.... Mr. Harrington will learn all this if he <lb/>
                  remains in the public life of our country. Maybe <lb/> Mr. Harrington merely made
                  an unfortunate and <lb/> immature break — if he did I forgive him, and <lb/> there
                  are no hard feelings. Again, perhaps he <lb/> fancied a perfectly sincere remark
                  to be a foul <lb/> attack upon his political virtue. In that case I <lb/> could be
                  sorry for his inexperience. But if it was <lb/> a deliberate piece of
                  throat-cutting, if it was part <lb/> and parcel of a planned campaign to rivet
                     respon<lb break="no"/>sible government on us, and to tune out every<lb break="no"/>thing but responsible government, then it's <lb/> another situation
                  altogether. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Now I turn to Mr. Hollett's remarks. I did not 
     <lb/>
     offer him a senatorship for two very sound 
     <lb/>
     reasons. First, because I have no senatorships to 
     <lb/>
     offer. Secondly, because ifI were going to offer 
     <lb/>
     him any job it would be something on a very 
     <lb/>
     much lower level than a senatorship. I do Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Hollett the credit of not having accused me 
     <lb/>
     directly of offering him a senatorship. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, I rise to a point of <lb/> order.
                  The present speaker is indulging in per<lb break="no"/>sonalities and refers to me
                  as Mr. Hollett. I <lb/> thought that was not allowed. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Do you rise to a point of par<lb break="no"/>liamentary procedure? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Yes, sir. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> During the House of Assembly <lb/> era, members
                  when addressing the Chair did not <lb/> refer to other members by name, but by the
                     dis<lb break="no"/>tricts they represented. But this Convention is not <lb/> a
                  parliament. Under the circumstances, I think <lb/> Mr. Smallwood has the right to
                  refer to you by <lb/> name, rather than as the member for Grand Falls. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> And now I will refer to Mr. <lb/>Hollett as the
                  junior member for Grand Falls. <lb/>Again I say I did not offer him a senatorship
                  for <lb/>the reasons I have already stated. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Here I have to call order. I do <lb/> not
                  propose to have personalities introduced, and <lb/> I do not want to have
                  aspersions cast upon any <lb/> member of the Convention. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> [think that Mr. Hollett implied <lb/> that it
                  was I who offered him a senatorship. I have <lb/> never exchanged more than 50
                  words with Mr. <lb/> Hollett in my life and I trust to his honour to make <lb/> it
                  clear that it was not to me he referred. My friend <lb/> Mr. Fudge's objection was
                  to the holding of a <lb/> little "side Convention" in my room at the New<lb break="no"/>foundland Hotel. I notice that a local paper also <lb/> referred to
                  these meetings, so-called. It is perfect<lb break="no"/>ly true that many
                  delegates — I might say two or <lb/> three dozen delegates, have visited me in my
                  <lb/> room at the hotel, some by my specific invitation, <lb/> some without any
                  particular invitation. I have <lb/> visited other delegates in their rooms. In my
                  room <lb/> and in their rooms, and in committee rooms in <lb/> this house, and
                  walking along the street, and in <lb/> the streetcar, I have often discussed
                  public affairs <lb/> with delegates and with non-delegates. I am quite <lb/> sure
                  that other delegates have done likewise. It's <lb/> a habit we have. It's a habit
                  all public men have. <lb/> You can't stop it. It isn't even sensible to want to
                  <lb/> stop it. It happens all over the world.... It's just <lb/> the ordinary,
                  practical, every day procedure for <lb/> men to talk things over, to try to
                  convince each <lb/> other, or to try to find out what the other man is <lb/>
                  thinking, to canvass the situation generally. <lb/> There is nothing improper or
                  unusual about it... <lb/> It is just simple inexperience, immature un<lb break="no"/>sophistication, to paint such meetings as sinister <lb/>
                  <pb n="136" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0136.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">136</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> or improper or unusual. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Now turning to Mr. Cashin. I like Mr. Cashin. 
     <lb/>
     I enjoy him. He fascinates me. His arguments 
     <lb/>
     fascinate me. His statements fascinate me. For 
     <lb/>
     instance, that statement he made here that he 
     <lb/>
     never said anything outside the House that he 
     <lb/>
     wouldn't be prepared to say in the House. Most 
     <lb/>
     men I'd hardly be willing to believe if they made 
     <lb/>
     such a statement. I think I believe Mr. Cashin 
     <lb/>
     when he makes it. And that other statement he 
     <lb/>
     made, when he said there was an ulterior motive 
     <lb/>
     behind this resolution. Mr. Cashin is not an easy 
     <lb/>
     one to fool. We can trust him always to ferret out 
     <lb/>
     ulterior motives and plots. He ferreted out an 
     <lb/>
     ulterior motive behind this Convention itself - <lb/> that it was just a bluff, a glorious stall, dripping 
     <lb/>
     with treachery, a clever stunt to keep Commis<lb break="no"/>sion of Government in power. But he admits that 
     <lb/>
     the members of the Convention are not aware of 
     <lb/>
     the ulterior motive behind this resolution to get 
     <lb/>
     information for our people. And he fears that the 
     <lb/>
     members do not see the ulterior motive behind 
     <lb/>
     the setting up of this Convention. He is deter<lb break="no"/>mined to protect the members of this Convention, 
     <lb/>
     and expose the ulterior motive behind the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion and behind the Convention. He's going to 
     <lb/>
     see that the country gets the only kind of govern<lb break="no"/>ment that he thinks is fit for the country, respon<lb break="no"/>sible government. He's against this resolution, on 
     <lb/>
     the ground that he knows the country is self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting anyway, so why waste time getting more 
     <lb/>
     information? He knows the country is self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting, because it's all in the Auditor General's 
     <lb/>
     report. There it is, according to him, as clear as 
     <lb/>
     mud, the clear proof that the country is self-sup<lb break="no"/>porting. We don't need to look any further. And 
     <lb/>
     yet, Mr. Chairman, one of his reasons for not 
     <lb/>
     sending a delegation to Ottawa is that the delega<lb break="no"/>tion would have no information to take with 
     <lb/>
     them. Wasn't he overlooking that remarkable 
     <lb/>
     piece of information about this country? 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Cashin in one breath says that on the basis of 
     <lb/>
     the 1895 confederation offer from Canada we'd 
     <lb/>
     get $300 million cash from Canada if we 
     <lb/>
     federated with her now. In the next breath he 
     <lb/>
     speaks about selling the country. There's some<lb break="no"/>thing wrong in this line of reasoning. I fear there's 
     <lb/>
     something wrong in a lot of his reasoning, for 
     <lb/>
     example when he convinces himself that Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister Attlee's reference to the three-year 
     <lb/>
     reconstruction programme of the Commission 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
          
     government proves a deep plot on Mr. Attlee's 
     <lb/>
     part to keep the Commission here another three 
     <lb/>
     years. I'm afraid I'm not impressed any more by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Cashin's standing as an authority on con<lb break="no"/>stitutional theory, constitutional history and 
     <lb/>
     constitutional practice, than I am by his grasp of 
     <lb/>
     financial matters. Before I leave Mr. Cashin for 
     <lb/>
     the time being, I must say that it appears to me 
     <lb/>
     that he is annoyed with me for not including him 
     <lb/>
     in my list of senatorships. I hasten to repair that 
     <lb/>
     blunder on my part. I have no more senatorships 
     <lb/>
     to offer. I'm sorry, but I promise him faithfully 
     <lb/>
     that if I should ever become prime minister of 
     <lb/>
     Canada I'll see that he is taken care of. I'll see 
     <lb/>
     that he is fixed up. I'll see that he gets a position 
     <lb/>
     fully in keeping with his parliamentary back<lb break="no"/>ground. I'll make him Gentleman Usher of the 
     <lb/>
     Black Rod. I'd give anything to see him all 
     <lb/>
     togged off in those dinky black pantaloons and 
     <lb/>
     three-cornered hat. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And now while I'm at it, I want to say a word 
     <lb/>
     about The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Sunday Herald</hi> newspaper. I want to 
     <lb/>
     say emphatically that it's not true that I'm paying 
     <lb/>
     that paper to attack me every week. There's not 
     <lb/>
     a word of truth in it. I'm grateful to them for their 
     <lb/>
     valuable attacks upon me. I hope they keep it up, 
     <lb/>
     but I'm definitely not paying them one cent for 
     <lb/>
     doing it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Turning to more important aspects of this 
     <lb/>
     question. I don't think that thoughtful New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders are glad to see such silly efforts 
     <lb/>
     being made to take their attention away from the 
     <lb/>
     main question in this resolution. The people of 
     <lb/>
     our country want to know the truth and they have 
     <lb/>
     a right to know the truth, the truth about Commis<lb break="no"/>sion government, the truth about responsible 
     <lb/>
     government, the truth about confederation. They 
     <lb/>
     would not thank me if I tried to keep the truth 
     <lb/>
     about Commission government away from them 
     <lb/>
     and I would not be so foolish as to try to keep it 
     <lb/>
     from them; or the truth about responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment either. And the people are not thanking 
     <lb/>
     anyone who is trying to keep the truth about 
     <lb/>
     confederation from them. All they want the 
     <lb/>
     people to hear about is responsible government, 
     <lb/>
     all they can see, all they are willing to talk about 
     <lb/>
     is responsible government. Their every thought 
     <lb/>
     is about responsible government, they're not 
     <lb/>
     satisfied for anything else to come before us. If 
     <lb/>
     they could have their way this Convention would 
     <lb/>
     close up right now after narrowing our people's 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="137" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0137.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">137</fw>
          
     choice down to responsible government. It mad<lb break="no"/>dens them, it infuriates them, when I introduce 
     <lb/>
     this resolution, when many delegates support it. 
     <lb/>
     It maddens them because it takes attention away 
     <lb/>
     from the one thing that they want the people to 
     <lb/>
     see, responsible government. But, sir, our people 
     <lb/>
     are not blind. They see through this political 
     <lb/>
     dodge. Our people know why this effort is being 
     <lb/>
     made to block this resolution. Our people have 
     <lb/>
     learned a lot in the past 20 years. They have their 
     <lb/>
     eyes open today. Mr. Chairman, I am not at this 
     <lb/>
     point referring to everyone who has spoken 
     <lb/>
     against the resolution. I want to make myself 
     <lb/>
     quite clear on this point. There are members who 
     <lb/>
     have spoken very sincerely against the motion, 
     <lb/>
     because they feared that it was trying to rush 
     <lb/>
     them. Not to them do I refer, but to a certain 
     <lb/>
     willful minority whose only policy is responsible 
     <lb/>
     government or bust. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We have heard here some silly talk about 
     <lb/>
     selling the country. Smallwood is trying to sell 
     <lb/>
     the country, they say. Could political bankruptcy 
     <lb/>
     go lower? The fanatical opponents of this motion 
     <lb/>
     must be pretty hard-up for an argument when 
     <lb/>
     they descend to such old-time political clap-trap, 
     <lb/>
     the sort of tripe that brought responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment into such contempt and disrepute before. 
     <lb/>
     Personal abuse, name-calling, charges of graft, 
     <lb/>
     bribery and corruption, accusations of selling the 
     <lb/>
     country and so forth, don't the gentlemen who 
     <lb/>
     stoop to such tactics see, don't they realise, that 
     <lb/>
     every time they get down to such depths, they're 
     <lb/>
     only reminding the people of the bad old days of 
     <lb/>
     responsible government? Don't they see that 
     <lb/>
     every such remark only makes the people more 
     <lb/>
     determined than ever never to touch responsible 
     <lb/>
     government again? Those people have a very 
     <lb/>
     poor opinion of our people's intelligence. They 
     <lb/>
    are gambling on the hope that our people have 
     <lb/> short memories. They are living in a world that is 
     <lb/> dead and past, that bad old world of playing 
     <lb/> politics, of playing politics as a game. Not ideas, 
     <lb/> but personalities; not policies, but name-calling; 
     <lb/> not great political principles, but accusations of 
     <lb/> graft, bribery, treachery and all the rest of the old 
     <lb/> time political ammunition-dump of trash and gar<lb break="no"/>bage. If you don't agree with a man, smear him. 
     <lb/> If you can't answer his arguments, try to draw 
     <lb/> attention away from his arguments by blackening 
     <lb/> his character. Accuse him of bribery, start a great 
     <lb/>
           

    
            <cb/>
          
     
 
           
           
     hullabaloo, a big noise, and maybe the public will 
     <lb/>
     forget the solid things he said. It's an old game, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman, but it doesn't work any more. Our 
     <lb/>
     people are on to that old trick of the political 
     <lb/>
     game. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But, sir, why should I complain because a few 
     <lb/>
     people say that I'm trying to sell the country? 
     <lb/>
     Better men than I, greater Newfoundlanders, 
     <lb/>
     higher patriots, have had the same charge hurled 
     <lb/>
     against them. That greatest patriot of all, the 
     <lb/>
     Right Honourable Sir Robert Bond, who oc<lb break="no"/>cupied a seat only two or three feet from where I 
     <lb/>
     stand today, had the same charge made against 
     <lb/>
     him. Here's a printed pamphlet published in 
     <lb/>
     1909, when he was prime minister. On the cover 
     <lb/>
     of this pamphlet, in heavy black type, are the 
     <lb/>
     words: "Bond's Awful Plot to Sell the Country." 
     <lb/>
     And what is this pamphlet about? It tells how our 
     <lb/>
     great Newfoundland patriot was a confederate 
     <lb/>
     who wanted to get Canada's terms of confedera<lb break="no"/>tion in 1909. For wanting to get the terms of 
     <lb/>
     confederation Sir Robert Bond was accused of 
     <lb/>
     trying to sell his country, so why should I com<lb break="no"/>plain for having the same charge hurled at me 
     <lb/>
     when I propose to get the terms? Sir Edward 
     <lb/>
     Morris not only tried to get the terms in 1914 but 
     <lb/>
     got them — was he trying to sell the country? 
     <lb/>
     Were Sir William Coaker and Sir Michael Cashin 
     <lb/>
     traitors to Newfoundland because they were 
     <lb/>
     anxious, in 1915, to get the terms of confedera<lb break="no"/>tion? Were Sir William Whiteway and 
     <lb/>
     Archbishop Howley traitors for believing in con<lb break="no"/>federation? Was Sir Richard Squires, were Sir 
     <lb/>
     Ambrose Shea and Sir Frederick Carter? Were 
     <lb/>
     those great Newfoundlanders all trying to sell the 
     <lb/>
     country? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, someone said, I believe it was 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Hollett, that he didn't believe that the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada would receive a delega<lb break="no"/>tion from this Convention. In the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons, the prime minister of Canada made this 
     <lb/>
     precise statement: "If the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland should ever decide that they wish to 
     <lb/>
     enter the Canadian federation and should make 
     <lb/>
     that decision clear beyond all possibility of 
     <lb/>
     misunderstanding, Canada would give most sym<lb break="no"/>pathetic consideration to the proposal."<ref target="#fn_03">[1]</ref> That 
     <lb/>
     was in l943. Coming down to late June of this 
     <lb/>
     present year, the Government of Canada made its 
     <lb/>
     position again very clear, in the words of Mr. St. 
     <lb/>
            

 <note xml:id="fn_03">[1] Canada, House of Commons Debates, 12 July 1943.</note>

            <pb n="138" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0138.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">138</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
           
     Laurent. Mr. St. Laurent, who is Canada's mini<lb break="no"/>ster of justice, was then acting prime minister of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, Mr. King being in Paris. Mr. St. Laurent 
     <lb/>
     was asked by a member of the Opposition if the 
     <lb/>
     government would extend an invitation to New<lb break="no"/>foundland to enter the Canadian federal union. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. St. Laurent replied for the government as 
     <lb/>
     follows: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     As the Hon. members know, just within 
     <lb/>
     the past few days an election has been held 
     <lb/>
     in Newfoundland for the purpose of con<lb break="no"/>stituting an assembly. The position of 
     <lb/>
     Canada is still as it has been stated on more 
     <lb/>
     than one occasion in this House. If the people 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland come to the conclusion 
     <lb/>
     that they would be happy to throw in their lot 
     <lb/>
     with Canada, their representations will be 
     <lb/>
     given most earnest and sympathetic con<lb break="no"/>sideration. But it has been said on more than 
     <lb/>
     one occasion in this House that this is some<lb break="no"/>thing concerning the inhabitants of the old 
     <lb/>
     colony of Newfoundland, and this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would not wish to appear to be interfer<lb break="no"/>ing in the affairs of that colony. Their 
     <lb/>
     delegates or representatives will be wel<lb break="no"/>comed here as cordially as we can welcome 
     <lb/>
     them. I believe there are many Canadians 
     <lb/>
     who feel that it would be to the mutual ad<lb break="no"/>vantage of Canada and Newfoundland to 
     <lb/>
     come closer together. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Mr. St. Laurent was followed immediately by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. John R. MacNichol, an Opposition member, 
     <lb/>
     who said: "If and when Newfoundland should 
     <lb/>
     send delegates to Canada to discuss the question 
     <lb/>
     of the entry of Newfoundland to Confederation, 
     <lb/>
     which I for one favour, I would strongly urge that 
     <lb/>
     no effort be made or no suggestion advanced to 
     <lb/>
     detach Labrador from Newfoundland." Mr. Mac<lb break="no"/>Nichol said he had been in Newfoundland and 
     <lb/>
     knew how strongly Newfoundlanders felt on this 
     <lb/>
     point. Mr. St. Laurent expressed his agreement. I 
     <lb/>
     think, Mr. Chairman, we may feel quite sure that 
     <lb/>
     Canada would receive a delegation from this 
     <lb/>
     house and impart any terms that she was willing 
     <lb/>
     to offer. Their only policy in this whole matter is 
     <lb/>
     that it must be the Newfoundland people them<lb break="no"/>selves who shall express a wish for confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. Canada simply won't accept Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     unless the Newfoundland people express a wish 
     <lb/>
     for it. The Newfoundland people cannot express 
     <lb/>
     a wish for it until they know the terms, and that's 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
         
     what this resolution asks us to do, to get the terms 
     <lb/>
     so that the Newfoundland people can judge for 
     <lb/>
     themselves, as they have every right to do. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We also know the attitude of the Opposition 
     <lb/>
     in Canada. At their annual conference last sum<lb break="no"/>mer they passed a resolution calling upon the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada to extend an invitation to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland to enter the federal union. And we 
     <lb/>
     know the attitude of the Canadian people also. In 
     <lb/>
     the Gallup poll held in Canada this summer a big 
     <lb/>
     majority of them declared that they would wel<lb break="no"/>come Newfoundland into their federal union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     So now, Mr. Chairman, we know all the fac<lb break="no"/>tors but one. We know that it is lawful for the 
     <lb/>
     Convention to send the delegation to Ottawa. We 
     <lb/>
     know that Ottawa will receive the delegation, and 
     <lb/>
     receive it cordially. We know that the opposition 
     <lb/>
     party will not oppose it. We know that the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian people will not oppose it. The only 
     <lb/>
     thing we still don't know is what the New<lb break="no"/>foundland people want. We don't know whether 
     <lb/>
     they want confederation or not — and we're not 
     <lb/>
     going to know until they vote in the referendum. 
     <lb/>
     All we can do is get the terms and conditions and 
     <lb/>
     that's all this resolution calls for. The rest can 
     <lb/>
     very safely be left to the people; once they know 
     <lb/>
     the terms, they'll know how to make up their 
     <lb/>
     minds all right, never you fear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am sorry, in a way, that when the committees 
     <lb/>
     were set up five weeks ago we didn't set up ten 
     <lb/>
     committees instead of nine. While nine commit<lb break="no"/>tees were getting the facts about Commission 
     <lb/>
     government and responsible government, the 
     <lb/>
     tenth committee could have been getting the facts 
     <lb/>
     about confederation. However, it isn't too late by 
     <lb/>
     any means. We can adopt this resolution and then 
     <lb/>
     the machinery can start. Word will finally come 
     <lb/>
     back to us saying very definitely whether Canada 
     <lb/>
     will receive the delegation, and the delegation 
     <lb/>
     itself could leave in December or early in 
     <lb/>
     January, for Ottawa. They'd probably be back in 
     <lb/>
     ten days or a fortnight, with the terms, and then 
     <lb/>
     the terms will be before us when we come around 
     <lb/>
     finally to discussing forms of government. If we 
     <lb/>
     think the terms are good, we'll be able to recom<lb break="no"/>mend that confederation on those terms be put 
     <lb/>
     before the people in the referendum. If we don't 
     <lb/>
     think they're worth putting before the people, We 
     <lb/>
     don't have to put them before the people. It's the 
     <lb/>
     people who'll decide. They'll have the last word, 
     <lb/>
     and the only word that counts. If we ever enter 
     <lb/>
         
            <pb n="139" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0139.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">139</fw>
           
     confederation it'll only be because our people 
     <lb/>
     will want it, and they'll want it, if they do, only 
     <lb/>
     because the terms will make this a better country 
     <lb/>
     for them to live in. We owe it to the people to get 
     <lb/>
     them the facts they need to make up their minds 
     <lb/>
     on this question. We owe them that. It is our plain 
     <lb/>
     duty to get the facts for them, and I do not see 
     <lb/>
     how we can fail in that duty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Once again, Mr. Chairman, let me repeat the 
     <lb/>
    solemn pledge I have made to this House and to 
     <lb/>the country: if the terms, when we get them, are 
     <lb/>good for our people, then I shall support them. If 
     <lb/>they are not good, then I shall oppose and con<lb break="no"/>demn them as strongly as anyone. Let us set the 
     <lb/>machinery going now that will eventually, eight 
     <lb/>or ten weeks from now, put the facts before us. 
     <lb/>Let us decide to get the machinery going and then 
     <lb/>forget about confederation until the facts are laid 
     <lb/>before us by the delegation after their return from 
     <lb/>Ottawa. Let us remember that it is the people of 
     <lb/>Newfoundland we are here to serve, first, last and 
     <lb/>all the time. Let us turn our backs upon nothing 
     <lb/>that might be good for our Newfoundland people. </p>

<p>
     <lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Chairman proposed a change in the word<lb break="no"/>ing of the motion which was accepted by the 
     <lb/>mover and seconder]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Now to that original question, <lb/>moved by Mr.
                  Smallwood and seconded by <lb/>Mr. Higgins K.C., the following amendment has
                  <lb/>been moved by Mr. Penney and seconded by <lb/>Mr. Roberts, namely: "That all
                  words after the <lb/>words 'national referendum' in the preamble to <lb/>the
                  motion be deleted, and the following sub<lb break="no"/>stituted therefor; namely:
                  'But that the question <lb/>of ascertaining the attitude of the Government of
                  <lb/>Canada towards the possibility of federal union <lb/>of Newfoundland with
                  Canada and the further <lb/>question of sending a delegation to Ottawa to
                  <lb/>ascertain the terms and conditions on the basis of <lb/>which the Government
                  of Canada consider that <lb/>such union might be effected, be deferred for
                  <lb/>consideration until the reports of the committees <lb/>appointed pursuant to
                  the session of September <lb/>20 have been presented to this Convention, or
                  <lb/>such earlier or other date as the Convention may <lb/>determine.'" <lb/>
               </p>

    

            <p>
     The debate on the original question has 
     <lb/>
     finished. The amendment submits a separate 
     <lb/>
     question. To that question several members al<lb break="no"/>ready have spoken, including Mr. Penney who 
     <lb/>
     moved it, Mr. Roberts who seconded it, Mr. 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
          
     Smallwood and Mr. Brown. The other members 
     <lb/>
     of the Convention if they so desire and see any 
     <lb/>
     need for so doing, may speak to the amendment. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> It is not my intention to delay the <lb/>debate. I
                  am neither very much enamoured of the <lb/>amendment, and certainly not of the
                  motion, but <lb/>I believe I shall vote for the amendment. I regret <lb/>there
                  seems to be from day to day a change in the <lb/>manner of procedure. One day we
                  seem to be <lb/>using parliamentary procedure, and some other <lb/>day we seem to
                  be using some other form of <lb/>procedure, so it makes it rather awkward when
                  <lb/>one gets to his feet to make some remarks. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I have to correct you, Mr. Hol<lb break="no"/>lett. There is no variance in the procedure <lb/> originally laid down
                  whatsoever. Where the rules <lb/> approved by this Convention are silent then
                     ordi<lb break="no"/>nary parliamentary procedure applies. If you <lb/> refer to
                  the point relative to the naming of a <lb/> member, I have explained that, and I
                  do not <lb/> propose to let your comment pass either unchal<lb break="no"/>lenged
                  or unmarked that from day to day there is <lb/> any variance in the procedure in
                  this assembly. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Please understand I am not casting <lb/>any
                  aspersions at the Chair. That is the feeling <lb/>which I have, maybe I am wrong.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Insofar as the Chairman con<lb break="no"/>trols
                  the procedure and regulates the conduct of <lb/> business, I can't imagine that
                  your reference has <lb/> any other inference than the one to which I now <lb/>
                  call your attention and on which I challenge you. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Speaking just a word to that, Mr. <lb/>Chairman, I
                  might say that in a debate a few days <lb/>ago there was strong objection taken by
                  the Chair <lb/>to what was then called personalities. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Exactly. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> And if the mover of the motion in <lb/> his reply
                  of a few moments ago did not use <lb/> personalities and was upheld by the Chair,
                  then I <lb/> must have heard wrongly. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You did hear wrongly. You did <lb/> not hear my
                  interruption of Mr. Smallwood, and <lb/> my direction to him that I do not allow
                     per<lb break="no"/>sonalities to be indulged in, and that if he con<lb break="no"/>tinued I would certainly have to call him to order. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Thank you, sir. I do feel that both <lb/>the
                  amendment and the motion are inopportune, <lb/>premature, and I doubt the
                  legality, or the ability, <lb/>of this Convention sending a delegation to con<lb break="no"/>sult with the Dominion's House of Commons. <lb/>Some reference has
                  been made to a remark which <lb/>
                  <pb n="140" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0140.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">140</fw>
                  <fw type="num">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> I made a week ago today, to the effect that
                  even <lb/> I was offered a senatorship, and the mover of the <lb/> motion stated a
                  moment ago that he inferred that <lb/> I was alluding to him. To that I will say
                  that I <lb/> always have had a great regard for the reasoning <lb/> powers of the
                  mover of the motion, and I suspect <lb/> strongly that he analysed the whole
                  statement <lb/> before he decided he arrived at a correct inter<lb break="no"/>pretation of the amendment. Now, if, on Monday <lb/> past, I set a sprat to
                  catch a herring, am I to be <lb/> blamed if I caught a confederate cod? I noticed
                  <lb/> the greediness with which the proposer grasped <lb/> at the bait, and I feel
                  that he took the bait, the hook <lb/> and all. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p> Getting back to the matter of sending a delega<lb break="no"/>tion to Canada, allow
                  me to refer you to section <lb/> 146 of the British North America Act, which <lb/>
                  makes provision for the entry of Newfoundland <lb/> into the Dominion of Canada as
                  a tenth province. <lb/> I shall read it, section 146: "It shall be lawful for
                  <lb/> the Queen, by and with the advice of Her <lb/> Majesty's Privy Council, on
                  the addresses from <lb/> the Houses of Parliament of Canada and the <lb/> Houses
                  of the respective legislatures of the Com<lb break="no"/>mons of Newfoundland,
                  Prince Edward Island <lb/> and British Columbia, to admit those Colonies or <lb/>
                  Provinces, or any of them into the Union." Does <lb/> that not presuppose that
                  before we can enter into <lb/> any union with the Dominion of Canada that we <lb/>
                  must have a legislature? Some people will say <lb/> you have your Commission of
                  Government, and <lb/> they have the authority of the legislature. That <lb/> may
                  be correct or it may not. If it is, is it not <lb/> therefore the bounden duty of
                  the Commission of <lb/> Government, if they have the power of the legis<lb break="no"/>lature, and if so many people in this country are <lb/> so desirous
                  of confederation, to go to Canada and <lb/> find out the terms? The Dominion of
                  Canada <lb/> would then be negotiating with a legitimate <lb/> government, not
                  with 45 men who were sent in <lb/> here to appraise the resources of this country.
                  <lb/> And, as Mr. Crosbie a moment ago pointed out, <lb/> does it not look
                  ridiculous to you that these 45 <lb/> men of this Convention should proceed to
                  <lb/> Canada without even knowing the extent of our <lb/> natural resources,
                  without even knowing just <lb/> how our finances are? In what position are we to
                  <lb/> ask Canada to lay her cards on the table if we <lb/> ourselves are unable to
                  put ours down? I wish it <lb/> to be clearly understood that I am not against
                  <lb/> confederation and I am not for confederation, and <lb/>
                  <cb/> as Mr. Bradley from Bonavista said, I am not for <lb/> or against
                  responsible government, and neither <lb/> am I for or against Commission of
                  Government <lb/> at this present juncture. What we are for, and <lb/> what we are
                  not for, should have been left to the <lb/> time when we had gotten those facts
                  which our <lb/> people sent us here for. But when one member, <lb/> whom I shall
                  now call the senior member for <lb/> Bonavista, elects to get on his feet on the
                  floor of <lb/> this house and make a political speech on the <lb/> issue of
                  confederation one hour long, and then <lb/> reply for another half hour, then I
                  submit that I or <lb/> anyone else who did not get up and object to his <lb/>
                  motion would be failing in our duty to the people <lb/> who sent us here. I do not
                  wish to say anything <lb/> more on confederation or responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment or Commission of Government at this <lb/> present time. I do
                  think we are wasting an awful <lb/> lot of time, and I submit that the quicker we
                  get <lb/> down to a vote on this issue and have done with <lb/> it the better. <lb/></p>
<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> As I said perhaps an hour ago, I <lb/> can
                  sympathise with those members of this Con<lb break="no"/>vention who fear that we
                  may be acting too <lb/> precipitately. I tried on that occasion to explain <lb/>
                  to them that acting now did not mean an imme<lb break="no"/>diate delegation to
                  Canada... Obviously if we <lb/> defer the passage of this resolution until some
                  <lb/> later date, by an equal space of time will the <lb/> departure of the
                  delegates be deferred. Why then <lb/> should we defer the institution of these
                  inquiries <lb/> until we have finished the inquiries upon which <lb/> our various
                  committees are engaged today? If we <lb/> do that it is perfectly obvious that
                  when we have <lb/> the financial picture of the country before us we <lb/> shall
                  not have the terms of confederation, and the <lb/> same thing exactly applies to
                  any inquiries which <lb/> may be directed to the United Kingdom... <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>Already in the press a rather indiscreet and 
     <lb/>untimely reference has been made to adjourn<lb break="no"/>ments of this Convention, in utter ignorance of 
     <lb/>the facts. There are few, if any, members of this 
     <lb/>Convention who desire to prolong it any further 
     <lb/>than necessary. It has been stated that this is 
     <lb/>costing the country somewhere in the neighbour<lb break="no"/>hood of $1,000 a day. I have never taken the 
     <lb/>trouble to compute the amount so I can neither 
     <lb/>confirm or deny the correctness of that statement. 
     <lb/>I have no desire to expend money belonging to 
     <lb/>the people of this country, and I feel that every 
     <lb/>member is of the same opinion, and if we are to 
     <lb/>
       
            <pb n="141" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0141.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">141</fw>
      
     postpone all consideration of the question 
     <lb/>
     whether we shall or shall not send a delegation to 
     <lb/>
     Canada, whether we shall or shall not make any 
     <lb/>
     inquiries of Britain, until we have all the facts in 
     <lb/>
     connection with our financial position, then the 
     <lb/>
     Convention has got to sit down and wait for 
     <lb/>
     another couple of months until we can secure the 
     <lb/>
     necessary information in connection with Con<lb break="no"/>federation or financial assistance from the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom. My object is to get this delegation 
     <lb/>
     appointed and working here in St John's now. I 
     <lb/>
     want them to be ready to go at the opportune time, 
     <lb/>
     and if we are to await our findings on the financial 
     <lb/>
     position of this country as disclosed by the 
     <lb/>
     various committees we have appointed, then we 
     <lb/>
     will not be ready when that financial information 
     <lb/>
     is at hand. We will then have to start in and get 
     <lb/>
     this other information from Canada and from the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I quite understand Mr. Penncy's motion, and 
     <lb/>
     have a great deal of sympathy with him, but it is 
     <lb/>
     so utterly indefinite it leaves the whole thing in 
     <lb/>
     the air. It means we shall simply spend two or 
     <lb/>
     three days here debating this subject for exactly 
     <lb/>
     nothing. It means that at some future unknown 
     <lb/>
     date we may again introduce a resolution, and 
     <lb/>
     discuss the question as to whether we shall send 
     <lb/>
     a delegation to Canada or not, and I think that the 
     <lb/>
     best way out of this is to pin down the situation 
     <lb/>
     in a manner which I think can be objectionable to 
     <lb/>
     nobody. The objection is to prematurity. It is, I 
     <lb/>
     presume, contended, that this information which 
     <lb/>
     it is proposed to obtain from the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government will not be of any avail to us or the 
     <lb/>
     people until we have ascertained our own finan<lb break="no"/>cial position. There may be something in that 
     <lb/>
     argument. It sounds as if it had some reason in it. 
     <lb/>
     But the point that I want to make clear is that by 
     <lb/>
     throwing this resolution in the air, as will happen 
     <lb/>
     if Mr. Penney's amendment passes in its present 
     <lb/>
     form, we shall still be nowhere When we have 
     <lb/>
     the financial position we shall not be ready to 
     <lb/>
     discuss it either in comparison with confedera<lb break="no"/>tion or anything else, and it was for that reason I 
     <lb/>
     intimated an hour ago that unless somebody else 
     <lb/>
     did it, and quickly, that I myself proposed to 
     <lb/>
     introduce a resolution for the purpose of making 
     <lb/>
     inquiries from the United Kingdom, because I 
     <lb/>
     want the machinery put into action now. My only 
     <lb/>
     object is to see that when we have all available 
     <lb/>
     information collected, a delegation leaves here 
     <lb/>
     
            <cb/>
      
     perhaps during the latter part of January. And that 
     <lb/>
     when we have that information, we also have the 
     <lb/>
     necessary information about the confederation 
     <lb/>
     question and about the assistance Britain will be 
     <lb/>
     able to give in certain eventualities. For that 
     <lb/>
     reason I propose to make a few observations on 
     <lb/>
     the amendment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     First I would like to refer to Mr. Hollett's 
     <lb/>
     quotation where he pointed out that section 146 
     <lb/>
     of the British North America Act was defined in 
     <lb/>
     a way which makes provision for Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     to become a province. You will notice I said "<hi rendition="simple:italic">a</hi> 
     <lb/>
     way" not "<hi rendition="simple:italic">the</hi> way". There are several ways 
     <lb/>
     usually of doing the same thing. It is perfectly 
     <lb/>
     true that in 1867 when the British North America 
     <lb/>
     Act was passed, section 146 was inserted setting 
     <lb/>
     up the machinery by which Newfoundland might 
     <lb/>
     be included as a province. But the conditions of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland then and now are different and, 
     <lb/>
     consequently, section 146 is inapplicable. Today 
     <lb/>
     there is no House of Assembly and no Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Council to pass any resolutions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I must dispute your statement <lb/> that there
                  is no legislature in Newfoundland. <lb/> There is. There is no responsible
                  government in <lb/> Newfoundland, but there is a legislature. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> Yes, but not a legislature which <lb/> would ever
                  undertake to do any such thing as to <lb/> legislate this country into
                  confederation with <lb/> Canada. Thus the position today is that whatever <lb/>
                  method may be adopted to bring about confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, if the people
                  so desire it, it will not be <lb/> brought about by the British North America Act,
                  <lb/> which is inapplicable and could not be utilised for <lb/> the purpose. I
                  doubt if this country can go into <lb/> confederation unless we get responsible
                     govern<lb break="no"/>ment back. But suppose we never get responsible <lb/>
                  government back; are the people of this country <lb/> to be precluded from voting
                  for confederation? Is <lb/> it legally possible that this country cannot vote
                  <lb/> for confederation simply because the people do <lb/> not want responsible
                  government? Furthermore, <lb/> I am prepared to stake whatever reputation I may
                  <lb/> have as a lawyer in stating that the British govern<lb break="no"/>ment can,
                  if it so desires, legislate this country <lb/> into the Dominion of Canada
                  tomorrow, with or <lb/> without our consent. I feel sure she would not <lb/>
                  without our consent; but with the consent of the <lb/> people of Newfoundland she
                  would, provided <lb/> always that Canada was an assenting party. It has <lb/> been
                  said that the Commission government was <lb/>
                  <pb n="142" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0142.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">142</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> quite competent to handle this question. I
                  am not <lb/> prepared to discuss that at the moment, though I <lb/> am prepared to
                  state that Commission govern<lb break="no"/>ment will never legislate upon the
                  subject. There <lb/> are few, if any, men today here who do not know <lb/> that
                  Commission government is nothing more <lb/> than the agent of the British
                  government, which <lb/> is nothing more than the agent of Great Britain. <lb/> Mr.
                  Chairman The present Commission of <lb/> Government is not an agent of the British
                     govern<lb break="no"/>ment. It is functioning for and legislating the <lb/>
                  affairs of Newfoundland and it does not act as <lb/> agent for any person or
                  government outside of <lb/> Newfoundland. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> But at the same time the Commis<lb break="no"/>sion government is in constant consultation with <lb/> the Dominions Office,
                  although I do not believe <lb/> for one moment that Commission government <lb/>
                  would attempt to impose confederation without <lb/> the consent of the British
                  Parliament. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I tried this afternoon to point out to this as<lb break="no"/>sembly that political speeches had nothing to do 
     <lb/>
     with the question, and that the merits or demerits 
     <lb/>
     of confederation had nothing to do with this 
     <lb/>
     debate. The question was whether or not we 
     <lb/>
     would go seeking information at an opportune 
     <lb/>
     time... Should the motion be shelved, the Con<lb break="no"/>vention would have to start all over again when 
     <lb/>
     it had the facts concerning the financial and 
     <lb/>
     economic condition of this country, and my effort 
     <lb/>
     is for the purpose of clarification to try and pin 
     <lb/>
     down the issue until we get something done and 
     <lb/>
     find out where we are.... I propose the following 
     <lb/>
     amendment: that the words after "That" in the 
     <lb/>
     first line of Mr. Penney's amendment be stricken 
     <lb/>
     out and that the words "and shall not proceed to 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa before January I, 1947" be inserted in the 
     <lb/>
     original motion after the word "Newfoundland" 
     <lb/>
     at the end of the third paragraph. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This strikes out the indefiniteness which com<lb break="no"/>pletely fills Mr. Penney's amendment and it adds 
     <lb/>
     to the original motion something which effects 
     <lb/>
     what Mr. Penney desires — a reasonable delay 
     <lb/>
     before the delegation goes to Ottawa. It means 
     <lb/>
     that the machinery be put in motion at once so 
     <lb/>
     that the facts would be available when required... 
     <lb/>
     The whole object is to appoint a delegation and 
     <lb/>
     allow it to work in Newfoundland until the time 
     <lb/>
     would present itself to proceed to Canada. And 
     <lb/>
     their departure is still a matter which lies in the 
     <lb/>
     hands of this Convention. In the same way, I 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     propose to see to it that another resolution is 
     <lb/>
     introduced and adopted in connection with en<lb break="no"/>quiries with the United Kingdom. I feel this 
     <lb/>
     amendment should meet with the approval of all 
     <lb/>
     those who want the facts... I move this amend<lb break="no"/>ment to the amendment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BURR2">Mr. Burry</persName> I rise to second this second amend<lb break="no"/>ment, because I think it is the right and proper <lb/> thing to do. I have been
                  informed and enlightened <lb/> considerably by this debate this afternoon. At
                  <lb/> first I thought it was a waste of time. Now I do <lb/> not consider it such
                  and I have very much <lb/> pleasure in supporting this second amendment. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Chairman, can you inform the <lb/>Convention by
                  what date this House will have to <lb/>finish its business in order to have a
                  referendum <lb/>in the spring or a referendum in the fall? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I imagine that in order to have a <lb/>
                  referendum in the spring of 1947 the business of <lb/> this Convention would have
                  to finish by the end <lb/> of January or sometime in February, 1947. If it is
                  <lb/> desired to have a referendum in the autumn of <lb/> 1947, then the business
                  of this Convention should <lb/> finish by the end of May or early in June. It has
                  <lb/> to be remembered that the recommendations <lb/> from this Convention will
                  have to go to the <lb/> United Kingdom government after having first <lb/> been
                  considered by the Secretary for Dominions <lb/> Affairs, and from the cabinet will
                  be presented to <lb/> Parliament, say in the form of a White Paper, to <lb/> be
                  considered by the House of Commons and <lb/> then by the House of Lords. These are
                  opinions <lb/> on my own part only and for which I have no <lb/> actual authority
                  but, in view of the fact that we <lb/> have the advantage of the presence of
                  Professor <lb/> Wheare with us at the moment, I might ask him, <lb/> on your
                  behalf, to give us his views on the ques<lb break="no"/>tion submitted by Mr.
                  Higgins. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Professor Wheare I would not like to add any<lb break="no"/>thing to what has been said by the Chairman I 
     <lb/>
     think the procedure outlined by the Chairman is 
     <lb/>
     correct... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Thank you. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, by what authority <lb/> do we have
                  the right to send a delegation from <lb/> this Convention to Canada? I fear that
                  if we send <lb/> a delegation we might find ourselves in an <lb/> awkward position
                  weeks or months hence by <lb/> being told that we had no such authority. I think
                  <lb/> there is something in Mr. Bradley's amendment. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There is no doubt in my mind <lb/>
                  <pb n="143" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0143.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">143</fw> that it is perfectly competent for this Convention <lb/>
                  to send a delegation to Ottawa or anywhere else <lb/> seeking information that is
                  desired upon any <lb/> basic fact. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> What I cannot understand is this: <lb/> when the
                  Dorninions Office through the Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government, or vice
                  versa, set up this <lb/> Convention, they also set up a commission of <lb/> two,
                  two men from England to come out here and <lb/> prepare a White Paper to guide us
                  in our delibera<lb break="no"/>tions. I searched through that and all I find are a
                  <lb/> set of facts. I cannot find anything to suggest that <lb/> we should go to
                  Canada and find out anything. <lb/> Why did not the imperial authorities in that
                  White <lb/> Paper state definitely that we were to find out the <lb/> terms of
                  confederation? Why did they not say that <lb/> was a form of government we should
                  talk about? <lb/> They only speak of a form or forms of govern<lb break="no"/>ment
                  and it seems to me that at the time they only <lb/> had in their minds a form of
                  government within <lb/> the territorial boundary of this island. If they <lb/>
                  meant "outside" why did they not supply us with <lb/> facts, as they did about
                  this country? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> What is contained or is not con<lb break="no"/>tained in that White Paper, to which you refer, <lb/> has nothing to do with the
                  question before the <lb/> Chair or to my ruling on that question.... I am not
                  <lb/> concerned with what is in the White Paper insofar <lb/> as the construction
                  of the National Convention <lb/> Act is concerned. It is totally irrelevant to the
                  <lb/> question or my ruling thereon. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> In this debate, I am rather confused <lb/> by the
                  question brought up by Mr. Hollett. We <lb/>have your ruling that it is within the
                  limits of this <lb/>Convention that we should seek the terms of
                  <lb/>confederation, but we have yet to decide whether <lb/>or not it would be
                  valid for this Convention to <lb/>place on the ballot paper this form of
                  government. <lb/>And what appeal has this assembly against your <lb/>decision?
                  <lb/>
               </p>

    

    

    

    

    

    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The assembly can overrule my <lb/> decision or
                  ruling. That does not deal with the <lb/>validity of your question, Mr. Fogwill.
                  It merely <lb/>deals with the wish of the Convention either to be <lb/>bound by my
                  ruling or not to be bound. <lb/>
               </p>

    

    

    

    

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention adjourned until 8 pm]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I hope I do not keep you too long. <lb/> We have
                  been long enough on this unfortunate <lb/>matter, much longer than it warrants. So
                  far, if my <lb/>computations are correct (and I am no mathe<lb break="no"/>matician) the debate has cost the country $8,000. <lb/>
               </p>

    

    

    
            <cb/>
            <p>
     If so the debate on confederation will cost in the 
     <lb/>
     vicinity of $40,000. But my reason for seconding 
     <lb/>
     this motion was because I understood it to be the 
     <lb/>
     wish of the majority of delegates that we have a 
     <lb/>
     spring referendum. I do not know if that was 
     <lb/>
     stated in the house or not. At all events it was 
     <lb/>
     discussed on a number of occasions in private 
     <lb/>
     sessions, and it was not the sessions of the "little 
     <lb/>
     National Convention", but sessions of full 
     <lb/>
     responsible parties. As you, sir, and the learned 
     <lb/>
     Professor Wheare have outlined, in order to have 
     <lb/>
     a spring referendum we must finish our business 
     <lb/>
     by the end of January. That would mean that not 
     <lb/>
     only must we have all of our facts in, but we must 
     <lb/>
     have the debate on the forms of government 
     <lb/>
     concluded and we must be ready at that time to 
     <lb/>
     send our recommendations across to England. If 
     <lb/>
     it is not the intention to have a spring referendum, 
     <lb/>
     as so many members wished at first, then we have 
     <lb/>
     to set our sights at a fall referendum. But even for 
     <lb/>
     a fall referendum, we must be finished here by 
     <lb/>
     the end of May. If it is the wish to have a fall 
     <lb/>
     referendum, then I say that the motion we should 
     <lb/>
     adopt here would be the amendment proposed by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Bradley. If we leave it indefinite, as in the 
     <lb/>
     other amendment, we do not know when we will 
     <lb/>
     be in a position to seek terms we all agree we must 
     <lb/>
     have.... We have a big task ahead, but I am 
     <lb/>
     confident that we can finish our fact gathering by 
     <lb/>
     the end of January, if we really want to do it. It is 
     <lb/>
     going to mean much harder work than we have 
     <lb/>
     been putting in so far.... If you gentlemen are 
     <lb/>
     prepared, and you think the necessity warrants, 
     <lb/>
     then by all means let us wait until May. We 
     <lb/>
     definitely have to be finished by May or we 
     <lb/>
     cannot have the referendum until the following 
     <lb/>
     spring. It is simply up to us to decide what we are 
     <lb/>
     going to shoot for. It is a common agreement 
     <lb/>
     among all of us that we have got to get these terms 
     <lb/>
     otherwise we will be blackguarded out of the 
     <lb/>
     country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are being blackguarded as it is by the very 
     <lb/>
     unseemly conduct which has happened in this 
     <lb/>
     House. I am sure Mr. Smallwood will probably 
     <lb/>
     feel offended, but it is most unfortunate, and he 
     <lb/>
     himself is responsible for that. I can understand 
     <lb/>
     how Mr. Smallwood feels; he is ardent in his 
     <lb/>
     advocacy, and he just had to get it off or blow up. 
     <lb/>
     One thing we do not want, and that is to be 
     <lb/>
     ridiculous in the sight of the country and this 
     <lb/>
     debate has been making us ridiculous. I am sure 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="144" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0144.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">144</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
           
     we all came into this House with one purpose 
     <lb/>
     only, to do a job and to show to the people of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland and the world that we can still 
     <lb/>
     produce legislators in this country; and because 
     <lb/>
     of that I say we have not done the country or 
     <lb/>
     ourselves credit by some of the remarks made in 
     <lb/>
     this debate. In future, please let us try and get our 
     <lb/>
     minds a little above the old days that this House 
     <lb/>
     had to put up with in the days of responsible 
     <lb/>
     government. If we are going to be a board of 
     <lb/>
     judges, we have to try and be impartial, without 
     <lb/>
     heat, abuse, or personal scurrility. I am convinced 
     <lb/>
     that we can do it and there is no necessity of our 
     <lb/>
     going down to the gutter where we have been in 
     <lb/>
     the past few days. We should do the job which 
     <lb/>
     we were sent here to do. For that reason I do not 
     <lb/>
     see why the decision should be delayed any 
     <lb/>
     longer than tonight. Once the decision is made, 
     <lb/>
     let us be finished with it entirely until the matter 
     <lb/>
     has to come before us for final decision. I agree 
     <lb/>
     with Mr. Fudge to the extent that it has meant 
     <lb/>
     taking sides; it has meant bad committee work 
     <lb/>
     and in a lot of cases, no committee work at all. 
     <lb/>
     We should try in future to keep the discussions 
     <lb/>
     on the level they should be and not let per<lb break="no"/>sonalities come into it. Unfortunately, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood has turned this House into a personal 
     <lb/>
     debate against him. When we have such notices 
     <lb/>
     in the paper as "They dug the grave but Joe was 
     <lb/>
     not in it", it is getting beyond a joke. In view of 
     <lb/>
     the indefiniteness of Mr. Penney's amendment 
     <lb/>
     and the general wish of all the delegates to have 
     <lb/>
     it examined, I am prepared to vote for the amend<lb break="no"/>ment put forward by Mr. Bradley. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> May I speak to the original amend<lb break="no"/>ment. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You have spoken to that. You <lb/> might speak
                  to the amendment to the amendment. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> I introduced the amendment, but I <lb/>did not make
                  any address in connection with it at <lb/>the time. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Unfortunately a member doing <lb/> as you did is
                  considered to have spoken to the <lb/> subject matter of the motion. However, it
                  is a <lb/> matter for the Convention to deal with. With the <lb/> permission of
                  the Convention you may be al<lb break="no"/>lowed to speak to the amendment to the
                     amend<lb break="no"/>ment. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> My proper understanding was an <lb/> amendment
                  contained very few words. The mo<lb break="no"/>tion contained a lotof words and
                  the mover talked <lb/>
                  <cb/> half an hour to introduce it to this House and half <lb/> an hour this
                  afternoon to reply; then the supporter <lb/> addressed this House quite a lengthy
                  time. If it is <lb/> in order, I would like to speak. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I take it for granted that Con<lb break="no"/>vention has no objection to your talking now. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> Before reading the remarks I have <lb/>prepared, I
                  would like to say that I did not consult <lb/>or confer with members of this
                  Convention, or <lb/>with my sponsors or friends in Carbonear or with <lb/>anyone,
                  and this is the only opportunity I may <lb/>have of addressing this House before a
                  decision <lb/>is made for or against the original amendment. I <lb/>thank Mr.
                  Roberts, representing the district of <lb/>St. Barbe for seconding the amendment
                  and the <lb/>other gentlemen who have supported it, and espe<lb break="no"/>cially
                  the representatives of labour in this House <lb/>who through their organisations
                  have closer con<lb break="no"/>tact with the people of Newfoundland than per<lb break="no"/>haps anyone else here. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I have listened to the addresses this afternoon 
     <lb/>
     of able speakers, and to the mover of the amend<lb break="no"/>ment to the amendment — an old politician, an 
     <lb/>
     able speaker, and a fine man. His amendment to 
     <lb/>
     the amendment was put in a very subtle way; but 
     <lb/>
     I say to members of this House, beware and think 
     <lb/>
     before you act. Since introducing this amend<lb break="no"/>ment, 1 have been particularly interested in the 
     <lb/>
     debate which followed, more particularly the part 
     <lb/>
     concerning the amendment itself. The amend<lb break="no"/>ment contained few words and that was in strik<lb break="no"/>ing contrast to the motion. Before deciding to 
     <lb/>
     move an amendment, it seemed to me that there 
     <lb/>
     was something fishy about the whole resolution 
     <lb/>
     and I decided to Oppose it. Since then and after 
     <lb/>
     listening to members' expressions of opinion, 
     <lb/>
     and noting newspaper comments, I am more than 
     <lb/>
     ever convinced that my sense of suspicion is 
     <lb/>
     more than justified. Further I believe that there 
     <lb/>
     was a political attempt to disrupt the feeling of 
     <lb/>
     this Convention at a ume when it needed peace. 
     <lb/>
     True, the wording of this attempt was 
     <lb/>
     camouflaged in a fact-finding mission to Ottawa 
     <lb/>
     at the expense of this country, but I may say that 
     <lb/>
     my sponsors and friends in the district of Car<lb break="no"/>bonear did not give a priority mandate to study 
     <lb/>
     the affairs of Canada first, they did give me a 
     <lb/>
     mandate to study and examine the affairs of New<lb break="no"/>foundland first and foremost. That is how I un<lb break="no"/>derstand it. If I am wrong, then I would say that 
     <lb/>
     these level-headed men made a great mistake in 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="145" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0145.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">145</fw>
          
     sending me over here to represent them in this 
     <lb/>
     National Convention We had hardly begun to get 
     <lb/>
     those facts concerning Newfoundland when a red 
     <lb/>
     herring was thrown across our path to divert 
     <lb/>
     attention and interest from the job we were sent 
     <lb/>
     here to do. This attempt was made when so far 
     <lb/>
     we have received only three reports in public 
     <lb/>
     session; and with regard to these reports, 
     <lb/>
     whatever may be said of them during discussion, 
     <lb/>
     insofar as information will allow them, they are 
     <lb/>
     a great credit to the committees concerned.... 
     <lb/>
     Several members supporting the motion stressed 
     <lb/>
     the time factor, that is an important point. I may 
     <lb/>
     say that there is no one in this building more 
     <lb/>
     anxious to be through with his job and back home 
     <lb/>
     to his own environment than I, but I submit there 
     <lb/>
     is a better way of doing this. In view of the 
     <lb/>
     expense to this country, we should try and hold 
     <lb/>
     sessions mornings as well as afternoons. 
     <lb/>
     Moreover, we must remember that Commission 
     <lb/>
     of Government have been in control of this 
     <lb/>
     country for 13 years and it is going to take time 
     <lb/>
     to get acquainted with the problems, and if the 
     <lb/>
     result of our findings will have a bearing on the 
     <lb/>
     future welfare of Newfoundland for generations 
     <lb/>
     to come, I submit the time factor is not so impor<lb break="no"/>tant as it may appear. Nor does it matter material<lb break="no"/>ly if the Commission continues in office for 
     <lb/>
     another year or two as long as it keeps within 
     <lb/>
     budget estimates and does not give away 
     <lb/>
     Labrador. May I say that there are some weighty 
     <lb/>
     problems that affect the future and the economy 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland more so than any others, the 
     <lb/>
     national debt, and the entry of our fishery 
     <lb/>
     products into the United States under fair trading 
     <lb/>
     tariff conditions. If we could have concentrated 
     <lb/>
     study and efforts to even partially solve these 
     <lb/>
     fundamental things, then I would say emphatical<lb break="no"/>ly any government of good honest men, call it 
     <lb/>
     what you may, will bring Newfoundland to a 
     <lb/>
     place of happiness and prosperity for all its 
     <lb/>
     people to a level yet unknown. God guard thee, 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I have been listening to debates <lb/> since last
                  Monday, and I am of the opinion that it <lb/> has gone far enough. We are wasting
                  valuable <lb/> time and getting nowhere. I am confident as far <lb/> as the
                  district which I represent is concerned, that <lb/> they want to learn facts about
                  any government <lb/> and the motion before this House at the present <lb/> time is
                  not a form of government, it is a fact <lb/>
                  <cb/> finding matter, it is to find out what Canada has <lb/> to offer us for the
                  future of Newfoundland. <lb/> Things have been said which were on the <lb/>
                  boisterous side and that is not what we came here <lb/> for. We came to go into
                  the economic conditions <lb/> of Newfoundland and we are doing that to the <lb/>
                  best of our ability. There would be nothing amiss <lb/> in our getting from Canada
                  facts as to what she <lb/> has to offer us for the future, and we can go on <lb/>
                  with our work; and when we are finished we can <lb/> go into those facts and I am
                  sure we will be none <lb/> the worse off.... I do not want to delay the House,
                  <lb/> I have much pleasure in supporting the amend<lb break="no"/>ment to
                  amendment to the motion made by <lb/> Mr. Bradley. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I would like to refer first to the <lb/> question
                  to which Mr. Higgins referred, the time <lb/> of the referendum. There is nobody
                  in the House <lb/> any more anxious than I am to get the job over, <lb/> but I am
                  not worried about spring or fall or any <lb/> referendum at all, until we are
                  ready for it. For <lb/> that reason I feel as I did the other day on the <lb/>
                  amendment made by Mr. Penney. I will not go <lb/> into a repetition as we have
                  been long enough <lb/> here now. I would like to refer to the amendment <lb/> to
                  the amendment made by Mr. Bradley. That can <lb/> be very confusing, I am not
                  suggesting that it was <lb/> meant to be confusing. If I understood the motion
                  <lb/> correctly, the amendment is practically identical <lb/> to the original
                  motion in intent or in effect. The <lb/> delegation when appointed would not leave
                  <lb/> before the 1st of January. I cannot see the <lb/> similarity to the
                  amendment of Mr. Penney's. <lb/> Mr. Penney's amendment in part states the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of ascertaining the attitude of Canada be <lb/> deferred for
                  consideration until reports of com<lb break="no"/>mittees are brought in. That is
                  absolutely dif<lb break="no"/>ferent from the amendment to the amendment. <lb/>
                  For that reason I do not see how I can vote for <lb/> anything but the amendment
                  of Mr. Penney. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> It makes one feel rather nervous <lb/>because I
                  realise my inability to reply to the <lb/>learned lawyers and learned politicians
                  who have <lb/>spoken, but before this vote is taken I would like <lb/>to say a few
                  words because I am very much <lb/>concerned about the whole matter. As I stated
                  <lb/>here on different occasions, I am here repre<lb break="no"/>senting people,
                  the majority of whom are poor, <lb/>and I feel it is my bounden duty to do
                  everything <lb/>in my power to see their interests are best <lb/>protected and
                  conserved. As a previous speaker <lb/>
                  <pb n="146" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0146.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">146</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">NOVEMBER 1946</fw> pointed out, if this amendment to the
                  amendment <lb/> does not go through we might be here until May <lb/> next.
                  Personally I would like to see it finished <lb/> next week, if possible, because I
                  realise that the <lb/> people who came here for this Convention are of <lb/> the
                  ordinary common people like myself. It is not <lb/> going to affect the
                  businessman how long we are <lb/> here, and I do not say that with prejudice, but
                  any <lb/> unnecessary delays will naturally come on the <lb/> Bell Island miner or
                  the labourer of St. John's or <lb/> the men in the woods, and for that reason I am
                  <lb/> prepared to work night and day to get through <lb/> with this Convention. I
                  have often worked harder. <lb/> I know what it is to go in the mines and work
                  night <lb/> and day. But I would like to be clear on this matter <lb/> now before
                  the Chair before I vote. I am going to <lb/> vote for this amendment, even if it
                  means we are <lb/> to be here until next May or June, because I want <lb/> to let
                  those who sent me here know that I am <lb/> doing all in my power to protect their
                  interests <lb/> and the interests of the people all over New<lb break="no"/>foundland as well. Furthermore I am voting for <lb/> the amendment because I
                  realise that by being too <lb/> hasty we might be doing harm instead of good. I
                  <lb/> am opposed to confederation as I am a firm <lb/> believer in the land of my
                  birth, and will not be <lb/> satisfied until Newfoundland possesses a respon<lb break="no"/>sible form of government, so as to make it a better <lb/> place to
                  live in with the least expenditure.... <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> Mr. Chairman, I want to vote for <lb/>the
                  amendment because I think it will give the <lb/>Convention time to put its own
                  House in order, <lb/>and give the various committees time to assemble <lb/>the
                  facts and present their reports and debate on <lb/>them.... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Mr. Chairman, I feel that we have al<lb break="no"/>lowed this debate to come down to too narrow a <lb/> vision, as some people are
                  thinking of the bit of <lb/> heat it engendered. I think that, looking at the
                  <lb/> problems of Newfoundland, the Convention <lb/> should find out what is in
                  our own country before <lb/> going to another for terms. I agree that some time
                  <lb/> or other in the future we could find what the terms <lb/> of confederation
                  would be, but there is no need <lb/> of rushing this issue. I do not want it
                  thought that <lb/> we are keeping valuable information from the <lb/> people, but
                  with such an important issue as con<lb break="no"/>federation with Canada or
                  anywhere else there <lb/> should be nothing left undone to ascertain the true
                  <lb/> facts, and we ought to have good terms ourselves <lb/> to offer. I for one
                  will support the amendment. <lb/>
               </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> Mr. Chairman, I would like to have <lb/> an
                  explanation on the terms of reference con<lb break="no"/>tained in the act of 1946
                  regarding what forms of <lb/> government should be placed before the people. <lb/>
                  I think we should know whether confederation is <lb/> included in the forms of
                  government to be placed <lb/> upon the ballot paper if a national referendum is
                  <lb/> recommended by this Convention. Frankly I do <lb/> not know what the terms
                  of reference are or if this <lb/> Convention is going to confine itself to any
                  <lb/> specific number of forms of government to be <lb/> balloted for. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I have listened very carefully to <lb/> those who
                  have spoken and I am wondering what <lb/> prompted me to come here, because the
                  whole <lb/> matter is so confusing. I had an idea that our duty <lb/> was to take
                  stock after doing business for a period <lb/> of 13 years, and that after doing
                  that we should <lb/> be able to find out as near exactly as possible <lb/> what
                  our assets are. But, unfortunately, this mat<lb break="no"/>ter of confederation
                  slipped in and the whole <lb/> thing has been interrupted so far as stock-taking
                  <lb/> is concerned. It appears to me, as a judge of all <lb/> trades, that the
                  pro-confederates have a boat for <lb/> sale and that boat is called the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Newfoundland</hi>, and <lb/> before there is a bid on
                  it at all, it is pronounced <lb/> 100 years behind the times, leaky and rotten.
                  <lb/> How can you expect to make a sale and a good <lb/> deal with it? In
                  supporting this amendment of <lb/> Mr. Penney I wish to go on record that I am
                  <lb/> prepared to defend this country to the best of my <lb/> ability and I say
                  let us find out all the facts of our <lb/> own country before taking it to another
                  to auction <lb/> off. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> Mr. Chairman, I have not spoken in <lb/> this
                  debate, except for a few minutes this after<lb break="no"/>noon, but I still say
                  we have had too many <lb/> speeches and too much time wasted. If we had <lb/> less
                  pussy-footing the debate on this resolution <lb/> would have been over long ago. I
                  think the whole <lb/> issue has been made confusing, and I think that <lb/> terms
                  from Canada should be obtained, otherwise <lb/> the Convention will be remiss in
                  its duty. The <lb/> only point I can see in prolonging the debate is to <lb/>
                  decide when a delegation should be sent to Ot<lb break="no"/>tawa. That is why I
                  support the resolution. How <lb/> ever, though I am not a politician, perhaps it
                  <lb/> would be a good thing if this matter would be <lb/> shelved until January
                  next and, with this in mind, <lb/> I could vote for Mr. Bradley's amendment, as
                  the <lb/> machinery must be put in motion and the facts <lb/>
                  <pb n="147" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0147.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="num">147</fw> collected on all matters of interest to the country. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> Mr. Chairman, I will support Mr. <lb/>Bradley's
                  amendment to the amendment because <lb/>it supplies the missing link to this
                  debate, and let <lb/>us challenge this whole thing now until we are in <lb/>a
                  position to talk about it intelligently. I am not a <lb/>confederate at the
                  present time, but I would like <lb/>to see all sides of the question brought out.
                  There <lb/>is no harm in putting the machinery in order, and <lb/>if the proper
                  machinery is set up I am sure we can <lb/>make our own time as regards sending a
                     delega<lb break="no"/>tion. I do not like the idea of setting up a commit<lb break="no"/>tee today and going off tomorrow. I again say that <lb/>I support
                  the amendment of Mr. Bradley. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I feel I would be unreasonably <lb/> prolonging
                  this debate if I spoke lengthily, so my <lb/> remarks shall be as brief as
                  possible. Up to the <lb/> present I am not a confederate. On the contrary, <lb/> I
                  have been accused very many times of being too <lb/> much Newfoundland. But there
                  is one thing I <lb/> shall make clear and that is that I have always <lb/> been
                  big enough to avoid the use of personalities <lb/> and to respect the opinions of
                  all persons, ir<lb break="no"/>respective of their political affiliations,
                  although <lb/> time and again I have been misquoted by some of <lb/> my best
                  friends. I support in all earnestness <lb/> Mr. Bradley's amendment to the
                  amendment. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> Mr. Chairman, speaking to <lb/>the original motion
                  here a few days ago I think I <lb/>made a statement that I would support the
                  motion. <lb/>Since then there have been amendments offered <lb/>by Mr. Penney and
                  Mr. Bradley. The original <lb/>motion made by Mr. Smallwood did not state any
                  <lb/>particular time when all these things were about <lb/>to happen. Mr. Penney's
                  amendment conveyed <lb/>something like what was known in the old politi<lb break="no"/>cal days as giving the question the six months' <lb/>hoist. If that
                  amendment is carried there may <lb/>never be a chance of getting this information
                  now <lb/>sought and this whole debate may have to be gone <lb/>over again... For
                  that reason I cannot support <lb/>Mr. Penney's amendment. I understand from
                  <lb/>some of the speeches that Mr. Bradley's amend<lb break="no"/>ment resembles
                  to a certain extent the original <lb/>motion, and it means that this Convention
                  will <lb/>still leave on record that it desires to be fully <lb/>informed on all
                  matters and provides that a <lb/>delegation shall not proceed to Ottawa before
                  <lb/>January 1st, 1947. That gives us something <lb/>definite and for that reason
                  I will support it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VINC1">Mr. Vincent</persName> I support whole-heartedly the <lb/>
                  <cb/> amendment so ably proposed by Mr. Bradley, <lb/> and in so doing I am not
                  impugning any other <lb/> person. I gave my support to Mr. Smallwood's <lb/>
                  motion and my reason therefor. Now the majority <lb/> of delegates have expressed
                  their willingness to <lb/> have a delegation sent to Ottawa and the <lb/>
                  delegates who supported Mr. Penney's amend<lb break="no"/>ment, without supporting
                  the main question, did <lb/> so only because of the time factor provided; <lb/>
                  others have supported Mr. Bradley's amendment <lb/> because it offers a compromise
                  and because a <lb/> definite time is set. It is highly desirable that we <lb/> get
                  back to discussions of committees and that <lb/> can only be achieved by a prompt
                  disposition of <lb/> the whole subject matter now before the Chair, <lb/> for my
                  opinion is that this Convention has no <lb/> right to refuse to examine any issue
                  brought <lb/> before it. Personally I am willing to explore every <lb/> form of
                  government, including representative, <lb/> responsible and confederation. The
                  people of <lb/> Bonavista North want to know the terms, if any, <lb/> that are
                  going to be made with Canada. I cannot <lb/> conceive how any delegate can stand
                  on his feet <lb/> and say we have no right to seek such and such <lb/> terms from
                  Canada. I very much regret, however, <lb/> that there was no trip to Ottawa
                  offered me. But <lb/> this is not the time to discuss transportation or <lb/> such
                  like matters and I reaffirm my obligation to <lb/> the people who sent me here. I
                  am not prepared <lb/> to say whether confederation is good or bad, and <lb/> I
                  resent the statement made that we are 100 years <lb/> behind the times. I am
                  prepared to examine any <lb/> issue brought in here in the best interests of <lb/>
                  Newfoundland and its people.... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, I rise to agree with <lb/> my
                  colleague from Grand Falls, and to show there <lb/> is no collusion between us.
                  The debate no doubt <lb/> is amusing. First we have a man proposing a <lb/> motion
                  in which he already believed, in fact we <lb/> know he believed in it because he
                  has been fight<lb break="no"/>ing for it for years, and he believes in the
                  principle <lb/> of that motion which was foisted upon us. <lb/> Mr. Higgins
                  seconded the motion and in the next <lb/> breath he does not agree with it at all.
                  Then <lb/> Mr. Burry stated last week that he agreed with the <lb/> motion,
                  although it was a little premature. This <lb/> afternoon he was supporting the
                  amendment to <lb/> the amendment. My colleague supported <lb/> Mr. Smallwood's
                  motion; now he is supporting <lb/> Mr. Bradley's. Then we have Mr. Ballam alter<lb break="no"/>ing his mind. I think this issue is not one which <lb/>
                  <pb n="148" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0148.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">148</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> should at all be considered at the present
                  time as <lb/> the facts relative to our own country's welfare <lb/> should first
                  be sought. I just rose to make it plain <lb/> that I am against the motion because
                  I feel there <lb/> is something subtle in it, and I will vote for the <lb/>
                  amendment. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FOWL2">Mr. Fowler</persName> Mr. Chairman, I contend that the <lb/> amendment
                  to the amendment was a political <lb/> move to further confuse the issue, split
                  the vote <lb/> and thus assure a majority in favour of the <lb/> original motion.
                  I therefore reaffirm my former <lb/> intention to support the amendment, and I
                  would <lb/> exhort all members to stick to their original <lb/> decision to
                  support the amendment proposed by <lb/> Mr. Penney, and not to be swayed by the
                     confus<lb break="no"/>ing amendment more confusingly presented by <lb/> the
                  learned member for Bonavista East.... I am <lb/> pleased to see that Mr. Bradley
                  confirms my <lb/> opinion as expressed on Thursday last, when he <lb/> says it
                  would be ridiculous to conceive of a <lb/> delegation proceeding to Canada without
                  first <lb/> being informed of our own financial and eco<lb break="no"/>nomic
                  position, a statement which should only <lb/> further strengthen the argument in
                  favour of <lb/> Mr. Penney's amendment, which in short just <lb/> means waiting
                  until such time as this Convention <lb/> may chose to send a delegation. I contend
                  that <lb/> this resolution should not have been brought in at <lb/> this time,
                  firstly because it has sown the seed of <lb/> distrust and misunderstanding among
                  the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of this Convention at a time when they <lb/> should be
                  working in harmony towards the com<lb break="no"/>pletion of the first and most
                  vital task, the reports <lb/> of the various committees, and secondly because
                  <lb/> in the ears and eyes of the public it will eclipse <lb/> the facts that
                  should be given careful study at this <lb/> time. I feel, that if there are people
                  in this country <lb/> interested in confederation, and if we believe in <lb/>
                  democracy, we must at the proper time give them <lb/> the opportunity to express
                  their desires, and I <lb/> think that had Mr. Smallwood awaited a more <lb/>
                  opportune time and introduced his resolution in <lb/> a different spirit there
                  could be little reasonable <lb/> opposition. I must confess that I was not invited
                  <lb/> to the alleged confederate conferences, nor did <lb/> Mr. Smailwood as yet
                  make any overture to me. <lb/> Probably I was considered too insignificant, or
                  <lb/> more likely he was aware of my attitude towards <lb/> the whole scheme. I
                  feel sure there is still some <lb/> honour left, even at this Convention. I
                  suggest <lb/> Mr. Chairman, that we define once and for all our <lb/>
                  <cb/> position, and then with confidence pursue our <lb/> tasks to a successful
                  conclusion, with equal rights <lb/> for all and privileges for none. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> Mr. Chairman, I do not propose to <lb/> make any
                  lengthy remarks. As a matter of fact I <lb/> have spoken only once, but I wish to
                  say that if <lb/> one were not so closely involved in this question, <lb/> and if
                  one were rather sitting in the gallery a great <lb/> deal of the logic displayed
                  would cause some <lb/> amusement. I must say that I do not understand <lb/> the
                  confusion regarding the amendment.... <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> Mr. Chairman, I beg to move an <lb/> amendment
                  that before we proceed further it is <lb/> essential for us to know exactly what
                  the terms <lb/> of reference of this Convention are. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There are four questions now <lb/> before the
                  Chair. We have the original motion, <lb/> the amendment, the amendment to the
                     amend<lb break="no"/>ment and now we have Mr. Fogwill's amend<lb break="no"/>ment, the terms of which I would like for him to <lb/> put in writing. It cannot
                  be a substantive motion. <lb/> I might say in passing, without having the ad<lb break="no"/>vantage of seeing your motion in writing, that <lb/> there is a
                  striking similarity in your motion to Mr. <lb/> Penney's amendment. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> I did not have an opportunity of <lb/> having it
                  prepared in writing. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Is it an amendment to the <lb/> original motion
                  or an amendment to one of the <lb/> amendments to the original motion? The ques<lb break="no"/>tion is inexplicably confused. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> I move this resolution as an amend<lb break="no"/>ment to the original motion. It is unfortunate that <lb/> the question before
                  the Chair should be intro<lb break="no"/>duced at this time. The motion is that it
                  is essen<lb break="no"/>tial, before we proceed further, to know exactly <lb/>
                  what the terms of reference of this Convention <lb/> are. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The terms of reference have <lb/> been
                  considered and ruled upon. Perhaps now, <lb/> insofar as the competency of the
                  Convention is <lb/> concerned to recommend that among other forms <lb/> of
                  government, confederation with Canada be <lb/> placed upon the ballot, our expert
                  adviser might <lb/> shorten this discussion and hasten the voting <lb/> upon these
                  rather complicated questions if he <lb/> would advise us and get rid of the
                  matter. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>Professor Wheare I am willing to give an opin<lb break="no"/>ion on that without any reservations at all; but 
     <lb/>many questions raised, I think, would be very 
     <lb/>doubtful ones to pronounce upon, If I understand 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="149" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0149.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">149</fw>
       
     Mr. Fogwill's question, it is this: is the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion competent to recommend to the government 
     <lb/>
     of the United Kingdom that the form of govern<lb break="no"/>ment, confederation with Canada, be placed upon 
     <lb/>
     the ballot? The answer, in my opinion, is Yes, the 
     <lb/>
     Convention is competent to recommend the plac<lb break="no"/>ing upon the ballot paper any form of government 
     <lb/>
     which, in their opinion, is worthwhile placing 
     <lb/>
     before the people of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Does that hold for union with the <lb/> United
                  States? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Professor Wheare The opinion which I just 
     <lb/>
     gave admitted of no qualifications, except that 
     <lb/>
     the form of government is worthwhile, in their 
     <lb/>
     opinion. That includes union with the United 
     <lb/>
     States, but you know you have to get the consent 
     <lb/>
     of the Government of the United States and, of 
     <lb/>
     course, the consent of the Government of the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom for all these forms. I see nothing 
     <lb/>
     in the terms of reference which requires the Con<lb break="no"/>vention to consider or recommend only forms of 
     <lb/>
     government within the British Empire, there is 
     <lb/>
     nothing here which excludes that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> My question is now answered. I <lb/> beg leave to
                  withdraw the motion, with the con<lb break="no"/>sent of my seconder. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> Mr. Chairman, it seems to me <lb/> that if Mr.
                  Wheare at the outset of this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion had given us a little talk
                  we might be further <lb/> ahead, instead of floundering around in amend<lb break="no"/>ments and substantive motions. However, when <lb/> we started we
                  thought the best way to get at the <lb/> facts was by breaking up into committees.
                  With <lb/> regard to Mr. Smallwood's statement I see no <lb/> reason to change my
                  stand from a week ago. I did <lb/> not at any time tell Mr. Smallwood that I would
                  <lb/> support his motion and I wish that to go into the <lb/> record. I did always
                  lend a sympathetic ear to <lb/> what he had to say. I am against the amendment
                  <lb/> to the amendment. The way I feel about the whole <lb/> thing now is to see
                  it thrown out. However, the <lb/> position has been clarified somewhat, and there
                  <lb/> is nothing we can do about it. I do not see why <lb/> we should rush this
                  thing, which is premature <lb/> anyway. We have been 14 years under one form <lb/>
                  of government and surely we can stand to wait <lb/> for another form for a
                  reasonable while. But I <lb/> want to make it clear that I did not say at any time
                  <lb/> that I would support Mr. Smallwood's motion. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BAIL3">Mr. Bailey</persName> Mr. Chairman, as the last speaker <lb/>remarked, we
                  have been floundering along and I <lb/>
                  <cb/> am sure we can thank Mr. Fogwill and Professor <lb/> Wheare for clarifying
                  the situation regarding our <lb/> status as a Convention. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Mr. Chairman, it is rather strange, but <lb/> the
                  essence of the two questions before the Chair <lb/> is simple. Do you or do you
                  not want terms from <lb/> Canada and do you or do you not want them now? <lb/> In
                  speaking thus I expect I am expressing the <lb/> view of a great many people.
                  Personally I do not <lb/> want them now and I am voting against the mo<lb break="no"/>tion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, just a few <lb/> words in reply
                  to Mr. Harrington. He says he did <lb/> not promise to vote for the motion I
                  introduced, <lb/> and I do not think that I said this afternoon that <lb/> he had
                  so promised. What I did say this afternoon <lb/> is that months ago Mr. Harrington
                  told me that he <lb/> would vote to get the terms of confederation, but <lb/> he
                  did not promise me with regard to this par<lb break="no"/>ticular motion of mine.
                  I would like to reply to <lb/> other remarks made with regard to this rushing
                  <lb/> business of getting the terms. I wonder if rushing <lb/> is quite the right
                  term to use. For 13 years we have <lb/> had Commission of Government; for 79 years
                  we <lb/> have had responsible government and for 23 <lb/> years we have had
                  representative government. <lb/> Now the country has spent over 100 years under
                  <lb/> those three forms of government and I fail to see <lb/> how the Convention
                  would be rushing in this <lb/> particular instance. It is true my motion had not
                  <lb/> specified the time with regard to the sending of a <lb/> delegation to
                  Canada but merely proposed that <lb/> negotiations be held as soon as possible
                  with the <lb/> Canadian government relative to the terms of <lb/> federal union. I
                  realise some members voted <lb/> against my motion as they were sincere in their
                  <lb/> belief that to accept it would be to taking a <lb/> premature step, and in
                  this connection Mr. <lb/> Bradley's motion was for the primary purpose of <lb/>
                  meeting the objections of those who claimed that <lb/> the original resolution was
                  premature. Now my <lb/> motion merely called for the accumulation of <lb/> facts
                  regarding possible confederation, whilst the <lb/> amendment suggested that the
                  collection of such <lb/> facts be postponed for an indefinite period, so that
                  <lb/> the acceptance of the amendment would only <lb/> leave the matter open for
                  future and acrimonious <lb/> debate which would not be the best interests of <lb/>
                  the Convention. My resolution was simply to <lb/> procure facts relevant to
                  confederation, but <lb/> would in no way give a delegation power to <lb/>
                  <pb n="150" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-04_Page_0150.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">150</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> negotiate with the Canadian government in <lb/> regard to possible federal
                  union. There are <lb/> thousands of Newfoundlanders tonight who have <lb/> a
                  strong desire for confederation and those people <lb/>
                  <cb/> have the right to request and receive all the facts <lb/> pertaining to the
                  terms of confederation. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-02-23, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

   
           <!-- <p>
     November 5, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     [The Secretary read a report and correspon<lb break="no"/>dence from the Newfoundland Industrial 
     <lb/>
     Development Board¹] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Butt I give notice that I will on tomorrow 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     move that the report of the Industrial Develop<lb break="no"/>ment Board be referred to a committee for con<lb break="no"/>sideration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion to send a Delegation to Ottawa² 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Butt In view of the fact that this report may 
     <lb/>
     have an effect upon the people's thinking, I move 
     <lb/>
     that the debate be adjourned until tomorrow, and 
     <lb/>
     that we proceed with the other orders of the day. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Chairman Anybody second that motion? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Kennedy I second the motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Moved by Mr. Butt and secon<lb break="no"/>ded by Mr. Kennedy that the debate on the mo<lb break="no"/>tion to send a delegation to Ottawa be adjourned 
     <lb/>
     until tomorrow to allow the members time to 
     <lb/>
     study the report and the enclosure of Mr. Pratt's 
     <lb/>
     address. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [After some debate, the motion to adjourn debate 
     <lb/>
     was defeated] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins Mr. Chairman, since adjouming 
     <lb/>
     last evening I gave some thought to the matter 
     <lb/>
     under discussion today with the idea of trying to 
     <lb/>
     reconcile the different points of view.... I sum it 
     <lb/>
     up in this way, in eight points: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. We are all agreed that we want the terms 
     <lb/>
     of confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. The difference between us is when is the 
     <lb/>
     time to make the inquiry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. Mr. Smallwood's motion is to start the 
     <lb/>
     machinery for the approach to Canada immedi<lb break="no"/>ately. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. Mr. Penney's amendment is to defer the 
     <lb/>
     approach until we have finished the reports. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. Mr. Bradley's amendment is the same as 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood's motion, but the delegation is 
     <lb/>
     not to leave before the first of January. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6. If Mr. Bradley's amendment is passed and 
     <lb/>
     the delegates named, they can begin work imme<lb break="no"/>diately and work through the Christmas vacation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     7. The delegates appointed would be 
     <lb/>
     honourable men and would, I am confident, not 
     <lb/>
     be prepared to consult with the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     authorities until they are armed with the neces<lb break="no"/>sary data. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     8. So that there would be no doubt in the 
     <lb/>
     minds of the members of the Convention, I sug<lb break="no"/>gest that if the amendment suggested by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Bradley was carried, that before the delegates left 
     <lb/>
     for Canada they individually assure the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion that they were so armed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With that safeguard I cannot imagine any 
     <lb/>
     doubt in the minds of the delegates as to the 
     <lb/>
     approach being in safe hands..... With that 
     <lb/>
     safeguard, I can see no objection to having the 
     <lb/>
     amendment moved by Mr. Bradley passed im<lb break="no"/>mediately. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Crummey I rise for the purpose of report<lb break="no"/>ing my position as to the matter before the Chair. 
     <lb/>
     I have listened attentively to all the speeches. 
     <lb/>
     Some of the discussion did not appeal to me. I do 
     <lb/>
     not intend to make a speech, I think time enough 
     <lb/>
     has been wasted. I will be as concise as I possibly 
     <lb/>
     can. The motion is that a delegation will be 
     <lb/>
     appointed from this National Convention. The 
     <lb/>
     amendment is that the sending of a delegation be 
     <lb/>
     deferred, and the reasons offered I consider 
     <lb/>
     sound. The amendment to the amendment is a 
     <lb/>
     simple matter of trying to befog the issue. The 
     <lb/>
     sending of a delegation from this Convention I 
     <lb/>
     cannot agree with, because I take the position that 
     <lb/>
     the matter of confederation, or federation must be 
     <lb/>
     negotiated by governments and we are not a 
     <lb/>
     govemment.... I want to state emphatically that I 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     ¹This Board was created in January 1942 to promote the innovation and expansion of diversified industries in 
     <lb/>
    Newfoundland. For further information see Peter Neary, Newfoundland in the Atlantic World, 1929-1949 
     <lb/>(Kingston and Montreal. 1988), p. 168. 
     <lb/>²Above, pp. 93, 104, 120, 128. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>