<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-03-24"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-03-24">24 March 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="371" to="376"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0371.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0372.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0373.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0374.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0375.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0376.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-08">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0371">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0371.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0372">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0372.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0373">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0373.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0374">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0374.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0375">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0375.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0376">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0376.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="371"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0371.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">March 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">371</fw>
            
<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">
     March 24, 1947 
</head>
</div>

<div type="section">

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Job gave notice that he would on tomorrow 
     <lb/>
     move that the Report of the Fisheries Committee 
     <lb/>
     be presented]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Mr. Job I make that motion, but suggest that,<lb/>with the consent of the House, we might proceed


    
            <cb/>

         
with the report today. It has been circulated, and <lb/>it is going to be read in sections, and after that,<lb/>with the consent of the whole House, I suggest<lb/>we go on debating it.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">Report of the Fisheries Committee:<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref>
<lb/>Committee of the Whole<lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I would like to draw your atten<lb break="no"/>tion to the fact that the object of a committee is 
     <lb/>
     not to debate principles, but to discuss and correct 
     <lb/>
     details of the bill or report which may be before 
     <lb/>
     the House. As there are several of those reports 
     <lb/>
     to consider and some are of considerable length, 
     <lb/>
     I suggest we confine ourselves so far as, possible 
     <lb/>
     to details of the report and not the matter of 
     <lb/>
     general principles, upon which perhaps more ex<lb break="no"/>tensive speeches may be required. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

       

    

            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> This Fisheries Report consists of some<lb/>160 pages, including the appendices; the report<lb/>itself consists of 68 pages. In introducing it I<lb/>would like to take into consideration some advice<lb/>I noticed in this morning's newspaper. It says,<lb/>"When the reports are introduced it is to be hoped<lb/>that comment will be brief and pointed, designed<lb/>to bring out the truth rather than let constituents<lb/>know that their delegates are doing their job." I<lb/>think that a good remark and I want to set a good<lb/>example by being short.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>I would like to refer to the serious loss this<lb/>Committee sustained by the serious illness of Mr.<lb/>Brown, who was a great strength with his great<lb/>knowledge of fisheries; it was really a bad blow<lb/>when he had to discontinue his work. Then again,<lb/>we were deprived of the services of our present<lb/>worthy Chairman with his knowledge of the<lb/>fisheries. I hope when you consider the report you<lb/>will hear these things in mind and realise we have<lb/>been handicapped. We have not been having the<lb/>best of our talent.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The main object of all these reports is to deter<lb break="no"/>mine by the presentation of facts and figures<lb/>whether the country is and will continue to be<lb/>self-supporting. By the term "self-supporting" I<lb/>mean not only whether it can balance its budget,<lb/>but also whether the country, if it stands alone,<lb/>can expect to provide a decent living and social<lb/>services for its 300,000-odd inhabitants. I would<lb/>say that perhaps the most important feature of this

            <cb/>
          
report is contained on page 38 which sums up the <lb/>value of fisheries during the year 1946. The<lb/>figures show the total value of our fisheries<lb/>during the calendar year 1946 was roughly $34.5<lb/>million, which includes an estimated $1 million<lb/>worth of fish consumed by our own population.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>We have received great assistance from the<lb/>Newfoundland Fisheries Board as well as from<lb/>the Customs Department in arriving at these<lb/>figures, and they can be taken as reasonably<lb/>accurate.<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>However, it is one thing to arrive at today's<lb/>valuation, which as we all know is a very much<lb/>inflated one, but it is quite another matter to arrive<lb/>at reliable figures for future years. The Commit<lb break="no"/>tee has (probably very rashly) mentioned a figure<lb/>of $24 million as a possible average. This is<lb/>actually a pure guess, and by some people may<lb/>be considered on the optimistic side. It will be<lb/>obvious to everyone that there are so many future<lb/>contingencies over which we have little or no<lb/>control that no estimate of this sort can really be<lb/>relied upon.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I would like to point out two features of the<lb/>report which I think will be specially interesting<lb/>to members of the Convention, as they may come<lb/>as a surprise. I refer to the sub-committee report<lb/>in the appendix on the matter of subsidiary<lb/>fisheries which shows a value of $2.6 million;<lb/>and also the report on by-products which shows<lb/>a value of nearly $1.7 million. These two<lb/>branches of the industry especially seem to be<lb/>capable of very material development. Our hope<lb/>seems to be in the further development of markets<lb/>for fresh and frozen fish and for canned products,<lb/>as a relief for the salt codfish industry, and also<lb/>in the further development of our herring fishery<lb/>which would seem to have scope for very large<lb/>development if properly encouraged, and by that<lb/>I mean research work<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>We have been fortunate in having the New<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_01">[1] Volume II:181. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
           

            <pb n="372"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0372.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">372</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">March 1947</fw>
    
     foundland Fisheries Board and its energetic and 
     <lb/>
     capable Chairman, Mr. Gushue, at the disposal of 
     <lb/>
     the country and I feel sure that if the trade and the 
     <lb/>
     people of Newfoundland will continue to place 
     <lb/>
     their confidence in Mr. Gushue and his very 
     <lb/>
     capable Board, there is every hope for the future 
     <lb/>
     of the fishing industry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As a closing comment, may I say that the 
     <lb/>
     Committee has worked hard and has done its best 
     <lb/>
     to present an intelligent report. The Committee 
     <lb/>
     invites fair criticism; but I ask the delegates to be 
     <lb/>
     reasonable and not expect ready answers to ques<lb break="no"/>tions which even a minister of fisheries might not 
     <lb/>
     be able to answer. I am not that minister. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In view of the voluminous nature of this 
     <lb/>
     report, I suggest it be divided for reading and 
     <lb/>
     debating purposes into 12 sections which I shall 
     <lb/>
     define as we proceed. The first section for treat<lb break="no"/>ment in this manner is on pages 1-15 of the report 
     <lb/>
     which will automatically include Appendix A, 
     <lb/>
     the report of the sub-committee on cold storage. 
     <lb/>
     These pages comprise also an introduction to the 
     <lb/>
     report. I therefore now request, Mr. Chairman, 
     <lb/>
     with your permission, that the Secretary read 
     <lb/>
     pages 1-15, and Appendix A. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read this section of the report]</hi> 
    </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Mr. Chairman, I want to make note of 
     <lb/>one omission I made when introducing this 
     <lb/>report. I had a note to remind me to inform those 
     <lb/>who don't know that the Committee was 
     <lb/>strengthened very much by the inclusion after<lb break="no"/>wards of Mr. William Keough, because he has 
     <lb/>kept our records wonderfully, and is actually 
     <lb/>responsible for the wording of this report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> This section is now open for 
     <lb/>
     debate. We shall deal with the different sections 
     <lb/>
     one by one and pass them seriatim. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> On page 6 of the Appendix — 
     <lb/>
     does that mean an individual plant? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> That is one plant. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> You gave the amount paid to 
     <lb/>
     fishermen and to labour employed in and around 
     <lb/>
     the plant for 1943-1946, and the figures rise every 
     <lb/>
     year, so that last year that plant paid $234,000 to 
     <lb/>
     the fishermen and to the plant workers $69,000. 
     <lb/>
     Can Mr. Job give us any idea of what those 
     <lb/>
     corresponding figures might be in 1947, taking 
     <lb/>
     that plant as being subject to the same conditions 
     <lb/>
     as other plants throughout the country? I am 
     <lb/>
     trying to get the position generally for the fresh 
     <lb/>
     fish industry in 1947. Could you give us an 
     

            <cb/>
           
     outline of what it might be? 
     </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> It is impossible to give any outline; we 
     <lb/>do not know what the position is going to be. We 
     <lb/>have not made any contracts. The American 
     <lb/>market at the present time is in a bad condition. 
     <lb/>The British market has not purchased any fish. It 
     <lb/>is utterly impossible to make any commitments. 
     <lb/>I would not risk stating what I think would hap<lb break="no"/>pen. We are all hoping that if we get a contract in 
     <lb/>the United States and if the American market 
     <lb/>recovers, we will produce on the same scale. It is 
     <lb/>indefinite. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Where was most of the fresh 
     <lb/>fish sold in 1946? What I am trying to get at is 
     <lb/>this — you mention the United States and the 
     <lb/>United Kingdom — the United Kingdom is still 
     <lb/>in the picture, is it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KEOU1">Mr. Keough</persName> Page 13 of the report shows the 
     <lb/>amounts which went to the different markets. I 
     <lb/>question whether a great deal more went to the 
     <lb/>States than to England. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Here it shows 7.5 million pounds ex<lb break="no"/>ported to Canada — some of that was trans<lb break="no"/>shipped to the States. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I do not want Mr. Job to say 
     <lb/>more than he can, but I am trying to get the fresh 
     <lb/>fish prospects for 1947-48. The position today is 
     <lb/>you can sell to the United Kingdom and United 
     <lb/>States and some to Canada; a lot of what went to 
     <lb/>Canada was re-sold to the United States? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> 90% of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I know Mr. Job is well-in<lb break="no"/>formed on this business — he is actually in it, 
     <lb/>how much are we likely to sell in 1947 to Great 
     <lb/>Britain and the United States? You say no con<lb break="no"/>tracts are made — is not that really late? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> No. This is about the time we make 
     <lb/>contracts with Great Britain; as a rule there have 
     <lb/>not been any contracts made ahead with the 
     <lb/>United States. The position there is very bad. 
     <lb/>There is a tremendous amount of fillets in cold 
     <lb/>storage and until that is disposed of, it is impos<lb break="no"/>sible to gauge the US market in the future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> How is the price shaping? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Very low, there has been a drop in 
     <lb/>prices. I do not want to talk about it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> On page 15 of your main report 
     <lb/>it says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Notwithstanding all the emphasis that has 
     <lb/>been put in the foregoing upon the impor<lb break="no"/>tance of the US market, it should not be 
    
            <pb n="373"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0373.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">March 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">373</fw>
           

     thought that it is the opinion of the Commit<lb break="no"/>tee that that is the only market to which we 
     <lb/>
     should seek access. Once adequate refrigera<lb break="no"/>tion facilities come to be somewhat exten<lb break="no"/>sively installed in other countries, then 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland should be ready to penetrate 
     <lb/>
     those markets to the maximum extent that 
     <lb/>
     may be possible. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Would Mr. Job give us a little on that? Is this 
     <lb/>
     the position literally that this country today, with 
     <lb/>
     $3-4 million invested in cold storage facilities 
     <lb/>
     and cold storage ships, is depending on only two 
     <lb/>
     countries, the United States and United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom? Is there anywhere else we can turn 
     <lb/>
     during this year or next? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Nothing definite. 
    </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> What is the trade doing about 
     <lb/>it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> The trade are on their toes about it; they 
     <lb/>are working in conjunction with the Fisheries 
     <lb/>Board. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> On page 14 of the main report 
     <lb/>it says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Given no further restrictions than now exist 
     <lb/>it is felt that we can shortly penetrate that 
     <lb/>market to such an extent as to dispose of a 
     <lb/>considerable part of the production that must 
     <lb/>be diverted from the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Would Mr. Job tell us what is meant by "given 
     <lb/>
     no further restriction"? We know there is an open 
     <lb/>
     quota of 18 million pounds from Newfoundland, 
     <lb/>
     Canada, Iceland, etc. at 1 7/8 cents a pound duty; 
     <lb/>
     over that 18 million pounds, 2.5 cents duty; "no 
     <lb/>
     further restrictions," does that refer to the 1 7/8 
     <lb/>
     cents, the 2.5 cents, or the quota of 18 million 
     <lb/>
     pounds? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> We refer to all three; and the future, in 
     <lb/>
     my opinion and which I have emphasised, 
     <lb/>
     depends on some arrangement with the US that 
     <lb/>
     will provide for years ahead, because we cannot 
     <lb/>
     plan. If we knew there were to be no funher 
     <lb/>
     restrictions, we could help production by adver<lb break="no"/>tising — there is no other way we can do it, unless 
     <lb/>
     we know that at any time the US will not put on 
     <lb/>
     a prohibitive duty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Suppose they said, "Let it stay 
     <lb/>
     as it is"? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> It is an open question. We have already 
     <lb/>
     read the opinions expressed in the Armstrong 
     <lb/>
     Report — a report which was gotten at consider<lb break="no"/>able expense to the government — that unless we 
   

            <cb/>
          
     can make some definite arrangement with the 
     <lb/>
     United States for future imports, we will not be 
     <lb/>
     in a very good position. I think that is true and 
     <lb/>
     therefore I think we are entitled to some arrange<lb break="no"/>ment because of the bases to which I referred on 
     <lb/>
     so many occasions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I notice that one plant referred to, 
     <lb/>
     the company paid an amount of $302,000 for fish 
     <lb/>
     and for labour. There were 15 plants, that would 
     <lb/>
     mean the total paid out would be $4 million; but 
     <lb/>
     I notice on page 13 the total received was 
     <lb/>
     $5,515,000. That would probably indicate a 
     <lb/>
     profit of $1 million. The point I am getting at is 
     <lb/>
     this: the Committee are lamenting, and I think 
     <lb/>
     rightly so, that there is likely to be a recession of 
     <lb/>
     trade in regard to fish. 1 would like to ask, have 
     <lb/>
     the profits in years past been such that they could 
     <lb/>
     very well take up some of the slack in a possible 
     <lb/>
     falling market, so that they might be able to pay 
     <lb/>
     the fishermen somewhere near the prices which 
     <lb/>
     were paid last year? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> That is a very pertinent question. I think 
     <lb/>
     in a case of this sort you have to provide for the 
     <lb/>
     writing off of your plant on an extensive scale out 
     <lb/>
     of your profits. Suppose we have to scrap that — 
     <lb/>
     you cannot tell what your profit is; you have to 
     <lb/>
     provide for the wiping off of capital, to provide 
     <lb/>
     for contingencies. I do not know what the reply 
     <lb/>
     would be; I do not think there is very material 
     <lb/>
     margin in it. The shareholders received nothing 
     <lb/>
     of any consequence. I tell you who has received 
     <lb/>
     a great deal and that is the government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> On page 3 of the Appendix "it 
     <lb/>
     would seem that Newfoundland producers are 
     <lb/>
     working under a heavy handicap as compared to 
     <lb/>
     the Canadians, and to build the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     production up to a worthwhile figure employing 
     <lb/>
     many thousands of people, some of the following 
     <lb/>
     things will have to be done." One is quality ofthe 
     <lb/>
     fillet; two is another system of producing fish 
     <lb/>
     through draggers and trawlers; and three is New<lb break="no"/>foundland products in competition with 
     <lb/>
     Canadian and American. What is the heavy hand<lb break="no"/>icap under which the Newfoundland producers 
     <lb/>
     are working compared with Canadians? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> That is already pointed out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The longer haul and freight on 
     <lb/>
     page 5? A, B and C? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> What are the handicaps under 
     <lb/>
     which our producers work compared to the 
   

            <pb n="374"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0374.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">374</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">March 1947</fw>
         

     Canadians, over and above this A, B and C? 
   </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> There may not be any other handicap; 
     <lb/>I do not say there is. I think they have some 
     <lb/>advantages in the way of better shore fish. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That is quality. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> That is an advantage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I am trying to get at the disad<lb break="no"/>vantages. To what extent is the fresh fish industry 
     <lb/>
     and the saltfish industry too, handicapped for 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland as compared with Canada or the 
     <lb/>
     United States or Iceland.... To what extent are our 
     <lb/>
     producers handicapped by customs duty col<lb break="no"/>lected on machinery and plants and shops and 
     <lb/>
     packages and equipment used in the industry, and 
     <lb/>
     second by the rising costs of the actual producers 
     <lb/>
     — the actual fishermen? You go back to page 1 
     <lb/>
     of the Appendix and you will note because of 
     <lb/>
     "The frozen blueberry industry was also a very 
     <lb/>
     substantial business and of very definite value to 
     <lb/>
     the country, owing to the fact that the cost of 
     <lb/>
     picking was very little and the number of pickers 
     <lb/>
     probably thousands, making for a wide distribu<lb break="no"/>tion of the cash paid out, which some years 
     <lb/>
     amounted to over $500,000." A man or woman 
     <lb/>
     goes out and picks one gallon or ten gallons of 
     <lb/>
     blueberries. I think the cost of producing that one 
     <lb/>
     gallon of berries, to that woman, is her cost of 
     <lb/>
     living. Similarly the fishermen in competition 
     <lb/>
     with fishermen of Iceland, Norway and Canada, 
     <lb/>
     have a higher cost of living which is due to some 
     <lb/>
     extent to taxation. Taking the two together — 
     <lb/>
     taxation on what he and his family eat and wear 
     <lb/>
     and use; taxation on machines, plants, wrapping, 
     <lb/>
     canons, paper — all these things that enter into 
     <lb/>
     the fish industry. I do not want to anticipate your 
     <lb/>
     sealing report, but there you make that very point 
     <lb/>
     that taxation on things going into the seal hunt, 
     <lb/>
     coaling the ships, equipment and the ship itself, 
     <lb/>
     is making the cost of production high. To what 
     <lb/>
     extent is it true in the fresh fish industry? How 
     <lb/>
     can it be helped by reduction of taxation? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I can answer that to a certain extent. 
     <lb/>
     The government has encouraged the cold storage 
     <lb/>
     industry very much by free entries. But I know of 
     <lb/>
     one case of an engine put into a vessel or steamer; 
     <lb/>
     the engine was purchased in Canada, in Van<lb break="no"/>couver, came over the railway to Halifax; by boat 
     <lb/>
     from there to Newfoundland — the engine cost 
     <lb/>
     about $30,000. We thought we could get it in free 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
           
     of duty; but it was charged up in the thousands. I 
     <lb/>
     think that was unfair because it was directly in 
     <lb/>
     the interest of the cold storage industry. On the 
     <lb/>
     whole the policy of the government has been to 
     <lb/>
     permit everything possible in connection with the 
     <lb/>
     cold storage industry to come in free of duty. 
     </p>


            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That is for fixed capital and 
     <lb/>capital equipment? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Capital equipment and material. I do 
     <lb/>
     not think they paid anything for linings or car<lb break="no"/>tons. You will have to give us notice of these 
     <lb/>
     questions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> On page 8. "Newfoundland would 
     <lb/>
     then be at the advantage of such multilaterial 
     <lb/>
     trade arrangements as would materialise — one 
     <lb/>
     of which, it is thought, sould be most favoured 
     <lb/>
     nation treatment for the entry ofour fish products 
     <lb/>
     into the United States." That sounds more like 
     <lb/>
     "unilateral" to me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KEOU1">Mr. Keough</persName> I thought any nation that entered 
     <lb/>
     this ITO<ref target="#fn_02">[1]</ref> would get preferential treatment all 
     <lb/>
     around; they would get most favoured nation 
     <lb/>
     treatment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> You may be right, but I cannot see 
     <lb/>
     it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KEOU1">Mr. Keough</persName> Outsiders would not have the same 
     <lb/>
     preferential treatment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There are 18 nations — 17 
     <lb/>
     invited by the United States to come together and 
     <lb/>
     form an international trade organization. The 
     <lb/>
     ITO, if it is formed, will be for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     enabling the members to enter into multilateral 
     <lb/>
     and bilateral trade agreements between each 
     <lb/>
     other. You may have any two or all 18 members 
     <lb/>
     coming to bilateral treaties in addition to multi<lb break="no"/>lateral. I understand Newfoundland is attempting 
     <lb/>
     at this conference, after it opens on April 8, to 
     <lb/>
     negotiate a bilateral trade treaty with the United 
     <lb/>
     States.... No doubt there will be other bilateral 
     <lb/>
     arrangements made as well. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I am not any more clear on the 
     <lb/>
     matter than I was. However, we will see what we 
     <lb/>
     shall find out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> This is a gigantic thing, this 
     <lb/>
     fresh fish industry. There are a lot of people in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland engaged in this industry. Here is 
     <lb/>
     a most valuable report that, in my humble 
     <lb/>
     opinion, is one of the finest documents ever 
     <lb/>
     produced in the history of Newfoundland, if not 
  

   

<note xml:id="fn_02">[1] The International Trade Organisation was a creation of the 1944 Bretton Woods Conference. It never came 
     <lb/>into actual existence, and was replaced by the GATT.</note>


            <pb n="375"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0375.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">March 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">375</fw>
         

     the finest, in connection with the fisheries. It 
     <lb/>
     would be a shame if it should not become known 
     <lb/>
     to the Newfoundland people, especially the 
     <lb/>
     fishermen. It would be a pity to skimp it. We are 
     <lb/>
     torn between two desires, to get through our work 
     <lb/>
     on the one hand, and to let the people know what 
     <lb/>
     is in the report on the other hand. I have not yet 
     <lb/>
     got a clear picture of what the prospects are for 
     <lb/>
     the fresh fish industry in Newfoundland. For 
     <lb/>
     example, we hear in the United States they are 
     <lb/>
     going into this fresh fish industry on a gigantic 
     <lb/>
     scale, building new plants, building draggers and 
     <lb/>
     trawlers in many dozens. In Canada they are 
     <lb/>
     doing the same thing; Iceland has already done it 
     <lb/>
     and are doing it even more; in England they are 
     <lb/>
     starting now on the construction of fresh fish 
     <lb/>
     refrigeration plants, and the same in Norway. 
     <lb/>
     What I am trying to do is to fit Newfoundland into 
     <lb/>
     that picture for the next four or five years. What 
     <lb/>
     is to be the outcome of this industry in New<lb break="no"/>foundland? We have the best fish in the world, 
     <lb/>
     lovely quality. What are the actual chances of 
     <lb/>
     marketing? What are the chances in competition 
     <lb/>
     with Canada, Iceland, Norway, England and 
     <lb/>
     France? France is building in St. Pierre, they tell 
     <lb/>
     us, a $4-5 million plant. How are we going to 
     <lb/>
     market this 30 million pounds of fresh fish in the 
     <lb/>
     next few years if the only markets are the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom and the United States, and all the 
     <lb/>
     countries in the world are trying to get fish into 
     <lb/>
     these two countries? Now, Mr. Job, I know if I 
     <lb/>
     could make him mad I could make him talk, but 
     <lb/>
     what is the picture? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Well, make him mad! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I can't make him mad, he is too 
     <lb/>
     much of a gentleman. I know the prospects for 
     <lb/>
     the next six months are not very bad, but I am 
     <lb/>
     asking him to look ahead of 1947, and give us the 
     <lb/>
     picture of the next four or five years of this very 
     <lb/>
     important fresh fish industry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I am afraid we can't give you any more 
     <lb/>
     than we have already given you in the report. I 
     <lb/>
     am not going to go ahead and say what the market 
     <lb/>
     will become; he can draw his own conclusions as 
     <lb/>
     well as we can. I believe the markets will come 
     <lb/>
     back, but when he talks of expansion in the USA, 
     <lb/>
     it is fresh fish expansion, not frozen fish expan<lb break="no"/>sion; that's one of the things we have to remem<lb break="no"/>ber as well. At the present time the market is 
     <lb/>
     overstocked in the United States. When Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood goes up there and goes around and 
   

            <cb/>
          

     see things, he will be able to judge better than I 
     <lb/>
     can. We have to make a guess. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> On page 2 of the Appendix: 
     <lb/>
     "Another heavy investment is in draggers, say 
     <lb/>
     around $350,000." I wonder if the Committee 
     <lb/>
     inquired as to the number of small and young fish 
     <lb/>
     that were killed and had to be thrown away? 
     <lb/>
     
  </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> It is so new that really we have not had 
     <lb/>time. These draggers have been going only about 
     <lb/>six months. Perhaps Mr. Crosbie could shed 
     <lb/>some light on that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> My experience with draggers is 
     <lb/>
     that very little fish is thrown overboard. There's 
     <lb/>
     a good deal of small fish caught, but most of them 
     <lb/>
     go down the hold with the other fish. We know 
     <lb/>
     what is brought in, but not what is thrown away. 
     <lb/>
     With regard to Mr. Smallwood's question, I am 
     <lb/>
     not so pessimistic as some people. In this country 
     <lb/>
     we only know one fish —- cod. Actually it is only 
     <lb/>
     one of the many varieties of fish that are required 
     <lb/>
     in the fish business. I think it has a tremendous 
     <lb/>
     future in this country over the next four or five 
     <lb/>
     years. There are markets that we have not heard 
     <lb/>
     about, and have never gone to look for. We don't 
     <lb/>
     actually know what conditions are. There is 
     <lb/>
     Brazil, these peeple consume a lot of fresh fish. 
     <lb/>
     With regard to competition from the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom, I don't think we are going to have any. 
     <lb/>
     Their catch will be all consumed in England and 
     <lb/>
     very little exported. Iceland's production is being 
     <lb/>
     bought by Russia, and probably will be for the 
     <lb/>
     next few years. I don't think we will have much 
     <lb/>
     competition there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> They are starting a five year 
     <lb/>
     plan there with regard to fish. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I don't care. I think there is a 
     <lb/>
     tremendous future in frozen fish and canned fish. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Where? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> Brazil and other places. One of the 
     <lb/>
     Committee men said to McLean, "You are near 
     <lb/>
     the United States market", and he said, "Yes, but 
     <lb/>
     we don't look to them, 40% is shipped to Canada 
     <lb/>
     and 60% to other countries." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That's canned fish? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> Yes, that's what I am talking about, 
     <lb/>
     frozen fish and canned. In San Paulo and Rio 
     <lb/>
     alone they consume a lot. There are other markets 
     <lb/>
     besides the USA that we ought to look to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> But are they doing that? I asked 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Job if the trade was doing anything about 
     <lb/>
     getting other markets apart from the United 
    

            <pb n="376"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-24_Page_0376.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">376</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">March 1947</fw>
          

     States, and he said, "Yes, the trade is very much 
     <lb/>
     alive to it, and very much on their toes." He 
     <lb/>
     mentions Brazil. Is anyone trying to sell fish in 
     <lb/>
     Brazil? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> Yes, as far as I know. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, are they trying to sell it 
     <lb/>
     anywhere else? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> I don't know, they don't tell me 
     <lb/>
     their trade secrets. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Well, the fresh fish people con<lb break="no"/>centrate too much on the United States. Are they 
     <lb/>
     paying enough attention to other markets? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> You are trying to pin me down to 
     <lb/>
     something I am not prepared to be pinned down 
     <lb/>
     to, and as far as I am concerned I won't be pinned 
     <lb/>
     down. You must remember that going into other 
     <lb/>
     markets costs a great deal of money. They have 
     <lb/>
     already spent a lot of money on advertising, and 
     <lb/>
     these people may not be prepared to go into these 
     <lb/>
     other markets and advertise. It may run into 
     <lb/>
     hundreds of thousands of dollars. I am not 
     <lb/>
     prepared to criticise them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> Getting back to fish again. Is 
     <lb/>
     there duty on all fish going into the United States? 
     <lb/>
     We have fillets, turbot, smelts, etc., is there duty 
     <lb/>
     on all of them? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Yes, but the duty varies on different 
     <lb/>
     sorts of fish. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I wonder if Mr. Job could tell me 
     <lb/>
     the price of fresh cod fillets in St. John's? I can 
     <lb/>
     tell you, 28 cents per pound. What do you think 
     <lb/>
     of that price? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> A very nice price if you can get it. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I am looking at the cost of living of 
     <lb/>the average St. John's man and woman. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I think if we could sell the fillets here 
     <lb/>
     at cost they would be very glad to do something. 
    
 </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> As far as I am concerned the section 
     <lb/>of the report as read is self-explanatory, and I am 


            <cb/>
          

     willing to accept it and move on to other business. 
     <lb/>
     I believe we should think over what kind of a 
     <lb/>
     delegation we are going to send to the United 
     <lb/>
     States to see about our markets for fresh fillets 
     <lb/>
     and other fishery products. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The section passed, and the Secretary read the<lb/>next section]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
    <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I suggest we adjourn until tomorrow to 
     <lb/>
     give the members time to master this report on 
     <lb/>
     the salt codfishery. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> We have not been making much 
     <lb/>
     progress of late, and I suggest to you that since a 
     <lb/>
     great deal of time has been lost as a result of a 
     <lb/>
     shortage of paper, and we have a great deal of 
     <lb/>
     work to do, it would be advisable to hold night 
     <lb/>
     sessions. However, I am entirely in your hands. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I think it would be a good idea, if it 
     <lb/>would not be putting too much on the ladies who 
     <lb/>are reporting the proceedings. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I will look after that. I will see 
     <lb/>
     that they are not driven too hard. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JONE5">Mr. Jones</persName> I think we should have one night to 
     <lb/>
     go over the report and see what we can make of 
     <lb/>
     it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> It is the most important part of the 
     <lb/>
     Fisheries Report. There is some justification for 
     <lb/>
     the request. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> In view of the fact that the members 
     <lb/>
     received the report only this afternoon, we might 
     <lb/>
     dispose of the night session until tomorrow night. 
     <lb/>
     I make that as a motion 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Before the motion, I would like to 
     <lb/>
     ask Mr. Job or Mr. Ashbourne, did they make any 
     <lb/>
     inquiries whatever into the figures of the 
     <lb/>
     fishermen's insurance scheme in connection with 
     <lb/>
     this country? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Yes, it is in the report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee rose and reported progress, and<lb/>the Convention adjourned]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

    
   <!-- GL, 2017-06-08, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
           <!-- <p>
     March 25, 1947. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Fisheries Committee:¹ 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Chairman Appendix B, gentlemen, Salt 
     <lb/>
     Codfish, is now under consideration.² 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Mr. Chairman, on page 10 of 
     <lb/>
     the Appendix: "We suggest that salt be provided 
     <lb/>
     at the very lowest possible price, and the matter 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     of heights on salt coming into Newfoundland be 
     <lb/>
     reviewed. We understand that the present rate of 
     <lb/>
     freight on salt brought here by the government 
     <lb/>
     boats is about three times its cost in the West 
     <lb/>
     Indies." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     ¹Volume II:181.<lb/>²Volume II:215.<lb/> 
               <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>