<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1948-01-09" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1948-01-09">9 January 1948</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1088" to="1098"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1088.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1089.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1090.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1091.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1092.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1093.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1094.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1095.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1096.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1097.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1098.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-08-16">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-08-16">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1088">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1088.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1089">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1089.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1090">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1090.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1091">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1091.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1092">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1092.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1093">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1093.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1094">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1094.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1095">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1095.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1096">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1096.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1097">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1097.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1098">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1098.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1088" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1088.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1088</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-08-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
<!--<p>
     [The committee rose and reported progress, and the Convention adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     January 9, 1948 
     <lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I would like to say that it is my 
     <lb/>
     intention to reply to the speech of Major Cashin 
     <lb/>
     and, in all probability to other speeches which 
     <lb/>
     may be made on these terms. But, sir, just when 
     <lb/>
     I should do it is a matter that has given me a 
     <lb/>
     considerable amount of concern in the last day or 
     <lb/>
     two because I happen to be very anxious, very 
     <lb/>
     eager, that the Convention should finish its work 
     <lb/>
     by the end of January, so that the referendum can 
     <lb/>
     be held this spring. For that reason, if I were to 
     <lb/>
     reply to the lengthy speech of Major Cashin and 
     <lb/>
     to speeches made by other members of the Con<lb break="no"/>vention, each one as it is made, it would take a 
     <lb/>
     considerable amount of time and might prolong 
     <lb/>
     the Convention beyond the end of January. I do 
     <lb/>
     not want to take that risk.... What I would like to 
     <lb/>
     feel a little confident about is this: after Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin has completed his speech, and if some 
     <lb/>
     other members speak attacking or criticising or 
     <lb/>
     analysing these terms of confederation, I would 
     <lb/>
     like to feel confident that I will have the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of replying to them. What I am trying to 
     <lb/>
     avoid is this: one man after the other attacks the 
     <lb/>
     confederation terms, criticises them, analyses 
     <lb/>
     them unfavourably; and then, before I have had 
     <lb/>
     the opportunity of replying, a closure motion 
     <lb/>
     could be put and adopted which would strangle 
     <lb/>
     any opportunity I would have of replying to these 
     <lb/>
     criticisms. I want very anxiously to avoid delay. 
     <lb/>
     I want to get out of this Convention by the end of 
     <lb/>
     January. I would like to see the referendum held 
     <lb/>
     this Spring. But I do not want to be deprived of 
     <lb/>
     the chance to reply. I can be deprived by the 
     <lb/>
     simple means of a closure motion.... I think that 
     <lb/>
     the gentlemen who are critical of these con<lb break="no"/>federation terms and who express their criticisms 
     <lb/>
     will be gentlemen enough not to bring in that 
     <lb/>
     closure motion and choke me off.... I put my trust 
     <lb/>
     in them. I put myself at the mercy of their sense 
     <lb/>
     of justice and fair play. After they have rapped 
     <lb/>
     the confederation terms. I will be given full, free 
     <lb/>
     and ample opportunity to reply with the freedom 
     <lb/>
     of debate in committee of the whole. With that 
     <lb/>
     understanding, I do not propose to reply to Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin when he completes his speech, but rather 
     <lb/>
     to wait until he and others have completed their 


            <cb/>
          

     speeches, and then reply to the lot of them in one 
     <lb/>
     speech. With these few remarks I move the mo<lb break="no"/>tion on the order paper. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Before I put that motion ... I 
     <lb/>
     want to say that I can give no guarantee that you 
     <lb/>
     will be permitted to speak at any given time; nor 
     <lb/>
     can I give any guarantee to any member that he 
     <lb/>
     will be able to speak to any motion at any time.... 
     <lb/>
     I have no authority to decide the number of times 
     <lb/>
     any member will speak in committee or the 
     <lb/>
     length of time he will speak on any subject before 
     <lb/>
     the Chair, as long as he confines himself strictly 
     <lb/>
     and in a proper manner to the business before the 
     <lb/>
     Chair. Therefore, if a closure motion is put to me, 
     <lb/>
     I will have to accept a closure motion at any time; 
     <lb/>
     with this qualification, that I will not accept a 
     <lb/>
     closure motion without notice.... And what the 
     <lb/>
     Chair has to keep in mind, in a closure motion, is 
     <lb/>
     to make sure that the rights of the minority or the 
     <lb/>
     rights of members who have not had the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity to express themselves fully, or at all, upon 
     <lb/>
     the business before the Chair shall not be 
     <lb/>
     abridged or taken away by the prompt putting and 
     <lb/>
     carrying of a closure motion. To put it simply, I 
     <lb/>
     am not prepared to guarantee to you, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood, or to any other member here, that he 
     <lb/>
     will be permitted to address the Chair, if you will, 
     <lb/>
     at 3 pm next Wednesday on a certain subject. 
     <lb/>
     How can I?.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> In view of the statement made by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood, which I suppose is official in 
     <lb/>
     character, that this Convention has to conclude 
     <lb/>
     its work by the end of January if we were to have 
     <lb/>
     the referendum this spring.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That is not official. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> It will be, when I read my reply. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I do not know whether it is 
     <lb/>official or not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Why all this talk about closure if it 
     <lb/>
     is not official? If it is official, I want to make a 
     <lb/>
     motion right now. If the referendum is to be held 
     <lb/>
     in the spring, then I am prepared to give notice of 
     <lb/>
     motion right now. We have only a few days left. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> There is a motion before the 
     <lb/>Chair. Notice can be given when I leave the chair 
     <lb/>of committee and resume the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="1089" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1089.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1089</fw>
           
</div>

<div type="section">
 <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report of the Ottawa Delegation 
     <lb/>
     Proposed Arrangements for the Entry of Newfoundland into Confederation 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Mr. Chairman, I am glad Mr. Small- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     wood brought that matter up. With regard to 
     <lb/>
     closure, it is immaterial to me; but I want to point 
     <lb/>
     out that before the Ottawa delegation left last 
     <lb/>
     year, this Convention was practically assured it 
     <lb/>
     would reconvene again around the middle of 
     <lb/>
     July, but the Ottawa delegation ignored that; they 
     <lb/>
     did not have the decency to communicate with 
     <lb/>
     the Secretary telling him to advise the members 
     <lb/>
     of the Convention that they were sorry about the 
     <lb/>
     delay; we had to take it upon ourselves to com<lb break="no"/>municate with them, and we were told we were 
     <lb/>
     committing an act of national treachery. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood can reply all he likes to my remarks. 
     <lb/>
     This confederation issue has been before this 
     <lb/>
     house for 16 months. That is all we have heard. 
     <lb/>
     Every report has been torn abroad and told what 
     <lb/>
     confederation would do. The thing should never 
     <lb/>
     have happened. Even the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Evening Telegram</hi> 
     <lb/>
     practically said it was a farce. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A few items have been drawn to my attention 
     <lb/>
     to bring up, and there are many points I omitted, 
     <lb/>
     particularly from the point of financial interest. 
     <lb/>
     A party asked me today to inquire what is going 
     <lb/>
     to happen to the Newfoundland Savings Bank in 
     <lb/>
     which there are $20 million belonging to our 
     <lb/>
     people at 2.5%. When the Ottawa delegation was 
     <lb/>
     discussing these matters, did they ask the Ottawa 
     <lb/>
     government what would become of the bank? It 
     <lb/>
     is a very important matter.... I am one of those 
     <lb/>
     who believes in that bank. If those savings are 
     <lb/>
     going to be reduced in annual interest charges, 
     <lb/>
     that money should be withdrawn; and for those 
     <lb/>
     in the country who have their savings in that 
     <lb/>
     bank, I am going to direct a question to the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Finance. 1 will draft a question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This so-called budget of Mr. Smallwood's<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     indicates to me that, in addition to paying an 
     <lb/>
     annual federal tax of around $230 per annum, 
     <lb/>
     every Newfoundlander, will have to find an ad<lb break="no"/>ditional $30 per year in provincial taxation. In all, 
     <lb/>
     therefore, the people of the country would have 
     <lb/>
     to find over $80 million each year to pay both 
     <lb/>
     federal and provincial taxation. In short, the 
     <lb/>
     whole thing means that the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland would be taxed to death — that the 
     <lb/>
     dole days would be considered luxurious living 


            <cb/>
    

     and opulence in comparison to the manner in 
     <lb/>
     which the people of our country would be forced 
     <lb/>
     to live in union with Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName>, there is a saying that there is 
     <lb/>
     none so blind as those who will not see, and it is 
     <lb/>
     certain that many of us refuse to see things as they 
     <lb/>
     are in this country today. They cannot plead 
     <lb/>
     ignorance, they cannot say they have not been 
     <lb/>
     told that the threats to our country have not been 
     <lb/>
     pointed out to them. Time and time again, the call 
     <lb/>
     has come to them to assume the duty which as 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlanders is rightly theirs. And whatever 
     <lb/>
     befalls us in the future, whatever disasters happen 
     <lb/>
     to us, the people generally cannot say that have 
     <lb/>
     not been asked to stave off such disasters. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am not speaking to hear the sound of my own 
     <lb/>
     voice. Nor am I trying to warp the judgement of 
     <lb/>
     the delegates to this Convention or the people of 
     <lb/>
     the country, or influence their minds with any 
     <lb/>
     more airy rhetoric or political spellbinding. My 
     <lb/>
     purpose has been, at this time particularly, to give 
     <lb/>
     hard, cold facts which cannot be denied or talked 
     <lb/>
     away. What I have said emanates from my sin<lb break="no"/>cere political belief which is based on the solid 
     <lb/>
     and eternal doctrine: first, a country belongs to its 
     <lb/>
     people; second, it is the solemn duty of the people 
     <lb/>
     of that country to shoulder the responsibility of 
     <lb/>
     governing it. Any divergence or avoidance of that 
     <lb/>
     doctrine, any excuse for acting contrary to that 
     <lb/>
     fundamental truth is cowardly, unediical and im<lb break="no"/>moral. The challenge which faces the people of 
     <lb/>
     this country today is the patriotic and moral chal<lb break="no"/>lenge to do their duty and to face their respon<lb break="no"/>sibilities like real men and women. It is a 
     <lb/>
     clear-cut issue — as clear and unambiguous as 
     <lb/>
     the challenge of right and wrong. But again I say, 
     <lb/>
     there are those amongst us who have shown that 
     <lb/>
     they are unwilling, or have not the capabilities of 
     <lb/>
     facing their responsibilities and accepting obliga<lb break="no"/>tions of democratic decency. They are prepared 
     <lb/>
     instead to assume the garb of mendicants and go 
     <lb/>
     begging at the back door of some outside country, 
     <lb/>
     asking to be taken in out of the rough world which 
     <lb/>
     they fear to face. Like Shakespeare's character, 
     <lb/>
     they are prepared to crawl under the huge legs of 
     <lb/>
     some foreign colossus and find themselves dis<lb break="no"/>honourable graves. But I know that there are 


<note xml:id="fn_01">[1] Volume II:522. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>    


            <pb n="1090" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1090.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1090</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
       

     many thousands amongst us who are not prepared 
     <lb/>
     to form their opinions on mere moral or ethical 
     <lb/>
     grounds. They prefer to deal with matters from a 
     <lb/>
     more practical standpoint. They ask for facts. 
     <lb/>
     Well, I think I have given them the facts. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In my opinion, Canada is today in a position 
     <lb/>
     where she finds she has overreached herself. She 
     <lb/>
     reminds me of the frog in the fable who wanted 
     <lb/>
     to be as big as a bull and who puffed himself up 
     <lb/>
     until he burst. Canada is an ambitious country 
     <lb/>
     and in the thirties she got the idea that she wanted 
     <lb/>
     to become a big nation. She put on long pants 
     <lb/>
     before she became of age. She wanted an army, 
     <lb/>
     she wanted a navy and all the trimmings. How 
     <lb/>
     she might have gotten on if World War II had not 
     <lb/>
     come along we do not know. But like other 
     <lb/>
     countries, the blast of war hit her, and today she 
     <lb/>
     is left in an exhausted position, struggling for her 
     <lb/>
     life, and her financial bloodstream is fast running 
     <lb/>
     dry. As I said, she is begging Uncle Sam for 
     <lb/>
     dollars and her people are on the rocky road of 
     <lb/>
     austerity.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I want to apologise for being so long discuss<lb break="no"/>ing this matter. I felt that it is of such great 
     <lb/>
     national importance that it required extensive 
     <lb/>
     study, and during Christmas recess I spent prac<lb break="no"/>tically all my time going into the Black Books 
     <lb/>
     and particularly the Grey Book. I felt, as a former 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Finance for Newfoundland, that I 
     <lb/>
     owed it to you people who sent me here, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly the District of St. John's West because 
     <lb/>
     when they elected me I told them that I would not 
     <lb/>
     let them down, and I am not going to let them 
     <lb/>
     down now. I felt I had to make a complete study 
     <lb/>
     with no one bothering me in order to work out 
     <lb/>
     these figures which I have given, and I have come 
     <lb/>
     to the conclusions which I have already given to 
     <lb/>
     the house and the country, which I elaborated on 
     <lb/>
     yesterday.... I have lived in Canada and worked 
     <lb/>
     there from coast to coast. I like Canada, it is a 
     <lb/>
     great country, but after living and working there, 
     <lb/>
     I want to give it as an honest opinion, that if 
     <lb/>
     confederation were good for Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     there would not be a stronger supporter of it in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland today, but I am honest in my 
     <lb/>
     opinion when I say that confederation will be the 
     <lb/>
     worst thing that ever struck Newfoundland.... 
     <lb/>
     Canada is in a worse position financially than 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland.... We are not begging for dollars, 
     <lb/>
     all we are trying to do is keep people from 
     <lb/>
     plundering our treasury. We can sympathise with 
    

            <cb/>
        

     Canada in her present plight, just as any other 
     <lb/>
     allies made prosperous by the war, but neverthe<lb break="no"/>less we must remember that charity begins at 
     <lb/>
     home, and our first duty and our first obligation 
     <lb/>
     we owe to ourselves, our families, our children 
     <lb/>
     and our children's children.... Canada is well 
     <lb/>
     aware, as we are, that if she can take over New<lb break="no"/>foundland she can richly benefit by our assets. 
     <lb/>
     For instance, if she controlled our rich Labrador 
     <lb/>
     possession, it would in a few years place her in a 
     <lb/>
     position where she could get all these American 
     <lb/>
     dollars which she urgently needs.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Is it not quite obvious from all the evidence 
     <lb/>
     available to us that Canada is definitely using her 
     <lb/>
     power and efforts to wrest from Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     this particular part of Labrador, together with its 
     <lb/>
     great undeveloped waterpower? Don't let us 
     <lb/>
     blind ourselves with the stupid and rather naive 
     <lb/>
     idea that the Privy Council's judgement protects 
     <lb/>
     us in the possession of our Labrador territory. 
     <lb/>
     Don't let us get that idea in our heads, because if 
     <lb/>
     the agreement made by our government in 1933 
     <lb/>
     with the British government can be converted 
     <lb/>
     into a scrap of paper, if the Atlantic Charter 
     <lb/>
     signed in our own Placentia Bay can become 
     <lb/>
     equally worthless, what dependence do you think 
     <lb/>
     we can place in a mere decision of the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council? Let us remember that there are more 
     <lb/>
     ways than one of skinning a cat. Why, I myself 
     <lb/>
     can think of three different ways at least right 
     <lb/>
     now, whereby Canada can usher us out of our 
     <lb/>
     Labrador territory, regardless of any Privy Coun<lb break="no"/>cil, if we were to unite with Canada and become 
     <lb/>
     the tenth province. It is contained in this Grey 
     <lb/>
     Book, and it is in there for that purpose. I quoted 
     <lb/>
     that yesterday, that within a period of eight years 
     <lb/>
     a royal commission, a royal force, like they had 
     <lb/>
     here in 1933, would come and find that the 
     <lb/>
     country is bankrupt and say, "We are going to 
     <lb/>
     take this", and I am convinced that, in the minds 
     <lb/>
     of some of our pro-confederates today is the 
     <lb/>
     thought that Canada will rent Labrador from us 
     <lb/>
     in order to bolster up that so-called budget that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood brought in here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName>, I do not intend to take up much 
     <lb/>
     further time, but in closing, I would wish to 
     <lb/>
     summarise briefly the meaning of all that I have 
     <lb/>
     said. As I see it, the situation is simply this: 
     <lb/>
     Canada wants this country and our Labrador pos<lb break="no"/>session, and the government of Great Britain has 
     <lb/>
     given her consent to this arrangement. There 
   

            <pb n="1091" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1091.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1091</fw>
        

     have been in this country since 1941, and are 
     <lb/>
     today, active agents whose business and object is 
     <lb/>
     to usher Newfoundland into confederation with 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and to induce our people to walk into the 
     <lb/>
     trap which has been baited. The outward 
     <lb/>
     evidence of the activities of these pro-con<lb break="no"/>federate agents is shown in the foisting of this 
     <lb/>
     Convention upon us, so that the agreement made 
     <lb/>
     with the Newfoundland government in 1933 
     <lb/>
     could be evaded. It is shown in the act of export<lb break="no"/>ing from this country a great portion of the 
     <lb/>
     people's treasury; in the reckless and deliberate 
     <lb/>
     squandering of our revenues to the tune of $40 
     <lb/>
     million a year; in the giving away of reckless 
     <lb/>
     concessions, and under disgraceful conditions, of 
     <lb/>
     our Labrador territory. It is evidenced by the false 
     <lb/>
     pictures of the fictitious prosperity which would 
     <lb/>
     be ours if we have confederation. It is shown by 
     <lb/>
     the actions of members of the Ottawa delegation, 
     <lb/>
     who in collaboration with the Canadian govern<lb break="no"/>ment, cooked up and brought back to us false 
     <lb/>
     estimates and misleading statements; by the ex<lb break="no"/>istence of secret documents given to that delega<lb break="no"/>tion and the failure to produce them before this 
     <lb/>
     Convention; by the circumstances under which 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian delegation was elected. All these 
     <lb/>
     things indicate to me at least beyond all doubt, 
     <lb/>
     that Newfoundland today is being conspired 
     <lb/>
     against from all sides. And if there was any doubt 
     <lb/>
     on this score, it must be dismissed when we see 
     <lb/>
     that the business of negotiating us into confedera<lb break="no"/>tion has been entrusted to a body such as this, 
     <lb/>
     which has no power to negotiate, no power to 
     <lb/>
     speak for the people, which in the last analysis 
     <lb/>
     has neither the knowledge, the experience, nor 
     <lb/>
     the qualifications to pass on this matter, a matter 
     <lb/>
     which any sensible person knows is one for a 
     <lb/>
     properly constituted and elected government. 
     <lb/>
     This whole business is not alone illegal, it is 
     <lb/>
     worse, it is immoral. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would ask you to believe me when I say that 
     <lb/>
     I have not said these things merely to make a case 
     <lb/>
     for responsible government, or because I am 
     <lb/>
     against confederation with Canada. I have made 
     <lb/>
     my criticisms against these terms as a New<lb break="no"/>foundlander rather than a politician — as a New<lb break="no"/>foundlander who sees in them a threat to his 
     <lb/>
     people and his country, who sees hidden in their 
     <lb/>
     beguiling phrases nothing less than an invitation 
     <lb/>
     to national disaster. For I say that I was never as 
     <lb/>
     certain of anything in my life, as I am of the 


            <cb/>
       

     worthlessness of these so-called Canadian terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now I realise that some people may not agree 
     <lb/>
     with me. They may see, or think they see, bright 
     <lb/>
     prospects for us under confederation with 
     <lb/>
     Canada. I cannot find it in my mind to judge them 
     <lb/>
     too harshly. For out of the political muddle which 
     <lb/>
     has been purposely created in this country, how 
     <lb/>
     can we expect the average man or woman to 
     <lb/>
     know what it is all about, when we, who have 
     <lb/>
     been close to the picture for over 16 months, are 
     <lb/>
     still looking for information? It is because I am 
     <lb/>
     aware of this bewilderment on the part of our 
     <lb/>
     people, that I feel it my duty to take upon myself 
     <lb/>
     the obligation of advising them to the best of my 
     <lb/>
     ability as to the road I think we should pursue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To those who, like myself, recognise the fact 
     <lb/>
     that the only proper and decent course open to us 
     <lb/>
     is to become masters in our own house, no further 
     <lb/>
     words of mine are necessary. But to those who 
     <lb/>
     may be beguiled to any degree by this confedera<lb break="no"/>tion mirage, I say do nothing further — make no 
     <lb/>
     new steps. Do not consider any negotiations until, 
     <lb/>
     as a first step, you have a duly audiorised govern<lb break="no"/>ment of your own to consider the whole matter. 
     <lb/>
     Any other course is sheer political madness. That 
     <lb/>
     is my solemn advice to you. Whether you take it 
     <lb/>
     or not rests with yourselves. And if we delegates 
     <lb/>
     have failed to carry that one message to the 
     <lb/>
     people who sent us here, then I say we have failed 
     <lb/>
     dismally in our duty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In closing I would ask your permission to 
     <lb/>
     express a purely personal opinion. I am con<lb break="no"/>vinced that although our country and our people 
     <lb/>
     are at present enshrouded in a pall of political 
     <lb/>
     darkness, they will eventually find their way into 
     <lb/>
     the light. This whole matter of bribes and 
     <lb/>
     promises will in the end be shown up for what it 
     <lb/>
     really is. And I say this not because our people 
     <lb/>
     would shrink from the new burden of taxation 
     <lb/>
     which confederation with Canada will place on 
     <lb/>
     their shoulders, not because of the vision of the 
     <lb/>
     thousands of homesteads which may have to be 
     <lb/>
     sold to satisfy the Canadian tax gatherers. No. It 
     <lb/>
     will not be for these things alone, that our people 
     <lb/>
     will spum this offer for them to sell out the land 
     <lb/>
     of their birth. I say our people will win through 
     <lb/>
     because of other, greater things. They will tri<lb break="no"/>umph, emerge from this ordeal, because there are 
     <lb/>
     still in this country such things as pride, courage 
     <lb/>
     and faith. Pride in the great traditions which have 
     <lb/>
     come down to us through the centuries of inde<lb break="no"/>
   

            <pb n="1092" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1092.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1092</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
  

     pendent living. Courage to face up to life and hew 
     <lb/>
     out our individual fortunes. And finally faith in 
     <lb/>
     our country, and in the great destiny which I am 
     <lb/>
     convinced lies ahead of us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That concludes my address, Mr. Chairman, in 
     <lb/>
     this respect. Now, before I sit down, I just want 
     <lb/>
     to read for the information of the committee a 
     <lb/>
     reply which I received in answer to a question. 
     <lb/>
     The question was placed on the order paper on 
     <lb/>
     January 6, and I got the reply last night. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     I give notice that I will on tomorrow ask His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency the Governor in Commission to 
     <lb/>
     ascertain from the United Kingdom govern<lb break="no"/>ment the latest date on which the recommen<lb break="no"/>dations of this Convention must be submitted 
     <lb/>
     to the Secretary of State for Commonwealth 
     <lb/>
     Relations in order to ensure the holding of a 
     <lb/>
     referendum in the Spring of 1948. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (2) In the event of the majority of the 
     <lb/>
     voters in the forthcoming referendum 
     <lb/>
     favouring a form of government other than 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government, at what time 
     <lb/>
     and by what method will the change to the 
     <lb/>
     new form of government become effective. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Now here's the letter written by Mr. Carew. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">St. John's, Nfld. 
     <lb/>January 8, 1948. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Dear Sir: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have to refer to the question asked by a 
     <lb/>
     member of the National Convention as to the 
     <lb/>
     latest date on which the recommendations of 
     <lb/>
     the Convention must be submitted to the Rt. 
     <lb/>
     Hon. the Secretary for Commonwealth Rela<lb break="no"/>tions in order to ensure the holding of a 
     <lb/>
     referendum in the spring of 1948. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Rt. Hon. the Secretary of State has 
     <lb/>
     already informed the Commission of 
     <lb/>
     Government that a period of at least one 
     <lb/>
     month will be required for the consideration 
     <lb/>
     of the recommendations of the Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Commission of Government have 
     <lb/>
     given consideration to the question of setting 
     <lb/>
     a date for the holding of a national referen<lb break="no"/>dum and I have been directed to communi<lb break="no"/>cate their views to the National Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is hoped that it will be possible to hold 
     <lb/>
     the referendum about the end of the month of 
     <lb/>
     May this year. It is impracticable to hold a 
     <lb/>
     poll during the period from early June to late 
     <lb/>
     September as so many people are away from 
     <lb/>
     their homes and may be disfranchised. Final 
  

            <cb/>
        

     arrangements cannot be made for holding the 
     <lb/>
     referendum until the necessary legislation 
     <lb/>
     has been passed and steps in this direction 
     <lb/>
     cannot be taken until a decision has been 
     <lb/>
     made as to the questions to be submitted to 
     <lb/>
     the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The members of the Convention, familiar 
     <lb/>
     with the difficulties of travel during the 
     <lb/>
     spring months in sections of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     and in Labrador will realise that ample time 
     <lb/>
     must be allowed for the distribution of ballot 
     <lb/>
     papers and other materials for all polling 
     <lb/>
     booths. The matters preliminary to the voting 
     <lb/>
     will take place in the following order — 
     <lb/>
     delivery of recommendations by the National 
     <lb/>
     Convention; consideration by HM Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in the United Kingdom; communica<lb break="no"/>tion of decision as to forms of government to 
     <lb/>
     the submitted to the people; final draft for 
     <lb/>
     publication of legislation for continent; pass<lb break="no"/>ing of legislation; printing of ballots and 
     <lb/>
     other forms; setting up of polling stations and 
     <lb/>
     distribution of election material. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In order to permit sufficient time to com<lb break="no"/>plete the necessary arrangements and to en<lb break="no"/>sure to all qualified electors of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland and Labrador the opportunity 
     <lb/>
     of voting, it will be necessary, if the referen<lb break="no"/>dum is to be held during the month of May, 
     <lb/>
     to have the recommendations of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion submitted at an early date. The Commis<lb break="no"/>sion are unable to give any assurance that the 
     <lb/>
     referendum will be possible this spring if the 
     <lb/>
     recommendations of the Convention are not 
     <lb/>
     received by the end of the present month. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="simple:right">
     Yours faithfully, 
     <lb/>
    W.J. Carew, Secretary. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>I will put this on the order paper, and it is tabled. 
     <lb/>There is another answer there also Mr. Chairman. 
     <lb/>It is immaterial, that's the most important. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Chairman, in addressing you 
     <lb/>and the members of the Convention this after<lb break="no"/>noon, I would like to point out that I do not intend 
     <lb/>to go over the ground which is very well covered 
     <lb/>by Mr. Hollett, Mr. Fogwill and Major Cashin in 
     <lb/>these admirable addresses which we have heard 
     <lb/>in the past few days, but I do intend to touch on 
     <lb/>the subject which I hope is noncontroversial, but 
     <lb/>at the same time is of real moment, and important 
     <lb/>to the people of Newfoundland, and to us of the 
     <lb/>Convention in particular. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="1093" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1093.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1093</fw>
            

<p>
     Now as you probably have gathered, I am not 
     <lb/>
     altogether sold on the idea of confederation. 
     <lb/>
     However, the profession of which my learned 
     <lb/>
     friend the Chairman, and Mr. Bradley and myself 
     <lb/>
     are members, demands of necessity that whether 
     <lb/>
     we like a case or not, whether we like the client 
     <lb/>
     who brings in the case or not, nevertheless, if we 
     <lb/>
     are retained to do a job we do that job to the best 
     <lb/>
     of our ability. We work hard to prepare it, and do 
     <lb/>
     all that needs to be done. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now in this particular instance, and I refer to 
     <lb/>
     the work of the delegation that went to Ottawa, I 
     <lb/>
     and my co-delegates were retained by this Con<lb break="no"/>vention to discuss with the Canadian government 
     <lb/>
     the matter of the basis of union between New<lb break="no"/>foundland and Canada. I can say quite truthfully 
     <lb/>
     that no matter what has been said in or what has 
     <lb/>
     been said out of the House, and no matter what 
     <lb/>
     jokes may have been made with respect to that 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa delegation and the time spent in Ottawa, 
     <lb/>
     and I myself probably added more to such type 
     <lb/>
     of jokes than any other single member, I can say 
     <lb/>
     quite truthfully that we did as good a job as any 
     <lb/>
     delegation from Newfoundland under the cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances could have done. I can say to you 
     <lb/>
     quite truthfully that we had no officials of any 
     <lb/>
     kind to help us, no officials from the government, 
     <lb/>
     or the civil service to help us. We were six men 
     <lb/>
     appointed by this Convention. I don't even say 
     <lb/>
     the six best men that you have. A great number 
     <lb/>
     of you did not even choose to be part of that 
     <lb/>
     delegation, probably some of you better than the 
     <lb/>
     men who did go up. But, even with the lack of 
     <lb/>
     assistance that we had, we did do as good a job 
     <lb/>
     as we possibly could and I trust that you will 
     <lb/>
     understand me when now I take a different stand. 
     <lb/>
     Being a lawyer, as I explained to you, and doing 
     <lb/>
     cases for people that we don't like, and preparing 
     <lb/>
     cases that we don't like to do, nevertheless when 
     <lb/>
     we agree to do a job we do it to the best of our 
     <lb/>
     ability. I am stressing that point because I hope 
     <lb/>
     you will judge that I am competent and fair- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     minded enough to give honest advice to you with 
     <lb/>
     respect to union between the two countries on the 
     <lb/>
     basis of the facts as brought back from Ottawa. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To begin my argument to you today, let me 
     <lb/>
     quote from the reply we received from the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government to our request for these 
     <lb/>
     discussions. It is contained in your Black Book: 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The Canadian government is of the opinion 
     <lb/>
     that the questions to be discussed with the 
  

            <cb/>
           

     delegation are of such complexity and of 
     <lb/>
     such significance for both countries that it is 
     <lb/>
     essential to have a complete and comprehen<lb break="no"/>sive exchange of information and a full and 
     <lb/>
     careful exploration by both parties of all the 
     <lb/>
     issues involved, so that an accurate apprecia<lb break="no"/>tion of the position may be gained on each 
     <lb/>
     side. 
     <lb/>
     
    </p></quote>


            <p>Now you have read and heard it on many oc<lb break="no"/>casions, but I draw your attention to these words, 
     <lb/>and that is, that the questions to be discussed are 
     <lb/>of such complexity and of such significance for 
     <lb/>both countries that it is essential to have a com<lb break="no"/>plete and careful exploration by both parties; and 
     <lb/>again, at the end of that message: "so that an 
     <lb/>accurate appreciation of the position may be 
     <lb/>gained on each side". You see how important it 
     <lb/>was to the Canadian government to make their 
     <lb/>position very clear. They recognized the com<lb break="no"/>plexity and the seriousness of this approach. As 
     <lb/>you are aware, and as I said before to you, we had 
     <lb/>no expert assistance of any kind to help us. We 
     <lb/>applied to the Commission of Government to 
     <lb/>assist us in this matter, but the request was 
     <lb/>refused, so we went off with what we had to do 
     <lb/>the best we could.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the Canadian side, the cabinet members 
     <lb/>
     designated to take part in the discussions were 
     <lb/>
     flanked by some of the top men of the civil 
     <lb/>
     service of Canada. Moreover, the problem of 
     <lb/>
     confederation had been under active study by this 
     <lb/>
     particular group since October of 1946, and ac<lb break="no"/>tually Canada has been studying the proposition 
     <lb/>
     for some years past. As you are aware, our 
     <lb/>
     delegation had no such opportunity of prepara<lb break="no"/>tion and certainly no such assistance during the 
     <lb/>
     discussions. In my opinion our delegation was 
     <lb/>
     not competent to fully discuss such an important 
     <lb/>
     matter without proper assistance, and without an 
     <lb/>
     adequate study of the problem. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I say quite sincerely that for any person, mem<lb break="no"/>ber of this Convention or not, to advise the people 
     <lb/>
     of this country to join in federal union with 
     <lb/>
     Canada without the necessary study of all the 
     <lb/>
     implications of such union, is nothing less than 
     <lb/>
     criminal. What, you ask, is the proper approach? 
     <lb/>
     In my opinion, before union should be recom<lb break="no"/>mended, a complete study of the Canadian sys<lb break="no"/>tem should be made by the various departmental 
     <lb/>
     heads of our civil service, to see and advise the 
     <lb/>
     effect such union would have. The heads of these 


            <pb n="1094" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1094.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1094</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
  

     departments would then confer with a delegation 
     <lb/>
     having full powers to negotiate. In other words, 
     <lb/>
     the case for Newfoundland would be carefully 
     <lb/>
     prepared and fully understood by those who are 
     <lb/>
     to present it, and moreover, the delegation repre<lb break="no"/>senting Newfoundland should have with them 
     <lb/>
     these same departmental heads to advise and 
     <lb/>
     assist throughout the negotiations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I trust my fellow members of the delegation 
     <lb/>
     will not take it that I am making any reflection on 
     <lb/>
     them when I say that the delegation was not 
     <lb/>
     competent to discuss the matters we were dis<lb break="no"/>cussing. This is not intended to be a reflection on 
     <lb/>
     the ability of any one of them, but simply — 
     <lb/>
     except possibly in the case of Mr. Smallwood — 
     <lb/>
     that none of us had studied the matter before the 
     <lb/>
     appointment of the delegation, and we were at a 
     <lb/>
     tremendous disadvantage with no technical ad<lb break="no"/>vice, and lastly, but most important of all, we had 
     <lb/>
     no power to negotiate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I frankly confess that the offer we have 
     <lb/>
     received appears to be fair, but I am fully confi<lb break="no"/>dent that a delegation properly informed, assisted 
     <lb/>
     by competent advisers, and with the power to 
     <lb/>
     negotiate, would receive a better offer from 
     <lb/>
     Canada than we received. I say that with full 
     <lb/>
     knowledge of what I am saying. From informa<lb break="no"/>tion I gathered from various sources during our 
     <lb/>
     visit to Ottawa, I am certain that the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government would have given us a better offer 
     <lb/>
     had the case been properly presented. Again I 
     <lb/>
     repeat, with full knowledge of what I am saying, 
     <lb/>
     that we can still get a better offer or, if you will, 
     <lb/>
     more favourable terms of confederation, if the 
     <lb/>
     approach is made by a government elected by and 
     <lb/>
     representative of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I do not want you to understand that our 
     <lb/>
     delegation did not do a good job or that we were 
     <lb/>
     not given every assistance by the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government. On the contrary, I can assure you 
     <lb/>
     that the delegation did a good job and further, that 
     <lb/>
     we had every co-operation from the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government. Every possible courtesy was ex<lb break="no"/>tended to us, from the time of our arrival in 
     <lb/>
     Canada until our departure. I have nothing but the 
     <lb/>
     greatest of praise and the kindliest feelings for all 
     <lb/>
     those with whom we came in contact, from the 
     <lb/>
     Prime Minister down. The representatives of the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian cabinet with whom we held these dis<lb break="no"/>cussions, were extremely generous of their time 
     <lb/>
     and more than considerate in the manner in which 
  

            <cb/>
       

     they treated us. These gentlemen are extremely 
     <lb/>
     busy, but at all times they endeavoured to meet 
     <lb/>
     our ideas with respect to meetings, no matter how 
     <lb/>
     inconvenient it was to them. Their advisers, 
     <lb/>
     among whom were included the top men of the 
     <lb/>
     civil service, were not only very kind, but at all 
     <lb/>
     times showed that they were anxious to assist us 
     <lb/>
     in every way possible. I gathered from what was 
     <lb/>
     said here on their return, that those who visited 
     <lb/>
     England did not get such a reception. However, 
     <lb/>
     I repeat to those of you who are inclined towards 
     <lb/>
     confederation, that the only proper way in fair<lb break="no"/>ness to Newfoundland, is that negotiations 
     <lb/>
     should be conducted by a Newfoundland govern<lb break="no"/>ment if we are to make the best possible deal for 
     <lb/>
     the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The facts we have brought back are a very 
     <lb/>
     good basis for future negotiations, and there need 
     <lb/>
     be no worry in your minds that if the present offer 
     <lb/>
     from Canada is not accepted, it will lapse. This 
     <lb/>
     was made clear at our last meeting when we were 
     <lb/>
     informed that, unless world economic conditions 
     <lb/>
     changed, the offer would remain the same if it 
     <lb/>
     was not accepted at this time, and negotiations 
     <lb/>
     later renewed. Therefore I say, in view of this 
     <lb/>
     fact, should we not first elect a government to 
     <lb/>
     finalise any such deal? If nothing else but from 
     <lb/>
     sentiment, if we are going to confederate, let us 
     <lb/>
     do it in the proper way. Let us go in the front door 
     <lb/>
     and not the back door! Let us, as befitting the 
     <lb/>
     dignity if this country of ours which is 450 years 
     <lb/>
     old, consummate union in a manner that befits 
     <lb/>
     such an important decision. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Short recess]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Just before that recess, I was com<lb break="no"/>menting on the fact that the report brought back 
     <lb/>
     by the delegation and embodied in the Black 
     <lb/>
     Books and the Grey Book, was in my opinion a 
     <lb/>
     good basis for future negotiation. That is as far as 
     <lb/>
     this country can go at the present time — it is a 
     <lb/>
     good basis for future negotiations between 
     <lb/>
     countries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     However, to return to the argument. It is easy 
     <lb/>
     to understand the reason for Canada wishing to 
     <lb/>
     acquire Newfoundland. To begin with, Canada 
     <lb/>
     is, I believe, the third largest country in area in 
     <lb/>
     the world, but she only has a population of some 
     <lb/>
     12 millions. She needs immigrants to develop her 
     <lb/>
     own country and is at present engaged in bringing 
     <lb/>
     them in by the thousands. She has tremendous 
     <lb/>
     areas of territory, good rich land at present lying 


            <pb n="1095" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1095.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1095</fw>
         

     idle. Why acquire more land that, in a large 
     <lb/>
     measure, does not compare with what they have 
     <lb/>
     at present? Why acquire additional territory that 
     <lb/>
     Canada appears to consider is merely going to be 
     <lb/>
     an additional drain on the pockets of her people? 
     <lb/>
     Various explanations have been advanced, from 
     <lb/>
     personal pride of the Prime Minister to complete 
     <lb/>
     a job his predecessors could not do, all the way 
     <lb/>
     down to the fact that Canada likes us and wants 
     <lb/>
     to help us. Tucked into the middle of all these 
     <lb/>
     reasons are the mineral resources of the island, 
     <lb/>
     but in my opinion the only real reason is our 
     <lb/>
     strategic geographical position. It is in this con<lb break="no"/>nection that I propose to address you at length 
     <lb/>
     today.... The United States, as well, recognises 
     <lb/>
     this fact. North American pressure and economic 
     <lb/>
     interest tend to take Newfoundland towards the 
     <lb/>
     United States, and it is the fear of New<lb break="no"/>foundland's becoming a possession of the United 
     <lb/>
     States more than any other single factor that is 
     <lb/>
     motivating the evident interest that Canada has in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Newfoundland, because of its position, pos<lb break="no"/>sesses a meaning that its economic weight alone 
     <lb/>
     could not give it. It is on the edge of two worlds 
     <lb/>
     — the North American continent and the North 
     <lb/>
     Atlantic basin. To the continent it is an outpost 
     <lb/>
     but in the North Atlantic it forces itself on the 
     <lb/>
     attention; it is in the forefront of the sailor's 
     <lb/>
     thoughts. When soundings are picked up on the 
     <lb/>
     Banks, America is coming near, and when the 
     <lb/>
     first landfall is made it is Newfoundland. The 
     <lb/>
     island is of the continent but not in it. As long as 
     <lb/>
     faces on the continent were turned westward, 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland was forgotten; but for some years 
     <lb/>
     past, events forced them to turn eastward again 
     <lb/>
     and so their glance had to rest on it. The island is 
     <lb/>
     a focus of the lines of force crossing the North 
     <lb/>
     Atlantic basin... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Higgins then gave a lengthy summary of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland's history, concentrating on its 
     <lb/>
     strategic position in the North Atlantic]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Four centuries of history reveal rather clearly 
     <lb/>
     the influences that play about the island of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. They are oceanic and continental; 
     <lb/>
     they radiate out from Europe and from the con<lb break="no"/>tinent of North America. They are not constant, 
     <lb/>
     but vary with the variations in the forms of politi<lb break="no"/>cal organisation in surrounding lands and with 
     <lb/>
     the combinations or severances between those 
     <lb/>
     political organisations. The island is revealed by 
   

            <cb/>
   

     its history to be a focus of lines of force, a place 
     <lb/>
     where international policies intersect. As such it 
     <lb/>
     will always be conspicuous in the history of the 
     <lb/>
     North Atlantic basin and usually so in that of the 
     <lb/>
     North American continent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Human history has alternated between ter<lb break="no"/>restrial and maritime periods. In the middle ages, 
     <lb/>
     the chief centres of movement, the chief routes, 
     <lb/>
     were within the continents. As a result of the 
     <lb/>
     discoveries beginning in the 15th century, 
     <lb/>
     mankind became maritime and the centres moved 
     <lb/>
     out to what had formerly been distant frontier 
     <lb/>
     countries. With exploration completed humanity 
     <lb/>
     tended to become terrestrial once more, the inte<lb break="no"/>rior continental masses, such as Germany and the 
     <lb/>
     United States, rising in importance as the 
     <lb/>
     maritime areas declined. Today ease of com<lb break="no"/>munication makes lakes of the oceans and hence 
     <lb/>
     the sharpness of the distinction is softened. The 
     <lb/>
     past war, indeed, has caused the maritime areas 
     <lb/>
     to take on a new importance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The English thrust into the Americas three 
     <lb/>
     centuries ago afforded a striking example of the 
     <lb/>
     rise in significance of the maritime world. Yet no 
     <lb/>
     sooner had settlements been made then the 
     <lb/>
     oceanic thrust began to be transformed into an 
     <lb/>
     indigenous continentalism, solidly based on the 
     <lb/>
     soil. This continentalism has steadily grown and 
     <lb/>
     upon it is now erected the world's greatest power, 
     <lb/>
     the United States. The resolution of extra-con<lb break="no"/>tinental rivalries by the English victory of 1763 
     <lb/>
     left one race supreme and its later unfortunate 
     <lb/>
     division as a result of the American revolution 
     <lb/>
     has not prevented harmonious co-operation be<lb break="no"/>tween its two parts in the threat of a common 
     <lb/>
     peril. Among other things, it has allowed the 
     <lb/>
     continent of North America to be thought of and 
     <lb/>
     dealt with as a unit in a way which Europe never 
     <lb/>
     could. This has made for a simplicity and large<lb break="no"/>ness of conception with all secondary details 
     <lb/>
     tending to fall into a general scheme. For ex<lb break="no"/>ample, plans for the defence of Europe have not 
     <lb/>
     entered into European thinking, but we in this 
     <lb/>
     continent are busy putting into execution plans 
     <lb/>
     for the defence of North America. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The American "fence" through the middle of 
     <lb/>
     the Pacific ocean and the American thrust 
     <lb/>
     eastward from the Atlantic ocean, together 
     <lb/>
     amount to a recognition that North America is an 
     <lb/>
     island and that its problems must be studied as 
     <lb/>
     those of an island; sea communications and out<lb break="no"/>
      

            <pb n="1096" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1096.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1096</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
   

     lying positions. In terms of defence this means 
     <lb/>
     that the continent as a whole must think in naval 
     <lb/>
     terms and must advance its defence far off from 
     <lb/>
     shore to prevent threat of invasion or of serious 
     <lb/>
     damage to the island citadel. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are concerned here with one aspect of the 
     <lb/>
     entire Atlantic effort— the thrust northeastward, 
     <lb/>
     particularly as it impinges on Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     This thrust is readily divisible into two arms, that 
     <lb/>
     along the coast and that coming out of the St. 
     <lb/>
     Lawrence valley. The Maritime Provinces of 
     <lb/>
     Canada and Newfoundland are the area in which 
     <lb/>
     the two thrusts meet. The area of meeting has not 
     <lb/>
     been stationary but constantly moving. In the 
     <lb/>
     17th century, French (or St. Lawrence) influence 
     <lb/>
     extended well into the present State of Maine. In 
     <lb/>
     the 18th the Gut of Canso was its extreme south<lb break="no"/>western limit. In the first half of the 19th, St. 
     <lb/>
     Lawrence influence was still further curtailed 
     <lb/>
     and was hardly visible beyond Gaspé. Then with 
     <lb/>
     modern communications came its rapid recovery. 
     <lb/>
     Confederation extended it throughout the three 
     <lb/>
     Maritime Provinces, and note the absorption of 
     <lb/>
     all local banking institutions by the large 
     <lb/>
     Canadian banks, and the Bank of Nova Scotia's 
     <lb/>
     conversion of itself into a Montreal organisation 
     <lb/>
     — and the economic forces of which Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion was a counterpart worked over the political 
     <lb/>
     boundary into Maine, once more tying a good 
     <lb/>
     part of that state into the structure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A similar extension went on to the north<lb break="no"/>eastward; with the railway built to Port-aux- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Basques, the way was open for an assault on the 
     <lb/>
     last stronghold of maritimism, Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     This assault was delayed, but when it came, the 
     <lb/>
     main manoeuvre in it was the establishment of 
     <lb/>
     the steamer route from Sydney to Port-aux- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Basques, and the building of the Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     railway across the island to St. John's. This of 
     <lb/>
     course was not the only means by which St. 
     <lb/>
     Lawrence influences came in, but it immensely 
     <lb/>
     facilitated their ingress. The Canadianisation of 
     <lb/>
     island finance was a subsidiary movement based 
     <lb/>
     on this St. Lawrence system of communication, 
     <lb/>
     as was the Canadianisation of two of our major 
     <lb/>
     denominations within recent years. Other eviden<lb break="no"/>ces of the St. Lawrence impact will suggest them<lb break="no"/>selves. In a mechanical age, the St. Lawrence 
     <lb/>
     holds the trump cards of transportation — steam<lb break="no"/>ship, rail and air. Its most serious disability is its 
     <lb/>
     winter closing, which forces it back to its second 
 

            <cb/>
          

     line through Sydney or Halifax. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Since the summer of 1940 political events 
     <lb/>
     have given renewed vitality to the other arm of 
     <lb/>
     the thrust. American influence has been vastly 
     <lb/>
     strengthened by the grant of the bases which has 
     <lb/>
     been characterised as "moving the American 
     <lb/>
     boundary 700 miles eastward". The American 
     <lb/>
     flag now flies in Newfoundland, American 
     <lb/>
     sailors and soldiers are to be seen on the streets 
     <lb/>
     and American ships in the harbour. American 
     <lb/>
     civilians are following, most of them as tourists 
     <lb/>
     and out of curiosity, some on the outlook for 
     <lb/>
     business. Behind this renewed Atlantic push lies 
     <lb/>
     the gigantic wealth and power of the United 
     <lb/>
     States... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If the Maritime Provinces are the continental 
     <lb/>
     termination of the Appalachian Barrier, New<lb break="no"/>foundland is in its extreme end, severed from the 
     <lb/>
     rest of the formation by the sea. It thus affords the 
     <lb/>
     clearest illustration of the marginal nature of the 
     <lb/>
     maritime region, set as it is squarely at the inter<lb break="no"/>section of the two lines of force. To put the point 
     <lb/>
     another way, it is within the overlapping fields of 
     <lb/>
     those two great metropolitan magnets which 
     <lb/>
     have been battling each other for three centuries 
     <lb/>
     past, Montreal and New York. Like other Atlan<lb break="no"/>tic lands, it is of course also within the magnetic 
     <lb/>
     field of another metropolitan area, Great Britain. 
     <lb/>
     The pulls of the three, as its history indicates, 
     <lb/>
     have never been constant or equal upon it. New<lb break="no"/>foundland may be likened to a buoy fast to a long 
     <lb/>
     mooring chain in water where strong currents 
     <lb/>
     run; the buoy streams out from its mooring first 
     <lb/>
     this way and then that, dependent upon the direc<lb break="no"/>tion of the current. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Newfoundland lies across the sea entrance to 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion of Canada, and may well be 
     <lb/>
     described as Canada's front door. If the door were 
     <lb/>
     closed by the island's coming into unfriendly 
     <lb/>
     possession, it would menace Canada's main 
     <lb/>
     highway with the outside world. The ports of the 
     <lb/>
     Maritime Provinces would remain, but their use 
     <lb/>
     involves an additional rail-haul of 500 to 1,000 
     <lb/>
     miles. If the door were locked, as by hostile 
     <lb/>
     occupation, it would be difficult to keep com<lb break="no"/>munication going even through the ports of the 
     <lb/>
     Maritimes. This becomes obvious when the nar<lb break="no"/>rowness and difficulty of the passages north and 
     <lb/>
     south of Newfoundland are realised... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The situation works just as well in reverse. 
     <lb/>
     Given effective defence of Newfoundland by 
   

            <pb n="1097" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1097.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1097</fw>
         

     Canada, it is difficult to see how an enemy sur<lb break="no"/>face vessel could get into the Gulf, or if it did, get 
     <lb/>
     out again, especially now that aircraft play so 
     <lb/>
     large a part in observation and attack. Submarines 
     <lb/>
     are a different story: both straits have ample 
     <lb/>
     water to allow submarines proceeding through 
     <lb/>
     submerged. The Straits of Bell Isle, with modem 
     <lb/>
     means of detection, could be made very 
     <lb/>
     dangerous to them, but no doubt they could still 
     <lb/>
     pass and repass Cabot Strait, but certainly not 
     <lb/>
     without considerable risk. If the island by some 
     <lb/>
     unlucky chance were to fall into hostile hands, it 
     <lb/>
     would be another story: shipping within the Gulf 
     <lb/>
     would be in constant peril. Everything con<lb break="no"/>sidered, Newfoundland may be held to be a very 
     <lb/>
     effective stopper in the Canadian bottle, or in the 
     <lb/>
     picturesque language of Mr. Churchill, "an 
     <lb/>
     orange in the mouth of a sucking pig". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Strategically our possession of Labrador is 
     <lb/>
     also very important. Apart altogether from the 
     <lb/>
     airport at Goose, seaplanes may very well be 
     <lb/>
     secreted in the deep fiords of Labrador and by 
     <lb/>
     building up caches of gasoline between Quebec 
     <lb/>
     and Ontario, and using the innumerable lakes of 
     <lb/>
     that part of the world, they could work across to 
     <lb/>
     within easy bombing distances of the main 
     <lb/>
     centres of the continent, strike sudden blows and 
     <lb/>
     be off again. Anyone who knows that country 
     <lb/>
     will grasp at once the difficulties involved in 
     <lb/>
     stalking a raider to his lair. If he had numerous 
     <lb/>
     caches of gasoline on various lakes, he could 
     <lb/>
     keep playing hide and seek indefinitely... The 
     <lb/>
     coast of Labrador, the natural base from which 
     <lb/>
     bush-raiding would be conducted, is definitely of 
     <lb/>
     great strategic importance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The great airport at Gander has changed the 
     <lb/>
     strategic picture of Newfoundland for it is so 
     <lb/>
     large and has such an enormous capacity in plane 
     <lb/>
     traffic that it becomes like a great fortress or 
     <lb/>
     battleship. It would be fatal to allow an enemy to 
     <lb/>
     damage it or capture it, hence the defences by 
     <lb/>
     which it is surrounded make the island still more 
     <lb/>
     like a fortress — a fortress from which the gar<lb break="no"/>rison can sally out at will and over oceanic dis<lb break="no"/>tances. From Newfoundland, modern bombing 
     <lb/>
     planes can reach the British Isles to the east and 
     <lb/>
     Martinique, Puerto Rico and New Orleans to the 
     <lb/>
     south, Kansas City and Regina to the west... If 
     <lb/>
     the Newfoundland airports were in hostile hands, 
     <lb/>
     many important centres might thus expect to be 
     <lb/>
     bombed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     The vital position of Newfoundland in the 
     <lb/>
     approaches to North America thus clearly comes 
     <lb/>
     out. It covers the whole of the eastern seaboard 
     <lb/>
     at least as far down as New York. If it were in the 
     <lb/>
     hands of an unfriendly power, all exits from the 
     <lb/>
     Gulf of St. Lawrence would be closed and every 
     <lb/>
     Atlantic coast port down as far as Boston would 
     <lb/>
     be subject to attack from the air. Even if the 
     <lb/>
     power which had seized it did not have complete 
     <lb/>
     command of the sea, it could slip out surface 
     <lb/>
     raiders as the Germans did in the last war.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The constant element in all strategic studies is 
     <lb/>
     geography in its aspects of distance, topography, 
     <lb/>
     means of communication and climate. The vary<lb break="no"/>ing element is national policy. Before specific 
     <lb/>
     strategic plans can be worked out, the policy of 
     <lb/>
     the state must be decided upon. If the state wishes 
     <lb/>
     to survive, the constant elements impose upon its 
     <lb/>
     policy a certain quality of predestination.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let us look at what the attitudes of the chief 
     <lb/>
     powers interested must necessarily therefore be 
     <lb/>
     towards Newfoundland. The countries con<lb break="no"/>sidered are Great Britain, the United States and 
     <lb/>
     Canada in the order named. The direct interest of 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain in Newfoundland is small. There is 
     <lb/>
     the historic connection, composed of sentiment, 
     <lb/>
     allegiance and finance, but for Great Britain 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland is necessarily a minor matter, one 
     <lb/>
     of the infinite embarrassing problems of empire, 
     <lb/>
     no more. The day has long gone by when British 
     <lb/>
     policy towards North America had any element 
     <lb/>
     of the dynamic about it — that day passed with 
     <lb/>
     the annexation of Canada in 1763 — and today 
     <lb/>
     North America represents for England not a 
     <lb/>
     sphere of interest but a supply base. Providing the 
     <lb/>
     supplies keep coming, the internal matters of the 
     <lb/>
     continent are a matter of indifference to Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain. Her anxiety about supplies would lead 
     <lb/>
     her to try to see that there are good bases from 
     <lb/>
     which they may be despatched, but efforts of this 
     <lb/>
     sort take the form of advice and request, not of 
     <lb/>
     direct action. In World War I, Great Britain was 
     <lb/>
     still acting indirectly in British North America 
     <lb/>
     and there was much British naval activity in the 
     <lb/>
     Atlantic ports, especially St. John's and Halifax. 
     <lb/>
     In the last war Canada replaced Great Britain, 
     <lb/>
     except in the matter of conveying ships. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     For the United States, on the other hand, New<lb break="no"/>foundland is vital. The United States could not 
     <lb/>
     possibly tolerate a hostile power in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. American naval thinking since 


            <pb n="1098" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-09_Page_1098.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1098</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
          

     Mahan's day is said to have desired a base in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland but there could have been no pos<lb break="no"/>sibility of obtaining the concession except under 
     <lb/>
     the pressure of a great emergency, such as oc<lb break="no"/>curred on the fall of France. The unconditional 
     <lb/>
     British grant of the Newfoundland bases there<lb break="no"/>fore represents something far larger than the mere 
     <lb/>
     panic of the moment; these bases seem to be part 
     <lb/>
     of a coherent, consistent pattern of American 
     <lb/>
     defence now of many years standing. This pattern 
     <lb/>
     works itself out bit by bit, either by conscious 
     <lb/>
     action based on long-range policy or by empiric 
     <lb/>
     processes enjoined by the circumstances of the 
     <lb/>
     moment and as opportunity offers, opportunity 
     <lb/>
     being political events of sufficient magnitude to 
     <lb/>
     scare the American public out of its ordinary 
     <lb/>
     indifference to matters of defence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     American expansion, of which schemes for 
     <lb/>
     defence form an aspect, has been continuous 
     <lb/>
     from the days of the first settlements and the 
     <lb/>
     doctrine of isolation has had little to do with it.... 
     <lb/>
     Since World War I at least, the motive in most of 
     <lb/>
     this expansion has been plain — to add to the 
     <lb/>
     security of the continental United States... The 
     <lb/>
     east coast, far the most important, for some 
     <lb/>
     curious reason, has been the most neglected — 
     <lb/>
     perhaps because of a half-conscious perception 
     <lb/>
     of Great Britain as a barrier against predatory 
     <lb/>
     Europe. Yet it must have been evident to keen 
     <lb/>
     students that the United States sooner or later 
     <lb/>
     would have to have Atlantic offshore defences 
     <lb/>
     comparable with those it possesses in the Pacific. 
     <lb/>
     That process was begun in the summer of 1940 
     <lb/>
     with the acquisition of bases in Bermuda and 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland and extended in 1941 with the 
     <lb/>
     moves into Greenland and Iceland. The United 
     <lb/>
     States has thus very consistently throughout its 
     <lb/>
     history followed a policy of securing control of 
     <lb/>
     all outposts from which threats to its security 
     <lb/>
     might be made. Its conception of outposts has 
     <lb/>
     grown with the increase in the range and effec<lb break="no"/>tiveness of the instruments of war. Where the 
     <lb/>
     conception will eventually lead American arms, 
     <lb/>
     is anyone's speculation... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whatever the temporary problems of adjust<lb break="no"/>ment yet unsettled, it is impossible to go about 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland today without feeling that some<lb break="no"/>thing big has occurred; something as big as the 
    

            <cb/>
         

     previous American advances eastward along the 
     <lb/>
     coast in 1745 and 1758. This advance has cut that 
     <lb/>
     much more of the continent out of the dominion 
     <lb/>
     of a non-American power. Actually, perhaps, out 
     <lb/>
     of the dominion of another power into whose 
     <lb/>
     possession the island came many generations 
     <lb/>
     ago. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The nation whose fortunes are most intimately 
     <lb/>
     bound up with Newfoundland is Canada. It is 
     <lb/>
     abundantly clear that it must be a major aspect of 
     <lb/>
     Canadian policy to ensure the retention of New<lb break="no"/>foundland in friendly hands and to see that even 
     <lb/>
     the friendliest of hands do not arrange things to 
     <lb/>
     her disadvantage. So long as Newfoundland was 
     <lb/>
     a simple British possession and there was no 
     <lb/>
     doubt of Great Britain's sea supremacy in the 
     <lb/>
     Atlantic, issues of sovereignty did not arise. 
     <lb/>
     Canadians were slow to grasp the changing posi<lb break="no"/>tion of Great Britain in sea power and the way in 
     <lb/>
     which that change might affect them. The whole 
     <lb/>
     issue was focused sharply in June, 1940. The fall 
     <lb/>
     of France and the possible fall of Great Britain 
     <lb/>
     was quickly reflected in Canada's assumption of 
     <lb/>
     responsibility for the defence of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     and in her increase of her forces there. This was 
     <lb/>
     the first direct Canadian intervention in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Canada is as yet politically an immature 
     <lb/>
     country that is only slowly realising its own in<lb break="no"/>dividuality; it is therefore not to be expected that 
     <lb/>
     it would have as clear-cut a policy as has the 
     <lb/>
     United States. Until June 1940, it was impossible 
     <lb/>
     to secure much attention to arguments urging that 
     <lb/>
     Canada should assume responsibilities in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I move now that the committee rise and report 
     <lb/>
     progress. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The committee report that they 
     <lb/>
     have considered the matter to them referred, 
     <lb/>
     made some progress and ask leave to sit again 
     <lb/>
     tomorrow. The motion is that the report of the 
     <lb/>
     committee be received and adopted. Motion car<lb break="no"/>ried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Notice of closure: I beg to move that 
     <lb/>
     immediately before the orders of the day are 
     <lb/>
     called on Wednesday, 14 January, 1948. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>