<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-11-23" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-11-23">23 November 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          
        <biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="188"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0183.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0184.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0185.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0186.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0187.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0188.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-01">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-01">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-08">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0183">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0183.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0184">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0184.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0185">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0185.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0186">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0186.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0187">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0187.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0188">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0188.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="183" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0183.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">183</fw>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-03-01, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

<!--<p>
     begun a distinguished career when he was called 
     <lb/>
     to be Chairman of the National Convention. This 
     <lb/>
     latter post, which held no material advantage 
     <lb/>
     whatever for him, I believe he prized most of all. 
     <lb/>
     I said "I believe" —- I think I am justified in 
     <lb/>
     saying that I know, for I knew the man. And now 
     <lb/>
     that he is gone, the greatest tribute that I can pay 
     <lb/>
     him is to say that, to me, he is now, as he always 
     <lb/>
     was and always will be Cyril Fox, the man. And 
     <lb/>
     yet he is not entirely gone from our midst. His 
     <lb/>
     cheery spirit can still guide us along the paths of 
     <lb/>
     unselfish effort and sound decision. May his clear 
     <lb/>
     intellect and his devoted patriotism abide with us 
     <lb/>
     to the end. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job Mr. Chairman, I have the honour to 
     <lb/>
     second the motion which has been so very elo<lb break="no"/>quently proposed by my friend, Mr. Bradley. 
     <lb/>
     There is not very much that I can add. I have 
     <lb/>
     known Cyril Fox in a personal way for many 
     <lb/>
     years. I have known him in recent years on the 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     banks of the river where we spent a week or two 
     <lb/>
     regularly, and under those circumstances one 
     <lb/>
     gets to know one's fellow companions. I have no 
     <lb/>
     hesitation in saying that during those times I 
     <lb/>
     never knew Cyril Fox to say an unkindly word 
     <lb/>
     about anyone; I have heard him say very many 
     <lb/>
     kind words about people and do very kind deeds. 
     <lb/>
     He was a devoted father and a devoted husband 
     <lb/>
     and his friends were very, very fond of him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I do not believe he would wish us to take a 
     <lb/>
     gloomy view of his absence here. I believe he 
     <lb/>
     would like us to feel that he is still with us, 
     <lb/>
     influencing us in our deliberations and helping us 
     <lb/>
     to solve the problems connected with the land 
     <lb/>
     which he loved. Cyril Fox was, to sum up his 
     <lb/>
     character, a true sportsman, a true gentleman and 
     <lb/>
     a true Christian in every sense of those words. I 
     <lb/>
     have the honour to second the motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>[The motion carried unanimously, and the Con<lb break="no"/>vention adjourned]<lb/>
            </p>

    
            <milestone type="unknown"/>-->

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     November 23, 1946<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName>. Gentlemen, I open the meeting <lb/> with some
                  ten members absent. I don't know <lb/> whether you wish to continue with the
                  meeting <lb/> or wait a little. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> How many? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Ten, sir. By now they should all <lb/> be here.
                  Well, if it is your wish, gentlemen, we <lb/> will continue. I will ask Mr. Cashin
                  to explain the <lb/> purpose of the meeting. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Mr. Chairman, on Thursday after<lb break="no"/>noon the Steering Committee met at the request <lb/> of the Commissioner for
                  Home Affairs and <lb/> Education, in his office, to discuss the vacancy of <lb/>
                  Chairman of the National Convention. Mr. Walsh <lb/> pointed out that when the
                  National Convention <lb/> Act<ref target="#fn_x1">[2]</ref> was being formed the
                  government had ap<lb break="no"/>proached Judge Fox, asking him whether or not
                  <lb/> he would accept the chairmanship of the National <lb/> Convention. That was
                  why it was inserted that the <lb/> Chairman should be a judge of the Supreme <lb/>
                  Court. Now Judge Fox has passed away, and we <lb/> find ourselves without a
                  Chairman, and Mr. <lb/> Walsh wanted to know what idea we had regard<lb break="no"/>ing the future position of Chairman; whether the <lb/> delegates would be
                  interested in electing their <lb/> own Chairman from the members, or whether the
                  <lb/> government would have to appoint one. If the <lb/>
                  <cb/> Convention members desire to elect one of their <lb/> own delegates as
                  Chairman of the Convention, <lb/> Mr. Walsh informed us that he felt that die
                     Con<lb break="no"/>vention Act could be amended to cover it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     That is really the object of the meeting here 
     <lb/>
     this morning, to ascertain whether or not we, as 
     <lb/>
     delegates, are interested in electing our own 
     <lb/>
     Chairman. That is the sum and substance of what 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Walsh told us the other afternoon. Now the 
     <lb/>
     matter is open for discussion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I don't think that is quite precisely <lb/> correct.
                  The idea is to explore the idea, not to limit <lb/> it to any one thing. I don't
                  think the government <lb/> has given it any real thought. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Well, I think they have, otherwise <lb/> they
                  would not have called us. They want to know <lb/> if we will do thejob or ifwe
                  want to throw it over <lb/> on them. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> If we do not do something they will <lb/> have to
                  appoint a judge of the Supreme Court. It <lb/> is up to us if we would rather have
                  one of oursel<lb break="no"/>ves or a judge of the Supreme Court. I am not <lb/>
                  quite sure if he definitely states that it would have <lb/> to be a member of the
                  Convention or not. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> No. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> We can make all sorts of suggestions, <lb/> and
                  whatever we decide they would try to fall in <lb/>
                  <note xml:id="fn_01">[1] The Secretary, Captain Warren, acted as Chairman.</note>
                  <note xml:id="fn_x1">[2] Volume II:1. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
                  <pb n="184" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0184.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">184</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> line. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Anybody else desiring to say <lb/> anything?
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> If we appoint somebody from the <lb/> Convention,
                  under the act, that Chairman will <lb/> have no vote. Is that correct? In case we
                  appoint <lb/> somebody as Chairman what about their vote <lb/> then? Would not the
                  Chairman of the Convention <lb/> be in an awkward position? He would not be <lb/>
                  allowed to cast a vote, and he would not be able <lb/> to take part in debate. I
                  understand the Chairman <lb/> can't take part in debates. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> The custom has been in the past for <lb/> the
                  Chairman of the committees to be allowed to <lb/> leave the Chair and take part in
                  the debate if he <lb/> wanted to. If he wanted to take part in a debate <lb/> he
                  could ask someone else to take the Chair while <lb/> he took his part. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JONE5">Mr. Jones</persName> Would he have a vote? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Yes. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I consider it quite a responsibility. <lb/> How
                  would they be chosen? Would it be a matter <lb/> of proposing and seconding and
                  being carried, or <lb/> would it be a secret vote? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Mr. Chairman, I hope you don't <lb/> think that I
                  am expressing myself too much, but <lb/> in ordinary parliamentary procedure the
                  Speaker <lb/> was usually proposed by the Prime Minister and <lb/> seconded in the
                  House by the leader of the Op<lb break="no"/>position, and was elected
                  unanimously. If we <lb/> decided to elect a man to become Chairman who <lb/> is a
                  member of this Convention, I think, sir, that <lb/> no member would take the job
                  unless he had the <lb/> unanimous backing of every member, and if we <lb/> can't
                  arrive at that decision then the only thing to <lb/> do is throw it back on the
                  government, and let <lb/> them appoint someone from the Court or else<lb break="no"/>where. I am prepared to take the chance and <lb/> suggest that this
                  Convention suggest to the <lb/> government that the act be amended to cover the
                  <lb/> appointmentof one of our delegates as Chairman, <lb/> and that delegate
                  would undoubtedly retain his <lb/> vote. No man here would want to be Chairman
                  <lb/> and lose his vote. After all he is elected by the <lb/> people and would
                  want to vote on a matter of vital <lb/> importance. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     I move that this Convention suggest to the 
     <lb/>
     government the changing of the Convention Act, 
     <lb/>
     and that Mr. Bradley be appointed Chairman of 
     <lb/>
     this Convention. I think Mr. Bradley is capable 
     <lb/>
     of the job, and he is a lawyer, etc. I make the 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     motion that Mr. Bradley be appointed Chairman, 
     <lb/>
     and that the government be asked to change the 
     <lb/>
     act to cover it. The clause in the act regarding a 
     <lb/>
     judge of the Supreme Court could be amended 
     <lb/>
     accordingly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I don't think it would be right <lb/> to
                  deprive any member of the Convention of his <lb/> vote, and my idea would be to
                  have him give a <lb/> casting vote. I see no reason why we should not <lb/> have a
                  member of our own Convention as a <lb/> Chairman. I feel sure that in the person
                  of <lb/> Mr. Bradley we have a man well fitted for the <lb/> position, a man who
                  occupied the position of <lb/> Attorney General of Newfoundland, and I would <lb/>
                  like it very much if the decision could be unani<lb break="no"/>mous. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I would like to support that, but unless <lb/> the
                  Convention is unanimous there is not much <lb/> that we can do. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Is it the idea that we leave it to <lb/> the
                  government to appoint Mr. Bradley? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> Yes, they amend the act. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I have no objection to that. On <lb/> the point
                  of a Supreme Court judge, if Mr. Winter <lb/> appoints himself to the bench, as he
                  has every <lb/> right to do, we will have on the Supreme Court <lb/> bench two
                  judges who were ex-commissioners, <lb/> one the Chief Justice and the other Mr.
                  Winter <lb/> himself. It seems to me that it would be wrong to <lb/> have as
                  Chairman of the Convention an ex- <lb break="yes"/> commissioner, an ex-member of
                  the government <lb/> which, amongst other forms of government, have <lb/> to be
                  reviewed by the Convention. That leaves <lb/> only one Supreme Court judge, namely
                  Judge <lb/> Dunfield. He, in addition to being a judge, is <lb/> chairman of the
                  Housing Corporation, a very <lb/> large outfit which takes up just about every
                  spare <lb/> minute of his time when he is not doing court <lb/> work, and I have
                  heard a rumour to the effect that <lb/> it is these two difficulties, first that
                  two of the <lb/> judges would be ex-commissioners, and second <lb/> that the only
                  remaining judge is also extremely <lb/> busy apart from his court work, which
                  promoted <lb/> in the government the thought that perhaps the <lb/> wisest thing
                  to do would to be repeal the clause <lb/> requiring a Supreme Court judge to be
                  chairman. <lb/> If we look around the town and around the <lb/> country to find
                  someone who is capable of being <lb/> Chairman, and in addition to being capable,
                     will<lb break="no"/>ing and with the time to spare to be Chairman, the <lb/>
                  woods are not exactly full. <lb/>
               </p>
            <pb n="185" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0185.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">185</fw>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> I disagree entirely that the Chairman <lb/> should
                  have not only a vote, but the casting vote. <lb/> I am a bit worried about the
                  question of voting as <lb/> far as the Chairman is concerned. I disagree also
                  <lb/> with Mr. Smallwood when he suggests that be<lb break="no"/>cause Mr. Winter
                  was a member of the Commis<lb break="no"/>sion of Government it might be unwise to
                  appoint <lb/> him. In that particular case there would be no <lb/> doubt at all
                  about his impartiality, even though he <lb/> has been a member of the Commission
                  of <lb/> Government. I can see that some people in that <lb/> position would not
                  be suitable, but I have no <lb/> objection to the proposal of Major Cashin, <lb/>
                  provided we can consider the question of voting. <lb/> The Chairman would be in a
                  rather difFIcult posi<lb break="no"/>tion when debate gets a bit heated and he
                  would <lb/> have to think about his position as chairman, and <lb/> also of how he
                  is going to vote, not only in the <lb/> minor matters, but in the main decision,
                  which in <lb/> my opinion takes all of any man's time. On the <lb/> question of
                  voting I would like to reserve our <lb/> opinion for a little while longer. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I think it would be a distinct loss to the <lb/>
                  Convention if Mr. Bradley, for instance, was in <lb/> the position of not being
                  able to take part in the <lb/> debates, and consequently in the voting. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, the Speaker in <lb/> the old days
                  always had a private seat to the right <lb/> of the official seat where he sat as
                  chairman. In <lb/> the old days, and in any parliament, the Speaker <lb/> vacated
                  the Chair and occupied his private seat <lb/> and took part in the debate. I have
                  seen and heard <lb/> Judge Fox do it, and Mr. Winter and Mr. Penney <lb/> (in 1919
                  when he was Speaker), and certainly I <lb/> have seen them vote. They don't avail
                  of their <lb/> right to speak or vote on everything that crops up, <lb/> but on
                  vital matters, as elected citizens, they do <lb/> avail of their right I agree
                  with Mr. Ashboume. <lb/> I don't see how he can give up his vote, but he <lb/>
                  should not give the casting vote. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> To be quite frank, although Mr. Brad<lb break="no"/>ley is here, I have come to almost wait for his <lb/> opinion. I give such
                  thought to it, and I hesitate <lb/> to see him out of the position where he would
                  be <lb/> there, and to know his opinion on any matter that <lb/> might come up.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashboume</persName> I consider that every member <lb/> of this
                  Convention has been given by his people <lb/> the power to vote, and whether he is
                  in the Chair <lb/> or whatever he is I don't think that vote should <lb/> be taken
                  from him. Rather than do that I think we <lb/>
                  <cb/> should give him more power commensurate with <lb/> his position, and I don't
                  advocate that that power <lb/> be given him of the casting vote, but rather than
                  <lb/> take away his power to vote at all, my idea would <lb/> be to give him more
                  power, that is the casting <lb/> vote, certainly we ought not to deprive him of
                  his <lb/> vote. The Chairman, Judge Fox, was appointed <lb/> by the government and
                  he could not have a vote, <lb/> but if we elect a Chairman now we have a man <lb/>
                  that was elected by the people, and naturally if <lb/> the people sent him here,
                  they sent him to exer<lb break="no"/>cise a vote. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p> 
                  <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I entirely support the last speaker. I <lb/> don' t
                  think it would be right to remove Mr. Brad<lb break="no"/>ley from his place on
                  the floor of the assembly, <lb/> but I can't see at the moment any more suitable
                  <lb/> person. I think it rests between Mr. Bradley and <lb/> Justice Dunfield. I
                  don't like to see Mr. Bradley <lb/> removed from the floor, but at the same time I
                  <lb/> think he is the most suitable person, but I think it <lb/> should be
                  unanimous. I feel that Mr. Bradley <lb/> should only use his vote under the most
                     extenuat<lb break="no"/>ing circumstances. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> Mr. Chairman, I think we <lb/> have to forget
                  that this is not the government, but <lb/> it is a Convention. When a Speaker is
                  appointed <lb/> by the government he is entirely in favour of the <lb/>
                  government, although he tries to conduct matters <lb/> as best he can, but his
                  opinions are definitely in <lb/> favour of the government. If we appoint a mem<lb break="no"/>ber of this Convention immediately this man is in <lb/> an
                  analogous position. If he casts his vote he will <lb/> always be partial. I can't
                  see how he can be <lb/> anything else. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There is no objection to his <lb/> being
                  partial so long as he is not partial between <lb/> one member and another, that is
                  in enforcing or <lb/> not enforcing a given rule for or against a mem<lb break="no"/>ber, but there is no argument against a chairman <lb/> being
                  partial. If a man is a human being he is <lb/> partial, he must have his oWn
                  personal beliefs, but <lb/> he must not use these to discriminate against any
                  <lb/> member. His only power is to enforce the rules. <lb/> His own opinions are
                  nobody's business but his<lb/>own.<lb/>
                  <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr.Ballam</persName> If we have the authority to put a <lb/> man in as
                  Chairman we can also put him out. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> Ithink we have no power to appoint, <lb/>only to
                  recommend. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> I was not speaking of the <lb/> Chairman being
                  partial towards members, but <lb/>
                  <pb n="186" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0186.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">186</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> being partial towards aquestion which may
                  come <lb/> before the house. If he casts a vote on any side of <lb/> an important
                  question his opponents will imme<lb break="no"/>diately say that he is partial. I
                  think it would be a <lb/> decided loss if Mr. Bradley could not express his <lb/>
                  opinion as he would like. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> As I understand it, we are talking <lb/> about the
                  appointing of a member of this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion as Chairman, and it
                  seems to me that two <lb/> outstanding matters should concern us most. One <lb/>
                  is the qualifications of the Chairman, and the <lb/> other is his impartiality. In
                  regard to the member <lb/> of this Convention named, all members here <lb/>
                  present know that we had differences in debate, <lb/> but as far as I am
                  concerned, it is over and <lb/> forgotten. I listened very attentively to the
                     elo<lb break="no"/>quent tribute which Mr. Bradley made to the late <lb/> Judge
                  Fox, and I do not think any man of good <lb/> common sense could make the
                  statements that <lb/> Mr. Bradley made in a public session unless he <lb/> meant
                  it sincerely. Apart altogether from the <lb/> voting matter, I do not feel myself
                  competent to <lb/> discuss that at this time. If the feeling of the <lb/>
                  Convention is unanimous, I rather think that <lb/> Mr. Bradley would make a
                  suitable and satisfac<lb break="no"/>tory Chairman. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> When I spoke just now, I had no <lb/> idea that
                  any member would take that respon<lb break="no"/>sibility. I am glad that one of
                  us is prepared to <lb/> take that responsibility. A good many of you have <lb/>
                  known Mr. Bradley a long time; I have known <lb/> him only since I came here to
                  this Convention.... <lb/> Should he be appointed, he will not be able to <lb/>
                  enter as fully into debates on the various ques<lb break="no"/>tions as he would
                  like to, but maybe Mr. Bradley <lb/> would be in a position to forego some of
                  these <lb/> things. I do not think it would be amiss if <lb/> Mr. Bradley would
                  express himself on this par<lb break="no"/>ticular point. Personally, I am
                  prepared to vote <lb/> for Mr. Bradley...., I would like to see everything <lb/>
                  working in harmony, and I do not see any reason <lb/> why a member of this
                  Convention, who is <lb/> capable, could not be appointed as chairman to <lb/>
                  guide our destinies in a satisfactory manner. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Are you ready for the question? <lb/>It is proposed
                  by Major Cashin and seconded by <lb/>Mr. Ashbourne that Mr. Bradley he recom<lb break="no"/>mended for Chairman and that the Commission <lb/>of Government be
                  advised to change the act. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried unanimously]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> This question of the Chairman <lb/> voting. The
                  act, in addition to providing for the <lb/> appointment of a Supreme Court judge,
                  provides <lb/> also that judge shall not have the right to vote, <lb/> and in
                  accordance with the act the standing orders <lb/> of the Convention also provide
                  that that Chair<lb break="no"/>man shall not vote. So in order to enable the <lb/>
                  Chairman to vote, it is necessary first to amend <lb/> the act, and second to
                  amend the standing orders. <lb/> That ought to be taken care of. The motion merely
                  <lb/> recommends that Mr. Bradley be appointed <lb/> Chairman and that the section
                  of the act be <lb/> repealed. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> And also that he retain his vote. <lb/> That was
                  my motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> My understanding of it is that <lb/> paragraph
                  one will be wiped out and the govern<lb break="no"/>ment will insert other words.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I would like to be placed on record <lb/> as
                  wishing to thank the Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment for giving us the
                  privilege of appointing our <lb/> own Chairman. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Chairman read paragraph 2 of the National<lb/>Convention Act<ref target="#fn_x2">[1]</ref>]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> If they amend the act, we will ap<lb break="no"/>point him My motion was that we appoint <lb/> Mr. Bradley and that the
                  Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment be advised to change the act — that
                  section <lb/> 2 be amended, and that the National Convention <lb/> as it exists,
                  be empowered to appoint a Chairman. <lb/> We have already done that. Now we want
                  to <lb/> change the act to cover that. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> We have not done that. What <lb/> we have done
                  in adopting Major Cashin's motion <lb/> is that we have notified the government
                  that we <lb/> want them to repeal that part of the act which <lb/> forbids the
                  appointment of a Chairman who is not <lb/> a judge of the Supreme Court, and to
                  appoint <lb/>Mr. Bradley at our request. We cannot appoint <lb/>him. We recommend
                  that they appoint him at our <lb/>request. A motion could be put that the act be
                  <lb/>amended by the government ensuring that the <lb/>new Chairman so nominated
                  shall have the right <lb/>to vote and subsequently that our standing rules <lb/>be
                  amended, if necessary, to ensure that he has a <lb/>vote. <lb/>
               </p>
   
    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> We should add, "and also that he <lb/> have the
                  right to speak." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Would it not be better to do all that in <lb/> one
                  motion? <lb/>
               </p>
   
<note xml:id="fn_x2">Volume II:1. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

            <pb n="187" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0187.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">187</fw>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> What I think should happen is, that <lb/> this
                  recommendation goes to the government; <lb/> they will draft an amendment to
                  clause 2 and send <lb/> it back here to see if it covers our request. Could <lb/>
                  we not appoint a sub-committee to discuss with <lb/> the government the fixing of
                  section 2? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> If the meeting agrees that that <lb/> is
                  included in your motion — that the Chairman <lb/> is to have his vote — that he is
                  not to lose his <lb/> privilege as a member. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> We all understand that. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> In view of Mr. Bradley's being now <lb/>
                  recommended to the government, and let us as<lb break="no"/>sume Mr. Bradley is
                  appointed by the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, then the fact that the Steering
                  Committee <lb/> will have to go over the rules of procedure and <lb/> fix them
                  according to the appointment to the <lb/> Chair, why all this trouble about
                  changing the <lb/> rules? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The Steering Committee has <lb/> no such right.
                  The committee is not a cabinet and <lb/> can decide nothing. The Convention has
                  that <lb/> right. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> There is a question of principle in<lb break="no"/>volved. Instead of making a recommendation, we <lb/> should appoint our own
                  Chairman now. We are <lb/> in session; this has come up. It is a question of <lb/>
                  principle and dignity. We ought to have the right <lb/> to appoint our own
                  Chairman and we ought to <lb/> decide whether the Chairman is to have the right
                  <lb/> to vote. We go back to the Commission and say, <lb/> "We want the right to
                  carry on ourselves." If you <lb/> trace back the history of the Convention, it is
                  a <lb/> parliament of disabilities. One of the rights of <lb/> parliament is that
                  it can make legislation. We are, <lb/> in effect, a minor parliament. Is not that
                  right, <lb/> Mr. Bradley? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> In principle you are right. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> We should undertake <hi rendition="simple:italic">now</hi> to appoint <lb/> Mr. Bradley as Chairman. We should undertake <lb/>
                  also to give him the right to retain his vote. It is a <lb/> question of
                  principle. If we are here to do a job, <lb/> let us do it. We ought to demand that
                  right. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> I would like to support Mr. <lb/> Butt
                  strongly. The right of parliamentary privi<lb break="no"/>lege has come up. Maybe
                  if we had asked for it <lb/> in the beginning we would have gotten it. If we <lb/>
                  are not to be a parliament of disabilities I make a <lb/> motion that we ask to be
                  given parliamentary <lb/> privileges. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I second that motion. If we <lb/>
                  <cb/> have parliamentary privileges, we can say what <lb/> we like and no one
                  outside can sue. We have not <lb/> got that right, and it may be necessary. I have
                  a <lb/> certain thing to say about a certain commissioner <lb/> and I am going to
                  say it. I would prefer not to be <lb/> sued. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Even if it is libelous? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Yes. I want to tell a certain <lb/>
                  commissioner he is a liar. If we had parliamentary <lb/> rights, a member, in the
                  public interest, has a <lb/> certain right to say certain things for which he
                  <lb/> could not be sued. He can be dealt with by par<lb break="no"/>liament, but
                  cannot be sued. It is a restraining <lb/> influence if it limits our freedom.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> I understand something about the <lb/> privileges
                  of parliament, but I would not go so far <lb/> as to vote for a recommendation of
                  that kind. I do <lb/> not think it is necessary, and, what is more to the <lb/>
                  point, I am perfectly sure you will get no such <lb/> authority from the
                  government. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> The motion has been put and car<lb break="no"/>ried by a unanimous vote; I suggest we form a <lb/> committee including the
                  Acting Chairman, <lb/> Mr. Higgins, Major Cashin and Mr. Smallwood <lb/> to see
                  that what we decided will be carried out <lb/> and let us be finished with it.
                  They could report <lb/> back to the meeting. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I support that. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> I wish to withdraw the motion. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[Mr. Smallwood, seconder, assented]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> On the question which I raised are we <lb/> going to
                  recommend, or are we going to appoint? <lb/> We ought not to let technicalities
                  stand in our <lb/> way. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> We suggest to the government that <lb/> they
                  change the act to cover the appointment of <lb/> a gentleman nominated by us.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> That is what we have done. We <lb/> have
                  nominated a Chairman and we ask them to <lb/> confirm it. The initiative comes
                  from us. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> I do not like to get into this debate. <lb/> I
                  would point out that the principle is correct. This <lb/> Convention should have
                  the right to select its own <lb/> Chairman. That is the basis of the whole thing.
                  I <lb/> would suggest that the motion take something of <lb/> this form: "That the
                  government he advised that <lb/> this Convention is of opinion that it should have
                  <lb/> power to select and recommend its own Chair<lb break="no"/>man and in
                  pursuance of that opinion..." whatever <lb/> else you would like to add. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> "And in pursuance of that <lb/>
                  <pb n="188" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-23_Page_0188.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">188</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> opinion it has today selected Mr. F. Gordon
                  <lb/> Bradley as Chairman, and asks the government <lb/> to change the act
                  accordingly." <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I think it would be a good idea <lb/>if the motion
                  was put in writing. The motion as <lb/>really voted on should be read by the
                  Secretary <lb/>before it is put so that there can be no doubt in the <lb/>minds of
                  those voting on it. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[A recess was called at this juncture so that a<lb/>sub-committee consisting of the Acting Chaer<lb/>man, Mr. Higgins, Mr. Cashin, Mr. Smallwood<lb/>and Mr. Ashboume, could draft a motion]</hi><lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Here is the motion, gentlemen: <lb/>Resolved that
                  we advise the Commission <lb/>of Government of our wish to be empowered <lb/>
                  <cb/> to select our own Chairman, and that we have <lb/> today selected Mr. E
                  Gordon Bradley, <lb/> K.C., for that position, subject to the consent <lb/> of the
                  Commission of Government, and that <lb/> we advise the Commission of Government of
                  <lb/> our wish that Mr. Bradley be appointed <lb/> Chairman of the National
                  Convention, and <lb/> that we request the Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment
                  to amend the National Convention Act <lb/> accordingly, and in such a way as not
                  to <lb/> deprive Mr. Bradley of his rights as an <lb/> elected delegate to the
                  National Convention. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The original motion, proposed by Mr. Cashin,<lb/>was rescinded, and the new motion carried. The<lb/>Convention adjourned]</hi><lb/> 
               <lb/>
            </p>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>