<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-11-07"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-11-07">7 November 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="164" to="174"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0164.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0165.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0166.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0167.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0168.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0169.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0170.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0171.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0172.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0173.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0174.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-02-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0164">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0164.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0165">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0165.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0166">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0166.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0167">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0167.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0168">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0168.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0169">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0169.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0170">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0170.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0171">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0171.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0172">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0172.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0173">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0173.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0174">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0174.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="164"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0164.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">164</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
<!-- GL, 2017-02-23, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 


           <!-- <p>
     people will carry on their boarding school. They 
     <lb/>
     take the children from the isolated villages and 
     <lb/>
     families around the coast and bring them into 
     <lb/>
     North West River and Cartwright, board them, 
     <lb/>
     feed them and clothe them for $40 a year, $4 a 
     <lb/>
     month, and now at North West River they will be 
     <lb/>
     sending them to the amalgamated school, and we 
     <lb/>
     are hoping that boarding school will increase. 
     <lb/>
     That means that from the lone villages and 
     <lb/>
     families along the coast the Children have the 
     <lb/>
      advantage of getting their education, and being 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     fed and clothed for the year, and under the 
     <lb/>
     denominational system the Anglican Church and 
     <lb/>
     the one I represent put teachers in the bigger 
     <lb/>
     villages along the coast, which gives us a fairly 
     <lb/>
     good system of education. The interest that the 
     <lb/>
     Grenfell Mission has had in the north has 
     <lb/>
     facilitated the matter of education to a great ex<lb break="no"/>tent, and it seems to function fairly well at the 
     <lb/>
     present time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [The committee rose and reported progress and 
     <lb/>
     the Convention adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head>
     November 7, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Chairman<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> Before we begin, I have to 
     <lb/>
     report that the health of Hon. Mr. Justice Fox has 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
         
     improved, as well as that of Mr. Brown and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Banfield. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head>
     Report of the Education Committee:<ref target="#fn_x1">[2]</ref>
 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Ashbourne ....The money spent on schools 
     <lb/>
     and teacher training has been discussed. They are 
     <lb/>
     both very important and necessary, complemen<lb break="no"/>tary to each other. We cannot allow the children 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland to spend their days in 
     <lb/>
     delapidated, unhealthy and unsanitary schools, 
     <lb/>
     and the Commission of Government should be 
     <lb/>
     highly congratulated for embarking on school 
     <lb/>
     reconstruction on a big scale, as well as in the 
     <lb/>
     raising of teachers' salaries, which still need fur<lb break="no"/>ther attention. Brainy people can command good 
     <lb/>
     wages, and if teaching does not offer the neces<lb break="no"/>sary pecuniary reward it is small wonder that the 
     <lb/>
     ambitious seek other employment, where their 
     <lb/>
     services are more adequately compensated. If we 
     <lb/>
     expect to have as leaders to train our youth, to 
     <lb/>
     reap the fruits of the capabilities and talents of 
     <lb/>
     those who have attained the heights of scholar<lb break="no"/>ship, we must be prepared to pay salaries to 
     <lb/>
     induce them to remain in the teaching profession. 
     <lb/>
     In some outport schools we lack teachers who can 
     <lb/>
     satisfactorily teach certain languages and 
     <lb/>
     science. Teachers who cannot give instruction in 
     <lb/>
     these subjects will be at a disadvantage and the 
     <lb/>
     pupils also.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With reference to common or amalgamated 
     <lb/>
     schools<ref target="#fn_02">[3]</ref>, there is a sincere desire on the part of 
     <lb/>
     many to have these schools; but on examination 
     <lb/>
     we find different grading of teachers. Where can 
     <lb/>
     we hope to get suitable teachers for common 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
   
           
     schools until we are assured that a uniform and 
     <lb/>
     standard diploma of competency is forthcoming? 
     <lb/>
     Doubt may exist regarding the qualifications of 
     <lb/>
     teachers, but I feel that more co-ordination of the 
     <lb/>
     various heads of the Department of Education 
     <lb/>
     might be a good idea. Then the matter of owner<lb break="no"/>ship of these common schools comes up, and who 
     <lb/>
     is going to be responsible for their maintenance 
     <lb/>
     and repairs? The present system in New<lb break="no"/>foundland has progressed very well, but if a 
     <lb/>
     concentration of the population were deemed 
     <lb/>
     advisable the matter would have to be solved. It 
     <lb/>
     is to be regretted that the building program has 
     <lb/>
     been temporarily halted owing to lack of nails 
     <lb/>
     and other building supplies. Another matter that 
     <lb/>
     calls for cement is school medical examination, 
     <lb/>
     which should be received by all pupils. For<lb break="no"/>tunately in Twillingate we have the Notre Dame 
     <lb/>
     Bay Memorial Hospital, and there is a clinic held 
     <lb/>
     by which each student can have a free medical 
     <lb/>
     examination. I believe this is the policy in vogue 
     <lb/>
     in St. John's also, but I would like to see it ex<lb break="no"/>tended to all the outports.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would like to pay tribute to the various school 
     <lb/>
     boards, as without their services I am afraid the 
     <lb/>
     whole plan of education could not function so 
     <lb/>
     well. I spent nine years as a member of a school 
     <lb/>
     board and in that time we had to pay 90% of our 
     <lb/>
     grant towards teachers salaries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Next there is the matter of free and compul<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_01">1 The Secretary, Captain Warren, acted as Chairman.</note> 
     
   <note xml:id="fn_x1">2 Volume II:65. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
   
     <note xml:id="fn_02">3 That is, non-denominational schools.</note><pb n="165"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0165.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">165</fw>sory education. In that the government made a 
     <lb/>
     step in the right direction.<ref target="#fn_03">[1]</ref> If pupils cannot pay 
     <lb/>
     half for school books, the government should see 
     <lb/>
     that they are provided free. I believe that it would 
     <lb/>
     be a good move to have a university here. Also, 
     <lb/>
     it is essential to have regional schools provided 
     <lb/>
     in the larger outports. I regret to have heard the 
     <lb/>
     figures given out yesterday, namely, that there 
     <lb/>
     were 325 ungraded teachers and 1,788 graded. 
     <lb/>
     This is surely the outcome of the low salaries paid 
     <lb/>
     in the past; and I hope now that salaries have been 
     <lb/>
     increased somewhat teachers will come forward 
     <lb/>
     to get their necessary grades. Adult education has 
     <lb/>
     been also mentioned and I am pleased to see the 
     <lb/>
     progress made. I would like to refer to political 
     <lb/>
     education; it is very necessary in Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     We must aim at true democracy and that means 
     <lb/>
     that we must be responsible for our own affairs. 
     <lb/>
     But it devolves upon the government to see that 
     <lb/>
     the people are educated politically so far as is 
     <lb/>
     possible 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Vincent As I see it, the Education Commit<lb break="no"/>tee has done a good job.... I believe their figures 
     <lb/>
     are essentially accurate and I am quite willing to 
     <lb/>
     discount the Chadwick-Jones paragraph on 
     <lb/>
     education in favour of theirs. They have 
     <lb/>
     presented a fair picture of a very important sub, 
     <lb/>
     ject.... There are ever-expanding fields of im<lb break="no"/>provement in education, for everyone will agree 
     <lb/>
     that the first requisite of a nation is the education 
     <lb/>
     of its children. The present estimates of slightly 
     <lb/>
     over $3 million for education is not at all adequate 
     <lb/>
     for the needs of such a sparsely populated country 
     <lb/>
     as ours, and, could our economy afford it, it might 
     <lb/>
     be double that amount. What of the future of the 
     <lb/>
     teaching profession? Are we agreed that the 
     <lb/>
     remuneration they receive is sufficient, and befits 
     <lb/>
     their high calling? Says the report, and I quote, 
     <lb/>
     "The median salary including augmentation and 
     <lb/>
     cost of living bonus is for 1945, $992." The 
     <lb/>
     average teacher actually receives today the 
     <lb/>
     modest sum of a little in excess of $82 per month 
     <lb/>
     for 12 months (it must not be mistakenly sup<lb break="no"/>posed that a teacher doesn't eat and spend some 
     <lb/>
     money in the holidays, which of course are 
     <lb/>
     without pay). Mr. Hollett spoke wisely when he 
     <lb/>
     affirmed that teachers' salaries are ridiculously 
     <lb/>
     low. I know of schools in this island with but one 
     <lb/>
     teacher, trying desperately to cope with the al<lb break="no"/>most insurmountable problem of having to teach 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
          
     all grades from Kindergarten to Junior Matricu<lb break="no"/>lation for the fabulous sum of $45 per month plus 
     <lb/>
     a small augmentation. Mr. Newell stressed 
     <lb/>
     yesterday that the cause of the high percentage of 
     <lb/>
     Ungraded teachers was mainly due to the great 
     <lb/>
     shortage in the profession. The real cause for this 
     <lb/>
     regrettable situation is obvious — can we expect 
     <lb/>
     our teachers to continue in the calling for such a 
     <lb/>
     ridiculously low scale of wages? Take up your 
     <lb/>
     daily paper tomorrow and you will read in the 
     <lb/>
     want ads — domestic servants wanted, $35 per 
     <lb/>
     month (that means plus board). Is it any wonder 
     <lb/>
     then that school-teachers seek other zones of 
     <lb/>
     employment? .... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Jackman One of the most important mat<lb break="no"/>ters, if not the most important, we have to deal 
     <lb/>
     with is education because it deals with human 
     <lb/>
     value. The boys and girls of today are the men 
     <lb/>
     and women of tomorrow. They constitute our 
     <lb/>
     greatest national asset. Our teachers are equally 
     <lb/>
     important. What are we doing to see that those 
     <lb/>
     teachers, whom we depend so much upon, are 
     <lb/>
     getting enough pay to live on in order to educate 
     <lb/>
     the children of the country? I would say that we 
     <lb/>
     are doing very little over this injustice. I know 
     <lb/>
     we, as a Convention, cannot do much because we 
     <lb/>
     have not got the authority but I think this Con<lb break="no"/>vention should at least try and call the attention 
     <lb/>
     of the people to this very important matter. The 
     <lb/>
     conditions under which so many of our teachers 
     <lb/>
     have to exist is scandalous. As Mr. Vincent has 
     <lb/>
     said, "Is it any wonder we have a shortage of 
     <lb/>
     teachers?" And he struck the nail on the head 
     <lb/>
     when he said it was because of small pay. I can 
     <lb/>
     give several examples of that. I know a chap at 
     <lb/>
     Bell Island who taught school for a number of 
     <lb/>
     years. He was single at the time and managed to 
     <lb/>
     get along, but eventually he got married and was 
     <lb/>
     compelled to leave the teaching profession and 
     <lb/>
     go down in the mines shovelling ore in order to 
     <lb/>
     feed, clothe and educate his family.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A balanced budget at the expense of human 
     <lb/>
     deprivation and suffering is not a balanced 
     <lb/>
     budget at all. If the government was to balance 
     <lb/>
     their budget at the expense of the teaching profes<lb break="no"/>sion, I don't want a balanced budget.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, I beg to move that the commit<lb break="no"/>tee of the whole place itself on record as being 
     <lb/>
     greatly dissatisifed with the present pay scale 
     <lb/>
     paid our teachers, particularly those in the lower 
     <lb/>
          
     <note xml:id="fn_03">The Commissron of Government instituted free and compulsory education in 1942.</note> 
   
            <pb n="166"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0166.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">166</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
          
     income group, as inadequate in view of the high 
     <lb/>
     cost of living, and that we feel that an immediate 
     <lb/>
     revision upward in the present basic salaries 
     <lb/>
     should be made, and we ask the Education Com<lb break="no"/>mittee to include this in their report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hillier I have read the Education Report 
     <lb/>
     through and it contains some very important in<lb break="no"/>formation. I think the report gives us an idea of 
     <lb/>
     what the expense of education will be in the 
     <lb/>
     future, also that it would be necessary to have a 
     <lb/>
     larger amount. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In speaking of education we have to go some<lb break="no"/>times beyond our immediate vicinity, to look 
     <lb/>
     abroad upon this country, and we will find there 
     <lb/>
     are many small communities containing small 
     <lb/>
     schools, and the boys and girls can never hope to 
     <lb/>
     rise beyond a moderate standard of education, 
     <lb/>
     because of the early age at which they are advised 
     <lb/>
     to leave school. To the few is extended the op<lb break="no"/>portunity to obtain an education. We are specially 
     <lb/>
     privileged in St. John's. In looking abroad again 
     <lb/>
     upon the outports there is a very large number of 
     <lb/>
     boys and girls whose parents have not the ways 
     <lb/>
     and means to send them to St. John's or else<lb break="no"/>where to get an education. But in some of these 
     <lb/>
     communities there is a lot of hidden talent. So in 
     <lb/>
    the large centers we must never lose sight of the 
     <lb/>many who have not our advantages... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Burry Much has been said about the need 
     <lb/>to raise teachers' salaries and give them a better 
     <lb/>opportunity to get a better education and training 
     <lb/>with which I agree heartily, and would like for 
     <lb/>the Education Department of the government to 
     <lb/>do all it can to interest the teachers in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. They will not be wasting money. Any 
     <lb/>money spent will be well spent in the interest of 
     <lb/>education, but we ought not to overlook the fact 
     <lb/>that the Commission of Government has made 
     <lb/>great strides to increase the earning power of our 
     <lb/>teachers, and while in the lower brackets it is 
     <lb/>rather low, and perhaps not too high in the higher 
     <lb/>brackets, the fact is that the average teacher today 
     <lb/>is getting much more than he or she used to get. 
     <lb/>When we make any suggestion or recommenda<lb break="no"/>tion to increase the salaries of teachers we ought 
     <lb/>to avoid using too harsh phrases such as 
     <lb/>"ridiculously low salaries"; because they are not 
     <lb/>so ridiculously low today... I want every member 
     <lb/>of the Convention to understand me properly. I 
     <lb/>
            
     
            <cb/>
          
     am not trying to discourage any effort to increase 
     <lb/>
     the salaries of teachers, but looking over this table 
     <lb/>
     I find that it refers to 1944, and there are only two 
     <lb/>
     teachers getting less than $300 a year, and 196 
     <lb/>
     teachers getting less than $500 or $600 a year. 
     <lb/>
     We all know that does not refer to the total 
     <lb/>
     amount that is paid to these teachers, because the 
     <lb/>
     cost of living bonus is not included, and the 
     <lb/>
     augmentation is not included. I am given to un<lb break="no"/>derstand that there is no graded teacher employed 
     <lb/>
     with an augmented salary of less than $660 for 
     <lb/>
     the school year. I don't know if the Committee 
     <lb/>
     will bear that out or not in their findings, but if 
     <lb/>
     that is so perhaps such words as "ridiculously low 
     <lb/>
     salaries" may not be used without bearing this in 
     <lb/>
     mind. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Any increase in salaries that can be given in 
     <lb/>
     the future ought to be given, but we ought to bear 
     <lb/>
     in mind that the salaries at the present time are 
     <lb/>
     not so very low compared with the past, and with 
     <lb/>
     what young people in St. John's and the outports 
     <lb/>
     earn in other callings. Perhaps that is not a fair 
     <lb/>
     comparison, but I am trying to avoid giving the 
     <lb/>
     public or the possible teachers the idea that they 
     <lb/>
     are not going to be paid at all no matter what 
     <lb/>
     grade they may get. We want to do all we can to 
     <lb/>
     get the young people to come into the teaching 
     <lb/>
     profession... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Starkes The report by the Education Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, is to my mind, not very encouraging to 
     <lb/>
     say the least.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let us look at the figures brought by our 
     <lb/>
     Education Committee. For the year l921-22 
     <lb/>
     when our expenditure was around $10 million we 
     <lb/>
     spent roughly $817,177, 8% of our total expen<lb break="no"/>diture<ref target="#fn_04">[1]</ref> ; in other words $24.35 per student. This 
     <lb/>
     was spent 25 years ago, and after 25 years of 
     <lb/>
     progress and advancement in education, this year 
     <lb/>
     1946-47, with an estimated expenditure of over 
     <lb/>
     $34 million, the Commission of Government es<lb break="no"/>timates spending around $3 1/2 million only, or 
     <lb/>
     10%.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Newell Mr. Chairman, before we go any 
     <lb/>
     further in this discussion of teachers' salaries, 
     <lb/>
     there are one or two things that I have to point 
     <lb/>
     out. One is that the figures given on page 7, 
     <lb/>
     contrary to the opinion expressed by the delegate 
     <lb/>
     from Labrador, do include the cost of living 
     <lb/>
     bonus... These are the average salaries up to 
     <lb/>
           

 <note xml:id="fn_04">1 In the original, Mr. Starkes gave the inaccurate figure of 12%, and based the rest of his speech on the as<lb break="no"/>sumption that the percentage of expenditure devoted to education had declined. </note>

            <pb n="167"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0167.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">167</fw>
          
     1944. I regret we did not read these tables yester<lb break="no"/>day all together, because some of these matters 
     <lb/>
     might have been straightened out as we went 
     <lb/>
     along. We are apt to pick out an item and over<lb break="no"/>look the real purpose for which these figures were 
     <lb/>
     given. I did not have, at the time of submitting 
     <lb/>
     these tables, the figures for 1945. The report of 
     <lb/>
    the Department of Education was delivered to me 
     <lb/>a few minutes ago, and, if you wish, I can give 
     <lb/>you some figures for 1945, which will make the 
     <lb/>position somewhat brighter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Page 7, paragraph 6. First of all there are no 
     <lb/>
    figures for June 30, 1946. They have not yet been 
     <lb/>compiled statistically.... While we have not any 
     <lb/>definite assurance from the department, it is prob<lb break="no"/>able that these teachers were only working for six 
     <lb/>months. Also in 1944 there were 31 teachers 
     <lb/>getting between $300 and $400. There were none 
     <lb/>so low as these in 1945. Also in 1944 there were 
     <lb/>some getting between $400 and $500, and there 
     <lb/>were none in 1945. In other words there were 273 
     <lb/>teachers getting less than $500, whereas in 1945 
     <lb/>there are none. That makes the situation quite 
     <lb/>different. It is regrettable that we did not have this 
     <lb/>report before... 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Bailey Mr. Chairman, no one in this world 
     <lb/>knows worse than myself the lack of an educa<lb break="no"/>tion. At 20 years of age I had to take copy books 
     <lb/>and learn to write, so I did not get much of a start 
     <lb/>in life. I am glad that we have this before the 
     <lb/>Convention and before the people, because it's 
     <lb/>the first chance I have had to learn about educa<lb break="no"/>tion in this country as it is. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     I have watched closely the statistics in dif<lb break="no"/>ferent countries where I have been, more par<lb break="no"/>ticularly in the United States, and I have come to 
     <lb/>
     the conclusion, not only in Newfoundland but in 
     <lb/>
     other parts, that teachers are the very poorest paid 
     <lb/>
     people in the world... I totally agree with this 
     <lb/>
     report in every way, and firmly believe that we 
     <lb/>
     cannot cut expenditure down, if anything it 
     <lb/>
     should be raised up. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am not in sympathy with the system of 
     <lb/>
     education in this country, especially in the out<lb break="no"/>ports. A lad in St. John's has got a chance, but 
     <lb/>
     under the system in the outports he has not. If we, 
     <lb/>
     along with two or three other spots in the world, 
     <lb/>
     have a different education system from the rest, 
     <lb/>
     surely all the world can't be wrong and we right? 
     <lb/>
     We have three denominational schools, in my 
     <lb/>home town today. One teacher has somewhere 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     between 40 and 50 children between the grades 
     <lb/>
     of four and eleven, and another has about 15 
     <lb/>
     between the grades of Kindergarten and eleven, 
     <lb/>
     and just alongside another teacher has a school of 
     <lb/>
     11 children. Consequently it is likely there won't 
     <lb/>
     be more than two or three children in that village 
     <lb/>
     that will make the grade. It is utterly impossible 
     <lb/>
     for a teacher to get through because he has too 
     <lb/>
     much on his hands. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I firmly believe our system of education is 
     <lb/>
     costing us at least half a million dollars too much. 
     <lb/>
     Probably our people are back where some 
     <lb/>
     countries were 150 years ago. It is not the fault of 
     <lb/>
     the country, there has been a real earnest en<lb break="no"/>deavour to adjust to more modern ideas. I think 
     <lb/>
     this should be stressed strongly, that we should 
     <lb/>
     get together and cut out the cost of the overhead, 
     <lb/>
     and if we can't increase the money, I believe it is 
     <lb/>
     up to every Newfoundlander to see that this sys<lb break="no"/>tem is changed as quickly as possible, so that our 
     <lb/>
     children can go out into the world equipped for 
     <lb/>
     their jobs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I know a man who left one of our outports a 
     <lb/>
     number of years ago, and although he started 
     <lb/>
     from scratch, by the time he was 35 years old he 
     <lb/>
     was head of one of the largest construction firms 
     <lb/>
     in the United States. I know what can be done, 
     <lb/>
     and I know what is being done in various parts of 
     <lb/>
     the world. I believe if we put in the Scotch system 
     <lb/>
     of education it would not be so expensive. There 
     <lb/>
     is nobody today that can face the world better 
     <lb/>
     than the Scotchman. If you go into a shipyard in 
     <lb/>
     the States every second man there is Mac, the 
     <lb/>
     architect, the manager, the office worker, be<lb break="no"/>cause he is the best equipped for every job. In the 
     <lb/>
     far-flung parts of the Empire, everywhere you 
     <lb/>
     will find the Scot. If he comes from the Hebrides 
     <lb/>
     or wherever he comes from, it is all the same, they 
     <lb/>
     are all educated and can take their university 
     <lb/>
     course, and wherever he goes he can carry on his 
     <lb/>
     education and pick up everything necessary. That 
     <lb/>
     is why Scotland today has the smallest percent<lb break="no"/>age of illiteracy in the world. I believe something 
     <lb/>
     can be done in this country; after all, it is what 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland desires today. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I have a great deal of admira<lb break="no"/>tion for the gentlemen in the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Education - for their enthusiasm on the job, for 
     <lb/>
     the extent to which they have successfully 
     <lb/>
     hounded more and more money out of the Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government, I give them credit for it. 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="168"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0168.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">168</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
           
     I think it is only fair for someone to say a word 
     <lb/>
     also for the education authorities before Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government came here at all. You will 
     <lb/>
     notice that the Education Committee's report 
     <lb/>
     drove a peg in, and dealt with the period from that 
     <lb/>
     peg. That peg was 1921-22, which was around 
     <lb/>
     the time that the Department of Education was 
     <lb/>
     set up. That department was set up with Dr. Ar<lb break="no"/>thur Barnes as the first Minister of Education. 
     <lb/>
     Dr. Barnes is still living at Bay Roberts, extreme<lb break="no"/>ly active mentally and physically, extremely in<lb break="no"/>terested still in education and in the affairs of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. He is one of the greatest New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders we have ever had in the field of 
     <lb/>
     education.... I do not remember the year, but I do 
     <lb/>
     remember the time when the total expenditure of 
     <lb/>
     public money on education in Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     reached the shocking amount of half a million 
     <lb/>
     dollars, considered by the education people in 
     <lb/>
     this country to be a magnificent achievement. 
     <lb/>
     Beginning with the creation of the department the 
     <lb/>
     total amount of public money earmarked for 
     <lb/>
     education began to rise steadily and almost un<lb break="no"/>brokenly, up to the very moment when the impact 
     <lb/>
     of the world depression was felt. So for that 
     <lb/>
     reason, the Education Committee wisely and fair<lb break="no"/>ly made its study of the progress of education, at 
     <lb/>
     least materially, over the priod 1921-22 up to the 
     <lb/>
     present time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Turn to page 3 of that report and you will 
     <lb/>
     notice that total expenditure rose steadily from 
     <lb/>
     1921-22 year by year until it reached $1 million 
     <lb/>
     in 1930-31.... This increase in expenditure, this 
     <lb/>
     growth in the education plant, is nothing spec<lb break="no"/>tacular; it is not a thing that began with Commis<lb break="no"/>sion of Government. This process of spending a 
     <lb/>
     larger proportion of money on it began before 
     <lb/>
     1921-22; it has been a process practically con<lb break="no"/>tinuous. We ought to give credit to the pioneers 
     <lb/>
     in education and especially to Dr. Barnes and Dr. 
     <lb/>
     Burke, who has just retired; also to Dr. Blackall 
     <lb/>
     and Dr. Curtis who worked and sacrificed to 
     <lb/>
     build education into what it is today. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett It is refreshing to hear Mr. Small<lb break="no"/>wood referring to the good men no longer in the 
     <lb/>
     limelight; I am sure we have had some grand men 
     <lb/>
     in the past. There is one thing in Mr. Small<lb break="no"/>wood's remarks referring to the expenditures in 
     <lb/>
     1921-22 — I do not know if I heard him correctly 
     <lb/>
     — if you look at the percentage it was 8.1 in 
     <lb/>
     1921-22, and in 1946 10.41. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I am aware of the percentages 
     <lb/>
     in the third column; but 8.1% of the total revenue 
     <lb/>
     is very much more money than 10.41% of the 
     <lb/>
     revenue of 1946-47. That is the point I am 
     <lb/>
     making. Relatively it is much more money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Starkes In 1921 when the revenue was 
     <lb/>
     $10.5 million our education grant was $817,000, 
     <lb/>
     and now the Commission of Government with a 
     <lb/>
     revenue of $34 million are spending 2% less on 
     <lb/>
     education than what was spent 25 years ago: 12% 
     <lb/>
     of our expenditure went on education. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett So far as I can see the percentage 
     <lb/>
     being spent now is greater. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Newell Assuming that the expenditure was 
     <lb/>
     $10 million 25 years ago, the percentage spent 
     <lb/>
     was 8.1%, I make it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman I think it better to defer this 
     <lb/>
     point, as Mr. Figary, who possesses one of the 
     <lb/>
     few books with accurate figures, is absent from 
     <lb/>
     the session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Harrington I am not interested in any ex<lb break="no"/>ercises of arithmetic as I think it is a waste of time. 
     <lb/>
     I did not propose to say anything on this report as 
     <lb/>
     I was a member of the committee.... Neverthe<lb break="no"/>less, there was one point raised by two speakers 
     <lb/>
     and that was the system of education. It was 
     <lb/>
     agreed at the outset that the current system was 
     <lb/>
     the most desirable, and I would like to go on 
     <lb/>
     record as being unalterably in favour of the 
     <lb/>
     present system because it is the best that could be 
     <lb/>
     devised. The history of this country shows that 
     <lb/>
     before there was any attempt made by any 
     <lb/>
     governmental authorities, the churches stepped 
     <lb/>
     into the breach and gave us what educational 
     <lb/>
     facilities we have at the present time, and I am 
     <lb/>
     quite convinced that, under conditions as they are 
     <lb/>
     in the country today, the present system is the best 
     <lb/>
     under the circumstances, and it does not come 
     <lb/>
     within our province as a Convention to interfere 
     <lb/>
     and supplant it by any means. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett With regard to Mr. Jackman's 
     <lb/>
     resolution, at the outset let me say that I am all in 
     <lb/>
     favour of giving teachers a living wage; but you 
     <lb/>
     will remember this Convention only has power 
     <lb/>
     to recommend, but not to demand. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Jackman I made the motion in good faith, 
     <lb/>
     and I thought there might be a recommendation 
     <lb/>
     go to the government on behalf of the teachers; 
     <lb/>
     but I would not urge to have it incorporated in the 
     <lb/>
     report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Miller I oppose Mr. Jackman's motion for 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="169"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0169.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">169</fw>
           
     two reasons. First because it is beyond the power 
     <lb/>
     of the Convention to approach the issue in such 
     <lb/>
     a manner; and secondly because the motion 
     <lb/>
     depends entirely upon statistics instead of a com<lb break="no"/>plete survey of the background. The matter of 
     <lb/>
     raising the scale of wages should be left to the 
     <lb/>
     authorities concerned. I would advise the Con<lb break="no"/>vention to be cautious unless it was equipped 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     with complete knowledge. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Jackman I realise how limited our author<lb break="no"/>ity is. The issue is purely a moral one and it is 
     <lb/>
     only asking that such important persons as school 
     <lb/>
     teachers be paid enough to live on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman The motion is that the Report of 
     <lb/>
     the Education Committee be received. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head>
     Report of the Forestry Committee:<ref target="#fn_x2">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Mr. Chairman, this report has been 
     <lb/>
     in the hands of delegates for about ten days and I 
     <lb/>
     would like to go ahead with it now and get it 
     <lb/>
     cleaned up. Monday<ref target="#fn_05">[2]</ref> is a holiday and there will 
     <lb/>
     be no sitting, and if the members of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion want we can sit tonight in order to get this 
     <lb/>
     thing finished as soon as possible. Whatever 
     <lb/>
     members ask for I will accommodate them to the 
     <lb/>
     best of my ability. The report covers the whole 
     <lb/>
     forestry situation, including the pulp and paper 
     <lb/>
     industry and saw mills, The committee took an 
     <lb/>
     overall picture of the whole country to try and 
     <lb/>
     bring out as accurately as we could the caming 
     <lb/>
     power we get from paper, pulp and local lumber<lb break="no"/>ing industries in Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Will you give us some idea of 
     <lb/>
     the basis of the computation?<ref target="#fn_06">[3]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin There's around 50 million feet of 
     <lb/>
     lumber cut annually by our own sawmills, and we 
     <lb/>
     had gentlemen on the Committee who had a good 
     <lb/>
     idea of the price of lumber, sawing, loading, etc. 
     <lb/>
     They figure about $35 a thousand, and lumber is 
     <lb/>
     selling today in St. John's for about $65. By the 
     <lb/>
     time you pay freight, etc., the man who actually 
     <lb/>
     produces it, if he had to do all these things, cut, 
     <lb/>
     saw, etc., would make $35 a thousand on it. That 
     <lb/>
     is how we estimated the earning power of the men 
     <lb/>
     engaged in cutting, sawing, etc. That is ap<lb break="no"/>proximate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Mr. Chairman, if you will turn 
     <lb/>
     to page 11, sec. 7.... Would you give us the basis 
     <lb/>
     of that belief? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>Mr. Cashin If you will notice the papers, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly here in St. John's, it is announced every<lb/>week. Building here is increasing constantly, and<lb/>they are going to require more lumber, and there<lb break="no"/>fore it will require more work in cutting, sawing,<lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     manufacturing, and we figure that therefore the 
     <lb/>
     earning power will increase. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins Mr. Chairman, I wonder if Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin would pass a comment on this. I notice in 
     <lb/>
     today's issue of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Evening Telegram</hi> that the 
     <lb/>
     editor comments on the report and says it is very 
     <lb/>
     fine in every way, he says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     In one important particular, however, the 
     <lb/>
     figures quoted are at least open to question. 
     <lb/>
     It states that there are in Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     22,000 square miles of timberland under 
     <lb/>
     leases. Out of the total area of 42,000 square 
     <lb/>
     miles, that would represent fifty percent or, 
     <lb/>
     excluding the area comprised of lakes and 
     <lb/>
     rivers, given in the report as one third of the 
     <lb/>
     total, seventy-five per cent of the whole land 
     <lb/>
     area in the island. So far as this paper is 
     <lb/>
     aware, there are no survey figures available 
     <lb/>
     to show what proportion of Newfoundland's 
     <lb/>
     surface is timberland, but if the surveys made 
     <lb/>
     in Canada to determine the extent of its 
     <lb/>
     forested lands may be regarded as a criterion, 
     <lb/>
     either the forest growth in this country is 
     <lb/>
     phenomenal or the figures are fantastic. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     I don't know if there is any basis for that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin In connection with that, I think it is 
     <lb/>
     agreed that one third of the island is composed of 
     <lb/>
     lakes, rivers, etc., and a lot of these are included 
     <lb/>
     in the leased land, and we got that information 
     <lb/>
     from the Department of Natural Resources. They 
     <lb/>
     gave us an idea, as closely as they could, on the 
     <lb/>
     amount of timber on these lands, It is figured 
     <lb/>
     today that the two pulp and paper companies, 
     <lb/>
     who control practically all the leasehold land in 
     <lb/>
     the country, have roughly between 45 and 50 
     <lb/>
     million cords of wood in these areas. The two 
     <lb/>
     companies have between them around 20,000 
     <lb/>
            
<note xml:id="fn_x2">1 Volume II:56. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

<note xml:id="fn_05">2 November 11.</note>
<note xml:id="fn_06">3 Of the earning power of sawmill operations.</note>
           


            <pb n="170"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0170.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">170</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
           
     square miles of timber land, which includes 
     <lb/>
     lakes, Grand Lake, Gander Lake, etc. They are 
     <lb/>
     paying rental on water as well as on land, I am 
     <lb/>
     pretty certain. I will let you know that the next 
     <lb/>
     day we meet. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood On Page 8, under "Birch," 
     <lb/>
     the last paragraph.... What does that mean? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Referring to the pulp and paper 
     <lb/>
     companies, there is considerable bitch on their 
     <lb/>
     property. They will not allow us to go in and cut 
     <lb/>
     where they are cutting at the present time, but I 
     <lb/>
     understand that they are only too delighted for the 
     <lb/>
     people to go in and cut on what has already been 
     <lb/>
     cut over. By "material assistance" I don't mean 
     <lb/>
     that the government should finance that venture, 
     <lb/>
     but they should encourage it by tariffs, etc. We 
     <lb/>
     have found out that there are markets in Canada, 
     <lb/>
     as well as in the United States, for birch. It is a 
     <lb/>
     wood which is very difficult to handle because it 
     <lb/>
     is very heavy, but at the same time the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity is there for men making furniture, veneer, 
     <lb/>
     etc., and I understand that quite an industry can 
     <lb/>
     be developed in that. I think Messrs. Wm. Dawe 
     <lb/>
     and Sons did export some of that over 20 years 
     <lb/>
     ago. I did not mean that it should be financed, but 
     <lb/>
     that it should be encouraged. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins On page 2, Major Cashin, of the 
     <lb/>
     report, you say there is $360,000 collected in 
     <lb/>
     revenue at Grand Falls. Is it suggested that that is 
     <lb/>
     from the wood working? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Prior to the inauguration of the 
     <lb/>
     paper mill at Grand Falls there was no revenue 
     <lb/>
     there. We attributed that to the fact that when 
     <lb/>
     Grand Falls was built up it brought in revenue in 
     <lb/>
     other ways. Buchans has a customs depart<lb break="no"/>ment in its own place. If you will go on further 
     <lb/>
     there was over $1 million collected in Corner 
     <lb/>
     Brook, and no doubt the herring fishery con<lb break="no"/>tributes a lot in the way of revenue, and if the pulp 
     <lb/>
     and paper industry had never been started we 
     <lb/>
     would have had considerable revenue.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Fudge In connection with this matter of 
     <lb/>
     birch, I may add that early last year I was called 
     <lb/>
     to the office of Bowaters<ref target="#fn_07">[1]</ref> and Mr. Shaw in<lb break="no"/>formed me that there was an outside concern 
     <lb/>
     interested in the birch, and that they were 
     <lb/>
     prepared to erect a mill or a factory which would 
     <lb/>
     employ some 150 men. We went on further to 
     <lb/>
     discuss the wage rate and it was all agreed upon. 
     <lb/>
     l am not in a position to state to this Convention 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     just what will happen, but when we were prepar<lb break="no"/>ing this report we took that as a possibility. I 
     <lb/>
     believe that there will soon be an industry 
     <lb/>
     opened, an American outfit, and that they will 
     <lb/>
     employ about 150 men in their factory there. The 
     <lb/>
     birch will be made into veneer I believe. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Dawe I believe there is a market for birch. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood On page 8 again, Mr. Chair<lb break="no"/>man, under the heading of "Labrador", in the 
     <lb/>
     second paragraph, there has been no reliable sur<lb break="no"/>vey made of the amount of timber on Labrador 
     <lb/>
     and the opinions vary. What estimates, or whose? 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Cashin I have seen various surveys of 
     <lb/>Labrador areas, some were not so good, others 
     <lb/>fairly good. I happened to see an aerial survey of 
     <lb/>Labrador some years ago, but I am not able to 
     <lb/>express an opinion as to the amount of wood in 
     <lb/>the various areas, but some people say 100 mil<lb break="no"/>lion cords. Other people say 50 million cords. 
     <lb/>There was a survey in Hamilton Inlet some years 
     <lb/>ago, and the gentleman in charge down there 
     <lb/>figured 50 million cords. I have seen the survey 
     <lb/>of the Sandwich Bay area and Eagle River on 
     <lb/>properties owned by the McMaster interests of 
     <lb/>Toronto, and these areas have over 10 million 
     <lb/>cords of wood. I know that the Hamilton River is 
     <lb/>heavily timbered. I would say that in those 300 
     <lb/>sq. miles there is some 1.5 to 2 million cords of 
     <lb/>wood. There is also the Double Mer property. A 
     <lb/>survey was made some 30 years ago and shows 
     <lb/>it carries 6 million cords of wood. I believe there 
     <lb/>is only 2 million on it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Adding them all together, Mr. Smallwood, I 
     <lb/>
    have no hesitation in saying there is at least 50 
     <lb/>million cords on it. I don't think there is 100 
     <lb/>million cords but 1 hope so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Hollett I might say that I read this report 
     <lb/>through when it was presented and remember I 
     <lb/>noticed there was a noticeable lack of statistics 
     <lb/>with regard to the earnings of our people general<lb break="no"/>ly from forestry, and of the amounts of revenue 
     <lb/>collected by the government down through the 
     <lb/>years. It would have been wiser if the Forestry 
     <lb/>Committee had brought in some statistics over a 
     <lb/>period of years since they would give us a broader 
     <lb/>idea of the value of our forests and our financial 
     <lb/>and economic set-up, and also the possibilities 
     <lb/>for the future. I can find nothing in this report 
     <lb/>which shows me those figures. I wonder if Major 
     <lb/>Cashin can tell me why. 
     <lb/></p>
          
     <note xml:id="fn_07">1 Bowaters operated the pulp and paper mill at Corner Brook (1938).</note> 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="171"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0171.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">171</fw>
            <p>
     Mr. Cashin In reply to Mr. Hollett, the govern<lb break="no"/>ment gets around $18 - 20,000 a year from those 
     <lb/>
     sources. There are estimates of the earning power 
     <lb/>
     of the pulp and paper mills, sawmills, and the 
     <lb/>
     cutting of pit props, etc. We want to get an idea 
     <lb/>
     of the forecast for the future. I refer particularly 
     <lb/>
     to the pulp and paper industry because it has been 
     <lb/>
     publicly announced in recent months, that Grand 
     <lb/>
     Falls is expanding, and also Corner Brook, and it 
     <lb/>
     is fairly easy, to figure out the earning power 
     <lb/>
     from these two sources. The thing was to get the 
     <lb/>
     earning power accruing to the country at the 
     <lb/>
     present time for wood sawn locally, and build up 
     <lb/>
     the total earning power of the people annually for 
     <lb/>
     all forest work. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I know there are plenty of loopholes in this 
     <lb/>
     report, and we are only too pleased to have any 
     <lb/>
     further information because I don't believe any 
     <lb/>
     report coming in here will be perfect. But it is the 
     <lb/>
     best we can do, and we can't all be on the same 
     <lb/>
     committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett I would like to know the value in 
     <lb/>
     wages paid over the years, of our forests, and in 
     <lb/>
     revenues collected by the government as a result 
     <lb/>
     of forest operations. If we had that over a period 
     <lb/>
     of years, from 1921 down to the present time, it 
     <lb/>
     would give us a clear picture to show just what 
     <lb/>
     advance has been made and what hope there is 
     <lb/>
     for the future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin In connection with revenues that 
     <lb/>
     might have been collected in the past 20 years, 
     <lb/>
     the Customs can't give it to you; it's impossible 
     <lb/>
     and we could only make a guess at it.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood The point raised by Mr. Hol<lb break="no"/>lett. The AND Company could tell you for the 
     <lb/>
     period beginning with their first year almost to 
     <lb/>
     date what they expended year by year.... 
     <lb/>
     Bowaters can do the same thing from the begin<lb break="no"/>ning.... There seems here to be a number of 
     <lb/>
     estimates and statements made without any sup<lb break="no"/>porting evidence whatever. The supporting 
     <lb/>
     evidence undoubtedly is there, but we are asked 
     <lb/>
     to accept it on faith, without the production by the 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the evidence on which they based 
     <lb/>
     those conclusions. You take on page 10 again, 
     <lb/>
     section 3 and 4. I am beginning now to guess that 
     <lb/>
     it has to do with the new machinery going in. 
     <lb/>
     Does it also refer to wage earning employees, or 
     <lb/>
     does it include them and woods operators? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Everything. In the thirties when the 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     newsprint industry was in the doldrums I was told 
     <lb/>
     they figured that to produce a ton of newsprint it 
     <lb/>
     cost about $25 in labour. Well you all know that 
     <lb/>
     the cost has gone sky high since that. That's why 
     <lb/>
     we based our figures that way, it costs roughly 
     <lb/>
     $25 a ton. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Another thing to which I would 
     <lb/>
     like to draw your attention, a matter of vital 
     <lb/>
     importance. You refer here to the three mile 
     <lb/>
     limit,<ref target="#fn_08">[1]</ref> and you say that large parts of it have been 
     <lb/>
     denuded, which is largely the case. I am especial<lb break="no"/>ly familiar with it in parts of Bonavista Centre, 
     <lb/>
     which overflows into Bonavista North, from 
     <lb/>
     Hare Bay up to Gambo, where there is no wood 
     <lb/>
     left, not a scrap. The people down there have sent 
     <lb/>
     a petition to the government, drawing their atten<lb break="no"/>tion to the fact that at the present time the three 
     <lb/>
     mile limit is cut out completely, and immediately 
     <lb/>
     adjacent are paper areas. I rather expected the 
     <lb/>
     report to contain a reference to the serious situa<lb break="no"/>tion that had arisen in many parts of the country 
     <lb/>
     where the three mile limit had been almost com<lb break="no"/>pletely cut out. The only timber remaining is that 
     <lb/>
     owned by the paper companies, and small saw<lb break="no"/>mill men have got to go in on the companies' land 
     <lb/>
     to cut, and pay royalties for so doing. Many such 
     <lb/>
     cases have happened in Bonavista Centre and 
     <lb/>
     Bonavista North. I know also of one or two cases 
     <lb/>
     where the government actually swapped Crown 
     <lb/>
     land limits for the convenience of Bowaters. I 
     <lb/>
     have in my possession a number of letters from 
     <lb/>
     Dark Cove and contiguous places around Gambo 
     <lb/>
     dealing with this same matter. It seems that the 
     <lb/>
     government did the swapping to provide the 
     <lb/>
     grounds for the statement that the output for local 
     <lb/>
     sawmills would increase. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin The increase is to be expected as a 
     <lb/>
     result of the increase in building and construc<lb break="no"/>tion. At present there are only 5 million cords of 
     <lb/>
     wood left on Crown lands in the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Burry The conditions obtaining in New<lb break="no"/>foundland, as pointed out by Mr. Smallwood, to 
     <lb/>
     the detriment of small mill owners and fishermen, 
     <lb/>
     have not become as bad in Labrador as yet, but it 
     <lb/>
     is becoming so, and where the Labrador Develop<lb break="no"/>ment Co. is operating the fishermen tell me that 
     <lb/>
     they have to go far afield in order to procure 
     <lb/>
     timber with which to build boats and stages. I 
     <lb/>
     think this is worth considering seriously now, 
     <lb/>
     before it gets too far. Besides it is one of the ways 
     <lb/>
      
            
          
      <note xml:id="fn_08">1 Forest within three miles of the coast was reserved for use by residents.</note> 
     
            <pb n="172"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0172.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">172</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
           
     to conserve Labrador. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins I wonder if the committee would 
     <lb/>
     consider rising now and sitting tonight, and then 
     <lb/>
     probably tomorrow we will be able to finish this 
     <lb/>
     report.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The committee of the whole adjourned until 8 
     <lb/>
     pm]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Vardy Mr. Chairman, as there were several 
     <lb/>
     complaints about the Education Report when it 
     <lb/>
     was discussed in committee, I suggest that the 
     <lb/>
     Forestry Report be read section by section so that 
     <lb/>
     the contents can be better digested. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Asst. Secretary read from the report] </hi>
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood With regard to paragraph 1, I 
     <lb/>
     wonder if Mr. Cashin could tell us the number of 
     <lb/>
     square miles of timber held? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin 22,000 square miles of timber area 
     <lb/>
     in the whole country by the two companies, in<lb break="no"/>cluding the water surface within those areas. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood What does that mean and how 
     <lb/>did they get their timber areas? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Most of it was held on 99-year 
     <lb/>
     leases and could not well be changed while the 
     <lb/>
     leases are in existence, but many of the leases 
     <lb/>
     came into possession of the Grand Falls Com<lb break="no"/>pany<ref target="#fn_09">[1]</ref> through purchase either from the Reid 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland Company, under the railway deal 
     <lb/>
     of 1898<ref target="#fn_10">[2]</ref>, or from private individuals, including 
     <lb/>
     Mr. H.J. Crowe, who had several pieces of tim<lb break="no"/>ber lands in those areas and sold his rights to the 
     <lb/>
     Grand Falls people after the commencement of 
     <lb/>
     the development in 1905. The rate of $2 per square 
     <lb/>
     mile was the annual fee paid for the fee simple 
     <lb/>
     areas and this was part of the terms of the leases. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Smallwood It is stated in the 4th paragraph 
     <lb/>of the report that timber areas are licensed for 99 
     <lb/>years. Is that statutory and unchangeable? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin It is statutory. Probably you might 
     <lb/>
     remember in 1931 action was taken because 
     <lb/>
     some people had not complied with the terms of 
     <lb/>
     their leases and they lost out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood How does that compare with 
     <lb/>
     the Crown land leases in Canada and in the 
     <lb/>
     United States? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Take the province of Quebec for 
     <lb/>
     example, the Crown gets $1.65 per cord 
     <lb/>
     stumpage. There have been cases in Quebec 
     <lb/>
     where the government sold outright to big com<lb break="no"/><cb/>panies at high prices, but generally the charge is 
     <lb/>
     $1.65 per cord stumpage or $1.65 per square foot 
     <lb/>
     of forest. A good square mile of timber land 
     <lb/>
     should have 3,500 cords of wood for each square 
     <lb/>
     mile of forest. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood Would Mr. Cashin be able to 
     <lb/>
     say definitely if that is unchangeable? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin My opinion is yes, but I have not 
     <lb/>
     checked on it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Crosbie What is the natural reafforestation 
     <lb/>
     per year in Newfoundland? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Grand Falls has been operating for 
     <lb/>
     over 40 years and has not been recut since. It is 
     <lb/>
     generally known in Canada to be 60 years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Crosbie I understand that 3% of the total 
     <lb/>
     growth is the figure roughly estimated for <choice><sic>reaf<lb break="no"/>forestation</sic><corr>reforestation</corr></choice> in Newfoundland. If that is so, there 
     <lb/>
     must be a million cords of wood dying on its feet. 
     <lb/>
   
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Cashin We discussed that matter at our 
     <lb/>meetings, and decided that if the natural regrowth 
     <lb/>is about 50 years, something should be done in 
     <lb/>order to guard against possible denudation of 
     <lb/>timber resources. Whilst we were getting infor<lb break="no"/>mation about this son of thing, we also learned 
     <lb/>what was being done to protect the forests from 
     <lb/>fires. The railway is spending $500,000 to con<lb break="no"/>vert coal burning locomotives into oil burners to 
     <lb/>prevent bush fires. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Ashbourne I notice that there is around 
     <lb/>
     $50,000 paid for granted property in rentals, and 
     <lb/>
     I was wondering if any of that amount is included 
     <lb/>
     for Labrador. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin I understand there are 30,000 miles 
     <lb/>
     under lease on Labrador, so that the total income 
     <lb/>
     from rentals there would be $20,000, and 
     <lb/>
     $30,000 from Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Harrington What we the paper companies 
     <lb/>
     actually paying for what they are getting? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin The government had no survey 
     <lb/>
     records of timber land, and information regarding 
     <lb/>
     figures could only be obtained from the com<lb break="no"/>panies concerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Higgins drew my attention to an editorial 
     <lb/>
     in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Evening Telegram</hi> this evening which 
     <lb/>
     questioned the report's statement of the timber 
     <lb/>
     owned by the AND Company. But if you take 
     <lb/>
     30% off for wastage you will find a different 
     <lb/>
     story. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
           
     <note xml:id="fn_09">1 Anglo-Newfoundland Development Company (AND). </note>
     <note xml:id="fn_10">2 The Reid Newfoundland Company received land entitlements under contracts signed with the New<lb break="no"/>foundland government in 1893, 1898 and 1901 for the operation of the railway.</note>

            <pb n="173"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0173.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">173</fw>
            <p>
     Mr. McCarthy Is there any pulpwood cut 
     <lb/>
     within the three mile limit? And is it being used 
     <lb/>
     locally? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Yes, within the past three years. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Burry I would like to know if there is any 
     <lb/>regulation governing the size of the stump 
     <lb/>remaining after a tree is cut. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin Yes, there is a regulation of a cer<lb break="no"/>tain specified size, but I cannot explain it in detail. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Fudge In all Bowaters' camps they have a 
     <lb/>
     height posted up and I think that the stumpage is 
     <lb/>
     not to exceed 12 inches. But I think small con<lb break="no"/>tractors cut everything in their way, regardless of 
     <lb/>
     size. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Smallwood I wonder if the production of 
     <lb/>
     cellulose is contemplated by the AND Company, 
     <lb/>
     as I know they had it under consideration in years 
     <lb/>
     past. I have here the wages and figures given by 
     <lb/>
     the AND Company showing that from 1907 to 
     <lb/>
     1940 the expenditure in wages and salaries in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland was $76 million; local purchases 
     <lb/>
     $14 million; railway freights $4¹/₂ million and so 
     <lb/>
     forth. Now I happen to know that that company 
     <lb/>
     has been giving these figures year by year from 
     <lb/>
     the beginning and they could give them up to the 
     <lb/>
     present year. The same thing applies with 
     <lb/>
     Bowaters at present. Their figures under wages 
     <lb/>
     and salaries and under other headings for the 
     <lb/>
     years 1923 to 1940 amounted to $86 million, as 
     <lb/>
     compared with $105 million by the AND Com<lb break="no"/>pany in expenditure from 1907 to 1940. Would 
     <lb/>
     the convenor of this committee undertake to get 
     <lb/>
     these figures up to the present? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin When we were preparing this report 
     <lb/>
     we had to be guided by our terms of reference, 
     <lb/>
     and were concerned with getting a picture of the 
     <lb/>
     economic and financial position of the country. I 
     <lb/>
     have no doubt but that the figures asked for will 
     <lb/>
     be made available for us by the companies con<lb break="no"/>cerned, although I do not think they have any 
     <lb/>
     great bearing on the country.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett I think it is most important and 
     <lb/>
     desirable that we have all the statistical informa<lb break="no"/>tion possible before us to aid us in our work. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Cashin Would not the figures in the Chad<lb break="no"/>wick-Jones report be of some assistance? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett I would rather not rely on that for 
     <lb/>
     reference, particularly dealing with Grand Falls 
     <lb/>
     where I have lived for some time. I would like to 
     <lb/>
     know with some degree of definiteness the num<lb break="no"/><cb/>ber of employees the AND Company have; the 
     <lb/>
     wages paid; the amount for local purchases and 
     <lb/>
     the amount of duty paid, so that we can see what 
     <lb/>
     value that company is to the country and to the 
     <lb/>
     revenue. Another desirable thing to know is if 
     <lb/>
     that company hopes to make anything else be<lb break="no"/>sides paper during their term in this country. In 
     <lb/>
     other countries such companies are making other 
     <lb/>
     wood products. If the AND Company or Bowaters 
     <lb/>
     cannot do that, let us get other companies to 
     <lb/>
     operate here and let us get the best we can out of 
     <lb/>
     the industry. However, 1 do think that if the 
     <lb/>
     Committee had an interview with the AND Com<lb break="no"/>pany more necessary information would be 
     <lb/>
     forthcoming to work on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin We would undertake to do that and 
     <lb/>
     have the information obtained embodied in a 
     <lb/>
     supplementary report, which it is proposed to 
     <lb/>
     bring in. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[There followed a discussion on how the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion might obtain additional information on the<lb/>newsprint industry. The section on reafforesta<lb break="no"/>tion was discussed briefly.]</hi><lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Mr. Cashin We were fortunate in having as 
     <lb/>
     convenor of the Committee, Mr. Fudge, who is 
     <lb/>
     connected with the union on the west coast and I 
     <lb/>
     would suggest that Mr. Fudge would reply to 
     <lb/>
     anything in connection with the labour situation 
     <lb/>
     of the pulp and paper industry. Mr. Brown, who 
     <lb/>
     is unfortunately ill, was also a member of the 
     <lb/>
     Committee and he was also connected with the 
     <lb/>
     labour unions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Fudge "It is a well-known fact that during 
     <lb/>
     depression years wages paid our woodsmen and 
     <lb/>
     other employees throughout this particular in<lb break="no"/>dustry were little better than sufficient to keep 
     <lb/>
     body and soul together." That is correct. in 1937 
     <lb/>
     when I came into the union which I represent,<ref target="#fn_11">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     the wages paid for a 10 hour day were $1.60; and 
     <lb/>
     the cutting of wood by contract was from 90 cents 
     <lb/>
     to not exceeding $1.50 per cord. The wages in 
     <lb/>
     1945-46 were $5.30 a day for a 10 hour day; 
     <lb/>
     cutters $3.60 per cord. All other rates were jacked 
     <lb/>
     up in proportion. If I remember, the board rate 
     <lb/>
     was 75 cents per day, and out of $1.60 you have 
     <lb/>
     some idea of what was left. Today they get $5.30 
     <lb/>
     and the board rate is 80 cents per day. I would 
     <lb/>
     like to say that the agreement which exists be<lb break="no"/>tween the union and the paper companies auto<lb break="no"/>matically dies on April 10, 1947; whereupon a 
     <lb/>
           
   
            
     <note xml:id="fn_11">1 The Newfoundland Labourers' Union.</note> 
    
            <pb n="174"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-11-07_Page_0174.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">174</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">November 1946</fw>
            

     new wage agreement will, I hope, be made up and 
     <lb/>
     we are looking forward to a further increase. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Hollett Can you give us the approximate 
     <lb/>earnings of woodcutters during the past season? 
     <lb/>I know they varied considerably, depending on 
     <lb/>the ability of the woodcutters. Could you give us 
     <lb/>the approximate figure? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Fudge I am speaking of the Bowater opera<lb break="no"/>tions. We find that the average cut per man is 
     <lb/>
     1 1/2 cords; he is paid not less than $3.86 on an 
     <lb/>
     average. You will find the average has increased, 
     <lb/>
     and the reason is because the men have better 
     <lb/>
     accommodations and better food and are there<lb break="no"/>fore better able to do a day's work. The average 
     <lb/>
     days' work in the woods per month is around 23 
     <lb/>
     working days. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Ballam The figures quoted here are 
     <lb/>
     average. I think the earnings of many men are 
     <lb/>
     much higher. You will always find that there are 
     <lb/>
     some who work better than others. They can clear 
     <lb/>
     $5 a day less one cent, that is the general overall 
     <lb/>
     average. There are fellows who have a chance of 
     <lb/>
     making $10 or $12 a day. There are fellows who 
     <lb/>
     make that average for months on end. They are 
     <lb/>
     extra good cutters. On a general average they 
     <lb/>
     clear $5 a day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Fudge I do not want to offend my friend, 
     <lb/>
     but I do not think that is correct. A logger does 
     <lb/>
     not clear $12 a day on an average. There are 
     <lb/>
     deductions for board and medical fees. They have 
     <lb/>
     to buy blankets and shirts. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett While we are on this particular 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     paragraph I rise to pay tribute to the work being 
     <lb/>
     done by the Woods Labour Board in connection 
     <lb/>
     with wages in the woods. If it had not been for 
     <lb/>
     that board and for the chairman<ref target="#fn_12">[1]</ref> who looked after 
     <lb/>
     their interests, we would have had considerable 
     <lb/>
     trouble in Newfoundland during war years.... In 
     <lb/>
     Grand Falls, I have known bodies of men who 
     <lb/>
     worked together in harmony and I wish to pay 
     <lb/>
     tribute to these unions in Grand Falls. It is only 
     <lb/>
     by the companies and the unions getting together 
     <lb/>
     that we can have harmony in woods operations 
     <lb/>
     and for that matter in all operations throughout 
     <lb/>
     the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Fudge There is another thing I would like 
     <lb/>
     to mention — forest fires. I remind the delegates 
     <lb/>
     that when you take into consideration the number 
     <lb/>
     of men working in the companies' woods during 
     <lb/>
     the summer months, and compare the number of 
     <lb/>
     tires, you will be surprised to hear that very 
     <lb/>
     seldom do we get a fire caused by woodsmen. 
     <lb/>
     There was only one year that we had two fires 
     <lb/>
     and there is, at times, anywhere from 5,000 to 
     <lb/>
     6,000 men engaged in the forest industry and I 
     <lb/>
     should say most of those men make little fires to 
     <lb/>
     boil their kettles and get their lunch twice a day, 
     <lb/>
     and it is remarkable to see how careful the 
     <lb/>
     woodsman is in protecting the forest. We should 
     <lb/>
     not forget them when bringing in this report. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[There was some discussion of the section on<lb/>local sawmills and the export of pitprops. The<lb/>committee of the whole then rose and reportezi<lb/>progress. The Convention adjourned]</hi><lb/>
            </p>
   
 <note xml:id="fn_12">1 R. Gushue.</note>


<!-- GL, 2017-02-23, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
            <!--<p>
     November 8, 1946² 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Report of the Forestry Committee:³ 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Cashin This concerns the whole territory of 
     <lb/>
     Labrador, and I should inform the committee that 
     <lb/>
     I have here a map which has been supplied to us 
     <lb/>
     by the Department of Natural Resources, show<lb break="no"/>ing where the different timber areas are located. 
     <lb/>
     I will pass it around. You will notice that in the 
     <lb/>
     Hamilton Inlet area there are 300 square miles 
     <lb/>
     under lease. About 100 square miles of that has 
     <lb/>
     been taken over by the airport at North West 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     River.⁴ The other 200 square miles left was at one 
     <lb/>
     time supposed to have over 2 million cords of 
     <lb/>
     wood. The lease on that expires within five years, 
     <lb/>
     also the Muskrat Falls waterpower. From the 
     <lb/>
     Hamilton River you come to Kenimau River — 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     2,100 square miles. That's a 99-year lease, with 
     <lb/>
     about 70 years to go. All the others are 99-year 
     <lb/>
     leases, and the people who have held them have 
     <lb/>
     paid $2 per square mile annually ever since they 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
    <lb/>²The Secretary, Captain Warren, acted as Chairman.<lb/>³Volume II:56.<lb/>⁴Goose Bay air base.<lb/> 
               <lb/>
            </p>-->


</div>         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>