<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1948-01-28" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1948-01-28">28 January 1948</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1424" to="1447"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1424.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1425.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1426.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1427.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1428.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1429.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1430.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1431.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1432.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1433.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1434.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1435.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1436.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1437.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1438.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1439.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1440.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1441.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1442.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1443.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1444.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1445.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1446.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1447.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-09-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-09-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1424">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1424.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1425">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1425.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1426">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1426.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1427">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1427.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1428">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1428.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1429">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1429.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1430">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1430.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1431">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1431.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1432">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1432.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1433">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1433.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1434">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1434.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1435">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1435.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1436">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1436.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1437">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1437.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1438">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1438.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1439">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1439.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1440">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1440.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1441">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1441.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1442">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1442.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1443">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1443.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1444">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1444.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1445">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1445.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1446">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1446.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1447">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1447.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1424" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1424.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1424</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>


<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     Midnight 
     <lb/>
     28 January, 1948 
</head>

</div>

<div type="section">

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KEOU1">Mr. Keough</persName> Mr. Chairman, not to all men is it 
     <lb/>
     given to stand at the barricades of decision in a 
     <lb/>
     moment when destiny is about to decide the 
     <lb/>
     future of a whole people, but to we who are 
     <lb/>
     gathered here it is so given. We keep this night a 
     <lb/>
     rendezvous with destiny. We keep this night an 
     <lb/>
     assignation with history. We vote this night upon 
     <lb/>
     a matter of supreme importance to the people of 
     <lb/>
     this island. And when we have finished with that 
     <lb/>
     business there will be no need for a verdict from 
     <lb/>
     posterity upon our excellence or otherwise, for in 
     <lb/>
     the very act of voting we shall have passed a 
     <lb/>
     verdict for posterity upon ourselves. It will not be 
     <lb/>
     necessary for posterity to judge us for we shall 
     <lb/>
     have judged ourselves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It may well be that this will be the last time in 
     <lb/>
     my life that I shall speak in this storied chamber. 
     <lb/>
     Certain I am that I shall have no further occasion 
     <lb/>
     to speak during this Convention. And so, sir, I 
     <lb/>
     must crave your indulgence for a moment, before 
     <lb/>
     I address myself to the motion in order that I may 
     <lb/>
     set the record straight on a matterin which I seem 
     <lb/>
     to have been much misunderstood. For the 
     <lb/>
     benefit of all those who have not been listening 
     <lb/>
     to what I have said in this Convention, but who 
     <lb/>
     may think that they have been, I wish to make the 
     <lb/>
     categoric statement that I have never said that 
     <lb/>
     what comes first and before all else in life is three 
     <lb/>
     square meals a day. It just so happens that I 
     <lb/>
     believe in God. And any man who believes in 
     <lb/>
     God must, in consequence, admit to a hierarchy 
     <lb/>
     of values in which the spiritual and moral take 
     <lb/>
     precedence over the material. I am quite aware 
     <lb/>
     that there are more important things in life than 
     <lb/>
     three square meals a day. The causes for which 
     <lb/>
     all generations of men have suffered persecution, 
     <lb/>
     for which they have endured torture and death, 
     <lb/>
     for which they have fought and gladly died, have 
     <lb/>
     drawn not upon the stomach for inspiration. True 
     <lb/>
     it is that men have fought and died and done 
     <lb/>
     murder in their time for food. But to bear witness 
     <lb/>
     to the good and the true and the beautiful — to 
     <lb/>
     bear witness to these things, men have starved. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It will perhaps help to explain my insistence 
     <lb/>
     upon the importance of three square meals a day 
     <lb/>
     if I say that, in the first instance, I came into this 
     <lb/>
     chamber fully determined to insist upon that very 
     <lb/>
     thing. I knew in advance that we should hear 
     <lb/>
     much of sacred heritage. I knew that there would 
  

            <cb/>
      

     be much pointing to these hallowed walls. I knew 
     <lb/>
     that we should hear much calling to witness of all 
     <lb/>
     those who were giants in their day and genera<lb break="no"/>tion. Indeed, I was afraid that we should hear so 
     <lb/>
     much of all these that we should hear of nothing 
     <lb/>
     else. I was afraid that we should work ourselves 
     <lb/>
     up into such ecstasies about the glories of our 
     <lb/>
     land and past, as to completely forget that there 
     <lb/>
     had gone into the making of that glory, in addition 
     <lb/>
     to much blood, sweat and tears, much hunger, 
     <lb/>
     much bitterness of spirit born of being out at the 
     <lb/>
     elbows and down at the heels. And so I did 
     <lb/>
     promise myself away back at the beginning to 
     <lb/>
     remind this Convention every now and then that 
     <lb/>
     sacred heritage is not enough — that it is also of 
     <lb/>
     some importance that the people eat. And to keep 
     <lb/>
     me reminded of my promise to myself, I brought 
     <lb/>
     into this house with me a monitor to sit at my 
     <lb/>
     elbow — a monitor whom I have called my last 
     <lb/>
     forgotten fisherman on the bill of Cape St. 
     <lb/>
     George. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Need I say it has notbeen a particular, specific, 
     <lb/>
     solitary individual in whose name I have spoken 
     <lb/>
     so frequently, but rather a symbolic figure, a 
     <lb/>
     figure symbolic of all the fishermen in all the 
     <lb/>
     harbours, on all the islands, on all the bills of all 
     <lb/>
     the capes of this country. Time and again I have 
     <lb/>
     undertaken to remind this Convention of that 
     <lb/>
     symbolic forgotten fisherman whose shadow is 
     <lb/>
     across all our history. I have spoken of the grim 
     <lb/>
     Gethsemane he has endured, of how great has 
     <lb/>
     been his historic difficulty in making ends meet, 
     <lb/>
     of how it has not been easy for him to bring up 
     <lb/>
     his children in the fear and love of God, and with 
     <lb/>
     their bellies empty. I am satisfied that I have done 
     <lb/>
     the most that I could in his name, and I am 
     <lb/>
     satisfied that I have been right in doing so. For 
     <lb/>
     the person of my last forgotten fisherman on the 
     <lb/>
     bill of Cape St. George is just as sacred to me as 
     <lb/>
     the person of the most revered statesman who 
     <lb/>
     ever sat in this house. I am convinced that I have 
     <lb/>
     not been in error in insisting upon three square 
     <lb/>
     meals a day for my symbolic fisherman. And in 
     <lb/>
     doing so I have thought that three square meals a 
     <lb/>
     day for him are not without reference to the 
     <lb/>
     spiritual. For I believe that other things being 
     <lb/>
     equal, a man can the more easily save his immor<lb break="no"/>tal soul on a full stomach than on an empty one. 
     <lb/>
     I wouldn't be surprised if that was part of what 
 

            <pb n="1425" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1425.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1425</fw>
      

     Christ had in mind when he enjoined us to feed 
     <lb/>
     the hungry. And certain I am that that land is the 
     <lb/>
     happier in which every man has a full stomach. 
     <lb/>
     True it is that without vision the people perish; 
     <lb/>
     but without three square meals a day, they perish 
     <lb/>
     just as surely. And anyone who doesn't think so 
     <lb/>
     might well try going without three square meals 
     <lb/>
     a day for a little while. I say for a little while, 
     <lb/>
     because I know that conviction will not long be 
     <lb/>
     delayed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have no regrets about the pains I have been 
     <lb/>
     at to emphasise the importance of three square 
     <lb/>
     meals a day; and I am satisfied that I have done 
     <lb/>
     so in a right spirit — in the spirit that, once 
     <lb/>
     satisfied of the safeguard of the spiritual and 
     <lb/>
     moral values that we all cherish, we should next 
     <lb/>
     be concerned to resolve the question of the form 
     <lb/>
     of government best suited to our needs, in terms 
     <lb/>
     of what form will make for the greatest economic 
     <lb/>
     advantage of the common man of this island. And 
     <lb/>
     if it be sacrilege to have done as much, then I 
     <lb/>
     suggest to you to make the most of it. But let me 
     <lb/>
     assure you that when on Friday next I walk down 
     <lb/>
     the steps outside for the last time, I shall have no 
     <lb/>
     regret in my heart for this thing that I have done 
     <lb/>
     here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now to turn to the motion before the Chair. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood, after making it quite clear 
     <lb/>
     beyond a shadow of doubt that he has resolved 
     <lb/>
     the problem of perpetual motion, has seen fit to 
     <lb/>
     terminate his endeavours in this Convention by 
     <lb/>
     asking us to recommend to His Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     Government in the United Kingdom that among 
     <lb/>
     the forms of government to be submitted to the 
     <lb/>
     people in the forthcoming national referendum 
     <lb/>
     should be confederation with Canada upon the 
     <lb/>
     basis submitted to the National Convention on 
     <lb/>
     November 6, 1947, by the Prime Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Canada. Beyond a doubt, Mr. Smallwood in 
     <lb/>
     moving this motion is seeking a result which a 
     <lb/>
     great many people in this island desire. It may be 
     <lb/>
     a matter of great surprise to some that any con<lb break="no"/>siderable body of people should desire any such 
     <lb/>
     thing. To many members of this Convention who 
     <lb/>
     have undertaken to decide in their omniscience 
     <lb/>
     to restrict the people's choice, and even to prefer 
     <lb/>
     what they should vote for, it may well appear an 
     <lb/>
     outrage that there should be any considerable 
     <lb/>
     body of opinion to the contrary of their view. But 
     <lb/>
     there is a considerable body of opinion to the 
     <lb/>
     contrary of what is the majority opinion of this 
    

            <cb/>
         

     Convention; and that makes the contrary opinion 
     <lb/>
     a matter of legitimate concern for us. I take it that 
     <lb/>
     this impartial body is still prepared to afford the 
     <lb/>
     view, even of that which may be a minority, a 
     <lb/>
     hearing, if not a chance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     What I have been at pains to try to decide for 
     <lb/>
     myself in the whole matter of this motion has 
     <lb/>
     been simply this: is there anything in the 
     <lb/>
     proposed arrangements themselves that puts 
     <lb/>
     them beyond and outside the pale of rightful 
     <lb/>
     submission to the people of Newfoundland — in 
     <lb/>
     other words is there something in them intrinsi<lb break="no"/>cally evil? Personally, I have come to the con<lb break="no"/>clusion that it does not devolve upon me to seek 
     <lb/>
     to determine here if the proposed arrangements 
     <lb/>
     for union are fair and equitable, or even if they 
     <lb/>
     are adequate. That is a decision for the people. 
     <lb/>
     And time and time again throughout history the 
     <lb/>
     collective common sense of the whole people has 
     <lb/>
     proved more adequate than has the collective 
     <lb/>
     common sense of the people's popular as<lb break="no"/>semblies. And in this instance I am quite prepared 
     <lb/>
     to leave this matter in the people's hands. And 
     <lb/>
     what I am concerned with here, is to decide 
     <lb/>
     whether there is any rightful impediment in the 
     <lb/>
     way of endorsing these proposed arrangements 
     <lb/>
     as a referendum alternate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have been listening for many weeks to the 
     <lb/>
     Don Quixotes of the National Convention tilting 
     <lb/>
     at the windmills of the proposed arrangements for 
     <lb/>
     union. I must give them credit for supplying the 
     <lb/>
     wind that drove the very windmills they were 
     <lb/>
     tilting at. But as far as I am concerned, no 
     <lb/>
     evidence has been adduced to indicate that the 
     <lb/>
     proposed arrangements are not fair and equitable, 
     <lb/>
     all the ranting and roaring like true New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders notwithstanding. Indeed, it is quite 
     <lb/>
     apparent that the proposed arrangements do offer 
     <lb/>
     some advantages in consequence of which the 
     <lb/>
     lives of our people would be changed for the 
     <lb/>
     better. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To put the matter in a nutshell, I have come to 
     <lb/>
     conclude that there is nothing within the 
     <lb/>
     proposed arrangements themselves that obliges 
     <lb/>
     me in conscience not to recommend them to the 
     <lb/>
     people for decision. And so I will recommend 
     <lb/>
     them. And that will be all that is expected of me 
     <lb/>
     here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I say that advisedly. The way I see it, I am not 
     <lb/>
     obligated to express here any preference for a 
     <lb/>
     particular form of government. It was not so 


            <pb n="1426" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1426.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1426</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
        

     written in the bond. What was written in the bond 
     <lb/>
     was that I should recommend possible forms of 
     <lb/>
     future government to be put before the people at 
     <lb/>
     a national referendum It was not mentioned that 
     <lb/>
     I should express a personal preference. And in<lb break="no"/>deed, the whole idea of expressing preference is 
     <lb/>
     repugnant to me. For by expressing preference, 
     <lb/>
     this Convention will register a majority approval 
     <lb/>
     of one form of government to the exclusion of all 
     <lb/>
     others, and thereby influence the result of the 
     <lb/>
     referendum. Little as we are thought of by all the 
     <lb/>
     holier-than-thous who are so certain that they 
     <lb/>
     could have done better, there are still many who 
     <lb/>
     would likely be influenced by a majority vote of 
     <lb/>
     the Convention. But for the Convention to take 
     <lb/>
     advantage of that likelihood and register a 
     <lb/>
     majority opinion, seems to me like a distortion of 
     <lb/>
     its purpose; and consequently I will not be a party 
     <lb/>
     to the expression of preference. For my part I 
     <lb/>
     would prefer that the people should go to the 
     <lb/>
     referendum with their minds unbiased by any 
     <lb/>
     majority declaration of preference by this Con<lb break="no"/>vention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As far as I am qualified to judge, I cannot see 
     <lb/>
     why the issue of union with Canada upon the 
     <lb/>
     basis of the proposed terms should not be put to 
     <lb/>
     the people. That is as far as I feel called upon to 
     <lb/>
     go in the matter at this moment. But I do have to 
     <lb/>
     face the query as to whether or not it is fitting and 
     <lb/>
     proper that our people should have the issue of 
     <lb/>
     union put to them under such circumstances as 
     <lb/>
     those of the national referendum that is to follow 
     <lb/>
     in a little while; not to, brings up the whole 
     <lb/>
     constitutional question... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To begin, let me say that I do not pretend to 
     <lb/>
     be an expert, an authority, or even a novice in 
     <lb/>
     constitutional law. To tell the truth, I don't know 
     <lb/>
     the first thing about it. My concern most of the 
     <lb/>
     days of my life has been with trying to help the 
     <lb/>
     little fellow the better to make both ends meet, 
     <lb/>
     and with his ideas of how things should go in this 
     <lb/>
     island. In consequence I am quite prepared to 
     <lb/>
     leave discussion of the constitutional position "at 
     <lb/>
     law" involved in the confederation issue to those 
     <lb/>
     in our midst who are eminent King's Counsel<lb break="no"/>lors, Doctors of the Law and Justices of the 
     <lb/>
     Peace. Being a simple soul, who thinks more in 
     <lb/>
     the same terms as the singer out on the squid-jig<lb break="no"/>ging ground than in the terms in which a Privy 
     <lb/>
     Counsellor thinks, it seems to me that all this 
     <lb/>
     current furor over the constitutional propriety of 
  

            <cb/>
        

     confederation being placed on the ballot paper is 
     <lb/>
     much ado about nothing. I am not prepared to 
     <lb/>
     accept the argument that makes the placing of 
     <lb/>
     confederation upon the referendum ballot a 
     <lb/>
     constitutional issue. Actually it is no argument at 
     <lb/>
     all to say that it is not constitutionally proper for 
     <lb/>
     confederation to appear upon the referendum 
     <lb/>
     paper, and that Commission of Government and 
     <lb/>
     responsible government should be the only alter<lb break="no"/>natives submitted to the people. The way I see it, 
     <lb/>
     all that is distortion of the realities of the matter. 
     <lb/>
     To me such an argument makes as much sense as 
     <lb/>
     it would to say that two and two make five — 
     <lb/>
     therefore the grass is pink in summer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have said that in determining upon referen<lb break="no"/>dum alternatives we are bound in conscience, by 
     <lb/>
     tradition, and in fact and by right reason in all 
     <lb/>
     things. I can find no cause therein to exclude 
     <lb/>
     confederation from the consideration of the 
     <lb/>
     people. It is not legitimate to contend to the 
     <lb/>
     contrary, on the grounds that proper constitution<lb break="no"/>al procedure requires return to responsible 
     <lb/>
     government before the people are approached to 
     <lb/>
     discover if they desire union with Canada. That 
     <lb/>
     is not the case. It may be that we should have to 
     <lb/>
     have some measure of restoration of responsible 
     <lb/>
     government before the act of passing into the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian confederation could be officially con<lb break="no"/>cluded. But that is a different matter, and in no 
     <lb/>
     way concerns the referendum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The referendum, to my mind, is a device in<lb break="no"/>tended purely and simply to find out what the 
     <lb/>
     people desire in the way of government. No 
     <lb/>
     considerations of constitutional propriety can 
     <lb/>
     conceivably be involved. It's to be a simple mat<lb break="no"/>ter of asking the people just what they prefer in 
     <lb/>
     the way of government — a matter every bit as 
     <lb/>
     simple as asking them what they would prefer in 
     <lb/>
     the way of pie. And there are no constitutional 
     <lb/>
     strings attached to the act of ascertaining the 
     <lb/>
     desired constitution, anymore than there would 
     <lb/>
     be constitutional strings attached to the act of 
     <lb/>
     ascertaining the desired pie — whether it be apple 
     <lb/>
     pie or blueberry pie, or pie by and by from 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa. Unless it can be shown that confedera<lb break="no"/>tion <hi rendition="simple:italic">per se</hi> is not a proper alternative, we may not 
     <lb/>
     seek to exclude it from the referendum out of 
     <lb/>
     consideration of constitutionality which do not 
     <lb/>
     enter into the matter. What the proper procedure 
     <lb/>
     would be to give effect to the preferred constitu<lb break="no"/>tion would be something else; then we would 


            <pb n="1427" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1427.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1427</fw>
          

     become concerned with constitutional propriety. 
     <lb/>
     But in the referendum we shall be concerned 
     <lb/>
     merely with the interrogative mood. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There is one further matter that should give us 
     <lb/>
     cause for concern in considering this whole mat<lb break="no"/>ter of union, and that is whether union would 
     <lb/>
     prejudice the survival of a distinctive national 
     <lb/>
     culture and civilisation that we should seek to 
     <lb/>
     maintain. There are people in this island to whom 
     <lb/>
     the whole confederation issue is like a red rag to 
     <lb/>
     a bull, and for about much the same reason they 
     <lb/>
     just don't like it no how. Mention confederation, 
     <lb/>
     and they'll rant and they'll roar in the approved 
     <lb/>
     grand manner about 30 pieces of silver, and nig<lb break="no"/>gers in the woodpile, and selling our sacred 
     <lb/>
     heritage up the St. Lawrence. Indeed, there has 
     <lb/>
     been so much of that sort of thing going on both 
     <lb/>
     within and without this Convention that one has 
     <lb/>
     to pause to enquire if perhaps there might be a 
     <lb/>
     modicum of truth in it all. I must confess that I 
     <lb/>
     am not too clear as to just exactly what the poets 
     <lb/>
     and the politicians have in mind when they take 
     <lb/>
     to being sentimental over our sacred heritage. I 
     <lb/>
     remember that I did one time see a fisherman's 
     <lb/>
     wife shovel fish guts into a brin bag and spell it 
     <lb/>
     on her back to her gardens a mile away. I feel 
     <lb/>
     certain that that is not what they have in mind by 
     <lb/>
     our sacred heritage. I remember that I did one 
     <lb/>
     time spend February in a most picturesque little 
     <lb/>
     cottage nailed to a cliff beside the sea. I didn't get 
     <lb/>
     warm for a month, and I feel certain that the 
     <lb/>
     people living there didn't get warm for the winter. 
     <lb/>
     I feel that that is not the sacred heritage over 
     <lb/>
     which our poets work themselves up into 
     <lb/>
     ecstasies, and over which our politicians work 
     <lb/>
     themselves into a lather. Indeed, it must be some<lb break="no"/>thing altogether different than the most of what 
     <lb/>
     one comes across in making the rounds of this 
     <lb/>
     country. But if by our sacred heritage the poets 
     <lb/>
     and the politicians mean that we know in this 
     <lb/>
     island a culture and civilisation so different, and 
     <lb/>
     so much more advanced than the culture and 
     <lb/>
     civilisation of the North American mainland that 
     <lb/>
     they are worth any sacrifice to preserve them, 
     <lb/>
     they had better stop wool-gathering on Mount 
     <lb/>
     Olympus, and come down and walk among the 
     <lb/>
     people and learn how the people live. You know, 
     <lb/>
     it could be that the best authority on the 
     <lb/>
     desirability of baby bonuses would be the people 
   

            <cb/>
         

     who have the babies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have come to conclude that there would not 
     <lb/>
     be involved in confederation any issue of the 
     <lb/>
     preservation of a distinct national culture and 
     <lb/>
     civilisation. Now that is not to say, mind you, that 
     <lb/>
     we have not evolved our own customs, our own 
     <lb/>
     institutions, our own peculiar way of life. We 
     <lb/>
     have. It so happens that we are the inheritors of 
     <lb/>
     what I have sometimes called a fish and brewis 
     <lb/>
     culture, of which the apex in song is the "come- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     all-ye" and of which as good an example in folk 
     <lb/>
     custom as any other is a Codroy Valley "mill<lb break="no"/>ing".<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> Of that fish and brewis culture I am as 
     <lb/>
     proud as any Newfoundlander. It is true that we 
     <lb/>
     are the inheritors of a great national tradition of 
     <lb/>
     bravery against the seas, of heroism defying the 
     <lb/>
     sea to do its worst — bravery and heroism ex<lb break="no"/>emplified for all time on a bleak October day on 
     <lb/>
     the bleak Labrador coast when a man named 
     <lb/>
     Jackman did 27 times head into the storm and 27 
     <lb/>
     times come ashore with a human life on his back.<ref target="#fn_02">[2]</ref> 
     <lb/>
     It is true that in this land we are the inheritors of 
     <lb/>
     a great Christian tradition; that at the end of every 
     <lb/>
     week, after we have braved the sea and dug the 
     <lb/>
     land and cut the pulpwood, we do still after the 
     <lb/>
     manner of our fathers land gather in a thousand 
     <lb/>
     churches to pray as our fathers prayed... All these 
     <lb/>
     things are true. It is true too that all these things 
     <lb/>
     can remain to be so in the event of confederation. 
     <lb/>
     The things dearest to our hearts in this land will 
     <lb/>
     not in the event of union be at issue. I give it to 
     <lb/>
     you as my considered opinion, for what it is 
     <lb/>
     worth, that if the confederation alternate shall 
     <lb/>
     come to confront us in the referendum, that there 
     <lb/>
     shall be involved therein no issue involving our 
     <lb/>
     distinct character as Newfoundlanders, no issue 
     <lb/>
     involving our national honour, no issue involving 
     <lb/>
     our distinct culture and way of life. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I come now to this final statement of my 
     <lb/>
     position in this matter. To such extent as I am 
     <lb/>
     qualified to judge, the proposed arrangements 
     <lb/>
     appear to me to contain nothing that constitutes a 
     <lb/>
     legitimate impediment in the way of their being 
     <lb/>
     submitted to the Newfoundland people. I can say 
     <lb/>
     in conscience I know of no good and sufficient 
     <lb/>
     reason why the Newfoundland people should not 
     <lb/>
     have the opportunity to vote upon the confedera<lb break="no"/>tion issue if they so desire. I will vote to give them 
     <lb/>
     that opportunity. I will vote for the motion before 
  

<note xml:id="fn_01">[1] A social gathering among women to prepare wool (a fulling bee).</note> 
 

<note xml:id="fn_02">[2] Captain W. Jackman's famous rescue of people from the schooner <hi rendition="simple:italic">Sea Slipper</hi> occurred in 1867.</note> 
  

            <pb n="1428" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1428.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1428</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
          

     the Chair. I could not do otherwise without seek<lb break="no"/>ing to abridge the rights of our people and without 
     <lb/>
     doing injury to my own integrity. My final con<lb break="no"/>clusion in the whole matter is that yet once again 
     <lb/>
     must I agree with myself in something that I said 
     <lb/>
     a long time ago — that in the great decision that 
     <lb/>
     confronts us, even if there be but one man in all 
     <lb/>
     this island who wishes to vote for return of 
     <lb/>
     responsible government, he is entitled to have the 
     <lb/>
     opportunity to do so — even if that one lone 
     <lb/>
     individual should happen to be Major Peter 
     <lb/>
     Cashin. Even if there be but one man in this island 
     <lb/>
     who wishes to vote for union with Canada, he is 
     <lb/>
     entitled to the opportunity to do so, even if that 
     <lb/>
     one lone individual should happen to be Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Joseph Smallwood. And even if there happens to 
     <lb/>
     be but one man in this island who wants to vote 
     <lb/>
     for retention of Commission of Government, he 
     <lb/>
     is entitled to the opportunity to do so — even if 
     <lb/>
     that one lone individual happens to be a person 
     <lb/>
     of no more consequence than my last forgotten 
     <lb/>
     fisherman on the bill of Cape St. George. I said 
     <lb/>
     that first many months ago when the Convention 
     <lb/>
     was still young. In the meantime I have come 
     <lb/>
     upon nothing to convince me to the contrary, so 
     <lb/>
     do I repeat it here at the end. I am still of that 
     <lb/>
     opinion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And now as we turn to the casting of our final 
     <lb/>
     vote, as we address ourselves to the pinnacle of 
     <lb/>
     our endeavour here, there is this that I would ask 
     <lb/>
     the Convention to bear in mind: let us remember 
     <lb/>
     in this hour, that all the days of our lives the mark 
     <lb/>
     of this Convention will be upon us. We can never 
     <lb/>
     be free of it, though we flee it down the nights 
     <lb/>
     and down the days and down the labyrinthine 
     <lb/>
     ways of our own souls. It will remain with us 
     <lb/>
     always. We are committed here to the serving of 
     <lb/>
     a great purpose in conscience and in honour. And 
     <lb/>
     our own conscience will judge us all the days of 
     <lb/>
     our lives if we fail in conscience, and history will 
     <lb/>
     judge us if we fail in honour. And we shall know 
     <lb/>
     no peace of mind again if in this historic hour we 
     <lb/>
     fail this land and this people. As, then, we apply 
     <lb/>
     ourselves to the final act of recommending the 
     <lb/>
     alternatives of government to be submitted to the 
     <lb/>
     people's choice, let us bear constantly in mind 
     <lb/>
     that it is a matter involving our conscience and 
     <lb/>
     our honour to recommend all legitimate alterna<lb break="no"/>tives consistent with right reason. In consequence 
     <lb/>
     let us at this moment have somewhat more than 
     <lb/>
     the courage of our connections. Let us be decided 
   

            <cb/>
     

     instead by the courage of our convictions. Let us 
     <lb/>
     remember that we shall leave no footprints in the 
     <lb/>
     sands of time with feet of clay. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The mark of this Convention will be upon us 
     <lb/>
     always in this too. We who are gathered here 
     <lb/>
     were by our election to this Convention in some 
     <lb/>
     measure set apart. We have the high honour of 
     <lb/>
     being the men to whom Newfoundland, at a 
     <lb/>
     moment of supreme decision, has turned for 
     <lb/>
     guidance. We have had full opportunity to study 
     <lb/>
     the elements of the issue that confronts us. We 
     <lb/>
     have had greater opportunity than most of our 
     <lb/>
     fellows to take the measure of this land and the 
     <lb/>
     measure of its necessity. And there has come 
     <lb/>
     upon us in consequence responsibility and 
     <lb/>
     dedication that will not end with this Convention. 
     <lb/>
     To whom much is given, of him much will be 
     <lb/>
     expected. And it will surely be expected of us 
     <lb/>
     after we have gone forth from here, that we shall 
     <lb/>
     serve with greater diligence than most the cause 
     <lb/>
     of human dignity and social justice in this land; 
     <lb/>
     for we have had greater opportunity than most to 
     <lb/>
     see wherein we could come to serve with ad<lb break="no"/>vantage. Indeed, there devolves upon us the plain 
     <lb/>
     duty to go forth from this Convention determined 
     <lb/>
     in our hearts and resolved in our souls that we 
     <lb/>
     shall leave no stone unturned, that we shall move 
     <lb/>
     whatever mountains must be moved, that we 
     <lb/>
     shall labour from dawn till dusk, that we shall 
     <lb/>
     cease not from argument or action, that we shall 
     <lb/>
     know no peace or no rest in our time until — 
     <lb/>
     come what form of government there may — we 
     <lb/>
     have made the fullest contribution that we may 
     <lb/>
     in our own time to the making of this land that 
     <lb/>
     we all do love: a land in which there will be peace 
     <lb/>
     and happiness and dignity, and enough for all. 
     <lb/>
      </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:VINC1">Mr. Vincent</persName> Mr. Chairman, I am not at the 
     <lb/>moment concerned with the nebulous conception 
     <lb/>of economic justice, nor am I greatly concerned 
     <lb/>with what my friend, Mr. Newell called 
     <lb/>"economic politics". The case as I see it is simply 
     <lb/>a motion to put on the ballot in the coming 
     <lb/>referendum this spring, confederation on the 
     <lb/>basis of the proposals submitted by the King 
     <lb/>government to this Convention. Anticipating 
     <lb/>this, of course, I previously recommended the 
     <lb/>terms to my constituents and to the country 
     <lb/>generally when I spoke to Mr. Bradley's motion 
     <lb/>introducing the proposals some weeks ago. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
  Mr. Chairman, as odd and strange as it may 
     <lb/>
     seem, there are some here who would, after a 
    

            <pb n="1429" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1429.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1429</fw>
       

     debate of six weeks on this issue of confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, deny the people a chance to choose for 
     <lb/>
     themselves. It has been made abundantly clear by 
     <lb/>
     you, sir, and by many other speakers, that this 
     <lb/>
     Convention was elected to make recommenda<lb break="no"/>tions on form or forms of government, and in my 
     <lb/>
     opinion any member of this assembly relegating 
     <lb/>
     to himself the right to think for another is assum<lb break="no"/>ing a prerogative that never was his. Mr. Higgins 
     <lb/>
     said the terms were fair; that is the opinion of a 
     <lb/>
     legal mind. Mr. Bradley approves and recom<lb break="no"/>mends them; again the opinion of a keen, legal 
     <lb/>
     brain. Great sections of the island have given 
     <lb/>
     their moral support to this issue, and yet we have 
     <lb/>
     members who will get up and say, "No, con<lb break="no"/>federation has no right to be on the ballot." Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Chairman and gentlemen, I can assure you in all 
     <lb/>
     sincerity, to make such a statement in my district 
     <lb/>
     would not only be sheer folly, but it would be 
     <lb/>
     positively dangerous, and as the elected repre<lb break="no"/>sentative for Bonavista North I demand that con<lb break="no"/>federation be placed on the ballot. I have also 
     <lb/>
     supported the other forms being put there as well. 
     <lb/>
     Critics have been trying hard to build up a case 
     <lb/>
     against the people having a choice. They have, 
     <lb/>
     with great forcefulness, invoked the almost 
     <lb/>
     sacred covenant of letters patent, the act suspend<lb break="no"/>ing responsible government. They might as well 
     <lb/>
     have read themselves a chapter out of Charles 
     <lb/>
     Dickens' <hi rendition="simple:italic">Oliver Twist</hi>, it would have been more 
     <lb/>
     entertaining and much more humourous. The or<lb break="no"/>dinary man, the fisherman, the common man (and 
     <lb/>
     he will swing the big stick next May), cares as 
     <lb/>
     much about that as he does about the value of a 
     <lb/>
     row of beans. What concerns him at the moment 
     <lb/>
     — and it is very important — is his freedom of 
     <lb/>
     choice, the right to make his own decisions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, I am giving my unqualified 
     <lb/>
     support to the motion. I am giving it my un<lb break="no"/>qualified support because I feel there are tens of 
     <lb/>
     thousands of intelligent Newfoundlanders who 
     <lb/>
     honestly want to see confederation on the ballot 
     <lb/>
     this spring. I support it because I am convinced 
     <lb/>
     that the terms offered by the government of Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister Mackenzie King are the best we can 
     <lb/>
     reasonably expect, bearing in mind that the nine 
     <lb/>
     other provinces of Canada entered confederation 
     <lb/>
     under less favourable arrangements. I support the 
     <lb/>
     motion wholeheartedly since, I am a pro-con<lb break="no"/>federate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The future of this island lies within the orbit 
  

            <cb/>
        

     of the western hemisphere. Today Canada and 
     <lb/>
     her great and powerful neighbour, the United 
     <lb/>
     States, probably have more in common than any 
     <lb/>
     other two nations in the world. No powerful 
     <lb/>
     machines of war patrol their lines of demarcation. 
     <lb/>
     No military barriers restrict the influx of citizenry 
     <lb/>
     of Canada into the United States. Our destiny 
     <lb/>
     must be with our western neighbours, not as an 
     <lb/>
     isolated unit assuming a false sense of inde<lb break="no"/>pendence that never was ours, but as a component 
     <lb/>
     of an economic interdependent union of the great 
     <lb/>
     western bloc of nations called North America. 
     <lb/>
     Somebody talked of sentiment. If I were asked to 
     <lb/>
     interpret Newfoundland, I would assert without 
     <lb/>
     fear of contradiction that for both realistic and 
     <lb/>
     sentimental reasons, our future lies with Canada. 
     <lb/>
     Our racial strains are the same as hers; our pride 
     <lb/>
     in the old order of British institutions is the same; 
     <lb/>
     our traditions, the age-old tradition of freedom 
     <lb/>
     for which our sons and hers have fought and died, 
     <lb/>
     will not change or be changed under union, and 
     <lb/>
     I, for one, would not wish them to. For I want the 
     <lb/>
     memories of the upsurge of British nationhood, 
     <lb/>
     of the growth through pain and peril of our Com<lb break="no"/>monwealth, to remain as real and as strong as they 
     <lb/>
     are today. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Canada, occupying the third largest national 
     <lb/>
     space in the world, exceeded only by Russia and 
     <lb/>
     China, with a population of only 12 million, still 
     <lb/>
     has a long way to go. Does the future look black 
     <lb/>
     for Canada? I do not think so. Only today, I read 
     <lb/>
     in a very reliable journal mat United States 
     <lb/>
     citizens have more than $5 billion invested in the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. Does that infer her future is dark? 
     <lb/>
     Canada is a creditor nation. Since the end of the 
     <lb/>
     war she has loaned England $1,250,000,000 and 
     <lb/>
     a further $750 million for export credits to Europe 
     <lb/>
     and Asia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The terms of union are attractive — old age 
     <lb/>
     pensions and family allowances offer much to 
     <lb/>
     our people. I very earnestly recommend them to 
     <lb/>
     my constituents and to the country generally, for, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman, I am fully convinced that in con<lb break="no"/>cert with the nine other provinces, and with the 
     <lb/>
     friendliness of our big southern confederacy the 
     <lb/>
     United States, our people will advance into a 
     <lb/>
     brighter era, and in the world of tomorrow will 
     <lb/>
     find a still more honourable and effective role to 
     <lb/>
     play. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, by way of concluding, and I 
     <lb/>
     shall be very brief, I would like to pay my respects 
   

            <pb n="1430" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1430.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1430</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
          

     to the Chair. Your task, sir, has been a very 
     <lb/>
     onerous one, but the wise judgement, cool 
     <lb/>
     decisions and great consideration which you 
     <lb/>
     have shown have added still more lustre to your 
     <lb/>
     already well-known abilities, and a greater ad<lb break="no"/>miration for one of Newfoundland's greatest 
     <lb/>
     sons. To your immediate predecessor, my learned 
     <lb/>
     associate from Bonavista Centre, I would say that 
     <lb/>
     when and if the records of this Convention are 
     <lb/>
     written, history will accord no mean place to the 
     <lb/>
     name of F. Gordon Bradley, K.C. I would also, 
     <lb/>
     pay tribute to the memory of that great and good 
     <lb/>
     man, the late Mr. Justice Fox; to me (and I knew 
     <lb/>
     him but a short time), his demise represented a 
     <lb/>
     personal tragedy, and I shall treasure memories 
     <lb/>
     of that kindly gentleman long after Conventions 
     <lb/>
     are forgotten. To members generally, I express a 
     <lb/>
     deep sense of gratitude. As far as I am concerned, 
     <lb/>
     this Convention has been a great lesson in politi<lb break="no"/>cal democracy at work, even though it may have 
     <lb/>
     been a very expensive one. Here the managing 
     <lb/>
     directors of the big vested interests were called 
     <lb/>
     by their first names by the ex-schoolteacher, the 
     <lb/>
     outport merchant. Here the ex-policeman from 
     <lb/>
     the west coast talked over his people's problems 
     <lb/>
     with the co-op worker from White Bay. Forty; 
     <lb/>
     five men with divergent views did much toward 
     <lb/>
     enlightening public opinion and awakening a 
     <lb/>
     sense of political responsibility among our 
     <lb/>
     people. If I may be permitted to be personal on a 
     <lb/>
     final note, and I trust it is not in bad taste, I would 
     <lb/>
     express my sincere thanks to my good friend, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Hickman, He probably more than any other has 
     <lb/>
     gone out of his way at times to extend those little 
     <lb/>
     courtesies that mean so much. Also to Mr. Cros<lb break="no"/>bie, the Hon. R.B. Job, Mr. Smallwood and to my 
     <lb/>
     great friend, Arch Northcott, and to members 
     <lb/>
     generally; and I make my final bow by saying, 
     <lb/>
     "Thank you, gentlemen." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> Mr. Chairman, I hesitated when this 
     <lb/>
     subject was being discussed in committee of the 
     <lb/>
     whole to engage in the debate. I felt it was being 
     <lb/>
     buffeted around the house, and that the discus<lb break="no"/>sion on it was being rendered in extremes on both 
     <lb/>
     sides. And so I mostly sat it out. However, in view 
     <lb/>
     of the bigness of the question, and in view of the 
     <lb/>
     fact that I, on both occasions, voted in favour of 
     <lb/>
     the motion to send a delegation to Ottawa to 
     <lb/>
     request the terms of union, I feel I should make 
     <lb/>
     some comment at this time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If I were asked why I supported getting the 
  

            <cb/>
        

     terms of union, I would say, yes, I would honestly 
     <lb/>
     swear that my first and perhaps only reason was 
     <lb/>
     a psychological one. We were called together to 
     <lb/>
     consider forms of government. The question of 
     <lb/>
     confederation had been up before. True, it has 
     <lb/>
     failed, but on its merits or demerits as the case 
     <lb/>
     may be. But it had become an object of con<lb break="no"/>tinuous curiosity and many unfounded argu<lb break="no"/>ments had, down through the years, been 
     <lb/>
     advanced in its favour. This old flame had been 
     <lb/>
     rapidly fanned in the interim between the an<lb break="no"/>nouncement of the holding of this Convention 
     <lb/>
     and its opening date, September 11, 1946. A 
     <lb/>
     glowing picture of union with Canada was laid 
     <lb/>
     before the people. It was not to be wondered at 
     <lb/>
     then, that since we were dealing with such ques<lb break="no"/>tions, that curiosity was further aroused and 
     <lb/>
     being aroused, had to be satisfied. It is not my 
     <lb/>
     intention now to comment on the methods 
     <lb/>
     adopted by the pro-confederates as to their fair<lb break="no"/>ness or otherwise, and I say but one thing, that 
     <lb/>
     they are, to my mind, not based on sound national 
     <lb/>
     principles and consequently could not be con<lb break="no"/>sidered as bait. A further remark is that its 
     <lb/>
     progress through this assembly has provided the 
     <lb/>
     means of passing on the bait. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And so I voted for the motion to send a delega<lb break="no"/>tion to Ottawa. That decision was against my 
     <lb/>
     feeling, for in the autonomous sovereign integrity 
     <lb/>
     of our country I had a strong belief. But my 
     <lb/>
     feelings, I felt, should be set aside for the mo<lb break="no"/>ment, and should yield to a proven case: a case in 
     <lb/>
     which all the evidence should be submitted and 
     <lb/>
     considered. And there a great shadow came over 
     <lb/>
     our subject, our inability to negotiate. I do not 
     <lb/>
     pass reflections on those who gave us this job to 
     <lb/>
     do, and who set the limits wherein we work. No 
     <lb/>
     part of this is unwittingly planned, and it is well 
     <lb/>
     that it is so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I voted to get the terms. That covered that. 
     <lb/>
     There was at one time a possibility of our having 
     <lb/>
     to consider what is still only a word, a con<lb break="no"/>dominion. The idea of investigating government 
     <lb/>
     of the North of Ireland status was hinted at, as 
     <lb/>
     was also a present-day application of repre<lb break="no"/>sentative government. All these, I believe, were 
     <lb/>
     possible forms of future government and one 
     <lb/>
     would act in a restrictive manner not to favour 
     <lb/>
     their being looked into. But having investigated 
     <lb/>
     these forms of government, it does not necessari<lb break="no"/>ly follow that one would recommend any or all 


            <pb n="1431" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1431.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1431</fw>
           

     of them for submission to the people in the refer<lb break="no"/>endum. For these forms would unquestionably 
     <lb/>
     apply with greater or lesser merit under different 
     <lb/>
     circumstances. To state my position clearly, I 
     <lb/>
     would not recommend a form of government for 
     <lb/>
     which I would not vote in a referendum. I would, 
     <lb/>
     Ifeel, be very lax in my duty and indeed, it would 
     <lb/>
     be plain deceit to do other than that. Sixteen 
     <lb/>
     months ago I might have said I think the people 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland are desirous of voting on cer<lb break="no"/>tain forms of government. Today I can only say 
     <lb/>
     the same, nor am I under duty to find out. But I 
     <lb/>
     am under duty to recommend what in my opinion 
     <lb/>
     should be put before the people. Obviously, to 
     <lb/>
     determine the wishes of the people was a purely 
     <lb/>
     mechanical matter; but to secure a recommenda<lb break="no"/>tion necessitated study, hence the Convention 
     <lb/>
     and its undertaking, and surely now, after all its 
     <lb/>
     cost to the country, our recommendation will 
     <lb/>
     have foundation on the facts as we saw them. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Chairman, are we shirking the first call of duty? 
     <lb/>
     Are we seeing enacted before our very eyes the 
     <lb/>
     first scene in the further degradation of our 
     <lb/>
     country? Must our way be still harder? Given the 
     <lb/>
     task to do, will history record us as having dis<lb break="no"/>charged that duty faithfully, or will it relate a 
     <lb/>
     gruesome story of putrefaction and prostitution 
     <lb/>
     of a great obligation? Sometimes I fear it has 
     <lb/>
     happened. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This country of ours has fought a hard fight 
     <lb/>
     down through the years, and progress and 
     <lb/>
     development were greatly retarded by outside 
     <lb/>
     forces. Despite all this, the great courage of its 
     <lb/>
     people and their determination to establish here 
     <lb/>
     a country fashioned to their own liking, made the 
     <lb/>
     task, though a difficult one, a desire of the heart. 
     <lb/>
     Here in the quiet though frugal comfort of their 
     <lb/>
     homes, they planned their undertakings — under<lb break="no"/>takings that would undoubtedly bring them great 
     <lb/>
     dangers. But danger to them created a more 
     <lb/>
     colourful existence. In this and many similar 
     <lb/>
     ways, a way of life was born. Meanwhile, what 
     <lb/>
     of our leaders? We hear, from those who would 
     <lb/>
     tear down the whole structure of our national life 
     <lb/>
     and culture, repeated attempts made to blacken 
     <lb/>
     our Newfoundland leaders of the past. The dark 
     <lb/>
     spots of our history are always held to the front, 
     <lb/>
     for fear can be instilled in our hearts by such a 
     <lb/>
     policy. Mr. Chairman, we had great men as 
     <lb/>
     judged in the age in which they lived. These men 
     <lb/>
     laid the foundation of the trade and commerce of 
 

            <cb/>
    

     the country which is still sound in many ways, 
     <lb/>
     though greatly distorted in others. I am not prone 
     <lb/>
     to dwell for long in history's pages. What of our 
     <lb/>
     trade and commerce? What of our leaders in this 
     <lb/>
     field? Notice, I make no mention of the producer, 
     <lb/>
     the fisherman, farmer, logger, miner. I want to 
     <lb/>
     deal, if possible, with those influences of govern<lb break="no"/>ment which may help or harm the producer. I am 
     <lb/>
     fully aware and quite willing to believe that our 
     <lb/>
     producers will do their part, and thus I dispose of 
     <lb/>
     that part of the subject. Time does not permit me 
     <lb/>
     to deal with more than one of our primary in<lb break="no"/>dustries, and I shall refer only to the fishing 
     <lb/>
     industry which is and will continue to be the chief 
     <lb/>
     industry of that section of Newfoundland from 
     <lb/>
     where I come. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The fishing industry emerged from the war 
     <lb/>
     period without any great shock. It could ill afford 
     <lb/>
     a shock — let that be fully appreciated. The war 
     <lb/>
     period, no one need be reminded, was abnormal 
     <lb/>
     in its demands both in quantity and price, and a 
     <lb/>
     serious falling off could have easily been the 
     <lb/>
     order of the day. This did not happen, and it was 
     <lb/>
     no accident that it did not — neither was it just 
     <lb/>
     good luck. It was, let there be no mistake about 
     <lb/>
     it, due to the vision, the constructive policy of our 
     <lb/>
     leaders in that field. True, we had an exchange 
     <lb/>
     problem, but even in this matter local suggestions 
     <lb/>
     capable of solving the problems of the day were 
     <lb/>
     readily forthcoming. We have gone a long way 
     <lb/>
     in the development of our fishing industry and in 
     <lb/>
     our marketing methods, and the future gives even 
     <lb/>
     further encouragement, for our next move 
     <lb/>
     promises to be the solving in part at least of that 
     <lb/>
     exchange of currency problem. If that can be once 
     <lb/>
     taken care of, then the Newfoundland producer 
     <lb/>
     will have considerably less to worry about. This 
     <lb/>
     is <hi rendition="simple:italic">our</hi> problem. We have to have it solved in 
     <lb/>
     particular reference to this country; we should 
     <lb/>
     trust it to no other country to do it for us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And now I feel I should dwell for a few 
     <lb/>
     moments on the effect of union with Canada on 
     <lb/>
     this industry. The first and perhaps the all-con<lb break="no"/>demning feature is that the control of all trade and 
     <lb/>
     commerce would rest in the hands of the federal 
     <lb/>
     government, as it is today in Canada. New<lb break="no"/>foundland is small in comparison with Canada; 
     <lb/>
     we are always reminded of that, but what we are 
     <lb/>
     not asked to be mindful of is that in the competi<lb break="no"/>tive market which exists, we are taking care of 
     <lb/>
     ourselves well. Union with Canada, as I see it, 
 

            <pb n="1432" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1432.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1432</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
          

     would seriously affect this. Those who would 
     <lb/>
     alarm us on our local matters endeavour to con<lb break="no"/>sole us on this question, and the ordinary word of 
     <lb/>
     caution they try to kill in an avalanche of words. 
     <lb/>
     They would be as helpless as you orl in the face 
     <lb/>
     of events that would follow union. Poor hope for 
     <lb/>
     our people, if they have to trust themselves 
     <lb/>
     forever to the charity and goodwill of a foreign 
     <lb/>
     master. We are the masters here; division of our 
     <lb/>
     people cannot be weighed in terms of supposedly 
     <lb/>
     improved services. We can and we rapidly are 
     <lb/>
     improving these services. The extent to which 
     <lb/>
     they shall progress will bear relation to capacity 
     <lb/>
     to pay. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I might be expected to comment on the man<lb break="no"/>ner in which we were told that in respect to local 
     <lb/>
     government we could please ourselves. That is 
     <lb/>
     largely true, but the truth was not fully presented. 
     <lb/>
     Local or municipal government in Canada is 
     <lb/>
     obliged to render greater and more costly services 
     <lb/>
     to the communities where they exist than they are 
     <lb/>
     in Newfoundland. For instance, half the cost of 
     <lb/>
     public relief, half the cost of education is thrown 
     <lb/>
     by the provincial government into the hands of 
     <lb/>
     local governments or councils as we know them. 
     <lb/>
     I do not grumble about the possibility of having 
     <lb/>
     to do this; what concerns me is the ability or 
     <lb/>
     inability of a council to take care of these added 
     <lb/>
     obligations. I can see in such a possibility the loss 
     <lb/>
     of the ground we have already gained, and a great 
     <lb/>
     and lasting injury done our people. But even 
     <lb/>
     these matters are secondary and could be 
     <lb/>
     sacrificed to great national principles if such 
     <lb/>
     could be served. Judged in this light, this union 
     <lb/>
     with Canada falls short again. For this is not a 
     <lb/>
     division; it is not a partition, it is absorption, it is 
     <lb/>
     the swallowing of a little country that was once 
     <lb/>
     called Newfoundland, and many of the 
     <lb/>
     privileges, many of the advantages which we 
     <lb/>
     now enjoy may cause indigestion to the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     appetite. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The coming referendum and the few remain<lb break="no"/>ing months prior thereto will be a most important 
     <lb/>
     time and event in the history of our country. 
     <lb/>
     There and then we shall go on record as a people, 
     <lb/>
     and the eyes of the world shall judge us accord<lb break="no"/>ingly for long years to come, for this is an ir<lb break="no"/>revocable decision, even as they today still judge 
     <lb/>
     Esau of old, who said to his brother, "Give me of 
     <lb/>
     thy red pottage for I am exceeding faint"; and 
     <lb/>
     Jacob the brother replied, "Sell me thy 
  

            <cb/>
       

     birthright." And Esau answering said, "Lo, if I 
     <lb/>
     die what will my birthright avail me?" Thus he 
     <lb/>
     would lose forever the birthright for which he had 
     <lb/>
     so little account, and all for a mess of pottage. 
     <lb/>
  </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FIGA1">Mr. Figary</persName> Mr. Chairman, I rise to support the 
     <lb/>motion which is now before the Chair. In listen<lb break="no"/>ing to addresses of members of this Convention 
     <lb/>at this time and at other times, I have come to this 
     <lb/>conclusion: that there have been too many long- 
     <lb break="yes"/>winded addresses which have been corrupting 
     <lb/>and confusing the minds of the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are here, Mr. Chairman, with this in mind: 
     <lb/>
     after considering the changes that have taken 
     <lb/>
     place in this country since 1934, to recommend 
     <lb/>
     to His Majesty's Government in Great Britain 
     <lb/>
     suitable forms of government to be placed before 
     <lb/>
     the people in a national referendum, who will 
     <lb/>
     decide as to the future set-up, and I will not try to 
     <lb/>
     block any form of government going on the ballot 
     <lb/>
     paper, and I do not think it advisable for any other 
     <lb/>
     member to try and do so. We have thousands and 
     <lb/>
     thousands of people who favour confederation 
     <lb/>
     with Canada, and I do not think it right and 
     <lb/>
     reasonable for us, as members of this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion, to try and deprive them of that privilege. In 
     <lb/>
     speaking of the terms offered by the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government, some I cannot accept but to a large 
     <lb/>
     extent, to my mind, they are quite favourable. 
     <lb/>
     The people of this country are looking for some<lb break="no"/>thing better than what they have been getting, and 
     <lb/>
     let us all hope that when the ballot is taken, a 
     <lb/>
     decision will be made in the right direction. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, I am not at all sure that this country is 
     <lb/>
     so wonderfully prosperous today as we have been 
     <lb/>
     asked to believe. I will admit some people are 
     <lb/>
     prosperous, but there are thousands of fishermen 
     <lb/>
     and labourers who are still looking for this 
     <lb/>
     prosperity that they hear so much about. There 
     <lb/>
     are thousands of our people who are struggling 
     <lb/>
     day by day and week by week with the terrible 
     <lb/>
     high cost of living, a cost of living that seems to 
     <lb/>
     climb higher and higher month by month. It takes 
     <lb/>
     pretty high wages today for a working man to 
     <lb/>
     support a family. And what about the thousands 
     <lb/>
     who don't get high wages in Newfoundland? I 
     <lb/>
     have noticed for a long time that the cost of living 
     <lb/>
     has an ugly habit of rising much faster than wages 
     <lb/>
     ever do. The fishermen and workers get hit every 
     <lb/>
     time. This Convention must not run away with 
     <lb/>
     the idea that all our people in this country are so 
     <lb/>
     wonderfully prosperous. I can tell you plainly 
 

            <pb n="1433" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1433.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1433</fw>
         

     that there are people who are half-fed, half- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     clothed, and a lot unemployed. And unemploy<lb break="no"/>ment is going to increase in the near future. This 
     <lb/>
     being so, let us extend some of this prosperity to 
     <lb/>
     these people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, I am not greatly interested in 
     <lb/>
     all the long tables of figures that have been 
     <lb/>
     presented to this Convention, nor do I think the 
     <lb/>
     people are interested in them. I am much more 
     <lb/>
     interested in the broad outline of the situation, 
     <lb/>
     and I am not too sure that everything is bright for 
     <lb/>
     the future in this country. There are too many 
     <lb/>
     signs of something altogether different, our 
     <lb/>
     people have long memories. There are thousands 
     <lb/>
     in this country who can remember back before 
     <lb/>
     the first world war. They remember how the price 
     <lb/>
     of fish and everything else went up when that war 
     <lb/>
     broke out. They remember very well the 
     <lb/>
     prosperity that came to Newfoundland in the first 
     <lb/>
     world war. Yes, and they remember the depres<lb break="no"/>sion and hard times and dole and poverty that 
     <lb/>
     came after the war. They remember that with very 
     <lb/>
     few exceptions that depression lasted all the time 
     <lb/>
     from the end of that war almost to the start of this 
     <lb/>
     war. And they remember also that when this war 
     <lb/>
     came, prices began to jump just as they did in the 
     <lb/>
     first world war. Now, Mr. Chairman, this second 
     <lb/>
     world war is over — or at least the actual fighting 
     <lb/>
     is over — and can you blame people for wonder<lb break="no"/>ing what is going to happen in the near future? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am a plain working man, a trade unionist. 
     <lb/>
     And I do know something about our New<lb break="no"/>foundland workers, and how they live and bring 
     <lb/>
     up their families. I know something of their strug<lb break="no"/>gles to live, I know something of their struggles 
     <lb/>
     to make both ends meet, and I know something 
     <lb/>
     of the hard years before the war, and the suffering 
     <lb/>
     our people endured. So Mr. Chairman, I must tell 
     <lb/>
     you frankly that I am a bit hard to convince when 
     <lb/>
     I am told that everything is all right and our future 
     <lb/>
     assured. My mind is not a bit romantic, and the 
     <lb/>
     hard facts of our people's struggle to live make a 
     <lb/>
     deeper impression on my mind than all the talk 
     <lb/>
     in the world about the glorious traditions and all 
     <lb/>
     sorts of things. I am not going to be carried away 
     <lb/>
     by any comforting assurances about our future, 
     <lb/>
     for when I remember the past I am still the more 
     <lb/>
     determined to keep my feet planted firmly on the 
     <lb/>
     ground. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We have heard a lot said in this Convention of 
     <lb/>
     the conditions existing in Canada. But, Mr. 
   

            <cb/>
           

     Chairman, it can't be so bad after all, as thousands 
     <lb/>
     of our people have gone there, obtained good 
     <lb/>
     positions and have made wonderful progress. I 
     <lb/>
     know lots of them, have been in their homes in 
     <lb/>
     cities such as Toronto and Montreal and other 
     <lb/>
     cities, and their positions are very encouraging. I 
     <lb/>
     will admit that there are people in Canada similar 
     <lb/>
     to those in Newfoundland to whom I have 
     <lb/>
     referred, but that exists in every country. There<lb break="no"/>fore, I say to the people of this country, don't be 
     <lb/>
     swayed by every wind and doctrine. Vote as your 
     <lb/>
     mind leads you, which I will do when the time 
     <lb/>
     comes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NORT2">Mr. Northcott</persName> Mr. Chairman, I want to say first 
     <lb/>
     of all just why I cannot vote for confederation, 
     <lb/>
     why I cannot suppon it. First, our fisheries are of 
     <lb/>
     paramount importance to me. Our people, a great 
     <lb/>
     many of them, live by the fisheries, and under the 
     <lb/>
     act we have no gilt-edge security that the federal 
     <lb/>
     government will take care of our fisheries. Our 
     <lb/>
     Fisheries Board may not function as heretofore. 
     <lb/>
     This is a thing the fishermen in Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     will want to bear in mind. Every fisherman will 
     <lb/>
     want to know the facts, the real facts, and the truth 
     <lb/>
     in connection with our fisheries and what will 
     <lb/>
     happen to the Fisheries Board. Gentlemen, we 
     <lb/>
     must export or perish. That is a very important 
     <lb/>
     thing. That is one of the reasons why I cannot 
     <lb/>
     support the motion now before the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am also of opinion that there are people in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland today who just cannot understand 
     <lb/>
     the terms of taxation and how they are going to 
     <lb/>
     be applied. You will remember that we have all 
     <lb/>
     been confused and bewildered. One person will 
     <lb/>
     tell you there is no taxation on a certain thing; 
     <lb/>
     another person will tell you there is taxation. Our 
     <lb/>
     people listening to the radio night after night are 
     <lb/>
     really confused over that issue, and I do not want 
     <lb/>
     to be a party to or in any way connected with 
     <lb/>
     anything that may lead them astray. I do not want 
     <lb/>
     the people to make a leap in the dark. This is a 
     <lb/>
     serious issue, and our people will want a long 
     <lb/>
     time to consider it before marking their vote. That 
     <lb/>
     is another reason why I am not prepared to sup<lb break="no"/>port the motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am not altogether opposed to confederation. 
     <lb/>
     I think it is a good thing. It is a new thing, and to 
     <lb/>
     us it may be a different way of life and we want 
     <lb/>
     to be careful of the path we trend and go slow 
     <lb/>
     before we mark our "x". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In closing I may say that I, too, was hurt in 
  

            <pb n="1434" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1434.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1434</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
         

     connection with the words used by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood just recently about the wealthy 
     <lb/>
     people. I am not one of these wealthy people. I 
     <lb/>
     know we have some wealthy people in this 
     <lb/>
     country, and they have done a good job and 
     <lb/>
     invested their money in many ways, giving many 
     <lb/>
     hundreds of people work, and I really feel hurt 
     <lb/>
     about that. I would like to say to Mr. Smallwood, 
     <lb/>
     "Let him that hath no sin cast the first stone." I 
     <lb/>
     am sorry, but I cannot support the motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> Mr. Chairman and gentlemen, in 
     <lb/>
     speaking to this motion, this question of federal 
     <lb/>
     union of Newfoundland with the Dominion of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, to say the least, Mr. Smallwood's ex<lb break="no"/>planation of the Black Books and the Grey Book 
     <lb/>
     have, so far as I am concerned, been very unsatis<lb break="no"/>factory. These Black Books do give a good 
     <lb/>
     general outline of the Dominion federal services, 
     <lb/>
     and also a description of Dominion federal ser<lb break="no"/>vices, and also a description of Dominion- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     provincial relations, but for one to appreciate 
     <lb/>
     properly these services and their application to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland as a province, the explanations of 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood have been worse than useless. 
     <lb/>
     Take, for example, the tax structure of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     what do we know about it now? What does the 
     <lb/>
     country know about it? What does Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood know about it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Some time ago, sir, I quoted some figures in 
     <lb/>
     respect to probable federal revenues which 
     <lb/>
     would be collected from the people of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland as a province. I had taken consid<lb break="no"/>erable time and trouble with this. I arrived at a 
     <lb/>
     figure, with the exception of the corporate and 
     <lb/>
     income tax, of over $10 million in excess of the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian estimate. Now this total was got by 
     <lb/>
     actually applying the Canadian taxes to our im<lb break="no"/>ports for the year 1946-47, and also by making a 
     <lb/>
     reasonable estimate of taxes on local production. 
     <lb/>
     This figure of $10 million is in my opinion con<lb break="no"/>servative. Mr. Smallwood, in his summing up of 
     <lb/>
     the debate in committee, showed agreement with 
     <lb/>
     one source of Canadian taxes, that is in the 
     <lb/>
     general sales tax, and when doing so he very 
     <lb/>
     conveniently used the Customs Blue Book for the 
     <lb/>
     year 1945-46 which showed imports of $9 mil<lb break="no"/>lion less than 1946-47. He also estimated taxable 
     <lb/>
     local production at only $5 million, which is 
     <lb/>
     absolutely absurd when it is realised that three 
     <lb/>
     items only of local manufacture amount to over 
     <lb/>
     $4 million in 1946-47. Now, sir, there has been 
    

            <cb/>
        

     much criticism and abuse directed at 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland's method of collecting taxes, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly the method of collecting taxes on im<lb break="no"/>ports. Of course it is not an ideal way. It rests 
     <lb/>
     heavily upon the wage earner, but until a better 
     <lb/>
     method is devised, this system will remain. It is, 
     <lb/>
     if I may say, inexpensive in operation consider<lb break="no"/>ing the scattered nature of our population when 
     <lb/>
     compared with methods used elsewhere. Of 
     <lb/>
     course, Mr. Chairman, the evils and iniquities of 
     <lb/>
     this kind of tax has been used by Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
     in his argument for confederation; so much so, 
     <lb/>
     that he apparently forgot all about the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     taxes. He used the old argument time and again, 
     <lb/>
     that of computing wholesalers' and retailers' 
     <lb/>
     profits on cost of goods plus duty. Is it possible 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Smallwood is so innocent that he thinks 
     <lb/>
     that under confederation the wage earner of New<lb break="no"/>foundland will have any relief from this? Let us 
     <lb/>
     consider for a moment the Canadian system of 
     <lb/>
     collecting taxes. The Canadian federal govern<lb break="no"/>ment imposes a series of taxes much worse in 
     <lb/>
     their application to the wage earner than we have 
     <lb/>
     in Newfoundland; they impose excise duties, ex<lb break="no"/>cise taxes, import taxes and the general sales tax, 
     <lb/>
     a multitude of taxes for which there seems to be 
     <lb/>
     no rhyme or reason. All of these taxes are in<lb break="no"/>direct, the import taxes are imposed on goods at 
     <lb/>
     the point of entry, excise duties, excise taxes and 
     <lb/>
     the general sales tax are imposed at the point of 
     <lb/>
     manufacture, and in their application to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland these taxes will be, in their effect 
     <lb/>
     on the wage earner, the same as our import taxes. 
     <lb/>
     The importer, the wholesaler and the retailer will 
     <lb/>
     make profits on all of these taxes. In this respect 
     <lb/>
     the position under federal union will remain un<lb break="no"/>changed — in fact, in my opinion, it will be 
     <lb/>
     worse. On many items of taxable goods in 
     <lb/>
     Canada there are two, three and sometimes four 
     <lb/>
     separate federal taxes before the goods reach the 
     <lb/>
     consumer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, it is the double and sometimes 
     <lb/>
     treble taxation which bears so heavily upon the 
     <lb/>
     wage earner, these are the taxes which dig down 
     <lb/>
     into the workingman's pocket. One or more of 
     <lb/>
     these taxes, sir, will be applied, with very few 
     <lb/>
     exceptions, to everything we use if this country 
     <lb/>
     enters federal union with Canada. I have com<lb break="no"/>puted the Canadian import taxes on a per capita 
     <lb/>
     basis, taking the average from the five year 
     <lb/>
     period ending in 1946. I have done the same in 
  

            <pb n="1435" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1435.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1435</fw>
        

     respect to excise duties, excise taxes and the 
     <lb/>
     general sales tax and I have got the following 
     <lb/>
     result: import taxes, $11.61 per head of popula<lb break="no"/>tion; excise duties $1l.67; excise and other taxes 
     <lb/>
     $18.02; sales tax $22.98. These taxes as applied 
     <lb/>
     to Newfoundland will result in a total taxation 
     <lb/>
     under these headings of $22,427,000. This figure 
     <lb/>
     is $2 million more than that which I had quoted 
     <lb/>
     before, and I am inclined to accept this latter 
     <lb/>
     figure, because I did not know when I examined 
     <lb/>
     them before as much as I do now of the tax 
     <lb/>
     structure of the federal government of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now let us consider personal income taxes. 
     <lb/>
     This is, I admit, a more difficult question. The 
     <lb/>
     only way by which I could arrive at any 
     <lb/>
     reasonable estimate in regard to income tax was 
     <lb/>
     to apply the Canadian income groups to similar 
     <lb/>
     income groups in this country. For the year 1945 
     <lb/>
     the average Canadian income tax in the income 
     <lb/>
     group earning less than $2,000 as applied to the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland taxpayer will amount to 
     <lb/>
     $386,138. The income groups earning between 
     <lb/>
     $2,000 and $3,000 will pay $620,527; between 
     <lb/>
     $3,000 and $5,000, $996,425; between $5,000 
     <lb/>
     and $10,000, $1,561,014; between $10,000 and 
     <lb/>
     $30,000, $2,003,625; over $30,000 the amount 
     <lb/>
     will be $1,239,120. A total of $6,806,849. These 
     <lb/>
     figures are based on the average tax collected in 
     <lb/>
     each income group on the estimated totals for the 
     <lb/>
     year 1945 and are taken from the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government official publication. Only 2.82% of 
     <lb/>
     our population are estimated to be income tax<lb break="no"/>payers for the year 1945, and this number will be 
     <lb/>
     considerably increased, probably doubled under 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian tax law. The exemptions will be 
     <lb/>
     reduced from $1,000 to $750 for single persons 
     <lb/>
     and from $2,000 to $1,500 for married taxpayers, 
     <lb/>
     and this will result, in my opinion, in increasing 
     <lb/>
     the total number of taxpayers in Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     to 18,000 persons. In concluding these remarks 
     <lb/>
     in respect to taxes I want to point out that if we 
     <lb/>
     took the total Canadian revenues from taxation 
     <lb/>
     for the year 1946, which amounted to $176.18 per 
     <lb/>
     head, and applied it to Newfoundland's popula<lb break="no"/>tion we get a figure of $56,377,600. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now sir, I want to make a few remarks about 
     <lb/>
     unemployment insurance. No doubt this in<lb break="no"/>surance plan has a lot to commend it; but sir, it 
     <lb/>
     will not be of much use to Newfoundland. The 
     <lb/>
     majority of Newfoundlanders are employed at 
     <lb/>
     work not covered by the Unemployment In<lb break="no"/>
       

            <cb/>

surance Act, although the Black Books state that 
     <lb/>
     lumbering, logging and stevedoring may be 
     <lb/>
     brought under the provisions of the Act within the 
     <lb/>
     next few months. Section 86 of the Act provides 
     <lb/>
     for the extension of the Act and also allows for 
     <lb/>
     the limiting of this extension to areas as 
     <lb/>
     prescribed by the Unemployment Commission as 
     <lb/>
     an insurance area; this does not mean that if the 
     <lb/>
     Act is extended to embrace all or any of the 
     <lb/>
     classifications of employment not now covered 
     <lb/>
     that these classifications would be extended to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. No, for example, stevedoring in 
     <lb/>
     the City of Halifax could be included and brought 
     <lb/>
     under the provisions of the Act and the cities of 
     <lb/>
     St. John's and Montreal could be left out. It 
     <lb/>
     depends upon the regularity of employment in 
     <lb/>
     any classification of work as to whether or not an 
     <lb/>
     area would be prescribed as an insurance area. It 
     <lb/>
     appears to me that if the Act were to be extended 
     <lb/>
     to cover most of the present exceptions that it 
     <lb/>
     would be of little value to us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now sir, what is the position of the Railway 
     <lb/>
     workers in respect to the terms? I agree, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Chairman, that the Railway workers will be of<lb break="no"/>fered corresponding employment with the CNR 
     <lb/>
     with all privileges and continuity of service ac<lb break="no"/>corded to the employees of the CNR. What does 
     <lb/>
     this mean? It means this — as the employees of 
     <lb/>
     both CNR and the Newfoundland Railway work 
     <lb/>
     under the provisions of signed working agree<lb break="no"/>ments, the continuity of service of both these 
     <lb/>
     railways are governed by the rules set forth in 
     <lb/>
     these agreements which are very similar in their 
     <lb/>
     scope. If, Mr. Chairman, the CNR should take 
     <lb/>
     over the Newfoundland Railway, then I say, if 
     <lb/>
     any time after that date, even one day after, it was 
     <lb/>
     decided to lay off any of the staff, the only thing 
     <lb/>
     necessary would be to give the required notice as 
     <lb/>
     set out in the working agreement covering the 
     <lb/>
     various classifications of workers, and 
     <lb/>
     employees would then be dispensed with in ac<lb break="no"/>cordance with the length of time they have been 
     <lb/>
     employed Required notice is sometimes as low 
     <lb/>
     as four days; others require up to a month. In any 
     <lb/>
     case, under the terms there is no guarantee of 
     <lb/>
     continuity of employment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, I want to make a few remarks 
     <lb/>
     in respect to railway pensions. In the first place 
     <lb/>
     these pensions are paid out of operating account, 
     <lb/>
     and this year this sum is estimated at $200,000. 
     <lb/>
     There is no provision in the terms in this regard, 
  

            <pb n="1436" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1436.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1436</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
       

     and according to a reply which I received in 
     <lb/>
     answer to a question, I gather that as there is no 
     <lb/>
     statute governing these pensions, and as railway 
     <lb/>
     pensions are a charge on operating account, these 
     <lb/>
     payments would not be a charge on New<lb break="no"/>foundland as a province. In any case, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood has not made any provision for it in 
     <lb/>
     his proposed budget. Under clause 17 of the terms 
     <lb/>
     it is definite, in my opinion, that the CNR and/or 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian government disclaim any respon<lb break="no"/>sibility for these payments. Therefore, sir, I must 
     <lb/>
     conclude that as from the date of union, those 
     <lb/>
     who are now retired and receiving pensions 
     <lb/>
     would be cut off; and all other employees, 3,000 
     <lb/>
     of them, would lose all the years of service which 
     <lb/>
     every one of them thought would be credited to 
     <lb/>
     them upon reaching retirement age — 3,000 
     <lb/>
     employees with about ten years average service 
     <lb/>
     each, 30,000 years of pensionable service gone 
     <lb/>
     up the creek. It may be argued that under any 
     <lb/>
     form of government pensions might become too 
     <lb/>
     expensive and therefore could be reduced or cut 
     <lb/>
     out; in my opinion, under confederation they 
     <lb/>
     would cease immediately; but under a form of 
     <lb/>
     government national in character, I believe an 
     <lb/>
     opportunity could be had of setting up a pension 
     <lb/>
     plan which would be contributory. In fact some 
     <lb/>
     steps have already been taken by the railway 
     <lb/>
     unions in this respect, a plan to which the 
     <lb/>
     employees could contribute and therefore have 
     <lb/>
     some assurance of a retiring allowance or pension 
     <lb/>
     when they become too old to work. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have little more to say, Mr. Chairman. In the 
     <lb/>
     field of agriculture, however, I think that our 
     <lb/>
     farmers are well aware of the implications of 
     <lb/>
     confederation and the effect that this form of 
     <lb/>
     government will have on their livelihood; they 
     <lb/>
     know much better than I do of the handicaps that 
     <lb/>
     this form of government would impose upon 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland's farm economy, and they will no 
     <lb/>
     doubt decide accordingly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In conclusion, I want to repeat that in my 
     <lb/>
     opinion if we federate, the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada will collect no less than $35 million a 
     <lb/>
     year in taxation from the Newfoundland people. 
     <lb/>
     With this in mind, and considering all other fac<lb break="no"/>tors involved, and realising what little real 
     <lb/>
     knowledge we have of this question, I cannot 
     <lb/>
     support the motion. I shall vote against it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> Before I speak on the motion before 
     <lb/>
     the Chair, I would like to refer to something Mr. 
    

            <cb/>
          

     Higgins said in his address. Mr, Higgins told us 
     <lb/>
     that the terms of confederation were a good basis; 
     <lb/>
     he told us that the terms were very good, but 
     <lb/>
     today, and only today, he found out he was in<lb break="no"/>competent to obtain such terms. Well, it is too bad 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Higgins did not find out his incompetency 
     <lb/>
     before we went to Ottawa, so that we could have 
     <lb/>
     had the opportunity of picking out a more com<lb break="no"/>petent man. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman, I believe the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland are going to take note of the way we 
     <lb/>
     vote on this motion now before us; and I think 
     <lb/>
     every one of us is on trial in the eyes of the people, 
     <lb/>
     They are going to judge us by the way we cast 
     <lb/>
     our votes on this resolution. There are those who 
     <lb/>
     will cast their votes against the motion because 
     <lb/>
     they do not like the form of government it men<lb break="no"/>tions. There are those who will let their own 
     <lb/>
     personal wishes come first, ahead of the public 
     <lb/>
     interest. Big men will show their bigness by 
     <lb/>
     voting for the motion, even though the motion 
     <lb/>
     recommends a form of government that they do 
     <lb/>
     not like. They will vote to give the people their 
     <lb/>
     chance to decide on this question. It is easy for a 
     <lb/>
     member of this Convention to vote in favour of a 
     <lb/>
     form of government he agrees with; but it takes 
     <lb/>
     a big man to vote in favour of a form of govern<lb break="no"/>ment that he disagrees with. When the vote is 
     <lb/>
     taken on the motion we will see how many big 
     <lb/>
     men we have here amongst us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I admit that it is fairly easy to think up excuses 
     <lb/>
     for voting against letting the people decide 
     <lb/>
     whether they want confederation or not. I could 
     <lb/>
     think up half a dozen excuses myself for not 
     <lb/>
     letting the people decide, and other members can 
     <lb/>
     also think up excuses. But excuses are one thing; 
     <lb/>
     reason is something else. I cannot think of one 
     <lb/>
     reason for voting against the motion, and I am 
     <lb/>
     still listening to hear any member give one real 
     <lb/>
     reason against the motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The motion itself is very plain and simple. It 
     <lb/>
     simply asks us to recommend that confederation 
     <lb/>
     be placed before the people for their decision, 
     <lb/>
     simply that and nothing more. It does not ask 
     <lb/>
     members to be in favour of confederation, but 
     <lb/>
     only to place it before the people, Even the 
     <lb/>
     strongest enemy of confederation can vote to let 
     <lb/>
     the people decide on the question. If I were an 
     <lb/>
     anticonfcderate I would stand up here and say 
     <lb/>
     something like this: "I don't like confederation. 
     <lb/>
     In the referendum I will vote against it. But I will 
    

            <pb n="1437" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1437.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="running">January 1948</fw>  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>     <fw type="num">1437</fw> 
  
            
  
     vote for the motion, for all the motion asks me to 
     <lb/>
     do is to be in favour of letting the people decide." 
     <lb/>
     If I were an anticonfederate, that is what I would 
     <lb/>
     say, and the people would respect me for saying 
     <lb/>
     it. Why, sir, even the anticonfederates amongst 
     <lb/>
     our people are expecting all the members of the 
     <lb/>
     Convention to vote in favour of this motion. 
     <lb/>
     They'll be ashamed of their anticonfederate 
     <lb/>
     leaders if they vote to deprive the people of their 
     <lb/>
     chance to decide the matter. That is the first point 
     <lb/>
     I wanted to make today, sir; that it is the duty of 
     <lb/>
     every member of the Convention to vote for this 
     <lb/>
     motion to submit the confederation question to 
     <lb/>
     the people themselves 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The second point I want to make is connected 
     <lb/>
     with a remark made by Mr. Banfield when he 
     <lb/>
     seconded the motion. Mr. Banfield said that the 
     <lb/>
     people of the southwest coast are all in favour of 
     <lb/>
     confederation. He said they are looking forward 
     <lb/>
     to referendum day to cast their votes for con<lb break="no"/>federation. Well, I have heard how strong the 
     <lb/>
     people are for confederation up on that great 
     <lb/>
     coast, and what Mr. Banfield said was no surprise 
     <lb/>
     to us. But Mr. Banfield must not run away with 
     <lb/>
     the idea that it is only on the southwest coast that 
     <lb/>
     there are confederates. I come from the west 
     <lb/>
     coast, the best coast in this country today. And I 
     <lb/>
     can tell you there are confederates on our coast 
     <lb/>
     too. Out on the west coast we have many good 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlanders who are just waiting for the 
     <lb/>
     chance to mark their "X's" for confederation with 
     <lb/>
     Canada. And I can tell you this: our west coast 
     <lb/>
     people are not going to be very pleased with any 
     <lb/>
     members who cast their votes against letting the 
     <lb/>
     people decide the question. We have a strong 
     <lb/>
     sense of fair play out on the west coast, sir. We 
     <lb/>
     believe in playing the game. We believe in giving 
     <lb/>
     the other fellow a chance. Live and let live. I 
     <lb/>
     won't go so far as to say that every man and 
     <lb/>
     woman on the west coast is in favour of con<lb break="no"/>federation, but I will say this: that even those who 
     <lb/>
     are against confederation are all in favour of 
     <lb/>
     letting the question be settled by <hi rendition="simple:italic">all</hi> the people in 
     <lb/>
     the referendum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To tell you the truth, Mr. Chairman, I cannot 
     <lb/>
     understand some men's line of thought. I know a 
     <lb/>
     certain district here on the Avalon Peninsula that 
     <lb/>
     is very strong for confederation. I do not know a 
     <lb/>
     great deal about the Avalon Peninsula, or the 
     <lb/>
     districts that make it up, but this one particular 
     <lb/>
     district I am thinking of, I happen to know very 
  

            <cb/>
         

     well; and I know they are very strong for con<lb break="no"/>federation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> It is not Carbonear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL2">Mr. Ballam</persName> And yet what do we find? We find 
     <lb/>
     the member for that very district standing up here 
     <lb/>
     and fighting tooth and nail against confederation, 
     <lb/>
     and fighting just as hard to keep confederation off 
     <lb/>
     the ballot in the referendum. He knows how his 
     <lb/>
     district feels. He knows all about the strong con<lb break="no"/>federation sentiment in his district, yet he seems 
     <lb/>
     to be willing to go right against his own people. 
     <lb/>
     I can't understand it. I won't condemn him, for it 
     <lb/>
     is a matter for his own conscience, butI must say 
     <lb/>
     it is more than I can understand. And I wonder 
     <lb/>
     how many other cases there are like that in this 
     <lb/>
     Convention?   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
    Mr. Chairman, I can see a great many good 
     <lb/>
     reasons why our country should become one of 
     <lb/>
     the provinces of Canada. I have given some <lb/> thought to the matter — I have tried to sort out 
     <lb/>
     my ideas on the subject. And let me say this first 
     <lb/>
     of all: I would be strongly opposed to confedera<lb break="no"/>tion if it meant that Canada was going to annex 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, if it meant that Canada was just 
     <lb/>
     going to take us over, body and bones. I do not 
     <lb/>
     want our country to be annexed or taken over by 
     <lb/>
     any country. If confederation meant that the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada would take us over and 
     <lb/>
     run us, then I for one would be opposed to con<lb break="no"/>federation. But confederation does not mean that 
     <lb/>
     at all. In fact, it means anything but that. Con<lb break="no"/>federation is a partnership. It means that New<lb break="no"/>foundland would become a province in the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian union. And even that does not state it 
     <lb/>
     clearly, Mr. Chairman, for Canada is not just a 
     <lb/>
     union of provinces. It is a federal union. I will 
     <lb/>
     explain what I mean. It so happens that I was the 
     <lb/>
     second man to become president of the New<lb break="no"/>foundland Federation of Labour. I was for years 
     <lb/>
     president of an important union in Comer Brook, 
     <lb/>
     and as such I played some part in forming the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland Federation of Labour. My union 
     <lb/>
     was only one of quite a number of unions in this 
     <lb/>
     country at that time. When the suggestion came 
     <lb/>
     up to form the federation, did it means that all 
     <lb/>
     those unions would be joined together to form 
     <lb/>
     one union? Is that what the Federation was, an 
     <lb/>
     amalgamation of all the individual unions? Did 
     <lb/>
     the Federation simply annex all those unions and 
     <lb/>
     form them into one union? No, that is not what 
     <lb/>
     happened at all. Every union kept its own rules 
   

            <pb n="1438" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1438.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1438</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
       

     and regulations. Every union went right on with 
     <lb/>
     its own officers, running its own affairs. But 
     <lb/>
     every union joined the Federation. The Federa<lb break="no"/>tion was a federal union of unions. There were 
     <lb/>
     certain matters and certain affairs that were too 
     <lb/>
     big for any one union to handle, and that is why 
     <lb/>
     the Federation was formed. Each union that 
     <lb/>
     linked up with the Federation held on to its own 
     <lb/>
     local autonomy and ran its own local affairs, but 
     <lb/>
     the Federation began to handle the things that 
     <lb/>
     were too big for any one union to run, and the 
     <lb/>
     Federation began to handle matters that were of 
     <lb/>
     common interest and concern to the individual 
     <lb/>
     unions 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And that's just how it is with the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     federal union. Each individual province goes 
     <lb/>
     right on handling its own purely local affairs, and 
     <lb/>
     the federal government takes over the manage<lb break="no"/>ment of the bigger things, such as the railway and 
     <lb/>
     veterans' affairs, and posts and telegraphs, and 
     <lb/>
     marine works and so forth. Each province elects 
     <lb/>
     its own government to run its own local affairs, 
     <lb/>
     and besides that elects so many members to the 
     <lb/>
     government of the whole federal union itself, that 
     <lb/>
     is, the federal government. No sir, confederation 
     <lb/>
     does not mean that Canada would take us over 
     <lb/>
     and run us. We would elect our own government 
     <lb/>
     every four or five years, and our own government 
     <lb/>
     would run us. At any rate, they would run us in 
     <lb/>
     certain things and the federal government would 
     <lb/>
     run us in other things. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A Nova Scotian is no less a Nova Scotian 
     <lb/>
     because he is also a Canadian. A Prince Edward 
     <lb/>
     Islander is no less a Prince Edward Islander be<lb break="no"/>cause he is a Canadian too. And a New<lb break="no"/>foundlander would be no less a Newfoundlander 
     <lb/>
     because he was also a Canadian. We are all 
     <lb/>
     Britishers, sir, but are we any the less New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders because we are Britishers? I am a 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlander, and proud of it; and if con<lb break="no"/>federation meant that I would have to become a 
     <lb/>
     Canadian and at the same time cease to be a 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlander, then I for one would be op<lb break="no"/>posed to confederation. We will always be New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders, and proud of it, even when we 
     <lb/>
     become Canadians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As I said here once before, that is one of the 
     <lb/>
     big things I like about confederation, that it will 
     <lb/>
     bring democracy back to us again. It will bring 
     <lb/>
     back democratic government. It will give us a 
     <lb/>
     voice in our own affairs again That is my first 
    

            <cb/>
   

     big point in favour of confederation. But sir, the 
     <lb/>
     biggest reason of all for confederation, as I see it, 
     <lb/>
     is that it will link us up with a great British nation. 
     <lb/>
     You would never guess it from some of the 
     <lb/>
     foolish things said about her in this Convention, 
     <lb/>
     but Canada happens to be the largest and richest 
     <lb/>
     nation in the British Commonwealth, next to 
     <lb/>
     Britain herself. I repeat that, Mr. Chairman: 
     <lb/>
     Canada is the largest and richest nation in the 
     <lb/>
     whole British Commonwealth, next to Britain 
     <lb/>
     herself. And as Mr. Ashboume remarked here, 
     <lb/>
     surely a system of government that works for 
     <lb/>
     12.5 million people will work just as well for 
     <lb/>
     12.75 million people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is only plain common sense to think that it 
     <lb/>
     would benefit this small country to throw in her 
     <lb/>
     lot with that great, wealthy British nation. We 
     <lb/>
     should never forget in this country that at the very 
     <lb/>
     time our country went broke, one of Canada's 
     <lb/>
     provinces went broke too. When Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     went broke in the early 1930s, the Province of 
     <lb/>
     Saskatchewan went broke. Where did we have to 
     <lb/>
     turn? To the old mother country. And thank God 
     <lb/>
     the mother country came to our rescue, because 
     <lb/>
     at that time she was able to But we had to give 
     <lb/>
     up our own government and come under the 
     <lb/>
     Commission system. Where did Saskatchewan 
     <lb/>
     turn? She turned to the federal government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada. Where else would she turn but to the 
     <lb/>
     government of the very union of which she was 
     <lb/>
     a member? She turned to the government of all 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and that government came to her rescue. 
     <lb/>
     But did she lose her own government? Did the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada take their government 
     <lb/>
     from them and put others over them? No, Sas<lb break="no"/>katchewan held on to her own government. 
     <lb/>
     Democracy remained in Saskatchewan. Self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     government remained. That's the difference, sir, 
     <lb/>
     when you are a province of Canada. You may run 
     <lb/>
     on hard times as a province, but you cannot go 
     <lb/>
     under. The government of the whole nation 
     <lb/>
     stands by you. And if we become a province of 
     <lb/>
     Canada with our own self-government, we will 
     <lb/>
     have a strong friend at our back in case we ever 
     <lb/>
     need one. That is something to think about, sir. 
     <lb/>
     For we must not get any foolish ideas into our 
     <lb/>
     heads that we will never need a friend. 
     <lb/>
     Everybody does. We know the kind of world we 
     <lb/>
     are living in. We know the uncertainties of this 
     <lb/>
     world, and the uncertainties of trade and finance. 
     <lb/>
     It is a big thing to know that you are lined up with 


            <pb n="1439" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1439.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1439</fw>
  

     someone bigger and stronger than yourself. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let us think on these things. Let us all in this 
     <lb/>
     Convention be big about this thing. Let us put 
     <lb/>
     aside pettiness and prejudice. Let us view it as 
     <lb/>
     statesmen. It is a very big issue and it calls for 
     <lb/>
     bigness of view. Instead of picking holes 
     <lb/>
     everywhere, let us try to see this thing impartially. 
     <lb/>
     Will confederation benefit the great majority of 
     <lb/>
     our people? Will it bring down the cost of living 
     <lb/>
     and raise the standard of our living? Will it give 
     <lb/>
     us a fairer system of taxation? Will it give the 
     <lb/>
     poorer man a better chance to live? Will it give 
     <lb/>
     our children a fairer chance in life? Will it 
     <lb/>
     strengthen our country? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Will it bring democracy and self-government 
     <lb/>
    back to us? I believe the answer is "yes" to all 
     <lb/>these questions, and it is with that belief that I 
     <lb/>must support this motion to put confederation 
     <lb/>before the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROBE2">Mr. Roberts</persName> Mr. Chairman, I wish to state that 
     <lb/>I will vote for the motion before the Chair. I feel 
     <lb/>in duty bound to do so, in View of the fact that 
     <lb/>many thousands of Newfoundlanders wish to 
     <lb/>vote for confederation. I wish also to state I hold 
     <lb/>no brief for the people of St. Barbe district, which 
     <lb/>I represent, as to how they will vote. They will do 
     <lb/>as they please. I have only one vote, and will do 
     <lb/>as I please with it. But I would like to tell all 
     <lb/>anticonfederates that if confederation does not go 
     <lb/>on the ballot paper, the people of the northwest 
     <lb/>coast will vote overwhelmingly for Commission 
     <lb/>of Government. The mention of responsible 
     <lb/>government stinks with them. After neglect by all 
     <lb/>responsible governments, and despite all the sen<lb break="no"/>timental poppycock that some of our so—called 
     <lb/>patriotic Newfoundlanders have been getting off 
     <lb/>their chests here the past few days, and despite all 
     <lb/>the taxations they have been hearing about, they 
     <lb/>know what to expect from responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment and they are willing to take a chance on 
     <lb/>confederation. You don't have to take my word 
     <lb/>for it, let any man who wishes to find out take a 
     <lb/>trip down that coast and talk about the glories of 
     <lb/>responsible government; butI warn him to have 
     <lb/>a plane standing by so as to make a quick 
     <lb/>getaway, especially if he should tell them they 
     <lb/>were disloyal or unpatriotic. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
   Mr. Chairman, a few days ago, a member of 
     <lb/>
     the Convention said to me, "If we enter in union, 
     <lb/>
     you will see scores of Canadian fishermen down 
     <lb/>
     on your coast fishing your lobsters." I may say to 
 

            <cb/>
   

     that member that the first lobster caught and 
     <lb/>
     packed for export on the northwest coast was 
     <lb/>
     done by Canadian fishermen who left the much 
     <lb/>
     abused, tax-ridden Maritime Provinces; thinking 
     <lb/>
     they were given a raw deal by their governments, 
     <lb/>
     they settled on our coasts. But within five years, 
     <lb/>
     after receiving a taste of our taxation and our low 
     <lb/>
     standard of living and backward facilities, they 
     <lb/>
     were glad enough to leave it, every one of them, 
     <lb/>
     and go back where they came from, taking with 
     <lb/>
     them scores of our northwest coast people, none 
     <lb/>
     of whom ever came back, only on vacation to 
     <lb/>
     visit their poor relatives and take more of them 
     <lb/>
     away. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Dozens of my relatives and friends, after vain<lb break="no"/>ly trying to make a living, have gathered together 
     <lb/>
     a bit of money with the help of their relatives 
     <lb/>
     abroad and travelled to Canada. Ask these people 
     <lb/>
     if they wish to come back to the living conditions 
     <lb/>
     they left, and they would surely think it quite a 
     <lb/>
     joke. My own mother, widowed in the early years 
     <lb/>
     of her marriage, left with three small children and 
     <lb/>
     little means of support, struggled for three or four 
     <lb/>
     years to keep her family together and maintain 
     <lb/>
     them; she had to give it up, give away her 
     <lb/>
     children, and on the advice of a relative in Canada 
     <lb/>
     went there and made a comfortable living. So I 
     <lb/>
     have a warm spot in my heart for the country 
     <lb/>
     which befriended my mother, above all other 
     <lb/>
     people on this earth. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We peeple on the west and northwest coasts 
     <lb/>
     have been in close contact with Canadians, both 
     <lb/>
     fishermen and financiers, for years and years, and 
     <lb/>
     have not found them the big bad wolves that the 
     <lb/>
     people in the interior and on the east coast seem 
     <lb/>
     to think they are. Surely, so many of our people 
     <lb/>
     would not stay in Canada if they were so tax-rid<lb break="no"/>den as some people try to make us believe they 
     <lb/>
     are. As I said before, the people of the west coast 
     <lb/>
     who have been in close contact with Canadians 
     <lb/>
     all their lives, must certainly regard the ravings 
     <lb/>
     that have been going on here about all thing 
     <lb/>
     Canadian as pure and simple stuff and nonsense. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I wish to touch briefly on two very much 
     <lb/>
     ridiculed subjects, namely family allowances and 
     <lb/>
     old age pensions. I have in mind a family not far 
     <lb/>
     from my home; a man with ten children and a sick 
     <lb/>
     wife. You can imagine, or can you, the awful 
     <lb/>
     struggle that man is having to make a living. I 
     <lb/>
     wonder would he scoff at a family allowance of 
     <lb/>
     $60 a month, would he worry about the dozens 
  

            <pb n="1440" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1440.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1440</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
         

     of taxes on a loaf of bread, if under confederation, 
     <lb/>
     he would get his flour for $12 a barrel, when he 
     <lb/>
     is paying $22 for it in Bonne Bay today? Would 
     <lb/>
     he worry about the hundreds of taxes on a pair of 
     <lb/>
     shoes, when under confederation he would be 
     <lb/>
     able to buy three pairs in the place of the two pairs 
     <lb/>
     he buys today? Boots and bread, sir, take a very 
     <lb/>
     large slice out of his budget. His fish he can get 
     <lb/>
     a scant half mile from his door, and his vegetables 
     <lb/>
     can be grown around his home. If he does pay 
     <lb/>
     property taxes, which he knows he is likely to 
     <lb/>
     pay, they will be small on his acre of land and his 
     <lb/>
     small unfinished, unfurnished home. He is 
     <lb/>
     paying plenty now, far more than his pocket can 
     <lb/>
     stand. He is not worrying either about the man 
     <lb/>
     who can afford to drive a motor car, own a fine 
     <lb/>
     house, he figures the man can well afford under 
     <lb/>
     confederation to pay his taxes and help pay some 
     <lb/>
     for him as well. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Old age pensions. I have in mind an old couple 
     <lb/>
     nearly 80 years of age each, living alone, getting 
     <lb/>
     very little help from relatives, trying to live on 
     <lb/>
     their old age pension. That man still has to go in 
     <lb/>
     the fishing boat to try and earn a few dollars to 
     <lb/>
     augment his pension. What a help it would be to 
     <lb/>
     receive $60 a month instead of the $10 they 
     <lb/>
     receive today. His property would not exceed 
     <lb/>
     $1,500, and even if it did exceed $2,000 and 
     <lb/>
     under Canadian rule the government did take it, 
     <lb/>
     would not they be entitled to it after his family 
     <lb/>
     had forsaken them and let the government look 
     <lb/>
     after them? I think they would have a perfect right 
     <lb/>
     to it, and I feel sure the old couple would think so 
     <lb/>
     too. The old age pensioners of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     need not worry about the government taking their 
     <lb/>
     property. Very few of them whom I have seen in 
     <lb/>
     the outports have property over $2,000, and if 
     <lb/>
     they have, they would not receive old age pen<lb break="no"/>sions. I have made out quite a number of applica<lb break="no"/>tions the past 20 years. I have a good idea of their 
     <lb/>
     property value. I am not going to touch on other 
     <lb/>
     taxations, this has been ably and thoroughly gone 
     <lb/>
     into by other speakers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There will, no doubt, be many changes and 
     <lb/>
     adjustments in the event of union, especially in 
     <lb/>
     the business world. But my thought about all that 
     <lb/>
     is, if our business men cannot adjust themselves 
     <lb/>
     to competition, they are not the men I take them 
     <lb/>
     to be. The proper thing to happen to them is to 
     <lb/>
     fold up. But don't worry, Water Street of St. 


     
            <cb/>
    

     John's, and all the little Water Streets of the 
     <lb/>
     outports, will be carrying on under confederation 
     <lb/>
     when I am drawing my old age pension. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And please don't let some people make you 
     <lb/>
     believe the only reason Canada wants New<lb break="no"/>foundland is to make a fortune out of us, and for 
     <lb/>
     the inhumane purpose of starving to death our 
     <lb/>
     300,000 people. That has not been the history of 
     <lb/>
     the democratic government of Canada. In my 
     <lb/>
     opinion Newfoundland has nothing to lose and 
     <lb/>
     very much to gain by closer contact with our 
     <lb/>
     neighbour, Canada, which fact will strengthen 
     <lb/>
     our bargaining power which members like to talk 
     <lb/>
     so much about. In union is strength..So let's hope 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlanders will remember that at the 
     <lb/>
     referendum. I will, by voting for confederation. 
     <lb/>
     
   </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I have had 
     <lb/>many of my statements taken and twisted; I have 
     <lb/>been frequently attacked, my motives questioned 
     <lb/>and my whole attitude subjected to such mis<lb break="no"/>representation and innuendo; and I have been 
     <lb/>called so many names — from Quisling to Judas 
     <lb/>Iscariot, from traitor to fool — that I suppose I 
     <lb/>would be justified if I were to take offence and 
     <lb/>become quite angry; but Lord bless you, sir, I do 
     <lb/>not. Instead, I take refuge in the words of the 
     <lb/>Psalmist:<ref target="#fn_03">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     And I am become a reproach to them; 
     <lb/>
     they saw me and they shaked their heads. 
     <lb/>
     Help me, O Lord, 
     <lb/>
     save me according to Thy mercy: 
     <lb/>
     And let them know that this is Thy hand; 
     <lb/>
     and that Thou, O Lord, hast done it. 
     <lb/>
     They will curse and Thou wilt bless; 
     <lb/>
     let them that rise up against me be 
     <lb/>
     confounded, but Thy servant shall rejoice. 
     <lb/>
     Let them that detract me be clothed 
     <lb/>
     with shame; 
     <lb/>
     let them be covered with their 
     <lb/>
     confusion as with double cloaks. 
     <lb/>
     I will give great thanks to the Lord with my 
     <lb/>
     mouth; 
     <lb/>
     and in the midst of many I will praise Him. 
     <lb/>
     Because he hath stood at the right hand of the 
     <lb/>
     poor, to save my soul from persecutors. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     I was greatly interested to see what Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin's reaction would be to my exposure of the 
     <lb/>
     shameful and scandalous profits cleaned up in 
     <lb/>
     this country by a handful of companies and con<lb break="no"/>cerns out of a handful of our people. To tell you 


<note xml:id="fn_03">[1] Mr. Smallwood quoted from Psalm 109, verses 25-31.</note> 
 



            <pb n="1441" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1441.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1441</fw>
      

     the truth, sir, I was expecting Major Cashin to 
     <lb/>
     come out and agree with me. He knows it was the 
     <lb/>
     stone sober truth. He knows that our people have 
     <lb/>
     been plundered and looted. I was glad to see that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Cranford agreed with me. He hates those 
     <lb/>
     monopolists. But Major Cashin actually 
     <lb/>
     defended those looters, he had kind words for 
     <lb/>
     them. He stated strongly that it was communistic 
     <lb/>
     to talk the way I did. It was not communistic to 
     <lb/>
     expose the profits made out of a handful of 
     <lb/>
     people. If anything is communistic or fascistic, it 
     <lb/>
     is the conduct of those who looted our people 
     <lb/>
     during the war. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Major Cashin said I used hard words. Perhaps 
     <lb/>
     I did. But what really matters is this: did I use true 
     <lb/>
     words? Were those profits made, or were they 
     <lb/>
     not? Was the Tax Assessor lying to us when he 
     <lb/>
     told us officially of that $15.5 million cleaned up 
     <lb/>
     in clear profits in just one short year? Are our 
     <lb/>
     people being plundered and looted, or are they 
     <lb/>
     not? That is the thing that matters. If they are, then 
     <lb/>
     no language is too hard to use to expose the fact. 
     <lb/>
     Sir, when you run up against a brutal fact like that 
     <lb/>
     it is no time for soft words, for pussy-footing, but 
     <lb/>
     for plain speaking. It was not I, Mr. Chairman, 
     <lb/>
     who said this, "There are too many middlemen 
     <lb/>
     and commission agents in Newfoundland who 
     <lb/>
     are really only parasites on the community." I did 
     <lb/>
     not say that, sir. It was our late Governor, Sir 
     <lb/>
     Humphrey Walwyn, in his farewell address to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. It was not I who said, "If I had 
     <lb/>
     my way I'd burn every local factory to the 
     <lb/>
     ground." I did not say that, sir. It was Mr. Cashin 
     <lb/>
     who said it, in this chamber. If my words were 
     <lb/>
     hard, sir, what would you call the words of 
     <lb/>
     Governor Walwyn and Mr. Cashin? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Major Cashin told us about the large profits — 
     <lb/>
     hundreds of millions, I think he said — made by 
     <lb/>
     29 corporations in Canada. Yes, I do not doubt 
     <lb/>
     that. But can he not see any difference in corpora<lb break="no"/>tions making large profits out of 12 million 
     <lb/>
     people, and making them out of our tiny handful 
     <lb/>
     of people in this country? As I said before, there 
     <lb/>
     may be room in Newfoundland for one mil<lb break="no"/>lionaire — there may be — but there certainly is 
     <lb/>
     not enough room for 21 millionaires. John D. 
     <lb/>
     Rockerfeller made billions of profits, and so did 
     <lb/>
     Henry Ford and Andrew Carnegie, but those mil<lb break="no"/>lionaires made their millions out of all the people 
     <lb/>
     of the world, not from a tiny handful of struggling 
     <lb/>
     people here in this little island. Men have become 
 

            <cb/>
          

     millionaires in Great Britain, France, and Canada 
     <lb/>
     and other lands, but it is a horse of a different 
     <lb/>
     colour when our tiny population is squeezed and 
     <lb/>
     looted to make millionaires. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Major Cashin says if we go into confederation, 
     <lb/>
     within three years our surplus will all be gone. 
     <lb/>
     No, it will not. It will not be gone within twice 
     <lb/>
     three years. But let me ask this question: if we do 
     <lb/>
     not go into confederation, how long will the 
     <lb/>
     surplus last? And especially, how long will it last 
     <lb/>
     if we should get the kind of government that the 
     <lb/>
     majority in this Convention want to get? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I was greatly amused by Major Cashin's 
     <lb/>
     repetition of his former exaggerated, extravagant 
     <lb/>
     and totally erroneous statement that under con<lb break="no"/>federation we would pay $80 million in taxes. He 
     <lb/>
     does not say how we would pay that amount. He 
     <lb/>
     won't condescend to tell us. He just makes this 
     <lb/>
     outrageous statement and apparently expects the 
     <lb/>
     faithful followers of his form of government to 
     <lb/>
     take it down, hook, line and sinker. The Canadian 
     <lb/>
     government itself says they will collect $20 mil<lb break="no"/>lion from us, and tells us in detail how they will 
     <lb/>
     do it. Major Cashin doesn't double it and make it 
     <lb/>
     $40 million. He does not treble it and make it $60 
     <lb/>
     million. No, he quadruples it and makes it $80 
     <lb/>
     million — exactly four times as much as the 
     <lb/>
     financial experts of the Canadian government 
     <lb/>
     estimate. It would not be so bad if only he gave 
     <lb/>
     us one single word of proof, just one little word. 
     <lb/>
     Is he quite sure it would not be $79 million or $81 
     <lb/>
     million? It wouldn't be $81.5 or $80.75 million 
     <lb/>
     now, would it? Or perhaps Major Cashin is $4 
     <lb/>
     million out, as he was in one of his budgets that 
     <lb/>
     he brought in here when he was Finance Minister. 
     <lb/>
     Now I remind you that the first time he spoke on 
     <lb/>
     the question, he quarrelled seriously and violent<lb break="no"/>ly with the Canadian government's estimate of 
     <lb/>
     $20 million a year. He said it was 20% out, that 
     <lb/>
     estimate, and drove it up to $24 million. That was 
     <lb/>
     the first time he spoke about it. The next time he 
     <lb/>
     spoke about it, he raised the ante, he put it at $32 
     <lb/>
     million. Then he spoke for the third time, and that 
     <lb/>
     time he raised it again, to $75 million. Now, in 
     <lb/>
     his latest speech, he has it up to $80 million. What 
     <lb/>
     is he doing, playing auction with himself? He has 
     <lb/>
     given us four different estimates — $24 million, 
     <lb/>
     $32 million, $75 million and $80 million. I 
     <lb/>
     daresay before the referendum rolls around he 
     <lb/>
     will have it up to $100 million. What's he trying 
     <lb/>
     to do, make the handful of souls in Newfoundland 
  

            <pb n="1442" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1442.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1442</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
   

     pay the whole cost of running the United Na<lb break="no"/>tions? I think we are just a little sick and weary 
     <lb/>
     of those fantastic guesses of Major Cashin. If he 
     <lb/>
     would only make up his mind as to which figure 
     <lb/>
     he means, we might be able to take him seriously. 
     <lb/>
     By the way, Mr. Chairman, the anticonfederates 
     <lb/>
     should really get together and do a little team<lb break="no"/>work sometimes, because all they have been 
     <lb/>
     doing is destroying each other's arguments. For 
     <lb/>
     instance, Mr. Hickman estimated that the provin<lb break="no"/>cial government would take $17 million a year in 
     <lb/>
     taxes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> $19 million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Hollett estimated $19 mil<lb break="no"/>lion and Major Cashin $19.2 million. In federal 
     <lb/>
     taxes, Major Cashin has given us all the estimates 
     <lb/>
     I have just mentioned, and tonight Mr. Fogwill 
     <lb/>
     gives us a brand new estimate of his own: $35 
     <lb/>
     million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> That is the right one. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> They should compare notes 
     <lb/>
     sometimes, and when they do, they will probably 
     <lb/>
     fall back on the Canadian govemment's official 
     <lb/>
     estimate of $20 million. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Major Cashin tells us that under confederation 
     <lb/>
     if the people want work they will have to get out 
     <lb/>
     of the country to get it. What he forgot to tell us 
     <lb/>
     is where the people will get work if we do not 
     <lb/>
     have confederation. We have not got confedera<lb break="no"/>tion now, but we have got 15,000-20,000 people 
     <lb/>
     on the dole. We have many hundreds of veterans 
     <lb/>
     of the late war out of work. Without confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, where will these men get jobs? Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin forgot to tell us. He tells us that with 
     <lb/>
     confederation they have to go out of the country 
     <lb/>
     to find jobs, but what our thousands of un<lb break="no"/>employed men would like to know is, where they 
     <lb/>
     are going to find jobs if we do not have con<lb break="no"/>federation? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Major Cashin tells us that confederation 
     <lb/>
     would be a threat to our educational system and 
     <lb/>
     that we would have non-denominational schools 
     <lb/>
     forced on us. Now, nothing said in this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion since the first day it opened is so untrue as 
     <lb/>
     that one. There is not one single word of truth in 
     <lb/>
     it, not a syllable, not even a letter of truth in it. It 
     <lb/>
     is completely and utterly false, definitely and 
     <lb/>
     finally false, wholly and undeniably false. I chal<lb break="no"/>lenge any man in Newfoundland — do you un<lb break="no"/>derstand, sir? — any man in Newfoundland to 
     <lb/>
     show that our school system, our denominational 
 

            <cb/>
         

     school system, is in the slightest danger from 
     <lb/>
     confederation. I challenge any man in this island 
     <lb/>
     to show that all existing rights of all denomina<lb break="no"/>tions are not absolutely safeguarded and 
     <lb/>
     protected under the terms of confederation. I say 
     <lb/>
     here and now that no denomination, not one 
     <lb/>
     denomination, has the slightest reason for uneasi<lb break="no"/>ness on this point. All existing rights have been 
     <lb/>
     fully guaranteed and protected, just exactly as 
     <lb/>
     they stand today. Any denomination that wishes 
     <lb/>
     to go right on with its own separate denomina<lb break="no"/>tional schools, paid for out of public funds, can 
     <lb/>
     do so under confederation, exactly as it can 
     <lb/>
     without confederation. Confederation will not 
     <lb/>
     make a particle of difference in our school sys<lb break="no"/>tem, and it is false and unworthy and mischievous 
     <lb/>
     to say it will, or even hint that it will. If there is 
     <lb/>
     in this island any denomination with separate 
     <lb/>
     school rights at the present time that fears that its 
     <lb/>
     rights would be put in danger, let that denomina<lb break="no"/>tion speak out, or take the proper steps, and it is 
     <lb/>
     the simplest and easiest thing in the world to 
     <lb/>
     copperfasten the matter. I know what I am talking 
     <lb/>
     about. I know it in great detail, in intimate detail. 
     <lb/>
     I know what I am talking about, sir, and there are 
     <lb/>
     others that know too. I say here and now that if 
     <lb/>
     any person of authority shows me that our 
     <lb/>
     denominational school system is in any danger 
     <lb/>
     whatsoever from confederation, I will drop all 
     <lb/>
     further support of confederation. I will go further, 
     <lb/>
     I will oppose confederation just as ardently as up 
     <lb/>
     to now I have supported it. So now, if Major 
     <lb/>
     Cashin wants me to oppose confederation, let 
     <lb/>
     him get busy and produce his proof. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Well, at last we know the truth about the 
     <lb/>
     matter of the government Savings Bank. It is 
     <lb/>
     exactly as I said all along. Full control over the 
     <lb/>
     Savings Bank will be held by our own govern<lb break="no"/>ment, exactly as it is today. The Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada has no law governing provincial savings 
     <lb/>
     banks, and it is left to the province itself, just as 
     <lb/>
     I said it would be. For a great many years the 
     <lb/>
     Province of Ontario has operated a savings bank, 
     <lb/>
     just as we have operated a savings bank, and the 
     <lb/>
     federal government has never interfered. Our 
     <lb/>
     Savings Bank will go right on as it is today. The 
     <lb/>
     provincial government will control it, and 
     <lb/>
     nobody else. The interest rates paid to depositors 
     <lb/>
     will be decided by our own government, just as 
     <lb/>
     they are now. Any profits made will go to our 
     <lb/>
     own government, just as they do now. But will 
  

            <pb n="1443" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1443.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1443</fw>
      

     these hard facts stop this loose talk about our 
     <lb/>
     Savings Bank? No, it will not. We will still hear 
     <lb/>
     the talk, all right, fast and loose. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett tells us that we are bound to have 
     <lb/>
     a certain percentage of our people who will be up 
     <lb/>
     against it, whatever form of government we may 
     <lb/>
     have. There is a lot of truth in that, and it is that 
     <lb/>
     very fact that makes me a confederate. I know 
     <lb/>
     exactly how these people will fare under every 
     <lb/>
     other kind of government, and I know how they 
     <lb/>
     will be treated, how their families will be treated 
     <lb/>
     under confederation. That is one of the things that 
     <lb/>
     makes me a confederate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett tells us that the Canadian and 
     <lb/>
     British governments are trying to get New<lb break="no"/>foundland into confederation, and that in this they 
     <lb/>
     are being aided and abetted by the Commission 
     <lb/>
     of Government. If Mr. Hollett can convince our 
     <lb/>
     people of that — that the British government and 
     <lb/>
     the Commission of Government would like New<lb break="no"/>foundland to go into confederation — then he 
     <lb/>
     will do more than any other hundred men to 
     <lb/>
     convince our people that confederation is the best 
     <lb/>
     thing for us. I hope Mr. Hollett and Major Cashin 
     <lb/>
     are right, I hope the British government and the 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government are both in favour of 
     <lb/>
     confederation. Our Newfoundland people are 
     <lb/>
     much more likely to be guided by the British 
     <lb/>
     government and by the Commission of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment than they are by Major Cashin and Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Hollett. If the British government and the Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government are for confederation, 
     <lb/>
     and Messrs. Cashin and Hollett are opposed to 
     <lb/>
     confederation, then I'll be happy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett asks why these microphones were 
     <lb/>
     put in this building. That is an easy one, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Chairman. The microphones were put here so that 
     <lb/>
     what we say could be broadcast to the people. 
     <lb/>
     What we say is broadcast so the people can hear 
     <lb/>
     it. They are given to hear it so that they can get a 
     <lb/>
     good idea of what they would he in for, if we got 
     <lb/>
     the kind of government that a majority of the 
     <lb/>
     members here want the country to have. Why, 
     <lb/>
     that fact alone makes the broadcasting of our 
     <lb/>
     proceedings worth at least a million dollars to our 
     <lb/>
     people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
    Mr. Vardy tells us that the large number of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland people who want to vote on the 
     <lb/>
     question of confederation in the referendum must 
     <lb/>
     be protected against themselves. They must be 
     <lb/>
     protected against themselves, Mr. Vardy says. 
 

            <cb/>
         

     But isn't that what Mr. Alderdice did, when he 
     <lb/>
     refused to let the people decide on the question 
     <lb/>
     of Commission of Government, although he had 
     <lb/>
     promised them that he would let them decide the 
     <lb/>
     question? He protected the people against them<lb break="no"/>selves, and now Mr. Vardy wants to protect the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland people against themselves. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Chairman, never in my life in this country have I 
     <lb/>
     heard the pure doctrine of Fascism and Nazism 
     <lb/>
     so neatly put as in that statement by Mr. Vardy. 
     <lb/>
     It is the very essence of dictatorship that a handful 
     <lb/>
     of men set out to protect the people against them<lb break="no"/>selves. Or is it the new democracy we have had 
     <lb/>
     preached at us in this Convention? This is the 
     <lb/>
     strangest doctrine I ever heard — that Mr. Vardy 
     <lb/>
     wants to protect the people against themselves. 
     <lb/>
     
   </p>

            <p>Then Mr. Vardy says, "The people did not 
     <lb/>authorise us to deal with this confederation mat<lb break="no"/>ter." This, from a member who on two occasions 
     <lb/>voted here in the Convention to send the delega<lb break="no"/>tion to Ottawa to get the terms of confederation! 
     <lb/>When Mr. Vardy voted twice to send for the fair 
     <lb/>and equitable basis of union, or the terms, what 
     <lb/>was in his mind? Did he mean the terms to be 
     <lb/>gotten and then thrown into the wastepaper bas<lb break="no"/>ket? Or did he mean them to be dealt with by us? 
     <lb/>The people, sir, did authorise us to deal with this 
     <lb/>confederation matter, for they authorised us as a 
     <lb/>Convention to deal with all forms of government 
     <lb/>that might be suitable to the people. To deal with 
     <lb/>them — not to decide them, but to let the people  
     <lb/>decide. But Mr. Vardy says to the people of 
     <lb/>Trinity North, "No, good people, I won't let you 
     <lb/>deal with this confederation matter. I will not let 
     <lb/>you vote on it. I am trying to protect you against 
     <lb/>yourselves." And sir, the people of Trinity North 
     <lb/>will remember those words at the right time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> And they will remember you, too. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I turn now to Mr. Higgins. Mr. 
     <lb/>Higgins touched on the question of divorce. This 
     <lb/>is an important matter and I am not going to waste 
     <lb/>time discussing any details. The position is very 
     <lb/>simple. We have no divorce law in New<lb break="no"/>foundland, and I hope we never shall. If we go 
     <lb/>into confederation we will take no divorce law in 
     <lb/>with us, for we have no divorce law. What about 
     <lb/>after we get in? Will we pass a divorce law then? 
     <lb/>No, we will not. Will Canada pass a law for 
     <lb/>Newfoundland, to grant divorce in New<lb break="no"/>foundland? No, sir, Canada will not. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada and the Parliament of Canada 


            <pb n="1444" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1444.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1444</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
         

     will not. They will pass no divorce law for New<lb break="no"/>foundland, and they will set up no divorce court 
     <lb/>
     in Newfoundland, unless — and here I ask you 
     <lb/>
     to pay special attention — unless we ask them to 
     <lb/>
     do it. And that, sir, we are not very likely to do, I 
     <lb/>
     am sure you will agree. The Parliament of 
     <lb/>
     Canada has power to set up a divorce court in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland if we go into confederation. Yes, 
     <lb/>
     that is a fact, they have the right and the power. 
     <lb/>
     But they will not use that right unless we ask them 
     <lb/>
     to do so. Never in all Canada's history has the 
     <lb/>
     Parliament of Canada used its power to set up a 
     <lb/>
     divorce court in a province unless and until that 
     <lb/>
     province asked for it. Ontario asked for it, and 
     <lb/>
     Prince Edward Island asked for it, and the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada did as they asked. If New<lb break="no"/>foundland should ever ask to have a divorce court 
     <lb/>
     set up, then the Parliament of Canada would do 
     <lb/>
     it, but not otherwise. Mr. Higgins, sir, is absolute<lb break="no"/>ly well aware of that fact, no one is better aware. 
     <lb/>
     It was Mr. Higgins himself, amongst others, who 
     <lb/>
     personally had some very special interviews on 
     <lb/>
     that very question in Ottawa. He was not the only 
     <lb/>
     one who had interviews, for Mr. Bradley also 
     <lb/>
     interviewed the very high personage whom Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Higgins interviewed — and I am not now refer<lb break="no"/>ring to anybody connected with the Government 
     <lb/>
     or Parliament of Canada, but someone much 
     <lb/>
     higher in a matter like this. There were various 
     <lb/>
     interviews, sir, and what did they all boil down 
     <lb/>
     to? They boiled down to this: that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada would be willing to put it in the 
     <lb/>
     very terms of union that never, for all time, would 
     <lb/>
     the Parliament, or could the Parliament of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, pass any law for divorce in Newfound<lb break="no"/>land or set up any divorce court in New<lb break="no"/>foundland, unless and until we ask for it 
     <lb/>
     ourselves, unless we ask them to do it. Let me 
     <lb/>
     make this very clear... To make the matter ab<lb break="no"/>solutely sure, and sure for all time, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada would be willing to put into the 
     <lb/>
     terms a special clause stripping from the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada any future right or power forever 
     <lb/>
     to do such a thing, unless and until we, as a 
     <lb/>
     country, should ask them to do it — and that is 
     <lb/>
     the thing that is extremely unlikely, that we 
     <lb/>
     would ask them. I say that the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada would include such a clause in the terms 
     <lb/>
     and that clause would become part of the British 
     <lb/>
     North America Act, if they were asked to place 
     <lb/>
     it there... There is only one condition. That con<lb break="no"/>
        

            <cb/>
    
dition is this, that the heads of our Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     churches, our Newfoundland denominations, ask 
     <lb/>
     to have it done and it will be done. That is all that 
     <lb/>
     is needed, sir, for the heads of the churches to 
     <lb/>
     signify their wish that such a clause be put in the 
     <lb/>
     terms. I am very sorry that this matter has been 
     <lb/>
     raised at all in this public fashion -it was not my 
     <lb/>
     doing. The matter had not been overlooked or 
     <lb/>
     neglected or ignored. Far from it. Steps have been 
     <lb/>
     taken to inform those most directly concerned 
     <lb/>
     with the facts as they stand. This was done even 
     <lb/>
     before we left Ottawa at all. And when I say steps, 
     <lb/>
     I mean eminently proper and dignified steps. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
    Mr. Higgins says that our Catholic fellow- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     citizens would not favour confederation unless 
     <lb/>
     some such clause was put in the terms, and in the 
     <lb/>
     BNA Act itself, making sure that divorce and 
     <lb/>
     divorce courts will not come to Newfoundland. I 
     <lb/>
     partly agree with him, and I add this further piece 
     <lb/>
     of information; that our Catholic citizens are not 
     <lb/>
     alone in that feeling. Others feel the same way 
     <lb/>
     about it, and have been informed fully of the 
     <lb/>
     situation. But I want it to be understood perfectly, 
     <lb/>
     that it only needs for the right people to say the 
     <lb/>
     word and that very clause will go into the terms. 
     <lb/>
     Why sir, the Prime Minister of Canada himself 
     <lb/>
     gave us a very broad hint in his letter to His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency. He said that in matters such as educa<lb break="no"/>tion — such as education -they would want to 
     <lb/>
     satisfy us. Sir, a clause was actually drafted and 
     <lb/>
     a copy of it was here in St. John's — is here in 
     <lb/>
     St. John's at this moment. It is wrong to drag this 
     <lb/>
     matter into this debate. Our people need not 
     <lb/>
     worry about this question of divorce. It is in good 
     <lb/>
     hands, far better, far abler, far more conscientious 
     <lb/>
     hands than either those of Mr. Higgins or me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Another point on Mr. Higgins, he wanted to 
     <lb/>
     know why so many Canadians were leaving 
     <lb/>
     Canada for the USA. The answer is simple. They 
     <lb/>
     are returning now at the rate of 11,000 a year; 
     <lb/>
     they cannot stand the high taxes in the United 
     <lb/>
     States. In addition to that 12,000 Americans set<lb break="no"/>tled in Canada in 1947. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There is only one point in Mr. Butt's speech 
     <lb/>
     to which I would refer. He said, "Let somebody 
     <lb/>
     better than we are decide this question." Exactly. 
     <lb/>
     The people of Newfoundland are better than we 
     <lb/>
     are. Let them decide. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Somebody referred to the Quebec provincial 
     <lb/>
     flag. Why sir, old loyal Nova Scotia has had her 
     <lb/>
     own provincial flag for over 200 years and they 


            <pb n="1445" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1445.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1445</fw>
        

     still fly the Union Jack. We have our own flag, 
     <lb/>
     the pink, white and green, in Newfoundland, and 
     <lb/>
     should we become a province that flag will still 
     <lb/>
     fly in Newfoundland as well as the Union Jack. 
     <lb/>
     It has for over 100 years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hickman solemnly assures us that he is 
     <lb/>
     not an anticonfederate. Well, he certainly did not 
     <lb/>
     go very far out of his way to praise confederation 
     <lb/>
     very much. He says the governments of two 
     <lb/>
     provinces have not yet accepted the tax agree<lb break="no"/>ment. That is true. But the governments of seven 
     <lb/>
     provinces have accepted. Mr. Hickman tells us 
     <lb/>
     that in 1946 one-third of Canada's revenue was 
     <lb/>
     raised from indirect taxes. That may be true. I will 
     <lb/>
     not vouch for one-third. In Newfoundland far 
     <lb/>
     over half the revenue was raised by indirect taxes. 
     <lb/>
     Quite a difference. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There are only two points in Mr. Crosbie's 
     <lb/>
     speech to which I will refer. He says there is a 
     <lb/>
     serious danger of our losing our fish markets in 
     <lb/>
     Europe; he quotes Mr. Gushue as having said so. 
     <lb/>
     But did Mr. Gushue say it was confederation that 
     <lb/>
     made this danger? No! The danger is here now, 
     <lb/>
     with no confederation. It is confederation that 
     <lb/>
     will help. Mr. Crosbie said that under confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, Canada will control our trade. There is not 
     <lb/>
     in all this country even one fish exporter who will 
     <lb/>
     not be able to go right on selling to the same 
     <lb/>
     markets just as long as he likes to do it. The 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government does not tell each exporter 
     <lb/>
     to what country or to what customer he may sell 
     <lb/>
     or export his fish or ore or paper or anything else. 
     <lb/>
     Canada has not become the third largest export<lb break="no"/>ing nation in the world by anything so stupid or 
     <lb/>
     silly as telling exporters where they may export. 
     <lb/>
     The other point is about the Fisheries Board, he 
     <lb/>
     is afraid it will have to go. But it won't have to 
     <lb/>
     go. It will stay and still serve our fishing industry, 
     <lb/>
     except that it will receive the extremely valuable 
     <lb/>
     assistance of the whole magnificent trade and 
     <lb/>
     commerce organization of the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Miller made an interesting point, he said 
     <lb/>
     he would not vote to recommend a form of 
     <lb/>
     government to go on the ballot that he would not 
     <lb/>
     vote for in the referendum itself. But that is what 
     <lb/>
     he did two or three days ago; he voted for Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government, but he was not prepared 
     <lb/>
     to vote for it himself. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I will not try to follow Mr. Fogwill's bewilder<lb break="no"/>ing flights of pure fancy, but he told us of the 


            <cb/>
  

     frightful taxes in Canada. According to him, they 
     <lb/>
     are away higher than here in Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     What I cannot understand is how the poor tax-rid<lb break="no"/>den Canadians manage to exist at all — why, in 
     <lb/>
     fact, they do not all flock down to Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     to escape taxation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There has been a lot of wonderful talk in this 
     <lb/>
     debate about the question of how the provincial 
     <lb/>
     government of Newfoundland would finance it<lb break="no"/>self under confederation, how it would balance 
     <lb/>
     its budget. Some members have magnified this, 
     <lb/>
     blown it up into gigantic proportions. They 
     <lb/>
     profess to regard it as a terrible and an insoluble 
     <lb/>
     problem, something they cannot see or under<lb break="no"/>stand. Let me give them a short simple lesson. 
     <lb/>
     The federal government will take $20 million 
     <lb/>
     from us in taxes each year. The provincial 
     <lb/>
     government will take another $5-6 million from 
     <lb/>
     us in taxes — call it $6 million. That is a total of 
     <lb/>
     $26 million altogether to be taken from us both 
     <lb/>
     governments — $26 million a year. What are we 
     <lb/>
     paying now? We are paying $40 million to our 
     <lb/>
     one government. $26 million taken from $40 
     <lb/>
     million is $14 million — $14 million less taxes 
     <lb/>
     than we are paying now. Under confederation we 
     <lb/>
     would save $14 million a year in taxes. "But", 
     <lb/>
     says someone, "what about the growth of our 
     <lb/>
     provincial government services? Aren't you 
     <lb/>
     going to make allowances for increase and im<lb break="no"/>provement of our provincial government services 
     <lb/>
     to the people?" "Haven't we got to expect in<lb break="no"/>creased education and health services to our 
     <lb/>
     people?", I am asked. Of course we have. There 
     <lb/>
     is no doubt about it. And why shouldn't we? We 
     <lb/>
     will save $14 million a year in taxes under con<lb break="no"/>federation. Is there anything to stop us from 
     <lb/>
     taking a million, or even two million of that $14 
     <lb/>
     million? Confederation will save $14 million a 
     <lb/>
     year in taxes for our people. It will put $ 14 million 
     <lb/>
     a year into their pockets, our peoples' pockets. 
     <lb/>
     All right, if we want to improve our provincial 
     <lb/>
     public services, let us take back a million or two 
     <lb/>
     of that $14 million and spend it on better educa<lb break="no"/>tion and health services for our people. We could 
     <lb/>
     do that, sir, and our people would not only have 
     <lb/>
     those better services, costing say another $2 mil<lb break="no"/>lion a year, but would still be $12 million a year 
     <lb/>
     better off in their pockets — and that's a million 
     <lb/>
     a month. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And then someone complains because I have 
     <lb/>
     not turned myself into the future provincial 
  

            <pb n="1446" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1446.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1446</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw>
         

     government of Newfoundland and decided ex<lb break="no"/>actly what taxes will be placed on our people to 
     <lb/>
     raise those few million dollars in provincial 
     <lb/>
     taxes. They demand that I shall here and now turn 
     <lb/>
     myself into the provincial treasurer or finance 
     <lb/>
     minister and name the taxes that will give the 
     <lb/>
     provincial government those few millions a year. 
     <lb/>
     If I refuse to oblige them they raise a great chatter 
     <lb/>
     about property taxes. Sir, are their imaginations 
     <lb/>
     so poverty-stricken that they can think of nothing 
     <lb/>
     but property taxes? Is their knowledge of taxation 
     <lb/>
     so microscopic that they cannot look around in 
     <lb/>
     this country and see how taxes can be raised by 
     <lb/>
     the government without putting taxes on the bits 
     <lb/>
     of property our people have? Let me remind you 
     <lb/>
     that we are today collecting certain taxes that we 
     <lb/>
     can and will go right on collecting under con<lb break="no"/>federation. Gasoline tax, motorcar and truck 
     <lb/>
     taxes, drivers' licenses, liquor profits, timber and 
     <lb/>
     mineral royalties, lumber royalties and a dozen 
     <lb/>
     other items that will bring us in close to $5 million 
     <lb/>
     a year. These are taxes that we have right now. 
     <lb/>
     These taxes can be kept on, and if we have any 
     <lb/>
     brains, any courage, any sense of fair play in us, 
     <lb/>
     we will collect the rest of the taxes we need out 
     <lb/>
     of the public domain of this country. And when 
     <lb/>
     I say that, I am not thinking only of the huge areas 
     <lb/>
     of holdings in this country that are tied up in the 
     <lb/>
     hands of persons living outside the country, but 
     <lb/>
     of actual operations going on right now. I am not 
     <lb/>
     going to tip my hand in this matter just now — 
     <lb/>
     the time will come for that — but when the right 
     <lb/>
     moment comes, I think I will be able to show 
     <lb/>
     some of our former finance ministers ways of 
     <lb/>
     getting taxes without grinding the faces of the 
     <lb/>
     poor. And that is a promise, if you want to take it 
     <lb/>
     that way, a promise or a threat, however you want 
     <lb/>
     to take it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir, the conduct of the members on this motion 
     <lb/>
     that will shortly be put to them for their vote will 
     <lb/>
     be watched closely by our people. It will be 
     <lb/>
     watched closely because by it our people will 
     <lb/>
     judge the fitness of all of us to play any future 
     <lb/>
     part in the public affairs of our country. We have 
     <lb/>
     heard many passionate declarations of belief in 
     <lb/>
     democracy. We have been told how very anxious 
     <lb/>
     certain members are that democracy should be 
     <lb/>
     restored to Newfoundland. We have been treated 
     <lb/>
     to many fierce denunciations of dictatorship and 
     <lb/>
     all its works. Well, we shall very soon see how 
     <lb/>
     sincere were those declarations. We shall soon 


            <cb/>
          

     see just how much they were meant. They have  
     <lb/>
     told us how much they love the people; how 
     <lb/>
     anxious they are that the people once again shall 
     <lb/>
     have control over their own country; how deter<lb break="no"/>mined they are that the people shall rule, and not 
     <lb/>
     dictators and outsiders. We shall soon see just 
     <lb/>
     how sincere these declarations really were. They 
     <lb/>
     have told us again and again that our people are 
     <lb/>
     well fitted to govern their country, that our people 
     <lb/>
     are educated and intelligent enough to make the 
     <lb/>
     proper decisions in the referendum, and that our 
     <lb/>
     people can be trusted to render the right verdict. 
     <lb/>
     We shall very soon see how much they meant 
     <lb/>
     those things. By their fruits ye shall know them; 
     <lb/>
     not by what they say, but by what they do; how 
     <lb/>
     they vote for this motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now with regard to those here who are not 
     <lb/>
     going to vote for this motion, it would be very 
     <lb/>
     interesting to know why they will not vote for it. 
     <lb/>
     After Mr. Bradley's speech they have lost com<lb break="no"/>pletely all the reasons they used to give for not 
     <lb/>
     placing confederation on the ballot. No longer 
     <lb/>
     can they say that the British government has 
     <lb/>
     broken its promise to restore responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment if the people request it. No longer can they 
     <lb/>
     say that Britain is not entitled to place on the 
     <lb/>
     ballot paper forms of government other than 
     <lb/>
     responsible government. No longer can they say 
     <lb/>
     that this National Convention cannot recommend 
     <lb/>
     other forms of government. No longer can they 
     <lb/>
     say that an elected government could get better 
     <lb/>
     terms. No longer can they say that we must have 
     <lb/>
     responsible government first. What have they left 
     <lb/>
     to say? What excuse can they think up now for 
     <lb/>
     cheating the people out of their right to decide the 
     <lb/>
     question of confederation in the referendum? Sir, 
     <lb/>
     there is only one reason they can have. They are 
     <lb/>
     afraid of confederation. They are afraid to put it 
     <lb/>
     on the ballot to let the people vote on it. They are 
     <lb/>
     afraid to let the people vote on it, for they fear 
     <lb/>
     that the people will vote for it. If they are not 
     <lb/>
     afraid, let them vote for this motion. I challenge 
     <lb/>
     them, I dare them to vote for this motion. I dare 
     <lb/>
     them to let the people decide on the question of 
     <lb/>
     confederation. We confederates were not afraid 
     <lb/>
     to let the people decide on responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment and Commission of Government. We voted 
     <lb/>
     to place those two forms on the ballot paper. If 
     <lb/>
     the anticonfederates are not afraid that the people 
     <lb/>
     will vote for confederation, let them vote now, 
     <lb/>
     tonight, to place confederation on the ballot in the 
   

            <pb n="1447" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1948-01-28-Midnight_Page_1447.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">January 1948</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">1447</fw>
       

     referendum. Come on, let them throw all their 
     <lb/>
     excuses out the window and vote for this motion. 
     <lb/>
     Let them show us that they are not afraid to let 
     <lb/>
     the people decide on confederation. I dare them 
     <lb/>
     to do it! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I move that the motion be now put, 
     <lb/>
     and in doing so I would like to make a brief 
     <lb/>
     explanation on one point which Mr. Smallwood 
     <lb/>
     brought up. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You have already spoken to the 
     <lb/>
     motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> By way of explanation? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> No, you can only speak once 
     <lb/>
     and you have already spoken. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> In that case, I move that the motion 
     <lb/>
     be now put. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Mr. Secretary, please ring the 
     <lb/>
     bells to make sure all members are in the cham<lb break="no"/>ber. The motion before the House is: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Be it resolved that the National Convention 
     <lb/>
     desires to recommend to His Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     Government in the United Kingdom that the 
     <lb/>
     following form of government be placed 
     <lb/>
     before the people of Newfoundland in the 
     <lb/>
     forthcoming national referendum, namely: 
     <lb/>
     Confederation with Canada upon the basis 
     <lb/>
     submitted to the National Convention on 
     <lb/>
     November 6, 1947, by the Prime Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     All members in favour of the motion, please to 
     <lb/>
     rise. 
     <lb/>
     </p>

            <p>For: Messrs. Banfield, MacDonald, 
     <lb/>Starkes, Spencer, Ballam, 
     <lb/>Figary, Vincent, Smallwood, 
     <lb/>Burry, McCarthy, Roberts, 
     <lb/>Keough, Newell and 
     <lb/>Ashbourne. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Recorded: Messrs. 
     <lb/>Hillier and Bradley. (16) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Against: Messrs. 
     <lb/>Goodridge, Watton, Hollett, 
     <lb/>Kennedy, Hannon, Fudge, 
     <lb/>Northcott, Penney, Reddy, 
     <lb/>Jackman, Dawe, Crummey, 
     <lb/>Miller, Ryan, Fowler, 
     <lb/>
    

            <cb/>
           

     Fogwill, Butt, MacCormack, 
     <lb/>
    Bailey, Vardy, Cranford, 
     <lb/>Harrington, Crosbie, Cashin, 
     <lb/>Hickman, Higgins. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Recorded: Messrs. 
     <lb/>Job, Jones and Brown. (29) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

    

            <p>
     The Chairman announced that he would deter<lb break="no"/>mine the personal preferences of members pur<lb break="no"/>suant to Rule 39 of the Rules of Procedure as 
     <lb/>
     between confederation with Canada on the basis 
     <lb/>
     of the proposals submitted to the Convention on 
     <lb/>
     November 6th, 1947, by the Prime Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and Commission of Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There appeared in favour of confederation on 
     <lb/>
     the said basis: Messrs. Banfield, McDonald, 
     <lb/>
     Starkes, Spencer, Ballam, Figary, Vincent, 
     <lb/>
     Smallwood, Barry, Roberts, Ashbourne, Bradley 
     <lb/>
     K.C. (recorded). 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Thereupon the Chairman announced that he 
     <lb/>
     would determine the personal preferences of 
     <lb/>
     members as between confederation with Canada 
     <lb/>
     on the said basis and responsible government as 
     <lb/>
     it existed in Newfoundland prior to its suspension 
     <lb/>
     in 1934. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There appeared in favour of confederation 
     <lb/>
     with Canada on the said basis: Messrs. Banfield, 
     <lb/>
     McDonald, Starkes, Spencer, Ballam, Figary, 
     <lb/>
     Vincent, Smallwood, Burry, Roberts, Ash<lb break="no"/>bourne, Bradley K.C. (recorded). 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Thereupon the Chairman announced that he 
     <lb/>
     would determine the personal preferences of 
     <lb/>
     members as between responsible government 
     <lb/>
     and both Commission of Government and con<lb break="no"/>federation with Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There appeared in favour of responsible 
     <lb/>
     government: Messrs. Goodridge, Watton, Hol<lb break="no"/>lett, Kennedy, Harmon, Fudge, Northcott, Pen<lb break="no"/>ney, Reddy, Jackman, Dawe, Crummey, Miller, 
     <lb/>
     Ryan, Fowler, Fogwill, Butt, McCormack, 
     <lb/>
     Bailey, Vardy, Cranford, Harrington, Crosbie, 
     <lb/>
     Cashin, Hickman, Higgins K.C., Brown 
     <lb/>
     (recorded). 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention adjourned at 5:30 am]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2017-09-20, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
            <!--<milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     January 29, 1948 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     [In private session, the Convention approved its 
     <lb/>
     final report as drafted by a committee chaired by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Cashin] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Mr. Chairman, I have three notices 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     of motion to give, and I trust the members, when 
     <lb/>
     they hear them, will be prepared to waive the 
     <lb/>
     usual notice and will agree to adopt them, or 
     <lb/>
     receive them, today. In accordance with the rules, 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>