<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNFNC_1947-03-10" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1947-03-10">10 March 1947</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNFNC">
          
               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
         <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

         <date when="1995"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="368"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0365.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0366.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0367.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0368.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-06-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-06-08">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0365">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0365.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0366">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0366.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0367">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0367.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0368">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0368.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="365" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0365.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">March 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">365</fw>
            
<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     March 10, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Orders of the day. Mr. Hollett to 
     <lb/>
     give notice that he will on tomorrow move the 
     <lb/>
     adoption of the following detailed statement of 
     <lb/>
     the questions to be submitted to His Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     Government in the United Kingdom as set out in 
     <lb/>
     the resolution of Mr. Hollett passed on February 
     <lb/>
     28, 1947....<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[At Mr. Hollett's request, the Convention agreed<lb/>to proceed with discussion of the motion immedi<lb break="no"/>ately]</hi>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Mr. Chairman, the motion before 
     <lb/>
     the House this afternoon arises out of the final 
     <lb/>
     paragraph in the motion made by me on the 28th 
     <lb/>
     day of February, 1947.... These matters had to be 
     <lb/>
     considered by the Steering Committee before 
     <lb/>
     being submitted to the Convention. We have had 
     <lb/>
     several meetings, and the result is the motion now 
     <lb/>
     before this House. I would like to draw attention 
     <lb/>
     to a slight difference between the matters raised 
     <lb/>
     by my previous motion and the one now before 
     <lb/>
     this House. The only items previously mentioned 
     <lb/>
     were: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     1. National debt; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. Military, naval and air bases in this 
     <lb/>
     country; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. Gander airport; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. Interest-free loans; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. Any matters relating to the future 
     <lb/>
     economic position of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>
     The motion today contains seven items, 
     <lb/>
     whereas the original motion contained only five: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p>
     1. The public debt; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. The interest-free loans; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. Development loans; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. The position arising out of the various 
     <lb/>
     base deals; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. The financing and control of New<lb break="no"/>foundland airports; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6. Trade and tariffs; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     7. Any other matters relative to New<lb break="no"/>foundland affairs which the delegation may 
     <lb/>
     raise and His Majesty's Government in the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom be willing to discuss. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Two sections have been added, namely 
     <lb/>
     development loans and trade and tariffs. There is 
     <lb/>
     no discrepancy between this motion today and 
     <lb/>
     the original motion, in that section five of the 
     <lb/>
     original motion reads: "Any matters relating to 
  

            <cb/>
         

     the future economic position of Newfoundland." 
     <lb/>....<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     This really is not my motion. It is the motion 
     <lb/>
     of the Steering Committee, but I was asked by the 
     <lb/>
     Chairman to bring the matter before you as it 
     <lb/>
     arose out of a motion which came before you on 
     <lb/>
     the 28th, and which was unanimously passed. 
     <lb/>
     May I refer you back again to the last clause of 
     <lb/>
     the original motion, which states "that the Steer<lb break="no"/>ing Committee be requested to prepare a detailed 
     <lb/>
     statement". I think the Committee will agree that 
     <lb/>
     it would have been very difficult to make such a 
     <lb/>
     detailed statement.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I feel, and I think the Steering Committee 
     <lb/>
     agrees, that one reason why we did not detail 
     <lb/>
     these various headings is probably this: that there 
     <lb/>
     are questions in these various headings here 
     <lb/>
     which concern only this Convention and His 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's Government in England. At the mo<lb break="no"/>ment they concern no other country. They do, I 
     <lb/>
     grant you, concern the people of this country, 
     <lb/>
     whom we represent, but I am quite sure that the 
     <lb/>
     people of this country do not want us to disclose 
     <lb/>
     to the world at large the various questions that 
     <lb/>
     will have to be asked under the various headings 
     <lb/>
     in the motion before you. There will be pertinent 
     <lb/>
     questions asked His Majesty's Government by 
     <lb/>
     any delegation that may proceed from here and 
     <lb/>
     I am sure that every member will agree that the 
     <lb/>
     very questions which we are to put to His 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's Government should not be public to 
     <lb/>
     the world at large at the present time. The answers 
     <lb/>
     to these questions which the delegation will bring 
     <lb/>
     back will, in due course, be published to the 
     <lb/>
     people of this country.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I make these explanations so that you may not 
     <lb/>
     be under any misapprehension, and think that the 
     <lb/>
     Steering Committee, or myself, in any way at<lb break="no"/>tempted to keep from you the detailed questions 
     <lb/>
     which are mentioned in the original motion, and 
     <lb/>
     which, as I may point out to you, arise out of the 
     <lb/>
     report of the committee which interviewed the 
     <lb/>
     Commission of Government here in New<lb break="no"/>foundland.<ref target="#fn_02">[2]</ref> I hope and trust that you will take that 
     <lb/>
     explanation in good faith. If there are any ques<lb break="no"/>tions which you would like to present to us you 
     <lb/>
     will have an opportunity now. Mr. Chairman, I 
     <lb/>
     would like to move that these questions be sub<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_01">[1] Above, p. 337.</note>

<note xml:id="fn_02">[2] Volume II:446. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
       

   <pb n="366" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0366.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">366</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">March 1947</fw>
    

     mitted to this house for their approval. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FUDG1">Mr. Fudge</persName> I second that motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It has been moved and seconded 
     <lb/>
     that the motion by Mr. Hollett be adopted. It has 
     <lb/>
     been seconded by Mr. Fudge. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> Question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Are you ready for the question? 
     <lb/>
      </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> I am afraid I can't accept Mr. 
     <lb/>Hollett's explanation. This motion distinctly 
     <lb/>gave permission to the Steering Committee to 
     <lb/>prepare a detailed statement of the questions to 
     <lb/>be submitted to His Majesty's Government. Here 
     <lb/>we have a report practically the same as the 
     <lb/>motion, without any other explanation than that 
     <lb/>which was included in the motion itself. If there 
     <lb/>is an explanation I am afraid I can't accept it. The 
     <lb/>point is, if we are to appoint a delegation to go to 
     <lb/>the United Kingdom, is not this Convention and 
     <lb/>the people of the country entitled to know just 
     <lb/>what the delegation is going for? They are going 
     <lb/>over to consult the home government on the 
     <lb/>public debt. Now the public debt includes quite a 
     <lb/>number of questions. Are you going to the old 
     <lb/>country to say that we would like to have this 
     <lb/>public debt cancelled? All sorts of questions arise 
     <lb/>out of that. I am disappointed that the Steering 
     <lb/>Committee did not go into the questions raised in 
     <lb/>the original motion, and give us some informa<lb break="no"/>tion as to what they are about to do. It looks as if 
     <lb/>the Steering Committee are asking us to appoint 
     <lb/>a delegation of six and practically give them a 
     <lb/>blank cheque. I think the Convention is entitled 
     <lb/>to know at least the main questions in regard to 
     <lb/>the public debt, or the interest-free loans, or the 
     <lb/>development loans, and the various base deals. Is 
     <lb/>there any information to give this Convention? I 
     <lb/>am very disappointed in this report. They have 
     <lb/>had somewhere around ten days to discuss this, 
     <lb/>and I think we should have the information 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEWE1">Mr. Newell</persName> I support the stand taken by Mr. 
     <lb/>MacDonald. I can appreciate the reticence of the 
     <lb/>Steering Committee to broadcast to the world at 
     <lb/>large questions which they do not want everyone 
     <lb/>to know about, but there are a great many ques<lb break="no"/>tions in connection with some of these items that 
     <lb/>have already been talked about so much, and 
     <lb/>broadcast to the world so often, that if the world 
     <lb/>has chosen to listen, it must by now know as 
     <lb/>much about these things as we do. However, the 
     <lb/>main criticism I have is this: if this were a report 
     <lb/>back to this Convention from the Steering Com<lb break="no"/>
        

            <cb/>
          mittee listing the various headings for the discus<lb break="no"/>sion with the Dominions Office, and it were to go 
     <lb/>
     no further than that, and we were to accept it for 
     <lb/>
     further preparation ofa brief, I think I should be 
     <lb/>
     prepared to accept it; but I wonder what sort of 
     <lb/>
     reception we would get from the Dominions Of<lb break="no"/>fice if we forwarded a communication stating that 
     <lb/>
     we should like to discuss the public debt, inter<lb break="no"/>est-free loans, development loans, etc. One of the 
     <lb/>
     members from Grand Falls said that a delegation 
     <lb/>
     going to England will have to be briefed. Of 
     <lb/>
     course it will. Presumably the delegation meeting 
     <lb/>
     us on the other side will also have to be briefed. 
     <lb/>
     ldon't imagine they would turn over the Cabinet 
     <lb/>
     to us for a week or ten days. It is only reasonable 
     <lb/>
     to suppose that we should know more details 
     <lb/>
     about the things they are to discuss. I wish to 
     <lb/>
     register my disappointment with this report. 
     <lb/>
    </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:KEOU1">Mr. Keough</persName> Mr. Chairman, I thoroughly agree 
     <lb/>with what Mr. MacDonald and Mr. Newell have 
     <lb/>said. This thing here is a hopelessly inadequate 
     <lb/>briefing. As far as I am concerned the leading 
     <lb/>question I want to see asked, the leading question 
     <lb/>as far as Newfoundlanders are concerned is this: 
     <lb/>is the British government prepared to entertain 
     <lb/>the idea of a return of Commission of Govern<lb break="yes"/>ment as it is now, or a modification of it, if a 
     <lb/>number of people in Newfoundland express a 
     <lb/>desire to have it retained? I have no guarantee that 
     <lb/>this question is going to be asked. I want the 
     <lb/>delegation to be able to answer "Yes" or "No" to 
     <lb/>that question, and under what circumstances. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I would like to draw the atten<lb break="no"/>tion of members to the fact that you have to read 
     <lb/>this detailed statement of matters to be discussed 
     <lb/>with the British government with the resolution 
     <lb/>itself. Is there any further discussion? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> Mr. Chairman, I hope it is not getting 
     <lb/>
     fashionable, but I really want to offer my word of 
     <lb/>
     dissatisfaction with the report too. After eight or 
     <lb/>
     ten days of the Steering Committee working on 
     <lb/>
     a report, sent out expressly to bring us back a 
     <lb/>
     detailed report, they come back with a curtailed 
     <lb/>
     report. Practically the only change in it is when 
     <lb/>
     they break up one clause and make two out of it, 
     <lb/>
     and the two clauses have less scope than the first 
     <lb/>
     one, and that particular clause was a very impor<lb break="no"/>tant one as well. The whole thing, as I see it, is 
     <lb/>
     the consummation of all the findings of the Con<lb break="no"/>vention. I don't agree with Mr. Hollett when he 
     <lb/>
     says that those who will proceed to England will 


            <pb n="367" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0367.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">March 1947</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">367</fw>
      

     have to enter into a study period. We entered into 
     <lb/>
     that last September. 
     <lb/>
    </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I did not say that, Mr. Miller. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> Well you did, Mr. Hollett, and I 
     <lb/>think it is about time we got it over and not spend 
     <lb/>any further time in study on the matter. In 
     <lb/>presenting this report today without the least bit 
     <lb/>of information, I can only say that I can't think so 
     <lb/>highly of the Steering Committee. It is as well to 
     <lb/>be frank. It does not appear that our opinion on 
     <lb/>this thing is worth anything. As members, must 
     <lb/>look at it in this way: we know the Steering 
     <lb/>Committee has met several times and what did 
     <lb/>they do? Bring back the same thing as they went 
     <lb/>out with. As far as I can see they threw a smoke<lb break="no"/>screen around the whole thing. I don't think this 
     <lb/>should go through this afternoon. I think we 
     <lb/>would be very foolish to make a snap judgement. 
     <lb/>As I see it the thing is not even plain. "Interest- 
     <lb break="yes"/>free loans" — what loans, those that we are going 
     <lb/>to look for in the future free of interest, or loans 
     <lb/>in the past? "Development loans" — what do we 
     <lb/>want them for? If we have no particular thing in 
     <lb/>mind we don't want it. Surely we are not going 
     <lb/>to go out and ask the world to support us. "The 
     <lb/>position arising out of the base deals." What can 
     <lb/>we gather out of that? Perhaps something, per<lb break="no"/>haps nothing. I would like to ask if there is a 
     <lb/>supplementary lease being applied for. I don't 
     <lb/>think I would get an answer to that, because I 
     <lb/>don't think the information is up to date. I don't 
     <lb/>think we entered into the financing of any airport 
     <lb/>except Gander, and I don't think the British 
     <lb/>government is in a position to make a statement 
     <lb/>on that even now. I don't intend to elaborate, I 
     <lb/>think the Steering Committee should have done 
     <lb/>that. The Steering Committee has presented this 
     <lb/>with the attitude of "Here's something, and it will 
     <lb/>go across without a word." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I don't intend to 
     <lb/>delay the House on this, but I think perhaps the 
     <lb/>key to the whole thing lies in a remark you made 
     <lb/>a moment ago yourself. This list has got to be read 
     <lb/>and considered in the light of Mr. Hollett's mo<lb break="no"/>tion of a week ago. That motion said that this 
     <lb/>House desired to send a delegation to the United 
     <lb/>Kingdom for the purpose of discussing what pos<lb break="no"/>sible fiscal and financial relationships there were 
     <lb/>to be in the future between Britain and ourselves, 
     <lb/>under: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     1. Commission government (if we con<lb break="no"/>
      

            <cb/>
      
tinued under Commission government); 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. Under responsible govemment, if we 
     <lb/>
    went back to that, or 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     3. Under some other form of government. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p></quote>


            <p>We want to send a delegation over to find out 
     <lb/>  what relationships, financial relationships, might 
     <lb/>exist under these different forms of government. 
     <lb/>The same resolution went on to say that a detailed 
     <lb/>list of the points that the delegation would take 
     <lb/>up with the British government should be drawn 
     <lb/>up by the Steering Committee and brought into 
     <lb/>the Convention for confirmation. This is the 
     <lb/>detailed list. First, the public debt. Someone 
     <lb/>wants to know what were they trying to find out 
     <lb/>about that. This surely, that at the moment and 
     <lb/>since 1934 the British government is guaran<lb break="no"/>teeing our public debt, the principal and the in<lb break="no"/>terest. Now the people of Newfoundland, before 
     <lb/>they vote in the referendum, surely need to know 
     <lb/>just what the position is and will be in regard to 
     <lb/>the public debt. Britain is now behind the debt. If 
     <lb/>we go back to responsible government will 
     <lb/>Britain be behind our public debt as to principal 
     <lb/>and interest? If we continue under Commission 
     <lb/>government, will Great Britain be behind the 
     <lb/>public debt? We do not know. Undoubtedly the 
     <lb/>delegation retuming from London will know and 
     <lb/>will pass the information on to the Convention, 
     <lb/>and through the Convention to the people of 
     <lb/>Newfoundland. That is all there would be about 
     <lb/>the public debt.... The interest-free loans, that can 
     <lb/>only refer to one thing, the loans made to Great 
     <lb/>Britain in the last four or five years. They are over 
     <lb/>there in England now, not paying us any interest, 
     <lb/>what will happen to them? We know that there is 
     <lb/>a terrible dollar situation. If they cannot pay the 
     <lb/>loan in dollars, in what way will we get it back? 
     <lb/>Development loans. Since Commission of 
     <lb/>Government, Great Britain has made loans for 
     <lb/>development purposes. What is the position in 
     <lb/>regard to that? It may be that Britain cannot make 
     <lb/>any more loans, but the population of New<lb break="no"/>foundland has got to know. With regard to the 
     <lb/>position arising out of the base deals. If there are 
     <lb/>some we are not concerned over, there is no harm 
     <lb/>in getting the details anyhow. But about control 
     <lb/>over Gander, let us have the story. There is no 
     <lb/>need to go into details under the different head<lb break="no"/>ings. I do not care what the Convention does, if 
     <lb/>they wish they can make the list ten times longer, 
     <lb/>but to my mind, the ground is covered. I believe 
  

            <pb n="368" facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1947-03-10_Page_0368.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">368</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">March 1947</fw>
      

     the delegation will bring back the answers to all 
     <lb/>
     the points under the different headings and we 
     <lb/>
     will have a complete story. Of that I have no 
     <lb/>
     doubt. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIGA1">Mr. Figary</persName> Are we in a position to know 
     <lb/>
     whether the Dominions Office will receive a 
     <lb/>
     delegation? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> We will not know until the re<lb break="no"/>quest goes through. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAWE1">Mr. Dawe</persName> One of the most important things is 
     <lb/>
     trade; another is tariffs. What are we going to 
     <lb/>
     develop? Where will we get the machinery? 
     <lb/>
     Whatever form of government we have, men 
     <lb/>
     must work to live. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOGW1">Mr. Fogwill</persName> The Steering Committee was re<lb break="no"/>quested to bring in a detailed statement. The other 
     <lb/>
     committees which brought in reports, brought in 
     <lb/>
     details. I agree with the other speakers who object 
     <lb/>
     to this report and I wish to register that objection. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIGG1">Mr. Higgins</persName> I move the adjournment until the 
     <lb/>
     call of the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HICK1">Mr. Hickman</persName> I second that motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> Before we go on to the adjournment, 
     <lb/>
     there is one matter I would like to have your 
     <lb/>
     ruling on. What manner will the Convention take 
     <lb/>
     in its ending? In what way will the findings of the 
     <lb/>
     different members or the different committees be 
     <lb/>
     presented. In what way will the vote be taken? 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> I rise to a point of order. There is a 
     <lb/>motion before the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Under the circumstances, it is 
     <lb/>
     always usual to allow a member to ask for infor<lb break="no"/>mation, even on a motion to adjourn. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> Ihave heard it put this way. After the 
     <lb/>
     information is all concluded, some member rises 
     <lb/>
     and proposes that Commission of Government 
     <lb/>
     must go on the referendum, and if it passes in the 
 
            <cb/>
        

     House it goes on the referendum, provided the 
     <lb/>
     Dominions Office is willing. Someone else 
     <lb/>
     proposes responsible government, and a third 
     <lb/>
     party proposes confederation. These three are 
     <lb/>
     placed on the referendum, the Convention is over 
     <lb/>
     and we go home. I would like to be clear on what 
     <lb/>
     the ending of the Convention would be like. I 
     <lb/>
     think now is the opportune time to have the 
     <lb/>
     question taken care of. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> In reply to your enquiry, I am 
     <lb/>
     not in a position at the moment to tell you what 
     <lb/>
     resolutions may be introduced on the questions 
     <lb/>
     of what possible forms of government are to be 
     <lb/>
     placed on the ballot. It may be one, it may be two 
     <lb/>
     or three, but it is impossible for me to tell you 
     <lb/>
     that. That really lies in the hands of the 44 men 
     <lb/>
     (or 43 men now, unfortunately) who sit on the 
     <lb/>
     benches. It is in your own hands. The only thing 
     <lb/>
     I can say, which may help you somewhat, is that 
     <lb/>
     the Convention dies when its final recommenda<lb break="no"/>tion has been sent to the British government; it 
     <lb/>
     has no further function after that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> I rise to a point of privilege. In 
     <lb/>
     connection with the recent talk on the delegation 
     <lb/>
     to Ottawa, there is an impression gone abroad 
     <lb/>
     that two of my authorities whom I quoted in my 
     <lb/>
     talk, had difference of opinion. I would like to 
     <lb/>
     correct that. i chose to disagree with Professor 
     <lb/>
     Wheare. l quoted from Professor Fraser who 
     <lb/>
     dealt with the political wisdom of this country 
     <lb/>
     going into confederation with Canada. I did not 
     <lb/>
     imply that there was difference of opinion be<lb break="no"/>tween Professor Wheare and Professor Fraser. I 
     <lb/>
     disagreed with the one and agreed with the other. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You fear you left the impression 
     <lb/>they disagreed on the law, whereas the disagree<lb break="no"/>ment was perhaps on the facts. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention adjourned] </hi>
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<!-- GL, 2017-06-13, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

           <!-- <p>
     March 19, 1947 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     [The Secretary read the following communica<lb break="no"/>tion] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Right Honourable the Secretary of 
     <lb/>
     State for Dominion Affairs has informed His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency the Governor in Commission that 
     <lb/>
     he will be glad to receive a delegation of the 
     <lb/>
     Convention consisting, as proposed, of its 
     <lb/>
     Chairman and six of its members, in order to 
     <lb/>
     provide them with an opportunity for raising 
     <lb/>
     certain questions with the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     Government on behalf of the Convention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     As a convenient date, Tuesday, April 29, 
     <lb/>
     and the following days is suggested. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Regarding the subjects set out in the 
     <lb/>
     resolution on which the delegation wish to 
     <lb/>
     seek information, the Secretary of State 
     <lb/>
     would be glad if the precise questions which 
     <lb/>
     the delegation propose to ask under these 
     <lb/>
     heads can be formulated and forwarded to 
     <lb/>
     him at the earliest possible date in order to 
     <lb/>
     allow time for them to be fully considered 
     <lb/>
     before the meeting with the delegation take 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>