<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-10-10"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-10-10">10 October 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
     
         
           <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

           <date when="1995"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="68" to="75"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0068.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0069.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0070.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0071.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0072.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0073.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0074.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0075.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-16">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-02-16">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
             <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-04">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0068">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0068.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0069">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0069.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0070">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0070.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0071">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0071.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0072">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0072.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0073">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0073.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0074">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0074.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0075">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0075.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="68"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0068.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">68</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
            
<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     October 10, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Before we proceed with
                                          the or<lb break="no"/>ders of the day, I regret to say
                                          that Mr. K.M. <lb/> Brown has had to return to his home on
                                          his <lb/> doctor's orders and will be away for perhaps
                                          <lb/> another week. We do hope he will have a speedy <lb/>
                                          recovery. I also regret to say that Mr. Fudge has <lb/>
                                          had bad news to the effect that his daughter is <lb/> very
                                          ill at home and he has had to return to Corner <lb/>
                                          <cb/> Brook. I received a telegram from him this after<lb
                                                 break="no"/>noon that his daughter's condition was
                                          improved <lb/> and that he hoped to return to the city by
                                          next <lb/> Sunday's express. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     I have also to inform you that Messrs. Job and 
     <lb/>
     Butt have been added to the Information Com<lb break="no"/>mittee; and that Messrs. Job, Butt and Hickman 
     <lb/>
     have been added to the Steering Committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">

          
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Fisheries Committee — Interim Report<ref target="#fn_x1">[1]</ref>
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Mr. Chairman, in the absence
                                          of Mr. <lb/> K.M. Brown, who is unfortunately
                                          incapacitated, <lb/> I have been requested as acting
                                          chairman of the <lb/> Fisheries Committee to present an
                                          interim report. <lb/> This is not a complete report, but I
                                          fancy that the <lb/> delegates will nevertheless find it
                                          both interest<lb break="no"/>ing and instructive, and, I
                                          hope, helpful to our <lb/> deliberations. It will give
                                          them a general idea of <lb/> the great importance of the
                                          cold storage industry <lb/> in Newfoundland. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     It gives plenty of food for thought, dealing 
     <lb/>
     mainly with our new industry. Many people in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland will agree with the Fisheries 
     <lb/>
     Committee's View that the future welfare and 
     <lb/>
     happiness of our people depend largely upon the 
     <lb/>
     future development of this industry. Delegates 
     <lb/>
     will find copies on their desks, and it has been 
     <lb/>
     suggested that it is not necessary to have the 
     <lb/>
     report read in full, as it can better be studied by 
     <lb/>
     the delegates at their homes or temporary 
     <lb/>
     quarters before being debated. I would however 
     <lb/>
     like to make a few comments in presenting it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     About five-sixths of the report deals merely 
     <lb/>
     with facts and figures of Newfoundland's cold 
     <lb/>
     storage industry. During the discussions of these 
     <lb/>
     facts it became evident to the members of your 
     <lb/>
     Fisheries Committee that the future prosperity of 
     <lb/>
     this industry, and indeed of our country, 
     <lb/>
     depended largely upon future tariff and tax arran<lb break="no"/>gements for entries of our products, especially 
     <lb/>
     those of our fisheries, into the United States of 
     <lb/>
     America, and that until some long-term arrange<lb break="no"/>ments regarding tariffs can be made for years 
     <lb/>
     ahead, it may be difficult to further develop our 
     <lb/>
     fisheries and particularly our cold storage in<lb break="no"/>dustry. People can hardly be expected to make 
     <lb/>
     large capital expenditures for expansion of an 
     <lb/>
     industry until reasonably certain that a definite 
     <lb/>
     market for their products is available, and that it 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
          
   
   
           
     cannot be suddenly taken away by the imposition 
     <lb/>
     of adverse tariffs. How vulnerable our country is 
     <lb/>
     as regards external tariffs is clearly shown by the 
     <lb/>
     effect of the so-called processing tax which was 
     <lb/>
     enacted by the USA some 10 or 15 years ago, and 
     <lb/>
     which has since then absolutely prevented expor<lb break="no"/>tation of our seal oil to the USA. Prior to this 
     <lb/>
     enactment something like 50 per cent or more of 
     <lb/>
     our seal oil production went to that market. The 
     <lb/>
     enactment discouraged, if it did not help actually 
     <lb/>
     to kill, a valuable industry. Today the world is 
     <lb/>
     literally crying out for fats, under which category 
     <lb/>
     our seal and herring oils come. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It naturally occurred to members that the USA 
     <lb/>
     might appreciate our need for some permanent 
     <lb/>
     tariff concessions, in view of the fact that she 
     <lb/>
     herself sought and obtained tariff concessions 
     <lb/>
     and long-term leases from us before erecting her 
     <lb/>
     permanent military and naval bases in New<lb break="no"/>foundland territories. She did this mainly for the 
     <lb/>
     protection of her people, and incidentally for the 
     <lb/>
     people of Great Britain, of Canada, and of the 
     <lb/>
     comparatively insignificant population of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. She asked for, or perhaps demanded, 
     <lb/>
     99 year leases and also freedom from customs 
     <lb/>
     and other taxation of every sort. These conces<lb break="no"/>sions under the serious stress of war times were 
     <lb/>
     granted by our Commission of Government no 
     <lb/>
     doubt at the instance of Great Britain, probably 
     <lb/>
     at the personal request of that greatest of war 
     <lb/>
     statesmen, the Honourable Winston Churchill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Can we blame him, or anyone else, for at that 
     <lb/>
     time overlooking the fact that they were asking 
     <lb/>
     us to concede without any actual consideration, 
     <lb/>
     long period leases of Newfoundland territory and 
     <lb/>
     other concessions which today Newfoundlanders 
     <lb/>
     consider should not have been conceded without 
     <lb/>
     some substantial quid pro quo for the owners? No 
     <lb/>
     doubt our little country, with her small popula<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_x1">1 Volume II:21 1. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note><pb n="69"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0069.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="num">69</fw>tion amounting to about 300,000 persons, was 
     <lb/>
     looked upon as a mere pawn in the game, which 
     <lb/>
     must be sacrificed to win the war. But I most 
     <lb/>
     strongly affirm that we think differently, and that 
     <lb/>
     we consider we are entitled to some substantial 
     <lb/>
     and permanent consideration in return for the 
     <lb/>
     concessions yielded. Admittedly it was no time 
     <lb/>
     for argument when these bases and concessions 
     <lb/>
     were granted, as the enemy was literally at our 
     <lb/>
     own gates and all statesmen were concentrating 
     <lb/>
     upon the first essential, namely the winning of the 
     <lb/>
     war. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I do not suggest that we have received no 
     <lb/>
     benefit from the occupation of these bases by our 
     <lb/>
     American friends, but I do suggest that we have 
     <lb/>
     received only a temporary benefit and that we 
     <lb/>
     had, and perhaps still have, the opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     securing a permanent benefit by means of special 
     <lb/>
     tax considerations in the USA in return for the 
     <lb/>
     concessions granted by us. I think every fair- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     minded person will agree that some reservation 
     <lb/>
     for future consideration might have been made 
     <lb/>
     when the long-term leases of our territory and 
     <lb/>
     freedom from taxation were being conceded 
     <lb/>
     without consultation with the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. For all we know, there may have been 
     <lb/>
     some reservations, but the bald fact remains that 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland has so far received <hi rendition="simple:italic">no quid pro 
     <lb/>
     quo</hi> for the valuable concessions granted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It was with this fact in mind that your Fisheries 
     <lb/>
     Committee added to the factual portion of the 
     <lb/>
     report the summary which I will read verbatim, 
     <lb/>
     as it is regarded by the Committee as airing one 
     <lb/>
     of the most important matters affecting the dis<lb break="no"/>cussions and recommendations of this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     To sum up the position it seems clear to 
     <lb/>
     the Fisheries Committee that a very strong 
     <lb/>
     case can be worked up for special considera<lb break="no"/>tion in any negotiations for improvement in 
     <lb/>
     trading relations with the United States of 
     <lb/>
     America, as well as with Canada and Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain, on the following grounds: 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <p>
     1. The future welfare of Newfoundland is 
     <lb/>
     without doubt mainly dependent upon a free 
     <lb/>
     market for her export products, especially 
     <lb/>
     those from the fisheries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. <hi rendition="simple:italic">The future ability of Newfoundland to 
     <lb/>
     secure and maintain for her fishermen and 
     <lb/>
     other inhabitants a fair and decent standard 
     <lb/>
     of living is largely dependent upon such free 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
           
     markets. </hi>
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. The strategical position of New<lb break="no"/>foundland as disclosed by conditions arising 
     <lb/>
     out of the recent world war, is of the utmost 
     <lb/>
     importance to the millions of people in the 
     <lb/>
     United States of America and also to those of 
     <lb/>
     Canada and Great Britain, and all these 
     <lb/>
     countries have a definite interest in assisting 
     <lb/>
     the people of Newfoundland to improve their 
     <lb/>
     standard of living for the following reasons: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (a) In the case of Canada the impor<lb break="no"/>tance of a prosperous Newfoundland is of 
     <lb/>
     special interest, owing to the fact that New<lb break="no"/>foundland's imports from Canada amount to 
     <lb/>
     a very large percentage of the total imports 
     <lb/>
     into Newfoundland, whereas unfortunately 
     <lb/>
     she is not in a position to provide in her own 
     <lb/>
     country a market for Newfoundland's chief 
     <lb/>
     exports. It is therefore to the interest of 
     <lb/>
     Canada to help and encourage our export 
     <lb/>
     trade in other directions, in order to retain and 
     <lb/>
     increase her present exports to New<lb break="no"/>foundland. Moreover Canada has already 
     <lb/>
     received important concessions from New<lb break="no"/>foundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (b) Great Britain is obviously anxious 
     <lb/>
     to assist us. In recent years she has supplied 
     <lb/>
     grants-in-aid to Newfoundland, but it is quite 
     <lb/>
     likely she may not be in a position to continue 
     <lb/>
     these in future years. She can assist us in 
     <lb/>
     making better tariff arrangements not only 
     <lb/>
     with the United States of America, but with 
     <lb/>
     other countries. Moreover, it can be borne in 
     <lb/>
     mind that it was with her authority that sec<lb break="no"/>tions of our territory have been ceded to the 
     <lb/>
     USA without any suitable <hi rendition="simple:italic">quid pro quo</hi> for 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (c) In the case of the USA, leases of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland territory for military and 
     <lb/>
     naval bases for 99 years, and at the same time 
     <lb/>
     facilities for free entry without taxation of 
     <lb/>
     any sort of products imported into this 
     <lb/>
     country for use at these bases, were conceded 
     <lb/>
     without any direct <hi rendition="simple:italic">quid pro quo</hi> for New<lb break="no"/>foundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. It would seem to be extremely impor<lb break="no"/>tant to the people of Newfoundland that 
     <lb/>
     negotiations should be initiated at an early 
     <lb/>
     date with a view to securing favourable trade 
     <lb/>
     arrangements for Newfoundland with the 
     <lb/>
     USA, not only on the basis of reciprocal tariff 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="70"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0070.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">70</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
           
     concessions, but also as a <hi rendition="simple:italic">quid pro quo</hi> for 
     <lb/>
     the concessions already granted by way of 99 
     <lb/>
     year leases and free customs entries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. Whilst this report deals mainly with 
     <lb/>
     the cold storage industry in relation to fish<lb break="no"/>eries, sight must not be lost of other New<lb break="no"/>foundland products which are, or may be, 
     <lb/>
     subject to duty and tax restrictions entering 
     <lb/>
     the USA, and which also have considerable 
     <lb/>
     bearing on Newfoundland economy. Among 
     <lb/>
     these may be mentioned: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (a) Herring and its by-products, such 
     <lb/>
     as herring oil and meal. 
     <lb/>
           

          
     (b) White fish meal. 
     <lb/>
           

            
     (c) Seal oil and seal skins. 
     <lb/>
            

           
     (d) Cod liver oil and common cod oil. 
     <lb/>
           

           
     (e) Salt codfish and all other fishery 
     <lb/>
     products including canned goods. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6. Recommendations contained herein 
     <lb/>
     must not be construed as limiting any views 
     <lb/>
     on the subject of tariffs which could be 
     <lb/>
     reasonably put forward in the interests of 
     <lb/>
     other Newfoundland industries, such as lum<lb break="no"/>bering, pulp and paper, and mining.<ref target="#fn_x2">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     I cannot believe, Mr. Chairman, that great 
     <lb/>
     countries like the USA, Canada, and of course, 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain, will fail to realise our viewpoint 
     <lb/>
     and will deny us the opportunity to expand our 
     <lb/>
     important fishery, sealing and other industries to 
     <lb/>
     a point that will enable us to improve our stand<lb break="no"/>ards of living, which have been the subject of so 
     <lb/>
     much destructive comment in the press of all 
     <lb/>
     these countries from time to time. They now have 
     <lb/>
     a chance to help us and I believe they will do so 
     <lb/>
     if properly approached with a direct appeal. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I cannot help believing that a round table 
     <lb/>
     conference between authorised representatives 
     <lb/>
     of these three great countries with Newfound<lb break="no"/>land representatives acting entirely in New<lb break="no"/>foundland interests, could not fail to arrive at 
     <lb/>
     some arrangement which would give us the tariff 
     <lb/>
     and tax free concessions which we so urgently 
     <lb/>
     require, to secure for our people by their own 
     <lb/>
     effort a respectable standard of living. It may be 
     <lb/>
     that during our discussions at this Convention of 
     <lb/>
     the forms of government to be recommended, 
     <lb/>
     one of those put forward might be some form of 
     <lb/>
     responsible government sponsored or fostered by 
     <lb/>
     a joint advisory council consisting of repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives from Great Britain, Canada, and the 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
         
   
          
     USA, with or without some partial control by 
     <lb/>
     such a council over our financial and external 
     <lb/>
     policy, to help us to keep from running off the 
     <lb/>
     rails This idea is not entirely my own, and I 
     <lb/>
     merely mention it in passing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I beg to move that the interim report of the 
     <lb/>
     Fisheries Committee be received and that the 
     <lb/>
     National Convention resolve itself into a com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the whole for further discussion of the 
     <lb/>
     report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SKEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Do you wish to have the
                                          report <lb/> read? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Copies of the report were
                                          laid on the <lb/> desks of the delegates, I thought
                                          perhaps they <lb/> would rather take it home and consider
                                          it. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SKEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I think it would finish
                                          your ad<lb break="no"/>dress if the report were read by
                                          you or by the <lb/> Secretary. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Secretary read the report]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:BUTT1">Mr. Butt</persName> Mr. Chairman, I am not a
                                          member of <lb/> the committee, but it is apparent that the
                                                 commit<lb break="no"/>tee wishes to give us the
                                          facts of the fishing <lb/> industry in Newfoundland, and
                                          this very impor<lb break="no"/>tant question has been
                                          agitating the minds of <lb/> many Newfoundlanders for some
                                          time. There are <lb/> a number of very important separate
                                          questions <lb/> involved in this wider one, and in order
                                          to deal <lb/> with them properly I suggest that the
                                          members <lb/> have some time to study the questions
                                          further. I <lb/> would therefore move, sir, that we
                                          adjourn the <lb/> debate until tomorrow afternoon at three
                                          o'clock. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIGA1">Mr. Figary</persName> I second that motion. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> You have heard the
                                          motion, <lb/> gentlemen. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There are ten members
                                          of the <lb/> Fisheries Committee. Are none of them perhaps
                                          <lb/> prepared to go on with the debate today? To them
                                          <lb/> the report is quite familiar, and could we not hear
                                          <lb/> from some of them today? I don't know if there <lb/>
                                          is any other business that could be done today. <lb/> This
                                          is the first session in two weeks, and to <lb/> adjourn
                                          within an hour of meeting seems a little <lb/> unnecessary
                                          if any of the other members of the <lb/> Fisheries
                                          Committee are prepared to go on with <lb/> the debate.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> I invite the comments of
                                          any <lb/> members of the Fisheries Committee on that <lb/>
                                          point before putting the motion for adjournment. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> Speaking as a member of that <lb/>committee, we have
                                          thrashed all this out in our <lb/>

<note xml:id="fn_x2">1 Volume II:213. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note> 

                                          <pb n="71"
                                                 facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0071.jpg"/>
                                          <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
                                          <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                                          <fw type="num">71</fw> meetings, and I don't think we can
                                          continue this <lb/> debate until the other members study
                                          the report <lb/> and bring in their questions. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Mr. Job, you moved that
                                          the <lb/> report be received and that it be referred to a
                                          <lb/> committee of the whole. Mr. Butt's motion will <lb/>
                                          not be superseding your motion in any way. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> May I be permitted to meet the commit<lb break="no"/>tee
                                          of the whole tomorrow? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> If I may speak again.
                                          Mr. Cros<lb break="no"/>bie, for whom I have the
                                          profoundest respect, is <lb/> not, I hope, going to be
                                          content with leaving us <lb/> with this written report
                                          without some amplifica<lb break="no"/>tion from him on the
                                          report. I take it that the whole <lb/> Fisheries Committee
                                          are not going to leave this <lb/>
                                          <cb/> written report of theirs as their only word, but
                                          that <lb/>they will, participate in the debate. <lb/>
                                   </p>
     
    

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> May I point out that
                                          that origin<lb break="no"/>al motion, which will be taken
                                          up tomorrow if we <lb/> now adjourn, is that the report be
                                          referred to a <lb/> committee of the whole. I take it that
                                          a full debate <lb/> in committee will then follow. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CROS2">Mr. Crosbie</persName> Mr. Chairman, that's only
                                          an in<lb break="no"/>terim report anyway. As far as the
                                          Fisheries Com<lb break="no"/>mittee is concerned it is
                                          only an attempt at what <lb/> we have to do. It is far
                                          from finished. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The debate will continue
                                          when <lb/> the Convention goes into committee. Is the
                                          House <lb/> ready for the question? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Report on the Financial and Economic Position of Newfoundland<ref target="#fn_x3">[1]</ref> 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> What is the wish of the
                                                 Conven<lb break="no"/>tion on the subject of the
                                          Chadwick and Jones <lb/> report? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> Mr. Chairman, with
                                          your permis<lb break="no"/>sion I would like to trespass
                                          on the time of the <lb/> Convention whilst I make a few
                                          general remarks <lb/> about some of the subjects that have
                                          been before <lb/> the Convention since its opening. It is,
                                          I think, <lb/> expected that every member should make some
                                          <lb/> contribution, no matter how modest it might be,
                                          <lb/> to aid the Convention in its work. That is ex<lb
                                                 break="no"/>pected of us by the country which sent
                                          the Con<lb break="no"/>vention here, and by the people of
                                          the different <lb/> sections who have chosen us to
                                          represent them <lb/> and to speak for them as well as we
                                          can. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     No matter what the outcome of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion may be, the section of the country that I come 
     <lb/>
     from will always have to depend almost entirely 
     <lb/>
     on the fisheries. For a great portion of the south<lb break="no"/>west section of Newfoundland the future 
     <lb/>
     economy is a matter of the development on pro<lb break="no"/>gressive lines of the fishing industry. I think 
     <lb/>
     everybody will agree with Mr. Wild when he 
     <lb/>
     says "there is room for considerable development 
     <lb/>
     of the fisheries", and we hope that, no matter what 
     <lb/>
     form of government is to follow the Convention, 
     <lb/>
     the policy outlined by Mr. Wild will be carried 
     <lb/>
     out when he says that "a determined effort will 
     <lb/>
     be made to stabilise prices and to ensure that 
     <lb/>
     primary producers are given a fairer deal than 
     <lb/>
     they often were in the past." If we could feel that 
     <lb/>
     this would be really the policy of the future 
     <lb/>
     government of Newfoundland, no matter what it 
     <lb/>
           
   
       
            <cb/>
            
     might be, it would be good and heartening news 
     <lb/>
     for large numbers of the fishermen throughout 
     <lb/>
     the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would like to stress that the men from the 
     <lb/>
     district I represent are engaged largely in what we 
     <lb/>
     call the deep sea fishery. This entails greater 
     <lb/>
     hardship than the shore fishing. The men leave 
     <lb/>
     their homes in the dead of winter when storms are 
     <lb/>
     most severe, and the danger and hardship to 
     <lb/>
     which they are subjected earn for them a special 
     <lb/>
     place in our consideration, and a special recogni<lb break="no"/>tion by the government in any future plans for the 
     <lb/>
     development of the fisheries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     There will have to be other means of work for 
     <lb/>
     the people in times outside the fishing season. We 
     <lb/>
     were glad to hear the remarks of the Governor the 
     <lb/>
     other day when he referred to the road from Burin 
     <lb/>
     Peninsula to Terenceville. The people of the 
     <lb/>
     peninsula have been looking forward to this main 
     <lb/>
     highway for many years. Some of the older 
     <lb/>
     people in the district still remember the first 
     <lb/>
     campaign of Sir Edward Morris when he came to 
     <lb/>
     the district nearly 40 years ago. Addressing the 
     <lb/>
     people of Burin, he spoke of the need for this road 
     <lb/>
     to help the development of the Burin Peninsula. 
     <lb/>
     Some people might be inclined to say this was 
     <lb/>
     done for political purposes, but however that may 
     <lb/>
     be, Lord Morris showed great insight into the 
     <lb/>
     future. We hope that in the reconstruction work 
     <lb/>
     of the next few years this important highway will 
     <lb/>
     have a foremost place. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Speaking of the election, I would ask that a 
     <lb/>
     date be selected which will enable every voter to 
     <lb/>
            

<note xml:id="fn_x3">1 Volume II:16. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>

            <pb n="72"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0072.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">72</fw> <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw> <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
         
     avail of his privilege to cast his vote at this 
     <lb/>
     important time in our country's affairs, and not 
     <lb/>
     one at which many of the people would be absent 
     <lb/>
     from their homes and therefore deprived of this 
     <lb/>
     privilege. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In conclusion I feel that every member of the 
     <lb/>
     Convention will do his utmost to justify the hopes 
     <lb/>
     and the wishes of the people of the country who 
     <lb/>
     sent us here. It will not be easy to recommend the 
     <lb/>
     form of government under which future New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders must live, but when the time comes 
     <lb/>
     for the people to make a choice, after hearing 
     <lb/>
     what the Convention has to say, I am sure the 
     <lb/>
     good judgment and the strong commonsense of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundlanders will guide them to make a wise 
     <lb/>
     decision. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Any other member wish to
                                          <lb/> speak on this motion? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> Mr. Chairman, I have
                                          not as <lb/> yet spoken to this motion on the Chadwick and
                                          <lb/> Jones report. When this report was brought in <lb/>
                                          first the Convention was more or less feeling <lb/>
                                          around, trying to get its feet, and I imagine that <lb/>
                                          this discussion was initiated to get things started <lb/>
                                          here. We had the Chadwick and Jones report, and <lb/>
                                          since then we have had the reconstruction plans <lb/> of
                                          the Commission of Government, the financial <lb/> report,
                                          etc., and now we have enough extraneous <lb/> matter. We
                                          have the Fisheries Report now, the <lb/> first real work
                                          that has been done by this Conven<lb break="no"/>tion. The
                                          Education Committee, I understand, <lb/> will have its
                                          report completed very soon, and <lb/> other committees are
                                          ready to come forward too, <lb/> so I would suggest that,
                                          if it meets with the <lb/> approval of the Convention, we
                                          give the Chad<lb break="no"/>wick and Jones report the six
                                          months hoist, and <lb/> get down to our own work as soon
                                          as possible. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> If the Convention wishes we <lb/>could have a
                                          motion to have this report accepted. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I think it was in fact "to receive". <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Then is the house ready for the <lb/>question?
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I take it this will be before
                                          the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion again for adoption? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Not necessarily, but it
                                          will be <lb/> laid on the table and reference can be had
                                          to it. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I think it would be a pity if it is not <lb/>debated for
                                          itself. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Well then, it would have
                                          to be <lb/> put before a committee of the whole, and it
                                          will <lb/> have to be read item by item. Is that what you <lb/>
                                          <cb/> meant? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> Well no, but I think we can
                                          go through <lb/> it quickly without going over it item by
                                          item - <lb/> just bring up the most important parts for
                                                 discus<lb break="no"/>sion. There are several
                                          errors in the report as a <lb/> matter of fact, and I
                                          think it would be a pity to <lb/> shut off all
                                          consideration of it. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:JACK5">Mr. Jackman</persName> Mr. Chairman, I have not
                                                 any<lb break="no"/>thing prepared to say in regards
                                          to this report, but <lb/> what I say now is just the way I
                                          feel about it. I <lb/> would say, sir, there is nothing in
                                          it we don't <lb/> already know, and therefore I would say
                                          here <lb/> that, as an individual, I am very much disap<lb
                                                 break="no"/>pointed in the report. I remember when
                                          the Com<lb break="no"/>mission of Government was
                                          instituted in this <lb/> country it promised two things —
                                          political educa<lb break="no"/>tion and economic
                                          development. There is no <lb/> question about it this
                                          Convention is a political <lb/> education, not only for us
                                          assembled here but for <lb/> the country as a whole. In
                                          regards to the economic <lb/> development of this country
                                          the Commission of <lb/> Government has failed utterly.
                                          There has not <lb/> been one major industry established in
                                          our <lb/> country. There has not been one which was <lb/>
                                          plugged. As regards the report I am against it <lb/>
                                          because I see nothing in it that is of importance <lb/> to
                                          us as a people — that is the economic develop<lb
                                                 break="no"/>ment of our country. I would not vote
                                          in favour <lb/> of its adoption. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The motion is not to
                                          adopt it, it <lb/> is merely to receive it. Is the
                                          Convention ready <lb/> for the question? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:MILL5">Mr. Miller</persName> It seems to me that
                                          shortly the <lb/> several committees will be bringing in
                                          their <lb/> reports, and I would consider it a nice way,
                                          when <lb/> these reports come in, to take that section of
                                          the <lb/> Chadwick~Jones report which deals with that
                                          <lb/> particular report... <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The Steering Committee
                                          will <lb/> tanke up your very admirable suggestion, but
                                                 per<lb break="no"/>haps it would be better to wait
                                          until the final <lb/> report of the Fisheries Committee is
                                          presented to <lb/> the Convention, for purposes of
                                          comparison. I <lb/> think yours is a very excellent
                                          suggestion. It <lb/> would be a pity to lose sight of the
                                          value of the <lb/> Chadwick-Jones report and it is of
                                          great impor<lb break="no"/>tance that the Convention
                                          should study it in <lb/> detail, and perhaps have it
                                          debated in detail, in <lb/> the way that Mr. Miller
                                          suggests. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:JOB1">Mr. Job</persName> I think it is a very good
                                          suggestion, but <lb/> I would like to point out that it is
                                          better to await <lb/>
                                          <pb n="73"
                                                 facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0073.jpg"/>
                                          <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
                                          <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                                          <fw type="num">73</fw> the final report of the Fisheries
                                          Committee. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The Steering Committee
                                          will <lb/> take your suggestion under consideration. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HOLL2">Mr. Hollett</persName> Before putting the
                                          question, I <lb/> would like to ask what exactly is meant
                                          by a <lb/> "motion to receive"? The only things I have
                                          <lb/> learned from that report are that we are self-sup<lb
                                                 break="no"/>porting; that the Commission of
                                          Government has <lb/> done an excellent job under the
                                          circumstances; <lb/> that the wartime economy has brought
                                          us tem<lb break="no"/>porary prosperity; but that we are
                                          going to have <lb/> a pretty tough time. All of us here
                                          who are at<lb break="no"/>tempting to study Newfoundland
                                          have studied <lb/> other documents besides the
                                          Chadwick-Jones <lb/> report and if we are to receive it, I
                                          would suggest <lb/> we file it away amongst other
                                          documents; put it <lb/> up against some other documents,
                                          or some other <lb/> facts which we have had in connection
                                          with the <lb/> economic and financial condition of New<lb
                                                 break="no"/>foundland. Before I can vote
                                          intelligently on the <lb/> motion to receive the
                                          Chadwick—Jones report, I <lb/> would like to know what
                                          that motion means. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It means nothing more than the <lb/>formal
                                          reception of the report by the Convention. <lb/>Heretofore
                                          it was laid merely on the individual <lb/>desks. It does
                                          not mean you accept it. Is the <lb/>Convention ready for
                                          the question? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The report was received]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> I would like to ask a
                                          question <lb/> in regard to a rumour. Is it true that the
                                                 commit<lb break="no"/>tees are not getting replies
                                          to some questions <lb/> asked the government departments,
                                          and that <lb/> some departments have refused point blank
                                          to <lb/> answer some of the questions? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> From what I understand,
                                          the <lb/> government departments are working assiduous<lb
                                                 break="no"/>ly on replies, and some questions have
                                          already <lb/> been answered. In regard to others, all have
                                          gone <lb/> to the various committees whose duty it is to
                                          <lb/> investigate matters under question. I do not think
                                          <lb/> it is true that any department has refused to give
                                          <lb/> information. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> It is true of one
                                          department, at <lb/> least. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> If that committee will
                                          report the <lb/> matter to the Information Committee it
                                          will be <lb/> investigated. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> In reference to my
                                          questions, I <lb/> have today received my first reply. It
                                          was merely <lb/> the production of a pamphlet — a matter
                                          of <lb/> reaching up in a cupboard and handing it down.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> It is going to take some
                                          time to <lb/> get certain answers. I want to tell you that
                                          the <lb/> Information Committee is working continuously,
                                          <lb/> and the committees themselves are not losing any
                                          <lb/> opportunity of obtaining any information. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> The point I want to
                                          make is in <lb/> connection with a question tabled in the
                                          house; <lb/> referred then to the Information Committee;
                                                 ap<lb break="no"/>proved by the Information
                                          Committee; and sent <lb/> forward to the government
                                          department con<lb break="no"/>cerned. With the result that
                                          an official of the <lb/> government department concerned
                                          appeared <lb/> before the committee concerned, and stated
                                          that <lb/> the reply was not and would not be forthcoming.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> We have heard nothing official<lb break="no"/>ly on
                                          that point.... <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I am speaking on behalf of
                                          Mr. <lb/> Fudge, chairman of the Forestry Committee. <lb/>
                                          There was one particular question we put to the <lb/>
                                          government and which went through in the ordi<lb
                                                 break="no"/>nary way: we asked if any applications
                                          were on <lb/> file asking for certain leases or timber
                                          rights on <lb/> the Labrador. As regards timber rights, we
                                          were <lb/> told by Mr. Turner or Mr. McLellan who repre<lb
                                                 break="no"/>sented the department that these
                                          questions they <lb/> were not permitted to answer. And I
                                          can tell you <lb/> the reason. We know that two or three
                                                 applica<lb break="no"/>tions were in the hands of
                                          the government. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Major Cashin knows. I
                                          do not <lb/> know. If applications are now pending for
                                          grants, <lb/> mineral rights, water power rights, I want
                                          to know <lb/> it. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> In reply to Mr. Smallwood,
                                          when <lb/> we make our report, we will tell him... <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Before the Information
                                                 Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, we had Mr. Walter
                                          Marshall, Secretary <lb/> for Finance, and he assured us
                                          all necessary in<lb break="no"/>formation would be
                                          supplied. The position is, as <lb/> I explained some time
                                          ago when we presented the <lb/> Report of the Steering
                                          Committee, that informa<lb break="no"/>tion necessary to
                                          the work of the Convention <lb/> would be sought; and it
                                          was the intention that all <lb/> questions should be
                                          submitted to the Information <lb/> Committee, that this
                                          Committee would examine <lb/> the questions to ensure that
                                          there was no duplica<lb break="no"/>tion and that only
                                          relevant questions would be <lb/> asked; that a certain
                                          restraint would be exercised <lb/> in order that there
                                          would not be an undue burden <lb/> placed upon the
                                          government departments. If <lb/> every type of question
                                          has to be answered and <lb/> answered in detail, not alone
                                          will it paralyse the <lb/>
                                          <pb n="74"
                                                 facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0074.jpg"/>
                                          <fw type="num">74</fw>
                                          <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                                          <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw> work of the civil
                                          service, but it will have the effect <lb/> of placing in a
                                          secondary position other very <lb/>important questions....
                                          We have no official <lb/>notification that any requests
                                          for information <lb/>were rejected. <lb/>
                                   </p>

    

    

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> In the event of the
                                          Information <lb/> Committee's turning down a question
                                          which to <lb/>them is irrelevant, is the committee
                                          involved <lb/>informed? <lb/>
                                   </p>

    

    

    

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The plan adopted by the
                                                 Infor<lb break="no"/>mation Committee is that where
                                          any doubt arises <lb/>as to the relevancy of the request
                                          for information, <lb/>the questioner is invited to come
                                          and discuss the <lb/>matter with the committee. Again we
                                          found that <lb/>for certain questions asked, the answers
                                          could be <lb/>gathered from certain reports which we then
                                          <lb/>placed in the hands of the questioner. Other ques<lb
                                                 break="no"/>tions are very difficult from the
                                          viewpoint of <lb/>finding the source of information. Some
                                          have to <lb/>be answered not by government departments but
                                          <lb/>by members of the trade. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> If the particular committee con<lb break="no"
                                          />cerned has been refused answers relative to <lb/>leases,
                                          it is a matter which should be reported <lb/>immediately
                                          to the Information Committee and <lb/>if we cannot get
                                          satisfaction, then we should <lb/>report it to this house
                                          and let the house deal with it. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> The Information Committee is <lb/>meeting every day
                                          so that every opportunity can <lb/>be availed of to obtain
                                          factual material essential <lb/>to the Convention; but we
                                          must have reference to <lb/>the terms of reference with
                                          regard to the relevan<lb break="no"/>cy of the question.
                                          We have to remember we are <lb/>not a parliament. We
                                          cannot go into matters in <lb/>the same way as a
                                          parliamentary government <lb/>could be investigated by an
                                          opposition. We are a <lb/>consultative body considering
                                          amongst ourselves <lb/>the financial and economic
                                          condition of the <lb/>country, and the information which
                                          the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion seeks, of necessity, has to
                                          be information <lb/>relevant to the work of the
                                          Convention. <lb/>
                                   </p>

    

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> There may be a
                                          suggestion of <lb/> faith and confidence in the executive
                                          and not for <lb/>us to worry, but the fact remains there
                                          is a pos~ <lb/>sibility the very future of this country is
                                          being <lb/>determined today by the government, by the
                                          <lb/>alienation of some of the resources out of which
                                          <lb/>the country has to get its revenue. True we are not
                                          <lb/>an opposition; we are not in opposition to the
                                          <lb/>government. I do not know what we can do to <lb/>
                                          
              <cb/> 
convey the idea that even while we are meeting,
                                          <lb/> perhaps some of the public domain in Labrador <lb/>
                                          is being bartered away, making it thereby impos<lb
                                                 break="no"/>sible for this country to be
                                          self-supporting in the <lb/> future. Members of this house
                                          have been com<lb break="no"/>plaining and grumbling — I am
                                          doing the un<lb break="no"/>popular thing of voicing it. I
                                          have had it said to <lb/> me in the dining room of the
                                          Newfoundland <lb/> Hotel, "Sitting around you are five
                                                 conces<lb break="no"/>sionaires seeking concessions
                                          in Labrador over <lb/> and above those already given."
                                          Perhaps we can <lb/> only talk about it, but we ought to
                                          let the country, <lb/> the government and the press and
                                          radio know that <lb/> we have lost the public domain of
                                          Newfoundland <lb/> itself; tied it up irrevocably as long
                                          as conces<lb break="no"/>sionaires care, bartered away by
                                          this and former <lb/> governments. What is left is being
                                          sought by <lb/> hungry concessionaires — hungry like flies
                                          <lb/> around a molasses puncheon — seeking the last <lb/>
                                          vestige of territory. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> We have no power or authority <lb/>to make
                                          recommendations in regard to matters of <lb/>policy. Our
                                          sole duty is within the four comers of <lb/>section 3 of
                                          the National Convention
                                          Act....<ref target="#fn_01">[1]</ref>
                                          That <lb/>is the full scope of our authority. In reply to
                                          <lb/>Mr. Smallwood, I have to advise you that we
                                          <lb/>cannot interfere with matters of government
                                          <lb/>policy. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAWE1">Mr. Dawe</persName> What is the use in bringing in the <lb/>report if we do
                                          not know what is happening? <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> If part of our duty is to examine the <lb/>position
                                          of the country, it seems to follow that we <lb/>have the
                                          right to know what assets this country <lb/>has, and it
                                          follows upon that we have a right to <lb/>know what is
                                          being done with the assets. I do not <lb/>know what the
                                          Commission is doing. I know <lb/>what they have done and I
                                          shall have something <lb/>to say about it before this
                                          Convention closes. But <lb/>I do not know what they are
                                          doing now. I want to <lb/>know what assets are left, and
                                          whether any at<lb break="no"/>tempt is being made to
                                          dispose of them by what <lb/>may be a dying government.
                                          The chairman of that <lb/>particular committee should
                                          report to the Infor<lb break="no"/>mation Committee and if
                                          that committee cannot <lb/>get satisfaction, it will be
                                          reported to the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> That is the procedure to be fol<lb break="no"
                                          />lowed... <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> As acting chairman of the Forestry <lb/>Committee, I
                                          wish to report that we have been <lb/>


<note xml:id="fn_01">1 Volume II:1. [Volume II is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</note>
    
                            
                                          <pb n="75"
                                                 facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-10_Page_0075.jpg"/>
                                          <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
                                          <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                                          <fw type="num">75</fw> refused information regarding the
                                          disposition of <lb/> some timber areas on Labrador. We
                                          have been <lb/> told that the government was not going to
                                          give <lb/> that information. I am taking this opportunity
                                          of <lb/> telling the Information Committee. I would like
                                          <lb/> to back up what Mr. Bradley has said — we are <lb/>
                                          here to find out facts as to the assets of the country <lb/>
                                          <cb/> and those very assets may be given away. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> It would be better if we
                                          had it in <lb/> writing. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I shall put it in writing
                                          after ad<lb break="no"/>journment. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The Convention adjourned]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-02-16, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

           <!-- <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     October 11, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Chairman At the request of the Fisheries Committee, Mr. Keough has been added to that 
     <lb/>committee.<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Interim Report of the Fisheries Committee:l 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     [The Secretary read pages 1 and 2 of the report] 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman That might be termed the first 
     <lb/>
     section of the report, gentlemen. Any member 
     <lb/>
     wishing to debate on the report may now speak. 
     <lb/>
     If you do not desire to discuss that section of the 
     <lb/>
     report, gentlemen. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Miller I acknowledge there is a fish plant in 
     <lb/>
     Long Harbour, Placentia Bay. I wonder if the 
     <lb/>
     government inspected that too, as it is not men<lb break="no"/>tioned here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job The bait depots are not included. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett With regard to the amount of capital 
     <lb/>
     invested, did the committee arrive at the amount 
     <lb/>
     invested by the government or did they not? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Job I don't know of any money invested by 
     <lb/>the government. That has certainly not been 
     <lb/>taken into account. There may be in one or two 
     <lb/>places advances made by the government which 
     <lb/>have been paid or partly repaid, but they have not 
     <lb/>been taken into account. These figures are rough 
     <lb/>I must confess, but they are the nearest we can 
     <lb/>get. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett I saw in the estimates where a cer<lb break="no"/>tain amount of money had been subsidised by the 
     <lb/>
     government for advances to possible corpora<lb break="no"/>tions. I understood also that a certain amount had 
     <lb/>
     been put out, and it might be suggested that the 
     <lb/>
     committee arrive at the true situation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Chairman The committee will make in<lb break="no"/>quiries into that point, Mr. Hollett. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Newell Mr. Chairman. in the fourth para<lb break="no"/>graph the wording is a little ambiguous. It reads: 
     <lb/>
     "The frozen blueberry industry was also a very 
     <lb/>
     substantial business and of very definite value to 
     <lb/>
     the country owing to the fact that the cost of 
     <lb/>
     picking was very little ...." As it reads it might 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     1Volume II:21 1. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     seem as if the value was of small return to the 
     <lb/>
     pickers, but I am sure that is not the thought of 
     <lb/>
     the Fishery Committee, or is it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Job I think that the idea was that the cost of 
     <lb/>
     the picking was small comparatively, and it was 
     <lb/>
     a very worthwhile return to the pickers. I think it 
     <lb/>
     was because the price paid to the pickers was 
     <lb/>
     small in past years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Hollett There is another question about bait 
     <lb/>
     sold to fishermen. The report states that "The bait 
     <lb/>
     frozen (squid and herring) was substantial, but 
     <lb/>
     nothing like the present-day volume because the 
     <lb/>
     fishermen were not generally so accustomed to 
     <lb/>
     using the frozen bait as they are now." I don't 
     <lb/>
     believe that, because years ago the only reason 
     <lb/>
     why fishermen did not use frozen bait very 
     <lb/>
     generally was because of the cost, which was 
     <lb/>
     almost prohibitive in view of the amount of 
     <lb/>
     money they received for the fish caught. I was 
     <lb/>
     wondering if the committee would be good 
     <lb/>
     enough to look into the present cost of bait as 
     <lb/>
     supplied to first, our shore fishermen, and second, 
     <lb/>
     our bank fishermen. It is absolutely essential if 
     <lb/>
     our fishermen are to use frozen bait that some 
     <lb/>
     means be found to supply that bait at the least 
     <lb/>
     possible cost. The committee might be able to get 
     <lb/>
     some figures with regard to that.... It is several 
     <lb/>
     years since I had anything to do with fishery 
     <lb/>
     conditions, but in those old days there were a 
     <lb/>
     good many cases of the fall fishing being given 
     <lb/>
     up merely because for that fishery it became 
     <lb/>
     necessary for the banking fleet to procure frozen 
     <lb/>
     bait, and after trying it for a number of years they 
     <lb/>
     discovered that the returns which the individual 
     <lb/>
     fisherman made on that trip were absolutely nil 
     <lb/>
     when they took into consideration the cost of 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>