<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNFNC_1946-10-31"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNFNC">Newfoundland National Convention</name>, <date when="1946-10-31">31 October 1946</date>, Debates on Confederation with Canada</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>J.K. Hiller and M.F. Harrington</editor>.
    
         
          <title>The Newfoundland National Convention 1946-1948 Vol 1</title>.
                    

          <date when="1995"/>.   
          

         <pubPlace>Montreal and Kingston</pubPlace>: <publisher>McGill-Queen's University Press</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="127"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0125.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0126.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0127.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-02-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-04">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0125">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0125.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0126">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0126.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0127">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0127.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="125"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0125.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">125</fw>

<!-- GL, 2017-02-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

            <!--<p>
     and seeing what these terms are, but it is prema<lb break="no"/>ture, sir. We have not yet got for the people of this 
     <lb/>
     country what we were sent here to get. Therefore 
     <lb/>
     I am in duty bound to vote against the resolution 
     <lb/>
     and to vote for the amendment. Nobody, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Smallwood or anybody else, has ever ap<lb break="no"/>proached me or offered me a senatorship or a trip 
     <lb/>
     to Ottawa or anything else. As perhaps the oldest 
     <lb/>
     member here I say here that nobody apart from 
     <lb/>
     God Almighty directs my course. I have a mind 
     <lb/>
     of my own. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     While men in this House today may come to 
     <lb/>
     the chamber for the first time, I know even more 
     <lb/>
     about what I speak than people whose fathers 
     <lb/>
     before them have spent their lifetime in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with the fisheries of this country. I am not 
     <lb/>
     one of those. I feel that we came here to do a duty 
     <lb/>
     to the people. I don't feel as Mr. Watton felt this 
     <lb/>
     afternoon that some are here with an ulterior 
     <lb/>
     motive. I have no ulterior motive. I was elected 
     <lb/>
     by acclamation. I was called out by the people in 
     <lb/>
     my own district, and not only one crowd but 
     <lb/>
     several. I never intended to run as a delegate to 
     <lb/>
     this Convention, but I did intend, if I was spared, 
     <lb/>
     to run in whatever election might come forward 
     <lb/>
     at a later date. I was called by my people, like it 
     <lb/>
     was said of me one time when I was called for 
     <lb/>
     another district. My reply was that it was not that 
     <lb/>
     I can't go there, I was not afraid to go there. I have 
     <lb/>
     never feared a political election or a political 
     <lb/>
     fight. I loved it, and I love it today. Therefore, 
     <lb/>
     when we come down to supporting this motion I 
     <lb/>
     feel that I can't do it in sincerity. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have been practically 30 years representing 
     <lb/>
     labour in this country. My younger days were 
     <lb/>
     spent in the Pacific coast fishery business in 
     <lb/>
     Alaska. I know all about fishing — more than 
     <lb/>
     many who have had so much prate on it. I was 
     <lb/>
     there with frozen fingers, on the Banks and in the 
     <lb/>
     dory. I have gone through the mill as much as the 
     <lb/>
     average man in this House has gone. Yet I don't 
     <lb/>
     come here pretending that I know it all. I have 
     <lb/>
     handled labour in this country for 29 years. I have 
     <lb/>
     led strikes and settled strikes, and got wages 
     <lb/>
     increased, and I have done many things for the 
     <lb/>
     people of this country, and I am not ashamed of 
     <lb/>
     it today. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Mr. Fudge referred to the Woods Labour 
     <lb/>
     Board. I am a member of that Woods Labour 
     <lb/>
     Board, and it has done a lot for this country, and 
     <lb/>
     is still doing it. That Woods Labour Board is 
     <lb/>
     showing to this country that we don't want 
     <lb/>
     anybody else to come in and run our own affairs. 
     <lb/>
     That Woods Labour Board, under the chairman<lb break="no"/>ship of the late revered and honoured Judge Hig<lb break="no"/>gins, and of the present Mr. Justice Fox, has done 
     <lb/>
     work that perhaps few others could do. We have 
     <lb/>
     experienced people on that board, and it has done 
     <lb/>
     a good job; therefore I join with my friend, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Fudge, in saying that we can handle our own 
     <lb/>
     affairs and we don't have to go to Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     You will find today in Canada places where 
     <lb/>
     people are just as backward as they are in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I have a piece of paper in my pocket 
     <lb/>
     now, I won't read it, but if I did I doubt if there 
     <lb/>
     would be ten men in this House who would vote 
     <lb/>
     for this resolution. Let it go. I will not read it now, 
     <lb/>
     I will leave it to some other time. I am not jumping 
     <lb/>
     to any conclusions, I know where I stand. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Some get up and make flowery speeches, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chairman. I have never read a speech in this 
     <lb/>
     assembly from the first day up to the present day, 
     <lb/>
     and you know sir, that the rules of the House of 
     <lb/>
     Assembly would not allow members to read their 
     <lb/>
     speeches. You had to get up and spit it out of you 
     <lb/>
     and have no hesitation in doing it. I have done it 
     <lb/>
     for years, and I hope I am doing it now. In the 
     <lb/>
     meantime, Mr. Chairman, I am not sorry to see 
     <lb/>
     that this is allowed now to the new members in 
     <lb/>
     this House. The only thing about it, are the 
     <lb/>
     speeches that the members read all written by 
     <lb/>
     themselves or by someone else? I don't have to 
     <lb/>
     write a speech to get up and express my opinion, 
     <lb/>
     I can get up and speak my mind without a written 
     <lb/>
     speech. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have never met Mr. Penney before coming 
     <lb/>
     here to this Convention, and I have not spoken 20 
     <lb/>
     words to you since you have been here, but I hold 
     <lb/>
     you in the highest esteem. Thank you for seeing 
     <lb/>
     fit to bring in this amendment. I think that in 
     <lb/>
     doing so you are doing no injustice... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [Mr. Brown collapsed at this point. The Conven<lb break="no"/>tion adjourned] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     October 31, 1946 
     <lb/>
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CASH2">Mr. Cashin</persName> I would like to make the motion that <lb/> this
                  House adjourn until Monday afternoon at 3 <lb/>
                  <cb/> o'clock, in respect for one of our delegates, <lb/> Mr. Brown, who dropped
                  here yesterday after<lb break="no"/><pb n="126"
                     facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0126.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">126</fw>
                  <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>noon at his post. I have known Mr. Brown for
                  <lb/> over 20 years. Both of us entered the House <lb/> together in 1923 — he was
                  on one side and I was <lb/> on the other — and were elected again in 1924 <lb/>
                  and 1928, and, as our association lengthened, my <lb/> respect and admiration for
                  Mr. Brown increased. <lb/> This afternoon as he lies stricken and uncon<lb
                     break="no"/>scious in the General Hospital, I feel that the <lb/> delegates in
                  this Convention, should join as one <lb/> in extending to his wife and family our
                  sincere <lb/> sympathy and adjourn. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BRAD3">Mr. Bradley</persName> It is scarce 24 hours since that <lb/> tragic
                  scene occurred on the floors of this as<lb break="no"/>sembly. I too have been
                  associated with <lb/> Mr. Brown for about the same period as Major <lb/> Cashin.
                  In fact we are all three, sir, much of the <lb/> same political vintage as regards
                  years. In addi<lb break="no"/>tion, Mr. Brown is a representative of the district
                  <lb/> which adjoins my own, and I feel that so near to <lb/> that tragic scene,
                  and with the picture in one's <lb/> mind of Mr. Brown lying unconscious, that it
                  <lb/> would unquestionably be proper to adjourn until <lb/> Monday. I second that
                  motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:STAR1">Mr. Starkes</persName> I support the mover and seconder <lb/> of this
                  important motion, who have been as<lb break="no"/>sociated with Mr. Brown for so
                  many years in <lb/> public life. I feel sure that not only this House, <lb/> but
                  the whole country regrets the accident that <lb/> happened yesterday, and I
                  approve heartily of the <lb/> motion made by Major Cashin. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:PENN2">Mr. Penney</persName> Although a stranger to Mr. Brown <lb/> until I
                  came to this House, after the happening of <lb/> yesterday, I feel I should
                  support the motion <lb/> before the Chair. Some of the last few words that <lb/>
                  Mr. Brown spoke in this House yesterday after<lb break="no"/>noon, he turned and
                  spoke them to me, a stranger. <lb/> I would be remiss in my duty if I did not
                  express <lb/> my hope that Mr. Brown will yet come out of this <lb/> serious
                  illness and resume his work with this <lb/> Convention. In the meantime I send my
                  sincere <lb/> good wishes for his recovery and for the comfort <lb/> of his wife
                  and children as they sit by his bedside. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD12">Mr. MacDonald</persName> I heartily endorse the motion <lb/>that this
                  Convention should adjourn until Mon<lb break="no"/>day in respect to our colleague
                  Mr. Brown. I have <lb/>known Mr. Brown quite a number of years, even <lb/>before
                  he entered political life-knew him when <lb/>he was a labour leader. I have always
                  found him <lb/>a man true to his convictions, fair and square to <lb/>deal with at
                  all times, and although we have <lb/>differed on some occasions, yet Mr. Brown is
                  a <lb/>
                  <cb/> very dear friend of mine, and I have much <lb/> pleasure in supporting the
                  motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HARR6">Mr. Harrington</persName> I feel I should rise to express <lb/> the
                  feelings of the younger members of the as<lb break="no"/>sembly. I have not been
                  associated with Mr. <lb/> Brown as long as some of the older members who <lb/>
                  have spoken here; butI have known him for a few <lb/> years, and have always found
                  him a very <lb/> forthright gentleman. Whatever his convictions <lb/> he was never
                  afraid to speak his mind, and he was <lb/> in the act of doing that yesterday when
                  he was <lb/> stricken, as Major Cashin said, at his post. I <lb/> would like to
                  join in sending the sympathetic <lb/> condolences of this House to his family.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SMAL1">Mr. Smallwood</persName> Mr. Chairman, I had not had <lb/> many
                  conversations with Mr. Brown, although <lb/> my acquaintance with him runs back to
                  the fall <lb/> of 1923, but on the night before last, in the lobby <lb/> of the
                  Hotel, we had quite a pleasant chat, which <lb/> I was personally very happy to
                  have. Yesterday <lb/> he collapsed in speaking to the motion that I <lb/> moved. I
                  know that he opposed the motion with <lb/> complete sincerity. I know his feeling
                  was that it <lb/> was his duty to speak his mind honestly, manful<lb break="no"
                  />ly, and he was doing that on that occasion. I <lb/> confess I hardly know
                  whether I would prefer he <lb/> had been supporting or opposing the motion. I <lb/>
                  know we can all agree that the loss of his <lb/> presence, even temporarily, will
                  be a severe one. <lb/> Men like Mr. Brown, of manly independence, <lb/> unafraid
                  to express their honest convictions, are <lb/> needed now as they will be in the
                  future. I hope, <lb/> sir, that Mr. Brown will be back again to play his <lb/>
                  part in this Convention and in the public life of <lb/> this country. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VINC1">Mr. Vincent</persName> As delegate from Bonavista <lb/> North, closely
                  associated with Mr. Brown, and <lb/> having known him for a period of years, I
                  wish <lb/> to concur with the previous speakers. Upon enter<lb break="no"/>ing the
                  public life of this country for the first time <lb/> as a delegate to the National
                  Convention his was <lb/> the first message of congratulation that I <lb/>
                  received. I extend my sincere sympathy to Mrs. <lb/> Brown and the family, and to
                  the good folk of <lb/> King's Cove and Bonavista South in general. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:REDD1">Mr. Reddy</persName> I heartily agree with the previous <lb/>speakers. I
                  regret the tragic accident which hap<lb break="no"/>pened to Mr. Brown, and I hope
                  that his recovery <lb/>will be a matter of a short time and he will be back
                  <lb/>to his post. I tender to his family my sincere <lb/>regrets. <lb/>
               </p>
            <pb n="127"
                facs="final/images/NFLD_National_Convention_1946-10-31_Page_0127.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">October 1946</fw>
            <fw type="running">NATIONAL CONVENTION</fw>
            <fw type="num">127</fw>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ASHB2">Mr. Ashbourne</persName> I would be remiss in my duty if <lb/> I did not
                  take voice my feelings as regards this <lb/> motion. I feel as a representative of
                  the district of <lb/> Twillingate, that we had the honour to have Mr. <lb/> Brown
                  as our representative for several years. <lb/> When I first entered the House of
                  Assembly I <lb/> entered with Mr. Brown, and the late Mr. George <lb/> Grimes, who
                  has entered into his eternal rest. I <lb/> feel I am voicing the sentiments of the
                  district of <lb/> Twillingate, as well as the whole of New<lb break="no"
                  />foundland, when I say that the people today regret <lb/> this unfortunate
                  accident and sickness from <lb/> which Mr. Brown is suffering. I know that <lb/>
                  throughout Newfoundland today, as Mr. Brown <lb/> is a national leader for labour,
                  and has fought and <lb/> championed their cause, the whole country is <lb/>
                  waiting for word which we hope will soon be <lb/> given of his recovery. As I
                  said, Mr. Brown was <lb/> a member for Twillingate district, and although <lb/> at
                  one time I opposed him as an independent <lb/> there, yet I will say that in all
                  our dealings <lb/> together we have been very friendly indeed, and <lb/> I trust
                  and pray that it will not be long before we <lb/> regain his service and his
                  influence. He is a very <lb/> responsible man, looking on both sides of an <lb/>
                  argument, fair minded, viewing the pros and the <lb/> cons, and I hope it will not
                  be long before he will <lb/> be again restored to health. In the meantime I <lb/>
                  would like to add my sympathy to his wife and <lb/> relatives at King's Cove and
                  elsewhere in New<lb break="no"/>foundland. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEN3">Mr. Spencer</persName> I was going to say I never knew <lb/> Mr. Brown
                  before I came to this Convention, but <lb/> that would hardly be true. It is true
                  that I never <lb/> met him until at this Convention, but I have heard <lb/> of him
                  for many years and say that I have fol<lb break="no"/>lowed his career with
                  interest and admired him <lb/> as a Newfoundlander with high standards. I join
                  <lb/> with this Convention in extending to his family <lb/> our deep sympathy at
                  this time. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FIGA1">Mr. Figary</persName> I support the motion now before the <lb/> Chair.
                  It has been my privilege to know Mr. <lb/>
                  <cb/> Brown for the last two or three years in the labour <lb/> movement. I know
                  of the great interest he has in <lb/> that movement, and for his fellow men. Since
                  <lb/> coming to this Convention I have sat by him here <lb/> and I have been very
                  much interested in what he <lb/> has had to say in this Convention and in the way
                  <lb/> in which he has his country at heart. I worked <lb/> with him on the
                  Fisheries Committee, and assure <lb/> you he is a very capable leader, and of
                  doing the <lb/> work assigned to him. Therefore, on behalf of the <lb/> district
                  of Burgeo, I want to extend my sincere <lb/> sympathy to the family of Mr. Brown.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HILL2">Mr. Hillier</persName> I wish to support this motion in <lb/> respect to
                  the adjournment of this House out of <lb/> respect for a fellow member of this
                  Convention. <lb/> Suffice it to say that he is one of our number and <lb/> that we
                  shall miss him. I heartily support the <lb/> motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:VARD1">Mr. Vardy</persName> I should like to support this motion, <lb/> and the
                  various speakers. I have known <lb/> Mr. Brown since we were boys; he is a little
                  older <lb/> than myself— not very much. I have been enter<lb break="no"/>tained at
                  his home. I am sure he is not only a good <lb/> representative, he is a good
                  neighbour. We shall <lb/> all miss him and shall naturally look forward to <lb/>
                  his return to this House as soon as medical <lb/> science can make it possible.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Chairman</persName> Is the House ready for the ques<lb break="no"
                  />tion? Proposed by Mr. Cashin, and seconded by <lb/> Mr. Bradley, that out of
                  respect and sympathy for <lb/> Mr. K.M. Brown, who was stricken yesterday in <lb/>
                  the course of the debate with such tragic sudden<lb break="no"/>ness, that this
                  Convention adjourn until Monday <lb/> next at 3 o'clock, and that there be placed
                  on our <lb/> records the expression of our fervent hope that <lb/> Mr. Brown may
                  have a speedy recovery, and <lb/> furthermore that we extend to Mrs. Brown and
                  <lb/> the family an expression of our sincere sympathy <lb/> at this time. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">[The motion carried, and the Convention ad<lb break="no"/>journed]</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>