<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-06-02"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-06-02">2 June 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
  
         
           <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.  
          

           <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="588" to="590"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0588.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0589.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0590.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0588">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0588.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0589">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0589.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0590">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0590.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="588" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0588.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">588</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS 
               DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 2, 1869<lb/></fw>
               
                    <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> moved an amendment 
               <lb/>
               to the 16th clause, providing that the Minister 
               <lb/>
               of Justice should examine every patent, and 
               <lb/>
               certify that all the requirements of the law 
               <lb/>
               had been complied with. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> said the ofﬁce of Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Justice might be vacant for some 
               <lb/>
               months, and during the time no patent would 
               <lb/>
               issue. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName>—I will take care of 
               <lb/>
               that. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> - Perhaps the Minister of Militia 
               <lb/>
               will not forever be in a position to take care 
               <lb/>
               of that. (Laughter.) He (Mr. Blake) thought 
               <lb/>
               the proposed amendment useless and mis<lb break="no"/>chievous. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> said it was a repeti<lb break="no"/>tion almost verbatim of a clause which had 
               <lb/>
               been in the patent law of the late Province 
               <lb/>
               of Canada for ﬁfteen or twenty years. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The amendment was agreed to, and clause 
               <lb/>
               16 as amended passed. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Clauses 17 and 18 were agreed to with 
               <lb/>
               some verbal amendments. Clauses 19 to 26 
               <lb/>
               were agreed to. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               On clause 27 a discussion arose as to what 
               <lb/>
               was to constitute the carrying on of the manu<lb break="no"/>facture without which the patent would, 
               <lb/>
               within three years, become void. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> contended that the manufac<lb break="no"/>ture should require to be continuous from 
               <lb/>
               the time of being commenced. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> defended the clause 
               <lb/> 
               as it stood, and argued that it should be left 
               <lb/>
               to the Commissioner of Patents, what con<lb break="no"/>stituted a carrying on of the manufacture. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The clause was agreed to. At the sugges<lb break="no"/>tion of Mr. Blake, 3lst clause was altered so 
               <lb/>
               as not to exclude British subjects and render 
               <lb/>
               them liable to residence in any of the Prov<lb break="no"/>inces for a year. The remaining clauses having 
               <lb/>
               been adopted in Committee. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> said he rose to express 
               <lb/>
               as an old friend, his intense sympathy with 
               <lb/>
               the position in which the hon. Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Public Works was placed. Last session that 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentleman’s colleagues stripped his ofﬁce 
               <lb/>
               of the only great duty he had to perform in 
               <lb/>
               the construction of the Intercolonial Railway. 
               <lb/>
               This session they had taken out of his hands 
               <lb/>
               that other great question which he had made 
               <lb/>
               
          
            <pb n="589" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0589.jpg"/>
            
           
               peculiarly his own, the acquisition of the 
               <lb/>
               North-West Territory. Tonight he had not 
               <lb/>
               been allowed even the poor comfort of tak<lb break="no"/>ing this Patent Bill through Committee. These 
               <lb/>
               repeated indignities being heaped upon his 
               <lb/>
               (Mr. Holton’s) hon. friend were very much 
               <lb/>
               deprecated. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> desired to relieve the 
               <lb/>
               hon. member for Chateauguay of the too 
               <lb/>
               heavy current sympathy which threatened to 
               <lb/>
               drown the heart and affections of that hon. 
               <lb/>
               member. The Patent Bill had been carried 
               <lb/>
               through Committee by him (Sir George 
               <lb/>
               Cartier) simply because his hon. colleague 
               <lb/>
               happened to be absent when the Bill was sent 
               <lb/>
               in from the Senate. It was to be hoped this 
               <lb/>
               explanation would prevent the noble heart of 
               <lb/>
               the member for Chateauguay from throbbing 
               <lb/>
               needlessly. (Laughter.) The hon. gentleman, 
               <lb/>
               amid roars of laughter, went into what he 
               <lb/>
               called physiology or bumpology to sustain his 
               <lb/>
               position, and expressed the hope that he had 
               <lb/>
               thereby relieved the member for Chateauguay 
               <lb/>
               in his dolorous sympathy. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> thought the member for 
               <lb/>
               Chateauguay unjust towards the Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Militia, as it was well known that hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman was always ready for any description 
               <lb/>
               of business on the shortest notice. (Laughter). 
               <lb/>
               He was like a well-known English statesman, 
               <lb/>
               who pressed himself as ready to take com<lb break="no"/>mand of the army, the Channel ﬂeet, or 
               <lb/>
               govern England. (Laughter). As for the 
               <lb/>
               measure before the House, it would, perhaps, 
               <lb/>
               have been better had it been conducted 
               <lb/>
               through by the Minister of Public Works, 
               <lb/>
               who would, at all events, have listened to 
               <lb/>
               some of the suggestions made in the amend<lb break="no"/>ment. (Hear). 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> thought, that though 
               <lb/>
               the member for Chateauguay might be sin<lb break="no"/>cere enough in his sympathy, the House and 
               <lb/>
               country would, under the circumstances, 
               <lb/>
               believe that there was something else meant 
               <lb/>
               than a mere expression of sympathy. For 
               <lb/>
               himself, he was not conscious that there was 
               <lb/>
               any occasion for the expression of sympathy. 
               <lb/>
               His relations with his colleagues had been of 
               <lb/>
               the most pleasant and agreeable character. 
               <lb/>
               Any claims or credit due to him he was quite 
               <lb/>
               ready to share with his colleagues. As to the 
               <lb/>
               North-West acquisition, he thought he was 
               <lb/>
               serving the Province in according cheerfully 
               <lb/>
               to his hon. friend that position in the negotia<lb break="no"/>tions, to which his seniority entitled him. As 
               <lb/>
               to the manner in which the negotiations 
               <lb/>
               were conducted by that hon. gentleman, as 
               <lb/>
               well as by his conduct of the measure in that 
               <lb/>
               House, and the support he brought to carry 
               <lb/>
            
            <pb n="590" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-02_Page_0590.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">590</fw> 
               <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 2, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
   
               it through, its success was in a great measure 
               <lb/>
               to be attributed. With regard to the present 
               <lb/>
               Bill, though the framework of it was sub<lb break="no"/>stantially his, he was quite content his hon. 
               <lb/>
               colleague should get the credit of carrying it 
               <lb/>
               through. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The Committee rose, and the reception of 
               <lb/>
               the report was ordered on Friday. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
   <div type="section">      
            
            <head>
               IMMIGRATION 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Hon. Mr. Langevin</persName> moved the House into 
               <lb/>
               Committee on the Bill respecting Immigration 
               <lb/>
               and Immigrants, Mr. Magill in the chair. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The Bill, as amended, was subsequently 
               <lb/>
               read a third time, and passed. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
   </div>

<div type="section">     
         
            
            <head>
               IMPROVEMENT OF HARBOURS IN 
               <lb/>
               THE MARITIME PROVINCES 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The House then went into Committee to 
               <lb/>
               consider the following resolution, on the mo<lb break="no"/>tion of the <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. Tilley</persName>;—“That it is 
               <lb/>
               expedient that provision shall be made, as 
               <lb/>
               hereinafter mentioned, for improving the 
               <lb/>
               harbours and channels, and facilitating the 
               <lb/>
               navigation at the several ports of Bathurst 
               <lb/>
               and Richibucto, New Brunswick; Mabou, 
               <lb/>
               Port Hood, Margaree and Cheticamp, in the 
               <lb/>
               Province of Nova Scotia; and for the purpose 
               <lb/>
               of making good to the Consolidated Revenue 
               <lb/>
               Fund any sums which may hereafter be voted 
               <lb/>
               by Parliament for that purpose, to authorize 
               <lb/>
               the Governor in Council to impose by procla<lb break="no"/>mation, from time to time, a tonnage duty 
               <lb/>
               not exceeding ten cents per ton on vessels 
               <lb/>
               entering any of the ports aforesaid mentioned 
               <lb/>
               in such proclamation, such duty to be pay<lb break="no"/>able not more than once in each year on any 
               <lb/>
               vessel not exceeding one hundred tons, and 
               <lb/>
               not more than twice in each year on any ves<lb break="no"/>sel exceeding one hundred tons measurement 
               <lb/>
               by register.” 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Report was concurred in, and the Bill 
               <lb/>
               founded thereon, which was introduced. 
               <lb/>
               Second reading to-morrow. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>
      <div type="section">      
            <head>
               DEPARTMENTAL REPORTS 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> was going to move the House 
               <lb/>
               again into Committee of Supply, when 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> called attention to the fact 
               <lb/>
               that there had yet been no audit of the public 
               <lb/>
               accounts, and it was not fair to ask the House 
               <lb/>
               to pass an opinion on them in that shape. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
    </div>     </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>