<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-06-10"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-06-10">10 June 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
   
     
         
           <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

           <date when="1975"/>.  
          

           <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="693"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-10_Page_693.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
       
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-24">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-24">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-10_Page_693">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-10_Page_693.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="693" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-10_Page_693.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="running">
               HOUSE OF COMMONS 
               <lb/></fw>
               <fw type="dateline">Thursday. June 10, 1869 
               <lb/></fw>
              

 <p>The Speaker took the chair at three o’clock. 
               <lb/></p>
               

            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Langevin brought down a return 
               <lb/>
               to the Address for a statement of all expenses 
               <lb/>
               connected with the survey and management 
               <lb/>
               of the Intercolonial Railway since the 1st 
               <lb/>
               April, 1868. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Cameron (Peel) introduced a Bill 
               <lb/>
               to amend and extend the charter of the 
               <lb/>
               Ontario Bank. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald moved that the 
               <lb/>
               House meet on Saturdays during the remain<lb break="no"/>der of the session, at 3 o’clock, and that the 
               <lb/>
               business be Government orders. Carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
    <div type="section">     
            
            <head>
               THE NORTH-WEST 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Rose brought down a message 
               <lb/>
               from His Excellency, recommending to the 
               <lb/>
               favourable consideration of the House resolu<lb break="no"/>tions as to a loan of £300,000 to pay the 
               <lb/>
               Hudson’s Bay Company, and £300,000 for 
               <lb/>
               opening up the North-West. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               On motion of Hon. Mr. Rose. the House re<lb break="no"/>solved to go into Commtitee of the Whole 
               <lb/>
               tomorrow to consider the said resolutions. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
    </div>

<div type="section">    
            
            <head>
               UNION OF NEWFOUNDLAND 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Rose moved concurrence in the 
               <lb/>
               resolutions reported from Committee of the 
               <lb/>
               Whole on the subject of the union of New<lb break="no"/>foundland with the Dominion of Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Blake rose to move an amendment 
               <lb/>
               having reference to that portion of the reso<lb break="no"/>lution, which applied to the acquisition by 
               <lb/>
               Canada of the public lands of Newfoundland. 
               <lb/>
               He would not wait till that resolution was 
               <lb/>
               moved, considering it material that amend<lb break="no"/>ments should be submitted at once, inasmuch 
               <lb/>
               as if it succeeded it would displace the whole 
               <lb/>
               of the present scheme, which would have to 
               <lb/>
               be re-arranged upon some other basis. He was 
               <lb/>
               opposed to the acquisition by Canada of the 
               <lb/>
               public lands of Newfoundland. He was deci<lb break="no"/>dedly opposed to the loss by Newfoundland 
               <lb/>
               of the public lands. The British North Amer<lb break="no"/>ica Act provided that the public lands of 
               <lb/>
               each of the Provinces which were by that 
               <lb/>
               Act united should be retained by those prov<lb break="no"/>inces. He believed the policy carried out by 
               <lb/>
               the Act in that respect was unquestionable. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>    
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>