<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_MB_1870-02-18"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-02-18">18 February 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>. 
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="68" to="69"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="77"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0068.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0069.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0077.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-08">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0068">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0068.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0069">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0069.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0077">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0077.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="68" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0068.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">68</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">
     February 18, 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     leading public men of both the great parties, 
     <lb/>
     who had so long and so fiercely struggled with 
     <lb/>
     each other, than the fact that in the presence of 
     <lb/>
     a great necessity, they had forgotten what was 
     <lb/>
     due to party, in order that they might accom<lb break="no"/>plish an important measure indispensable to 
     <lb/>
     the progress, properity and security of their 
     <lb/>
     common country. If there was any foundation 
     <lb/>
     for the statement of the honourable member 
     <lb/>
     for Lambton, as to the present critical condi<lb break="no"/>tion of our country, he must see that the same 
     <lb/>
     necessity existed for the patriotic combination 
     <lb/>
     of those who in the first place sacrificed party 
     <lb/>
     considerations for the accomplishment of the 
     <lb/>
     Confederation of British North America. He 
     <lb/>
     was persuaded, notwithstanding the remarks 
     <lb/>
     of the hon. gentleman who had just spoken, 
     <lb/>
     that the great Reform party who had sacrificed 
     <lb/>
     so much at the shrine of patriotism since the 
     <lb/>
     inception of the measure, would not recede 
     <lb/>
     from the position they had assumed when they 
     <lb/>
     declared in the face of the people that they 
     <lb/>
     would forget for a time the duty they owed to 
     <lb/>
     party, and combine with those with whom, 
     <lb/>
     throughout their political career, they had been 
     <lb/>
     placed in a position of the strongest antago<lb break="no"/>nism. It was only necessary to listen to the 
     <lb/>
     remarks of the hon. gentleman to see that the 
     <lb/>
     reasons which impelled the heads of the great 
     <lb/>
     parties in this country to combine and forget 
     <lb/>
     their previous hostility towards each other, 
     <lb/>
     still existed to impel them to preserve the same 
     <lb/>
     unflinching attitude which they believed the 
     <lb/>
     best interests of the people demanded. Did the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman wish the people to believe that 
     <lb/>
     this question was settled, when he told the 
     <lb/>
     House in such forcible terms that the Province 
     <lb/>
     of Nova Scotia was still disaffected, and that 
     <lb/>
     the North-West Territory was in the midst of 
     <lb/>
     an insurrection? Was the hon. gentleman, 
     <lb/>
     under such circumstances, prepared to light 
     <lb/>
     the torch of party discord, and return to the 
     <lb/>
     state of things that existed before the forma<lb break="no"/>tion of that political combination which had 
     <lb/>
     already achieved so much for the country at 
     <lb/>
     large? The House would not forget how, in the 
     <lb/>
     struggles for party ascendancy, denomination 
     <lb/>
     had been arrayed against denomination, 
     <lb/>
     nationality against nationality, section against 
     <lb/>
     section, until the credit of Canada was dragged 
     <lb/>
     down to the lowest ebb, and the credit of New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick and Nova Scotia also imperilled 
     <lb/>
     and, indeed, materially affected by the same 
     <lb/>
     causes. He regretted that the Hon. Mr. Brown, 
     <lb/>
     to whom honour would be ever accorded for 
     <lb/>
     the part he took in the inception of the Coali<lb break="no"/>tion which had brought about such great 
     <lb/>
     results, should have thought proper, at the 
     <lb/>
     most critical period of our political history, to 
     <lb/>
     withdraw his support and co-operation from a 
     <lb/>
     Government, framed upon principles so elevat<lb break="no"/>ed and so essential to the best interests of the 
     <lb/>
   
        <!--    <p>
     [Hon. Mr. Tupper—L’hon. M. Tupper.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
           
            <pb n="69" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0069.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     18 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
           
     country. From the very first hour they came 
     <lb/>
     into power, they had steadily kept in view the 
     <lb/>
     patriotic object which they had pledged them<lb break="no"/>selves to accomplish. He had listened with the 
     <lb/>
     deepest attention to the criticism of gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     who had been former supporters of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment as well as of those who were their 
     <lb/>
     persistent opponents. They had pronounced the 
     <lb/>
     efforts of the Coalition to advance the great 
     <lb/>
     measure of Confederation entirely ineffective. 
     <lb/>
     He defied those honourable gentlemen to show 
     <lb/>
     in what respects there had been a failure. He 
     <lb/>
     would like them to point to the pages of history 
     <lb/>
     and show where as much had been done in as 
     <lb/>
     short a time in the case of any similar measure 
     <lb/>
     of national importance. That measure had con<lb break="no"/>solidated four millions of people who had been 
     <lb/>
     previously separated in different Provinces, 
     <lb/>
     embracing a territory of nearly four hundred 
     <lb/>
     thousand square miles exclusive of the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West. The political systems of the Provinces 
     <lb/>
     had been changed and brought under one gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, without a single blow being struck. 
     <lb/>
     Instead of resulting in failure, the combination 
     <lb/>
     of parties had led to the most magnificent 
     <lb/>
     success. In the Province of Nova Scotia a great 
     <lb/>
     change had been effected in a remarkably 
     <lb/>
     short time; it was only necessary to compare its 
     <lb/>
     present condition with that which it occupied 
     <lb/>
     when he first stood up to address that House, 
     <lb/>
     to see what the wise policy of the Administra<lb break="no"/>tion had accomplished. A calm and impartial 
     <lb/>
     review of the present situation of the Confed<lb break="no"/>eration, from one end to the other, would at 
     <lb/>
     once show that a great revolution had been 
     <lb/>
     effected peacefully and successfully, through 
     <lb/>
     the statesmanlike efforts of the men who had 
     <lb/>
     combined with the most patriotic aims in view. 
     <lb/>
     As respects the North-West difficulty, he 
     <lb/>
     entertained the most sanguine expectations 
     <lb/>
     that it would be speedily arranged most satis<lb break="no"/>factorily. This opinion was based on informa<lb break="no"/>tion he had derived from the visit he had been 
     <lb/>
     able to pay that country, only a few weeks 
     <lb/>
     previously. He had the pleasure of passing 
     <lb/>
     some days within the territory itself, and some 
     <lb/>
     weeks in a section of country characterized by 
     <lb/>
     similar natural features and resources; and he 
     <lb/>
     must say that his opinion of the capabilities of 
     <lb/>
     the country had been considerably elevated. He 
     <lb/>
     had listened, with great pain, to the remarks 
     <lb/>
     that had fallen from the honourable member 
     <lb/>
     from Terrebonne. The position that that hon<lb break="no"/>ourable gentleman had assumed, with respect 
     <lb/>
     to that delicate question, was untenable, and 
     <lb/>
     calculated to sacrifice the best interests of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. That territory afforded a field of 
     <lb/>
     immigration that could not be found in any 
     <lb/>
     other part of British North America. At an 
     <lb/>
     early day the House would have the satisfac<lb break="no"/>tion of knowing that, by the annexation of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West, they had not only strengthened 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            
            <pb n="77" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0077.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     18 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
            <p>
     ests of the country, that the House should wait 
     <lb/>
     until the policy of the Government on so 
     <lb/>
     important a question was brought down and 
     <lb/>
     fully explained. If the Finance Minister suc<lb break="no"/>ceeded in dealing with this great question in a 
     <lb/>
     manner satisfactory to the great commercial 
     <lb/>
     interests involved, he would obtain as he 
     <lb/>
     deserved the support of the House and the 
     <lb/>
     thanks of the country. After a calm and dispas<lb break="no"/>sionate review of the course pursued by the 
     <lb/>
     Government, he believed that a large majority 
     <lb/>
     of the House would agree with him in the 
     <lb/>
     opinion that the time had not arrived when 
     <lb/>
     power could be entrusted in the hands of the 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen opposite, without seriously retard<lb break="no"/>ing the great work of consolidating and 
     <lb/>
     extending the Confederation of British North 
     <lb/>
     America from Newfoundland to Vancouver’s 
     <lb/>
     Island, and imperiling the best interests of all 
     <lb/>
     classes of our people. (Loud cheering.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Huntington then reviewed the 
     <lb/>
     speech of the member for Cumberland. That 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman had no doubt good cause for 
     <lb/>
     congratulation. He had boasted that Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia had been conciliated, but though a few 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen had been conciliated, was there any 
     <lb/>
     more faith in the Dominion among the people 
     <lb/>
     of Nova Scotia? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Dr. Tupper said the people of Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia had as often as the opportunity offered, 
     <lb/>
     by large majorities endorsed the action of gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen who had joined the government, and 
     <lb/>
     more volunteers had offered themselves for 
     <lb/>
     enrolment than the Act required. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Huntington went on to refer to 
     <lb/>
     the North-West difficulties, and condemned 
     <lb/>
     the government’s policy on that question. It 
     <lb/>
     was the same policy, the same want of fore<lb break="no"/>sight, that they had followed in reference to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland and Prince Edward’s Island. 
     <lb/>
     There might be glory in future for Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, but the government deserved no credit<lb break="no"/>they were but carrying out the inevitable 
     <lb/>
     Imperial policy. The hon. member for Cumber<lb break="no"/>land should be the last man to ask them to give 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
          
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>