<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1947-04-25" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1947-04-25">25 April 1947</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

       
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Twentieth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1947"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmond Cloutier, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="2435" to="2436"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1947-04-25_Page_2435.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1947-04-25_Page_2436.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-30">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1947-04-25_Page_2435">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1947-04-25_Page_2435.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1947-04-25_Page_2436">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1947-04-25_Page_2436.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="2435" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1947-04-25_Page_2435.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">APRIL 25, 1947</fw>
             <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Private Bills</hi></fw>

            <fw type="num">2435</fw>
              
            
         
            
            <p>
              [...] pletely new area in Canada, an area that has 
               <lb/>
               great promise. Section 20 of the bill provides: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               The works and undertakings of the company 
               <lb/>
               are hereby declared to be for the general advan<lb break="no"/>tage of Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               I believe this bill is worthy of the support 
               <lb/>
               of every hon. member in this house. It will 
               <lb/>
               certainly open up a vast new mining area in 
               <lb/>
               Canada and provide employment in a part of 
               <lb/>
               the country which is devoid of opportunities 
               <lb/>
               for employment at the present time. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HAZE1">Mr. HAZEN</persName>: Is there any dominion legis<lb break="no"/>lation
               which provides for the payment of a <lb/> subsidy to a company that constructs a
                  rail<lb break="no"/>road declared to be for the general advantage <lb/> of Canada?
               <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CHEV2">Mr. CHEVRIER</persName>: I know of no such sub<lb break="no"/>sidy paid
               under conditions set out by my hon. <lb/> friend. At one time assistance was given
               for <lb/> the construction of branch lines, but that was <lb/> many years ago. That
               certainly is not the <lb/> policy of the government today. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HAZE1">Mr. HAZEN</persName>: Is there any legislation on <lb/> our statute books
               about it? <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CHEV2">Mr. CHEVRIER</persName>: None that I am aware of. <lb/>
            </p>
<p>
               Section agreed to. </p>
            
<p>
               Sections 2 to 6 inclusive agreed to. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               On section 7—Line of railway described. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACN2">Mr. MacNICOL</persName>: Is either the minister, the <lb/> hon. member who
               introduced the bill or the <lb/> minister of reconstruction in a position to say
               <lb/> whether it is the Marguerite, the Moisie or the <lb/> Wacouno-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:RINF1">Mr. RINFRET</persName> : The Mosie and the <lb/> Wacouno. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACN2">Mr. MacNICOL</persName>: That is a tributary of the <lb/> other river?
               <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:RINF1">Mr. RINFRET</persName>: That is right. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACN2">Mr. MacNICOL</persName>: Why is the Marguerite <lb/> mentioned, because it
               is ten miles west? <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CHUR1">Mr. CHURCH</persName>: I should like to ask a <lb/> question of the
               Secretary of State for External <lb/> Affairs. This section gives authority to the
               <lb/> company to construct and operate a line of <lb/> railway running into Labrador,
               which is not <lb/> a part of Canada. I would ask the minister <lb/> what is the
               meaning of these words: <lb/></p>
               
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">provided that authority be obtained from New<lb break="no"/>foundland for the construction and operation of 
               <lb/>
               this section of the railway—</quote>
               <lb/>
               
         
            
            <p>
               Note this: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               —thence northwesterly to a suitable port on 
               <lb/>
               Ungava bay. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
       
            <p>
               There is no port there at the present time. 
               <lb/>
               Will this interfere with the negotiations be<lb break="no"/><cb/>tween Canada and Newfoundland as to the 
               <lb/>
               latter joining Canada, announced in the house 
               <lb/>
               the other day by the Secretary of State for 
               <lb/>
               External Affairs? And where is the port on 
               <lb/>
               Ungava bay? Do the words I have quoted 
               <lb/>
               mean that this company can negotiate with 
               <lb/>
               another government over the head of the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of Canada? Can a private company 
               <lb/>
               and private people do this? I should like to 
               <lb/>
               know from the Minister of Transport whether 
               <lb/>
               the Canadian National Railways has aban<lb break="no"/>doned this territory on the St. Lawrence and 
               <lb/>
               in Labrador. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: I will try to answer <lb/> some of the
               questions involved in the request <lb/> made by the hon. member. What is being <lb/>
               done here has two aspects. One is the incor<lb break="no"/>poration of a company
               which thereby gets the <lb/> right to act as a person; the second is the <lb/> grant
               to that company of the right to build <lb/> a railway in Canadian territory. Under
               our <lb/> system no one, neither a company nor an <lb/> individual, can build a
               railway without a <lb/> charter from the government of Canada if it <lb/> is to be
               interprovincial or if it is to connect <lb/> Canada with another country, or from a
                  prov<lb break="no"/>ince if the railway is to be entirely within <lb/> the
               province. This parliament can grant no <lb/> rights to build a railway outside its
               territory, <lb/> but it can give a company the capacity to <lb/> receive such rights
               from the appropriate auth<lb break="no"/>ority. That matter came before the privy
                  coun<lb break="no"/>cil several years ago. One was a case con<lb break="no"/>cerning the John Deere Plow Company, and <lb/> the other was a case concerning the
               Bonanza <lb/> Creek Mining Company. The capacity to <lb/> receive powers can be
               granted by this parlia<lb break="no"/>ment in creating a corporation, and that is all
               <lb/> that this parliament can do with respect to <lb/> any portion of the railway
               that would be out<lb break="no"/>side Canadian territory. It can have the <lb/>
               capacity to receive a franchise from the sov<lb break="no"/>ereign of the territory
               outside Canada where <lb/> it may operate. I do not think that would be <lb/> dealing
               with a foreign government over the <lb/> head of the Canadian government any more
               <lb/> than it would in the case of a United States <lb/> company that gets a charter
               here for the <lb/> operation of a subsidiary in Canada. There <lb/> does not appear
               to be any international con<lb break="no"/>flict here. All states assert the right to
               give <lb/> companies the capacity to receive powers from <lb/> whosoever may be
               willing to grant powers to <lb/> them. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               With respect to the port on Ungava bay I 
               <lb/>
               have no information whatsoever. I do not 
               <lb/>
               know whether there is a port there or whether 
               <lb/>
               one can be developed there. But reading the 
               <lb/>
               bill I gather that the intention is to have a 
               <lb/>
               
       
            <pb n="2436" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1947-04-25_Page_2436.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">2436</fw>
               <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Private Bills</hi></fw> 
               
<fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
        
               railway that would go out of Canada, through 
               <lb/>
               Labrador, then come back into Canada and 
               <lb/>
               proceed through Canadian territory to Ungava 
               <lb/>
               bay. But the company will not be able, under 
               <lb/>
               this charter, to do anything outside Canada 
               <lb/>
               without getting a franchise from the sovereign 
               <lb/>
               of the territory outside Canada where it 
               <lb/>
               may desire to operate. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CHUR1">Mr. CHURCH</persName>: We are a party to Great <lb/> Britain's granting of
               a ninety-nine year lease, <lb/> binding Canada with America, which is prac<lb break="no"/>tically a freehold of all the Newfoundland <lb/> bases, and that
               includes Labrador inland as <lb/> well as on the ocean. In view of that <lb/>
               agreement, have we the power as a parliament <lb/> to go into Newfoundland and give
               away, not <lb/> only the bases, but the land and the bay <lb/> where they are trying
               to develop a port? <lb/> Ungava bay is a big bay and they have no <lb/> port there
               yet, and the bill is in the dark <lb/> on it. Have we the power to do this in <lb/>
               view of the ninety-nine year lease made by <lb/> the British government with the
               United <lb/> States for the use of all these bases in New<lb break="no"/>foundland
               and right down to British Guiana, <lb/> Which is the size of Great Britain? You <lb/>
               know, Mr. Chairman, that in the last war <lb/> German boats came right up the St.
               Lawrence <lb/> and we had a secret meeting of parliament <lb/> in connection with
               that. I contend that <lb/> Canada is bound by that ninety-nine year <lb/> lease and
               that we have no power to part with <lb/> this property. <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               These people told the railway committee 
               <lb/>
               that they had dealt with a former Newfound<lb break="no"/>land government before the war. I would ask 
               <lb/>
               the Minister of Transport, what was the nature 
               <lb/>
               of the arrangement, if any, the said company 
               <lb/>
               made with the old provisional government of 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland? What form did it take? Was 
               <lb/>
               it just an act of the provisional government? 
               <lb/>
               If it was, no wonder Newfoundland went 
               <lb/>
               bankrupt. I think the committee is entitled 
               <lb/>
               to this information. Does not the agreement 
               <lb/>
               with the United States for a ninety-nine year 
               <lb/>
               lease of bases include not only the bases on 
               <lb/>
               the ocean but the bases on the land and in 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland and all of Labrador, and all 
               <lb/>
               the inlets on the coast? In the last war 
               <lb/>
               German boats were up near Iceland and 
               <lb/>
               Greenland, ofi' Newfoundland, and in the St. 
               <lb/>
               Lawrence and Hudson strait, and we had to 
               <lb/>
               send ships up there. It cost a lot of money 
               <lb/>
               and lives. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            <p>
               The House of Commons is passing this bill 
               <lb/>
               blindly, and we shall regret it in the days to 
               <lb/>
               come if we hand over all this territory to 
               <lb/>
               private ownership forever. It is not a work 
               <lb/>
               for the general advantage of Canada. It is 
               <lb/>
               
         <cb/>

               not even within Canada. So how can it be 
               <lb/>
               for the general advantage of Canada when the 
               <lb/>
               territory and inlets are not in Canada at all? 
               <lb/>
               We might just as well claim that inlets and 
               <lb/>
               coves in China are works for the general 
               <lb/>
               advantage of Canada. I should like to know 
               <lb/>
               if the legal department of the crown has been 
               <lb/>
               consulted about this bill. I do not like 
               <lb/>
               to worry the Minister of Justice. I shall not 
               <lb/>
               ask him for his legal opinion, but I think he 
               <lb/>
               should have been consulted as to whether 
               <lb/>
               this bill is worth the paper it is written on. 
               <lb/>
               It goes over the heads of the Canadian and 
               <lb/>
               British governments and over the head of the 
               <lb/>
               provisional government of Newfoundland. 
               <lb/>
               Great Britain had a temporary trusteeship 
               <lb/>
               over the whole country of Newfoundland while 
               <lb/>
               the war was on. I should like to know who 
               <lb/>
               drafted and recommended this bill. I think 
               <lb/>
               all that information should be on the table. 
               <lb/>
               So far as I am concerned I do not think it 
               <lb/>
               makes any difference. I feel that I have done 
               <lb/>
               my duty as a member of parliament in calling 
               <lb/>
               the attention of the committee to what is 
               <lb/>
               involved in this omnibus bill. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Most of the people are fine people. They 
               <lb/>
               are not being criticized personally at all. I 
               <lb/>
               do not blame them for coming to parliament 
               <lb/>
               and asking for this legislation, because this 
               <lb/>
               is a pretty easy institution which we have 
               <lb/>
               assembled here. Nobody would give away 
               <lb/>
               that property in this way if they owned it 
               <lb/>
               themselves. What we are dealing with here 
               <lb/>
               is the mining industry. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCKA3">Mr. McKAY</persName>: On first view this bill appears <lb/> to me to be a
               virtual monopoly. If that is so <lb/> I should like to ask the Minister of Trans<lb break="no"/>port whether it will prohibit the operation <lb/> of any other railway
               company in that par<lb break="no"/>ticular area. If it does not I cannot see that
               <lb/> there should be any real objection to the bill. <lb/> On the surface it does
               appear to me, though, <lb/> that it would prohibit all other railways from <lb/>
               going into that district. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CHEV2">Mr. CHEVRIER</persName>: I do not think there is <lb/> any difficulty in
               answering the hon. member's <lb/> question. This bill, no more than any other <lb/>
               bill which is approved by a. committee of <lb/> the house, creates a monopoly. Any
               other <lb/> corporation or company which seeks similar <lb/> rights can apply to
               parliament in the same <lb/> way as did this company, and its application <lb/> will
               be dealt with by the committee on rail<lb break="no"/>ways, canals and telegraph
               lines. While I <lb/> do not know what the answer would be, I am <lb/> sure that the
               committee would want to give <lb/> such corporation similar rights to these. The
               <lb/> answer is, therefore, that this bill does not <lb/> preclude another company
               from making <lb/> application. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>