<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1949-01-27" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1949-01-27">27 January 1949</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Twentieth Parliament, Fifth Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1949"/>. 
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmond Cloutier, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          

          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="18"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0015.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0016.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0017.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0018.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-09-25">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-09-25">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0015">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0015.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0016">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0016.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0017">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0017.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0018">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0018.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="15" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0015.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">JANUARY 27, 1949</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Business of the House</hi></fw> <fw type="num">15</fw>


<!-- GL, 2017-09-25, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day --> 
           <!-- <p>
     12, 1949, and that I had accepted his invi<lb break="no"/>tation. The United States ambassador called 
     <lb/>
     on me yesterday morning to extend the 
     <lb/>
     invitation. I told Mr. Steinhardt I would 
     <lb/>
     naturally be pleased to accept it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The President was kind enough to indicate 
     <lb/>
     that he would like to renew our acquaintance 
     <lb/>
     and to discuss the matters which are of 
     <lb/>
     common interest to our two countries as 
     <lb/>
     neighbours, and also the world situation as 
     <lb/>
     it affects our two countries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Everyone knows that the friendly personal 
     <lb/>
     relations between the late President Roose<lb break="no"/>velt and our Prime Minister were of inesti<lb break="no"/>mable advantage to this continent and to 
     <lb/>
     the world. President Truman has expressed 
     <lb/>
     the desire, which I fully share, to maintain 
     <lb/>
     these friendly personal relations between the 
     <lb/>
     leaders of the governments of our two 
     <lb/>
     countries. Hon. members will recall that 
     <lb/>
     President Truman visited Ottawa in June, 
     <lb/>
     1947, at the invitation of my predecessor, 
     <lb/>
     and that his Visit was both pleasant and 
     <lb/>
     beneficial. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     REPORTS AND PAPERS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Right Hon. L. S. St. Laurent</persName> (Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister): I table herewith, in English and 
     <lb/>
     in French, the terms of union of Newfound<lb break="no"/>land with Canada, and answers to the 
     <lb/>
     questions raised by the Newfoundland dele<lb break="no"/>gation when it was here discussing these 
     <lb/>
     terms of union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Also the orders in council passed since 
     <lb/>
     prorogation of the last session of parliament 
     <lb/>
     with respect to the transfer of duties; orders 
     <lb/>
     in council of August 17, 1948, November 5, 
     <lb/>
     1948, two of November 15, 1948, and 
     <lb/>
     December 8, 1948. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCA2">Hon. J. J. McCann</persName> (Minister of National 
     <lb/>
     Revenue): I desire to lay on the table the 
     <lb/>
     annual report of the Department of National 
     <lb/>
     Revenue for the year ended March 31, 1948, 
     <lb/>
     in English and in French. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I also wish to report that, with reference 
     <lb/>
     to the export of petroleum and pulpwood, no 
     <lb/>
     orders or regulations have been issued under 
     <lb/>
     the export of petroleum and pulpwood regu<lb break="no"/>lations established under chapter 63 of the 
     <lb/>
     Revised Statutes of Canada, 1927, since the 
     <lb/>
     last return made to parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With reference to the Canada-United King<lb break="no"/>dom income tax agreement, no orders or 
     <lb/>
     regulations have been issued under chapter 
     <lb/>
     38 of the Statutes of 1946, being the Canada- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     United Kingdom income tax agreement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With reference to the Canada—United King<lb break="no"/>dom succession duty agreement, no regula<lb break="no"/>tions or orders have been issued under chap<lb break="no"/>ter 39 of the statutes of 1946, being the 
     <lb/>
     Canada-United Kingdom succession duty 
     <lb/>
     agreement section. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
 
   
            <p>
     With reference to the Canada-United States 
     <lb/>
     tax convention, no orders or regulations have 
     <lb/>
     been issued under the convention relating to 
     <lb/>
     succession duties, enacted as chapter 31 of the 
     <lb/>
     statutes of 1934, since these were tabled in 
     <lb/>
     the house on March 20, 1946. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     (For complete list of reports and papers 
     <lb/>
     tabled, see <hi rendition="simple:italic">Votes and Proceedings</hi>, No. 2, 
     <lb/>
     January 27,- 1949.) 
     <lb/>
            </p></div>

   <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     HOUSE OF COMMONS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">APPOINTMENT OF DEPUTY CHAIRMAN OF 
<lb/>
     COMMITTEES OF THE WHOLE</head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Right Hon. L. S. St. Laurent</persName> (Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister): If I may have the unanimous con<lb break="no"/>sent of the house to do so, I should like at 
     <lb/>
     this time to move: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That William Henry Golding, Esquire, member for 
     <lb/>
     the electoral district of Huron-Perth, be appointed 
     <lb/>
     deputy chairman of committees of the whole house. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Some hon. Members: Hear, hear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: I thought the manner in 
     <lb/>
     which the hon. member performed his duties 
     <lb/>
     as deputy chairman of committees of the 
     <lb/>
     whole in previous sessions would assure me 
     <lb/>
     of the unanimous consent for which I have 
     <lb/>
     asked. I therefore move, seconded by the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Trade and Commerce (Mr. Howe), 
     <lb/>
     the foregoing motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p></div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     BUSINESS OF THE HOUSE 
            </head>

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     PRECEDENCE or GOVERNMENT BUSINESS 
     
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Right Hon. L. S. St. Laurent</persName> (Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister): Yesterday the discussion with 
     <lb/>
     regard to the procedure for today was con<lb break="no"/>cluded as follows, as reported in <hi rendition="simple:italic">Hansard</hi> at 
     <lb/>
     page 12: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Mr. St. Laurent: In order to avoid debate I am 
     <lb/>
     quite prepared to withdraw the motion and to trust 
     <lb/>
     that it will be the desire of hon. members tomorrow 
     <lb/>
     that we proceed with the debate on the address. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     The leader of the opposition (Mr. Drew) 
     <lb/>
     said: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     So that there may be no misunderstanding. I was 
     <lb/>
     dealing with a motion in a certain form. The Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister has indicated his willingness to withdraw 
     <lb/>
     that motion. We come now to another point. There 
     <lb/>
     can be no objection to proceeding with the debate 
     <lb/>
     in the usual way in so far as the mover and 
     <lb/>
     seconder are concerned. but I am unaware of any 
     <lb/>
     precedent for the leader of the opposition and the 
     <lb/>
     Prime Minister following immediately afterwards 
     <lb/>
     under such circumstances as we have here. I do 
     <lb/>
     not think that should be suggested. The speech 
     <lb/>
     from the throne has only been presented today. The 
     <lb/>
     debate is on that speech, and it is customary to 
     <lb/>
     afford the leader of the opposition an opportunity 
     <lb/>
     to examine it so that his remarks will deal with it. 
     <lb/>
     I want to make that observation now that the Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister has withdrawn the motion. I make the 
     <lb/>
     observation as to my views of the procedure on the 
     <lb/>
     debate merely for the purpose of avoiding any mis<lb break="no"/>understanding tomorrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     On the assumption that the foregoing repre<lb break="no"/>sented the feeling of the house generally, I 



            <pb n="16" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0016.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">16</fw>
            <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS</fw>
       
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Business of the House</hi></fw>
 

     now move that we proceed forthwith to con<lb break="no"/>sider the speech delivered yesterday by His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency to both houses of parliament. I 
     <lb/>
     understand that it is in order to make this 
     <lb/>
     kind of motion to apply to the proceedings of 
     <lb/>
     today only, but I would have no objection to 
     <lb/>
     its applying to the proceedings of the house 
     <lb/>
     until otherwise ordered by the house, if it is 
     <lb/>
     the desire of hon. members that the motion 
     <lb/>
     be in that form. I have it in the two alterna<lb break="no"/>tive forms: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That the speech of His Excellency the Governor 
     <lb/>
     General to both houses of parliament be taken into 
     <lb/>
     consideration forthwith. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Or: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That the speech of His Excellency the Governor 
     <lb/>
     General to both houses of parliament be taken into 
     <lb/>
     consideration forthwith and that this order have 
     <lb/>
     precedence over all other business except introduc<lb break="no"/>tion of bills and government notices of motions 
     <lb/>
     until otherwise ordered by the house. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     I am informed that as to the more complete 
     <lb/>
     motion, the technical objection can be raised 
     <lb/>
     that forty-eight hours' notice has not been 
     <lb/>
     given. If that objection is taken, I suggest 
     <lb/>
     the first form, which would provide for the 
     <lb/>
     speech being dealt with today. As to the 
     <lb/>
     observation of the leader of the opposition 
     <lb/>
     that since the speech was delivered only 
     <lb/>
     yesterday it would be unusual to require him 
     <lb/>
     to deal with it today, if he still feels that 
     <lb/>
     way about it, and wishes, after the mover and 
     <lb/>
     the seconder have been heard, to move the 
     <lb/>
     adjournment of the debate, we on this side 
     <lb/>
     of the house would raise no objection. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DREW2">Mr. George A. Drew</persName> (Leader of the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion): The proposal which has just been made 
     <lb/>
     by the Prime Minister is, I think, in accord 
     <lb/>
     with the suggestion I made at the conclusion 
     <lb/>
     of my remarks yesterday. While I am unable, 
     <lb/>
     of course, to indicate unanimous consent 
     <lb/>
     except in so far as I may be able to do so 
     <lb/>
     for the members of the party which I lead, 
     <lb/>
     I am quite prepared to consent to proceeding 
     <lb/>
     with the debate if the second motion which 
     <lb/>
     has been read is introduced; it is in accord<lb break="no"/>ance with the established practice. I do so 
     <lb/>
     on the understanding which has been indi<lb break="no"/>cated by the Prime Minister, that at the 
     <lb/>
     conclusion of the speech of the seconder I 
     <lb/>
     move adjournment of the debate in the usual 
     <lb/>
     way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:COLD1">Mr. Coldwell</persName>: I think that is quite satis<lb break="no"/>factory, Mr. Speaker. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LOW1">Mr. Low</persName>: That will be satisfactory to our 
     <lb/>
     group. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: I move, seconded by the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Trade and Commerce (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Howe): 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That the speech of His Excellency the Governor 
     <lb/>
    General to both houses of parliament be taken into 
     <lb/>consideration forthwith and that this order have 
 
            <cb/>
  
   
        
     precedence over all other business except introduc<lb break="no"/>tion of bills and government notices of motions until 
     <lb/>
     otherwise ordered by the house. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DREW2">Mr. Drew</persName>: Just to clarify the record on 
     <lb/>
     this point, Mr. Speaker, I have noted some<lb break="no"/>thing which I think should be explained to 
     <lb/>
     the house before we proceed with the debate. 
     <lb/>
     I received my copy of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Votes and Proceedings</hi> 
     <lb/>
     earlier in the day, and I find that the same 
     <lb/>
     copy is still on the desks of most of the mem<lb break="no"/>bers. A few minutes ago a new copy of 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Votes and Proceedings</hi> for yesterday was 
     <lb/>
     tabled. It includes two additional items 
     <lb/>
     which were not in the first printed copies 
     <lb/>
     distributed to the members this morning. 
     <lb/>
     The second of the additional items is a notice 
     <lb/>
     of motion by the Prime Minister. It reads 
     <lb/>
     as follows: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That on and after Monday, January 31, 1949, and 
     <lb/>
     every sitting day thereafter until and including 
     <lb/>
     Friday, February 11, 1949. government notices of 
     <lb/>
     motions and government orders shall have prece<lb break="no"/>dence over all other business except introduction of 
     <lb/>
     bills. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     On inquiry I found that the copy which 
     <lb/>
     contains the motion I have just read is not 
     <lb/>
     yet on the desks of most hon. members. I 
     <lb/>
     think it would clarify the procedure if we 
     <lb/>
     could be told why one copy of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Votes and Pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings</hi> was delivered and then a subsequent 
     <lb/>
     copy delivered which contains a new and 
     <lb/>
     very important motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Speaker</persName>: I must say to the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man that I shall look into the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: I can give an answer to 
     <lb/>
     the leader of the opposition right away. As. 
     <lb/>
     I announced in the house yesterday afternoon, 
     <lb/>
     I gave notice of this motion, which is the last 
     <lb/>
     item on the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Votes and Proceedings</hi> that the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman has just read, and when I got 
     <lb/>
     the first issue of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Votes and Proceedings</hi> this. 
     <lb/>
     morning I was surprised to find it was not 
     <lb/>
     there. I communicated with the Clerk of the 
     <lb/>
     House, who verified the fact that he had it, 
     <lb/>
     but through some omission it had not gone 
     <lb/>
     to the printer. He told me that it was not 
     <lb/>
     the first time that there had been an over<lb break="no"/>sight of this kind, and that he would see that 
     <lb/>
     the printer had the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Votes and Proceedings</hi> 
     <lb/>
     completed in time for the sitting this after<lb break="no"/>noon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I think I might take this opportunity to say 
     <lb/>
     that I have had representations from hon. 
     <lb/>
     members on both sides of the house, who, in 
     <lb/>
     spite of their realization of the urgency of 
     <lb/>
     proceeding with the Newfoundland terms of 
     <lb/>
     union so that we may have them dealt with 
     <lb/>
     by this parliament and subsequently by the 
     <lb/>
     parliament of the United Kingdom before 
     <lb/>
     March 31, feel they would like to have all 
     <lb/>
     next week devoted to the debate on the 
     <lb/>
     address. When this motion is called tomorrow, 
   

            <pb n="17" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0017.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">JANUARY 27, 1949</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Address-Mr. Brown</hi></fw> <fw type="num">17</fw>
         

     if I can have the consent of the house to do 
     <lb/>
     so, I shall substitute for the dates that are 
     <lb/>
     mentioned the corresponding dates one week 
     <lb/>
     later. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SPEECH FROM THE THRONE 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">ADDRESS IN REPLY, MOVED BY MR. D. F. BROWN 
<lb/>
     (ESSEX WEST) AND SECONDED BY MR. LEOPOLD 
     <lb/>
     DEMERS (LAVAL-TWO MOUNTAINS)</head>
   
            <p>
     The house proceeded to the consideration 
     <lb/>
     of the speech delivered by His Excellency the 
     <lb/>
     Governor General at the opening of the 
     <lb/>
     session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BROW2">Mr. D. F. Brown</persName> (Essex West): In rising to 
     <lb/>
     propose a resolution of appreciation to His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency, the Governor General of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     for his gracious speech addressed to both 
     <lb/>
     houses of parliament, the people of the con<lb break="no"/>stituency of Essex West, which I have the 
     <lb/>
     pleasure to represent in this house, are 
     <lb/>
     honoured and privileged to join with 
     <lb/>
     Canadians from the Atlantic to the Pacific in 
     <lb/>
     our tribute of loyalty and affection to His 
     <lb/>
     Majesty, George VI, our king, and his gracious 
     <lb/>
     consort, Queen Elizabeth. We do this, not 
     <lb/>
     with a feeling of subservience or subordina<lb break="no"/>tion, but with the dignity of fidelity and 
     <lb/>
     allegiance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We recognize and admire the attitude of 
     <lb/>
     sincerity which Their Majesties attach to 
     <lb/>
     their high office, their kindliness to the prob<lb break="no"/>lems affecting their millions of subjects, their 
     <lb/>
     thoughtfulness of those afflicted, and the 
     <lb/>
     standard they have set for the world in their 
     <lb/>
     domestic lives by the grace, gentility and 
     <lb/>
     simplicity of their home living. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Canadians in all walks of life have learned 
     <lb/>
     with rejoicing of His Majesty's recent 
     <lb/>
     recovery from a serious physical disorder, and 
     <lb/>
     have breathed a prayer of thanksgiving for 
     <lb/>
     his restoration to health and strength. We 
     <lb/>
     humbly express to him our sympathy in the 
     <lb/>
     discomfort and suffering which he has 
     <lb/>
     endured, but are consoled by the promise that 
     <lb/>
     "the darkest hour precedes the dawn". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The British commonwealth of nations for 
     <lb/>
     many years has looked, hopefully and expect<lb break="no"/>antly, for word of an heir to the throne. On 
     <lb/>
     November 14, 1948, this long awaited promise 
     <lb/>
     was fulfilled in the birth of "wee Bonnie 
     <lb/>
     Prince Charlie" to Her Royal Highness Prin<lb break="no"/>cess Elizabeth and the Duke of Edinburgh. 
     <lb/>
     To the parents of the baby, christened Charles 
     <lb/>
     Philip Arthur George of Edinburgh, we 
     <lb/>
     extend our sincere congratulations. To the 
     <lb/>
     baby, all Canada extends its hope and prayer 
     <lb/>
     for a lifetime of health for himself, happiness 
     <lb/>
     with his family, and success in his relation<lb break="no"/>ship with his loyal subjects. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>


   
            <p>
     The year just passed has brought many 
     <lb/>
     changes in our national life and personalities. 
     <lb/>
     The Right Hon. William Lyon Mackenzie 
     <lb/>
     King, who had held office longer than any 
     <lb/>
     other prime minister in the British empire, 
     <lb/>
     retired from his post as Prime Minister and 
     <lb/>
     leader of the Liberal party. Mr. King's 
     <lb/>
     dynamic leadership of the House of Commons, 
     <lb/>
     his unbounded energy in upholding that 
     <lb/>
     which he thought best for his country, and 
     <lb/>
     his unfailing courtesy, thoughtfulness and 
     <lb/>
     kindness, will always be an inspiration to the 
     <lb/>
     members of this house. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A man of peace, who abhorred war, he led 
     <lb/>
     Canada Victoriously through the bitter storm 
     <lb/>
     and strife of conflict into the calm harbour 
     <lb/>
     of peace and prosperity, with distinction to 
     <lb/>
     himself and with honour to his country. His 
     <lb/>
     career of self-sacrificing service will be a 
     <lb/>
     beacon light to the youth of Canada for 
     <lb/>
     generations yet unborn. His followers will 
     <lb/>
     remember his uncanny insight and perspica<lb break="no"/>city ; the opposition will remember him for 
     <lb/>
     his vigour and tenacity; but the little people 
     <lb/>
     of Canada will remember him as their friend 
     <lb/>
     and champion. History will be very kind to 
     <lb/>
     William Lyon Mackenzie King. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     During the past year the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Neepawa (Mr. Bracken) found it necessary to 
     <lb/>
     retire as leader of the official opposition. 
     <lb/>
     During his term the hon. member endeared 
     <lb/>
     himself to all members of this house, regard<lb break="no"/>less of party affiliations, by his warmth of 
     <lb/>
     friendliness, his vigour of opposition in the 
     <lb/>
     house, and his courtesy and affability outside 
     <lb/>
     the house. We wish him well. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the turning of the pages of the history 
     <lb/>
     of this house, we are now proud to have as 
     <lb/>
     our leader one who is truly a Canadian of 
     <lb/>
     distinction—Right Hon. Louis Stephen St. 
     <lb/>
     Laurent. Mr. St. Laurent, having heard the 
     <lb/>
     clear call of duty, has rejected personal placid 
     <lb/>
     interests to accept the highest post of service 
     <lb/>
     to his country—that of Prime Minister. In 
     <lb/>
     this arduous position he will have every 
     <lb/>
     opportunity of displaying to the fullest extent 
     <lb/>
     his widely known powers of conciliation and 
     <lb/>
     sagacity. We on this side of the house are 
     <lb/>
     privileged to serve under his benevolent 
     <lb/>
     direction and admonition. May Canada con<lb break="no"/>tinue to prosper and expand in stature among 
     <lb/>
     the nations of the world during his term of 
     <lb/>
     office. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It has been said that a government is as 
     <lb/>
     strong as its opposition. We are also welcom<lb break="no"/>ing a new leader of the official opposition, 
     <lb/>
     who comes to this chamber with many years 
     <lb/>
     of experience as premier of my own prov<lb break="no"/>ince, the province of Ontario. He has shown 
     <lb/>
     much energy and aggressiveness in his public 
     <lb/>
     career. We trust that his leadership of the 
     <lb/>
     opposition will be vigorous and constructive. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-27_Page_0018.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">18</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Address—Mr. Brown</hi></fw> <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS</fw> 


   
            <p>
     On the 11th day of December, 1948, an 
     <lb/>
     agreement was entered into by the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     of Canada having the effect of bringing into 
     <lb/>
     the confederation of the Dominion of Canada 
     <lb/>
     the province of Newfoundland, thus uniting 
     <lb/>
     in legislative matters two branches of the 
     <lb/>
     British commonwealth of nations, living side 
     <lb/>
     by side and having similar hopes and ideals. 
     <lb/>
     The people of my constituency join with all 
     <lb/>
     Canada in extending a warm and cordial wel<lb break="no"/>come to Newfoundland, the tenth province of 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian family of provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The agreement for union of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     has not come about without having to hurdle 
     <lb/>
     many obstacles; but with two groups of 
     <lb/>
     people, such as Canada and Newfoundland, 
     <lb/>
     with the same customs, principles, and aspir<lb break="no"/>ations, the union would seem to be natural. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Upon referendum submitted to the people 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland, the desire to enter into 
     <lb/>
     confederation with Canada was expressed. 
     <lb/>
     Subsequently representatives of Canada and 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland met and determined the 
     <lb/>
     arrangements for the union, which upon 
     <lb/>
     approval of the parliament of Canada will 
     <lb/>
     come into effect on the 3lst day of March 
     <lb/>
     next. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Canada and Newfoundland have much in 
     <lb/>
     common for a union. Both have the same 
     <lb/>
     heritage in freedom of action, speech and 
     <lb/>
     religion. Both have the same political tradi<lb break="no"/>tions. Both have grown to maturity side by 
     <lb/>
     side, and each has been able to observe the 
     <lb/>
     progress of the other. Both have realized 
     <lb/>
     that in a fast—moving world they need one 
     <lb/>
     another for their common defence. Both see 
     <lb/>
     that the greatest good, by way of special 
     <lb/>
     reforms and security, can come to the ordin<lb break="no"/>ary citizen in both places only if united we 
     <lb/>
     stand. We believe we can offer to Newfound<lb break="no"/>land much in the way of trade, but we need 
     <lb/>
     also what Newfoundland has to contribute. 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland has lumber and pulpwood; it 
     <lb/>
     has fish and sea foods. It has vast deposits of 
     <lb/>
     iron ore and other metals. But, more than 
     <lb/>
     anything else, we welcome the people of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. We realize they are a proud 
     <lb/>
     people, of rugged nature, strong and indus<lb break="no"/>trious, anxious to take their full share of 
     <lb/>
     responsibility, and that they expect their full 
     <lb/>
     share of the gains. We Canadians are proud 
     <lb/>
     to become associated with them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We will undoubtedly encounter differences 
     <lb/>
     of opinion from time to time; but, having 
     <lb/>
     visited each of the nine existing provinces of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, I have observed that, while govern<lb break="no"/>ments may often disagree, the common people 
     <lb/>
     of our dominion have the same high goal 
     <lb/>
     always before them—that of peace, industry, 
     <lb/>
     integrity, and security. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is in this spirit of partnership that we 
     <lb/>
     extend our welcome to the tenth province of 
     <lb/>
          
   
   

            <cb/>

        
     the Dominion of Canada, the province of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland. 
            </p>
            

            <p>
     My constituency, that of Essex West, 
     <lb/>
     borders on the Detroit river for approximately 
     <lb/>
     fifteen miles. Discussions on the St. Law<lb break="no"/>rence waterway development are therefore of 
     <lb/>
     vital interest to us, as they should be to all 
     <lb/>
     other parts of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     By our methods of production we in Canada 
     <lb/>
     do not depend upon domestic markets. We 
     <lb/>
     are a trading nation. We export to the four 
     <lb/>
     corners of the world. In fact I believe we 
     <lb/>
     export about one-third of all the goods we 
     <lb/>
     produce. This probably would be much 
     <lb/>
     higher in my own constituency. We are 
     <lb/>
     therefore most anxious to devise ways and 
     <lb/>
     means by which, wherever and whenever 
     <lb/>
     possible, we can reduce the cost of the goods 
     <lb/>
     we produce and at the same time maintain 
     <lb/>
     our high level of living. One of the items 
     <lb/>
     which contribute to the increased price of 
     <lb/>
     our goods in competition with other goods of 
     <lb/>
     a similar nature on the world market is that 
     <lb/>
     of transportation of our goods to the consumer 
     <lb/>
     in the distant land. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Canada has access to 2,400 miles of water<lb break="no"/>ways from Fort William to the Atlantic ocean. 
     <lb/>
     This great waterway, for the most part, is of 
     <lb/>
     deep navigable water with a height of 600 
     <lb/>
     feet of falling energy. This waterway is 
     <lb/>
     similar to a series of saucepans with the spout 
     <lb/>
     of one dropping into the pan below, but with 
     <lb/>
     the spout of the final saucepan corroded with 
     <lb/>
     rocks, timber, and fear—fear of debt and 
     <lb/>
     disaster. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Time passes on. When Jacques Cartier 
     <lb/>
     sailed up the St. Lawrence to claim the 
     <lb/>
     wilderness for France, little did he realize 
     <lb/>
     what he was starting—for this was the first 
     <lb/>
     link in the chain of events which has led to 
     <lb/>
     the struggle to obtain a free outlet to the sea 
     <lb/>
     —a freedom from the bonds of nature. 
     <lb/>
     Champlain, La Salle and all the great explor<lb break="no"/>ers have seen the need for this direct water 
     <lb/>
     route from the sea to that great inland 
     <lb/>
     empire of Canada. And now it is hoped the 
     <lb/>
     final removal of the impediment of the ages 
     <lb/>
     will be realized. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Since the days of the early settlers in 
     <lb/>
     Canada, wheelbarrows have become bull<lb break="no"/>dozers; the old buckboard has become the 
     <lb/>
     sleek sedan; the magic lantern, the television 
     <lb/>
     set. The sailing vessel has become the modern 
     <lb/>
     oil burner. And the steamships have grown 
     <lb/>
     from the impressive length of 250 feet and a 
     <lb/>
     capacity of 2,000 tons to the ships of today 
     <lb/>
     with a length of 600 feet and capacity of 
     <lb/>
     20,000 tons. Ships of this latter class pass 
     <lb/>
     along the border of my constituency unnoticed 
     <lb/>
     every few minutes of the day for eight or 
     <lb/>
     nine months of the year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>