<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1869-04-21"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-04-21">21 April 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
 
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

           <date when="1975"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="38"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-21_Page_0037.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-21_Page_0038.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="nguyenkim" when="2017-01-16"> Marked-up people. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-21_Page_0037">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-21_Page_0037.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-21_Page_0038">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-21_Page_0038.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="37" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-21_Page_0037.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               21 avril 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p>
               [...] Insolvency Law was acceptable to the House, 
               <lb/>
               he thought it would be found that the details 
               <lb/>
               could be discussed with most advantage in 
               <lb/>
               Committee of the Whole. He had no intention 
               <lb/>
               to hurry the measure, and introduced it thus 
               <lb/>
               early in order that they might receive upon 
               <lb/>
               it the views of the commercial men of all 
               <lb/>
               parts of the country. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The second reading was put down for 
               <lb/>
               Friday. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> brought down a <lb/> message from His
               Excellency, graciously <lb/> acknowledging the Address by the House, <lb/> in reply
               to the Speech from the Throne. <lb/>
            </p>
            
       <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">GALT vs. CHANDLER 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:GALT1">Hon. Mr. Galt</persName> gave notice for Friday next <lb/> of an address
                  to His Excellency for copies <lb/> of all correspondence with the Imperial <lb/>
                  Government, relating to the outlay incurred <lb/> by Canada in the defence of the
                  frontier of <lb/> the United States, in 1863 and 1864, and also <lb/> arising out
                  of the threatened Fenian invasion <lb/> subsequently, as constituting a claim for
                  <lb/> indemnity from the United States. He said his <lb/> object in giving this
                  notice was to afford the <lb/> House and opportunity of expressing their <lb/>
                  opinions upon the very extraordinary proceed<lb break="no"/>ings which took place
                  in Washington on <lb/> Monday last, when there was referred to the <lb/> Committee
                  on Foreign Relations a resolution <lb/> of Senator Chandler, whereby it was
                  quietly <lb/> proposed that all the British North American <lb/> possessions
                  should be given to the United <lb/> States in liquidation of the <hi
                     rendition="simple:italic">Alabama</hi> claims. <lb/> He thought that was a
                  question which should <lb/> be discussed in this House, and he had <lb/> therefore
                  given this notice. <lb/>
               </p>
       </div>    
         
            <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">STANDING COMMITTEE 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> On motion of <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> the <lb/> House concurred in
                  the lists of Standing <lb/> Committees reported yesterday. <lb/>
               </p>
            </div>     
         
            <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">PRINTING COMMITTEE 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> On motion of <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> a message was <lb/> ordered to be
                  sent to the Senate requesting <lb/> their Honours to appoint members of a Joint
                  <lb/> Committee on printing. <lb/>
               </p>
            
            </div>

<div type="section"> 
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">NEWFOUNDLAND 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> brought down a <lb/> message from His
                  Excellency, transmitting <lb/> a copy of a despatch from the Governor of <lb/>
                  Newfoundland of the 20th March, 1869, for<lb break="no"/>warding copies of
                  resolutions passed by the <lb/>
                  <pb n="38" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-21_Page_0038.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">38</fw>
                  <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline"> April 21, 1869<lb/>
                  </fw> Council and Assembly of Newfoundland, stat<lb break="no"/>ing the terms on
                  which they would consider <lb/> It expedient to join the Dominion of Canada. <lb/>
               </p>
</div>      
         
      <div type="section">   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">MURRAY CANAL
            </head>
<p> In reply to Mr. Keeler,<lb/>
               </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> said the state of the finances <lb/> would not
                  permit the Government this year <lb/> to recommend an appropriation for the <lb/>
                  construction of the Murray Canal. <lb/>
               </p>
            
      </div>

<div type="section">  
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">RECIPROCITY<lb/></head>
            
<p> In reply to Mr. Bechard, <lb/>
               </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> said the Government were <lb/> not in
                  possession of any official information <lb/> on the subject of negotiating a
                  Reciprocity <lb/> Treaty with the United States. <lb/>
               </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">RATE OF INTEREST<lb/></head>
           
 <p> In reply to Mr. Masson (Soulanges), <lb/>
               </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> said the question of intro<lb break="no"
                  />ducing a measure to limit the rate of interest <lb/> throughout the Dominion was
                  at present <lb/> under the consideration of the Government. <lb/>
               </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">   
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">FATHER McMAHON<lb/></head>
           
 <p> In reply to Mr. Masson (Soulanges), <lb/>
               </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said it was not the <lb/> present
                  intention of the Government to make <lb/> any recommendation as to exercising the
                  <lb/> royal prerogative of mercy, in favour of Rev. <lb/> Father McMahon and the
                  other Fenian pris<lb break="no"/>oners. <lb/>
               </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">    
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">MAIL SERVICE<lb/></head>
           
 <p> In reply to Mr. Cameron (Inverness),<lb/>
               </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said the subject <lb/> of ferrying the
                  mail across the Strait of <lb/> Canso was now under the consideration of <lb/> the
                  Post-office Department, with a view to <lb/> having the ferry at such a place as
                  would <lb/> meet the views and interests of the inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants. <lb/>
               </p>
            
</div>   
            
      <div type="section">  
            
<head rendition="simple:centre">P. O. SAVINGS BANKS<lb/></head>
           
 <p> In reply to Mr. Paquet, <lb/>
               </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> stated the Government might <lb/> probably
                  raise the amount which might be <lb/> received by the Post-office Savings Banks
                  <lb/> above the present maximum of $1,000, but [...]
               </p>
            
      </div>      
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>