<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1870-04-21" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-04-21">21 April 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1870">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.

         
           <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.    
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1140" to="1140"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-04-21_Page_1140.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
         
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-04-21_Page_1140">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-04-21_Page_1140.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1140" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-04-21_Page_1140.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1140</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               April 21, 1870<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
            <p>
              [...] told last year that the Territory was to cost 
               <lb/>
               £300,000, but he found that the Government 
               <lb/>
               had sent out orders through the militia with a 
               <lb/>
               view to take possession of this Territory. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir George-È. Cartier</persName> said that the <lb/> item did not at
               all go for military purposes, it <lb/> was merely for opening communication. The
               <lb/> Red River question was too large to come up at <lb/> the present time. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MASS3">Mr. Masson</persName> said if no part of the sum was to <lb/> be employed
               for military purposes there could <lb/> be no objection to accepting his amendment.
               <lb/> The intention of the Government was to send a <lb/> military force. He had
               twice offered his ser<lb break="no"/>vices against the Fenians, but he could not
               <lb/> permit the Government to go and raise an <lb/> army to take possession of a
               country with <lb/> which they had nothing to do. The people of <lb/> the North-West
               ought to be put on the same <lb/> terms as the people of Newfoundland or Prince <lb/>
               Edward's Island. They had no idea of compell<lb break="no"/>ing those Provinces to
               enter the Union by force <lb/> of arms; and a different rule ought not to be <lb/>
               followed in the case of the North-West. If they <lb/> sent a soldier to that
               Territory there would be <lb/> a war of Catholics and Protestants. (No, no.) <lb/>
               There would be a war between nation and <lb/> nation, and race and race. (No, no.)
               And the <lb/> first shot that would be fired there would lose <lb/> us the Territory.
               (No.) He was well convinced <lb/> of that. He spoke from conviction, and a sense
               <lb/> of duty he owed to his constituency. He <lb/> thought that a peaceful policy
               would settle all <lb/> difficulties with less expense and greater satis<lb break="no"/>faction to the country. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—No, no, (hear). <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MASS3">Mr. Masson</persName> said that a war there would end <lb/> in a war with
               the United States. That was his <lb/> opinion, but he might be mistaken. It would be
               <lb/> satisfactory to no part of the country, for he <lb/> did not believe that there
               would be a single <lb/> man that would offer to go and take possession <lb/> of a
               country where they had no position at all. <lb/> No, it was for the Imperial
               Government to give <lb/> them peaceful possession of that territory, and <lb/> when
               they had it in peaceful possession he was <lb/> willing, old as he was, to go and
               defend it. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said that it <lb/> was quite clear
               that the resolution went much <lb/> further than Mr. Masson had gone in his <lb/>
               speech. He stated that if this vote did not go for <lb/> any military expenditure he
               would have no <lb/> objection to its passing, but it went much fur<lb break="no"/>ther, for it related to the general revenue of the <lb/> Dominion. The hon.
               gentleman's speech and <lb/> resolutions did not agree—his motion meant <lb/> one
               thing and his words another. It was too [...]</p>
            
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>