<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1948-04-20"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1948-04-20">20 April 1948</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Twentieth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
           

          <date when="1948"/>.    
          

         <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmond Cloutier, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="3157" to="3158"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-04-20_Page_3157.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-04-20_Page_3158.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-04-20_Page_3157">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-04-20_Page_3157.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-04-20_Page_3158">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-04-20_Page_3158.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="3157" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-04-20_Page_3157.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
     APRIL 20, 1948 
     <lb/>
            </fw><fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Dairy Industry Act</hi> </fw>
     <lb/>
    <fw type="num"> 3157 </fw>
    
    
     
            <p>
     ernment report concludes with one paragraph 
     <lb/>
     which I think I should put on record. Speak<lb break="no"/>ing 
  
      of margarine, it says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     Its manufacture has been and is still opposed 
     <lb/>
     by the dairy interests. These interests do not 
     <lb/>
     appear to realize that the national well-being of 
     <lb/>
     a people must come before sectional gains. At 
     <lb/>
     present there is not enough butter to meet the 
     <lb/>
     purchasing power of the nation, let alone its 
     <lb/>
     nutritional needs. Even if butter production is 
     <lb/>
     expanded to supply the needs of those who can 
     <lb/>
     afford it there will always be a very large group 
     <lb/>
     of people whose wages will be so low, in relation 
     <lb/>
     to the price of butter, that they could not aﬂord 
     <lb/>
     it at any price. The manufacture of margarine 
     <lb/>
     is intended to ﬁll the present gap between the 
     <lb/>
     production of and the demand for butter, and 
     <lb/>
     to supply the nutritional needs of the poorly 
     <lb/>
     paid groups in order to improve their health and 
     <lb/>
     working capacity. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>

            <p>
     What a splendid stand for our sister domin<lb break="no"/>ion 

     to have taken. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Within the last year another aspect has 
     <lb/>
     become apparent in the margarine situation, 
     <lb/>
     an international aspect brought about by two 
     <lb/>
     things, the Geneva trade agreements and the 
     <lb/>
     suggested entry of Newfoundland into  
     <lb/>
     con<lb break="no"/>federation. The Geneva trade agreements have 
     <lb/>
     been rightly heralded, by the democratic 
     <lb/>
     world at least, as a tremendous advance in 
     <lb/>
     international understanding and a breaking 
     <lb/>
     down of the barriers between nations to 
     <lb/>
     encourage world commerce and so stimulate 
     <lb/>
     world recovery; and none of the nations has 
     <lb/>
     so great a stake in this program as Canada, 
     <lb/>
     which is so dependent upon world markets. 
     <lb/>
     This great agreement was only reached, of 
     <lb/>
     course, through important concessions being 
     <lb/>
     made by each of the participating nations. One 
     <lb/>
     of those conditions is contained in article XI 
     <lb/>
     of the general agreement, which provides that 
     <lb/>
     there shall be no ban on the importation of 
     <lb/>
     any product of any of the signatory nations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Canadian experts who were at Geneva 
     <lb/>
     appeared before the senate committee last 
     <lb/>
     year and said that Canada had fought very 
     <lb/>
     hard against this condition because of our 
     <lb/>
     margarine situation, but that in the end we 
     <lb/>
     had given up and so were pledged to abide 
     <lb/>
     by that clause. Further evidence along that 
     <lb/>
     line was given in a statement by the leader 
     <lb/>
     of the government in the senate last year, 
     <lb/>
     which is found at page 34 of senate <hi rendition="simple:italic">Hansard</hi>, 
     <lb/>
     where he said in part: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     Under article XI of the general agreement we 
     <lb/>
     are bound to remove our ban on the import of 
     <lb/>
     oleomargarine. The product is not speciﬁcally 
     <lb/>
     mentioned, but we have bound ourselves to abstain 
     <lb/>
      from prohibitions of that nature. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>

            <p>
     Almost immediately following this declara<lb break="no"/>tion we were informed by a government press 
     <lb/>
     release, and I quote 
     <lb/></p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     . . . there is nothing in the Geneva agreement. 
     <lb/>
     nor is there apt to be anything in the Havana 
     <lb/>
          <cb/>

     modiﬁcation, to prevent us putting duties and 
     <lb/>
     taxes on the margarine as high as may be felt 
     <lb/>
     proper to leave the dairy industry completely 
     <lb/>
     undisturbed. 
     <lb/>
</quote>

            <p>
     If parliament should follow such a course; if 
     <lb/>
     we should agree in principle to the spirit of 
     <lb/>
     the agreements and then immediately turn 
     <lb/>
     around and by a cynical evasion impose 
     <lb/>
     tariffs which are in effect the ban which was 
     <lb/>
     just removed, then I say we as a nation are 
     <lb/>
     guilty of the most arrant hypocrisy. Further 
     <lb/>
     I say that if every other nation takes similar 
     <lb/>
     evasive methods to escape the concessions 
     <lb/>
     they made, then the Geneva trade agreements 
     <lb/>
     will not be worth the paper they are written 
     <lb/>
     on. They will be even more worthless, I 
     <lb/>
     would say, than our own signature if it is our 
     <lb/>
     intention to evade the spirit of the conces<lb break="no"/>sions 
    
      by some technicality. If we intend to 
     <lb/>
     abide by these agreements, then I say the 
     <lb/>
     only sort of tariff we can in honour place on 
     <lb/>
     the importation of margarine is one no higher 
     <lb/>
     than that we imposed when margarine was 
     <lb/>
     last imported into this country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Newfoundland proposals have an 
     <lb/>
     equally shocking implication. This sister 
     <lb/>
     country, with climate and geography much 
     <lb/>
     like our own, had another problem in com<lb break="no"/>mon 

      with us. They found their butter pro<lb break="no"/>duction 
     <lb/>
      was insufﬁcient to meet domestic 
     <lb/>
     needs; but they did not stick their heads in 
     <lb/>
     the sand like an ostrich. They embarked, 
     <lb/>
     after mature considerations, upon the manu<lb break="no"/>facture  
   
      of margarine, using mainly their own 
     <lb/>
     domestic oils; and margarine now sells for 
     <lb/>
     roughly half the price of butter there. When 
     <lb/>
     they inquired about the conditions under 
     <lb/>
     which they might enter confederation, natur<lb break="no"/>ally 
    
      they were most anxious to preserve this 
     <lb/>
     right and insisted upon it. The Dominion of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, in- its turn, agreed; with this pro<lb break="no"/>vision, 
    
      however, that margarine manufactured 
     <lb/>
     in Newfoundland could not cross the pro<lb break="no"/>vincial  
    
     boundaries. This amazing condition 
     <lb/>
     strikes at the very economic heart of the 
     <lb/>
     pact of confederation. Paragraph 121 of the 
     <lb/>
     British North America Act reads: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     All articles of the growth, produce or manu<lb break="no"/>facture of any one of the provinces shall, from 
     <lb/>
     and after the union, be admitted free into each 
     <lb/>
     of the other provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>

            <p>
     The fathers of confederation intended Canada 
     <lb/>
     to be one economic unit, not nine Balkan states 
     <lb/>
     with customs houses lining every provincial 
     <lb/>
     boundary. This provision, therefore, strikes 
     <lb/>
     at the very heart of the economic foundation 
     <lb/>
     of confederation. It can be achieved only by 
     <lb/>
     an amendment to section 121 of the British 
     <lb/>
     North America Act. This is an amazing 
     <lb/>
     thing. Apparently it is almost impossible to 
     <lb/>
     secure amendments to the British North 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="3158" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-04-20_Page_3158.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">3158 </fw>
   <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Dairy Industry Act</hi></fw> 
    <fw type="running">COMMONS  <lb/></fw>
    
   
           
     America Act for which the great bulk of the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian people long, such as an amend<lb break="no"/>ment Which will permit contributory old age 
     <lb/>
     pensions, an amendment which will permit 
     <lb/>
     national health insurance, or an amendment 
     <lb/>
     which will permit national control of labour 
     <lb/>
     legislation; but apparently no difﬁculty is 
     <lb/>
     anticipated in securing an amendment to the 
     <lb/>
     British North America Act which, though 
     <lb/>
     shaking confederation, will please the dairy 
     <lb/>
     industry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If such an amendment is obtained it will 
     <lb/>
     have to be one of two kinds. Either it will 
     <lb/>
     have speciﬁcally to mention margarine and 
     <lb/>
     the boundaries of Newfoundland, in which 
     <lb/>
     case we shall debase our national constitution 
     <lb/>
     by the mention of one trivial article of com<lb break="no"/>merce which is singled out for discriminatory 
     <lb/>
     treatment, or it will have to be a general 
     <lb/>
     amendment permitting other provinces to 
     <lb/>
     impose bans. So shortly we may have 
     <lb/>
     Ontario banning British Columbia apples, 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia banning Alberta coal, Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia banning Prince Edward Island potatoes, 
     <lb/>
     thus breaking down the economic heart of 
     <lb/>
     confederation. Such however, is the power of 
     <lb/>
     the butter industry in this country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now getting away from the principles 
     <lb/>
     behind this ban, or rather the lack of principles 
     <lb/>
     behind it, let me turn now and look at the 
     <lb/>
     various groups involved. Who are against 
     <lb/>
     margarine? Just one group: the dairy inter<lb break="no"/>ests of Canada; and for just one reason: they 
     <lb/>
     feel that the sale of margarine will affect 
     <lb/>
     their pocketbooks. One reason, a purely selﬁsh 
     <lb/>
     one, is behind this ban. They, of course, 
     <lb/>
     expand this reason into a much bigger sphere. 
     <lb/>
     They say it is more than that. They say the 
     <lb/>
     sale of margarine would depress the sale and 
     <lb/>
     price of butter. They say butter is the 
     <lb/>
     cornerstone of our dairy industry, so that it 
     <lb/>
     will depress the dairy industry. Then they 
     <lb/>
     say the dairy industry is the cornerstone of 
     <lb/>
     our agriculture, so that it will depress agricul<lb break="no"/>ture; and agriculture is the cornerstone of 
     <lb/>
     Canadian industry, so the eventual result of 
     <lb/>
     the lifting of the ban on margarine will be a 
     <lb/>
     national depression. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. CASE: That is right. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. SINCLAIR: My hon. friend across the 
     <lb/>
     way is quite familiar with ballads and poetry. 
     <lb/>
     I say that is exactly the same type of logic 
     <lb/>
     which traced the loss of a great battle back 
     <lb/>
     to the loss of a horseshoe nail. The same 
     <lb/>
     argument, of course, was used by the pro<lb break="no"/>ponents of the cotton law of the eighteenth 
     <lb/>
     century, except that then it was wool and 
     <lb/>
     linen which were the cornerstone of British 
     <lb/>
     industry. It was used again by the champions 
     <lb/>
     of the corn laws in the nineteenth century, 
     <lb/>
            
   
          <!--  <p>
     [Mr. Sinclair.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            <cb/>
          
     though this time grain was the cornerstone. 
     <lb/>
     Both predicted national ruin unless those bans 
     <lb/>
     were maintained. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     History shows how false were their 
     <lb/>
     assertions; and history today shows that the 
     <lb/>
     assertion of the butter industry that this must 
     <lb/>
     ruin Canada is equally false. The history of 
     <lb/>
     every other country in the world shows that 
     <lb/>
     the introduction of margarine has not debased 
     <lb/>
     the dairy industry or agriculture as a whole 
     <lb/>
     but has helped the dairy industry. Both 
     <lb/>
     countries with butter for export, like New 
     <lb/>
     Zealand, Holland or Denmark, and those 
     <lb/>
     which like Canada are in short supply, such as 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, the United Kingdom, the 
     <lb/>
     United States, Norway and South Africa, 
     <lb/>
     have found this to be so, for all today, with 
     <lb/>
     margarine, have healthy dairy industries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The thing about this that interests me very 
     <lb/>
     much is the fact that for years we have wit<lb break="no"/>nessed crocodile tears on the part of the dairy 
     <lb/>
     industry about the money they lost on butter. 
     <lb/>
     They were always losing money on butter. 
     <lb/>
     If butter was such a money loser one would 
     <lb/>
     think the dairy industry would welcome a 
     <lb/>
     chance to get rid of this loss leader by the 
     <lb/>
     importation and manufacture of margarine, 
     <lb/>
     letting margarine take that loss and leaving 
     <lb/>
     the dairy industry free to go into the more 
     <lb/>
     lucrative ﬁeld of the production of milk, ice<lb break="no"/>cream and cheese. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     What is the truth of the matter? The truth 
     <lb/>
     is that the sale of oleomargarine in Canada 
     <lb/>
     would have very very little effect upon butter 
     <lb/>
     sales or butter prices. In the United States, 
     <lb/>
     for example, butter sells at about a dollar a 
     <lb/>
     pound and margarine at from thirty-ﬁve to 
     <lb/>
     forty—ﬁve cents a pound. The great sale of 
     <lb/>
     oleomargarine is to people who today are 
     <lb/>
     either not buying butter because they can<lb break="no"/>not afford it or not buying all the butter they 
     <lb/>
     would like. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     More than that, the manufacture of oleo<lb break="no"/>margarine is naturally complementary to 
     <lb/>
     butter making, since it uses the skim milk 
     <lb/>
     which is a by—product of butter. More than 
     <lb/>
     that, the dairy industry gains from the oleo<lb break="no"/>margarine manufacture, because there is more 
     <lb/>
     oil cake which comes as a by—product of the 
     <lb/>
     increased production of vegetable oils which 
     <lb/>
     will be necessary. The records of Canada also 
     <lb/>
     show that, because between 1917 and 1923, 
     <lb/>
     when we had oleomargarine, butter production 
     <lb/>
     and consumption in Canada gained each year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I turn then to their second defence, the 
     <lb/>
     argument of protection. I shall deal with 
     <lb/>
     that at the close of my speech. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The next argument which we hear so often 
     <lb/>
     repeated is that We could not have any oleo-<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>