<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1869-06-09"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-06-09">9 June 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
 
         
           <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="675" to="692"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0675.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0676.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0677.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0678.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0679.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0680.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0681.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0682.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0683.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0684.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0685.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0686.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0687.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0688.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0689.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0690.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0691.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0692.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0675">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0675.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0676">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0676.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0677">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0677.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0678">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0678.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0679">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0679.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0680">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0680.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0681">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0681.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0682">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0682.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0683">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0683.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0684">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0684.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0685">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0685.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0686">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0686.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0687">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0687.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0688">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0688.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0689">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0689.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0690">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0690.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0691">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0691.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0692">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0692.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="675" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0675.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="running">DÉBATS DES</fw>
            <fw type="num">COMMUNES</fw>-->

<div type="section">
            <head>HOUSE OF COMMONS</head>
            
            <p>
               Wednesday, June 9, 1869<lb/></p>
           
<p>
               The Speaker took the chair at 3 o’clock. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
</div>     
      <div type="section">    
            <head> L'ISLET ELECTION<lb/>
               
            </head>
            
            
            <p>
               Mr. M. C. Cameron presented the final re<lb break="no"/>port of the L’Islet Election Committee, de<lb break="no"/>claiming that the election was null and void, 
               <lb/>
               but that the defence of the sitting member, 
               <lb/>
               Mr. Pouliot, was not frivilous or vexatious. 
               <lb/>
               The decision was based on the ground that 
               <lb/>
               the returning ofiicer had disfranchised cer<lb break="no"/>tain parishes by not granting them a poll, 
               <lb/>
               and was arrived at by a majority of 3 to 2. 
               <lb/>
               Yeas, Messrs D. A. Macdonald, Connell and 
               <lb/>
               Cameron. Nays, Messrs. Caron and Cimon. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
      </div>        
         
            <div type="section">
            <head>YORK ROADS</head>
            
<p>
               Hon. Mr. Langevin brought down a return 
               <lb/>
               to the address for all correspondence etc., 
               <lb/>
               respecting the claims of the Government 
               <lb/>
               against James Beaty Esq. and the York 
               <lb/>
               Roads Company. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            </div>          
         
            <div type="section">
            <head>THE NORTH WEST</head>
            
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Rose gave notice of resolutions 
               <lb/>
               to authorize the Government to raise a loan 
               <lb/>
               of £300,000 sterling on the Imperial guaran<lb break="no"/>tee to pay the Hudson’s Bay Company, and 
               <lb/>
               a further loan not exceeding £300,000 ster<lb break="no"/>ling, for the purpose of opening up communi<lb break="no"/>cation with the North West Territory, or<lb break="no"/>ganizing a government therein, and promot<lb break="no"/>ing its settlement. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            </div>      
            
<div type="section">
            <head>INSOLVENCY LAWS</head>
          
  <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald moved the House 
               <lb/>
               into Committee of the Whole on the Act re<lb break="no"/>specting Insolvency. Mr. Harrison in the 
               <lb/>
               Chair. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott moved the first clause of 
               <lb/>
               the Bill, which provided that the Act should 
               <lb/>
               apply to all persons, traders as well as non- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               traders, except that in the case of non-traders 
               <lb/>
               there should be no voluntary assignment 
               <lb/>
               under the Act. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie said he still retained the 
               <lb/>
               convictions respecting this measure which he 
               <lb/>
               had already expressed. He would not again 
               <lb/>
               take up the time of the House, but hoped 
               <lb/>
               that the changes mad-e in the Bill would be 
               <lb/>
               explained clause by clause. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
     
   
            <pb n="676" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0676.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">676</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               June 9, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Holton suggested that the member 
               <lb/>
               for Argenteuil might in this first clause make 
               <lb/>
               a general statement of the changes. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott replied that the changes 
               <lb/>
               were too numerous to admit of this course. 
               <lb/>
               Besides he did not think there were in the 
               <lb/>
               Bill changes of much importance as to prin<lb break="no"/>ciples. The changes were chiefly in the direc<lb break="no"/>tion of simplifying the procedure, shortening 
               <lb/>
               delays and giving increased power in many 
               <lb/>
               respects to the creditors. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Ross (Prince Edward) moved that the 
               <lb/>
               word non-trader in the 1st clause be struck 
               <lb/>
               out. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Ferguson asked if non-traders were 
               <lb/>
               not to be allowed to take the benefit of the 
               <lb/>
               Act. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott replied that they might be 
               <lb/>
               put under its operation by their creditors, 
               <lb/>
               but could not do so at their own option. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Ferguson doubted very much whether 
               <lb/>
               this law was wanted at all or not, and if an 
               <lb/>
               opportunity were given it for a six months 
               <lb/>
               hoist, or repealing the whole law, he would 
               <lb/>
               be found in that direction. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Geoffrion thought that that the non- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               trader should come under the Act as did the 
               <lb/>
               trader, and said that such a law ought to be 
               <lb/>
               made applicable to Lower Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            
            <p>
               Sir George E. Cartier was not in favor of an 
               <lb/>
extension of the provisions of the Bill to non-<lb break="yes"/>
traders in Quebec. It was unnecessary, as the 
               <lb/>
               distribution of the estate of non-traders was 
               <lb/>
               provided for by the Common Law of that 
               <lb/>
               Province. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            
            
         
            
            
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Irvine also argued that there was 
               <lb/>
               no necessity for this law in Quebec, that 
               <lb/>
               the regular trader, who from his position 
               <lb/>
               was largely exposed. to risk and might fail 
               <lb/>
               occasionally, should have means provided for 
               <lb/>
               relieving him of his liabilities when unable 
               <lb/>
               to meet them. It was only fair to the creditor 
               <lb/>
               to afiord him an easy, simple means of 
               <lb/>
               liquidating the estate, but this would not 
               <lb/>
               apply to the non-trader. If he fell into debt 
               <lb/>
               it was not by misfortune but by extravagance. 
               <lb/>
               Hence there was no reason for exceptional 
               <lb/>
               legislation in his favour and as to his credi<lb break="no"/>tors, if they trusted him beyond his means 
               <lb/>
               they only got what they deserved. For these 
               <lb/>
               reasons he would vote against this clause of 
               <lb/>
               the Bill, and he did so the more readily as in 
               <lb/>
               
          
           
            <pb n="677" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0677.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               9 juin 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
          
               Quebec the law provides for the distribution 
               <lb/>
               of the assets of a non-trader who was unable 
               <lb/>
               to pay his debts. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Holton said that the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man who had just taken his seat had fallen 
               <lb/>
               into the fallacy of assuming that this Bill, and 
               <lb/>
               insolvent laws generally, were contrived in the 
               <lb/>
               interest of the debtor class. Now the whole 
               <lb/>
               scope of the present measure was to enable the 
               <lb/>
               creditors to distribute the estate on some 
               <lb/>
               equitable principle. Incidentally, and only in<lb break="no"/>cidentally, the debtor class might benefit by 
               <lb/>
               getting the discharge from liability. That was 
               <lb/>
               his view of the scope and purport of the law. 
               <lb/>
               Coming to the application of the measure to 
               <lb/>
               non-traders, he would say that the creditors 
               <lb/>
               of non-trades had an equal interest with credi<lb break="no"/>tors of traders in getting at the effects and 
               <lb/>
               securing a proper distribution of the estate of 
               <lb/>
               an insolvent debtor. But the Minister of Militia 
               <lb/>
               argued that the power asked for the retaining 
               <lb/>
               of non-traders was possessed already in Que<lb break="no"/>bec. He (Mr. Holton) thought it very objec<lb break="no"/>tionable to make an exception of a particular 
               <lb/>
               Province in any legislation competent for this 
               <lb/>
               Parliament to enact; and for his part, while he 
               <lb/>
               desired to see the principle of this Bill applied 
               <lb/>
               to non-traders, sooner than see an exception 
               <lb/>
               made by any Province in the matter, he would 
               <lb/>
               infinitely rather that non traders should be 
               <lb/>
               excluded from the operation of the Act. The 
               <lb/>
               object of the Dominion Parliament should be 
               <lb/>
               to assimilate the laws and not legislate ex<lb break="no"/>ceptionally. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Bodwell said that the question arose 
               <lb/>
               who were traders and who non-traders. If 
               <lb/>
               every man was a trader, who bought and sold, 
               <lb/>
               he would like to know what individual in the 
               <lb/>
               community was not a trader. If a man trading 
               <lb/>
               in a particular line of business was unfortu<lb break="no"/>nate, and allowed his business to go into the 
               <lb/>
               Insolvent Court, why should not a trader in 
               <lb/>
               any other line of business have an equal right? 
               <lb/>
               Many were engaged in produce dealings, and 
               <lb/>
               throughout the West a farmer could not be 
               <lb/>
               found who did not deal more or less outside 
               <lb/>
               of the regular business. Were no remedies to 
               <lb/>
               be provided for these classes in the event of 
               <lb/>
               a failure. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Currier—If a farmer does business in 
               <lb/>
               that way he is a trader. If he not only sold 
               <lb/>
               his own stuff, but buys and sells, he is prac<lb break="no"/>tically a trader. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Holton—And if a lawyer fails? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
       
            <pb n="678" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0678.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">678</fw>  <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               June 9, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
            <p>
               Mr. Currier—If a lawyer is so improvident 
               <lb/>
               as to buy property which he has no means of 
               <lb/>
               paying for, he ought to be punished. 
               <lb/>
               (Laughter). 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Bodwell still saw great difficulty in 
               <lb/>
               drawing a distinction between traders and 
               <lb/>
               non-traders. Scarcely a man was engaged in 
               <lb/>
               manufacturing but bought and sold, nor did he 
               <lb/>
               know an instance of a man engaged in the 
               <lb/>
               learned professions who did not speculate 
               <lb/>
               more or less. Desiring to see the law extended 
               <lb/>
               to all classes of the community, he would 
               <lb/>
               move in amendment to the amendment that 
               <lb/>
               the latter portion of the clause “except that in 
               <lb/>
               the case of non-traders there shall be no vol<lb break="no"/>untary assignment under this Act,” be struck 
               <lb/>
               out. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Ross (Dundas)—If it is desirable that 
               <lb/>
               there should be an Insolvency Law, he could 
               <lb/>
               not see why it should be made exceptional in 
               <lb/>
               its operation. He was prepared to vote to do 
               <lb/>
               away with the law altogether; but, if we had 
               <lb/>
               such a law, one class of persons who got in<lb break="no"/>volved ought to have the same opportunity of 
               <lb/>
               getting relieved as another. The amendment, 
               <lb/>
               however, of the member for South Oxford did 
               <lb/>
               not meet his views. He would rather leave the 
               <lb/>
               law as it was. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Smith did not understand how 
               <lb/>
               it was possible to discriminate between traders 
               <lb/>
               and non-traders. He would let the operation 
               <lb/>
               of the law be uniform and applicable to all 
               <lb/>
               alike. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Dufresne said an Insolvency Law was 
               <lb/>
               exceptional. Every principle of law and justice 
               <lb/>
               required a man to pay his debts; but ex<lb break="no"/>perience showed that certain exceptions might 
               <lb/>
               be desirable. In Lower Canada it was consid<lb break="no"/>ered that a trader acted as an agent between 
               <lb/>
               other parties, and that circumstances which 
               <lb/>
               he could not control might prevent his meet<lb break="no"/>ing his obligations. Traders occupied an ex<lb break="no"/>ceptional position, and they required such a 
               <lb/>
               law as this, but the general principle was that 
               <lb/>
               every man should pay what he owes. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie—No divorce between a man 
               <lb/>
               and his debts (laughter). 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Dufresne—Yes, that is the principle. 
               <lb/>
               They were willing, therefore, to allow an 
               <lb/>
               exception in that case; but not to extend it to 
               <lb/>
               others. If honourable gentlemen from other 
               <lb/>
               sections wished the law to apply to non- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               traders, they might make that provision with 
               <lb/>
               reference to their own sections; but he hoped 
               <lb/>
               they would not force it on Lower Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
       
           
            <pb n="679" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0679.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               9 juin 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Wood said that in Ontario the 
               <lb/>
               working of the Insolvency Act had not found 
               <lb/>
               much favour with any large class of the com<lb break="no"/>munity. A large portion of the merchants, 
               <lb/>
               farmers, &amp;c., would be glad to see the Insol<lb break="no"/>vency Law done away with altogether. The 
               <lb/>
               working of the law had proved most unsatis<lb break="no"/>factory. Not one estate in a dozen had paid 
               <lb/>
               10 cents on the dollar after meeting expenses. 
               <lb/>
               Many had paid nothing. He believed there 
               <lb/>
               were cases of persons who had deliberately 
               <lb/>
               contracted debts with the intention of getting 
               <lb/>
               rid of them under this law. It was said it was 
               <lb/>
               impossible to distinguish between traders and 
               <lb/>
               non-traders. If the distinction was not defined 
               <lb/>
               in the Act, it had been clearly defined by 
               <lb/>
               many decisions in Courts. He thought it un<lb break="no"/>advisable to change the first clause, which, 
               <lb/>
               while allowing persons, whether traders or 
               <lb/>
               non-traders, to take advantage of the Act, did 
               <lb/>
               not allow non-traders to make a voluntary 
               <lb/>
               assignment. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Dunkin thought the clause could 
               <lb/>
               not stand as it was. No Court of law had 
               <lb/>
               any difficulty in deciding who were traders 
               <lb/>
               and who were not. The true principle in this 
               <lb/>
               matter was that of the amendment, not the 
               <lb/>
               amendment to the amendment. What they 
               <lb/>
               wanted to deal with here, especially with 
               <lb/>
               their limited jurisdiction, was the insolvency 
               <lb/>
               of the trading class. If this Parliament was 
               <lb/>
               to impose a uniform rule in a matter of this 
               <lb/>
               kind on all the Provinces, in spite of the 
               <lb/>
               objections of any particular Province, what 
               <lb/>
               was the value of the jurisdiction assigned to 
               <lb/>
               the Provincial Legislatures with regard to 
               <lb/>
               property and civil rights? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Smith—Does the hon. gentleman 
               <lb/>
               mean that under the Union Act this Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment has not the power to deal with non- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               traders? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Dunkin said he did not go so 
               <lb/>
               far as that, but he was opposed to this Par<lb break="no"/>liament straining its jurisdiction too far, and 
               <lb/>
               that in a matter of this kind, it should not 
               <lb/>
               force on Quebec what it did not ask and 
               <lb/>
               what it did not like. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Jones, (Leeds), had listened patiently, 
               <lb/>
               but with pain to the remarks of the member 
               <lb/>
               for Brome. We either had control over the 
               <lb/>
               matter of insolvency or we had not. If we 
               <lb/>
               had, what force was there in his arguments, 
               <lb/>
               and why should he attempt to get up a feel<lb break="no"/>ing between Quebec and the other Provinces? 
               <lb/>
               He had been surprised to hear a member of 
               <lb/>
               the Government of Quebec arguing in a circle 
               <lb/>
               and contradicting himself. He (Mr. Jones) 
               <lb/>
               
       
            <pb n="680" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0680.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">680</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">
               June 9, 1869</fw>
        
               believed that equal rights should be extended 
               <lb/>
               to all classes of the community, whether 
               <lb/>
               traders or non-traders, and that any one 
               <lb/>
               unable to meet his liabilities and who was 
               <lb/>
               simply unfortunate, should be allowed to 
               <lb/>
               take advantage of the Act. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Blake thought there could be no doubt 
               <lb/>
               as to the power of this Parliament to legis<lb break="no"/>late With regard to non—traders, as well as 
               <lb/>
               traders, the Union Act giving it exclusive 
               <lb/>
               jurisdiction over both bankruptcy and insol<lb break="no"/>vency. It was known that in England bank<lb break="no"/>ruptcy was the term technically applied to 
               <lb/>
               the case of traders, and insolvency the term 
               <lb/>
               applied to the case of non-traders; and he 
               <lb/>
               could not conceive why the two terms should 
               <lb/>
               have been used unless it were intended that 
               <lb/>
               this Parliament might declare that non- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               traders as well as traders might be dis<lb break="no"/>charged from their liabilities under certain 
               <lb/>
               restrictions. As regarded the policy of ex<lb break="no"/>tending the law to non-traders, that was a 
               <lb/>
               different matter. If the interests of the other 
               <lb/>
               Provinces demanded that there should be a 
               <lb/>
               general insolvent law, as distinguished from 
               <lb/>
               a bankrupt law, all that could be said against 
               <lb/>
               it in Quebec was that there was an equal 
               <lb/>
               distribution in the case of non-traders. He 
               <lb/>
               did not think that should be a sufficient<lb/>
               objection to their applying a general system 
               <lb/>
               to the whole country. It would require to be 
               <lb/>
               an objection founded on some inconvenience 
               <lb/>
               in Quebec Which should induce them not to 
               <lb/>
               apply the system to the whole country, unless 
               <lb/>
               there were very strong and powerful reasons 
               <lb/>
               overbearing that inconvenience. What was the 
               <lb/>
               object of a bankrupt or insolvent law at all? 
               <lb/>
               Was it in the interest of the debtor, in the 
               <lb/>
               interest of the creditor, in their joint interest, 
               <lb/>
               or in the interest of he community at large? 
               <lb/>
               He apprehended it was not solely in the inter<lb break="no"/>est of the debtor or the creditor, but rather 
               <lb/>
               that it was in the public interest such a law 
               <lb/>
               should be established, and that in certain 
               <lb/>
               cases there should be a machinery for the 
               <lb/>
               speedy discussion and realization of the estate 
               <lb/>
               of a person unable to meet his obligations, 
               <lb/>
               and of relieving such person from further 
               <lb/>
               liabilities when his whole estate had been 
               <lb/>
               realized. Whether the public interest then 
               <lb/>
               demanded in this country and in our state 
               <lb/>
               of circumstances that that arrangement 
               <lb/>
               should be extended to non-trader, was, he 
               <lb/>
               thought, practically the question that we had 
               <lb/>
               before us. While he was willing to agree 
               <lb/>
               that the operation of our insolvent law in the 
               <lb/>
               past had been such as to render that law to 
               <lb/>
               a large extent unpopular, he apprehended a 
               <lb/>
               great many of the objections which had been 
               <lb/>
               taken to it were due, not to the law, but to 
               <lb/>
               the lax mode in which it had been worked 
               <lb/>
               
          
            <pb n="681" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0681.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               9 juin 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
           
               by persons who had an interest in improperly 
               <lb/>
               working it. So long as creditors took the 
               <lb/>
               short sighted course of compromising frauds 
               <lb/>
               so as to get a little more in the pound rather 
               <lb/>
               than let the frauds go before the Courts, so 
               <lb/>
               long would any insolvent law which could be 
               <lb/>
               put on the statute book be abused. If the 
               <lb/>
               creditor would take the true view and let 
               <lb/>
               the provisions of the law be carried out with 
               <lb/>
               reference to frauds, he would find those cases 
               <lb/>
               of fraud would become more and more rare. 
               <lb/>
               He believed, therefore, the abuse of the law 
               <lb/>
               was mainly attributable to the neglect and 
               <lb/>
               blindness of those whose direct interest it 
               <lb/>
               was to maintain it. But as regarded the 
               <lb/>
               amendment now before the chair, he must 
               <lb/>
               say that it did not seem to him that prac<lb break="no"/>tically there was a very large class of cases 
               <lb/>
               in Which it was proposed to extend the law 
               <lb/>
               to non-traders. In the first place, no voluntary 
               <lb/>
               assignment was allowed in the case of non- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               traders; in the second place, when they came 
               <lb/>
               to the provisions as to compulsory liquida<lb break="no"/>tion, the 14th clause laid down certain cases 
               <lb/>
               in which the law should apply to all cases 
               <lb/>
               of debtors. These were, if the debtor 
               <lb/>
               absconded, if there was a fraudulent secretion 
               <lb/>
               of property, if there was a fraudulent assign<lb break="no"/>ment of property, if there was a procuring of 
               <lb/>
               property to be taken in execution, with intent 
               <lb/>
               to defraud, &amp;c.—but simple default, and a 
               <lb/>
               simple inability to pay, although that ina<lb break="no"/>bility might be established by the return to 
               <lb/>
               an execution of no goods, was not enough to 
               <lb/>
               drive the non-trader into compulsory liquida<lb break="no"/>tion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Halton—That is wrong.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Blake—But according to this Bill, and 
               <lb/>
               according to the law as it had been since 1864, 
               <lb/>
               that was so. It was only in the cases specified 
               <lb/>
               in the 14th clause to which he had referred, 
               <lb/>
               that a non-trader could be put into compul<lb break="no"/>sory liquidation at all. He confessed that it 
               <lb/>
               appeared to him that the fragmentary appli<lb break="no"/>cation of the law to non-traders was not well 
               <lb/>
               considered and they would have a grave 
               <lb/>
               question to deal with, if any hon. gentleman 
               <lb/>
               proposed to wipe out altogether the distinc<lb break="no"/>tion between traders and non-traders, and 
               <lb/>
               to give us one law for all as regarded both 
               <lb/>
               voluntary and compulsory liquidation. That 
               <lb/>
               however, was not the proposition before the 
               <lb/>
               House. Now the position was this—that in a 
               <lb/>
               few cases at the instance of the creditors 
               <lb/>
               there might be compulsory liquidation in the 
               <lb/>
               case of the non-traders. In his own Province 
               <lb/>
               he did not believe that the law as it stood 
               <lb/>
               would be resorted to by creditors against 
               <lb/>
               non-traders. In many instances it merely 
               <lb/>
         
            <pb n="682" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0682.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">682</fw>  <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               June 9, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
      
               allowed persons to be taken where it was 
               <lb/>
               alleged that goods or lands had been fraudu<lb break="no"/>lently made away with. He thought that the 
               <lb/>
               law, as it stood in this respect, was extremely 
               <lb/>
               unjust to the creditors. It permitted a volun<lb break="no"/>tary assignment to the non-trader. It al<lb break="no"/>lowed him to whitewash himself; but it did 
               <lb/>
               not practically give the creditor power to 
               <lb/>
               put him into compulsory liquidation, unless 
               <lb/>
               he violated the law of the land in the par<lb break="no"/>ticulars he had referred to. He hailed the 
               <lb/>
               alterations made by this Bill as an improve<lb break="no"/>ment and was prepared to support it in 
               <lb/>
               preference to the Law now on the statute 
               <lb/>
               book, although he would prefer to see it 
               <lb/>
               apply to traders only, unless the whole Bill 
               <lb/>
               was to be re-cast.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Holton said that unquestionably 
               <lb/>
               the member for West Durham had pointed 
               <lb/>
               out the inconsequential character of the sub<lb break="no"/>sequent clauses with this clause. At this stage, 
               <lb/>
               it would be better if the member having 
               <lb/>
               charge of the Bill should state his view of 
               <lb/>
               this matter. His (Mr. Holton’s) understanding 
               <lb/>
               was that the Bill was to be made applicable 
               <lb/>
               throughout to non-traders, in the same sense 
               <lb/>
               and to the same extent as traders.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott did not understand that to 
               <lb/>
               be the decision of the Committee; and it was 
               <lb/>
               impossible it could have been their intention. 
               <lb/>
               Apart from the fact that they passed the 
               <lb/>
               measure clause by clause, and after the most 
               <lb/>
               careful consideration framed the measure as 
               <lb/>
               it stood, it was quite clear that they never 
               <lb/>
               intended the Bill to apply to non-traders in 
               <lb/>
               all respects as to traders, for this reason, 
               <lb/>
               that the exceptions to which the member for 
               <lb/>
               West Durham referred were peculiar to trad<lb break="no"/>ing, and could not be made to apply to non- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               traders. One of these exceptions is, that if a 
               <lb/>
               man ceases to meet his liabilities as they 
               <lb/>
               become due, and does not assign his estate 
               <lb/>
               within a certain number of days, that he 
               <lb/>
               should be called on for an assignment. The 
               <lb/>
               member for Chateauguay himself would be 
               <lb/>
               the first to object to such a provision as that 
               <lb/>
               being made applicable to the non-trader. The 
               <lb/>
               trader loses his credit and may be said to 
               <lb/>
               be insolvent when he stops payment. In 
               <lb/>
               ninety-nine cases out of a hundred, stoppage 
               <lb/>
               of payment by a trader indicates that he 
               <lb/>
               has not enough to pay his debts in full. The 
               <lb/>
               mere failure of a non-trader to pay a debt 
               <lb/>
               when it matures does not, to the same extent, 
               <lb/>
               indicate any such thing. He should not, 
               <lb/>
               therefore, be made liable to the provisions of 
               <lb/>
               the Act. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Holton said he referred to com<lb break="no"/>pulsory liquidation in the 14th clause, and 
               <lb/>
               
          
           
            <pb n="683" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0683.jpg"/>
          <!--  <fw type="dateline">
               9 juin 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
         
               maintained that in dealing with compulsory 
               <lb/>
               liquidation the decision on the first clause 
               <lb/>
               must remove all distinction in the others, 
               <lb/>
               as to traders and non-traders. He thought the 
               <lb/>
               words, “of being a trader,” in that clause 
               <lb/>
               aught necessarily to have been struck out. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott maintained his position, 
               <lb/>
               and after some further debate said, in reply 
               <lb/>
               to the member for Chateauguay, that no clause 
               <lb/>
               short of No. 80, if he recollected aright, had 
               <lb/>
               been left by the Committee to the Chairman 
               <lb/>
               to draw up.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Gray said that the question before 
               <lb/>
               the House was not so much what the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee intended to do as what they did do. 
               <lb/>
               His understanding of the Bill was that 
               <lb/>
               throughout it referred to non-traders as 
               <lb/>
               well as traders and he differed altogether 
               <lb/>
               from the views advanced by the member for 
               <lb/>
               Brome. If such views were to prevail, better 
               <lb/>
               Confederation had never taken place. He 
               <lb/>
               thought that if one question more than an<lb break="no"/>other came within the province of the Dom<lb break="no"/>inion Parliament it was this of bankruptcy 
               <lb/>
               and insolvency. In the Maritime Provinces at 
               <lb/>
               present, persons could not be relieved of 
               <lb/>
               their debts and the result was that persons 
               <lb/>
               from these Provinces frequently went to Eng<lb break="no"/>land and did business on a small scale for a 
               <lb/>
               few weeks to bring them within the pro<lb break="no"/>visions of the bankrupt laws, and the credi<lb break="no"/>tors soon found themselves divested of all 
               <lb/>
               control over the property. In his opinion 
               <lb/>
               there ought to be a good Insolvency Law for 
               <lb/>
               the Dominion, applicable equally to all por<lb break="no"/>tions. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. J. H. Cameron said that in Ontario the 
               <lb/>
               non—trader was liable to voluntary and invol<lb break="no"/>untary assignments, but under the provisions 
               <lb/>
               of the present Bill the voluntary assignment 
               <lb/>
               was prevented, while the other remained. His 
               <lb/>
               impression was that the law was to be exactly 
               <lb/>
               the same as in Ontario before, except that a 
               <lb/>
               non-trader could not by his own voluntary 
               <lb/>
               act go into insolvency. He had not at all sup<lb break="no"/>posed that the effect of the present Bill was 
               <lb/>
               that any creditor or number of creditors 
               <lb/>
               could put a non-trader into bankruptcy. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Holton was satisfied the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman was mistaken. The Bill, as introduced, 
               <lb/>
               excepted Quebec from the operation of the 
               <lb/>
               law as far as non-traders were concerned. On 
               <lb/>
               his (Mr. Holton’s) motion the Committee re<lb break="no"/>solved that the Bill should be made applicable 
               <lb/>
               to traders and non-traders throughout the 
               <lb/>
               Dominion, with the proviso that a non-trader 
               <lb/>
               should not have power to make a voluntary 
               <lb/>
               
        
            <pb n="684" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0684.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">684</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>  <fw type="dateline">
               June 9, 1869</fw>
          
               assignment. He desired to call attention to the 
               <lb/>
               circumstance that the other night the Minister 
               <lb/>
               of Justice, in whose power the Bill stood, gave 
               <lb/>
               as a reason for not then presenting the mea<lb break="no"/>sure, that the member for Argenteuil had un<lb break="no"/>dertaken to recast the clauses affected by the 
               <lb/>
               decision come to in the committee. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott thought that the member 
               <lb/>
               for Chateauguay had not thrown any new 
               <lb/>
               light on this subject. Before discussing the 
               <lb/>
               clauses of the Bill the Committee resolved to 
               <lb/>
               come to a decision on one or more leading 
               <lb/>
               points which permeated the Bill. Among 
               <lb/>
               these was the question—shall the exception of 
               <lb/>
               the Province of Quebec from the ruling that 
               <lb/>
               this law should be applicable to traders and 
               <lb/>
               non-traders be continued, or shall the law be 
               <lb/>
               applicable to all the Provinces not excepting 
               <lb/>
               Quebec? And as the honourable member for 
               <lb/>
               Peel said, it was never intended to change the 
               <lb/>
               position of the non-trader from that then pre<lb break="no"/>vailing in Upper Canada. The fact was, that if 
               <lb/>
               non-traders were to come under the operation 
               <lb/>
               of the 15th clause the Bill would simply be 
               <lb/>
               converted into a summary process of forcing a 
               <lb/>
               man to pay his debts, and such a thing was 
               <lb/>
               never contemplated by the Committee. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               After recess,</p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
               ENFRANCHISEMENT OF INDIANS 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>

            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Langevin moved the consideration 
               <lb/>
               of the amendment to his Indian Bill from the 
               <lb/>
               Senate. Carried. Second reading to-morrow.</p>
            
            
            <p>Twelve clauses of Sir John A. Macdonald’s 
               <lb/>
               Criminal Bill were reported from the Senate, 
               <lb/>
               with amendments, which were read a first 
               <lb/>
               time. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>      
      
<div type="section">   
            
            <head>
               INSOLVENCY LAW<lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The House then went into Committee on the 
               <lb/>
               Insolvency Bill, Mr. Harrison in the chair. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott, on resuming the debate, 
               <lb/>
               said this Bill provided a number of excep<lb break="no"/>tional remedies in favour of the trader, which 
               <lb/>
               could not apply in the case of the non-trader. 
               <lb/>
               If further legislation were needed, let each 
               <lb/>
               Province legislate regarding non-traders for 
               <lb/>
               itself. Both as regarding debtor and creditor 
               <lb/>
               there was no reason for including non-traders 
               <lb/>
               in the Bill. The creditors do not require the 
               <lb/>
               excessive remedy, and the debtor shall not be 
               <lb/>
               allowed to take advantage of the provisions 
               <lb/>
               extended to traders. He would rather see the<lb/>
               
         
            <pb n="685" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0685.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               9 juin 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
           
               amendment adopted and place a limit than ex<lb break="no"/>tend such a provision to the whole Dominion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. D. A. Macdonald did not see that the 
               <lb/>
               Bill ought to be passed. The disastrous state 
               <lb/>
               of trade which was held to make this measure 
               <lb/>
               necessary was owing chiefly to the greed of 
               <lb/>
               Montreal merchants in pushing their goods off<lb/>
               in every direction. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Workman said he was tired of that style 
               <lb/>
               of argument. It was absurd; he could not un<lb break="no"/>derstand it. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. D. A. Macdonald said he withdrew the 
               <lb/>
               charge, as far as the honourable gentleman 
               <lb/>
               himself was concerned. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Street could not see why the non-traders 
               <lb/>
               should not, under certain circumstances, be en<lb break="no"/>titled to ask the relief which this Bill proposes. 
               <lb/>
               At the same time, the resolutions imposed by 
               <lb/>
               the Committee were, in his (Mr. Street’s) opin<lb break="no"/>ion, good ones. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Chipman said that in Nova Scotia they 
               <lb/>
               had an Insolvent Debtor’s Act, administered 
               <lb/>
               by a Board of Commissioners, whose services 
               <lb/>
               were obtained without fee or reward. Their 
               <lb/>
               work was well done, and therefore he was not 
               <lb/>
               disposed to vote for the present Bill. He ob<lb break="no"/>jected, too, to the exceptional legislation to 
               <lb/>
               be imposed under this Bill—holding that the 
               <lb/>
               law should be made for all, or not at all. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Bodwell replied to the arguments 
               <lb/>
               against his amendment, averring that they 
               <lb/>
               were nearly all offered in the interest of the 
               <lb/>
               wholesale merchants and creditors. In support 
               <lb/>
               of his amendment, he instanced the numbers 
               <lb/>
               who speculated largely in oil lands not long 
               <lb/>
               since, and contributed largely to the prosperity 
               <lb/>
               of the country. Should such men be prevented 
               <lb/>
               from taking advantage of the provisions of the 
               <lb/>
               Act? There were many such cases, and he 
               <lb/>
               failed to see that any case had been made 
               <lb/>
               out against the non-trader.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald said that from the 
               <lb/>
               great variety of laws in the Provinces on 
               <lb/>
               this subject and from the difference of opin<lb break="no"/>ion advanced during the debate, it was 
               <lb/>
               clear, if they wanted an Insolvency Bill this 
               <lb/>
               session, the only way to get it would be by 
               <lb/>
               accepting the proposition that the Bill be 
               <lb/>
               confined to traders only over all the Do<lb break="no"/><pb n="686" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0686.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">686</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               June 9, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>minion. This would give a law on which all 
               <lb/>
               were agreed—a measure for the relief of 
               <lb/>
               traders and traders only. There was a good 
               <lb/>
               deal of force in the argument advanced by 
               <lb/>
               the member for South Oxford that the law 
               <lb/>
               should be general, but lest the bill should 
               <lb/>
               not become law this session it was best to 
               <lb/>
               modify it by making it applicable to traders 
               <lb/>
               only. Next session, on a fair representation 
               <lb/>
               from any one Province, the law could be ex<lb break="no"/>tended so as to meet their case. (Hear, hear.) 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Bodwell's amendment was then put 
               <lb/>
               and lost, and Mr. Ross’s carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The clause as amended was carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Blake—How does the 1st clause read 
               <lb/>
               now? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The Chairman—This Act shall apply to 
               <lb/>
               traders only. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               On the second clause, which provided for 
               <lb/>
               assignments, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Blake objected to a section of it which 
               <lb/>
               interfered with voluntary assignments. It was 
               <lb/>
               not well, he thought, to interpose any ob<lb break="no"/>stacle in this direction. He would rather place 
               <lb/>
               restrictions on the discharge of the debtor 
               <lb/>
               than raise any obstacles to his making an 
               <lb/>
               assignment. In this respect he much preferred 
               <lb/>
               the Bill as it originally stood. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. John Sandfield Macdonald said there 
               <lb/>
               should be some provision for punishing par<lb break="no"/>ties who did not make an assignment when 
               <lb/>
               they ought to do so, and he read a letter 
               <lb/>
               from a distinguished Judge, who expressed 
               <lb/>
               his concurrence in the views he (Mr. Sand<lb break="no"/>field Macdonald) had expressed at the second 
               <lb/>
               reading of the Bill as to the outrageously 
               <lb/>
               easy manner in which fraudulent debtors 
               <lb/>
               were allowed to whitewash themselves, and 
               <lb/>
               said that for the last twenty-five years our 
               <lb/>
               laws had been far too much in favour of the 
               <lb/>
               debtor, rather than of the creditor. In Eng<lb break="no"/>land, the finger of scorn was pointed at the 
               <lb/>
               man Who defrauded his creditors. Here, he 
               <lb/>
               was considered a very clever fellow, and the 
               <lb/>
               law gave him every facility. He contended 
               <lb/>
               that some other machinery should be pro<lb break="no"/>vided for carrying out the law than had hith<lb break="no"/>erto existed, or this law would be as in<lb break="no"/>operative as any of its predecessors. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott pointed out that it would 
               <lb/>
               involve great expense to establish special 
               <lb/>
               Courts of Bankruptcy Commissioners. He be<lb break="no"/>lieved that in Lower Canada the Judges had 
               <lb/>
               performed the duty of suspending certificates, 
               <lb/>
               where such a course was called for.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
           
            <pb n="687" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0687.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               9 juin 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Wood said the arrangements of 
               <lb/>
               the bill prevented no honest man from mak<lb break="no"/>ing an assignment, while they offered at least 
               <lb/>
               some small obstacle in the way of a dishonest 
               <lb/>
               man doing so. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Blake argued that no barrier should 
               <lb/>
               be interposed in the way of a debtor going 
               <lb/>
               into insolvency when unable to meet his en<lb break="no"/>gagements. He, therefore, moved to strike out 
               <lb/>
               the words in 2nd clause which required con<lb break="no"/>sent of a certain proportion of the creditors 
               <lb/>
               to a voluntary assignment. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The amendment was agreed to, and the 
               <lb/>
               clause as amended was carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Clauses 3 to 13 were agreed to, the words 
               <lb/>
               in section 1 “being a trader,” being struck 
               <lb/>
               out. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Clauses 15 to 19 were agreed to. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Clause 20 being moved, allowing certain 
               <lb/>
               proceeding to be taken in the Province of 
               <lb/>
               Quebec on an <hi rendition="simple:italic">ex parte</hi> affidavit of one cred<lb break="no"/>itor, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Blake asked why a different amount of 
               <lb/>
               evidence should be considered sufficient in 
               <lb/>
               Quebec from what was necessary in other 
               <lb/>
               Provinces. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott explained the origin of the 
               <lb/>
               distinction. In 1864, when it was proposed 
               <lb/>
               with regard to the provisions as to intent to 
               <lb/>
               defraud, that an <hi rendition="simple:italic">ex parte</hi> affidavit of one 
               <lb/>
               credtior should be sufficient to warrant pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings, it was urged on behalf of Ontario, 
               <lb/>
               that this was a very arbitrary proceeding, and 
               <lb/>
               it was agreed that as regarded Ontario the 
               <lb/>
               evidence of two witnesses should be necessary. 
               <lb/>
               In Quebec, however, they had not been un<lb break="no"/>accustomed to that sort of thing, and they had 
               <lb/>
               found no injury result from it. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Blake urged that there should be uni<lb break="no"/>formity, and that the evidence of one witness 
               <lb/>
               should not be sufficient in one Province to put 
               <lb/>
               a debtor in liquidation, when in the other 
               <lb/>
               Provinces the evidence of two witnesses was 
               <lb/>
               required.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir George E. Cartier said the principle in 
               <lb/>
               question had long been in operation in Lower 
               <lb/>
               Canada and no abuse had resulted. If two 
               <lb/>
               affidavits were required, the proceedings in 
               <lb/>
               bankruptcy would be more formal than any<lb break="no"/>thing else. If hon. gentlemen desired the 
               <lb/>
               assimilation of the laws he could assure hon. 
               <lb/>
               members from the other Provinces that no 
               <lb/>
               inconvenience would follow the adpotion of 
               <lb/>
               the Lower Canada plan.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott contended that on account 
               <lb/>
               of the difference in the systems of the various 
               <lb/>
               
         
            <pb n="688" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0688.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">688</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">
               June 9, 1869</fw>
          

               Provinces, it would be convenient to maintain 
               <lb/>
               this difference of procedure. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Blake thought it was more than a differ<lb break="no"/>ence of procedure that one witness should be 
               <lb/>
               required in Quebec and two witnesses for the 
               <lb/>
               other Provinces. This anomaly should be swept 
               <lb/>
               away, and the law made uniform for the 
               <lb/>
               Dominion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir George E. Cartier thought the other 
               <lb/>
               Provinces might perhaps dispense with one 
               <lb/>
               of the witnesses, but he believed his hon. 
               <lb/>
               friend (Mr. Abbott) had acted cautiously in 
               <lb/>
               not interfering with the existing systems of 
               <lb/>
               procedure. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The clause was agreed to. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Clauses 21 to 28 were agreed to. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott moved an addition to the 
               <lb/>
               29th clause, providing that if no creditors were 
               <lb/>
               present at the meeting to appoint an assignee, 
               <lb/>
               the Judge might appoint one. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The clause as thus amended was agreed to. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The remaining clauses to 155 having been 
               <lb/>
               carried the Committee went back to the 60th 
               <lb/>
               clause. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Wood desired an amendment to 
               <lb/>
               the latter part of the clause, which he said 
               <lb/>
               was not worded properly. He wished to make 
               <lb/>
               it clear that the provision of the Act did not 
               <lb/>
               affect any lien created by the seizure by the 
               <lb/>
               Sheriff. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott said he thought the sug<lb break="no"/>gestion a good one. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               After some further discussion the clause 
               <lb/>
               was passed without amendment. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Some discussion took place on the 148th 
               <lb/>
               clause, which provides that all offences pu<lb break="no"/>nishable by the Act with imprisonment, shall 
               <lb/>
               be tried by the Court of Queen’s Bench with<lb break="no"/>out a jury. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. John Sandfield Macdonald protested 
               <lb/>
               against one mode of trial being provided for 
               <lb/>
               Quebec and another for the other Provinces. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald said that symmetry 
               <lb/>
               to a certain extent was desirable; but if there 
               <lb/>
               was anything to be complained of in the 
               <lb/>
               absence of trial by jury in Quebec, it was 
               <lb/>
               for the 65 members representing that Province 
               <lb/>
               to complain, and not for a member from 
               <lb/>
               Ontario. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. John Sandfield Macdonald said his 
               <lb/>
               complaint was that the gentleman in charge 
               <lb/>
               of the Bill (Mr. Abbott) was not introducing a 
               <lb/>
                     
            <pb n="689" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0689.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               9 juin 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
    
               new principle into the legislation of Lower 
               <lb/>
               Canada. The principle was one recognized in 
               <lb/>
               the Consolidated Statutes of Lower Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Holton was in favor of uniformity 
               <lb/>
               in this as in other matters of legislation, and 
               <lb/>
               he should be surprised if the Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Militia would declare that the feelings of any 
               <lb/>
               portion of the people of Lower Canada would 
               <lb/>
               be outraged by having the privilege of trial 
               <lb/>
               by jury secured to them in proceedings under 
               <lb/>
               the insolvency law. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir George E. Cartier said there was nothing 
               <lb/>
               the people of Lower Canada disliked so much 
               <lb/>
               as the failure of justice or that frauds should 
               <lb/>
               go unpunished. In commercial cases trial by 
               <lb/>
               jury could be demanded, but out of 1,200 or 
               <lb/>
               1,500 cases in a year trial by jury was not de<lb break="no"/>manded in more than 25 cases. They preferred 
               <lb/>
               that cases of this kind should be tried by the 
               <lb/>
               Judge, believing that frauds would thereby be 
               <lb/>
               more effectually punished. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Blake said the correct deduction from 
               <lb/>
               the premises of the Minister of Militia that the 
               <lb/>
               people of Lower Canada abhorred fraud 
               <lb/>
               would be that they should be entrusted with 
               <lb/>
               the power of trying cases of fraud. He dis<lb break="no"/>sented from the doctrine of the Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Justice, that only the members from Lower 
               <lb/>
               Canada should discuss this clause. He (Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Blake) held it was a matter of consequence to 
               <lb/>
               the whole Dominion that there should be uni<lb break="no"/>formity in the laws. This clause not only in<lb break="no"/>troduced dissimilarity between the procedure 
               <lb/>
               in Quebec and the procedure in the other 
               <lb/>
               Provinces, but it introduced dissimilarity be<lb break="no"/>tween the mode of trial of criminal cases in 
               <lb/>
               Quebec under this Act, and the trial of other 
               <lb/>
               criminal cases in that Province in which a 
               <lb/>
               jury was required. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Morris denied that there would be a 
               <lb/>
               dissimilarity in the mode of trial of similar 
               <lb/>
               classes of cases in Lower Canada. In com<lb break="no"/>mercial cases there—and these were com<lb break="no"/>mercial cases—trial by jury was not demanded 
               <lb/>
               in more than three cases out of a hundred. 
               <lb/>
               In Ontario last session, the practice of Lower 
               <lb/>
               Canada as to the trial of commercial cases had 
               <lb/>
               been adopted. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Irvine said in the Quebec district 
               <lb/>
               there were not more than four or five jury 
               <lb/>
               trials in commercial cases in a year, and he 
               <lb/>
               had been surprised to hear that there were so 
               <lb/>
               many as had been stated in the Montreal dis<lb break="no"/>trict. It was not in accordance with the feel<lb break="no"/>ings of the people of Quebec that there should 
               <lb/>
               be trials in such cases. The petty jurors were 
               <lb/>
               taken from a class who would be inclined to 
               <lb/>
               
            
            <pb n="690" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0690.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">690</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               June 9, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
        
               treat cases of this kind with leniency; and if 
               <lb/>
               trial by jury were provided for these cases, a 
               <lb/>
               conviction would be very rarely secured. If 
               <lb/>
               they gave the offender trial by jury, they only 
               <lb/>
               gave him a strong chance of escaping. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald thought the member 
               <lb/>
               for Durham now had an answer when it was 
               <lb/>
               shown that there was a sufficient reason why 
               <lb/>
               the system of trial by jury in these cases 
               <lb/>
               should not extend to Quebec. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Chauveau, in French, supported 
               <lb/>
               the clause. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Gray said the difficulty referred to 
               <lb/>
               by the Solicitor General of Quebec, of getting 
               <lb/>
               jurors in that Province who would faithfully 
               <lb/>
               do their duty in the administration of the 
               <lb/>
               criminal law, did not exist in New Brunswick, 
               <lb/>
               and he should not be very sorry that for the 
               <lb/>
               sake of symmetry his Province should be de<lb break="no"/>prived of the right of trial by jury. If, how<lb break="no"/>ever, the state of the administration of Justice 
               <lb/>
               in Quebec was such that there would be no 
               <lb/>
               security for the punishment of fraud without 
               <lb/>
               the provision, he was prepared to allow an 
               <lb/>
               exceptional provision for that Province. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Geoffrion, in French, expressed his dis<lb break="no"/>sent from the position of the Solicitor General 
               <lb/>
               of Lower Canada, that it was impossible to get 
               <lb/>
               justice from juries in that Province. He 
               <lb/>
               thought the right of trial by jury was prized 
               <lb/>
               in Lower Canada as well as in the rest of the 
               <lb/>
               Dominion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Chauveau made some remarks in 
               <lb/>
               reply to Mr. Geoffrion and vindicated the 
               <lb/>
               character of the jurors of Quebec, whom he 
               <lb/>
               held to be just as capable of rendering justice 
               <lb/>
               as those of any other Province. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Blake said the Premier of Quebec was 
               <lb/>
               quite at variance with his colleague, the 
               <lb/>
               Solicitor-General. The latter honorable gentle<lb break="no"/>man had given an answer to his question why 
               <lb/>
               there ought to be a variation, when he said 
               <lb/>
               the class of jurors was such that trial by jury 
               <lb/>
               would result in a failure of justice. But if the 
               <lb/>
               view of the Premier of Quebec was correct 
               <lb/>
               the variation rested on a mere whim and 
               <lb/>
               caprice, and his question remained why they 
               <lb/>
               should deprive British subjects who resided in 
               <lb/>
               Lower Canada of their birth-right, trial by 
               <lb/>
               jury, which was accorded to all Her Majesty’s 
               <lb/>
               subjects in the other Provinces. If, however, 
               <lb/>
               the view of the Solicitor-General was correct 
               <lb/>
               —if the jury system in Quebec was in such a 
               <lb/>
               state that these things could not be tried be<lb break="no"/>fore juries, then men’s lives were not safe in 
               <lb/>
               the Province of Quebec. (Hear, hear.) If juries 
               <lb/>
         
            <pb n="691" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0691.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               9 juin 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
          
               could not be entrusted with cases of this kind, 
               <lb/>
               they could not be trusted with cases in which 
               <lb/>
               men’s lives were at stake. It was a state of 
               <lb/>
               things which this Parliament could not cor<lb break="no"/>rect, but the Legislature of Quebec, under the 
               <lb/>
               direction of the Solicitor-General, ought to 
               <lb/>
               correct it. If corrected, the reason f0r the 
               <lb/>
               anomaly would cease, and this Parliament 
               <lb/>
               should not legislate in a wrong direction and 
               <lb/>
               enact an anomaly 0n the assumption that the 
               <lb/>
               Legislature of Quebec would not do its duty. 
               <lb/>
               On the contrary, they should legislate on the 
               <lb/>
               assumption that the Quebec Legislature would 
               <lb/>
               do its duty and correct its jury system. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir George E. Cartier would give not merely 
               <lb/>
               reasoning but authority for the position he had 
               <lb/>
               taken, In 1849, under the Baldwin-Lafontaine 
               <lb/>
               administration, it was a law enacted by the 
               <lb/>
               Parliament of Canada that in the case of fraud 
               <lb/>
               and misconduct power was given to the Judge 
               <lb/>
               in Chambers to imprison any fraudulent 
               <lb/>
               debtor for a term not exceeding one year, in 
               <lb/>
               a matter not amounting to $80. This was au<lb break="no"/>thority which ought to be satisfactory to the 
               <lb/>
               member for West Durham. No offence was 
               <lb/>
               taken by Lower Canada regarding that law, 
               <lb/>
               but on the contrary he had recently got an 
               <lb/>
               extension of it to make it more rigorous. This 
               <lb/>
               present measure provides that a party in a 
               <lb/>
               similar case is to be tried before the Court of 
               <lb/>
               Queen’s Bench. The present measure was 
               <lb/>
               therefore an amendment of the old law. The 
               <lb/>
               term of punishment was extended to 3 years 
               <lb/>
               under this Act; but the punishment was the 
               <lb/>
               same and there was the advantage that the 
               <lb/>
               decision, instead of being by one man, would 
               <lb/>
               be by a full Court. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Holton thought the Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Militia had not met the point raised by the 
               <lb/>
               member for West Durham. It was declared 
               <lb/>
               that in cases such as these a man was not 
               <lb/>
               entitled to trial by jury, but was to be tried 
               <lb/>
               by the Judge, because, according to the Pre<lb break="no"/>mier of Lower Canada, the Solicitor-General 
               <lb/>
               for Lower Canada and the Minister of Militia, 
               <lb/>
               the people of Lower Canada are not to be 
               <lb/>
               trusted with the trial of these cases though 
               <lb/>
               the other Provinces are. At a time when the 
               <lb/>
               Government are proposing to assimilate the 
               <lb/>
               laws of all the Provinces they dissimilate this. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Irvine said his argument had been 
               <lb/>
               misinterpreted. He never said that the juries 
               <lb/>
               of the Province of Quebec were an exception 
               <lb/>
               to any part for this duty. He had maintained, 
               <lb/>
               and still maintained, that this was a class of 
               <lb/>
               cases which ought not to be submitted to juries 
               <lb/>
               in any Province. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Chauveau denied that there ought 
               <lb/>
               to be absolute uniformity of Legislation for<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            <pb n="692" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-09_Page_0692.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">692</fw>  <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               June 9, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
            <p>
               the Dominion. He objected to such absolute 
               <lb/>
               Irvine-Democratic rule. It was a doctrine 
               <lb/>
               which would not suit any Province. Much 
               <lb/>
               wiser was it to keep to the views of the Minis<lb break="no"/>ter of Justice, and not force on any Province, 
               <lb/>
               hastily, any measure to which they were 
               <lb/>
               averse. As to the question itself, he did not 
               <lb/>
               over like the arrangement at first. Still, he 
               <lb/>
               saw good reason for the arrangement pro<lb break="no"/>posed; as there were matters to be decided 
               <lb/>
               which one man, well versed in accounts, might 
               <lb/>
               more equitably decide, than twelve men selec<lb break="no"/>ted at random. If the system did not suit 
               <lb/>
               one or the other Province, let them allow 
               <lb/>
               those to have it who wished it. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Abbott stated that this 148th clause 
               <lb/>
               had been passed some time ago, and discussion 
               <lb/>
               on it had been irregular. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Committee rose, and reported the Bill 
               <lb/>
               as amended. Report ordered to be read to<lb break="no"/>morrow.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The House adjourned at 12.35.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
           
     </div>    </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>