<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1870-03-29"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-03-29">29 March 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.

         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.


          <biblScope unit="page" from="756" to="757"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-29_Page_0756.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-29_Page_0757.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-29_Page_0756">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-29_Page_0756.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-29_Page_0757">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-29_Page_0757.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="756" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-29_Page_0756.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">756</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               March 29, 1870 
               </fw>
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> was not free from political bias and he could <lb/>
               give them a means of accomplishing that <lb/> object. He also argued that revisions
               that could <lb/> take effect after the framing of the list would <lb/> prevent all
               Government interference with the <lb/> lists, but that was no reason why they should
               <lb/> pass a defective law and he hoped that they <lb/> would never have such a
               primary list. For the <lb/> sake of uniformity they were to initiate what <lb/> was
               called a policy of concession, but what he <lb/> termed a policy of sacrifices; and
               the result <lb/> would be that every Province would have a <lb/> franchise which they
               did not like. (Hear.) <lb/> They were each asked to sacrifice themselves <lb/> in
               order that there might be a common sacri<lb break="no"/>fice. (Laughter.) The
               question was whether <lb/> they should look at the franchise on the ground <lb/> of
               Confederation of the four Provinces already <lb/> in union or to the accomplishment
               of the grand <lb/> design first held before their eyes, and for the <lb/>
               accomplishment of which the hon. gentleman <lb/> formed his Government and went to
               the people <lb/> upon, and on the necessity of the realizations <lb/> of which he
               based the question of the con<lb break="no"/>tinued existence of his Government. They
               were <lb/> told by the hon. gentleman that the admission <lb/> of Newfoundland was
               not a matter of years, <lb/> but of weeks and months; but if it was true, as <lb/> it
               had been asserted, and facts seemed to justi<lb break="no"/>fy the statement, that a
               very large majority of <lb/> the people of Newfoundland would, by that <lb/> law, be
               disfranchised—by adopting that princi<lb break="no"/>ple of uniformity, one of two
               questions would <lb/> have to be decided—either that Newfoundland <lb/> would not
               enter into the Union, or that an <lb/> exception must be made in her favour. The
               <lb/> hon. gentlemen opposite would not like to see <lb/> Newfoundland stay out; but
               they could not <lb/> expect the voters there to accept a system by <lb/> which they
               were depriving themselves of all <lb/> power in the Dominion. They must therefore
               <lb/> be prepared to make an exception in that case. <lb/> But would the Minister of
               Justice make an <lb/> exception in the case of Algoma, the greater <lb/> proportion
               of whose constituents would be dis<lb break="no"/>franchised by that Bill. (Hear,
               hear.) Therefore <lb/> if uniformity were to be decreed it must be <lb/> decreed for
               all. The Government presented to <lb/> the Confederation party in Newfoundland the
               <lb/> difficulty of meeting their opponents on the <lb/> question of
               disfranchisement. The people of <lb/> Newfoundland would not vote away their <lb/>
               political rights, and if he were a resident of <lb/> that Island he would be one of
               those who <lb/> would not vote away his political rights, which <lb/> would be the
               case if that Bill became law. Then <lb/> there was the Red River question. How would
               <lb/> the people of that country look at the question <lb/> of uniformity, and how
               would the people of <lb/> British Columbia regard it? Gentlemen oppo<lb break="no"
               />site inflicted many a serious blow at the fabric <lb/> of Confederation; but none
               would prove great<pb n="757" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-29_Page_0757.jpg"/>
               <!--<fw type="dateline">
               29 mars 1870 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->er
               than that scheme if carried into law. He <lb/> hoped the House would let the law
               stand, as it <lb/> was altered from time to time by the Local <lb/> Legislatures. The
               question of expense was also <lb/> a most serious one, and on that as well as on
               <lb/> other grounds, he hoped the House would <lb/> concur in the amendment proposed
               by the hon. <lb/> member for Hochelaga. (Applause.) <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> moved that the <lb/> Committee rise,
               report progress, and ask leave <lb/> to sit again on Thursday.—Carried. <lb/>
            </p>
            
   <div type="section">      
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               THUNDER BAY ROAD 
               
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Hon. Mr. Langevin</persName> presented papers con<lb break="no"/>nected
                  with the road between Thunder Bay <lb/> and Fort Garry. <lb/>
               </p>
            
   </div>

<div type="section">  
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               THE FINANCIAL STATEMENT</head>

            <p>
               In reply to the Hon. Mr. Holton,<lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HINC1">Hon. Sir Francis Hincks</persName> said he could not <lb/> tell at what
                  time he would bring down the <lb/> Budget until the Estimates were ready. They
                  <lb/> were almost ready to come down, and he was <lb/> told to-day they would be
                  ready to-morrow. It <lb/> was absolutely impossible until he laid the <lb/>
                  Estimates on the table, to say when he could <lb/> bring down the Budget. <lb/>
               </p>
            
</div>
      <div type="section">      
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               THE RED RIVER MURDER 
          
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> said a very painful rumour had <lb/> been abroad as
                  to the execution of a person at <lb/> Red River. He wished to know if the
                     Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had received any information on the <lb/> subject?
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said the Gov<lb break="no"
                  />ernment had no official or reliable information <lb/> on the subject. All he
                  could say was that they <lb/> had received a message from a gentleman at St. <lb/>
                  Paul marked "private," stating that it was said <lb/> a person named Scott had
                  been shot by the <lb/> Provisional Government. What was the foun<lb break="no"
                  />dation for the statement, he (Sir John) did not <lb/> know. <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> hoped the Government had <lb/> taken some means
                  to procure accurate infor<lb break="no"/>mation, for if the person who had assumed
                  <lb/> authority at Red River had proceeded to the <lb/> length of taking a
                  Canadian life he hoped the <lb/> Government would not fail to do their duty. He
                  <lb/> wished to know whether the Government had <lb/> taken means to ascertain the
                  accuracy of the <lb/> statement. <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said steps <lb/> would be taken by
                  the Government to inquire <lb/> into the truth of the matter. <lb/>
               </p>
      </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>