<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1869-04-16"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-04-16">16 April 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
 
         
         <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.  
          

           <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="12"/>.
 <biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="22"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0011.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0012.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0018.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0019.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0020.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0021.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0022.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="nguyenkim" when="2017-01-16"> Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0011">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0011.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0012">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0012.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0018">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0018.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0019">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0019.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0020">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0020.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0021">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0021.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0022">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0022.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="11" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0011.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               16 avril 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p>
               [...] now returned after a most successful mission 
               <lb/>
               and the negotiations could be renewed. In the 
               <lb/>
               meantime he could inform the House that the 
               <lb/>
               Department of Inland Revenue had been 
               <lb/>
               most successfully managed by the Post<lb break="no"/>master-General, who attended to these ad<lb break="no"/>ditional arduous duties during the whole of 
               <lb/>
               the winter, though at great personal loss and 
               <lb/>
               labour. The interests of the public service in 
               <lb/>
               this respect had not, therefore, suffered in 
               <lb/>
               any way. The thing, of course, could not be 
               <lb/>
               carried on, and it was the intention of the 
               <lb/>
               Government to fill up the vacancy, and place 
               <lb/>
               a responsible man at the head of the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment. As to the proportional representation 
               <lb/>
               of the Provinces in the Cabinet, his honour<lb break="no"/>able friend would remember that it was 
               <lb/>
               stated by the Government during the first 
               <lb/>
               session that these matters, the formation of 
               <lb/>
               the Government, division of the offices, &amp;c., 
               <lb/>
               were of necessity experimental, and this was 
               <lb/>
               the case yet. In the event of the absorption 
               <lb/>
               of the great North-West and Newfoundland 
               <lb/>
               into the Dominion, new duties and responsi<lb break="no"/>bilities would be involved, and very probably 
               <lb/>
               a re-adjustment of the different heads of the 
               <lb/>
               Departments. But he had no doubt that with<lb break="no"/>in the limits of a legitimate opposition, the 
               <lb/>
               Government would be supported in any ef<lb break="no"/>forts they might make to administer the new 
               <lb/>
               state of affairs. As to Mr. Howe, he (Sir 
               <lb/>
               John) hoped the people of Hants would soon 
               <lb/>
               enable that hon. gentleman to explain his 
               <lb/>
               own position on the floor of the House. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> thanked the Minister of <lb/> Justice for
               his full and explicit information. <lb/> It would be unusual and inconvenient to
               <lb/> debate at that moment the policy involved in <lb/> the explanations; but there
               was just one <lb/> point more that ought to be explained. The <lb/> Minister of
               Justice said in the course of his <lb/> explanations, that negotiations had been
                  en<lb break="no"/>tered into with the view of filling the vacant <lb/> offices
               before the two members of the Cabinet <lb/> went to England. As a matter of courtesy,
               <lb/> the House was entitled to know what direc<lb break="no"/>tion these
               negotiations took, and why they <lb/> did not go on. Having been informed that <lb/>
               negotiations had been entered into, the House <lb/> was entitled to know all about
               them. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said that at the <lb/> proper time a full
               and frank explanation <lb/> would be given. The negotiations ought never <lb/> to be
               stated until they came to a result. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         <!--   <fw type="running">DÉBATS DES COMMUNES</fw>
            <fw type="num">11</fw>-->

            <pb n="12" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0012.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">12</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 16, 1869<lb/></fw>
            
<p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName>—You mentioned them <lb/> yourself.
               (Laughter.)<lb/>
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said that it was <lb/> merely mentioned.
               <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said there was one other <lb/> point. The House
               had just been informed that <lb/> the filling up of certain offices had been a <lb/>
               matter of experiment. It would be desirable <lb/> that the House should be informed
                  concern<lb break="no"/>ing the two offices of Secretaries of State. Of <lb/>
               course, this House was aware that the duties <lb/> of both offices had been discharged
               by one <lb/> person, the member for Dorchester. The <lb/> House was entitled to know
               if that honour<lb break="no"/>able gentleman was hereafter to discharge <lb/> the
               duties of both offices. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> was glad his atten<lb break="no"/>tion had
               been called to that subject. The <lb/> office of Secretary of State had been created
               <lb/> because the necessity was felt for having a <lb/> channel of communication
               between the Do<lb break="no"/>minion and Provincial Governments. It was <lb/> deemed
               desirable that the numerous ques<lb break="no"/>tions which it was supposed would
               arise in <lb/> this way should be disposed of by some one <lb/> Minister. On the
               commencement of the new <lb/> order of things, however, it was found that <lb/> until
               the relative positions of the Provincial <lb/> and Dominion Governments were
                  ascertain<lb break="no"/>ed, until they came to be clearly defined like <lb/> those
               of old established Governments, a good <lb/> portion of the subjects which would be
                  or<lb break="no"/>dinarily assigned to the charge of the Sec<lb break="no"/>retary
               of State, had to be disposed of by the <lb/> Minister of Justice. So many questions
               arose <lb/> in constitutional law and kindred topics, that <lb/> he, as Minister of
               Justice, had been obliged <lb/> to direct his attention to them. Therefore a <lb/>
               great deal of the work which would even<lb break="no"/>tually fall on some such
               officer as the Secre<lb break="no"/>tary of State, devolved at present on the <lb/>
               Minister of Justice. All correspondence be<lb break="no"/>tween the Provinces and the
               Dominion of <lb/> course was conducted by the Secretary of <lb/> State. For the
               present it was proposed that <lb/> things should remain as they were, because <lb/>
               it was clear that if there was any necessity <lb/> for the offices, before the
               extension of the <lb/> Dominion boundary, that necessity would be <lb/> greatly
               increased the moment Newfoundland <lb/> and the North West became part of the Do<lb
                  break="no"/>minion. As he had stated before, the distribu<lb break="no"/>tion of
               offices and power was of necessity to <lb/> a great extent experimental in the
               Dominion. <lb/> From the mover of the Address they had <lb/> heard what the
               Government would be ex<lb break="no"/>pected to do if they assumed the control of
               <lb/> the North-West. The subjects then alluded <lb/> to as having to be dealt with
               were numerous <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0018.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">18</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 16, 1869<lb/></fw>
            

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>
               not among them a man who could make any 
               <lb/>
               pretentions to military knowledge, and he 
               <lb/>
               believed matters to be worse still in the 
               <lb/>
               county adjoining. These appointments had 
               <lb/>
               been avowedly made from one little party; 
               <lb/>
               and they had the hon. gentleman who was in<lb break="no"/>trusted with this selection avowing in his own 
               <lb/>
               paper that, until all his Tory friends had been 
               <lb/>
               satisfied, not one should get a commission who 
               <lb/>
               had opposed the Government or himself at 
               <lb/>
               the last election. (Hear, hear.) This was the 
               <lb/>
               new mode of administering the Militia affairs 
               <lb/>
               of the Dominion. (Hear, hear.) In the Militia 
               <lb/>
               administration there had not only been ex<lb break="no"/>travagance, but there had been a direct viola<lb break="no"/>tion of the votes passed by this House, and 
               <lb/>
               the utmost practical inefficiency. He was told 
               <lb/>
               the other day, on good authority, that in one 
               <lb/>
               parish, where it was known there were alto<lb break="no"/>gether only 65 male adults, a return had been 
               <lb/>
               made of something over 300, in order to in<lb break="no"/>crease the amount allowed per head for 
               <lb/>
               enrollment. He made these complaints with 
               <lb/>
               profound regret. He was desirous to see the 
               <lb/>
               Militia force organized on an efficient footing, 
               <lb/>
               and he was sorry to say that, so far as he had 
               <lb/>
               been able to observe, this had not been done. 
               <lb/>
               The Minister of Militia was not directly to 
               <lb/>
               blame, having been absent from the country 
               <lb/>
               for six months, but some one ought to be held 
               <lb/>
               responsible. Until the papers were brought 
               <lb/>
               down, it would be manifestly inexpedient to 
               <lb/>
               discuss the question as to the admission of 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland into the Confederation; but 
               <lb/>
               as a sincere friend of the Union of the Prov<lb break="no"/>inces and British connection, he congratu<lb break="no"/>lated the Government, the House and the 
               <lb/>
               country on the application of another of our 
               <lb/>
               North American Colonies to be admitted 
               <lb/>
               into the Union, and he begged to say that 
               <lb/>
               anything he could do to aid the Government 
               <lb/>
               in carrying this matter to a successful com<lb break="no"/>pletion should be done most heartily and 
               <lb/>
               most cheerfully. (Hear, hear.) In regard to 
               <lb/>
               the opening up of the North-West Territory, 
               <lb/>
               he hoped the propositions of the Government 
               <lb/>
               would be so well considered that it would 
               <lb/>
               not be necessary for the hon. gentlemen acting 
               <lb/>
               with him to propose any serious amendment, 
               <lb/>
               as it was for the interest of the country that 
               <lb/>
               all questions connected with the opening up 
               <lb/>
               of that vast Territory should be settled as 
               <lb/>
               soon as possible, and upon as equitable a 
               <lb/>
               basis as possible. It was a serious matter to 
               <lb/>
               undertake the government of that great Prov<lb break="no"/>ince, as it soon would be, and the whole 
               <lb/>
               matter was one which would require the 
               <lb/>
               utmost attention of the Government and all 
               <lb/>
               other members of this House. He particularly 
               <lb/>
               recognized in that his own responsibility, as 
               <lb/>
               a member of the House, and should aid in<lb/>
       
            <pb n="19" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0019.jpg"/>
          <!--  <fw type="dateline">
               16 avril 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
     
               perfecting arrangements which would have 
               <lb/>
               an influence on the condition of all the Prov<lb break="no"/>inces for many generations. Mr. Mackenzie 
               <lb/>
               then reverted to the pernicious system in<lb break="no"/>augurated by this Government, in allowing 
               <lb/>
               officeholders to retain their seats in the House 
               <lb/>
               without even requiring them to go before 
               <lb/>
               their constituents for re—election. He said they 
               <lb/>
               might just as well admit Judges and other 
               <lb/>
               such functionaries as the Arbitrator between 
               <lb/>
               the Provinces and the Intercolonial Railroad 
               <lb/>
               Commissioners. He had heard that another 
               <lb/>
               member of the House was to be appointed a 
               <lb/>
               Commissioner for codifying the laws; but he 
               <lb/>
               sincerely trusted that if such a step had been 
               <lb/>
               intended it would be reconsidered. Such a 
               <lb/>
               policy was in the highest degree destructive 
               <lb/>
               of public morality, and would gradually de<lb break="no"/>stroy in the public mind that respect which 
               <lb/>
               ought to exist for the Legislature of the 
               <lb/>
               country. There was another point to which 
               <lb/>
               he would allude before sitting down. The 
               <lb/>
               Minister of Justice professed to have con<lb break="no"/>structed this Government on the Coalition 
               <lb/>
               principle. They had been told by the Minister 
               <lb/>
               of Public Works and the late Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Inland Revenue that it was solely because it 
               <lb/>
               was a Coalition Government that they had 
               <lb/>
               entered it—that it was solely because such a 
               <lb/>
               Government was necessary in order to the 
               <lb/>
               right conducting of our affairs, and in order 
               <lb/>
               to sustain some hon. gentlemen in the Lower 
               <lb/>
               Province who had taken office, that they had 
               <lb/>
               consented to enter it. Those hon. gentlemen 
               <lb/>
               also claim that the three Reformers from On<lb break="no"/>tario, and the others from the Lower Prov<lb break="no"/>inces, would be able to counterpoise the 
               <lb/>
               Conservative element, or at least to equal it. 
               <lb/>
               Well, if it was necessary that the Province 
               <lb/>
               of Ontario should have three representatives 
               <lb/>
               from the Reform ranks in the Cabinet, how 
               <lb/>
               must it have suffered when there was only 
               <lb/>
               one such representative, and that one absent 
               <lb/>
               from the country for the last six months, 
               <lb/>
               allowing the Conservative element to run 
               <lb/>
               riot in the organization of the militia, the 
               <lb/>
               management of the Intercolonial and every<lb break="no"/>thing else. (Hear, hear.) The Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Customs belonged originally to the Reform 
               <lb/>
               party, and perhaps it might be said that the 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentleman had been suflicient for the 
               <lb/>
               interests of that party in the Cabinet, in the 
               <lb/>
               absence of his colleague; but if the hon. 
               <lb/>
               gentleman yielded as easily on every matter 
               <lb/>
               that concerned the party he professed to rep<lb break="no"/>resent as he seemed to have yielded with 
               <lb/>
               reference to the Intercolonial route, the pro<lb break="no"/>tection given by him amounted to very little. 
               <lb/>
               The result had shown that he (Mr. Mac<lb break="no"/>kenzie) was right in the prophecy he 
               <lb/>
               ventured to make when the Coalition was<lb/>
          
       
            <pb n="20" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0020.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">20</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 16, 1869<lb/></fw>
           
               formed, that it would end in the absorption 
               <lb/>
               of the minority element. (Hear, hear). 
               <lb/>
               Some of the Conservative organs, indeed, 
               <lb/>
               had claimed that, as at the last election, the 
               <lb/>
Conservative element came a majority 
               <lb/>
               amongst the representatives of Ontario; 
               <lb/>
               therefore, the Ontario Conservatives were 
               <lb/>
entitled to three seats in the Cabinet, and the 
               <lb/>
               Reformers to but two. With reference to this 
               <lb/>
               he (Mr. Mackenzie) contended that this result 
               <lb/>
               had been obtained by its being sedulously 
               <lb/>
               urged upon the people that it did not matter 
               <lb/>
               whether a Conservative or a Reformer was 
               <lb/>
               elected, and that the only question with refer<lb break="no"/>ence to a candidate should be whether he 
               <lb/>
               would support the Government. In this way, 
               <lb/>
               by the joint action of the Minister of Justice 
               <lb/>
               and the Premier of Ontario, the Reformers 
               <lb/>
               had been cheated out of a fair representation 
               <lb/>
               in this House. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
 
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD2">Hon. J. S. Macdonald</persName>—We beat you, at all <lb/> events. <lb/>
            </p>
            
    
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said they had tried to <lb/> beat him, but had
               completely failed. The <lb/> honourable gentleman ventured to make a <lb/> pilgrimage
               into his (Mr. Mackenzie's) county, <lb/> but was compelled to beat an ignominious
               <lb/> retreat, and his majority was twice the num<lb break="no"/>ber of the electors,
               if not of the souls, in the <lb/> whole constituency. (Hear, hear). He had <lb/>
               thought it expedient to call the attention of <lb/> the Liberals in the House to the
               manner in <lb/> which they had been treated by honourable <lb/> gentlemen opposite.
               He had never expected <lb/> that the Minister of Public Works would be <lb/> either
               the representative or the protector of <lb/> the Reform party in the Cabinet; but he
               had <lb/> expected that some decent measure of atten<lb break="no"/>tion would have
               been paid to the position <lb/> that was taken in the organization of the <lb/>
               Government. Mr. Mackenzie then said he <lb/> would refrain from entering on any more
               full <lb/> discussion of the matters embraced in the <lb/> address, until the papers
               were brought down, <lb/> and again congratulated the House on the <lb/> prospect we
               had that we should soon be not <lb/> merely in theory, but in fact, a Confederation
               <lb/> of the British North American Provinces<lb break="no"/>knit together in such a
               way as to promote <lb/> mutual interests and to maintain the glory of <lb/> our
               fatherland and our connection with it. <lb/> (Cheers). <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Paragraphs two to five were agreed to. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Paragraph six, relating to the North-West 
               <lb/>
               negotiations having been put-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> said there was an evi<lb break="no"/>dent desire
               on the part of the House not <lb/>
               <pb n="21" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0021.jpg"/>
               <!--<fw type="dateline">
               16 avril 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
               to prolong the debate, and agreeing in that <lb/> desire, he would not make a speech.
               He felt <lb/> bound to say, however, that so far as he <lb/> could judge from the
               papers which had been <lb/> published, he conceived we had nothing <lb/> whatever to
               congratulate ourselves upon <lb/> in the result of the mission to England. <lb/> He
               had been from the initiation of <lb/> the movement an agreeing party to <lb/> the
               policy of acquiring the North-West and <lb/> he still thought it most desirable we
               <lb/> should acquire it; but he must say, so far as <lb/> he could judge from these
               papers, that our <lb/> case had been most deplorably mismanaged. <lb/> We had now,
               perhaps, an opportunity of <lb/> getting that Territory; but it was on terms <lb/>
               which ought never to have been assented to. <lb/> He should be prepared at the proper
               time to <lb/> show, unless there were something in the <lb/> papers which had not yet
               been given to the <lb/> public, that our representatives had been <lb/> completely
               out-generaled by the very able <lb/> men who represented the H. B. Co. in Eng<lb
                  break="no"/>land, and also by the Colonial Minister him<lb break="no"/>self. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The sixth and the remaining paragraphs 
               <lb/>
               of the Address were agreed to.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> then moved that the <lb/> resolutions be
               referred to a Committee, con<lb break="no"/>sisting of Messrs. Cartier, Tilley,
               Langevin, <lb/> Simpson, Bolton and the mover to prepare <lb/> and report an
               Address—Carried. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The Committee immediately reported the 
               <lb/>
               Address, which was ordered to be engrossed 
               <lb/>
               and presented to His Excellency by such 
               <lb/>
               members of the House as are members of 
               <lb/>
               the Privy Council. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> reminded the Premier <lb/> that the names of the
               Intercolonial Railway <lb/> Commissioners had not yet been finally an<lb break="no"
               />nounced to the House. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said a message, <lb/> making the
               announcement, was in his office <lb/> ready to be brought down. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> asked when the papers <lb/> relating to the Nova
               Scotia arrangement, the <lb/> admission of Newfoundland and the acqui<lb break="no"
               />sition of the Hudson's Bay Territory would <lb/> be brought down? <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said the Nova Sco<lb break="no"/>tia
               papers were complete, and would be <lb/> brought down immediately. The Newfound<lb
                  break="no"/>land papers were incomplete, but he would <lb/> consider whether he
               could bring down the <lb/> papers showing what had been done so far. <lb/> The
               Hudson's Bay papers were also incom<lb break="no"/><pb n="22"
                  facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0022.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">22</fw>
               <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
               <fw type="dateline">April 16, 1869<lb/></fw>plete. The Governor-General was warranted
               <lb/> in making the statement he did as to the <lb/> acceptance of the proposal by
               the Company, <lb/> having received a cable despatched to that <lb/> effect from Earl
               Granville; but of course <lb/> a despatch from Earl Granville must be re<lb
                  break="no"/>ceived before the House could be invited to <lb/> take action. <lb/>
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> then moved that on Tues<lb break="no"/>day next
               His Excellency's speech be taken <lb/> into consideration as the first formal step
               <lb/> towards constituting a Committee of Supply. <lb/> Carried. <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The House at 20 minutes past 5 adjourned 
               <lb/>
               till Monday. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
           
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>