<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1869-05-28" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-05-28">28 May 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.

          
         
         <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

         <date when="1975"/>.    
          

           <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="489" to="489"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-28_Page_0489.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
      
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
<change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-02-14">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-28_Page_0489">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-28_Page_0489.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="489" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-28_Page_0489.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               28 mai 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p>
              [...] sixty-nine millions of people. To ﬁll up, and 
               <lb/>
               organize and develop, and govern such a 
               <lb/>
               country would give scope and employment 
               <lb/>
               enough for all our skill and energies. The 
               <lb/>
               utmost anxiety had been shown by the Duke 
               <lb/>
               of Buckingham, the Earl of Granville, and 
               <lb/>
               other British Ministers to obtain for Canada 
               <lb/>
               on terms which would not be burdensome to 
               <lb/>
               us, the control and management of the terri<lb break="no"/>tory, and it was evident that so soon as the 
               <lb/>
               transfer was made there would be in the 
               <lb/>
               mother country a strong desire on the part 
               <lb/>
               of those who wished to better their condition 
               <lb/>
               to emigrate to Canada, with the view of 
               <lb/>
               proceeding to the North-West, and there ﬁnd<lb break="no"/>ing new homes under the shelter of British 
               <lb/>
               institutions. That desire already existed, and 
               <lb/>
               it would be very much increased when it 
               <lb/>
               became known that we had taken posssession 
               <lb/>
               of the country and organized a suitable Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment over it. He considered we were now 
               <lb/>
               on the eve of obtaining the great objects we 
               <lb/>
               had in contemplation. When the Coalition 
               <lb/>
               Government of 1864 was formed the Minister 
               <lb/>
               of Militia had informed the House that there 
               <lb/>
               was at that time a prospect of securing the 
               <lb/>
               admission of Newfoundland. We knew that 
               <lb/>
               British Columbia was only waiting the settle<lb break="no"/>ment of the question with regard to the 
               <lb/>
               Northwest territory, to ask admission also; so 
               <lb/>
               that we might look forward to having our 
               <lb/>
               Confederacy extend in a short time from 
               <lb/>
               ocean to ocean, as was contemplated in the 
               <lb/>
               Quebec resolutions. At the time of the Toronto 
               <lb/>
               Convention, he (Mr. McDougall) was subjected 
               <lb/>
               to a good deal of unpleasant comments from 
               <lb/>
               his former political friends, the member for 
               <lb/>
               Lambton and others, for having resolved to 
               <lb/>
               maintain his position in the Government until 
               <lb/>
               the work they had undertaken was com<lb break="no"/>pleted. He recollected the sneer with which 
               <lb/>
               the acquisition of the North West was re<lb break="no"/>ferred to, as if it would take many years to 
               <lb/>
               bring that about, and as if he made the com<lb break="no"/>pletion of the work merely an excuse for re<lb break="no"/>maining in ofﬁce. He was proud to believe 
               <lb/>
               that they were now on the eve of the com<lb break="no"/>pletion of that work, and that it would be 
               <lb/>
               entirely completed before this Government, 
               <lb/>
               in its present form, was dissolved. Only when 
               <lb/>
               it was so completed would he feel that he had 
               <lb/>
               accomplished the work which he set about 
               <lb/>
               in 1864; and all the assaults made on him 
               <lb/>
               would fall harmless in presence of the fact 
               <lb/>
               that they had achieved a successful result 
               <lb/>
               in ﬁnishing the great work they had then 
               <lb/>
               undertaken.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said that looking at the par<lb break="no"/>ticular point as to whether it was better to <lb/> accept such terms or continue an
               almost in- [...]<lb/>
            </p>
          
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>