<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1948-02-06"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title> 
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1948-02-06">6 February 1948</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Twentieth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
           

          <date when="1948"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmond Cloutier, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="940" to="944"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0940.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0941.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0942.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0943.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0944.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0940">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0940.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0941">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0941.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0942">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0942.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0943">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0943.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0944">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0944.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="940" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0940.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">940</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
            
            <fw type="running">
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Address—Mr. Dorion</hi> 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The question of expense may be raised. Let 
               <lb/>
               me point out that the total amount paid by 
               <lb/>
               the Canadian National Railways out of its 
               <lb/>
               revenues in respect of pensions is only 2.6 per 
               <lb/>
               cent. I make this appeal to the minister. I 
               <lb/>
               ask him to give consideration to assuring the 
               <lb/>
               railway employees of the Canadian National 
               <lb/>
               Railways that degree of security after retire<lb break="no"/>ment which other classes in this country 
               <lb/>
               are receiving today. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. FREDERIC DORION (Charlevoix<lb break="no"/>Saguenay): I should like to take advantage of 
               <lb/>
               this debate to express my personal views on 
               <lb/>
               a matter which is of very great importance to 
               <lb/>
               the people of this country, and especially to 
               <lb/>
               the province of Quebec, namely, the question 
               <lb/>
               of the ownership of the Labrador territory. I 
               <lb/>
               have given some study to that question; I 
               <lb/>
               was particularly interested in it because I have 
               <lb/>
               the honour to represent the only constituency 
               <lb/>
               in the dominion that is bounded by the 
               <lb/>
               Labrador territory. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               When the delegates of Newfoundland came 
               <lb/>
               to Ottawa last summer and met the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of the Canadian government to 
               <lb/>
               study the possibility of Newfoundland enter<lb break="no"/>ing into the Canadian confederation, I 
               <lb/>
               endeavoured to follow as closely as possible 
               <lb/>
               the discussion which took place at the time. 
               <lb/>
               The reports given us by the newspapers failed 
               <lb/>
               to give us a full account of the discussions, 
               <lb/>
               and when we were called for the present 
               <lb/>
               session I was glad to have the opportunity of 
               <lb/>
               reading the report which was published by the 
               <lb/>
               government in two volumes entitled: “Report 
               <lb/>
               of meetings between delegates from the 
               <lb/>
               national convention of Newfoundland and 
               <lb/>
               representatives of the government of Canada.” 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               I was also much interested in reading the 
               <lb/>
               letter written by the Prime Minister (Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Mackenzie King) on October 29, 1947, to the 
               <lb/>
               governor of Newfoundland, together with the 
               <lb/>
               “proposed arrangements for the entry of New<lb break="no"/>foundland into confederation” which was 
               <lb/>
               annexed to the letter, and printed in a separ<lb break="no"/>ate pamphlet, under the caption: “Terms 
               <lb/>
               believed to constitute a fair and equitable 
               <lb/>
               basis for union of Newfoundland with Canada 
               <lb/>
               should the people of Newfoundland desire to 
               <lb/>
               enter into confederation.” 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            <p>
               Notwithstanding the vote which was taken 
               <lb/>
               in the national convention of Newfoundland 
               <lb/>
               some days ago, I am sure that the question 
               <lb/>
               involved is not disposed of, and we may well 
               <lb/>
               rest assured that in the near future the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of the entry of Newfoundland into our 
               <lb/>

               confederation will be the subject of further 
               <lb/>
               discussions. That is the reason why I feel it is 
               <lb/>
               our duty to study as closely as possible the 
               <lb/>
               
       <cb/>
            
         
               conditions under which the Canadian govern<lb break="no"/>ment would see ﬁt to accept this new province 
               <lb/>
               in our confederation. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We must not forget either that our neigh<lb break="no"/>bour to the south seems to be very much 
               <lb/>
               interested in the settlement of that matter. 
               <lb/>
               Not later than last Thursday, January 29, we 
               <lb/>
               could read in the newspapers a dispatch from 
               <lb/>
               Washington as follows: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               An unofﬁcial, tentative proposal from New<lb break="no"/>foundland for “closer association” with the 
               <lb/>
               United States is receiving scant attention here 
               <lb/>
               this morning. It would call for interference 
               <lb/>
               by the United States before the approaching 
               <lb/>
               plebisicite in the colony to the extent of a 
               <lb/>
               declaration promising support for an indepen<lb break="no"/>dent government and for help in developing a 
               <lb/>
               steel industry in Newfoundland and Labrador 
               <lb/>
               which, it claims, would save the United States 
               <lb/>
               from becoming dependent on Canada for iron or 
               <lb/>
               steel. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               Everyone knows that when we speak of 
               <lb/>
               developing a steel or iron industry in that part 
               <lb/>
               of the continent we have in mind the territory 
               <lb/>
               known as Labrador on the mainland, much 
               <lb/>
               more than the island of Newfoundland itself. 
               <lb/>
               That is the reason why it is of the utmost im<lb break="no"/>portance to ascertain whether that territory be<lb break="no"/>longs really to Newfoundland. In the course 
               <lb/>
               of my remarks I will endeavour to show, Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Speaker, that notwithstanding the report of the 
               <lb/>
               judicial committee of the privy council made 
               <lb/>
               in March, 1927, that territory still belongs to 
               <lb/>
               the province of Quebec. Mark you, sir, it must 
               <lb/>
               be noted that the privy council did not render 
               <lb/>
               a judgment, a judicial decision; it was no more 
               <lb/>
               than a report on a reference which, as I will 
               <lb/>
               show later on, was badly drafted, incomplete, 
               <lb/>
               not properly presented, and proper action on it 
               <lb/>
               has never been taken. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               In reading the report of the conference which 
               <lb/>
               took place last summer, I noticed that quite 
               <lb/>
               a number of questions were asked by the New<lb break="no"/>foundland delegation for the purpose of estab<lb break="no"/>lishing the position of the parties in regard to 
               <lb/>
               the matters involved in the questions. I was 
               <lb/>
               quite surprised to read at page 158 of volume 
               <lb/>
               2 of the report the following question regard<lb break="no"/>ing Labrador: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
               Question: If Newfoundland joined Canada, 
               <lb/>
               would. Labrador remain a part of the province 
               <lb/>
               of Newfoundland? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Answer: The Canadian government has 
               <lb/>
               always felt that it is bound by the award made 
               <lb/>
               by the judicial committee of the privy council 
               <lb/>
               in 1927 with respect to the Labrador boundary. 
               <lb/>
               The Canadian government assumes that, if New<lb break="no"/>foundland became a province of Canada, New<lb break="no"/>foundland Labrador would be a part of that 
               <lb/>
               province. Section 3 of the British North 
               <lb/>
               America Act of 1871 might also be consulted. It 
               <lb/>
               is clear from this section that the parliament 
               <lb/>
               of Canada cannot alter the boundaries of &amp; 
               <lb/>
               province without the consent of the legislature 
               <lb/>
               of the province concerned. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p></quote>
            
            <pb n="941" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0941.jpg"/>
       
            <fw type="dateline">
               FEBRUARY 6, 1948</fw>

               <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Address—Mr. Dorion</hi> </fw>
              <fw type="num">941</fw>
            
            <p>
               In reading that question it came to my mind 
               <lb/>
               that if the delegates of Newfoundland thought 
               <lb/>
               it advisable to ask it, it was surely because 
               <lb/>
               they were far from being convinced that the 
               <lb/>
               matter had been ﬁnally settled by the report 
               <lb/>
               of the privy council; otherwise I cannot 
               <lb/>
               imagine that they would have asked such a 
               <lb/>
               question. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I was also very much surprised to read in 
               <lb/>
               the proposed arrangements submitted to the 
               <lb/>
               government of Newfoundland by the Prime 
               <lb/>
               Minister the following paragraph, page 5 of the 
               <lb/>
               pamphlet, section 2: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               The province of Newfoundland will include 
               <lb/>
               the territory of Labrador defined by the award 
               <lb/>
               of the judicial committee of the privy council 
               <lb/>
               in 1927 as Newfoundland territory. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               And one may further notice that such 
               <lb/>
               statement comes right at the beginning of the 
               <lb/>
               proposed arrangements, as if it was one of 
               <lb/>
               the most important questions to be decided. 
               <lb/>
               We can surely infer, from the special care 
               <lb/>
               and the particular consideration given to 
               <lb/>
               that matter relating to the boundary between 
               <lb/>
               the province of Quebec and Newfoundland, 
               <lb/>
               that it has never been settled before, and 
               <lb/>
               that the interested parties are willing to take 
               <lb/>
               advantage of the entry into confederation of 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland to settle the matter ﬁnally. But 
               <lb/>
               my contention is that the Canadian govern<lb break="no"/>ment has not the right, has not the legal 
               <lb/>
               power, to dispose of a territory belonging to 
               <lb/>
               the province of Quebec; and I will go as 
               <lb/>
               far as to say that even if there was an  agree<lb break="no"/>ment between Newfoundland and Canada to 
               <lb/>
               that eﬂect, it would be ultra vires of the 
               <lb/>
               powers of the government, and the problem 
               <lb/>
               itself would not be solved. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Since the Canadian government rely upon 
               <lb/>
               what they call the award of the judicial com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the privy council for the purpose of 
               <lb/>
               admitting the rights of Newfoundland over 
               <lb/>
               the Labrador territory, I will endeavour, Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Speaker, to explain and to prove that nothing 
               <lb/>
               whatsoever has been ﬁnally decided by this 
               <lb/>
               report and that the province of Quebec still 
               <lb/>
               has jurisdiction over that territory. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               To enable us to understand as clearly as 
               <lb/>
               possible this important problem, we must go 
               <lb/>
               back as far as 1763 and see what were the 
               <lb/>
               different measures which were passed by the 
               <lb/>
               imperial government as well as by the 
               <lb/>
               Canadian government in relation to that 
               <lb/>
               matter. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            <p>
               Everyone knows that in 1763, by the treaty 
               <lb/>
               of Paris, the French government ceded to His 
               <lb/>
               Majesty the King of England all the terri<lb break="no"/>tories on the North American continent. In 
               <lb/>
               the same year a commission was issued under 
               <lb/>
               the great seal of His Majesty, by which 
               <lb/>

               
        <cb/>
               Captain Graves was appointed as “Governor 
               <lb/>
               and commissioner in chief of the island! of 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland and all the coasts of Labrador 
               <lb/>
               from Hudson strait to river St. John”. This 
               <lb/>
               gave jurisdiction to the governor of New<lb break="no"/>foundland over Labrador coast itself, and 
               <lb/>
               also over a part of the coast in the gulf of 
               <lb/>
               St. Lawrence as far as Anticosti island. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               In October of the same year, 1763, the 
               <lb/>
               British government decided to form four 
               <lb/>
               separate governments in North America-<lb/>
Quebec, East Florida, West Florida and 
               <lb/>
               Granada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The government of Quebec had jurisdiction 
               <lb/>
               over the territory adjoining the St. Lawrence 
               <lb/>
               river starting from river St. John. But in 
               <lb/>
               1774, by the Quebec Act, it was enacted that 
               <lb/>
               all the territories on the mainland would form 
               <lb/>
               part of the government of Quebec. Therefore, 
               <lb/>
               in virtue of that act, the governor of New<lb break="no"/>foundland lost his jurisdiction over all the 
               <lb/>
               territories included in the Labrador peninsula. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Later on, in 1809, the Newfoundland Act 
               <lb/>
               was passed by the British government, and 
               <lb/>
               then all the territories that were given to 
               <lb/>
               the government of Newfoundland in 1763 
               <lb/>
               were restored to the same government. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Finally, in 1825, by an act called. “The 
               <lb/>
               British North America Act of 1825”, it was 
               <lb/>
               decided that the part of the coast of the gulf 
               <lb/>
               of St. Lawrence from river St. John to Anse 
               <lb/>
               Sablon in Belle-Isle strait would form part 
               <lb/>
               of the province of Quebec. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               One may observe that in each of these acts 
               <lb/>
               we ﬁnd no mention of the inland territories; 
               <lb/>
               they all deal with the coast itself. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We now come to 1871, when the British 
               <lb/>
               North America Act of 1871 was passed by the 
               <lb/>
               British government. We ﬁnd it in chapter 
               <lb/>
               28, 34 Victoria, and it is entitled, “An act 
               <lb/>
               respecting the establishment of provinces in 
               <lb/>
               the Dominion of Canada”. Section 3 of that 
               <lb/>
               act enacts: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               The parliament of Canada may from time to 
               <lb/>
               time, with the consent of the legislature of any 
               <lb/>
               province of the said dominion, increase, dimin<lb break="no"/>ish, or otherwise alter the limits of such prov<lb break="no"/>ince, upon such terms and conditions as may be 
               <lb/>
               agreed to by the said legislature, and may, with 
               <lb/>
               the like consent, make provision respecting the 
               <lb/>
               effect and operation of any such increase or 
               <lb/>
               diminution or alteration of territory in rela<lb break="no"/>tion to any province affected thereby. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               I should like here to draw the attention of 
               <lb/>
               the government to the principle clearly 
               <lb/>
               established by that statute, to the effect that 
               <lb/>
               the parliament of Canada cannot do anything 
               <lb/>
               regarding the boundaries of a province with<lb break="no"/>out ﬁrst obtaining the consent of the province 
               <lb/>
               concerned. The government of today should 
               <lb/>
         
            <pb n="942" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0942.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">942</fw>
           <fw type="running">
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Address—Mr. Dorion</hi> 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
            
            
               take note that in virtue of that statute there 
               <lb/>
               are provincial governments and that in many 
               <lb/>
               matters these provincial governments must 
               <lb/>
               have their say before the parliament of 
               <lb/>
               Canada takes any decision. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               In virtue of that same principle, the state<lb break="no"/>ment I read a few minutes ago, made by the 
               <lb/>
               Prime Minister in connection with the pro<lb break="no"/>posed arrangements concerning the territory 
               <lb/>
               of Labrador, should not have been made 
               <lb/>
               without the consent of the province of Quebec. 
               <lb/>
               Furthermore, the same principle is in accord<lb break="no"/>ance with the British North America Act of 
               <lb/>
               1867, section 92, paragraph 5. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Not only do we ﬁnd the enactment I have 
               <lb/>
               just mentioned in the British North America 
               <lb/>
               Act of 1871, but we see that in 1898 this prin<lb break="no"/>ciple, regarding the consent of the province 
               <lb/>
               concerned in all matters pertaining to the 
               <lb/>
               alteration of its boundaries, was applied when 
               <lb/>
               an act respecting the northwestern, northern, 
               <lb/>
               and northeastern boundaries of the province 
               <lb/>
               of Quebec was passed by chapter 3 of 61 
               <lb/>
               Victoria, statutes of Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               A similar act was passed by the Quebec 
               <lb/>
               legislature in the same year 1898, and there<lb break="no"/>fore, in accordance with the principle enacted 
               <lb/>
               in the British North America Act of 1871, 
               <lb/>
               the Canadian government, with the consent 
               <lb/>
               of the Quebec legislature, decided that the 
               <lb/>
               boundaries of the province of Quebec should 
               <lb/>
               be extended to James bay, and then to the 
               <lb/>
               east Main river and further to the Hamilton 
               <lb/>
               river, as far as Hamilton inlet, on the Atlantic 
               <lb/>
               coast. By this statute, the northern bound<lb break="no"/>aries of the province of Quebec were limited 
               <lb/>
               to the Hamilton river, which, as everyone 
               <lb/>
               is aware, is within the territory known as 
               <lb/>
               Labrador. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               In the year 1912, by chapter 45 of 2 George 
               <lb/>
               V, the parliament of Canada decided to extend 
               <lb/>
               once more the territory of the province of 
               <lb/>
               Quebec together with the territories of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba and Ontario. By section 2 of chapter 
               <lb/>
               45 it was enacted that the new boundaries of 
               <lb/>
               the province of Quebec would include what 
               <lb/>
               was called at the time Ungava territory; and 
               <lb/>
               it was clearly established that the new 
               <lb/>
               boundaries would include the territory north 
               <lb/>
               of Hamilton river, that is to say all the 
               <lb/>
               Labrador territory. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            <p>
               As we have just seen, the two Canadian 
               <lb/>
               statutes giving expressly to the province of 
               <lb/>
               Quebec the territory claimed by Newfound<lb break="no"/>land were passed in 1898 and 1912, that is to 
               <lb/>
               say, at a time when the imperial government 
               <lb/>
               had the right to disallow any act passed by 
               <lb/>

               the Canadian government. Therefore, these 
               <lb/>
               two statutes, having never been disallowed, 
               <lb/>
               must have their full force and value. It has 
               <lb/>
               been contended that they were ultra vires, 
               <lb/>
               
          <cb/>

               but if such had been the case, why is it that 
               <lb/>
               the government of Newfoundland did not 
               <lb/>
               ask the British government to disallow them? 
               <lb/>
               We must therefore conclude that they were 
               <lb/>
               tacitly conﬁrmed by the British government 
               <lb/>
               and tacitly accepted by the Newfoundland 
               <lb/>
               government. That is the reason why I said 
               <lb/>
               at the outset that the territory known as 
               <lb/>
               Labrador peninsula belongs to the province 
               <lb/>
               of Quebec. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               In 1920, after discussions had been started 
               <lb/>
               between the government of Newfoundland and 
               <lb/>
               the government of the province of Quebec 
               <lb/>
               regarding the issue by the government of 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland of a licence for cutting timber 
               <lb/>
               in the neighbourhood of Hamilton river, the 
               <lb/>
               Canadian government decided to refer to the 
               <lb/>
               privy council the question of the boundaries 
               <lb/>
               between Quebec and Newfoundland. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               A ﬁrst memorandum of agreement between 
               <lb/>
               Canada and Newfoundland was signed on 
               <lb/>
               November 11, 1920, but it was later amended 
               <lb/>
               and replaced by a new agreement dated 
               <lb/>
               November 20, 1922. We must notice here that 
               <lb/>
               by this agreement the two political parties 
               <lb/>
               which existed at the time—the Conservative 
               <lb/>
               and Liberal parties—did not hesitate to violate, 
               <lb/>
               one after the other, the principle enacted in 
               <lb/>
               the British North America Act of 1871. Every<lb break="no"/>one is aware that in 1920 we had a Conserva<lb break="no"/>tive government here in Ottawa, and that in 
               <lb/>
               1922 we had a Liberal government. In fact 
               <lb/>
               on behalf of the Canadian government the 
               <lb/>
               ﬁrst agreement was signed in 1920 by Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Charles J. Doherty, and the second one in 
               <lb/>
               1922, on behalf of the same government, was 
               <lb/>
               signed by Sir Lomer Gouin. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It is worth reading the main part of that 
               <lb/>
               agreement, which is as follows: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
              <p> In the matter of the boundary between the 
               <lb/>
               dominion of Canada and the colony of New<lb break="no"/>foundland in the Labrador peninsula: 
               <lb/></p>
             
            <p>
               The government of the dominion of Canada 
               <lb/>
               and the government of the colony of Newfound<lb break="no"/>land having mutually agreed to submit for refer<lb break="no"/>ence by His Majesty to the judicial committee 
               <lb/>
               of His Majesty’s Privy Council, for their deci<lb break="no"/>sion, the following question, viz.: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               “What is the location and definition of the 
               <lb/>
               boundary as between Canada and Newfound<lb break="no"/>land in the Labrador  peninsula under the 
               <lb/>
               statutes, orders in council and proclamations?" 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            </quote>
         
            
            <p>
               And it is signed by the Attorney General of 
               <lb/>
               Canada and the Attorney General of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               However, we must take note that the real 
               <lb/>
               dispute was not between the Canadian gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and the Newfoundland government, 
               <lb/>
               but between the latter and the government of 
               <lb/>
               the province of Quebec. How is it that the 
               <lb/>
               province of Quebec was not a party to the 
               <lb/>
               reference made to the privy council? We see 
               <lb/>
               that the proceedings for the Canadian gov<lb break="no"/><pb n="943" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0943.jpg"/><fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 6, 1948 </fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Address—Mr. Dorian</hi></fw>  <fw type="num">943<lb/></fw>ernment were signed by four attorneys general, 
               <lb/>
               one of them being Charles Lanctot, then 
               <lb/>
               attorney general of the province of Quebec; 
               <lb/>
               but ofﬁcially and legally the province of 
               <lb/>
               Quebec was out of the case. The least that 
               <lb/>
               could have been done would be for the 
               <lb/>
               Canadian government to submit the proposed 
               <lb/>
               agreement to the Quebec legislature in accord<lb break="no"/>ance with the British North America Act of 
               <lb/>
               1871, and obtain the consent of that legislature. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            
            <p>
               I must add that in signing such an agree<lb break="no"/>ment in 1922 the Liberal government dis<lb break="no"/>carded an engagement that had been taken in 
               <lb/>
               1908 by their leader, the then prime minister, 
               <lb/>
               Sir Wilfrid Laurier. In fact, on July 13, 1908, 
               <lb/>
               in introducing in this house a motion for the 
               <lb/>
               bill that was passed in 1912 regarding the 
               <lb/>
               extension of boundaries of Manitoba, Ontario 
               <lb/>
               and Quebec, we find, at column 12,789 of the 
               <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Hansard</hi> of that year, a statement made by 
               <lb/>
               Sir Wilfrid Laurier. Speaking of the dispute 
               <lb/>
               which had arisen between Newfoundland and 
               <lb/>
               Quebec, he said: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               We have taken the precaution to ask the prov<lb break="no"/>ince of Quebec to be a party to that arbitration 
               <lb/>
               because it is interested in the boundary where- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               ever it may ultimately be decided to be. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               And further on he says: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               In 1881, when the act was passed extending 
               <lb/>
               the boundary of Manitoba to the frontier of 
               <lb/>
               Ontario, the contest was removed from Canada 
               <lb/>
               to Ontario and Manitoba; they were the parties 
               <lb/>
               who fought the issue. In the same way, if we 
               <lb/>
               allow this territory to go to Quebec, Quebec 
               <lb/>
               will become interested in the question; then, 
               <lb/>
               though we retain. our sovereignty, I think they 
               <lb/>
               should have a say and become a party to the 
               <lb/>
               question.  
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               Notwithstanding that engagement, as I said 
               <lb/>
               a few minutes ago, when the second agreement 
               <lb/>
               was signed in 1922 by the Liberal government 
               <lb/>
               it does not appear anywhere that it had been 
               <lb/>
               signed with the consent of the Quebec legis<lb break="no"/>lature. And today the present government goes 
               <lb/>
               much further in putting aside the directions 
               <lb/>
               given by its ex-leader, and does not hesitate 
               <lb/>
               to dispose ﬁnally of the same territory without 
               <lb/>
               consulting the province of Quebec. That is the 
               <lb/>
               reason why I contend that this offer by the 
               <lb/>
               Canadian government to the government of 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland is not worth the paper on which 
               <lb/>
               it is written, and I am sure that the province 
               <lb/>
               of Quebec will never assent to such an agree<lb break="no"/>ment. That is also why the present govern<lb break="no"/>ment should refrain from offering to New<lb break="no"/>foundland a territory over which it has no 
               <lb/>
               jurisdiction, so as to prevent a regrettable mis<lb break="no"/>understanding which would result in a real 
               <lb/>
               conﬂict between the Canadian government and 
               <lb/>
               one of the provinces.  
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            <p>
               Let us now make an analysis of the value 
               <lb/>
               of the report of the privy council and see if 
               <lb/>
               
           <cb/>

               we can ﬁnd in it some ﬁnal solution to the 
               <lb/>
               problem. It is interesting to note in the read<lb break="no"/>ing of the report itself that Their Lordships 
               <lb/>
               clearly show that the question submitted to 
               <lb/>
               them was not properly and completely pre<lb break="no"/>sented. If we refer to page 2 of their report 
               <lb/>
               we read: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               But the duty of the board is not to consider 
               <lb/>
               where the boundary in question might wisely 
               <lb/>
               and conveniently be drawn, but only to deter<lb break="no"/>mine where, under the documents of title which 
               <lb/>
               have been brought to their notice, that boun<lb break="no"/>dary is actually to be found. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               Further at page 11 of the same report, the 
               <lb/>
               Lord Chancellor states: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               In these circumstances the question to be 
               <lb/>
               determined is not whether Newfoundland pos<lb break="no"/>sesses territory upon the peninsula of Labrador, 
               <lb/>
               but rwhat is the inland boundary of that terri<lb break="no"/>tory. Is it to be defined by a line following 
               <lb/>
               the sinuosities of the shore at -a distance of one 
               <lb/>
               mile or thereabouts from high-water mark, or 
               <lb/>
               is it to be found at the watershed of the rivers 
               <lb/>
               falling into the sea on. that shore? No third 
               <lb/>
               alternative has been suggested by any person. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               And at page 14: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               The case for Canada admits that it may be 
               <lb/>
               found impracticable to lay down such a line 
               <lb/>
               upon the land, and suggests that, in order that 
               <lb/>
               neither party may suffer by reason of this 
               <lb/>
               difficulty, the boundary should be drawn along 
               <lb/>
               the coast at a distance of one mile from high- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               water mark; but Their Lordships cannot think 
               <lb/>
               that in- adopting such a proposal they would be 
               <lb/>
               performing the duty cast upon them by the 
               <lb/>
               terms of reference to determine the boundary 
               <lb/>
               ”under the statutes, orders in council and 
               <lb/>
               proclamations.” 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               Then we come to the conclusion of the report, 
               <lb/>
               which we ﬁnd at page 23, the last words of 
               <lb/>
               which are: “and they will humbly advise His 
               <lb/>
               Majesty accordingly.” Therefore that report 
               <lb/>
               shows not only that the question was not 
               <lb/>
               properly submitted to the privy council, but 
               <lb/>
               that there was no binding decision rendered. 
               <lb/>
               In fact we must ask ourselves what was done 
               <lb/>
               after and as a consequence of that report. Was 
               <lb/>
               there any legislation by the Imperial, the 
               <lb/>
               Canadian or the Newfoundland government? 
               <lb/>
               There was none. Was there any treaty or any 
               <lb/>
               agreement embodying the ﬁndings of the privy 
               <lb/>
               council? There was none either. Then I be<lb break="no"/>lieve I am right in contending that the Whole 
               <lb/>
               matter still stands as it was decided by the 
               <lb/>
               Canadian statutes of 1898 and 1912. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p> 
               Furthermore I contend that this matter 
               <lb/>
               should never have been submitted to the privy 
               <lb/>
               council because it was a tribunal of one of the 
               <lb/>
               parties. I must however emphatically declare 
               <lb/>
               that I would not for a moment cast any re<lb break="no"/>ﬂection on the integrity and honesty of the 
               <lb/>
               members of the privy council; but as a matter 
               <lb/>
               of fact I do not think we ever saw in the history 
               <lb/>
               of the world a case of delimitation of 
               <lb/>
               boundaries being submitted to the tribunal of 
               <lb/>
               
        
            
            <pb n="944" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-02-06_Page_0944.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">
               944</fw>
               
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Address—Mr. Hazen</hi> 
                 </fw>
            
         
            
            <fw type="running">
               COMMONS 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
         
    
               one of the interested parties. My contention 
               <lb/>
               is that the question should have been sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to an international arbitration in which 
               <lb/>
               all the parties, and especially the province of 
               <lb/>
               Quebec, was represented. There is no doubt 
               <lb/>
               that the whole matter is still wide open, and 
               <lb/>
               I hope that someone will ﬁnd some way of 
               <lb/>
               arriving at a ﬁnal settlement of the question. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. D. K. HAZEN (Saint John-Albert) : Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Speaker, this debate affords me an oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity for which I have waited some time, 
               <lb/>
               to bring to the attention of the house a mat<lb break="no"/>ter which concerns the maritime provinces. 
               <lb/>
               I refer to the shipping of Canadian goods 
               <lb/>
               through Canadian ports. I believe I would be 
               <lb/>
               remiss in my duty as the representative in 
               <lb/>
               this house of the seaport of Saint John if I 
               <lb/>
               did not say something about that matter at 
               <lb/>
               this time, as certain acts of the Canadian gov<lb break="no"/>ernment railways in recent months have been 
               <lb/>
               detrimental to the development of Canadian 
               <lb/>
               trade through Canadian ports and the cause 
               <lb/>
               of deep resentment in the maritimes. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               To give the story from the beginning I want 
               <lb/>
               to refer to an Associated Press dispatch from 
               <lb/>
               Portland, Maine, dated July 23 last, which 
               <lb/>
               quoted Mr. R. C. Vaughan, president of the 
               <lb/>
               Canadian National Railways, as saying in an 
               <lb/>
               interview that the C.N.R. has “a big stake” 
               <lb/>
               in Portland, and that “we’re going to do every<lb break="no"/>thing we can for the port of Portland." 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               This statement did not pass unnoticed in the 
               <lb/>
               maritime provinces. It was regarded there as a 
               <lb/>
               reversal of government policy and a betrayal 
               <lb/>
               of maritime workers and maritime interests. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Canadian ports of Saint John and Hali<lb break="no"/>fax, which are washed by the waters of the 
               <lb/>
               Atlantic ocean, and are open both summer and 
               <lb/>
               winter, look to the ofﬁcials of the Canadian 
               <lb/>
               government railways to use their utmost 
               <lb/>
               endeavours to promote the use of those ports 
               <lb/>
               in the national interest and in furtherance of 
               <lb/>
               government policy, or what has been govern<lb break="no"/>ment policy in the past. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The workers of the ports of Saint John and 
               <lb/>
               Halifax, who rendered great service during the 
               <lb/>
               war years and who are harassed now by a 
               <lb/>
               steadily increasing cost of living, look to the 
               <lb/>
               Canadian National Railways to provide them, 
               <lb/>
               as far as it is possible, with continuous 
               <lb/>
               employment. They know that everything the 
               <lb/>
               C.N.R. does for the port of Portland is done 
               <lb/>
               at their expense, and that the trade sent 
               <lb/>
               through Portland takes dollars from their 
               <lb/>
               pockets. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               In an editorial on July 25 last the Saint John 
               <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Telegraph-Journal</hi> said that Mr. Vaughan’s 
               <lb/>
               
    statement<lb/>—</p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
-is a clear threat to Saint John and Halifax, 
               <lb/>
               for whatever is done for Portland by the nation<lb break="no"/>ally-owned railway system will be done at our 
               <lb/>
               expense. 
               <lb/></quote>
               
         <cb/>
            
            <p>
               Continuing, the editorial said Mr. Vaughan’s 
               <lb/>
               statement was-<lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">——an open admission that the objective of the 
               <lb/>
               C.N.R. was to build up ports of the United 
               <lb/>
               States, even though it means destroying the 
               <lb/>
               business of the national ports of Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The press of Halifax was also quite out<lb break="no"/>spoken in condemning Mr. Vaughan’s alleged 
               <lb/>
               remarks. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               On July 25 of last year Mr. J. D. McKenna, 
               <lb/>
               mayor of the city of Saint John, wired the 
               <lb/>
               Minister of Transport (Mr. Chevrier) protest<lb break="no"/>ing Mr. Vaughan’s alleged statement. After 
               <lb/>
               quoting it he said: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               I hesitate to believe that Mr. Vaughan was 
               <lb/>
               guilty of any such indiscretion—If Mr. Vaughan 
               <lb/>
               made the remark credited to him I think be 
               <lb/>
               displayed bad judgment, and I am quite sure 
               <lb/>
               he cannot be voicing your views or those of the 
               <lb/>
               government. To suggest that the money of 
               <lb/>
               the people of Canada be used to develop Port<lb break="no"/>land, at a time when Saint John and Halifax 
               <lb/>
               are in dire need of additional port tonnage, is 
               <lb/>
               suggesting a policy which, it was generally 
               <lb/>
               understood, ended in Canada over twenty years 
               <lb/>
               ago.  I know that no member of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment is more interested than you in maintaining 
               <lb/>
               the earnings of Canadian ports. Just how 
               <lb/>
               this can be done by sending this business to 
               <lb/>
               United States ports is beyond my comprehen<lb break="no"/>sion, and the understanding of any real Cana<lb break="no"/>dian. If Mr. Vaughan made the suggestion, I 
               <lb/>
               think that some announcement should be made 
               <lb/>
               at once to assure Canadian ports that their 
               <lb/>
               interests will be safeguarded and at the same 
               <lb/>
               time disillusion the people of Portland as to 
               <lb/>
               any such promise. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
         
            
            <p>
               In reply to the mayor's telegram the 
               <lb/>
               minister wired as follows: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               I have your telegram referring to statement 
               <lb/>
               alleged to have been made by R. C. Vaughan, 
               <lb/>
               president of Canadian National Railways, which 
               <lb/>
               I have not seen. Please let me assure you 
               <lb/>
               that statements of policy always emanate from 
               <lb/>
               the government or one of its ministers. The 
               <lb/>
               policy of the government is to encourage and 
               <lb/>
               assist its national ports to the fullest extent, 
               <lb/>
               further, to use the facilities of our national 
               <lb/>
               ports to the maximum and to increase those 
               <lb/>
               facilities when required. In evidence of this 
               <lb/>
               the government has spent from 1936 to 1946, 
               <lb/>
               for capital and reconstruction of our national 
               <lb/>
               ports, approximately $18,000,000. This year’s 
               <lb/>
               estimate for the port of Saint John contains 
               <lb/>
               initial appropriations which will mean eventual 
               <lb/>
               expenditure within a year or two of approxi<lb break="no"/>mately $3,000,000. National harbours board 
               <lb/>
               informs me surveys are under way for further 
               <lb/>
               expansion. All of which is an indication that 
               <lb/>
               government has very much in mind the develop<lb break="no"/>ment and expansion of facilities at the port of 
               <lb/>
               Saint John. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The mayor of Saint John replied to this 
               <lb/>
               wire as follows: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               Thanks for your telegram of the 26th instant. 
               <lb/>
               Interpret it to mean ﬁrst that even if Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Vaughan made the alleged statement it carries 
               <lb/>
               no weight; second, that your answer is a deﬁ<lb break="no"/>nite contradiction that Portland will be devel<lb break="no"/>oped and it is also an assurance that Canadian 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>