<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1867-11-14"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1867-11-14">14 November 1867</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, First Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1967"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Roger Duhamel</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="75"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-14_Page_074.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-14_Page_075.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-21">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-14_Page_074">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-14_Page_074.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-14_Page_075">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-14_Page_075.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="74" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-14_Page_074.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">74</fw>

            <p> lar declaratory
clauses are found in the <lb/>
Quebec Act, and the Union Act of 1840, they <lb/>
were both statutes framed in England exclu<lb break="no"/>sively, while the clauses, and all the remain<lb break="no"/>der, were drafted and proposed by Colonists <lb/>
only. It is remarkable that a hundred years <lb/>
after the Stamp Act and Tea Tax; ninety <lb/>
years after the Declaration of Independence; <lb/>
nearly half a century after the promulgation <lb/>
of “the Monroe Doctrine”; the representatives <lb/>
of these Provinces should have taken upon <lb/>
themselves, so solemnly to re-assert as fun<lb break="no"/>damental constitutional propositions, the <lb/>
sovereignty of the English Crown, over all <lb/>
our territory. (Applause.) What was done in <lb/>
this way in 1840, and in 1799, was done by <lb/>
others; but these declaratory clauses are our <lb/>
own work. I do not say that we are free to <lb/>
take any other course; I do not pretend that <lb/>
we could have raised, even if we would, the <lb/>
question of Sovereignty, in 1864 or in 1867; I <lb/>
only speak of the cardinal fact as I ﬁnd it, <lb/>
that we have here, by our own act, selected <lb/>
the monarchical form of Government for our<lb break="no"/>selves and for our children; that for them <lb/>
and for ourselves, we have entered into this <lb/>
solemn compart to uphold the constitutional <lb/>
monarchy in this country; and that the <lb/>
Queen, and her Imperial Parliament and <lb/>
Government, have, on their part, by the pas<lb break="no"/>sage of this Bill with these provisions, with <lb/>
equal solemnity, constituted themselves par<lb break="no"/>ties to this compact and agreement. (Hear, <lb/>
hear.) I do not desire, sir, to dwell at present, <lb/>
on all the corrollaries and consequences likely <lb/>
to ﬂow from this formal and solemn estab<lb break="no"/>lishment of monarchy on this Continent, by <lb/>
the voluntary act of four millions of its <lb/>
inhabitants, but this is the path which by this <lb/>
Act, we have voluntarily chosen to enter—by <lb/>
this path, if we are not to abandon it, we are <lb/>
to journey on into the future, and whither it <lb/>
leads there we must follow. Sir, for one, I can <lb/>
truly say, that I saw and felt all along the <lb/>
solemnity of the selection we were called <lb/>
upon to make, but I never doubted, no not <lb/>
for one instant, that we had decided well in <lb/>
choosing to afﬁrm so unmistakably as we <lb/>
have done the principles of Constitutional <lb/>
and responsible monarchy, for these Prov<lb break="no"/>inces. I am fully aware of the intense propa<lb break="no"/>gandist force which resides in the democratic <lb/>
idea. I know there are democratic fanatics <lb/>
who damn all other sects in politics, but their <lb/>
own; but looking back to the venerable cen<lb break="no"/>turies of Christian civilization which have <lb/>
preceded us, I am not taught, that it is best <lb/>
for the people, that the headship of the State <lb/>
should be frequently elective. Our Republican<lb/>
                      <cb/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES <lb/>
            </fw>
 
            <fw type="dateline"> November 14, 1867 <lb/>
            </fw>

 neighbours may prefer their own
institutions <lb/>
as much as pleases them; but at all events, <lb/>
they must allow us to have a preference also, <lb/>
even though it should not quite coincide with <lb/>
their own. (Hear, hear.) We can honour and <lb/>
reverence their illustrious Martyr President, <lb/>
who fell a victim to his duties; but they must <lb/>
permit us also, to reserve some of our admi<lb break="no"/>ration and sympathy, for the Martyr of <lb/>
Queretaro, as well as the Martyr of Mexico: <lb/>
for that gallant gentleman, a true Prince, the <lb/>
worthiest to rule that Mexico had ever seen, <lb/>
but of whom Mexico was not worthy: that <lb/>
cruelly murdered Prince, whose efﬁgy the <lb/>
House of Hapsburg may be proud to raise in <lb/>
long procession of the Illustrious Princes, his <lb/>
ancestors! Sir, I certainly cannot agree with <lb/>
the honourable member (Mr. Howe) that the <lb/>
time or the means chosen, ought to subject us <lb/>
to the displeasure of our Republican neigh<lb break="no"/>bours. This Union project is a very old <lb/>
one—as old as the country, and though has<lb break="no"/>tened by recent events among them and <lb/>
among ourselves, it certainly dates long <lb/>
beyond the ﬁring by Beauregard on Fort <lb/>
Sumter. No question of Sovereignty was <lb/>
raised by us; we merely embodied and re<lb break="no"/>affirmed a power that already
existed, and <lb/>
which the Republic always recognized as ex<lb break="no"/>isting in North America. If we had sought to <lb/>
plant a despotism by their side—without rep<lb break="no"/>resentative institutions—without securing <lb/>
the common rights of free men, sprung from <lb/>
the same source as their own; then, indeed, <lb/>
they might have cause for suspicion and <lb/>
displeasure. As it is I deny that we have <lb/>
given them any such cause, and I submit that <lb/>
such an argument, or assertion ought not to be <lb/>
advanced on the ﬂoor of a Canadian Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. (Hear, hear.) The honourable member <lb/>
opposite (Mr. Howe) also bestowed a good <lb/>
deal of his ready ridicule on the expression so <lb/>
often used in His Excellency’s Speech—of “a <lb/>
new nationality.” He was not precise in stat<lb break="no"/>ing his objections to the use of that expres<lb break="no"/>sion; but I inferred that he thought it prema<lb break="no"/>ture as to time, and inconsistent with the <lb/>
continuance of the Imperial connection. He <lb/>
talked of walking upon stilts, and having “the <lb/>
stilts knocked from under us,” as if our <lb/>
increased stature as a people in 1867, was a <lb/>
forced and artiﬁcial increase. I need not surely <lb/>
remind the honourable member, that in the <lb/>
year 1800 including Newfoundland and Prince <lb/>
Edward Island, with the British mainland <lb/>
we were less than 400,000 souls altogether; <lb/>
and when the Sydenham Union was carried, <lb/>
about two millions, While we are now, includ<lb break="no"/>ing the same Provinces, fully 4,000,000. (Hear, <lb/>
            
            <pb n="75" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-14_Page_075.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
               November 14, 1867 
               <lb/>  
            </fw>
      
               hear.) These living millions are stilts, and we 
               <lb/>
               are vain enough to think we can stand on 
               <lb/>
               them. In 1790, the United States commenced 
               <lb/>
               with a total population of 3,900,000 souls, but 
               <lb/>
               they had, it is true, no gigantic native neigh<lb break="no"/>bours on their ﬂanks; still they had the 
               <lb/>
               power of England on this side, of Spain in the 
               <lb/>
               Floridas, and of France in Louisiana. They 
               <lb/>
               began modestly and moderately, and they 
               <lb/>
               have advanced by degrees, in their “new 
               <lb/>
               nationality”. I ask the honourable gentleman 
               <lb/>
               this question—if he does not look forward to 
               <lb/>
               a new nationality here, in these Provinces, to 
               <lb/>
               what does he look forward? Surely he must 
               <lb/>
               see that a population which increased in sixty 
               <lb/>
               years, a hundred fold, cannot be reckoned 
               <lb/>
               upon as a stationary quantity? With some 
               <lb/>
               nations the best ambition is to keep what 
               <lb/>
               they have got; but these are nations of ﬁxed 
               <lb/>
               population and full boundaries. Extending as 
               <lb/>
               we are in space—increasing in num<lb break="no"/>ber—improving in intercourse—we cannot 
               <lb/>
               stand still politically, even if we tried. (Hear, 
               <lb/>
               hear.) But the honourable member and his 
               <lb/>
               followers seem to have some confused notion 
               <lb/>
               in their heads, that a new nation cannot exist 
               <lb/>
               within the Empire, consistently with the 
               <lb/>
               Imperial connection. Sir, I don’t know where 
               <lb/>
               they got such a notion, but it is a very 
               <lb/>
               childish one, and contrary to all experience. 
               <lb/>
               The Federal principle is precisely adopted to 
               <lb/>
               meet a difﬁculty of that kind, and has for 
               <lb/>
               many centuries met it successfully. In the 
               <lb/>
               German Empire there never was any difﬁcul<lb break="no"/>ty as to the simple existence of separate 
               <lb/>
               nationalities and kingdoms; in the Spanish 
               <lb/>
               Empire, so long as its sovereigns respected 
               <lb/>
               the rights and liberties of the component 
               <lb/>
               parts, there was no difﬁculty of holding 
               <lb/>
               together the kingdoms of the Netherlands, of 
               <lb/>
               Aragon, and Naples; in the Austrian Empire, 
               <lb/>
               when the rights of the ancient kingdom of 
               <lb/>
               Hungary were respected the kingdom was in 
               <lb/>
               fact, the mainstay of the Empire. In our own 
               <lb/>
               day, we have in Hindostan an Empire within 
               <lb/>
               an Empire, so constituted expressly on the 
               <lb/>
               ground of strengthening the Imperial connec<lb break="no"/>tion by the wisest statesmen, our contem<lb break="no"/>poraries. So far, therefore, as to that childish 
               <lb/>
               and foolish notion of incompatibility. But the 
               <lb/>
               honourable member will not allow, that even 
               <lb/>
               With our four millions, we have men enough 
               <lb/>
               to start in the onerous career of a new 
               <lb/>
               nationality. What amount of population does 
               <lb/>
               he suppose then to be necessary to such a 
               <lb/>
               start? For colonies, as colonies, to get togeth<lb break="no"/>er and keep together, four millions of inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants is no small achievement, and if we have 
               <lb/>
               not increased more largely by immigration of 
               <lb/>
               <cb/>
     
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">75</fw>
            
      
               late years than we have—if our present 
               <lb/>
               population is 80 per cent native born to 20 
               <lb/>
               per cent born abroad—I will tell the honour<lb break="no"/>able member why we have not attracted and 
               <lb/>
               retained more people, from the other side of 
               <lb/>
               the Atlantic. We have not attracted more 
               <lb/>
               people, because we have not made our coun<lb break="no"/>try attractive; because we are not known as a 
               <lb/>
               nation abroad; because these isolated Prov<lb break="no"/>inces did not impress the imagination of the 
               <lb/>
               emigrating classes. Who in the byeways of 
               <lb/>
               Germany, or even of Britain, knew anything 
               <lb/>
               of Canada, up to the other day? In those 
               <lb/>
               hives of human labour, they knew only one 
               <lb/>
               country—America—and One seaport—New 
               <lb/>
               York. But once give your Provinces united 
               <lb/>
               the aspect of Empire, make them a power 
               <lb/>
               and a name, and the reputation and credit of 
               <lb/>
               the Dominion will be our best immigration 
               <lb/>
               agents abroad. (Hear, hear.) As to our inabili<lb break="no"/>ty to stand alone, with the numbers we have, 
               <lb/>
               I beg to observe, sir, that in my opinion, it 
               <lb/>
               depends very much on our unanimity or 
               <lb/>
               division. No power on earth can take forci<lb break="no"/>ble possession of this country, if we are united 
               <lb/>
               as one man, in its defence. (Applause.) No 
               <lb/>
               population that can be stirred up against us, 
               <lb/>
               can put a hostile four millions, face to face 
               <lb/>
               with us on our own soil. If every man, 
               <lb/>
               woman and child in Canada, is imbued with 
               <lb/>
               the spirit which enabled Switzerland to hold 
               <lb/>
               her own against the Austrian Empire, and 
               <lb/>
               Spain in her decline to cast out Napoleon in 
               <lb/>
               his vigour, we will be safe enough, within our 
               <lb/>
               rivers and rapids in summer, and our snowed 
               <lb/>
               up roads and freezing skies in winter. (Hear, 
               <lb/>
               hear.) We complain sometimes of our rigorous 
               <lb/>
               winters, but there is this compensation at 
               <lb/>
               least, that no invading force that bivouacked 
               <lb/>
               out for one genuine Canadian night, would 
               <lb/>
               ever answer to the call of the long roll again. 
               <lb/>
               (Hear, hear.) My own views on the subject of 
               <lb/>
               defence are pretty well known, and when my 
               <lb/>
               honourable friend (Mr. Cartier) brings down 
               <lb/>
               his measure, if the House desires to hear 
               <lb/>
               them, I shall be happy to meet its wishes: but 
               <lb/>
               I will now only say this, that I hope to see 
               <lb/>
               the military spirit of our population en<lb break="no"/>couraged in every way; that I hope to see 
               <lb/>
               riﬂe matches and tournaments become as 
               <lb/>
               familiar municipal institutions as town meet<lb break="no"/>ings, of county agricultural fairs. (Applause.) 
               <lb/>
               I cannot, for one, agree that the best way to 
               <lb/>
               make ourselves respected abroad, to secure 
               <lb/>
               impunity from attack, is to depreciate the 
               <lb/>
               sources of our strength; but rather to rely 
               <lb/>
               upon and make the most of what Lord Bacon, 
               <lb/>
               in his “true greatness of Britain,” considers a 
               <lb/>
               main element of a nation’s strength, “its 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>