<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1870-02-18" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-02-18">18 February 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
   
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="62"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0061.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0062.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0061">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0061.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0062">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0062.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="61" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0061.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               18 février 1870 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said that the first thing <lb/> required of a man
               when he changed from the <lb/> Liberal side of the Government side was, to <lb/>
               abuse the Globe newspaper, (laughter). It was <lb/> satisfactory to find so old a
               member, so willing <lb/> to come into the traces of the first Minister of <lb/> the
               Crown, and abuse the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi>. It was a well <lb/>
               known fact that thirty-two or thirty-three Lib<lb break="no"/>eral members had been
               brought to the House, <lb/> and, in defiance of this gross accusation, he <lb/> could
               say that they had not given factious <lb/> opposition, but had at all times preferred
               to <lb/> meet the Government in an open, manly way. <lb/> He would now ask the reason
               why the Union <lb/> cause had not in the slightest degree advanced. <lb/> It was
               simply because this combination, this <lb/> coalition was formed, not to advance the
               Union <lb/> cause, but to advance a political party to a <lb/> position which they
               might occupy, we were <lb/> told, for years to come by the influence of the <lb/>
               expenditure for the construction of the Inter- <lb break="yes"/> colonial Railway. He
               would venture to say that <lb/> if the Liberal party had been in power from <lb/>
               that time to the present, there would have been <lb/> at this moment a completed
               Confederation of <lb/> all the Provinces of British North America. But <lb/> after
               this Parliament had provided the most <lb/> liberal terms for Newfoundland and Prince
               <lb/> Edward Island they had been rejected, and <lb/> other Provinces would not join
               the Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion; and he held that it was because the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of Canada was distrusted, that the <lb/> people of the East
               and West, and North and <lb/> South declined to have any political associa<lb break="no"/>tion with them (hear, hear). He would now <lb/> proceed to discuss the
               measures which the <lb/> Government saw fit to take, in order, apparent<lb break="no"/>ly, to secure the results they promised long ago. <lb/> He recollected that during
               the elections he had <lb/> been told that if the Government secured a <lb/> majority
               in Parliament there could not be a <lb/> doubt the union of the Provinces—union with
               <lb/> the Maritime Provinces, would be a certainty, <lb/> and union with Newfoundland
               and Prince <lb/> Edward Island would be a matter not of years <lb/> or months, but of
               weeks. He had moved for <lb/> correspondence that he expected would show <lb/> the
               state of advancement of this union, but to <lb/> his extreme surprise he was told
               that no corre<lb break="no"/>spondence had taken place (hear, hear). Refer<lb break="no"/>ring to the negotiations for admitting New<lb break="no"/>foundland,
               he (Mr. Mackenzie) contended that <lb/> the Government had taken entirely wrong <lb/>
               ground in offering to assume control of the <lb/> public lands of that island. These
               public lands <lb/> were claimed by the Anti-Confederates at the <lb/> late election
               to be of immense value, and the <lb/> mineral lands to be perhaps the most valuable
               <lb/> upon this Continent, and that the Canadian <lb/> Government would get the
               entire benefit of <lb/> these riches. He maintained that the Federal <lb/> Government
               should have nothing to do with <lb/>
               <pb n="62" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-18_Page_0062.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">62</fw>
               <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
               <fw type="dateline">February 18, 1870<lb/></fw> these lands, and this was the view of
               the people <lb/> of Newfoundland. With regard to the accession <lb/> of the North
               West, he did not intend to enter <lb/> upon a discussion of a personal nature, but he
               <lb/> had heard reports respecting language said to <lb/> have been used by the Hon.
               Secretary of State, <lb/> which he must characterize as unwise in the <lb/> extreme,
               and unworthy of his position as the <lb/> delegate of Canada to that country. These
               <lb/> reported expressions were only in entire <lb/> accordance with his (Mr. Howe's)
               utterances <lb/> in this House, where he had said that the single <lb/> State of
               Minnesota could turn out more men in <lb/> a week than the whole Dominion of Canada,
               to <lb/> take and keep possession of this Country. The <lb/> indulgence of such
               expressions and sentiments <lb/> was not part of wisdom or statesmanship, or <lb/>
               prudence, especially on the part of a minister <lb/> of the Crown. The hon. gentleman
               must have <lb/> known something of the condition of the coun<lb break="no"/>try, and
               of the feelings of the people, but he <lb/> had taken no opportunity of giving any
                  infor<lb break="no"/>mation to Mr. McDougall. He had not <lb/> endeavoured to
               intercept Mr. McDougall, to <lb/> give him information, but had allowed him to <lb/>
               go on to Pembina, where he played such a <lb/> wretched and humiliating part. He had
               seen <lb/> recently the instructions which had been given <lb/> to Mr. McDougall, but
               they were without date, <lb/> and he would like to know when they were <lb/>
               delivered to him. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said Mr. <lb/> McDougall had seen a
               copy of the preliminary <lb/> instructions on the 28th of Sept., before he left <lb/>
               Ottawa, and they had been forwarded to Mr. <lb/> McDougall at Toronto. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> asked Mr. McDougall when <lb/> he received the
               preliminary instructions. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCDO8">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> said he had seen the <lb/> instructions on
               the 28th of Sept., at Ottawa, <lb/> and a copy had reached him at Toronto two <lb/>
               days afterwards. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> thought Mr. McDougall seri<lb break="no"/>ously to
               blame for not proceeding at once to <lb/> discharge the object of his mission
               (laughter). <lb/> He should at least have endeavoured to get <lb/> there before the
               breaking out of the insurrec<lb break="no"/>tion. He blamed Government for not
               carrying <lb/> out the agreement with the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and the
               Hudson's Bay Company, and <lb/> maintained that this conduct gave encourage<lb break="no"/>ment to the adventurers in the Red River Ter<lb break="no"/>ritory,
               who had misled the people, and who <lb/> desired to profit by some new
               arrangements.<lb/>
            </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>