<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1869-05-21" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-05-21">21 May 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1869">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.

         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="432" to="432"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-21_Page_0432.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
         
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
<change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-02-14">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-21_Page_0432">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-21_Page_0432.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="432" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-21_Page_0432.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">432</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">May 21, 1869<lb/></fw>
            
<p>
              [...] ing of the article, as he had just read it. 
               <lb/>
               Besides the Government were not responsible 
               <lb/>
               for any newspaper statement. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
            
            <p>
               The Committee reserved the item $40,000 
               <lb/>
               to meet the possible amount beyond the aver<lb break="no"/>age salaries voted. The items under the head 
               <lb/>
               Administration of Justice, amounting to $52,<lb break="no"/>000, were also carried; as well as the items 
               <lb/>
               under the head of Police $43,440; and under 
               <lb/>
               the head Legislation, as far as "Commission 
               <lb/>
               for making provisions for the uniformity of 
               <lb/>
               the laws of the Provinces, $20,000. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               In explanation of the item, Sir John A. 
               <lb/>
               Macdonald said the sum set apart for the 
               <lb/>
               Assimiliation of the Laws was about the same 
               <lb/>
               as that voted for the Codiﬁcation of the Laws 
               <lb/>
               of the old Province of Canada. It was in<lb break="no"/>tended that the sittings of the Commission 
               <lb/>
               should be as continuous as possible, so that 
               <lb/>
               by next session the laws of the three Provin<lb break="no"/>ces, and possibly also of Newfoundland, 
               <lb/>
               would all be assimilated. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> asked if it was the inten<lb break="no"/>tion of
               the Government to remunerate, in any <lb/> way, any member of the House for this
               <lb/> work? <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> replied that it was <lb/> the intention of
               the Government to do so. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said that the contemplated <lb/> course of the
               Government would be another <lb/> infringment of the Independence of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, and Ministers, if they were wise, would <lb/> never take such a
               step. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said that these re<lb break="no"/>marks
               were not at all called for and should <lb/> not have been received until the House
               had <lb/> something before them in which to take <lb/> action. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> thought the remarks of <lb/> the member for
               Lambton exceedingly per<lb break="no"/>tinent. A case had been made out in the <lb/>
               showing of the Government, such as has been <lb/> always felt to warrant their being
               gravely <lb/> censured. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. Mills</persName> said that however excellent the <lb/> projected code
               of laws might be in itself, and <lb/> however desirable it might be to have a uni<lb break="no"/>form system throughout the Dominion, he <lb/> looked on any attempt in
               the direction in<lb break="no"/>dicated as an effort to change our Union from <lb/> a
               federal to a legislative one. When the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment undertook by a
               commission to secure <lb/> a uniform system of laws respecting property <lb/> and
               civil rights, it was in reality an attempt <lb/> to take away power from the Local
               Legis- [...] <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            
            
           
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>