<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1888-03-09"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1888-03-09">9 March 1888</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

        
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1888"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>MacLean, Roger &amp; Co., Wellington Street </publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="111"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1888-03-09_Page_0111.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
        
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1888-03-09_Page_0111">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1888-03-09_Page_0111.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="111" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1888-03-09_Page_0111.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1888</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw>
            <fw type="num">111</fw>
            
            <p>
               [...]sentatives of the Government of Manitoba who are at 
               <lb/>
               present here, to an interview with him in relation to the 
               <lb/>
               difﬁculties existing between that Province and the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion. Now, as I understand constitutional government, the 
               <lb/>
               business of the country is carried on by the Ministers, who 
               <lb/>
               are responsible to this House and to the people for the acts 
               <lb/>
               which pass under the name of the Government, and hence 
               <lb/>
               under the name of Her Gracious Majesty the Queen; and 
               <lb/>
               if it is true, and I believe it is, that by the invitation of the 
               <lb/>
               Governor those gentlemen have had an interview with him 
               <lb/>
               on these matters, I would like to know whether it was 
               <lb/>
               at the instance of the Government or at the instance of the 
               <lb/>
               Governor himself ? If it was the latter, I should regret that, 
               <lb/>
               at the close of a long career, which has been satisfactory 
               <lb/>
               alike to the people and the Government, His Excellency 
               <lb/>
               should attempt to interfere with matters that pertain solely 
               <lb/>
               to his advisers, and for which they are responsible. There<lb break="no"/>fore, I would like to know whether the Governor has acted 
               <lb/>
               on behalf of his Government, or whether he has assumed a 
               <lb/>
               responsibility which, in my opinion, he has no right to 
               <lb/>
               assume ? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN</persName>. I hope the hon. gentleman <lb/> will renew
               his question when the hon. First Minister is here. <lb/> The charge that the hon.
               gentleman makes, or supposes <lb/> can be made, against His Excellency the Governor
               General, <lb/> is one that should he met by the First Minister. For my <lb/> own
               part, all I can say to the hon. gentleman is that we, as <lb/> the responsible
               advisers of the Crown, are ready at all times <lb/> to take the responsibilities of
               any act of the Governor <lb/> General in matters of State; and His Excellency, to my
               <lb/> knowledge, and I have no doubt to the knowledge of the <lb/> House, has never
               exposed himself to be called to account <lb/> for any interference that would not be
               in a constitutional <lb/> way. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MITC2">Mr. MITCHELL</persName>. It is not a question whether the <lb/> Government
               assumed the responsibilty of the acts of the <lb/> Governor or not. The question I
               put is whether the <lb/> Governor performed this act with the knowledge and at <lb/>
               the request of the Government of the day, or whether he <lb/> assumed it on his own
               mere motion. If the latter, I hold <lb/> that he is interfering with matters with
               which he has no <lb/> right to interfere under the Constitution. Now that the <lb/>
               hon. First Minister has come in, I would repeat the question <lb/> to him. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. I may say that I was not <lb/> aware, and
               I do not know that any of my colleagues were <lb/> aware, that His Excellency had
               sent for these two gentle<lb break="no"/>men to talk over public matters. I had not
               heard of it until <lb/> just this moment, but I take exception to the doctrine that
               <lb/> the Governor General or Her Majesty cannot talk to such <lb/> people as she or
               he may choose. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. If my hon. friend for Northumberland <lb/> will
               allow me, I would take exception to what he has said. <lb/> Whether Mr. Greenway, or
               any other member or members <lb/> of the Manitoba Government, were invited by the
               Governor <lb/> General, or by this Government, to meet His Excellency, is <lb/> of
               little moment, as the Government are the official advisers <lb/> of His Excellency,
               and must be held responsible in either <lb/> case. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MITC2">Mr. MITCHELL</persName>. I do not object to holding them re<lb break="no"
               />sponsible for it. That was not the point. What I wanted <lb/> to know was, whether
               His Excellency, on his own more <lb/> motion, did this, because, if he did, I hold he
               was wrong? <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. The Government are the parties respon<lb break="no"
               />sible <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MITC2">Mr. MITCHELL</persName>. There is another matter of some im<lb break="no"
               />portance with which I think the House should be made <lb/> acquainted before the
               Orders of the Day are called. It is <lb/> this: I ﬁnd in the Montreal <hi
                  rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi> the following :-<lb/>
            </p>

<cb/>

<div type="section">
            <head>“NEWFOUNDLAND ASKED TO ENTER THE CONFEDERATION. 
               <lb/>
               “DELEGATES TO VISIT OTTAWA. 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               “<hi rendition="simple:italic">The Proposition Well Received and Likely to be Accepted by the 
               <lb/>
               Ancient Colony</hi>. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               “HALIFAX, N.S., March 8.-—[Special.]—The Halifax Herald will pub<lb break="no"/>lish to-morrow a special cablegram from St. John's, Nfld., showing that 
               <lb/>
               practical steps have been taken to embrace the ancient colony of New<lb break="no"/>foundland in the Canadian Confederation. The following correspond<lb break="no"/>ence was laid before the Newfoundland Legislature to-day :- <lb/>
            </quote>

            <p>“<hi rendition="simple:italic">The Governor General of Canada to the Governor of Newfoundland:</hi> 
               <lb/>
               “March 6, 1888. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               “It is considered by my Government that, if your Government ap<lb break="no"/>proves, the time would be convenient for the discussion of the question 
               <lb/>
               of the admission of Newfoundland into the Federal Union, and that no 
               <lb/>
               difficulty would be likely to arise in arranging the terms. Under these 
               <lb/>
               circumstances could you send a. deputation to Ottawa, with power to ne<lb break="no"/>gotiate? In our opinion the deputation should represent the Opposition 
               <lb/>
               as well as the Ministerial party. As the Canadian Session has begun, 
               <lb/>
               and may be short, I would suggest the expediency of the deputation sail<lb break="no"/>ing by the steamer leaving on the 19th inst. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
         
            
            <p>
               “<hi rendition="simple:italic">The Governor of Newfoundland to the Governor General of Canada:</hi> 
               <lb/>
               “March 7, 1888. 
               <lb/></p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
              <p> “I have received your telegram and laid it before my Ministers. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               “The question is now being discussed among the parties, and your 
               <lb/>
               correspondent has no doubt but that a deputation will be sent." 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</quote>
            
            <p>
               This appears in one of the numerous organs of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and I presume it to be correct. I think that as Par<lb break="no"/>liament is in Session, before a communication of that kind 
               <lb/>
               should be sent to another colony the Parliament of Canada 
               <lb/>
               ought to have been taken into consultation on the subject. 
               <lb/>
               ln so important a question as that of admitting a remote 
               <lb/>
               Province like Newfoundland into the Union, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should not have assumed the responsibility of acting 
               <lb/>
               as they appear to have done, without having taken the 
               <lb/>
               Parliament of Canada into their conﬁdence, while that Par<lb break="no"/>liament is in Session. I would like the right hon. the First 
               <lb/>
               Minister to say whether there is any truth in the statement 
               <lb/>
               or not. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. It is true; those negoti<lb break="no"
                  />ations have taken place. <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. Then I think the <lb/> House has
                  been treated with scant courtesy, very scant <lb/> courtesy, indeed—hon. gentlemen
                  on that side as well as on <lb/> this— by a matter of that importance being ﬁrst
                  made pub<lb break="no"/>lic through the medium of one of those paid hirelings of
                  <lb/> the hon. gentleman. I think it is utterly discourteous and <lb/>
                  unconstitutional, and it goes to show that true constitu<lb break="no"/>tional
                  parliamentary government is becoming utterly un<lb break="no"/>known in Canada. We
                  have a one-man power, we have an <lb/> autocrat here to do as he pleases; and to
                  all practical pur<lb break="no"/>poses, the people of Canada would be better off
                  if they <lb/> would send 130 or 140 proxies to the hon. gentleman, and <lb/> thus
                  save expense. <lb/>
               </p>
</div>         
         
      <div type="section">  
            <head>
               THE ONDERDONK ARBITRATION. 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:POPE1">Mr. POPE</persName>. I was not in a position the other day to <lb/>
                  answer the question put by the hon. member for St. John <lb/> (Mr. Weldon), but I
                  am happy to be able to do so now. <lb/> The amount of the valuation of the rolling
                  stock taken, <lb/> under the terms of the contract, from the contractors of the
                  <lb/> western section of the Canadian Pacific Railway in British <lb/> Columbia,
                  is as follows:-<lb/>
               </p>

<table>
<row><cell>Eight locomotives and 185 platform cars .........</cell> <cell>$199,535 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Account for the transportation of the above 
               <lb/>
from British Columbia to Chaudiere… ...... .. </cell><cell>22,028 19</cell></row>
<row><cell>Account for the repairs of the above ........ . </cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:underline">4,016 92</hi> </cell></row>
<row><cell>Total ......................................................</cell> <cell><hi rendition="simple:underline">$225,570 11 </hi></cell></row>
</table>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Against that we have the following:- [...]<lb/>
            </p>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>