<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1870-03-30"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-03-30">30 March 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.

         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="774" to="778"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0774.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0775.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0776.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0777.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0778.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0774">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0774.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0775">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0775.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0776">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0776.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0777">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0777.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0778">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0778.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="774" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0774.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">774</fw> <fw type="num">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               March 30, 1870 <lb/>
               </fw>
            
            <p>
               give back to Nova Scotia what she had spent 
               <lb/>
               since the Quebec Conference. Thank God the 
               <lb/>
               Dominion was rich enough to be honest. Gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen opposite did not always adhere to the 
               <lb/>
               Quebec Resolutions. Last session when the 
               <lb/>
               resolutions respecting Newfoundland were 
               <lb/>
               before the House, although it was provided by 
               <lb/>
               these Quebec Resolutions that the Dominion 
               <lb/>
               should buy up all the Crown Lands, gentlemen 
               <lb/>
               on the opposition benches supported an amend<lb break="no"/>ment against that arrangement respecting 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland. They did not think the Quebec 
               <lb/>
               Resolutions were so sacred that they could not 
               <lb/>
               be amended. How did the Parliament of the 
               <lb/>
               United Kingdom treat Ireland after 1800? 
               <lb/>
               Every one of the arrangements entered into 
               <lb/>
               respecting revenue, had since been altered, as 
               <lb/>
               he showed by the report of the special commit<lb break="no"/>tee appointed to investigate the matter. It was 
               <lb/>
               well known with what difficulty the Union 
               <lb/>
               had been carried, and yet the arrangements 
               <lb/>
               were altered shortly after. That this Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment had acted wisely and justly was evi<lb break="no"/>denced by the decision of the Imperial Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment as well as by the altered tone of the 
               <lb/>
               representatives of Nova Scotia in dealing with 
               <lb/>
               general interests and entering heartily into 
               <lb/>
               their consideration, even although many would 
               <lb/>
               still be anxious to be separated. But they 
               <lb/>
               would all confess they had been treated justly 
               <lb/>
               here. All had heard of the struggles of nations 
               <lb/>
               for liberty; and of English patriots not fearing 
               <lb/>
               to wade through blood and war. They saw how 
               <lb/>
               the Colonial system had grown up from a 
               <lb/>
               bureaucracy to responsible Government, won 
               <lb/>
               by persistent exertions. But history was silent 
               <lb/>
               on any case but this, where a people said they 
               <lb/>
               had too much liberty and were not fit to be 
               <lb/>
               trusted with their own money, like the lunatic, 
               <lb/>
               feeling the fit coming on him, asking to be 
               <lb/>
               manacled. A people which considers itself a 
               <lb/>
               nation which some thought fit to walk alone, 
               <lb/>
               they asserted was not fit to spend its own 
               <lb/>
               money. That was what was said by the hon. 
               <lb/>
               member for West Durham. When Fox said that 
               <lb/>
               the Prince of Wales was Regent by Right 
               <lb/>
               Divine, Pitt said, “Then marry him.” They 
               <lb/>
               could not unwhig the mover for bringing for<lb break="no"/>ward a motion to deprive the people of their 
               <lb/>
               liberty, which might have been expected from 
               <lb/>
               an old Tory like himself, (laughter). Had he 
               <lb/>
               brought forward such a motion, how many 
               <lb/>
               stones would have been thrown at his head. He 
               <lb/>
               held that he and his friends were the expo<lb break="no"/>nents of the wishes of the people, and would 
               <lb/>
               maintain their liberty. Then, of what use was 
               <lb/>
               the motion? The mover says that the alteration 
               <lb/>
               would have been obtained by an Address to the 
               <lb/>
               Imperial Parliament. It would not, therefore, 
               <lb/>
               prevent all the log-rolling, and all they would 
               <lb/>
               obtain by this was a mess of pottage. The 
               <lb/>
               Imperial Parliament had handed over all power 
              
            
            
            <pb n="775" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0775.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               30 mars 1870 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
 
               to the Dominion, except the treaty-making 
               <lb/>
               power and that of making peace and war. 
               <lb/>
               Everything asked for would be given, just as 
               <lb/>
               was done in 1841, when everything asked for 
               <lb/>
               was given at once, and all the changes at once 
               <lb/>
               acceded to, even the Civil list. And so the 
               <lb/>
               attack upon the Constitution was useless, 
               <lb/>
               worse than a crime—it was a blunder. Nobody 
               <lb/>
               knew this better than the member for Lamb<lb break="no"/>ton. He did not know how he was going to vote, 
               <lb/>
               but if he supported the motion of Mr. Blake, he 
               <lb/>
               would vote against all his recorded opinions. 
               <lb/>
               He declared that the salary to the Governor, 
               <lb/>
               fixed at £10,000, was an infringement on the 
               <lb/>
               rights of the people, and would not be satisfied 
               <lb/>
               till the stain was removed by asserting the 
               <lb/>
               duty of maintaining the right of this House to 
               <lb/>
               deal with its own money. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie—It was a good vote. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald—So good that 
               <lb/>
               he would follow it. He would move an amend<lb break="no"/>ment in the very words of that motion, that it 
               <lb/>
               is the undeniable privilege of Parliament to fix 
               <lb/>
               and determine the amount of all expenses 
               <lb/>
               chargeable to the public funds of the country, 
               <lb/>
               (cheers and laughter.) 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie said it was a mistake of the 
               <lb/>
               Minister of Justice if he thought he would 
               <lb/>
               embarrass him by this amendment. His amend<lb break="no"/>ment then was to the motion of the Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Justice, who maintained that the Imperial Par<lb break="no"/>liament had a right to expend any money of 
               <lb/>
               this country that it chose for civil Government. 
               <lb/>
               He was, however, compelled by indignant 
               <lb/>
               public opinion, as expressed by the members of 
               <lb/>
               the House, and was compelled to accept his 
               <lb/>
               motion. He was amused by hearing the Minis<lb break="no"/>ter of Justice refer to a book with which he 
               <lb/>
               was less familiar than with the Statute Book. 
               <lb/>
               He charged the member for West Durham with 
               <lb/>
               troubling Israel. If he was satisfied to occupy 
               <lb/>
               the position of the other parties to the parallel, 
               <lb/>
               that gentleman need not be dissatisfied. He did 
               <lb/>
               not seem to be aware that the quotation</p>
            
         
            <pb n="776" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0776.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">776</fw>  <fw type="num">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               March 30, 1870 <lb/>
               </fw>
            
            <p>
               referred to the meeting between Ahab and 
               <lb/>
               Elijah, before the false prophets were put to 
               <lb/>
               the sword. The prophet Elijah when accused of 
               <lb/>
               troubling Israel answered, “I have not troubled 
               <lb/>
               Israel but thou and thy fathers house in that 
               <lb/>
               thou hast forsaken the Commandments of the 
               <lb/>
               Lord and followed Baal” (loud laughter and 
               <lb/>
               cheers). The Minister of Justice had followed 
               <lb/>
               Baal, and it took the prophet in the shape of 
               <lb/>
               the member for West Durham to bring him 
               <lb/>
               back to reason and righteousness, (renewed 
               <lb/>
               laughter). When the Minister of Justice lacked 
               <lb/>
               argument it was always made known for he 
               <lb/>
               made up for it by being voluble, noisy and 
               <lb/>
               declamatory. His first point was that they had 
               <lb/>
               a perfect right to do what they pleased with 
               <lb/>
               their own. He denied this. They could only do 
               <lb/>
               with it according to the usages of civilized 
               <lb/>
               society. If every one could do as he liked with 
               <lb/>
               his own, why had Ontario been prevented from 
               <lb/>
               doing so with its own? The Minister of Justice 
               <lb/>
               told that Government they had no right to vote 
               <lb/>
               $1,000 to the judges because it was against the 
               <lb/>
               Act. (Hear, hear.) If the Legislature of Ontario 
               <lb/>
               were bound by that Act, the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment were bound in the same way to the 
               <lb/>
               Imperial Government. (Hear, hear.) But the 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentlemen would not get off with the 
               <lb/>
               mere statement that as he did what he pleased 
               <lb/>
               with his own, so they had a right to vote a 
               <lb/>
               certain sum of money. He (Mr. Mackenzie) was 
               <lb/>
               a little surprised that the hon. member for 
               <lb/>
               Colchester should have been so disingenuous 
               <lb/>
               as to have put the matter in that way. It was 
               <lb/>
               more than that. The wording of the resolution 
               <lb/>
               passed last year, followed very closely the 
               <lb/>
               words of the 114th section of the Confederation 
               <lb/>
               Act. The section stated that Nova Scotia should 
               <lb/>
               be liable to Canada for the amount by which 
               <lb/>
               its debt exceeded $8,000,000, but the words of 
               <lb/>
               the statute passed by the hon. gentleman—for 
               <lb/>
               he assumed the responsibility of it—were in 
               <lb/>
               the first clause “that Nova Scotia shall be 
               <lb/>
               liable to Canada for the amount by which its 
               <lb/>
               debt exceeds $9,160,000”, so that the very words 
               <lb/>
               of the Union Act were changed, and they were 
               <lb/>
               told in the succeeding section that this Act 
               <lb/>
               shall be considered as amending the 114 and 
               <lb/>
               115 sections of the Union Act. (Hear, hear.) 
               <lb/>
               The Hon. Minister here assumed the responsi<lb break="no"/>bility of deliberately amending an Imperial 
               <lb/>
               statute settling the amount of debt by which 
               <lb/>
               that Province was to come into the Union. The 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentleman had alluded in defence of that 
               <lb/>
               to the fact that the Parliament of England and 
               <lb/>
               Ireland had changed the terms of the debt upon 
               <lb/>
               which the two countries had become united; 
               <lb/>
               but there was no analogy since there was no 
               <lb/>
               superior power in that case to appeal to, or that 
               <lb/>
               had given them their existence as a Union. 
               <lb/>
               Here they lived under a Constitution furnished 
               <lb/>
               them by the Imperial Government itself with 
               
            
           
            <pb n="777" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0777.jpg"/>
           <!-- <fw type="dateline">
               30 mars 1870 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
       
               their own consent, and there still existed that 
               <lb/>
               authority without which they could not move; 
               <lb/>
               and unless the hon. gentleman could prove that 
               <lb/>
               they were in a position to alter the Union of 
               <lb/>
               the four Provinces without reference to the 
               <lb/>
               Imperial Government, his argument was 
               <lb/>
               extremely worthless. With regard to the high 
               <lb/>
               opinion expressed of the law officers of the 
               <lb/>
               Crown, and the respect they were to pay them 
               <lb/>
               according to the hon. gentleman, it was abso<lb break="no"/>lutely not a week ago that he had sneered at 
               <lb/>
               men who occupied much higher position in the 
               <lb/>
               Government of England than the Attorney 
               <lb/>
               General. He seemed to make them just as it 
               <lb/>
               suited him, making them great or mean as 
               <lb/>
               necessity required. (Laughter.) He even called 
               <lb/>
               the Under Secretary of State, on the receipt of 
               <lb/>
               some despatches, very destructive to the credit 
               <lb/>
               of himself as a statesman, “a mere understrap<lb break="no"/>per”; but now they were to bow down to his 
               <lb/>
               opinions. (Laughter.) Another Minister had 
               <lb/>
               declared that he would never yield to the opin<lb break="no"/>ion of any English Minister, and perhaps he 
               <lb/>
               would show the House how far the Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Justice was wrong when he yielded to the 
               <lb/>
               dictation of the Attorney-General. (Hear, 
               <lb/>
               hear.) The Minister of Justice said that Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Blake did not accept the decision of the House 
               <lb/>
               last year. In so far as that was considered to be 
               <lb/>
               inevitable they accepted it; but they took their 
               <lb/>
               ground, not that Nova Scotia was not entitled 
               <lb/>
               to some consideration of her claims, for they 
               <lb/>
               supported an amendment that the House 
               <lb/>
               should go into Committee to consider their 
               <lb/>
               grievances, but the hon. gentleman took oppo<lb break="no"/>site ground, and the attempt to go into Com<lb break="no"/>mittee failed. The Honourable Secretary of 
               <lb/>
               State had not had manliness yet to acknowl<lb break="no"/>edge the efforts made by the Opposition on 
               <lb/>
               that occasion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Howe said he was not there at the 
               <lb/>
               time, and he knew nothing about it. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie said the hon. gentleman had 
               <lb/>
               a convenient lubricity of memory occasionally. 
               <lb/>
               The hon. gentleman did not fail to make enqui<lb break="no"/>ry when he returned from England. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Howe—I made no enquiries. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            <pb n="778" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-30_Page_0778.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">778</fw> <fw type="num">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               March 30, 1870<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie—Well, you have got it now, 
               <lb/>
               and I hope you will profit by it. Another thing 
               <lb/>
               the Minister of Justice made a great point of 
               <lb/>
               was that they were a great people. That they 
               <lb/>
               had rights and should protect them; but it was 
               <lb/>
               not a week since they were told that Canada 
               <lb/>
               was so petty a country that if we were to send 
               <lb/>
               a delegate to any foreign country they would 
               <lb/>
               not know where he came from. It suited the 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentleman’s purposes to make them out 
               <lb/>
               now a powerful country, but another time and 
               <lb/>
               they were a very weak and contemptible 
               <lb/>
               people indeed. (Great laughter.) He did not 
               <lb/>
               consider it necessary to go over the able argu<lb break="no"/>ments of the hon. member for West Durham, 
               <lb/>
               because not a single one had been referred to 
               <lb/>
               by the Minister of Justice. He imagined that 
               <lb/>
               they acted inconsistently in objecting to the 
               <lb/>
               terms of Newfoundland, because it had been 
               <lb/>
               adopted at the Quebec Conference. It was un<lb break="no"/>necessary to go over arguments on this point 
               <lb/>
               brought forward last session. The resolutions 
               <lb/>
               were agreed to at Quebec on an understanding 
               <lb/>
               that they were to be accepted at that time, and 
               <lb/>
               the whole were to be as a treaty, to be either 
               <lb/>
               wholly accepted, or not. Newfoundland, how<lb break="no"/>ever, refused to accept those terms; but when 
               <lb/>
               they sent a delegation to this place, he (Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Mackenzie) felt most anxious that such 
               <lb/>
               arrangements should be made as would lead to 
               <lb/>
               her entry. He believed that the proposition 
               <lb/>
               which they made would have been accepted by 
               <lb/>
               that people; but the resolutions which the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment insisted on passing, ensured their 
               <lb/>
               rejection at the polls. The hon. gentleman had 
               <lb/>
               made one statement—he said that the course 
               <lb/>
               they proposed was precisely the same, except 
               <lb/>
               in name, such as if they had proposed to pass 
               <lb/>
               an Address to Her Majesty, in order that they 
               <lb/>
               might pay that sum to Nova Scotia. The ground 
               <lb/>
               they took was that that was a union of the four 
               <lb/>
               Provinces, and they could not alter the Act of 
               <lb/>
               Union without the sanction and agreement of 
               <lb/>
               those four parties to the agreement; that an 
               <lb/>
               appeal to England should be made, which, if 
               <lb/>
               favourable, then the Act could be passed; but if 
               <lb/>
               the Government could alter the 114th section 
               <lb/>
               of the Act, they could alter any part of it, and 
               <lb/>
               could, for instance, give a larger representation 
               <lb/>
               to any of the Provinces in that House by the 
               <lb/>
               same means. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Howe said that Nova Scotia would 
               <lb/>
               have been compelled, without the compromise 
               <lb/>
               of last session, to resort to direct taxation to 
               <lb/>
               enable her to maintain her local services, 
               <lb/>
               whereas Ontario had a large surplus on hand, 
               <lb/>
               so that the Premier of that Province could, as 
               <lb/>
               he had been informed he did, sometimes, carry 
               
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>