<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1948-06-19" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1948-06-19">19 June 1948</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:YU1">Thomson Yu</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Twentieth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1948"/>. 
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmond Cloutier, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          
          
          <biblScope unit="page" from="5543" to="5551"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5543.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5544.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5545.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5546.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5547.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5548.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5549.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5550.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5551.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
        
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-07-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="YuTom" when="2017-07-07">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5543">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5543.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5544">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5544.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5545">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5545.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5546">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5546.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5547">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5547.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5548">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5548.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5549">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5549.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5550">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5550.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5551">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5551.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="5543" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5543.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">JUNE 19, 1948</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Supply-External Affairs</hi></fw><fw type="num">5543</fw>
            
            
            <p>
 [...] thing that, rightly or wrongly, either party 
     <lb/>
     might regard as making any change preju<lb break="no"/>dicial to it, while the truce is in operation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HACK1">Mr. HACKETT</persName>: Has Canada sent any 
     <lb/>
     personnel to Palestine and, if so, under what 
     <lb/>
     conditions? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: No, Canada has sent 
     <lb/>
     no personnel to Palestine. So far as I am 
     <lb/>
     informed, a very small guard of fifty is 
     <lb/>
     being recruited voluntarily from the ordinary 
     <lb/>
     staff of the secretariat of the united nations, 
     <lb/>
     and I believe that that guard was being flown 
     <lb/>
     from New York today. It consists of fifty of 
     <lb/>
     the regular personnel of the secretariat of the 
     <lb/>
     united nations, who volunteered to act as a 
     <lb/>
     token guard to assist the mediator in his 
     <lb/>
     undertaking to bring about a settlement 
     <lb/>
     there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HACK1">Mr. HACKETT</persName>: Have any Canadians 
     <lb/>
     joined that unit? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: No Canadians have 
     <lb/>
     joined that unit. My information is that all 
     <lb/>
     but five are United States citizens. Two are 
     <lb/>
     French citizens who were in the employ of 
     <lb/>
     the united nations at Lake Success; one is 
     <lb/>
     of Swedish origin, and another is of Danish 
     <lb/>
     origin.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD8">Mr. MACDONNELL</persName> (Muskoka-Ontario): 
     <lb/>
     Do they go as civilians? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: They go as civilians 
     <lb/>
     employed by the united nations in a custodial 
     <lb/>
     capacity. They were guards of the premises 
     <lb/>
     at Flushing Meadows and Lake Success, and 
     <lb/>
     they probably went in the uniforms they 
     <lb/>
     wore as members of the custodial staff of 
     <lb/>
     the secretariat, but about that I am not sure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JAQU1">Mr. JAQUES</persName>: Will those fifty people who 
     <lb/>
     are going to Palestine be the nucleus of an 
     <lb/>
     international police force? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: I do not know that 
     <lb/>
     there is any international police force other 
     <lb/>
     than the custodial force the united nations 
     <lb/>
     have at Flushing Meadows and Lake Success. 
     <lb/>
     They go as bodyguards for the mediator and 
     <lb/>
     to assist him in the organization of his office 
     <lb/>
     on the island of Rhodes. I think it is for 
     <lb/>
     the purpose of bringing together the parties 
     <lb/>
     to this dispute and trying to get them to 
     <lb/>
     recognize that certain solutions are inevitable 
     <lb/>
     and should be accepted without bloodshed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With respect to the constitution or semi- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     permanent constitution for the three zones 
     <lb/>
     occupied by the forces of the United Kingdom, 
     <lb/>
     the United States and France, as I stated 
     <lb/>
     some time ago in the house we did not ask 
     <lb/>
     to be invited to attend the discussions which 
     <lb/>
     took place in London, although we were kept 
     <lb/>
     informed of everything that was going on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
       <cb/>
       <p>
     The reason we did not insist upon being 
     <lb/>
     brought in at that time was our recognition 
     <lb/>
     of the fact that if we had been brought in, a 
     <lb/>
     great many others would also have been 
     <lb/>
     brought in and it might have hampered the 
     <lb/>
     negotiations which were taking place for this 
     <lb/>
     semi-permanent solution. However, we 
     <lb/>
     reserved our position that when the peace 
     <lb/>
     treaty was being considered we wished to have 
     <lb/>
     a role commensurate with the role we had 
     <lb/>
     in carrying on wartime operations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HACK1">Mr. HACKETT</persName>: I understood that Canada 
     <lb/>
     has submitted a. memorandum suggesting a 
     <lb/>
     form of government based on the principle of 
     <lb/>
     federalism which might be applicable in 
     <lb/>
     Trizonia. The suggested form of government 
     <lb/>
     differed slightly from that of our own system, 
     <lb/>
     in that the component states were to be the 
     <lb/>
     residuary legatees of all power, whereas here 
     <lb/>
     the dominion is. If my information is accurate, 
     <lb/>
     I should like to know whether we submitted 
     <lb/>
     that memorandum on our own initiative or 
     <lb/>
     upon invitation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: It was submitted to 
     <lb/>
     the officials of six governments participating 
     <lb/>
     in the London talks, as a comment upon the 
     <lb/>
     information that was 'being communicated to 
     <lb/>
     us. We have not published the memorandum 
     <lb/>
     we submitted, because we thought that, by 
     <lb/>
     doing so, it might further complicate the 
     <lb/>
     negotiations which were being held. We had 
     <lb/>
     nothing of a serious consequence to comment 
     <lb/>
     upon in the drafts that we were receiving as 
     <lb/>
     being then under discussion in that meeting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The hon. member asked when we might 
     <lb/>
     expect the Canadian representative on the 
     <lb/>
     war criminal court in Japan to return to Can<lb break="no"/>ada. I am not able to give the exact date, 
     <lb/>
     but I may say I had the privilege of having 
     <lb/>
     a long conversation some days ago with Briga<lb break="no"/>dier Nolan, who had acted as Canadian prose— 
     <lb/>
     cutor in these trials. He informed me that the 
     <lb/>
     trials had been completed and the cases taken 
     <lb/>
     under advisement. He told me that the mem— 
     <lb/>
     bers of the tribunal would be there only as 
     <lb/>
     long as may be required for them to prepare<lb/>
     their judgment and reasons for their judg<lb break="no"/>ment. I hope that Within weeks Mr. Justice 
     <lb/>
     McDougall will be back in Canada. At that 
     <lb/>
     time I am sure he will be glad to take up 
     <lb/>
     his ordinary duties as a member of the court 
     <lb/>
     of appeals of the province of Quebec. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. member asked about Canada's rela<lb break="no"/>tions with China at the present time. There 
     <lb/>
     have been no recent developments in that 
     <lb/>
     regard. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then he asked as to what steps, if any, were 
     <lb/>
     being taken with regard to the entry of New<lb break="no"/>foundland into confederation. As hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers know, the first vote was not decisive and 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="5544" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5544.jpg"/>

<fw type="num">5544</fw><fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Supply-External Affairs</hi></fw><fw type="running">Commons</fw>
               
     the second vote, which will be held on July 
     <lb/>
     22, is to be on two questions only, responsible 
     <lb/>
     government and confederation. We have main<lb break="no"/>tained and are maintaining the attitude that, 
     <lb/>
     after having made what we consider is a fair 
     <lb/>
     offer, it is exclusively the right of the people 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland to express their acceptance 
     <lb/>
     or rejection of that offer. We have been 
     <lb/>
     most careful to avoid doing anything that 
     <lb/>
     either party might regard as an attempt to 
     <lb/>
     influence the votes of the inhabitants of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DIEF1">Mr. DIEFENBAKER</persName>: During the past 
     <lb/>
     couple of days I have received a number of 
     <lb/>
     representations from Newfoundland in regard 
     <lb/>
     to the question to which the minister has just 
     <lb/>
     referred. I should like to refer to these and 
     <lb/>
     then ask a question. The first representation 
     <lb/>
     is in the form of a telegram which was sent to 
     <lb/>
     the Hon. the Secretary of State for Commer<lb break="no"/>rial Relations in London, and reads: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

          <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>
     The undersigned members of the bar of New<lb break="no"/>foundland are of the considered opinion and 
     <lb/>
     firmly maintain that the address to His Majesty 
     <lb/>
     by the Newfoundland legislature and the New<lb break="no"/>foundland Act of 1933 enacted by the British 
     <lb/>
     parliament provided specifically that Newfound<lb break="no"/>land's constitution would be merely suspended 
     <lb/>
     and would be restored to the people at their 
     <lb/>
     request when the country again became self-<lb break="yes"/>
     supporting. As the national convention has de<lb break="no"/>cided that Newfoundland is self-supporting, 
     <lb/>
     therefore only two forms of government can be 
     <lb/>
     considered and submitted to the people in the 
     <lb/>
     referendum, namely, responsible government and 
     <lb/>
     commission government. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     That was signed by what I am informed is 
     <lb/>
     a majority of the members of the bar there. 
     <lb/>
     Today I received a telegram which I should 
     <lb/>
     like to bring to the attention of the minister. 
     <lb/>
     This reads: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>
     Forwarding information King stated New<lb break="no"/>foundland should "indicate clearly and beyond 
     <lb/>
     all possibility of misunderstanding their will to 
     <lb/>
     become a province." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     This telegram then asks if 50 per cent of 
     <lb/>
     total electorate or 70 per cent, of vote cast 
     <lb/>
     would be considered sufficient on the part of 
     <lb/>
     the government of Canada to warrant their 
     <lb/>
     accepting Newfoundland's application to join 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion of Canada. At what point will 
     <lb/>
     the government consider that the Newfound<lb break="no"/>land authorities and the people as a whole 
     <lb/>
     desire to be included within the Canadian con<lb break="no"/>federation ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: Mr. Chairman, I can<lb break="no"/>not say anything that would be binding in 
     <lb/>
     that regard. I do not think the government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada will attempt to examine the various 
     <lb/>
     representations that may be made to the com<lb break="no"/>monwealth relations office or that may be 
     <lb/>
     made to others. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<cb/>
            <p>
     There was received from the Governor of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland a communication asking us to 
     <lb/>
     receive a delegation from the national con<lb break="no"/>vention and then submit such conditions as we 
     <lb/>
     would consider fair for the entry of Newfound<lb break="no"/>land into Canada. Those conditions were sub<lb break="no"/>mitted. If the authorities recognized as speak<lb break="no"/>ing for Newfoundland report that the people 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland wish to join Canada on the 
     <lb/>
     conditions expressed» in the proposals that 
     <lb/>
     were submitted, it will then, I think, be the 
     <lb/>
     responsibility of the government to bring to 
     <lb/>
     parliament a recommendation that those con<lb break="no"/>ditions be made available to Newfoundland, 
     <lb/>
     and it will be for the commission of govern<lb break="no"/>ment or the parliament of the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     under which that commission of government 
     <lb/>
     functions to complete the arrangements, which 
     <lb/>
     will in my view no doubt require legislation 
     <lb/>
     by the parliament of the United Kingdom and 
     <lb/>
     possibly also by the Canadian parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DIEF1">Mr. DIEFENBAKER</persName>: It would require 
     <lb/>
     legislation by the Canadian parliament to be 
     <lb/>
     consummated? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: It would require action 
     <lb/>
     by the Canadian parliament. I do not think 
     <lb/>
     this government or any other government 
     <lb/>
     would venture to consummate a thing of such 
     <lb/>
     magnitude without having it decided by the 
     <lb/>
     parliament of Canada. It will be the respon<lb break="no"/>sibility of the government to make a recom<lb break="no"/>mendation to parliament, and the government, 
     <lb/>
     of course, will have to accept responsibility for 
     <lb/>
     the acceptance or the rejection by parliament 
     <lb/>
     of its recommendation. But the government 
     <lb/>
     will not attempt to say that it could complete 
     <lb/>
     the union without the approbation of parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DIEF1">Mr. DIEFENBAKER</persName>: Would the minister 
     <lb/>
     not say it would require an almost overwhelm<lb break="no"/>ing vote of the people of Newfoundland in 
     <lb/>
     order to justify Newfoundland being joined 
     <lb/>
     to Canada? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: The degree to which 
     <lb/>
     the consent of the population of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     would require to be expressed would have to 
     <lb/>
     be appraised by those who are responsible at 
     <lb/>
     the present time for Newfoundland affairs. If 
     <lb/>
     the government of Newfoundland, having con<lb break="no"/>sulted the population, represented to us that 
     <lb/>
     the population wished confederation to be con<lb break="no"/>summated I think we would not go behind 
     <lb/>
     that declaration to examine to what extent 
     <lb/>
     they were justified in making such a repre<lb break="no"/>sentation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     At the present time the constitution of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland is still suspended, and it is the 
     <lb/>
     parliament of the United Kingdom that has 
     <lb/>
     legislative jurisdiction over Newfoundland. It 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="5545" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5545.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">JUNE 19, 1948</fw><fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Supply-External Affairs</hi></fw> <fw type="num">5545</fw>
            
     exercises that through a commission of gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, but it is under the legislative juris<lb break="no"/>diction of the parliament at Westminster and 
     <lb/>
     I do not think the British government or the 
     <lb/>
     British parliament would act in a manner that 
     <lb/>
     it did not feel was proper in the interests of 
     <lb/>
     the inhabitants of Newfoundland, after con<lb break="no"/>sulting them in these two plebiscites. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HACK1">Mr. HACKETT</persName>:   I understand that the 
     <lb/>
     government might wish that a statute express 
     <lb/>
     the will of parliament on granting to New<lb break="no"/>foundland access to the dominion. Does that 
     <lb/>
     mean that the minister considers that the 
     <lb/>
     provision in the British North America Act 
     <lb/>
     concerning the admission of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     into confederation is but a power to be exer<lb break="no"/>cised in the ordinary way, that is, by legisla<lb break="no"/>tion enacted by parliament. I do not recall 
     <lb/>
     the exact words of the British North America 
     <lb/>
     Act, but it contains a provision which antici<lb break="no"/>pates the possibility of Newfoundland becom<lb break="no"/>ing a province of Canada, and my query is: 
     <lb/>
     Does the minister consider that enactment 
     <lb/>
     merely as a power which parliament may 
     <lb/>
     exercise, or is it something more than that 
     <lb/>
     which would only require executive action to 
     <lb/>
     carry the admission into effect? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POUL3">Mr. POULIOT</persName>: What difference does it 
     <lb/>
     make? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: It makes a difference 
     <lb/>
     as to the proper procedure to bring it about. 
     <lb/>
     The British North America Act contemplated 
     <lb/>
     that there might be union between Canada 
     <lb/>
     and Newfoundland on a joint address of the 
     <lb/>
     houses of parliament of Canada and the legis<lb break="no"/>lature of Newfoundland. That principle could 
     <lb/>
     be resorted to; but it would require, in order 
     <lb/>
     to be resorted to, the restoration of self-<lb break="yes"/>
     government in Newfoundland, and then joint 
     <lb/>
     addresses under the terms of section 146 of 
     <lb/>
     the British North America Act. On those 
     <lb/>
     joint addresses, union could be consummated 
     <lb/>
     by order of His Majesty in council without 
     <lb/>
     legislation in the parliament at Westminster 
     <lb/>
     or legislation in the parliament of Canada. 
     <lb/>
     But if that method is not. resorted to, the 
     <lb/>
     matter is not expressly provided for and 
     <lb/>
     would have to be accomplished by new legis<lb break="no"/>lation that could, I suppose, be adopted only 
     <lb/>
     by the parliament at Westminster if there 
     <lb/>
     were joint addresses from the houses of the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian parliament asking that it be done. 
     <lb/>
     The parliament at Westminster amends the 
     <lb/>
     British North America Act and makes pro<lb break="no"/>vision with respect to Canada, but only on 
     <lb/>
     the request of the houses of the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     parliament; and that could probably be the 
     <lb/>
     method adopted. The one provided for in 
     <lb/>
     the British North America Act would require, 
     <lb/>
     as a condition precedent, that self-government 
    
            <cb/>
            
     be restored to Newfoundland, that a legisla<lb break="no"/>ture be elected in Newfoundland and that 
     <lb/>
     there be an address from that legislature as 
     <lb/>
     well as from the Canadian parliament for an 
     <lb/>
     order in council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HACK1">Mr. HACKETT</persName>: I had a little difficulty in 
     <lb/>
     following the minister when he seemed to 
     <lb/>
     consider the disability of Newfoundland as 
     <lb/>
     creating a disability in Canada. I readily 
     <lb/>
     understand that the government might wish 
     <lb/>
     to pass a statute. I understand that, but I was 
     <lb/>
     not certain whether or not it would be neces<lb break="no"/>sary in order effectively to carry out the union 
     <lb/>
     to do more than pass addresses in Canada; it, 
     <lb/>
     of course, being necessary that Newfoundland, 
     <lb/>
     in view of the suspension of parliamentary life 
     <lb/>
     there, go to Westminster for the authorization 
     <lb/>
     which results—I do not say this in any dis<lb break="no"/>respectful way—from its temporary tutelage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: I think the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber is technically right. that it would be 
     <lb/>
     sufficient to justify legislation by the parlia<lb break="no"/>ment at Westminster placing Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     within Canada to have addresses from the 
     <lb/>
     houses of parliament in Canada, and the 
     <lb/>
     agreement of Newfoundland to the legislation 
     <lb/>
     would be a matter that would be the responsi<lb break="no"/>bility of the parliament at Westminster. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DIEF1">Mr. DIEFENBAKER</persName>: One question arises 
     <lb/>
     from that. Has the minister given considera<lb break="no"/>tion to the Newfoundland Act of 1934? A 
     <lb/>
     perusal of that act would indicate that the 
     <lb/>
     United Kingdom pledged itself to restore self-<lb break="yes"/>government there at any time that Newfound<lb break="no"/>land became self-supporting. In view of the 
     <lb/>
     section of the British North America Act 
     <lb/>
     which the minister has just read, and having 
     <lb/>
     regard to the Newfoundland Act of 1934 that 
     <lb/>
     self-government is to be restored in New<lb break="no"/>foundland, would it not be a condition prece<lb break="no"/>dent before confederation between the nine 
     <lb/>
     provinces of Canada and Newfoundland could 
     <lb/>
     be consummated? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: No, I do not think so. 
     <lb/>
     I think all we have to do is to look after our 
     <lb/>
     responsibility, and leave it to those who have 
     <lb/>
     constitutional responsibility for the fate of 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland to ascertain whether they are <lb/>
     fulfilling their obligations, whether the obliga<lb break="no"/>tions arise out of the Newfoundland Act or 
     <lb/>
     otherwise. I think we can in perfect con<lb break="no"/>fidence leave it to the Newfoundland and 
     <lb/>
     British authorities to clear everything required 
     <lb/>
     on their side to enable a proper union to be 
     <lb/>
     consummated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DIEF1">Mr. DIEFENBAKER</persName>: Has the minister 
     <lb/>
     received any representations from Newfound— 
     <lb/>
     land, or the peOple of Newfoundland or any 
     <lb/>
     group in that country, against any action on 
     <lb/>
     the part of Canada? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="5546" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5546.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">5546</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Supply—External Affairs</hi></fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: The department 
     <lb/>
     would, of course, receive courteously and file 
     <lb/>
     anything that would come from any group in 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, but the department would not 
     <lb/>
     act on anything that does not come from 
     <lb/>
     those who have the constitutional responsibil— 
     <lb/>
     ity for the government of Newfoundland at 
     <lb/>
     the present time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACI1">Mr. MacINNIS</persName>: With noted lawyers on my 
     <lb/>
     right, I was wondering, since the position is 
     <lb/>
     now that a referendum is to be taken on two 
     <lb/>
     questions—union with Canada or responsible 
     <lb/>
     government—if the vote decides for union 
     <lb/>
     with Canada it decides against responsible 
     <lb/>
     government. Surely the United Kingdom 
     <lb/>
     would not then insist that Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     should have responsible government before it 
     <lb/>
     could have union with Canada. It seems to 
     <lb/>
     me that the question we are discussing is 
     <lb/>
     purely academic. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DIEF1">Mr. DIEFENBAKER</persName>: It is not academic 
     <lb/>
     so far as the people there are concerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACI1">Mr. MacINNIS</persName>: But the people there are 
     <lb/>
     going to decide. If they decide by whatever 
     <lb/>
     majority they do decide I do not think 
     <lb/>
     Canada can say to the authorities in New<lb break="no"/>foundland or to the authorities in the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom, if they should be acting for New<lb break="no"/>foundland, that we cannot accept Newfound<lb break="no"/>land as a province because the decision of the 
     <lb/>
     people has not been decisive enough. I claim 
     <lb/>
     that this discussion is purely academic until 
     <lb/>
     such time as the referendum is taken and we 
     <lb/>
     begin to work it out. Certainly we cannot do 
     <lb/>
     anything about it tonight. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CHUR1">Mr. CHURCH</persName>: I wish to say something on 
     <lb/>
     the administration item. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The CHAIRMAN</persName>: Order. The discussion 
     <lb/>
     is on Newfoundland. We should try to com<lb break="no"/>plete that discussion before discussing other 
     <lb/>
     subjects. If the hon. member is to speak on 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland it will be proper for him to 
     <lb/>
     speak now. If not, would he mind waiting until 
     <lb/>
     we have exhausted the discussion on this 
     <lb/>
     subject? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CHUR1">Mr. CHURCH</persName>: I do not wish to be here all 
     <lb/>
     evening waiting for others to speak. I have 
     <lb/>
     made a study of this question since I came here 
     <lb/>
     in 1921, and am not like some of the amateur 
     <lb/>
     diplomats who are now appearing on the 
     <lb/>
     scene. I have been following this situation for 
     <lb/>
     many years past. I want to find out from the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary of State for External Affairs what is 
     <lb/>
     or What is not the policy of the government at 
     <lb/>
     the present time regarding foreign affairs. We 
     <lb/>
     may have an invasion just like a thief in the 
     <lb/>
     night, the way it came at Pearl Harbor. What 
     <lb/>
     are you going to do about it? There is no use 
     <lb/>
     in our pretending that we are a first-class power 
     <lb/>
            
            
            <cb/>
           
     when we are not. I have never been at one of 
     <lb/>
     those UNO conventions because I do not 
     <lb/>
     believe in them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In his opening address this session, the 
     <lb/>
     minister said that the foreign policy of Canada 
     <lb/>
     was wrapped up exclusively with the UNO. 
     <lb/>
     That is the present policy of the government. 
     <lb/>
     There is no use in our pretending that we can 
     <lb/>
     rely on such agencies any longer. That was 
     <lb/>
     shown by the action of Gottwald regarding 
     <lb/>
     Czechoslovakia in the deposing of the late 
     <lb/>
     president. It shocked the whole human world, 
     <lb/>
     and shows us the grave danger we are in. What 
     <lb/>
     is this famous UNO in which the minister has 
     <lb/>
     confidence? We used to have an empire parlia— 
     <lb/>
     mentary association. They safeguarded our 
     <lb/>
     interests so far as foreign affairs were con<lb break="no"/>cerned. They forgot all about the empire and 
     <lb/>
     became pan—American. We are not a first-class 
     <lb/>
     power. We have had two wars to teach us 
     <lb/>
     that lesson. You have had this second UNO 
     <lb/>
     league of nations. We had the first league of 
     <lb/>
     nations on which this country expended nearly 
     <lb/>
     $5,000,000 in sending deputations over to 
     <lb/>
     Geneva. They built buildings costing fabulous 
     <lb/>
     sums of money, millions of dollars in Switzer<lb break="no"/>land and Geneva, and, after that was done, it 
     <lb/>
     was found that it was a hollow mockery, a 
     <lb/>
     sham and a humbug, and drove us into a 
     <lb/>
     second war. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There was not a newspaper in the country 
     <lb/>
     except one or two which had three or four 
     <lb/>
     lines about the collapse of Geneva, and- the 
     <lb/>
     buildings there are wasted. We sent these 
     <lb/>
     deputations over there, which was supposed 
     <lb/>
     to be a consolation prize for those members 
     <lb/>
     of the government and others to have a little 
     <lb/>
     side trip after the session was over. My hon. 
     <lb/>
     friends to the left believed in it. My hon. 
     <lb/>
     friends to the left, away back in 1938, six 
     <lb/>
     months after Munich, right up to the opening 
     <lb/>
     of the war years, asked what was the use of 
     <lb/>
     depending on Glasgow and London for 
     <lb/>
     defence, when we would get all the defence we 
     <lb/>
     wanted in Washington; but we had a rude 
     <lb/>
     awakening in 1939. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The second war was caused by whom? It 
     <lb/>
     was caused by the very people in England, in 
     <lb/>
     Canada and in the other dominions who were 
     <lb/>
     members of What they called this league of 
     <lb/>
     nations society, which we are now recom<lb break="no"/>mending for a $5,000 grant, consisting of well<lb break="no"/>meaning highbrows, parlour pinks, professors, 
     <lb/>
     and; others. Britain will come to life again 
     <lb/>
     in Canada. There is no use in our depending 
     <lb/>
     on any such agencies as UNO and similar 
     <lb/>
     societies. It was the proposal of the late 
     <lb/>
     great president of the United States to bring 
     <lb/>
     Geneva to San Francisco, and New York to 
     <lb/>
     Lake Success. Now the congress at Washington 
     <lb/>
     wishes to get rid of the UNO. Congress wants 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="5547" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5547.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">JUNE 19, 1948</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Supply-External Affairs</hi></fw> <fw type="num">5547</fw>
 
     to get it out of the country. Next week a 
     <lb/>
     Republican convention is to be held in 
     <lb/>
     Philadelphia for the purpose of selecting a 
     <lb/>
     candidate for the presidency. Opinions were 
     <lb/>
     expressed in congress in favour of getting the 
     <lb/>
     UNO out of the country. The second world 
     <lb/>
     war had hardly ended when people started 
     <lb/>
     their efforts once more to establish a second 
     <lb/>
     league of nations, now known as UNO. There 
     <lb/>
     was, as everyone knows, a great gathering at 
     <lb/>
     San Francisco, and we had our own ambas<lb break="no"/>sadors there, ambassadors from our own party 
     <lb/>
     and others. They were there trying to learn 
     <lb/>
     diplomacy in a day, just like this magnificent 
     <lb/>
     institution. that the minister has at the present 
     <lb/>
     time at Lake Success. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The government has been spending vast 
     <lb/>
     sums of money on this UNO institution. It 
     <lb/>
     has gone up to nearly $10,000,000, there being 
     <lb/>
     an increase this year of $1,074,974 for salaries 
     <lb/>
     alone, or a salary total of $5,083,082. Just 
     <lb/>
     imagine that! And What did they do at San 
     <lb/>
     Francisco? They divided the nations into 
     <lb/>
     powers, large and small, and our own repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives were there and agreed to give 
     <lb/>
     the Big Five a veto power. Foreign affairs 
     <lb/>
     will always be a political issue in this country. 
     <lb/>
     It always has been and it is a blessing that it 
     <lb/>
     has, instead of a non-party one, by giving a 
     <lb/>
     few a trip to such farces as Lake Success. 
     <lb/>
     Canada's policy in foreign affairs is the UNO, 
     <lb/>
     and "Let us pretend". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In the first war we were not prepared, and 
     <lb/>
     yet a million men went from the dominions 
     <lb/>
     to participate in the first war. They went 
     <lb/>
     under the individual sovereignty status and 
     <lb/>
     autonomy of every dominion, and of those 
     <lb/>
     men 130,000 fell on the field of battle. Those 
     <lb/>
     men enlisted and died of their own volition, 
     <lb/>
     and the men of the dominions repeated it in 
     <lb/>
     the second war in five times the number. But 
     <lb/>
     in the period between the two wars another 
     <lb/>
     organization was started up. Efforts of this 
     <lb/>
     kind in league of nations societies or peace 
     <lb/>
     societies have been a failure for 100 years or 
     <lb/>
     more. We remember the concert of Europe 
     <lb/>
     from 1815 to 1823, when Russia, Prussia, and 
     <lb/>
     Austria formed what was known as the Holy 
     <lb/>
     Alliance. They were going to survey condi<lb break="no"/>tions in Europe every five years and when war 
     <lb/>
     seemed- imminent they would endeavour to 
     <lb/>
     bring about peace. It was such a humbug that 
     <lb/>
     a great prime minister, George Canning, pro<lb break="no"/>posed that Britain get out of Europe 
     <lb/>
     altogether. It simply led to the Monroe 
     <lb/>
     doctrine. The Holy Alliance lasted from 1815 
     <lb/>
     to 1823 and culminated in what has come to 
     <lb/>
     be known as the Monroe doctrine. What was 
     <lb/>
     that doctrine? In a word, Mr. Chairman, it 
     <lb/>
     was nothing more than the supremacy of 
     <lb/>
     Britain on the seas. And that is what has 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     maintained the peace of the world for 100 
     <lb/>
     years from 1815 to the great war of 1914— 
     <lb/>
     British supremacy on the seas. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     There has been talk, since the end of the 
     <lb/>
     second war, about a new UNO, and they have 
     <lb/>
     opened up in New York, at Lake Success after 
     <lb/>
     San Francisco. They have opened up another 
     <lb/>
     agency there, and two of the principal sup<lb break="no"/>porters and boosters of UNO, the London 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Economist</hi> and the London <hi rendition="simple:italic">Times</hi>, have been 
     <lb/>
     compelled to say recently it has been a disap<lb break="no"/>pointment and a failure, and to demand an 
     <lb/>
     end of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The fact is that there is no use in our 
     <lb/>
     depending on that organization any longer. 
     <lb/>
     Are we going to spend another $10,000,000 
     <lb/>
     this year on that organization? What is the 
     <lb/>
     use of deceiving ourselves? Why cherish the 
     <lb/>
     delusion that UNO can keep the peace? We 
     <lb/>
     are as close to war as Churchill has said, as 
     <lb/>
     Truman has said, as General Bradley, before 
     <lb/>
     the congress committee at Washington, has 
     <lb/>
     said, and as the admiral of the fleet at Wash<lb break="no"/>ington said not so long ago. We are as close to 
     <lb/>
     war today as we were in August 1939. We are 
     <lb/>
     back where we were then. Conditions have 
     <lb/>
     not changed a particle. There is no use in 
     <lb/>
     pretending that we can depend for peace on 
     <lb/>
     any such agency as the united nations organiza<lb break="no"/>tion at Lake Success. I call it a Lake Failure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I have been trying to find out what the 
     <lb/>
     foreign policy of this country is and I am 
     <lb/>
     bound to say that I have failed in the attempt. 
     <lb/>
     We have no foreign policy and we never did 
     <lb/>
     have one. The foreign policy the minister 
     <lb/>
     announced earlier in the session was simply 
     <lb/>
     dependence upon the united nations organiza<lb break="no"/>tion. That was the cornerstone of our policy, 
     <lb/>
     and if it is the cornerstone of that policy, 
     <lb/>
     then I regret to say that I fear invasion. 
     <lb/>
     We did nothing to encourage parliamentary 
     <lb/>
     association within the empire. We tried to 
     <lb/>
     bring on a debate in the spring of 1947 regard<lb break="no"/>ing the scuttling of the empire. The empire 
     <lb/>
     has been cut to pieces. We have seen what 
     <lb/>
     happened in Egypt. We lost our lifeline in 
     <lb/>
     the Mediterranean; we lost the Suez canal. 
     <lb/>
     And there is Palestine. I will say nothing 
     <lb/>
     about that tonight, because we all know what 
     <lb/>
     the situation there is. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I repeat, Mr. Chairman, this government has 
     <lb/>
     no foreign policy and never did have one; 
     <lb/>
     neither did our delegates to the UNO in New 
     <lb/>
     York have a policy. Not a soldier was to be 
     <lb/>
     sent by Canada or the United States to fight 
     <lb/>
     in Palestine. What is the use of Trygve Lie 
     <lb/>
     and all his works at the UNO? This second 
     <lb/>
     league of nations has tried many agencies, 
     <lb/>
     and what does Trygve Lie say about it all? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="5548" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5548.jpg"/>
       <fw type="num">5548</fw>  <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Supply—External Affairs</hi></fw>    <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
   
            <p>
     In my opinion we are simply wasting the 
     <lb/>
     people's money at Lake Success. We are 
     <lb/>
     throwing $10,000,000 into the sink-hole. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The situation in the Atlantic today is 
     <lb/>
     dangerous. The British government, Canada 
     <lb/>
     consenting, gave up all its bases from New<lb break="no"/>foundland to British Guiana to the United 
     <lb/>
     States for ninety—nine years. I pointed out at 
     <lb/>
     the time what the result of that would be. I 
     <lb/>
     pointed out the eflect it would have upon 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland's joining confederation, and my 
     <lb/>
     predictions have been justified. What was that 
     <lb/>
     lease for? It was a 99-year lease, practically a 
     <lb/>
     freehold lease, entered into for a consideration 
     <lb/>
     that proved of very little practical value. The 
     <lb/>
     lease should have been cancelled long ago and 
     <lb/>
     charged up to lend-lease. It was entered into 
     <lb/>
     in the darkest days of the battle of the 
     <lb/>
     Atlantic, and in return for that lease Britain 
     <lb/>
     was given some fifty old, out-of-date ships. 
     <lb/>
     Many of them had to go into dry dock, being 
     <lb/>
     of no use. Others had no coal. Then Pearl 
     <lb/>
     Harbor broke and we got a lesson, and 
     <lb/>
     Canada was nearly invaded. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have been talking about a foreign policy. 
     <lb/>
     The United States has never had a foreign 
     <lb/>
     policy any more than we have had. For 100 
     <lb/>
     years it has been without such a policy. Its 
     <lb/>
     foreign policy was that of Andrew Jackson, 
     <lb/>
     George Washington and Madison. And what 
     <lb/>
     was the essence of that policy? Simply this: 
     <lb/>
     no foreign entanglement unless the shores of 
     <lb/>
     America are invaded. When the United 
     <lb/>
     States fought the Spanish-American war in 
     <lb/>
     1898 that was the ground they took. After<lb break="no"/>wards they wanted to abandon Manila. Our 
     <lb/>
     foreign policy now is to depend upon the 
     <lb/>
     league of nations at UNO and that we have no 
     <lb/>
     commitments; we simply yet take the attitude 
     <lb/>
     that "Parliament will decide" if war comes. 
     <lb/>
     That attitude, as I have pointed out before, 
     <lb/>
     has led to the scuttling of the British empire 
     <lb/>
     during the past two years. Britain, together 
     <lb/>
     with the dominions, stood' alone for two and a 
     <lb/>
     half, nearly three years, from 1939 to 1942, 
     <lb/>
     against the mighty forces of the enemy, and if 
     <lb/>
     the war was to have been lost, then surely it 
     <lb/>
     would have been lost in those three years, 
     <lb/>
     before aid came. But Britain weathered the 
     <lb/>
     storm. If Britain and the dominions do not 
     <lb/>
     hang together there is little hope for peace 
     <lb/>
     so far as the British empire is concerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But not only have bases been given up in 
     <lb/>
     the Atlantic; we have given up bases in our 
     <lb/>
     own country, Canada, to the United States. 
     <lb/>
     Why, I do not know. Surely the United States 
     <lb/>
     have enough to do to look after their own 
     <lb/>
     country. We have a great ally in the country 
     <lb/>
     to the south of us. The Anglo-Saxon race, the 
     <lb/>
     British peoples and those of the United States, 
     <lb/>
     are the hope of the world for peace in the 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
            
     future; but they must be up and doing, 
     <lb/>
     because we are living in an armed world in 
     <lb/>
     which there has been no peace and in which 
     <lb/>
     there is no real peace now. This will prove to 
     <lb/>
     have been a forty-year war before it is all 
     <lb/>
     over, from 1914 to 1954. Let us not talk about 
     <lb/>
     peace when there is no peace. Look at the 
     <lb/>
     situation in India where millions of people 
     <lb/>
     are left to be massacred. Look at the situa<lb break="no"/>tion in Palestine. Look at the Suez. And we 
     <lb/>
     know what the consequences were from the 
     <lb/>
     invasion of Czechoslovakia. Thousands of men 
     <lb/>
     in the Russian satellite countries in the Bal<lb break="no"/>kans and eastern Europe are being put to work 
     <lb/>
     on dry docks and more are sent to the Arctic 
     <lb/>
     circle as slaves from Russia's satellite states. 
     <lb/>
     It is impossible to find out from the united 
     <lb/>
     nations organization how many people are so 
     <lb/>
     treated. No one can find out anything about 
     <lb/>
     them, so what use is the UNO? Roumania is 
     <lb/>
     gone; the Balkans are gone and all that kind 
     <lb/>
     of thing. I am far from satisfied with what 
     <lb/>
     has been done in the British corridor over in 
     <lb/>
     Germany. Canada has no say over there. We 
     <lb/>
     are just a. minor power. We consented to be 
     <lb/>
     a minor power at San Francisco when the Big 
     <lb/>
     Five insisted on and obtained the veto power 
     <lb/>
     and all that kind of thing. You will have 
     <lb/>
     nothing to say about the peace plans whereas, 
     <lb/>
     if you had hung together with the mother 
     <lb/>
     country, you would have something to say 
     <lb/>
     about them. The situation in South Africa is 
     <lb/>
     hopeless. There are those in this house—and 
     <lb/>
     I have never been one of them—who speak in 
     <lb/>
     eulogy of the late prime minister, Lieutenant 
     <lb/>
     General Smuts, of South Africa. He is a repub<lb break="no"/>lican. He has all along wanted to set up a 
     <lb/>
     republic in South Africa. He has always been 
     <lb/>
     against having a British governor general, and 
     <lb/>
     would not give the ballot to the black troops 
     <lb/>
     who marched across the desert with Alexander 
     <lb/>
     and Montgomery. He was one of the cabinet 
     <lb/>
     of the pro-Germans there before world war II. 
     <lb/>
     He also signed the charter of the league of 
     <lb/>
     nations. Yet he says now the UNO have no 
     <lb/>
     power and no jurisdiction over the colonies. 
     <lb/>
     </p>
            <p>No country in the world is going to give up 
     <lb/>its control of its own affairs or sovereignty to 
     <lb/>any foreign power or any foreign body like 
     <lb/>the UNO, unless the country is so small or 
     <lb/>has such poor defences that it could be cap<lb break="no"/>tured in any event. Who is going to give up 
     <lb/>his sovereignty? Are we in Canada to do 
     <lb/>that? One of the minister's deputies went 
     <lb/>away down to Lake Success and Washington. 
     <lb/>He has been making some speeches and he is 
     <lb/>in favour of giving up sovereignty over our 
     <lb/>bases in Canada to the UNO. Where would 
     <lb/>we have been in the first war if Britain had 
     <lb/>given up these bases at the Cape, at Gibraltar, 
     <lb/>at Suez, or at Hong Kong to a foreign country 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="5549" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5549.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">JUNE 19, 1948</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Supply—External Affairs</hi></fw><fw type="num">5549 </fw>
   
     or a league of nations? We would have had 
     <lb/>
     to remain neutral also in the first and second 
     <lb/>
     wars and we would have lost both wars. That 
     <lb/>
     is what giving up bases would have meant. 
     <lb/>
     Yet we have mischievous representatives away 
     <lb/>
     down at the UNO at Lake Success telling us 
     <lb/>
     to give up our sovereignty and to let foreign 
     <lb/>
     powers establish bases here in Canada and 
     <lb/>
     to let them keep the bases they have. 
     <lb/></p>

            <p>
     I think that is about all I have to say 
     <lb/>
     about that, but there is another point I wish 
     <lb/>
     to mention. The minister has referred to the 
     <lb/>
     situation in the Suez, in Palestine, in Ger<lb break="no"/>many, in China and in India. It is a tragedy. 
     <lb/>
     Wait till history is written about the situation 
     <lb/>
     in India and all these places. Britain main<lb break="no"/>tained peace, justice and freedom in India 
     <lb/>
     for over one hundred years. She did the same 
     <lb/>
     thing in Palestine. She took a mandate there. 
     <lb/>
     As I said the other evening in the house, there 
     <lb/>
     are about eighteen powers claiming a say in 
     <lb/>
     the Palestine situation. The Arabs have been 
     <lb/>
     there for hundreds of years. Turkey had it. 
     <lb/>
     When the first war broke out, Turkey was 
     <lb/>
    opposed to us. The Arabs had it. Egypt 
     <lb/>had it. Rome had it. Persia had it. Greece 
     <lb/>had it. Syria had it. All these nations have 
     <lb/>ruled Palestine. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     A great mistake was made in what was done 
     <lb/>
    at the close of the last war, after General 
     <lb/>Allenby marched into Palestine. I was on the 
     <lb/>same platform when he spoke at the exhibi<lb break="no"/>tion a few years ago and explained the 
     <lb/>situation. If you are depending on the UNO, 
     <lb/>you are depending on something that does not 
     <lb/>exist. It has no defence force. Who is going 
     <lb/>to be in a defence force to go to Palestine 
     <lb/>in a situation like that? If you read the 
     <lb/>articles in the papers and know the truth 
     <lb/>about it, you will realize the situation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Wait till the truth is known about the 
     <lb/>scuttling of the empire in India and the Suez, 
     <lb/>giving up the whole lifeline through the Medi<lb break="no"/>terranean to a foreign power and the UNO, 
     <lb/>so that we have no control at all over the 
     <lb/>Mediterranean. If war came, the enemy could 
     <lb/>come down through the Red sea and right 
     <lb/>across into Canada in about half a day. I 
     <lb/>can tell you this: We are just pretending. 
     <lb/>What is being done in Germany? Nothing. 
     <lb/>In Japan the situation is the same. China is 
     <lb/>on the verge of civil war. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     What are we going to do about the title 
     <lb/>
     of the king? It is not divisible, in my opinion. 
     <lb/>
     We have had legal authority for that. The 
     <lb/>
     king is now king of Canada, but no longer is 
     <lb/>
     he emperor of India. The scuttling and the 
     <lb/>
     dissolution of the British empire have gone 
     <lb/>
     on. A large body of public opinion in this 
     <lb/>
     country thinks the same way as I do about 
     <lb/>
     the state of affairs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <cb/>
            <p>
     Canada, which was first in the diamond 
     <lb/>
     jubilee procession, is today nowhere. We 
     <lb/>
     have no foreign policy except that of the 
     <lb/>
     UNO, a sham organization, with the extrava<lb break="no"/>gance of the external affairs department that 
     <lb/>
     goes on down there, $9,000,000 or $10,000,000 
     <lb/>
     being spent in this work, and no security at 
     <lb/>
     all. If you look over the estimates you find 
     <lb/>
     that thousands and tens of thousands of dol<lb break="no"/>lars are just wasted in administrative offices. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Just recently in the city of Toronto we had 
     <lb/>
     a trade exhibition to which came people from 
     <lb/>
     the seven seas. It was magnificent to see what 
     <lb/>
     these trade agents had done the world over, 
     <lb/>
     long before we ever had this magnificent 
     <lb/>
     organization of ambassadors and consuls gen<lb break="no"/>eral. Wait till the return is brought down for 
     <lb/>
     the travelling expenses. Here is a new group 
     <lb/>
     of seven or eight of the health department now 
     <lb/>
     on the ship bound for Geneva. Several hun<lb break="no"/>dred thousand dollars are being spent in one 
     <lb/>
     department on travelling expenses. When it 
     <lb/>
     is all added up it amounts to $1,000,000, 
     <lb/>
     $2,000,000 or $3,000,000 for Canada's travelling 
     <lb/>
     expenses. Canada, a small nation with ten or 
     <lb/>
     eleven million people, cannot stand that any 
     <lb/>
     longer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There should have been a conference of 
     <lb/>
     Britain and the dominions long ago. Mr. Cur<lb break="no"/>tin and Mr. Fraser from New Zealand and 
     <lb/>
     Australia, from where the Deputy Speaker is 
     <lb/>
     now sitting, addressed this house. They wanted 
     <lb/>
     to have an empire conference like the ones 
     <lb/>
     we used to have every ten years, to take up 
     <lb/>
     questions of trade, defence and migration. Sir 
     <lb/>
     Wilfrid Laurier had one while he was in power. 
     <lb/>
     He proposed a policy for this country that 
     <lb/>
     when Britain was at war, Canada was at war 
     <lb/>
     also. That was the policy we had in two wars. 
     <lb/>
     I have referred to the first war when a mil<lb break="no"/>lion men went voluntarily, under their own 
     <lb/>
     status and autonomy, and 130,000 fell. In 
     <lb/>
     the second war the situation was the same, 
     <lb/>
     except that ten times the number went. That 
     <lb/>
     was the policy : when Britain is at war, Canada 
     <lb/>
     is at war. If we go into a third war I venture 
     <lb/>
     to say the policy will be the same. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Are we to wait until the enemy sails up the 
     <lb/>
     St. Lawrence? They were pretty close to it 
     <lb/>
     the last time, in 1943, 1944 and 1945. They 
     <lb/>
     were up to the St. Lawrence when a secret 
     <lb/>
     meeting was held in this chamber in the 
     <lb/>
     second war, and they came up fairly far. 
     <lb/>
     Thousands of us, if not the whole House of 
     <lb/>
     Commons, might have been carted away 
     <lb/>
     overseas. They got a long distance up the 
     <lb/>
     St. Lawrence. Are we to wait until that hap<lb break="no"/>pens again? I say no. The way to avoid it 
     <lb/>
     is to pretend no longer. There is no use in 
     <lb/>
     spending any dollars on the UNO at Lake 
     <lb/>
     Success. As I have said before, if they would 
     <lb/>
     only close up for about a year, and Canada 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="5550" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5550.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="num">5550 </fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Supply—External Affairs</hi></fw>
     <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
     
     
   
     
     get out of it altogether, we would be better 
     <lb/>
     off and have a chance of peace and security. 
     <lb/>
     ERP or the Marshall plan is just a blueprint. 
     <lb/>
     As the Archbishop of Canterbury said the 
     <lb/>
     other day in England, he was greatly disap<lb break="no"/>pointed in Lake Success and the way the 
     <lb/>
     empire had been dissolved. I quoted his 
     <lb/>
     remarks in the house the other night and I 
     <lb/>
     will not do so again. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am absolutely opposed to the policy of 
     <lb/>
     this government on foreign affairs. I believe 
     <lb/>
     that this item should be reduced to reason<lb break="no"/>able proportions, to about $1,000,000 a year. 
     <lb/>
     That would be plenty to spend on such agencies 
     <lb/>
     as are now proposed, because you have no 
     <lb/>
     foreign policy except the UNO. That is the 
     <lb/>
     cornerstone of it. What has the UNO done? 
     <lb/>
     It has just dissolved the whole British empire. 
     <lb/>
     They want us to give up our bases on the 
     <lb/>
     seven seas. If we do so, you know what will 
     <lb/>
     happen. We shall have the enemy out here. 
     <lb/>
     Owing to this league of nations, we lost two 
     <lb/>
     of our great allies in the first war. In the 
     <lb/>
     second war you have lost one of them already. 
     <lb/>
     I can tell you this, that if you just keep on 
     <lb/>
     pretending for another year we shall be just 
     <lb/>
     as close to war as we were in 1939, when the 
     <lb/>
     second war broke out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: I believe I had the 
     <lb/>
     floor, but I took my seat to allow the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member to ask a question—and with the 
     <lb/>
     result the committee has seen. However I 
     <lb/>
     am quite willing to sit down again if the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Muskoka-Ontario wishes 
     <lb/>
     to ask a question—because I hope it will be 
     <lb/>
     a question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD8">Mr. MACDONNELL</persName> (Muskoka-Ontario): 
     <lb/>
     It will be a question, and one in regard to 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland—which I take it we can now 
     <lb/>
     return to. I wish to ask this question on the 
     <lb/>
     point made by the minister as to the con<lb break="no"/>stitutional position. I understand that posi<lb break="no"/>tion clearly, and I would ask another ques<lb break="no"/>tion, which, it seems to me, is relevant. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Supposing in fact that the constitutional 
     <lb/>
     requirements the minister has outlined are 
     <lb/>
     complied with, but that nevertheless we 
     <lb/>
     know there is a strong minority—perhaps 
     <lb/>
     almost half the people in Newfoundland— 
     <lb/>
     who are opposed to any union with us; in the 
     <lb/>
     minister's opinion would that be a matter 
     <lb/>
     of indifference to us? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: No, I do not think 
     <lb/>
     it would be a, matter of indifference to us. 
     <lb/>
     But. we have made an offer to the consti— 
     <lb/>
     tuted authorities of Newfoundland, and I 
     <lb/>
     do not think we could back away from that 
     <lb/>
     offer if the constituted authorities came to 
     <lb/>
     us and said, "The majority in Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     want confederation." Of course this parlia<lb break="no"/>ment might be disposed to say there is not 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     such a decisive majority, in spite of the 
     <lb/>
     statement made by the constituted 
     <lb/>
     authorities, as would require or justify the 
     <lb/>
     carrying out of the offer we made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     My own personal view with respect to 
     <lb/>
     these negotiations has been that it would be 
     <lb/>
     a serious responsibility to do or say anything 
     <lb/>
     which would prevent the entry of Newfound<lb break="no"/>land into Canada. I may be an optimist, 
     <lb/>
     but I do believe that the Canadian nation 
     <lb/>
     is destined to occupy an important place 
     <lb/>
     in world affairs. I do believe, further, that 
     <lb/>
     that place in world affairs would be better 
     <lb/>
     preserved by a territory which extended 
     <lb/>
     right out to the broad ocean and if access 
     <lb/>
     thereto was not closed to Canada by another 
     <lb/>
     sovereignty over the territories of Newfound<lb break="no"/>land and Labrador. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Because of that attitude, we made offers 
     <lb/>
     which would involve quite costly require<lb break="no"/>ments from the Canadian people at the 
     <lb/>
     present time. But I think we would have 
     <lb/>
     been remiss in our duty to future generations 
     <lb/>
     of Canadians not to have done so. That 
     <lb/>
     offer having been made, if there is a desire 
     <lb/>
     on the part of the people of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     to accept it, I think the government will 
     <lb/>
     be disposed to recommend to parliament that 
     <lb/>
     it be implemented. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It might be that there would come about 
     <lb/>
     in Newfoundland a division of opinion that 
     <lb/>
     would show that the time was not ripe for 
     <lb/>
     union to take place, and that it would not 
     <lb/>
     be easy to have it work satisfactorily in what 
     <lb/>
     would then be a new province. That is 
     <lb/>
     something which I hope we shall not have 
     <lb/>
     to face, and about which I would prefer not 
     <lb/>
     to have to express any views, unless we do 
     <lb/>
     have to face it. I hope there will be a clear-<lb break="yes"/>cut decision in this second vote. I hope it 
     <lb/>
     will not be so close as to leave us in the 
     <lb/>
     embarrassing position of having to take in 
     <lb/>
     a large group of recalcitrants, or having to 
     <lb/>
     renounce the opportunity of completing 
     <lb/>
     what the fathers of confederation originally 
     <lb/>
     intended. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD8">Mr. MACDONNELL</persName> (Muskoka-Ontario): 
     <lb/>
     One further supplementary question, if I may. 
     <lb/>
     I did not understand the minister to say— 
     <lb/>
     at least I hope I did not—that by our action 
     <lb/>
     we have put it beyond our .power to go back 
     <lb/>
     if, in fact, there is now a legal acceptance, 
     <lb/>
     legally given to Newfoundland, but with a 
     <lb/>
     strong and large dissenting minority. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. ST. LAURENT</persName>: That matter would be 
     <lb/>one which would have to be faced in a states<lb break="no"/>manlike manner by the authorities in the<lb/>United Kingdom and those in Canada. They<lb/>are the ones who have legal jurisdiction. I am<lb/>reminded of the view I expressed about demo<lb break="no"/>
            
            <pb n="5551" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-19_Page_5551.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">JUNE 19, 1948</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Supply-External Affairs</hi></fw> <fw type="num">5551</fw>
            
     cracy. In a democracy the will of the majority 
     <lb/>
     must prevail; but a majority should not impose 
     <lb/>
     a decision that is not in the real interests of 
     <lb/>
     the community, or without giving careful con<lb break="no"/>sideration to the views of the minority and 
     <lb/>
     the reasons for those views. And I think that 
     <lb/>
     when the time comes for a decision as to 
     <lb/>
     whether this will he proceeded with or not, the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian government and the United King<lb break="no"/>dom government will have to take into con<lb break="no"/>sideration the facts as they will have appeared 
     <lb/>
     from the vote of the people of Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then the hon. member for Stanstead asked 
     <lb/>
     me to deal with two or three other questions, 
     <lb/>
     one of which had to do with the St. Lawrence 
     <lb/>
     seaway. Members of the committee will 
     <lb/>
     recall that the basic agreement was signed in 
     <lb/>
     March, 1941, was referred to the senate com<lb break="no"/>mittee on foreign affairs in the United States, 
     <lb/>
     and favourably reported upon this year. But 
     <lb/>
     it was recommitted to the committee on 
     <lb/>
     foreign affairs by a vote in the senate of the 
     <lb/>
     United States on February 27, 1948. That was 
     <lb/>
     a vote of fifty-seven to thirty. It is there<lb break="no"/>fore not being proceeded with expeditiously 
     <lb/>
     by the United States senate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There have been reports in the newspapers 
     <lb/>
     as to the desire of Ontario and the state of 
     <lb/>
     New York to proceed with certain power 
     <lb/>
     developments; but there have been no official 
     <lb/>
     communications to the government of Canada 
     <lb/>
     in that regard and, so far as I know, no appli<lb break="no"/>cation to the international joint commission 
     <lb/>
     with respect thereto. There is nothing I can 
     <lb/>
     communicate to the committee beyond the 
     <lb/>
     information I have obtained from the reading 
     <lb/>
     of reports in the newspapers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then the hon. member asked me about the 
     <lb/>
     royal style and titles. As hon. members will 
     <lb/>
     recall, an act of this parliament was passed 
     <lb/>
     last year expressing the acquiescence of Canada 
     <lb/>
     in the dropping from the royal style and titles 
     <lb/>
     of the words, "Emperor of India". We are 
     <lb/>
     informed that a proclamation will be issued by 
     <lb/>
     His Majesty fixing June 22 as the date from 
     <lb/>
     which those words will be dropped from the 
     <lb/>
     royal style and titles in the United Kingdom, 
     <lb/>
     and the governor in council has adopted a 
     <lb/>
     minute of council to have a notice to that 
     <lb/>
     effect published in the official gazette, when 
     <lb/>
     we get confirmation that that is the date to be 
     <lb/>
     acted upon in the United Kingdom. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. member asked if there had been 
     <lb/>
     any changes in our relations with the South 
     <lb/>
     African government since the election. There 
     <lb/>
     have been no changes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then he asked what has been done toward 
     <lb/>
     building up our relations with western Europe 
     <lb/>
     and other members of the commonwealth. 
     <lb/>
     There has been nothing accomplished, but what 
     <lb/>
     we have been doing was recently reported in 
     <lb/>

<cb/>

     the Ottawa <hi rendition="simple:italic">Journal</hi> as a crusade by Canada for 
     <lb/>
     the completion of a western union or north 
     <lb/>
     Atlantic regional pact. I think that title, of 
     <lb/>
     course, perhaps justly describes the attitude we 
     <lb/>
     have adopted. We feel that, should war break 
     <lb/>
     out that affected the United Kingdom and the 
     <lb/>
     United States, we would inevitably be in<lb break="no"/>volved and that there might be great value in 
     <lb/>
     having consummated a regional pact whereby 
     <lb/>
     these western European countries, the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom and the United States and ourselves, 
     <lb/>
     would guarantee each other's security. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We had hoped that the united nations would 
     <lb/>
     guarantee the security of all of us, but that 
     <lb/>
     has not been accomplished, and we think there 
     <lb/>
     would be value in a regional pact whereby 
     <lb/>
     these western European democracies, the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom, the United States and ourselves 
     <lb/>
     agreed to stand together, to pool for defence 
     <lb/>
     purposes our respective potentials and co<lb break="no"/>ordinate right away our forces, so that it would 
     <lb/>
     appear to any possible aggressor that he would 
     <lb/>
     have to be prepared to overcome us all if he 
     <lb/>
     attempted any aggression. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We do not think a pact that did not include 
     <lb/>
     those major powers would be sufliciently im<lb break="no"/>pressive to require us to be a party to it. We 
     <lb/>
     think this western union is a good thing, but 
     <lb/>
     our adhesion to it without the United States 
     <lb/>
     would add very little to it. We are hopeful 
     <lb/>
     that it will develop into something which will 
     <lb/>
     comprise the United States along with those 
     <lb/>
     who are already members, and in that event 
     <lb/>
     we think the people of Canada would wish that 
     <lb/>
     we also be associated with it, not because we 
     <lb/>
     want to assert domination over anyone, but 
     <lb/>
     because we realize that if the group in this 
     <lb/>
     regional pact became involved in war we would 
     <lb/>
     necessarily be involved with them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That is something that the people of 
     <lb/>
     Canada might prefer to avoid, but it is some<lb break="no"/>thing which they could not avoid even if they 
     <lb/>
     wished to. That being so, if there is any 
     <lb/>
     value in preparedness we think the people of 
     <lb/>
     Canada would be glad to see us making that 
     <lb/>
     preparation in a co-ordinated fashion with 
     <lb/>
     others whose way of life is the same as ours 
     <lb/>
     and whose security is part of our own security. 
     <lb/>
     That has not proceeded very far, although 
     <lb/>
     there has been the adoption by an overwhelm<lb break="no"/>ing majority in the United States senate of 
     <lb/>
     Senator Vandenberg's resolution recommending 
     <lb/>
     the setting up of such a. security group. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. member asked what our relations 
     <lb/>
     were with the members of the commonwealth. 
     <lb/>
     Our relations with the members of the com<lb break="no"/>monwealth revolve around the United King<lb break="no"/>dom as being the pivot of the commonwealth. 
     <lb/>
     We do not think anything that the United [...] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>