<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1870-03-28"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-03-28">28 March 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
 
         
         <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="730" to="730"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-28_Page_0730.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
          
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-28_Page_0730">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-28_Page_0730.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="730" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-28_Page_0730.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">730</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               March 28, 1870<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
            <p>
               deep interest in the improvement of the navi<lb break="no"/>gation of the Ottawa, and he was satisfied that 
               <lb/>
               the policy of the Government in this matter 
               <lb/>
               was the correct one. That, as already 
               <lb/>
               announced by the Minister of Public Works, 
               <lb/>
               was to first improve the navigation between 
               <lb/>
               Montreal and Ottawa. The hon. member for 
               <lb/>
               South Renfrew had charged the Government 
               <lb/>
               with discouraging trade with other countries; 
               <lb/>
               but such was not the fact. With regard to the 
               <lb/>
               West Indies, he was not aware that there was 
               <lb/>
               anything to prevent commerce with these 
               <lb/>
               countries. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. McDougall (South Renfrew) said the 
               <lb/>
               Government had discouraged trade with other 
               <lb/>
               countries when they voted against the proposi<lb break="no"/>tion to trade directly with other countries. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Sir Francis Hincks said he did not 
               <lb/>
               understand what the hon. gentleman meant. 
               <lb/>
               There was nothing to prevent trade with the 
               <lb/>
               West Indies. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Halton—Will you state what has 
               <lb/>
               been done of late years as to suggestions made 
               <lb/>
               in the report of the Trade Committee? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Sir Francis Hincks said the chief 
               <lb/>
               object of that report was with reference to 
               <lb/>
               postal communication. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Holton—Does the Hon. Finance 
               <lb/>
               Minister admit that the report of the Commis<lb break="no"/>sion has fallen still-born? That project, which 
               <lb/>
               has been referred to in speeches from the 
               <lb/>
               Throne, and which he vaunted as a substitute 
               <lb/>
               for Reciprocity has been a failure. (Hear, 
               <lb/>
               hear.) 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Sir Francis Hincks said the principal 
               <lb/>
               recommendation of the report had reference to 
               <lb/>
               postal communication. That subject had 
               <lb/>
               engaged the most anxious attention of the Post 
               <lb/>
               Office Department since the time of the Com<lb break="no"/>mission. But a number of circumstances had 
               <lb/>
               intervened to prevent the establishment of a 
               <lb/>
               postal communication with the West Indies. 
               <lb/>
               The principal of these was the delay of New<lb break="no"/>foundland in coming into the Confederation. A 
               <lb/>
               scheme of communication with the West Indies 
               <lb/>
               had been arranged and would have been estab<lb break="no"/>lished if Newfoundland had entered the Union. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. McDonald (Middlesex West) thought 
               <lb/>
               that the eight feet depth of the Erie Canal 
               <lb/>
               would be sufficient. It would cost $32,000,000 to 
               <lb/>
               make it ten feet, and not above half that sum to 
               <lb/>
               make it eight feet. 
               </p>
            
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>