<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1947-05-06"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1947-05-06">6 May 1947</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Twentieth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
         

           <date when="1947"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmond Cloutier, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="2825" to="2825"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1947-05-06_Page_2825.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
      
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1947-05-06_Page_2825">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1947-05-06_Page_2825.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="2825" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1947-05-06_Page_2825.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
               MAY 6, 1947 
             
            </fw>
             <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Private Bills 
             </hi></fw>
               
            <fw type="num">
               2825 
               </fw>
      
            <p>
               Mr. CHURCH: I want to ask one question 
               <lb/>
               about section 7. We are giving the company 
               <lb/>
               the right to build a railway and, as the Secre<lb break="no"/>tary of State for External Affairs said the 
               <lb/>
               other night, we can only give them jurisdiction 
               <lb/>
               in Canada, and only capacity to act. I would 
               <lb/>
               call the attention of the government to a 
               <lb/>
               meeting held today between fifteen representa<lb break="no"/>tives of Newfoundland and the British govern<lb break="no"/>ment in London, England, regarding New<lb break="no"/>foundland's future government. The repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of Newfoundland were insisting that 
               <lb/>
               Labrador be part of that country, and said 
               <lb/>
               they are now to come to Canada in June and 
               <lb/>
               go into the question of the tenth province of 
               <lb/>
               Canada's federation, Newfoundland and Lab<lb break="no"/>rador, and the whole future of it. Under 
               <lb/>
               section 7 the company is given power to act, 
               <lb/>
               capacity powers only as a corporation to con<lb break="no"/>struct within Canada. To proceed with con<lb break="no"/>struction beyond Canada. they will have to 
               <lb/>
               deal with Newfoundland. and Labrador. I under<lb break="no"/>stand that they dealt with them twenty years 
               <lb/>
               ago but spent only about $100,000. While I 
               <lb/>
               do not believe in railways and coal mines and 
               <lb/>
               electric distribution systems being taken over 
               <lb/>
               as is now being done in England, I believe that 
               <lb/>
               the Canadian National Railways should have 
               <lb/>
               had a survey made of this territory not only 
               <lb/>
               in Canada but in Labrador. The policy of 
               <lb/>
               our national railway in the past has been to go 
               <lb/>
               into territories far less profitable than this 
               <lb/>
               proposition may turn out to be. While 
               <lb/>
               these mining men are going in at their own 
               <lb/>
               expense and surveys have been made under 
               <lb/>
               section 7, the fact remains that we are giving 
               <lb/>
               away public property. We have only the 
               <lb/>
               capacity to give the company railway and 
               <lb/>
               subsidiary powers to operate within Canada. 
               <lb/>
               For anything else the company wants outside 
               <lb/>
               Canada, hotels, power, highways, ocean services, 
               <lb/>
               vessels, elevators, wharves, it will have to deal 
               <lb/>
               with the provisional government of Labrador 
               <lb/>
               and Newfoundland. I would: ask the Secretary 
               <lb/>
               of State for External Affairs if that is not 
               <lb/>
               right? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
            
            <p>
               Mr. ST. LAURENT: I think the hon. 
               <lb/>
               gentleman is quite right, though perhaps not 
               <lb/>
               quite complete. The purposes of this bill as 
               <lb/>
               I read it are two-fold. One is to incorporate a 
               <lb/>
               company, thereby giving it the capacity to 
               <lb/>
               acquire powers through any jurisdiction that 
               <lb/>
               may be willing to grant powers to it; and the 
               <lb/>
               other is to build a railway from a point on 
               <lb/>
               the St. Lawrence in Quebec to the border 
               <lb/>
               between Quebec and Labrador. That is some<lb break="no"/>thing which, under the British North America 
               <lb/>
               Act, can be granted only by parliament. There 
               <lb/>
               is no doubt that the parliament of Canada 
               <lb/>
               cannot grant the right to the company to build 
               <lb/>
               
         
            
         
            <!--<p>
               83166—180 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>-->


               a railway in Labrador, but the parliament of 
               <lb/>
               Canada can grant the capacity to the corpora<lb break="no"/>tion to go to the government of Labrador and 
               <lb/>
               acquire from that government the right to 
               <lb/>
               build in the territory governed by the com<lb break="no"/>mission government. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. POULIOT: A moment ago I heard one 
               <lb/>
               hon. member say that he has the right to argue 
               <lb/>
               in this committee just as well as in the railway 
               <lb/>
               committee. He is perfectly right. The differ<lb break="no"/>ence is that in the railway committee wit<lb break="no"/>nesses and experts can be heard and be asked 
               <lb/>
               questions to satisfy the minds of hon. members 
               <lb/>
               who desire information. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               (Translation) : 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Chairman, in order to ascertain the 
               <lb/>
               opinion of the provincial government in re<lb break="no"/>gard to this bill, I sent a copy thereof to 
               <lb/>
               the premier of Quebec, asking him to kindly 
               <lb/>
               let me have his views.
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I received today the following telegram, 
               <lb/>
               copy of which I shall hand over to the hon. 
               <lb/>
               member for Outremont (Mr. Rinfret). It 
               <lb/>
               reads as follows: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               Thank you for your kindness in sending me 
               <lb/>
               copy of Bill "H" <hi rendition="simple:italic">re</hi> Quebec North Shore and 
               <lb/>
               Labrador Railway Company, which I have re<lb break="no"/>ceived this morning, a few moments before the 
               <lb/>
               house met. Insofar as the territory of the prov<lb break="no"/>ince of Quebec is concerned, it is obvious that 
               <lb/>
               the provincial authorities alone have the power 
               <lb/>
               to deal with hotels, water power and their 
               <lb/>
               operation as well as with transportation by 
               <lb/>
               truck, bus and automobile. In the province of 
               <lb/>
               Quebec, there are proper agencies having the 
               <lb/>
               power and the duty to supervise and control the 
               <lb/>
               operations arising from the use of highways and 
               <lb/>
               the development of provincial natural resources. 
               <lb/>
               As always, we are prepared to cooperate sin<lb break="no"/>cerely with the federal authorities in order to 
               <lb/>
               solve the problems which concern both the 
               <lb/>
               dominion and the provincial authorities, accord<lb break="no"/>ing to their respective constitutional rights and 
               <lb/>
               on a friendly basis if possible. However, you 
               <lb/>
               understand that encroachments can never serve 
               <lb/>
               as a basis for cooperation. Again I thank you 
               <lb/>
               for your courtesy in this connection. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Maurice L. Duplessis. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               I wish to ask the hon. member who has 
               <lb/>
               sponsored this bill whether it is the intention 
               <lb/>
               of the company to have subsidiary companies 
               <lb/>
               exercise the rights which may be granted to 
               <lb/>
               it under this bill. It is necessary to distinguish 
               <lb/>
               as between the right itself and the power to 
               <lb/>
               exercise such right. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               This information would be of great inter<lb break="no"/>est to the public. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               (Text): 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Mr. RINFRET: I do not think the general 
               <lb/>
               remarks just made by the hon. member for 
               <lb/>
               Temiscouata apply to section 7. They might 
               <lb/>
               apply to section 11. I will reserve my reply 
               <lb/>
               until we reach that section. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>