<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1869-06-11"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-06-11">11 June 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
  
         
           <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

           <date when="1975"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="740" to="742"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0740.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0741.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0742.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0740">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0740.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0741">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0741.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0742">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0742.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="740" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0740.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">740</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 11, 1869</fw>
            
            <p>
               constitutional barrier in the way of their 
               <lb/>
               adding to those grants. Stress had been laid 
               <lb/>
               on the words "for the public service of Can<lb break="no"/>ada." These were not to be interpreted too 
               <lb/>
               rigidly. They could not be held as restricting 
               <lb/>
               them from voting a sum for the relief of pub<lb break="no"/>lic distress abroad. We could not withhold 
               <lb/>
               what the Union Act gave Nova Scotia; but 
               <lb/>
               we could give more if we pleased. The mem<lb break="no"/>ber for West Durham had referred to an Act 
               <lb/>
               of the Ontario Government voting money to 
               <lb/>
               Judges as <hi rendition="simple:italic">ultra vires</hi>; but what was the main 
               <lb/>
               objection to that Act? He did not under<lb break="no"/>stand that it was said a Provincial Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture could vote money only for provincial pur<lb break="no"/>poses; but the objection was that it had 
               <lb/>
               contravened a great object of public policy 
               <lb/>
               by putting Judges in the position of serving 
               <lb/>
               two masters. The Ontario and Quebec Legis<lb break="no"/>latures had both of them voted money for 
               <lb/>
               the relief of distress in Nova Scotia and at 
               <lb/>
               Red River. No one could say that their so 
               <lb/>
               doing was unconstitutional. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald said those who were 
               <lb/>
               in favour of Confederation would vote against 
               <lb/>
               the amendment. (Loud cries of No, No). It 
               <lb/>
               was well that the veil should be removed 
               <lb/>
               and the position exactly understood. It was 
               <lb/>
               well that the member for Lambton, by second<lb break="no"/>ing this amendment, had at last revealed his 
               <lb/>
               true position as an enemy to Confederation. 
               <lb/>
               (Cries of No, No, and ironical cheers.) That 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentleman had claimed to be a friend 
               <lb/>
               of Confederation and had made all kinds of 
               <lb/>
               professions on the subject. But when he found 
               <lb/>
               the key-stone of Confederation was about to 
               <lb/>
               be put in its place, without which all other 
               <lb/>
               efforts were useless, the hon. gentleman for 
               <lb/>
               party considerations, negated all his pre<lb break="no"/>vious professions. Rather than see Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion carried out by the present Government, 
               <lb/>
               to which he was opposed, he would insidious<lb break="no"/>ly, if not openly, oppose it. (No, No.) The ob<lb break="no"/>ject of Confederation was to bring all British 
               <lb/>
               North America into one Union. We were now 
               <lb/>
               incorporating the North-West, we were about 
               <lb/>
               to admit Newfoundland. All that remained 
               <lb/>
               was this measure to pacify Nova Scotia and 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentlemen opposite were found opposing 
               <lb/>
               it. If the gentlemen opposite were successful, 
               <lb/>
               then there would be a jubilee among anti- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               Unionists, and such classes in Nova Scotia, 
               <lb/>
               throughout Canada, and outside of the Domi<lb break="no"/>nion as well. Let them reconcile Nova Scotia 
               <lb/>
               —the very keystone of the Dominion. The 
               <lb/>
               people of that Province at first refused to 
               <lb/>
               come into the Union, but now were about to 
               <lb/>
               be reconciled.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <pb n="741" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0741.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               11 juin 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p>
               Mr. Le Vesconte—No, no! 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald—The whole action 
               <lb/>
               of the Local Legislature showed that they 
               <lb/>
               accepted it. This very day the Treasurer of 
               <lb/>
               Nova Scotia had telegraphed that he hoped 
               <lb/>
               the grant was made, that he might get the 
               <lb/>
               money. (Great laughter.) There might be 
               <lb/>
               some few fossils like his hon. friend from 
               <lb/>
               Richmond, old tories like himself who did not 
               <lb/>
               care to change, but except a few like him the 
               <lb/>
               people of Nova Scotia had accepted it. A 
               <lb/>
               majority of the representatives of Nova Scotia 
               <lb/>
               in this House had accepted it, and the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of Nova Scotia had accepted it. The 
               <lb/>
               simple question raised by this amendment 
               <lb/>
               was Confederation or no Confederation. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Holton—I thought that was settled 
               <lb/>
               long ago. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald—It was settled by 
               <lb/>
               law in 1867 against the desire and vote of 
               <lb/>
               that hon. gentleman and ever since he had 
               <lb/>
               done all in his power to obstruct it. The mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Durham West had contended that this 
               <lb/>
               matter was one to be settled by England. 
               <lb/>
               Hon. gentlemen would give up to the Imperial 
               <lb/>
               Parliament the control of our money and a 
               <lb/>
               different doctrine was laid down in the dis<lb break="no"/>cussion on the Governor-General's salary. It 
               <lb/>
               was then decided by the member for Oxford 
               <lb/>
               South that for the Imperial authorities to in<lb break="no"/>terfere with us in that matter was to trample 
               <lb/>
               on the liberties of the people of Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie—Order. If the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man seeks to make out his argument by drag<lb break="no"/>ging in matters foreign to this debate, I ask 
               <lb/>
               the interference of the Speaker. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The Speaker <hi rendition="simple:italic">pro tem</hi>., Hon. Mr. Blanchet, 
               <lb/>
               said the Minister of Justice was out of order 
               <lb/>
               in alluding to a previous debate. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald said any gentleman 
               <lb/>
               going to the library and looking over the 
               <lb/>
               newspapers, would find that such words were 
               <lb/>
               used in a certain Colonial Parliament with 
               <lb/>
               reference to the Governor's salary: but the 
               <lb/>
               question was whether this arrangement was 
               <lb/>
               a right one or a wrong one. If they admitted 
               <lb/>
               it was a right one they should place it in the 
               <lb/>
               hands of the Government to carry it out. This 
               <lb/>
               amendment was a mean motion—an attempt 
               <lb/>
               by a side wind to prevent the success of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, instead of fairly meeting the ques<lb break="no"/>tion. The argument of the member for West 
               <lb/>
               Durham was hardly worth replying to. His 
               <lb/>
               
     
            <pb n="742" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-11_Page_0742.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">742</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               June 11, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
         
               answer to it was that as a Parliament they 
               <lb/>
               had a right to do what they pleased with their 
               <lb/>
               own. They might draw it away if they pleased. 
               <lb/>
               It constituted the difference between a free 
               <lb/>
               and a servile people to retain or give up the 
               <lb/>
               control of their own money. Recently the col<lb break="no"/>onists of Red River had been afflicted by a 
               <lb/>
               plague of locusts. Suppose a similar disaster 
               <lb/>
               were to happen Ontario, causing a failure of 
               <lb/>
               its crops and a state of famine, and it was 
               <lb/>
               proposed to vote money to relieve the distress; 
               <lb/>
               such a vote could not be made according to the 
               <lb/>
               argument which had been presented from the 
               <lb/>
               other side. He repeated that this was a blow 
               <lb/>
               at the Union, and looking at the division 
               <lb/>
               on the Newfoundland resolutions yesterday, 
               <lb/>
               there would be found the same lurking desire 
               <lb/>
               to impede the wheels of Confederation. If this 
               <lb/>
               motion carried there would be a jubilee among 
               <lb/>
               the avowed anti-Confederate rebels, and An<lb break="no"/>nexationists of Nova Scotia, and it would be 
               <lb/>
               the cause of corresponding depression to those 
               <lb/>
               in that-Province who desire the Union to be 
               <lb/>
               successful. If the hon. gentlemen repudiated 
               <lb/>
               this arrangement which had been entered 
               <lb/>
               into with Nova Scotia, they would give a 
               <lb/>
               death-blow to Confederation, and on them, 
               <lb/>
               not on him, would rest the responsibility of 
               <lb/>
               so suicidal an act. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Halton made a motion of adjourn<lb break="no"/>ment to allow a reply to be made by the gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen attacked by the Minister of Justice. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie desired to say a few words 
               <lb/>
               in reply to the very extraordinary attack made 
               <lb/>
               by the Premier on himself, and also on those 
               <lb/>
               with whom he usually acted. He had never 
               <lb/>
               witnessed a more unjustifiable attack made in 
               <lb/>
               this House. It was no new thing, however, for 
               <lb/>
               the hon. gentleman to make such attacks. It 
               <lb/>
               was part of his tactics. Those who had sat in 
               <lb/>
               Parliament with that hon. gentleman so long 
               <lb/>
               as he had done could recall many instances in 
               <lb/>
               which, when worsted in argument, when he 
               <lb/>
               found the sense of the House was against him, 
               <lb/>
               and the leading men of his own party forced 
               <lb/>
               to take ground against the position he occu<lb break="no"/>pied, he tried to simulate passion and at<lb break="no"/>tempted to cover his weakness by hurling un<lb break="no"/>founded reproaches at his opponents. The hon. 
               <lb/>
               gentleman and his satellites had sought to 
               <lb/>
               defeat him at his election in '67 by calling him 
               <lb/>
               a disunionist; but, when he came here and as<lb break="no"/>sisted the Government in carrying the very 
               <lb/>
               measure necessary to the completion of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, they complimented him as a friend 
               <lb/>
               of Union. Now, however, because he did not 
               <lb/>
               choose to accept the hon. gentleman's mode of 
               <lb/>
               settling this difficulty, which he looked upon 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>