<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1870-03-18" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-03-18">18 March 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1870">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
   
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

           <date when="1979"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="531" to="532"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-18_Page_0531.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-18_Page_0532.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-18_Page_0531">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-18_Page_0531.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-18_Page_0532">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-18_Page_0532.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="531" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-18_Page_0531.jpg"/>
           <!-- <fw type="dateline">
               18 mars 1870 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p>
              [...] habiliments of the Government even to those 
               <lb/>
               satin breeches, which seemed at this moment 
               <lb/>
               the great topic of conversation in Ontario? 
               <lb/>
               (Great laughter.) 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BOLT1">Mr. Bolton</persName> said, he was prepared to yield <lb/> many points in a
               measure of compromise; but <lb/> the question of the ballot was one which was <lb/>
               very popular in New Brunswick, and the re<lb break="no"/>moval of which would be
               regarded as a great <lb/> injury, and he hoped the Government would <lb/> consent to
               allow the ballot to be still enjoyed <lb/> in New Brunswick, though in all other
               <lb/> respects, the law might be made uniform in all <lb/> the Provinces. Such a
               course would be no <lb/> injury to the other Provinces, and would allow <lb/> New
               Brunswick to continue to enjoy what they <lb/> considered a great boon. In other
               points the <lb/> people of New Brunswick would yield their <lb/> opinions if they
               would be allowed to retain the <lb/> ballot. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSS10">Mr. Ross</persName> (Victoria, N.S.) During the eight <lb/> years that I
               had the honour of a seat in the <lb/> Parliament of Nova Scotia, I had no desire to
               <lb/> be considered anything more than one of its <lb/> silent members, and here
               also, I have no desire <lb/> to take up the time by imposing my ideas on <lb/> the
               attention of the House, but the franchise of <lb/> the country is a matter in which
               we are all <lb/> interested, and I would like to say a little on <lb/> that subject.
               I have examined carefully the <lb/> Franchise Act now before the House, and find
               <lb/> that at least one-fourth of my constituency will <lb/> be disfranchised by it,
               and that will apply to <lb/> the whole Province of Nova Scotia. I was <lb/> pleased
               to find the Minister of Justice state <lb/> that he had no doubt but the Bill would
               be <lb/> largely amended in committee; and I hope it <lb/> will be cut up, dissected
               and disembowelled, so <lb/> that when it passed its various stages very <lb/> little
               more than the name would be left. The <lb/> present franchise has worked well in Nova
               <lb/> Scotia, and there is no desire to have it <lb/> changed. If, then, the
               Government desire to <lb/> have the franchise under their own control, all <lb/> that
               they have to do is to appoint their own <lb/> officers to prepare the rolls, and then
               they will <lb/> have all the guards necessary to have every<lb break="no"/>thing they
               require. In this progressive age, <lb/> when Conservative England is extending the
               <lb/> franchise in all parts of the Empire, will it be <lb/> said that in her name
               have been curtailed the <lb/> responsibilities and privileges already con<lb break="no"/>ferred on the people? Once you confer the fran<lb break="no"/>chise on
               a people, taking it away again will be <lb/> considered and resented as a grievance.
               It is <lb/> quite evident that the Government have aban<lb break="no"/>doned all hope
               of having Newfoundland <lb/> brought into this Union, or to have the intend<lb break="no"/><pb n="532" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-18_Page_0532.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">532</fw>
               <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
               <fw type="dateline"> March 18, 1870<lb/>
               </fw>ed franchise extended to that Province; for, <lb/> under its operation, you
               would not poll 8,000 <lb/> votes outside of St. John's and Harbour Grace. <lb/> The
               simultaneous polling Act was first intro<lb break="no"/>duced in Nova Scotia by the
               present Judge in <lb/> Equity, and its operation has proved a great <lb/> blessing to
               us in preserving peace and order, <lb/> and preventing riots and bloodshed in many
               <lb/> counties where political feeling ran high. <lb/> Taking this great blessing
               away from us will <lb/> be doing us a great injury, and one that is <lb/> calculated
               to restore trouble and confusion, <lb/> when all this would be avoided by permitting
               <lb/> us to retain this beneficial feature in the Act <lb/> refused. If the
               Government will not extend <lb/> this Act to all parts of the Dominion, I hope <lb/>
               they will allow it still to be retained in Nova <lb/> Scotia. The hon. member from
               St. John stated <lb/> what a loss it would be to England if the <lb/> present Prime
               Minister would have lost his <lb/> election; but, suppose that he was to be <lb/>
               removed by death, would not the Government <lb/> of England go on the same as ever,
               and would <lb/> not the country prosper as if he never had <lb/> existed? Suppose
               that the member from St. <lb/> John would be defeated at the next election—a <lb/>
               calamity we would all have to deplore—but if <lb/> such a thing could be possible,
               what then but <lb/> that the people of St. John would have <lb/> returned another
               member—certainly not one <lb/> possessing as much eloquence or as much mili<lb break="no"/>tary experience—but possessing more indepen<lb break="no"/>dence than
               the present member. Great men <lb/> change sides, and are removed; and many think
               <lb/> that if some of the members of the present <lb/> Government were cast aside
               that better men <lb/> would replace them; but one thing certain is, <lb/> that the
               prosperity of the country would not be <lb/> retarded, should some of them at any
               time lose <lb/> their seats at an election. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               On motion of Mr. Fortin, the debate was 
               <lb/>
               adjourned. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The House then adjourned at 12:35 am. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>