<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1868-04-06" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1868-04-06">6 April 1868</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1867-1868">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
  
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, First Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1967"/>.   
          

           <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Roger Duhamel</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="466"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1868-04-06_Page_0466.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
          
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-29">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-29">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Naik_Armand" when="2017-01-16">Marked-up people. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1868-04-06_Page_0466">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1868-04-06_Page_0466.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="466" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1868-04-06_Page_0466.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">466</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES<lb/></fw><fw type="dateline"> April 6, 1868 <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:GIBB1">Mr. Gibbs</persName> said he had no hesitation in <lb/> giving the vote he
               had done the other day, <lb/> but the remarks of the honourable member <lb/> were
               rather ungracious, coming from a gen<lb break="no"/>tleman who introduced his last
               resolution <lb/> well knowing, from the fate of the first, that <lb/> the information
               asked for would not be <lb/> granted, and who, because he could not get <lb/> all,
               would take none. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said that the motion moved <lb/> by the honourable
               member for Chateauguay, <lb/> to which allusion had been made, was one <lb/>
               suggested by the member of South Lennox, <lb/> and spoken favourably of by the
               members for <lb/> Renfrew and South Ontario. One of these <lb/> gentlemen having
               suggested the motion to the <lb/> member for Chateauguay with whom they <lb/> had
               been in accord in bank sentiments, noth<lb break="no"/>ing was more natural than that
               honourable <lb/> gentleman should make the motion, and he <lb/> (Mr. Mackenzie)
               confessed, however, that he <lb/> was never more astonished in his life than to <lb/>
               see one member after another member stand <lb/> up and vote against this very motion.
               (Hear <lb/> and laughter). <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART3">Mr. Cartwright</persName> was free to acknowledge he <lb/> did suggest the
               motion, but he bowed to the <lb/> judgment of the Minister of Justice in the <lb/>
               matter, who had desired that compliance with <lb/> the resolution would be adverse to
               the public <lb/> interest. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said that not a single mem<lb break="no"/>ber of
               the Ministry said the motion of the <lb/> member for Chateauguay was adverse to the
               <lb/> public interest. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:GALT1">Hon. Mr. Galt</persName> protested against its being <lb/> taken for
               granted that the Government were <lb/> at a great disadvantage in consequence of
               <lb/> their arrangement with the Bank of Mont<lb break="no"/>real. He wished to bear
               his testimony to the <lb/> fair dealing of that institution towards the <lb/>
               Government. In circumstances of very con<lb break="no"/>siderable financial difficulty
               the Government <lb/> had received assistance from the Bank of <lb/> Montreal, the
               absence of which would per<lb break="no"/>haps have proved exceedingly embarrassing
               to <lb/> the Ministry of the day. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> At six o'clock the House rose.<lb/>
After the recess.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> having obtained leave to <lb/> speak, said he did
               not decide to allow the <lb/> statement of the member for Chateauguay to <lb/> pass
               unchallenged. Now, he would state once <lb/> for all, that the Government desired to
               give <lb/> the fullest information of all the transactions <lb/>
               <cb/> they had with their fiscal agents. There was <lb/> nothing whatever in these the
               Government <lb/> need to be afraid of. All these transactions <lb/> had been solely
               dictated and carried on with <lb/> an eye to the public interest. No information
               <lb/> which the House or country has a right to <lb/> expect would be withheld. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> hoped, as every informa<lb break="no"/>tion was
               to be given, that the correspondence <lb/> on this subject, which he had asked for,
               <lb/> would be forthcoming. He had no hesitation <lb/> in saying that at one time
               when he was in the <lb/> Administration, the Bank of Montreal was a <lb/> useful
               public servant—now it would become <lb/> master.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD2">Hon. John S. Macdonald</persName> said the statement <lb/> of the member
               for Chateauguay regarding <lb/> the Bank of Montreal was not warranted. He <lb/>
               protested against this continued harping <lb/> against the Bank of Montreal. The fact
               was <lb/> that the bank was patronized by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment because it
               had helped them cheerful<lb break="no"/>ly and materially in times of need, and was
               <lb/> besides by far the best managed institution of <lb/> that time in the Dominion.
               Let the member <lb/> for Chateauguay attack the Government and <lb/> let the servant
               of the Government alone. It <lb/> was unfair to attack the Bank of Montreal <lb/>
               when the gentlemen of the Treasury Benches <lb/> were the really responsible parties.
               <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:PARK2">Dr. Parker</persName> thought that even though there <lb/> was nothing to
               conceal, as the Minister of <lb/> Finance stated, still his continued mystery on
               <lb/> the subject would excite suspicion in the <lb/> country. He would prefer that
               the whole <lb/> information should be given. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p> The motion was carried. <lb/>
            </p>
<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre"> LABRADOR <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FORT3">Mr. Fortin</persName> moved an address for all corre<lb break="no"/>spondence between the Government of the <lb/> late Province of Canada and of the
                  Dominion <lb/> of Canada and Newfoundland, in relation to <lb/> the boundary line
                  of Labrador.—Carried. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:FORT3">Mr. Fortin</persName> moved an address for all corre<lb break="no"/>spondence relating to the custom duties ex<lb break="no"/>acted by the
                  Newfoundland Government <lb/> from Canadian fishermen on the Coast of <lb/>
                  Labrador.—Carried. <lb/>
               </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre"> NOVA SCOTIA—REPEAL—DR.
TUPPER <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MCDO3">Mr. McDonald</persName> (Antigonish) moved for a <lb/> copy of the
                  address of the House of Assembly <lb/> of Nova Scotia, praying for the repeal of
                  so <lb/> much of the British North America Act as [...]
               </p>
</div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>