<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1948-01-29"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1948-01-29">29 January 1948</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Twentieth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
    

         <date when="1948"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmond Cloutier, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="662" to="662"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-01-29_Page_0662.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
        
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-01-29_Page_0662">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-01-29_Page_0662.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="662" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-01-29_Page_0662.jpg"/>
           
<!-- GL, 2016-12-20, manually entered text and marked-up from ocr done at home, first image processed was incorrect. --> 

<fw type="num">662</fw>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Inquiries of the Ministry</hi></fw>    <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>

<div type="section">
<head>
IMPORT RESTRICTIONS—PLANS FOR SPRING<lb/>
PLANTING<lb/></head>

<p>On the orders of the day:</p>
<p>
Mr. G. K. FRASER (Peterborough West):<lb/>
I should like to direct a question to the<lb/>
Minister of Agriculture or the Minister of<lb/>
Finance. Does the government intend to<lb/>
announce the future plans regarding the impor<lb break="no"/>tation of lettuce, celery and vegetables, so that<lb/>
the vegetable growers and hothouse men can<lb/>
plan for the future and the needs of the<lb/>
Canadian people? Their vegetable seeds for<lb/>
the spring planting must be ordered at once.<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. SPEAKER: Order.<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. FRASER: Mr. Speaker, this is a very<lb/>
important question because the vegetable men<lb/>
have to order their vegetable seeds within the<lb/>
next month.<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. GRAYDON: These people are not<lb/>
interested in the vegetable growers; one can<lb/>
easily see that.<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. FRASER: Mr. Speaker, may I not have<lb/>
an answer to that question?<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. GRAYDON: He should have an answer<lb/>
to the question. It has to do with urgent<lb/>
business of everyone.<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. SPEAKER: Order.<lb/></p>
<p>
Hon. DOUGLAS ABBOTT (Minister of<lb/>
Finance): I always like to answer questions. A<lb/>
delegation from the vegetable growers came<lb/>
to see me this morning. That may be what<lb/>
has prompted my hon. friend’s question.<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. GRAYDON: There is nothing wrong<lb/>
with that.<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. FRASER: No.<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. ABBOTT: I discussed the matter of<lb/>
fresh vegetables with them. I pointed out that<lb/>
the import restrictions on these vegetables are<lb/>
part of our exchange conservation program,<lb/>
essentially temporary ID. their nature, but that<lb/>
for obvious reasons it was impossible for me<lb/>
or for anyone else to say how long it would<lb/>
be necessary to keep these restrictions on.<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. FRASER: My question was prompted<lb/>
by a letter which I wrote the Department of<lb/>
Agriculture on January 5.<lb/>
</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head>CANADA—NEWFOUNDLAND</head>
<p>
REQUEST FOR STATEMENT ON ACTION OF<lb/>
NEWFOUNDLAND NATIONAL CONVENTION<lb/></p>
<p>
On the orders of the day:<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. GORDON GRAYDON (Peel): I<lb/>
should like to direct a question to the Secre<lb break="no"/>tary of State for External Affairs. In view of<lb/>
the interest across Canada in our negotiations<lb/>
<!--[Mr. Abbott]--><cb/>

with Newfoundland, and the fact that yester<lb break="no"/>day its national convention opposed the sub<lb break="no"/>mission of the confederation plan to the people<lb/>
of Newfoundland, would the government<lb/>
through the Prime Minister or the Secretary<lb/>
of State for External Affairs make a statement<lb/>
to the house so that the country will under<lb break="no"/>stand from parliament, rather than from the<lb/>
press so far away, just how the situation now<lb/>
stands, whether or not the door is closed to<lb/>
further negotiations, and the prospect of<lb/>
further confederation discussions?<lb/></p>
<p>
Right Hon. L. S. ST. LAURENT (Secretary<lb/>
of State for External Affairs): I will examine<lb/>
carefully the terms of the question that has<lb/>
just been asked by -the hon. member and<lb/>
endeavour to have some statement made. The<lb/>
hon. member will realize that the Canadian<lb/>
government stated terms which in its opinion<lb/>
would be fair for union and is taking no part<lb/>
whatsoever in presenting those terms to the<lb/>
people of Newfoundland, nor would it venture<lb/>
to do or say anything which might be regarded<lb/>
there as trying to influence the decision of the<lb/>
free people of Newfoundland.<lb/></p>
<p>
The information we have is that there was<lb/>
a vote against recommending to the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the United Kingdom the inclusion on<lb/>
the ballot of any question about union with<lb/>
Canada. The information we have is that<lb/>
this national convention was an advisory body<lb/>
and that its decisions were not binding either<lb/>
on the people of Newfoundland or on the<lb/>
United Kingdom government. We have not<lb/>
received any information of decisions taken<lb/>
since the report in the newspapers of the vote<lb/>
in the national convention.<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. GRAYDON: I take it from the minis<lb break="no"/>ter’s remarks that the door to further negotia<lb break="no"/>tions is not definitely closed.<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. ST. LAURENT: No. The offer is still<lb/>
before the people of Newfoundland and before<lb/>
the commission government of Newfoundland.<lb/></p>
<p>
The national convention has expressed by<lb/>
vote its views, but it is only, as I said, an<lb/>
advisory body and the matter still has to be<lb/>
dealt with by those who have the constitutional<lb/>
responsibility for a decision.<lb/></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head>EXCESS PROFITS TAX</head>
<p>
INQUIRY WITH RESPECT T0 NEWSPAPER REPORT<lb/></p>
<p>
On the orders of the day:<lb/></p>
<p>
Mr. J. M. MACDONNELL (Muskoka-<lb break="yes"/>
Ontario): Mr. Speaker, I should like to<lb/>
address a question to the Minister of Finance<lb/>
of which I have had no chance to give him<lb/>
notice. In view of the report appearing in the<lb/>
press that the Minister of Transport intimated<lb/>
that the government was considering an exten-<lb/></p>

  </div>     </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>