<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1888-04-09"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1888-04-09">9 April 1888</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Second Session</title>.
   
                    

          <date when="1888"/>.   
          

           <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>MacLean, Roger &amp; Co., Wellington Street </publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="664" to="665"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1888-04-09_Page_0664.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1888-04-09_Page_0665.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1888-04-09_Page_0664">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1888-04-09_Page_0664.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1888-04-09_Page_0665">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1888-04-09_Page_0665.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="664" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1888-04-09_Page_0664.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">664</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">APRIL 9,</fw>
            
            
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Alert</hi>, and was very glad to hear that contradicted by 
               <lb/>
               somebody who professes to know, because I wish to express 
               <lb/>
               as strongly as I can my disapprobation of such a. course. 
               <lb/>
               I have heard it rumored since that the department 
               <lb/>
               are about to call for tenders for the construction of a larger 
               <lb/>
               and better boat to supplement the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Northern Light</hi>. I hope 
               <lb/>
               that rumor is true. I was in hopes we would have had an 
               <lb/>
oﬁicial statement made to night by the hon. the Minister <lb/>
of Marine, because after the plain, practical and convincing 
               <lb/>
               statements made by my hon. friend, based as they are upon 
               <lb/>
               historical facts and upon the declaration made by the High 
               <lb/>
               Commissioner to Earl Granville as to the intention of the 
               <lb/>
               Government, and upon the suggestion which Earl Granville 
               <lb/>
               made to this Government, I hoped we would have heard 
               <lb/>
               tonight what the policy of the Government is. I think 
               <lb/>
               my hon. friend has made out a complete case, and has put 
               <lb/>
               the House in full possession of the facts, and I do think 
               <lb/>
               our long-suﬂering people are entitled to have their griev<lb break="no"/>ances in this very serious matter removed. We have been 
               <lb/>
               year after year pressing this matter, and I am sure the 
               <lb/>
               House does not want me to go over the old story, and I am 
               <lb/>
               not going to do it again tonight, because my hon. friend 
               <lb/>
               has anticipated me and has put the points better than I 
               <lb/>
               could, but I do begin to have some assurance from the Min<lb break="no"/>ister in reference to that wharf, and, if he can give it in 
               <lb/>
               the absence of the Minister of Marine, some information as 
               <lb/>
               to the action of the Department of Marine in reference to 
               <lb/>
               the censtruction of another steamboat. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            <p>
               Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN. I was about to rise just now, 
               <lb/>
               When I saw the hon. gentleman wished to say a few words, 
               <lb/>
               and I thought it better he should speak ﬁrst so that I 
               <lb/>
               might answer both gentlemen—the mover of the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion (Mr. Perry) and the member for Queen’s (Mr. Davies) 
               <lb/>
               —at the same time. In answer to the last question of the 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentleman, I may say that the contract for the wharf 
               <lb/>
               or pier at Cape Tormentine was broken by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment because the contractor did not proceed with the work 
               <lb/>
               quickly and evidently could not go on. Under those cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances we called for new tenders, and have given a 
               <lb/>
               new contract. The contract has been signed, and I under<lb break="no"/>stand that the contractors are men who are quite able to 
               <lb/>
               perform the work, which will he proceeded with with all 
               <lb/>
               due vigor. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. DAVIES (P. E I.) Will the hon. gentleman state 
               <lb/>
               who they are ? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN. I do not remember now. 
               <lb/>
               When the Estimates come on, I shall be able to give the 
               <lb/>
               names. As to the boat, I cannot positively say, but, as far 
               <lb/>
               as I recollect, the intention of the Minister of Marine and 
               <lb/>
               Fisheries is to provide a new boat. In reference to the 
               <lb/>
               remarks of the mover of the motion, I may say, ﬁrst, that 
               <lb/>
               there will be no objection to bring down the papers, and 
               <lb/>
               second, that the survey made in 1886 was communicated to 
               <lb/>
               the House and hon. gentlemen know what was the result 
               <lb/>
               of that survey. The hon. gentleman complains that no 
               <lb/>
               work has been done in the direction of constructing a sub<lb break="no"/>way. I do not suppose he expected that we would pro<lb break="no"/>ceed in that way. He knew, and I think the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man who spoke last stated, that the Minister of Finance had 
               <lb/>
               made a statement that we would give our attention to that 
               <lb/>
               work, and that we would have new explorations made to 
               <lb/>
               see whether the work was a feasible one or not. Well, I 
               <lb/>
               am glad to say that the last survey, which was made in 
               <lb/>
               July and August, 1887, has given a much better result than 
               <lb/>
               the ﬁrst survey of 1886, and, if we go on in that way, 
               <lb/>
               improving all the time, we shall ﬁnd the distance very 
               <lb/>
               small. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. DAVIES (P.E.I.) By the next election. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN. I did not say that. The 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentleman says so, and I am glad to hear him ﬁx a
           <!-- <p>
               Mr. Davies (P.E.I.) 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>-->

            
         <cb/>
            
            
           
               date, because the Government of course will thus know the 
               <lb/>
               wishes of hon. gentlemen on the other side. The engineer 
               <lb/>
               in the month of August took a series of borings in a line 
               <lb/>
               from Carleton Point to a point in New Brunswick, I think 
               <lb/>
               Munsey Point. The greatest depth of water found is ninety- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               one feet, the bottom is more favorable than on the line of 
               <lb/>
               soundings taken in 1886, and the distance is six and a half 
               <lb/>
               miles, which is one and a half miles less than on the line of 
               <lb/>
borings taken in 1886. This shows that, as I said, if we go<lb/>
on in that way, we shall ﬁnd the distance very small, and I 
               <lb/>
               think that in any case this result is much more favorable 
               <lb/>
               and must please hon. gentlemen so far, at all events, 
               <lb/>
               as the survey goes, as it shows that, if the matter has been 
               <lb/>
               left over for a year to obtain new soundings and new 
               <lb/>
               measurements, the time has not been lost in vain, that we 
               <lb/>
               have obtained a much better line by this survey than we 
               <lb/>
               had in 1886. I have no objection to the granting of the 
               <lb/>
               motion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

  
            <p>
               Mr. DAVIES (P.E.I.) I would like to be permitted to ask 
               <lb/>
               the hon. gentleman whether the result of the survey has been 
               <lb/>
               so satisfactory as to induce him to believe it to be right and 
               <lb/>
               proper that he should purpose a subsidy or a vote to the 
               <lb/>
               House to carry the work out, either by means of a company 
               <lb/>
               or by Government contract? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN. I am afraid that is a ques<lb break="no"/>tion which I cannot answer immediately. I think it is one 
               <lb/>
               of those questions that must be left to the consideration of 
               <lb/>
               the Government, and the hon. gentleman may be sure, 
               <lb/>
               after the surveys which we have made, that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will give to the matter their best consideration. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. DAVIES (P. E. I.) I fear we cannot hope for any<lb break="no"/>thing in the supplementaries? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN. That is a pleasure left for 
               <lb/>
               the hon. gentleman to discover. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. ROBERTSON. Have the Government any offers 
               <lb/>
               from any company to build a subway for any particular 
               <lb/>
               sum? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN. I am not aware. There 
               <lb/>
               may have been some offer of that kind in the Railway 
               <lb/>
               Department, but I am not in a position to answer that 
               <lb/>
               definitely. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Motion agreed to. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
     <div type="section">
            
            <head>
               NEWFOUNDLAND AND CON FEDERATION.</head>
            <p>
               Mr. LAURIER moved for: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               Copies of all correspondence exchanged between the Government of 
               <lb/>
               Canada and the Government of Newfoundland concerning the admission <lb/>
               of Newfoundland into the Confederation.</quote>
           
 <p>
               He said: I have no intention to comment on the subject 
               <lb/>
               at this moment. My only object is to have as soon as 
               <lb/>
               possible before the House the papers on that important 
               <lb/>
               question. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN. I hope the hon. gentleman 
               <lb/>
               will not insist upon his motion after what I shall say. This 
               <lb/>
               matter is now engaging the attention of the Government, 
               <lb/>
               and, as the hon. gentleman will see from the newspapers 
               <lb/>
               that a delegation is coming to Canada about this matter, 
               <lb/>
               we think the public interest would not allow us to lay this 
               <lb/>
               correspondence now before Parliament. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. LAURIER. If I understand from the hon. 
               <lb/>
               gentleman that the correspondence is still going on, 
               <lb/>
               that it is not yet in a ﬁt condition to be published, I will not 
               <lb/>
               press my motion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN. It is not.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT. The Minister, I sup<lb break="no"/>pose, has no objections to inform us when he expects the 
               <lb/>
          
            <pb n="665" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1888-04-09_Page_0665.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1888.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw>
            <fw type="num">665</fw>
            
      
               delegation to arrive, and perhaps he might give us the 
               <lb/>
               names of the gentlemen, if he has been made acquainted 
               <lb/>
               with them in advance. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN. I am not able to give the 
               <lb/>
               names of the gentlemen who will form the delegation, nor 
               <lb/>
               the precise date of their coming to Canada, but I suppose it 
               <lb/>
               will be about the end of this month. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. MITCHELL. Perhaps the hon . gentleman could 
               <lb/>
               tell us whether the Parliament of Newfoundland has 
               <lb/>
               authorised the delegation, or whether their Parliament has 
               <lb/>
               given any authority to a delegation to come here. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN. I am not able to give that 
               <lb/>
               information. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Motion withdrawn. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
     </div>   
           
<div type="section">
            <head>
               MEMBER INTRODUCED. 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The following member, having previously taken the oath 
               <lb/>
               according to law, and subscribed the Roll containing the 
               <lb/>
               same, took his seat in the House: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               DAVID BISHOP MEIGS, Esq., Member for the Electoral District of Missis<lb break="no"/>quoi, introduced by Hon. Mr. Laurier and Mr. Fisder. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
</div>     
      
<div type="section">      
            <head>
               ASSISTANCE TO WRECKING VESSELS.<lb/></head>
            <p>
               Mr. EDGAR moved for: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               Copies of all papers. &amp;c., with reference to: 1. The refusal of the 
               <lb/>
               United States authorities to allow Canadian wrecking vessels and ma<lb break="no"/>chinery to assist Canadian vessels while in distress in United States 
               <lb/>
               waters. 2. The refusal of the Canadian authorities to allow United 
               <lb/>
               States wrecking vessels and machinery to assist United States vessels 
               <lb/>
               while in distress in Canadian waters. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               He said: There is a Bill before the House standing, I 
               <lb/>
               think, for its second reading, introduced by the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Frontenac (Mr. Kirkpatrick), which relates closely 
               <lb/>
               to this subject, and I sincerely hope the hon. member will 
               <lb/>
               press his Bill, and that it will receive the support of both 
               <lb/>
               sides of this House. His Bill is to permit American vessels 
               <lb/>
               to aid vessels which are wrecked or disabled in Canadian 
               <lb/>
               waters. I suppose that that Bill would not have been in<lb break="no"/>troduced by that hon. gentleman unless the Canadian au<lb break="no"/>thorities had hitherto prevented American vessels from 
               <lb/>
               aiding wrecked or disabled vessels in Canadian waters. I 
               <lb/>
               have no doubt, however, that the reason why the Canadian 
               <lb/>
               authorities took this exceeding harsh line was because the 
               <lb/>
               American Government prevented Canadian vessels from 
               <lb/>
               assisting vessels which were wrecked in American waters. 
               <lb/>
               I think it will be of considerable advantage to this 
               <lb/>
               House, in the consideration of the Bill to which I have 
               <lb/>
               referred, if these papers are bi ought down, so much, at 
               <lb/>
               least, as the Government feel at liberty to bring down, 
               <lb/>
               and I hope they will bring them all down. The 
               <lb/>
               motion refers not only to correspondence and Orders in 
               <lb/>
               Council with reference to the refusal of the United 
               <lb/>
               States authorities to allow Canadian wrecking vessels 
               <lb/>
               and machinery to assist vessels in American waters, 
               <lb/>
               but also as to the refusal of the Canadian authorities 
               <lb/>
               to allow Americans to do so, so that we will have both 
               <lb/>
               features of the case before us when we have these papers. 
               <lb/>
               1 have no doubt, as I said before, that the Canadian author<lb break="no"/>ities could not have adopted the harsh measures which they 
               <lb/>
               have in this matter, and which are to be cured by this Bill, 
               <lb/>
               unless the Americans had done the same, but I ﬁnd in the 
               <lb/>
               United States Congress they do not take exactly that view 
               <lb/>
               of the case. They seem to think that the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment has acted much more harshly towards them than they 
               <lb/>
               have acted towards the Canadian Government. However, 
               <lb/>
               the papers will show how that is. But in order to show 
               <lb/>
               the once the view that is taken of the matter on the other 
               <lb/>
               side, I will refer to a resolution which was introduced into 
               <lb/>
               
      
            
         
            
          <!--  <p>
               84 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>-->
            
         <cb/>
            
         
               the House of Representatives by Mr. Nutting, early in the 
               <lb/>
               month of February. In that resolution it is recited: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               “Whereas, it is alleged that the Canadian authorities for years have 
               <lb/>
               refused. and new refuse to allow American wrecking vessels and ma<lb break="no"/>chinery to assist American vessels while in distress in Canadian canals<lb/>
               and waters.” 
               <lb/></quote>

<p>
               So far, I take it, he must be correct, or else the Bill of 
               <lb/>
               the hon. member for Frontenac would not be necessary. 
               <lb/>
               He then goes on to make an allegation, which I confess, I 
               <lb/>
               very much doubt, but he says: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               “And it is alleged further that Canadian wrecking vessels and ma<lb break="no"/>chinery have been, and now are allowed to come into American waters 
               <lb/>
               and assist any vessel there in distress.”
               
            </quote>
  
            <p>
               Now, whether that is so or not, we will perhaps ﬁnd out 
               <lb/>
               when this correspondence is brought down. But he quotes 
               <lb/>
               a couple of letters from American vessel owners and cap<lb break="no"/>tains which show certainly the great hardship to them of 
               <lb/>
               the practice of the two Governments. One is a letter from 
               <lb/>
               Oswego, dated 1st February, 1888, by Mr. John K. Pope. 
               <lb/>
               He says: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               “On or about the 30th day of September, 1881, I. being controlling 
               <lb/>
               owner of steam-barge <hi rendition="simple:italic">Thompson Kingsford</hi>, was notified that she was 
               <lb/>
               ashore at Wellington, Out., and immediate assistance was needed. I 
               <lb/>
               informed our wrecker, Mr. Allan, who expressed himself ready to start, 
               <lb/>
           providing the Canadian authorities would give him permission to work 
               <lb/>
               in their waters. I therefore applied by wire to the hon. Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Marine at Ottawa, and after a long delay was informed that the assist<lb break="no"/>ance needed could be procured at Kingston, and the application was 
               <lb/>
               denied I thought the treatment was severe, especially as my tugs were 
               <lb/>
               all ready to go, and we could have got the barge out of danger in 24 
               <lb/>
               hours. As it was, during the delay, or rather by the delay. in waiting 
               <lb/>
               for an answer, she was subjected to a severe gale, causing great damage 
               <lb/>
               and eventually costing us about $l,200 more than it would if we could 
               <lb/>
               have done the work ourselves. A gain, about the 19th day of August 
               <lb/>
               1882, the same barge was sunk in the Bay of Quinté by collision, and I 
               <lb/>
               again made application to go to her relief with my own appliances, 
               <lb/>
               and was again refused.” 
               <lb/></quote>

<p>
               Then another letter was quoted by Mr. Nutting, which was 
               <lb/>
               sent to him by Albert Quonce, also of Oswego, dated 1st 
               <lb/>
               February, 1888, in which Mr. Quonce stated: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               “At the suggestion of Mr. Allan I make the following statement: 
               <lb/>
               On or about the 3rd day of November, l882, the schooner <hi rendition="simple:italic">Camanche</hi>, of 
               <lb/>
               which I was controlling owner, was sunk in the Welland Canal, near 
               <lb/>
               Port Colborne. Although Buffalo was but twenty miles from her and 
               <lb/>
               assistance could have been secured in six hours, we were told that Am<lb break="no"/>erican assistance would not be permitted, although at that moment the 
               <lb/>
               steam pumps were loaded and ready to come. The result was we had 
               <lb/>
               to wait for assistance from Amherstburg, nearly three hundred miles 
               <lb/>
               distant, and causing delay of three days. Owing to the delay the 
               <lb/>
               vessel’s cargo<lb/>
               
             swelled and sprung her entire deck up, and almost ruined<lb/>
the vessel.” 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>

       
            <p>
               These statements will show the view taken on the other 
               <lb/>
               side, of our harsh law, and I am sure if we can do anything 
               <lb/>
               to secure an improvement for the sake of common human<lb break="no"/>ity as well as for the sake of commercial friendship with 
               <lb/>
               the United States, the Government will hasten to bring 
               <lb/>
               down these returns so that, if possible, we may have them 
               <lb/>
               before us when considering the Bill of the hon. member for 
               <lb/>
               Frontenac (Mr. Kirkpatrick).<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. BOWELL. I would suggest that in the ﬁrst para<lb break="no"/>graph the words “not already brought down,” be inserted 
               <lb/>
               after the words “departmental orders.” Some years ago 
               <lb/>
               a large amount of correspondence was laid before the 
               <lb/>
               House, and I do not suppose it is necessary to duplicate the 
               <lb/>
               return. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT. Was the return printed? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Mr. BOWELL. I think it was; I know it was, because 
               <lb/>
               I have a copy of the printed return on the table in my 
               <lb/>
               ofﬁce. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Mr. EDGAR. When was the return made? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            <p>
               Mr. BOWELL. I am not sure, I cannot say the year, 
               <lb/>
               but I can furnish the information. However, all the cor<lb break="no"/>respondence and orders made in regard to this subject will 
               <lb/>
               be brought down, other than those which have already been 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
</div>      
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>