<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1869-06-17" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-06-17">17 June 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
   
         
           <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="854" to="854"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-17_Page_0854.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
         
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>

<change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-02-14">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-17_Page_0854">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-17_Page_0854.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="854" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-06-17_Page_0854.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">854</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 17, 1869<lb/></fw>
            
<p>be accepted by the Legislature of each Prov<lb break="no"/>ince. <lb/>
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> replied to the Minister of Militia, <lb/> and
               contended that it was eminently proper <lb/> that, from the very outset, any action
               by the <lb/> Dominion Government, looking in the direc<lb break="no"/>tion of taking
               away from the Local Legisla<lb break="no"/>tures their control over property and
               civil <lb/> rights, should be carefully discussed. He con<lb break="no"/>sidered
               sound policy was against this Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment assuming control over these
               laws; ﬁrst <lb/> because it would be against the proper work<lb break="no"/>ing of
               the Federal system, and second because <lb/> it would give this Parliament control
               over the <lb/> laws of Ontario, New Brunswick, and Nova <lb/> Scotia, with which
               one-third of its members<lb break="no"/>those from Quebec—had no concern. Such a
               <lb/> policy, he believed, was wrong; and even from <lb/> the point of view of those
               who thought other<lb break="no"/>wise, it must be regarded as premature, look<lb break="no"/>ing to the position of Nova Scotia and to the <lb/> coming in of
               Newfoundland. Moreover, with<lb break="no"/>out the concurrence of the Local
               Legislatures, <lb/> the money spent on this object would be <lb/> thrown away; and
               that concurrence he did <lb/> not believe would be given. As regarded, at <lb/>
               least, his own Province, his voice would be <lb/> raised against such concurrence.
               <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said it was possible <lb/> that Ontario,
               Nova Scotia and New Brunswick <lb/> might never have precisely the same laws, but
               <lb/> it was, at least, desirable that they should <lb/> have an opportunity of
               obtaining uniformity <lb/> of their laws. There had been a gradual diver<lb break="no"/>gence of the laws in those Provinces, and it <lb/> was of importance
               to their well-being that that <lb/> divergence should be done away with. The <lb/>
               most likely way to accomplish that was to <lb/> have a Commission of experts familiar
               with <lb/> the laws of the various Provinces, to report a <lb/> body of laws which
               the Provinces might either <lb/> accept or reject. The member for Durham said <lb/>
               this movement was premature, because New<lb break="no"/>foundland was not yet in the
               Union. That <lb/> Province had been very careful to maintain its <lb/> Civil Law, the
               law of England. The whole of <lb/> its own laws in that department might be con<lb break="no"/>tained in a very thin volume. There would be <lb/> little difficulty,
               therefore, as regarded that <lb/> Province. No one Province could afford to pay <lb/>
               the expense of such a commission as this, and <lb/> if it did a Provincial commission
               would look <lb/> at the consolidation of the law from a Provin<lb break="no"/>cial
               point of view. He was surprised that the <lb/> member for Durham should oppose this
               or <lb/> should not desire a uniform system of laws <lb/> over all the Provinces. It
               was of importance <lb/> that the members of the bar of one Province <lb/> should be
               in a position to go to the bar of an [...]<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>