<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1948-03-11" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1948-03-11">11 March 1948</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          

         
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Twentieth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
                    

           <date when="1948"/>.    
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmond Cloutier, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="2095" to="2096"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-03-11_Page_2095.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-03-11_Page_2096.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-30">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-03-11_Page_2095">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-03-11_Page_2095.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-03-11_Page_2096">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-03-11_Page_2096.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="2095" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-03-11_Page_2095.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2095</fw>


<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS</head>

            <head rendition="simple:centre">Thursday, March 11, 1948</head> 
             

            <p>
               The house met at three o'clock. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>

    <div type="section">        
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               HOUSE OF COMMONS 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">POST OFFICE—DISTRIBUTION OF COMMUNIST 
<lb/>
               NEWSPAPER</head>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DORI2">Mr. FREDERIC DORION</persName> (Charlevoix- <lb break="yes"/> Saguenay):
                  Mr. Speaker, I rise to a question <lb/> of privilege. A few days ago many members,
                  <lb/> and I was one of them, received through the <lb/> post office of the House
                  of Commons a copy <lb/> of the communist newspaper <hi rendition="simple:italic">Combat</hi>. The <lb/> envelopes containing that paper, like the one <lb/> I
                  hold in my hand, did not bear any post <lb/> office mark, contrary to section 275
                  of the <lb/> post office regulations, which reads as follows-<lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>: Order. I would ask the <lb/> hon. member to state
                  his question of privilege. <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DORI2">Mr. DORION</persName>: I am about to do so, Mr. <lb/> Speaker, but I
                  submit that on a question of <lb/> privilege we are entitled to explain why we
                  <lb/> raise the question. The section to which I <lb/> refer reads: <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               Postmasters should be careful to postmark 
               <lb/>
               distinctly all letters, registered or ordinary, 
               <lb/>
               posted or received at their offices, and to 
               <lb/>
               effectually cancel all stamps thereon. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               As the envelopes we received did not bear 
               <lb/>
               any postmark as required by the rules, we 
               <lb/>
               cannot identify the post office they were mailed 
               <lb/>
               at or where they came from. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It is stated in that newspaper that it was 
               <lb/>
               published in Montreal, but we cannot ascertain 
               <lb/>
               where it was mailed. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               My point of privilege, Mr. Speaker, is that 
               <lb/>
               our mail boxes are not rubbish cans and that 
               <lb/>
               they should be used only in accordance with 
               <lb/>
               the post ofice regulations. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
    </div>

<div type="section">      
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               DEBATES BRANCH—REPORT OF CIVIL SERVICE 
               <lb/>
               COMMISSION 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>: I have the honour to lay on <lb/> the table of
                  the house a report of the civil <lb/> service commission relating to the
                  appointment <lb/> of Miss M. E. Black to a permanent position in <lb/> the debates
                  branch of the House of Commons. <lb/>
               </p>
           <!-- <p>
               5849—134 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>-->

</div>

<div type="section">
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               REPORTS OF COMMITTEES 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">BANKING AND COMMERCE—FIRST AND SECOND 
<lb/>
               REPORTS—CONCURRENCE IN FIRST REPORT</head>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CLEA1">Mr. HUGHES CLEAVER</persName> (Halton) pre<lb break="no"/>sented the
                  first and second reports of the stand<lb break="no"/>ing committee on banking and
                  commerce, and <lb/> moved that the first report be concurred in. <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Motion agreed to. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>    
         
      <div type="section">      
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               NEWFOUNDLAND 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">QUESTIONS SUBMITTED TO CANADIAN GOVERNMENT 
<lb/>
               AND ANSWERS THERETO</head>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Right Hon. L. S. ST. LAURENT</persName> (Secretary <lb/> of State for
                  External Affairs): Yesterday there <lb/> was a question on the order paper by the
                  hon. <lb/> member for Broadview (Mr. Church) with <lb/> respect to developments in
                  connection with <lb/> the possible entry of Newfoundland into con<lb break="no"/>federation, and I asked that it be allowed to <lb/> stand. As I understand that
                  the Prime <lb/> Minister has information to communicate to <lb/> the house today,
                  before that is done, I should <lb/> like to table copies of certain additional
                     ques<lb break="no"/>tions that were submitted to the Canadian <lb/> government
                  by the governor of Newfoundland, <lb/> and copies of the answers that were given
                  <lb/> to those questions. <lb/>
               </p>
            
      </div>   
            
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               ANNOUNCEMENT OF REFERENDUM ON FUTURE 
               <lb/>
               FORM OF GOVERNMENT 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:KING1">Right Hon. W. L. MACKENZIE KING</persName>
                  <lb/> (Prime Minister): Mr. Speaker, I might give <lb/> the house immediately the
                  statement to which <lb/> my hon. friend the Secretary of State for <lb/> External
                  Affairs has just referred. <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               We have been advised by the United King<lb break="no"/>dom government that a statement is to be 
               <lb/>
               issued today in Newfoundland announcing 
               <lb/>
               that the people of Newfoundland will be given 
               <lb/>
               the opportunity shortly to vote in a refer<lb break="no"/>endum on their future form of government. 
               <lb/>
               Three questions will be submitted to the 
               <lb/>
               people: continuation of commission govern<lb break="no"/>ment for a five-year period; restoration of 
               <lb/>
               responsible government as it existed in 1933 
               <lb/>
               prior to the establishment of commission of 
               <lb/>
               
      
            
            <pb n="2096" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-03-11_Page_2096.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">2096</fw>
            
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Newfoundland</hi></fw>

            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
         
            
     
               government; and confederation with Canada. 
               <lb/>
               If no form of government receives an absolute 
               <lb/>
               majority, a second vote will be held some 
               <lb/>
               time later on the two forms receiving the 
               <lb/>
               largest support. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I think it would be useful were I to remind 
               <lb/>
               the house of the recent steps preceding the 
               <lb/>
               present announcement. It will be recalled 
               <lb/>
               that last summer a delegation from the 
               <lb/>
               national convention visited Ottawa to ascer<lb break="no"/>tain what fair and equitable basis might exist 
               <lb/>
               for federal union of Newfoundland and 
               <lb/>
               Canada. A committee of the cabinet was 
               <lb/>
               appointed to meet with the Newfoundland 
               <lb/>
               delegation. Several meetings were held dur<lb break="no"/>ing the summer for the exchange of informa<lb break="no"/>tion and exploration of the many issues that 
               <lb/>
               would be involved in union. At the close of 
               <lb/>
               these meetings a comprehensive report was 
               <lb/>
               issued, copies of which were tabled early in 
               <lb/>
               the present session of parliament. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               After due deliberation the government sent 
               <lb/>
               the governor of Newfoundland, for trans<lb break="no"/>mission to the national convention, a state<lb break="no"/>ment of terms believed to constitute a fair 
               <lb/>
               and equitable basis of union of Newfoundland 
               <lb/>
               with Canada should the people of Newfound<lb break="no"/>land so desire. In a covering letter under 
               <lb/>
               date of October 29 last to the governor, I 
               <lb/>
               said in part: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               I feel I must emphasize that as far as the 
               <lb/>
               financial aspects of the proposed arrangements 
               <lb/>
               for union are concerned, the government of 
               <lb/>
               Canada believes that the arrangements go as 
               <lb/>
               far as the government can go under the circum<lb break="no"/>stances. The government could not readily con<lb break="no"/>template any change in these arrangements 
               <lb/>
               which would impose larger financial burdens on 
               <lb/>
               Canada. On the other hand, with respect to 
               <lb/>
               those matters which are primarily of provincial 
               <lb/>
               concern, such as education, the government of 
               <lb/>
               Canada would not wish to set down any rigid 
               <lb/>
               conditions, and it would be prepared to give 
               <lb/>
               reasonable consideration to suggestions for modi<lb break="no"/>fication or addition. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The statement of terms transmitted by the 
               <lb/>
               Canadian government was discussed at length 
               <lb/>
               by the national convention in Newfoundland. 
               <lb/>
               The convention, however, voted 29 to 16 
               <lb/>
               against recommending the inclusion of con<lb break="no"/>federation on the referendum ballot. Sub<lb break="no"/>sequently many telegrams, bearing the names, 
               <lb/>
               it is said, of some 50,000 voters, were sent to 
               <lb/>
               members of the convention for transmission 
               <lb/>
               to the Secretary of State for Commonwealth 
               <lb/>
               Relations requesting that the people be per<lb break="no"/>mitted to vote on the question. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            <p>
               The national convention was only em<lb break="no"/>powered to make recommendations regarding 
               <lb/>
               the questions to be included on the refer<lb break="no"/>endum ballot, decision on the matter remain<lb break="no"/><cb/>ing with the United Kingdom government. 
               <lb/>
               The dispatch from the United Kingdom gov<lb break="no"/>ernment made public today in Newfoundland 
               <lb/>
               explains that-<lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">—the terms offered by the Canadian government 
               <lb/>
               represent the result of long discussion with a 
               <lb/>
               body of Nevwfoundlanders who were elected to 
               <lb/>
               the convention and the issues involved appear 
               <lb/>
               to have been sufficiently clarified to enable the 
               <lb/>
               people of Newfoundland to express an opinion 
               <lb/>
               as to whether confederation with Canada would 
               <lb/>
               commend itself to them. In these circumstances 
               <lb/>
               and having regard to the number of members 
               <lb/>
               of the convention who supported the inclusion 
               <lb/>
               of confederation with Canada in the ballot 
               <lb/>
               paper, His Majesty's government have come to 
               <lb/>
               the conclusion that it would not be right that 
               <lb/>
               the people of Newfoundland should be deprived 
               <lb/>
               of an opportunity to considering the issue. 
               <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The decision to include confederation on the 
               <lb/>
               ballot having been taken by the United King<lb break="no"/>dom government, the outcome will be watched 
               <lb/>
               with deep interest by the people of Canada. 
               <lb/>
               The question as to their future form of gov<lb break="no"/>ernment is, of course, one for the people of 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland alone to decide. Neither the 
               <lb/>
               government nor the people of Canada would 
               <lb/>
               wish to influence in any way their decision. 
               <lb/>
               Should the people of Newfoundland express 
               <lb/>
               clearly their will that Newfoundland should 
               <lb/>
               enter confederation, I am sure that the people 
               <lb/>
               of Canada, will welcome them as partners in 
               <lb/>
               a larger Canada. Should they decide other<lb break="no"/>wise, this decision, I am no less sure, will be 
               <lb/>
               received with understanding and respect by 
               <lb/>
               the people of Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DORI2">Mr. DORION</persName>: Will the proposed arrange<lb break="no"/>ment
                  addressed by the Canadian government <lb/> to Newfoundland be submitted to this
                  house <lb/> before any agreement is concluded, in case <lb/> the result of the
                  referendum in Newfoundland <lb/> is favourable to its entry into confederation?
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:KING1">Mr. MACKENZIE KING</persName>: The answer is <lb/> yes. That is part of
                  the terms we are prepared <lb/> to recommend. <lb/>
               </p>
            
</div>     
      <div type="section">    
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               PRIVATE BILLS 
               <lb/></head>
<head rendition="simple:centre">
              FIRST READINGS—SENATE BILLS 
               
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Bill No. 127, for the relief of Joseph Onfroy 
               <lb/>
               Pilon.——Mr. Maybank. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Bill No. 128, for the relief of Thelma May 
               <lb/>
               Heggie May.—Mr. Maybank. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Bill No. 129, for the relief of Molly Renetta 
               <lb/>
               Fry Bist.—Mr. Maybank. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Bill No. 130, for the relief of Patricia Potter 
               <lb/>
               Parker.—Mr. Maybank. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Bill No. 131, for the relief of Helen May 
               <lb/>
               Smith Saunders.—Mr. Maybank. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
      </div>       
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>