<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1868-03-17"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1868-03-17">17 November 1868</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, First Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1967"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Roger Duhamel</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1868-03-17_Page_0355.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
         
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-29">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-29">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1868-03-17_Page_0355">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1868-03-17_Page_0355.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="355" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1868-03-17_Page_0355.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">
               March 17, 1868 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw><fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES<lb/></fw><fw type="num">355</fw>
            
            <p>
               correspondence to 5th December had been 
               <lb/>
               brought down, then the Government stood 
               <lb/>
               convicted of having moved the address with<lb break="no"/>out having any proper basis for it whatever. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. McDougall said the position taken 
               <lb/>
               by the member for Chateauguay seemed to be 
               <lb/>
               this—that the Government should have en<lb break="no"/>tered into some kind of negotiations, secret or 
               <lb/>
               otherwise, in order to ascertain beforehand 
               <lb/>
               what special terms and conditions ought to be 
               <lb/>
               adopted in bringing this Territory under the 
               <lb/>
               jurisdiction of the Government of this coun<lb break="no"/>try. The Government had taken a different 
               <lb/>
               view, the Union Act declaring that the 
               <lb/>
               North-West Territory might be handed over 
               <lb/>
               to the jurisdiction of Canada on such terms 
               <lb/>
               and conditions as should expressed in the 
               <lb/>
               address of the two Houses of Parliament. The 
               <lb/>
               Government assumed that, in pursuance of 
               <lb/>
               that Act, what they had to do was to ascer<lb break="no"/>tain for themselves the terms and conditions 
               <lb/>
               on which they would accept the Territory, 
               <lb/>
               and having got the assent of both Houses to 
               <lb/>
               these terms, they forwarded the address to 
               <lb/>
               the Home Government, and now awaited 
               <lb/>
               their answer. An honourable gentleman op<lb break="no"/>posite thought this Government was censura<lb break="no"/>ble, because no answer was yet received. 
               <lb/>
               Surely they were not to settle both sides of 
               <lb/>
               the contract. If the Imperial Government and 
               <lb/>
               Parliament had other terms and conditions to 
               <lb/>
               propose, we would have to pronounce upon 
               <lb/>
               them when presented to us. As regarded the 
               <lb/>
               delay, they hoped and expected that probably 
               <lb/>
               the next mail would bring the answer of the 
               <lb/>
               Imperial Government. The House knew that 
               <lb/>
               in England the Premier had retired, and 
               <lb/>
               another had taken his place, and necessarily 
               <lb/>
               delays and changes of policy would occur. 
               <lb/>
               This might account for some of the delay in 
               <lb/>
               answering the address, which he confessed he 
               <lb/>
               very much regretted. He did think there were 
               <lb/>
               high reasons of State why this question 
               <lb/>
               should be settled at the earliest moment; he 
               <lb/>
               thought so still, and he must say there had 
               <lb/>
               been no failure of duty on the part of this 
               <lb/>
               Government in urging the matter. As regard<lb break="no"/>ed what he had said during the last election, 
               <lb/>
               one could not be expected to stand by all the 
               <lb/>
               pictures of imagination which might be 
               <lb/>
               drawn during the heat of an election contest. 
               <lb/>
               (Laughter). He would say, however, that in 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland there were several gentlemen 
               <lb/>
               occupying prominent positions, who took part 
               <lb/>
               in the negotiations of 1864, and who were 
               <lb/>
               still anxious that that Colony should enter 
               <lb/>
               the Union. It was well known what views 
               <lb/>
               were expressed by the Governor of New<cb/><lb break="no"/>foundland, when recently in this country, and 
               <lb/>
               the newspapers of the last few weeks showed 
               <lb/>
               that there was a desire prevailing among a 
               <lb/>
               large portion of the people of that Colony to 
               <lb/>
               join their fortunes with ours. As regarded 
               <lb/>
               British Columbia, at a public meeting presid<lb break="no"/>ed over by the Mayor of Victoria, resolutions 
               <lb/>
               in favour of Union were passed, and similar 
               <lb/>
               resolutions had previously been passed unani<lb break="no"/>mously, he believed, by the Legislature. He 
               <lb/>
               thought, therefore, he had been justiﬁed in 
               <lb/>
               assuming, with overtures of this kind from 
               <lb/>
               the other Colonies, that the Union would soon 
               <lb/>
               be extended. Delays had occurred, but he 
               <lb/>
               believed that in a short time we would have 
               <lb/>
               formal proceedings, which would be a basis 
               <lb/>
               for action, and the extension of the Union, 
               <lb/>
               therefore, he looked upon as no myth. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie pointed out that the visit of 
               <lb/>
               the Governor of Newfoundland and the ac<lb break="no"/>tion taken in British Columbia were subse<lb break="no"/>quent to the speeches made by the Minister 
               <lb/>
               of Public Works to which he had referred. He 
               <lb/>
               was happy to believe that there was a desire 
               <lb/>
               for Union among a large proportion of the 
               <lb/>
               population of these colonies, but such unau<lb break="no"/>thorized statements as those of the Minister 
               <lb/>
               of Public Works, admitted to have been made 
               <lb/>
               without any foundation, were calculated to do 
               <lb/>
               more harm than good, by raising hopes which 
               <lb/>
               must be disappointed to a greater or lesser 
               <lb/>
               extent. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald said the Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Public Works had not meant it to be inferred 
               <lb/>
               that the expressions used by the Governor of 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland and the resolutions passed in 
               <lb/>
               British Columbia were the only indications 
               <lb/>
               the Government had had of a prospect of 
               <lb/>
               Union with those Colonies. He could assure 
               <lb/>
               the House they had had frequent communica<lb break="no"/>tion of a very important nature, all tending 
               <lb/>
               in the direction of an extension of the Union 
               <lb/>
               long before these indications. They had had 
               <lb/>
               no ofﬁcial communications. The member for 
               <lb/>
               Lambton must know, or no doubt as a mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the Government would soon know, 
               <lb/>
               that ofﬁcial communications conveyed results, 
               <lb/>
               and that the most important portion of the 
               <lb/>
               public business was transacted by being made 
               <lb/>
               matter of arrangements and discussion in an 
               <lb/>
               unofﬁcial form before the results were com<lb break="no"/>municated in oﬂicial documents. His honoura<lb break="no"/>ble friend was quite justiﬁed in stating he 
               <lb/>
               had reason to believe that Confederation 
               <lb/>
               would, ere long, be extended East and West. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Savary said this discussion gave him a 
               <lb/>
               favourable opportunity of making a remark 
               <lb/>
               which he thought it his duty to make on 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>