<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1895-04-19" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1895-04-19">19 April 1895</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          

         
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Fifth Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1895"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="14"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1895-04-19_Page_0013.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
        
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-30">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1895-04-19_Page_0013">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1895-04-19_Page_0013.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="13" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1895-04-19_Page_0013.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">13</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">[APRIL 19, 1895]</fw> <fw type="num">14</fw>
               
      
            <p>
               [...] has been most materially reduced. Take. in 
               <lb/>
               the first place, 'the goods that have been 
               <lb/>
               entered for consumption. In this year, as 
               <lb/>
               against/last year—and I am speaking as to 
               <lb/>
               values—there has been a decrease of eight 
               <lb/>
               millions and a half worth of goods; then, 
               <lb/>
               the duty collected on these goods, as con<lb break="no"/>trasted with the preceding year, has been less 
               <lb/>
               by a million and three-quarters of dollars. 
               <lb/>
               But the most noticeable changes have been 
               <lb/>
               in respect of the very goods which were 
               <lb/>
               aflected by a reduction in the tariff, as wit<lb break="no"/>nessed in the fact that the revenue deriv<lb break="no"/>able from woollen goods has decreased, as 
               <lb/>
               compared with the preceding year, by a mil<lb break="no"/>lion and a half; the revenue in respect of 
               <lb/>
               iron has decreased by a million and a 
               <lb/>
               quarter; and that in respect to silks, by 
               <lb/>
               $300,000. The great falling off in the ex<lb break="no"/>cise this year of $1,000,000 as com<lb break="no"/>pared with last year, has, too, helped 
               <lb/>
               to increase that deficit. Now, Sir, on 
               <lb/>
the whole there is a deficit, but the 
               <lb/>
               reasons are' ample, the matter is explain<lb break="no"/>able; and the fact that there is a deficit this 
               <lb/>
               year will not be looked upon by the country 
               <lb/>
               as a proof that such a state of affairs must 
               <lb/>
               exist under a Conservative Administration, 
               <lb/>
               but the people will regard it as a rarity and 
               <lb/>
               a novelty. I trust, Sir, that the deficit will 
               <lb/>
               not amount to what has been prophesied, 
               <lb/>and that, having a due regard to the 
               <lb/>
               efficiency of the public service, economy may 
               <lb/>
               be practised to such an extent as to make 
               <lb/>
               that deficit as small as possible. Now I 
               <lb/>
               come to another clause in the Address, that 
               <lb/>
               which makes mention of the probable ad<lb break="no"/>mission of the oldest British colony in Amer<lb break="no"/>ica as part of the confederation. When 
               <lb/>
               the scheme of confederation was broached 
               <lb/>
               and when it was effected in 1867, aye, and 
               <lb/>
               even before that, it was thought by the 
               <lb/>
               fathers of confederation that this great 
               <lb/>
               work would never be consummated, would 
               <lb/>
               never be finally completed, until within our 
               <lb/>
               borders was embraced every colony in 
               <lb/>
               North America under the flag of Great 
               <lb/>
               Britain; and from time to time overtures 
               <lb/>
               and propositions have been made to that 
               <lb/>
               end. I am pleased to see that at last they 
               <lb/>
               have taken a tangible form, and in this city, 
               <lb/>
               as the capital of the Dominion, a very im<lb break="no"/>portant conference was held a few weeks 
               <lb/>
               ago, from which we trust beneficial results 
               <lb/>
               will follow. The terms of the offer upon 
               <lb/>
               which Newfoundland proposes coming into 
               <lb/>
               this confederacy, and the terms which were 
               <lb/>
               offered by the Federal Government, have 
               <lb/>
               not yet been made public; but I think I 
               <lb/>
               echo the hope of every Canadian, and of 
               <lb/>
               every parliamentarian, irrespective of poli<lb break="no"/>tics, that those terms may be of such a 
               <lb/>
               nature that a consummation of that 
               <lb/>
               union may be brought about. We, in this 
               <lb/>
               portion of the Dominion, particularly in the 
               <lb/>
               province of Ontario, not having been in 
               <lb/>
               touch with the people of Newfoundland, 
               <lb/>
               have only known it as rather a sterile, bleak 
               <lb/>
               and inhospitable island ; but I am happy to 
               <lb/>
               
            
         
        <cb/>    
            
            
         
            
            
   
               say that our views in that respect have been 
               <lb/>
               entirely changed by a speech delivered in 
               <lb/>
               Ottawa last week by the Hon. Mr. Bond. 
               <lb/>
               With their thrifty, industrious and hardy 
               <lb/>
               population, of somewhat over 200,000, en<lb break="no"/>gaged, as they are, largely in the greatest of 
               <lb/>
               all hardships, the fishing industry, also in<lb break="no"/>terested as they are interested in the lum<lb break="no"/>ber business, and interested as they are 
               <lb/>
               in the great industry of mining, in which 
               <lb/>
               $5,000,000 is invested; not having, as we, 
               <lb/>
               in the western provinces have, great manu<lb break="no"/>facturing enterprises, it must of necessity 
               <lb/>
               result that they should be, and would be in 
               <lb/>
               due course of. time, if any considerable in<lb break="no"/>terchange of commodities took place. good 
               <lb/>
               customers of ours, as of the $7,000,000 worth 
               <lb/>
               of goods imported into that island, only 
               <lb/>
               $2,500,000 worth came from these provinces. 
               <lb/>
               So I believe that, if that consolidation is 
               <lb/>
               brought about, if that colony is admitted, a 
               <lb/>
               union will be accomplished which will 
               <lb/>
               greatly add to the material prosperity of the 
               <lb/>
               whole Dominion. Moreover, Sir. we will 
               <lb/>
               then guard and control every entrance to 
               <lb/>
               the British possessions on the Atlantic; and 
               <lb/>
               then it will be the proud boast of every 
               <lb/>
               Canadian, that from the western shores of 
               <lb/>
               this continent, where the waters of. the 
               <lb/>
               Pacific lave the golden sands of British Col<lb break="no"/>umbia, to the far east, where Newfound<lb break="no"/>land's rock-bound coasts are dashed by the 
               <lb/>
               billows of the Atlantic, all shall be under<lb/>
               the sway of the confederation of Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BELL4">Mr. BELLEY</persName>. (Translation) In rising to <lb/> second the motion
               just moved. by the hon. <lb/> member for East Simcoe (Mr. Bennett), I <lb/> must say
               that the Manitoba school question <lb/> referred to in the Speech from the Throne
               <lb/> has given rise to that other question Whether <lb/> the moment had not come to
               break the tie <lb/> which unites us to the Dominion and <lb/> seek elsewhere other
               destinies for us. <lb/> Many wise and enlightened people, men <lb/> from all sections
               of the community and <lb/> from all races, have had, in the face of the <lb/> general
               mistrust which for nearly five years <lb/> now has unsettled every mind, to painfully
               <lb/> consider whether the Dominion could last <lb/> much longer, and whether the
               time had not <lb/> come, as I said, to break the tie which <lb/> unites us to it,
               should not Manitoba or the <lb/> Federal Government remedy the injustices <lb/> done
               and replace, so to say, in its former <lb/> position the fundamental stone which the
               <lb/> Manitoba Government had taken out of the <lb/> very basis of the Dominion
               structure. <lb/> Thank God, owing to the spirit of justice <lb/> of the people, owing
               to the common sense <lb/> which prevails everywhere in the Dominion, <lb/> owing
               especially to the courage shown by <lb/> the Government with respect to that school
               <lb/> question, the minds may now regain their <lb/> composedness, uneasiness may
               disappear <lb/> and hope revive among all the races which <lb/> have made this
               country their own. For <lb/> these reasons, I might be allowed to tender <lb/> to the
               executive our most sincere thanks on [...]
            </p>

            
         
            
            
            
         
            
            
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>