<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1869-05-10" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-05-10">10 May 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.

         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

           <date when="1975"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="232"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-10_Page_0232.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
         
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

        <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
        <change who="nguyenkim" when="2017-01-16"> Marked-up people. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-10_Page_0232">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-10_Page_0232.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="232" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-05-10_Page_0232.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">232</fw>    <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               May 10, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Mr. Rose</persName> of gold now in circulation, which would <lb/> require
               to be recoined, would be all brought <lb/> to England for that purpose, as the
               coining <lb/> would there be done for nothing. The Com<lb break="no"/>missioners also
               recommended that any change <lb/> should be carried out by means of a conven<lb break="no"/>tion or treaty, into which the various nations <lb/> should enter, and
               suggested a number of <lb/> matters, such as the remitting of coin which <lb/> had
               lost by sweating or use, as to which there <lb/> must be internal arrangements. He
               understood <lb/> that it was now the impression, both in <lb/> France and the United
               States, that the recom<lb break="no"/>mendation of the English Commissioners had
               <lb/> much merit in them, if they should not wholly <lb/> be accepted, and the
               English sovereign adopted <lb/> as the standard. This would cause very little <lb/>
               inconvenience to these countries, for the <lb/> pound sterling had been practically
               the <lb/> standard throughout the world up to the time <lb/> of the French
               Revolution, and in the United <lb/> States during the suspension of specie pay<lb break="no"/>ments, it was of little consequence what <lb/> particular coin was
               taken as the standard, <lb/> whereas the investigations of the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioners had shewn that the world at large <lb/> would be more inconvenienced by
               changing <lb/> from the English sovereign than the United <lb/> States by a change
               from their five dollar piece, <lb/> or France by assimilating her 25 franc piece <lb/>
               to the sovereign. Under these circumstances <lb/> he thought we should submit a
               little longer to <lb/> the inconvenience arising from the difierence <lb/> of currency
               in these Provinces. He supposed <lb/> his hon. friends from Nova Scotia would not
               <lb/> like for a month or two, or a year or two to <lb/> change the Nova Scotia
               currency, by assimi<lb break="no"/>lating it to ours, and then have to go back <lb/>
               again to their present system in the event of <lb/> France and the United States
               adopting the <lb/> English sovereign.<lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—The United States surely <lb/> won't take a
               sovereign. (Laughter.)<lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName>—Perhaps they won't refuse <lb/> one financially.
               (Hear, hear.) He thought it <lb/> would be necessary under the circumstances <lb/> he
               had explained, that we should subject <lb/> ourselves for some days longer to the
                  incon<lb break="no"/>venience of having different systems of money <lb/> and
               accounts prevailing in the different <lb/> Provinces. He hoped we would soon get
               <lb/> Newfoundland into the Confederation. New<lb break="no"/>foundland also had a
               different standard of <lb/> money, differing both from Nova Scotia and <lb/> the rest
               of the Dominion. In Newfoundland, <lb/> the sovereign, he believed, was worth $4.80,
               <lb/> while in Nova Scotia it was worth $5, and <lb/> here, $4.86 3/4. The Hudson's
               Bay Territory <lb/> again, which we hoped soon to incorporate [...]<lb/>
            </p>
            
        
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>