<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1870-03-21"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-03-21">21 March 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
      
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="580" to="580"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-21_Page_0580.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
          
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-21_Page_0580">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-21_Page_0580.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="580" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-03-21_Page_0580.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">580</fw>  <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               March 21, 1870 
               </fw>
            
            <p>
               others of great danger to the country. I, for one, 
               <lb/>
               as most of you all know, had no Part in framing 
               <lb/>
               this Confederation measure; it was not for a 
               <lb/>
               time acceptable to me, but having come here 
               <lb/>
               and having accepted it, I feel that my hon. 
               <lb/>
               friends from Shefford and Sherbrooke would 
               <lb/>
               act more wisely if, instead of making the great 
               <lb/>
               interests of this Confederacy a party question, 
               <lb/>
               they were to endeavour to combine upon some 
               <lb/>
               policy that would have for its object the suc<lb break="no"/>cess of this experiment, in the only way it 
               <lb/>
               seems to be practicable, (cheers). Now, sir, 
               <lb/>
               something has been said of Prince Edward 
               <lb/>
               Island and Newfoundland. I would say to the 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentlemen opposite, if they want Prince 
               <lb/>
               Edward Island and Newfoundland to enter the 
               <lb/>
               Confederacy, is it likely they will come in 
               <lb/>
               when they see that in questions of this magni<lb break="no"/>tude we cannot sink our party feelings, and 
               <lb/>
               cannot consider it as a question touching our 
               <lb/>
               commercial relations with other nations. If my 
               <lb/>
               hon. friend therefore would be content to look 
               <lb/>
               at this question merely as one touching our 
               <lb/>
               commercial relations, in order to secure the 
               <lb/>
               success of this great experiment of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, I think it would be much more wise than 
               <lb/>
               the course they have taken. Now, Mr. Speaker, 
               <lb/>
               I feel I have treated the subject at greater 
               <lb/>
               length than I intended, and have thrown out 
               <lb/>
               observations which occurred to me during the 
               <lb/>
               course of this debate, and I can only say that as 
               <lb/>
               the matter has been made a party question by 
               <lb/>
               the hon. members for Sherbrooke and Shef<lb break="no"/>ford, they can hardly expect that we can allow 
               <lb/>
               it to give him a party triumph, (hear, hear). My 
               <lb/>
               hon. friend does not suppose we are quite so 
               <lb/>
               soft as to allow him to choose the ground upon 
               <lb/>
               which to fight a party fight, and therefore the 
               <lb/>
               result will prove that the hon. member for 
               <lb/>
               Shefford will have no other choice but to 
               <lb/>
               accept the consequences of the course he has 
               <lb/>
               taken. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
           
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>