<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1869-04-15"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-04-15">15 April 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
         <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

           <date when="1975"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-15_Page_0001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-15_Page_0002.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-13">Created this
            document,completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="nguyenkim" when="2017-01-16"> Marked-up people. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-15_Page_0001">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-15_Page_0001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-15_Page_0002">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-15_Page_0002.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-15_Page_0001.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               15 avril 1869 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
        
<div type="section">  
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               HOUSE OF COMMONS 
               <lb/></head>

              <p rendition="simple:right">Thursday, April 15, 1869<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The Parliament met this day for the des<lb break="no"/>patch of business at three p.m. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               A message was brought by René Kimber, 
               <lb/>
               Esquire, Gentleman Usher of the Black 
               <lb/>
               Rod:-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               His Excellency, the Governor—General, de<lb break="no"/>sires the immediate attendance of this Hon<lb break="no"/>orable House in the Senate Chamber. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Accordingly, Mr. Speaker, with the House, 
               <lb/>
               went to the Senate Chamber; 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               And being returned, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Ordered, That the Honorable Sir John A. 
               <lb/>
               Macdonald have leave to bring in a Bill re<lb break="no"/>specting the administration of Oaths of Of<lb break="no"/>fice. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               He accordingly presented the said Bill to 
               <lb/>
               the House, and the same was received and 
               <lb/>
               read the first time. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The following new members were intro<lb break="no"/>duced: Mr. Amos Wright, (West York), in<lb break="no"/>troduced by Messrs. Mackenzie and Holton; 
               <lb/>
               Mr. Pelletier, (Kamouraska), by Messrs. Joly 
               <lb/>
               and Tremblay; Mr. Pickard, (York, NB.), 
               <lb/>
               by Messrs. Connell and Burpee; Dr. Lacerte, 
               <lb/>
               (St. Maurice) and Mr. McDougall, (Three 
               <lb/>
               Rivers), by Mr. Langevin and Sir John A. 
               <lb/>
               Macdonald. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Speaker</persName> reported, That when the House <lb/> did attend
                  His Excellency the Governor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral this day in the Senate
                  Chamber, His <lb/> Excellency was pleased to make a Speech to <lb/> both Houses of
                  Parliament, of which Mr. <lb/> Speaker said he had, to prevent mistakes, ob<lb
                     break="no"/>tained a copy, which he read to the House as <lb/> followeth:-<lb/>
               </p>
            <p>Honorable Gentlemen of the Senate,-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Gentlemen of the House of Commons,-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I have great satisfaction in having recourse 
               <lb/>
               to your advice, and I rejoice to think that on 
               <lb/>
               this, the first occasion on which I have had 
               <lb/>
               the honour of addressing you, we may con<lb break="no"/>gratulate ourselves on the aspect of public 
               <lb/>
               affairs at home and abroad, on the prevalence 
               <lb/>
               of peaceful counsels amongst nations, and on 
               <lb/>
               indications of agreement and tranquility fa<lb break="no"/>vorable alike to the development of foreign 
               <lb/>
               commerce and the prosecution of domestic 
               <lb/>
               industry.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            <pb n="2" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1869-04-15_Page_0002.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 15, 1869</fw>
            
            <p>
               The great scheme of Confederation was 
               <lb/>
               successfully inaugurated under the auspices 
               <lb/>
               of my Predeccessor. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It is to me a source of pride to find my 
               <lb/>
               name in honorable association with the rising 
               <lb/>
               fortunes of the Dominion of Canada, and I 
               <lb/>
               shall count it a happiness, as well as a duty, 
               <lb/>
               to co-operate, to the utmost of my ability, in 
               <lb/>
               furthering your efforts to strengthen the ties 
               <lb/>
               that bind the different provinces together, and 
               <lb/>
               to ensure the attachment of the people to the 
               <lb/>
               soil, by the enactment of wise and equal 
               <lb/>
               laws. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Your efforts in these directions seem now, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               more than ever, likely to be called into ac<lb break="no"/>tion, inasmuch as the terms upon which great 
               <lb/>
               accessions are offered to the Dominion will 
               <lb/>
               be submitted for your immediate considera<lb break="no"/>tion. 
               <lb/>
               In consequence of the Duke of Buckingham 
               <lb/>
               and Chandos' despatch of the 8th August of 
               <lb/>
               last year, stating that His Grace proposed to 
               <lb/>
               enter into negotiations with the Hudson's Bay 
               <lb/>
               Company, as to the terms on which they 
               <lb/>
               would be willing to surrender their rights 
               <lb/>
               and claims in the North—West Territory, Lord 
               <lb/>
               Monck sent home to England two Members 
               <lb/>
               of the Privy Council as a deputation to watch 
               <lb/>
               the course of the proceedings and attend to 
               <lb/>
               the interests of Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The conferences in London, and the corre<lb break="no"/>spondence on the subject have been brought 
               <lb/>
               to a definite issue by the proposal which, 
               <lb/>
               after a full review of the circumstances, Earl 
               <lb/>
               Granville made on the part of Her Majesty's 
               <lb/>
               Government for the consideration of the 
               <lb/>
               people of Canada and of the Hudson's Bay 
               <lb/>
               Company. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I have received the intelligence that the 
               <lb/>
               Hudson's Bay Company has, after some de<lb break="no"/>liberation, decided upon accepting the terms 
               <lb/>
               laid down by the Secretary of State for the 
               <lb/>
               Colonies. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               I have directed that the report of the mis<lb break="no"/>sion, and all the papers connected therewith, 
               <lb/>
               shall be duly laid before Parliament, and I 
               <lb/>
               commend them to your serious consideration, 
               <lb/>
               in view of the great importance of the sub<lb break="no"/>ject no less than in the hope that this long 
               <lb/>
               vexed question may be closed without further 
               <lb/>
               delay. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               I was much gratified by communications 
               <lb/>
               from the Governor of Newfoundland, ex<lb break="no"/>pressing the desire for admission into the 
               <lb/>
               Union which prevails amongst the inhabitants 
               <lb/>
               of that Colony, and especially by his despatch 
               <lb/>
               of the 20th March last, covering copies of 
               <lb/>
               Resolutions which have been passed by the [...]
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>