<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1870-02-21"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-02-21">21 February 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
   
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>. 
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="119"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0117.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0118.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0119.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0117">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0117.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0118">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0118.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0119">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0119.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="117" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0117.jpg"/>
           <!-- <fw type="dateline">21 février 1870 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie—I did not bring it up as a 
               <lb/>
               grievance, but as a deception practiced upon 
               <lb/>
               Reformers at the elections in 1867. I wish the 
               <lb/>
               whole of you were Conservatives, and then we 
               <lb/>
               would have no difficulty. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Sir George-È. Cartier said the matter 
               <lb/>
               did not affect or interest the representatives of 
               <lb/>
               the other Provinces. The hon. member for 
               <lb/>
               Lambton said that he wished to see them all 
               <lb/>
               Conservatives; but let him try to get up a 
               <lb/>
               Liberal party. With regard to the charge of the 
               <lb/>
               want of success in Confederation, and support<lb break="no"/>ing it by the cases of Newfoundland and Prince 
               <lb/>
               Edward Island, and the North West, he would 
               <lb/>
               refer to those countries. With regard to New<lb break="no"/>foundland, it had rejected the proposal; but the 
               <lb/>
               terms were not those of the Government but of 
               <lb/>
               the House. The House agreed to their proposed 
               <lb/>
               terms, and then they ceased to be their pro<lb break="no"/>posals; and he was surprised to see that such 
               <lb/>
               intelligent men as the members for Lambton 
               <lb/>
               and Sherbrooke should found their charges 
               <lb/>
               upon such a foundation. He would tell the 
               <lb/>
               House that if they would be quiet, in a short 
               <lb/>
               time the terms would be accepted. With regard 
               <lb/>
               to Prince Edward Island, the Government had 
               <lb/>
               made certain proposals, but they did not like to 
               <lb/>
               do anything without the approval of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. They had telegraphed the terms they 
               <lb/>
               should submit, and they had not yet received a 
               <lb/>
               reply. They could not force such powerful 
               <lb/>
               Provinces as Newfoundland and Prince 
               <lb/>
               Edward Island to accept their terms, but they 
               <lb/>
               must wait. With regard to the North-West Ter<lb break="no"/>ritory, the proceedings adopted had not been 
               <lb/>
               the action simply of the Government, but had 
               <lb/>
               been adopted by the House. After the plans had 
               <lb/>
               been adopted by Parliament the House was 
               <lb/>
               responsible for them. He hoped his hon. friend 
               <lb/>
               did not object to that. The responsibility rested 
               <lb/>
               not upon the Government, but upon the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment which had passed it; they had done all in 
               <lb/>
               their power to bring about the admission of the 
               <lb/>
               North-West into Confederation. He would 
               <lb/>
               admit that at the time the Confederation Act 
               <lb/>
               was discussed in Quebec, and at the discus<lb break="no"/>sions on it, they were not in possession of all 
               <lb/>
               the information that was desirable. The idea 
               <lb/>
               was that the Hudson Bay Company were not 
               <lb/>
               treating the inhabitants kindly, and that they 
               <lb/>
               would enter the Union gladly, but recent cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances showed that the Government of 
               <lb/>
               the country was not as unpopular as it was 
               <lb/>
               represented. His own impression was that the 
               <lb/>
               population had become indifferent to it, and 
               <lb/>
               the late lamentable circumstances proved that 
               <lb/>
               it was partly unpopular. He regretted that his 
               <lb/>
               own colleague was now to be addressed as an 
               <lb/>
               opponent. Before he accepted the office, he 
               <lb/>
               came to him (Sir George) and asked him 
               <lb/>
               
          
            <pb n="118" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0118.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">118</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 21, 1870<lb/></fw>
            
           
               whether he would support him. He promised 
               <lb/>
               him to do so for he thought that he would have 
               <lb/>
               been a good Governor. He thought now that he 
               <lb/>
               would have been a good Governor if he could 
               <lb/>
               have got into the country and could have 
               <lb/>
               explained to the settlers that the Government 
               <lb/>
               intended to do them no wrong. There could be 
               <lb/>
               no doubt that the Scotch and English half- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               breeds did not find fault with what the French 
               <lb/>
               Canadian half-breeds were doing. It had been 
               <lb/>
               published in some papers that there was a 
               <lb/>
               conspiracy against his hon. friend, because a 
               <lb/>
               French Gouvernor ought to be sent there, and 
               <lb/>
               that the Territory ought to be a second Quebec. 
               <lb/>
               He thought that these statements were the 
               <lb/>
               most wicked untruths that had ever been pub<lb break="no"/>lished. He had promised his friend his support, 
               <lb/>
               and he should not have been guilty of doing 
               <lb/>
               anything to give the least appearance of truth 
               <lb/>
               to such a wicked and mischievous untruth. The 
               <lb/>
               French Canadians were an impulsive race, and 
               <lb/>
               he thought it very wrong for a writer or a 
               <lb/>
               speaker to attempt to raise a disturbance in the 
               <lb/>
               East as well as in the West. They were French 
               <lb/>
               Canadians, but they were also British subjects 
               <lb/>
               (cheers), and were as much British, even if not 
               <lb/>
               more so, than the British, (cheers). He was a 
               <lb/>
               pure Frenchman, and he defied them to pro<lb break="no"/>duce a more loyal man. Suppose that he was 
               <lb/>
               appointed to the Governorship, would his 
               <lb/>
               being a French Canadian make him unfit for 
               <lb/>
               that position? (No! no.) Sir G.-E. Cartier then 
               <lb/>
               contrasted the liberality of the Provinces of 
               <lb/>
               Ontario and Quebec, and gave a stirring 
               <lb/>
               description of the loyalty of the old French 
               <lb/>
               inhabitants of the Province of Quebec. As to 
               <lb/>
               the inhabitants of the Red River, the French 
               <lb/>
               had gone there with their fathers, but some 
               <lb/>
               stupid fanatical papers had said there should 
               <lb/>
               be no Frenchmen there. At any rate there was 
               <lb/>
               no intention to send a French Government 
               <lb/>
               there; but still their paper had no right to 
               <lb/>
               speak of the French population as they had 
               <lb/>
               done. The Red River must be a Province like 
               <lb/>
               Quebec, Ontario, Nova Scotia, or New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, but a Province for every race to settle in. 
               <lb/>
               He thanked God there were in Lower Canada 
               <lb/>
               250,000 honest English-speaking residents; and 
               <lb/>
               he and his co-nationalists only regretted that 
               <lb/>
               there were not double the number. At the last 
               <lb/>
               census there were 80,000 French Canadians in 
               <lb/>
               Upper Canada. He hoped at the next census 
               <lb/>
               there would be 100,000 more (laughter), and he 
               <lb/>
               was convinced that the Upper Province would 
               <lb/>
               not be the worse for this increase. The address 
               <lb/>
               stated that the policy of conciliation would be 
               <lb/>
               adopted. There was the case of Ireland, con<lb break="no"/>quered hundreds of years ago, and the misgov<lb break="no"/>ernment there was only now about to be 
               <lb/>
               relieved by Protestant votes. We wanted no 
               <lb/>
               such state of things here—no country baptized 
               <lb/>
               in blood. The House and country ought to be<lb/>
               
           
            <pb n="119" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0119.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
               21 février 1870 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
           
               thankful that the North-West Territory would 
               <lb/>
               be annexed without a drop of blood being shed, 
               <lb/>
               (hear, hear). The moderation of the half-breeds 
               <lb/>
               had been remarkable; and now they under<lb break="no"/>stood the policy of the Government was to be 
               <lb/>
               pacific. He was afraid that Mr. Macdougall had 
               <lb/>
               been misled by some designing people in Red 
               <lb/>
               River. But papers would come before the 
               <lb/>
               House, and they would show the necessity of 
               <lb/>
               having this unfortunate difficulty settled as 
               <lb/>
               soon as possible. Some papers asserted that 
               <lb/>
               Bishop Taché had encouraged the movement. 
               <lb/>
               He had the authority of Bishop Taché to deny 
               <lb/>
               it <hi rendition="simple:italic">in toto</hi>. Some days before Bishop Taché left 
               <lb/>
               for Rome in December last, Bishop Taché was 
               <lb/>
               informed that Mr. Macdougall was to come. 
               <lb/>
               The Bishop wrote to the College of St. Boni<lb break="no"/>face, to the nuns in the convent there, telling 
               <lb/>
               them to welcome Mr. Macdougall. The nuns 
               <lb/>
               having the little children under their control, 
               <lb/>
               were prepared to receive him by singing the 
               <lb/>
               National Anthem. As to the remarks which Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Mackenzie had made as to the militia he (Sir 
               <lb/>
               George) could inform him that there were 
               <lb/>
               enrolled in Lower Canada 43,000 men, or 3,500 
               <lb/>
               beyond the quota. There was also an excess 
               <lb/>
               over the quota in Ontario, New Brunswick, and 
               <lb/>
               Nova Scotia. There had been strictures as to 
               <lb/>
               the success of Confederation, but could it be 
               <lb/>
               denied that the Nova Scotian’s difficulty <hi rendition="simple:italic">de 
               <lb/>
               facto</hi> had been settled? It was well after all that 
               <lb/>
               the Constitutional Act of Confederation had 
               <lb/>
               been tested in Nova Scotia. There the Local 
               <lb/>
               Parliament was against the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, but still it could not impede the whole of 
               <lb/>
               Confederation. By the action of the last Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment giving justice to Nova Scotia, the cause of 
               <lb/>
               Confederation had been vastly strengthened. 
               <lb/>
               Sir A. T. Galt had accused the Government of 
               <lb/>
               slowness in carrying out Confederation; but 
               <lb/>
               New Jersey and Rhode Island had been for 
               <lb/>
               years out of the American Union. Let Sir A. T. 
               <lb/>
               Galt, who is so great an admirer of American 
               <lb/>
               institutions, give the Dominion the same time 
               <lb/>
               for the work of Confederation. The work of 
               <lb/>
               incorporating Red River, Newfoundland and 
               <lb/>
               Prince Edward Island would be completed 
               <lb/>
               before our American neighbors had settled 
               <lb/>
               their difficulties. The Hon. Mr. Huntington had 
               <lb/>
               taken part in a meeting in the Eastern Town<lb break="no"/>ships, called for the discussion of Indepen<lb break="no"/>dence, but luckily the member for Missisquoi 
               <lb/>
               (Mr. Chamberlin) was there and opposed him. 
               <lb/>
               The result was that Mr. Huntington did not try 
               <lb/>
               to hold a meeting of the same kind anywhere 
               <lb/>
               else in Lower Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
        
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>