<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1867-11-15"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1867-11-15">15 November 1867</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, First Session</title>.
                    

        <date when="1967"/>.  
          

         <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Roger Duhamel</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="82"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-15_Page_0082.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
         
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-29">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-29">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-15_Page_0082">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-15_Page_0082.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="82" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1867-11-15_Page_0082.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">82</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES<lb/></fw> <fw type="dateline">November 15, 1867<lb/></fw>
 <div type="section">           

<head>VALUE OF SILVER COIN</head>
            
            <p>
               Mr. Morrison inquired whether the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment intended to introduce a measure for 
               <lb/>
               the regulation of the value of foreign silver 
               <lb/>
               coinage as part of the currency of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald said the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would introduce a Bill on currency 
               <lb/>
               which would include the particular subject 
               <lb/>
               mentioned. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
 </div>        
         
      <div type="section">     
            <head>
               MOVING FOR RETURNS 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie moved an address for a 
               <lb/>
               return, showing the distribution of sums paid 
               <lb/>
               out of the public chest to defray the expenses 
               <lb/>
               of the elections for this House. Carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie moved an address for a 
               <lb/>
               return of the votes polled in each electoral 
               <lb/>
               division during the late election. Carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Lawson moved for a number of returns 
               <lb/>
               respecting the sale of the Hamilton and Port 
               <lb/>
               Dover plank road. Carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Holton moved for an address for 
               <lb/>
               copies of all agreements and correspondence 
               <lb/>
               between the Government and the late 
               <lb/>
               Province of Canada and the Bank of Mont<lb break="no"/>real, having reference to the provisions of 
               <lb/>
               the act of 1866, to provide for the issue of 
               <lb/>
               provincial notes; and also all correspondence 
               <lb/>
               since 1st August, 1866, between the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the late Province of Canada as 
               <lb/>
               well as that of the Dominion of Canada with 
               <lb/>
               the Bank of Montreal respecting the mode of 
               <lb/>
               conducting the public accounts, and the terms 
               <lb/>
               on which it should continue to be held by the 
               <lb/>
               bank. Carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Oliver moved for returns respecting 
               <lb/>
               the Inland Custom House ofﬁces of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion, the amount of money collected, the 
               <lb/>
               expenses, etc. Carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie, in the absence of Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Blake, moved for copies of all warrants, or<lb break="no"/>ders, records, etc. in relation to the extradi<lb break="no"/>tion of Lamirande. Carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
      </div>
          
         
<div type="section">           
           
 <head>
               UNION OF ALL THE BRITISH NORTH 
               <lb/>
               AMERICAN PROVINCES. 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie moved an address for copies 
               <lb/>
               of all correspondence held with the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernments of the Colonies of Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island, Newfoundland and British Co<cb/><lb break="no"/>lumbia, and with the Imperial Government 
               <lb/>
               on the question of uniting these colonies and 
               <lb/>
               the unorganized territory in the North-West 
               <lb/>
               with the Dominion of Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald said the corre<lb break="no"/>spondence on these very important subjects 
               <lb/>
               was in such a state that he did not think it 
               <lb/>
               expedient to have it brought down at present. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Mackenzie said he had moved this 
               <lb/>
               because, during the elections, he had had the 
               <lb/>
               pleasure of hearing a Minister of the Crown 
               <lb/>
               declare publicly that the correspondence with 
               <lb/>
               some of these colonies was in such a state of 
               <lb/>
               forwardness that the question of a union with 
               <lb/>
               some of them was in all likelihood a question 
               <lb/>
               of months if not of weeks. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald was understood to 
               <lb/>
               say that he hoped this result would very soon 
               <lb/>
               be realized with reference to some of the 
               <lb/>
               colonies, and the motion might be repeated at 
               <lb/>
               some future day, but at present it was not for 
               <lb/>
               the interest of the country that the corre<lb break="no"/>spondence should be brought down. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The motion was accordingly withdrawn. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>           
         
      <div type="section">     
            <head>
               TITLES CONFERRED ON MINISTERS 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Parker, seconded by Mr. White moved 
               <lb/>
               an address to His Excellency that he will be 
               <lb/>
               pleased to lay before the House copies of any 
               <lb/>
               representations addressed to His Excellency 
               <lb/>
               by members of this House respecting the 
               <lb/>
               marks of Royal favour which Her Majesty 
               <lb/>
               had been pleased to confer upon them, and 
               <lb/>
               of all despatches on the same subject to or 
               <lb/>
               from Her Majesty’s principal Secretary of 
               <lb/>
               State for the Colonies. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir John A. Macdonald said he was afraid 
               <lb/>
               he could not consent to the passage of this 
               <lb/>
               address; any representations that might have 
               <lb/>
               been made to His Excellency, and any des<lb break="no"/>patches addressed to the Colonial Secretary 
               <lb/>
               were addressed to the Governor General in his 
               <lb/>
               Imperial capacity and had reference to a 
               <lb/>
               subject with which the House had no con<lb break="no"/>cern. The conferring of Royal favour was an 
               <lb/>
               act of Her Majesty in her Imperial position, 
               <lb/>
               and any action of the Governor-General in 
               <lb/>
               the matter was in his capacity as an Imperial 
               <lb/>
               ofﬁcer. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Dr. Parker said he had not had time to look 
               <lb/>
               up authorities, but he had found one case in 
               <lb/>
               which the granting of those honours by the 
               <lb/>
               Crown gave dissatisfaction and was made the 
               <lb/>
               subject of discussion in Parliament. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
      </div>   
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>