<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1949-02-04"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1949-02-04">4 February 1949</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Twentieth Parliament, Fifth Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1949"/>. 
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmond Cloutier, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="231"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-02-04_Page_0231.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
     
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-09-26">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-09-26">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1949-02-04_Page_0231">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-02-04_Page_0231.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="231" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-02-04_Page_0231.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">231</fw>

<div type="section">


<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS</head>

</div>

<div type="section">
           

<p rendition="simple:right"><emph>Friday, February 4, 1949</emph></p> 


            <p>
     The house met at three o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     INCOME TAX 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>COMMUNICATION OF INFORMATION TO THE 
     <lb/>
     SENATE OR HOUSE OF COMMONS</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KNOW1">Mr. Stanley Knowles</persName> (Winnipeg North 
     <lb/>
     Centre) moved for leave to introduce Bill 
     <lb/>
     No. 10, to amend the Income Tax Act. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. Members</persName>: Explain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KNOW1">Mr. Knowles</persName>: Mr. Speaker, this bill would 
     <lb/>
     add to section 121 of the new Income Tax 
     <lb/>
     Act the following words which are underlined 
     <lb/>
     in the bill: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Provided that nothing in this section shall operate 
     <lb/>
     to prevent a minister of the crown from communi<lb break="no"/>cating to the Senate or to the House of Commons 
     <lb/>
     any information with respect to corporations ob<lb break="no"/>tained under the provisions of this act. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     The purpose of this amendment is to 
     <lb/>
     remove in part the restrictions as to secrecy 
     <lb/>
     imposed by section 121 of the Income Tax 
     <lb/>
     Act, which as it stands at present can have 
     <lb/>
     the effect of preventing a minister of the 
     <lb/>
     crown from giving the Senate or the House 
     <lb/>
     such information as it might be perfectly 
     <lb/>
     legitimate to ask for and obtain. No change 
     <lb/>
     is made by this bill in the matter of informa<lb break="no"/>tion obtained from personal income tax 
     <lb/>
     returns. Such information must still be kept 
     <lb/>
     secret. I may say that in this particular the 
     <lb/>
     bill is different from the one which I intro<lb break="no"/>duced last year and to which some objection 
     <lb/>
     was taken. On the other hand, this amend<lb break="no"/>ment would make it possible to make public 
     <lb/>
     any information respecting corporations 
     <lb/>
     obtained by the income tax division of the 
     <lb/>
     Department of National Revenue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to and bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CANADIAN COMMERCIAL CORPORATION 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>ADVANCES BY WAY OF LOAN—EXTENSION OF LIFE 
     <lb/>
     OF THE CORPORATION</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Right Hon. L. S. St. Laurent (for the Minis<lb break="no"/>ter of Trade and Commerce) moved that the 
     <lb/>
     house go into committee at the next sitting to 
     <lb/>
     consider the following resolution: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That it is expedient to present a bill to amend the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian Commercial Corporation Act to provide 
     <lb/>
     authority for advances to the corporation by way of 
     <lb/>
     loan out of the consolidated revenue fund and to 
     <lb/>
     extend the time of operation of the act. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <cb/>
            

<p>
     He said: His Excellency the Governor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, having been made acquainted with the 
     <lb/>
     subject matter of this resolution, recom<lb break="no"/>mends it to the consideration of the house. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     STATUTE LAW AMENDMENT 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>AMENDMENTS TO IMPLEMENT TERMS OF UNION 
     <lb/>
     OF NEWFOUNDLAND WITH CANADA</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GARS1">Hon. Stuart S. Garson</persName> (Minister of Justice) 
     <lb/>
     moved that the house go into committee at 
     <lb/>
     the next sitting to consider the following 
     <lb/>
     resolution: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That it is expedient to present a bill to amend 
     <lb/>
     several statutes to make them applicable to or 
     <lb/>
     otherwise conform with the Canadian confederation 
     <lb/>
     as and when Newfoundland becomes a province of 
     <lb/>
     Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     He said: His Excellency the Governor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, having been made acquainted with the 
     <lb/>
     subject matter of this resolution, recom<lb break="no"/>mends it to the consideration of the house. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     HOUSE OF COMMONS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>BUSINESS OF THE HOUSE—QUESTIONS AND 
     <lb/>
     NOTICES OF MOTIONS FOR PRODUCTION OF PAPERS</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

   
            <p>
     On the orders of the day: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DREW2">Mr. George A. Drew</persName> (Leader of the Oppo<lb break="no"/>sition): May I ask the Prime Minister when 
     <lb/>
     provision will be made for answering the 
     <lb/>
     sixty-nine questions now on the order paper, 
     <lb/>
     and for dealing with notices of motion for 
     <lb/>
     production of papers? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Right Hon. L. S. St. Laurent (Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister): I shall be glad to take the question of 
     <lb/>
     the leader of the opposition as notice. I will 
     <lb/>
     discuss the matter with my colleagues and 
     <lb/>
     give an answer at the earliest opportunity. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>REVISION OF STANDING ORDERS—RECOMMENDA<lb break="no"/>TIONS OF SPECIAL COMMITTEE OF LAST SESSION</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KNOW1">Mr. Stanley Knowles</persName> (Winnipeg North Cen<lb break="no"/>tre): May I direct a question to the Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister? Has the government given con<lb break="no"/>sideration to recommending to the house the 
     <lb/>
     adoption of any of the proposed changes in 
     <lb/>
     standing orders that were recommended to 
     <lb/>
     the house last session by a committee of 
     <lb/>
     which Your Honour was chairman, and the 
     <lb/>
     report of which, as the Prime Minister will 
     <lb/>
     recall, was unanimous? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>