<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1948-06-04"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1948-06-04">4 June 1948</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Twentieth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
               

          <date when="1948"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmond Cloutier, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="4789" to="4789"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-04_Page_4789.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
        
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-30">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-04_Page_4789">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-04_Page_4789.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="4789" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1948-06-04_Page_4789.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">JUNE 4, 1948</fw> 
    
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Supply—Post Office</hi></fw>
     
     <fw type="num">4789</fw> 
     
<div type="section">

            <head>
     HOUSE OF COMMONS 
     <lb/></head>
<p>
     INQUIRY AS TO SETTING UP OF RADIO COMMITTEE 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On the orders of the day: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DIEF1">Mr. J. G. DIEFENBAKER</persName> (Lake Centre): <lb/> Mr. Speaker, I
                  wish to direct a question to the <lb/> Prime Minister, in the absence of the
                     appro<lb break="no"/>priate minister. In view of the fact that the <lb/> house
                  has decided today to sit from eleven <lb/> o'clock in the morning, beginning
                  shortly, is <lb/> the Prime Minister in a position to advise <lb/> whether, having
                  regard to recent changes in <lb/> policy by the Canadian Broadcasting Corpora<lb
                     break="no"/>tion, the radio committee will be set up during <lb/> the rest of
                  the present session? <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:KING1">Right Hon. W. L. MACKENZIE KING</persName>
                  <lb/> (Prime Minister) : I am sorry I cannot give my <lb/> hon. friend an answer
                  offhand, but I shall hope <lb/> to be prepared to give an answer on Monday. <lb/>
               </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     NEWFOUNDLAND 
     <lb/></head>
<p>
     REFERENDUM ON FUTURE FORM OF GOVERNMENT 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On the orders of the day: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:KING1">Right Hon. W. L. MACKENZIE KING</persName>
                  <lb/> (Prime Minister): The house may be inter<lb break="no"/>ested in having the
                  latest word in regard to the <lb/> referendum taken in Newfoundland a day or <lb/>
                  two ago on the future form of government in <lb/> that colony. Only nine out of
                  twenty-five dist<lb break="no"/>ricts have complete returns. While incomplete
                  <lb/> the latest returns for the whole. up to 12.30 <lb/> today's Newfoundland
                  time, indicate the vote: <lb/> for responsible government, 65.991; for con<lb
                     break="no"/>federation, 60,147; for commission government, <lb/> 20,805.
                  Apparently no form of government will <lb/> have a majority, and another
                  referendum will <lb/> therefore have to be held, probably some <lb/> weeks hence,
                  to decide between the two forms, <lb/> responsible government or confederation.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     SUPPLY 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The house in committee of supply. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Macdonald (Brantford City) in the chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     POST OFFICE DEPARTMENT 
     <lb/></p>
<p>
     309. Departmental administration, $1,096,287. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DIEF1">Mr. DIEFENBAKER</persName>: There are one or two <lb/> matters, Mr.
                  Chairman, which I should like <lb/> to "bring to the attention of the minister
                  with <lb/> a view to securing some information from him. <lb/> The first has to do
                  with representations that <lb/> have been made to me by postmasters in <lb/>
                  revenue offices. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     For these men and women there are no such 
     <lb/>
     things as minimum salaries or hours of employ<lb break="no"/>ment, holidays or promotion. They render a 
     <lb/>
     great service to the people of the country as a 
     <lb/>
     whole; they receive their payment on a com<lb break="no"/>mission basis, and since they are not classified 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
          
   
          
     as civil servants, they receive no pension. 
     <lb/>
     According to representations made to me, dur<lb break="no"/>ing the war they worked for a number of gov<lb break="no"/>ernment departments without any remunera<lb break="no"/>tion, giving assistance in reporting enemy 
     <lb/>
     aliens, national registration, the foreign 
     <lb/>
     exchange control board, and generally making 
     <lb/>
     themselves useful in connection with various 
     <lb/>
     activities furthering the war effort. Having 
     <lb/>
     regard to the increase in the cost of living, and 
     <lb/>
     the surplus enjoyed by the post office depart<lb break="no"/>ment, what consideration has the government 
     <lb/>
     given to providing for a 25 per cent increase 
     <lb/>
     in rates as requested by these postmasters? 
     <lb/>
     Also, what if anything, is being done toward 
     <lb/>
     the establishment of a pension plan for them? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Under the present deputy postmaster gen<lb break="no"/>eral, in common with hon. members in all parts 
     <lb/>
     of this house I have observed an attitude that 
     <lb/>
     I desire to commend. When matters are 
     <lb/>
     brought to the attention of the deputy post<lb break="no"/>master general, he has been most diligent in 
     <lb/>
     his endeavour to remove any cause of incon<lb break="no"/>venience. I think it only fair to say that; for 
     <lb/>
     after all, many of these officials are doing 
     <lb/>
     responsible, effective and efficient work. Too 
     <lb/>
     often we take for granted what they are doing, 
     <lb/>
     and fail to pass on to them and to those who 
     <lb/>
     work with them the commendation of the con<lb break="no"/>stituents whom we represent in parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     What consideration, if any, has been given 
     <lb/>
     during the year to the reduction of the postage 
     <lb/>
     rate from four cents to three cents, which was 
     <lb/>
     indicated last year as a possibility? The mat<lb break="no"/>ter is one that I think deserves the considera<lb break="no"/>tion of the minister, and I feel that the com<lb break="no"/>mittee should have an explanation with 
     <lb/>
     regard to it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I want to join with the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Wentworth in the representations he made 
     <lb/>
     last evening on a matter to which he has 
     <lb/>
     made frequent reference. He asked that some<lb break="no"/>thing be done to relieve the people from the 
     <lb/>
     present high postage rates on parcels sent to 
     <lb/>
     Britain to help the people over there. I know 
     <lb/>
     of two or three persons in my own constituency 
     <lb/>
     who during the last year have sent parcels, to 
     <lb/>
     the limit now allowed, to the parents of young 
     <lb/>
     men who served in the armed forces of this 
     <lb/>
     country and whose acquaintance they made 
     <lb/>
     during the war. The minister has had this 
     <lb/>
     matter brought to his attention on previous 
     <lb/>
     occasions. I know he would have the support 
     <lb/>
     of Canadians everywhere were he to make 
     <lb/>
     provision to remove, as far as possible, the 
     <lb/>
     postage rates on parcels being sent to Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain by patriotic Canadians with a view 
     <lb/>
     to assisting the people over there to get 
     <lb/>
     additional nutritional value in their diet. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
     </div>    </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>