<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_NFLD_1949-01-26" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1949-01-26">26 January 1949</date>, Canadian Confederation with Newfoundland</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Twentieth Parliament, Fifth Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1949"/>. 
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmond Cloutier, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="11"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0009.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0010.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0011.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-09-25">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-09-25">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0009">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0009.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0010">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0010.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0011">
         <graphic url="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0011.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="9" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0009.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">JANUARY 26, 1949</fw>  <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Business of the House</hi></fw> <fw type="num">9</fw>
    

<!-- GL, 2017-09-25, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day --> 
            <!--<p>
     bers to compose the standing committees of this 
     <lb/>
     house under standing order 63, said committee to 
     <lb/>
     be composed of Messrs. Fournier (Hull), Claxton, 
     <lb/>
     Casselman, Knowles and Weir. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     INTERNAL ECONOMY COMMISSION 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Right Hon. L. S. St. Laurent</persName> (Prime Minis<lb break="no"/>ter) presented the following message from His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency the Governor General: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The Governor General transmits to the House of 
     <lb/>
     Commons a certified copy of an approved minute 
     <lb/>
     of council, appointing the Hon. J. A. MacKinnon, 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Mines and Resources, the Hon. Colin 
     <lb/>
     Gibson, Secretary of State, the Hon. Alphonse 
     <lb/>
     Fournier, Minister of Public Works. the Hon. D. C. 
     <lb/>
     Abbott, Minister of Finance, to act with the Speaker 
     <lb/>
     of the House of Commons as commissioners for the 
     <lb/>
     purposes and under the provisions of chapter 145 
     <lb/>
     of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1927, intituled: 
     <lb/>
     An act respecting the House of Commons. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     LIBRARY OF PARLIAMENT 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Report of. the joint librarians of parliament. 
     <lb/>
     —Mr. Speaker. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     HOUSE OF COMMONS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">RESIGNATION OF CLERK ASSISTANT AND 
<lb/>
     APPOINTMENT OF DEPUTY CLERK 
     <lb/>
     ASSISTANT</head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Speaker</persName>: I have the honour to inform 
     <lb/>
     the house that during the recess the resigna<lb break="no"/>tion has been received of Roy T. Graham, 
     <lb/>
     Esquire, K.C., as clerk assistant, and that 
     <lb/>
     John T. Dun, Esquire, Chief of Committees 
     <lb/>
     and Private Legislation Branch, has been 
     <lb/>
     appointed as deputy clerk assistant. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     BUSINESS OF THE HOUSE 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">MOTION FOR PRECEDENCE OF DEBATE ON ADDRESS 
<lb/>
     —DEBATE ON ADMISSION OF NEWFOUNDLAND 
     <lb/>
     INTO CONFEDERATION</head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Right Hon. L. S. St. Laurent</persName> (Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister): Mr. Speaker, I beg leave to move, 
     <lb/>
     seconded by the Minister of Trade and Com<lb break="no"/>merce (Mr. Howe): 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That the speech of His Excellency the Governor 
     <lb/>
     General to both houses of parliament be taken into 
     <lb/>
     consideration on Thursday next, and that this order 
     <lb/>
     have precedence over all business except the intro<lb break="no"/>duction of bills and government notices of motions 
     <lb/>
     on Thursday and Friday, January 27 and 28, 1949. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     I had intended at the same time to move 
     <lb/>
     for an order of the house on the subject of 
     <lb/>
     business of the house next week, but I have 
     <lb/>
     been informed by some hon. members that 
     <lb/>
     that arrangement had not yet appealed to 
     <lb/>
     them as being the best that could be made, 
     <lb/>
     that there might have to be a debate on a 
     <lb/>
     motion of that kind, and that it would better 
     <lb/>
     suit their convenience if the debate did not 
     <lb/>
     take place until Friday. So, instead of com<lb break="no"/>bining that with the motion I now put before 
     <lb/>
     the house, I would simply give notice of a 


            <cb/>

     motion to be made on Friday with respect to 
     <lb/>
     procedure for next week and following days. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DREW2">Mr. George A. Drew</persName> (Leader of the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion): Mr. Speaker, as this motion is not in 
     <lb/>
     the usual form, I think it would be very 
     <lb/>
     helpful to hon. members if the Prime Minister 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. St. Laurent) would explain the effect of 
     <lb/>
     the motion, and what he suggests should be 
     <lb/>
     done tomorrow under that motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: The motion is not in the 
     <lb/>
     usual form, inasmuch as it does not extend 
     <lb/>
     to the whole of the time during which the 
     <lb/>
     address of His Excellency the Governor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral and addresses in reply may be under 
     <lb/>
     debate in the house. But it does provide, in 
     <lb/>
     the usual form, that tomorrow and Friday the 
     <lb/>
     speech from the throne be considered. The 
     <lb/>
     procedure on adoption of the motion would 
     <lb/>
     be that the address would be moved and 
     <lb/>
     seconded tomorrow. Then I would assume 
     <lb/>
     that, in accordance with traditional practice, 
     <lb/>
     Your Honour would recognize first the leader 
     <lb/>
     of the opposition (Mr. Drew), that I should 
     <lb/>
     follow him, that he would then recognize the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Rosetown-Biggar (Mr. Cold<lb break="no"/>well), and following the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Rosetown-Biggar, the hon. member for— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GRAY2">Mr. Graydon</persName>: No; you did not do that 
     <lb/>
    before. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: —the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Peace River (Mr. Low). After those hon. 
     <lb/>
     members have been heard, then the debate 
     <lb/>
     would continue in such order as might be 
     <lb/>
     arranged by the Whips, in the usual manner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I had intended at this time to move that 
     <lb/>
     afterwards, from Monday, January 31, until 
     <lb/>
     and including Friday, February 11, matters 
     <lb/>
     having to do with the entry of Newfoundland 
     <lb/>
     into confederation should have precedence 
     <lb/>
     over other matters. But I was told by some 
     <lb/>
     hon. members that that did not appeal to 
     <lb/>
     them as being the proper procedure, that 
     <lb/>
     there would be debate on a motion of that 
     <lb/>
     kind, and that it would be preferable not to 
     <lb/>
     have the debate which would be expected 
     <lb/>
     this afternoon in view of the fact that other 
     <lb/>
     engagements had been made. I am therefore 
     <lb/>
     giving notice that I will make that motion 
     <lb/>
     on Friday. The purpose of the motion will 
     <lb/>
     be that on and from January 31 until Friday, 
     <lb/>
     February 11, the matters dealing with the 
     <lb/>
     entry of Newfoundland shall have precedence. 
     <lb/>
     However I am not making that motion at the 
     <lb/>
     present time; I am putting a notice on the 
     <lb/>
     order paper. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DREW2">Mr. Drew</persName>: Mr. Speaker, I do think that 
     <lb/>
     hon. members should recognize the effect of 
     <lb/>
     the motion in the form in which it is pre<lb break="no"/>sented. In the form in which it is presented 
     <lb/>
     the debate on the speech from the throne will 
 

            <pb n="10" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0010.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">10</fw>  <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Business of the House</hi></fw> <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS</fw>
  
     have precedence only for Thursday and Fri<lb break="no"/>day, and to carry forward the debate under 
     <lb/>
     the usual terms or following the usual pro<lb break="no"/>cedure would require another motion, were 
     <lb/>
     it not for the fact that the Prime Minister has 
     <lb/>
     indicated that he intends to introduce a motion 
     <lb/>
     which would have the effect of postponing 
     <lb/>
     the debate on the speech from the throne. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I do not think it would be appropriate for 
     <lb/>
     me to make any comments on this motion in 
     <lb/>
     relation to the motion of which notice has 
     <lb/>
     been given. Nevertheless the effect of this 
     <lb/>
     motion is such that it would be unwise to 
     <lb/>
     ignore the position in which the debate on 
     <lb/>
     the speech from the throne is left unless the 
     <lb/>
     second motion is carried by the house. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     While the Prime Minister may assume that 
     <lb/>
     he will be able to persuade a sufficient number 
     <lb/>
     of hon. members to produce that result by 
     <lb/>
     their votes, such assumption should not blind 
     <lb/>
     hon. members to the fact that if this motion 
     <lb/>
     as it now stands is carried nothing will have 
     <lb/>
     been done to provide for the continued debate 
     <lb/>
     on the speech from the throne after Friday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I suggest that not only is this motion con<lb break="no"/>trary to any motion that has been introduced 
     <lb/>
     in this house since confederation; it is a 
     <lb/>
     motion which it carried in its present form 
     <lb/>
     presupposes the ability of the government to 
     <lb/>
     carry a subsequent motion by the accept<lb break="no"/>ance by members of one party of the decision 
     <lb/>
     of the Prime Minister without any regard to 
     <lb/>
     another motion. The continuance of this 
     <lb/>
     debate rests entirely upon that assumption, 
     <lb/>
     which, it seems to me, is not consistent with 
     <lb/>
     our parliamentary practice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I urge the Prime Minister seriously to con<lb break="no"/>sider the withdrawal at this point of the 
     <lb/>
     motion and the substitution, which he can 
     <lb/>
     easily make, of the ordinary motion to the 
     <lb/>
     effect that the debate continue to have pre<lb break="no"/>cedence. Then if the subsequent motion gains 
     <lb/>
     the support of this house the effect will be the 
     <lb/>
     carrying forward of the debate anyway. Such 
     <lb/>
     a motion would not in any way be subject to 
     <lb/>
     the disabilities that this motion contains. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I should like to point out that I as well as 
     <lb/>
     other hon. members of the house are under 
     <lb/>
     some handicap in debating a motion such as 
     <lb/>
     this because it deals with the address of His 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's representative. It is customary, 
     <lb/>
     and I believe the record will show that it 
     <lb/>
     has always been the practice, that the motion 
     <lb/>
     provide that the debate have precedence over 
     <lb/>
     all other government business. On those 
     <lb/>
     rare occasions when a subsequent motion 
     <lb/>
     was moved which had the effect of postponing 
     <lb/>
     the debate it related to the debate in the 
     <lb/>
     customary form and provided for the carry<lb break="no"/>ing forward of that debate without any such 
     <lb/>
     limitations as are now laid down. I again 
     <lb/>
     ask the Prime Minister to take this into 
     <lb/>
     consideration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    
            <cb/>
            
<p>
     <persName ref="pers:COLD1">Mr. M. J. Coldwell</persName> (Rosetown-Biggar): Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, I should like to support the leader of 
     <lb/>
     the opposition (Mr. Drew). This motion, being 
     <lb/>
     worded as it is, does exactly what he says it 
     <lb/>
     does: it limits the debate to two days. It 
     <lb/>
     seems to me that if we pass this motion we 
     <lb/>
     shall be limiting ourselves to Thursday and 
     <lb/>
     Friday. Without notice of another motion we 
     <lb/>
     might find ourselves in a difficult position 
     <lb/>
     if the proposal of the government should 
     <lb/>
     not carry on Friday. In a democratic insti<lb break="no"/>tution we have always the right to pre<lb break="no"/>suppose that hon. members may not always 
     <lb/>
     vote in accordance with the wishes of the 
     <lb/>
     government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I join the leader of the opposition in sug<lb break="no"/>gesting that the wording of the motion be 
     <lb/>
     changed. We can deal with the situation as it 
     <lb/>
     arises on Friday, when the other motion 
     <lb/>
     which the Prime Minister (Mr. St. Laurent) 
     <lb/>
     has foreshadowed can be discussed and, if the 
     <lb/>
     house sees fit, passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: I cannot accede to the 
     <lb/>
     request made by the leader of the opposition 
     <lb/>
     and by the hon. member for Rosetown-Biggar 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Coldwell) because that would be asking 
     <lb/>
     the house to make an order and expecting the 
     <lb/>
     house to reverse that order on Friday. I 
     <lb/>
     moved my motion in this form because I had 
     <lb/>
     been told by hon. members that there would 
     <lb/>
     be a debate upon any motion made in an 
     <lb/>
     attempt to postpone the debate on the address. 
     <lb/>
     If that were so I thought it would be prefer<lb break="no"/>able to have it made on Friday. I am quite 
     <lb/>
     prepared to agree to that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am prepared to state here that I am mak<lb break="no"/>ing no other assumption than the assumption 
     <lb/>
     that this motion provides for the order of 
     <lb/>
     business for two days and that a motion will 
     <lb/>
     have to be made on Friday for the order of 
     <lb/>
     business subsequent to that. If the order on 
     <lb/>
     Friday is not made in the terms of the motion 
     <lb/>
     of which I have given notice, I can move 
     <lb/>
     another motion for that order of business. 
     <lb/>
     This is merely to determine that we can go 
     <lb/>
     on tomorrow and Friday with the debate on 
     <lb/>
     the address. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROWE2">Mr. Rowe</persName>: By unanimous consent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: No, not by unanimous 
     <lb/>
     consent but by virtue of the motion I am now 
     <lb/>
     putting before the house. If hon. members 
     <lb/>
     wish to have a debate this afternoon I am 
     <lb/>
     quite prepared to have it. I even suggested 
     <lb/>
     that we should have it. However, I was told 
     <lb/>
     that that would not meet their convenience 
     <lb/>
     because other arrangements had been made 
     <lb/>
     for the rest of the day. It was necessary to 
     <lb/>
     make some provision for tomorrow and 
     <lb/>
     Friday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Friday I will move that the debate on 
     <lb/>
     the address be not given precedence during 
     <lb/>
     those days, but that precedence be given to 


            <pb n="11" facs="final/images/NFLD_H_of_C_1949-01-26_Page_0011.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">JANUARY 26, 1949</fw>   <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Business of the House</hi></fw>  <fw type="num">11</fw>
         

     the measure with respect to Newfoundland. 
     <lb/>
     We do not mean to adopt any dictatorial 
     <lb/>
     attitude. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. Members</persName>: Oh, oh. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: Hon. members can say 
     <lb/>
     "Oh, oh" all they like, but that is the fact. I 
     <lb/>
     know the intent of our desires just as well 
     <lb/>
     as hon. members who are saying "Oh, oh". I 
     <lb/>
     wish to meet in the greatest degree possible 
     <lb/>
     the convenience of all hon. members in the 
     <lb/>
     house. I do not want to start a debate today 
     <lb/>
     on the reasons for proceeding immediately 
     <lb/>
     with the Newfoundland measure; that will 
     <lb/>
     come on Friday. If we cannot arrange some<lb break="no"/>thing that appears to be satisfactory to the 
     <lb/>
     majority of the members of the house, we will 
     <lb/>
     arrange something else. There is no inten<lb break="no"/>tion of getting a snap decision of the house, 
     <lb/>
     but I do not think it would be appropriate for 
     <lb/>
     me to ask the house to make one order today 
     <lb/>
     and then come back on Friday and ask it to 
     <lb/>
     vary that order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DREW2">Mr. Drew</persName>: I have asked the Prime Minister 
     <lb/>
     to reconsider this, but since he has not done 
     <lb/>
     so I would point out that this motion does not 
     <lb/>
     produce the effect which he has indicated to 
     <lb/>
     the house. He says that this would have the 
     <lb/>
     effect of carrying on the debate; that unless 
     <lb/>
     there was another motion we would go on 
     <lb/>
     with the debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: Oh, no, I did not say that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:DREW2">Mr. Drew</persName>: That was the impression I 
     <lb/>
     gained. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: I am sorry I did not 
     <lb/>
     express myself sufficiently clearly. I said that 
     <lb/>
     If we could not arrange to go on with the 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland matter we would make some 
     <lb/>
     other arrangement for using the time of the 
     <lb/>
     house from Monday onward. I quite realize 
     <lb/>
     that some provision will have to be made on 
     <lb/>
     Friday for the business of the house during 
     <lb/>
     the days of next week and following. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DREW2">Mr. Drew</persName>: I should like to continue what 
     <lb/>
     I was pointing out. The practice I have sug<lb break="no"/>gested is the accepted practice and Hansard 
     <lb/>
     will show clearly that the right hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Glengarry (Mr. Mackenzie King) on the 
     <lb/>
     last occasion, when he as Prime Minister 
     <lb/>
     presented a motion of a similar character, 
     <lb/>
     presented the motion that has always been 
     <lb/>
     presented to deal with the speech from the 
     <lb/>
     throne and give it precedence. On the very 
     <lb/>
     occasion when he did that he indicated that 
     <lb/>
     he would be introducing another motion 
     <lb/>
     which would have the effect of postponing the 
     <lb/>
     debate on a certain day. Therefore there is 
     <lb/>
     no inconsistency in presenting the usual 
  

            <cb/>
  

     motion to give precedence to the debate, and 
     <lb/>
     to give on Friday, as the Prime Minister now 
     <lb/>
     has, notice of a motion, to be debated then, 
     <lb/>
     which, if carried by the house, would have 
     <lb/>
     the effect of postponing the debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This motion is not in the form in which a 
     <lb/>
     motion for debate on the speech from the 
     <lb/>
     throne has been put forward traditionally in 
     <lb/>
     this house. My understanding of the rule is 
     <lb/>
     that such a motion requires unanimous con<lb break="no"/>sent, or forty-eight hours' notice. I indicate 
     <lb/>
     to you, Mr. Speaker, that I do not consent to 
     <lb/>
     proceeding with this motion in its present 
     <lb/>
     form. I want to make quite sure that no sug<lb break="no"/>gestion can be made that we are blocking the 
     <lb/>
     debate on the speech from the throne. There<lb break="no"/>fore, if the Prime Minister will now introduce 
     <lb/>
     the motion that has been used regularly since 
     <lb/>
     confederation, we will support it and give 
     <lb/>
     unanimous consent.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KNOW1">Mr. Stanley Knowles</persName> (Winnipeg North 
     <lb/>
     Centre): The Prime Minister indicated that 
     <lb/>
     one of his aims was to avoid a debate on pro<lb break="no"/>cedure today, but it must be apparent to him' 
     <lb/>
     that he has made the very move which is 
     <lb/>
     likely to produce a prolonged debate. Yet I 
     <lb/>
     suggest it is still possible to avoid a pro<lb break="no"/>cedural debate today if he will accept the. 
     <lb/>
     suggestion made by the leader of the opposi<lb break="no"/>tion (Mr. Drew) and the leader of this group. 
     <lb/>
     All he has to do is to withdraw the motion 
     <lb/>
     he has made and make the motion that has 
     <lb/>
     been made on almost every occasion, namely, 
     <lb/>
     that the debate on the address begin tomor<lb break="no"/>row and have precedence until it is con<lb break="no"/>cluded. As the leader of the opposition has 
     <lb/>
     said, he can then give notice that on Friday 
     <lb/>
     it is his intention to move a motion to the 
     <lb/>
     effect that notwithstanding the order of 
     <lb/>
     January 26 such and such shall be the case. 
     <lb/>
     I would point out that not only was this done 
     <lb/>
     in that manner last year, but in many sessions 
     <lb/>
     the debate on the address has proceeded for a 
     <lb/>
     considerable period of time and has then been 
     <lb/>
     interrupted by a subsequent motion. I would 
     <lb/>
     suggest that the Prime Minister should make 
     <lb/>
     the usual motion. If he will accept that sug<lb break="no"/>gestion he will avoid a debate today. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: I think the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     is making a mistake. The motion that was 
     <lb/>
     made was that the debate on the address have 
     <lb/>
     precedence for one day and that on the 
     <lb/>
     following Monday measures arising out of 
     <lb/>
     the emergency legislation— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KNOW1">Mr. Knowles</persName>: On a point of order, that was 
     <lb/>
     interpreted to go on and on, indefinitely. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR6">Mr. St. Laurent</persName>: Yes, but the motion that. 
     <lb/>
     was made was not that the debate on the 
     <lb/>
     address have precedence until concluded. It 
     <lb/>
     was that it have precedence only over the 
     <lb/>
     Monday following the opening of parliament [...] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>