<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="Morris_Chapter_03"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreatyNeg">Treaty Negotiations</name>, <date from="1862-10" to="1862-11">October 1862 to November 1862</date>, Between Canada and First Nations of Manitoba and the Northwest Territories.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:Morris">
          

               <author>Alexander Morris</author>.
          
         
          <title>The Treaties of Canada with the Indians of Manitoba and the North-West Territories Including the Negotiations on Which They Are Based, and Other Information Relating Thereto.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1880"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>: <publisher>Willing &amp; Williamson</publisher>.
          
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="24"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_022.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_023.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_024.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-28">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-28">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_022">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_022.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_023">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_023.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_024">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_024.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <pb n="22" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_022.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">22</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 


<div type="chapter">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">CHAPTER III.</head>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">THE MANITOULIN ISLAND TREATY.</p>


            <p>
     SOME years after the completion of the Robinson Treaties, 
     <lb/>
     the then Government of the old Province of Canada 
     <lb/>
     deemed it desirable to effect a treaty with the Indians dwelling 
     <lb/>
     upon the Great Manitoulin Island in Lake Huron, as a comple<lb break="no"/>ment to the former treaties, and with the object of rendering 
     <lb/>
     available for settlement the large tract of good land upon the 
     <lb/>
     Island. The duty was entrusted to the Honorable William 
     <lb/>
     McDougall, then Superintendent-General of Indian Affairs, 
     <lb/>
     who, in the month of October, 1862, proceeded to the Island, 
     <lb/>
     accompanied by the late William Spragge, Esq., Deputy Super<lb break="no"/>intendent of Indian Affairs, and Mr. F. Assicknack, of the 
     <lb/>
     Indian Office, Toronto, as interpreter. Mr. McDougall encoun<lb break="no"/>tered considerable difficulties, but by firmness and decision 
     <lb/>
     eventually succeeded in obtaining a surrender from the Indians 
     <lb/>
     of the Island, excluding however from the surrender that 
     <lb/>
     portion of it easterly of Heywood Island and the Manitoulin 
     <lb/>
     Gulf. 
       </p>

            <p>The terms of the treaty, which will be found in the Appen<lb break="no"/>dix, were adapted to the peculiar circumstances of the Indians 
     <lb/>and were well and wisely framed. The result has been to ren<lb break="no"/>der available for settlement a large tract of land on the Island, 
     <lb/>much of which is now occupied by a prosperous and thriving 
     <lb/>population. I conclude this brief notice of an important treaty 
     <lb/>by submitting, to the attention of the reader, the report of the 
     <lb/>Hon. W. McDougall, to His Excellency the Governor-General 
     <lb/>in Council, of the results of his mission. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <pb n="23" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_023.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Manitoulin Island Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">23</fw>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     MANITOULIN ISLAND, <hi rendition="simple:italic">November 3rd, 1862.</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The undersigned has the honor to state for the information of His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency the Governor-General in Council, that, under the authority of the 
     <lb/>
     Order in Council of the twelfth day of September, 1862, he proceeded early 
     <lb/>
     in the month of October last to visit the Great Manitoulin Island, accom<lb break="no"/>panied by William Spragge, Esq., Deputy Superintendent of Indian Affairs, 
     <lb/>
     and Mr. F. Assicknack of the Indian Office, Toronto, as interpreter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The resident agent, Captain Ironside, under instructions from the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment, had caused the Indians residing on the Island to be notified of the 
     <lb/>
     intended visit of the undersigned, and of its object, and had summoned them 
     <lb/>
     to attend at Manitowaning on the fourth ultimo. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Chiefs and principal men, with the exception of one or two detained 
     <lb/>
     by illness, and nearly all the males above} the age of eighteen years, were 
     <lb/>
     present at the council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The undersigned stated the object of his visit, explained the wishes of the 
     <lb/>
     Government in regard to the settlement of the Island, and proposed the 
     <lb/>
     terms in respect to the Indians specified in the Order in Council authorizing 
     <lb/>
     the negotiation. The Indians had selected one of their Chiefs to reply to 
     <lb/>
     the overtures of the Government, and without taking time to consider these 
     <lb/>
     overtures he proceeded to announce the determination of the Indians to 
     <lb/>
     reject them unconditionally. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The undersigned made some further explanations, and directed an ajourn<lb break="no"/>ment of the council for an hour, during which time the Indians were re<lb break="no"/>quested to consider the propositions he had made with care and deliberation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On re-assembling there was an evident disposition among the bands living 
     <lb/>
     westwardly of the place of meeting to listen favorably to the propositions 
     <lb/>
     of the Government, but the majority were still unwilling to treat, and by 
     <lb/>
     intimidation and threats of violence prevented any open expression of opinion 
     <lb/>
     except by the old war Chief, Assicknack, who declared his full assent to the 
     <lb/>
     wishes of the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Ascertaining that the Chief's opposition came from Indians living east<lb break="no"/>wardly of Heywood Sound, the undersigned determined to modify the pro<lb break="no"/>positions of the Government, so as to meet in some degree the objections 
     <lb/>
     from that quarter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     He accordingly adjourned the council until the following Monday, the 
     <lb/>
     first day of meeting being Saturday, informing the Indians that those who 
     <lb/>
     were disposed to continue the negotiations would remain while those who 
     <lb/>
     had resolved to reject every proposition of the Government might go home. 
     <lb/>
     He also informed them that no threats or intimidation would be allowed, 
     <lb/>
     and that any one who should attempt violence would be surely punished. 
     <lb/>
     Nearly all the Indians remained or returned on Monday, and being apprised 
     <lb/>
     of the nature of the proposition the undersigned intended to submit, namely, 
     <lb/>
     to exclude that part of the island eastwardly of the Manitoulin Gulf and 
     <lb/>
     Heywood Sound from the proposed agreement, they came to the adjourned 
     <lb/>
      
          
            <pb n="24" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_03_Page_024.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">24</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     
           
     meeting in a more friendly mood and expressed their willingness to surren<lb break="no"/>der for sale and settlement all that part of the island westwardly of the Gulf 
     <lb/>
     and Sound.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The undersigned submits herewith the deed or instrument which embodies 
     <lb/>
     the agreement made and concluded between the respective parties. It was 
     <lb/>
     executed by the undersigned and the Deputy-Superintendent of Indian 
     <lb/>
     Affairs on behalf of the Government, and by nineteen of the Chiefs and prin<lb break="no"/>cipal men on behalf of the Indians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In consequence of the modification of the terms of agreement authorized 
     <lb/>
     by the Order in Council as above-mentioned and the addition of other terms 
     <lb/>
     deemed necessary to prevent future difficulty, and which will be found in 
     <lb/>
     the instrument, the undersigned caused a provision to be inserted that it 
     <lb/>
     was not to take effect until approved by the Governor-General in Council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The undersigned therefore now begs to submit the same for such approval. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     (Signed) WM. McDOUGALL, 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Superintendent—General of Indian Affairs</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>