<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="Morris_Chapter_12"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreatyNeg">Treaty Negotiations</name>, <date from="1877" to="1878">1877 to 1878</date>, Between Canada and First Nations of Manitoba and the Northwest Territories.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <author>Alexander Morris</author>.
          
         
          <title>The Treaties of Canada with the Indians of Manitoba and the North-West Territories Including the Negotiations on Which They Are Based, and Other Information Relating Thereto.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1880"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>: <publisher>Willing &amp; Williamson</publisher>.
          
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="298"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_285.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_286.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_287.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_288.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_289.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_290.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_291.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_292.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_293.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_294.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_295.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_296.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_297.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_298.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-04-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-04-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_285">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_285.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_286">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_286.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_287">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_287.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_288">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_288.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_289">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_289.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_290">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_290.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_291">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_291.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_292">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_292.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_293">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_293.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_294">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_294.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_295">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_295.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_296">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_296.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_297">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_297.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_298">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_298.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="285"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_285.jpg"/>
         
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Administration of the Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">285</fw> 
  
            
   <div type="chapter">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CHAPTER XII. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     THE ADMINISTRATION OF THE TREATIES—TIIE HALF-BREEDS— 
     <lb/>
     THE FUTURE OF THE INDIAN TRIBES. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     HAVING placed before my readers, a history of the treaties 
     <lb/>
    of Canada with the Indian tribes, of Manitoba, the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>West Territories and Kee-watin, I now proceed, in conclusion, 
     <lb/>to deal with the administration of these treaties and to con<lb break="no"/>sider the future of these interesting aboriginal races. I remark 
     <lb/>in the first place that the provisions of these treaties must be 
     <lb/>carried out with the utmost good faith and the nicest exactness. 
     <lb/>The Indians of Canada have, owing to the manner in which 
     <lb/>they were dealt with for generations by the Hudson's Bay Com<lb break="no"/>pany, the former rulers of these vast territories, an abiding con<lb break="no"/>fidence in the Government of the Queen, or the Great Mother, 
     <lb/>as they style her. This must not, at all hazards, be shaken. It 
     <lb/>can be easily and fully maintained. The treaties are all based 
     <lb/>upon the models of that made at the Stone Fort in 1871 and 
     <lb/>the one made in 1873 at the north-west angle of the Lake of 
     <lb/>the Woods with the Chippewa tribes, and these again are based, 
     <lb/>in many material features, on those made by the Hon. W. B. 
     <lb/>Robinson with the Chippewas dwelling on the shores of Lakes 
     <lb/>Huron and Superior in 1860. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
    

            <p>
     These may be summarized thus : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. A relinquishment, in all the great region from Lake 
     <lb/>
     Superior to the foot of the Rocky Mountains, of all their right 
     <lb/>
     and tr e to the lands covered by the treaties, saving certain 
     <lb/>
     reservations for their own use, and 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. In return for such relinquishment, permission to the In<lb break="no"/>
          
            <pb n="286"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_286.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">286</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
   

     dians to hunt over the ceded territory and to fish in the waters 
     <lb/>
     thereof, excepting such portions of the territory as pass from 
     <lb/>
     the Crown into the occupation of individuals or otherwise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. The perpetual payment of annuities of five dollars per 
     <lb/>
     head to each Indian—man, woman and child. The payment 
     <lb/>
     of an annual salary of twenty-five dollars to each Chief, and of 
     <lb/>
     fifteen dollars to each Councillor, or head man, of a Chief (thus 
     <lb/>
     making them in a sense officers of the Crown), and in addition, 
     <lb/>
     suits of official clothing for the Chiefs and head men, British 
     <lb/>
     flags for the Chiefs, and silver medals. These last are given 
     <lb/>
     both in the United States and in Canada, in conformity with 
     <lb/>
     an ancient custom, and are much prized and cherished by the 
     <lb/>
     Chiefs and their families. Frequently the Indians have ex<lb break="no"/>hibited to me with pride, old medals issued, with the likeness 
     <lb/>
     of the King before the American war of Independence, and 
     <lb/>
     which have passed down as heirlooms of their families. On one 
     <lb/>
     occasion a young Chief, who had come of age and aspired to be 
     <lb/>
     recognized as a Chief, was decorated in my presence with the 
     <lb/>
     old King George silver medal, by one of the band, to whom it 
     <lb/>
     had been entrusted for safe keeping by the young man's father, 
     <lb/>
     who was a Chief, with the charge that on the boy's coming of 
     <lb/>
     age, it would be delivered over to him. The Chieftainships 
     <lb/>
     were at first partly hereditary, partly won by deeds of dar<lb break="no"/>ing and of leadership against the foe. They are now gen<lb break="no"/>erally elective, though the tendency to hereditary succession 
     <lb/>
     still largely exists. The power of the Chiefs has been much 
     <lb/>
     broken of late, and I am of opinion that it is of importance to 
     <lb/>
     strengthen the hands of the Chiefs and Councillors by a due 
     <lb/>
     recognition of their offices and respect being shewn them. 
     <lb/>
     They should be strongly impressed with the belief that they 
     <lb/>
     are officers of the Crown, and that it is their duty to see that 
     <lb/>
     the Indians of their tribes obey the provisions of the treaties. 
     <lb/>
     The importance of upholding the Chiefs, may be illustrated by 
     <lb/>
     an incident which occurred near Fort Ellice, after the making 
     <lb/>
     of the treaty. A party composed of three men and the wife 
     

            <pb n="287"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_287.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Administration of the Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">287</fw> 
     

     of one of them, were travelling as freighters ; two of the men 
     <lb/>
     were Half-breeds, the other a Canadian. One night, one of 
     <lb/>
     the Half-breeds shot the Canadian, and attempted to kill the 
     <lb/>
     other Half-breed, who fled to an Indian camp in the vicinity. 
     <lb/>
     The Chief of the band was there, and he at once took his 
     <lb/>
     young men with him, proceeded to the scene of the murder, 
     <lb/>
     and after making the offender a prisoner, took him to the 
     <lb/>
     nearest police station and delivered him to the authorities. 
     <lb/>
     The culprit was subsequently tried in Manitoba, convicted of 
     <lb/>
     murder and hanged. For this action the Chief received the 
     <lb/>
     thanks of His Excellency the Earl of Dufferin, then Governor- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     General of Canada. This case affords an illustration of the 
     <lb/>
     value of the recognition of the Chiefs of the various bands, 
     <lb/>
     and shews of how much advantage, it is to the Crown to possess 
     <lb/>
     so large a number of Indian officials, duly recognized as such, 
     <lb/>
     and who can be inspired with a proper sense of their responsi<lb break="no"/>bility to the Government and to their bands, as well as to 
     <lb/>
     others. In all the negotiations for treaties, the Chiefs took a 
     <lb/>
     controlling part, and generally exhibited great common sense 
     <lb/>
     and excellent judgment. It is therefore of the utmost import<lb break="no"/>ance to retain their confidence and cause their office to be 
     <lb/>
     recognized and respected by both whites and Indians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. The allotment of lands to the Indians, to be set aside 
     <lb/>
     as reserves for them for homes and agricultural purposes, and 
     <lb/>
     which cannot be sold or alienated without their consent, and 
     <lb/>
     then only for their benefit; the extent of lands thus set apart 
     <lb/>
     being generally one section for each family of five. I regard 
     <lb/>
     this system as of great value. It at once secures to the In<lb break="no"/>dian tribes tracts of land, which cannot be interfered with, by 
     <lb/>
     the rush of immigration, and affords the means of inducing 
     <lb/>
     them to establish homes and learn the arts of agriculture. I 
     <lb/>
     regard the Canadian system of allotting reserves to one or 
     <lb/>
     more bands together, in the localities in which they have had 
     <lb/>
     the habit of living, as far preferable to the American system 
     <lb/>
     of placing whole tribes, in large reserves, which eventually 
    

            <pb n="288"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_288.jpg"/>
    
     <fw type="num">288</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

     become the object of cupidity to the whites, and the breaking 
     <lb/>
     up of which, has so often led to Indian wars and great dis<lb break="no"/>content even if warfare did not result. The Indians, have a 
     <lb/>
     strong attachment to the localities, in which they and their 
     <lb/>
     fathers have been accustomed to dwell, and it is desirable to 
     <lb/>
     to cultivate this home feeling of attachment to the soil. More<lb break="no"/>over, the Canadian system of band reserves has a tendency to 
     <lb/>
     diminish the offensive strength of the Indian tribes, should 
     <lb/>
     they ever become restless, a remote contingency, if the treaties 
     <lb/>
     are carefully observed. Besides, the fact of the reserves being 
     <lb/>
     scattered throughout the territories, will enable the Indians to 
     <lb/>
     obtain markets among the white settlers, for any surplus pro<lb break="no"/>duce they may eventually have to dispose of. It will be found 
     <lb/>
     desirable, to assign to each family parts of the reserve for their 
     <lb/>
     own use, so as to give them a sense of property in it, but all 
     <lb/>
     power of sale or alienation of such lands should be rigidly pro<lb break="no"/>hibited. Any premature enfranchisement of the Indians, or 
     <lb/>
     power given them to part with their lands, would inevitably 
     <lb/>
     lead to the speedy breaking up of the reserves, and the 
     <lb/>
     return of the Indians to their wandering mode of life, and 
     <lb/>
     thereby to the re-creation of a difficulty which the assignment 
     <lb/>
     of reserves was calculated to obviate. There is no parallel 
     <lb/>
     between the condition of the North-Western Indians, and that 
     <lb/>
     of the Indians who have so long been under the fostering care 
     <lb/>
     of the Government in the older Provinces of Ontario and 
     <lb/>
     Quebec. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. A very important feature of all the treaties, is the giving 
     <lb/>
     to the Indian bands, agricultural implements, oxen, cattle (to 
     <lb/>
     form the nuclei of herds), and seed grain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Indians are fully aware that their old mode of life is pass<lb break="no"/>ing away. They are not " unconscious of their destiny ;" on the 
     <lb/>
     contrary, they are harassed with fears as to the future of their 
     <lb/>
     children and the hard present of their own lives. They are 
     <lb/>
     tractable, docile, and willing to learn. ' They recognize the fact 
     <lb/>
     that they must seek part of their living from "the mother 
     

            <pb n="289"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_289.jpg"/>
           <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Administration of the Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">289</fw> 
     

     earth," to use their own phraseology. A Chief at Fort Pitt 
     <lb/>
     said to me,—"I got a plough from Mr. Christie of the Com<lb break="no"/>pany twelve years ago. I have no cattle ; I put myself and 
     <lb/>
     my young men in front of it in the spring, and drag it through 
     <lb/>
     the ground. I have no hoes; I make them out of the roots 
     <lb/>
     of trees. Surely, when the Great Mother hears of our needs, 
     <lb/>
     she will come to our help."<ref target="#fn_01">*</ref> Such a disposition as this should 
     <lb/>
     be encouraged. Induce the Indians to erect houses on their 
     <lb/>
     farms, and plant their " gardens " as they call them, and then 
     <lb/>
     while away on their hunts, their wives and children will have 
     <lb/>
     houses to dwell in, and will care for their patches of corn and 
     <lb/>
     grain and potatoes. Then, too, the cattle given them will ex<lb break="no"/>pand into herds. It is true that the number assigned to each 
     <lb/>
     band is comparatively limited, and the Government are not 
     <lb/>
     bound to extend the number. This was done advisedly, by the 
     <lb/>
     successive Governments of Canada, and the Commissioners, 
     <lb/>
     acting under their instructions; for it was felt, that it was 
     <lb/>
     an experiment to entrust them with cattle, owing to their in<lb break="no"/>experience with regard to housing them and providing fodder 
     <lb/>
     for them in winter, and owing, moreover, to the danger of 
     <lb/>
     their using them for food, if short of buffalo meat or game. 
     <lb/>
     Besides, it was felt, that as the Indian is, and naturally so, 
     <lb/>
     always asking, it was better, that if the Government saw their 
     <lb/>
     way safely to increase the number of cattle given to any band, 
     <lb/>
     it should be, not as a matter of right, but of grace and favor, 
     <lb/>
     and as a reward for exertion in the care of them, and as an in<lb break="no"/>centive to industry. Already, the prospect of many of the 
     <lb/>
     bands turning their attention to raising food from the soil is 
     <lb/>
     very hopeful. In the reserve of St. Peter's, in Manitoba, the 
     <lb/>
     Church of England has for many years had a church and mis<lb break="no"/>sion, and long before the advent of Canada as ruler of the 
     <lb/>
     lands, the Indians of the Indian settlement had their houses and 
     <lb/>
     gardens, the produce of which, went to supplement the results of 
   
     <note xml:id="fn_01">*This band a year ago raised, sufficient farm produce to support them<lb break="no"/>selves without hunting.</note> 
    

            <pb n="290"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_290.jpg"/>
         
<fw type="num">290</fw> <fw><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

     fishing and hunting. And so on the shores and islands of the 
     <lb/>
     Lake of the Woods and on Rainy Lake, the Indians had their 
     <lb/>
     gardens. Since the treaties, the Indians are turning their 
     <lb/>
     attention much more to cultivating the soil. The Indian dis<lb break="no"/>trict agent in the Qu'Appelle region, reported in November, 
     <lb/>
     1878, that of the twenty-four bands in this treaty, eleven are 
     <lb/>
     gradually turning their attention to farming, and of these 
     <lb/>
     Chief Cote, of Swan River, is the most advanced, having har<lb break="no"/>vested that year two hundred and eighty bushels of barley, over 
     <lb/>
     three thousand bushels of potatoes, and a large quantity of 
     <lb/>
     other vegetables. The increase from the four cows he received 
     <lb/>
     two years since is eleven head. This may appear large, but 
     <lb/>
     such is the fact. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Lieut.-Gov. Laird reported in 1877, "That some of the bands 
     <lb/>
     within the limits of Treaties Numbers Four and Six sowed 
     <lb/>
     grain and potatoes with good results that year, one band having 
     <lb/>
     about one hundred acres under cultivation." He also states 
     <lb/>
     that the Indians are very desirous of farming, and that he has 
     <lb/>
     hopes that a much larger quantity of seed will be sown next 
     <lb/>
     year (1879). He also states that the band at White Fish 
     <lb/>
     Lake, raised enough that year to maintain themselves without 
     <lb/>
     going to hunt. The Superintendent also reported that in the 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba superintendency "a general desire to be taught 
     <lb/>
     farming, building and other civilized arts exists, and some of 
     <lb/>
     the Indians in Treaty Number Three, living in the vicinity of 
     <lb/>
     Fort Francis, are said to evince enterprise and progress in 
     <lb/>
     their farming operations." At Lac Seule, also in this treaty, 
     <lb/>
     the progress of the Indians is quite marked. They have 
     <lb/>
     established two villages in order to have the benefit of schools. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Indian agent in the Lake Manitoba district makes a simi<lb break="no"/>lar statement. One band has eighteen small farms of one 
     <lb/>
     hundred acres in all, on which they raise potatoes, Indian corn 
     <lb/>
     and garden vegetables. They have twenty-nine houses, twenty- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     four horses, and thirty-six head of cattle, of their own. Another 
     <lb/>
     built during the year a good school-house, nineteen new houses, 
    

            <pb n="291"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_291.jpg"/>
     
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Administration of the Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">291</fw> 
     

     and had one hundred and twenty-five acres under cultivation. 
     <lb/>
     Another had just begun farming, built six houses, two stables 
     <lb/>
     and a barn, and possess seven head of cattle. Still another 
     <lb/>
     had twenty-three houses and one hundred and fifty acres under 
     <lb/>
     tillage, raising barley, wheat, potatoes and vegetables, and 
     <lb/>
     having thirty-six head of cattle. It is unnecessary to multiply 
     <lb/>
     instances, of the aptitude, the Indians are exhibiting, within so 
     <lb/>
     recent a period after the completion of the treaties, to avail 
     <lb/>
     themselves of obtaining their subsistence from the soil. Their 
     <lb/>
     desire to do so, should be cultivated to the fullest extent. 
     <lb/>
     They are, of course, generally ignorant of the proper mode of 
     <lb/>
     farming. In the year 1876, I reported to the Minister of the 
     <lb/>
     Interior, the Hon. David Mills, after my return from the 
     <lb/>
     negotiation of the treaties at Forts Carlton and Pitt, "that 
     <lb/>
     measures ought to be taken to instruct the Indians in farming 
     <lb/>
     and building." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I said "that their present mode of living is passing away; 
     <lb/>
     the Indians are tractable, docile and willing to learn. I think 
     <lb/>
     that advantage should be taken of this disposition to teach 
     <lb/>
     them to become self-supporting, which can best be accomplished 
     <lb/>
     by the aid of a few practical farmers and carpenters to instruct 
     <lb/>
     them in farming and house-building." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This view was corroborated by my successor, Lieutenant- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Governor Laird, who in 1878 reported from Battleford "that 
     <lb/>
     if it were possible to employ a few good, practical men to aid 
     <lb/>
     and instruct the Indians at seed time, I am of opinion that 
     <lb/>
     most of the bands on the Saskatchewan would soon be able to 
     <lb/>
     raise sufficient crops to meet their most pressing wants." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is satisfactory to know, that the Government of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     decided to act on these suggestions, at least in part, and have 
     <lb/>
     during the past summer sent farm instructors into the Plain 
     <lb/>
     country. It is to be hoped, that this step may prove as fruit<lb break="no"/>ful of good results, as the earnest desire of the Indians to farm 
     <lb/>
     would lead us to believe it may be. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="292"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_292.jpg"/>
      <fw type="num">292</fw>
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    
            
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     SCHOOLS. 
   
            </p>

            <p>6. The treaties provide for the establishment of schools, on 
     <lb/>the reserves, for the instruction of the Indian children. This 
     <lb/>is a very important feature, and is deserving of being pressed 
     <lb/>with the utmost energy. The new generation can be trained 
     <lb/>in the habits and ways of civilized life—prepared to encounter 
     <lb/>the difficulties with which they will be surrounded, by the 
     <lb/>influx of settlers, and fitted for maintaining themselves as 
     <lb/>tillers of the soil. The erection of a school-house on a reserve 
     <lb/>will be attended with slight expense, and the Indians would 
     <lb/>often give their labour towards its construction. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>7. The treaties all provide for the exclusion of the sale of 
     <lb/>spirits, or "fire-water," on the reserves. The Indians them<lb break="no"/>selves know their weakness. Their wise men say, "If it is 
     <lb/>there we will use it, give us a strong law against it." A 
     <lb/>general prohibitory liquor law, originally enacted by the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>West Council and re-enacted by the Parliament of Canada, is 
     <lb/>in force in the North-West Territories and has been productive 
     <lb/>of much benefit, but will, in the near future, be difficult of 
     <lb/>enforcement owing to the vast extent of the territory. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Such are the main features of the treaties between Canada 
     <lb/>and the Indians, and, few as they are, they comprehend the 
     <lb/>whole future of the Indians and of their relations to the 
     <lb/>Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="simple:centre">MACHINERY OF GOVERNMENT. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>To carry them out, the treaty area has been divided into 
     <lb/>two Superintendencies, that of Manitoba, including Treaties 
     <lb/>Numbers One, Two Three and Four; and that of the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>West Territories, including Treaties Numbers Five, Six and 
     <lb/>Seven. Mr. Dewdney, late a Member of the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons from British Columbia, has recently been appointed to 
     <lb/>the latter Superintendeney as Chief Superintendent, and has 
     <lb/>spent the summer among the Indian tribes. He has had large 
    


            <pb n="293"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_293.jpg"/>
      
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Half-breeds</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">293</fw> 
     

     experience among Indians, and will prove, I have no doubt, 
     <lb/>
     an efficient and able officer. His residence will be in his 
     <lb/>
     Superintendency, and he will be able to meet the Indians and 
     <lb/>
     supervise his deputies. Under the Superintendents are agents 
     <lb/>
     having charge of particular districts and the bands within 
     <lb/>
     them, who reside among them. The Chief Superintendents 
     <lb/>
     and agents are officers of the Department of the Interior, and 
     <lb/>
     are directed by and report to the Deputy Superintendent of 
     <lb/>
     Indian Affairs at Ottawa, Lawrence Vankoughnet, Esq., who 
     <lb/>
     has had long experience of Indian management in the older 
     <lb/>
     Provinces, and his superior, Col. Dennis, Deputy Minister of 
     <lb/>
     the Interior, who had a large practical acquaintance with the 
     <lb/>
     North-West, and the head of the Department, now the Premier 
     <lb/>
     of the Dominion, the Right Hon. Sir John Macdonald. The 
     <lb/>
     system of management is thus a complete one, and doubtless, day 
     <lb/>
     by day, its mode of management, will be perfected and adapted 
     <lb/>
     to the growing exigencies and wants of the native population. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     THE HALF-BREEDS. 

            </p>
   
            <p>
     Ere passing from the subject, I cannot refrain from alluding 
     <lb/>
     to the Half-breed population of the North-West Territories. 
     <lb/>
     Those people are mainly of French Canadian descent, though 
     <lb/>
     there are a few of Scotch blood in the territories. Their influ<lb break="no"/>ence with the Indian population is extensive. In Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     there is a large population of French Metis and Scotch Half- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     breeds, and they are proud of their mixed blood. This race is 
     <lb/>
     an important factor with regard to all North-West questions. 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency the Earl of Dufferin, with his keen apprecia<lb break="no"/>tion of men and facts, astutely seized the position and thus 
     <lb/>
     referred to them in his speech at a banquet in his honor, given 
     <lb/>
     by the citizens of the whilome hamlet, and new city of Win<lb break="no"/>nipeg, on the occasion of his visit to the Province of Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     in the year 1877. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "There is no doubt that a great deal of the good feeling 
    

            <pb n="294"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_294.jpg"/>
            

              <fw type="num">294</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
   
     
     thus subsisting between the red men and ourselves is due to 
     <lb/>
     the influence and interposition of that invaluable class of men 
     <lb/>
     the Half-breed settlers and pioneers of Manitoba, who, com<lb break="no"/>bining as they do the hardihood, the endurance and love of 
     <lb/>
     enterprise generated by the strain of Indian blood within their 
     <lb/>
     viens, with the civilization, the instruction, and the intellec<lb break="no"/>tual power derived from their fathers, have preached the 
     <lb/>
     Gospel of peace and good will, and mutual respect, with 
     <lb/>
     equally beneficent results to the Indian Chieftain in his lodge 
     <lb/>
     and to the British settler in the shanty. They have been 
     <lb/>
     the ambassadors between the east and the west ; the interpre<lb break="no"/>ters of civilization and its exigencies to the dwellers on the 
     <lb/>
     prairie as well as the exponents to the white men of the con<lb break="no"/>sideration justly due to the susceptibilities, the sensitive self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     respect, the prejudices, the innate craving for justice, of the 
     <lb/>
     Indian race. In fact they have done for the colony what 
     <lb/>
     otherwise would have been left unaccomplished, and have in<lb break="no"/>troduced between the white population and the red man a 
     <lb/>
     traditional feeling of amity and friendship which but for them 
     <lb/>
     it might have been impossible to establish." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     For my own part, I can frankly say, that I always had the 
     <lb/>
     confidence, support and active co-operation of the Half-breeds of 
     <lb/>
     all origins, in my negotiations with the Indian tribes, and I owe 
     <lb/>
     them this full acknowledgment thereof. The Half-breeds in 
     <lb/>
     the territories are of three classes—1st, those who, as at St. 
     <lb/>
     Laurent, near Prince Albert, the Qu'Appelle Lakes and Edmon<lb break="no"/>ton, have their farms and homes ; 2nd, those who are entirely 
     <lb/>
     identified with the Indians, living with them, and speaking their 
     <lb/>
     language ; 3rd, those who do not farm, but live after the habits 
     <lb/>
     of the Indians, by the pursuit of the buffalo and the chase. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>As to the first class, the question is an easy one. They will, 
     <lb/>of course, be recognized as possessors of the soil, and con<lb break="no"/>firmed by the Government in their holdings, and will continue 
     <lb/>to make their living by farming and trading. 
   
            </p>

    
  
            <pb n="295"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_295.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Future of the Indians</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">295</fw> 
    
   
            <p>
     The second class have been recognized as Indians, and have 
     <lb/>
     passed into the bands among whom they reside. . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The position of the third class is more difficult. The loss 
     <lb/>
     of the means of livelihood by the destruction of the buffalo, 
     <lb/>
     presses upon them, as upon our Indian tribes ; and with regard 
     <lb/>
     to them I reported in 1876, and I have seen no reason to 
     <lb/>
     change my views, as follows : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " There is another class of the population in the North-West 
     <lb/>
     whose position I desire to bring under the notice of the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council. I refer to the wandering Half-breeds of the plains, who 
     <lb/>
     are chiefly of French descent and live the life of the Indians. 
     <lb/>
     There are a few who are identified with the Indians, but there 
     <lb/>
     is a large class of Metis who live by the hunt of the buffalo, and 
     <lb/>
     have no settled homes. I think that a census of the numbers 
     <lb/>
     of these should be procured, and while I would not be disposed 
     <lb/>
     to recommend their being brought under the treaties, I would 
     <lb/>
     suggest that land should be assigned to them, and that on their 
     <lb/>
     settling down, if after an examination into their circumstances, 
     <lb/>
     it should be found necessary and expedient, some assistance 
     <lb/>
     should be given them to enable them to enter upon agricultural 
     <lb/>
     operations." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     FUTURE OF THE INDIANS. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     And now I come, to a very important question, What is to 
     <lb/>
     be the future of the Indian population. of the North-West. I 
     <lb/>
     believe it to be a hopeful one. I have every confidence in the 
     <lb/>
     desire and ability of the present administration, as of any suc<lb break="no"/>ceeding one, to carry out the provisions of the treaties, and to 
     <lb/>
     extend a helping hand to this helpless population. That, con<lb break="no"/>ceded, with the machinery at their disposal, with a judicious 
     <lb/>
     selection of agents and farm instructors, and the additional aid 
     <lb/>
     of well-selected carpenters, and efficient school teachers, I look 
     <lb/>
     forward to seeing the Indians, faithful allies of the Crown, while 
     <lb/>
     they can gradually be made an increasing and self-supporting 
     <lb/>
     population. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <pb n="296"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_296.jpg"/>
         <fw type="num">296</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw>
   
            <p>
     They are wards of Canada, let us do our duty by them, and 
     <lb/>
     repeat in the North-west, the success which has attended our 
     <lb/>
     dealings with them in old Canada, for the last hundred years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But the Churches too have their duties to fulfil. There is a 
     <lb/>
     common ground between the Christian Churches and the In<lb break="no"/>dians, as they all believe as we do, in a Great Spirit. The 
     <lb/>
     transition thence to the Christian's God is an easy one. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Many of them appeal for missionaries, and utter the Mace<lb break="no"/>donian cry, "come over and help us." The Churches have 
     <lb/>
     already done and are doing much. The Church of Rome has 
     <lb/>
     its bishops and clergy, who haVe long been laboring assiduously 
     <lb/>
     and actively. The Church of England has its bishops and 
     <lb/>
     clergy on the shores of the Hudson's Bay, in the cold region of 
     <lb/>
     the Mackenzie and the dioceses of Rupert's Land and Saskat<lb break="no"/>chewan. The Methodist Church has its missions on Lake 
     <lb/>
     \Vinnipeg, in the Saskatchewan Valley, and on the slopes of 
     <lb/>
     the Rocky Mountains. The Presbyterians have lately com<lb break="no"/>menced a work among the Chippewas and Sioux. There is 
     <lb/>
     room enough and to spare, for all, and the Churches should 
     <lb/>
     expand and maintain their work. Already many of the mis<lb break="no"/>sionaries have made records which will live in history: among 
     <lb/>
     those of recent times, Archbishop Tache, Bishop Grandin, Pere 
     <lb/>
     Lacombe, and many others of the Catholic Church; Bishops 
     <lb/>
     Machray, Bompas, Archdeacons Cochran and Cowley of the 
     <lb/>
     Church of England; Revs. Messrs. Macdougall of the Wes<lb break="no"/>leyan and Nisbet of the Presbyterian Churches, have lived and 
     <lb/>
     labored, and though some of them have gone to their rest, they 
     <lb/>
     have left and will leave behind them a record of self-denial, un<lb break="no"/>tiring zeal, and many good results. Let the Churches persevere 
     <lb/>
     and prosper. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And now I close. Let us have Christianity and civilization 
     <lb/>
     to leaven the mass of he-athenism and paganism among the 
     <lb/>
     Indian tribes; let us have a wise and paternal Government 
     <lb/>
     faithfully carrying out the provisions of our treaties, and doing 
   

            <pb n="297"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_297.jpg"/>
           
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Future of the Indians</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">297</fw>

     its utmost to help and elevate the Indian population, who have 
     <lb/>
     been cast upon our care, and we will have peace, progress, and 
     <lb/>
     concord among them in the North-West ; and instead of the 
     <lb/>
     Indian melting away, as one of them in older Canada, tersely 
     <lb/>
     put it, "as snow before the sun," we will see our Indian popu<lb break="no"/>lation, loyal subjects of the Crown, happy, prosperous and self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     sustaining, and Canada will be enabled to feel, that in a truly 
     <lb/>
     patriotic spirit, our country has done its duty by the red men 
     <lb/>
     of the North-West, and thereby to herself. So may it be. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <pb n="298"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_298.jpg"/>
         
     <fw type="num">298</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    
          <figure facs="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_12_Page_298_image_crop.jpg"></figure>

<figure>
<figDesc>description...</figDesc>
<graphic url=""/>
</figure>
   
            <p>
     NOTE—The foregoing represents a copy of the signatures of the contract<lb break="no"/>ing parties to the Selkirk Treaty, the Indians signing by their own distinctive 
     <lb/>
     marks, and also affixing their signs opposite the tracts of country claimed 
     <lb/>
     by them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
    </div>     </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>