<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="Morris_Chapter_04"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreatyNeg">Treaty Negotiations</name>, <date from="1870" to="1870-08">Fall 1870 to August 1871</date>, Between Canada and First Nations of Manitoba and the Northwest Territories.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:Morris">
          

               <author>Alexander Morris</author>.
          
         
          <title>The Treaties of Canada with the Indians of Manitoba and the North-West Territories Including the Negotiations on Which They Are Based, and Other Information Relating Thereto.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1880"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>: <publisher>Willing &amp; Williamson</publisher>.
          
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="43"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_025.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_026.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_027.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_028.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_029.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_030.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_031.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_032.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_033.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_034.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_035.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_036.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_037.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_038.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_039.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_040.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_041.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_042.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_043.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-28">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-28">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_025">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_025.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_026">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_026.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_027">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_027.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_028">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_028.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_029">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_029.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_030">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_030.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_031">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_031.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_032">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_032.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_033">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_033.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_034">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_034.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_035">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_035.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_036">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_036.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_037">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_037.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_038">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_038.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_039">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_039.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_040">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_040.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_041">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_041.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_042">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_042.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_043">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_043.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <pb n="25" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_025.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Stone Fort and Manitoba Post Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">25</fw>
   
<div type="chapter">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">CHAPTER IV.</head>

            <p rendition="simple:centre">THE STONE FORT AND MANITOBA POST TREATIES NUMBERS<lb/>ONE AND TWO.</p>

            <p>IN the year 1871, the late Honorable Joseph Howe, then<lb/>Secretary of State of Canada, recommended the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment, by the Privy Council of Canada, of Mr. Wemyss Mc<lb break="no"/>Kenzie Simpson, as Indian Commissioner, in consequence of<lb/>"the necessity of arranging with the bands of Indians inhabit<lb break="no"/>ing the tract of country between Thunder Bay and the Stone<lb/>Fort, for the cession, subject to certain reserves such as they<lb/>accepted the appointment, and in company with Messrs. S. J.<lb/>Dawson and Robert Pether visited the Ojjibewas or Chippawa<lb/>Indians, between Thunder Bay and the north-west angle of the<lb/>Lake of Woods, and took the initiator steps for securing a<lb/>treaty with them thereafter. On his arrival at Fort Garry, he<lb/>put himself, as directed by his instructions, in communication<lb/>with his Honor, the Hon. A. G. Archibald, then Lieutenant-<lb break="yes"/>Governor of Manitoba and the North-West Territories. A<lb/>conference took place between His Honor, Messrs. Simpson,<lb/>Dawson and Pether, and the Hon. James McKay, a member,<lb/>at that time of the Executive Council of Manitoba, and him<lb break="no"/>self a half-breed intimately acquainted with the Indian tribes,<lb/>and possessed of much influence over them. The Indians in<lb/>Manitoba, in the fall of 1870, had applied to the Lieutenant-<lb break="yes"/>Governor to enter into a treaty with them, and had been<lb/>informed that in the ensuing year negotiations would be opened<lb/>with them. They were full of uneasiness, owing to the influx of<lb/>population, denied the validity of the Selkirk Treaty, and had

            <pb n="26" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_026.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">26</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     
     in some instances obstructed settlers and surveyors. In view 
     <lb/>
     of the anxiety and uneasiness prevailing, these gentlemen were 
     <lb/>
     of opinion " that it was desirable to secure the extinction of the 
     <lb/>
     Indian title not only to the lands within Manitoba, but also to 
     <lb/>
     so much of the timber grounds east and north of the Province 
     <lb/>
     as were required for immediate entry and use, and also of a 
     <lb/>
     large tract of cultivable ground west of the Portage, where 
     <lb/>
     there were very few Indian inhabitants." It was therefore 
     <lb/>
     resolved to open negotiations at the Lower Fort Garry, or 
     <lb/>
     Stone Fort, with the Indians of the Province, and certain adjacent 
     <lb/>
     timber districts, and with the Indians of the other districts at 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba Post, a Hudson's Bay fort, at the north end of Lake 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba, the territory being occupied principally by one 
     <lb/>
     nation, the Chippawas, of whom the Saulteaux of the lakes are 
     <lb/>
     a branch, although there are also a number of Swampy Crees 
     <lb/>
     resident within it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Simpson accordingly issued proclamations, inviting the 
     <lb/>
     Indians to meet him on the 25th of July and 17th of August, 
     <lb/>
     1871, at these points respectively, to negotiate an Indian treaty. 
     <lb/>
     The Lieutenant-Governor also issued a proclamation forbidding 
     <lb/>
     the sale or gift of intoxicating liquors during the negotiation of 
     <lb/>
     the treaty, and applied to Major Irvine to detail a few of the 
     <lb/>
     troops under his command to preserve order, which request was 
     <lb/>
     acceded to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Lieutenant-Governor and Mr Simpson arrived at the 
     <lb/>
     Stone Fort on the 24th of July, 1871, but as the Indians nad 
     <lb/>
     not all arrived the meeting was postponed fill the 27th, when 
     <lb/>
     a thousand Indians were found to have assembled, and a con<lb break="no"/>siderable number of half-breeds and other inhabitants of the 
     <lb/>
     country were present, awaiting with anxiety to learn the policy 
     <lb/>
     of the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Lieutenant-Governor Archibald, after the Indians were as<lb break="no"/>sembled opened the proceedings by delivering the following<lb/>address:<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>"On the 13th September last, on my first arrival in the<lb/>
            

    
            <pb n="27" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_027.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Stone Fort and Manitoba Post Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">27</fw>
   
           
     country, I met a number of you at the mission, I told you I 
     <lb/>
     could not then negotiate a Treaty with the Indians, but that I 
     <lb/>
     was charged by your Great Mother, the Queen, to tell you that 
     <lb/>
     she had been very glad to see that you had acted during the 
     <lb/>
     troubles like good and true children of your Great Mother. I 
     <lb/>
     told you also that as soon as possible you would all be called 
     <lb/>
     together to consider the terms of a treaty to be entered into 
     <lb/>
     between you and your Great Mother. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " I advised you to disperse to your homes, and gave you some 
     <lb/>
     ammunition to enable you to gain a livelihood during the winter 
     <lb/>
     by hunting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " I promised that in the spring you would be sent for, and that 
     <lb/>
     either I, or some person directly appointed to represent your 
     <lb/>
     Great Mother, should be here to meet you, and notice would be 
     <lb/>
     given you when to convene at this place to talk over what was 
     <lb/>
     right to be done. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " Early in the spring, Mr. Simpson, who sits beside me, was 
     <lb/>
     made Commissioner. He left his home at once for this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, by Rainy Lake and the Lake of the Woods. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " The Indians of the lake districts meet, as you know, on 
     <lb/>
     Rainy River yearly, about the 20th June, to fish for sturgeon, 
     <lb/>
     and they could not be called together sooner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " Mr. Simpson met them there at that time, and talked over 
     <lb/>
     their affairs with them, and made certain arrangements with 
     <lb/>
     them. He then hurried on to see you, and reached this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince a week ago last Sunday. He then sent messengers at 
     <lb/>
     once to all the Indians within certain bounds, asking them to 
     <lb/>
     meet him here on the 25th day of July. Some of you were 
     <lb/>
     unable to come so soon, and he has therefore, at the instance 
     <lb/>
     of those who were here, waited till to-day to open the talk. I 
     <lb/>
     believe that now you are all arrived, and ready to proceed to 
     <lb/>
     business. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " It will be the duty of the Commissioner to talk to you on 
     <lb/>
     the particular details of the treaty, and I will give place to him 
     <lb/>
     presently, but there are one or two things of a general kind 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="28" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_028.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">28</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw>  
     

     which I would like, before I close, to bring to your notice, for 
     <lb/>
     you to think about among yourselves.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>i "First. Your Great Mother, the Queen, wishes to do justice  
     <lb/>to all her children alike. She will deal fairly with those of the 
     <lb/>setting sun, just as she would with those of the rising sun. She 
     <lb/>wishes order and peace to reign through all her country, and  
     <lb/>while her arm is strong to punish the wicked man. her hand is 
     <lb/>also open to reward the good man everywhere in her Dominions.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> " Your Great Mother wishes the good of all races under her  
     <lb/> sway. She Wishes her red children to be happy and contented.   
     <lb/> She wishes them to live in comfort. She would like them to  
     <lb/> adopt the habits of the whites, to till land and raise food, and  
     <lb/> store it up against a time of want. She thinks this would be  
     <lb/> the best thing for her red children to do, that it would make  
     <lb/> them safer from famine and distress, and make their homes  
     <lb/>more comfortable.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"But the Queen, though she may think it good for you to 
     <lb/>adopt civilized habits, has no idea of compelling you to do so.  
     <lb/>This she leaves to your choice, and you need not live like the 
     <lb/> white man unless you can be persuaded to do so of your own   
     <lb/> free will. Many of you, however, are already doing this.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> " I drove yesterday through the village below this Fort.". 
     <lb/>  There I saw many well-built houses, and many well-tilled fields  
     <lb/> with wheat and barley and potatoes growing, and giving prom<lb break="no"/>ise of plenty for the winter to come. The people who till these   
     <lb/>  fields and 1ive in these houses are men of your own race, and   
     <lb/>  they shew that you can live and prosper and provide like the   
     <lb/> white man.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     "What I saw in my drive is enough to prove that even if   
     <lb/>
    there was not a buffalo or a fur-bearing animal in the country, 
     <lb/> you could live and be surrounded with comfort by what you  
     <lb/>can raise from the soil.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"Your Great Mother, therefore, will lay aside for you 'lots'  
     <lb/>of land to be used by you and your children forever. She will   
     <lb/>not allow the white man to intrude upon these lots. She will  
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="29" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_029.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Stone Fort and Manitoba Post Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">29</fw>
   
         

     make rules to keep them for you, so that as long as the sun 
     <lb/>
     shall shine, there shall be no Indian who has not a place that 
     <lb/>
     he can call his home, where he can go and pitch his camp, or if 
     <lb/>
     he chooses, build his house and till his land. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "These reserves will be large enough, but you must not expect 
     <lb/>
     them to be larger than will be enough to give a farm to each 
     <lb/>
     family, where farms shall be required. They will enable you 
     <lb/>
     to earn a living should the chase fail, and should you choose to 
     <lb/>
     get your living by tilling, you must not expect to have included 
     <lb/>
     in your reserve more of hay grounds than will be reasonably 
     <lb/>
     sufficient for your purposes in case you adopt the habits of 
     <lb/>
     farmers. The old settlers and the settlers that are coming in, 
     <lb/>
     must be dealt with on the principles of fairness and justice as 
     <lb/>
     well as yourselves. Your Great Mother knows no difference 
     <lb/>
     between any of her people. Another thing I want you to think 
     <lb/>
     over is this: in laying aside these reserves, and in everything 
     <lb/>
     else that the Queen shall do for you, you must understand that 
     <lb/>
     she can do for you no more than she has done for her red child<lb break="no"/>ren in the East. If she were to do more for you that would be 
     <lb/>
     unjust for them. She will not do less for you because you are 
     <lb/>
     all her children alike, and she must treat you all alike. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "When you have made your treaty you will still be free to 
     <lb/>
     hunt over much of the land included in the treaty. Much of it is 
     <lb/>
     rocky and unfit for cultivation, much of it that is wooded is 
     <lb/>
     beyond the places where the white man will require to go, at 
     <lb/>
     all events for some time to come. Till these lands are needed 
     <lb/>
     for use you will be free to hunt over them, and make all the 
     <lb/>
     use of them which you have made in the past. But when lands 
     <lb/>
     are needed to be tilled or occupied, you must not go on them 
     <lb/>
     any more. There will still be plenty of land that is neither 
     <lb/>
     tilled nor occupied where you can go and roam and hunt as you 
     <lb/>
     have always done, and, if you wish to farm, you will go to your 
     <lb/>
     own reserve where you will find a place ready for you to live 
     <lb/>
     on and cultivate. . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "There is another thing I have to say to you. Your Great 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="30" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_030.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">30</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    

     Mother cannot come here herself to talk with you, but she has 
     <lb/>
     sent a messenger who has her confidence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " Mr. Simpson will tell you truly all her wishes. As the 
     <lb/>
     Queen has made her choice of a chief to represent her, you 
     <lb/>
     must, on your part, point out to us the chiefs you wish to repre<lb break="no"/>sent you, as the persons you have faith in. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " Mr. Simpson cannot talk to all your braves and people, but 
     <lb/>
     when he talks to chiefs who have your confidence he is talking 
     <lb/>
     to you all, and when he hears the voice of one of your chiefs 
     <lb/>
     whom you name he will hear the voice of you all. It is for 
     <lb/>
     you to say who shall talk for you, and also who shall be your 
     <lb/>
     chief men. Let them be good Indians, who know your wishes 
     <lb/>
     and whom you have faith in. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " You will look to the Commissioner to fulfil everything he 
     <lb/>
     agrees to do, and the Queen will look to the chiefs you name to 
     <lb/>
     us, to see that you keep your parts of the agreement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " It is our wish to deal with you fairly and frankly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " If you have any questions to ask, ask them, if you have 
     <lb/>
     anything you wish the Queen to know, speak out plainly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " Now chiefs and braves and people, I introduce to you Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Simpson, who will say anything he thinks fit in addition to 
     <lb/>
     what I have said. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " When you hear his voice you are listening to your Great 
     <lb/>
     Mother the Queen, whom God bless and preserve long to reign 
     <lb/>
     over us." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Simpson also addressed them, and thereafter, in compli<lb break="no"/>ance with a request of the Lieutenant-Governor, the Indians 
     <lb/>
     retired to select their chiefs and principal spokesmen. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the next day the conference was resumed, the chiefs and 
     <lb/>
     spokesmen being presented. The Indians, on being asked to 
     <lb/>
     express their views, " stated that there was a cloud before them 
     <lb/>
     which made things dark, and they did not wish to commence 
     <lb/>
     the proceedings till the cloud was dispersed." On inquiry it 
     <lb/>
     was ascertained that they referred to the imprisonment of four 
     <lb/>
     Swampy Cree Indians, who had been convicted under a local 
    
            
            <pb n="31" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_031.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Stone Fort and Manitoba Post Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">31</fw>
   
            
     law, of breach of contract, as boatmen, with the Hudson's Bay 
     <lb/>
     Company, and on default of payment of a fine, had been sent to 
     <lb/>
     prison. The Lieutenant-Governor, as a matter of favor, ordered 
     <lb/>
     the release of these prisoners, and the sky became clear. Next 
     <lb/>
     day the Indians met again and declared that they would never 
     <lb/>
     again raise their voice against the enforcement of the law, but 
     <lb/>
     much difficulty was experienced in getting them to understand 
     <lb/>
     the views of the Government—they wishing to have two-thirds 
     <lb/>
     of the Province as a reserve. Eventually on the 3rd of August, 
     <lb/>
     1871, a treaty was concluded, its principal features being the 
     <lb/>
     relinquishment to Her Majesty of the Indian title; the reserving 
     <lb/>
     of tracts of land for the Indians, sufficient to furnish 160 acres 
     <lb/>
     of land to each family of five ; providing for the maintenance of 
     <lb/>
     schools, and prohibition of the sale of intoxicating liquors on the 
     <lb/>
     reserves ; a present of three dollars per head to the Indians and 
     <lb/>
     the payment to them of an annuity of three dollars per head.<ref target="#fn_01">*</ref> 
     <lb/>
     (See copy of treaty which will be found in the Appendix.) On 
     <lb/>
     the 21st of August Mr. Commissioner Simpson, accompanied 
     <lb/>
     by the Lieutenant-Governor, the Hon. James McKay, and Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Molyneux St. John (lately Sheriff of the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories), met the Indians at Manitoba .Post, and found them 
     <lb/>
     disposed to accept the terms of the treaty made at the Stone 
     <lb/>
     Fort, with which they had already become familiar, so that 
     <lb/>
     little time was lost in effecting a treaty with them as they had 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     no special terms to prefer. By these two treaties, there was 
     <lb/>
     acquired by the Crown, the extinguishment of the Indian title 
     <lb/>
     in Manitoba, and in a tract of country fully equal in resources 
     <lb/>
     beyond it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Having submitted these preliminary remarks, I conclude my 
     <lb/>
     notice of these treaties by quoting, as matter alike of historical 
     <lb/>
     record and practical interest, the despatches of Lieutenant-<lb break="yes"/>
            

            <note xml:id="fn_01">* In consequence of misunderstandings having arisen, owing to the Indians 
     <lb/>
     alleging that certain promises had been made to them which were not speci<lb break="no"/>fied in these treaties, a revision of them became necessary, and was effected 
     <lb/>
     in 1875, as will be seen reported hereafter.</note>

            <pb n="32" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_032.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">32</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw>
   
        
     Governor Archibald and the excellent and instructive report, 
     <lb/>
    addressed to the Secretary of State by Mr. Simpson, embracing 
     <lb/>as it does a full and graphic narrative of the proceedings which 
     <lb/>took place at the negotiation of these treaties, and of the diffi<lb break="no"/>culties which were encountered by the Commissioner, and the 
     <lb/>mode in which they were overcome. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     GOVERNMENT HOUSE, 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">SILVER HEIGHTS, <hi rendition="simple:italic">July 22nd, 1871</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     SIR,—I have the honor to enclose you copy of a proclamation I have 
     <lb/>
     caused to be issued, with a view to prevent the danger arising from intoxi<lb break="no"/>cating drinks being given to the Indians, on the occasion of the meeting to 
     <lb/>
     negotiate a treaty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I look upon the proceedings, we are now initiating, as important in their 
     <lb/>
     bearing upon our relations to the Indians of the whole continent. In fact, 
     <lb/>
     the terms we now agree upon will probably shape the arrangements we shall 
     <lb/>
     have to make with all the Indians between the Red River and the Rocky 
     <lb/>
     Mountains. It will therefore be well to neglect nothing that is within our 
     <lb/>
     power to enable us to start fairly with the negotiations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With that view, I have, amongst other things, asked Major Irvine to 
     <lb/>
     detail a few of his troops to be present at the opening of the treaty. Mili<lb break="no"/>tary display has always a great effect on savages, and the presence, even of 
     <lb/>
     a few troops, will have a good tendency. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I fear we shall have to incur a considerable expenditure for presents of 
     <lb/>
     food, etc., during the negotiations ; but any cost for that purpose I shall 
     <lb/>
     deem a matter of minor consequence. The real burden to be considered is 
     <lb/>
     that which has to be borne in each recurring year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I doubt if it will be found practicable to make arrangements upon so 
     <lb/>
     favorable a basis as that prescribed by His Excellency the Governor-General, 
     <lb/>
     as the maximum to be allowed, in case of a treaty with the Lake Indians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Nor indeed would it be right, if we look to what we receive, to measure 
     <lb/>
     the benefits we derive from coming into possession of the magnificent terri<lb break="no"/>tory we are appropriating here, by what would be fair to allow for the rocks 
     <lb/>and swamps and muskegs of the lake country east of this Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     But to this subject I shall probably take occasion to call your attention at 
     <lb/>
     an early day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     I have, etc., 
     </p>

            <p rendition="simple:right"><persName ref="pers:ARCH2">ADAMS G. ARCHIBALD</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>THE HONORABLE 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE PROVINCES, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Ottawa</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <pb n="33" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_033.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Stone Fort and Manitoba Post Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">33</fw>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     Lower Fort Garry, <hi rendition="simple:italic">July 29th, 1871</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     SIR,—I have the honor to inform you that on Monday last I came to this 
     <lb/>
     Fort with the Commissioner to meet the Indians called here, with a view to 
     <lb/>
     negotiate a treaty, intending to open the business on Tuesday morning. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It appeared, however, on inquiry, that some bands of Indians had not 
     <lb/>
     arrived on Tuesday morning, and we were therefore obliged to postpone the 
     <lb/>
     opening of the meeting till Thursday. On that day the Indians from all the 
     <lb/>
     sections of the country to which the invitation extended were found present 
     <lb/>
     to the number of about one thousand. A considerable body of half-breeds 
     <lb/>
     and other inhabitants of the country were also present, awaiting with some 
     <lb/>
     anxiety to learn what should be announced as the policy of the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I enclose you a memorandum of the observations with which I opened the 
     <lb/>
     meeting. On reading them you will observe one or two points which may 
     <lb/>
     require some explanation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     At the time of the treaty with the Earl of Selkirk, certain Indians signed 
     <lb/>
     as Chiefs and representatives of their people. Some of the Indians now deny 
     <lb/>
     that these men ever were Chiefs or had authority to sign the treaty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With a view therefore to avoid a recurrence of any such question, we asked 
     <lb/>
     the Indians, as a first step, to agree among themselves in selecting their 
     <lb/>
     Chiefs, and then to present them to us and have their names and authority 
     <lb/>
     recorded. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Furthermore, the Indians seem to have false ideas of the meaning of a 
     <lb/>
     reserve. They have been led to suppose that large tracts of ground were to 
     <lb/>
     be set aside for them as hunting grounds, including timber lands, of which 
     <lb/>
     they might sell the wood as if they were proprietors of the soil. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I wished to correct this idea at the outset. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Simpson followed me with some observations in the same strain, after 
     <lb/>
     which the Indians retired to select their Chiefs and spokesmen. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Friday morning the Chiefs and spokesmen were duly presented, and 
     <lb/>
     after their names were recorded, the Indians were invited to express their 
     <lb/>
     views. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After some delay they stated that there was a cloud before them which 
     <lb/>
     made things dark, and they did not wish to commence the proceedings till 
     <lb/>
     the cloud was dispersed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On inquiring into their meaning, I found that they were referring to some 
     <lb/>
     four of their number who were prisoners in gaol. It seems that some Swampy 
     <lb/>
     Indians had entered into a contract with the Hudson's Bay Company as 
     <lb/>
     boatmen, and had deserted, and had been brought up before magistrates 
     <lb/>
     under a local law of last session, and fined, and in default of payment sent 
     <lb/>
     to prison for forty days. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Of this term some considerable part had expired. A few of the offenders 
     <lb/>
     had paid their fines, but there were still four Indians remaining in prison. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On learning the facts I told the Indians that I could not listen to them if 
     <lb/>
     they made a demand for the release of the Indians as a matter of right; that 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="34" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_034.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="num">34</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    

     every subject of the Queen, whether Indian,  half-breed or white, was equal 
     <lb/>
     in the eye of the law; that every offender against the law must be punished, 
     <lb/>
    whatever race he belonged to; but  I said that on the opening of negotia<lb break="no"/>tions with them the Queen would like to see all her Indians taking part in 
     <lb/>them, and if the whole body present were to ask as a matter of grace and 
     <lb/>favor, under the circumstances, that their brethren should be released, Her 
     <lb/>Majesty would be willing to consent to their discharge; she would grant as 
     <lb/>a favor what she must refuse if asked for on any other ground. They replied 
     <lb/>by saying that they begged it as a matter of favor only. Thereupon I acceded 
     <lb/>to their request, and directed the discharge of the four Indians. This was 
     <lb/>received with great satisfaction.  I explained again, that there might be no 
     <lb/>misunderstanding about it, that henceforth every offender against the law 
     <lb/>must be punished. They all expressed their acquiescence in what  I said. 
     <lb/>The discharge of the prisoners had an excellent effect. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Next morning the Indians, through one of their spokesmen, declared in 
     <lb/>
     presence of the whole body assembled, that from this time they would never 
     <lb/>
     raise their voice against the law being enforced. After the order of the 
     <lb/>
     release, the Chiefs and spokesmen addressed us, questions were asked and 
     <lb/>
     answered, and some progress made in the negotiations. Eventually the 
     <lb/>
     meeting adjourned till this morning at ten o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A general acquiescence in the views laid down by Mr. Simpson and myself 
     <lb/>
     was expressed; but it was quite clear, by the proceedings of to-day, that our 
     <lb/>
     views were imperfectly apprehended. When we met this morning, the 
     <lb/>
     Indians were invited to state their wishes as to the reserves, they were to 
     <lb/>
     say how much they thought would be sufficient, and whether they wished 
     <lb/>
     them all in one or in several places. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In defining the limits of their reserves, so far as we could see, they wished 
     <lb/>
     to have about two-thirds of the Province. We heard them out, and then 
     <lb/>
     told them it was quite clear that they had entirely misunderstood the mean<lb break="no"/>ing and intention of reserves. We explained the object of these in something 
     <lb/>
     like the language of the memorandum enclosed, and then told them it was of 
     <lb/>
     no use for them to entertain any such ideas, which were entirely out of the 
     <lb/>
     question. We told them that whether they wished it or not, immigrants 
     <lb/>
     would come in and fill up the country; that every year from this one twice 
     <lb/>
     as many in number as their whole people there assembled would pour into 
     <lb/>
     the Province, and in a little while would spread all over it, and that now 
     <lb/>
     was the time for them to come to an arrangement that would secure homes 
     <lb/>
     and annuities for themselves and their children. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We told them that what we proposed to allow them was an extent of one 
     <lb/>
     hundred and sixty acres for each family of five, or in that proportion ; that 
     <lb/>
     they might have their land where they chose, not interfering with existing 
     <lb/>
     occupants; that we should allow an annuity of twelve dollars for every 
     <lb/>
     family of five, or in that proportion per head. We requested them to think 
     <lb/>
     over these propositions till Monday morning. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If they thought it better to have no treaty at all, they might do without 
    

            <pb n="35" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_035.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Stone Fort and Manitoba Post Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">35</fw> 
       
           

     one, but they must make up their minds ; if there was to be a treaty, it must 
     <lb/>
     be on a basis like that offered. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That under some such arrangements, the Indians in the east were living 
     <lb/>
     happy and contented, enjoying themselves, drawing their annuities, and 
     <lb/>
     satisfied with their position. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The observations seemed to command the acquiescence of the majority, 
     <lb/>
     and on Monday morning we hope to meet them in a better frame for the 
     <lb/>
     discussion and settlement of the treaty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     I have, etc., 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right"><persName ref="pers:ARCH2">ADAMS G. ARCHIBALD</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     THE HONORABLE 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE PROVINCES. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     LOWER FORT GARRY, MANITOBA, <hi rendition="simple:italic">July 30th, 1871</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     SIR,—I have the honor to inform you, for the information of His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency the Governor-General, that I arrived in this Province on the 16th 
     <lb/>
     instant, and, after consultation with the Lieutenant-Governor of Manitoba, 
     <lb/>
     determined upon summoning the Indians of this part of the country to a 
     <lb/>
     conference for the purpose of negotiating a treaty at Lower Fort Garry, on 
     <lb/>
     Tuesday, the 25th instant, leaving for a future date the negotiation with 
     <lb/>
     the Indians westward of and outside of the Province of Manitoba. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Proclamations were issued, and every means taken to insure the attendance 
     <lb/>
     of the Indians, and on Monday, the 24th instant, I proceeded to Lower Fort 
     <lb/>
     Garry, where I met His Excellency the Lieutenant-Governor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Tuesday, finding that only a small portion of the Indians had arrived, 
     <lb/>
     we held a preliminary conference with Henry Prince—the Chief of the 
     <lb/>
     Swampies and Chippewas residing on what is known as the Indian Reserve, 
     <lb/>
     between Lower Fort Garry and Lake Winnipeg—at which we arranged a 
     <lb/>
     meeting for the next day at twelve o'clock, for the purpose of ascertaining 
     <lb/>
     the names of the Chiefs and head men of the several tribes. At this pre<lb break="no"/>liminary conference, Henry Prince said that he could not then enter upon 
     <lb/>
     any negotiations, as he was not empowered to speak or act for those bands 
     <lb/>
     of Indians not then present. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In the meantime it was found necessary to feed the Indians assembled 
     <lb/>
     here, and accordingly provisions were purchased and rations served out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Wednesday, the 26th, His Excellency the Lieutenant-Governor and 
     <lb/>
     myself met those Indians who had arrived, in council, and addressed them 
     <lb/>
     with the view of explaining the purport of my commission, and the matters 
     <lb/>
     which were to form the subject of a treaty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It having been reported that the Indians who had not then arrived were 
     <lb/>
     on their road here, we agreed that another meeting should take place on the 
     <lb/>
     following day, at which the Chiefs and head men were to be presented to us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_036.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">36</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     
   
            <p>
     On Thursday, pursuant to appointment, we again met the Indians, when 
     <lb/>
     the Chiefs and head men of the several bands present were named and pre<lb break="no"/>sented. I then explained to them the nature of Indian reserves, and desired 
     <lb/>
     them to determine, in council among themselves, the locality in which they 
     <lb/>
     desired their reserves to be laid out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Friday, the 28th, we again met the Indians, but they were not then 
     <lb/>
     prepared to state their demands, and another meeting was appointed for 
     <lb/>
     Saturday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Saturday, the 29th, we again met them, all having by this time arrived. 
     <lb/>
     When the subject of reserves came up, it was found that the Indians had 
     <lb/>
     misunderstood the object of these reservations, for their demands in this 
     <lb/>
     respect were utterly out of the question. After a prolonged discussion with 
     <lb/>
     them, I consulted with the Lieutenant-Governor, and determined to let 
     <lb/>
     them at once understand the terms that I was prepared to offer, and I pointed 
     <lb/>
     out that the terms offered were those which would receive Her Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     consent. On further explanation of the subject, the Indians appeared to be 
     <lb/>
     satisfied, and willing to acquiesce in our arrangements as hereinafter men<lb break="no"/>tioned; and having given them diagrams showing the size of the lots they 
     <lb/>
     would individually become possessed of, and having informed them of the 
     <lb/>
     amount of their annuity, it was finally settled that they should meet on 
     <lb/>
     Monday, the 31st, and acquaint me with their decision. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The reserves will comprise sufficient land to give each family of five persons 
     <lb/>
     one hundred and sixty acres, or in like proportion, together with an annual 
     <lb/>
     payment in perpetuity of twelve dollars for each family of persons, or 
     <lb/>
     in like proportion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As far as I can judge, I am inclined to think that the Indians will accept 
     <lb/>
     these terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am happy to be able to say that the precautions taken to prevent the 
     <lb/>
     introduction of liquor amongst the Indians have been wholly successful, and 
     <lb/>
     that perfect order and contentment have prevailed up to the present time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     I have, etc. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     <persName ref="pers:SIMP2">WEMYSS M. SIMPSON</persName>, 
     <lb/>
     </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Indian Commissioner</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>THE HONORABLE 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE PROVINCES, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Ottawa</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <pb n="37" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_037.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Stone Fort and Manitoba Post Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">37</fw>
   
            
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p rendition="simple:right">
     OTTAWA, <hi rendition="simple:italic">November 3rd, 1871</hi>. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>TO THE HONORABLE 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE PROVINCES, 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Ottawa</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     SIR,—I have the honor to submit to you, for the information of His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency the Governor-General, a report of my negotiations with the Indians 
     <lb/>
     of the Province of Manitoba, and with certain of the Indians of the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West Territory, entered upon by me, in accordance with your instructions, 
     <lb/>
     dated 3rd May, 1871. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Having, in association with S. J. Dawson, Esq., and Robert Pether, Esq. , 
     <lb/>
     effected a preliminary arrangement with the Indians of Rainy Lake, the 
     <lb/>
     particulars of which I have already had the honor of reporting to you in my 
     <lb/>
     Report, dated July 11th, 1871, I proceeded by the Lake of the Woods and 
     <lb/>
     Dawson Road to Fort Garry, at which place I arrived on the 16th July. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Bearing in mind your desire that I should confer with the Lieutenant- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Governor of Manitoba, I called upon Mr. Archibald, and learned from him 
     <lb/>
     that the Indians were anxiously awaiting my arrival, and were much excited 
     <lb/>
     on the subject of their lands being occupied without attention being first 
     <lb/>
     given to their claims for compensation. Amongst the settlers, also, an 
     <lb/>
     uneasy feeling existed, arising partly from the often-repeated demands of 
     <lb/>
     the Indians for a treaty with themselves, and partly from the fact that 
     <lb/>
     certain settlers in the neighborhood of Portage la Prairie and other parts of 
     <lb/>
     the Province, had been warned by the Indians not to cut wood or otherwise 
     <lb/>
     take possession of the lands upon which they were squatting. The Indians, 
     <lb/>
     it appeared, consented to their remaining on their holdings until sufficient 
     <lb/>
     time had been allowed for my arrival, and the conclusion of a treaty ; but 
     <lb/>
     they were unwilling to allow the settlers the free use of the country for 
     <lb/>
     themselves or their cattle. Mr. Archibald, and those residents in the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Manitoba with whom I conversed on the subject, appeared to think 
     <lb/>
     that no time should be lost in meeting the Indians, as some assurances had 
     <lb/>
     already been given them that a treaty would be made with them during the 
     <lb/>
     summer of 1871 ; and I therefore, at once, issued notices calling certain of 
     <lb/>
     the Indians together, naming two places at which I would meet them. The 
     <lb/>
     first meeting, to which were asked the Indians of the Province and certain 
     <lb/>
     others on the eastern side, was to be held on the 25th of July, at the Stone 
     <lb/>
     Fort, a Hudson's Bay Company's Post, situated on the Red River, about 
     <lb/>
     twenty miles northward of Fort Garry—a locality chosen as being the most 
     <lb/>
     central for those invited. The second meeting was appointed to be held on 
     <lb/>
     August 17th, at Manitoba Post, a Hudson's Bay Company's Post, at the 
     <lb/>
     north-west extremity of Lake Manitoba, as it was deemed that such of the 
     <lb/>
     hands of Indians residing without the limits of the Province of Manitoba, 
     <lb/>
     as I purposed to deal with at present, would meet there more readily than 
     <lb/>
     elsewhere. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Monday, the 24th of July, I met the Lieutenant-Governor of Manitoba 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="38" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_038.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="num">38</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    
     at the Stone Fort; but negotiations were unavoidably  delayed, owing to the 
     <lb/>
     fact that only one band of Indians had arrived, and that until all were on 
     <lb/>
     the spot those present declined to discuss the subject of a treaty, except in 
     <lb/>
    an informal manner. Amongst these, as amongst other Indians with whom  
     <lb/> I have come in contact, there exists great jealousy of one another, in all 
     <lb/>matters relating to their communications with the officials of Her Majesty; 
     <lb/>and in order to facilitate the object in view, it was most desirable that 
     <lb/>suspicion and jealousy of all kinds should be allayed. The fact of the Com<lb break="no"/>missioner having arrived was sufficient evidence of the good intentions of 
     <lb/>Her Majesty's Government, and it seemed better to await the arrival of all 
     <lb/>whom  I had summoned, than to press matters to an issue while any were 
     <lb/>absent. This, however, entailed the necessity of feeding those who were 
     <lb/>already there, and others as they arrived. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     It is customary in dealing with Indians to do so, and in this case it was 
     <lb/>
     absolutely necessary, for, obviously, it would have been impossible to invite 
     <lb/>
     those people from a distance, and then leave them to starve at our doors, or, 
     <lb/>
     in search of food, to plunder the neighborhood into which they had been 
     <lb/>
     introduced. At that season of the year the Indians were not engaged in 
     <lb/>
     fishing or hunting, and consequently large numbers of men, women and 
     <lb/>
     children attended at the place of meeting, for all of whom food was provided. 
     <lb/>
     The price of provisions, even at the lowest price for which they could be 
     <lb/>
     obtained, was high, pork being fifty dollars a barrel, and flour twenty shil<lb break="no"/>lings sterling per hundred, and such cattle as  I was able to purchase £16 per 
     <lb/>
     head; so that the expense of keeping the Indians during the negotiation of 
     <lb/>
     treaty and payment of the gratuity, which lasted eleven days, forms no small 
     <lb/>
     share of the total expenditure. In addition to this expense, it was thought 
     <lb/>
     necessary by the Lieutenant-Governor that Major Irvine, commanding the 
     <lb/>
     troops at Fort Garry, should be requested to furnish a guard at the Stone 
     <lb/>
     Fort during the negotiations, and that there should be at hand, also, a force 
     <lb/>
     of constabulary, for the purpose of preventing the introduction of liquor 
     <lb/>
     amongst the Indian encampments. Other expenses of a somewhat similar 
     <lb/>
     nature were incurred, which would be totally unnecessary upon any future 
     <lb/>
     occasion of payment being made to the Indians of Manitoba. I may here 
     <lb/>
     refer to the apparently prolonged duration of the first negotiation, and 
     <lb/>
     explain, in reference thereto, the causes, or some of them, that entailed the 
     <lb/>
     loss of time and attendant expense. For some time a doubt has existed 
     <lb/>
     whether the Chief, nominally at the head of the Indians of the Indian settle<lb break="no"/>ment, possessed the good will and confidence of that band; and I thought it 
     <lb/>
     advisable to require that the several bands of Indians should select such 
     <lb/>
     Chiefs as they thought proper, and present these men as their authorized 
     <lb/>
     Chiefs, before anything was said as to the terms of a treaty. The Indians 
     <lb/>
     having acquiesced in this proposal, forthwith proceeded to such election; but 
     <lb/>
     the proceeding apparently involved discussion and consideration amongst 
     <lb/>
     themselves, and two days elapsed before the men chosen were presented for 
     <lb/>
     recognition, and the business of the meeting commenced. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
           
            <pb n="39" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_039.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Stone Fort and Manitoba Post Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">39</fw> 
     
   
            <p>
     When the peculiar circumstances surrounding the position of the Indians 
     <lb/>
     of the Province were pointed out, the future of the country predicted, and 
     <lb/>
     the views and intentions of the Government explained by the Lieutenant- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Governor and myself, the Indians professed a desire for time to think over 
     <lb/>
     what had been said before making any reply ; and when their answer came 
     <lb/>
     it proved to contain demands of such an exorbitant nature, that much time 
     <lb/>
     was spent in reducing their terms to a basis upon which an arrangement 
     <lb/>
     could be made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Every band had its spokesman, in addition to its Chief, and each seemed 
     <lb/>
     to vie with another in the dimensions of their requirements. I may mention, 
     <lb/>
     as an illustration, that in the matter of reserves, the quantity of land de<lb break="no"/>manded for each band amounted to about three townships per Indian, and 
     <lb/>
     included the greater part of the settled portions of the Province. It was 
     <lb/>
     not until the 3rd of August, or nine days after the first meeting, that the 
     <lb/>
     basis of arrangement was arrived at, upon which is founded the treaty of 
     <lb/>
     that date. Then, and by means of mutual concessions, the following terms 
     <lb/>
     were agreed upon. For the cession of the country described in the treaty 
     <lb/>
     referred to, and comprising the Province of Manitoba, and certain country 
     <lb/>
     in the north-east thereof, every Indian was to receive a sum of three dollars 
     <lb/>
     a year in perpetuity, and a reserve was to be set apart for each band, of 
     <lb/>
     sufficient size to allow one hundred and sixty acres to each family of five 
     <lb/>
     persons, or in like proportion as the family might be greater or less than five. 
     <lb/>
     As each Indian settled down upon his share of the reserve, and commenced 
     <lb/>
     the cultivation of his land, he was to receive a plough and harrow. Each 
     <lb/>
     Chief was to receive a cow and a male and female of the smaller kinds of 
     <lb/>
     animals bred upon a farm. There was to be a bull for the general use of 
     <lb/>
    each reserve. In addition to this, each Chief was to receive a dress, a flag 
     <lb/>and a medal, as marks of distinction ; and each Chief, with the exception of 
     <lb/>Bozawequare, the Chief of the Portage band, was to receive a buggy, or 
     <lb/>light spring waggon. Two councillors and two braves of each band were to 
     <lb/>receive a dress, somewhat inferior to that provided for the Chiefs, and the 
     <lb/>braves and councillors of the Portage band excepted, were to receive a buggy. 
     <lb/>Every Indian was to receive a gratuity of three dollars, which, though given 
     <lb/>as a payment for good behaviour, was to be understood to cover all dimen<lb break="no"/>sions for the past. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     On this basis the treaty was signed by myself and the several Chiefs, on 
     <lb/>
     behalf of themselves and their respective bands, on the 3rd of August, 1871, 
     <lb/>
     and on the following day the payment commenced. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The three dollars gratuity, above referred to, will not occur in the ordinary 
     <lb/>
     annual payments to the Indians of Manitoba, and, though doubling the 
     <lb/>
     amount paid this year, may now properly be regarded as belonging to a 
     <lb/>
     previous year, but only now liquidated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A large number of Indians, entitled to share in the treaty, were absent on 
     <lb/>
     the 3rd August, and in the belief that I should, almost immediately, be able 
     <lb/>
     to obtain a more accurate knowledge than I possessed of the numbers of 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="40" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_040.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">40</fw>
      <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

     the several bands, I paid to each person present  only three dollars—the 
     <lb/>
     gratuity—postponing for a short time the first annual payment. Having 
     <lb/>
     completed this disbursement, I prepared to start for Manitoba Post, to open 
     <lb/>
     negotiations with the Indians on the immediate north and north-west borders 
     <lb/>
     of the Province of Manitoba, promising however to visit the several bands 
     <lb/>
     of the first treaty, in their own districts, and to there pay them. By this 
     <lb/>
     means the necessity for their leaving their own homes, and for the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment's feeding them while they were being paid, and during their journey 
     <lb/>
     home, was avoided. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After completing the treaty at Manitoba Post, of which mention is herein<lb break="no"/>after made, I visited Portage la Prairie, the Indian settlement at St. Peter's, 
     <lb/>
     Riviere Marais, and the Town of Winnipeg, according to my promise, and 
     <lb/>
      at each place, with the exception of Riviere Marais, found the Indians 
     <lb/>
        satisfied with the treaty, and awaiting their payment. At Riviere Marais, 
     <lb/>
     which was the rendezvous appointed by the bands living in the neighborhood 
     <lb/>
     of Pembina, I found that the Indians had either misunderstood the advice 
     <lb/>
     given them by parties in the settlement, well disposed towards the treaty, 
     <lb/>
     or, as I have some reason to believe, had become unsettled by the represen<lb break="no"/>tations made by persons in the vicinity of Pembina, whose interests lay 
     <lb/>
     elsewhere than in the Province of Manitoba; for, on my announcing my 
     <lb/>
     readiness to pay them, they demurred at receiving their money until some 
     <lb/>
     further concessions had been made by me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      With a view to inducing the Indians to adopt the habits and labors of 
     <lb/>
    civilization, it had been agreed, at the signing of the treaty as before men<lb break="no"/>tioned, to give certain animals as a nucleus for stocking the several reserves, 
     <lb/>together with certain farming implements; and it was now represented to 
     <lb/>  me by the spokesman of the bands, that as the Queen had, with that kindness  
     <lb/>of heart which distinguished her dealings with her red children, expressed   
     <lb/>desire to see the Indians discard their former precarious mode of living and 
     <lb/> adopt the agricultural pursuits of the white man, they were desirous of 
     <lb/> acceding to the wish of their great Mother, and were now prepared to 
     <lb/> receive the gifts she had been good enough to speak of, through her Com<lb break="no"/>missioner, in full. But, as it could make no difference whatever to their   
     <lb/> great Mother whether these things were given in kind or in money value,   
     <lb/> her red children of the Pembina bands were resolved to receive them in the  
     <lb/> latter form. I had put a valuation upon all the articles mentioned in the   
     <lb/>  supplement to the treaty, and could go no further in the matter unless I was   
     <lb/> prepared to pay them for all these articles at the rates they would now pro<lb break="no"/>ceed to mention. I declined to comply with the request, and they declined   
     <lb/>  to receive their first annual payment, whereupon I broke up my camp and    
     <lb/>  returned to Winnipeg. As I foresaw at the time, this determination on    
     <lb/> their part was shortly repented, and a number of their leading men were    
     <lb/> subsequently paid at Winnipeg; while at the request of the Indians, the     
     <lb/> money for the remainder, together with a pay sheet, was forwarded to the    
     <lb/> offier in charge of the Hudson's Bay Company's Post at Pembina, with  
     <lb/>
      
            <pb n="41" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_041.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Stone Fort and Manitoba Post Treaties.</hi></fw> <fw type="num">41</fw> 
     

     instructions to pay the Indians as per list as ,each might present himself. 
     <lb/>
     At Portage la Prairie, although the number paid at the Stone Fort was 
     <lb/>
     largely increased, there still remained many who, from absence or other 
     <lb/>
     causes, were not paid, and by the request of the Chief the money was left 
     <lb/>
     for these with the officers in charge of the Hudson's Bay Company's Post, 
     <lb/>
     in the same manner as was done for the Pembina bands. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As I was unable to proceed to Fort Alexander, the payments for the 
     <lb/>
     Indians, or for such of them as were present at the signing of the treaty, 
     <lb/>
     were sent in like manner to the officer in charge of the Hudson's Bay Com<lb break="no"/>pany's Post at Fort Alexander ; but it may be as well to mention that the 
     <lb/>
     number so paid will fall far short of the total number belonging to that 
     <lb/>
     place. The latter remark will apply to the Pembina band, for their payment 
     <lb/>
     was sent as per gratuity list, and there must necessarily have been others 
     <lb/>
     who did not receive payment. All these must receive their back payments 
     <lb/>
     during the course <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>.
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     During the payment of the several hands, it was found that in some, and 
     <lb/>
     most notably in the Indian settlement and Broken Head River Band, a 
     <lb/>
     number of those residing among the Indians, and calling themselves Indians, 
     <lb/>
     are in reality half-breeds, and entitled to share in the land grant under the 
     <lb/>
     provisions of the Manitoba Act. I was most particular, therefore, in causing 
     <lb/>
     it to be explained, generally and to individuals, that any person now electing 
     <lb/>
     to be classed with Indians, and receiving the Indian pay and gratuity, would, 
     <lb/>
     I believed, thereby forfeit his or her right to another grant as a half-breed ; 
     <lb/>
     and in all cases where it was known that a man was a half-breed, the matter, 
     <lb/>
     as it affected himself and his children, was explained to him, and the choice 
     <lb/>
     given him to characterize himself. A very few only decided upon taking 
     <lb/>
     their grants as half-breeds.  The explanation of this apparent sacrifice is 
     <lb/>
     found in the fact that the mass of these persons have lived all their lives on 
     <lb/>
     the Indian reserves (so called), and would rather receive such benefits as may 
     <lb/>
     accrue to them under the Indian treaty than ,wait the realization of any 
     <lb/>
     value in their half-breed grant. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Lieutenant-Governor of Manitoba having expressed a desire to be 
     <lb/>
     present at the negotiation of the treaty at Manitoba Post, His Honor, 
     <lb/>
     accompanied by the Hon. James McKay, proceeded thither with me, in 
     <lb/>
     company with Mr. Molyneux St. John, the Clerk of the Legislative Assembly 
     <lb/>
     of Manitoba, who had assisted me in the duties connected with the former 
     <lb/>
     treaty and payments. I left Winnipeg on the 13th August, but owing to 
     <lb/>
     adverse winds on Lake Manitoba did not arrive until two days after the 
     <lb/>
     time appointed. I found that in the meanwhile, the officer in charge of 
     <lb/>
     the Hudson's Bay Company's Post had been obliged to give some provisions 
     <lb/>
     to the Indians pending my arrival but on my speaking to the leading men 
     <lb/>
     of the bands assembled, it was evident that the Indians of this part had no 
     <lb/>
     special demands to make, but having a knowledge of the former treaty, 
     <lb/>
     desired to be dealt with in the same manner and on the same terms as those 
     <lb/>
     adopted by the indians of the Province of Manitoba. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_042.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">42</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     
     <p>The negotiation with these bands therefore occuppied little time, and on 
     <lb/>
     the 21st August, 1871, a treaty was concluded by which a tract of country 
     <lb/>
     three times as large as Province of Manitoba was surrendered by the 
     <lb/>
     Indians to the Crown. Payment in full, that is to say, the gratuity and the 
     <lb/>
     first payment was at once made; and I have since written to the officers in 
     <lb/>
     charge of the Hudson's Bay Company's Posts within the tract above referred 
     <lb/>
     to, requesting them to pressure for me a reliable census of the Indians, parties 
     <lb/>
     to this treaty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have referred to the cost of effecting these treaties, and remarked that 
     <lb/>
     it will prove to be expensive. It may be regarded as entirely so, as far as 
     <lb/>
     the Indians with whom the dealings were held are concerned.  In the future 
     <lb/>
     the annual payment will be only one half to each Indian of the amount paid 
     <lb/>
     this year, for the gratuity was the same as the payment and the heavy 
     <lb/>
     expenses of feeding the Indians while at the place of <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> on their 
     <lb/>
     journey home will be avoided by the payment being made on or near their 
     <lb/>
     own reserves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     All the collateral expenses, therefore, of the year, including dresses, 
     <lb/>
     medals, presents to the Indians, etc., etc., will not appear in the expenses 
     <lb/>
     attending during future payments. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But it is to be remembered that a large number of Indians, whose lands 
     <lb/>
     were ceded by the second treaty, were not present.  The distance from the 
     <lb/>
     hunting grounds of some to Manitoba Post is very great : but while their 
     <lb/>
     absence was to be regretted for some reasons, it effected a very considerable 
     <lb/>
     saving in the item of provisions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     During the ensuing season, these persons will probably be found at the 
     <lb/>
     place where the payments will be made, and will then require their payments 
     <lb/>
     as if they had been present at the signing of' the treaty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Of the land ceded in the Province of Manitoba, it will be hardly necessary 
     <lb/>
     for me to speak, as His Excellency the Governor General is already in pos<lb break="no"/>ession of accurate information Inimhiim' its fertility and resources : but I 
     <lb/>
     may observe that, valuable as are these lands, they are fully equalled if not 
     <lb/>
     exceeded by the country of which the Government now comes into posses<lb break="no"/>sion by virtue of they treaty concluded at Manitoba Post.  Already, settlers 
     <lb/>
     from the Provinces in Canada and elsewhere are pushing their way beyond 
     <lb/>
     the limits of the Province of Manitoba : and there is nothing but the arbitrary 
     <lb/>
     limits of that Province and certain wood and water advantages found in 
     <lb/>
     the territory beyond it, to distinguish one part of the country from the other. 
     <lb/>
     The fertility that is possessed by Manitoba is shared by the country and its 
     <lb/>
     "mining The water courses of the Province are excelled by those of the 
     <lb/>
     territory : and the want of wood which threatens serious difficulty in the 
     <lb/>
     one is by no means so apparent in the other. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     the Indians of both parts have a firm belief in the honor and integrity of 
     <lb/>
     Her Majesty's representatives, and are fully impressed with the idea that 
     <lb/>
     the amelioration of their present condition is one of the objects of Her 
     <lb/>
     Majesty in making these treaties. Although many years will elapse before 
     <lb/>
        
            <pb n="43" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_04_Page_043.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Stone Fort and Manitoba Post Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">43</fw>
     
     they can be regarded as a settled population - settled in the sense of follow<lb break="no"/>ing agricultural practices - the Indians have already shown a disposition to 
     <lb/>
     provide against the vicissitudes of the chase by cultivating small patches of 
     <lb/>
     corn and potatoes.  Moreover, in the Province of Manitoba, where labor is 
     <lb/>
     scarce. Indians give great assistance in gathering: in the crops. At Portage 
     <lb/>
     la Prairie, both Chippawa and Sioux were largely employed in the grain 
     <lb/>
     field: and in other parishes l found many farmers whose employees were 
     <lb/>
     nearly all Indians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Although serious trouble has from time to time occurred across the 
     <lb/>
     boundary line, with Indians of' the same tribes, and indeed of the same 
     <lb/>
     bands as those in Manitoba, there is no reason to fear any trouble with 
     <lb/>
     those who regard themselves as subjects of Her Majesty. their desire is 
     <lb/>
     to live at peace with the white man,  to trade with him, and, when they are 
     <lb/>
     disposed, to work for him: and I believe that nothing but gross injustice or 
     <lb/>
     oppression will induce them either to foget the allegiance which they now 
     <lb/>
     claim with pride, or molest the white subjects of the sovereign whom they 
     <lb/>
     regard as their Supreme Chief. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The system of an annual payment in money I regard as a good one, because 
     <lb/>
     the recipient is enabled to purchase just what he requires when he cab get it 
     <lb/>
     most cheaply, and it also enables him to buy articles at second hand, from 
     <lb/>
     settlers and others, that are quite as useful to him as are the same things 
     <lb/>
     when new.  The sum of three dollars does not appear to be large enough to 
     <lb/>
     enable an Indian to provide' himself with many of his winter necessaries; 
     <lb/>
     but as he receives the same amount for his wife or wives, and for each of 
     <lb/>
     his children, the aggregate sum is usually sufficient to prepare nany com<lb break="no"/>forts for his famly which he would otherwise be compelled to deny himself. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
       *        *          *          *          *          *          *          *          *      
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I take this opportunity of acknowledging the assistance afforded me in 
     <lb/>
     successfully completing the two treaties, to which I have referred. by His 
     <lb/>
     Honor the Lieutenant-Governor of Manitoba, the Hon. James McKay, and 
     <lb/>
     the officers of the Hudson's Bay Company. In a country where transport 
     <lb/>
     and all other business facilities are necessarily so scarce, the services rendered 
     <lb/>
     to the Government by the officers in charge of the several Hudson's Bay Posts 
     <lb/>
     has been most opportune and valuable.
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     I have, etc., 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     <persName ref="pers:SIMP2">WEMYSS M. SIMPSON</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Indian Commissioner</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>