<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="Morris_Chapter_02"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreatyNeg">Treaty Negotiations</name>, <date when="1850">1850</date>, Between Canada and First Nations of Manitoba and the Northwest Territories.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <author>Alexander Morris</author>.
          
         
          <title>The Treaties of Canada with the Indians of Manitoba and the North-West Territories Including the Negotiations on Which They Are Based, and Other Information Relating Thereto.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1880"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>: <publisher>Willing &amp; Williamson</publisher>.
          
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="21"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_016.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_017.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_018.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_019.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_020.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_021.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-28">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-28">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_016">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_016.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_017">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_017.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_018">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_018.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_019">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_019.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_020">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_020.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_021">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_021.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <pb n="16" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_016.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="num">16</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     
<div type="chapter">
            <head>CHAPTER II.</head>

            <p>THE ROBINSON TREATIES.</p>
            

<p>
     IN consequence of the discovery of minerals, on the shores of 
     <lb/>
     Lakes Huron and Superior, the Government of the late Pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Canada, deemed it desirable, to extinguish the Indian 
     <lb/>
     title, and in order to that end, in the year 1850, entrusted the 
     <lb/>
     duty to the late Honorable William B. Robinson, who discharged 
     <lb/>
     his duties with great tact and judgment, succeeding in making 
     <lb/>
     two treaties, which were the forerunners of the future treaties, 
     <lb/>
     and shaped their course. The main features of the Robinson 
     <lb/>
     Treaties—viz., annuities, reserves for the Indians, and liberty to 
     <lb/>
     fish and hunt on the unconceded domain of the Crown—having 
     <lb/>
     been followed in these treaties. A special feature of the Robin<lb break="no"/>son Treaties, was the adjustment of a claim made by the Indians 
     <lb/>
     to be paid, the amount received, by the Government, for the sale 
     <lb/>
     of mining locations. This was arranged, by Mr. Robinson, 
     <lb/>
     agreeing to pay them, the sum of £4,000 and an annuity of 
     <lb/>
     about £1,000, thus avoiding any dispute that might arise as 
     <lb/>
     to the amounts actually received by the Government. The 
     <lb/>
     number of Indians included in the treaties were stated by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Robinson to be : on Lake Superior, 1240, including 84 half- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     breeds ; and on Lake Huron 1422, including 200 half-breeds.<ref target="#fn_01">*</ref> 
     <lb/>
     The relations of the Indians and half-breeds, have long been 
     <lb/>
     cordial ; and in the negotiations as to these initial treaties, as 
     <lb/>
     in the subsequent ones, the claims of the half-breeds, to recog<lb break="no"/>nition, was urged by the Indians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
          
   
<note xml:id="fn_01">* The census return of the Department of the Interior for the year 1878 
     <lb/>
     gives the numbers of these Indians as follows:</note>

 <!-- GL, 2017-03-28, untaggedTable commented out table to be marked-up at later date.

     <lb/>
     Chippawas of Lake Superior . . . . . . . . . . 1,947 
     <lb/>
     Chippawas of Lake Huron . . . . . . . . . . 1,458 
     <lb/>
            -->
   
            
            <pb n="17" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_017.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Robinson Treaties.</hi></fw> <fw type="num">17</fw>
   
            <p>
     I cannot do better, in giving information with regard to these 
     <lb/>
     treaties, than simply to reproduce the Report of Mr. Robinson to 
     <lb/>
     the Honorable Colonel Bruce, Superintendent-General of In<lb break="no"/>dian Affairs, in which he describes the course of his negotia<lb break="no"/>tions and communicates their results. A copy of the treaties 
     <lb/>
     will be found in the Appendix. The Report is as follows: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     TORONTO, <hi rendition="simple:italic">24th September, 1850</hi>. 
     <lb/>
    Sir:—I have the honor herewith to transmit the Treaty which on the 
     <lb/>part of the Government I was commissioned to negotiate with the tribes of 
     <lb/>Indians inhabiting the northern shore of Lakes Huron and Superior ; and I 
     <lb/>trust that the terms on which I succeeded in obtaining the surrender of all 
     <lb/>the lands in question, with the exception of some small reservations made by 
     <lb/>the Indians, may be considered satisfactory. They were such as I thought 
     <lb/>it advisable to offer, in order that the matter might be finally settled, with<lb break="no"/>out having any just grounds of complaint on the part of the Indians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The Indians had been advised by certain interested parties to insist on 
     <lb/>
     such extravagant terms as I felt it quite impossible to grant; and from the 
     <lb/>
     fact that the American Government had paid very liberally for the land sur<lb break="no"/>rendered by their Indians on the south side of Lake Superior, and that our 
     <lb/>
     own in other parts of the country were in receipt of annuities much larger 
     <lb/>
     than I offered, I had some difficulty in obtaining the assent of a few of the 
     <lb/>
     chiefs to my proposition. , 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I explained to the chiefs in council the difference between the lands ceded 
     <lb/>
     heretofore in this Province, and those then under consideration, they were 
     <lb/>
     of good quality and sold readily at prices which enabled the Government to 
     <lb/>
     be more liberal, they were also occupied by the whites in such a manner as 
     <lb/>
     to preclude the possibility of the Indian hunting over or having access to 
     <lb/>
     them: whereas the lands now ceded are notoriously barren and sterile, and 
     <lb/>
     will in all probability never be settled except in a few localities by mining 
     <lb/>
     companies, whose establishments among the Indians, instead of being pre<lb break="no"/>judicial, would prove of great benefit as they would afford a market for any 
     <lb/>
     things they may have to sell, and bring provisions and stores of all kinds 
     <lb/>
     among them at reasonable prices. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Neither did the British Government contemplate the removal of the 
     <lb/>
     Indians from their present haunts to some (to them) unknown region in the 
     <lb/>
     far West, as had been the case with their brethren on the American side. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I told them that the two chiefs who were In Toronto last winter (Shingua<lb break="no"/>couse and Nebennigoebing) only asked the amount which the Government 
     <lb/>
     had received for mining locations, after deducting the expenses attending 
     <lb/>
     their sale. That amount was about eight thousand pounds which the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment would pay them without any annuity or certainty of further benefit; 
     <lb/>
     or one-half of it down, and an annuity of about one thousand pounds. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="18" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_018.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">18</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw>
   
            <p>
        
    There were twenty-one chiefs present, about the same number of principal 
     <lb/>men, and a large number of other Indians belonging to the different bands, 
     <lb/>and they all preferred the latter proposition, though two of them (Shingua<lb break="no"/>couse and Nebennigoebing) insisted on receiving an annuity equal to ten 
     <lb/>dollars per head. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The chiefs from Lake Superior desired to treat separately for their terri<lb break="no"/>tory and said at once in council that they accepted my offer. I told them 
     <lb/>
     that I would have the treaty ready on the following morning, and I immedi<lb break="no"/>ately proceeded to prepare it; and, as agreed upon, they signed it cheerfully 
     <lb/>
     at the time appointed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I then told the chiefs from Lake Huron (who were all present when the 
     <lb/>
     others signed) that I should have a similar treaty ready for their signature, 
     <lb/>
     the next morning, when those who signed it would receive their money ; and 
     <lb/>
     that as a large majority of them had agreed to my terms I should abide by 
     <lb/>
     them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I accordingly prepared the treaty and proceeded on the morning of the 
     <lb/>
     ninth instant to the council-room to have it formally executed in the pres<lb break="no"/>ence of proper witnesses—all the chiefs and others were present. I told them 
     <lb/>
     I was then ready to receive their signatures; the two chiefs, Shinguacouse 
     <lb/>
     and Nebennigoebing, repeated their demand of ten dollars a head by way of 
     <lb/>
     annuity, and also insisted that I should insert in the treaty a condition 
     <lb/>
     securing to some sixty half-breeds a free grant of one hundred acres of land 
     <lb/>
     each. I told them they already had my answer as to a larger annuity, and 
     <lb/>
     that I had no power to give them free grants of land. The other chiefs came 
     <lb/>
     forward to sign the treaty and seeing this the two who had resisted up to this 
     <lb/>
     time also came to the table and signed first, the rest immediately following. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I trust his Excellency will approve of my having concluded the treaty on 
     <lb/>
     the basis of a small annuity and the immediate and final settlement of the 
     <lb/>
     matter, rather than paying the Indians the full amount of all moneys on 
     <lb/>
     hand, and a promise of accounting to them for future sales. The latter 
     <lb/>
     course would have entailed much trouble on the Government, besides giving 
     <lb/>
     an opportunity to evil disposed persons to make the Indians suspicious of 
     <lb/>
     any accounts that might be furnished. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Believing that His Excellency and the Government were desirous of leav<lb break="no"/>ing the Indians no just cause of complaint on their surrendering the exten<lb break="no"/>sive territory embraced in the treaty ; and knowing there were individuals 
     <lb/>
     who most assiduously endeavored to create dissatisfaction among them, I 
     <lb/>
     inserted a clause securing to them certain prospective advantages should the 
     <lb/>
     lands in question prove sufficiently productive at any future period to enable 
     <lb/>
     the Government without loss to increase the annuity.<ref target="#fn_02">*</ref> This was so reason<lb break="no"/><note xml:id="fn_02">*The annuities under these treaties have recently been increased, the 
     <lb/>
     following item having been inserted in the Supplies Act of Canada, viz., 
     <lb/>
     " Annual grant to bring up annuities payable under the Robinson Treaty 
     <lb/>
     to the Chippawas of Lakes Huron and Superior, from 96 cents to $4 per 
     <lb/>
     head, $14,000." </note>


            <pb n="19" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_019.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Robinson Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">19</fw>ble and just that I had no difficulty in making them comprehend it, and it 
     <lb/>
     in a great measure silenced the clamor raised by their evil advisers.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In allowing the Indians to retain reservations of land for their own use I 
     <lb/>
     was governed by the fact that they in most cases asked for such tracts as they 
     <lb/>
     had heretofore been in the habit of using for purposes of residence and culti<lb break="no"/>vation, and by securing these to them and the right of hunting and fishing 
     <lb/>
     over the ceded territory, they cannot say that the Government takes from 
     <lb/>
     their usual means of subsistence and therefore have no claims for support, 
     <lb/>
     which they no doubt would have preferred, had this not been done. The 
     <lb/>
     reservation at Garden River is the largest and perhaps of most value, but as 
     <lb/>
     it is occupied by the most numerous band of Indians, and from its locality 
     <lb/>
     (nine miles from the Sault) is likely to attract others to fit, I think it was 
     <lb/>
     right to grant what they expressed a desire to retain. There are two mining 
     <lb/>
     locations at this place, which should not be finally disposed of unless by the 
     <lb/>
     full consent of Shinguacouse and his band; they are in the heart of the vil<lb break="no"/>lage and shew no indications of mineral wealth, they are numbered 14 and 
     <lb/>
     15 on the small map appended to Messrs. Anderson and Vidal's report. I 
     <lb/>
     pledged my word on the part of the Government that the sale of these loca<lb break="no"/>tions should not be completed, and as the locatees have not, I believe, com<lb break="no"/>plied with the conditions of the Crown Lands Department there can be no 
     <lb/>
     difficulty in cancelling the transaction. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The chiefs are desirous that their several reservations should be marked 
     <lb/>
     by proper posts or monuments, and I have told them the Government 
     <lb/>
     would probably send some one next spring for that purpose. As I know 
     <lb/>
     many of the localities I shall be able to give the necessary information when 
     <lb/>
     required. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When at Sault Ste. Marie last May, I took measures for ascertaining as 
     <lb/>
     nearly as possible the number of Indians inhabiting the north shore of the 
     <lb/>
     two lakes; and was fortunate enough to get a very correct census, particu<lb break="no"/>larly of Lake Superior. I found this information very useful at the council, 
     <lb/>
     as it enabled me successfully to contradict the assertion (made by those who 
     <lb/>
     were inciting the chiefs to resist my offers) that there were on Lake Superior 
     <lb/>
     alone, eight thousand Indians. The number on that lake, including eighty- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     four half-breeds, is only twelve hundred and forty—and on Lake Huron, 
     <lb/>
     about fourteen hundred and twenty-two, including probably two-hundred 
     <lb/>
     half-breeds; and when I paid the Indians they acknowledged they knew of 
     <lb/>
     no other families than those on my list. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The number paid, as appears on the pay list, does not show the whole 
     <lb/>
     strength of the different bands, as I was obliged at their own request to 
     <lb/>
     omit some members of the very large families. I have annexed to this 
     <lb/>
     Report the names of the chiefs, their localities, and number of souls in each 
     <lb/>
     band as recognized by me in apportioning the money, thinking it will be use<lb break="no"/>ful when paying the annuity hereafter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This information may I believe be fully relied on for Lake Superior, but the 
     <lb/>
     census for Lake Huron is not so perfect; and I would suggest that Captain 
     <lb/>
         
            <pb n="20" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_020.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">20</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

     Ironside should be furnished with copies of that document and also of the 
     <lb/>
     pay-lists, in order that he may correct, in time, any errors that are found to 
     <lb/>exist.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
      As the half-breeds at Sault Ste. Marie and other places may seek to be recog<lb break="no"/>nized by the Government in future payments, it may be well that I should that 
     <lb/>
    state here the answer that I gave to their demands on the present occasion. 
     <lb/>I told them I came to treat with the chiefs who were present, that the money 
     <lb/>would be paid to them—and their receipt was sufficient for me—that when 
     <lb/>in their possession they might give as much or as little to that class of claim<lb break="no"/>ants as they pleased. To this no one, not even their advisers, could object, 
     <lb/>and I heard no more on the subject. At the earnest request of the chiefs 
     <lb/>themselves I undertook the distribution of the money among their respective 
     <lb/>bands, and all parties expressed themselves perfectly satisfied with my divis<lb break="no"/>ion of their funds. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On my arrival at Penetanguishene I found the chiefs Yellowhead and 
     <lb/>Snake, from Lake Simcoe, and Aissance, from Beausoleil's Island, waiting to 
     <lb/>see me, to prefer their claim to a small tract of land between Penetangui<lb break="no"/>shene and the vicinity of the River Severn. I was aware of their intending on 
     <lb/>to make such a claim and took the precaution of asking the chiefs assembled  
     <lb/>in council at the Sault whether it was well founded, they emphatically 
     <lb/>declared that those chiefs had no claim on Lake Huron, that they had long 
     <lb/>since ceded their lands and were in the receipt of a large annuity, this I 
     <lb/>believe to be the case, and Captain Anderson, whom I met there, is of the<lb/>same opinion; but I promised to inquire into it and give them an answer,<lb/> 
               <lb/>and I will therefore thank you to cause the necessary information from your<lb/>office to be furnished to me on the subject. Should it appear that these<lb/>chiefs have any claim I think I could get their surrender of it for a small<lb/>amount, and there remain sufficient funds at my disposal for the purpose.<lb/>
            </p>

    
            <p>
     The Canadians resident on the lands just surrendered at Sault Ste. Marie 
     <lb/>
     are very anxious to obtain titles to the land on which they have long resided 
     <lb/>
     and made improvements; they applied to me after the treaty and I advised 
     <lb/>
     them to memorialize the Government the usual way, setting forth the man<lb break="no"/>ner in which they were put in possession by the military authorities of the 
     <lb/>
     time, and that I had little doubt that the Government would do them jus<lb break="no"/>tice. I think the survey of the tract should be made so as to interfere as 
     <lb/>
     little as possible with their respective clearings and that those who can show 
     <lb/>
     a fair claim to the favorable consideration of the Government should be lib<lb break="no"/>erally dealt with. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It will be seen on referring to the treaty that I have kept within the 
     <lb/>
     amount at my disposal. Of the £4,160 agreed by me to be paid to the 
     <lb/>
     Indians of both lakes, there remains £75 unexpended. I could not from the 
     <lb/>
     information I possessed tell exactly the number of families I should have to 
     <lb/>
     pay, and thought it prudent to reserve a small sum to make good any omis<lb break="no"/>sions, there may still be a few who will prefer claims, though I know of 
     <lb/>
     none at present. If not, the amount can be paid next year with the annuity 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="21" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_02_Page_021.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Robinson Treaties</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">21</fw> 
    
     to such families as are most deserving; or it may be properly applied in 
     <lb/>
     extinguishing the claim made by the Lake Simcoe Indians, should it appear 
     <lb/>
     on inquiry to be just. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The whole amount given to me in August was £5,033 6s. 8d., of this sum 
     <lb/>
     their remains £800, which I have placed in the Bank of Upper Canada 
     <lb/>
     to the credit of the Receiver-General, and I have prepared a detailed account 
     <lb/>
     of the whole, which, with the proper vouchers, I shall deliver to the Account<lb break="no"/>ant of the Crown Lands Department. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have much pleasure in acknowledging the valuable assistance afforded 
     <lb/>
     me by all the officers of the Honorable the Hudson's Bay Company resident 
     <lb/>
     on the lakes; and the prompt manner in which their Governor, Sir George 
     <lb/>
     Simpson, kindly placed their services at my disposal. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The report made last year by Messrs. Anderson and Vidal I found of 
     <lb/>
     much use to me, and the long services and experience of the former gentle<lb break="no"/>man in Indian affairs enabled him to give me many valuable suggestions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Captain Cooper and his officers by attending at the council, and otherwise, 
     <lb/>
     gave me most cheerfully all the aid in their power; and Captain Ironside, of 
     <lb/>
     your Department, with his assistant, Assickinach, were of essential service 
     <lb/>
    to me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     I found it absolutely necessary to have the aid of some one in taking the 
     <lb/>
     census of the Lake Huron Indians at the time they were receiving their 
     <lb/>
     presents at Manitoulin; and as Captain Ironside was fully occupied in 
     <lb/>
     attending to his own duty, I requested Mr. Keating, who had long known 
     <lb/>
     the Indians on that lake, to give me his assistance. This he cheerfully and 
     <lb/>
     very efficiently did, and afterwards was with me in distributing and paying 
     <lb/>
     out the money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have, in course of my negotiations with the Indians on the present 
     <lb/>
     occasion, collected some information which may be useful to your Depart<lb break="no"/>ment and will at an early day send it to you. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I will thank you to lay the two treaties accompanying this Report before 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency, and trust they may meet with his approval. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I have, &amp;c., 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     (Signed) W. B. ROBINSON. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Hon. COL. BRUCE, 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Superintendent-General, Indian Affairs</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>