<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="Morris_Chapter_07"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreatyNeg">Treaty Negotiations</name>, <date from="1875-10" to="1876-07">October 1875 to July 1876</date>, Between Canada and First Nations of Manitoba and the Northwest Territories.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:Morris">
          

               <author>Alexander Morris</author>.
          
         
          <title>The Treaties of Canada with the Indians of Manitoba and the North-West Territories Including the Negotiations on Which They Are Based, and Other Information Relating Thereto.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1880"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>: <publisher>Willing &amp; Williamson</publisher>.
          
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="142"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_126.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_127.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_128.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_129.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_130.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_131.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_132.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_133.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_134.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_135.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_136.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_137.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_138.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_139.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_140.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_141.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_142.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-04-18">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-04-18">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_126">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_126.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_127">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_127.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_128">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_128.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_129">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_129.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_130">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_130.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_131">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_131.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_132">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_132.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_133">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_133.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_134">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_134.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_135">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_135.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_136">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_136.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_137">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_137.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_138">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_138.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_139">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_139.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_140">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_140.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_141">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_141.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_142">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_142.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="126"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_126.jpg"/>
         
   
            <fw type="num">126</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians.</hi></fw> 
    

   <div type="chapter">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CHAPTER VII. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     THE REVISION OF TREATIES NUMBERS ONE AND TWO. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>


            <p>WHEN Treaties, Numbers One and Two, were made, cer<lb break="no"/>tain verbal promises were unfortunately made to the 
     <lb/>
     Indians, which were not included in the written text of the 
     <lb/>
    treaties, nor recognized or referred to, when these Treaties were 
     <lb/>ratified by the Privy Council. This, naturally, led to misunder<lb break="no"/>standing with the Indians, and to widespread dissatisfaction 
     <lb/>among them. This state of matters was reported to the Council 
     <lb/>by the successive Lieut.-Governors of Manitoba, and by the 
     <lb/>Superintendent of Indian Affairs. On examination of the 
     <lb/>original Treaty Number One, the Minister of the Interior 
     <lb/>reported that a memorandum was found attached to it signed 
     <lb/>by Mr. Commissioner Simpson, His Hon. Governor Archi<lb break="no"/>bald, Mr. St. John and the Hon. Mr. McKay, purporting 
     <lb/>to contain their understanding of the terms upon which the 
     <lb/>Indians concluded the treaty. This memorandum was as 
     <lb/>follows : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Memorandum of things outside of the Treaty which were promised at the Treaty 
     <lb/>
     at the Lower Fort, signed the 3rd day of August, A.D. 1871.</hi>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     For each Chief that signed the treaty, a dress distinguishing him as 
     <lb/>
    Chief. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     For braves and for councillors of each Chief, a dress: it being sup<lb break="no"/>posed that the braves and councillors will be two for each Chief. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     For each Chief, except Yellow Quill, a buggy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     For the braves and councillors of each Chief, except Yellow Quill, a 
     <lb/>
     buggy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In lieu of a yoke of oxen for each reserve, a bull for each, and a cow for 
     <lb/>
     each Chief ; a boar for each reserve, and a sow for each Chief, and a male 
     <lb/>
     and female of each kind of animal raised by farmers ; these when the Indians 
     <lb/>
     are prepared to receive them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
        
            <pb n="127"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_127.jpg"/>
          <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Revision of Treaties One and Two</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">127</fw> 
    
            <p>
     A plow and a harrow for each settler cultivating the ground. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     These animals and their issue to be Government property, but to be allow<lb break="no"/>ed for the use of the Indians, under the superintendence and control of the 
     <lb/>
     Indian Commissioner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Thc buggies to be the property of the Indians to whom they are given. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The above contains an inventory of the terms concluded with the Indians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     <persName ref="pers:SIMP2">WEMYSS M. SIMPSON</persName>, 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:STJO1">MOLYNEUX ST. JOHN</persName>, 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">A. G. ARCHIBALD</persName>, 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:MCKA4">JAS. McKAY</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     The Privy Council, by Order in Council, agreed to consider 
     <lb/>
     this memorandum as part of the original treaties, and in<lb break="no"/>structed the Indian Commissioner to carry out the promises 
     <lb/>
     therein contained, which had not been implemented. They also 
     <lb/>
     agreed to offer to raise the annuities from three to five dollars 
     <lb/>
     per head, to pay a further annual sum of twenty dollars to 
     <lb/>
     each chief, and to give a suit of clothing every three years to each 
     <lb/>
     chief and head man, allowing four head men to each band, upon 
     <lb/>
     the distinct understanding however, that any Indian accepting 
     <lb/>
     the increased payment, thereby formally abandoned all claims 
     <lb/>
     against the Government, in connection with the verbal promises 
     <lb/>
     of the Commissioners, other than those recognized by the treaty 
     <lb/>
     and the memorandum above referred to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Government then invited Lieut.-Gov. Morris, in con<lb break="no"/>junction with the Indian Commissioner, Lieut.-Col. Provencher, 
     <lb/>
     to visit the several bands interested in the treaties, with a 
     <lb/>
     view to submit to them the new terms, and obtain their 
     <lb/>
     acceptance of the proposed revision of the treaties. His Honor 
     <lb/>
     accordingly placed his services at the disposal of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and was at his request accompanied by the Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McKay, who had been present at the making of the original 
     <lb/>
     treaties, and was well versed in the Indian tongues. In 
     <lb/>
     October 1875, these gentlemen entered upon the task confided 
     <lb/>
     to them, and first proceeded to meet the large and important 
     <lb/>
     band of St. Peters, in the Province of Manitoba. The matter 
     <lb/>
     was fully discussed with the Indians, the Order in Council, 
     
            <pb n="128"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_128.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">128</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    

     and memorandum read and explained to them, and their writ<lb break="no"/>ten assent to the new terms obtained. After their return 
     <lb/>
     from St. Peters, owing to the advanced season of the year, it 
     <lb/>
     was decided to divide the work, the Lieutenant-Governor 
     <lb/>
     requesting the Indian Commissioner to proceed to Fort Alex<lb break="no"/>ander on Lake Winnipeg, and to the Broken Head and Roseau 
     <lb/>
     Rivers, while Messrs. Morris and McKay, would undertake to 
     <lb/>
     meet the Indians included in Treaty Number Two at Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     House on Lake Manitoba. Colonel Provencher met the 
     <lb/>
     Indians at the places above mentioned, and obtained the 
     <lb/>
     assent of the Indians of the three bands to the revised treaty. 
     <lb/>
     Messrs. Morris and McKay proceeded by carriage to Lake 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba, and thence in a sail boat, where they met the 
     <lb/>
     Indians of the six bands of Treaty Number Two, and after 
     <lb/>
     full discussion, tha Indians cordially accepted the new terms, 
     <lb/>
     and thus was pleasantly and agreeably closed, with all the 
     <lb/>
     bands of Treaties One and Two, except that of the Portage 
     <lb/>
     band, who were not summoned to any of the conferences, a 
     <lb/>
     fruitful source of dissension and difficulty. The experience 
     <lb/>
     derived from this misunderstanding, proved however, of 
     <lb/>
     benefit with regard to all the treaties, subsequent to Treaties 
     <lb/>
     One and Two, as the greatest care was thereafter taken to 
     <lb/>
     have all promises fully set out in the treaties, and to have the 
     <lb/>
     treaties thoroughly and fully explained to the Indians, and 
     <lb/>
     understood by them to contain the whole agreement between 
     <lb/>
     them and the Crown, The arrangement, however, of the 
     <lb/>
     matter with the Portage band was one of more difficulty. This 
     <lb/>
     band had always been troublesome. In 1870, they had warned 
     <lb/>
     off settlers and Governor MacTavish of the Hudson's Bay Com<lb break="no"/>pany had been obliged to send the Hon. James McKay to 
     <lb/>
     make terms for three years with them for the admission of 
     <lb/>
     settlers. In 1874, they twice sent messengers with tobacco 
     <lb/>
     (the usual Indian credentials for such messengers) to 
     <lb/>
     Qu'Appelle to prevent the making of the treaty there. Besides 
     <lb/>
     the claims to the outside promises, preferred by the other 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="129"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_129.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Revision of Treaties One and Two</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">129</fw> 
    

     Indians, they had an additional grievance, which they pressed 
     <lb/>
     with much pertinacity. To obtain their adhesion to Treaty 
     <lb/>
     Number One, the Commissioners had given them preferential 
     <lb/>
     terms in respect to their reserve, and the wording in the treaty 
     <lb/>
     of these terms enhanced the difficulty. The language used was 
     <lb/>
     as follows: "And for the use of the Indians of whom Oo-za- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     we-kwan is Chief, so much land on the south and east side of 
     <lb/>
     the Assiniboine, as will furnish one hundred and sixty acres 
     <lb/>
     for each family of five, or in that proportion for larger or 
     <lb/>
     smaller families, reserving also a further tract enclosing said 
     <lb/>
     reserve, to contain an equivalent to twenty-five square miles 
     <lb/>
     of equal breadth, to be laid out around the reserve." The 
     <lb/>
     enclosure around the homestead reserve led to extravagant 
     <lb/>
     demands by them. They did not understand its extent, and 
     <lb/>
     claimed nearly half of the Province of Manitoba under it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Indians constantly interviewed the Lieutenant-Governor 
     <lb/>
     on the subject, and when the Hon. Mr. Laird, then Minister 
     <lb/>
     of the Interior, visited Manitoba, they twice pressed their 
     <lb/>
     demands upon him. The Government requested the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Messrs. Morris and McKay to endeavor to settle the long 
     <lb/>
     pending dispute, and they proceeded to the Round Plain on 
     <lb/>
     the river Assiniboine with that view. They met the Indians, 
     <lb/>
     some five hundred in number, but without result. The Indians 
     <lb/>
     were divided among themselves. A portion of the band had 
     <lb/>
     forsaken Chief Yellow Quill and wished the recognition of the 
     <lb/>
     Great Bear, grandson of Pee-qual-kee-quash, a former chief of 
     <lb/>
     the band. The Yellow Quill band wanted the reserve assigned 
     <lb/>
     in one locality ; the adherents of the Bear said that place was 
     <lb/>
     unsuited for farming, and they wished it to be placed at the 
     <lb/>
     Round Plain, where they had already commenced a settlement. 
     <lb/>
     The land to which they were entitled under the treaty was 
     <lb/>
     34,000 acres, but their demands were excessive. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Chief Yellow Quill was apprehensive of his own follow<lb break="no"/>ers, and besides the danger of collision between the two sections 
     <lb/>
     was imminent. The Commissioners finally intimated to the 
     <lb/>
   
            <pb n="130"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_130.jpg"/>
         
     <fw type="num">130</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    

     band that they would do nothing with them that year, but 
     <lb/>
     would make the customary payment of the annuities under the 
     <lb/>
     original treaty and leave them till next year to make up their 
     <lb/>
     minds as to accepting the new terms, to which the Indians 
     <lb/>
     agreed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In 1876, the Government again requested Mr. Morris to 
     <lb/>
     meet these Indians and endeavor to arrange the long pending 
     <lb/>
     dispute with them, and in July he travelled to the Long Plain 
     <lb/>
     on the Assiniboine with that object in view. He had pre<lb break="no"/>viously summoned the band to meet there, and had also sum<lb break="no"/>moned a portion of the band known as the White Mud River 
     <lb/>
     Indians, dwelling on the shores of Lake Manitoba, who were 
     <lb/>
     nominally under the chieftainship of Yellow Quill, and were, 
     <lb/>
     as such, entitled to a portion of the original reserve, but did 
     <lb/>
     not recognize the Chief. Mr. Morris was accompanied by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Graham, of the Indian Department, Secretary and Pay<lb break="no"/>master. On arrival at his destination, the Lieutenant-Governor 
     <lb/>
     found the Indians assembled, but in three camps. Those 
     <lb/>
     adhering to Yellow Quill, the Bear, and the White Mud River 
     <lb/>
     Indians, being located on different parts of the plains. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Reid, Surveyor, was also present, to explain the extent and 
     <lb/>
     exact dimensions of the proposed reserve. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The next day the Indians were assembled, and the confer<lb break="no"/>ence lasted for two days. The Yellow Quill band were still 
     <lb/>
     obstructive, but the other two sections were disposed to accept 
     <lb/>
     the terms. The question of the reserve was the main difficulty. 
     <lb/>
     The Yellow Quill band still desired a reserve for the whole. 
     <lb/>
     The others wished to remain, the Bear's party at the Round 
     <lb/>
     Plain, and the White Mud River Indians at Lake Manitoba, 
     <lb/>
     where they resided and had houses and farms. In the interval 
     <lb/>
     from the previous year, the Bear's band had built several 
     <lb/>
     houses, and made enclosures for farming. Eventually, the 
     <lb/>
     Indians were made to comprehend the extent of land they 
     <lb/>
     were really entitled to, but the Governor intimated that the 
     <lb/>
     land was for all, and that he would divide the band into three, 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="131"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_131.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Revision of Treaties One and Two</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">131</fw> 
     
          

     each with a Chief and councillors, and that he would give each 
     <lb/>
     band a portion of the whole number of acres, proportionate to 
     <lb/>
     their numbers—the Bear at the Round Plain, the White Mud 
     <lb/>
     Indians at their place of residence, and the Yellow Quill 
     <lb/>
     band wherever they might select, in unoccupied territory. 
     <lb/>
     After long consultations among themselves the Indians accepted 
     <lb/>
     the proposal. The Bear was recognized as a Chief, and a Chief 
     <lb/>
     selected by the White Mud River band was accepted as such. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Indians also agreed to accept the revised terms of Treaty 
     <lb/>
     Number One, and an agreement in accordance with the under<lb break="no"/>standing was prepared and signed by the Lieutenant-Governor, 
     <lb/>
     and the Chief and head men. The Indians preferred a request 
     <lb/>
     to receive the two dollars, increased amount, which, as they 
     <lb/>
     said, "had slipped through their fingers last year," which was 
     <lb/>
     granted, and also that the councillors should be paid yearly, as 
     <lb/>
     in the other treaties, subsequently made. This the Governor 
     <lb/>
     promised to recommend, and it was eventually granted, being 
     <lb/>
     made applicable to all the band in Treaties Numbers One and 
     <lb/>
     Two. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Thus was so far closed, a controversy which had lasted for 
     <lb/>
     some years, and had been fruitful of unpleasant feelings, the 
     <lb/>
     negotiations terminating in that result having been from a 
     <lb/>
     variety of causes more difficult to bring to a satisfactory 
     <lb/>
     solution than the actual making of treaties, for the acquisition 
     <lb/>
     of large extents of territory. On the leaving of the Lieutenant- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Governor, the morning after the conclusion of the arrange<lb break="no"/>ment, the Indians assembled and gave three cheers for the 
     <lb/>
     Queen and Governor, and fired a <hi rendition="simple:italic">feu de joie</hi>. Mr. Reid at once 
     <lb/>
     proceeded to set aside the reserves for the Bear and White 
     <lb/>
     Mud bands, but the selection of a reserve by the Yellow Quill 
     <lb/>
     band was attended with still further further difficulty, although 
     <lb/>
     it was eventually pointed out by them, and surveyed by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Reid, it being in a very desirable locality. The despatches of 
     <lb/>
     the Lieutenant-Governor to the Minister of the Interior, giving 
     <lb/>
     an account in full of the negotiations for the revision of the 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="132"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_132.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="num">132</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
   
            
   
           
     Treaties Numbers One and Two, will complete this record, and 
     <lb/>
     will be found to give a clear narrative of them. These are as 
     <lb/>
     follows : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     GOVERNMENT HOUSE 
     <lb/>
     FORT GARRY, MANITOBA, <hi rendition="simple:italic">5th October, 1875</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Sir,—I have the honor to inform you that in pursuance of your request 
     <lb/>
     that I should meet the Indians of Treaties Numbers One and Two, with a 
     <lb/>
     view to a revision of the terms thereof, and an adjustment of the disputed 
     <lb/>
     questions connected therewith, I proceeded to the St. Peter Reserve on the 
     <lb/>
     5th of August and encamped near the Indian tents. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the 6th I met Chief Prince and his band, being accompanied by the 
     <lb/>
     Hon. James McKay, who at my request gave me the benefit of his valuable 
     <lb/>
     services, and by Mr. Provencher. I explained to the Indians the terms 
     <lb/>
     offered to them by the Government, and obtained their written assent 
     <lb/>
     thereto, endorsed on a parchment copy of the Order in Council of date the 
     <lb/>
     30th April, 1875. As however there are in the bands of Treaties Numbers 
     <lb/>
     One and Two, four councillors, <hi rendition="simple:italic">i.e.</hi>, head men, and two braves, we were 
     <lb/>
     under the necessity of agreeing that they should continue at that number, 
     <lb/>
     instead of two, as specified in the report of the Privy Council. We then 
     <lb/>
     brought before them your request that the portion of the reserve embraced 
     <lb/>
     in the proposed new town near the Pacific Railway crossing should be sold 
     <lb/>
     for their benefit, to which they agreed, and the formal instrument of sur<lb break="no"/>render will be enclosed to you by the Indian Commissioner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Indians living at Nettley Creek asked to have a reserve assigned 
     <lb/>
     them there, and I promised to bring their request under your notice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I did not bring up the question of the division of the band into two, as my 
     <lb/>
     experience with the Portage band, arising from a similar difficulty, led me to 
     <lb/>
     fear that complications might arise from the proposal which might prevent 
     <lb/>
     the settlement of the more important matter of the disposal of the open 
     <lb/>
     questions relating to the treaty. I was therefore of opinion that the 
     <lb/>
     division of the band should be postponed to next year, and acted upon that 
     <lb/>
     opinion. A party of Norway House Indians were present and asked for a 
     <lb/>
     reserve at the Grassy Narrows. I informed them that one could not be 
     <lb/>
     granted at that place, and learning from them that the Chief at Norway 
     <lb/>
     House was about leaving there with a party of Indians to confer with me, 
     <lb/>
     I engaged three of the Indians present to proceed at once to Norway House 
     <lb/>
     and inform the Indians that I would meet them there about the middle of 
     <lb/>
     September. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have since learned that they met the Chief after he had left Norway 
     <lb/>
     House or Fort Garry, and caused him to return. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
       
               <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     
    I have the honor to be, etc., 
     <lb/> <persName ref="pers:MORR1">ALEXANDER MORRIS</persName>, 
     <lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut.-Governor</hi>.<lb/>
            </p>
   
</quote>
            <pb n="133"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_133.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Revision of Treaties One and Two</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">133</fw> 
     
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">  
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     GOVERNMENT HOUSE, 
     <lb/>
     FORT GARRY, MANITOBA, <hi rendition="simple:italic">4th October, 1875</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     SIR, —I have the honor to inform you that after my return from St. 
     <lb/>
     Peters, finding that in view of my contemplated mission to Lake Winnipeg 
     <lb/>
     it would be impossible for me to visit all the bands of Indians included in 
     <lb/>
     Treaties Numbers One and Two, I requested the Indian Commissioner, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Provencher, to proceed to meet them at Fort Alexander and the 
     <lb/>
     Broken Head and Roseau rivers, while I should proceed to Lake Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     and meet at Manitoba House the various bands of Indians included in 
     <lb/>
     Treaty Number Two. In pursuance of this arrangement, I left here on the 
     <lb/>
     17th of August for Oak Point, on Lake Manitoba, where I was to take a 
     <lb/>
     boat for Manitoba Post. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I was accompanied by the Hon. James McKay, whose presence enabled 
     <lb/>
     me to dispense with an interpreter, and was of importance otherwise, as he 
     <lb/>
     had assisted my predecessor in the making of the treaty originally at Mani<lb break="no"/>toba Post. Mr. Graham, of the Indian Department, also accompanied me 
     <lb/>
     to make the payments and distribute the pensions. I reached Oak Point 
     <lb/>
     on the afternoon of the 18th, and left there on the afternoon of the 20th, 
     <lb/>
     arriving at Manitoba House on the evening of the 21st. The next day being 
     <lb/>
     Sunday, nothing of course was done relating to my mission, but on Monday 
     <lb/>
     morning I met the Indians at ten o'clock on the lake shore. The six bands 
     <lb/>
     included in the treaty were all represented by their Chiefs and head men 
     <lb/>
     and a large number of their people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I explained to them the object of our mission, my remarks being fully 
     <lb/>
     interpreted by Mr. McKay, and obtained their assent in writing to the 
     <lb/>
     Order in Council of the 30th April last, the terms of which were accepted 
     <lb/>
     with cordiality and good feeling by the Indians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The new medals and uniforms were distributed to the Chiefs and head 
     <lb/>
     men, and the payments under the revised treaty were then commenced by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. McKay and Mr. Graham, and continued until 12.30 p.m. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the 24th, the payments were resumed and concluded, but owing to 
     <lb/>
     heavy rain and high winds, we were unable to leave Manitoba Post until 
     <lb/>
     the 25th. The Indians on our departure again firing their guns in token 
     <lb/>
     of their respect and good will. Owing to stormy weather, which obliged us 
     <lb/>
     to encamp on Bird Island, we did not return to Oak Point until the after<lb break="no"/>noon of the 27th. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     0n the 28th, the Indians residing in that vicinity, and belonging to 
     <lb/>
     Sousanye's band, were paid by Messrs. McKay and Graham. I returned 
     <lb/>
     to Fort Garry on the 1st September, in the afternoon, my journey having 
     <lb/>
     been protracted by unfavorable weather, and by the fact that owing to the 
     <lb/>
     prevalence of shoals. the navigation of Lake Manitoba is difficult in stormy 
     <lb/>
     weather. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As only a small portion of the Riding House Indians were present, I in<lb break="no"/>formed them that Mr. Graham would proceed to the mountains after our 
     

            <pb n="134"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_134.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="num">134</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

     return, to make the payments, and that I would send by him a reply to 
     <lb/>
     their requests, as to the retention by them of the reserve originally desig<lb break="no"/>nated in the treaty, and this I have since done affirmatively with your 
     <lb/>
     sanction. Mr. Provencher succeeded in obtaining the adhesion of the 
     <lb/>
     bands at Fort Alexander, Broken Head and Roseau rivers to the new 
     <lb/>
     terms, and has handed me the copies of the Order in Council with their 
     <lb/>
     assents endorsed thereon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     You will therefore perceive that with the exception of the Portage band 
     <lb/>
     with regard to whom I wrote you fully on the 2nd of August last, the 
     <lb/>
     assent of all the Indians interested therein to the proposed mode of settle<lb break="no"/>ment of the unrecorded promises made at the conclusion of Treaties 
     <lb/>
     Numbers One and Two, has been obtained, and I feel that I have reason to 
     <lb/>
     congratulate the Privy Council on the removal of a fruitful source of diffi<lb break="no"/>culty and discontent. But I would add. that it becomes all the more 
     <lb/>
     important that a better system of Indian administration should be devised 
     <lb/>
     so as to secure the prompt and rigid carrying out of the new terms in their 
     <lb/>
     entirety. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     You are already in possession of my views on this subject, and I trust that 
     <lb/>
     local agents will be appointed to be supervised by the Indian Commissioner 
     <lb/>
     and that an Indian Council of advice and control, sitting at Fort Garry, 
     <lb/>
     will be entrusted with the direction of the Treaties One, Two, and the 
     <lb/>
     upper portion of Three, and the new Treaty Number Five, so as to secure 
     <lb/>
     prompt and effective administration of Indian Affairs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Under the system of local agents, the necessity of large gatherings of the 
     <lb/>
     Indians will be avoided, and much expense to the Government, and 
     <lb/>
     inconvenience to the Indians, avoided. I have further to record my sense 
     <lb/>
     of the services rendered to me by Messrs. McKay and Graham. The latter 
     <lb/>
     discharged his duties with promptitude and efficiency, and Mr. McKay and 
     <lb/>
     he introduced a mode of distribution of the provisions to which I would call 
     <lb/>
    your attention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">I have the honor to be, etc., 
     <lb/>
               <persName ref="pers:MORR1">ALEXANDER MORRIS</persName>, 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut. -Governor</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     GOVERNMENT HOUSE, 
     <lb/>
     FORT GARRY, MANITOBA, <hi rendition="simple:italic">2nd August, 1875</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     SIR, —In accordance with your request I have commenced my visits to the 
     <lb/>
     Indian bands included in Treaties Numbers One and Two, with a view to 
     <lb/>
     settling the matters in dispute. I left here on the 22nd inst., and was 
     <lb/>
     accompanied by the Hon. James McKay, whom I had invited to accom<lb break="no"/>pany me in consequence of his having been present at the making of the 
     <lb/>
     treaties. and by the Indian Commissioner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I reached the Round Plain on the Assiniboine river, where Yellow Quill's 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="135"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_135.jpg"/>
           

    <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Revision of Treaties One and Two</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">135</fw> 
     
            
     band of Saulteaux had assembled on the 26th, and met the Indians next day, 
     <lb/>
     explaining to them our mission, and telling them what I was empowered to 
     <lb/>
     promise them. This band, as you are aware, has always been dissatisfied, 
     <lb/>
     and have been difficult to deal with. I found them in an intractable frame 
     <lb/>
     of mind, and the difficulty of the position was enhanced by a division 
     <lb/>
     amongst themselves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The original Chief of the Portage band was Pee-quah-kee-quah, who was 
     <lb/>
     a party to the treaty with Lord Selkirk. On his death he was succeeded 
     <lb/>
     by his son, who died some years ago, leaving a boy, who has now grown up. 
     <lb/>
     Yellow Quill was appointed chief by the Hudson's Bay Company when 
     <lb/>
     Pee-quah-kee-quah's son died. The grandson is now grown up and has 
     <lb/>
     returned from the plains, where he has been, and claims to be recognized as an 
     <lb/>
     hereditary chief, and about half the band have followed his lead. After we 
     <lb/>
     had been in conference for some time, an Indian rose and told me that when the 
     <lb/>
     chief of the Portage died, he charged him to keep the land for his son, and 
     <lb/>
     that they wished a reserve at the Portage. Another rose and produced Pee- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     quah-kee-quah's King George medal, and said the chief had placed it in his 
     <lb/>
     keeping and charged him to deliver it to his son, when he was old enough 
     <lb/>
     to be a chief, and then placed it round the neck of Kes-kee-maquah, or the 
     <lb/>
     Short Bear. They then asked that I should receive him as a chief, in place 
     <lb/>
     of Yellow Quill. I told them that could not be done. That Yellow Quill must 
     <lb/>
     remain a chief, but that I would report their request on behalf of the young 
     <lb/>
     chief to the Government at Ottawa and let them know their decision, but 
     <lb/>
     that they could get no reserve at the Portage, as only that mentioned in the 
     <lb/>
     treaty would be given, and with this they were satisfied. The conference 
     <lb/>
     then went on, the two parties sitting apart and holding no intercourse with 
     <lb/>
     each other. I spent two days with them, making no progress, as they 
     <lb/>
     claimed that a reserve thirty miles by twenty was promised them, as shewn in 
     <lb/>
     the rough sketch enclosed, made at their dictation and marked " A." I pro<lb break="no"/>duced the plan of the reserve. as proposed to be allotted to them, containing 
     <lb/>
     34,000 acres, but Yellow Quill said it was not in the right place, and was not 
     <lb/>
     what was promised, and morever it was not surrounded by the belt of five 
     <lb/>
     miles, mentioned in the treaty, but was only partially so, and did not cross the 
     <lb/>
     river. I told them they could get no more land than was promised in the 
     <lb/>
     treaty. They appealed to Mr. McKay whether the Reserve was not pro<lb break="no"/>mised to be on both sides cf the river, and he admitted that it was. I told 
     <lb/>
     them it was not so written in the treaty, and that if the Government should 
     <lb/>
     allow it to cross the rive": the rights of navigation must be conserved, but I 
     <lb/>
     would consult the Queen's Councillors. They replied that they would go to 
     <lb/>
     the " Grand Father " and get him to intercede for them, meaning the " Pre<lb break="no"/>sident of the United States." as I afterwards discovered, an American 
     <lb/>
     Indian having persuaded them to take this course. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     They refused to discuss rr accept anything until the Reserve Question was 
     <lb/>
     settled, and while I was speaking on the afternoon of the second day, 
     <lb/>
     Yellow Quill's Councillors went away, and left him alone, when he followed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="136"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_136.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">136</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
   
            <p>
     I then left the Council tent, leaving word that I would depart in the morn<lb break="no"/>ing. Yellow Quill came back and said that he would accept the five dol<lb break="no"/>lars, but Mr. McKay told him he had not taken my hand, and that it 
     <lb/>would not be paid, as my offer was conditioned on a settlement of all 
     <lb/>questions between them and the Government. About six o'clock, Yellow 
     <lb/>Quill and his Councillors sent me the following message which had been 
     <lb/>written for them by Mr. Deputy Sheriff Setter from their dictation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     "They didn't come to see you. You came to see them, and if you choose 
     <lb/>
     to come and speak to them again, you can come if you like." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I felt that I must now deal firmly with them, and therefore prepared the 
     <lb/>
     following reply: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " It is not right, for they came to see me at my request, as their Governor, 
     <lb/>
     and I came to meet them. After spending two days with them, their Chief in<lb break="no"/>sulted me by rising and going out while I was speaking, and breaking up 
     <lb/>
    the Conference. I represent the Queen, and his action was disrespectful to 
     <lb/>her. I will not go to meet you again. If you are sorry for the way I have 
     <lb/>been treated you can come and see me." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     I charged Mr. McKay to deliver it to them in their Council, which he 
     <lb/>
     did, when they denied having meant to send the message in the terms in 
     <lb/>
     which it was, and disclaimed all intended offence. The message had its 
     <lb/>
     desired effect, but their disclaimer was not correct, as Mr. Setter informs 
     <lb/>
     me that he had originally written a welcome to me, which they caused 
     <lb/>
     him to strike out, and to say that " I could come if I chose." Next morn<lb break="no"/>ing I struck my tents and loaded my waggons and prepared to leave. See<lb break="no"/>ing this, Yellow Quill and his Councillors came to Mr. McKay, and asked 
     <lb/>
     if I would not see them again, to which I consented. On proceeding to 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Provencher's pay tent, I met the Chief, Yellow Quill. His spokesman 
     <lb/>
     rose, saying " that they were glad to have met me, that they had found my 
     <lb/>
     words good; that they had not desired to offend the Queen or me, and were 
     <lb/>
     sorry ; that God had watched us during two days, and He was again look<lb break="no"/>ing on." I accepted their apology, and then proceeded to practical business. 
     <lb/>
     the whole tone and demeanor of the Indians being changed, having become 
     <lb/>
     cordial and friendly. I may mention here, that Yellow Quill reproached his 
     <lb/>
     Councillors for their conduct. He also informed Mr. McKay privately, 
     <lb/>
     that he could not act otherwise as he was in danger of his life from some of 
     <lb/>
     his own "braves." He was guarded all the time bya man armed with a 
     <lb/>
     bow and steel-pointed arrows. I promised to state their claims as to the 
     <lb/>
     reserve, but told them it would not be granted, but that I Would change the 
     <lb/>
     location of the reserve, as it had been selected without their approval, and 
     <lb/>
     would represent their view as to its locality, and as to crossing the river, 
     <lb/>
     the navigation of which, however, could not be interfered with. They 
     <lb/>
     asked to be paid three dollars per head or one dollar per year for the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing transaction: In 1868a number of Ontario farmers had settled on 
     <lb/>
     Rat Creek. Yellow Quill's band drove them off and trouble was impending. 
     <lb/>
     Governor McTavish sent Mr: McKay up to arrange the difficulty, in antici<lb break="no"/><pb n="137"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_137.jpg"/>
         
     
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Revision of Treaties One and Two</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">137</fw>pation of the advent of Canadian power. He made a lease for three years 
     <lb/>
     of their rights, assuring them that before that time the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would make a treaty with them and recognize the temporary arrange<lb break="no"/>ment, and in consquence the settlers were unmolested. The question was 
     <lb/>
     not raised at the " Stone Fort " Treaty, and I told them I had not known 
     <lb/>
     of it before, but supposed the Government would hold that the treaty had 
     <lb/>
     covered it, and that the extra two dollars would compensate for it, but that 
     <lb/>
     I would represent their views and give them an answer. They complained 
     <lb/>
     of the mode of payment, as my predecessor assured them that their child<lb break="no"/>ren who were absent should be paid when they presented themselves, and 
     <lb/>
     that they only got two years payment instead of the full amount. As these 
     <lb/>
     were Mr. Provencher's instructions I promised to report it. They express<lb break="no"/>ed themselves quite satisfied with the arrangements as to the outside pro<lb break="no"/>mises, and would gladly accept of it, if the reserve question was settled, but 
     <lb/>
     that they could not receive that as surveyed. I took the opportunity of ex<lb break="no"/>plaining to them that the "President of the United States " had no power 
     <lb/>
     here, and that the Queen and Her Councillors were the only authorities 
     <lb/>
     they had to deal with, and that I would state their wishes as fullv as 
     <lb/>
     they could do themselves. They asked if I would come back, but I said 
     <lb/>
     not this year, but next year either I or some other Commissioner would 
     <lb/>
     meet them. Eventually they cheerfully agreed to accept the three dollars 
     <lb/>
     annuity as usual, and to defer a final adjustment of the question between us 
     <lb/>
     until next year, and promised to accompany any one I sent to select the 
     <lb/>
     reserve and agree on its locality. They again thanked me for my kindness 
     <lb/>
     and patience with them, and I took leave of them. I regard the result as 
     <lb/>
     very satisfactory, as I left the band contented, and you are aware of their 
     <lb/>
     intimate relation with the "Plain Indians," and the difficulty their mes<lb break="no"/>sage to Qn'Appelle, " that the white man had not kept his promises,'." 
     <lb/>
     caused us then, and it is very important that they should be satisfied. I re<lb break="no"/>turned to the Portage, and Mr. Provencher proceeded to Totogan, and paid 
     <lb/>
     the White Mud section of the band, numbering one hundred and thirty, 
     <lb/>
     who are nominally included in it, but do not recognize Yellow Quill's 
     <lb/>
     authority, the usual annuities, which they accepted without demur. 
     <lb/> </p>

            <p>I would now make the following recommendations : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>1st. That you should write to Yellow Quill declining to entertain his 
     <lb/>demands for the large reserve, but offering to them a reserve including the 
     <lb/>" Eagle's Nest" on the north side of the river, and laid off in the terms of 
     <lb/>the treaty, with the land comprised in the one hundred and sixty acres for 
     <lb/>each family, surrounded by the belt mentioned in the treaty, in the manner 
     <lb/>suggested in the enclosed rough sketch "B, " reserving the rights of navi<lb break="no"/>gation and access to the river. The land is of inferior quality to that 
     <lb/>already offered them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>2nd. I would propose that the young chief should be recognized as head of 
     <lb/>the section of the band adhering to him. He and his section are ready to 
     <lb/>accept the terms and the reserve as described in the treaty. They behaved 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="138"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_138.jpg"/>
           
            <fw type="num">138</fw>   <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

     very well and told Mr. McKay that they were glad I had not recognized 
     <lb/>
     him then, as it would have led to bloodshed, and they would be content if the 
     <lb/>
     recognition came when the reserve was settled. The young chief is an intelli<lb break="no"/>gent, well disposed man, aged about twenty-six. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3rd. I would propose that the White Mud Indians, who live there con<lb break="no"/>stantly, should be recognized as a distinct band and should elect a Chief. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4th. I would recommend that the arrears due to Indians who have not yet 
     <lb/>
     received their annuities, should be paid in full at once, but that a period of 
     <lb/>
     two years should be fixed for those bona fide members of the band to come in 
     <lb/>
     and be paid, and that after that they should only receive one year's payment. 
     <lb/>
     If these steps are taken, I think we shall have no more trouble with these 
     <lb/>
     Indians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In conclusion I have to express my obligations to the Hon. Mr. Mckay 
     <lb/>
     for the valuable services he rendered me. The Indians told me they would 
     <lb/>
     not have come into the Stone Fort Treaty but for him, and I know it was 
     <lb/>
     the case. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="simple:right">
     I have the honor to be, etc., 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:MORR1">ALEXANDER MORRIS</persName>; 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut.-Governor</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     GOVERNMENT HOUSE, 
     <lb/>
     FORT GARRY, MANITOBA, <hi rendition="simple:italic">8th July 1876</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     To THE HONORABLE THE MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     SIR—I have the honor to inform you that, in compliance with your request, 
     <lb/>
     I left this on the 14th ult. with the view of proceeding to the Long Plain on 
     <lb/>
     the Assiniboine, in order to meet the Indians of the Portage Band, to 
     <lb/>
     arrange the dispute with regard to the reserve, and to settle the outside pro<lb break="no"/>mises. Mr. Graham, of the Indian Department, and Mr. Reid, P.L.S., 
     <lb/>
     also went there at my request, the one to act as paymaster, and the other, as 
     <lb/>
     you wished, to survey the reserve. Owing to the prevalence of heavy rain 
     <lb/>
     the roads were in so bad a condition that I was four days in reaching the 
     <lb/>
     Long Plain, while we were also subjected to incovenience and expense by 
     <lb/>
     the detention of the provisions, owing to the same cause. Added to my 
     <lb/>
     other discomforts was the presence of mosquitoes in incredible numbers, so 
     <lb/>
     that the journey and the sojourn at the Plain were anything but pleasurable. 
     <lb/>
     I had taken the precaution to request Mr. Cummings, the interpreter, to 
     <lb/>
     summon the White Mud Indians as well as Yellow Quill's band, and those 
     <lb/>
     who adhered to the Short Bear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On my arrival at the Long Plains, which I accomplished on the 17th, I 
     <lb/>
     found about five hundred Indians assembled, but camped in three separate 
     <lb/>
     encampments. On arriving, I was saluted by a few de joie. At the Port<lb break="no"/>age, Mr. Graham had obtained some provisions, which he had sent forward 
     <lb/>
    in carts. 
     <lb/>  </p>
               
            <pb n="139"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_139.jpg"/>
          
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Revision of Treaties One and Two</hi>.</fw>  <fw type="num">139</fw> 
     
   
            <p>
     On our way we met some carts sent by the Indians to relieve my waggons 
     <lb/>
     of the tents and baggage, the Indian trail being almost impracticable ; but 
     <lb/>
     instead of so using them I sent them on toward the Portage to meet the 
     <lb/>
     loaded carts, and was thus enabled to get the temporary supply of pro<lb break="no"/>visions to the Plain, which was fortunate, as the Indians were without 
     <lb/>
     food. The evening of my arrival the Councillors of Yellow Quill came to 
     <lb/>
     talk with me, but I declined to do so, telling them that the Chief had not 
     <lb/>
     come, and I would only speak with him. I acted thus, in consequence of 
     <lb/>
     the conduct of their head men, last year, when they controlled the Chief and 
     <lb/>
     coerced the whole band. In a. short time Yellow Quill came with them to 
     <lb/>
     see me, and finding that they had come about provisions, I referred them to 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Graham, who, I informed them, had charge of the provisions and pay<lb break="no"/>ments. The incident had a marked effect in giving tone to the following 
     <lb/>
     negotiations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Monday I met the Indians, who ranged themselves in three parties. I 
     <lb/>
     explained to them the proposed arrangement of the outside promises very 
     <lb/>
     fully, and told them that as they were willing to accept of the settlement 
     <lb/>
     last year, I did so for their information only. I then took up the question 
     <lb/>
     of the reserve, read the terms in which it was referred to in the Stone Fort 
     <lb/>
     Treaty, explained to them that they were getting double the land any other 
     <lb/>
     Indians in Treaties Numbers One and Two were doing, but told them the 
     <lb/>
     reserve belonged to all of them, and not to Yellow Quill's band alone. I 
     <lb/>
     then called on them to speak to me, asking Yellow Quill first. He said he 
     <lb/>
     did not understand the extent of the reserve. I then asked Mr. Reid to 
     <lb/>
     shew them a diagram of it, and to explain to them its length in ordinary 
     <lb/>
     miles, and otherwise, which he did very satisfactorily, and at length they 
     <lb/>
     comprehended it. I then called on Short Bear's band to express their 
     <lb/>
     views. They said they wanted a reserve at the Long Plain, if it was only 
     <lb/>
     a little piece 0f land ; that they liked the place, that they had built houses 
     <lb/>
     and planted gardens, had cut oak to build more houses, and wished to farm 
     <lb/>
     there. I then called on the White Mud Indians. They said that they 
     <lb/>
     were Christians and had always lived at the White Mud River ; that they 
     <lb/>
     did not wish to join either Yellow Quill's or Short Bear's reserve, but 
     <lb/>
     desireda reserve at the Big Point. I told them they could not have it 
     <lb/>
     there, as there were settlers, and the Government wished them to join one 
     <lb/>
     of the other bands, and explained to them that their holdings would be 
     <lb/>
     respected, except where inadvertently sold. I took this course, as I had 
     <lb/>
     ascertained that the plan of Yellow Quill's head men was to make no settle<lb break="no"/>ment this year, and that they had induced the other Indians to agree to 
     <lb/>
     act in that way. I accordingly so shaped my opening speech and my deal<lb break="no"/>ings with the Indians as to defeat this project, by securing the support of 
     <lb/>
     Short Bear's and the White Mud Indians, which I succeeded in doing, 
     <lb/>
     though Yellow Quill's spokesman taunted the others with having broken 
     <lb/>
     their agreement. As the conference proceeded, Yellow Quill's councillors 
     <lb/>
     said they did not want the band broken up, as they wished all to live 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="140"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_140.jpg"/>
         
     <fw type="num">140</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    

     together. I told Yellow Quill he would have his reserve on both sides of 
     <lb/>
     the river, reserving, the navigation, and that if they could agree to go to 
     <lb/>
     one reserve, I would be pleased; but if not, that I would settle the matter. 
     <lb/>
     Yellow Quill said his councillors were willing that the other Indians should 
     <lb/>
     have a separate reserve provided they retained the belt of twenty-five miles, 
     <lb/>
     in addition to their proportion of the reserve. I informed them this could 
     <lb/>
     not be done; the reserve belonged to all. They then asked for an adjourn<lb break="no"/>ment, in order that they might meet together and have a smoke over it, to 
     <lb/>
     assemble again when I hoisted my flag. After a couple of hours interval I 
     <lb/>
     agnin convened them. The Short Bears and White Mud Indians adhered 
     <lb/>
     to what they stated to me, but Yellow Quill's band insisted on one reserve 
     <lb/>
     for all, but admitted that the objections of Short Bear's band to the place 
     <lb/>
     asked by them were well founded, and that it was sandy and unfit for 
     <lb/>
     farming, and that they would like to select a reserve higher up the 
     <lb/>
     River Assiniboine. I then adjourned the conference until morning, and 
     <lb/>
     asked them to meet together and be prepared for settlement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Tuesday, the 20th June, the Indians again respOnded to the hoisting 
     <lb/>
     of my flag, and met at 9 o'clock. Yellow Quill told me that his band are 
     <lb/>
     now willing to separate from the others, and wished to select a reserve 
     <lb/>
     higher up the river. I informed them that I would accede to their request, 
     <lb/>
     but that they must do it at once, and on the approval thereof by the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council it would be laid off. Short Bear's band still desired a reserve at the 
     <lb/>
     Long Plain, to which I assented. The White Mud River Indians asked for 
     <lb/>
     a separate reserve where they could farm, and I informed them that under 
     <lb/>
     the discretionary powers I possessed I would have a reserve selected for them, 
     <lb/>
     giving them their proportion of the original reserve. The Indians then 
     <lb/>
     asked that the two dollars per head, which had, as they said, slipped through 
     <lb/>
      their fingers last year, should be paid to them, and I told them that I had been 
     <lb/>authorized to do so, which gave them much satisfaction. In anticipation of 
     <lb/>a settlement I had prepared a draft agreement, which was being copied for 
     <lb/>me by Mr. Graham. I informed them of this, and stated that I would sign 
     <lb/>it, and that the Chiefs and Councillors must do so likewise, so that there 
     <lb/>could be no misunderstanding. When the agreement was completed, I 
     <lb/>asked Mr. Cummings, the Interpreter, to read it to them, which he did. 
     <lb/>Three Indians, who understood English, and who had at an early period 
     <lb/>been selected by the Indians to check the interpretation of what was said, 
     <lb/>standing by, and Mr. Cummings being assisted by Mr. Cook, of St. James, 
     <lb/>who, at Mr. Cummings' request, I had associated with him, on the Indians 
     <lb/>choosing their interpreters. I then signed the agreement, and called upon 
     <lb/>Yellow Quill to do so. He came forward cheerfully and said he would 
     <lb/>sign it, because he now understood what he never did before, viz., what was 
     <lb/>agreed to at the Stone Fort. I then called on his Councillors to sign, but 
     <lb/>they refused, saying they had agreed by the mouth. I then told the Indians 
     <lb/>that unless the Councillors signed nothing could be done, and that the Coun<lb break="no"/>.cillors who refused would be responsible for the failure of the negotiations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
            <pb n="141"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_141.jpg"/>
  
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Revision of Treaties One and Two</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">141</fw> 
     
            <p>
     One of them then signed, but the other persistently refused. I repeated 
     <lb/>
     my warning, and at length he reluctantly came forward and said he wished 
     <lb/>
     to ask me a question, " Would the head men be paid ?" I told him I had 
     <lb/>
     no authority to do so, but would report his request. He said he did not 
     <lb/>
     expect it this year, but hoped for it next. Eventually he signed the agree<lb break="no"/>ment. I then said I would recognize Short Bear as a Chief, and asked him 
     <lb/>
     to select his Councillors and braves. He did so at once, making a judicious 
     <lb/>
     choice, and came forward to touch the pen, saying, " I thank you for my 
     <lb/>
     people. " His Councillors promptly followed, one of them asking for a part 
     <lb/>
     of the reserve on the other side of the river, which I refused. I then called 
     <lb/>
     on the White Mud River Indians to select a Chief and one Councillor, 
     <lb/>
     being under the impression at the time that they were the least numerous 
     <lb/>
     band, which, however, has turned out not to be the case, which they did at 
     <lb/>
     once, and on their being presented to me they signed the agreement. I 
     <lb/>
     then gave a medal to Yellow Quill, and promised to send the other two 
     <lb/>
     Chiefs medals when procured from Ottawa, the supply here being exhausted. 
     <lb/>
     To the Chiefs and Councillors suits of clothing were then distributed, Yel<lb break="no"/>low Quill and his head men having hitherto refused to accept either medals 
     <lb/>
     or coats, but now taking them. Yellow Quill then presented me with a 
     <lb/>
     skin coat, and said that he parted with the Other Indians as friends, and 
     <lb/>
     that there would be no hard feelings. The conference then broke up, and 
     <lb/>
     thus terminated a difficulty which has existed for several years, and the 
     <lb/>
     influence of which was felt as an obstacle, as you are aware, at Qu'Appelle 
     <lb/>
    when the treaty was made there. Mr. Graham at once commenced the 
     <lb/>payments, and during the evening the three Chiefs and their Councillors 
     <lb/>called on me, evidently being on the most friendly terms with each other, 
     <lb/>a state of things which had not existed for a considerable period. In the 
     <lb/>morning, as I was leaving for the Portage, the Indians assembled near my 
     <lb/>waggon and gave three checrs for the Queen and three for the Governor, 
     <lb/>and I then drove off amid a salute of firearms from all sections of the 
     <lb/>encampment. I left Mr. Graham to complete the payments, and here 
     <lb/>record my sense of the efficient services he rendered me. He understands 
     <lb/>the Indian character, and gets on well with them. I requested Mr. Reid 
     <lb/>to visit the White Mud region and ascertain what persons are entitled to 
     <lb/>holdings under the terms of your instructions, and also to survey Short 
     <lb/>Bear's reserve. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

            <p>
     Yellow Quill is to go without delay to look up a reserve, and as there are 
     <lb/>
     no settlers in the region in question, I propose that if Mr. Reid sees no 
     <lb/>
     objection to the locality he should at once lay it off, so as to effectually ter<lb break="no"/>minate the chronic difficulty with this band. I shall be glad to receive by 
     <lb/>
     telegram your approval of his doing so. The interpreters, Mr. Cummings 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Cook, of St. James, a trader, and Kissoway, an Indian trader belong<lb break="no"/>ing to the band, rendered me much service ; the latter trades in the west, 
     <lb/>
     and was passing the Portage on his way to Fort Garry, and as he belonged to 
     <lb/>
     Yellow Quill's band, and is a relative of his, being a son of the deceased 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="142"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_07_Page_142.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="num">142</fw>   <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

     Pecheto, (another of whose sons was the spokesman at Qu'Appelle, as you 
     <lb/>
     will recollect) he came to the Long Plains to advise the band to come to 
     <lb/>
     terms. He remained at my request until the negotiations were concluded, 
     <lb/>
     and exerted a most beneficial influence over Yellow Quill's band. I call 
     <lb/>
     your attention to the request of Yellow Quill's Councillors, that they should 
     <lb/>
     be paid. As in Treaties Three, Four and Five, they are paid, and as the 
     <lb/>
     expense would not be large, I am of opinion that before the Superintendent 
     <lb/>
     of Indian Affairs for the Superintendency of Manitoba proceeds to make 
     <lb/>
     the payments in Treaties One and Two, he should be authorized to pay the 
     <lb/>
     head men. It will be difficult to explain why the difference is made, and it 
     <lb/>
     will secure in every hand, men who will feel that they are officers of the 
     <lb/>
     Crown and remunerated as such. I returned to Fort Garry on the 23rd 
     <lb/>
     inst., encountering on the way a very severe thunder storm, which com<lb break="no"/>pelled me to take advantage of the very acceptable shelter of the kindly 
     <lb/>
     proffered residence of the Hon. Mr. Breland, at White Horse Plains, 
     <lb/>
     instead of a tent on the thoroughly-drenched prairie. I congratulate you 
     <lb/>
     that with the successful issue of this negotiation is closed, in Treaties One 
     <lb/>
     and Two, the vexed question of the open promises. I forward by this 
     <lb/>
     mail a copy of the agreement I have above alluded to, retaining the original 
     <lb/>
     for the present, and will be pleased to hear of its speedy approval by the 
     <lb/>
     Privy Council. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">I have the honor to be, etc., 
     <lb/>
           
     <persName ref="pers:MORR1">ALEXANDER MORRIS</persName>, 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut.-Governor</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

    </div>     </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>