<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="Morris_Chapter_08"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreatyNeg">Treaty Negotiations</name>, <date from="1875-09" to="1876-09">September 1875 to September 1876</date>, Between Canada and First Nations of Manitoba and the Northwest Territories.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <author>Alexander Morris</author>.
          
         
          <title>The Treaties of Canada with the Indians of Manitoba and the North-West Territories Including the Negotiations on Which They Are Based, and Other Information Relating Thereto.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1880"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>: <publisher>Willing &amp; Williamson</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="167"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_143.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_144.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_145.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_146.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_147.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_148.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_149.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_150.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_151.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_152.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_153.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_154.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_155.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_156.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_157.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_158.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_159.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_160.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_161.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_162.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_163.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_164.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_165.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_166.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_167.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-04-18">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-04-18">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_143">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_143.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_144">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_144.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_145">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_145.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_146">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_146.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_147">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_147.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_148">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_148.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_149">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_149.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_150">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_150.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_151">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_151.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_152">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_152.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_153">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_153.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_154">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_154.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_155">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_155.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_156">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_156.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_157">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_157.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_158">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_158.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_159">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_159.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_160">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_160.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_161">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_161.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_162">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_162.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_163">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_163.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_164">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_164.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_165">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_165.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_166">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_166.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_167">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_167.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="143"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_143.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">143</fw> 
     
<div type="chapter">  
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CHAPTER VIII. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     THE WINNIPEG TREATY, NUMBER FIVE. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     THIS treaty, covers an area of approximately about 100,000 
     <lb/>
     square miles. The region is inhabited by Chippewas and 
     <lb/>
     Swampy Crees. The necessity for it had become urgent. The 
     <lb/>
     lake is a large and valuable sheet of water, being some three 
     <lb/>
     hundred miles long. The Red River flows into it and the 
     <lb/>
     Nelson River flows from it into Hudson's Bay. Steam navi<lb break="no"/>gation had been successfully established by the Hudson's Bay 
     <lb/>
     Company on Lake Winnipeg. A tramway of five miles in 
     <lb/>
     length was being built by them to avoid the Grand Rapids and 
     <lb/>
     connect that navigation with steamers on the River Saskatche<lb break="no"/>wan. On the west side of the lake, a settlement of Icelandic 
     <lb/>
     immigrants had been founded, and some other localities were 
     <lb/>
     admirably adapted for settlement. Moreover, until the con<lb break="no"/>struction of the Pacific Railway west of the city of Winnipeg, 
     <lb/>
     the lake and Saskatchewan River are destined to become the 
     <lb/>
     principal thoroughfare of communication between Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     and the fertile prairies in the west. A band of Indians resid<lb break="no"/>ing at Norway House, who had supported themselves by 
     <lb/>
     serving the Hudson's Bay Company as boatmen on the route 
     <lb/>
     from Lake Winnipeg to the Hudson Bay, by way of the Nel<lb break="no"/>son River, but whose occupation was gone, owing to supplies 
     <lb/>
     being brought in by way of the Red River, desired to migrate 
     <lb/>
     to the western shore of Lake Winnipeg, and support themselves 
     <lb/>
     there by farming. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>For these and other reasons, the Minister of the Interior 
     <lb/>reported " that it was essential that the Indian title to all the 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="144"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_144.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="num">144</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

     territory in the vicinity of the lake should be extinguished so 
     <lb/>
     that settlers and traders might have undisturbed access to its 
     <lb/>
     waters, shores, islands, inlets and tributary streams." The mouth 
     <lb/>
     of the Saskatchewan River especially seemed to be of impor<lb break="no"/>tance, as presenting an eligible site for a future town. For 
     <lb/>these reasons the Privy Council of Canada, in the year 1875, 
     <lb/>appointed Lieut.-Gov. Morris, and the Hon. James McKay, to 
     <lb/>treat with these Indians. It may be here stated that this 
     <lb/>remarkable man, the son of an Orkneyman by an Indian 
     <lb/>mother, has recently died at a comparatively early age. Origi<lb break="no"/>nally in the service of the Hudson's Bay Company, he became 
     <lb/>a trader on his own account. Thoroughly understanding the 
     <lb/>Indian character, he possessed large influence over the Indian 
     <lb/>tribes, which he always used for the benefit and the advantage . 
     <lb/>of the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The Hudson's Bay Company, to resume this narrative, kindly 
     <lb/>
     placed their propeller steamer, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Colville</hi>, at the service of 
     <lb/>
     the Commissioners, and the Board in London, in view of the 
     <lb/>
     public service rendered by its use by the Commissioners, even<lb break="no"/>tually declined to make any charge for its employment. A 
     <lb/>
     full report of the voyage of the Commissioners, and of the re<lb break="no"/>sults of their mission, will be found in the despatch of the 
     <lb/>
     Lieutenant-Governor, which will be found at the end of this 
     <lb/>
     chapter. Suflice it to say, that the Commissioners proceeded 
     <lb/>
     first to Berens River, on the east side of the lake, and made a 
     <lb/>
     treaty with the Indians of that side of the lake, thence they 
     <lb/>
     sailed to the head of Lake Winnipeg, descended the Nelson 
     <lb/>
     River to Norway House, where no steamer had ever before 
     <lb/>
     been, and concluded a treaty with the Indians there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     They also promised the Indians to give those of them who 
     <lb/>
     chose to remove, a reserve on the west side of Lake Winnipeg, 
     <lb/>at Fisher's River, about forty miles from the Icelandic settlement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     A considerable number of families have since removed there, 
     <lb/>
     and have formed a very promising settlement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     From Nelson River the Commissioners proceeded to the 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="145"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_145.jpg"/>
         
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">145</fw> 
    

     mouth of the Great Saskatchewan River, and met the Indians 
     <lb/>
     who live there. Their houses were built at the foot of the 
     <lb/>
     Grand Rapids, and in the immediate vicinity of the Hudson's 
     <lb/>
     Bay, Tramway, some seven miles from the mouth of the river. 
     <lb/>
     The river is here deep to the very shore, so that the steamer 
     <lb/>
     ran long aside the bank, and was moored by ropes attached to 
     <lb/>
     the Chief's house. The Commissioners met the Indians and 
     <lb/>
     informed them of the desire of the Government to control the 
     <lb/>
     land where they had settled, and to give them a reserve, in<lb break="no"/>stead, on the opposite side of the river. They said, they would 
     <lb/>
     surrender the locality in question, and go to the south side of the 
     <lb/>
     river, if a small sum was given them, to aid them in removing 
     <lb/>
     their houses or building others. To this the Commissioners 
     <lb/>
     willingly acceded, and promised that the next year a sum of 
     <lb/>
     five hundred dollars would be paid them for that purpose. 
     <lb/>
     The treaty was then signed, the Commissioners having extended 
     <lb/>
     the boundaries of the treaty limits, so as to include the Swampy 
     <lb/>
     Cree Indians at the Pas or Wahpahpuha, a settlement on the 
     <lb/>
     Saskatchewan River, and recommended that Commissioners 
     <lb/>
     should be sent in the ensuing summer to complete the work. 
     <lb/>
     The Commissioners then returned to Winnipeg, after a voy<lb break="no"/>age, on and around the lake, of about one thousand miles. 
     <lb/>
     The terms of the treaty were identical with those of Treaties 
     <lb/>
     Numbers Three and Four, except that a smaller quantity of 
     <lb/>
     land was granted to each family, being one hundred and sixty, 
     <lb/>
     or in some cases one hundred acres to each family of five, while 
     <lb/>
     under Treaties Numbers Three and Four the quantity of land 
     <lb/>
     allowed was six hundred and forty acres to each such family. 
     <lb/>
     The gratuity paid each Indian in recognition of the treaty was 
     <lb/>
     also five dollars per head, instead of twelve dollars the cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances under which the treaty was made being different. 
     <lb/>
     The area covered by these treaties was approximately about 
     <lb/>
     100,000 square miles and has been described as lying north of 
     <lb/>
     the territory covered by Treaties Numbers Two and Three, ex<lb break="no"/>tending west to Cumberland House (on the Saskatchewan 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="146"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_146.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="num">146</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

     River) and including the country east and west of Lake Winni<lb break="no"/>peg, and of Nelson River- as far north as Split Lake. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In 1876, Lieut.-Gov. Morris, in accordance with his sugges<lb break="no"/>tions to that effect, was requested by the Minister of the 
     <lb/>
     Interior, to take steps for completing the treaty, and. entrusted 
     <lb/>
     the duty to the Hon. Thomas Howard, and J. Lestock Reid, 
     <lb/>
     Esq., Domninion Land Surveyor He gave them formal in<lb break="no"/>structions, and directed them to meet the Indians together at 
     <lb/>
     Dog Head Point, on the lake, to treat with the Island Indians 
     <lb/>
     there and thence to proceed to Berens River to meet the Indians 
     <lb/>
     of the rapids of that river who had not been able to be present 
     <lb/>
     the previous year, and thereafter directed Mr. Howard to pro<lb break="no"/>ceed to the mouth of the Saskatchewan and pay the Indians the 
     <lb/>
     five hundred dollars for removal of the houses, and thence to go 
     <lb/>
     up the Saskatchewan to the Pas and deal with the Indians there, 
     <lb/>
     while Mr. Reid was to proceed from Berens River to Norway 
     <lb/>
     House, and arrange with the Indians for the removal of such 
     <lb/>
     of them as desired it, to Fisher's River, on Lake Winnipeg. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     These gentlemen accordingly in July, 1876, proceeded in 
     <lb/>
     York boats (large sail boats) to their respective destinations, 
     <lb/>
     and were very successful in accomplishing the work confided 
     <lb/>
     to them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I now append the official despatch of Lieut.-Gov. Morris, 
     <lb/>
     dated 11th October, 1875, giving an account of the making of 
     <lb/>
     the treaty and of the journey, and his despatch of the 17th 
     <lb/>
     November, 1876, relating to the completion of the treaty, to<lb break="no"/>gether with extracts from the reports of Messrs. Howard and 
     <lb/>
     Reid. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     FORT GARRY, <hi rendition="simple:italic">October 11th, 1875</hi>. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>

            <p>To THE HONORABLE THE MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Sir—I have the honor to inform you, that under authority of the Com<lb break="no"/>mission of the Privy Council to that effect, I proceeded to Lake Winnipeg 
     <lb/>
     for the purpose of making a treaty with the Saulteaux and Swampy Cree 
     <lb/>
     Indians, in company with my associate, the Hon. James McKay,leaving Fort 
     <lb/>
     Garry for Chief Prince's Landing on the Red River, on the 17th September 
     <lb/>
     last, in order to embark on the Hudson's Bay Company's new propeller, the 
     <lb/>
        
            <pb n="147"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_147.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">147</fw> 
     

     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Colville</hi>, which Chief Commissioner Graham had kindly placed at our dis<lb break="no"/>posal on advantageous terms. We selected this mode of conveyance, as 
     <lb/>
     travelling and conveyance of provisions in York boats would, at the ad<lb break="no"/>vanced period of the season, have occupied at least eight weeks, if at all 
     <lb/>
     practicable. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The steamer left the landing at five o'clock on the 18th September, but 
     <lb/>
     owing to the prevalence of a gale of northerly wind was compelled to be 
     <lb/>
     anchored at the three channels of the Red River, inside of the bar which 
     <lb/>
     obstructs the entrance of the lake. The wind continued during the 18th 
     <lb/>
     and 19th, but on the afternoon of the latter day, Captain Hackland, a sailor 
     <lb/>
     of much practical experience on the Northern Seas, decided to risk going 
     <lb/>
     out, as the water on the bar was running down so fast that he feared that 
     <lb/>
     the steamer would be unable to cross over the bar. I may remark that 
     <lb/>
     the wind causes the waters of the lake to ebb and flow into the river with 
     <lb/>
     great rapidity, and that the bar is so serious an obstruction to an important 
     <lb/>
     navigation, that it ought to be examined with a view to ascertain the cost 
     <lb/>
     and practicability of its removal. Leaving our anchorage, We crossed the 
     <lb/>
     bar at three in the afternoon with difficulty, and proceeded on our voyage ; 
     <lb/>
     anchored opposite the mouth of the Berens River on Monday, the 20th, at 
     <lb/>
     nine a.m., to await the arrival of a pilot, as no steamer had ever before 
     <lb/>
     entered the river. Under the pilotage of a Chief and a Councillor, we 
     <lb/>
     reached Berens River Post, the Indians greeting us with volleys of firearms, 
     <lb/>
     and at once summoned the Indians to meet us in the Wesleyan Mission 
     <lb/>
     School House, which the Rev. Mr. Young kindly placed at our disposal. 
     <lb/>
     We met the Indians at four o'clock, and explained the object of our visit. 
     <lb/>
     The question of reserves was one of some difficulty, but eventually this 
     <lb/>
     was arranged, and the Indians agreed to accept our offer, and the indenture 
     <lb/>
     of treaty was signed by the Chiefs and head men about eleven p.m. The 
     <lb/>
     payment of the present of five dollars per head, provided by the treaty, was 
     <lb/>
     immediately commenced by Mr. McKay and the Hon. Thomas Howard, 
     <lb/>
     who accompanied me as Secretary and Pay Master, and was continued 
     <lb/>
     until one a.m., when the payment was concluded. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The steamer left next day, the 21st, for Norway House, but the captain 
     <lb/>
     was obliged to anchor at George's Island in the evening, owing to the stormy 
     <lb/>
     weather. The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Colville</hi> remained at anchor all the next day, the 22nd, but 
     <lb/>
     left at midnight for Nelson River. We sighted the Mossy and Montreal 
     <lb/>
     points, at the mouth of that river, about nine a.m. on the 23rd, and arrived 
     <lb/>
     at the old or abandoned Norway House at eleven o'clock, under the guid<lb break="no"/>ance of Roderick Ross, Esquire, of the Hudson's Bay Company's Service, at 
     <lb/>
     Norway House, who had been engaged for some days in examining the 
     <lb/>
     channel, in anticipation of our visit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Nelson River expands into Play Green Lake, a large stream of water 
     <lb/>
     studded with islands, presenting a remarkable resemblance to the Thous<lb break="no"/>and Islands of the St. Lawrence River. The distance from the mouth of 
     <lb/>
     the river to Norway House is twenty miles. We arrived at Norway House 
  
            <pb n="148"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_148.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="num">148</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    

     at three o'clock and were welcomed there by the Indians, who fired a 
     <lb/>
     salute.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the 24th we met the Indians in a large store-house of the Hudson's Bay 
     <lb/>
     Company, and asked them to present their Chiefs and head men. We 
     <lb/>
     found that there were two distinct bands of Indians, the Christian Indians 
     <lb/>
     of Norway House, and the Wood or Pagan Indians of Cross Lake. Each 
     <lb/>
     elected their Chiefs by popular vote in a most business-like manner, and 
     <lb/>
     the Chiefs, after consulting the bands, selected the head men. We then 
     <lb/>
     accepted the Chiefs, and I made an explanation of the object of our visit in 
     <lb/>
     English, and the Hon. James McKay in the Indian dialect. We severed the 
     <lb/>
     questions of terms and reserves, postponing the latter till we had disposed 
     <lb/>
     of the former. The Indians gratefully accepted of the offered terms, and 
     <lb/>
     we adjourned the conference to enable them to consult as to reserves. On 
     <lb/>
     re-assembling, the Christian Chief stated that as they could no longer count 
     <lb/>
     on employment in boating for the Hudson's Bay Company, owing to the 
     <lb/>
     introduction of steam navigation, he and a portion of his band wished to 
     <lb/>
     migrate to Lake Winnipeg, where they could obtain a livelihood by farm<lb break="no"/>ing and fishing. We explained why we could not grant them a reserve for 
     <lb/>
     that purpose at the Grassy Narrows as they wished, owing to the proposed 
     <lb/>
     Icelandic settlement there, but offered to allot them a reserve at Fisher 
     <lb/>
     River, about forty miles north of the Narrows, and this they accepted. It 
     <lb/>
     is supposed that some eighty or ninety families will remove there in spring, 
     <lb/>
     and it was arranged that those who remain, instead of receiving a reserve, 
     <lb/>
     should retain their present houses and gardens. The Chief of the Pagan 
     <lb/>
     band, who has, however, recently been baptized, stated that the Wood 
     <lb/>
     Indians wished to remain at Cross Lake, and we agreed that a reserve 
     <lb/>
     should be allotted them there. The treaty was then signed and the medals 
     <lb/>
     and uniforms presented. The Chiefs, on behalf of their people, thanked 
     <lb/>
     Her Majesty and her officers for their kindness to the Indian people, which 
     <lb/>
     I suitably acknowledged, and the payment of the presents was commenced 
     <lb/>
     by Messrs. McKay and Howard, and completed on the 15th. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We left that day at half-past three amidst cheering by the Indians and a 
     <lb/>
     salute of fire-arms, and came to anchor in Play Green Lake, at Kettle 
     <lb/>
     Island, at half-past five. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The steamer left Kettle Island next moming at six o'clock for the Grand 
     <lb/>
     Rapids of the Saskatchewan, which we reached at four o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The original post of the Hudson's Bay Company, at the mouth of the 
     <lb/>
     river, has been abandoned, and a new one established on their reserve, some 
     <lb/>
     six miles higher up the river, at the head of the portage, which the river 
     <lb/>
     steamer descends to. The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Colville</hi>, at our request ran up to the Chief's 
     <lb/>
     house, situated on the shore of a deep bay, and was moored and gangways 
     <lb/>
     laid out to the shore. We found an Indian village on the north side, and 
     <lb/>
     also the Chief's house, which was built on the only spot where good and in<lb break="no"/>expensive wharfage can be had, and ascertained afterwards that the Indians 
     <lb/>
     claimed the whole north shore for a reserve. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="149"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_149.jpg"/>
       

     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">149</fw> 
     

   
            <p>
     On the 27th we met the Indians near the Chief's house in the open air, at 
     <lb/>
     a spot where a large fire had been lighted by them, as the weather was cold. 
     <lb/>
     We took a similar course as at Norway House in severing the question of 
     <lb/>
     terms of the treaty and reserves, and with like satisfactory results. After a 
     <lb/>
     lengthy discussion the Indians agreed to accept the terms, and we then 
     <lb/>
     entered upon the difficult question of the reserves. They complained of the 
     <lb/>
     Hudson's Bay Campany's reserve, and wished to have the land covered by 
     <lb/>
     it, but we explained whatever had been promised the Company would be 
     <lb/>
     given just as promises made to them would be kept. They said the Com<lb break="no"/>pany's reserve should be at the abandoned post at the mouth of the river, 
     <lb/>
     and not at the end of the portage. We informed them that we would inquire 
     <lb/>
     as to this. They then claimed a reserve on both sides of the river of large 
     <lb/>
     extent, and extending up to the head of the Grand Rapids, but this we 
     <lb/>
     declined to accede to. Eventually, as the locality they had hitherto occu<lb break="no"/>pied is so important a point, controlling as it does the means of communi<lb break="no"/>cation between the mouth of the river, and the head of the rapids, and 
     <lb/>
     where a " train-way " will no doubt ere long require to be constructed, pre<lb break="no"/>senting also deep-water navigation and excellent wharfage, and evidently 
     <lb/>
     being moreover the site where a town will spring up, we offered them 
     <lb/>
     reserve on the south side of the river. They objected, that they had their 
     <lb/>
     houses and gardens on the north side of the river, but said that as the 
     <lb/>
     Queen's Government were treating them so kindly, that they would go to 
     <lb/>
     south side of the river, if a small sum was given them to assist in removing 
     <lb/>
     their houses, or building others, and this as will be seen by the terms of the 
     <lb/>
     treaty, we agreed to do, believing it to be alike in the interests of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to have the control of so important a point as the mouth of the 
     <lb/>
     great internal river of the Saskatchewan, and yet only just to the Indians, 
     <lb/>
     who were making what was to them so large a concession to the wishes of 
     <lb/>
     the Commissioners. On our agreeing to the proposal, the treaty was cheer<lb break="no"/>fully signed by the Chief and head men, and the payment of the present was 
     <lb/>
     made to them, together with a distribution of some provisions. I enclose a 
     <lb/>
     tracing of the mouth of the river, copied from a sketch thereof kindly made 
     <lb/>
     for me by Mr. Ross, which will enable you to understand the actual 
     <lb/>
     position of the locality in question, and the better appreciate our reasons 
     <lb/>
     for our action in the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The steamer left the Grand Rapids in the afternoon of the 27th, and the 
     <lb/>
     captain took his course for the mouth of the Red. River, but anchored, as 
     <lb/>
     the night became very dark, between George's Island and Swampy Island. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the 28th, resuming our course at half-past five a.m., we sighted Berens 
     <lb/>
     River Mission House at eight o'clock, and passed into the channel between 
     <lb/>
     Black Bear Island and Dog Head or Wapang Point, at 12.30 ; then observ<lb break="no"/>ing a number of Indians on the shore making signals to us by firing guns, 
     <lb/>
     we requested the captain to approach the shore. The water being very deep 
     <lb/>
     the steamer went close inshore and anchored —the Indians coming off to us 
     <lb/>
     in their canoes. We found them to be headed by Thickfoot, a principal 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="150"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_150.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="num">150</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

     Indian of the band inhabiting the islands, and some of those and the Jack 
     <lb/>
     Head band of the West Shore, and explained to them the object of our visit. 
     <lb/>
     They told us they had heard of it, and had been waiting to see us. Thickfoot 
     <lb/>
     said the Island Indians at Big Island, Black Island, Wapang and the other 
     <lb/>
     islands in the vicinity had no chief ; that they numbered one hundred and 
     <lb/>
     twenty-eight, and those at Jack-Fish Head sixty. Thickfoot said he had 
     <lb/>
     cattle and would like to have a place assigned to his people on the main 
     <lb/>
     shore, where they could live by farming and fishing. We suggested Fisher 
     <lb/>
     River to them, which they approved of. Eventually we decided on paying 
     <lb/>
     these Indians—took Thickfoot's adhesion to the treaty, of which I enclose a 
     <lb/>
     copy, and authorized him to notify the Indians to meet at the Dog Head 
     <lb/>
     Point next summer, at a time to be intimated to them, and to request them 
     <lb/>
     in the mean time to select a Chief and Councillors. Thickfoot expressed 
     <lb/>
     gratitude for the kindness of the Government, and his belief that Indians 
     <lb/>
     of the various Islands and of Jack Head Point would cheerfully accept the 
     <lb/>
     Queen's benevolence and settle on a reserve. After paying this party, and 
     <lb/>
     distributing a small quantity of provisions among them, we resumed our 
     <lb/>
     voyage, and, owing to the character of the navigation, again came to anchor 
     <lb/>
     in George's Channel at seven o'clock, p.m. On the 29th, we left our an<lb break="no"/>chorage at five o'clock a.m., and entered the mouth of the Red River at 
     <lb/>
     twelve o'clock, crossing the bar without difficulty, as the weather was calm. 
     <lb/>
     We arrived at the Stone Fort at three o'clock in the afternoon, but had to 
     <lb/>
     remain there till next day, awaiting the arrival of conveyances from Winni<lb break="no"/>peg. Mr. McKay and I left the Stone Fort on the 30th at seven a.m. leav<lb break="no"/>ing our baggage and a portion of the provisions which had not been used to 
     <lb/>
     be forwarded by the steamer <hi rendition="simple:italic">Swallow</hi>, and reached Fort Garry at ten o'clock, 
     <lb/>
     thus terminating a journey of over one thousand miles, and having satisfac<lb break="no"/>torily closed a treaty with the Saulteaux and Swampy Crees, which will 
     <lb/>
     prove of much importance in view of the probable rapid settlement of the 
     <lb/>
     west coast of Lake Winnipeg. The journey, moreover, is of interest, as 
     <lb/>
     having been the first occasion on which a steam vessel entered the waters of 
     <lb/>
     Berens River and of the Nelson River, the waters of which river fall into 
     <lb/>
     the Hudson's Bay, and as having demonstrated the practicability of direct 
     <lb/>
     steam navigation through a distance of three hundred and sixty miles from 
     <lb/>
     the city of Winnipeg to Norway House. I may mention here that the pre<lb break="no"/>valence of timber suitable for fuel and building purposes, of lime and sand<lb break="no"/>stone, of much good soil, and natural hay lands on the west shore of the 
     <lb/>
     lake, together with the great abundance of white fish, sturgeon and other 
     <lb/>
     fish in the lake, will ensure, ere long, a large settlement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The east coast is much inferior to the west coast, as far as I could learn, 
     <lb/>
     but appeared to be thickly wooded, and it is understood that indications of 
     <lb/>
     minerals have been found in several places. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I now beg to call your attention to the boundaries of the treaty, which, 
     <lb/>
     you will observe, vary somewhat from those suggested in your memorandum 
     <lb/>
     to the Privy Council. The Commissioners adopted as the southern bound<lb break="no"/><pb n="151"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_151.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">151</fw>ary of the treaty limits, the northern boundary of Treaties Numbers 
     <lb/>
     Two and Three. They included in the limits all the territory to which' the 
     <lb/>
     Indians ceding, claimed hunting and other rights, but they fixed the western 
     <lb/>
     boundary as defined in the treaty, for the following reasons : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1st. The extension of the boundary carries the treaty to the western limit 
     <lb/>
     of the lands claimed by the Saulteaux aud Swampy Cree Tribes of Indians, 
     <lb/>
     and creates an eastern base for the treaties to be made with the Plain Crees 
     <lb/>
     next year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2nd. The Swampy Crees at the Pas, on the Saskatchewan, would other<lb break="no"/>wise have had to be included in the western treaties. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3rd. That the extension of the boundaries will add some six hundred to 
     <lb/>
     the number of Indians in the suggested limits, of whom three hundred at 
     <lb/>
     Wahpahhuha or the Pas on the Saskatchewan would have had to be treated 
     <lb/>
     with owing to the navigation of the Saskatchewan, in any event. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4th. The inclusion of the Norway House Indians in the treaty, and the 
     <lb/>
     surrender of their rights, involved a larger area of territory. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5th. That a number of the Norway House Indians came from Moose Lake 
     <lb/>
     and the Cumberland region, and possessed rights there which have been in<lb break="no"/>cluded in the boundaries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6th. Unless the boundaries had been properly defined, in conformity with 
     <lb/>
     known geographical points, a portion of the country lying between the 
     <lb/>
     territories formerly ceded and those comprised in Treaty Number Five, 
     <lb/>
     would have been left with the Indian title unextinguished. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     For these reasons, the Commissioners defined the boundaries as they are 
     <lb/>
     laid down in the treaty, and it will remain with the Government to send a 
     <lb/>
     Commissioner to the Pas to obtain the adhesion of the Indians there to the 
     <lb/>
     treaty next summer, or not as they shall decide, though the Commissioners 
     <lb/>
     strongly urge that step to be taken as a necessity. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I forward the original of the treaty to you by the Hon. Mr. Christie, and 
     <lb/>
     in order to the better understanding of the treaty area, I enclose a very 
     <lb/>
     valuable map copied from one made for me at my request on board of the 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Colville</hi>, by Roderick Ross, Esq., who accompanied me from Norway House 
     <lb/>
     to the Stone Fort, and to whom I was indebted for much valuable assistance 
     <lb/>
     and co-operation, as we were in fact to the Company's oflicers generally. 
     <lb/>
     This map is prepared from actual observation, and locates many places not 
     <lb/>
     indicated on any existing map, and covering as it does an area of over 
     <lb/>
     100,000 square miles, which, exclusive of the great waters, has been included 
     <lb/>
     in the treaty, possesses much value. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I enclcse herewith duplicates of the pay sheets, a statement of the cash 
     <lb/>
     expenditure, shewing the balance on hand of the credit which was given me 
     <lb/>
     for the purposes of the treaty, and statements of the distribution of the 
     <lb/>
     provisions and of the clothing, and medals, as given to the chiefs and head 
     <lb/>
     men. These statements will shew that every arrangement was made to 
     <lb/>
     secure the utmost economy in effecting the treaty, and yet to give satisfac<lb break="no"/>tion to the Indians concerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="152"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_152.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="num">152</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    
   
            <p>
     I mention here.that the Indians were uniformly informed that no back 
     <lb/>
     payments of the present would be made to those who did not attend the 
     <lb/>
     meetings with the Commissioners, but that next year those not present 
     <lb/>
     would receive payment with the others, if they presented themselves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have to express my sense of the services rendered to the Government by 
     <lb/>
     my associate the Hon. James McKay, and the Hon. Thomas Howard, who 
     <lb/>
     acted as Secretary and Pay Master to the Commissioners as well as of the 
     <lb/>
     many kind services we received from Captain Hackland, and the other offi<lb break="no"/>cers of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Colville</hi>, from the Wesleyan Missionaries, and from the officers of 
     <lb/>
     the Hudson's Bay Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I take this opportunity of suggesting that the supervision of Treaty Num<lb break="no"/>ber Five, and the carrying out of the treaty obligations with the Indians 
     <lb/>
     of the St. Peter's Band, and of those of Fort Alexander and the River 
     <lb/>
     Roseau and Broken Head, which fall into Lake Winnipeg, should be 
     <lb/>
     entrusted to alocal agent, stationed at the Stone Fort or in the vicinity 
     <lb/>
     of St. Peter's, and who would thence supervise the whole District. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In conclusion, I have only to express the hope that the action of the 
     <lb/>
     Commissioners, which in every respect was governed by a desire to promote 
     <lb/>
     the public interest, will receive the approval of the Privy Council, and be 
     <lb/>
     regarded by them as the satisfactory discharge of an onerous and responsible 
     <lb/>duty.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     
     I have the honor to be, Sir, 
     <lb/>
          
     Your obedient servant, 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MORR1">ALEXANDER MORRIS</persName>, 
     <lb/>
          <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut.-Gov. N. W. T.</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     GOVERNMENT HOUSE, 
     <lb/>
     FORT GARRY, <hi rendition="simple:italic">17th November, 1876</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     TO THE HONORABLE THE MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Sir,—I recommended in my despatch of the 7th June, that measures 
     <lb/>
     should be adopted to secure the adhesion of the Indians, who had not been 
     <lb/>
     met with when Treaty Number Five was concluded, and was requested by 
     <lb/>
     you to entrust the duty to Mr. Graham, of the Indian Department here, 
     <lb/>
     or to the Hon. Thomas Howard, Mr. Graham was unable to leave the 
     <lb/>
     office. I, therefore entrusted the matter to Mr. Howard and J. Lestock 
     <lb/>
     Reid, D.L.S. I gave these gentleman written instructions, a copy of which 
     <lb/>
     will be found appended to the report of Mr. Howard, in which I directed 
     <lb/>
     them to meet the Island Indians and those of Berens River together, and 
     <lb/>
     then to separate, Mr. Reid proceeding to Norway House and Mr. Howard 
     <lb/>
     to the Grand Rapids of the Saskatchewan and the Pas, this course being 
     <lb/>
     necessary to enable the work to be accomplished during the season. I have 
     <lb/>
     pleasure in informing you that these gentlemen discharged their mission 
     <lb/>
     most successfully and satisfactorily, as will be seen from the following 
     <lb/>
     reports, which I enclose, viz :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="153"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_153.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">153</fw> 
     

            <p>
     A. Joint report of Messrs. Howard and Reid as to the Island Indians of 
     <lb/>
     Lake Winnipeg and those of Berens River. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     B. Report of Mr. Howard as to the band at the Grand Rapids, and as to 
     <lb/>
     his negotiations with the Indians at the Pas. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     C. Report of Mr. Reid with regard to the Norway House Indians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     D. Report of Mr. Howard, submitting the accounts of the expenditure 
     <lb/>
     incurred in carrying out my instructions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. It will appear from these reports that the Commissioners obtained the 
     <lb/>
     assent of the scattered bands among the islands and shores of Lake Winni<lb break="no"/>peg, and had them united in a band with one Chief and his Councillors. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. That the Indians of the Grand Rapids of the Berens River accepted 
     <lb/>
     the treaty, being received as part of the band of Jacob Berens, and that 
     <lb/>
     the latter band wish their reserves to be allotted them and some hay lands 
     <lb/>
     assigned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. That the Norway House Indians contemplate removal to Fisher's 
     <lb/>
     River, on Lake Winnineg. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. That the Indians of Grand Rapids have removed, as they agreed to do 
     <lb/>
     last year, from the point where they had settled on the Saskatchewan, and 
     <lb/>
     which had been set apart as the site of a town. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. That the Indians of the Pas, Cumberland, and Moose Lake gave 
     <lb/>
     their adhesion to the treaty, and, subject to the approval of the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council, have agreed upon the localities for their reserves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6. That the bands at the Grand Rapids, the Pas, and Cumberland are in a 
     <lb/>
     sufficiently advanced position to be allowed the grant for their schools. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1 forward herewith the balance sheet of Mr. Howard for the receipts and 
     <lb/>
     disbursements connected with the completion of the treaty and the pay<lb break="no"/>ments, as also the various vouchers in support thereof. I placed the charge 
     <lb/>
     of the financial arrangements in the hands of Mr. Howard, on whom also 
     <lb/>
     fell the longest period of service in the work entrusted to the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioners. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I also forward by parcel post, registered, the original of the assents to the 
     <lb/>
     treaty of the various bands. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To prevent complications and misunderstandings, it would be desirable 
     <lb/>
     that many of the reserves should be surveyed without delay, and, from 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Reid's connection with the treaty, and his fitness for the work, I think 
     <lb/>
     that he would be a suitable person to be employed in the duty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would remark in conclusion, that I requested Mr. Provencher to obtain 
     <lb/>
     the assent to the treaty of the band at the mouth of the Black River, and that 
     <lb/>
     he informs me that he obtained their adhesion and has so reported to you. 
     <lb/>
     The having obtained the assent of the whole of the Indians within the region 
     <lb/>
     treated for so far, is a most satisfactory feature of the year's operations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     I have, &amp;c. , 
     <lb/>
       
     <persName ref="pers:MORR1">ALEXANDER MORRIS</persName>, 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut.-Governor</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <pb n="154"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_154.jpg"/>
     
     <fw type="num">154</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
  
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>A.</emph> 
   
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     WINNIPEG, <hi rendition="simple:italic">October 10th, 1876</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p> To the Hon. ALEXANDER Morris, <lb/>
                     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieutenant-Governor, Fort Garry</hi>. <lb/>
                  </p>
   
            <p>
     Sir,—Under instructions received from you, dated 14th July last, we were 
     <lb/>
     directed to proceed to the Dog Head Point and Berens River, on Lake Winni<lb break="no"/>peg, and there obtain the adhesion of certain Indians to the treaty that was 
     <lb/>
     made and concluded at Norway House last year, and we have now the honor 
     <lb/>
     to report . . . . . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With a fair wind and fine weather we reached the Narrows on Monday 
     <lb/>
     afternoon, the 24th, at half-past four. Mr. Howard called at the Hud<lb break="no"/>son's Bay Company's post to see about the provisions stored there, where he 
     <lb/>
     found Thickfoot and the Jack-Fish Head Indians encamped, about twenty- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     five families in all, and learned from them that they were desirous to meet 
     <lb/>
     and speak to us where they were, and not across the Narrows at the Dog 
     <lb/>
     Head ; but as the place of meeting was distinctly fixed, Mr. Howard 
     <lb/>
     informed them that they would have to move their camps. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Reid having, in the meantime, gone to the Dog Head Point, was 
     <lb/>
     received with a salute from the Indians there encamped, viz.: the Blood 
     <lb/>
     Vein River, Big Island and Sandy Bar bands, and, almost simultaneously 
     <lb/>
     with Mr. Howard's arrival there, the Indians belonging to Thickfoot and the 
     <lb/>
     Jack Fish Head arrived also. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We hardly had time to make our camp before being waited upon by a 
     <lb/>
     representative from all the bands except Thickfoot's, and they desired to 
     <lb/>
     know when we would be prepared to have a conference; and, having told 
     <lb/>
     them that the following day, the 25th, was the day appointed, and that we 
     <lb/>
     would meet them at eleven o'clock in the morning, we gave them some pro<lb break="no"/>visions and they withdrew. Thickfoot subsequently called upon us and 
     <lb/>
     stated that he was prepared at any time to meet us and sign the treaty, 
     <lb/>
     that he had learned that it was our intention to make only one Chief for all 
     <lb/>
     the Indians gathered there ; that he had felt when the paper was placed in 
     <lb/>
     his hands last year by the Governor, that he was making him the Chief ; 
     <lb/>
     that he had notified all the Indians that were there as he had agreed, and 
     <lb/>
     that they had threatened him with violence for saying he was to be Chief, 
     <lb/>
     and that he was afraid now to join them in any way, and that he and his 
     <lb/>
     band wished to be spoken to by themselves. Upon hearing this, we informed 
     <lb/>
     him that he need not be afraid of violence, that the paper the Governor 
     <lb/>
     gave him merely stated that he was a principal Indian, and we would cer<lb break="no"/>tainly recognize him as such, and if the Indians desired him to be their Chief 
     <lb/>
     it would be a great pleasure to us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The following morning the Indians sent word by a representative from 
     <lb/>
     each hand, except Thickfoot's, that they desired another day to meet in 
     <lb/>
     council before having a conference; but, feeling they had sufficient time 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="155"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_155.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">155</fw> 
     

     already, yet not wishing to hurry them too much, we extended the hour of 
     <lb/>
     meeting to four o 'clock on the same day, which satisfied them, and when 
     <lb/>
     they promised to be ready. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     About three o 'clock we were informed that the Indians had gathered, so 
     <lb/>
     we at once proceeded to meet them. The place we had chosen for the con<lb break="no"/>ference was on a granite plateau, and at one end our crews had erected a 
     <lb/>
     covering with boughs; a more suitable spot for the meeting could not be 
     <lb/>
     found. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After inquiring if they had all gathered, and, being assurred that they 
     <lb/>
     had, we began to explain the object of our mission, but immediately saw 
     <lb/>
     that the bands were determined to be considered distinct and wished to be 
     <lb/>
     treated with separately, when we informed them that only one Chief would 
     <lb/>
     be allowed, and that before we could proceed any further we would require 
     <lb/>
     them all to meet together in council and there select one Chief and three 
     <lb/>
     Councillors, and be prepared to present them to us on the following day. 
     <lb/>
     This evidently gave great satisfaction to the Island Band, of which Ka-tuk- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     e-pin-ois was head man, but they all withdrew ; before doing so, agreeing to 
     <lb/>
     be ready the next day at noon to meet us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Before the hour appointed for the meeting the next day, another dele<lb break="no"/>gation came over and informed us that the Indians were not yet prepared, 
     <lb/>
     that they could not come to any decision as to who should be Chief, and 
     <lb/>
     again asked to have the hour of meeting extended to three o'clock, which 
     <lb/>
     we did upon the understanding that if they were not then prepared we 
     <lb/>
     would return and report the facts to you. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Shortly after, we noticed Thickfoot and his Indians sitting near our tents, 
     <lb/>
     and evidently taking no part in the selection of a Chief, so we called him 
     <lb/>
     over and found him still disinclined to join the other Indians. He stated   
     <lb/>
     that they would not have him as Chief, and that he would therefore remain 
     <lb/>
     away. We then explained that he could he head man of his band by 
     <lb/>
     being elected a Councillor to whoever would be appointed Chief, and at last 
     <lb/>
     prevailing upon him to go with his Indians to the Council tent, we requested 
     <lb/>
     the Rev. Mr. Cochrane to proceed to the Indian encampment and state to 
     <lb/>
     them that from each band other than the one from which the chief was 
     <lb/>
     chosen, a Councillor would have to be taken. By this means we saw our 
     <lb/>
     way to satisfy all the bands, and Mr. Cochrane having notified the Indians 
     <lb/>
     accordingly, we felt confident the choice of a chief would soon be made ; but 
     <lb/>
     in this we were disappointed, as a messenger shortly after arrived and said 
     <lb/>
     no choice could be made, as Ka-tuk-e-pin-ais would do nothing unless he 
     <lb/>
     was chosen Chief. 0n hearing this Mr. Cochrane decided to visit the 
     <lb/>
     Indians in Council, and, having done so, proposed to them that they should 
     <lb/>
     elect a Chief by ballot, and having got them all to agree to this proposition, 
     <lb/>
     they proceeded to the election. Several ballots had to be taken, and at last 
     <lb/>
     resulted in favor of the chief Indian of the Blood Vein River band, Sa-ha- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     oha-way-ass, and the Councillors elected were the head men from the Big 
     <lb/>
     Island, Doghead. and Jack Fish Head bands. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="156"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_156.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="num">156</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

   
            <p>
     At three o'clock p.m. , we were notified that the Indians had again gath<lb break="no"/>ered, when we proceeded to the place of meeting, and were presented 
     <lb/>
     to the Chief and two of his Councillors. Ka-tuk-e-pin-ais, the third Coun<lb break="no"/>cillor, coming forward, said his band did not want him to act as Councillor; 
     <lb/>
     that he had seen the Governor the other day, and had been told by him that 
     <lb/>
     he would be the Chief of the Island Indians. Whereupon we informed him 
     <lb/>
     that no such promise had been made by you, and that we could only recog<lb break="no"/>nize the choice of the majority. He then desired to withdraw from the 
     <lb/>
     negotiations, and wait until he saw you, before signing the treaty ; but as 
     <lb/>
     we had learned that out of the twenty-two families that were in his 
     <lb/>
     band, all, with one or two exceptions, had received the annuity since 1870, 
     <lb/>
     with the St. Peter's Band, we made them sit by themselves, and then 
     <lb/>
     explained that by receiving the annuity as a large number of them had done, 
     <lb/>
     they had really agreed to the treaty, and that we were there only to deal 
     <lb/>
     with those of the band that had at no time received money from the Queen. 
     <lb/>
     Ka-tuk-e-pin-ais then said that there were very few of his Indians that had 
     <lb/>
     not received money from the Queen, but that he never had ; that he was 
     <lb/>
     quite prepared to sign the treaty now, only some of his people did not want 
     <lb/>
     him to do so, unless we agreed to give them the Big Island for a reserve. 
     <lb/>
     This we at once refused, and at the same time told them that unless he and 
     <lb/>
     all his band agreed to the terms we offeredthem without further delay, they 
     <lb/>
     might return to their homes. Hearing this, they all withdrew, but soon 
     <lb/>
     returned, when Ka-tuk-e-pin-ais said one or two of his people did not want 
     <lb/>
     him to sign any treaty, but most of them did, and that he was going to do 
     <lb/>
     so. He then took his seat along with the Chiefs and other Councillors, and 
     <lb/>
     we proceeded to explain the terms of the treaty. When we came to the 
     <lb/>
     clause referring to the reserves, each band was anxious that the places where 
     <lb/>
     they are in the habit of living should be granted them as reserves, and the 
     <lb/>
     locations of the same mentioned in the treaty ; but as our instructions were 
     <lb/>
     positive on this point, we refused, but assured them that the names of the 
     <lb/>
     places they asked for, we would certainly forward with our report to you, 
     <lb/>
     and we stated that with the exception of the location asked for by the 
     <lb/>
     Sandy Bar Indians, we felt sure the Government would grant their request, 
     <lb/>
     and give them their reserves where they desired. The following were the 
     <lb/>
     localities mentioned :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     DOG HEAD BAND.—The point opposite the Dog Head. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     BLOOD VEIN RIVER BAND. —At mouth of Blood Vein River. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     BIG ISLAND BAND.—At mouth of Badthroat River. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     JACK-FISH HEAD BAND.—The north side of Jack Head Point, at the 
     <lb/>
     Lobstick, and the 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     SANDY BAR BAND.—White Mud River, west side of Lake Winnipeg. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It must be remembered that four bands out of the above named, viz. :— 
     <lb/>
     Big Island, Jack-Fish Head, Dog Head and Blood Vein River, are distinct 
     <lb/>
     bands, those at Sandy Bar really belonging to the St. Peter's Band of Indians. 
     <lb/>
     and that they have always lived at the diflirentmointe upon the lake from 
     <lb/>
        
            <pb n="157"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_157.jpg"/>
         
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">157</fw>
    
    
     which they take their names, and they therefore look upon these points as 
     <lb/>
    their homes. We would, therefore, beg to recommend that the request of 
     <lb/>of all, with the exception of the Sandy Bar Indians, be granted, although in 
     <lb/>doing so we are aware of the desire of the Government that Indians 
     <lb/>should not be encouraged to break up into small bands, yet we feel 
     <lb/>sure in this instance it would be impossible to get them all upon any one 
     <lb/>reserve. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     The adhesion we had signed on Wednesday evening, July 26th, and we 
     <lb/>
     then arranged to begin the payments of annuities the following morning at 
     <lb/>
     nine o'clock, which was done, and the payments completed by four o'clock 
     <lb/>
     on the same day. We then distributed the implements, ammunition, twine, 
     <lb/>
     and balance of provisions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As already stated, the Indians at Sandy Bar, were formerly paid with 
     <lb/>
     the St. Peter's band. They are now included in the limits of Treaty Five, 
     <lb/>
     and desire to receive their annuity with the Island band. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Having distributed the presents, we immediately moved our camp to an 
     <lb/>
     island about a quarter of a mile from the Point, and there remained until 
     <lb/>
     Saturday morning, the 29th, when, having a favourable wind, we set sail 
     <lb/>
     and arrived off the mouth of Berens River, and camped on Lobstick 
     <lb/>
     Island the following morning, Sunday, at half-past nine o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We remained there until Tuesday, and then moved our camp to the 
     <lb/>
     Methodist Mission. The next day we went over in one of our boats to the 
     <lb/>
     Hudson's Bay Company's post, where we met Mr. Flett, the officer in charge 
     <lb/>
     and received from him the provisions that had been previously forwarded 
     <lb/>
     and which he had in store, and then returned to our camp. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Flett informed us that the Indians from the Narrows of Berens 
     <lb/>
     River, he expected would arrive that evening, and on Thursday, visited us 
     <lb/>
     to say that they had arrived and were then holding a council. The same 
     <lb/>
     afternoon the Chief and Councillors called upon us and desired to know 
     <lb/>
     when we would be prepared to meet them, and though the 5th was the day 
     <lb/>
     appointed, we thought it advisable, as all the Indians were then gathered 
     <lb/>
     there, and were anxious to return to their homes, to appoint the following 
     <lb/>
     day, the 4th August. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The next morning the Indians came over from where they were encamped 
     <lb/>
     near the Hudson's Bay post, in York boats ; and when we learned that they 
     <lb/>
     were all in the school-house We proceeded there, and met, in addition to the 
     <lb/>
     Berens River band, about thirty Indians from the Grand Rapids of Berens 
     <lb/>
     River. We explained the object of our mission, and found the Indians from 
     <lb/>
     the Rapids most anxious to accept the Queen's bounty and benevolence, some 
     <lb/>
     of them had already accepted the annunity with the Lac Seule Indians we 
     <lb/>
     found, so we immediately told them that it was only to those that had not 
     <lb/>
     previously received money or presents from the Queen, that the first part of 
     <lb/>
     our mission extended, and with whom it was necessary we should first speak. 
     <lb/>
     The head man, Num-ak-ow-ah-nuk-wape, then said that he was fully prepared, 
     <lb/>
     on behalf of all his Indians, to accept the same terms as given to the Berens 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="158"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_158.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="num">158</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    

     River band, only he wanted his reserve where he then lived, at the'Grand 
     <lb/>
     Rapids ; upon which we told him that before we could speak further, we must 
     <lb/>
     be assured by the band that he was their head man, and this the band at once 
     <lb/>
     did. \Ve then thought it advisable to recommend that they should make the 
     <lb/>
     Chief of the Berens River band their Chief, and make their head man a Coun<lb break="no"/>cillor to him, and although our proposition was not at once received satis<lb break="no"/>factorily, we ultimately prevailed upon them to accept it, and the Chief was 
     <lb/>
     at once elected. By this means we saved the expenses necessarily incurred 
     <lb/>
     in maintaining one Chief and two Councillors. We then stated that we 
     <lb/>
     were prepared to grant them their reserve where they asked for it ; and 
     <lb/>
     having explained the treaty to them, clause by clause, and mentioned in the 
     <lb/>
     adhesion where the reserve should be, the adhesion was duly signed by the 
     <lb/>
     Chief and Councillors. The payment of the annuity was then gone on with 
     <lb/>
     and finished that afternoon at four o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We then distributed the implements, ammunition, twine and provisions. 
     <lb/>
     When we had finished, the Chief and Councillors came forward, and thanked 
     <lb/>
     us for all that had been done for them; they said they were well pleased 
     <lb/>
     with what they had received, and desired us to inform you of the fact, which 
     <lb/>
     we accordingly promised. They then returned in the same boats they had 
     <lb/>
     come over in : before leaving the bank, giving three cheers for the Queen 
     <lb/>
     and three for the Governor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are very much pleased to inform you that the best possible feeling 
     <lb/>
     appears to exist between the Indians in this region. They all appeared 
     <lb/>
     anxious to farm and settle down, and we heard that a number of houses 
     <lb/>
     had been built at Poplar River, and considerable clearing done there since 
     <lb/>
     the treaty was made with them last year ; the implements and tools we 
     <lb/>
     brought them were therefore most acceptable. As these bands live at a con<lb break="no"/>siderable distance from each other, we would recommend that an extra 
     <lb/>
     supply of tools he allowed them. We also feel satisfied that the animals 
     <lb/>
     promised by the treaty might be furnished, as we certainly consider them 
     <lb/>
     in a position to take care of the same. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As you directed, we informed them that their application for hay lands 
     <lb/>
     had been forwarded to the Government, and this gave them great satis<lb break="no"/>faction. The following morning, Saturday, August 5th, Mr. Reid left for 
     <lb/>
     Norway House, and during the afternoon of the same day, Mr. Howard 
     <lb/>
     sailed for the Stone Fort on the Red River.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Having obtained the adhesion of the Indians at the Dog Head, and at 
     <lb/>
     Berens River, our duties as Joint Commissioners under your instructions 
     <lb/>
     ceased.... 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We were fortunate enough to secure the services of the Rev. Henry 
     <lb/>
     Cochrane, who kindly acted as interpreter. Being in the Province on a 
     <lb/>
     visit from his mission at the Pas, and desirous of returning, 'Mr. Howard 
     <lb/>
     gave him a passage in his boat. and be rendered us the most valuable assist<lb break="no"/>ance throughout. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Having thus referred to the different matters connected with our mission 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="159"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_159.jpg"/>
         
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> 
   
            <fw type="num">159</fw>
            
     while acting together, and assuring you that our aim and desire was to 
     <lb/>
     fulfill it to your entire satisfaction, which we trust we have done, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     We have the honor to be, Sir,   
     <lb/>
     Your obedient servants, 
     <lb/>
        
     <persName ref="pers:HOWA2">THOS. HOWARD</persName>, 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:REID3">J. LESTOCK REID</persName>, 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioners..</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>


            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>B.</emph> 
     <lb/></p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p rendition="simple:right">
     Winnipeg, <hi rendition="simple:italic">October 10th, 1876</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     To THE HONORABLE ALEXANDER MORRIS, 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieutenant-Governor, Fort Garry</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     SIR,— I have the honor to inform you that in compliance with your 
     <lb/>
     instructions, a copy of which I hereunto annex, I proceeded, accompanied by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Reid, to the Dog Head and Berens River on Lake Winnipeg, and there 
     <lb/>
     successfully secured the adhesion of the Island and Grand Rapids of Berens 
     <lb/>
     River Bands of Indians to Treaty Number Five, and, having 'paid the 
     <lb/>
     annuities to the Berens River Indians, returned to the Stone Fort. As 
     <lb/>
     mentioned in the joint report submitted to you by Mr. Reid and myself, I 
     <lb/>
     had the greatest difficulty in procuring a boat to take me on my mission, 
     <lb/>
     and only through the kindness of Mr. Flett. of the Hudson's Bay Company, 
     <lb/>
     at the Stone Fort, was I able to obtain even the loan of one as far as Berens 
     <lb/>
     River, from where I had to return it. . . . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I left the Stone Fort for the Grand Rapids, on the morning of the 17th of 
     <lb/>
     August, and after a very fast, though rough and dangerous passage, reached 
     <lb/>
     the mouth of the Saskatchewan river, early on the morning of the 26th. I 
     <lb/>
     found, on entering the river, that the Indians were encamped near its 
     <lb/>
     mouth, on the south bank, where I landed, and arranged to meet them at 
     <lb/>
     noon that day. As the provisions were stored at the Hudson's Bay Company's 
     <lb/>
     post, about a mile and a half up the river, I decided to camp at the foot of 
     <lb/>
     the road leading across the four-mile Portage, and having done so, and in 
     <lb/>
     the meantime sent the provisions to the Indian camp, I returned there at 
     <lb/>
     the time agreed upon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The band having assembled, I stated to them the object of my mission— 
     <lb/>
     that I had been directed to pay them the annuity and deliver some of the 
     <lb/>
     tools and implements granted them by the treaty, and also to distribute 
     <lb/>
     amongst those that formerly had houses and gardens on the north bank of 
     <lb/>
     the river, and had moved to where they were then living, as stipulated in 
     <lb/>
     the treaty, the sum of five hundred dollars. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To my surprise, the Chief at once expressed his astonishment at my saying 
     <lb/>
     that the treaty had been made last year, and said he had only a talk then 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="160"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_160.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="num">160</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    

     with the Governor preliminary to making the treaty this year, and that they 
     <lb/>
     were only then prepared to be treated with. I explained to the band how 
     <lb/>
     I had been present myself when it was made, and that I would have it read 
     <lb/>
     to them. I accordingly requested Mr. Cochrane to do so, explaining it 
     <lb/>
     thoroughly; yet, it was only after a great deal of talking on their part, 
     <lb/>
     during which they made most unreasonable demands, and many explanations 
     <lb/>
     on my part, that the Indians were satisfied that a treaty had been made, 
     <lb/>
     when they requested me to go on with the payments; at the same time a 
     <lb/>
     number of them stated that they had been misled by one of the counsellors, 
     <lb/>
     Joseph Atkinson by name. I then paid the annuity, distributed the 
     <lb/>
     provisions, tools, implements, etc., and gave the Chief a copy of the treaty, 
     <lb/>
     and, arranging to meet them again on Monday, the 28th, I returned to my 
     <lb/>
     camp at midnight. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Monday, I met them as agreed, and at once began and made inquiries 
     <lb/>
     as to who had houses and gardens on the north bank and had moved their 
     <lb/>
     houses to the south bank, and I found that all those that had formerly lived 
     <lb/>
     on the north bank had removed from there. I noticed that great feeling 
     <lb/>
     existed amongst them all as to the division of the five hundred dollars 
     <lb/>
     granted. All the band congregated round me and the large majority 
     <lb/>
     desired that the amount should be divided equally between them all, and 
     <lb/>
     claimed that every one belonging to the band was entitled to participate in 
     <lb/>
     the division; so I thought it best to leave it to themselves to decide how the 
     <lb/>
     amount should be distributed, and they only succeeded in doing so after a 
     <lb/>
     great deal of talking, and, I regret to say, quarrelling; but they at last 
     <lb/>
     arranged it, and I was requested by the Chief and Councillors to divide it 
     <lb/>
     amongst the whole band in such proportions as I thought right, so I 
     <lb/>
     proceeded at once to what turned out to be a long and troublesome under<lb break="no"/>taking; but having as I considered made a fair and equitable distribution 
     <lb/>
     of the amount, I paid the same, had the document witnessed by the Chief 
     <lb/>
     and Councillors, and only got back to my camp again at midnight. As I 
     <lb/>
     before said, all the Indians had removed to the south bank of the river, but 
     <lb/>
     had made no preparations to build, and were merely living in tents. Close 
     <lb/>
     to the encampment, at the mouth of the river, the Church Missionary 
     <lb/>
     Society have put up a large building to answer the purposes of a church and 
     <lb/>
     school-house. Care must be taken and strict watch kept over this band. 
     <lb/>
     Living as they do on the bank of a navigable river, where people are 
     <lb/>
     constantly passing, they can give great trouble and annoyance, and, I am 
     <lb/>
     sorry to say, are inclined to do so. Several complaints were made to me 
     <lb/>
     while there, and I spoke to the Indians regarding them. They promised me 
     <lb/>
     to abide faithfully by the terms of the treaty henceforth and not give any 
     <lb/>
     further annoyance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     While occupied paying the Indians there, my crew were engaged in taking 
     <lb/>
     my boat and supplies across the Portage. They left the camp early on 
     <lb/>
     Monday morning, and with the assistance kindly rendered them by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Matheson, of the Hudson's Bay Company, succeeded in reaching the north end 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="161"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_161.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">161</fw> 
     

     of the Portage on Tuesday evening. That same afternoon I walked over 
     <lb/>
     the four-mile Portage and found there a number of buildings belonging to 
     <lb/>
     the Hudson's Bay Company. To this point the Saskatchewan River steamer 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Northcote</hi> descends and receives the supplies for the different posts belonging 
     <lb/>
     to the Company to the West and North-West. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Wednesday morning, the 30th, I left for the Pas. From the Grand 
     <lb/>
     Rapids to the Narrows, before entering Cedar Lake, a distance of eighteen 
     <lb/>
     or twenty miles, a continuous rapid extends, and it is only by tracking and 
     <lb/>
     poling simultaneously that you are at all able to ascend the river. The 
     <lb/>
     first day I made only nine miles on my way and camped at the Demi 
     <lb/>
     Charge, and it was late in the evening on the second day when I reached 
     <lb/>
     Cedar Lake. This lake is about thirty-five miles in length and is very 
     <lb/>
     shallow and dangerous in stormy weather. I was fortunate enough to have 
     <lb/>
     very calm weather, and, therefore, crossed it without any delay and entered 
     <lb/>
     the Saskatchewan again at the Che-ma-wa-win or "Seining place," early 
     <lb/>
     on Saturday morning, September 2nd. Noticing a large encampment of 
     <lb/>
     Indians there, I landed and found they were part of the Moose Lake band. 
     <lb/>
     They desired that I should treat with them where they were, and not bring 
     <lb/>
     them to the Pas, but upon my telling them that I could only treat with 
     <lb/>
     them at the appointed place of meeting, they readily assented to follow me 
     <lb/>
     up, and having given them some provisions to take them there, and secured 
     <lb/>
     the services of one of them to act as guide, I again started on my journey. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I was then three days and two nights ascending the river, and on Tues<lb break="no"/>day morning, the 5th September, the day appointed for me to meet the 
     <lb/>
     Indians, I arrived at the Pas or Devon Mission, on my way up having been 
     <lb/>
     passed by the Indians from the Che-ma-wa-win. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On entering the river after leaving Cedar Lake the whole aspect of the 
     <lb/>
     country changes, and from there to the Pas, and, I understand, for fully 
     <lb/>
     one hundred miles above it, nothing but marsh can be seen ; so much so 
     <lb/>
     that it was difficult along the bank of the river to find a spot dry enough to 
     <lb/>
     camp upon, and I was, consequently, obliged to eat and sleep in my boat. 
     <lb/>
     The dreariness of this voyage can hardly be realized, and it was with feelings 
     <lb/>
     of delight that I landed at the Mission at the Pas where the Rev. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Cochrane received me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Cochrane had accompanied me from the Stone Fort and had been in 
     <lb/>
     my boat up to the night before I arrived, when, meeting some Indians that 
     <lb/>
     were on the look-out for us, he returned with them in their canoe and 
     <lb/>
     reached his home shortly before I arrived. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Pas or Devon Mission is situated on the south bank of the Saskatche<lb break="no"/>wan, distant, I should say, one hundred and forty miles from Grand 
     <lb/>
     Rapids. The Church Missionary Society have a very nice church, school<lb break="no"/>house and parsonage there; and the Hudson's Bay Company one of their 
     <lb/>
     posts. There are also a large number of houses belonging to the Indians of 
     <lb/>
     the place; and on the other bank the firm of Kew, Stobart &amp; Co., have 
     <lb/>
     erected a store for trading purposes. There are also several dwelling-houses 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="162"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_162.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="num">162</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    

     on the north bank. Altogether, the appearance of the place, on my arrival, 
     <lb/>
     was most prepossessing. The banks were covered with Indians with their 
     <lb/>
     canoes. and immediately the boat rounded the point below the Mission and 
     <lb/>
     came in view a salute was fired, the like of which, I was subsequently told, 
     <lb/>
     had never been heard in the " Ratty Country." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Having landed at the Mission, Mr. Cochrane informed me that he had, as 
     <lb/>
     I requested, summoned the Indians to meet in the school-house at three 
     <lb/>
     o'clock that afternoon, and when the hour arrived I proceeded there and 
     <lb/>
     found upwards of five hundred Indians gathered. I stated the object of my 
     <lb/>
     mission to them, and was at once assured of their desire to accept of, and 
     <lb/>
     their gratitude for, the Queen's bounty and benevolence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I found that the Pas and Cumberland bands of Indians had acknowledged 
     <lb/>
     Chiefs, but that the Moose Lake band had none, owing to a division amongst 
     <lb/>
     them. It appeared that the Indians from the Che-ma-wa-win desired to be 
     <lb/>
     a distinct band and have their reserves where I had seen them at the 
     <lb/>
     entrance of the river from Cedar Lake; but noticing, on my way up, the 
     <lb/>
     unfitness of the locality for a reserve, and having learned that at Moose Lake, 
     <lb/>
     where part of the band desired to live, a most suitable locality could be had, 
     <lb/>
     I had decided before meeting them upon the course I should take, which 
     <lb/>
     was, not to encourage the division in the band, and allow only one Chief ; 
     <lb/>
     and this I did, and succeeded, without much trouble, in getting the band to 
     <lb/>
     unite. I then requested all the Indians to meet in council and select their 
     <lb/>
     Chief and head men, and be prepared the following morning to present them 
     <lb/>
     to me, when I would be ready to speak to them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The next morning at eleven o'clock I met them and found they had done 
     <lb/>
     as I requested, and having been presented to the Chiefs and Councillors I 
     <lb/>
     proceeded to explain the terms of the treaty that I desired to receive their 
     <lb/>
     adhesion to. The Chiefs immediately stated that they wanted to make a 
     <lb/>
     treaty of their own, and it was only after great difficulty that I could make 
     <lb/>
     them understand that in reality it was not a new treaty they were about to 
     <lb/>
     make. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     They had heard of the terms granted the Indians at Carlton, and this 
     <lb/>
     acted most prejudicially at one time against the successful carrying out of 
     <lb/>
     my mission ; but I at last made them understand the difference between 
     <lb/>
     their position and the Plain Indians, by pointing out that the land they 
     <lb/>
     would surrender would be useless to the Queen, while what the Plain Indians 
     <lb/>
     gave up would be of value to her for homes for her white children. They 
     <lb/>
     then agreed to accept the terms offered if I would agree to give them reserves 
     <lb/>
     where they desired; and to their demands I patiently listened, and having 
     <lb/>
     at last come to a satisfactory understanding I adjourned the meeting to the 
     <lb/>
     following day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Before proceeding further, I would draw your attention to the localities 
     <lb/>
     I granted for reserves, subject to the. approval of the Government, and beg 
     <lb/>
     to inform you that I made every inquiry as to the extent of farming land 
     <lb/>
     in each locality mentioned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="163"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_163.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">163</fw>
    
   
            <p>
     At the Narrows, at Moose Lake, there is considerable good land, and a 
     <lb/>
     suitable place for a reserve can be had for the Moose Lake band.  
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>For the Pas and Cumberland Indians I had to mention several localities. 
     <lb/>At the Pas all the land obtainable is now cultivated, and consists of a 
     <lb/>vegetable garden and one field attached to the Mission, and a few patches of 
     <lb/>potatoes here and there. A short distance from the river the marsh begins, 
     <lb/>and extends to the south for miles ; and the same thing occurs to the north. 
     <lb/>In fact, on both banks of the river at this point, and from the Che-ma-wa- 
     <lb break="yes"/>win up to it, one hundred and fifty acres of land fit for cultivation cannot 
     <lb/>be found ; and about Cumberland the country in every respect is similar. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The following day, Thursday the 7th, I met the Indians at three p.m., 
     <lb/>
     and had the adhesion read to them and signed. I then presented the medals 
     <lb/>
     and clothing to the Chiefs and Councillors, with which they were greatly 
     <lb/>
     pleased, and having congratulated them upon wearing the Queen's uniform, 
     <lb/>
     and having in return been heartily thanked by them for what had been 
     <lb/>
     done, I proceeded to pay them, and continued to do so up to seven o'clock, 
     <lb/>
     when the funds at my disposal being exhausted, I directed them to meet me 
     <lb/>
     again the following morning at nine o'clock, which they did, and I completed 
     <lb/>
     the payments the same evening at five o'clock. I then distributed the balance 
     <lb/>
     of provisions and the ammunition and twine. The implements and tools I 
     <lb/>
     had been unable to bring from Grand Rapids, my boat being very heavily 
     <lb/>
     laden ; but Mr. Belanger, of the Hudson's Bay Company, kindly promised to 
     <lb/>
     have them brought up free of charge in a boat that was going to the Grand 
     <lb/>
     Rapids in a few days ; I therefore gave the Chief of the Pas band an order 
     <lb/>
     for the chest of tools and the implements. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The following day, Saturday, having again seen all the Chiefs and Coun<lb break="no"/>cillors and received their thanks, and after many expressions of gratitude 
     <lb/>
     from the Indians gathered, I left the Pas at half-past two o'clock p.m., and 
     <lb/>
     with rowing and floating alternately during the afternoon and night, reached 
     <lb/>
     the Che-ma-wa-win on Sunday evening ; crossed Cedar Lake on Monday, 
     <lb/>
     and landed at the head of Grand Rapids on Tuesday morning. I then ran 
     <lb/>
     the rapids and hoisted the sail at the mouth of the river at two p.m., having 
     <lb/>
     called upon Mr. Matheson and seen the Chief of the Indians there on my 
     <lb/>
     way down. I then made all haste to return here, but, owing to contrary 
     <lb/>
     winds, only succeeded in reaching the Stone Fort on the 20th September, yet, 
     <lb/>
     having made a very quick trip, unprecedented in fact, and in carrying out 
     <lb/>
     the mission entrusted to me, travelled in an open boat, thirteen hundred miles. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would now inform you that three out of the four bands of Indians I met 
     <lb/>
     on the Saskatchewan, viz., the Grand Rapids, Pas and Cumberland, are in 
     <lb/>
     a position to receive at once from the Government the grant allowed for the 
     <lb/>
     maintenance of schools of instruction ; at the Grand Rapids a large school<lb break="no"/>house is by this time entirely completed ; and at the Pas and Cumberland, 
     <lb/>
     schools, under the charge of the Church Missionary Society, have been in 
     <lb/>
     existence some years. The Indians belonging to the bands I have named 
     <lb/>
     desired that the assistance promised should be given as soon as possible. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="164"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_164.jpg"/>
        
    <fw type="num">164</fw>  <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    
   
            <p>
     I would now mention the very valuable services rendered the Government 
     <lb/>
     by the Rev. Mr. Cochrane, who acted as interpreter at the Dog Head, 
     <lb/>
     Berens River; Grand Rapids and the Pas, and who was at all times ready 
     <lb/>
     to give his advice and assistance ; as well as by Mr. A. M. Muckle, who 
     <lb/>
     accompanied me and assisted in making the payments ; and by Mr. Nursey, 
     <lb/>
     who took charge of the boat with supplies for the Pas. To Mr. Matheson, 
     <lb/>
     of the Hudson's Bay Company, Grand Rapids, and Mr. Belanger, of Cumber<lb break="no"/>land House, I am deeply indebted, and take this opportunity of tendering 
     <lb/>
     these gentlemen my sincere thanks for the assistance rendered me and the 
     <lb/>
     many kindnesses I received from them. I enclose herewith the pay-sheet 
     <lb/>
     of the different bands I paid, a statement of the cash expenditure, and 
     <lb/>
     statements shewing quantities of provisions, implements, etc., received and 
     <lb/>
     how distributed, with a statement of clothing, medals, etc., given to the 
     <lb/>
     Chiefs and Councillors, and a report I received from Mr. Bedson. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And, trusting that the manner in which I have carried out the mission 
     <lb/>
     entrusted to my care, may meet with your approval, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     I have the honor to be, Sir, 
     <lb/>
      Your obedient servant, 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWA2">THOMAS HOWARD</persName>, 
     <lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner</hi>.<lb/>
            </p></quote>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
      FORT GARRY, <hi rendition="simple:italic">July 14th, 1876</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     TO THE HON. THOS. HOWARD AND J. LESTOCK REID, ESQ. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     DEAR SIRS, —Under authority from the Minister of the Interior, I have to 
     <lb/>
     request you to proceed to Lake Winnipeg for the purpose of—on behalf of 
     <lb/>
     the Privy Council of Canada— securing the adhesion to Treaty Number 
     <lb/>
     Five of the Indians who have not yet been dealt with, and to make the 
     <lb/>
     necessary payments to the others. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1st. You will, if possible, together proceed to or meet at the following 
     <lb/>
     places, being there on the days named, viz.: Dog-Head Point, 25th July, 
     <lb/>
     and Berens River on the 5th August. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2nd. Mr. Howard will then proceed to the mouth of the Saskatchewan, 
     <lb/>
     so as to reach there on the 25th of August, and then arrive at the Pas on the 
     <lb/>
     5th of September. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3rd. Mr. Reid will proceed from Berens River to Norway House, to 
     <lb/>
     arrive there on or before the 25th of August. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4th. You or either of you will secure the adhesion of the Island Indians 
     <lb/>
     to the treaty after the form annexed, and will request them to select a 
     <lb/>
     Chief and three Councillors, and will be authorized to promise them a reserve 
     <lb/>
     of one hundred and sixty acres to each family of five, or that proportion for 
     <lb/>
     larger or smaller families, to be selected for them by the person chosen for 
     <lb/>
     that end by the Privy Council with their approval. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="165"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_165.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">165</fw>
     

            <p>
     5th. You or either of you will obtain the adhesion of the Indians of the 
     <lb/>
     Grand Rapids of Berens River to the treaty according to the form annexed. 
     <lb/>
     You will ask them to select a Chief and three Councillors. A similar 
     <lb/>
     provision will be made as to a reserve, but if necessary you can fix the 
     <lb/>
     locality at the Sandy Narrows above the rapids on the Berens River, 
     <lb/>
     reserving free navigation and access to the shores to all Her Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     subjects. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6th. Mr. Reid will pay the Norway House and Cross Lake Indians, and 
     <lb/>
     will ascertain the intentions of the Norway House Indians as to the time of 
     <lb/>
     their removal to Fisher River, of which I am unadvised. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     7th. Mr. Howard will pay the Indians at the mouth of the Saskatchewan, 
     <lb/>
     and if the Indians have removed their houses, as agreed by the treaty, will 
     <lb/>
     pay them five hundred dollars, but if not and some have removed, will pay 
     <lb/>
     such their proportionate share of the five hundred dollars. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     8th. You will distribute the implements, tools, etc., sent among the 
     <lb/>
     Indians, as also the ammunition and twine. Cattle cannot be given till the 
     <lb/>
     Indians are sufficiently settled on the reserves to make it seem that they will 
     <lb/>
     be cared for. You will report any cases where you find this to be the case, 
     <lb/>
     for future action. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     9th. You will inform the Berens River Indians that their application for 
     <lb/>
     a hay reserve has been forwarded to the Privy Council by me, and that they 
     <lb/>
     will receive a reply hereafter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     10th. Mr. Howard will secure the adhesion of the Indians at the Pas to 
     <lb/>
     the treaty providing that reserves of one hundred and sixty acres to each 
     <lb/>
     family of five will be granted at places selected for them by an officer of the 
     <lb/>
     Privy Council, with their approval ; but it will probably be necessary to 
     <lb/>
     give them a reserve at the Pas where they reside, reserving carefully free 
     <lb/>
     navigation and access to the shores. As the extent of land there 
     <lb/>
     s very narrow, it may be desirable to indicate localities where 
     <lb/>
     farming reserves will be granted, subject to the approval of the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     11th. The Moose Lake Indians are a distinct band, and will probably 
     <lb/>
     desire the recognition of two separate Chiefs and the allotment of separate 
     <lb/>
     reserves to them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     12th. The Cumberland House Indians are another band, but very much 
     <lb/>
     scattered ; the question of a reserve will have to be considered, and, in con<lb break="no"/>nection with it, as in other cases, respect for actual, bona fide, substantial 
     <lb/>
     improvements, and for the rights of settlers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     13th. In all cases the places indicated for reserves to be subject to Her 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's approval in Council, and free navigation and access to the shores 
     <lb/>
     to be reserved. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     14th. In the case of new adhesions to the treaty, which are in fact new 
     <lb/>
     treaties, only five dollars is to be paid, but persons belonging to bands 
     <lb/>
     treated with last year are to receive last year's  payment, if then absent, if 
     <lb/>
     necessary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="166"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_166.jpg"/>
            
<fw type="num">166</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

            <p>
     15th. You will each take with you a suitable person, to be approved of 
     <lb/>
     by me, to assist you in the payment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="simple:right">I have the honor to be, 
     <lb/>Your obedient servant, 
     <lb/> <persName ref="pers:MORR1">ALEXANDER MORRIS</persName>, 
     <lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut.-Governor</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

<p rendition="simple:centre"><emph>C.</emph></p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     WINNIPEG, <hi rendition="simple:italic">October 14th. 1876</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     To THE HON. ALEXANDER Morris, 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut.-Governor</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir,—Referring to your letter of instructions under date of the 14th of 
     <lb/>
     July, relative to the payment of the Norway House and Cross Lake bands 
     <lb/>
     of Indians, I have the honor to submit the following report :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Having, in co-operation with the Hon. Thomas Howard, paid the Indians 
     <lb/>
     of Berens River and successfully secured the adhesion of the Island and 
     <lb/>
     Upper Berens River bands of Indians to Treaty Number Five, on the 
     <lb/>
     morning of Saturday, the 5th of August, I left for Norway House, which 
     <lb/>
     place, owing to stormy weather and strong head winds, I did not succeed in 
     <lb/>
     reaching until the morning of the 12th. On the way I was met by Indians 
     <lb/>
     proceeding to inspect their reserve at Fisher's River, who brought a letter 
     <lb/>
     from the Chiefs of Norway House and Cross Lake, stating that the Indians 
     <lb/>
     were all assembled, and requesting to be paid at the earliest possible date. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On reaching this place, Norway House, after having camp pitched at a 
     <lb/>
     short distance from the fort, I dispatched messengers to the several camps 
     <lb/>
     and villages, notifying the Indians of my arrival and desiring the Chiefs to 
     <lb/>
     meet me on the Monday morning following. On Sunday evening divine 
     <lb/>
     service was held within the fort by the Rev. Mr. Ruttan, Wesleyan 
     <lb/>
     missionary, at which a large number of Indians were present. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Monday morning, the Chiefs and most of the Indians of both bands 
     <lb/>
     having assembled at my camp, the Cross Lake band requested to be paid 
     <lb/>
     there, and the Norway House Chief asked that his people might be paid in 
     <lb/>
     the school-house in their village about two miles from the fort. On hearing 
     <lb/>
     that all the Indians that could come were assembled, I consented to pay them 
     <lb/>
     where they desired, and told the Cross Lake Chief to bring his people at 
     <lb/>
     noon to receive their gratuities, the payment of which was satisfactorily 
     <lb/>
     completed the same day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The next day I crossed over to the Indian village and paid the Norway 
     <lb/>
     House bands their annuities. . . . . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The following morning, Wednesday, August 16th, the Chiefs and Indians 
     <lb/>
     of the two bands having assembled at my camp, I distributed the provisions 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="167"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_08_Page_167.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Winnipeg Treaty</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">167</fw> 
     

     implements, &amp;c., which were received with the greatest degree of gratifica<lb break="no"/>tion and satisfaction. . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On my inquiring of the Chief of Norway House when his band would be 
     <lb/>
     prepared to remove to their reserve at the Fisher River, he informed me 
     <lb/>
     that he had sent two of his people to that locality to report on the same, and 
     <lb/>
     that he could not say anything definite on the matter until their return. I 
     <lb/>
     might here state that, on my way back to Winnipeg I met these men re<lb break="no"/>turning from Fisher's River, who expressed themselves as highly pleased 
     <lb/>
     with the proposed location, and that the band in all probability would re<lb break="no"/>move there in the spring. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whilst at Norway House I was waited upon by a Chief and four Council<lb break="no"/>lors from the vicinity of Oxford House, who were anxious to know if the 
     <lb/>
     same bounties would be extended to them as were being extended to their 
     <lb/>
     brethren of Norway House and Cross Lake, and also whether they could 
     <lb/>
     obtain a reserve on Lake Winnipeg, as the country in which they were 
     <lb/>
     living was totally unfit for cultivation, and that they had the greatest 
     <lb/>
     difficulty in procuring a livelihood. I told them that I had no idea what 
     <lb/>
     were the intentions of the Government with regard to those Indians living 
     <lb/>
     north of the present Treaty, but that I would make known their requests 
     <lb/>
     to Your Excellency, and that they would be duly notified of any action the 
     <lb/>
     Government might take in the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I left Norway House on my return trip, on the morning of the 18th, 
     <lb/>
     arriving at Winnipeg on the afternoon of Saturday the 26th, having that 
     <lb/>
     morning paid my boat's crew off at Selkirk. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I would here mention that previous to my departure from Norway House 
     <lb/>
     there was a very hearty and apparently sincere expression of gratitude, on 
     <lb/>
     the part of all the Indians present, for the liberality extended to them, and 
     <lb/>
     a general and spoken wish that their thanks be conveyed to the Queen's 
     <lb/>
     Representative in this Province for his kind interest in their welfare. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I cannot conclude without hearing testimony to the kindness of Mr. Ross, 
     <lb/>
     Hudson's Bay Company's Factor, and the Rev. Mr. Ruttan, Wesleyan 
     <lb/>
     missionary, for services rendered during the few days occupied in my 
     <lb/>
     making the payments at Norway House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I enclose herewith statement of expenditure, &amp;c., &amp;c., with vouchers 
     <lb/>
     attached. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="simple:right">
     I have the honor to be, Sir, 
     <lb/>
     Your obedient servant, 
     <lb/>
         <persName ref="pers:REID3">J. LESTOCK REID</persName>,
            <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner</hi></p></quote>

     </div>    </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>