<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="Morris_Chapter_01"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreatyNeg">Treaty Negotiations</name>, <date from="1811" to="1817">1811 to 1817</date>, Between Canada and First Nations of Manitoba and the Northwest Territories.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:Morris">
          

               <author>Alexander Morris</author>.
          
         
          <title>The Treaties of Canada with the Indians of Manitoba and the North-West Territories Including the Negotiations on Which They Are Based, and Other Information Relating Thereto.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1880"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>: <publisher>Willing &amp; Williamson</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="15"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_013.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_014.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_015.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-28">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-28">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_013">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_013.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_014">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_014.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_015">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_015.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <pb n="13" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_013.jpg"/>
            
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Selkirk Treaty.</hi></fw> <fw type="num">13</fw>

<div type="chapter">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">CHAPTER I.</head>

            <p rendition="simple:centre">THE SELKIRK TREATY.</p>


            <p>
     IN the year 1811, the Earl of Selkirk purchased from the  
     <lb/>
      Governor and Company of Adventurers trading into Hud<lb break="no"/>son's Bay, in consideration of ten shillings and certain agree<lb break="no"/>ments and understandings contained in the Indenture, a large 
     <lb/>
     tract of territory within Rupert's Land described in the Inden<lb break="no"/>ture as follows:  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " All that tract of land or territory being within and forming 
     <lb/>
     part of the aforesaid lands and territories of the said Governor 
     <lb/>
     and Company, bounded by an imaginary line running as fol<lb break="no"/>lows, that is to say, beginning on the western shore of the Lake 
     <lb/>
     Winnipic, otherwise Winnipeg, at a point in fifty-two degrees 
     <lb/>
     and thirty north latitude and thence running due west to the 
     <lb/>
     Lake Winnipegoos, otherwise called Little Winnipeg, then in a 
     <lb/>
     southerly direction through the said Lake so as to strike its 
     <lb/>
     western shore in latitude fifty-two degrees, then due west to the 
     <lb/>
     place where the parallel of fifty-two degrees north latitude 
     <lb/>
     intersects the western branch of Red River, otherwise called 
     <lb/>
     Asseniboine River, then due south from that point of intersec<lb break="no"/>tion to the height of land which separates the waters running 
     <lb/>
     into Hudson's Bay from those of the Missouri and Mississippi, 
     <lb/>
     then in an easterly direction along the said height of land to the 
     <lb/>
     source of the River Winnipic, or Winnipeg (meaning by such 
     <lb/>
     last named river the principal branch of the waters which unite 
     <lb/>
     in Lake Sagenagos), thence along the main stream of these waters 
     <lb/>
     and the middle of the several lakes through which they flow 
     <lb/>
     to the mouth of the Winnipic River and thence in an northerly 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="14" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_014.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">14</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians.</hi></fw> 
     
     direction through the middle of Lake Winnipic to the place of 
     <lb/>
    beginning." The deed is accompanied by a map intended to 
     <lb/>show the tract of country, and there is an endorsement on the , 
     <lb/>map that as the surveys were not sufficient to ascertain with pre<lb break="no"/>cision whether, latitude 52° does intersect the river called Red 
     <lb/>or Assiniboine River, it was agreed, that in case the waters of 
     <lb/>of Red River, shall on more accurate survey be found, not to 
     <lb/>extend so far north as latitude 52°, then the west boundary of 
     <lb/>the tract of land intended to be within the grant, should be a 
     <lb/>line drawn due north and south, through the post upon the Red 
     <lb/>River, marked on the plan as " Carlton House." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
            <p>
     The Company reserved the right to call upon the Earl to set 
     <lb/>
     off one-tenth, however, of the tract for the use of the servants of 
     <lb/>
     the Company—and the Earl covenanted, within ten years, to 
     <lb/>
     settle within the tract one thousand families, each of them con<lb break="no"/>sisting of one married couple at the least, on pain of revocation 
     <lb/>
     of the grant, if on receipt of notice to that effect from the Com<lb break="no"/>pany he did not, within three years after the receipt of the 
     <lb/>
     notice, complete the settlement of the one thousand families. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In pursuance of his obligations, Lord Selkirk, in the autumn 
     <lb/>
     of the year 1811, sent out a number of families from the County 
     <lb/>
     of Sutherland, in Scotland, who spent the winter at Fort 
     <lb/>
     Churchill on the western shore of Hudson's Bay. On the 
     <lb/>
     arrival of spring, they travelled thence to the confluence of 
     <lb/>
     the Assiniboine and Red Rivers, and thus was commenced the 
     <lb/>
     interesting settlement of the Red River, which is now included 
     <lb/>
     in the Province of Manitoba. It is not my purpose to notice 
     <lb/>
     here the eventful history of the Selkirk colonists, and I will 
     <lb/>
     only note the fact that in 1836, the Company bought back the 
     <lb/>
     whole tract, from the heirs of Lord Selkirk, for the sum of 
     <lb/>
     £84,000, the rights of colonists who had purchased land 
     <lb/>
     between 1811 and 1836, being respected. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In the year 1817 the Earl of Selkirk, visited his wide domain, 
     <lb/>
     and entered into negotiations with the Indian tribes, for the 
     <lb/>
     extinction of their title, to a tract of land described as follows: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_01_Page_015.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Selkirk Treaty.</hi></fw> <fw type="num">15</fw> 
     
   
            <p>
     <ref target="#fn_01">*</ref> "All that tract of land adjacent to Red River and Assini<lb break="no"/>boine River, beginning at the mouth of Red River and extend<lb break="no"/>ing along the same as far as Great Forks at the mouth of Red 
     <lb/>
     Lake River and along Assiniboine River as far as the Musk 
     <lb/>
     Rat River, otherwise called Rivière des Champignons, and ex<lb break="no"/>tending to the distance of six miles from Fort Douglas on every 
     <lb/>
     side, and likewise from Fort Doer, and also from the Great 
     <lb/>
     Forks and in other posts extending in breadth to the distance 
     <lb/>
     of two English statute miles back from the banks of the river." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Indians then inhabiting the region were described as 
     <lb/>
     being of the Chippawa or Saulteaux and Killistine or Cree 
     <lb/>
     nations. They were made to comprehend, the depth of the land 
     <lb/>
     they were surrendering, by being told, that it was the greatest 
     <lb/>
     distance, at which a horse on the level prairie could be seen, or 
     <lb/>
     daylight seen under his belly between his legs. The consider<lb break="no"/>ation for the surrender, was, the payment of one hundred pounds 
     <lb/>
     of good merchantable tobacco, to each nation annually. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The treaty was signed by Lord Selkirk and by five Indian 
     <lb/>
     chiefs, who affixed thereto drawings of the animals after which 
     <lb/>
     they were named, by way of signature, a <hi rendition="simple:italic">fac simile</hi> of which 
     <lb/>
     will be found elsewhere The surrender was to the Sovereign. 
     <lb/>
     Lord, King George the Third. The treaty was accompanied 
     <lb/>
     by a map which shows that the tract surrendered extended to 
     <lb/>
     Grand Forks in what is now United States territory. A copy 
     <lb/>
    of the treaty will be found in the Appendix and will prove of 
     <lb/>interest. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<note xml:id="fn_01">* A large portion of the ceded territory is now comprehended in the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritory of Dakota, United States.</note>

        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>