<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="Morris_Chapter_11"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreatyNeg">Treaty Negotiations</name>, <date from="1862" to="1878">1862 to 1878</date>, Between Canada and First Nations of Manitoba and the Northwest Territories.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:Morris">
          

               <author>Alexander Morris</author>.
          
         
          <title>The Treaties of Canada with the Indians of Manitoba and the North-West Territories Including the Negotiations on Which They Are Based, and Other Information Relating Thereto.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1880"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>: <publisher>Willing &amp; Williamson</publisher>.
          
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="284"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_276.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_277.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_278.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_279.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_280.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_281.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_282.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_283.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_284.hocr.html"/>
               </item>

            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-04-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-04-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_276">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_276.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_277">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_277.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_278">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_278.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_279">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_279.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_280">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_280.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_281">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_281.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_282">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_282.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_283">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_283.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_284">
         <graphic url="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_284.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="276"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_276.jpg"/>
        
     <fw type="num">276</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     
            
   <div type="chapter">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CHAPTER XI. 

            </head>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     THE SIOUX IN THE NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     MUCH interest has been awakened with regard to this war<lb break="no"/>like race, owing to recent events ; namely, the war be<lb break="no"/>tween them and the United States, the destruction by them of 
     <lb/>Captain Custer's command, and their subsequent flight into 
     <lb/>British territory, and now prolonged sojourn therein. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

            <p>
     Prior, however, to this irruption, a portion of the Sioux tribe 
     <lb/>
     of American Indians, took refuge in the Red River settlement, 
     <lb/>
     after the massacre of the whites by the Indians in Minnesota, 
     <lb/>
     in the year 1862. Their arrival caused great consternation in 
     <lb/>
     the settlement. The main body took up a position at Sturgeon 
     <lb/>
     Creek, about six miles from Fort Garry, now the City of Win<lb break="no"/>nipeg, and others, at Poplar Point, and the Turtle Mountain. 
     <lb/>
     The Governor and Council of Assiniboia then governed the 
     <lb/>
     Province of Assiniboia, under the Hudson's Bay Company, and 
     <lb/>
     was composed of representative men. Their deliberations 
     <lb/>
     were grave and anxious. In December, 1863, the Governor- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     in-Chief, Mr. Dallas, reported to the Council, that he had 
     <lb/>
     visited the principal camp of the Sioux at Sturgeon Creek, and 
     <lb/>
     found there about five hundred men, women and children, and 
     <lb/>
     more had since arrived ; that he had found them in great des<lb break="no"/>titution and suffering, from want of food and clothing, and 
     <lb/>
     that after consultation with Governor Mactavish, of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Assiniboia, he had offered sufficient provisions to 
     <lb/>
     enable them to remove to such a distance from the settlement 
     <lb/>
     as would place it beyond all danger and apprehension, and also 
     <lb/>
     offered to have the provisions conveyed for them, and ammuni<lb break="no"/>tion supplied them to procure game, but they had positively 
  

            <pb n="277"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_277.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Sioux in the North-West Territories</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">277</fw> 
  

     refused to go away—giving as a reason the inability of the old 
     <lb/>
     men, women and children, to travel in the winter. The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor was in consequence authorized by the Council, to offer 
     <lb/>
     them the means of transport, for those who were unable to walk. 
     <lb/>
     The Indians then removed to White Horse Plains, a distance 
     <lb/>
     of twenty miles only from Fort Garry, and camped there. A 
     <lb/>
     supply of food was given them, but no ammunition. The 
     <lb/>
     United States military authorities in December, 1863, sent an 
     <lb/>
     envoy to see the Governor-in-Chief of Rupert's Land, and the 
     <lb/>
     North-West Territories, with a view to ordering the Sioux to 
     <lb/>
     return to United States territory. The Governor was assured, 
     <lb/>
     that, though the American authorities would punish such of 
     <lb/>
     the Sioux as had actually been engaged in the massacre, they 
     <lb/>
     would furnish the innocent with all needful supplies of food 
     <lb/>
     and clothing for the winter, in the event of giving themselves 
     <lb/>
     up peaceably. The Council, on hearing this statement, author<lb break="no"/>ized the granting permission to the American authorities to 
     <lb/>
     enter into negotiations with the Sioux in the territories, on 
     <lb/>
     condition that they adopted no aggressive measures against 
     <lb/>
     them, and that in the event of the Americans accepting the 
     <lb/>
     proposed permission, they should protect themselves by a suf<lb break="no"/>ficient guard to preclude the danger of attack from the In<lb break="no"/>dians, and to ensure the preservation of peace. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In January, 1864, the Council considered a despatch from 
     <lb/>
     Major Hatch, in command of the American forces, represent<lb break="no"/>ing that on the approach of spring, he apprehended a renewal 
     <lb/>
     of the barbarous scenes of 1862 and 1863, and asked author<lb break="no"/>ity to cross the national boundaries and pursue and capture the 
     <lb/>
     murderers, wherever they might be found. The Council ac<lb break="no"/>corded the permission asked, but it was never acted on. It is 
     <lb/>
     not likely that a permission to cross our borders in pursuit of 
     <lb/>
     a flying enemy would ever again be granted. It was conceded 
     <lb/>
     in exceptional circumstances by an irresponsible Government, 
     <lb/>
     but the growth of the Dominion of Canada has been such, and 
     <lb/>
     its relations to the empire have become so intimate, that it 
  

            <pb n="278"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_278.jpg"/>
           
    <fw type="num">278</fw> <fw type="running">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians.</fw> 
   

     would not in my judgment be granted, if at all, except in con<lb break="no"/>cert with the Imperal Government. The Governor also re<lb break="no"/>ported to the Council, that the main body of the Sioux on the 
     <lb/>
     Missouri in the United States, had sent him a message asking 
     <lb/>
     his advice as to making peace with the Americans, and ex<lb break="no"/>pressing a desire to visit Red River in spring, and that he had 
     <lb/>
     advised the Sioux to make peace with the Americans, as other<lb break="no"/>wise, the war would be renewed with increased vigor next 
     <lb/>
     summer. He had also counselled them not to visit the Red 
     <lb/>
     River country. The Council warned the Sioux not to visit 
     <lb/>
     the settlement, but in the summer of 1866, the advice 
     <lb/>
     was disregarded. A band of Sioux came to Fort Garry 
     <lb/>
     and were leaving quietly, with a number of Saulteaux, but 
     <lb/>
     when about a mile from the Fort, they were attacked by a 
     <lb/>
     band of Red Lake Saulteaux Indians, who had just come into 
     <lb/>
     the settlement from the United States, and five of them were 
     <lb/>
     shot. The remainder fled for their lives. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Council apprehended that the Sioux might congregate 
     <lb/>
     in force, and a collision take place between the Sioux and the 
     <lb/>
     Saulteaux, and therefore authorized the formation of a body of 
     <lb/>
     from fifty to one hundred mounted armed men from among the 
     <lb/>
     settlers, to prevent the Sioux from coming into the settlement. 
     <lb/>
     Fortunately they did not return and a collision was avoided. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In 1866, the American authorities again opened up communi<lb break="no"/>cations with the Governor and Council of Assiniboia, through 
     <lb/>
     Colonel Adams, who intimated that he had been authorized by 
     <lb/>
     Brevet Major-General Corse, commanding the District of Min<lb break="no"/>nesota, "to use every possible means to induce the hostile 
     <lb/>
     Sioux to surrender themselves at Fort Abercrombie, and to 
     <lb/>
     grant them protection and entire absolution for all past offences 
     <lb/>
     in the event of giving themselves up," and asking the aid of 
     <lb/>
     the Council, to endeavor to influence the Sioux to accede to 
     <lb/>
     the proposals he made. The Council accordingly authorized 
     <lb/>
     Judge Black and Mr. McClure to communicate to the Chiefs of 
     <lb/>
     the Sioux, the letter of Colonel Adams, and endeavor to induce 
   

            <pb n="279"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_279.jpg"/>
         
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Sioux in the North-West Territories</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">279</fw>
     


     them to accept of it, and to supply them with what provi<lb break="no"/>sions might be necessary to carry the Sioux to Fort Aber<lb break="no"/>crombie. 
     
            </p>

            <p>
     All efforts having that end in view failed, and the Sioux 
     <lb/>
     remained, some in the Province of Assiniboia, and others in 
     <lb/>
     the territories beyond, As time went on, in 1870, the country 
     <lb/>
     passed under the rule of Canada, and when the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada was established in the Province of Manitoba, which 
     <lb/>
     included the district of Assiniboia, the Sioux were found liv<lb break="no"/>ing quietly in tents, in the parishes of Poplar Point, High 
     <lb/>
     Bluff, and Portage la Prairie, in what became the new Province 
     <lb/>
     of Manitoba. Immigrants from Ontario, had begun to settle 
     <lb/>
     in that section of the Province, and the settlement rapidly 
     <lb/>
     increased. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Sioux were found very useful, and were employed as 
     <lb/>
     labourers, cutting grain, making fence-rails, and ploughing for 
     <lb/>
     the settlers. They also endeavored to gain a subsistence, by kill<lb break="no"/>ing game and fur-bearing animals, and by fishing. They fre<lb break="no"/>quently applied to Lieut.-Gov. Archibald, to be allowed to settle 
     <lb/>
     on a reserve, where they might support themselves by farming, 
     <lb/>
     a step which that officer favored. In 1873, they renewed the 
     <lb/>
     application to his successor, Lieut.-Gov. Morris, who having 
     <lb/>
     obtained authority to do so, promised to give them a reserve; 
     <lb/>
     upwards of one hundred of these Sioux, resident within Mani<lb break="no"/>toba, having waited upon him, and represented "that they had 
     <lb/>
     no homes or means of living," and asked for land and agricul<lb break="no"/>tural implements. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     They were informed, that the case was exceptional, and that 
     <lb/>
     what would be done, would be as a matter of grace and not 
     <lb/>
     of right, which they admitted. They were also told that the 
     <lb/>
     reserve would be for themselves alone, and that the Sioux now 
     <lb/>
     in the States must remain there. A reserve was proposed to 
     <lb/>
     them on Lake Manitoba, but they were unwilling to go there, 
     <lb/>
     being afraid of the Saulteaux, and especially the Red Lake 
     <lb/>
     Saulteaux. 

            </p>

            <pb n="280"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_280.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="num">280</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     
   
            <p>
     It is satisfactory to state, that after the treaty at the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West Angle, the Saulteaux having become bound to live at 
     <lb/>
     peace with all people under Canadian authority, sent the aged 
     <lb/>
     Chief Kou-croche to see the Lieutenant-Governor at Fort Garry, 
     <lb/>
     to acquaint him of their desire to make peace with the Sioux 
     <lb/>
     The Chief said the words he had heard at the Angle were good, 
     <lb/>
     he had promised to live at peace with all men, and he now 
     <lb/>
     wished to make friends with the Sioux. The distrust between 
     <lb/>
     the two tribes had been great, owing to past events. At the 
     <lb/>
     Angle, but for the presence of the troops, the Chippewas would 
     <lb/>
     have fled, it having been circulated among them, that the Sioux 
     <lb/>
     were coming to attack them. Permission was given to the 
     <lb/>
     Chief to pay his visit to the Sioux, and messengers were sent 
     <lb/>
     to them, in advance, to explain the object of his visit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The result of the interview was satisfactory, and the ancient 
     <lb/>
     feud was buried. In 1874, two reserves were allotted the 
     <lb/>
     Sioux, one on the Assiniboine River, at Oak River, and another 
     <lb/>
     still further west, at Bird Tail Creek. These reserves were 
     <lb/>
     surveyed, the former containing eight thousand and the latter 
     <lb/>
     seven thousand acres. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Settlements, were commenced, on both reserves, and cattle, 
     <lb/>
     seed and agricultural implements were supplied to them. In 
     <lb/>
     1875, the Lieutentant-Governor finding that a large number 
     <lb/>
     still continued their nomadic life, in the vicinity of Poplar 
     <lb/>
     Point and Portage la Prairie, visited them, and obtained their 
     <lb/>
     promise to remove to the reserves—which the majority eventu<lb break="no"/>ally did. Kenneth Mackenzie, Esq., M.P.P., a very successful 
     <lb/>
     farmer from Ontario, who had largely employed Sioux labor<lb break="no"/>ers, kindly agreed to visit the Assiniboine reserve and direct 
     <lb/>
     them from time to time as to the agricultural operations. The 
     <lb/>
     Church of England undertook the establishment of a mission 
     <lb/>
     and erected buildings there, while the Presbyterians opened 
     <lb/>
     a mission at Bird Tail Creek, and obtained the services of 
     <lb/>
     a native ordained Sioux miinster, from the Presbytery of 
     <lb/>
     Dakotah. The number of these Sioux is estimated at about 
  
            <pb n="281"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_281.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Sioux in the North-West Territories</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">281</fw> 
    

     fifteen hundred. Both settlements give promise of becoming 
     <lb/>
     self-sustaining, and in view of the rapid settlement of the 
     <lb/>
     country, some disposition of them had become necessary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     During their sojourn of thirteen years on British territory, 
     <lb/>
     these Indians have on the whole, been orderly, and there was 
     <lb/>
     only one grave crime committed among them, under peculiar 
     <lb/>
     circumstances—the putting to death of one of their number, 
     <lb/>
     which was done under their tribal laws. An indictment was 
     <lb/>
     laid before the Grand Jury of Manitoba. and a true bill found 
     <lb/>
     against those concerned in this affair, but the chief actors in the 
     <lb/>
     tragedy fled. Had they been tried, their defence would prob<lb break="no"/>ably have been that the act was committed in self-defence. 
     <lb/>
    The slain man having, as the Chief represented, killed one 
     <lb/>of the tribe, cruelly assaulted another, and threatened the 
     <lb/>lives of others. When the war broke out between the 
     <lb/>Sioux and the American Government, the American Sioux, 
     <lb/>endeavored to induce those in Canadian territory to join 
     <lb/>them, but they refused. Precautionary measures were how<lb break="no"/>ever taken and messengers sent to them, by the Lieuten<lb break="no"/>ant-Governor, to warn them against taking any part. They 
     <lb/>disclaimed all intention to do so, and said they meant to 
     <lb/>live peacefully, being grateful for the kindness with which 
     <lb/>they had been treated. Besides these Manitoban Sioux, there 
     <lb/>were two other bands in the North-West Territories—one at 
     <lb/>Turtle Mountains, and another large party in the bounds of 
     <lb/>the Qu'Appelle Treaty. In 1876 the latter sent their Chiefs to 
     <lb/>see Lieut.-Gov. Morris and the Hon. Mr. Laird, at Qu'Appelle, 
     <lb/>and asked to be assigned a home. They were told that their 
     <lb/>case would be represented to the Canadian authorities. In 
     <lb/>1877, the Sioux at the Turtle Mountains, sent two deputations 
     <lb/>to the Lieutenant-Governor, to ask for a reserve in that region. 
     <lb/>They said they had lived for fifteen years in British territory 
     <lb/>they wanted land to be given them and implements to cultivate 
     <lb/>the soil, and seed to sow, and scythes and sickles to reap their 
     <lb/>grain, and some cattle. 
      </p>


            <pb n="282"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_282.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">282</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
    

            <p>
     They were told that they had no claim on the Queen, as 
     <lb/>
     they were not British Indians, unless she chose to help them 
     <lb/>
     out of her benevolence. This they cheerfully admitted, but 
     <lb/>
     hoped that they would be helped. They were further in<lb break="no"/>formed that if a reserve was granted them, it could not be 
     <lb/>
     near the boundary line as they wished, and that they must 
     <lb/>
     avoid all interference with the American trouble with their 
     <lb/>
     nation. This they willingly promised, and said "they had 
     <lb/>
     already taken care to have nothing to do with the matter." 
     <lb/>
     These Sioux were very intelligent and superior Indians, and 
     <lb/>
     were well dressed. A reserve was subsequently allotted to 
     <lb/>
     them in the year 1876, in the vicinity of Oak Lake, about 
     <lb/>
     fifty miles due north of Turtle Mountains, allowing them the' 
     <lb/>
     same quantity of land, which had been given the Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     Sioux, viz., 80 acres to each band of five persons, and they will 
     <lb/>
     doubtless follow the example of their brethren on the other 
     <lb/>
     two reserves. With regard to the Sioux to whom reserves 
     <lb/>
     have been assigned, the then Minister of the Interior, the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     David Mills, thus reported in 1877 : "The report of the Deputy 
     <lb/>
     Superintendent-General in 1877 gives some details respecting 
     <lb/>
     the operations of the Manitoba Sioux on their reserves, during 
     <lb/>
     the past year. He says: 'Upon the whole, they appear to 
     <lb/>
     have made fair progress in cultivating the land, and their pros<lb break="no"/>pects for the future, had they the advice and assistance of some 
     <lb/>
     good farmers, for a few years, would be encouraging. Indeed, 
     <lb/>
     the Sioux generally, who are resident in Canada, appear to 
     <lb/>
     be more intelligent, industrious, and self-reliant, than the other 
     <lb/>
     Indian bands in the North-West.' " 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     While the authorities were thus successfully dealing with the 
     <lb/>
     problem of how to provide a future for these wandering Sioux, 
     <lb/>
     a grave difficulty presented itself by the incursion into the 
     <lb/>
     North-West Territories of a large body of American Sioux 
     <lb/>
     (supposed to be under the lead of what is now an historic name, 
     <lb/>
     the Sitting Bull), who had fled from the American troops. The 
   

            <pb n="283"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_283.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Sioux in the North-West Territories</hi>.</fw> <fw type="num">283</fw> 
    

     Minister of the Interior, the <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Hon. David Mills</persName>, in 1877, thus 
     <lb/>
     alluded to this difficult subject :  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " The presence of Sitting Bull and his warriors in Canada is 
     <lb/>
     a source of anxiety both to the Government of Canada and the 
     <lb/>
     United States. These Indians harbor feelings of fierce hostility 
     <lb/>
     towards, and thorough distrust of, the United States people and 
     <lb/>
     Government. These feelings may be traced to two principal 
     <lb/>
     causes, the dishonesty of Indian agents and the failure of the 
     <lb/>
     Federal authorities to protect the Indian reservations from being 
     <lb/>
     taken possession of by an adventurous and somewhat lawless 
     <lb/>
     white population. The officers of the North-West Mounted 
     <lb/>
     Police have been instructed to impress upon Sitting Bull and 
     <lb/>
     his warriors the necessity of keeping the peace towards the 
     <lb/>
     people of the United States, and there is no reason for suppos<lb break="no"/>ing they will not heed the warnings which have been given 
     <lb/>
     them. It is not, however, desirable to encourage them to 
     <lb/>
     remain on Canadian territory, and Col. McLeod has been 
     <lb/>
     accordingly instructed to impress them with their probable 
     <lb/>
     future hardships after the failure of the buffalo, should they 
     <lb/>
     elect to remain in Canada ; that the President of the United 
     <lb/>
     States and his Cabinet are upright men, willing and anxious to 
     <lb/>
     do justice to the Indians ; and should they return peacefully 
     <lb/>
     they will be properly cared for, and any treaty made with them 
     <lb/>
     will be honestly fulfilled. It is desirable that as wards of the 
     <lb/>
     United States they should return to that country, upon the 
     <lb/>
     Government of which morally devolves the burden and the 
     <lb/>
     responsibility of their civilization." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Sioux have since continued within the borders of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     and the Minister of the Interior, Sir John Macdonald, reported 
     <lb/>
     in 1878, " That it is only just to them to say, that they have 
     <lb/>
     behaved remarkably well ever since they crossed into Canada." 
     <lb/>
     Their presence in the North-West Territories has, however, 
     <lb/>
     been attended and will be followed, in any event, by serious 
     <lb/>
    consequences. The natural food supply of our Canadian 
    

            <pb n="284"
                facs="final/images/Morris_MB_NWT_Treaties_Chapt_11_Page_284.jpg"/>
     
     <fw type="num">284</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Treaties of Canada with the Indians</hi>.</fw> 
     

     Indians, the Crees, Chippewas, Assiniboines and Blackfeet, 
     <lb/>
     of the Plain Country, viz., the buffalo, was rapidly diminish<lb break="no"/>ing, and the advent of so large a body of foreign Indians 
     <lb/>
     has precipitated its diminution, so that the final extinction of 
     <lb/>
     the buffalo is fast drawing near. Already the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, in the discharge of a national obligation, which has ever 
     <lb/>
     been recognized by all civilized authorities, has been obliged 
     <lb/>
     to come to the aid of the Blackfeet and other Indians to avert 
     <lb/>
     the danger and suffering from famine. The Sioux are already 
     <lb/>
     feeling the hardships of their position, and it will tax the skill 
     <lb/>
     and energies of the Government of Canada to provide a remedy. 
     <lb/>
     Already, at the instance of the Hon. David Mills, then Minister 
     <lb/>
     of the Interior (who visited Washington for the purpose), an 
     <lb/>
     effort was made by the American Government to induce the 
     <lb/>
     Sioux to return to their homes. Envoys were sent to them 
     <lb/>
     from the United States, but they declined to accept the over<lb break="no"/>tures made to them. On the previous occasion of the flight 
     <lb/>
     into our territories of the Sioux, the American Government, as 
     <lb/>
     has been before recited, after an interval of nearly four years, 
     <lb/>
     offered them protection on their return journey from British 
     <lb/>
     territory to their homes in the United States and " entire abso<lb break="no"/>lution for all past offences." This forms a precedent which 
     <lb/>
     should be invoked and would doubtless be accepted by the 
     <lb/>
     Sioux if they can be induced to believe in the good faith 
     <lb/>
     of the American Government towards them. Every effort 
     <lb/>
     should be made to bring about so desirable a result, and 
     <lb/>
     the subject will doubtless engage in the future, as it has done 
     <lb/>
     in the past, the anxious consideration and wise action of the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian Government, who have a right to appeal to the 
     <lb/>
     President of the United States and his advisers, to relieve them 
     <lb/>
     from the incubus of the presence in our territories of so 
     <lb/>
     many of the wards of that Government, and who are without 
     <lb/>
     the means or opportunities of obtaining a livelihood for them<lb break="no"/>selves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>