<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-07" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-02-07">7 February 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-02-23"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-23_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-11-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-23_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-23_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-23_Page_2.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    

<p>...?" º <lb/></p> 

<p>| | - £º **.*.*.*. * | *= <lb/>
- - 8. §. <lb/></p> 

<p>*Young lady rºciºe <lb/>
#jºi. <lb/>
is rºsiº the namº <lb/>
jºseph. This most interest <lb/></p> 

<p>8 º'clock in the morn <lb/></p> 

<p>- #: - <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>i tº - - .. - w for the first time learned that he had . A Bill to provide fºr the maintenance of wives and o: <lb/></p> 

<p>- HousP OF ASSEMBLY. º. *:::::::::::::: **ś|. º:º:a:::::::::::::: Fº#. PRESENTATI <lb/>
- igiº. º.º. knºw that gºlemn had ever donº | of Faſº's deserted --- - z - -- T. <lb/>
... * *:::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: *** ºf <lb/></p> 

<p>- at three o'cloc - the every day. Was It ho gfibe. Government mºre ***** - ... in the fºresentation <lb/></p> 

<p>8. one prºtºsí to giºrge were regired therº, and it wº, ºgº st offics wi -čáthºlic. He &amp;Ir, A Bit tº provide for the recovery of penalt glace ontº <lb/>
... . . . of the ... "...# ... ."...º.º.º.º. ...":"... ."...fººt d on this o <lb/></p> 

<p>the ºfficienc t <lb/>
. . . . <lb/></p> 

<p>presen <lb/></p> 

<p>yer. <lb/></p> 

<p>zances. <lb/></p> 

<p>gº." it Carbonear has be <lb/>
A Bill to <lb/></p> 

<p>- $º the adáress of -the house in regiº." * ***.*.*. this sppointmen <lb break="no"/>and were not it would not be fit to live im. " . . . - wb or in <lb/></p> 

<p>#...yºspeech as the opening of the **iº", * ºre nºt suffiantly tºº. . ."...it'." d <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>- - - ere n tession-w arm tml aracter... adverse claims made-upon persons-h <lb/></p> 

<p>tim *ś|º.º.º. º.º.º.º.º." <lb/></p> 

<p>able Courts of Law to giver <lb/></p> 

<p>againſt <lb/>
no intºwt <lb/></p> 

<p>g retu - - - <lb break="no"/>the house the retly of his paid - -- n -- s r <lb/>
º:*::::::::::::::::::::A;"|†† º;|:::::::::::::: ºfº" "w ºi. <lb/>
e Lºdger. - - step in their profession. If t - jº reli <lb/>
*:::::::Asimº tº: flººr. º: º ºlºmºnº- ºr j: i..."; <lb/>
, of his Excellency the Governor, presen ..., |sult the feeling othº.º.º. 1 °º. - the ºccasion, especially the al <lb/>
| * the following documents:- work on the wharves, but it appear once, jºint. -—s # 3...". <lb/>
| *:::::::::::::sº sº fººl.ºrºº::::::::::::::::::::::::::::...] Tº *: *.*.*... <lb/>
| cºlºr ºf ºne, tº jºiº.;:"...". ſt ºtlufmmitmer . . ...º.º.º. <lb/>
- # 4 iºts rail,.]:::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: *** * * *8" &amp; "". - ...hers of the clergy, entered <lb/>
iſſil aft; º º, ºº:::::::::: *. † - ... i. º. º. - fºrwards commenced the <lb/>
3. er 1 it was perfectly true that the Stigehº —this was a matter. 3 Q. <lb/>
- | tº "...]::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: ST. Jo H.W.?.S. <lb/>
- *:::::...i.amnestrºsting the fileſia, *.*.*.*. r a #. * . 3. Hºlº. |--Taussow, FEBRUAar. 23, 1865, sº <lb/>
- º;...". uld not get sti ical treatment here, i remember that sºme few yeºgº. - t -- <lb break="no"/>: *ś, a rºads the Hºlº tº ºr ºn tº a <lb/>
H.: ... º.º.º. 1; with his health much im e was very efficient effected, and twº 1 gentlemen had been ºp- .*.*.*. <lb/>
- }} || fº.º.º. . . . ºff of "...ii.º.º.º. º.º.º.º.º.;|. spray comestº <lb/>
|- ſº tº iº...ºs...}...]; ..."ºś|...º.º.º.º.º. flºº.º.º.º.º. <lb/>
.*.*. jºiji. Tºlº": monthly mail, Englishdiº bººtlºº <lb/>
- H. *:::::::::::::::Huº, on tº lºº, * * * * *|: º," our space is so occupied with the Legislative it. <lb/>
:1 - orary Magistrates out) knew that tº la <lb break="no"/>Court, for the year 1864: - norary - is on the ta h ... W. H. iśyanā ºil of bates that we can only find roºm at Present for the d spiritua t <lb/>
flºº"::::::::::::::::::... a. º. "...º.º.º. ſº, tº the nº ...". §.". <lb/>
- ..". nment relative to the petition, stative private prºliº, and hºº." new - necessary pº <lb/>
-- ..º.º. º.º.º. ººººººººystºpºgº, E. p. ii.º.º. "...º.º.º dºzº ut <lb/>
- # ...thºs of his is #. Tº tº inst tº petition is on the Government bººt ºf thºg #1% º no jºins ºf ºrij age. ... <lb/>
;: *"...º.º.º..."wº company, for the the table was pºt and ºut the cºlºny, pſi tºy lºgº.º.º.º. ... jºis... º. <lb/>
- # r 1834 d.º.ºirs; geºlºgiº |ºl.". ." ..."...#| Riº. This hº <lb/>
| *...*, *, uniºn ind cºmmercial Banks for bºniº |º. <lb/></p> 

<p>...'. <lb/></p> 

<p>*::::::... mºi" ºr <lb/></p> 

<p>. the year 1864. appointed on Contingencies and Printing: p ºrity in two loººººº... .s. <lb break="no"/>: ing Dock company for the year ºrdered that the on Receiver General and Messrs before; are was a greater security The new Minister inspain seems to have grown wise: * <lb/>
- | } Rºturn from the Floating Dock Company *|pºº lºº º: ...". º: º: jºin a jº <lb/></p> 

<p>4. <lb/></p> 

<p>-------- i.- for the year || Committee <lb/>
Return from Vail's Joint Stock Company y Mr Talbor pursuant to notice ask <lb/>
ºãº º ºſſi. . <lb/></p> 

<p>tº the ºn As ºf lº <lb/></p> 

<p>tion tram worldy <lb/>
to her former state and min <lb/></p> 

<p>t w8t Miłł Report and Returns for the - agree and they are now wer <lb/>
'; º' " 8. †iº |::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: *...". º:...i. <lb/>
tºr tº lie on the tabl th of the late Dr Rochford. 3. 3m not to be Satıştiº ºn the which she poss <lb/></p> 

<p>- §: §:º: ... .ºn, ". of sex gºal replied that the con- ment. If the late intº hid been a ...; *. Conti - and experience, the mºde of <lb/>
| º... .". ſº lºº.º.º.º.º. <lb/>
ad, praying for compensatioã fºr loss.sºta consideration ºp; , it wºººoººººººº Pº: "" jºy any dis inct movement in the Government ºr; <lb/>
º: ..","...". jºi iſ ºn bit to exclude Roman Catholic, ſº office. ... " "...º.º.º.º.: 1. <lb/>
... .º.º.º. j.n. i.isº ºngºing tº aſſeniº || Hon. Arrowser Gºssº sºil thºſe was nº in jºire eming form; anº. <lb/>
... "...º.º.º. i. º. ii. Wii. º. º.º.º. ºn Gºvernment tº jºi... i. º. #. <lb/></p> 

<p>A. ... "...p. that is house would were two who held the appºintment ther was no pºs: throw the slights disparagºmen; upºn, the ºars: ji, iii. 3. holding th and if it suc;;; i.e."º... s. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºfflºº; ºr: |º. tº jº. <lb/></p> 

<p>ry creditable view of a most aus upon en- ust either of inability or lùºom;18tency, - - <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>#...'...". there was no necessity for a second appoint- but because his infirmilies and deº id not , some of her sister nun. We <lb/>
'town. It would be recollected that ment. Th t ean arrangement. permit him ſuly to discharge all his duties at the; <lb/>
- º d formerly petitioned the house, al. for a Hospital. The Gºvernmen were perſectly aware ºf ptoms of constitutional sentinents have not madéºn; º; <lb/>
- i..."....... one for a the numbers of patients and the nature of the d way in that empire. There has been some rioting in ſº <lb/></p> 

<p>jºin ºil of his Royal Highness was considerable time past, and he was allowed to have a ſtreated at the Hospital; and they were ſºily ºpe: ||.Taft, origin <lb/>
creditable to Air. Alams, and he ought...not to - ".. º.º.º.º.º.º.º. <lb/></p> 

<p>- ermitted to be a loser by the transaction. He gave u sºry. Their opinion upon <lb/></p> 

<p>§:...'...'..."...º. im I by Dr. Mºken, who had assured them t <lb/></p> 

<p>. was crowded with visitors, and when, being the only artist as to need 3. t <lb/></p> 

<p>in his line here, he might have realised <lb/></p> 

<p>ting <lb/>
ºl. <lb/>
at losing he eclii and advancement which at sched to, <lb/>
3 their city by the transference of the Court to Florence. <lb/>
''...}|...º.º.º.º. <lb/>
ey says: . The Cardinal passed a y mi <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>º;|ºº "º <lb/>
s <lb/></p> 

<p>necessary. By this me.ns the Hospital was well a <lb/>
... ....."...º.º. <lb/></p> 

<p>e did not see huw gue man <lb/>
uties which formerly de­ <lb/></p> 

<p>he at he would be compensated, wºlved apºn two, unless it were shown that there were <lb/>
it he rºunder the impression that he would be or fewer patients in the Hospital, and consequently less squin ... <lb/>
......". be attended tº, ile did not think that it views which they ºught tº ſºlºſº | pani, in the <lb/>
that ing. Qi aii public institutions the so y present enlighteued age; that jãºrah <lb/>
º..." ... .º.º..."...". .*. <lb/></p> 

<p>º gº, ºgº ººlºº.º.º.º. <lb/></p> 

<p>cate, <lb/></p> 

<p>At the conclusion of the ce <lb/></p> 

<p>pany present, amounting to s <lb/>
*ons, we y <lb/></p> 

<p>iness, and fle was a Joser besides. He (Alr; <lb/>
business; at Adams was promised <lb/></p> 

<p>necessaril <lb/></p> 

<p>ter, <lb/></p> 

<p>d on the south bank of ſº <lb/>
by fire on the 39th alt. <lb/>
j <lb/></p> 

<p>#..."...º.º. <lb/>
a that, he should at all events, be bºre harmless. The -<lb break="maybe"/>pºlic view taken by M. Adamº of the lining ºf intrussed the cate of thot institution <lb/></p> 

<p>i. Fºº of Wales, would be long, regarded as a | wata praºce, and he (Mr Talbot) thought | ce <lb/>
3.noſis of an auspicious event. Mr. Adams had left his that under the circuinº ºshe could nºt give is that ºne ºf <lb/>
business, which was 3 ºrs and nºtiºn when the intereºs ºf the public re. should be a ſtoniº, Githºlic ºbsician ſº hºmºsº <lb/></p> 

<p>in Ya. <lb/>
ch anxiety prevailed a <lb/></p> 

<p>another to th: Sacred <lb/></p> 

<p>was lost on the French coast <lb/></p> 

<p>or aq. The stººge theºry was started that be. near <lb/>
- from Liverpoºl, and a number of the <lb/></p> 

<p>- Rev. Superiorºnd her of <lb/>
atients were Rumin Catholics, thºre cession to their <lb/></p> 

<p>number, and <lb/>
oducing resulta's <lb/>
of society, an <lb/></p> 

<p>and had gone <lb/>
d to get iſſiographed, and had lost| quired. When there were twº medical men in charge we must hºse a Potastant and Roºm ºthºlºgy: <lb/>
jº iſ thought sºngsisitiºn was due ºne was always arrºn, hº(\l:Talbot) now to tie |ºriºtt sºlº.ºliºsº... [s <lb/>
º, hiº, and that we would be wanting is respect to the first time bºard that ºr Rºchºrd Protestant and Roma Catho; and a Protes: <lb/>
jºif we did not take the prayer of the pºlition into preventº from alºnging ºdºliº. He had never d <lb/>
eonsideration. eard any complaint of his being ... absent, if <lb/>
After some further observations by Messrs. E. D. Shea, theſe were ever any complaints, and he (Mr. Talbot) <lb/>
wº, ſºnouſ, Casey, Bºrton, Titº, and Gºa, the understºod there bººi hºyºtº, were nº -<lb break="maybe"/>jū tº ºur wº. " ":" ſº |º. <lb/>
carrie investigatiºn a short time ago; Dr. Rothfort was not | Protestant ºr a Roman Catholic rop <lb/>
subject of it. He (Mr. Talbot) did not like to a <lb/>
.*.*.*.*.*.*.*.*... . <lb/>
ute th <lb/></p> 

<p>eleven miles an hour, Four persons were lost. <lb/></p> 

<p>BY <lb/></p> 

<p>*ELEGRAPH. <lb/></p> 

<p>than <lb/></p> 

<p>EATEST Frog Tag states. " <lb/>
i New <lb/></p> 

<p>Warrews.x gave notice that, on to-mºrrow, he <lb/>
... .º.º.º. <lb/>
the petition of Q. Adams. <lb/>
". ... ºtition frºm Peter McKay <lb/>
and the other police constables of Carbonesſ, which was <lb/>
received and read, praying for an increase of sºary. <lb/>
E, in m the petition lie oa <lb/></p> 

<p>o mig ... Away Wi <lb/>
sectarian tash. Do not Rºman Catholics through­ <lb/>
out the cºuntry employ Protestaut doctors, and ºice <lb/>
versa—the only quºtion with them being as to ability <lb/>
†.º.º.º.º. <lb/>
jo. ..."jºi. <lb/>
as this—he would like to kn <lb/>
sented the <lb/></p> 

<p>believe, the whole number of <lb/>
no more than eight or nine. <lb/></p> 

<p>tro Tag £Drtoº of rite <lb/></p> 

<p>that was - º:cº.º.º.º. * * <lb/>
------ ... Carolina to endeavout to check Shennan. <lb/>
d observe that the If there was dimiant Roman Catholic constituency of their diº- "º e - he oppone <lb/>
º: .# tºº.": |jºsº.º.º.º. * * * * tº <lb/>
... to discharge; and they we us than they had hitherto been, them fºr the their district. Nºw, he ſhºº. y - }Altom, as averse to that gº <lb/></p> 

<p>A. ... hil Bºº" <lb/>
w of reason the impression that both the medical gentlemen at the #." to-day <lb/></p> 

<p>204. <lb/>
ensation for their services, sake of economy there mºght be some 8 - renc - the enlightenment and civil <lb/>
: #. ..". resp a 2-ms. Lºst in the appointment of only one Superintendent. But Hospital were Romº Catholi French have again been defeated in Mexico. jº. <lb/>
sessi #jhi ºntº a similar petition, ºn the cºntrary, the patients were ºn the increase, the take. However, it it was dº nºt; he New Yoºk, Feb. 20–P.M. nese, in their opposition, <lb/>
- *...*.*...". fiegº wºuld have no objection tº *ślsº: Cºmmittee ºf the Gen. Beauregarihas offilially announced as ºp. <lb/>
------- Supply, on account of the deficie - -<lb break="maybe"/>º, "ºº". "...º. gº." |siºi is Fºr is are now irºi; <lb/></p> 

<p>institution, nurses and others, down 10n 9 <lb/></p> 

<p>to the 'Augusta, ... . . . . <lb break="no"/>the establishmen; , Bºit ſºlº ſº; hº gº | Töm. Grant tiegraph, as follows-"The Richmºnd; <lb/>
-Ray-officiall <lb/></p> 

<p>o, <lb/></p> 

<p>tºº.º.º.º.º.º.º. ºre of Coſimº, is ºpiºi ºf sºroſiº, ºr &amp; <lb/>
§ <lb/></p> 

<p>map to attempt to deceive either the Roman Catholics | E. <lb/></p> 

<p>will be scan <lb break="no"/>was sent to the Editor by <lb/></p> 

<p>minºr of to pounces the evacua- writer, in cominenting <lb/></p> 

<p>of Harbor Grata. tant, or Protes sº of St. John's, their ºwn, ºften, ºn tº <lb/>
Air. ºf . fice should be 6 h ... ... For himself he was i. y per wº Edward Shea, in the debate <lb/>
- Uarbunear. He thou; cº 8Hould be othér - y a cer believed Gen. - º <lb/>
º well paid for the services at iie (Mr. Talbot) said this in all sincetity, for he felt e ºf the honorable members—was out of he way of - *** $º <lb/>
- - Mr. RoRKE-E45. it was just, and equitable and right. . Was it nºt nº- hºuld nº ºthi." ". . . ." Gºd opened to-day at 202and closed at 200. delivered <lb/>
Mr. Rºsour—Well, £45, stg. was goºd pay ºr in that as dread momeº, when the soul was peºple are not blººd; º unders motives - in <lb/>
were allowed to work on the wharves. Look at our quive; jiàngs of this moral world, when and the men, and the facility with which a little ex- I, O C A. E. n <lb/>
loyed jing a vulsed the bell of death, when citemeat can be got u Beigwi, Feb. 21. w <lb/>
*1 this world was fading befºre the glimpses ºf r tºney General had a very The line was down between here and Harbor Grace; for travel, the paſſeſ would nº. <lb/></p> 

<p>morning. It wa cut at Folo <lb/>
the length between three poles carried away. " <lb/></p> 

<p>operator went out, put in what wire he had taken <lb/>
with him, and returned for a reaching the <lb/>
break he found the wire he had put in an hour or two <lb/>
to return <lb/></p> 

<p>and more glºrious hereafter, that He resorted to th: Grace until the 11th, the Y <lb/>
ºul be one ming in th i.....? <lb/></p> 

<p>of t subject of a letter bearing a <lb/></p> 

<p>nt, the same day tº <lb/></p> 

<p>jº, RoREE was sorry the hon member was so badly <lb/>
informed respecting the state and duties of the Carbo­ <lb/>
r Police It was not the case that the force <lb/></p> 

<p>terests? He did nºt <lb/></p> 

<p>John's <lb/></p> 

<p>o, or time to wor <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/>
+ mot be had. attended the sufferer sh <lb/>
his eternal in <lb/></p> 

<p>- #!: ...'. ..."; to was as grea previously cut and taken away, and iſ Mr. Eitor-anºi, º, . <lb/>
£er number 0 men were away a 8 woulu ºr he appoi again for more. Altogether about seventy yards of the grass jº. <lb/>
# , numb era away at the re Protestants to have ºr, itemouf appointed to:::::::::: *º" ºr mºves in <lb/></p> 

<p>jº ºffic."f hº <lb/></p> 

<p>ee with <lb/>
He trusted the government would reco <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/>
lished. <lb/>
; <lb/></p> 

<p>f ght. But if he were there in the fºil, when they - eneral ought to be above turning us into ridicule, - <lb break="no"/>i - the . . ºfferent ..". ...: mäe ºn appointment which would H. &amp; Cº) told him º: we took as *..." in- ſhe Canadian ent met on the 19th ulio. The <lb/>
'. member 84 Fre-auxe e satisf cory t3 the co terest in our Prºtestant lºººººººº," the hon Governor-General urged Confederation in strong ---<lb break="maybe"/>--&gt; * work on the wharves—lie (Mr. Rorke):rem Mr. Casey.—If thºre neral did. He (Mr Casey) wanted no, ..urg -<lb break="maybe"/>| | jº.º.º.º.º.º.: ...º.º. #:..."... . ."..."...". *...*.*.*.*.*.*.*. ..... <lb/>
- # jºsº wºrk on bºard a vessel. He knew that they had h. anºther, it was Cºcº and he ºpiºijº ºligºte, ºpted by ºily tº i; ły return their sincer­ <lb/>
*: * (ºne ºfteºrºwo, pºtººs whº indulged in wrº only place in the eº ºne son Štúra; General was bound to carry szinst 17, conſideration is cºnsidered virtually "ºf £etty Harbºr ºf the <lb/>
t #:;...";..."...; and disea:*:::::::: ºuld in cºin in a Lºcºmº "sºn" <lb/>
- f ti --- ----neº- • petition W is cer --s t. 'the - - -<lb break="maybe"/>- j, ..."...". .*.*.*.*.*.*. membu, pºke giani, but nºted to, and tº <lb/>
- - the Revd. Mr. Winterbotham. Would these gentiemen MAILs per Merºn for Ha <lb/></p> 

<p>... m. "... the may of noi. vote on the subject was therefore unanimºusly <lb/>
favourable <lb/>
Mr. Tatbot was not influenced by a feeling for an wa -<lb break="maybe"/>jº: ...º.º.º.º.º.º. <lb/>
.*.*.*.*.*.*, j ºf seatin the Executive Council on the grºund tº <lb/>
jºin ºth. ..., &amp; nºiſ no j could not support Confederation. The Assembly hº <lb/>
the public. If two medical men had not been required been dissolved, to appeal to the country on this que: <lb/>
why had they been kept there?. He thought it was <lb/>
excu <lb/></p> 

<p>certify to the character and services of the pºlice force, there. There <lb/>
if they did not consider them deserving, rºm typhus fever, and <lb/>
Ir, Casey.—For his part he did not see the necessity to the present Government that there should <lb/>
for such a large police force in Carbonear—Carboneur one attendant. No one doubted that ge <lb/>
was a peaceable place. Tae, Stipendiary Magistrale, it msn's ability, but he had a large prix <lb/>
had been stated was engaged in trade, and was a sent | could he interests of the jugliº <lb/>
ths whole summer; and when policemen were wanted <lb/>
they were three or four miles from. Iown, cultiva <lb/></p> 

<p>aſternoon at 8 o'clock—late <lb/>
until half-past 3, <lb/></p> 

<p>=­ <lb/>
Maghreb, Jan 12, at St Matth <lb/>
#. *::::::::::::::: <lb/>
5, of 13 Canonbury-place e <lb/>
ſº...";". <lb/></p> 

<p>§ <lb/></p> 

<p>q <lb/>
and Mr.Tilley was confident that the result would, <lb/></p> 

<p>baurs, which necessarily occupied a grºat part ºn ------ to Ball <lb/>
tº º |:::::::::::: *****|†º * ...W.;; <lb/>
#.:*::::::::::::::... .º.º.º.º. Tº It is not proposed to lºssolve in Nova Scotia," <lb/>
jº º is: i.i.d.º.º.º iſ , , ºn Arrºyº gº tº nº the gºvernment had nº doubt ºf ºnes Gaº" <lb/></p> 

<p>PASSExq: <lb/></p> 

<p>po iceaman economy in i t instance. "I was a maxim and on leave granted, brºught in the following Bills, ti <lb/>
... ... .;..... tºyºs' " <lb/></p> 

<p>no rity in both Houses, -<lb break="maybe"/>-n made respects­ <lb/></p> 

<p>b -<lb break="maybe"/>uid be had; laid dowa by the hon the Premier when he "I which we - Per Merli <lb break="no"/>by the present efficient it. . . . . . ." ..., ºf colour. Tº ſºling ºne changºlianº.; i.º.º.º. <lb/>
lººke re;;::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: ###:::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::iº ºi ºniºiº. <lb/>
traº's health readered his absence necessary duringine | dons. The late incumbent was a Bonan Catholic, and in certain cases." favourable, |;: *­ <lb/>
- # <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Tº = <lb/></p> 

<p>* * * T. H.E. N.E.W. F.O.U.N. D. L.A.N.D. E. R. '' <lb/></p> 

<p>::::::::::::::::: nd FRESENTATION COXVENT. Sale by Auction. Notice. Notices, <lb break="no"/>:... .....…..…. . tº THIS DAY, a A GENERAL MEETING..."...º.º. ... <lb/>
**, *, *, *, *.i. º platei º;; Thººl, ſº second, ſhird, ºr fourth periods of five <lb/>
on the forfeiture of certain recogni. fººt <lb/></p> 

<p>... Jere <lb/>
-- - - - - recede from the period at which the lives were ac, <lb/>
ble Courts of Law to give relief agains ãºsived the nami, ...i. 100 Qrs, fresh BEEF - W. *.…...: ceped, º * * * º <lb/>
*::::::::::::::::::::: º!"; }; i."; Life Assiſrahe: €9mpany|º. <lb/>
i such claims, º. rls, prime PQRK - - clined tº reduce their Rates. These Rates were <lb/>
these Bills be severally read a second .#...'...". x * Merlin" from Halifax. -<lb break="maybe"/>'The ... ºr, ..."ºº­ <lb/></p> 

<p>5 Bris. White BEANS, <lb/>
February 23. <lb/></p> 

<p>was HELD witHis rāE iſ ori <lb/>
COMPANY'S OFFICE, 5, GEOR3E STREET, <lb/></p> 

<p>o a jºurned until to-morrow at the - *EDINBURGH, <lb/>
ON THURSDAY. THE 15FR OF DECEMBER, <lb/></p> 

<p>8! <lb/>
pecially the <lb/></p> 

<p>- with presented at once, an imposing and graceſ, <lb/>
At the appointed hºur the Right Rev. Dr. <lb/></p> 

<p>- attended e Very Rev. ixe-n an <lb/>
ſtºſºmimºr. ºš <lb/>
- - ºfterwards commenced the celebration of the Mass. <lb/></p> 

<p>CEIVE THE <lb/></p> 

<p>To RE ºth <lb/>
Report by the Board of Directors; <lb/>
0x re. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºngratulations on the h <lb/></p> 

<p>x rete -<lb break="maybe"/>Ixwest IGATION OF THE Coxip ANys? <lb/></p> 

<p>ºcess which ha -<lb break="maybe"/>- - pany's ºperations during the last five years <lb/>
ST. JOH.W.?.S.: ſº: - AFFAIRS'AxD DiVISION OF º: "..."..."; i.'...; <lb/>
;DAY, FEBRUARY. 23, 1865. . fally dispº,; blº, with hiºye. PROFITS, AS AT 25Th existencº. <lb break="no"/>;...; AY, 1864, By Order of the Directors, <lb/>
ners ospray and Merlin arri .*.*.*.*.*.*. - - WILL THOS. THOMSON," <lb/>
- - r e e, the Bishop, GEORG&amp; Motº, Esq., Adrocate Stirli <lb break="no"/>g from Halifax di on th #|SEAºNºº, ºi, ogº ºf §:::::::::::::::::: Actua <lb/></p> 

<p>D. cluxle GREGoñº"? <lb/>
Secretary. <lb/></p> 

<p>º:|..." i. ºº: Einiº <lb/>
----- hip dwelt at great persons willing to enter into Contracts for the under- - e <lb/>
|English dates bein 8 wº #. Service the Rºyal, ENGINEER THE PROFITS REALISED ..] Edinburgh, 15th December, 1864. <lb/></p> 

<p>9x THE WHARF of - .0F-ºrah: ...;;....j}. | <lb/>
Clift, Wood &amp; Co., + Colonial; ºi. º: <lb/></p> 

<p>so occupied with the Legislative de. ness and force three Years puring the period from 25th May 1859 to 25th Ms. <lb/>
an only find room at present for the and spiri ... [. *::::::: ****** * *::::::::::::::::: NEW FOUNH)4, A.N.D. <lb/>
tracts which follow, but the home the previous six months which she .."...º.º.;: ... º: tº . I. O'B HEAD OFFICE, SE, JOHNS. <lb/>
ed to the ration were months ics being given mg 8tatement w W this result 13 'Brien, Esq., Mercha <lb break="no"/>voted to the necessary preparation for the life on 9 º "** by frºm the calculations:– rien, Esq., Merchant Wm. Henry M. <lb/></p> 

<p>she was then about to enter—six months spºn <lb/>
d directio <lb/></p> 

<p>* | either <lb/>
n 1,--Timbe <lb/></p> 

<p>portant:­ <lb/>
at Leeds and Manchester drew forth <lb/>
reform.The olī s* <lb/></p> 

<p>tus W. Harvey, Esq., Merchant, <lb/>
derth ruction an r &amp;c. - - <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>m3 of refºrm. is war: in .:****** **, r* . f all Medical Adviser-Henry Hunt Stabb, M.D. - -<lb break="maybe"/>ºly novely being the spiech ºf Ead ..º.º.º.º.º. . . .2–1.jme, Sand, Bricks, Cement, &amp;c. ... Agent, F. J. W.Y.A.T.T.: <lb/>
...'...}. 3—Plulubers. Painters and Glaziers 8 "|&amp;#39; 14 11| Fºnº, jº - º <lb/></p> 

<p>- work and \{aterials. 1. |z221,154 is a —- |-------<lb break="maybe"/></p> 

<p>.*.*.*.*. 4—Smiths Work and supply of Iron- 82,665 17 1 Athenæum ſectures. <lb/></p> 

<p>we and offin. - - - - mongery. 1,807 9 -<lb break="maybe"/>ards tion frºm world.y cares and vanities, or return again As enºmerated in the respective Schedules which with 33 *HE An - i. <lb/>
ow very fikely to adjast the di her former state 32d mingle in the concerts of itions of Contract may be seen at the Office ,20i 19 rºl.ºhiºhit <lb/></p> 

<p>*"...º.º.º. dº ſº. º.º.º.º.º.º.:* - will Commence on MONDAY the 16th January, at <lb/></p> 

<p>the Temperance Hall, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Feb. 27—R.J. Kent, Esq.-Subject—The Ironbuke. <lb/></p> 

<p>*º-ºº-ººrºº: <lb/></p> 

<p>ºf Wehluce <lb/></p> 

<p>Maisºn, sº ºn. <lb/>
others will be announced in due course. Each <lb/></p> 

<p>Lecture will commence at 8 o'clock,-Daois open at <lb/>
uarter past Seven, <lb/></p> 

<p>*Hºº: 15,407 iſ 7 <lb/>
he Tenders to express the prices at per cent above ºr r <lb/>
º::::::::::::::::::::::"...º. - 351,237 15 11 <lb/>
lims, and ts be addressed to the Senior Cozmissariat <lb/></p> 

<p>inct ºn 3W <lb/>
Prussia the elements of happiness or <lb/>
* a threatening form; and tie Parli <lb/></p> 

<p>ecurity tº the amount of £100 Sterling, will be re­ <lb/>
quired for the due fulfilment of each of the Cantrac: <lb/>
Payment will be made guarterly in Bills on Her <lb/></p> 

<p>*.*.*. *:::::::::::: ...","...". _* * * <lb/>
"...º.º. sho! § t a local Bank it under that sum. Remains,.....! #63,456 19 0 <lb/>
: over the Cºurt. In A33. ºp's ºf anº. ºr ran:, ..., Add Rum mº - - <lb break="no"/>... ... ºº::::::..º.º.º.º.º.º. tº: º:::::::::::::::::::::::" <lb/>
.. ... ." the present interesting occasiºn with - #;| intº ºut atti investigatº, 10.125 0 0 D. W. PRowse, <lb/>
the *.*.*...; Depart | Total Profits of period, from 25th January 5, Secretary <lb/></p> 

<p>pant comp <lb/>
Sisters. The Reception music, which was from De <lb/>
Monti, was also admirably executed, <lb/>
At the conclusion of the ceremony the whole com­ <lb/>
pany present, amounting to some four hundred per­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Aisy 1859 to 25th Atay, 1864 || 473,581. 19 0 <lb/>
- LAN CASHIRE <lb/>
Insurance Company. <lb/></p> 

<p>toll <lb/></p> 

<p>#eatre, situated on the south bank of <lb/>
was destroyed by fire on the 30thull. <lb/></p> 

<p>pIVISION OF PROFITS. <lb/>
ivil the above sum of <lb/></p> 

<p>::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: FIRE AND LIFE <lb/>
:::::::::::::::::::::: *:::::::::::::::::::::"... " "...º." - <lb break="no"/>... ."... . º;...º.º. º. º.º.º.º.º. º: *::::: ****"... . . . capital, woºloss stentisa. <lb/>
# ºr j:::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: ***. Fu, tº;; <lb/></p> 

<p>• mail steamere have recently been lost. i. º; s.". *... *** **, *, ** Tºjº <lb/></p> 

<p>Nº. <lb/></p> 

<p>itón market, that staple falli <lb/></p> 

<p>Head office: Exchange-Street, Manchester. <lb/>
OF DIRECTORs: <lb/></p> 

<p>R <lb/></p> 

<p>John Todd, Esq., Chairman, <lb/></p> 

<p>illiam H. Bradley, Esq.; William Pilkington, Esq.; <lb/>
Esq. Blackburn <lb/></p> 

<p>Peat or Bag Earth from the ----- -<lb break="maybe"/>sºlº; <lb/>
... "...","...'. ...","...] ...º. <lb/></p> 

<p>for the tenant ºf the signal Hill Farm, to dig ted <lb/>
been opened since || Ale <lb/>
... <lb/></p> 

<p>C <lb/>
6 feel glad that their la- | . For the right of rein <lb/>
h <lb/></p> 

<p>carry Axay any Peat or Bog, Earth required for <lb/></p> 

<p>manurug 'he said fºrm, but for no other purposes. -<lb break="maybe"/>rties iemuering wº. be .."...ount: ºlay 1839, and the piectors: <lb/></p> 

<p>- all numberin ney may be ugpo r in ste ling mon tinue this rate, which was that giveſ at the l <lb/>
Y TELEGRAPH.::::::::::::::::::::" ºrºº::::::::::::::::::::::::: n, <lb/>
- - which the Right Rev. Dr. Mu heir punctual payment ºf the same quarterly sºlº given the ºiest ºf Division ºf Profits with |j. Robinson Ray, Esq., Edward wanklyn, Esq. <lb/>
:ST FROM THE STATES, " tºy, a period of less that twenty years, when, we ... Fºrms of ſºde will be ſurnishid on applicatiºn at '.... ºils.; in M. Barton Wood, Esq. <lb/>
New York; Feb. 17–P.M. ber of nuns in the country was the Cºmmissatia; office, or at the Office ºf the Com. º;|2. Sº <lb/>
ºnent has received information that the or dime, * * **ś. - ...;; George Stewart, General Manager. <lb/>
pººl ºn Cºleº --- ..º.º.º. tº * **** as fair a method in the sºil. <lb/>
º, * * [to THE EDITOR of THE NewfoundLANDER.j º, - .*.*.*.*.*, *, *. <lb/>
ºn, it sºuth Monday, Feb. 20. t, John's, 16th Yeb., 1865, - ention to the Statements - THE <lb break="no"/>"..."...":"...g., . sº-wºº.º.º.º. *** g.º.º. SYSTEM AND REGULATIONS <lb/>
... " * occupation o to disgraceful falsehººd to introduce the name of Dr. A. Wigh Nº. tº: jº." of rhiz: <lb/>
tº. #º Last Night for the Season 1 ||º] Life.Association of Scotland <lb/>
nave again been defeated in Mexico. elightenment and civilisation of the 19th cen: - duce their Rates for various climates, and they have, <lb break="no"/>.. É'.*** * fact rotten- FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE POOR. sºley were sound to jo, give ºppºſi; ººlºº 4880i4Nº. 4MP.4 wºulºs <lb/></p> 

<p>New York, Feb. 20–P.M. <lb/></p> 

<p>most serious consideration; but <lb/></p> 

<p>i.;;|...}. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºrihu ºftily nº ºp- This morning'sbay-Book publishes a letter, purport. the arguments brought forward, and studying with the utmost value for their pagments; a 6 pro­ <lb/>
*...*.*.*.*:::::::,;;; º: º; *º: §:...'"; º: ºº:: <lb/></p> 

<p>re no instant, but from the fºllowing statement of facts it º - tent Pº <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>- ill be se at the 88. - catiºn, an a to authorise their making the sed reduction. mall Qu Policy-hoºdër. <lb/>
dº......, n.d.º.º. º f is H E R mº's Hai..., |º] sº <lb/>
-day officially announces the evacua- The writer, i º: "ºf...". + less at lower. Premiums, in many places. and Freedom frºm any Extra Charges for Occupation or <lb/>
top on Thursday last." jº.º.º.º. QN THIS THURSDAY, Night, º.º. º. p <lb/>
ºleº's army ſum ºr seventy perd war. Shea in the ºn tº jail. When the following will be produced—The very t -- #... .º.º.º. <lb/>
a Gen. Lee contemplates the evacuation $º. that#. .; º to it. interesting and exciting Drama, in 3 Acts, §. f º .... . ledg Exemption from the Risks of Partnership. <lb/>
- - - 8 ºpeech of Mir, Shea w88 º ...". * | rivii; associatio -<lb break="maybe"/>to-day at 202,and closed at 200, ºº:: Ti *:::::::::::::::::::::::::::"...º.º. Tº..."...º.º. º <lb/>
I () &amp; A. L. finia; the gº, hºps. . it. - * @rphan ºf Geneva, , , ..."...'...."..., |y|...}º. <lb/>
BRIGUs, Feb. 21. *ś ºiºninº. jº".|:.. d the benefit. Small institutions - <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Grace <lb/>
, and <lb/>
6. <lb/></p> 

<p>hown between here and Harbor <lb/>
it was found cut at Fºley's Hill <lb/>
een three poles carried away. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºut, put in what wire he had taken <lb/></p> 

<p>- - *: *** gºvº. , ºffices, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>ºjº. With beautiful stage effects ºf in ºngºfiºn ºrii ºff Tºlsºn. Amºlºyº Decessed <lb/></p> 

<p>until the fith, the very earliest possible time The wholeſ toº. sia::::::...'...'... .". Pol £rº, amount. ,000 <lb/>
had of a debate which is the The whole: to concl - to a matrow circle, may transact business on lower to ............................ ...: #2600 <lb/></p> 

<p>..".: The ºld wºmatºring Farce||...",". continuance of such | jiàº'ài. 3.; <lb/></p> 

<p>during the lives of the Assured, but with these; amongs Policy-holders during their life <lb/></p> 

<p>Colonial Union. <lb/>
ºned to dissºlve in Nova Scotia, and <lb/></p> 

<p>Grace the ºn: ...a...? air- -<lb break="maybe"/>sturned for more. Quº reachiºg the *:::::::::: The Hillerick Bºy. Hºº::iº ... 3234,000 <lb/>
- -- *...." -- By kind p ion of Capt. Wright, the Brass compet They have their local advantages, and The Accumulated Fund Reserved on hand -<lb break="maybe"/>ºjº.º.º.º.º.º. Ball ºf the jºyal Artillery will aſſini. may be preferred by those more especially who can , amount to... ....... 3.853,000 <lb/>
º, and was was has had his valentine ºr Tickets of Ádmission–Fromiseau, or Balcony, tº part ºf anagement and ºth ºver thºr |All he ººlºº <lb/>
t fak'sºs is 3d. . . . . . . . ºngº, Bºhº, ºne ºhº iºn. Intelº ºn investmeº is <lb/>
-- OBSERVER, Lash's and the Bookstores. ks fºrward with prudent anxiety to the future, long upwards ºf:::::::::: £220,000 <lb/>
mit on the 19,h ulto, The - t?, C is, at soft 'erred as the lifetime of an individual may be, the jJivisiox of Pitoriis. <lb/>
ſal urged Confederation in strong THE º, ºne º 'º. ...º.º.º. , ............: <lb/>
Aidress of the Assembly in reply to fiends ºf the lº Captain Jºhn Bunk; most || Hºrrºr-nº-r jj .*.*.*.*.*.*.*.*.*.*.*.*. <lb/>
g been adopted by a majority of 70 respectful:y return their sincers thanks to the inhab. *ś §ºss,; ..º.º.º." ny as in Eli #;;..."º: ...; <lb/>
ºnfederation is considered virtually * ºf Fetty Harbor ºf their kind estion, in re. I Hºf; ... }; flººmingº is ºfton not to fliº: in fact receiving back; every year, that porti <lb/>
. In the Legislative Council two *ing from the deep his body and that of his son. i.º.º.º.º.º. § {º fºur-hº ºwn ºn musiunie <lb/>
against it, but none voted so, and the --- fººt |...","..."...ſ.. . In Class B, the Profits are allºcated by way of Ad. <lb/>
subject was therefore unanimously ..º.º. ºil. i.i. I am authorized to raise by . . as to the Sumº Assured. by way <lb/>
*ſternoon at 3 o'clock—late letters will be received Twenty-three Thousand and 6tr NG POLICIES <lb/>
- - o ti iring them wo the world, * umě-a88ured sha <lb/>
sk, Mr. Hatheway had resigned his until half-past 3. Seven . "... .#. "..." 8 Wor the lapse .*.*.*.*.*. łł <lb/>
ve Council on d Yºº jº.". "j";º. um. <lb/>
rt Confederation. The Å ha an 12, a - ing Interest a ºf pad increased very considerably, during the period o ATE ſex ſitàx is on the profit schem <lb/>
º: ... ºff tºº gº, ºligº, ... .** |::::::::::::::::::::...'...'...}|si"...º. <lb/>
... #: *:::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: ...º.º.º.º. º. 46 to 1839| Eater Entrants." <lb/>
ey was confident that the result w to Susanna §: thirãº..*.*.*.*. Giºiº. WESãº Great 8 ºme e last Indies <lb break="no"/>General W. Infantry <lb/></p> 

<p>arch next, from pe:80 ing to lead money fo jº <lb/>
ng, Royal Marine Light - #ºviščiaiº |º <lb/>
Çum <lb/></p> 

<p>º: NEWFoux bºxid BRANCH, <lb/>
creast:3 re;3 er HEAſ) <lb/></p> 

<p>the abºe perio ... Jørix '8. <lb/></p> 

<p>Flº-S <lb/>
Diºcrºi. <lb/>
* H. K. Dickingpº, jº. James cormick, t <lb/></p> 

<p>- ade's must express how many Dollars will be <lb/></p> 

<p>had no doubt of carrying Confeder" - sº for every Qūe Hundred jjøllars. <lb/>
es <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>majority in both Hou P PASSENGERs. ºut ºf pairwin it - ...º.º. lººk <lb/>
inst the change eontinues wery strong. ºr Merlin from Haifax-Mesºs.g. Bennett, Lord * - in ...] Medical Officer. W. C.8imms, M.D. <lb/>
.."... lºº" *... the first §: . * - "..., <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>