<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-03" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1869-02-03">3 February 1869</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1869-02-05"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-05_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2019-01-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2019-01-07">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-05_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-05_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-05_Page_2.jpg"/>

<fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>

<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, Feb. 3.</p>
    
<p>The House met at 3 o'clock. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName> and <persName ref="pers:PARS1">Mr. PARSONS</persName> called the atten<lb break="no"/>tion of the House to the system of issuing tickets of <lb/>
admission to the House. Hon. members were <lb/>
daily pestered with applicants for tickets, to the <lb/>
serious interruption of their business. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> assured hon. members that he <lb/>
would endeavour to have the matter satisfactorily <lb/>
arranged. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
On motion of <persName ref="pers:GODD1">Mr. GODDEN</persName>, pursuant to order of <lb/>
the day, the House resolved itself into Committee of <lb/>
the Whole on the Address of thanks to His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency the Governor, Mr. KNIGHT in the chair. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The first paragraph was then read and adopted. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The secoid paragraph having been read. <lb/></p>
        
        <p><persName ref="pers:PARS1">Mr. PARSONS</persName> said the first paragraph of this <lb/>
Address purposes to thank His Excellency for his <lb/>
gracious speech, and for the uniform courtesy which <lb/>
He has exhibited to this Assembly. Where <choice><sic>conld</sic><corr>could</corr></choice> <lb/>
one find a greater illustration, of the happy state of <lb/>
affairs existing in Newfoundland? For the past <lb/>
five years, we have been dwelling in the utmost <lb/>
peace and harmony. One would fancy that the <lb/>
millennium had arrived. Now what occasion was <lb/>
there to thank His Excellency for this? His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency was certainly a very graceful gentleman; but <lb/>
it as rather ridiculous to offer him the solemn <lb/>
thanks of the House because he had refrained from <lb/>
<choice><sic>pulilng</sic><corr>pulling</corr></choice> the hon. the Premier by the nose, and <lb/>
because he did not kick the Executive Council out <lb/>
of Government House. Gracious Speech, forsooth. <lb/>
Was it not high time to get rid of this nonsense? <lb/>
He (Mr. P) could see nothing, for which to thank <lb/>
His excellency in so special and peculiar a manner. <lb/>
The second paragraph of the Address read as <lb/>
follows:<lb/></p>
    
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>We fully approve of the course taken by the <lb/>
Executive Government in issuing the Proclamation <lb/>
in June last, that relief in future would be confined to <lb/>
destitute widows and orphans, and to the sick and <lb/>
infirm poor. We believe this act well timed, and <lb/>
we cordially hope and trust that the Executive may <lb/>
be successful in its efforts to suppress the demora<lb break="no"/>lizing system of able-bodied pauper relief." <lb/></p>
        </quote>
    
        <p>
Now there was not a single human being in the <lb/>
country to whom the course pursued by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment could commend itself. He (Mr. P.) did <choice><sic>no</sic><corr>not</corr></choice> <lb/>
deny the demoralizing influence of pauper relief, <lb/>
but he certainly did contend that Government <lb/>
before cutting off from the people the only source <lb/>
maintenance on which they had relied, should have <lb/>
furnished them with some means of supporting <lb/>
themselves and their families. But hon. gentlemen <lb/>
opposite cared little how deeply the country might <lb/>
be steeped in poverty, so long as they could save <lb/>
the Revenue. £30,000 have been annually expend<lb break="no"/>ed, and Government had shown no anxiety to obtain <lb/>
any return for this enormous outlay. Every man <lb/>
who applied for relief was received and welcomed; <lb/>
no inquiry was made, and indiscriminate charity was <lb/>
issued broadcast, and why? Because hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men, members of the Executive were importers of <lb/>
Indian meal and molasses. The hon. the Premier <lb/>
purchased meal from the hon. Mr. this, and molas<lb break="no"/>ses from the hon. Mr. that, though he himself was <lb/>
the introducer of the Placemen's Act, by which <lb/>
Government contractors were made ineligible as <lb/>
legislators. And whose money had hon. gentlemen <lb/>
been expending? The pauper's own money. Not <lb/>
a man but had paid for every fraction of the pittance <lb/>
which he received, in money or in labour, in sweat, <lb/>
in peril, aye and in death. The speculation of hon. <lb/>
gentlemen opposite was a good one. An Executive <lb/>
Councillor had only to trade upon his politics, let <lb/>
his stock in trade be meal and molasses; let him <lb/>
fill up the interstices with strategy, and he could <lb/>
not fail to succeed. Upon the second paragraph <lb/>
he (Mr. P.) had to propose an amendment, which <lb/>
was as follows:— <lb/></p>
    
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>While we admit the necessity of the large outlay under the <lb/>
head of relief for the able bodied poor, we cannot refrain <lb/>
from expressing our disapproval of the injudicious mode <lb/>
in which such outlaw was effected; and our regret that no <lb/>
remedial measures had been adopted by the Government <lb/>
to relieve the evils accruing to the poor from its sudden <lb/> 
stoppage. <lb/></p>
    </quote>
    
    <p>
In his speech his Excellency's says that "notwith<lb break="no"/>standing all the guards" at the disposal of the <lb/>
Government, the drain upon the revenue was an<lb break="no"/>nually increasing. What "guards" did his <lb/>
Excellency refer to? The only guard he required <lb/>
was honesty, rectitude of purpose; but unfortu<lb break="no"/>nately that was not fortheoming. He contended <lb/>
that if this £30,000 had been spent in the employ<lb break="no"/>ment of the fisherinen of the country, after the <lb/>
completion of their hard summer's labour, there <lb/>
would not have been a pauper in the country. He <lb/>
believed that the outcry about the condition of <lb/>
the country was merely got up to frighten the <lb/>
people into Confederation. It was true, the times <lb/>
were bad, but they had been bad before now. <lb/>
So long as we have to import the commonest ne<lb break="no"/>cessaries of life, there will be paupers. But if this <lb/>
£30,000 had been employed in assisting the poor <lb/>
fisherman to cultivate his homestead, how different <lb/>
would the result have been? Five acres of land <lb/>
were sufficient to maintain a poor man and his <lb/>
family. Let the poor man till his land, and with <lb/>
the wealth which God sends him from the sea, he <lb/>
will make a comforthble subsistence. Never was <lb/>
a country more blessed by Providence, and yet <lb/>
we could daily hear it denounced, merely for the <lb/>
purpose of debasing the people of the country, and <lb/>
making them believe that a change was required, <lb/>
and that for that change we must look abroad, and <lb/>
not within ourselves. Doubtless a change was <lb/>
necessary, but the change must be radical and in<lb break="no"/>ternal, not from without. The poor man of the <lb/>
country, who, as he pays no taxes, is unaffected <lb/>
by taxation, might ask what he could lose by Con<lb break="no"/>federation. Now, at least, he possesses the in<lb break="no"/>alienable birth right of British freedom. Under <lb/>
this nefarious union he would be curtailed of his <lb/>
liberty. Why, he would hardly be allowed to <lb/>
sneeze. Let the men of money look to it, then. <lb/>
They must necessarily be affected by this scheme. <lb/>
Oppressive taxation would press them down. <lb/>
Cauada would tax their food, their clothes, their <lb/>
beds, their boats, their nets, their hooks and their <lb/>
lines. She would tax everything they possessed <lb/>
when living, and their coffins after they were <lb/>
dead. The able bodied poor want you to open up <lb/>
the resources of the county, and not to give them <lb/>
yellow meal. The hon, member then referred to <lb/>
the importance of our fisheries, and contended <lb/>
that the Government should foster and protect this <lb/>
branch of our industry. He pictured the miseries <lb/>
of those who were without food, and stigmatised <lb/>
the Proclamation of the Government relative to <lb/>
poor relief as the most cruel and despotic act that <lb/>
ever emanated from the most despostic of Govern<lb break="no"/>ments. He begged therefore to propose the amend<lb break="no"/>ment which he had read. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:PINS2">MR. PINSENT</persName>.—The Speech with which the <lb/>
Governor has opened the present session of the <lb/>
Legislature is one of more than ordinary import<lb break="no"/>ance. It is the first, in fact in the career of <lb/>
the present Government, which has been mark<lb break="no"/>ed with a decisive policy, upon the two great <lb/>
questions of Poor Relief and Confederation. It <lb/>
gives us some very important and, so far satis<lb break="no"/>factory, information, upon the French Shore <lb/> 
<cb/>
question: and the provisions made for the <lb/>
Mail service are such as give promise of greater <lb/>
efficiency, comfort and convenience, under the <lb/>
Inman, than under the Cunard Contract; and <lb/>
for these matters much credit was due to the <lb/>
Executive and to the Governor himself. <lb/>
With reference to the Proclamation designed to <lb/>
suppress the "gigantic evils" which have been <lb/>
produced by an ill regulated system of Pauper <lb/>
Relief, he was disposed to think that, in the <lb/>
absence of positive measures for the improve<lb break="no"/>ment of the condition of the people, the Execu<lb break="no"/>tive has done wisely in, so far at least, with<lb break="no"/>holding its hand. Whether consistently with <lb/>
the calls of humanity, and without the substitu<lb break="no"/>tion of some new mode of succour, this sudden <lb/>
and radical change can be continued throughout <lb/>
the coming three months, is now a question <lb/>
the responsibility of which rests more with this <lb/>
House than with the Government. This admin<lb break="no"/>istration seems to have failed, and he knew of <lb/>
no other that could succeed, nor had he heard <lb/>
any serious plan suggested by any party or <lb/>
person in the Legislature or out of it, for the <lb/>
amelioration of this country and its people, by <lb/>
the use solely of any nueans within ourselves. <lb/>
The Opposition can suggest none. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName>.—We are not the Executive. <lb/>
        We are not paid for it,—you are. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:PINS2">Mr. PINSENT</persName>.—No, and he was not a member <lb/>
of the Government, nor was he paid, but he con<lb break="no"/>sidered that it was no less his duty, and that of <lb/>
every member of the House, in the faithful dis<lb break="no"/>charge of his obligations to the people, in their <lb/>
present straits to devise and suggest positive <lb/>
measures of amelioration, if he could. If he <lb/>
could not, it showed that there were none to <lb/>
offer. How were the representatives of the <lb/>
people to demonstrate their fitness to rule, and <lb/>
to succeed to Government, unless they manifest<lb break="no"/>ed a capacity to do that which those in power <lb/>
failed to do. But this Proclamation was con<lb break="no"/>demned by the amendment of the hon. member, <lb/>
Mr. Parsons. The policy of the Government <lb/>
is denounced to-day by the Opposition, which <lb/>
yesterday unanimously declared its approval of <lb/>
that policy in this respect, and took credit <lb/>
to itself for having instigated and forced <lb/>
it, and of initiating a course so creditable. <lb/>
He supposed this change of opinion arose from <lb/>
the change of leadership. The hon. leader Mr. <lb/>
Glen, did not approve of the non-relief plan <lb/>
for which he was such an advocate. Was the <lb/>
hon. member Mr. Parsons, really in earnest, in <lb/>
condemning the Government for their action <lb/>
in checking this ill-regulated system of Poor <lb/>
Relief? And yet he offers no other remedy in <lb/>
the House, and he has never suggested any <lb/>
remedial measures but the Torbay Factory Bill, <lb/>
and Steam Bait skiff, and he has shewn no out<lb break="no"/>side activity in public charities, in associations <lb/>
for relief. He could not claim the credit that <lb/>
attached to the gallant Major, who is the active <lb/>
Secretary of an extensive Benevolent Institution, <lb/>
nor to the hon. member for St. John's West, <lb/>
Mr. Biennan, who, no doubt, subscribed liberal<lb break="no"/>ly. Reflections had been cast upon members <lb/>
of the Government, who were said to have in<lb break="no"/>properly profited by the distribution of pauper <lb/>
relief; and others, who were said to have absorbed <lb/>
the greater part. It was a grave imputation, <lb/>
which rested on the unsupported assertion of the <lb/>
hon. member, which could not be proved by the <lb/>
public accounts. If any fraud of that kind could <lb/>
be proved, he (Mr. P.) would be sorry to sup<lb break="no"/>port such an administration. He believed this <lb/>
coarge was unsupported in fact. The general <lb/>
system of Poor Relief had been defective; but <lb/>
no more so lately than before. The men <lb/>
accused if using these means of rapacity <lb/>
had stopped it. But as to the Proclamation, <lb/>
the view he (Mr. P.) took was that the Procla<lb break="no"/>mation may limit the Governmental ex<lb break="no"/>penditure, but cannot eradicate pauper-relief. <lb/>
The Government may, by the hard lesson of <lb/>
aggavated adversity, teach a greater measure, of <lb/>
thrift and self reliance, and some good may <lb/>
this be done, but there is a limit to all this. We <lb/>
must, while we refuse to aid, devise, if we can, <lb/>
the means and opportunities for improvement <lb/>
and industry. Mark the present con<lb break="no"/>dition of this country. We are truly <lb/>
told in the speech from the throne that the past <lb/>
year has been unmarked by disaster or epidemic <lb/>
disease, that both fisheries and the crops have <lb/>
been attended with good average results, that <lb/>
the price of provisions has been moderate. Where <lb/>
are the corresponding effects, where the results <lb/>
we should naturally look for from such a state <lb/>
of things, in the comfort, the independence, <lb/>
and happiness of the people? Is not the con<lb break="no"/>dition of the working classes the reverse of these <lb/>
three? Is it not deplorable? Is there a mem<lb break="no"/>ber of this House, a very large proportion of <lb/>
whose constituents is not in a wretchedly destitute <lb/>
state? Our duties had already been reduced <lb/>
to little better than a pauper-relief agency; and <lb/>
honorable members are, by the policy of <lb/>
the Government, as indicated in its Proclama<lb break="no"/>tion, deprived even of that privilege. But, con<lb break="no"/>soling reflectien, we have the luxury of Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government, this magnificent travesty of <lb/>
of the British Constitution, King, Lords and <lb/>
Commons; and yet how many hon. members <lb/>
are there that would like to see the man who <lb/>
could say of the mace—"take away this bau<lb break="no"/>ble," and who would knock the pillars of the <lb/>
Constitution about our ears; and it this were, <lb/>
or could be done, and the civil expenditure were <lb/>
reduced to any such short of a degradation of <lb/>
the public service, are the people to beuefit sub<lb break="no"/>stantially by a mere political administrative <lb/>
change of that sort? The folly of this was <lb/>
forcibly demonstrated the other day, when it <lb/>
was shown that if £25,000 could be saved out <lb/>
of £32,000, (which in itself was a simple ab<lb break="no"/>surdity, and merely putting it so) and the amount <lb/>
distributed amongst the fishermen, it would <lb/>
not improve their condition if they got it, <lb/>
being only twenty shillings a year, and yet some <lb/>
such a plan, falling very short of even so much <lb/>
good, appears to be the only suggestion that the <lb/>
most reductive wisdom in this House can make. <lb/>
    
    <cb/>

Not that he (Mr. P.) deprecated, for he would <lb/>
        commend judicious economy—it would be good; <lb/>
so far as it went. What are we to do then? <lb/>
Shall we try beyond ourselves when the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity is offered? When we find the whole <lb/>
trade and industry of the country, and with <lb/>
those its general condition, in an unhealthy an <lb/>
demoralised state, and going from bad to worse <lb/>
year by year, in the presence of comparative <lb/>
abundance, shall we halt or hesitate in our <lb/>
choice, between enduring the irramediable ills <lb/>
and sufferings we have, and entering upon a <lb/>
new order of things, in which there can be no <lb/>
possible risk of aggravating our evils, and which, <lb/>
if it should change, must alter our condition for <lb/>
the better? He (Mr. P.) spoke of the principal <lb/>
subject of his Excellancy's speech, Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. The hon. member then went on to say <lb/>
that he regarded this question as one of too <lb/>
grave importance to be lightly treated, one in<lb break="no"/>finitely raised above all questions of party. <lb/>
The man must be a traitor to his country who <lb/>
could make it the battle ground of faction. <lb/>
Neither one side nor the other could recommend <lb/>
its arguments to the intelligence and respect of <lb/>
the country by personal abuse or trivial treat<lb break="no"/>ment. Assailing men for their motives, and im<lb break="no"/>pugning, their sincerity, could do no good, and <lb/>
could be suggested by no motive but to lead the <lb/>
public away from the deliberate investigation of <lb/>
the question on its own merits. He believed a <lb/>
great change of opinion had taken place. He <lb/>
blamed no man for changing or modifying his <lb/>
views, from reflection upon so grave a matter. <lb/>
But a long time had been allowed for delibe<lb break="no"/>ration, and in that period he knew of no man <lb/>
who had, from a Confederate opinion, changed <lb/>
to the opposite view. The revulsion had been <lb/>
altogether the other way, and the intelligence of <lb/>
the community was now, he believed, almost <lb/>
entirely in favor of union. There were those who <lb/>
had hoped against hope, and found it fruitless. <lb/>
There had been doubters and alarmists, who <lb/>
now trembled, <lb/></p>
    
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>
"Even at the sounds themselves had made." <lb/></p>
    </quote>
    
    <p>
For his part, he had never opposed the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of Confederation. He had always advo<lb break="no"/>cated union; but he had taken exception to the <lb/>
Quebec <choice><sic>Gonvention</sic><corr>Convention</corr></choice>, as possessing some features <lb/>
that required correction, and as being wanting <lb/>
in some provisions which it should contain. <lb/>
He had always opposed the adoption of the mea<lb break="no"/>sure without the endeavour to correct these <lb/>
defects, and he had always opposed the deter<lb break="no"/>mination of the question without an appeal to <lb/>
the people, and had cooperated in an endeavor <lb/>
to prevent the possibility of any such attempt, <lb/>
and he had always desired and contended that <lb/>
the measure could not, in justice to the country, <lb/>
be submitted for its suffrages, without an ascer<lb break="no"/>tainment of the terms. It would be merely de<lb break="no"/>ceiving the constituencies, and keeping concealed <lb/>
from them the true issues they had to deter<lb break="no"/>mine, to go before them without being enabled <lb/>
to explain the principles and the main conditions <lb/>
        of the project. Delay, <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> to last year, may <lb/>
have been discreet. Our position up to that <lb/>
time may have improved. Time had been <lb/>
afforded for observing the operation of the mea<lb break="no"/>sure with others, and of ascertaining what cor<lb break="no"/>rections and improvements were susceptible of <lb/>
being made. Then, last year, our opportunity <lb/>
had arrived, when the difficulty with Nova <lb/>
Scotia was pending, but a feeling of considera<lb break="no"/>tion for our sister colony held us back then.— <lb/>
Disaffection had arisen there, chiefly from the <lb/>
mode of carrying the measure; but whatever <lb/>
the cause, the struggle had ended in failure and <lb/>
defeat; and its champion was now President of <lb/>
the Privy Council of the Naw. Dominion, that <lb/>
same Mr. Howe, with whom Colonial union had <lb/>
been the dream of his youth, the aspiration of <lb/>
his maturer years, and with whom one would <lb/>
have thought it would have been the cherished <lb/>
object of his old age. It may be that, for a <lb/>
short time, he had forgotten his old love in the <lb/>
indignation of offended patriotism, but he had <lb/>
been taken at last into the warm embrace of <lb/>
the confederate arms. The time had now ar<lb break="no"/>rived when further delay might be fatal. The <lb/>
provisions of the Quebec Convention could now <lb/>
be improved upon in all essential points. We <lb/>
should now unquestionably obtain a larger sub<lb break="no"/>sidy, an objection which he once held that the <lb/>
capitation money was not to be increased in the <lb/>
ratio of population, was already removed <lb/>
Taxes and assessments on mining operations <lb/>
had been entirely repealed. Light dues had <lb/>
been remitted; articles used in the fishery had <lb/>
been admitted free of duty, and above all, an <lb/>
exception which had been taken, not without <lb/>
reason, that we should at certain seasons be <lb/>
<choice><sic>plaeed</sic><corr>placed</corr></choice> at a commercial disadvantage by Amer<lb break="no"/>ican produce being subject to a tax when that <lb/>
of Canada was free of duty, had been removed <lb/>
by legislatfon, which annulled all duties on the <lb/>
importation of flour and breadstuffs from <lb/>
the United States. There was the bet<lb break="no"/>ter, half of a Reciprocity Treaty already, <lb/>
with the probability of the establishment of such <lb/>
a treaty at no distant time, an object which, re<lb break="no"/>maining isolated, we could not effect for our<lb break="no"/>selves. Thus were all the staple necessities of <lb/>
life admitted duty free. If we continued as we <lb/>
are, it was an utter impossibility to forego taxes <lb/>
upon any importations. Our present tariff was <lb/>
enormous, and there was no hope of material <lb/>
reduction. Many intelligent persons placed <lb/>
great faith, and were willing to accept Confede<lb break="no"/>ration in view of the general benefits and bless<lb break="no"/>ings which history and experience and the laws <lb/>
of progress and political economy taught that <lb/>
equitable unions produced. But we were not <lb/>
coufined to such reflections; our faith must be <lb/>
further strengthened by our own exceptional <lb/>
position. Isolation and solitude were our bane, <lb/>
and yet some would hug and foster this charac<lb break="no"/>teristic of barbarism. How were we to remove <lb/>
or mitigate it? Would any intelligent man <lb/>
believe that improved means of intercourse <lb/>
between ourselves and the outside world was <lb/>
not an important step in that direction; that <lb/>
assimilation with a more advanced, more pros<lb break="no"/>
<cb/>
perous wealthy and progressive people, with its <lb/>
consequent sympathy and example; that mutual <lb/>
freedom of trade and industry, would not be un<lb break="no"/>attended with those advantages which in all <lb/>
parts of the civilized world had followed from <lb/>
such conditions? But even abundant fisheries <lb/>
had been found inadequate to the support of the <lb/>
people, yet we had great mineral resources, and <lb/>
where were the ability, the capital, the disposi<lb break="no"/>tion within ourselves to work them? so of our <lb/>
timber lands. We have gypsum, lime, the <lb/>
finest pottery clay, &amp;c.,and they remain useless. <lb/>
Our fisheries are badly conducted, under an <lb/>
effete system, and especially a great source of <lb/>
wealth, the herring fishery, was positively not <lb/>
only neglected, but abused. Manufactures were <lb/>
active in Canada, that might be prosecuted <lb/>
under a different system with equal success <lb/>
here—we have the material and water power to <lb/>
any extent, and coal in prospect. The country <lb/>
was well adapted for those woollen manufactures <lb/>
for which Canada had become remarkable. We <lb/>
export tens of thousands of seal skins, and thou<lb break="no"/>sands of hides, that afters successive freights, <lb/>
duties, charges and profits, come back either <lb/>
from England or Canada in the shape of leather <lb/>
and the manufactures of leather, and sell at a <lb/>
large profit here. Those who talked of the <lb/>
poverty and bankruptcy of Canada, had either <lb/>
never been there, or having seen that <lb/>
magnificent country, misrepresented the <lb/>
facts. Millions would yet find a home <lb/> 
there, and have room and verge enough. It <lb/>
was yet but very partially settled. There <lb/>
were immense fertile and productive sec<lb break="no"/>tions of the country to be peopled; and in its <lb/>
present infancy it possessed splendid cities, some <lb/>
thousands of miles of railway, an unsurpassed <lb/>
system of steam communication, internal and <lb/>
oceanic, factories of all kinds, an immense forest <lb/>
industry, vast mineral resources, unbounded <lb/>
agricultural capabilities, prolific fisheries, public <lb/>
institutions competing with any in the world, <lb/>
and social and intellectual life in its highest <lb/>
phases. He had gone to Canada, almost ex<lb break="no"/>pressly to see and judge for himself what manner <lb/>
of country that was with which we were asked <lb/>
to ally ourselves. He expected to find some <lb/>
similarity to our own colonial features. The <lb/>
picture was a very different one. The latest <lb/>
returns of exports that he held were those of <lb/>
1867, and he would cite some of the principal, <lb/>
and those which most concerned us; produce of <lb/>
the forest, about $14,000,000; of agriculture, <lb/>
$17,000,000; of the fisheries, $800,000; of mines <lb/>
$300,000; manufactures, $900,000; flour alone, <lb/>
$5,000,000; barley and rye, (chiefly exported to <lb/>
the United States,) $4,000,000; meal $5,000,<lb break="no"/>000; wheat, $4,000,000; leather, $140,000, and <lb/>
so forth. Now it must be remembered that <lb/>
these and many other articles were the exports, <lb/>
there being retained in the country, besides, all <lb/>
that was required for home consumpion. How <lb/>
different from our present condition. Ours was <lb/>
an exhaustive process. Every thing went away <lb/>
from us. Nothing remained. All the surplus <lb/>
wealth went elsewhere, chiefly to Britain. <lb/>
The people starved. The Canadian home has <lb/>
made attractive; most of the money made <lb/>
there was spent there; the people, from the <lb/>
richest to the poorest, were identified with the <lb/>
country. Anti-confederates were heard to say, <lb/>
"True they have a railway system, but it does <lb/>
not pay. It is partially a public expense." <lb/>
Such men confined their ideas to the mere outlay <lb/>
and direct return in money. Such a position <lb/>
was entirely falacious. It was part of a chain <lb/>
of intercommunication and of traffic, which had <lb/>
raised the value of all products, which had led <lb/>
to extended settlement and cultivation, which <lb/>
had cheapened importe and promoted all civiliza<lb break="no"/>tion. In these ways it had returned to the <lb/>
country ten thousand times the actual expense. <lb/>
Would Canadians do without it now? No, <lb/>
they would as soon think of blotting the country <lb/>
from the face of the earth. There were some <lb/>
who would cite Ireland as an example of an <lb/>
unfortunate union, and raise prejudices from <lb/>
such an argument, against Confederation. It <lb/>
was not an apt or fair comparison. Here we <lb/>
associated with equal rights. Here we should <lb/>
enjoy the privileges of the British constitution <lb/>
in its full perfection, without blot or blemish; <lb/>
Education established on a basis which offended <lb/>
none. The fullest measure of civil liberty, and <lb/>
perfect freedom and equality in religion. In <lb/>
another view he regarded this measure of Con<lb break="no"/>federation as a step in the logic of events that <lb/>
would be worked out. The history of this <lb/>
Colony, so remote as to make it the most an<lb break="no"/>cient dependency of the Crown, was marked with <lb/>
several eras. At the cominencement of this <lb/>
century, it was just allowed to emerge from the <lb/>
condition of a temporary fishing resort. Then <lb/>
we had an absolute Governor and Council, next <lb/>
a Legislature, then the system of responsibility. <lb/>
So we had been educated and fitted for a broad<lb break="no"/>er grander and more national position and sphere <lb/>
of action. Having eljoyed the questionable <lb/>
blessing, and been taught by the experience of <lb/>
local Government, the parent state having <lb/> 
guided and controlled our infant steps to a der<lb break="no"/>gree of maturity, points us to a field of action <lb/>
where the exercise of constitutional Govern<lb break="no"/>ment can be better and more effectively applied. <lb/>
The machinery and paraphernalia of our pre<lb break="no"/>sent system are too much for this country, and <lb/>
they will be reduced in their scope and shorn of <lb/>
there costliness, while we shall still have a <lb/>
local Government and a voice in the concerns <lb/>
of a great people and a united and progressive <lb/>
Dominion. He had seen an excellent simile <lb/>
from a Harbor Grace friend, who compared <lb/> 
the unwillingness of the people for change, to the <lb/>
aversion countrymen at first had to Sam Slick's <lb/>
clocks. Sam would visit a farm house, offer his <lb/>
wares for sale. No, they had done without a <lb/>
clock all their lives, and knew the time of day <lb/>
well enough without it. Sam requested that <lb/> 
they would oblige him by letting one remain in <lb/>
their house until his return. He left it, wound <lb/>
it up for them, taugut them how to keep it in <lb/>
order. After a while Sam returus to get back. [...] <lb/></p> 
    
    <!-- IC, 2019-01-07, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>his clock. Oh, no, they w <lb/>
on any account; could not <lb/>
had learned the use and be <lb/>
of it. So it was with any <lb/>
an old fashioned people, <lb/>
difficult to move from ti <lb/>
and 'beaten track than <lb/>
believed <lb/>
* " our doubts were traitors, <lb/>
§: And made us lose the good w <lb/>
By fearing to attempt." <lb/>
He appended a statement <lb/>
even the hon. member Aſ <lb/>
question, as to the amount <lb/>
which would be assumed by <lb/>
ernment, and of the allow <lb/>
the most unfavorable aspec <lb/>
it. This included the intº <lb/>
debt, which would be ass <lb/>
Government, and we mig; <lb/>
larger expenditure under H <lb/>
Geºlogical Survey, Fisherie: <lb/>
: 1.IABILITIES AS <lb/>
Governor, Secretary, Servants a <lb/>
House................. <lb/>
Receiver General's Gfflee <lb/>
Surveyor General's Office. <lb/></p> 

<p>Judges Supreme Court &amp; La <lb/>
Customs. <lb/></p> 

<p>Wolunteer Force. <lb/>Repairs Public Buildings. ..... <lb/>
- Marina Hospital........ <lb/>: Interest on Public Debt <lb/>
Light Houses... <lb/>
, Miscellaneous..., -\-\-\-\-\-<lb/>ALuowancks tº <lb/>
Capitaticn Money...;;.......... <lb/>
Interest on C23 per Head... <lb/>
* Surrender of Crown Lands.... <lb/></p> 

<p>. Less Interest on our Public. De <lb/>
*- -\-\-  </p> 

<p>His (Mr. P's.) policy, and it <lb/>
recommend the Government, <lb/>
No more philandering with <lb/>
gravity demanded deliberate <lb/>
was idle to talk of submitting <lb/>
judgment of the people, until <lb/>
Erranged as the basis of u <lb/>
Dominion would agree *..." <lb/>
by'this House, as wouli recei <lb/>
o, Iſer Majesty, and ouch as <lb/>
to the country for its adoptid <lb/>
occupy some time, but the ini <lb/>
taken without delay. It trou <lb/>
an intelligent Legislature, des <lb/>
people, to istorm them. It <lb/>
deceiving them, and conceals <lb/>
to pursue any other course. <lb/>
this great practical revoluti <lb/>
its Providential designs, hot <lb/>
be the instrument in their <lb/>
IIe trusted that hou, membe <lb/>
were anti-confederates, woul <lb/>
sible example of their great <lb/>
who, convinced of the fully <lb/>
a wise and experienced º <lb/>
retreat, and obtaining increa <lb/>
his country, is sow coutribu: <lb/>
his intellect to the consolidat <lb/>
the Dominion Government. <lb/>
read with pleasure the cla <lb/>
letters of "Gutsider," in the M. <lb/>
he would recommend their p <lb/>
capable of forming an intellige <lb/>
this great question. He w <lb/>
speech with the last paragraph <lb/>
"Viewing the great Uuion pro <lb/>
independently of questious of 1. <lb/>
we are sensible uſ a sort of iustin <lb/>
adopt it. Twenty thousand pount <lb/>
not make Newfoundland more or <lb/>
she drifts into the current of civili <lb/>
Confederation is not a financial q <lb/>
one,—ours is a disease that mone <lb/>
will only aggavate, as experience <lb/>
want thore things that gold can I. <lb/>
belf-dependence, assimilation wit <lb/>
that surround us; and tiless cati <lb/>
by union, union of rule, union <lb/>
union of interests." <lb/>
Mr. GLEN was sorry the <lb/>
gentleman had not coulined h <lb/>
ject belore the chair, which <lb/>
TIe had given them a long spe: <lb/>
federation. and told them, of S <lb/>
but forget to say that the clock <lb/>
soon as it was paid for, and so <lb/>
Confederation. They would pro <lb/>
but when they had thein in, woul: <lb/>
with them. He (Mr. G.) hoped <lb/>
go in. It Canada had not had <lb/>
$5,000,000 of Treasury notes, las <lb/>
would be bankrupt. That did no <lb/>
ing finances. When the Treasur <lb/>
asked for the subsidy due to that <lb/>
not get it for a long time, and the <lb/>
in the same way if they joined th <lb/>
G.) considered the Goverument <lb/>
be disgraceful. The people were <lb/>
and he had that very day to give <lb/>
to 125 of His constituents who c <lb/>
relief. He had advised them to go <lb/>
but he would not see them. It w <lb/>
the Government to allow these th <lb/>
no eivilized government but would <lb/>
they came to hear that this Goverſ <lb/>
the people to starve. It was is <lb/>
raceful is any G ºvernment. T <lb/>
parishing, and some had already <lb/>
KMr. G.) did not like to say as y <lb/>
actually died from starvation. <lb/>
: The Committee then rose, a <lb/>
reported progress. To sit ag <lb/>
alter which the House adjº <lb/>
morrow. | <lb/></p> 

<p>-ºl <lb/>
"Attack and DºfENCE,-1 be <lb/>
ease is developed, the vitaliorces a <lb/>
it... In order inat they may cougui <lb/>
with Radway's Ready Relief... Nat <lb/>
will be euabled to repeal the first, <lb/>
and to triumph over pain. A sing <lb/>
will prevent a long and dangerous <lb/>
tered early enough. <lb/>
Price 60 cents per bottle. Sold <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>