<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-01-21" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
    <title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-01-21">21 January 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-02-02"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-02_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="lyallg" when="2018-11-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNDLA_1865-02-02_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-02_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-02_Page_1.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER</fw>
    
    <fw type="dateline">St. John's, Thursday, February 2, 1865</fw>
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    
    <!-- GL, 2018-11-06, Commented out below as it does not pertain to Debate Day --> <!-- 

<p>s <lb/>
tail to procure Mrs. WINSLow's Sooth; <lb/>
upor children teething. This waſ. <lb/>
a the prescription of one of the be <lb/>
ians and nurses in the United sº <lb/>
used for thirty years with never failin <lb/>
success by millions, of mothers and ºf <lb/>
n the feeble infant cf one week old to t s <lb/>
nºt only relieves the child from pain, i. <lb/>
s the stomach and bowels, corrects acidit t º <lb/>
tone and energy to the whole system. # <lb/>
t instantly relieve Griping in the Bowels *­ <lb/>
ic. We believe it the best and surest remed, <lb/>
ld in all cases of Dissentery and Diarhº <lb/>
hether it arises from teething or any ºt. <lb/>
ull directions for use will accompany each <lb/>
one genuine unless the fac-simile of Curti, <lb/>
is on the outside wrapper. Price only 25 <lb/>
lottle. Sold by all Medicine Dealers. off. <lb/>
reet, New York, and 205 High Holbº <lb/></p> 

<p>ngland. <lb/>
MRS. WINSLOW, <lb/>
nced Nurse and Female Physician, presents <lb/>
ntion of mothers, her Soothing Syrup for <lb/>
ething, which greatly facilitates the process <lb/>
by softening the gums, reducing all infi. <lb/>
ill allay all pain and spasmodic action, and <lb/>
egulate the bowels. Depend upon it, m. <lb/>
I give rest to yourselves, and relief and <lb/>
our inſants. We have put up and sold this <lb/>
over thirty years, and can say, in confiden. <lb/>
ºf it what we have never boen able to sº <lb/>
r medicine—never has it failed in a single <lb/>
effect a cure, when timely used. Neº <lb/>
ºw an instance of dissatisfaction by any one <lb/>
t. On the contrary, all speak delighted <lb/>
*rations, and speaks in terius of commenda. <lb/>
magical effects and medical virtues. We <lb/>
is matter what we do now," after thirty <lb/>
ºrience, and pledge our reputation for the <lb/>
ºf what we here declare. In almost every <lb/>
i.ere the infant is suffering from pair and <lb/>
, relief will be found in fifteen or twenty <lb/>
ter the syrup is administered. Full direc. <lb/>
sing will accompany each bottle. Nons <lb/>
illess the ſac-simile of Curtis and Perkins, <lb/>
is on the outside wrapper. Sold by Drug. <lb/>
ghout the wºrld. ... Principal Office, 48 by <lb/>
', and 205 High Holboin, Engiand. Priºs <lb/>
hts per bottle. <lb/>
wing is as extract from a letter written by <lb/>
S Holme, Pastor of the Pierrepont-street <lb/>
*ich, Brooklyn, NY, to the "Journal and <lb/>
." Cincinnati, O., and speaks volumes in <lb/>
hat world-renowned medicine, Mrs. WINs. <lb/>
thing Syrup for Children Teething—" W. <lb/>
ertisement in your c lumns of Mrs. Wins. } <lb/>
ling Syrup. Now we never said a word in <lb/>
• patent medicine before in our life, but we <lb/>
iled to say to your readers that this is no <lb/>
we have tried it, and know it to be all i <lb/>
is probably one of the most successful <lb/>
ºf the day, because it in one of the best <lb/>
of your readers who have babies can't do <lb/>
iuy in a supply." <lb/>
J. DEARIN, St. John's, <lb/>
As ent for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>PHO E.W. H.W. F.H R4, <lb/>
- 4. *** *** wº. <lb/>
###tº $ºpºny. <lb/>
ird Street and Chering Cross, London. <lb/>
ESTA || || | SH ſº ty–1782 <lb/>
Thustº ES ANi DIRECTORS. <lb/></p> 

<p>irtou, Esq. Kirkman ix. Hodg: an Esq. <lb/>
<lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>ºpe, " i. i** - Horra, <lb/></p> 

<p>ston, " William J. Lancastor, " <lb/>
* Jºhn b. Mugen, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Fºser, " John Miasterman, Esq. M. P. <lb/></p> 

<p>ulter, " Jºhn Timnby Oxley tsa <lb/></p> 

<p>igodhart." George Stanley Reptor. " <lb/></p> 

<p>ºrdon, " |Benjamin Shºw, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>tº: " |Matthew Whiting, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Jgsor, " Franrik Wiison, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>8ECRETA Riks f <lb/></p> 

<p>William HARRIs Esq. <lb/>
GeoRGs',\ illiam LoveLL, Esq. <lb/></p> 

<p>ENIX FIRE OFFICE is confidently tº: <lb/></p> 

<p>i to the notice of the public—for the libera <lb/>
motitude with which all claims upon it are <lb/>
d paid- as well as for the almost unlimited <lb/>
ich it affords, comprising in addition to the <lb/>
ed Capital of the Coupany, the whole for <lb/>
umerous Proprietary. composed oſsomeº <lb/>
opulent gentlemen and Merchants in the <lb/></p> 

<p>goion. <lb/>
'ENIX CFFICF has carried on an exten­ <lb/>
ccessful busines: for upwards of seventy­ <lb/>
The duty paid by it to Government for <lb/>
in Great Briain and Ireland exceed <lb/>
terling per unnum. <lb/>
ind short time Insurances are undertaken <lb/>
ENIX Q9MPANY on almost every de­ <lb/>
risk, in Newfoundland at a moderate late <lb/>
which may be know on application to <lb/>
it their office, in St. John's, where policies <lb/>
ee of charge. <lb/>
W. &amp; G. RENDEI.L, <lb/>
Agents for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>'i'HE COLONIAL <lb/></p> 

<p>Assirance tompany <lb/></p> 

<p>EstarlishED 1846. <lb/>
AL, ONE MILLION STERLING. <lb/></p> 

<p>ge of Assuring before 25th: <lb/></p> 

<p>May 1863. <lb/>
IRD DIVISION OF PROFITS. <lb/>
the advantage of this year's entry to the <lb/></p> 

<p>ne, Proposals must be lodged at the Offies <lb/></p> 

<p>Newfoundland,or with one of the Agents <lb/>
25th May next. <lb/>
PARS BONUS will be allocated at the <lb/>
Profits in 1864 to Policies opened before <lb/>
the Books for the Present Year. <lb/></p> 

<p>ATER BY SPECIAL ACT of PARLIAMENT. <lb/></p> 

<p>Governor. <lb/>
iT HON. THE EARL OF ELGIN &amp; <lb/>
!)INE. Gover Nor-General of INDIA. <lb/>
ICE-\-5 GEORGESTREET, EDINBURGH <lb/>
Directors in St. John's, Newfoundland. <lb/>
O'Brien, Esq. Walter Grieve, Esq., <lb/>
Merchant. <lb/>
William Henry Mare, Esq. <lb/>
Adviser—Henry Hunt Stabb, M.D. <lb/>
tgent–Frederick J. Wyatt. <lb/>
'ION OF THE COMPANY. <lb/>
me of the Company............ £130,000. <lb/>
y have divided Profits on two occasions­ <lb/>
d 1859. <lb/>
£1000,opened in 1847,has beenincreased <lb/>
y the application of the Bonus; other <lb/>
proportion. - - 0. <lb/>
'd every five years; next division, in 186 <lb/></p> 

<p>* <lb/></p> 

<p>t <lb/></p> 

<p>'' <lb/></p> 

<p>¥ <lb/></p> 

<p>N <lb/></p> 

<p>th <lb/></p> 

<p>%. , <lb/></p> 

<p>F = (ſhe 3ienſmundlai <lb/></p> 

<p>se:= <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>No. 3,635. <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, Thursday, February 2, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>cº­ <lb/></p> 

<p>- d Puhlished every Monday and Thursday <lb/></p> 

<p>*... by EDWARD DALTQN SHEA, at his <lb/>
ºffice in IjugE WORTH STREET-Terms–One <lb/>
ºftinea per annum payable in advance. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Advertisements not limited (Auction-sales and notice <lb/>
ºich determine themselves excepted) are repeated <lb/>
until ordered in writing to be withdrawn, and aro <lb/>
charged for accordingly. <lb/></p> 

<p>This paper is filed,and may be seen, free of charge at <lb/>
Followay's Pills and Ointment Establishment, 244 <lb/>
8trand, London. <lb/></p>--> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">REPORT OF THE DELEGATES <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">TO THE QUEBEC CONVENTION ON THE <lb/>
FEDERAL UNION of the BRITISH NORTH <lb/>
AMERICAN PROVINCES</hi>. <lb/></head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">ST. JOHN's, JANUARY 21st, 1865.</p>
    
    <p>
SIR,- <lb/>
        
        Having been honoured by the Government of this <lb/>
Colony with the appointment of Delegates to the <lb/>
General Colonial Convention at Quebec, on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject of the Union of the British North America <lb/>
Provinces, we proceeded in the Steamer " St. <lb/>
George" on the 23rd September last, and arrived in <lb/>
due course at our destination. The Meeting was <lb/>
appointed to be held at Quebec on the 10th Octo<lb break="no"/>ber, on which day the Delegates from the several <lb/>
Provinces met in the Parliament Buildings in that <lb/>
City. Canada was represented by the members of <lb/>
the Executive Council of that Province, twelve in <lb/>
number, Nova Scotia had five Delegates, New <lb/>
Brunswick seven, Newfoundland two and Prince <lb/>
Edward Island seven, the credentials of the Dele<lb break="no"/>gates from the Jower Provinces were handed in, and <lb/>
the Convention was then organized by electing Sir <lb/>
Etienne Tache, Premier of Canada, to be Chairman, <lb/>
and the several Provincial Secretaries and Mr. Shea <lb/>
to be Secretaries to the Convention. </p>
    
    
    <p>
Sometime previously a Meeting took place at <lb/>
Charlottetown, of Delegates from Nova Scotia, <lb/>
New Brunswick and P.E. Island for the purpose <lb/>
of considering the question of a Legislative Union <lb/>
of these Provinces, and while so engaged, some <lb/>
members of the Canadian Government presented <lb/>
themselves with a proposal for the Union of all the <lb/>
Provinces, which was so far received, with favor that <lb/>
the consideration of the original question was sus<lb break="no"/>pended, and the larger one entertained and discus<lb break="no"/>sed. The Meeting then adjourned to Halffax, <lb/>
where the Delegates met shortly after and proceeded <lb/>
with their deliberations, which resulted in a resolu<lb break="no"/>tion that a further Conference should be held at <lb/>
Querec, to which Newfoundland should be invited <lb/>
to send representatives.</p>
    
    
    <p>Though the subject had been fully discussed in all <lb/>
its general bearings at these earlier meetings, it was <lb/>
now necessary to treat it more specially in relation <lb/>
to the position the Colonies should respectively oc<lb break="no"/>cupy in the contemplated Union, and moreover, the <lb/>
Newfoundland Delegates not having had the advan<lb break="no"/>tage of being present at the previous meetings, it was <lb/>
suggested that an exposition of the whole question <lb/>
should be gone into on their account. This was <lb/>
agreed to and the business proceedings were accord<lb break="no"/>ingly opened by the Hon. John A. McDonald, At<lb break="no"/>torney General of Upper Canada, in an elaborate <lb/>
statement, showing the great benefits of combination <lb/>
to communities circumstanced as the British North <lb/>
American Colonies—drawn not only from the nature <lb/>
of things as respects the Provinces in their present <lb/>
state, in relation to each other, but fortified also by <lb/>
the experience of the working of the Union of the <lb/>
Canadas, and the more important example of the <lb/>
neighbouring States, which had become so great un<lb break="no"/>der the Union they formed on their separation from <lb/>
the mother country. The necessity for Union was <lb/>
also shewn by Mr. McDonald, who considered it the <lb/>
policy clearly indicated by the Home Government, <lb/>
where it was justly felt that the time had arrived <lb/>
when the British North American Provinces should <lb/>
assume the position demanded by their numbers, <lb/>
wealth, extent of territory, and growing importance, <lb/>
and it was alone by a Union of the whole that they <lb/>
could fit themselves for the great place now open to <lb/>
them, and which the efforts of individual Provinces <lb/>
could never enable them to attain.</p>
    
    <p>
In view of the framing of a constitution, the de<lb break="no"/>feats of the American system were fully considered. <lb/>
Though the wisdom of the men who framed that con<lb break="no"/>sutution, had been attested by its success for three <lb/>
quarters of a century, it still embraced principles <lb/>
which rendered it unable to bear the strain of the <lb/>
crisis which lately arose, furnishing a most instruc<lb break="no"/>tive lesson at the present time. The admitted great <lb/>
defect of the Federal system of the United States is <lb/>
the weakness of the Executive, which compelled them <lb/>
in their day of trial to resort to the exercise of power <lb/>
unknown to the law, placing private and public liber<lb break="no"/>ty at the mercy of arbitrary suthority. </p>
    
    <p>
These was a very general feeling in the Confer<lb break="no"/>ence that a legislative union would confer the great<lb break="no"/>er advantages on the General Confederation, as the <lb/>
Government, under such a system, would possess <lb/>
larger authority and more commanding influence. <lb/>
But many difficulties presented themselves which de<lb break="no"/>prived this view or its desired feasibility. The <lb/>
wer Canadians would not consent to any plan <lb/>
wheh placed their peculiar institutions beyond their <lb/>
immediate control; while it was also felt that public <lb/>
opinion in the lower provinces was not ripe for the <lb/>
extreme change which the abrogation of their local <lb/>
legislatures would involve. </p>
    
    
    <p>
These matters having been fully considered, the <lb/>
Colference decided as their first resolution, "That <lb/>
the best interest and present and future prosperity <lb/>
of British North America will be promoted by a <lb/>
Federal Union under the Crown of Great Britain, <lb/>
provided such Union can be effected on principles <lb/>
just to the several Provinces. </p>
    
    <p>
In the Resolutions adopted by the Conference to <lb/>
carry this Union into effect, care has been takeu to <lb/>
avoid the cause of weakness disclosed in the work<lb break="no"/>ing of the American Constitution. The General <lb/>
Government will be formed upon the principles of <lb/>
to present colonial system. Executive Responsi<lb break="no"/>bility being maintained, while it will not, as in the <lb/>
inited States, be dependent, either for its organiza<lb break="no"/>tion,or authority, on the volition or acts of any of <lb/>
the local Governments. The structure of these lat<lb break="no"/>for bodies is left in each case to the presentiocal <lb/>
legislatures to determine, and uniformity of pian not <lb/>
being necessary, they are severally left to frame <lb/>
such arrangements in tuis Icspect as the altered cir<lb break="no"/>cumstance and the peculiar condition of each pro<lb break="no"/>vince may seem to render desirable. The powers of <lb/>
the General and Local Governments are defined so <lb/>
as to Prevent any probable causes of conflict—all <lb/>
        

<cb/>
    



powers of a general nature being vested in the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Government, and local questions being reserved <lb/>
for the subordinate bodies.</p>
    
    <p>It was unanimously decided that the principle of <lb/>
Elective Councils should not be adopted in the new <lb/>
Constitution, and that the appointments should be <lb/>
for life, and should vest in the General Government, <lb/>
In the composition of this branch of the Legislature, <lb/>
the Lower Provinces have a larger representation <lb/>
than their due, if population alone were the govern<lb break="no"/>ing consideration. For the purpose of this arrange<lb break="no"/>ment it was proposed at the early meetings at Prince <lb/>
Edward Island and Halifax, that Upper and Lower <lb/>
Canada should each be made a section, and the Lower <lb/>
Provinces a third, with equal representation for each <lb/>
part. There was a difference of opinion as to whe<lb break="no"/>ther Newfoundland intended to be included in <lb/>
the number assigned to the Lower Provinces, but the <lb/>
Canadian Delegates, although maintaining that they <lb/>
had included Newfoundland in the arrangement, at <lb/>
length yielded the point, and four additional members <lb/>
were added for this colony. "We may seem in this <lb/>
case to have received less that our relative right of <lb/> 
    representation, but so also would Upper Canada and <lb/>

Nova Scotia stand if the question were regarded with <lb/>
numerical strictness. But it will easily be understood <lb/>
that unless such a large project as the Union of the <lb/>
Provinces, with the various and diverse interests it <lb/>
involves, were met in a spirit of fair compromise, no <lb/>
satisfactory general result could be arrived at, and in <lb/>
this instance the Delegates representing Upper Cana<lb break="no"/>da, Nova Scotia and Newfoundland made a conces<lb break="no"/>sion of extreme rights to the other Provinces,although <lb/>
in relation to the whole number, this colony has a <lb/>
larger share than would be signable by this rule. </p>
    
    <p>
The principle of population alone governs the com<lb break="no"/>position of the Lower House, which is to consist of <lb/>
196 members, eight being awarded as the portion of <lb/>
this colony. It will be seen that this number would <lb/>
give us a full representation in the popular Branch, <lb/>
which is the influential and virtually governing Body <lb/>
in all Governments where the principles of Responsi<lb break="no"/>ble Government prevail.</p>
    
    <p>
The General Government is to assume the public <lb/>
debts of the several Provinces, on the equitable plan <lb/>
by which no one Province will be charged with more <lb/>
than its own obligations on this account. </p>
    
    <p>
The surrender of the Customs Revenues to the <lb/>
General Government, embraces the condition that <lb/>
subsidies shall be made to the several Provinces for <lb/>
the support of their Local Institutions. In none of <lb/>
the Provinces is direct taxation held in favor, <lb/>
though in all but this colony, it prevails to <lb/>
a certain extent. We feel, however, that in <lb/>
this respect we could not consent to dis<lb break="no"/>turb our exceptional position, though a difficulty <lb/>
arose because of the insufficiency for our requiremerts <lb/>
of the pro rata amount of subsidy that was sufficient <lb/>
for the wants of the other Provinces. It was, how<lb break="no"/>ever, agreed on, to avoid the necessity of resorting <lb/>
to direst taxation, to meet the deficiency of means in <lb/>
our case, that Newfoundland should receivea special <lb/>
subsidy of one hundred and fifty thousand dollars per <lb/>
annum, in consideration of the transfer to the General <lb/>
Government of the control of our ungranted and un<lb break="no"/>occupied Crown Lands and Minerals, and this arrange<lb break="no"/>ment places the question of our means on a satis<lb break="no"/>factory footing. </p>
    
    
    
    <p>
The full and explicit character of the report of the <lb/>
Conference, which we beg to annex, renders it unne<lb break="no"/>cessary for us to go further into detail on this impor<lb break="no"/>tant subject, which occupied the time of the Delegates <lb/>
for ten hours daily from the 19th to the 27th October, <lb/>
when our labours were brought to a termination and <lb/>
the report was unanimously agreed to.</p>
    
    <p>
Men of all parties were presunt at the Conference <lb/>
from the various British North American Provinces, <lb/>
but the influence of local differences found no place <lb/>
in the deliberations. We feel warranted in asserting <lb/>
our belief that no inquiry was ever conducted under <lb/>
a higher sense of the responsibility of the occasion, <lb/>
or with a more single desire to arrive at the best re<lb break="no"/>sults for the great interests at stake. While it would <lb/>
be impossible to suppose that the report embodies <lb/>
every individual view of the Delegates on all the <lb/>
points it embraces, as a whole it was unreservedly <lb/>
adopted. It is the emanation of the best judgment <lb/>
of the Conference, unbiased by a wish for the undue <lb/>
advancement of party or sectional interests, and the <lb/>
spirit of calm discussion which pervaded the whole <lb/>
inquiry of which this report in the result, cannot fail <lb/>
to commend it to the earnest attention of all whose <lb/>
interests it affects. For ourselves, we have but to <lb/>
state that we affixed our signatures, as individuals, to <lb/>
that report with the full conviction that the welfare <lb/>
of the colony will be promoted by entering the Union <lb/>
it proposes, and that we cannot reject it without ag<lb break="no"/>gravating the injurious consequences of our present <lb/>
insolation. </p>
    
    <p>
We beg to annex a statement showing the amount <lb/>
and particulars of the charges from which this colony <lb/>
would be relieved under the Confederation, and the <lb/>
amount that would be available for the purposes of <lb/>
the Local Government.</p>
    
    <p rendition="simple:right">
We have the honor to be Sir, <lb/>
Your most obedient servants, <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CART5">F. B. T. CARTER</persName>, <lb/>
        <persName ref="pers:SHEA2">A. SHEA</persName>.</p>
    
    
    
    <!-- GL, 2018-11-06, Commented out below as it does not pertain to Debate Day --> <!-- </p> 

<p>£35,71stg. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT. <lb/>
Iuterest on $25 per head on 130,000 in­ <lb/>
habitants, $3,250,000, at 5 per centum $162,500 <lb/></p> 

<p>80 cents per head on 130,000.... 1u4,000 <lb/>
Grant tor Surrender of Crown La &amp; 150,000 <lb/>
. $416,500 <lb/></p> 

<p>Less interest payable on Public Debt, <lb/>
£10,210 Sterling......... ........ 47,124 <lb/>
$369,376 <lb/></p> 

<p>January, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p><lb/></p> 

<p>HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY. <lb/></p> 

<p>FRIDAY, Jan. 27. <lb/></p> 

<p>The SPEAKER and Members met in the Assembly <lb/>
Hall shortly before two o'clock. <lb/></p> 

<p>At two o'clock the Usher of the Black Riddelivered <lb/>
a message at the Bar from his Excel-ney the Gºver­ <lb/>
nor, commanding the attendance of Mr. Speaker and <lb/>
the members in the Council Chamber. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. SPEAKER and the members proceeded to the <lb/>
Council Chamber accordingly, and being returned. <lb/></p> 

<p>The SPEAKER informed the House, that when in at­ <lb/>
tendance on the Governor, his Excellency had been <lb/>
pleased to open the session with a speech, of which, <lb/>
for the sake of accuracy, he had obtained a copy, which <lb/>
he read to the House. (Published in Monday's <lb/>
Newfoundlander. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. WYATT rose to move the appointment of a <lb/>
select Committee to prepare the draft of an address in <lb/>
reply to the gracious speech with which his Excellency <lb/>
had been pleased to open the session. He (Mr. Wyatt) <lb/>
was sure they had all listened to the speech with par­ <lb/>
ticular attention, as he was satisfied there would be but <lb/>
One op ing it in that house and throughout <lb/>
the colony. His Excellency had addressed the Legis. <lb/>
lature for the first time since his assumption of the <lb/>
Government; and they must all feel gratified with the <lb/>
deep interest he manifested for the improvement of the <lb/>
country. He (Mr. Wyatt) felt he was ouly expressing <lb/>
the feeling of the House when he said they would give <lb/>
the most careful attention to all the suggestions of his <lb/>
Excellency, especially as these suggestions were for <lb/>
the benefit of the people whose representatives they <lb/>
were. They felt, with his Excellency, for the suffering <lb/>
to which so many of the people were reduced, alising <lb/>
from the failure of the seal fishery, last spring, the <lb/>
short catch in the shore cod-fishery, and the partial <lb/>
failure of the Labrador fishery. Having, in numerous <lb/>
instances, secured notining to sustain themselves and <lb/>
their families during the winter, a large number of the <lb/>
fishermen were in circumstances of deep distress, which <lb/>
the Government were doing all in their power to mit­ <lb/>
igate. The system of relief which had grown up of <lb/>
laate years was one of which they all dumplained, and <lb/>
which was liable to many abuses; but still they must <lb/>
not suffer the people to starve. It was necessary, <lb/>
however, that the attention of the House shall be <lb/>
given to the subject of poor relief, with the view of <lb/>
checking the growing evil of pauperism. His Excel­ <lb/>
lency suggested that they should give encouragement <lb/>
to the Mackerel and Bank fisheries, which were a <lb/>
source of profitable employment to the fishermen of <lb/>
other countries. The Bank fishery had been neglected <lb/>
for years, and with the present high price of fish there <lb/>
was every prospect of its proving remunerative. Th: <lb/>
Mackerel and Salmon fisheries were of great impor­ <lb/>
tance, and should have every encouragment the Legis­ <lb/>
lature could give them. His Excellency also directed <lb/>
their attention to the mineral resources of the Island, <lb/>
which there was reason to anticipate would furnish <lb/>
means of employment to a large number of our people, <lb/>
as well as a source of wealth to capitalists. He would <lb/>
now saj a few words on a subject of the deepest impor­ <lb/>
tance to the country, the proposed federation of the <lb/>
British North American Coionies. The Government <lb/>
had been invited last summer, to take part in a conven­ <lb/>
tion, at Quebec to take this important question into <lb/>
consideration, and had appointed the hon, the Speaker <lb/>
of that house, and the hon member for Piacentia and St. <lb/>
Mary's, lyelegates from this colony to the Convention. <lb/>
Although the Report of the proceedings of that Con­ <lb/>
ference was not yet laid before the House, it had been <lb/>
made public through the newspapers, and he was satis­ <lb/>
fied it had been read by every member of the House. <lb/>
They must all agree with his Excellency that the sub­ <lb/>
ject was one of the deepest interest to the whole com­ <lb/>
munity, and one which they ought to approach in a <lb/>
spirit of calm examination, with an earnest desire to <lb/>
come to such a conclusiod as would best promote the <lb/>
permanent interests of the colony. He (Mr. Wyatt) <lb/>
was aware that there was much difference of opinion <lb/>
it, this colony on the subject. Many considered the <lb/>
terms proposed for the admission of Newfoundland <lb/>
very favorable, while others were of a different opinion. <lb/>
It would be for the House, when the papers were laid <lb/>
before them, to weigh all that would be urged for and <lb/>
against the union. If, upon full consideration, it <lb/>
should be the opinion of the House that the decision <lb/>
should be referred to their constituents, he trusted <lb/>
that the matter would be fairly placed before those <lb/>
they represented. It was not a matter into which <lb/>
they should hastily rush, for they ought to bear in <lb/>
mind that the union once effected, it would be impos­ <lb/>
sible to undo it, should they not find it to their ad­ <lb/>
vantage. There were several other important subjects <lb/>
referred to in his Excellency's speech, to which the <lb/>
attention of the House would be directed in the course <lb/>
ef the session, and which he (Mr. Wyatt) was satisfied <lb/>
would receive that careful attention to which their <lb/>
importance entitled them. In conclusion, he (Mr. <lb/>
Wyatt) would join in his Excellency's prayer that the <lb/>
Altnighty Ruler of all events would bless their labors, <lb/>
and those of the whole community, and render them <lb/>
more productive, and the country more prosperous <lb/>
than for many years past. He moved that a Select <lb/>
Committee be appointed. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. WHITEway had much pleasure in seconding <lb/>
the motion proposed by his honorable friend Mr. <lb/>
Wyatt. That gentleman had spoken truly when he <lb/>
said that the speech of his Exceitency the Governor <lb/>
referred to many matters of great interest and im­ <lb/>
psrtance, as regards this country. But there was <lb/>
one surject alluded to in that speech, of paramount <lb/>
importance—that of the proposed Confederation of <lb/>
the British North American colonies. No one who <lb/>
had listened to the speech of his Excellency could but <lb/>
have been deeply impressed with the eminently en­ <lb/>
lightened views it contained. The dignified ione, <lb/>
style and language of his Excellency represent him <lb/>
as one possessing all the characteristics essential in <lb/>
the Representative of Her most Gracious Majesty the <lb/>
Queen. His Excellency had been among us but a <lb/>
short time; but that period had been devoted to ac­ <lb/>
quiring a thorough knowledge of the condition and <lb/>
requirements of the people. He had now given us <lb/>
the benefit of his inquiries. He had discovered evils, and <lb/>
he had not failed to suggest remedies. He had now <lb/>
discovered a great and growing evil which his prede­ <lb/>
cessors had pointed at, but which no government had <lb/>
as yet had the hardihood to grapple with and eradi­ <lb/>
cate, that abominable system as regards pauper re­ <lb/>
liet, which existed in this country. The reinedy sug­ <lb/>
gested by his Excellency was the only one which coard <lb/>
be imployed to secure an economical administration <lb/>
of the paupar fund; that is the raising of that fund by <lb/>
direct taxion, and casting upon the tax payers them­ <lb/>
selves, in every community, in duty of caecki,g the <lb/>
expenditure; or, in others words, making each Dis­ <lb/>
trict support its own paupers. He (Mr. Whiteway) <lb/></p> 

<p>ne opinion <lb/></p> 

<p>regrette that the Bill brought in by the government, <lb/>
during the last session, having this object in view, <lb/>
had been withdrawn. The enormous annual drain <lb/>
from the general revenue for poor relief had stayed <lb/>
public improvements; and public buildings were going <lb/>
into decay, our roads were scarcely passable, and their <lb/>
was no new work in operation. He (Mr. Whiteway) <lb/>
was gratified to learn that there was an intention on <lb/>
the part of the government to introduce some measure <lb/>
calculated to resuscitate the Bank Fishery. It was <lb/>
much to be regretted that sufficient enterprise did not <lb/>
exist amongst us to induce an active competition with <lb/>
foreigners in this branch of the fisheries; and that <lb/>
we were satisfied to depend altogether upon our shore <lb/>
and Labrador fisheries. He believed that the peºple <lb/>
of this country would be much better off, if, inst 'ad <lb/>
of lºcating themselves upon the most extreme points <lb/>
of land, as they had done, upon the coast, and carry­ <lb/>
ing on the fishery in small punts, as it were at their <lb/>
very doors, they had settled at the heads of the bays, <lb/>
where existed lands adapted for agricultural purposes. <lb/>
Then if they were provided with a larger class of fish­ <lb/>
ing craft, large enough to proceed to the Banks, if <lb/>
necessary.one branch of the family night be employed <lb/>
in making agriculture an auxiliary to the fishery, <lb/>
during the absence of the fisheimen, and upon <lb/>
their... return, attend to the curing department. <lb/>
He (Mr. Whiteway) was glad to see a recommenda­ <lb/>
tion to encourage agriculture. The best way, be be­ <lb/>
haved, to accomplish this, was to make good roads to <lb/>
the country. No sooner is a good road made through <lb/>
a piece of good land, than we at once see a tilt spring <lb/>
up, then a potato piot is cleared. Next follows a <lb/>
cottage, and a little firm. Give the people facilities <lb/>
for communication, free grants of land, and agriculture <lb/>
will advance. It requires no bounty. There is every <lb/>
reason to believe that sheep may be kept to an unlimi­ <lb/>
ted number upon our wild pasturage; but it seems to, <lb/>
be the cry on all sides, that the dogs prove a great <lb/>
obstacle... He (Mr. Whiteway) regretted that, not­ <lb/>
withstanding the strenuous efforts of one who had <lb/>
evinced a deep interest in agricultural improvement <lb/>
generally, and had accomplished much in that direction, <lb/>
Mr. Justice Robinson, his attempt to establish a joint <lb/>
stock company for the purpose of carrying out sheep <lb/>
farming on a large scale, had as yet come to nothing; <lb/>
not from lack of energy on the part of that gentleman, <lb/>
but because of the absence of that enterprising spirit <lb/>
among the people which induces a deviation from the <lb/>
old beaten track, and an embarking in new pursuits. <lb/>
The great and all-important subject of Education, it <lb/>
seemed, would be brought before the House during <lb/>
the present session. He (Mr. Whiteway) believed <lb/>
that in no colony of Great Britain was there so large <lb/>
an amonnt, in proportion to its population, appropr.­ <lb/>
ated oy the Government for educational purposes; but <lb/>
the benefits derived from it were not commensurate <lb/>
with the exuendiure. However, he did not *gree <lb/>
with those who asserted that the money was thrown <lb/>
away, fur it much good had been accomplished, a <lb/>
desire from improvement had been created, a taste for <lb/>
knowledge, and the people of the smallest settlement <lb/>
are now anxious to have their children taught, and the <lb/>
closing of their school would be viewed as a great <lb/>
deprivation, The idea of establishing a normal train­ <lb/>
ing school for teachers was a good oue, and, if carried <lb/>
out, would tend materially to improvement. The <lb/>
great want felt was for efficient teachers were obtained, <lb/>
tney must be adequately paid, for men of attainments <lb/>
would not be satisfied with the small salaries which <lb/>
are now paid. In his(Mr. Whiteway's) opinion, th–y <lb/>
had now arrived when the Government may fairly say <lb/>
to the people of every locality where a school is re­ <lb/>
quired, if you will subscribe or guarantee one half or <lb/>
one third, the government would provide the other <lb/>
half or two thirus of the teacher's salary; and it might <lb/>
be depended upon that there are few places in which <lb/>
to secure a good teacher, the people would not willing­ <lb/>
ly lend their aid, for they now are feeling the au van­ <lb/>
tages of having good schools. He (Mr. Whiteway) <lb/>
had frequently before, in his place in the house, spo­ <lb/>
ken of the ruin which must ensue from the manner <lb/>
in which our salmon fisheries were prosecuted. In <lb/>
rivers heretofore prolific, scarce a saluon now was to <lb/>
be scen. He had seen a net stretched across a river <lb/>
from bank to bank, the salmon piaying about below <lb/>
it, barred from getting into the river, and several sal­ <lb/>
mon in the net, which had not been visited for two <lb/>
days. This, perhaps, was an isolated case, but those <lb/>
who had attended to the subject knew well that in <lb/>
prosecuting this fishery the most ruinous practices <lb/>
were followed. There is an excellent law upon our <lb/>
statute book relative to this subject, but it is nugatory, <lb/>
there being no police regulations to secure its being <lb/>
garried out. More and more it was becoming apparent <lb/>
how necessary was our establishment of some general <lb/>
supervision of . he fisheries. Tue appointment of an <lb/>
able. educated and energetic man, as a general super­ <lb/>
intendent ºf the fisheries, with a handsome salary, to <lb/>
secure the services of an efficient person, having at <lb/>
his command a steamer, for the purpose of visiting <lb/>
every part of the Island, during the summer, and in­ <lb/>
wested with inagisterial authority, to enſurce the laws <lb/>
relative to the fisheries, was the only way this could <lb/>
be effected, and looking to the all importance of the <lb/>
subject, it was that for which, no matter what it might <lb/>
cost, should be the first money appropriated from the <lb/>
revenue; for the country was woolly dependent on <lb/>
the fisheries. The great question of Confederation <lb/>
was unquestionably the most important ever sub­ <lb/>
mitted to the L-gislatura of this coautry; and the <lb/>
view of being united to a country so rich in resources <lb/>
as Canada, New Brunswick add Nova Scotia, and form­ <lb/>
ing the nucleus of a great nation, was peculiary fas­ <lb/>
cinating and attractive. That country possessed every <lb/>
interual resource uecessary to becoine grº at; and it <lb/>
required no prºphetic spirit to forete what sue would <lb/>
be. Her unbounded forests, her vast mineral depos­ <lb/>
its as yet put partially developed, her rich plains, <lb/>
nelas for agricultural operation-, her magnificent <lb/>
rivers intersecting every part of the county, and <lb/>
forming natural bighway 8 for the tra.sport of her <lb/>
prouace, the safe and capacious hºrupurs of Nova <lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick, afforded th; means <lb/>
wnica required oaly sufficient population to raise her <lb/>
to the first rank, as a dependency, and in the course <lb/>
of years, the equal of the parent state. Was there <lb/>
anything wanting tilat nature had not bes.owed in <lb/>
that country 2 Still it had been said. that Canada <lb/>
wanted to tax Newfoundland to sustain her resources. <lb/>
Rich Canada abstracting from the barren island of <lb/>
Newfoundland, with 100,000 inhabitants one-thirtieth <lb/>
part of the whole population, a something to susta a <lb/>
her resources. The vicw was too absurd to need <lb/>
cominent. But it was a matter that required grave <lb/>
consideration. When once we had embarked in cou­ <lb/>
federation thera was no return. We were bound fur <lb/>
exer. It should not be disposed of hastily, hut be ap­ <lb/>
proached in a spirit of calul deliteration and at neat <lb/>
enquiry. Bat when once a conclusion had been ar­ <lb/></p> 

<p>* * - * * * <lb/></p> 

<p>*­ <lb/>
* . . <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/>
;: <lb/>
; <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>