<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-06" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1869-02-06">6 February 1869</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1869-02-10"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="4"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_3.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_4.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2019-01-25">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2019-01-25">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_3"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_3.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_4"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_4.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="3" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_3.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">3</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANER.</fw>


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-25, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->
<!--<p>"[costſNUED FROM. Last PAGE.] <lb/>
and in many of the provisions by which it was <lb/>
...d he would wish to see it sottened down<lb break="no"/>If, then, this taxation should be continued, am. <lb/>
cºntinued it must be if Government should <lb/>
yield to the pressure of hon. members,the necessad <lb/>
*yeffect will be that the struggling man will be <lb/>
brought to a level with the pauper- But not <lb/>
one ord of sympathy do we hear for this class, <lb/>
and not one word of sympathy for the supplying <lb/>
merchant, who, after losing principal and inter<lb break="no"/>est, upon the supplies he issues, loses the heavy <lb/>
duties which he has paid, and often, loses his <lb/>
capitul into the bargain. He believed that <lb/>
all the evils of the country took their rise from <lb/>
the credit system, which bears as heavily as <lb/>
slavery upon the people, and which has brought <lb/>
ruin, not only to the supplying, but to the sup<lb break="no"/>plied. The ſaith between parties was broken <lb/>
down, and if the system could be done, ºy <lb/>
with all classes would be benefitted. As to Con: <lb/>
federation, his (Mr. R's) sentiments were well <lb/>
known. He had besa favorable to it even <lb/>
before he became a member of this IIouse, and <lb/>
he was still convinced that it would prove <lb/>
teneficial to the country. But he did not, be: <lb/>
lieve that it would wipe away pauperism all at <lb/>
... Even after Confederallon became, as: <lb/>
complished. We should still have to contend <lb/>
with pauperism. ... But there Wº... gº". <lb/>
opinion among all classe: in favour of the <lb/>
sºheme, and in his own district many of the <lb/>
leading men had come completely round, and <lb/>
many would accept Confederatiºn *** * the <lb/>
terms of the Quebec Convention. However, <lb/>
he merely touched upon this subject in pºsing: <lb/>
He was still of the opinion that a union with <lb/>
Canada upon equitable term.could not fail to <lb/>
prove advantageous to us: The matter before <lb/>
the chair was oas upon which every hºn mºm<lb break="no"/>ber should express his opinion. For his pºº <lb/>
gave his cordial adherence tº the course adopte <lb/>
Sã by the Government in oilºring." resolute <lb/>
resistance to the resumption of pauper relieſ. <lb/>
Mr. Hodsºr—The Government of Sir <lb/>
Hugh Hoyles gave more scope.* Pauper <lb/>
Relief than any other Government, in this <lb/>
country. The Opposition were nº the origi<lb break="no"/>nators of pauperism, and the population they <lb/>
represented was the best in Newfoundland. <lb/>
ºr, Roºzz-It was fifteen years old then<lb break="no"/>Mr. H, was not in the habit of telling lies. It <lb/>
was too much truth he toll. It was because hº <lb/>
ºld the truth that he evoked the hostility of <lb/>
ion, members and of other men. For the in<lb break="no"/>formation of the hon. member, Mr. Rorke, he <lb/>
would tell him that if the policy of Mr. Kent's <lb/>
government had been carried out he would <lb/>
not be dealing in pauper relief. It had not <lb/>
been chronic. <lb/>
Mr. Bennerr wished to say a few words in <lb/>
sustainment of the position which the Gov<lb break="no"/>ºnment had assumed upon the question of <lb/>
poor relief. He believed, and the Opposition <lb/>
or at least those of them who were candid and <lb/>
sensible men, would admit that in this matter <lb/>
the Government had been actuated by ue <lb/>
political motive. The Government were, tº <lb/>
tertain to be sustained in the course they had <lb/>
taken, by the intelligent and independent, as <lb/>
they were certain to receive the disapprobat.on <lb/>
et all those who looked to then for support<lb break="no"/>and as the latter class was far the more <lb/>
numerous one, they must of course expect <lb/>
that the disapprobation would be the greatºr. <lb/>
The Government were, however, sustained by <lb/>
conscious rectitude—by the knowledge that <lb/>
they had done what was right and prope . <lb/>
He felt proud of the stand which the Govera<lb break="no"/>ment had taken, for it was a noble one<lb break="no"/>and had to be taken at some time. It was a <lb/>
matter of contention where and by whom <lb/>
the system of poor , relief to the able<lb break="no"/>bodied had been introduced and who was to <lb/>
blame for it. He (Mr. B.) was too young a <lb/>
member of this Assembly to know himself, but <lb/>
nothing was certain,it was ea.ing as that the very <lb/>
vitals of the country. He considered that it <lb/>
was stopped at a very good time, though for <lb/>
himself he must say that he would have desried <lb/>
to have seen it done some three years ago. It <lb/>
became plain to every man that sooner or later <lb/>
this system must have au end, and what time <lb/>
could be better for stopping it than when there <lb/>
wasa prospect of a fair fishery? That was the case <lb/>
last year. Last winter when poor relief was <lb/>
given out and the packet irozen up in Placentia <lb/>
§ay and the Ariel at the Northward lic <lb/>
(Mr. B.) felt that it was indeed a trying <lb/>
time. Many families to the Westward <lb/>
supported themselves by Herrings, alone. <lb/>
Bº (Mr. B.) would indeed be sorry that the <lb/>
Government should let any man starve. This <lb/>
poor rekef system was something like a man <lb/>
with a chronic desease. He meets a surgeon <lb/>
who says if the affected part is cut of you will <lb/>
live, otherwise you die. He submits to the <lb/>
ºperation. He keenly feels the cutting of the <lb/>
knife as it divided the tissues, sinews, and <lb/>
veins; but in a few days the anguish passes away; <lb/>
he is a new man and he blesses the surgeon who <lb/>
sould not have saved him without making him <lb/>
suffer for a time. The poor relief system bore the <lb/>
aame analogy to the Government that the dis<lb break="no"/>ease did to the man. The people would no <lb/>
doubt suffer a little, but it was for their ulimate <lb/>
good. He had much pleasure in giving cordial <lb/>
support to paragraph belors the chair. <lb/>
The motion that the second paragraph be adop<lb break="no"/>isd, was then put and carried. <lb/>
The Committee then rose, and reported pro<lb break="no"/>gress. To sit again to-morrow. <lb/>
The House then adjourned until to-norrow <lb/>
at 8 o'clock. <lb/></p> 
-->
<p rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, February 6, <lb/></p> 

<p>The House met at 3 o'clock, pursuant to adjourn<lb/>ment. <lb/></p> 

<p>
<persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName> complained that his speech of Wednes<lb break="no"/>day fast bad not been properly reposed. Talking <lb/>
of the poor relief he had said that he did not find so <lb/>
    much <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> with the Proclamation as with the speech <lb/>
    of his Excellency, whcih it was known was <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> speech <lb/>
    of <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>

<cb/>

been given. Surely the Executive were aware, that <lb/>
such was not the case, that a great portion of the <lb/>
people could not provide themselves with subsistence <lb/>
for the coming winter. They were completely des<lb break="no"/>titute until the fish came—numbers had to go with<lb break="no"/>out food to catch fish for their daily food. It was <lb/>
cruel to say that these men should provide, for the <lb/>
coming winter. How could they do it? That part <lb/>
of the speech was heartless. Most of these had no <lb/>
seed potatoes and had to live on their neighbors. <lb/>
He had also mentioned a circumstance which occur<lb break="no"/>red in the East Indies and it was not reported. <lb/>
There was a famine there and those who perished <lb/>
numbered by thousands. A telegram was sent to <lb/>
the Imperial Government. The Secretary for India <lb/>
immediately replied, authorising the use of the pub<lb break="no"/>lic funds to any amount for that they should not <lb/>
permit any British subject to starve. The merchants <lb/>
subscribed £10,000 and telegraphed that that money <lb/>
could be used and more if required. Not only was <lb/>
that sum provided for, but seed for the rice crop was <lb/>
distributed for the next year, and men were employ<lb break="no"/>ed to bring water from a long way off, so that no <lb/>
second failure should happen. That was a paternal <lb/>
Government and he wanted to contrast it with ours, <lb/>
which was going to allow the people to starve. The <lb/>
Imperial Government would, he (Mr. G.) felt sure, <lb/>
be much annoyed if any people here were allowed <lb/>
to perish. With the Imperial Government whites <lb/>
were as good as black, and he believed the people <lb/>
who were starving in India were blacks. None of <lb/>
this had been reported, while the hon. and learned <lb/>
member for Brigus was reported at such length that <lb/>
every one was afraid to read it. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Messrs. Hogsett, Talbot, and Renouf also com<lb break="no"/>plained that their speeches were neither fully nor <lb/>
correctly reported. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA1">HON. A. SHEA</persName>.—From the conduct of hon mem<lb break="no"/>bers opposite, a stranger visiting this. Assembly <lb/>
would have considerable difficulty in ariving at the <lb/>
conclusion that it was convened for the transaction <lb/>
of important public business. The last two hours <lb/>
have been frittered away with the most puerile <lb/>
miserable feelings as to the reports and the Reporters. <lb/>
Were hon gentlemen so uncertain of their status in <lb/>
the opinion of the public that they had only to rely <lb/>
upon the clap-trap denunciations, of the reports, <lb/>
which session after session they had been uttering? <lb/>
Surely hon gentlemen whose position was no strong <lb/>
as theirs, could very well afford even to allow their <lb/>
remarks to go unreported. For his hon (Mr S) part <lb/>
he would be willing to make a bargain with hon <lb/>
gentlemen, if the Reporters would only agree to <lb/>
publish every word of what hon members opposite <lb/>
said, he would be quite content that the Government <lb/>
should go unreported. The character of the Op<lb break="no"/>position would then speak for itself, and the public <lb/>
would say these gentlemen constitute the Opposition <lb/>
and in Opposition they should be left. It appeared <lb/>
then that the leadership of the Opposition had been <lb/>
changed, and he had to congratulate the Opposition <lb/>
on the announcement lately made by the hon <lb/>
member Mr. Glen,that they were now a united body, <lb/>
that they had discarded the hon member Mr Hogsett; <lb/>
they had found him doubtless an able and an ener<lb break="no"/>getic leader, a very ene, getic leader, but he was the <lb/>
Jonah of the lot, and they had discovered that it was <lb/>
necessary to throw him overboard. Well, they had <lb/>
east the hon. member overboard,and he (hon Mr.S) <lb/>
did not dispute their discretion. For the last four <lb/>
years they bad the repatation of being rather un<lb break="no"/>harmonious, and the causes of this discord he hon (A. <lb/>
S) would endeavour to trace. Some two years ago <lb/>
ths hon member (Mr Hogsett) discovered that <lb/>
something not very creditable was said of him in <lb/>
one of the Halifax papers.<lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:HOGS1">MR. HOGSETT</persName>—Yes, and you wrote it. You <lb/>
are a scoundrel. You always were a scoundrel. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The hon. the SPEAKER</persName>—So long as I have the <lb/>
privilege of maintaining order in this House, I shall <lb/>
not allow expressions such as this to pass unmarked <lb/>
by my disapproval, and if there be any approach to a <lb/>
repetition of them I shall certainly take the chair and <lb/>
use such means as are at the disposal of the House to <lb/>
prevent the recurrence of unseeuly language or to <lb/>
punish it. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Hon. A. SHEA</persName>—It is an extraordinary fact that <lb/>
those persons who are most free with insolent obser<lb break="no"/>vations cannot bear the have the pickled rod applied <lb/>
to their bare backs, wriggling and twisting and <lb/>
burning, they exhibit a most uneasy consciousness of <lb/>
their punishment. To proceed. The hon, gentle<lb break="no"/>man want to Halifax to vindicate his reputation, but <lb/>
before going he called upon him (hon. A Shea) for a <lb/>
note of recominendation. He (hon. A Shea) was not <lb/>
very anxious to give the hon. member a note, for <lb/>
there in a certain class of persons whom one does not <lb/>
care to recommend; but he did not want to refuse <lb/>
and he gave the hon. member a note of that kind <lb/>
which a man gives when he would rather let it alone <lb/>
On the faith of that note, and one from the hon. <lb/>
Attorney General, the hon. member got into good <lb/>
company with which he beeane so enamoured that <lb/>
though he had left here a violent Anti Confederate, <lb/>
in one short fortnight he returned a rabid Confede<lb break="no"/>rate and denounced his party. The hon. member <lb/>
was impatient of any delay in the matter of Con<lb break="no"/>federation and even in Halifax he had pledged his <lb/>
word that as leader of the opposition he would have <lb/>
the whole matter arranged and delegates would be <lb/>
forthwith despatched to the convention then about <lb/>
to sit in Loudon. After that the hon. member <lb/>
had a travelling fit, and in his absence <lb/>
a great many ugly things were said of him by his <lb/>
friends. When he returned, we had what is popu<lb break="no"/>larly termed "wigs on the green." He came in in a <lb/>
temper; he said ugly things of his friends, we had <lb/>
very disgracelul scenes nearly every day, and the <lb/>
propinquity of the parties suggested the necessity of <lb/>
the police. For that session the hoa gentleman was <lb/>
adrift, and no approach to union was made. This <lb/>
time the hon member was the scape-goat, that was <lb/>
episode No. 1 illustrative of the exceeding harmony <lb/>
of this united party. The next year the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber Mr. Parsons was the scapegoat. They discovered, <lb/>
he thought that they discovered that that hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman had been "raising the wind" somewhere, <lb/>
and it was just about the time that the hon and gallant <lb/>
Major was scouting that military appointment of his, <lb/>
and in fact they were all hunting together. As the <lb/>
story goes the hon member. Mr Parsons doubled <lb/>
them all; what he got they did not know, but they <lb/>
strongly suspected that it was some of the stuff with <lb/>
which people buy butter. They said that he had used <lb/>
his share and be should not hunt with them again. <lb/>
        They made things very uncomfortable for him and, <lb/>
his desk was actually put up with a broom upon it <lb/>
and a label "For Sale." Ultimately, this came to <lb/>
an end, and this was episode No. 2 in the harmony <lb/>
of the party. The fact is, that though they are so <lb/>
few in number, this eterual itching for something <lb/>
which is got on that side of the House, makes them <lb/>
all so jealous that they are determined that not one <lb/>
shall get before another. The real understanding <lb/>
between them is, in effect,not even as good as it looks <lb/>
At the present time they are threatening, vengeance <lb/>
npon some one else; and this is the harmouious <lb/>
party headed by the hon member Mr Glen. The <lb/>
hon and veutrable geutleman had undertaken an <lb/>
onerous duty, and it his tenure of office depended <lb/> 
upon the preservation of order anong his party, he <lb/>
        <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> (Mr S) heard that it would soon be given up in <lb/>

<cb/>

disgust. We have listened in vain for the reasons <lb/>
and circumstances which led to the dethronement of <lb/>
the former leader. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
He could now refer to the Speech of the hon. <lb/>
member, Mr. Renouf, delivered last evening, a <lb/>
speech which had been very properly charac<lb break="no"/>terised by the hon. Member for Carbonear, Mr. <lb/>
Rorke, as one containing merely a rehash of all <lb/>
the old utterances to which we had been listen<lb break="no"/>ing for the past four years. It was made up of <lb/>
his staple topics, topics, which with him never <lb/>
die out, and without which he would be utterly <lb/>
unable to make a speech. All knew what these <lb/>
topics were; the Amalgamated Government, <lb/>
Confederation, the hon. Receiver General and <lb/>
himself, (hon. Mr. S.) the late Chairman of <lb/>
the Board of Works, Mr. Casey, occasionally <lb/>
because he was an absent man, came in for a <lb/>
share of vituperative abuse. Now suppose the <lb/>
Government and those connected with it deserv<lb break="no"/>ed all the abuse which the abundant vocabulary <lb/>
of the hon. member heaped upon them; sup<lb break="no"/>pose all the charges which he had made were <lb/>
perfectly true, suppose that we were all of that <lb/>
abandoned character which he describes, how <lb/>
does all that affect the question under considera<lb break="no"/>tion One would imagine that after having <lb/>
spent four years in abusing us, without strength<lb break="no"/>ening or elevating his own party in the eyes of <lb/>
the public, and without injury to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, the hon. member would have made an <lb/>
effort to produce something original. Why did <lb/>
he not consult his colleague, and ask him to <lb/>
suggest something to make a strong impression? <lb/>
But no, it was the old story of the blind horse <lb/>
tarning the mill, and the effusions of the hon. <lb/>
member were so nauseating that they only serve<lb break="no"/>ed to put hon. gentlemen on this side of the <lb/>
Honse asleep. Certainly there were some <lb/>
allowances to be made for the feelings of <lb/>
irritation under which hon. gentlemen opposite <lb/>
aboured. They had now been in opposition <lb/>
eight or nine years; and four years ago, when <lb/>
the question of Confederation came before the <lb/>
country, they had great hopes of doing something <lb/>
for themselves. They fell in with the strong <lb/>
and popular side. They took the flowing tide, <lb/>
and year after year expected to see the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment make some false step, by which they would <lb/>
walk into office. They thought that the goal <lb/>
time was near at hand, that the promised land <lb/>
was in view, when they would be called upon to <lb/>
enjoy the exquisite delight of seeing the hon. <lb/>
member. Mr. Hogsett, once more Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, and once more the protector of ther rights <lb/>
and liberties. Things, however, were looking <lb/>
gloomy with them of late. The feeling that exist<lb break="no"/>ed so strong two or three years ago had under<lb break="no"/>gone a complete change. The tide was slacken<lb break="no"/>ing, and from present appearances, they feared <lb/>
that the grand objects to which they had been look<lb break="no"/>ing forward were not likely to be effected. They saw <lb/>
that public opinion was not what it had been; <lb/>
that Confederation was not now the dreaded <lb/>
bugbear it had becn considered. Lately, in tile <lb/>
district of Harbor Grace, the supposed stronghold <lb/>
of the Anti-Confederates, an important election <lb/>
had taken place, an election that had resulted in <lb/>
the return to this House of a gentleman pledged to <lb/>
support Confederation. This was indeed a death<lb break="no"/>blow to the hopes of hon. members opposite. <lb/>
        They were now desirous of doing away with tile <lb/>
effect of that election, and say it turned on differ<lb break="no"/>ent causes, that the hon. member. Mr. Godden, <lb/>
never published his views of Confederation in his <lb/>
Address. Well, there was an old stager on the <lb/>
other side, who knew very well how the pulse of <lb/>
the district beat, an artful clever tellow, who knew <lb/>
well how to manipulate the people. Wn at was <lb/>
his course? In his Address he spoke of every <lb/>
subject but Confederation; because he had before <lb/>
committed himself to an opinin, upon it, and haul <lb/>
he again referred to the question he would have <lb/>
ruined his prospects. If he had believed that the <lb/>
Electors of that district were opposed to Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, would he not have made use of it? Under <lb/>
all these circumstances, then, we were justified in <lb/>
regarding the result of this election as a deliberate <lb/>
expression of opinion upon the subject of Confed<lb break="no"/>eration by the people of the district of Harbor <lb/>
Grace. Besides all this, we had the testimony of <lb/>
the hon. member for Carbonear, Mr. Rorke, who <lb/>
was always consistent upon, this question. That <lb/>
election also proved that the people of that dis<lb break="no"/>trict were satisfied with the manner in which the <lb/>
affairs of the Colony had been managed by the <lb/>
present Government, that they desired to see Con<lb break="no"/>federation settled, and the Opposition kept; here <lb/>
they were, in the minority, where they were harm<lb break="no"/>less, and where, for ttie benefit of the country, <lb/>
they should remain. They say, with the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, of all political imposters keep as clear of <lb/>
the roaring patriots, of those who roar their flatu<lb break="no"/>lent rhetoric, day atter day, and whose only <lb/>
desire is to place themselves in positions of emolu<lb break="no"/>ment, Now what were we called upon to consi<lb break="no"/>der in the question before us? He would not <lb/>
contine himself merely to the paragraph before <lb/>
the chair, but would refer also to the one which <lb/>
had been adopted last evening. The question of <lb/>
the condition of the poor necessarily raised ano<lb break="no"/>ther. How was that conditiou to be relieved, <lb/>
and what was the remedy? The doctrine of the <lb/>
Government was, that there was at present no <lb/>
substantial relief to be tound within ourselves, <lb/>
that that relief must come from an agency outside, <lb/>
who had the power and the means of doing for us <lb/>
what we could not do for ourselves. We may be <lb/>
as capable as any men to conduct our own affairs, <lb/>
but the power to do so no longer remained with us. <lb/>
It was not a question, whether we were willing or <lb/>
able, but whether we had the power to effect any <lb/>
benefit for the country as we are. This, then, <lb/>
was the doctrine upon which the Government <lb/>
took its stand. What we were laboring under <lb/>
now was want of employment for the people. If <lb/>
the labouring population had means of employ<lb break="no"/>ment, we would not have, them now starving <lb/>
about our streets. Additional, means of employ<lb break="no"/>ment, then, was what was needed. The merchants <lb/>
here were not disposed to exteud their trade, but, <lb/>
on the contrary, were very much curtailing it. <lb/>
That was of course their own business, and they <lb/>
had a perfect right to do what they liked. The <lb/>
supply last year had been a very meagre one, and <lb/>
this year it would be less. Under these circum<lb break="no"/>stances the proposition of saving £25,000 of our <lb/>
Civil Expenditure, however likable in itself, <lb/>
would be useless as a means of restoring the <lb/>
country to prosperity. It was idle to think that it <lb/>
would have any effect. It was certainly wise and pro<lb break="no"/>per that we should make all the reduction that was <lb/>
        possible and consistent <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> discharge <lb/>
of the public service. But the proposal as it <lb/>
stood was easily comprehended. If such ever <lb/>
were done, the opposition, if they got into <lb/>
power, would bring back the present existing <lb/>
state of things, so that their assumed patriotism <lb/>
    has not likely, in this instance, to decieve any<lb break="no"/>one. Were hon. members <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> enough to <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> be<lb break="no"/>
    
    <cb/>
    
    lieve that such a flimsy pretext would effect the <lb/>
        purpose they had in view? Look on the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
dition of the operative population, last spring. <lb/>
Hundreds of them could not obtain employment <lb/>
or supplies, and had to stow themselves away <lb/>
in Labrador vessels, to endeavour to earn a <lb/>
precarious subsistence. What prospect, then, <lb/>
was before us this spring? And what means <lb/>
were at our disposal to free the streets from the <lb/>
starving and wretched creatures that would fill <lb/>
them? If then, we can do no good for them <lb/>
ourselves, if we could find no employment for <lb/>
them, it is surely wise to seek assistance from <lb/>
those who are able to give it; and this was the <lb/>
course which the Government proposed to <lb/>
adopt. As we were likely to have a repetition <lb/>
of the state of things, which existed last spring, <lb/>
and as we were unable to obtain among our<lb break="no"/>selves employment for the people, we <lb/>
thought it advisable to put ourselves in commu<lb break="no"/>nication with the Authorities in Canada and <lb/>
obtain employment for our men on the Railway <lb/>
works that are progressing there. He (hon. Mr. <lb/>
S.) was happy to say that the efforts to effect <lb/>
this had been successful, and in the spring he would <lb/>
be prepared to enter into an agreement with and <lb/>
hire eight hundred men for this purpose. They <lb/>
would all be hired by, written agreement, and <lb/>
their wages would be paid thoughly, and one half <lb/>
could be received by their wives and families here. <lb/>
They would be taken to Canada in a steamer, and <lb/>
at the end of the season would be sent back to <lb/>
their homes if they desired it. He would, then, <lb/>
leave it to the public to say what the effect of this <lb/>
would be. This, them, was what the Government <lb/>
had been doing while the opposition were roaring. <lb/>
Take eight hundred men out of St. John's, and it <lb/>
would give employment to all those who remained. <lb/>
However, the opposition might think lightly of it, <lb/>
he (hon. Mr. S.) would tell them that when he <lb/>
said he would be prepared to give employment to <lb/>
800 men, the public would believe him. He was <lb/>
satisfied to leave the matter to the good judge<lb break="no"/>ment of the people, and was assured it would take <lb/>
more than the sneers of the opposition to affect so <lb/>
good an arragenment. He perfectly agreed with <lb/>
those who said that it was a misfortune that we <lb/>
should be obliged to send them away, but surely <lb/>
that was better than keeping them here to to starve, <lb/>
and their absence would be the means of letting <lb/>
others get reasonable wages for their services. <lb/>
This, then, is a part of what we have been <lb/>
doing, and this is what we meant by <lb/>
what opposition call selling the country by Con<lb break="no"/>federation. Here the hon. member referred to <lb/>
a letter read by the hon. member, Mr. Renouf, <lb/>
and which he stated had come from Ottawa, <lb/>
adressing the people of Newfoundland not to <lb/>
come there for employment. He drew atteation <lb/>
to what he called the clumsy way in waich the <lb/>
hon. member, Mr. Renouf, sought to effect his <lb/>
purpose, and pointed out that portion of it which <lb/>
stated that Emigrants were daily arriving from <lb/>
Europe, as a contradiction the position which <lb/>
the hon. member endeavoured to sustain. <lb/>
There was an idea abroad that it was the inter<lb break="no"/>est of the merehants to keep down the price of <lb/>
labor. He (hon. Mr. S.) did not agree with <lb/>
that, or that such could be the interest of any <lb/>
class. If the people were not kept employed, <lb/>
all the interests which depended on the laborer <lb/>
must share his circumstances. There was no <lb/>
more sure sign of the state of any country that <lb/>
        the condition of its laboring classes <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> might <lb/>
appear badly that the men should go as away <lb/>
but he (hon. Mr. S.) doubted if the men them<lb break="no"/>selves would think so, or if they would place <lb/>
faith in those who endeavored to persuade them <lb/>
to that offset. He hoped improved prospects <lb/>
in this country would enable them to return. <lb/>
No force would be used; they could go or stay, <lb/>
just at it pleased them to do, The House had <lb/>
been treated to great dissertations on pauper <lb/>
relief, and on this paragraph in the address. <lb/>
He (hon. Mr. S.) really found it difficult to <lb/>
comprehend the views of hon. members op<lb break="no"/>posite. On the first day of the session the <lb/>
Government, Proclamation was highly com<lb break="no"/>manded by them, the only exception taken <lb/>
being that the Government should have pro<lb break="no"/>vided seed potatoes. He (hon. Mr. S.) hardly <lb/>
ever knew of any benefit being derived from <lb/>
the issue of seed potatoes, and he had no faith in <lb/>
such a course, for the seed potatoes were, in <lb/>
most cases, either eaten, or never reached those <lb/>
for whom they were intended. However, last <lb/>
spring, the Government, in deference with wishes <lb/>
of the House, were prepared to issus them, and <lb/>
entered into correspondence with parties in the <lb/>
other Provinces, in order to ascertain terms, &amp;c. <lb/>
They found the prices asked were enormous, <lb/>
about 11s per barrel at the place of shipment, <lb/>
and one fourth of them might be unfit for use <lb/>
on arrival here. No unqualified guarantee to <lb/>
issue had been given by the Government, but <lb/>
only an intimation that if they could do so they <lb/>
would; and if it had been practicable, on reason<lb break="no"/>able conditions, it would have been done. The <lb/>
finances of the country were in such a condition <lb/>
that they could not make the necessary ad<lb break="no"/>vances, and they felt that, under the circum<lb break="no"/>stances, they should abandon the idea. Was <lb/>
no one to be thougut of but those who had land? <lb/>
What do hon. members opposite propose to do <lb/>
for the fishermen? Their claims were equally <lb/>
good, yet hon. members did not propose that <lb/>
one shilling should be provided for them. <lb/>
Those who had land ought to be in a position to <lb/>
provide their own seed potatoes, and be inde<lb break="no"/>pendent of such aid from the Government. <lb/>
The effect of the Government's refusal to buy <lb/>
was that the seed patotous came down for sale, <lb/>
and as the Government was not in the market, <lb/>
every industrious man was enabled to obtaian <lb/>
seed potatoes at a reasonable rate. Every <lb/>
barrel that came was put in the ground. The <lb/>
Government could have done no more. They <lb/>
might have given them to differeut people, but <lb/>
that was all. No more would have been plant<lb break="no"/>ed. Year after year the Government had been <lb/>
taunted with this poor relief. They would <lb/>
now give a trial to its suppression. They meant <lb/>
        to abide by the Proclamation to its fullest ex<lb break="no"/>tent. It was called for. It might be <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> and <lb/>
severe to some, but it was a measure of common <lb/>
justice and fair ply to the country at large. <lb/> 
The system of pauper relief was over a quarter <lb/> 
of a century old, so that on that score there was <lb/> 



    <!-- IC, 2019-01-25, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>very little room for rº <lb/>
equally to blame. . The <lb/>
escaps his share of thºr <lb/>
and cowardly, and could <lb/>
the facts were before t <lb/>
Mr. S.) merely disclain <lb/>
member to lay the blame <lb/>
The dodge of denial had <lb/>
and so frequently and lo <lb/>
S.) would have believed i <lb/>
the contrary,and he had o <lb/>
duce to hou.member opp <lb/>
and convicted thens of ml <lb/>
that they had begged of <lb/>
issue Poor Relief, and th: <lb/>
tion relief had been issue. <lb/>
an attempt at some round <lb/>
nication, but the Governm <lb/>
mise anything but direct <lb/>
though hon. members mu <lb/>
the Government were in p <lb/>
munications, they disclaid <lb/>
attack the Government. <lb/>
would have the public to <lb/>
eould thus deny tileir own <lb/>
a tolerable good specimen <lb/>
and showed the result of ti <lb/>
§ear ss the Government. <lb/>
a statement of the expend <lb/>
bodied poor in the year 1 <lb/>
mambers read from the st. <lb/>
received by each district.) <lb/>
that with the exception of <lb/>
war, in proportion to P <lb/>
difference between any one <lb/>
8..John's having, as asual, <lb/>
anembrs oppºsite said the <lb/>
ble, that they did not force <lb/>
this expenditure. If they <lb/>
that the expenditure was <lb/>
was not sequired, why not <lb/>
ment and tell thein so, and <lb/>
it? They did not do so, b <lb/>
diture to go on, and <lb/>
jeast, became rasponsible. <lb/>
them to endeavor by m <lb/>
denial of their band writit <lb/>
responsibility, or fasten on <lb/>
pºor relief. Was not the <lb/>
Main expended with the co <lb/>
repre enta io is, from time <lb/>
mambers of that district 2 <lb/>
psaditure was not warrant <lb/>
these lion, members were r <lb/>
in not asking that it shonid <lb/>
(hon. Mr. S.) did not maa. <lb/>
did not best out the expe <lb/>
that the members had the <lb/>
they should not attempt to <lb/>
abil ty. The circumstanc <lb/>
tue system of poor relief, <lb/>
buost men to think that an <lb/>
down sh, uld be made. W <lb/>
the Proclamation was iss <lb/>
approved ot. Tuo old syst <lb/>
siſ down to one dead Îevel, <lb/>
try without an independe <lb/>
symptoms of a desirº to giv <lb/>
tion were now becoming ap <lb/>
Mr. Hogskrr —Nºt on out <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. SHEA.- Yes, * <lb/>
hon. leader ot the Oppositio, <lb/>
inhumau, and proclaimed his <lb/>
means to induce the Goverut <lb/>
and he is suitporteſt by hon, u <lb/>
Mr. HøgskºT.-\-No. <lb/>
Hon. Mr. SHEA.-Ynti chº <lb/>
made his state, neut. The attº <lb/>
induce the Guveruinent to ab <lb/>
on this imatter. Were there <lb/>
country who had a duty to di <lb/>
poor as well as the Govern <lb/>
3ountry was the relief of the <lb/>
Government. The systein ha. <lb/>
iu existence, and no doubt tº <lb/>
termination of it would bring <lb/>
in such a state of things it b <lb/>
all to lend a relping hand to <lb/>
was sorry to see that as yº <lb/>
John's did not come up to ti <lb/>
appear to appreciate the to <lb/>
the country is placed. This <lb/>
the neeessity of considering V <lb/>
not by Statüte compel all to <lb/>
to their taeans. He ſhon. M <lb/>
the hors. niemixer for Ferryla <lb/>
110 ntan would be allowed to <lb/>
arreat difficulties if the questio. <lb/>
opened again. The old abus' <lb/>
for it is a thing which contains <lb/>
elements and temptations to <lb/>
it would be matter of great re; <lb/>
of circumstances, the Governii <lb/>
pelled to yield. The Go, <lb/>
duty to perfºrm, and it was <lb/>
they were withou; a law to <lb/>
the poor. He knew there w <lb/>
great difficulties in the way <lb/>
Provisions of such a law, and <lb/>
Proportions of assessments, b <lb/>
for the Governiment any loug <lb/>
Juty of keeping the paupers. <lb/>
ºuths of hard suſtering, dit <lb/>
efore them, and he hoped all <lb/>
and contribute to tide the pêu'ſ <lb/>
*; think they would again <lb/>
*::::::::#; and if these tuou <lb/>
}. . the prospects of the <lb/>
#. ºugh improved. Oue <lb/>
solation was that in this criºl <lb/>
on our 9wn resources, as wºre <lb/>
claita *.*ny other people, I <lb/>
the Potaisión, we cºnti mak. <lb/>
people there. When the Nº. <lb/>
tailed, last year, and great iſ <lb/>
É. *uión;8t, the fisheru <lb/>
elt to ask for relief, but ſºle I, <lb/>
Flo and Quebec and tha cºº <lb/>
ent cities, ſurwarded £10,000 <lb/>
That was a practical proof ºt <lb/>
They had a claim, and they <lb/>
and funds were sent them, uſ, <lb/>
ºf dis;ribution telegraphed this <lb/>
&amp;uired, No doubt some would <lb/>
but call it what you will, <lb/>
**.xelcome here now?" w <lb/>
**sisting our people, but we <lb/>
ºld it would be or 'great dau <lb/>
Canada in forag paupérés. <lb/>
was expected to do all, and to <lb/>
No tuatiºn whº went ºw <lb/>
ºnent were to blame, a.d the <lb/>
to be cast on their should. <lb/>
logic of hon, gentl <lb/>
• gentlenipa d <lb/>
$xamine the question. Tws <lb/>
<lb break="no"/> </p>-->

<pb n="4" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_4.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">4</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>

    <!-- IC, 2019-01-25, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>ºve that such a flimsy pretext would effect the <lb/>
rpose they had in view? Look on the &amp;eg <lb/>
tion of the operative population, last *Pring, <lb/>
undreds of them could not obtain employment <lb/>
supplies, and had to stow thanselves away <lb/>
Labrador vessels, to endeavour to earn a <lb/>
ecarious subsistence. What prospect, then, <lb/>
* before us this spring 7 And what means <lb/>
re at our disposal to free the streets from the <lb/>
rving and wretched creatures that would filt <lb/>
sm? If then, we can do uo good for thºs <lb/>
iselves, if we could find no umployment for <lb/>
*m, it is surely wise to seek assistance from <lb/>
ge who are able to give it; and this was the <lb/>
irse which the Government proposed tº <lb/>
opt. As we were likely to have a repetition <lb/>
th" state of things which existed last sprint, <lb/>
i as we were unable to obtain among ou. <lb/>
ves employment for the people, we <lb/>
rugbt it advisable to put ourselves in com.nu. <lb/>
ation with the Authorities in Canad , and <lb/>
an employment for our men on the Railway <lb/>
rks that are progressing there. He (hon. Alº. <lb/>
was happy to say that the efforts to affaes. <lb/>
3 had been successful,and iu the spring he woult <lb/>
prepared to enter into an agreeinent with and <lb/>
e eignt, hundred mººn ior tin.s purpose. They <lb/>
uld all be hired by written agreement, and <lb/>
ºir wages would be paid unoucilly, and one mair <lb/>
uld be received by their wives and families her. <lb/>
ey would be taken to Canada in a steamer, aſſº <lb/>
the end of the season would be sent tº t = <lb/>
* hones, it they desired it. He would, then, <lb/>
we it to the public to szy what ind effect of th: <lb/>
uld be. This, then, was what the Goverumc.it <lb/>
been doing while tue opposition were roaring. <lb/>
ke tight hundred men out of St. John's, and tº <lb/>
ald give employinent to all those whora mained. <lb/>
wever, the opposition inigh; think lizatly of it, <lb/>
(non. Mr. S.) would tell then that wien h; <lb/>
d he would be prepared to give employment tº <lb/>
men, the public wºuld believe hun. He was <lb/>
isfied tº leaveºle matter to the good judge. <lb/>
ut of the people, and was assurel iſ wo iſ take <lb/>
ºre than the sneers ol the opposition to safects, <lb/>
jd an arrangemeist. He periectly agreed with <lb/>
»ie who said that it was a mistortune that wº <lb/>
juid be obliged to swind thout away, but surely <lb/>
t was better tuan keeping them here to st ºrve, <lb/>
d their absence would be the insaus of letting <lb/>
ters get reasonable wages for their gorvideº <lb/>
is, then, is a part of what we have bºº, <lb/>
ing, aud, this is ...what we meant by <lb/>
at opposition call selling the country by Cº. <lb/>
iération. Here the hon, mainher re-erred to <lb/>
atter read by the hon, usnuber, Mr. Rºnouſ, <lb/>
d which he stated had come from Ottawa, <lb/>
riding the people ct Newfoundlani not to <lb/>
me there fur simployment. He drew atteation <lb/>
what he called the clumsy way in waich tus <lb/>
1. member, Mr. Rºnouf, sought tº effect his <lb/>
rpºse, and pointed out that portion of it which <lb/>
ted that Biagrants were daily arriving fio a <lb/>
repº, as a co-irisdiction the position which <lb/>
hog, inenber entieavoured to sustaio. <lb/>
•re was an idua abroad that it was the inter<lb break="no"/>of thº mºrehants to keep down the prica of <lb/>
or. He (hon. Mr. S.) did not agree with <lb/>
t, or hit such could be the interest of any <lb/>
• If the people were not keok emeloyed, <lb/>
the interests which depended on the iaborer <lb/>
st share his circt instancos. There was as <lb/>
ºre ºute sign of the etate of any country that <lb/>
* condition of its laboring classes. It might <lb/>
pear badly that the men should go as y, <lb/>
the (hen Mr. S.) doubted if the men the A. <lb/>
ives would think so, or if they woull place <lb/>
thin those who endeavored to persuade inen <lb/>
that effect. He hoped improved prospects <lb/>
this cºuntry would enable them to return. <lb/>
* lorse would be used; they could go or stay, <lb/>
t at it pleased them to do. The House had <lb/>
in treated to great dissertations on pauper <lb/>
ief, and on this paragraph in the address. <lb/>
(hon. Mr. S.) really found it difficult to <lb/>
mprehend the views of hon. members op<lb break="no"/>ite, 0.1 the first day of the session the <lb/>
vernment, Proclamation was highly eome <lb/>
rºded by them, the only exception taken <lb/>
ng that the Government should have pro<lb break="no"/>ed seed potatoes. He (hon. Mr. S.) hardly <lb/>
r know of any benefit being derived from <lb/>
issue of seed potatoes, and he had no faith in <lb/>
b a course, for the seed potatoes were, in <lb/>
st cases, either eaten, or nºver retched those <lb/>
whom they were intended. However, last <lb/>
ing, the Goverument,in deference with wishes <lb/>
be House, were prepared to issus them, and <lb/>
ered into correspondence with parties in the <lb/>
r Provinces in order to ascertain terms, &amp;c. <lb/>
y iound tus prices asked were bnormous, <lb/>
113 per barrel at the place of shipment, <lb/>
one fourth ot then might be unfit for use <lb/>
arrival here. No unqualified guaranted to <lb/>
e had been given by Wue Goverument, bus <lb/>
ºn intimation that it they could do so they <lb/>
ld; and if it had been practicable,on reason<lb break="no"/>B conditions, it would have been done. The <lb/>
nces of the country were in such a condition <lb/>
they cºuld nºt inake the necessary ad<lb break="no"/>ces, and they fit that, under the circum<lb break="no"/>coºr they shouli abatdon the idea. Was <lb/>
one to be thougut of but those who had land? <lb/>
at dº hon, members opposite proposs to do <lb/>
the fishermen? . Their claims wer, equally <lb/>
3, yet hou. members did not propose that <lb/>
shilling should be provided for them. <lb/>
Pse who had laud ought to be in a position to <lb/>
wide their own seed potatºes, and be inde<lb break="no"/>dent of such aid iron the Govern ment. <lb/>
effect of ite Government's, refusal to buy <lb/>
that the seed patotous came down for sale, <lb/>
as the Governinent was not in the market, <lb/>
y industrious man was enabled to obtaia <lb/>
Potatoes at a ressonals rats. Every <lb/>
ſet that came was put in the ground. The <lb/>
Wernment could have dole no more. Ther <lb/>
* have given them to differeut people, but <lb/>
* all . No inors woulſ have been plaut, <lb/>
Year after year the Government had been <lb/>
ºtel with ºis poor relist. They wouli <lb/>
give a triº to its suppression. They nesus <lb/>
bida by tus Proclamation to its ſuisst ex<lb break="no"/>It was called for. It might be saarp and <lb/>
}rd to soiue, but it was a ugasure of cominoa <lb/>
ce and fair ply to the country at large<lb break="no"/>systein of pauper relier was over a quarer <lb/>
Gºulu 'y of i, to that cathat score thers was <lb/></p> 

<p>* <lb/>
-\-&gt; <lb/>
T <lb/></p> 

<p>W.A. <lb/></p> 

<p>—* * - ſºmeºmºn <lb/></p> -->

very little room for recrimination. All were <lb/> 
equally to blame. The attempt of any one to <lb/>
escape his share of the responsibility was mean <lb/> 
and cowardly, and could not escape detection, for <lb/>
the facts were before the House. He (hon. <lb/>
Mr. S.) merely disclaimed the right of any hon. <lb/>
member to lay the blame to one side or the other. <lb/>
The dodge of denial had been tried last year also, <lb/>
and so frequently and loudly that he (hon. Mr. <lb/>
S.) would have believed it iſ he had not proof to <lb/>
the contrary,and he had on that occasion to pro<lb break="no"/>duce to hon. members opposite their own writing <lb/>
and convicted them of mistatement, and showed <lb/>
that they had begged of the Government to <lb/>
issue Poor Relief, and that on their representa<lb break="no"/>tion relief bad been issued. There had been <lb/>
an attempt at some round about way of commu<lb break="no"/>nication, but the Government refused to recog<lb break="no"/>mise any thing but direct communication. Yet <lb/>
though hon. members must have known that <lb/>
the Government were in possession of these com<lb break="no"/>munications, they disclaim all responsibility and <lb/>
attack the Government. He (hon. Mr. S.) <lb/>
would have the public to judge of men who <lb/>
could thus deny their own acts. Last year was <lb/>
a tolerable good specimen of preceding years, <lb/>
and showed the result of the pressure brought to <lb/>
bear as the Government. He held in his hand <lb/>
a statement of the expenditure of relief to able <lb/>
bodied poor in the year 1868. (Here the hon. <lb/>
mambers read from the statement the amount <lb/>
received by each district.) It would appear <lb/>
that with the exception of Fortune Bay, there <lb/>
was, in proportion to population, but little <lb/>
difference between any one district and another, <lb/>
St. John's having, as usual, the lion's share. Hon. <lb/>
members opposite said they were not responsi<lb break="no"/>ble, that they did not force the Government to <lb/>
this expenditure. If they knew, as they did, <lb/>
that the expenditure was going on, and that it <lb/>
was not required, why not come to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and tell thein so, and request them to stop <lb/>
it? They did not do so, but allowed the expen<lb break="no"/>diture to go on, and by their silence, at <lb/>
least, became rapponsible. How idle it was of <lb/>
them to endeavor by misrepresentation and <lb/>
denial of their hand writing, to escape their <lb/>
responsibility, or fasten on others the odium of <lb/>
poor relief. Was not the amount for Harbor <lb/>
Main expended with the concurence and on the <lb/>
        repre<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>, from time to time, made by the <lb/>
numbers of that district? Then of that ex<lb break="no"/>penditure was not warranted by circumstances, <lb/>
these hon. members were recreant to their duty, <lb/>
in not asking that it should be stopped. He <lb/>
(hon. Mr. S.) did not mean to say that the facts <lb/>
did not bear out the expenditure, but seeing <lb/>
that the members had the supervision of it, <lb/>
they should not attempt to escape their respon<lb break="no"/>sibility. The circumstances counected with <lb/>
the system of poor reliaf, last year, brought <lb/>
most men to think that an attempt to put it <lb/>
down should be made. With that intention <lb/>
the Proclamation was issued, and generally <lb/>
approved of. The old system tended to bring <lb/>
        all down to one dead level, aud leave the coun<lb break="no"/>try without an independent middle class.— <lb/>
        Symptoms of a desire to give up the Proclama<lb break="no"/>tion were now becoming apparent. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName>—Not on our side. <lb/></p> 

    <p><persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Hon. Mr. SHEA</persName>.—Yes, and no where else. The <lb/>
hon. leader of the Opposition, Mr. Glen, called it <lb/>
inhuman, and proclaimed his intention of using all <lb/>
means to induce the Government to abandon it, <lb/>
and he is supported by hon. members opposite. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName>.—No. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Hon. Mr. SHEA</persName>.—You cheered him when he <lb/>
made his statement. The attempt is now made to <lb/>
induce the Government to abandon their position <lb/>
on this matter. Were there not others in the <lb/>
country who had a duty to discharge towards the <lb/>
poor as well as the Government? In no other <lb/>
country was the relief of the poor thrown on the <lb/>
Government. The system had been over 25 years <lb/>
in existence, and no doubt the somewhat abrupt <lb/>
termination of it would bring suffering to many. <lb/>
In such a state of things it became incumbent on <lb/>
all to lend a helping hand to the distressed. He <lb/>
was sorry to see that as yet the people of St. <lb/>
John's did not come up to the mark, and did not <lb/>
appear to appreciate the terrible crisis in which <lb/>
the country is placed. This would bring them to <lb/>
the necessity of considering whether they should <lb/>
not by Statute compel all to contribute according <lb/>
to their means. He (hon. Mr. S.) agreed with <lb/>
the hon. member for Ferryland in the hope that <lb/>
no man would be allowed to starve, but foresaw <lb/>
great difficulties if the question of Poor Relief was <lb/>
opened again. The old abuses would be revived, <lb/>
for it is a thing which contains within itself all the <lb/>
slements and temptations to abuse. He thought <lb/>
it would be matter of great regret if, from pressure <lb/>
of circumstances, the Government should be com<lb break="no"/>pelled to yield. The Community had their <lb/>
duty to perform, and it was to be regretted that <lb/>
they were without a law to compel all to assist <lb/>
the poor. He knew there would be many and <lb/>
great difficulties in the way of carrying out the <lb/>
Provisions of such a law, and in adjusting tne due <lb/>
proportions of assessments, but it was impossible <lb/>
for the Government any longer to undertake the <lb/>
duty of keeping the paupers. There were three <lb/>
months of hard suffering, difficulty and privation <lb/>
before them, and he hoped all would do their duty <lb/>
and contribute to tide the people over it. He did <lb/>
not think they would again see such a period of <lb/>
suffering, and if these months were over, he <lb/>
believed the prospects of the country would be <lb/>
found much improved. One consequence of our <lb/>
isolation was that in this crisis we had to depend <lb/>
on our own resources, as we had no legitimate <lb/>
claim on any other people. If we were united to <lb/>
the Dominion, we could make an appeal to the <lb/>
people there. When the Nova Scotia fisheries <lb/>
failed, last year, and great distress cousequently <lb/>
prevailed amongst the fishermen, they were not <lb/>
left to ask for relief, but the Legislatures of Onta<lb break="no"/>rio and Quebec and the corporations of differ<lb break="no"/>ent cities, forwarded £10,000 to relieve them. <lb/>
That was a practical proof of the benefit of Union. <lb/>
They had a claim, and they were recognised, <lb/>
and funds were sent them, until the Committees <lb/>
of distribution telegraphed that no more was re<lb break="no"/>quired. No doubt some would call that a bribe; <lb/>
but call it what you will, would not such relief <lb/>
be welcome here now? We want means of <lb/>
assisting our people, but we have now no right <lb/>
and it would be of great damage to us to go to <lb/>
        Canada in <hi rendition="simple:italic">formus paupers</hi>. The Government <lb/>
was expected to do all, and to be responsible for <lb/>
all. No matter what went wrong, The Government <lb/>
was expected to to do all, and to be responsible for <lb/>
        all. No matter wehat went wrong, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment were to blame, and the responsibility was <lb/>
to be cast on their shoulders. Such was the <lb/>
logic of hon. gentlemen opposite. Let us <lb/>
examine the question. What connection was <lb/> 

<cb/>

there between the acts of the Government and <lb/>
the causes out of which pauperism arose? It <lb/>
arose in a great degree from the decline of the <lb/>
seal fishery. Some years ago 120 vessels, tak<lb break="no"/>ing about 5,000 men, used to sail from St. <lb/>
John's to that fishery. There was not a man <lb/>
who did not, on an average, represent four other <lb/>
persons. There was a substantial benefit to the <lb/>
people, for not only were those who went pro<lb break="no"/>vided for, but those who remained at home were <lb/>
furnished with the means of getting through the <lb/>
severest part of the year. That fishery has <lb/>
declined, and thus a large amount of poverty <lb/>
was brought on the people. He doubted if <lb/>
1,000 men would be employed out of St. John's <lb/>
this year, and thus at least 20,000 paople would <lb/>
be left unprovided for. Now in what way were <lb/>
the Government responsible for that? What <lb/>
had they to do with the decline of and short <lb/>
outfit for the seal fishery? The Government <lb/>
were prepared to bear the full weight of that <lb/>
responsibility which properly attached to them, <lb/>
but not that which grew out of a state of things <lb/>
over which they had no control. What had the <lb/>
Government to do with the failure of the pota<lb break="no"/>toe crop? This had been for the past twenty <lb/>
years a great blight on the industry of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple. It was attributable to causes which the <lb/>
most scientific enquiries, conducted by the ablest <lb/>
men, have failed to explain, and when laid at <lb/>
the door of the Government, it is done in the <lb/>
utter recklessuess of party warfare. For the <lb/>
last five years the price of food had been high. <lb/>
In what way was the Government responsible <lb/>
for that? They were no more responsible for <lb/>
the high prices of former years, than they were <lb/>
for the present low prices. Here then were <lb/>
three substautial causes of the decline of the <lb/>
prosperity of the country, and over none of them <lb/>
could it be said that the Government had any <lb/>
control. They were completely outside the <lb/>
functions of Government, and it was strange <lb/>
that in an Assembly of rational men it should <lb/>
        be necessary to make such <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>, owing to <lb/>
the misrepresentation of party warfare. But <lb/>
so it is the reckless statements of hon. gentlemen <lb/>
opposite forced the Government to replies which <lb/>
would not be thought of anywhere else. Do <lb/>
not the public acts of the Government furnish <lb/>
hon. members with matter for comment and <lb/>
attack? It would appear not. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment were fully prepared to bear the onus of its <lb/>
acts and its policy, and hon. members opposite, <lb/>
who boast so much of their political attainments, <lb/>
should meet them on these grounds, and not take <lb/>
up such miserable rags of argument as they do day <lb/>
after day. When he said that even the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber, Mr. Hogsett, himself a man fit for anything, <lb/>
could not bave succeeded beter than the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, he felt that it was the highest compliment <lb/>
which the Government could pay themselves. Only <lb/>
consider the aptitude for business which the hon. <lb/>
member possessed. Why, he had actually built a <lb/>
dredge boat, a feat which one might venture to say <lb/>
was never before performed by an Attorney General <lb/>
in a British Colony. A man who could talk law and <lb/>
logic, and had actually the ability to build a dredge <lb/>
boat. Nay, more, he had managed the affairs of <lb/>
the Board of Works. The accounts got into a mess. <lb/>
The hon. member came down to put things straight, <lb/> <!--IC STOPPED HERE-->
and the straight measure he put upon them has <lb/>
never sit ce been taken out of theim. The then <lb/>
Receiver General, Mr. Glen, thought that his old <lb/>
tashioned ideas of book-keeping were correct, but <lb/>
the hon, member diſtºred frºm him, and . . . . <lb/>
sued. through which the hon. member was thrown <lb/>
put, just as he had lately been expelled from his <lb/>
leadership. Bus setting aside all these things, a <lb/>
much "sore important in Itter de manded our atten. <lb/>
tion, the irrepressible question of Conte leration. <lb/>
His Excellency says that it is high time for us to <lb/>
take soune act on in this matter. It is high time <lb/>
that the present condition of the people should be <lb/>
replaced by some more wholesome state of things. <lb/></p> 

<p>The very stones call aloud for a change. I; is <lb/>
asked, with reckless hardihood, what evidences for <lb/>
ºuchº change exist?...The evidences are everywhere. <lb/></p> 

<p>Go, through Water Street, and note the unoccupied <lb/>
buildings, from one end of it to another, ile (hon. <lb/>
Mr. S.) was never wedded to Confederatiºn alone <lb/>
as a means of escape from our difficulties. He was <lb/>
prepared to receive any feasible proposition which <lb/>
night be brought, torward for that purpose. No <lb/>
feasible proposal had ever been sugzested by the <lb/>
opponents of Confederation. However prosperous <lb/>
we might be, we have not in ourselves that inherent <lb/>
force which would enable us to urge on these mea. <lb/>
*** which could conduce to our prosperity. Every. <lb/>
body teels that a stand still policy will no longe <lb/>
avail. . The question has never been argued on fºr <lb/>
ground. . In this Assembly there is a party prepar. <lb/>
ed to deal with the question as never they were <lb/>
before prepared. There is a majority prepared or <lb/>
carry it, and was it to be supposed that inese gentle. <lb/>
men would assumu this position if they were ignoe<lb break="no"/>ani of the state ºf public feeling, especially with the <lb/>
impendiug certainty ef having soon to render an <lb/>
account of their stewardship? What s renger evi. <lb/>
dense of a most important change in public opinions? <lb/>
In St. John's the change is notorious. Even in the <lb/>
| Room, where formerly the subject could <lb/>
not be rationally discussed the large majority now <lb/>
upheld the question, and by none was it violently <lb/>
opposed. Doubtless there was a change, and that <lb/>
too founded on a basis which it is impossinle to be <lb/>
lieve can be at any future time dis urbed. Why <lb/>
has this change taken place f The minds of those <lb/>
who were turmerly hostile to the scheme were <lb/>
limpressed with sensitious of fear that their opera<lb break="no"/>tious iu trade would be injuriously affected. These <lb/>
sensations, have been reluoved; they have been <lb/>
made to give way, before trunger and sterner <lb/>
reasons, tue condition of the people of the country. <lb/>
The fisheries are falling off, pºpula.ion is dwinding <lb/>
away, trade of every kiud has become depressau. <lb/>
These men had seen that the continuaace of the <lb/>
preseat systeuſ means the continuance of those <lb/>
disorders under which we have ground, and they <lb/>
would not be tags of ordinary intelligence did they <lb/>
hesitate to adopt that change. The Government <lb/></p> 

<p>then should detºrmiut, to act in accordancu with the <lb/>
public feeling. They felt that the time was ripe <lb/></p> 

<p>for action, that arrangements of the most favourable <lb/></p> 

<p>charactar could now be, made, and they would <lb/></p> 

<p>be un, rue to tueir trusts did ſuey not take steps to <lb/></p> 

<p>bring the matter before this House for sonsideration. <lb/></p> 

<p>He confessed tast he and his hon, friend, the At<lb break="no"/>torney Generai felt proud of the position which upon <lb/></p> 

<p>this question they had taken... Four years ago, they <lb/></p> 

<p>were laet with a storm of reprobation. Every <lb/></p> 

<p>doscription of misrepresentation was put <lb/></p> 

<p>forward to poison the minds of the , peºple­ <lb/></p> 

<p>These <lb/>
These <lb/></p> 

<p>fight and 3 to die. <lb/>
have been all played out. <lb/></p> 

<p>killed out by the light of reason and cºmmon sense. <lb/>
Was not pride under such circumstances excusable? <lb/>
His hon friend and himself had stood up defiantly in <lb/>
the face of public opinion. They felt that the day <lb/></p> 

<p>tance upon us. They believed that it was in accord, <lb/>
**ith the progressive feelings of the present day. <lb/>
They had been no weathercocks; they had no shifts <lb/>
*...plain. They did not run a tilt against public <lb/>
feeling, and seek to force it. They had been con<lb break="no"/>tent to wait the turn of the tide, well assured that in <lb/>
due time turn it must. <lb/>
[Here the hon, member requested the indulgence <lb/>
of the House for a few minutes and retired. A <lb/>
ºort time after he sent, a message informing the <lb/>
House that he wisunwell, and did no: purpase con<lb break="no"/>tinking his observations this evening.] <lb/>
Mr. Hogsºrt—Certainly the Government have <lb/>
played the trick of a monkey. They have put for<lb break="no"/>ward their best gun as the exponent of their policy, <lb/>
and in supporting that policy he has attacked in the <lb/>
most Billingsgate language every hon, member on <lb/>
this side of the IIouse. The hon. gentleman has <lb/>
appealed to the condition of the country. He Says <lb/>
gº ºradº is languishing, the labouring population is <lb/>
fast leaving the country, and he gives that as a rea. <lb/>
son why we should ally ourselves with the Dominion <lb/>
of Canada. Supposing that we are in that condi. <lb/>
tion is it policy to disclose our cards and say, "Take <lb/>
us, forgod's sake, and make us soldiers, or what you <lb/>
will f" Under such circumstances what terms could <lb/>
we expect He (Mr. H.) had heard for the first <lb/>
time the doctrine that the remedy for a country's <lb/>
misfortune is the exportation of its inhabitants. <lb/>
Newfoundland has within herself capacities for the <lb/>
support of 3,000,000 people, but because the Gov. <lb/>
*mºnt are incapable of stimulating the people <lb/>
in the right direction, we must fºrsooth go to <lb/>
Canada, and the great remedy is that 800 persons <lb/>
will be employed by the Canadian Government upon <lb/>
the railroad. Hundreds of poor Irishmen, driven <lb/>
from their homes, have died upon the railroads of <lb/>
America from physical exhaustion, and have in <lb/>
*}, as left their children to fill paupers' graves, <lb/>
He (Mr. H.) warned the people to pause before <lb/>
leaving their bomes and families and committing <lb/>
themselves to the tender mercies of the Canadia; <lb/>
Dominion and of Mr. Sandford Fleming, the Cana<lb break="no"/>dian contractor. Export them] Nº, ship that <lb/>
leaves our shores that does not carry away the pride <lb/>
of Newfoundland, not a single measure was adopt<lb break="no"/>ed to stop that emigration." The people are tired <lb/>
of struggling agains; the inactivity" of the Gover. <lb/>
ment, and, from day to day they are leaving our <lb/>
shores, while the Government pocketing the public <lb/>
money don't move their little fingers tosho; how <lb/>
the condition of the people may be amelioraj. <lb/>
There was once a Casterºgh, and the is a h; <lb/>
ever did, was to cut his own throat, and if the hon <lb/>
member Mr Shea, were to out his own throat, <lb/>
Newfoundland would be benefited, and its liberties <lb/>
Prºved. He (Mr H) had years ago been called <lb/>
j. by Mr Shea and Sir Little to sustain the policy <lb/>
of their Government; at Placentia for 9 years he hº <lb/>
represented that district, and glad were Mr Kent <lb/>
and Mr Shea to send for George James Hogsett, the <lb/>
humble, outcas', to support their policy. When the <lb/>
ºntest between Mr. Süea and the present sir Hugh <lb/>
W Hoyle, took place at Burn, he (Mr H) was <lb/>
asked to go there to work up the election. He did <lb/>
go there; his own expenses amounted to £80, and so <lb/>
deeply ingrained is pauperism in the family, that <lb/>
this big bullaboo could not pay his election expenses, <lb/>
and the outcast had to pay £110 for his return. He <lb/>
(ºr H) did not pretend to be a saint, for if he did <lb/>
so he would nºt be believed, but he could conscien<lb break="no"/>tious y, say that from the day when he had first <lb/>
given his adhesion to the liberal cause he hau been <lb/>
faithful to it. What were the terms upon which <lb/>
thi, analgamatº Government was formed, they <lb/>
were that the Receiver General should have office <lb/>
at £300 a year, the hon member Mr Shaa, a seat in <lb/>
the Executive, and his brother the othee of Financial <lb/>
Secretary: They had deluded the people of Placentia <lb/>
and St. Mary's, and in order to fix the hon member <lb/>
Mr Barron, they gave him the Secretaryship of the <lb/>
Water Company, at £200 a year. These then were <lb/>
the men who stood up and attacked us,who thro' good <lb/>
report and evil report had remained firm and true to <lb/>
out principles. But what was their pleaf Why <lb/>
that there unus' no longer be any sectarian differences, <lb/>
and yet ever since the hon Attorney General <lb/>
has had the appointment of every offico under <lb/>
the Government, since this amalgamated Gc vern<lb break="no"/>inent had been formed there had not been one <lb/>
single Roman Catholic appointed to any office of <lb/>
englument. Why, even the Bench had been filled <lb/>
with class anon, as well as co-religionists. Weil I <lb/>
these traitors would be a blow-away at the bustings. <lb/>
There they would receive the punishments of traitors. <lb/>
The Roman Catholic constituents of this, Colony <lb/>
numbering 50,000 were not to b3 sacrificed for the <lb/>
Sheas or the Kents. But when the hon Attorney <lb/>
General fancied that these traitors expressed the <lb/>
feelings and views of the Roman Catholic community, <lb/>
he never made a greater mistake in his li:e, and he <lb/>
would find out that mistake at the next election. He <lb/>
(Mr H) cared not for olfice. He did not require a <lb/>
silk gown of a Judge's wig, to sustain his position at <lb/>
the Bar. He could uneet his opponents there as well <lb/>
as here, aud when the Government put forward such <lb/>
a man to attack him (Air H ) the last of his race, <lb/>
they would find that a man who relied ou honesty <lb/>
and a straightforward course has God for his help. <lb/>
and if he has he does not want the devil. Poor pai. <lb/>
try insigniãcent ours, the dregs of society, the curse <lb/>
of your own county and ours I Men like you sold <lb/>
the fairest country under Heaven, and when you die, <lb/>
and ºry to make up your account with God Alnigh. <lb/>
ly, do you think he will listen to you. And yet you <lb/>
put forward such a bully to malign us, . He (Mr H) <lb/>
had been walking the streets for his principles, and <lb/>
God Alinghty had given him bread. And yet this <lb/>
wan cones forward to disgorge his vile vituperation <lb/>
against us. Does he say a word about the rotten <lb/>
meal that he sold to his (Mr. B.) d strict and <lb/>
wilich was so bad that the piſs cruid uot eat it. <lb/>
If ever a lamily role ſo the devil with the public chest <lb/>
on their backs it was tue Receiver General, the hou. <lb/>
A. Shus, and that, elegant, nice young man the <lb/>
Blitºr of the Newfoundlander. He would assure <lb/>
the hon. Attorney General that he was i: <lb/>
be fancied that such men would, at the next general <lb/>
election be returned as the exponeuts of the views on <lb/>
the Rouan Catholic population. . With regard to <lb/>
other hou. members opposite this side of the House <lb/>
was prepared to meet them iu fair debate, but when, <lb/>
such unen were put forward we would denounce <lb/>
then as long as we were able tº do so. <lb/>Tue Committee tiled rose, reported progress, and <lb/>
asked leave to at again on Monday next. <lb/>
House then adjourned till Monday. <lb/></p> 


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-25, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>Use woodells woºl LozRNGES. See <lb/></p> 

<p>tricks however <lb/>
spectres and ºn-\-&gt;-\-\-\-\-/-\-\-\-\- \, <lb/>
hºgºblins have had their time, but they have been <lb/></p> 

<p>would come when the question would force its accep­ <lb/></p> 

<p>-\-&gt; -\-&gt; <lb/>
..] <lb/>
=N*E* <lb/>
powerful .."...? that if (!onfederation (ſ <lb break="no"/>were, accomplished their sons and husband,: r <lb/>
wºld be, compelled to go to Canada", |t §ſtufm?lmºr. <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOHN'S, <lb/>
WEDNESDAY, FEBRUARY 10, 1869. <lb/></p> 

<p>*For the sake of greater convenºn. in the <lb/>
publicatioon of the Assembly debates, our future <lb/>
*mbers during the session will be issued ort <lb/>
Wednesdays and Fridays, and, when necessary on <lb/>
Mondays. <lb/>
WE trust that the length of the Reports will be: <lb/>
considered a sufficient excuss for occasional irregu<lb break="no"/>larity in the hours of publication. <lb/>
*sees<lb break="no"/>Tār Address in reply to His Excellency's Speech <lb/>
drags through the Assembly day by day. A good <lb/>
part of Monday evening was devoted by the gallant <lb/>
"Major" to abuse of "Outsider" and the Nº. <lb/>
foundlander, both of whom, it is said, are in pro<lb break="no"/>found tribulation anent the " Major's" opinion of <lb/>
their respective merits! The address will probably <lb/>
take a day or two more to dispose of it. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Late news from Barin informs us that the princi<lb break="no"/>pal inhabitants there have originated, with very en<lb break="no"/>couraging success, a movement for the relief of their <lb/>
own poor. A meeting was convened for the pure' <lb/>
Pose at the Court House, and resolutions adopted to <lb/>
the effect that collections should be made by each. <lb/>
religious denomination for the assistance of the <lb/>
poor who belonged to it. They made up between: <lb/>
them sufficient funds for the purchase of somewhat <lb/>
over two hundred barrels of flour, which was being <lb/>
distributed amongst the indigent under the manage<lb break="no"/>ment of specially appointed persons, the recipients <lb/>
undertaking to repay the amount of advances, in <lb/>
fish, in the month of July. The work of relief was <lb/>
thus progressing, and it was more than probable <lb/>
that the poor would be sustained by these means for <lb/>
several weeks to come. The effort thus made re<lb break="no"/>flects high credit upon the people of Burin, and we <lb/>
trust will be emulated in other places whose better <lb/>
means'make it more easily practicable. <lb/></p> 

<p>An inquest was held on Saturday at harbor Grace <lb/>
on the bodies of two men named McCarthy and <lb/>
Cahill which were found in the snow on the road <lb/>
between Harbor Grace and Carbonear. These poor <lb/>
*atures appear to have been lost in the snow storm, <lb/>
of Thursday night. <lb/></p> 

<p>*-*-*s-\-\-<lb break="maybe"/>A telegram announces the arrival of the Steamer <lb/>
City of Durham hence at Liverpool in nine and s <lb/>
half days. <lb/></p> 

<p>UIED.—On Thursday norning, after a very protrac<lb break="no"/>ted illness, Maggie Chancey, aged 12 years and 7 <lb/>
*... eldest daughter of Mr. John'soper, of <lb/>
Carbonear. <lb/>
On Friday morning last, after an illness of severa <lb/>
months, Thomas Byrne, Bºq, aged 70 years, a native <lb/>
of Kilkenny, Ireland, who for 37 years was in the ser<lb break="no"/>vice of the Local Government, as surveyor, in which <lb/>
capacity his efficiency could not be exceeded. This <lb/>
was for several years one of the Representatives in <lb/>
the House of Åssembly for the District of Harbor <lb/>
Main; and in all his relations in life,whether private, <lb/>
official or public, his characterstood high for honesty <lb/>
ºnd.honor, while his disposition was nost retiring. <lb/>
He has leſ, a large family to lament the loss of "kind <lb/>
and affectionate parent. <lb/></p> 

<p>BY TELEGRAPH. <lb/>
TO THE COMMERBIAL ROOM. <lb/></p> 

<p>MAGRID, Feb. 4. <lb/>
Bands of Carlists have appeared in Catálonia from <lb/>
the valley of Adonia, and seek to produce a rising <lb/>
against the Provisional Government. Troops havº <lb/>
baen sent to disperse them. The Press of the Ci p <lb/>
fearing civil war, has urged on the Government §: <lb/>
necessity of taking active measures, and the people to <lb/>
unite against the reactionary part. <lb/>
HALIFAx, Feb. 6. <lb/>
The City of Baltimore which left Liverpool on the <lb/>
20th January, bound to New York, put into this <lb/>
port yesterday short of coal. She encountered very <lb/>
heavy weather, lost bowsprit, jibbooa and part ºf <lb/>
rigging. Alter coaling she proceeded. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>LATEST., <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Lowdox, Feb. 5. <lb/>
There was a large meeting hare last might, in favor <lb/>
of granting an amnesty to the Fenian prisoners. <lb/></p> 

<p>MADRID, Feb. 5. <lb/>
Bºpartero has refused a seat in the core, to which <lb/>
he was ſately elected. <lb/></p> 

<p>LoNDoN, Feb. 6, <lb/>
Preparations for the meeting of Parliament are <lb/>
nearly completed. <lb/>
In the ºommºns Mr. Henry Cowper will inovs. <lb/>
and Mr. Mundell will second, the addres, to the <lb/>
Queen. <lb/>
Lord Clarendon's health is much impairad. It is <lb/>
expected be will soon be obliged to retire from the <lb/>
Foreign Office, <lb/>
MADR11), Feb. G. <lb/>
The Marquis Moustier, late French Minister of <lb/>
Foreign Affairs, died yesterdav. <lb/>
MoxtREAL, Fab. 6. <lb/>
The Governor General left this imorning for Otta<lb break="no"/>wa and Lt. Governor Howland for Toronto, Gover. <lb/>
nor General expressed opinion that Montreal shºuld <lb/>
be the seat of Government, and he will use his influ. <lb/>
ence to have it brought here. Several well-known <lb/>
£ºniºus have lait for States, fearing revelation, by <lb/>
Whelan. <lb/>
Gold 135. Cuba news—Letters from Havana <lb/>
state Revolutionists are hopeful, and the feeling <lb/>
against Spanish rule grown stionger daily. <lb/>
=s <lb/></p> 

<p>Sale by Auction. <lb/></p> 

<p>THIS DAY, <lb/>
Wednesday, at 12 o'elock, <lb/>
Ox IIIE WiiABy OF <lb/></p> 

<p>A. S. H. E. A. <lb/>
600 Barrels <lb/>
FLOUR, <lb/></p> 

<p>Patra, Sata, Superine, an 1 lairer g-s?ew. <lb/></p> 

<p>A feeling of terror was arroused in the minds of the <lb/>
Peaples, specially of the wonsa, (and we know how <lb/></p> 

<p>advertusasat iu ago, ºr calauan. <lb/></p> 

<p>W. H. MARE, <lb/>
Žeb.12, … " <lb/></p> 

<p>A: . , 42. <lb/></p> 

<p>#. <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>