<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-02" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
    <title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-03-02">2 March 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-04-17"/>,
<date when="1865-04-27"/>,
<date when="1865-05-01"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="2"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-04-17_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-04-27_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-04-27_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-12-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-12-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-04-17_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-04-17_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-04-27_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-04-27_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-04-27_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-04-27_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-04-17_Page_2.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>


    <!-- IC, 2018-12-11, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->

<!--<p>They had ignored the fact that Canadian manufactures <lb/>
of woolens, leather, hardware, &amp;c., would be imported <lb/>
here duty free, and that in proportion as we consumed <lb/>
these goods must the revenue from the same class of <lb/>
goods from England decrease. . He thought we should <lb/>
be gainers by our free importation from Canada, not <lb/>
only in a fiscal point of view, but as affording employ<lb break="no"/>meit to our women of the labouring classes in ºp n<lb break="no"/>ning, weaving and making up matrials for clothing; <lb/>
and any arrangement which wouid provide suitable <lb/>
occupation for the female population ought to be wel<lb break="no"/>comed by every one interested in our common pros<lb break="no"/>perity. It was impossible to believe hon members <lb/>
serious in their apprehension on the score of taxation <lb/>
in view of the necessary changa of condition under <lb/>
Confederation, and bearing in mind the interest of the <lb/>
General Government in making as light as possible <lb/>
those burdens which it would have to share. The as<lb break="no"/>surance given by the Secretary of State for the Colon<lb break="no"/>ies on this head, and the security we should have in <lb/>
the watchfulness of members representing the other <lb/>
maritime colonies, as well as of those who should be <lb/>
sent trom Newfoundland, ought to satisfy hon mem<lb break="no"/>bers that there need be no anxiety as to excessive tax <lb/>
ation. It was very remarkable how nervous hon. <lb/>
members became in mere anticipation of most impro<lb break="no"/>bable burdens, while they were willing to bear actual <lb/>
and heavy burdens of present taxation, in the shape <lb/>
of puperism, depreciation of property, and other <lb/>
'evils that prostrate the energies of the country. And <lb/>
they further seem to forget that, even if we take their <lb/>
advice and stay as we are, we must submit to further <lb/>
taxation, though only for the purpose of paying off our <lb/>
existing debt. It had been pretended that Canada was <lb/>
eagerly bent upon securing us to help to pay her <lb/>
debt. The idea seemed to him (Mr. Shea) to convey <lb/>
a bitter mockery of our financial position. It should <lb/>
be first known that we could pay our own debts, before <lb/>
its being at all likely that we could excite the cupidity <lb/>
of other countries. And even if our condition in this <lb/>
respect were improved, why, to talk of Canada having <lb/>
designs upon us to help her out of any difficulties, was <lb/>
as reasonable as to suppose that our own Government <lb/>
should make a raid upon Quidi Wid, or Goat's Cove, <lb/>
to compel the inhajitants of those classical localities <lb/>
to discaarge our present liabilities. , Great alarm <lb/>
seemed to exist that we should part with the nºanage<lb break="no"/>ment of our fisheries; but a moment's reflection would <lb/>
show that our fisheries were more likely to he better <lb/>
managed and protected by a powerful government <lb/>
interested as well as ourselves in their conservation, <lb/>
than by any small efforts of our own. We should then <lb/>
have a chance of having our salmon and herring fisher<lb break="no"/>ies turned to good account; and this surely would be <lb/>
a vast improvement on the present plan of consigning <lb/>
these valuable resources to neglect. But the hollow<lb break="no"/>ness of some of those outside doors, who now made <lb/>
stock of this cry about the fisheries, was manifest when <lb/>
we remember that if these very people had their way, <lb/>
our fisheries would long since have been wrested from <lb/>
us by the French convention; for they had done their <lb/>
worst to oppose that self-government which alone <lb/>
gave us the power to resist the spoilation. The Solic<lb break="no"/>tor General waxed pathetic over what he called the <lb/>
loss of our local Legislature, and told us the people <lb/>
had much more regard than formerly for our local <lb/>
institutions. The hon gentleman had related an in<lb break="no"/>stance of very hard things haid years ago by some <lb/>
one he had met in the street at a very late hour of the <lb/>
night. It must have been on some very rare occasion <lb/>
indeed, to account for the Solicitor General having <lb/>
been at large at an unseasonable time. But he (Mr. <lb/></p> 

<p>Shea) much feared that if the people judged of the <lb/></p> 

<p>Legislature by the amount of good of a practical kind <lb/>
that we had since done for them, their opinion of us <lb/>
would not be found much more flictering than that <lb/>
which had greated the ears of the Sºlicitor General on <lb/>
his nocturnal perambulations. The same hon gentle<lb break="no"/>man had also ridiculed the idea of our eight members <lb/>
being effective in the Confederate Ležislature. Well, <lb/>
if they only exercised there anything like the influence <lb/>
brought to bear on our own Governinent by one <lb/>
member from Harbor Grace, we need never feur for <lb/>
the sustainment of our interests in the Confederate <lb/>
Parliament. Reference had been made to those politi<lb break="no"/>cal distractions in Canada which had caused such fre<lb break="no"/>quent changes of government; but the hon member <lb/>
who made this allusion should have seen that it only <lb/>
told against his own view, because _these differences <lb/>
there would render the combined efforts of our eignt <lb/>
members all the more powerful and avail 'ble to the <lb/>
interests of the co ony. We were threatened with <lb/>
losing the protection of England; but we had only to <lb/>
read the views of British statesmen and the British <lb/></p> 

<p>ress to see that the union would cement and consul<lb break="no"/>idate our connection with the parent state; and that it <lb/>
would be in rejecting it that we should run tue risk of <lb/>
forfeiting our right to Imperial consid ration. It was <lb/>
plain beyond any possible doubt that Great Britain <lb/>
earnestly desired this measure; and it was absurd to <lb/>
suppose that we were likely to conciliate her favour by <lb/>
flying in the face of her advice and admonitions. The <lb/>
union with Ireland had been held up to scare us away <lb/>
from this proposition. But had the Irish union with <lb/>
England been a real and honest one, had Ireland only <lb/>
been governed as was Yorkshire, Lancashire, or any <lb/>
other county of England, the agitation for repeal would <lb/>
never have been raised. That agitation was the result <lb/>
of despair of a true union; and it was monstrous to <lb/>
pretend any parallel in the present case, where there <lb/>
were no causes existing, as in the instance of unhappy <lb/>
Ireland, to prevent fulfilment of the union which we <lb/>
were invited to enter. The horrors of the draft were <lb/>
also pictured to our imaginations by hon members; but <lb/>
they must be well aware that, in this respect, our po<lb break="no"/>sition would not be in any degree changed by Confed<lb break="no"/>eration. The draft was never resorted to but in those <lb/>
extreme national emergencies which suspend even law <lb/>
itself—Any such crisis as regarded us was highly im<lb break="no"/>probable. But if it ever arose, even in our present <lb/>
ielations with the mother country, Great Britain her<lb break="no"/>self would have that power which we are now asked to <lb/>
believe could only be exercised by the Confederate <lb/>
Government. This was but another of the scarecrows <lb/>
set up to alarm the people with imaginary dangers, <lb/>
and turn their minds from the real evils of their pre<lb break="no"/>sent condition. Hon inembers had argued that even <lb/>
though advantageºus to the sister colonies, union <lb/>
could not benefit Newfoundland, so different were our <lb/>
circumstances from theirs. He (Mr. Shet) regretted <lb/>
to be obliged to agree with them, that our circum<lb break="no"/>stances are indeed very different from those of New <lb/>
Brunswick or Nova Scotia; but this very difference, so <lb/>
far from being a reason against Confederation, was a <lb/>
strong one in its favour. These colonies were prosper<lb break="no"/>ous and progressing. Pauperism, as it is with us, was <lb/>
wbolly unknown to them; and they could afford, it they <lb/>
thought fit, to go on, as they have shown theniselves <lb/>
able to do, on their own account. Ours was a condi. <lb/>
tion opposite of this—the Colony had been for years <lb/>
going down the hill; and the best of the labouring <lb/>
classes were fleeing its shores to seek bread. Our <lb/>
resources, though contess'dly good, required an aid <lb/>
that we could not give them; and a reliable prospect <lb/>
of th's au was attora-d oy our junction with older and <lb/>
wet, ther cuminunities, 1ſ the measure suited the <lb/>
other Col ules, it appeared to him that it was all the <lb/>
more desirable for us, in proportion to our greater <lb/>
need of a helping hand. We are foºd our isolation <lb/>
is a rºaºun as ainst it. It is, if we desire to perpetuate <lb/>
this isolation, which we all agree to consider so i ju<lb break="no"/>rious to our interests. A pour man offered a mesus <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>of living might as well say that while the offer might <lb/>
suit his better off neighbºur, it was useless to him, <lb/>
because of his poverty. The steam communication to <lb/>
be provided for us by the Confederate government, <lb/>
some hon members regard as very uncertain. He <lb/>
(Mr. Shel) Jii not so consider it. It seemed to him <lb/>
to be a necessary consequence of the union; but on <lb/>
this view he certiny would not rely altogether; and <lb/>
ha would have steam secured by agreement, for he <lb/>
regarded this as an indispensible condition. It was <lb/>
supposed by some that we were not interested in the <lb/>
railroads, canals and such public works of the other <lb/>
provinces. But it must be evident, on a moment's <lb/>
thought, that we had an important interest in what<lb break="no"/>ever means tended to cheapen produce and enhance <lb/>
the value of libour. O ºr mines and minerals, it was <lb/>
s ill said, would be lost to us; but han members knew <lb/>
well that th's statement was grºundless, that these <lb/>
mines would be always just as free and open to our <lb/>
people as now, and with the greater probability, under <lb/>
Confederation. of being made practically open and <lb/>
valuable to then, instead of being useless, as they are <lb/>
now, from want of means or enterprise to work them. <lb/>
We were told of the all-sufficiency of our fisheries for <lb/>
the support of the people; but the wretchedness an <lb/>
want around us answered and refuted that grossest of <lb/>
fallacies. Confeieration was considered by some a <lb/>
too speculative project for us to entertain. It was not <lb/>
to be denied that about all such changes there was <lb/>
something more or less speculative. Nose of us could <lb/>
pretend to guarantee the beneficial operation of the <lb/>
measure, no matter how just and strong were the <lb/>
grounds of our expectations. It might as well have <lb/>
been objected that Responsible Government, Free <lb/>
Trade or any other change we have known, ought not <lb/>
to have been advocated, because no security could be <lb/>
given that it would realise its promises. In sºuch ca<lb break="no"/>ses we were cºmpelled to rely upon certain principles <lb/>
the safety of which haſ been tested by the experience <lb/>
of other countries; and these had been shown to be <lb/>
conclusively in our favour on the subject under consi<lb break="no"/>deration. But he would remind those who cavitled <lb/>
about the point of a speculation, that not even this <lb/>
mush could be said in favour of the course they had <lb/>
recommended.-There was nothing, even speculative, <lb/>
about the results of their choice to remain as we are, <lb/>
for that plalaly meant, to pass from bad to worse, <lb/>
even into the slough of Despond itself. That was a <lb/>
clear, inevitable certainly before us, -and yet it was <lb/>
preferred to the proposed change, because we could <lb/>
not guarantee that this change wouli work all the <lb/>
good we anticipated from it. "We are ad monished to <lb/>
trust to Providence; and far be it from him (Mº. <lb/>
Shea) to gainsay this proposition, under any and all <lb/>
circumstances, but let us well weigh its meaning. <lb/>
Providence provides us with sense and reason, and, in <lb/>
worldly affairs, manifestly intended these attributes <lb/>
to be our guides as far as they can reach our require<lb break="no"/>ments. If, then, we choose not to use these guides, <lb/>
and will run our heals against walls, can we complain <lb/>
that our trust in Providence has been misplaced, it our <lb/>
heads get the worse for the contact? To him (Mr. <lb/>
Shea) it seened something worse than profane to talk <lb/>
of trust in Provilence to avert from us the consequen<lb break="no"/>ces of our own deliberate and designing folly. It was, <lb/>
however, most sa isfactory to find in an ine, allegations <lb/>
put forward by the oppone its of union, how unsub. <lb/>
stantial was all the material they could urge against <lb/>
it. The futility of their so-called arguments was so <lb/>
fºr useful, that the country would see how unassail<lb break="no"/>able was our position by any stronger or in ºre legit:<lb break="no"/>mate means. He (Mr. Shea) would now rapeat the <lb/>
onallenge tº hon unenbers oposed to him, to au;gest <lb/>
someºning better themselves, if they were determined <lb/>
tº resist the measure now offered to our acceptance. <lb/>
It would not dº to tºll as we could stºy as we were. <lb/>
I was an itsult to the unlerstanding of the public, <lb/>
and it was a cruel insult to the thousands of our la: <lb/>
bouring population and our tradesman of al.: sorts, <lb/>
now piling away for want of emplºyment. But, if it <lb/>
turned oil that hon menoes were only loud o ject<lb break="no"/>ºrs, and were incapable of proposing one single step <lb/>
of themselves to which the country might look with <lb/>
the faintest, hopº, it would behove that country to <lb/>
decide whether, in view of the circumstances arºund <lb/>
us, it will ºccept the advice to do nothing but sink <lb/>
deeper and deeper in wretchedness and degradation, <lb/>
or whether, moved by manly energy and the progres<lb break="no"/>sive spirit of the day, it will put fortn its best efforts <lb/>
to ea incipate itself from the causes of desline, and <lb/>
enjoy its place and share in the advanced civilization <lb/>
of British North B nºrica. He concluded by support. <lb/>
ing the Resolution whicn committed this momentous <lb/>
question to the muture reflection of the country. <lb/>
Mr. MooRE.—A remark made by the hon member <lb/>
who had just sat down (Mr. E. D. Shea) was that <lb/>
Confederation would drive poverty from our <lb/>
shores, and raise our people from their present state <lb/>
of lestitution to a state of prosp ºrity. Now if these <lb/>
prophecies of the hon gentleman should prove to be <lb/>
not more correct than similar assertions made by him <lb/>
and others on the introdu', ion of Responsible Go<lb break="no"/>vernment into this country, certainly Confederation <lb/>
will be any thing but the boon represented; and will <lb/>
fall far short of the sanguine expectations of those <lb/>
who are so unuch in favor of it. What has been the <lb/>
experience of the last ten years, since the establish<lb break="no"/>ment of Responsible Grovernment * Why, we never <lb/>
befºre had such, destitution amongst our operative <lb/>
population, as during the laſter half of that period. <lb/>
He (Mr. Moore) did not wish to infer that the same <lb/>
result would follow Confederation, if caried into effect, <lb/>
nor did he say that Responsible Government contri<lb break="no"/>buted much to the depressed circumstances of the <lb/>
country, although well known to be too expensive a <lb/>
machinery ſor so small a population as we are com<lb break="no"/>posed of. Neither did he think that any system of <lb/>
governmert would produce prosperity in the face of <lb/>
prevailing bad fisheries. He (Mr. Moore) was not <lb/>
oap sed to Confederation in the abstract. He believ<lb break="no"/>ed it was a principal which must be established and <lb/>
brought about in the course of time. There were <lb/>
causes in operation which would necessarily lead to <lb/>
the burden of their defence being thrown on the North <lb/>
American Colonies, to a greater extent than hitherto. <lb/>
The British taxpayers are crying out for a reduction <lb/>
of taxation. The products of the British artizans' <lb/>
labour have no longer protection in the markets of <lb/>
the more important Cºlonies; and they reasonably <lb/>
object to be taxed for the protection of those who deal <lb/>
witn them only as far as it suits their convenience. <lb/>
And why should the British artizan be taxed for the <lb/>
benefit of the colonist, whose trade is entirely free, <lb/>
and who, besides, is rolling in comparative wealth, <lb/>
whilst many of the operative population in England, <lb/>
Scotland and Ireland are struggling for the bare means <lb/>
of subsistence 2. The statesmen of England see the <lb/>
necessity of yielding to opposition raised against the <lb/>
military expenditure in the colonies. Besides, there <lb/>
is reason to believe that the expenditure has some<lb break="no"/>times been largely increased by the colonists them<lb break="no"/>selves,in order that they may profit by it; for instance, <lb/>
that the war in New Zealand was provoked by the <lb/>
colonists, contrary to the desire of the British Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment were involved in it, and were in honour <lb/>
bound to sapport the coiodists, whether they were <lb/>
right or wrong. But, for the future, it is evident, <lb/>
from the tone of leading statesmen, if these colon st; <lb/>
involve themselves with the aborigines, or with any <lb/>
neighbouring nation or , people, on imaginary or <lb/>
other causes,contrary to the policy of the British Gov. <lb/>
ernment, they must defend themselves. The same, in <lb/></p> 

<p>effect, is now said to the North American Colonies. <lb/>
From the fact of the Canadians countenancing, to all <lb/>
appearance, the late raid across the Uniteſ: States' <lb/>
border by Southern sympathizers, robbing the Bank; <lb/>
and firing upon and mortally wounding citizens of <lb/>
St. Alhans, Canada has now to turn out a portiºn of <lb/>
her militia and Wounteers for the protection of her <lb/>
frontier. The British Government very properly <lb/>
said, if you conduct yourselves towards, your neigh<lb break="no"/>burs in such a manner as to excite their hostility, you <lb/>
must take the consequences. And there could <lb/>
be no doubt that, for the future, these large <lb/>
Provinces must make provision for their own defence; <lb/>
by making their militia efficient, and that they will <lb/>
also be caled upon to contribute towards the main<lb break="no"/>tenance of a regular army, and will have to provide <lb/>
themselves with a navy. He (M. Moore) did say <lb/>
that in the face of circumstances involving such an <lb/>
enormous expenditure as will inavitably be entailed <lb/>
upon Canada, it would be unwise to pledge this colo<lb break="no"/>my to join such an alliance on the basis proposed in the <lb/>
report of the Quebec Conference Neither did he be<lb break="no"/>lieve that Newfoundland was originally included in the <lb/>
proposed scheme, or expected to join therein. Nor <lb/>
did he see that we would be benefited commercially by <lb/>
entering into Confederation on such terms. The <lb/>
geographical position of New Brunswick and Nova <lb/>
Scotia, contiguous to Canada, placed them in a very <lb/>
different and more favo arable position in regard to <lb/>
Confederation than this Island; and still it was seen <lb/>
that these provinces h-sitated about entering the union <lb/>
and taking upon themselves their share of the im-, <lb/>
mense responsibility. And was not that enough to <lb/>
warrant us to keep back? It had been said that we <lb/>
are not so far advanced in population, wealth, or <lb/>
material improvement as the other colonies, and that <lb/>
the union would confer great benefit on Newfound<lb break="no"/>land, that we wou d derive great advantag's from the <lb/>
railroads, canals, and other improvements of Canada. <lb/>
He admitted that we would, and will benefit, whether <lb/>
we enter cc.nfederation or not; in the same ratio as <lb/>
we have benefited, and will benefit by every improve<lb break="no"/>ment in other countries wherever our comm ree ex<lb break="no"/>tends. For instance, by the extension of railroads in <lb/>
Spain, which has tended to facilitate the transport of <lb/>
gools and merchandise required for the interior of <lb/>
that country, the article of codfish being largely con<lb break="no"/>sum ºd by the inhabitants. Hence the facilities affºrd<lb break="no"/>ed by these railroads have greatly tended to increase <lb/>
the demand, and enhance the price of that staple <lb/>
product. Canada had constructed ber railroads <lb/>
and canals for her own advantage —for the <lb/>
conveyance of her produce to the seapor s, <lb/>
and of the produce of other countries into the interior; <lb/>
also to induce customers'from other countries to resort <lb/>
to her markets to purchate of the abun lance of her <lb/>
products, in preference to that of the United Sates. <lb/>
In this way Newfoundland will derive great benefit by <lb/>
these improvements, without being compelled to pay <lb/>
for them. We might, in the course of years, find it <lb/>
for our advantage to go into the Confederation; but <lb/>
would not now, under the constitution laid before us, <lb/>
unless some far more favourable terms are offered <lb/>
than the present. A great deal had been said about <lb/>
steam communication. It had been a great boon to <lb/>
every country; and he granted it would be goºd for <lb/>
us if established. One of the arguments put forwald <lb/>
of the alvantažes of steam communication between <lb/>
tnis island and Canada was .hat it would affold facili<lb break="no"/>ties for our operative population to proceed to Canaia <lb/>
where there was a field for their labour. But he did <lb/>
not see how the prosperity of this country was to be <lb/>
promoted by the more energetic of our working <lb/>
classes leaving us, some of whom would no doubt <lb/>
prosper in Canada. But it was not a portion of the <lb/>
most energetic of our population going elsewhere and <lb/>
prospering that would restore the prosperity of this <lb/>
country. For the mater of any of our people pro<lb break="no"/>ceeding to Canada, what is there to prevent them <lb/>
going now * The general colonial policy is to induce <lb/>
people to settle in the respective colºnies; but it would <lb/>
seem, by what some hon gentlemen have stated, <lb/>
that the policy of this unfortunate country should be <lb/>
to banish and send our people out of it as fast as they <lb/>
can go; and by their exert.ons in Canada we are to <lb/>
be raise 1 from our present depressed state. If we <lb/>
require steam communication, it will be better for us <lb/>
to pay for it directl , and then we shall have it; but <lb/>
there is no guarantee in the Q lebec resolntions that <lb/>
we would have it under Con ederation. The tariff of <lb/>
Canada, on which , the calculations for the proposed <lb/>
union were based, is protective. It was denue i by <lb/>
the hon member for Pacantia, Mr Shea, that the Cº<lb break="no"/>nadian tariff is protective, or that it should now be a <lb/>
matter 2f consideration, as a different tariff would be <lb/>
adopted by the Confederate Legislature. But he <lb/>
(Mr Moore) could not look upon the matter in that <lb/>
light. That tariff is protective; and he (Mr Moore) <lb/>
considered it a matter of vital importance to this <lb/>
Colony, that we should well consider and understand, <lb/>
before entering Confederation, the position we woul-i <lb/>
be placed in with regard to it, and the affect it would <lb/>
have on the country. A protective tariff would not be <lb/>
beneficial to Newfoundland at present. For example, <lb/>
our duty upon manufactured leatherware, at present, <lb/>
is 11 per cent; but under the Canadian tariff it is 25 <lb/>
per cent. Would not this difference of 14 per cent <lb/>
be a bounty to the Canadian manufacturers?" It was <lb/>
idle to say that they would not take advantage of it. <lb/>
Another consideration-supposing the question of <lb/>
union had not been thougnt of, and that our govern<lb break="no"/>ment proposed a tariff similar to that of Canada, <lb/>
woad it receive any support in th s House? He <lb/>
believed no government in this colony would dare to <lb/>
introduce such a tariff; and, if not, why should we <lb/>
put it in the power of another government to do so? <lb/>
That tariff would produce at least £50,000 over the <lb/>
amount guaranteed to us by the Quebec resolutions. <lb/>
Wny should we send £30,000 a year to Canada, and <lb/>
more than probable have to subunit to a direct taxa<lb break="no"/>tion of £20,000 a year besides to support our poor <lb/>
and for other purposes? If Confederation would re<lb break="no"/>move the barriers of ice that sometimes block our <lb/>
coast, regulat- the winds, and give us more prosperous <lb/>
fisheries, then that would be an advantage. twº<lb break="no"/>foundland requires free trade; and can we have it to <lb/>
a grea er extent by confederation than we have at <lb/>
present? The Canadian markets are as free to us now <lb/>
as we can desire. Some few articles of Canadian <lb/>
manufacture might suit us; but we cannot afford to <lb/>
shut ourselves out from the British or any other mar<lb break="no"/>ket for the purpose of fostering Canadian manufac<lb break="no"/>tures at our expense. It would be more for our advan<lb break="no"/>tage to continue our present relation with Great <lb/>
Britain, even if we shºuld have to pay, according to <lb/>
our pºpulation, a small amount towards the mainte<lb break="no"/>nance of a military force for our defence. And when <lb/>
the British government saw the desire of the people <lb/>
of this Colony to establish Volunteer Companies, as <lb/>
they are doing with such spirit and ardour, to be <lb/>
ready to aid and assist in their own defence, they <lb/>
would not compel us to join the Confederation con. <lb/>
trary to our expressed wishes and interests. What <lb/>
the trade of Newfoundland requires is that we should <lb/>
be as free to go tº the markets of the world as possi<lb break="no"/>ble, and with as little taxation ſaid on out imports as <lb/>
practicable, and try to keep foreign markets open to <lb/>
our exports-to-endeavour to encourage the people to <lb/>
devote more of their attention to agriculture, which <lb/>
must prove more profitaole to the contry than Con­ <lb/></p> 

<p>federation. I'ne prosperity of the country mast <lb/>
|º upon the energes of the people, and the re­ <lb/></p> 

<p>sources within themselves, and not on the prosperit <lb/>
or resources of another country. It is patent. <lb/>
the fishermen generally have a reluctance tº tº. <lb/>
themselves to agriculture, from the very nature. . <lb/>
pursuits being so vastly different from the puniº <lb/>
the fisheries. But necessity would show and teach <lb/>
them that it is their best alternative; and from th <lb/>
and other resources he anticipated more effective at <lb/>
permanent relief for the present destitution ºf <lb/>
portion of our operative. Populrtion, than fro, <lb/>
union with the other British North American 6. <lb/>
In 185 s <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>On motion of the hon ATToRNEY GENERAL the <lb/>
Committee then rose, and the Chairman reported. <lb/>
gress. To sit again to-morrow. <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon RECEIVER GENERAL. by command of his <lb/>
Excellency the Governor, presented to the Hous, ths <lb/>
following documents:­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Shipping returns for 1864. <lb/>
Return of Imports and exports for 1864. <lb/>
Ordered that these documents lie on the table. <lb/>
The house then adjourned until Thursday at thrº <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/></p>-->
    
    <p rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, March 2.</p>
    
    <p>
The house met at 3 o'clock. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr KENT</persName> presented a petition from Michael Bany <lb/>
and others, of the Major's Path, which was received <lb/>
and read, praying for a grant to complete that road. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:WINT1">Dr. WINTER</persName> presented a petition from John Tilley <lb/>
and others, of Shoal Harbor, Random Sound, which <lb/>
was received and read, praying for a grant to make a <lb/>
road down the North side of the harbor. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KAVA1">Mr. KAVANAGH</persName> presented petitions from Patrick <lb/>
McDonald and others, of Outer Cove, from John <lb/>
Pounder and others, of Gallows Cove, from Robert <lb/>
Firm and others, of the same place, from James Kelly <lb/>
and others, of Outer Cove, and from Thomas Power <lb/>
and others, of Shoe Cove, which were severally re<lb break="no"/>ceived and read, praying for grants to open and repair <lb/>
roads in these settlements. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that these petitions lie on the table. <lb/></p> 

<p>On motion of the hon. <persName ref="pers:CART5">ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>, pur<lb break="no"/>suant to order of the day, the house resolved itself <lb/>
    into committee of the whole on the further considera<lb break="no"/>tion of the Confederation of the British North Amer<lb break="no"/>ican Colonies,—<persName ref="pers:KNIG2">Mr. KNIGHT</persName> in the chair. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WINT1">Dr. WINTER</persName>—The critical remarks of the hon and <lb/>
learned menoer for Fogo, Mr. Whiteway, on the de<lb break="no"/>crease of the representation of Newfoundland in 1871, <lb/>
under Confederation, required reply, as they were <lb/>
specially directed against his (Dr Winter's) views of <lb/>
the operation of the 21st Resolution of the Quebec <lb/>
Conference. The hon and learned member, Mr. White<lb break="no"/>way, said that he "must confess that he failed to com<lb break="no"/>prehend the hon gentleman's long array of figures." <lb/>
The resolution in the Report of he Delegates on this <lb/>
subject appeared very simple. It was this:– "No <lb/>
reduction small be made in the number of members <lb/>
returned by any section, unless its population shall <lb/>
have decreased relatively to the population of the <lb/>
whole union, to the extent of 5 per centum." Now, <lb/>
(said Mr. W ), to illustrate the case, assuming the <lb/>
whole population to be 4,000,000, (which was near the <lb/>
present number) 5 per cent on this would be 200,000. <lb/>
Our present population was only 130,000. Therefore <lb/>
the island must be depopulated before we could lose a <lb/>
representative. But he (Mr. W.) would read what <lb/>
Mr. Galt said on the subject, when addressing his <lb/>
constituents at Sherbrooke, C. E., and surely his was <lb/>
an opinion, on the construction of the Resolution, which <lb/>
the hon and learned member for Trinity would respect. <lb/>
He said —"The House would never have less than 194 <lb/>
members; but it would increase at a very slow rate." <lb/>
This latter remark applied truly to Lower Canada and <lb/>
the other Maritime Provinces, and fully bore out his <lb/>
(Dr Winter's) argument, that whilst the representa<lb break="no"/>tion of the whole union would appear to increase "at <lb/>
a very slow rate," the upper section—Canada West <lb/>
—would, in 36 years, have an unjustly preponderating <lb/>
majority over Lower Canada and the other Maritime <lb/>
Provinces, although these latter will have a majority <lb/>
of 23 on entering the union. But Mr. Galt gave no <lb/>
opinion on the constitution of the 21st Resolution, <lb/>
which runs thus:– "No reduction shall be made in <lb/>
the number of members returned by any section, <lb/>
unless its population shall have decreased relatively <lb/>
to the population of the whole union, to the extent of <lb/>
five per centum." Mr. Galt comprehends the effect of <lb/>
the 21st Resolution, as well as its construction; and <lb/>
certainly would not commit himself to an <choice><sic>sbsurdity</sic><corr>ubsurdity</corr></choice>, by <lb/>
telling his constituents at Sherbrooke, Canada East,that <lb/>
the population of Upper Canada, Newfoundland, or <lb/>
any other section of the union must decrease 200,000, <lb/>
being 5 per cent on 4'000,000, before any reduction <lb/>
shall be made in the number of members returned by <lb/>
that section of the Confederatton. So much for the <lb/>
authority quoted by the hon and learned member for <lb/>
Fogo, Mr. Whiteway, to illustrate the case submitted <lb/>
by him to the House and the country. Now to il<lb break="no"/>lustrate his (Dr. Winter's) view, 5 per cert on <lb/>
4,000,000—the whole population—is 200,000, which <lb/>
divided by the total number of members (194) gives <lb/>
1,003, as per cent for each member. This multiplied <lb/>
by the number of members for each section or Pro<lb break="no"/>vince will show the relative amount of decrease of <lb/>
population required by the 21st Resolution before <lb/>
any of them will lose a member: as shown in the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing tabular statement. <lb/></p> 

<table>
    <row><cell>Upper Canada,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">82</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1003</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">............82,246</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Nova Scotia,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">19</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">"</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">............19,057</cell></row>
    <row><cell>New Brunswick,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">15</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">"</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">............15,045</cell></row>
    <row><cell>P. E. Island</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">5</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">"</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">............5,015</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Newfoundland,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">8</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">"</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">............8,024</cell></row>
</table>
    

<p>Now Newfoundland will, in 1871, have increased from <lb/>
130,000 to 155,740; but as the ratio of Lower Canada <lb/>
will give 21,495 for each of her 65 members, New<lb break="no"/>foundland will require 8 times 21,495, or 171,960, to <lb/>
enable her to return 8 members. But having decreased <lb/>
    16,221—more than double the amount of 5 per cent, <lb/>
or 8,024, relatively to the proportion of the whole <lb/>
union, consequently will lose a member, and will re<lb break="no"/>tain 7, in place of 8. Such was his (Dr. Winter's) <lb/>
view of the matter, to which he would adhere until <lb/>
some sound and logical reasons were given to convince <lb/>
him to the contrary. <lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:WHIT6">Mr. WHITEWAY</persName>—What he had stated was that it <lb/>
might possibly have been from his (Mr. W.'s) ob<lb break="no"/>tuseness, but he could not understand the hon and<lb/>
learned member's long array of figures or his mode of <lb/>
calculation. Now his (Mr. W.) figures were very <lb/>
simple. If the hon gentleman would only take <lb/>
4,000,000, the present estimated population of the <lb/>
Confederacy, at 5 per cent, he would find that to con<lb break="no"/>stitute a reduction sufficient to deprive us of a mem<lb break="no"/>ber, we would lose exactly 200,000, or in other words, <lb/>
the colony must be entirely depopulated before we <lb/>
could lose a member. He (Mr. W.) was confirmed <lb/>
in this view of the matter by the opinion of Mr. Galt, <lb/>
who said that the house would never have less than <lb/>
134 members, but it would increase at a very slow rate. <lb/>
Now fortified by such an opinion as that, he (Mr. W) <lb/>
must adhere to what he before stated, that he could <lb/>
not understand the learned Doctor's figures on the <lb/>
mode of calculation. <lb/></p> 
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2018-12-11, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>i <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>f <lb/></p> 

<p>3 <lb/></p> 

<p>T <lb/></p> 

<p>such beaming faces, such cor <lb/></p> 

<p>Čít Štuſ <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/>ST. JOE <lb/>
MONDAY, APR <lb/>
-*** <lb/>
aside local matter <lb/>
ble us to make roo <lb/></p> 

<p>w; lay <lb/></p> 

<p>ber to en" <lb/>
news received here on S <lb/>
from New York. We take <lb/></p> 

<p>the capture of Richmond fro <lb/>
of the 4th instant:­ <lb/></p> 

<p>THE CAPTURE <lb/></p> 

<p>n our summary of war <lb/></p> 

<p>it. W. the point where Ge: <lb/>
temporary cessation of hostilit <lb/>
Up to that time our *. #. <lb/>
ing success; save the ill <lb/></p> 

<p>!*::::: sdvance beyond the <lb/>
had gone amise: The grand <lb/>
the stern resolve and unco <lb/>
"Northern horde" were in fu. <lb/>
that our leaders had resolve <lb/>
...rength—that this, *, nº <lb/>
holiday parade, but that..." <lb/>
ºuvre meant business. 'the <lb/>
ºne; the long-delayed and 8 <lb/>
was presenti, the day of door <lb/>
ºwned. We have already <lb/>
features of the contest; from <lb/>
Grant's movement on Wedn: <lb/>
lull in the furious contest on S <lb/>
that point the record is broke <lb/>
ºver-helming as to dwarf all o <lb/>
attention—Richmond is captu <lb/>
ºnce of this truth needs no in <lb/>
breathes freely—the end, dra <lb/>
portant fact eince the first g <lb/>
was announced early yesterºl <lb/>
Times, in the following brief <lb/>
dent: " This morning Lieut. <lb/>
tersburgh evacuated, and he <lb/>
mond also is. He is pushi <lb/>
if possible, the retreating <lb/>
glorious announcement. * <lb/>
by a note from Secretary <lb/>
* It appears from a dispatch 9 <lb/>
ceived by this Department th <lb/>
command are in Richmond. <lb/>
mond, at 8+ this morning." <lb/>
doubt was removed; the truth <lb/>
stronghold was ours; the Lit <lb/>
Belle Island, the capital of th <lb/>
under the baycnets of Union <lb/>
ment was hailed with the <lb/></p> 

<p>even embracings, such indiffe <lb/>
such has'e to display some m <lb/>
never before occurred. All <lb/>
diant with "red, white and <lb/>
stantly suspended; even gol <lb/>
peril, and sang and dauced <lb/>
gay-beards were boys agai <lb/>
lay-ground, and the most <lb/>
indulged in by staid old togi: <lb/>
triumphed over convention. <lb/>
astounding events were going <lb/>
was made—at about 2:30 P.M <lb/>
telegram, sent under the san <lb/>
ment: " Gen Weitzel telegra <lb/>
Richmond at 8:15 this mor <lb/>
guns. The enemy left in gr <lb/>
fire in one place. And muk <lb/>
out. The people receive us <lb/>
sions of joy. Gen Grant st <lb/>
with the ermy toward the <lb/>
Lee's retreating army, if poº <lb/>
has gone to the front.'" <lb/>
doubly surr," and glorious <lb/>
live with Bunker Hill and <lb/>
citement has been seen º <lb/></p> 

<p>four years ago, the sullen <lb/>
upon Sumter startled the na <lb/>
streets and marts of trade t <lb/>
teeth of a betrayed and inst <lb/>
Our losses up to the prese <lb/>
twenty-five hundred; while <lb/>
some parts of the line, at le. <lb/>
own; but, of course, the to <lb/>
Another account says—" <lb/>
rible, and the losses heavy c <lb/></p> 

<p>loss thus far is three times <lb/>
The Gold Room fell nine <lb/>
news from Richmond. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Flood In The Sr. <lb/>
AT Montreal—The Vict <lb/>
Iſo <lb/></p> 

<p>The river rose several <lb/>
piled with ice to a great h <lb/>
came near striking a tube <lb/>
terday morning the river <lb/>
William, Wellington, and <lb/>
and 6 o'clock in the evenir <lb/>
the water rushed over tº <lb/>
Commission-street. At aſ <lb/>
as high as St. Paul and Sl <lb/>
Trunk Railway track bel <lb/>
tanneries is intindated. 'I <lb/>
this morning. The inun <lb/>
covered with rafts formed <lb/>
present, hy far the greate <lb/>
the city is inaccessible ex <lb/>
causing the greatest suffe <lb/>
Later—4 o'clock, P.M. <lb/>
falling. <lb/></p> 

<p>ASSASSINAT <lb/>
DENT LINCOI <lb/></p> 

<p>AND SON. <lb/></p> 

<p>WE give below thi <lb/>
intelligence, received her <lb/>
evening, of the assassin <lb/>
Mr. Seward and his so <lb/>
come to band:­ <lb/></p> 

<p>President Lincoln she <lb/>
*assinated. Mr. Lincol <lb/>
<lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>By TE <lb/></p> 

<p>It is stated that Jeffe <lb/>
resident, was et Dan <lb/>
Lynchburg, on Saturd. <lb/>
bat le was recentl <lb/>
bama, between Federa <lb/>
orrest. The latter w <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-04-27_Page_1.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">St. John's, Thursday, April 27, 1865.</fw>
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2018-12-11, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>- Notice. <lb/>
ers TTMothers T. Moſhºff <lb/></p> 

<p>T tail to procure Mrs. WINslow, ers Ti <lb/>
yrup for children teething. This <lb/>
tion is the prescription of one of th <lb/>
sicians and nurses in the United s. <lb break="no"/>n used for thirty years with never ...it <lb/>
nd success, by millions of mother, a ºiling. <lb/>
om the feeble infant of one week .." chi. <lb/>
It not only relieves the child from pai to the <lb/>
tes the stomach and bowels, corrects . but <lb/>
is tone and energy to the whole .."; <lb/>
ost instantly relieve Griping in the #. <lb/>
olic. We believe it the best and sures: . sand <lb/>
orld in all cases of Dissentery and 5. <lb/>
whether it arises from teething or an idea in <lb/>
Full directions for use will sº ºther <lb/>
None genuine unless the fac-similé .#. <lb/>
ns is on the outside wrapper. Price ... <lb/>
r .*. #. º Medicine Dealers #. <lb/>
Street, New York, and 205 Hi - r <lb/>
England. - High Holbon, <lb/></p> 

<p>MRS. WINSLOW, º <lb/></p> 

<p>rienced Nurse and Female Physician <lb/>
tention of mothers, her Soothing Syrup f <lb/>
teething, which greatly facilitates the º <lb/>
ng, by softening the gums, reducing all i. <lb/>
Hwill allay all pain and spasmodic action a a<lb break="no"/>regulate the bowels. Depend upon it - . <lb/>
will give 1est to yourselves, and relief º <lb/>
your inſants. We have put up and sold. <lb/>
r over thirty years, and can say, in coni. <lb/>
of it what we have never boea able to . <lb/>
her medicine—never has it failed in a sin le <lb/>
to effect a cure, when timely used. N. <lb/>
now an instance of dissatisfaction by any on. <lb/>
it. On the contrary; all speak delight. <lb/>
ºperations, und speaks in terins of commenda. <lb/>
* magical effects and medical virtues. We <lb/>
this matter "what we do now,", after thirty <lb/></p> 

<p>presents <lb/></p> 

<p>t of what, we here decare. In almost every <lb/>
where the infant is suffering from pair and <lb/>
ºn, relief will be found in fifteen or twenty <lb/>
after the syrup is administered. Full dire. <lb/>
using will accompany each bottle. Nons <lb/>
unless the ſac-simile of Curtis and Perkins <lb/>
k, is on the outside wrapper. Sold by prºg: <lb/>
ºughout the wºrld. Principal Office, 48 psy <lb/>
Y, and 205 High Ho-born, England. Priºs <lb/>
ents per bottle. <lb/>
lowing is an extract from a letter written by <lb/>
J S Holme, Pastor of the Pierrepont-streat <lb/>
'huich, Brooklyn, NY, to the "Journal and <lb/>
ºr," Cincinnati, O., and speaks volumes in. <lb/>
that world-renownel medicine, Mrs. Wins. <lb/>
uthing Syrup for Children Teething—"We <lb/>
vertisement in your c lumns of Mrs. Wins<lb break="no"/>thirg Syrup. Now we never said a word in <lb/>
a patent medicine before in our life, but we <lb/>
elled to say to your readers that this is no <lb/>
|-we have tried it, and know it to be all i <lb/>
It is probably one of the most successfu <lb/>
of the day, because it is one of the best <lb/>
e of your readers who have babies ean't do <lb/>
º lay in a supply." <lb/>
J. Dlº ARIN, St. John's, <lb break="no"/>Agent for Newfoundland." <lb/></p> 

<p>PIHO É \ IX FIRE <lb/>
stºratice Collipany. ". <lb/></p> 

<p>bard Street and Charing Cross, London.: <lb/>
ESTA BL 18 HEL)–1782 <lb/>
Titus Tres AN in DiRECTOR8. <lb/>
Burton, Esq. Kirkman D. Hodg on Esq. <lb/>
F. oope, " . James Horne, -\-<lb break="maybe"/>alton, " William J. Lancaster, * <lb/>
" John D. Magen, º <lb/>
John Masterman, Esq. M., P. <lb/>
John Timohy Oxley sai <lb/>
George Stanley Reptor. " <lb/>
Benjamin Shaw, <lb break="no"/>Matthew Whiting, <lb/>
Franzis Wilson, <lb/>
skCRETARIES <lb/>
WILLIAM HARRIs Esq. * * <lb/>
Großge WiLLIAM LoveLL, Esq. <lb/>
ENIX FIRE OF FICE is confidently re<lb break="no"/>d to the notice of the public—for the libera <lb/>
omotitude with which all claims upon it are <lb/>
d paid - as well as for the almost unlimited <lb/>
ich it affords, comprising in addition to the <lb/>
ted Capital of the Crumpany, the whole for <lb/>
numerous Proprieta y. composed oſsom <lb/>
t opulent gentlemen and Merchants in the <lb/>
gdom. <lb/>
UENIX of FICE has carried on an exten <lb/>
ccessful busines: for upwards of seveuty<lb break="no"/>The duty paid by it to Government for <lb/>
in Great Briain and Ireland exceed <lb/>
terling per annurn. <lb/>
nd short time Insurances are undertaken <lb/>
ENIX COMPANY on almost every de<lb break="no"/>iisk, in Newfoundland at a moderate rate <lb/>
which may be know on application to <lb/>
t their oline, in St. John's, where policies <lb/></p> 

<p>ee of charge. <lb break="no"/>... &amp; G. RENDEI.L, <lb/>
Agents for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>'i'HE COLONIAL. <lb/>
x -i, - ºf "aw -<lb break="maybe"/>ASNirante üompany <lb/>
Estarlished 1846. <lb/>
AL, ONE MILLION STERLING. <lb/>
ge of Assuring before 25th <lb/>
May 1863. <lb/>
ird DIVISION OF PROFITS. <lb/>
the advantage of this year's entry to ths <lb/>
e, Proposals must be lodged at the Offie" <lb/>
, Newfoundland, or with one of the Agent" <lb/>
25th May next. <lb/>
ARS BöNUS will be allocated at th: <lb/>
Profits in 1864 to Policies opened before <lb/></p> 

<p>the Books for the Present Year. <lb/>
ATER BY spreial Act of PARLIAMENT. <lb/></p> 

<p>Governor. <lb/></p> 

<p>T HON, fit. EARL of ELGIN &amp; <lb/>
1) INE. Governor-General of INDIA. <lb/>
IcE-\-5 GeoRGEstreet, EDINBURGB <lb/>
Directors in St. John's, Newfoundland<lb break="no"/>O'Brien, Esq. Walter Grieve, Esq.,; <lb/></p> 

<p>Merchant.. fi. <lb/>
William Henry Mare, Esq. º <lb/>
Adviser-Henry Hunt'sºb, M. D. '. <lb/>
igent–Frederick J. Wyatt. <lb/>
"ION OF THE GOMPANY., <lb/>
me of the Company........ e139,"00". <lb/>
ty have divided Profits on two occasions* <lb/></p> 

<p>1859. <lb/></p> 

<p>£1000,opened in 1847,has beenincreased <lb/>
ºy the application of the Bonus; otbed <lb/>
proportion. <lb/>
i esery five years; next division in 1860. <lb/>
received in any part of the world wher <lb/>
ave been es:ablished <lb/></p> 

<p>|:5. <lb/></p> 

<p>*, <lb/>
Foser, " <lb/>
Fuller, " <lb/>
Goodhant" <lb/>
ordon. " <lb/></p> 

<p>perience, and pledge our reputation for th: <lb/></p> 

<p>=== <lb/></p> 

<p>No. 3,659. &gt; <lb/></p> 

<p>Túhe 3iewſmålander, <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, Thursday, April 27, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>… -\- ...— ...: fºx <lb/></p> 

<p>Printed and Published every Monday and Thursday <lb/>
mornings by E]). WARD DALTON SHEA, at his <lb/>
office in DUCKWORTH STREAT-Terms One <lb/>
Guinea per annº payable in advance. <lb/>
inertisements not limited (Auction-sales and notices <lb/>
... determine themselves excepted) are repeated <lb/>
jordered in writing to be withdrawn, and are <lb/>
charged for accordingly. <lb/>
This paper is filed,and ºy be seen free 6 charge a <lb/>
ºf...ys Pill and ointment Establishment, 244 <lb/>
strand, London. <lb/>
SPECIAL INTIMATION. <lb/>
The BENEFITS of Life Assurance with the <lb/>
SMALLEST OUTLAY, <lb/></p> 

<p>combined with the FULLEST SECURITY. <lb/></p> 

<p>- irable object has been attained by the Polic <lb/>
This desira º holders of the y y <lb/></p> 

<p>Life.Association of Scotland <lb/></p> 

<p>By means of its Allocation of Profit in Cash towards <lb/>
the Annual Reduction of the Premiums payable for the <lb/>
Policies, the older Policy-holders paying at present <lb/>
anſ, 12.6d. (instead of 20s) per £1 of the Premiums; <lb/>
and by the following <lb/>
REGULATION FOR FURTHER.DIMINISHING <lb/>
oUTLAY FOR LIFE ASSURANCE. <lb/></p> 

<p>Urtil the time when the premiums may be expected <lb/>
to be reduced by the application of prefits, the Assured <lb/>
fºr £500 or upwards, may leave unpaid a cons derable <lb/>
portion (one-third or one-fourth) of the premiums i.e<lb break="no"/>£ºry to keep the policy in force. The unpaid part <lb/>
is allowed to remain in the hands of the Assured as <lb/>
long as he pleases, and he is not asked to pay interest <lb/>
thereon; but the amount, with accumulated interest, <lb/>
jībe deducted from the sum assured at death. New <lb/>
Entrants thus at once commence with <lb/>
pºſeNTS MUCH BELOW THE TABULAR <lb/></p> 

<p>RATES, <lb/>
and continue to make such reduced payments for six <lb/>
years, when they become entitled to reduction of the <lb/>
premiums by the application of Profits. They will, <lb/>
hevertheless, receive the same benefits and the same <lb/>
share of profit, as if the full premiums had been paid; <lb/>
Present outlay is also further diminished by means of <lb/>
the Association s <lb/>
iNCREASING POLICIES <lb/></p> 

<p>in which the sums Assured shall increase by the mere <lb/>
ispse of time to dozbie the original amount, withºut <lb/>
corresponding increase of premium i and, under the <lb/>
Participating Class, the premiums will be reducible by <lb/>
application of Profits. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Policies do Not Contain several of the Res<lb break="no"/>Prictions commonly imposed on Assured Lives, and <lb/>
conſer on the Policy-holders unusual and important <lb/>
liabilities and privileges. <lb/></p> 

<p>rº-ENTRANTs on or before 5TH APRIL. <lb/>
will secure a decided advantage over later Entrants <lb/>
at the Division of Proſlt. <lb/></p> 

<p>* . <lb/>
NEW FOUNijLAND BRANCH. <lb/>
HEAD OFFICE.-ST. JOHN'S. <lb/>
DIRECTORs: <lb/>
H. K. Dickinson, Esq. Hon. James Cormack. <lb/>
Robert Grieve, Esq. <lb/></p> 

<p>Agent and Secretary.....................E. L. JARWIS. <lb/>
March 7 <lb/></p> 

<p>FTHE Company carrying on business as Mºrchant: <lb/>
in Greenock, under the firm , of KERR &amp; <lb/>
McBride, and in Newſoundland under the firm of <lb/>
McBRIDE &amp; KeRR, was dissolved on the 20th day of <lb/>
February, 1865, of mutual col sent of the subscribers, <lb/>
only partners thereof. -<lb break="maybe"/>Åiſ debts due by the dissolved Company will be paid <lb/>
by the company carrying ºn business in Greenock <lb/>
under the firm of R. K. Mct:RIDE &amp; Co., and in New<lb break="no"/>foundland under the firm of McBRIDE &amp; Co-to whom <lb/>
the stock of the dissolved concern has been transfer<lb break="no"/>red, and who are to carry on the business in future for <lb/>
their own behoof; and they are also authorized to <lb/>
receive payment of, and to discharge all debts due to, <lb/>
the dissolved concern. <lb/>
Greenock, 1st March, 1865. <lb/>
ROBERT KERR. <lb/>
JAMES McBRIDE, <lb/>
PETER McBRIDE, <lb/>
THos KING, Witness. <lb/>
CHARLEs SHANNoN, Witness. <lb/>
March 23. 1 m. <lb/></p> 

<p>LAN CASHIRE <lb/>
Insurance Company. <lb/></p> 

<p>FIRE AND LIFE. <lb/></p> 

<p>CAPITAL THyo MILLIONS STERLING. <lb/>
Head Office: Exchange-Street, Manchester. <lb/>
Board of DIRECTORS <lb break="no"/>John Todd, Esq., Chairman: <lb/>
william H. Bradley, Esq. William Pilkington, Esq., <lb/>
John Clegg, Esq. | Blackburn. <lb/>
B. Darbyshire, Esq., Liv-Joseph Schofield, Esq. <lb/>
erpool. N. Shelmerdine, Esq. <lb/>
Alexander Ewing Esq., James Smith, Esq., Liver<lb break="no"/>Glasgow pool. <lb/>
Samuel Hargreaves, Esq.' James Wagstaff, Esq., Lon<lb break="no"/>John Knowles, Esq. on, <lb/>
J. Robinson Kay, Esq., Edward Wanklyn, Esq. <lb/>
Bury. Barton Wood, Esq. <lb/>
J. Schºfield Mayson, Esq. <lb/>
George Stewart, General Manager: <lb/>
E. L. Jarry IS. <lb/>
Agent for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> -->
    
</div>
    <div type="debate">
    

<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head>
    
    <p rendition="simple:right">Thrsday, March 2.</p>
        
        <p rendition="simple:centre">(To be continued.)</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CASE2">Mr. CASEY</persName> had, on a former occasion, given his <lb/>
opinions on that important question; and although he <lb/>
had since listened attentively to the very able speeches <lb/>
of the supporters of Confederation, he had heard noth<lb break="no"/>ing to change his views. The Attorney General had <lb/>
gone into a historical and constitutional review of the <lb/>
results of the union of small states into large confedera<lb break="no"/>cies. He (Mr. Casey) believed the hon gentleman was <lb/>
honest in his advocacy of union, but he had failed to <lb/>
convince him (Mr. Casey) hat it would be for our in<lb break="no"/>terest to join it. He said, if our people were in distress, <lb/>
we could apply to the general government for relief. <lb/>
He (Mr. Casey) very much doubted the succes of the <lb/>
    application,—They gave us a certain sum by the Quebec <lb/>
    
    <cb/>

Resolutions, which was to be in full for all claims; and <lb/>
if we should be in distress, and applied to the General <lb/>
Government, we would probably be told to borrow on <lb/>
security of the annual allowance made to us. It was <lb/>
stated that notwithstanding the high tariff of Canada <lb/>
we would not pay more to the revenue than we do now, <lb/>
on account of the large quantity of Canadian manufac<lb break="no"/>ture that would come into this Colony duty free. It <lb/>
appeared the Canadians were themselves large consu<lb break="no"/>mers of British goods, and when they could not supply <lb/>
their own wants, how were they to supply ours? The <lb/>
hon member for Carbonear, Mr. Rorke, spoke of sam<lb break="no"/>ples of Canadian boots and leatherware, harness, &amp;c., <lb/>
received by him last fall, but there was a large importa<lb break="no"/>tion of English leather, as well as of boots and shoes, <lb/>
into Canada, notwithstanding the heavy import duties of <lb/>
that Province,—He (Mr. Casey) regretted to say that <lb/>
of late years, much extravagance, in the way of dress, <lb/>
had crept in amongst us. He recollected the time <lb/>
when the operative classes and the fishermen were com<lb break="no"/>fortably clad in a much less expensive fashion than now. <lb/>
Guernsey frocks and coating, jackets and trowsers, of a <lb/>
very superior description, and other useful article of <lb/>
clothing, were imported by West of England houses, and <lb/>
sold at a moderate price. But latterly, he (Mr. Casey) <lb/>
regretted to say, a large quantity of more expensive, and <lb/>
comparatively useless articles had been imported. He <lb/>
fully concurred in the observations of the hon member, <lb/>
Mr. Rorke, about the importance of checking all extrava<lb break="no"/>gance. He (Mr. Casey) thought, so far as regarded <lb/>
boots and shoes, their manufacture here ought to be en<lb break="no"/>couraged, which would furnish a good deal of employ<lb break="no"/>ment to our own people. He was glad to learn that a <lb/>
tannery was about to be established here; and if its <lb/>
proprietors succeeded in making as good leather as its <lb/>
imported, they would have a ready demand for all they <lb/>
could manufacture, while they would give a good deal <lb/>
of employment to shoemakers, as well as to operative <lb/>
tanners and curriers. He looked to greater benefit be<lb break="no"/>ing conferred on our people by encouraging local indus<lb break="no"/>try than by Confederation, for he must say that he did <lb/>
not relish this confederation business at all, more par<lb break="no"/>ticularly on the terms of the Quebec Resolutions. It <lb/>
was stated that we would get our provisions as cheaply <lb/>
from Canada as from the United States. We might, in <lb/>
the summer months, but the navigation of the St. <lb/>
Lawrence closed early, and it might be a question where <lb/>
we should get our supplies during the six winter <lb/>
months. He did not think, however, that Confederation <lb/>
would change the course of trade. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:RORK1">Mr. RORKE</persName>.—The completion of the Grand Trunk <lb/>
Railway would throw the Canadian market open to us <lb/>
during the whole year. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CASE2">Mr. CASEY</persName>.—The completion of the Grand Trunk <lb/>
railroad would do good; but not so much as was main<lb break="no"/>tained by the supporters of Confederation. Another <lb/>
matter—we were toid that under Confederation we would <lb/>
have a large dock here for the repair of vessels that <lb/>
might be disabled in passing our coast. No doubt such <lb/>
a dock would furnish a good deal of employment, which <lb/> 
would be of great advantage to ship carpenters and <lb/> 
others; but, if there was sufficient employment to ren<lb break="no"/>der it profitable, it would be established, Confederation <lb/>
or no Confederation. But he (Mr. Casey) set very little <lb/>
value of these sort of speculative promises. He re<lb break="no"/>membered, some time ago, that Mr. Maguire, the Mays <lb/>
or of Cork, and many other leading men of that city, <lb/>
applied to the British Government for a similar estab<lb break="no"/>lishment at Queenstown, which is a place of resort for all <lb/>
disabled ships crossing the Atlantic for British ports. <lb/>
One of her Aljesty's ships had put in there, in a dam<lb break="no"/>aged state, on one occasion; and although she might <lb/>
have been repaired there, steamers were sent to tow her <lb/>
to an English bockyard for repairs. And so it would be <lb/>
here. As England turned a deaf ear to the deputation <lb/>
from Cork, so would the general government refuse to <lb/>
listen to us. If Dockyards were wanted, they would <lb/>
have them built elsewhere, even although this port <lb/>
might be the most suitable place. It had been urged <lb/>
that we have now an expenditure of £100,000 a year, <lb/>
from which the people derive little or no benefit. He <lb/>
must agree with that remark, to some extent, unfor<lb break="no"/>tunately, for some years past, far too much money <lb/>
was expended in pauper relief. We ought to have had <lb/>
a road grant of £20,000 a year, which would have <lb/>
opened up the country, and would, at the same time <lb/>
have furnished employment to those men who were <lb/>
unsuccessful at the fisheries and prevented their being <lb/>
degraded by applying for pauper relief. He (Mr. Casey) <lb/>
    condemned the present system of pauper relief in <hi rendition="simple:italic">toto</hi>. <lb/>
Even those who received it derived very little advan<lb break="no"/>tage from it. It ought to be reduced to one half or one <lb/>
third of its present amount, and the saving added to the <lb/>
Road Grant. The Solicitor General said increased <lb/>
taxation was his principal reason for opposing Confed<lb break="no"/>eration. The people of Newfoundland could not afford <lb/>
to pay more than they now pay end if there was any <lb/>
increase, the consequence would be that they would be <lb/>
unable to pay. The hon member, Mr. Moore, said <lb/>
Responsible Government was too expensive for this <lb/>
Colony. Why, since the establishment of itesponsible <lb/>
Government, there had been a reduction of official <lb/>
salaries; and it could not be said that it had not worked <lb/>
as well in this Colony as in any other; and the man<lb break="no"/>ner in which our operative population had conducted <lb/>
themselves during a period of deep distress, was highly <lb/>
creditable to them. And would our constituencies give <lb/>
up their independent position, which was gained by a <lb/>
severe and protracted struggle? And for what were <lb/>
they called upon to make such a sacrifice? Why, for <lb/>
the honor and glory of sending eight members to the <lb/>
Confederate Parliament, where they would have no <lb/>
influence whatever. Then the sum proposed to be given <lb/>
us, in lieu of what we are called upon to surrender to the <lb/>
General Government, would be barely sufficient to meet <lb/>
our current expenditure, and would afford very little, if <lb/>
anything, or carrying out improvements, or developing <lb/>
our resources. We were to receive only £80,000 a year, <lb/>
and to have £32,000 of our present expenditure assumed <lb/>
by the General Government. After meeting our current <lb/>
expenditure, we would hardly have a shilling for roads, <lb/>
out of this sum. We were also told that Confederation <lb/>
is necessary for purposes of defence, that we will be <lb/>
called upon to defend ourselves; and that the British <lb/>
North American Colonies must combine for that pur<lb break="no"/>pose. But how could a union with the other colonies do <lb/>
anything for the protection of such a colony as this? <lb/>
In the event of war, this Island must be defended by the <lb/>
British navy. We are told that for many years to come <lb/>
the Confederation will have no navy aud all would <lb/>
admit that an army alone would not be sufficient for our <lb/>
defence, for a naval squadron having the command of our <lb/>
coast would starve us into submission in a few months. <lb/>
Even if the other Provinces had troops to spare for our <lb/>
protection, in place of looking to us, as we might antici<lb break="no"/>pate, for assistance, they could not hold this Islald <lb/>
against an enemy superior to them on them on the sea. No <lb/>
doubt, in case of invasion, our people would be ready to <lb/>
defend themselves; and if the Volunteer movement were <lb/>
        
        <cb/>

extended, he believed it would be a proceeding in the <lb/>
right direction. But he (Mr Casey) did not believe the <lb/>
Imperial Government intended to withdraw the protection <lb/>
of the British navy and of the troops from the colonies. <lb/>
Such a course would be in opposition to the views of the <lb/>
most distinguished British and Colonial statesmen. He <lb/>
(Mr. Casey) would read from the Edinburgh Review on <lb/>
the Report of the Select Committee of the House of <lb/>
Commons on Colonial military expenditure, printed by <lb/>
    the order of the House, July 11, 1864— <lb/></p>
        
        <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
        <p>"The Duke of Newcastle, who speaks with official <lb/>
authority on the subject, thus expresses himself, on the <lb/>
            case of Canada,—'I think one of the duties which de<lb break="no"/>volve upon the mother country is the defence of a colony. <lb/>
            <hi rendition="simple:italic">I do hot know what advantage a colony would find in <lb/>
its relative position, if the mother country did not protect <lb/>
it</hi>. Just on account of the petuliar position of Canada, <lb/>
I think the Imperial Government is bound to keep up a <lb/>
certain amount of force in time of peace, and a much <lb/>
larger force in the event of war. With those parties <lb/>
who would be aggressive, Canada stands in a different <lb/>
position from any other colony, we have. Take, for <lb/>
instance, Austrialia. The real defence of Australia must <lb/>
be by our fleet; but the fleet can do little to assist <lb/>
Canada, except it be by sending small vessels up the St. <lb/>
Lawrence; and nearly the whole assistance to be ren<lb break="no"/>dered by this country to Canada must be by a land <lb/>
force.'"—Report, No. 2992. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>Such was the deliberate opinion of a late lamented <lb/>
statesman, whose experience as Secretary of State for <lb/>
the Colonies gave peculiar importance to his views. He <lb/>
    (Mr. Casey) would also quote the opinion of a distin<lb break="no"/>guished colonist to the same effect. The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Edinburgh <lb/>
Review</hi>, in quoting this gentleman's evidence before the <lb/>
    Committee of the House of Commons, observes:— <lb/></p>
        
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>"Sir Stewart Donaldson, who has held the office of <lb/>
Colonial Secretary, and Colonial Treasurer in New South <lb/>
Wales, and was a member of the Colonial Legislature <lb/>
for upwards of eleven years, testifies to the Colonial <lb/>
opinion, that the mother country ought to protect the <lb/>
colony against dangers which flow from her own foreign <lb/>
policy. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>"Chairman.—Do you say that the claim of those <lb/>
colonies in respect of their defences mainly rests upon <lb/>
            the points in which they may be involved by the con<lb break="no"/>flicts of England with foreign powers?— <lb/></p>
        
        <p>"Yes,—I think that principle is very generally <lb/>
accepted in the Colonies, that, as they are not free agents <lb/>
with regard to European complications, they ought not <lb/>
to be left in a state undefence in case some enemy of the <lb/>
mother country should take advautage of their defence<lb break="no"/>less situation and invade them, or combard their towns; <lb/>
and that so long as the mother country is liable to be <lb/>
involved in European wars, and so long as enemies from <lb/>
without may do damage to the colonial interests, it is <lb/>
felt that England is bound to protect the colonies, at all <lb/>
events, on the seaboard, &amp;c.—(Report, No. 2653.) <lb/></p>
    </quote>
        
        <p>
But the Delegates, before they separated at Quebec, <lb/>
pledged themselves to the maintenance of an army and a <lb/>
navy. Now he (Mr. Casey) would ask, was Newfound<lb break="no"/>land in a position to meet such an expenditure as this <lb/>
would involve? It was stated that a million of dollars <lb/>
annually would meet the required expenditure. It was <lb/>
absurd to suppose that this sum would go any length <lb/>
towards the raising and maintenance of an army alone; <lb/>
and as for a navy, it would not build; much less maintain <lb/>
the mere semblance of a naval armament. He (Mr. <lb/>
Casey) would quote from a speech by Mr. Millar at a <lb/>
public meeting at Halifax, on the military expenditure <lb/>
necessary for the defence of the provinces. That gentle<lb break="no"/>man said:— <lb/></p> 


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"With the knowledge that the British Government <lb/>
has been urging Canada to fortify her frontier let we <lb/>
turn your attention to section 67, which says:—"All <lb/>
engagements that may, before the union, be entered into <lb/>
with the imperial government for the defence of the coun<lb break="no"/>try shall be assumed by the General Government—So if <lb/>
Canada has assumed liabilities to the extent of five, ten or <lb/>
twenty millions of dollars, we must contribute to their <lb/>
payment, gentlemen on both sides are particular in their <lb/>
figures about comparatively small matters, but here is <lb/>
one item alone that may swell to millions, about which <lb/>
we are perfectly in the dark. It should stagger the <lb/>
friends of the measure. I have said sir, the British <lb/>
Government at the present time is prepared to defend us <lb/>
for imperial interest's; let us become part of the con<lb break="no"/>templated Confederation, and our position will be changed. <lb/>
If we become part of a great Empire, we must be prepa<lb break="no"/>red to assume our share of its responsibilities. It is <lb/>
boasted, that the English press and Government are fa<lb break="no"/>vourable to the change, but would it not be strange if it <lb/>
were otherwise? They expect we are going to take a <lb/>
great burden off their shoulders and place it on our own. <lb/>
They expend over $6,000,000 yearly on these Colonies <lb/>
that they expect to save by Confederation. Sir, in our <lb/>
eagerness to become an empire we appear to forget the <lb/>
cost its glitter and magnificance will entail. Suppose <lb/>
this union be brought about. Suppose we agree to yield <lb/>
up the immunities of our present situation what will then <lb/>
be our position? Beside us we will have a formidable and <lb/>
aggressive nation, who at all times, hereafter will possess <lb/>
a standing army of 200,000, in addition to a large popu<lb break="no"/>lation inured to the privations, the dangers, and the dis<lb break="no"/>cipline of war; with this pleasant neighbour, entertain<lb break="no"/>ing no kindly feelings towards us, our great Empire will <lb/>
require a better standing army of its own. I am going <lb/>
to be very economical, and although twenty regiments <lb/>
under such circumstances would be a small provision, I <lb/>
am only going to reckon this cost. I will take the cost <lb/>
of the Canadian Rifies, (1350 men) for my basis, every <lb/>
man of whom, it is estimated, when drilled and equipped <lb/>
&amp;c. stood Great Britain £100 Stg a head. At this <lb/>
rate the "raising" of twenty Regiments would amount <lb/>
to the neat sum of $13,500,000. The "pay" of the <lb/>
Canadian Rifles, when according to the army Estimates, <lb/>
is £41,575, 14 Stg. not including clothing, arms, &amp;c. for <lb/>
twenty regiments would give us an annual disoursement <lb/>
of $154,525, for this service without outfits or incidental <lb/>
charges, we will also require at the lowest calculation a <lb/>
dozen brigades of Artillery, the expense of equipping <lb/>
which I am not able to give but it must be something <lb/>
startling; the yearly pay alone of a brigade of Artillery <lb/>
is £24,500 sterling. These are some of the pleasant <lb/>
burthens in store for us when we become "a Great Em<lb break="no"/>pire." (Cheers) These are items that have entered into <lb/>
the figures of no gentlemen, because, like the clause <lb/>
providing for the defence of Canada they have wisely <lb/>
been left in doubt and undefined, it requires, however <lb/>
no great prescience to foretell that our burdens under <lb/>
this Confederation, instead of $12,000,000 annually, be<lb break="no"/>fore five years will double that sum. The doubling of <lb/>
our taxation must follow, in place of even $4.00 per <lb/>
head unay be $8,00. But it may be asked if the dangers of <lb/>
attack from a hostile neighbour will be great in case of <lb/>
union, will they not be more so, if we remain as we are? <lb/>
So far as Nova Scotia is concerned, I answer—no. Can<lb break="no"/>ada is the weak joint in these Colonies. It is to defend <lb/>
Canada not the whole Provinces, union is wanted. If <lb/>
Canada desires to remain as she is she must assume all <lb/> 

<cb/>

the burthens her situation demands, we are not to the <lb/>
same extent under any such necessity." (Cheers.) <lb/></p>
</quote>
        
    <p>
Now would the supporters of Confederation say how <lb/>
such an expenditure could be met from Colonial finds, <lb/>
without such excessive taxation as it would be impossible <lb/>
for us to pay? Let hon members state what amount of <lb/>
taxation would be inevitable. If they complained in <lb/>
Nova Scotia, where they would have the benefit of the <lb/>
Grand Trunk railway, bringing to their doors a large <lb/>
amount of Western trade, the profits of which would go <lb/>
far to enable them to meet the increased taxation that <lb/>
would result from the union and its consequences, why <lb/>
should we, who have no such prospects, render ourselves <lb/>
liable to such taxation? But besides the heavy taxation, <lb/>
and the giving over to the General Government of our <lb/>
mines and minerals, and of the power to legislate for our <lb/>
fisheries, the patronage of all the offices in our Customs. <lb/>
Post Office and Lighthouses, as well as in our Courts of <lb/>
Justice, would be vested in the General Government. <lb/>
They would appoint our Judges, our Posmaster General, <lb/>
and all his subordinates, and also the whole of the <lb/>
Customs' staff, throughout the Colony, and pay them out <lb/>
of the taxes levied upon us. There offices might be <lb/>
filled by Canadians, Nova Scotians, or New Brunswick<lb break="no"/>ers; but there would be very little probability of the <lb/>
patronage being conferred on Newfoundlanders. At <lb/>
present, under Responsible government, all offices in <lb/>
this Colory, from the highest to the lowest, with the <lb/>
exception of that of governor, were given to our own <lb/>
people; but what influence would our eight members in <lb/>
the Federal House of Commons have to secure offices for <lb/>
Newfoundland, when opposed by the influence of Canada, <lb/>
New Brunswick or Nova Scotia? The Attorney Gene<lb break="no"/>ral and other supporters of Confederation had told us of <lb/>
the prospect of our educated young men under confede<lb break="no"/>ration—that they could go to Canada, where there <lb/>
would be a field for their exertions. He (Mr. Casey) <lb/>
believed that Canada had young men for all the appoint<lb break="no"/>ments that would be in the gift of the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, while New Brunswickers and Nova Scotians would <lb/>
also be looking for a share of them; and that, so far <lb/>
from our young men participating in its patronage in <lb/>
Canada, all our own offices worth accepting would be <lb/>
bestowed by the general government upon the friends of <lb/>
their supporters in the other provinces, what influence <lb/>
would our eight members have in a House of Commons—<lb/>
consisting of 194, all eager to benefit their own friends <lb/>
and supporters? He (Mr. Casey) would repeat, that <lb/>
he could see no real tangible benefit to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of Newfoundland to be derived from this <lb/>
proposed Confederation of the British North Ameri<lb break="no"/>can Colonies, and therefore he opposed it. If he <lb/>
saw that it would benefit his native country, he <lb/>
would give it his hearty support; but after giving the <lb/>
matter the fullest consideration, it was his deliberate <lb/>
opinion that it was calculated to prove ruinous to this <lb/>
country. He cordially approved of the Resolution before <lb/>
the chair. Let the matter go to the constituencies and <lb/>
let them pronounce upon it. He had every confidence <lb/>
as to the decision they would come to. Confederation <lb/>
might be some benefit to Nova Scotia and New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, although it was strongly opposed in both provin<lb break="no"/>ces. But for his part, he did not see of what advantage <lb/>
it would be to Newfoundland, and he certainly did see <lb/>
many powerful reasons why we should reject it. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
<persName ref="pers:NOWL2">Mr. NOWLAN</persName> wished to make a few observations on <lb/>
that important subject. He felt it his duty to express his <lb/>
opinions upon it, so that his constieuents might know his <lb/>
sentiments; for he conceived it the duty, of every hon <lb/>
member of the house to state his views fully and unequi<lb break="no"/>vocally upon such an important subject as that, involving <lb/>
the most momentous consequences to the present and <lb/>
future generations. After the long and able speeches of <lb/>
hon gentlemen who had preceded him, he (Mr. Nowlan) <lb/>
did not intend to enter into the subject at any great <lb/>
length. No question of equal importance had come be<lb break="no"/>fore the legislature of this colony on any former occasion, <lb/>
and although the house was not now called upon to pro<lb break="no"/>nounce any decision upon it, still it had been very pro<lb break="no"/>perly taken up by hon members on its merits; and they <lb/>
had all themselves addressed to the consideration of whe<lb break="no"/>ther it would not be for,the advantage of this colony to en<lb break="no"/>ter into a Confederation with the other British North Amer<lb break="no"/>ican Colonies, on the terms and conditions embodied in <lb/>
the Resolutions adopted at the Quebec Conference. In <lb/>
considering such a subject as that, he was of opinion that <lb/>
it should be regarded entirely on its own merits, and he <lb/>
could say for himself that he came to the consideration <lb/>
with an unbiassed mind. He would admit that he would <lb/>
not be opposed to a union of this Colony with the other <lb/>
British North American Colonies, provided we could en<lb break="no"/>ter that union on fair and equitable terms. He had <lb/>
given the subject a great deal of consideration, and had <lb/>
endeavoured to make himself acquainted with the matter <lb/>
in all its bearing on this Island; and the more he looked <lb/>
into it, the more he was convinced that it would not be <lb/>
for the interests of Newfoundland to enter into the pro<lb break="no"/>posed union on the terms laid down in the resolutions. <lb/>
At the same time, he must say his leanings were in fa<lb break="no"/>vour of a union upon most satisfactory terms. He did <lb/>
not think, however, that the terms proposed were such <lb/>
as it would be for the interests of this Colony to accept. <lb/>
He would be disposed to vote for it, if he could say that <lb/>
it was calcuated to confer any permanent or substantial <lb/>
benefit on the country. But so far from that, he feared <lb/>
that if we rushed hastily into this confederation scheme, <lb/>
we might soon have much cause to regret it. If we look<lb break="no"/>ed at this mater in a financial point of view, it would <lb/>
be seen that this Colony would be subjected to <lb/>
a severe loss. The hon member for Ferryland, <lb/>
Mr. Glen who was looked upon as a sound and <lb/>
cautious <choice><sic>finncier</sic><corr>financier</corr></choice>, had very plainly shewn that we <lb/>
would lose annually by accepting this project, no less <lb/>
than from Forty to Fifty thousand pounds. That was <lb/>
a very serious consideration and ought not to be lightly <lb/>
passed over. Our revenue under the existing tariff, was, <lb/>
on an average of years £100,000, and taxing our popu<lb break="no"/>lation at 120,000, our taxation in the shape of Custom's <lb/>
duties is 16s, 8d. stg, per head; and we have always <lb/>
been able to raise sufficient money under this tariff, for <lb/>
the requirements of the country. But if we should go <lb/>
into this Confederation, and the Canadian tariff applied <lb/>
to our imports, what would be the result The Customs <lb/>
returns laid upon the table show that the revenue col<lb break="no"/>lected in this Island would be increased to £157,000 a <lb/>
year, or 25s per head of our population, an audition of <lb/>
50 per cent upon our present rate of taxation, being an <lb/>
enormous addition to the present heavy burden, upon <lb/>
our people; and the worst feature in the affair is the <lb/>
fact that the people of this country would not receive <lb/>
any benefit from the enormous increase of taxation. If <lb/>
our revenue under the Canadian tariff should amount to <lb/>
this large sum, the whole surplus would go to Canada, <lb/>
after paying our subsidy of £112,000 and we would love <lb/>
annually the sum of £45,000, being the difference between <lb/>
these amounts; which would be handed over to the <lb/>
General Government, to be expended in improvements <lb/>
in the other colonies, in any way the Federal House of <lb/>
Commons should chose to sanction, such railways, canals, <lb/>
and of her public works, in the advantages of which this <lb/></p>

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-04-27_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">2</fw>
        
        <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>



<p>country would participate to a very small extent. It <lb/>
appeared to him (Mr. Nowlan) that the sacrifices we <lb/>
were called upon to make were greater than those <lb/>
proposed for any of the other colonies, while they <lb/>
were without any corresponding advantages. Under <lb/>
the Resolutions agreed to at Quebec, we were called <lb/>
upon to give up, to a certain extent, our Legislative <lb/>
independence, to surrender our mines and minerals <lb/>
and our waste lands, and certain of our public build<lb break="no"/>ings, and a sum of £45,000 annually, of our public <lb/> 
revenue, which would be applied towards the comple<lb/>tion of such works as the Grand Trunk Railway and <lb/>
the Canals of Canada, and to the military defence of <lb/>
that Province, and no hon. member would contend <lb/>
that our interest in these was equal to that of the <lb/>
other colonies, or that we would not be much bene<lb break="no"/>fited by an expenditure of equal amount on public <lb/>
works in this Island. Besides, we were called upon <lb/>
to give the General Government and Legislature, in <lb/>
which we would have but a very limited influence, the <lb/>
power of taxing us to any extent they might hereafter <lb/>
think necessary. These were some of the sacrifices we <lb/>
would have to make if we joined the Confederation; <lb/>
and he (Mr. Nowlan) did not think the country would, <lb/>
under these circumstances, enter into the proposed <lb/>
union on the terms of the Quebec Resolutions. We <lb/>
ought to pause before voluntarily committing ourselves <lb/>
to this scheme for ever. And what were we to recieve <lb/>
in for all these sacrifices. Only the small sum <lb/>
of £112,000 a year, with the control of only £80,000 <lb/>
of that amount. That was all we were to have to pro<lb break="no"/>vide for our civil expenditure, our Road service, and <lb/>
for Education. This is not sufficient, at present, for <lb/>
the public requirements. But if we are to have all the <lb/>
good things which the supporters of Confederation tell <lb/>
us will flow from it—if in the course of twenty or <lb/>
thirty years the resources of the country are to be so <lb/>
much developed, our mines and minerals profitably <lb/>
worked by Canadian capitalists, the waste lands of the <lb/>
country settled and cultivated, manufactories put in <lb/>
profitable operation, and, as a consequence, our popu<lb break="no"/>lation more than doubled, what would the Custom's <lb/>
revenue of this Island then amount to? Would it be <lb/>
short of £300,000 per annum, while all of it at our <lb/>
own disposal would still be only £80,000? Then <lb/>
how could we find means to provide for our local re<lb break="no"/>quirements? We must necessarily resort to direct <lb/>
taxation, so distasteful to all classes in this communi<lb break="no"/>ty; and which he (Mr. Nowlan) believed could not <lb/>
be carried out. But, however reluctant we might be<lb/>
to resort to direct taxation to meet our own wants, the <lb/>
General Government would have the power to do so, <lb/>
to meet theirs. They would have the power to tax <lb/>
our lands, our houses, horses, carriages, vessels and <lb/>
fishing stages, as well as to impose an export duty <lb/>
upon our fish and oil. These were matters requiring <lb/>
serious consideration, and which ought not to be <lb/>
hastily disposed of. We were told by the advocates <lb/>
of Confederation, that if we entered it we should have <lb/>
direct steam communication with Canada and with <lb/>
Great Britain, and have our coastal steam communica<lb break="no"/>tion improved. But there was no guarantee for this <lb/>
being done. There was not one word of the subject <lb/>
in the Quebec Resolutions, notwithstanding that so <lb/>
much of our revenue would have to go towards the <lb/>
<choice><sic>consurretion</sic><corr>construction</corr></choice> of the Grand Trunk Railway, which was <lb/>
expressly provided for in the Quebec Resolutions, as <lb/>
well as the enlargement of the canals of Canada. He <lb/>
(Mr. Nowlan) said the matter of steam communication <lb/>
ought to be definitely settled previous to the question <lb/>
of Confederation being entertained. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Placentia, Mr. Shea, stated that the people of <lb/>
Canada paid less taxation per head, under their high <lb/>
tariff, than we pay in this Colony. That was admit<lb break="no"/>ted; and it was one of the disadvantages which he <lb/>
(Mr. Nowlan) saw in the proposal for union. The <lb/>
Canadians, under their high tariff, paid in Customs <lb/>
and Excise duties about 14s. per head, while we, in <lb/>
Newfoundlaud, would have to pay, if the same tariff <lb/>
should be put in force here, no less than 25s perhead. <lb/>
It would, therefore, be seen how very unfairly that <lb/>
tariff would operate upon us. If we looked at it in <lb/>
another light, we would find that a population of <lb/>
120,000 in this Colony, would pay under that tariff <lb/>
£157,000 a year, or 25s per head, while 120,000 of <lb/>
Canada, would pay only £84,000, or 14s. per head <lb/>
thus showing that we would pay annually in Customs' <lb/>
duties £73,000 more than an equal population in <lb/>
Canada, or that we would be subjected to nearly <lb/>
double the rate of taxation of Canada. Would any <lb/>
intelligent person say such inequality of burdens was <lb/>
fair, or that it would ever be voluntarily submitted to? <lb/>
Any one who took the trouble to look into those could <lb/>
not fail to see the very unequal taxation to which this <lb/>
country would be subjected; while the advantages we <lb/>
could derive from Confederation would be much less <lb/>
than the other colonies would enjoy. If we enter<lb break="no"/>ed into the Confederation on the proposed terms, this <lb/>
rate of taxation would be inevitable. But it might be <lb/>
asked how the Canadian tariff would operate so un<lb break="no"/>fairly upon us? Simply in this way, that the people <lb/>
of Canada are largely engaged in agricultural and <lb/>
manufacturing pursuits; and in a position to supply <lb/>
themselves with domestic and home manufactures to a <lb/>
large extent, while we import all woollens and all the <lb/>
cottons, as well as all the leatherware we consume. <lb/>
We are entirely a consuming population, producing <lb/>
but a small portion of our food, and scarcely any of <lb/>
the materials of wearing apparel. We thus consume <lb/>
nearly double the quantity of dutiable goods per head <lb/>
that is consumed by the Canadians, who are large <lb/>
producers themselves. In this statement, he (Mr. <lb/>
Nowlan) was borne out by Mr. Galt, the finance <lb/>
Minister of Canada, who in his speech to the constitu<lb break="no"/>ents at Sherbrooke, said on the subject of the tariff— <lb/>"
Newfoundland, being a fishing population, the am<lb break="no"/>ount of dutiable articles which they consume was <lb/>
about double, per head, what it was here in Canada. <lb/>
They would, therefore, in the shape of Customs du<lb break="no"/>ties, be contributing to the Confederation a larger <lb/>
proportion than properly belonged to them." We <lb/>
could not have a better authority on this subject than <lb/>
Mr. Galt, a gentleman who, from his position, no <lb/>
doubt understood the difference in the working of the <lb/>
Canadian tariff here and in Canada. It had been <lb/>
stated by some of the advocates of Confederation that <lb/>
    the Canadian tariff would not be adopted by the Fed<lb break="no"/>eral Legislature.—But any person who took the <lb/>
trouble to look into the matter must see that a lower <lb/>
tariff than that of Canada, for the Confederated Colo<lb break="no"/>nies, would not produce sufficient revenue to meet the <lb/>
requirements of the Federal Government. It was ad<lb break="no"/>mitted that at least a Customs revenue of 12 millions <lb/>
of dollars would be required and he (Mr. Nowlan) <lb/>
could not see how that amount could be raised with a <lb/>
lower tariff. The following statesmen would show the <lb/>
populatien of each Province, and the probable amount <lb/>
per head that each would have to pay in Customs and <lb/>
Excise duties uuder the present Citadian tariff:— <lb/></p> 
        
        <table>
            <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Population.</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$ c.</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
            <row><cell>Canada,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,500,000</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2 80</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$7,000,000</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Nova Scotia</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">330,000</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1 320 000</cell></row>
            <row><cell>New Brunswick,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">252,000</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">324 000</cell></row>
            <row><cell>P. E. Island,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">81,000</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">324 000</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Newfoundland,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">130,000</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">5 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">650,000</hi></cell></row>
            <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">10,292,000</cell></row>
        </table>
        
        <table>
            <row><cell>Estimated proceeds of Public <lb/> Works, &amp;c................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">1 000,000</hi></cell></row>
            <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$11,292,000</cell></row>
        </table>
        
<cb/>

<p>This amount of revenue is less than the estimate; <lb/>
which is sufficient to show that a lower tariff would <lb/>
not be adequate to meet the mere annual requirement <lb/>
of the General Government, not to speak of the cost <lb/>
of an army and a navy, and the outlay to put the coun<lb break="no"/>try in a state of defence; and also for the completion <lb/>
of the grand Trunk Railway and the enlargement of <lb/>
the canals, and for the other public works to be car<lb break="no"/>ried out under Confederation. These were matters <lb/>
which ought to be seriously considered and satisfac<lb break="no"/>torily arranged previous to entering into the union. <lb/>
We had been told that if we declined entering the <lb/>
union upon these unequal terms, we would not obtain <lb/>
such good terms afterwards. He (Mr Nowlan) felt <lb/>
very little anxiety upon that point. It, as had been <lb/>
stated, it is the policy of the British government to <lb/>
carry out a Federal union of the British North Ame<lb break="no"/>rican provinces, their influence would be sufficient to <lb/>
procure our admission at any time they might deem <lb/>
expedient, as well as to secure us equable terms. He <lb/>
(Mr Nowlan) believed it was the wish of the parent <lb/>
State that the other Colonies should be united; and it <lb/>
was only natural that such a union should be effeeted. <lb/>
They were situated on the same continent, contiguous <lb/>
to each other, divided only by imaginary lines. The <lb/>
habits, the sympathies and the callings of the people <lb/>
are similar, and they have much and frequent inter<lb break="no"/>course with each other. But we are very differently <lb/>
circumstanced. Our interests are not identical with <lb/>
theirs. We are entirely a fishing population, and this <lb/>
Island is separated from them by <choice><sic>hsndreds</sic><corr>hundreds</corr></choice> of miles of <lb/>
sea. Besides, it is evident, from the information we <lb/>
possess, through the papers laid before the House, <lb/>
that there was at first no intention of including New<lb break="no"/>foundland in the proposed union. It was by a mere <lb/>
accident that we were invited to send Delegates at the <lb/>
Conference held at Quebec. The hon the Attorney <lb/>
General happened to be at Halifax on private business <lb/>
when the Charlottetown Conference was about being <lb/>
held; and in an interview with the Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary of Nova Scotia, he impressed that gentleman <lb/>
with his own views, that Newfoundland should parti<lb break="no"/>cipate in any advantages derivable from the union to <lb/>
    be then considered—the Legislative union of the mar<lb break="no"/>itime Provinces—Subsequently, the Government of <lb/>
this Colony were invited to send Delegates to a Con<lb break="no"/>ference at Quebec, to consider the proposal of a Fe<lb break="no"/>deral union of all the British North Americal Colo<lb break="no"/>nies; and the invitation was complied with; but the <lb/>
Delegates were merely to watch the proceedings, and <lb/>
without authority to bind this colony to anything. <lb/>
That was the origin of our connection with this mat<lb break="no"/>ter; and judging from these facts, was it reasonable <lb/>
to suppose that the British Government would force <lb/>
us into this union against our consent? He (Mr. <lb/>
Nowlan) thought not. With respect to the military <lb/>
aspect of the question, our people, it is clear, are a <lb/>
fishing and seafaring people, and would, most prooab<lb break="no"/>ly, always be so. But if a necessity should arise in <lb/>
the event of a war, no doubt they would be required <lb/>
to contribute their share of troops for the defence of <lb/>
the Confederated Colonies. It had been stated that <lb/>
the aggregate amount of our import duties would not <lb/>
be increased, even if the present Canadian tariff were <lb/>
supplied—that we would import largely of manufactur<lb break="no"/>ed goods from Canada. But he (Mr Nowlan) did not <lb/>
consider that our importations from Canada would be <lb/>
much more than they are at present. The manufac<lb break="no"/>tures of Canada are not so well suited to the tastes of <lb/>
our people as British manufactured guods, and he be<lb break="no"/>heved it would be no easy matter to change the tastes <lb/>
and habits of our people in this respect; and he could <lb/>
not see any great advantage that would accrue to us <lb/>
even if we were to purchase our goods in Canada. If <lb/>
be thought that manufactures would spring up here <lb/>
amongst ourselves to any extent, as one of the results <lb/>
of Confederation, and thus give employment to our <lb/>
people, be might be disposed to regard the matter in <lb/> 
a somewhat more favourable light; but he saw very <lb/> 
little chance of such taking place. Some hon mem<lb break="no"/>bers had stated that the debt of Canada is represented <lb/>
by great Public Works, and that the province is in <lb/>
a flourishing condition, whilst Newfoundland was re<lb break="no"/>presented as a poor, pauperised country, without posi<lb break="no"/>tion or influence. It imust be admitted that this <choice><sic>colo<lb break="no"/>ay</sic><corr>colony</corr></choice>, as at present, is in a depressed condition, owing <lb/>
to successive bed fisheries. But he (Mr Nowlan) <lb/>
would like to know if confederation would remove our <lb/>
pauperism. He did not believe that it would; but if <lb/>
we had a few seasons of good fisheries, pauperism <lb/>
would disappear, whether we have Confederation or <lb/>
not. Our revenue is at present sufficient for our re<lb break="no"/>quirements, and our debt is only 8 dollars a head for <lb/>
our population. But what is the financial condition <lb/>
of Canada, the country we are asked to join? Her <lb/>
debt is 25 dollars per head, and it would be seen by <lb/>
reference to the public accounts of that country, that <lb/>
for the last eight or ten years preceding 1864 the rev<lb break="no"/>enue was not equal to the expenditure, and the politi<lb break="no"/>cal state of the country was such, owing to differences <lb/>
of race and religion, that they had frequent changes <lb/>
of government, and that latterly no party could carry <lb/>
on the government, longer than for a few months. <lb/>
They had been running into debt at a frightful rate, <lb/>
about one-fourth of their present debt having resulted <lb/>
from deficiencies in the annual revenue. Bad as our <lb/>
condition is, it is not so bad as this. So it apperrs <lb/>
that Canada is not after all in such a flourishing con<lb break="no"/>dition as the supporters of Confederation would have <lb/>
us believe. Our delegates, no doubt, had made the <lb/>
best bargain they could for us under the circumstanc<lb break="no"/>es, but he (Mr Nowlan) could not vote for the union <lb/>
on the terms which they had agreed upon. He could <lb/>
not see any substantial advantage to be derived from <lb/>
it. The hon member for Placentia, Mr. Shea, said we <lb/>
are to have a loock established here for the repair of <lb/>
large vessels disabled on their voyage between the <lb/>
other North American Colonies and the United King<lb break="no"/>dom, that we are to have transatlantic steam commu<lb break="no"/>nication, and a line of Steamers to Canada, and the <lb/>
local postal service improved. But not one of these <lb/>
matters was guaranteed by the Quebec Resolutions. <lb/>
It was not a little remarkable that when some of those <lb/>
who are now such strenuous advocates for Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion were contending for Responsible government and <lb/>
Free Trade, we were told of the improvements which <lb/>
would result from these concessions, improvements <lb/>
which had not all been realised; and these same par<lb break="no"/>ties now tell us that even with Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, a small Legislature such as ours is powerless to <lb/>
do the country much good, and that the remedy for <lb/>
our poverty and misfortunes is confederation, which <lb/>
will give us a Federal Legislature at Ottawa, to <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
all our ills. He (Mr Nowlan) thought we ought to be <lb/>
call <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>, and to hesitate about adopting the views of <lb/>
these hon members on this question of Confederation. <lb/>
They may be just as much in error now as by their own <lb/>
admission they were ten years ago on Responsible <lb/>
Government. There was another matter which he <lb/>
(Mr Nowlan) could not help referring to—the difference <lb/>
of opinion among the adventuers of this measure. One <lb/>
hon member was entirely in favour of this union; but <lb/>
he objected to our giving Mines, Minerals and <lb/>
Crown Lands. Another was of the opinion that Confed<lb break="no"/>eration would be most beneficial if we had steam com<lb break="no"/>munication with Britain and Canada, and the hon and <lb/>
learned Doctor took exception to the basis of re<lb break="no"/>presentation and shewed by figures that in 36 years <lb/>
    hence we would lose two of our eight memebers— <lb/>
while Upper Canada also would have more members than <lb/>
all the Confederation besides. If these hon members <lb/>
were sincre, they should have opposed Confedera<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

tion until the causes of their objections were remov<lb break="no"/>ed. And the constituencies would have some diffi<lb break="no"/>culty in giving their support to parties who were <lb/>
partly for, and partly against confederation. The <lb/>
hon member for Port de Grave, Mr. Leamon, was <lb/>
candid and home t. He spoke in favour of Confede<lb break="no"/>ration. and would have gone immediately into the <lb/>
discussions of the resolutions. It was urged that the <lb/>
British Government would withdraw the troops if we <lb/>
refused to enter the union. He (Mr. Nowlan) be<lb break="no"/>lieved the British Government would always afford us <lb/>
that military and naval protection that we had hitherto <lb/>
received. The most important interest we have to <lb/>
protect is our fisheries; and the encroachments most <lb/>
complained of were those of the French on the Labra<lb break="no"/>dor and at other points; and he was satisfied that a <lb/>
ship-of-war would be sent every summer to protect <lb/>
our fisheries, and that the detachment of troops <lb/>
stationed here would not be withdrawn. The other <lb/>
<choice><sic>Colouies</sic><corr>Colonies</corr></choice> are as much interested in the protection of <lb/>
the Labrador fisheries as we are, and, they would <lb/>
have the same interest in them after Confederation as <lb/>
now, and whether we should go into Confederation or <lb/>
not, our interest would receive the same protection as <lb/>
those of the other Colonies. These were his senti<lb break="no"/>ments on that important question. He was opposed <lb/>
to Confederation on the terms laid down in the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Resolutions; and he was glad that the matter <lb/>
was not to be disposed of hastily. It was of too much <lb/>
importance to be decided without reference to the <lb/>
constituencies. The constitution under which hon <lb/>
members held their seats was not given to that House, <lb/>
but to the people of the country, and they alone had <lb/>
the right to consent to such an important change as <lb/>
Confederation would effect upon it. He had much <lb/>
pleasure, therefore, in supporting the Resolution <lb/>
before the chair. He was glad the hon leader of the <lb/>
Government had laid such a temperate Resolution on <lb/>
the table. It met the views both of the supporters <lb/>
and the opponents of Confederation, as it postponed <lb/>
the decision of the question until after the constituen<lb break="no"/>cies shall have pronounced upon it. He thought it <lb/>
should be made the platform at the approaching <lb/>
General Election. He (Mr. Nowlan) was prepared <lb/>
to go before his constituents on the views he had now <lb/>
expressed, and if they should not return him, he was <lb/>
prepared to bow to their decision, however much he <lb/>
might value a seat in that House. But he would <lb/>
never be a party to ceding away the rights and priv<lb break="no"/>ileges of the people. With these remarks he would <lb/>
support the Resolution before the chair, and let the <lb/>
mitter be decided by the Constituencies at the ap<lb break="no"/>proaching General Election. <lb/></p>


        <!-- IC, 2018-12-11, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->


<!--<p>Royal ARTILLERY.—Holloway's Ointment and <lb/>
Pills.-A serjeant in the Royal Artillery, writes, on <lb/>
December 12th, 1862, from Poonamattee, Midras <lb/>
Presidency, that his right leg, from the ar, kle to the <lb/>
calf, was a quagmire of disease and corruption; that <lb/>
he was on the hospital roll for twelve mºntas, with<lb break="no"/>out any improvement in his case; that he, as a forlorn <lb/>
hope, resolved to try Hylioway's celebrated Oinºument <lb/>
and Pills. These soon gave ease, expe led the end <lb/>
humours from the limb, heale the apparently incura<lb break="no"/>ble sore, and restored him to sound health. Soldiers <lb/>
and sailors are earnestly recommended to have re<lb break="no"/>course to these invaluable medicaulants for curiug old <lb/>
wounds, sores, or ulcers—more particularly when taey <lb/>
have arisen from imprudence and seem incurable. <lb/></p> 

<p>- - —e<lb break="no"/>EveRYTHING IN SEAson. That grey hairs are hon<lb break="no"/>f." in old age is a proveroi il matter; bºt are <lb/></p> 

<p>ey so in youin P <lb/>
Hair Restorer and Zylot, alsa'mun, or Hair Dressing, <lb/>
are suited to botn young and ord, they restore grey <lb/>
hair to its youthful color, giving the roots the natural <lb/>
nourisment. They renew, preserve and increase the <lb/>
growth. Every Druggist sells them. J. J. Dearin, <lb/>
Sole Agent for Newfoundland, to wilon all orders <lb/>
must be addressed. <lb/></p> 

<p>(Lºt ſtufºuſſimtr. <lb/></p> -->
        
        
        
        
        <!--IC CHECK IF THIS IS RELEVENT 2018-12-11-->

<!--<p>ST. JOH.W'S: <lb/>
THURSDAY, APRIL 27, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>WHEN the question of Confederation came under dis<lb break="no"/>cussion a few months ago, the cry was raised for party <lb/>
purposes that the measure was to be forced into <lb/>
adoption before the people had time to give it consid<lb break="no"/>eration. This ad captandum appeal was known to tell <lb/>
more with the uninformed masses than any argument <lb/>
on the merits of the proposition itself, and it certainly <lb/>
did answer the purpose of getting up a roar, which is <lb/>
never without some effect somewhere, particularly on <lb/>
the eve of a General Election. Had there been a little <lb/>
more reflecting capacity in those to whom this misre<lb break="no"/>presentation was addressed, the absurdity of the story <lb/>
would soon have revealed itself; for the idea of preci<lb break="no"/>pitancy or force in amatter involving such grave issue: <lb/>
could only exist where those responsible in the ease <lb/>
were fit subjects for Bedlam. We know of course that <lb/>
this misstatement has already been exposed, and how <lb/>
consistent with themselves and with common sense were <lb/>
the explanations of the friends of Union when theºright <lb/>
time arrived. The occasion was not one for individual <lb/>
or party triumph, nor could it ſail to be seen that they <lb/>
were the worst enemies of the project who would urge <lb/></p> 

<p>A vast amount of prejudice and misconception was <lb/>
abroad which might well be left to time and inquiry <lb/></p> 

<p>tions of the Assembly recognised these views, and the <lb/>
wisdom of that course is generally admitted, for it pro<lb break="no"/>perly devolved on the people the responsibility of de<lb break="no"/>ciding the matter at the election, when time will have <lb/>
been afforded for its fullest investigation. <lb/>
We refer to these proceedings just now in order to <lb/>
connect them with another sensation-movement of the <lb/>
same kind which has just been usherel it. The disco<lb break="no"/>very has been made that the recent arrangements of <lb/>
the Government have a view to the ſurtherance of <lb/>
Confederation. We have ever had a sincere wish to <lb/>
keep this great question in its true place—above he <lb/>
level of party politics; and we regret the new attempt <lb/></p> 

<p>-\-\- *::::::::::: == <lb/></p> 

<p>but to the people of the country, and they alone had <lb/></p> 

<p>MR4. S. A. ALLEN s World­ <lb/></p> 

<p>hasty action while the public mind was unprepared. | <lb/></p> 

<p>to dissipate. The course marked out in the Resolu- i. <lb/></p> 

<p>w.º. ººz -\-\-\-\-\- ******** **::::… <lb/></p> 

<p>'º. <lb/>
w <lb/>
s # *, *: . <lb/>
other and wholly independent groundsthough the ef <lb/>
was not wanting to supersede just claims in far Ott <lb/>
those who had opposed Confederation, and for thi <lb/>
reason vione. If men with pretensions Other º <lb/>
paramount had been excluded because of their homil <lb/>
to the proposed Union, the Government would i. <lb/>
be fairly open to criticism on this head. . But . <lb/>
the arrangement is just that which would sunº <lb/>
have been made "had Confederation never been º <lb/>
of, the pretence that this question influenced the ºl. <lb/>
struction of the Governmeet inevitably fºll, º <lb/>
ground. <lb/>The Resolution of the Assembly was passed in good § <lb/>
faith, and by it the decision of the prºject of Unioni, <lb/>left to the free choice of the country. We do not * <lb/>
how the Government could, if they would, influens <lb/>
that decision in any way. They have from the finſ' <lb/>
held it an open question,-the most prominent mis <lb/>
bers of the Government having expressed strong Opiº, <lb/>
ions on both sides without any disturbance of is <lb/>
official relations. So it will be still, as adverse win <lb/>
are yet entertained by members of the Execulin, <lb/>
which doubtless they are severally at liberty to º <lb/> </p> 

<p>force. We have no doubt of the ultimate adoptions <lb/>
Confederation by the Provinces, but we deprecateps <lb/>
questing the Government to cause inquiry through <lb/>
the Magistrates into the origin of all fires. This wº <lb/>
concerned, these inquiries will be rigilly carriel intº <lb/>
effect. . <lb/></p> 

<p>Out: <lb/></p> 

<p>cipitancy, for unquestionably while the public mindi, <lb/>
imperfectly instructed, delay for the purpose oſſuthu <lb/>
in formation is the wise course. The successful operatin <lb/>
of a measure like this dependa inuch on the feeling a <lb/>
the people being ripe for its reception, and those whº <lb/>
would exhibit anxiety to urge it before the propertim <lb/>
must be wanting in that judgment which should <lb/>
belong to men to whom itnportant trusts are ºn <lb/>
fided for the public benefit. <lb/>
-º-º-º-º-º-º-º­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Amongst the Addresses passed in the late session ºl <lb/>
the Legislature was one; moved by Mr. GLEN, it <lb/>
regard as a very just and useful measure, Hitherſ, <lb/>
in most cases of fires the causes have been either altº. § <lb/>
gether unknown or involved in mystery. This ignº<lb break="no"/>rance or uncertainty has had very injuridih <lb/>
results—it has spread abroad a painlul feel. <lb/>
ing of insecurity, and has doubtless in many <lb/>
instances led to great injustice to insurers. Besidei <lb/>
alſ this, the wrong-doer has had impunity and encou<lb break="no"/>ragement, and unjust suspicion has often tainted the <lb/>
character of innocent men. Magisterial investigation <lb/>
seems to us a good means of protection against thºut <lb/>
avils, and we trust that for the sake of all the intºft's <lb/></p> 
-->



        <!-- IC, 2018-12-11, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>i <lb/>
| <lb/>
| <lb/></p> 

<p>Died, at Parkwood, Ascot, Catala, on the 27th <lb/>
March, Mary Livingston, aged 78 years, widºw oth <lb/>
late Lieut.-èol. William Morris, late of Her Majesty'' <lb/>
Army. The deceased was sister of the late Mrs. Pt <lb/>
W. Carter, both daughters of the late, John Living lºt <lb/>
Esq., of this city. <lb/>
At Ferryland on the 12, h inst., <lb/>
"trix-tiger—Mr. Richard-Sullivan, <lb/>
Irelard. - . . . <lb/>
on Thurs lay last, the 26th instant, after s long <lb/>
and painful illness, Elizabeth Jane Cochrane, aged? <lb/>
years, second daughter of Mr. G. Clarke, Royal Ea. <lb/>
gineer Lodge, beloved by all who knew hºr:. . . ." <lb/>
On Monday last, at the St. John's II spital. Mrs <lb/>
Elizabeth Holden, the much-esteemed matron of that <lb/>
institution, aged 52 years. <lb/>
on Monday, the 34th inst, Mr. Thomas O'Donnel <lb/>
a native of Cahir, County Tipperary, Ireland, aged 35 <lb/>
years, sincerely and deservedly regreted by a large <lb/>
number of sorrowing friends, and relatives, Hii <lb/>
funeral will take place from his late residence in Waitt <lb/>
Street, on this day, Thursday, at 2 o'clock, p.m. May <lb/></p> 

<p>in the 84th year ol <lb/>
n" <lb/></p> 

<p>he rest in peace. <lb/></p> 

<p>SHIPPING INTELLIGENCE. <lb/></p> 

<p>ENTEREO. <lb/>
April 24–Lady Mulgrave, Murmaud, Port Mulgravº <lb/>
T N Mollºy <lb/>
Lady Havelock, McDonald, Antigonish, J &amp; W Pitts <lb/>
Lord Clyde, Matheson, Baddeck, Clift, Wool &amp; Co. <lb/></p> 

<p>25-portia, Down, Liverpool, Bowring Brothers <lb/>
* CLEA-Riº D. <lb/>
April 22—Silver Light, Boucher, Quebec, Harveſ, <lb/>
- Tucker &amp; Co <lb/>
othello, McLeod, Barbadoes, Baine, Johnston &amp; Co <lb/>
24–Amelia, Richard, Glace Bay, Clift, Wond &amp; Co. <lb/>
25—Lucy Ann, Boudrot, Arichat, W Grieve &amp; Co <lb/>
Rosetta, Marmaud, Sydney, K McLea &amp; Sous <lb/>
—f <lb/></p> 

<p>: ... Sale by Auction. <lb/></p> 

<p>TO-MORROW, <lb/>
(FRIDAY,) at 11 o'clock, <lb/>
At the South-side Premises of <lb/></p> 

<p>Robert Alsop &amp; Co., <lb/>
The residue of <lb/></p> 

<p>Stock and Utensils, <lb/></p> 

<p>As per particulars in Handbills. <lb/></p> 

<p>li. K. Dickinson, <lb/>
Auctioneers' <lb/></p> 

<p>April 27, <lb/></p> 

<p>(Yn. Sale. <lb/>
ON THE WHARF of <lb/></p> 

<p>Thomas N. Holloy &amp; Co., <lb/></p> 

<p>: A Cargo Prime <lb/></p> 

<p>C O .4 I, <lb/></p> 

<p>Just received Ex "Lady Mulgrave" from Port Rich<lb break="no"/>mond, will be sold cheap if applied for immediataly. <lb/>
April 27. w. <lb/></p> 

<p>arº <lb/></p> 

<p>... i. <lb/></p> 

<p>Population. $ c. <lb/></p> 

<p>Qana's. - 2,500,000 280 $7,000.000 <lb/>
Nova Scotia 330,000 4.10 1320 000 <lb/>
New Brunswick, 252,000 4 UU 1,008, it O <lb/>
P.E. Island, 81.00 40) 3.24 00 g <lb/>
Newfoundland, 130,000 500 650,000 <lb/>
10,292,000 <lb/></p> 

<p>Estimated proceeds of Public <lb/>Works, &amp;c.;.:;...&amp; 100),000 <lb/></p> 

<p>$11,292,0.9 ° <lb/></p> 

<p>i wº tie Upp-r Ua ada would have more memº-rs than <lb/></p> 

<p>of opinion am yog the aiwon,es of his m asure. Qce <lb/>
hon member was entirely in favour of this uniog i but <lb/>
he objected to our givini, u, oºr Mines, Minerals and <lb/>
Crown lands. Ano.her w is ºf opia on that Coufed<lb break="no"/>eratioſ. would be most ben-ficial if we tad stean coal<lb break="no"/>mun...ation with Britain and Canadi, and the hon and <lb/>
1-aned Dºcter took except on to the basis of re<lb break="no"/>re-evation. and shºwed by figures that in 36 years <lb/>
i.ence we w , i.1 iose two of our eight members<lb/> </p> 

<p>all the Cºnfederation besides. If these hon members <lb/>
were s.re re, ther should have opposed C3afedera­ <lb/></p> 

<p>has never eatered. <lb/></p> 

<p>to make it subservient to such uses. <lb/>
the Courier in the hope that "no friend of Confede<lb break="no"/>ration in the Government or out of it will shrink from <lb/>
the expression of his opinion" when called on to avow <lb/>
it, but we cannot consent that Confederation shad be <lb/>
used to raise prºjudices or false alarms,or be made to <lb/>
a peara reason where it did not operate and has no just <lb/>
application. Into the consideration of the arrangements <lb/>
for the coalition Goverdment the idea of Confederation <lb/>
The selections were determined on <lb/></p> 

<p>We agree with <lb/></p> 

<p>THOMAS N. MOLLOY &amp; Co. <lb/>
April 27. <lb/> </p> 

<p>50 Barrels No. 1 Rockland LIME <lb/></p> 

<p>20 M. B.H.I.U.K. <lb/></p> 

<p>10 Tons Free STONE <lb/> </p> 

<p>Tuomº N. MOLLOY &amp; Co. <lb/>
in a <lb/></p> 

<p>Apr 127. <lb/></p> 

<p>30 M. Hemlock BUARD <lb/></p> 

<p>4J M. S.ruce i)itto <lb/>
2.0 M. Sawn SHINGLES <lb/>
3 O M. Ditto I.A. THS <lb/></p> 

<p>50 Tons SLANTLING * <lb/></p> 

<p>==T BY . . <lb/>
glliam Hountse <lb/>
JWilli er "Pride of the Isl <lb/></p> 

<p>ived <lb/>
just rece. largé stock of <lb/></p> 

<p>º, usual <lb/>
their us ridport <lb/></p> 

<p>APLIN SEINES of al <lb/>
§§ §§§ and º <lb/>
º &amp; S of various <lb/>
ANCE BUN *ś. NETS, SH <lb/></p> 

<p>NG <lb/>
iN <lb/>
COD º; and 1 <lb/></p> 

<p>ST: * tº d SQUi <lb/>
§jöRE, SEP ºn <lb/>
# of all dºrp.: <lb/>
as DORSET ALEinºdº, 9 <lb/>
Per "Three sº fro <lb/>
WHITE ºf AD, Black, Green <lb/>
PAINT$…y. i,M TA <lb/>
Bj Barrels STOCKHOLM <lb/>
30 Half-barrels G. o <lb/></p> 

<p>is COAL TAR <lb/>
; . ...a half barrels STOC <lb/>
I <lb/></p> 

<p>PITCH. <lb/></p> 

<p>Pri <lb/></p> 

<p>By Ewen <lb/>
- E.: Three Sisters" from <lb/>
"20 Barrels, 3 dozen Bridge's Po <lb/></p> 

<p>ire Brick <lb/>
1% É. Portlard Cement <lb/></p> 

<p>Pitch, Tar, Oakum, Bricks <lb/>
40 Tons Coal (now landing) <lb/></p> 

<p>And on the Premises lately occup <lb/></p> 

<p>South-side, \ <lb/></p> 

<p>1 west India Fish Screw <lb/></p> 

<p>1 Wharf Crane! <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>J <lb/></p> 

<p>1 Seal Wat <lb/></p> 

<p>3 New Boilers <lb/></p> 

<p>April 24. 2in. <lb/>
Notices. <lb/></p> 

<p>North British and <lb/>
Insurance C <lb/></p> 

<p>FIRE AND <lb/>
BONUS YEA <lb/></p> 



<p>TH attention of the public is <lb/></p> 

<p>the advantages at-ending I. <lb/>
the present year. under which pur. <lb/>
entitled to participate in the sept <lb/>
will be declared at the end of 18% <lb/></p> 

<p>the high standing of this office <lb/>
tiples on which its bonuses," <lb/>
opportunity now offered well, wº <lb/>
parties prºpositig to effect Life Ii <lb/></p> 

<p>April 27. <lb/>
* * For Char <lb/>
the a. ſ. sapoºr (B. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Pride of the <lb/></p> 

<p>£oward Balmanno, Master. W <lb/>
Freight if with É. dispatch. <lb/>
Apply to the Captain ºn board <lb/>
WM, 1ſt <lb/>
April 27. *­ <lb/></p> 

<p>FOR LON 1 <lb/>
The Brigantil <lb/></p> 

<p>Three Si <lb/></p> 

<p>has room for 80 to 40 tons on F <lb/>
2ins, <lb/>
T TO LE1 <lb/>
FOR THE SUM <lb/>
THAT DESIP <lb/>
C O T'T' A <lb/>
on the Property of the late D* <lb/>
"Craig M <lb/></p> 

<p>April 24. <lb/></p> 

<p>Apply to <lb/>
April 27. ( <lb/>
sº-º-º-º-º: <lb/></p> 

<p>Two Dwelling <lb/>
well finished, situated in Go <lb/></p> 

<p>Southeott's Buildings. <lb/>
—AlSO,­ <lb/></p> 

<p>A Hot <lb/></p> 

<p>inWaterStreet opposite Mºrs' <lb/>
Possession given immediately. . . <lb/></p> 

<p>Apply '. <lb/>
April 24. - <lb/> </p> 

<p>(And possession given on <lb/>
That commodious BRICK * <lb/>
* - -<lb/>'Toussaint's <lb/>
With KII CHEN, FROST <lb/>
and F Jºe, Płtook WAULT <lb/>
Apply tº <lb/>
#,AURENC <lb/></p> 

<p>April 17. 3 w. <lb/>
(Possession given <lb/></p> 

<p>ºf HE <lb/></p> 

<p>Pucelling <lb/>
No. 2, Waldon Buildings, Q1 <lb/>
occupied by W. W. Waitawā' <lb/></p> 

<p>April 10. - - - -<lb/>'I HAT VE,&amp;Y Lyk <lb/>
I) welling <lb/>
The property of Aºtº. Nºw <lb/>
the North siue of Water Stree <lb/>
their Waterside ptemises. T <lb/>
attached, and the Outhouses at <lb/>
evnvenient. <lb/></p> 

<p>Possess.on given ist May n <lb/>
Appº. <lb/>
March 23. t <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_1.jpg"/> 
        
        <fw type="num">1</fw>
        
        <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
        
        <fw type="running">St. John's, Monday, May 1, 1865.</fw>


        <!-- IC, 2018-12-11, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>T­ <lb/></p> 

<p>otice. <lb/></p> 

<p>— <lb/>
TMothers T. Māºri <lb/></p> 

<p>procure Mrs. WINSLow" ... * * <lb/>
...iº.". ...; <lb/>
the prescription of one of tº ". <lb/>
and nurses in the United State est: <lb/>
for thirty years with never fa º it <lb/>
ºss, by millions of mother, sº §: <lb/>
|eeble infant of one week old . -<lb/>bly relieves the child frº.º. <lb/>
ſtomach and bowels, oorrect; .# <lb/></p> 

<p>ind energy to the whole System ity, <lb/></p> 

<p>ntly relieve Griping in the Bower, It <lb/></p> 

<p>e believe it the best and sures: re, and <lb/>
all cases of Dissentery and Diarh ned <lb/></p> 

<p>*r it arises from teething or any º -<lb/>rections for use will *çeompanve er <lb/>
tenuine unless the fac-simil: of C º <lb/>
the outside wrapper. Price ...'. <lb/>
* Sold by all Medicine Dealers. §. <lb/>
New York, and 205 High H. <lb/></p> 

<p>hd. <lb/>
RS. WINSLOW, <lb/></p> 

<p>Nurse and Female Physician <lb/>
of mothers, her sº. §.". <lb/>
ig, which greatly facilitates th: ... <lb/>
softening the gums, reducing all infi s <lb/>
|lay all pain and spasmodic actiºn a º <lb/>
ate the bowels. Depend upon it." . <lb/>
iye rest tº yourselves, and reliº. <lb/>
inſants. We have put up and jã this <lb/>
| thirty years, and can say, in conſ. <lb/>
what we have never boea able to . <lb/>
edicine—never has it failed in sº <lb/>
et a cure, when timely used. Never <lb/>
R instance of dissatisfaction by any ong <lb/>
un the contrary; all speak delighted <lb/>
ions, and speaks in tenuis of commenda. <lb/>
#ical effects and medical virtue. We <lb/>
batter "what we do now," after thirty <lb/>
nce. and pledge our reputation for the <lb/>
that we here declare. In almost every <lb/>
# the infant is suffering from pair and <lb/>
slief will be found in fifteen or twenty <lb/>
the syrup is administered. Full dire: <lb/>
# will accompany, each bottle. None <lb/>
iss the fac-simile of Curtis and Perkin, <lb/>
on the outside wrapper. Sold by prºg: <lb/>
put the world ... Principal Office, 48 Dey <lb/>
and 205 High Ho-born, England. Price <lb/>
per bottle. -<lb/>ng is an extract from a letter written by <lb/>
Holme, Pastor of the Pierrepont-stres: <lb/>
*h, Brooklyn, N Y, to the "Journal and <lb/>
Cincinnati, O., and speaks volumes in <lb/>
world-renowned medicine, Mrs. WINs. <lb/>
ng Syrup for Children Teething—"We <lb/>
isement in your cºlumns of Mrs. Wins<lb break="no"/>g Syrup. Now we never said a word in <lb/>
atent medicine before in our life, but we <lb/>
1 to say to your readers that this is no <lb/>
have tried it, and know it to be all i <lb/>
* probably one of the most successful <lb/>
the day, because it in one of the best <lb/>
your readers who have bahies can't do <lb/>
y in a supply." <lb/>
J. DEARIN, St. John's, <lb/>
Agent for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>PHOENIX FIRE <lb/></p> 

<p>º * 5. r <lb/>
raitce Cºpany. <lb/>
i Street and Charing Cross, London. <lb/>
ESTABLISHED–1782 <lb/>
TRU8TH 88 ANI, DIRECTOR8. <lb/>
ton, Esq. Kirkman D. Hodgº on Esq. <lb/>
ºpe, " .Jaines Horne, -6 <lb/></p> 

<p>rt, " William J. Lancaster, " <lb/>
" John D. Magen, <lb/> </p> 

<p>ser, " John Mºgterman, Esq. M. P. <lb/>
ler, " John Timohy Oxley sq; <lb/>
odhant" |George Stanley keptor. " <lb/>
ion, " Benjamin Shaw, <lb/> </p> 

<p>* Matthew Whiting, 44 <lb/>
Fran is Wilson, <lb/></p> 

<p>8R crººrº RIEs <lb/></p> 

<p>WiLLIAM HARRIs Esq. * <lb/>
George William Lowell, Esq. <lb/>
NIX FIRE UFFICE is confidently re<lb break="no"/>o the notice of the public—for the liberu <lb/>
|vtitude with which all claims upon it are <lb/>
paid- as well as for the almost unlimited <lb/>
tº it affords, comprising in addition to the <lb/>
Capital of the Cempany, the whole for <lb/>
us Proprieta y, composed oſsom <lb/>
pulent gentlemen and Merchants in the <lb/></p> 

<p>orm. <lb/></p> 

<p>NIX OPFICF has carried on an exten <lb/>
'ssful business for upwards of seventy<lb break="no"/>| The duty paid by it to Government for <lb/></p> 

<p>n Great Hºri ain and Ireland exceed <lb/>
rling per annum. <lb/>
| short time Insurances are undertaken <lb/>
NIX COMPANY on almost every de<lb break="no"/>sk, in Newfoundland at a moderate rate <lb/>
hich may be know on application to <lb/>
their office, in St. John's, where policies <lb/>
of charge. <lb/></p> 

<p>W. &amp; G. RENDEI.L, <lb/>
Agents for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE COLONIAL <lb/></p> 

<p>4 - -<lb/>SSIrance Ú0hpāilf <lb/>
Estarlished 1846. <lb/>
L, ONE MILLION STERLING. <lb/>e of Assuring before 25th <lb/></p> 

<p>May 1863. <lb/> </p> 

<p>D IDIVISIt)N OF PROFITS. <lb/>
he advantage of this year's entry to the <lb/>
. Proposals must be lodged at the Offie" <lb/>
tewfoundland, or with one of the Agent" <lb/>
5th May next. <lb/>
RS BöNUs will be allocated at the <lb/>
ofts in 1864 to Policies opened before <lb/></p> 

<p>* Books for the Present Year. <lb/>
ER BY special act of PARLIAMENT. <lb/></p> 

<p>Governor. -<lb/>HON.THE EARL OF ELGIN &amp; <lb/>
NE. Governor-General, of INDIA. <lb/>
E-\-5 GEORGE STREET, EDINBURGH <lb/>
irectors in St. John's, Newfoundland. <lb/>
Brien, Esq. Walter Grieve, Esq., <lb/>
Merchant. <lb/>
William Henry Mare, Esq. <lb/>
ldviser—Henry Hunt Stabb, M. D. <lb/>
ent–Frederick J. Wyatt. -<lb/>'ON OF THE COMPANY. <lb/>
e of the Company............ £130,000 <lb/>
have divided Profits on two occasions­ <lb/></p> 

<p>1000,opened in 1847,has been increased <lb/></p> 

<p>the application of the Bonus; otbed <lb/>
Iroportion. -<lb/>avery five years; next division in 186". <lb/>
sceived in any part of the world whº <lb/>
e been established <lb/></p> 

<p>3lenſuumillander, <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, Monday, May 1, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>- Pubºished every Monday and Thursday <lb/></p> 

<p>*::::::::::::::::ºsiº <lb/>
2..."; fluck WoRTH STREET-Terms one <lb/>
Guinea per annº payable in advance. -<lb/>jºrtisements not limited (Auction-sales end notices <lb/></p> 

<p>A. #ich determine themselves excepted) are repeated <lb/>
j ordered in writing to be withdrawn, and are <lb/>
charged for accordingly. <lb/></p> 

<p>This paper is filed,and may be seen free of charge at <lb/>
ºilovay's Pill and Ointment Establishment, 24% <lb/></p> 

<p>grand, London. <lb/>
== <lb/>
SPECIAL IN TIMATION. <lb/>
The BENEFITS of Life Assºanee with the <lb/>
SMALLE87' 0UT LAY, <lb/>
ombined with the FULLEST SECURITY, <lb/></p> 

<p>is desirable object has been attained by the Policy <lb/>
This desira º holders of the <lb/></p> 

<p>Life.Association of Scotland <lb/></p> 

<p>By means of its Alocation of Profit in Cash towards <lb/>
º, Annual Reduction of the Premiums payable for the <lb/>
Policies, the older Policy-holders paying at present <lb/>
only 12s. 6d. (instead of 20s ) per £1 of the Premiums; <lb/>
and by the fºllowing <lb/>
REGULATION FOR FURTHER PIMINISHING <lb/>
OUILAY FOR LIFE ASSURANCE. <lb/></p> 

<p>Urtil the time when the premiums may be expected <lb/>
to be reduced by the application of prºfits, the Assured <lb/>
for £500 or upwards, may leave unpaid a cons derabie <lb/></p> 

<p>ortion (one-third or one-fourth) of the premiums re<lb break="no"/>sensary to keep the policy in force. . The unpaid part <lb/>
is allowed to remain in the hands of the Assured as <lb/>
long as he pleases, and he is not asked to pay interest <lb/>
thereon; but the amount, with accumulated interest, <lb/>
will be deducted from the sum assured at death, New <lb/>
Entrants thus at once commence with <lb/>
PAYMEN IS MUCH BELOW THE TABULAR <lb/></p> 

<p>RATES, <lb/>
and continue to make such reduced payments for six <lb/>
years, when they become entitled to reduction of the <lb/>
premiums by the applica:ion of Profits. They will, <lb/>
nevertheless, receive the same benefits and the same <lb/>
Share of profit, as if the full premiums had been paid. <lb/>
Present outlay is also further diminished by means of <lb/>
the Associations <lb/>
INCREASING POLICIES <lb/></p> 

<p>in which the sums Assured shall increase by the mere <lb/>
lapse of time to dowble the original amount, without <lb/>
corresponding increase of premium; and, under the <lb/>
Participating Class, the premi will be reducible by <lb/>
appliea'ion of Profits. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Policies do Not Contain several of the Res<lb break="no"/>raictions commonly imposed on Assured Lives, and <lb/>
couler wm the Policy-holders unusual and important <lb/>
liabilities and privileges. <lb/></p> 

<p>tº-entrants on or before 5TH APRIL <lb/>
will secure a decided advantage over later Entrants <lb/>
at the Division of brofit. <lb/></p> 

<p>NEWFG UN i) LAND BRANCH. <lb/>
HEAL) () FFICE.-ST. JOHN S. <lb/>
prºtectors: <lb/>
H. K. Dickinaon, Esq. Hon. James Cormack. <lb/>
Robert Grieve, Esq. <lb/>
Agent and Secretary.....................E. L. JARWIS. <lb/>
March 7 <lb/>
TH: Company carrying on business as wercurants <lb/>
in Greenwrk, under the firm of KERR &amp; <lb/>
McRRide, and in Newfoundland under the firm of <lb/>
McBride &amp; H ERR, was dissolv-d on the 20th day of <lb/>
February, 1865, of mutual cel.sent of the subscribers, <lb/>
only partners thereof. <lb/>
All debts due by the dissolved Company will he paid <lb/>
by the Company carrying ºn business in Greenock <lb/>
under the firm of R. K. Mct;Ride &amp; Co. and in New<lb break="no"/>ſoutſiland under the firm of Michride &amp; Co.—to whom <lb/>
the Stock of the dissolved concern has been transfer<lb break="no"/>red, and who are tº carry on the business in future for <lb/>
their own behoof; and they are also author.z-d to <lb/>
receive payment of, and tº discharge all debts due to, <lb/>
the dissolved concern. <lb/>
Greenock, 1st March, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>ROBERT KERR. <lb/>
JAMES McIBRIDE. <lb/>
PEl Elt MctiltiDE, <lb/>
Thos KING, Witness. <lb/>
Charles Shannon, Witness. <lb/>
March 23. 1 m. <lb/></p> 

<p>*AN CASHIRE <lb/>
Insurance Company. <lb/></p> 

<p>FIRE AND life. <lb/></p> 

<p>CAPITAL TRWO MILLION'S STERLING. <lb/>
Head Office: Exchange-Street, \lanchester. <lb/>
Board of LIRECTORs: <lb/>
- John Todd, Esq., Chairman. <lb/>
William H. Bradley, Esq. William Pilkington, Esq., <lb/>
John Clegg, Esq. Blackburn. <lb/>
• Darbyshire, Esq., Liv-Joseph Schofield, Esq. <lb/>
erpool. N. Shelmerdine, Esq. <lb/>
Alexander Ewing Esq., James Smith, Esq., Liver­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Glasgow pool. <lb/>
Şamuel Hargreaves, Esq. James Wagstaff, Esq., Lon<lb break="no"/>John Knowles, Esq. don <lb/></p> 

<p>J. Robinson Kay, Esq., Edward Wanklyn, Esq. <lb/>
Bury. Barton Wood, Esq. <lb/>
J. Schofield Mayson, Esq <lb/>
George Stewart, General Manager. <lb/>
E. I. JARWIS. <lb/>
Agent for Newfoundland. <lb/>
<lb/>Royal ARTillery.—Holloway's Ointment and <lb/>
Pills-A sej, ant in the Royal Artillery, writes, on <lb/>
December 12th, 1862, fom Poonamattee, Madras <lb/>
Presidency, that his right lg, from the arxie to the <lb/>
Falſ, was a quagmire of disease and corruption; that <lb/>
he was on the hoptal roll for twelve mºnths, with<lb break="no"/>Rut any improvement in his case; that he, as a forlorn <lb/>
ope, resolved to try Holloway's celebrated Ointment <lb/>
and Pills. These soon gave ease, expe led the end <lb/>
umours from the limb, healed the apparently incura<lb break="no"/>tle sore, and restored him to sound health. <lb/></p> 

<p>-º­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Everything In Season. That grey hairs are hon<lb break="no"/>ºrable in old age is a proverbial matter; but are <lb/>
they so in youth P Mrs. S. A. Allen's World<lb break="no"/>Har Restorer and Zylobalsamum, or Hair Dressing, <lb/>
** suited to both young and old, they restore grey <lb/>
hair to its youthful color, giving the roots the natural <lb/>
tourisment. They renew, preserve and increase the <lb/>
§rowth. Every 1)ruggist sells them. J. J. Dearin, <lb/></p>--> 

    </div>
    <div type="debate">


<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head> 

<p>THURSDAY, March 2.</p>
        
        <p>
<persName ref="pers:EVAN2">Mr. EVANS</persName> did not know that he could say much on <lb/>
this important question which had not been said by hon <lb/>
members who had already addressed the House on the <lb/>
subject. Still he considered it his duty to state his <lb/>
opinions upon a question of such deep importance, in<lb break="no"/>volving as it did the present and future destinies of the <lb/>
country. He fully concurred in the course proposed in <lb/>
the resolution before the chair. The question ought to <lb/>
be fully considered by the constituencies previous to any <lb/>
decision being come to upon it in that House; and he <lb/>
cordially concurred in the views of the hon leader of the <lb/>
Government in that respect. The interests of this Is<lb break="no"/>land, in all time coming, were involved in the decision <lb/>
that would be come to, and therefore too much consi<lb break="no"/>deration could be given to the question. After the most <lb/>
careful consideration of all that had been advanted on <lb/>
both sides in that debate, he must say that the opinions <lb/>
he had previously formed were strengthened—that the <lb/>
weight of evidence and arguments was in favour of Con<lb break="no"/>federation. So far from believing that Confederation <lb/>
would weaken the ties which bind us to the parent state, <lb/>
he considered that these ties would thereby be strength<lb break="no"/>ened. He (Mr. Evans) would be no party to any pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings which he believed calculated to separate this <lb/>
Colony from Great Britain; but he believed that in <lb/>
supporting Confeueration he was prolonging, if not per<lb break="no"/>petrating the connection. The Confederacy would at <lb/>
once become a powerful state, while its progress in popu<lb break="no"/>lation and the development of material resources, judg<lb break="no"/>ing by the past, must be such as, in half a century <lb/>
hence, would place us in the very first position on this <lb/>
side of the Atlantic. At the same time, with the gener<lb break="no"/>ous assistance of the mother country, and the <lb/>
protection which her navy would afford to our fisheries <lb/>
and commerce, we would have no cause for anxiety as to <lb/>
the aggression of any foreign power, either in Europe <lb/>
or America. As to the ability of the Confederation to <lb/>
repel invasion, should it be attempted, he need only <lb/>
refer to the history of the revolutionary war of the <lb/>
United States. The thirteen United Colonies, with a <lb/>
population under the present population of British <lb/>
North America, and with fewer material resources, suc<lb break="no"/>cessfully resisted all the efforts of the mother country <lb/>
to retain them under her dominion; and if they could <lb/>
do that, notwithstanding that at the commencement of <lb/>
the struggle England held military possession of the <lb/>
country, would we not be sufficiently powerful to repel <lb/>
foreign aggression, when we had the military and naval <lb/>
protection of Great Britain combined with our own <lb/>
efforts? But what could the isolated Provinces of <lb/>
British North America do for their own defence, were <lb/>
they to be now attacked by an enemy? Would it be <lb/>
possible for them to combine for the purpose? It was <lb/>
well known that such combination, without union, would <lb/>
be impracticable. What could our population of 130,<lb break="no"/>000, scattered along such an extent of coast, do for <lb/>
their own protection? We have neither the influence <lb/>
nor the power to command that respect which we would <lb/>
enjoy as a component portion of a Confederacy num<lb break="no"/>bering four millions, and which a few years would raise <lb/>
to four times that number, with a territory stretching <lb/>
from the Atlantic to the Pacific. And as to the means <lb/>
of defraying our civil expenditure, and promoting educa<lb break="no"/>tion and the extension of roads, our means under Con<lb break="no"/>federation would be fully as ample as now; while, if <lb/>
we gave up a certain portion of our independent legisla<lb break="no"/>tion, we would be admitted to legislate to the same ex<lb break="no"/>tent, for the Confederacy, through our representatives <lb/>
in the Federal House of Commons. We did not so <lb/>
much part with our power of legislation as we combined <lb/>
with the other British Colonies to legislate in common <lb/>
for objects of common interest. He certainly felt some<lb break="no"/>what alarmed at the learned Doctor's long array of <lb/>
figures; and if he thought there was any danger of a <lb/>
reduction in the number of members allotted to us, he <lb/>
would say, that it would be well to guard by an <lb/>
express stipulation against such a contingency. But <lb/>
he did not think we should ohject to the number <lb/>
of members assigned to us. We were fairly con<lb break="no"/>sidered, on the basis of population, and considering <lb/>
the ability and success with which our Delegates sus<lb break="no"/>tained our interests at the Conference at Quebec, he felt <lb/>
no anxiety as to our interest being properly attended to <lb/>
in the Federal Parliament, provided the constituencies <lb/>
exercise proper judgment in the selection of representa<lb break="no"/>tives; and any increase in their number would certainly <lb/>
not facilitate the selection of suitable representatives. <lb/>
Besides, as had been remarked by the hon and learned <lb/>
member for Fogo, Mr. Whiteway, the other provinces <lb/>
are interested in the fisheries, in common with ourselves, <lb/>
and Canada especially had for some time past bestowed <lb/>
great attention upon her fisheries, although of minor <lb/>
importance compared with ours. He did not apprehead <lb/>
that it would be disadvantageous to us to surrender our <lb/>
ungranted Crown Lands witnout mines and minerals to <lb/>
the General Government. He was of opinion that the <lb/>
apprehensions of hon members on that subject were <lb/>
groundless. The General Government would have no <lb/>
interest except to render our Crown lands available for the <lb/>
public benefit; and they would be as open to us for settle<lb break="no"/>ment as they are now. If our mineral resources are as <lb/>
valuable as they are represented, it was only <lb/>
necessary that they should be known to secure abundance of <lb/>
capital to work them; and it would not be denied that a <lb/>
thorough geological survey of the Island would be more <lb/>
effectively carried out by the General Government than <lb/>
by our own unaided efforts. With respect to the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of the tariff, he did see some difficulty, but he con<lb break="no"/>sidered it by no means insurmountable; and considering <lb/>
the liberal manner in which the representation of our <lb/>
Delegates were met at the Conference, he was satisfied <lb/>
every consideration would be extended to us. If the <lb/>
existing Canadian tariff were applied to our imports, we <lb/>
might at first be more highly taxed than now. But the <lb/>
hon member, for Placentia and St. Mary's Mr. Shea, <lb/>
had shown that we would soon have an importation of <lb/>
Canadian goods, which of course would come in duty <lb/>
free; and from what the hon member for Carbonear, Mr. <lb/>
Rorke stated as to the quality and prices of the samples of <lb/>
Canadian leather, boots, shoes, and other articles he had <lb/>
from Quebec, last fall, there was no reason to doubt that <lb/>
we would find it for our advantage to import Canada <lb/>
manufactured leather to a considerable extent; and he <lb/>
agreed with hon members who anticipated that we would <lb/>
also import Canadian woollens, to some extent. He was <lb/>
also satisfied that the union would lead to the establis<lb break="no"/>ment of local manufactures. But these changes would be <lb/>
only of gradual introduction; and in the mean<lb break="no"/>time, it ought to be arranged that we should <lb/>
not be required to contribute more to the general reve<lb break="no"/>nue, accoiding to population, than the other colonies. <lb/>
The hon member for Ferryland, Mr. Glen, objected that <lb/>
there were no stipulations in the Resolutions against an <lb/>
export duty upon fish and oil. He (Mr. Evans) did not <lb/>
think any such stipulations necessary, for he was perfect<lb break="no"/>ly satisfied that the General Government would not at<lb break="no"/>tempt it. There was no export duty on fish and oil from <lb/>

<cb/>

any of the British North American Colonies now; but <lb/>
there was an export duty on timber from New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, in lieu of stumpage, and upon Coal and other min<lb break="no"/>erals in Nova Scotia, in lieu of Royalty; and the stipu<lb break="no"/>lation in the Resolutions, that there should be no export <lb/>
duty on these, was simply because, as a portion of the <lb/>
Crown lands revenue, they belonged to Nova Scotia and <lb/>
New Brunswick respectively, and they found it most <lb/>
convenient in these provinces to collect the revenue upon <lb/>
them by an export duty. But he (Mr. Evans) did not <lb/>
believe the General Government would attempt to im<lb break="no"/>pose any export duties, which was contrary to the en<lb break="no"/>lightened spirit of modern commercial legislation. The <lb/>
hon member also complained of the Canadian tariff as <lb/>
protective while our interests lay in the direction of Free <lb/>
Trade; and also that Freneh saught fish was admitted <lb/>
into Canada, duty free, and would also come in here un<lb break="no"/>der the Canadian tarif. But the Canadian tariff would <lb/>
not be adopted by the Federal Legislature without modi<lb break="no"/>fication, even if the existing import duties under it should <lb/>
be retained. The Federal tariff would, of course, be <lb/>
adapted to the local requirements of the several Colonies. <lb/>
He did not look upon the proposed Confederation as <lb/>
the submission of this Colony to a hostile country which <lb/>
would pay little regard to our interests, but an alliance <lb/>
with sister Colonies, for the promotion of our mutual <lb/>
interests, which could only be done by the general Le<lb break="no"/>gislature carefully considering the wants and wishes of <lb/>
the several Confederated Colonies.—Of course steam <lb/>
communication with the United Kingdom and with Cana<lb break="no"/>da, was indispensible to the beneficial operation of the <lb/>
union. The steamers for Canada should call at some of <lb/>
the ports of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick on the <lb/>
Gulf of St. Lawrence. This would open up a valuable <lb/>
trade with these Colonies; and in return for our imports <lb/>
from them, they would be good customers for our her<lb break="no"/>rings and other fishery products. He hoped the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would erect an additional number of Lighthouses <lb/>
on our south western Coast, along what was the highway <lb/>
to the Gulf of the river St. Lawrence. Confederation <lb/>
would give us a uniform currency, as well as a uniform <lb/>
tariff, and it could not be denied that both would prove <lb/>
advantageous in our business relations with the other <lb/>
colonies. It has been urged that our commercial inter<lb break="no"/>course with the other Colonies is limited. But the com<lb break="no"/>merce of British North America, though extensive now, <lb/>
can only be said to be in its infancy; and as population <lb/>
increased, the demands for the products of our fisheries <lb/>
in the other colonies would increase still more rapidly, for <lb/>
Agriculture and other pursuits would, no doubt occupy <lb/>
the attention of their people to a large extent; and we <lb/>
might anticipate supplying them to a much greater ex<lb break="no"/>tent than now with the produce of our fisheries. It <lb/>
had been objected that there is no uniformity of interests <lb/>
between Canada and this Colony, that we are a fishing <lb/>
community, while Canada is an agricultural, lumbering <lb/>
and manufacturing country. But for that very reason <lb/>
he considered that we would be of the greater advantage <lb/>
to each other. We would be good customers for the <lb/>
flour, pork and butter of Canada, and also, he believed <lb/>
for Canadian manufactures, while Canada would afford <lb/>
us an extensive market for our herrings and some other <lb/>
articles of which we had an unlimited supply of very <lb/>
superior quality; and he had not the least doubt that as <lb/>
population increased in Canada and the North Western <lb/>
territory, the demand for the products of our fisheries for <lb/>
these markets would exceed any thing at present antici<lb break="no"/>pated. With the modifications in the resolutions to <lb/>
which he had referred, he was of opinion that the pro<lb break="no"/>poposed union would operate beneficially for Newfound<lb break="no"/>land. The present condition of a large portion of <lb/>
our operative population was most distressing; and <lb/>
it was our bounden duty to devise some means for <lb/>
their relief. Hitherto they had derived but little benefit <lb/>
from the immense treasures drawn from our waters. In <lb/>
years of prosperous fisheries they were comfortable; but <lb/>
when the catch was short, partly, no doubt, from impro<lb break="no"/>vidence, but chiefly from the precarious nature of their <lb/>
occupaion, large numbers were reduced to destitution. <lb/>
It was admitted on all hands that other occupations <lb/>
besides the fisheries, must be provided for a considera<lb break="no"/>ble number of our people, or that they must emigrate; <lb/>
and as this proposal of union appeared to open up to us <lb/>
a prospect beneficial to our operative population, as calcu<lb break="no"/>lated to provide them with increased employment, he <lb/>
thought we would be recreant to our duty to the country <lb/>
if we did not take it into serious cousideration. The <lb/>
hon. member for Bonavesta, Mr. Wyatt, said our interests <lb/>
would be attended to on the other side of the water, <lb/>
better than by any delegation from this Colony; but he <lb/>
(Mr. Evans) did mean to disparage the efforts of gentle<lb break="no"/>men in England interested in this Colony, when he said <lb/>
he would be sorry to see the protection of our constitu<lb break="no"/>tional rights entrusted to any person not responsiole to <lb/>
the people of the country, and he did think that in a <lb/>
matter of such vital importance it was essential to the <lb/>
protection of our interests that we should be represented <lb/>
at the final passing of the Imperial Act, by Delegates <lb/>
thoroughly informed as to our interests, and the wants <lb/>
and wishes of the constituencies of the colony. It would <lb/>
appear, however, that a final conclusion will not be come <lb/>
to on the subject by some of the other colonies, and <lb/>
therefore the members returned to the next House of <lb/>
Assembly would have an opportunity of considering the <lb/>
whole question, with the great advantage of being furnish<lb break="no"/>ed with the views of the constituencies upon it, and be<lb break="no"/>ing fully informed as to the course, taken by the Legisla<lb break="no"/>tures of the other colonies. He (Mr. Evans) would not <lb/>
longer occupy the time of the house. He looked upon <lb/>
Confederation, on fair terms, as calculated to be eminently <lb/>
beneficial to this Colony. With the two or three modi<lb break="no"/>fications of the resolutions, to which he had referred, and <lb/>
which, he believed, could be easily accomplished, he <lb/>
considered it would result beneficially to the country, and <lb/>
would greatly promote the progress of its people, socially <lb/>
commercially and politically. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
On motion of hon <persName ref="pers:CART5">ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>, the committee <lb/>
then rose, and the Chairman reported progress. To sit <lb/>
again to-morrow. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
<persName ref="pers:PARS1">Mr. PARSONS</persName> gave notice that, on Thursday next, he <lb/>
would ask leave to bring in a Bill to provide for the <lb/>
election of a Light-house on Cape St. Francis. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
<persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. PENOUF</persName> gave notice that, on to-morrow, he would <lb/>
ask the Acting Colonial Secretary what action has been <lb/>
taken by the Government to furnish the British North <lb/>
American Association of London, with Parliamentary, <lb/>
statistical and other documentary information relating to <lb/>
this Island, the character of such documents, if any, <lb/>
sent since the reception by the Government of the circu<lb break="no"/>lar and rules of the said Association, dated 1st March, <lb/>
18623. Also, for a statement, showing the localities of <lb/>
the Pillar letter boxes in this town, how often they are <lb/>
empited of their contents, the number of newspapers and <lb/>
letters deposited in these boxes for town and outport <lb/>
delivery, the British North American Provinces, Great <lb/>
Britain and Ireland, and foreign Countries, with, the <lb/>
amount of revenue drawn from the said Pillar boxes, <lb/>
from date of establishmelt to the end of February last. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
The House then adjourned until to-morrow at three <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/></p>

        <!-- IC, 2018-12-11, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

<!--<p>TUESDAY, March 6. <lb/>
The house met at three o'clock. <lb/>
Mr. Evans presented a petition from James Harvey <lb/>
and others. of: Burin, which was received and read, <lb/>
º that he may be compensated for making a road <lb/>
there. <lb/>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/>
The SURVEYor GENERAL presented a petition from <lb/>
David Candow and others, of King's Cove and settlements <lb/>
adjucent, which was received and read, praying for a grant <lb/>
to complete the road between that settlement and <lb/>
Bonavista. <lb/>
Q dered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/>
Mr. GLEN presented a petition from Robert Raymond <lb/>
and other, of the Goulds, which was received and <lb/>
read, praying for a grant to open a road to Shoal Bay. <lb/>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/>
Mr. GLEN also presented a petition from John H. <lb/>
McKie, of Bay Bulls, which was received and read set<lb break="no"/>ting forth that he had filled the office of Stipendiary <lb/>
Magistrate and Preventive Officer of Customs at that <lb/>
place, for the last 53 years, and praying for a retiring <lb/>
allowance sufficient to support him in his old age. <lb/>
Mr. GLEN, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
table, would observe that he believed that the claims of <lb/>
the petitioner to liberal consideration would be recogni<lb break="no"/>zed on both sides of the house. He was now eighty-one <lb/>
years of age, and had served the colony for fifty-three <lb/>
years, and ihere never, was a complaint of the manner <lb/>
n which he discharged his duties. He found it neces<lb break="no"/>sary, on account of his increasing infirmities, to resign <lb/>
his offire some months ago, and the Goverlment granted <lb/>
him tile usual allowance of half salary, on his retires <lb/>
ment, being £75 a year; which was the same as was <lb/>
given to other retiring magistrates who had been only 7 <lb/>
or 8 years in office. The Goverment bowever, consented <lb/>
to the matter being brought before the house, that his <lb/>
claim to an increased allowance, on account of his long <lb/>
services, might he considered by hon members. He <lb/>
(Mr. Glen) intendel to propose in committee on supply, <lb/>
that the retiring allowance be made £100 a year, with <lb/>
which the petitioner would be perfectly satisfied. <lb/>
Mr. E. 1). SHEA.—The manner in which that claim <lb/>
came before the house entitled it to the most favourable <lb/>
consideration by hon members on both sides. The pe. <lb/>
titioner had spent a long life in the public service. He <lb/>
had given great satisfaction, and his character for integri<lb break="no"/>ty stood high; and while the government, adopted the <lb/>
usual course in the matter, they mark, d their apprecius <lb/>
tion by suggesting that his claim should be brought...bo<lb break="no"/>fore the house for special consideration. He (Mr. Shea) <lb/>
was satisfied hon memoers on both sides of the house <lb/>
would readily assent to the very moderate increase <lb/>
which would be proposed, that the retiring allowance to <lb/>
their venerable gentleman be increased from £75 to £100 <lb/>
a year. <lb/>
3. A. Shea fully agreed in all that had been said <lb/>
respecting the services of the petitioner. He had known <lb/>
that gentieman for many years, and he would only ob<lb break="no"/>serve that his conduct ſublicly and privately had secu<lb break="no"/>red him the respect of all to whom he was known. , He <lb/>
had given the country the service of a long life, and he <lb/>
(wir. Shea) had no doubt that house would take the same <lb/>
view of the case as the government had done; that his <lb/>
long services fully entitleſ him to the very moderate in<lb break="no"/>e ense of his retiring allowance suggested by the bon <lb/>
member who presented the petition. In the appointinent <lb/>
ºf the gentleman who succeeded him, the government <lb/>
had selected a worthy man an old and respectable resi<lb break="no"/>dent; and it was highly creditable to them to have selec<lb break="no"/>ted for the office a gentleman so eminently qualified, <lb/>
Ordered that the petition lie on the tab e. <lb/>
Mr. LeaMon presented a petition from Edward <lb/>
O'Keefe and others, of Brigus, which was received and <lb/>
road, praving for a grant to erect a public wharf there. <lb/>
Mr. LEAMon, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
tebie, would observe that it was on a su'ject of great <lb/>
importance to the community. All the wharves at Bri<lb break="no"/>gus were owned by private parties; mostly by planters, <lb/>
who did not care to have them made use of for the public <lb/>
accommodation; and in the fall of the year especially, <lb/>
much inconvenience was experienced when the Concep<lb break="no"/>tion Bay Steamer arrived, in landing and embarking <lb/>
passengers and goods. <lb/>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/>
The SURVEYon GENERAL presented a petition from <lb/>
Samuel Evans and others, of Greenspond, which was <lb/>
received and rea', praying for a grant to build a bridge <lb/>
between that Island and Ship Island; also a petition <lb/>
from John White and others, of Greenspond, which was <lb/>
received and rend, praying that no further grant be mada <lb/>
to * the bridge between that Island and Ship. <lb/>
Island. <lb/>
Mr. WYArt had great pleasure in supporting tha <lb/>
prayer of the latter of these petitions. The former he <lb/>
would oppose, as the bridge prayed for would ruin, the <lb/>
harbor, if erected. <lb/>
Ordered that these petitions lie on the table. <lb/>
Mr. E. 1). SHEA presented a petition from Michael <lb/>
Hayes and others, of Brigus South, which was received <lb/>
and read, praying for a grant to repair the bridge to the <lb/>
Island there. <lb/>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/>
Dr. WINTER_presented petitions from James Verge <lb/>
and othere, of Trinity, from Michael Murphy and others, <lb/>
of Trinity Harbor, from A. H. Cole and others, of <lb/>
British Harbor, from James Werge and others, of Plate <lb/>
Cove, from A. W. Breunner and others, Trinity South <lb/>
Side, and from Thomas Lawler aud others, uf British <lb/>
arbor, whicn were severally received and read, pray<lb break="no"/>ing for grants to repair ald complete roads in these <lb/>
lucalities. <lb/>
Ordered that these petitions lie on the table. <lb/></p> 

<p>I}r. WIN rea also presented a Fetition from B. Sweet<lb break="no"/>land and others, of King's Cove, which was received and <lb/>
read, praying fºr the appointment of a keeper of the <lb/>
half-way house between Trinity and King's Cºve; also <lb/>
a petition from Alexander Bremner and others, Con<lb break="no"/>missiºners of the public wharf at Catalina, which was <lb/>
received and read, praying for an additional grant for its <lb/>
competion. <lb/></p> 

<p>Ordered tha', these petitions lie on the table. <lb/></p> 

<p>Dr. W INTEB gave notice that, on to-morrow he would <lb/>
move an address to his Excellency the Governor in <lb/>
Council, on the petition from the Commissioners for the <lb/>
erection of a public wharf at Catalina; also that he would <lb/>
ask the Surveyor General to lay before the house an <lb/>
estimate of the expeuse of erecting a bleakwater at <lb/>
Grates Cove. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. LEAMox gave notice that he would, on to-morrow, <lb/>
move an address to his Excellency the Governor on the <lb/>
petition of the inhabitants of Brigus, for a grant to erect <lb/>
-. c whalf there. <lb/></p> 

<p>The hun Acting Colonial Secretary, by command of <lb/>
his Exc-leucy, the Governor, presented to the house the <lb/>
repºrt of the Board cf Works fur the year 1864, with <lb/>
accompanying documents relating to the various tery.ices <lb/>
under control of the Buard. <lb/> </p> 

<p>o'clock. <lb/></p> 

<p>Ord-red that these documents lie on the table, <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>