<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-04" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1869-02-04">4 February 1869</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1869-02-10"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="5"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="3"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_5.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_3.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2019-01-25">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2019-01-25">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_5"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_5.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_3"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_3.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_1.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">St. John's, Wednesday, February 10, 1869.</fw>
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2019-01-25, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>herful that the world has ever known. <lb/></p> 

<p>and in whatevex share disease exists, <lb/>
equal to its subjection and ºut. <lb/></p> 

<p>B, SrCº. <lb/>
the mousehold newery of all nations. <lb/>
y attack the very soor of the samplaint, <lb/>
restore the drooping energies of the <lb/>
Uxctioxas? REFORMATIOM, <lb/></p> 

<p>= sºrorº A.C.E. <lb/>
at is the operation of the Pills? They <lb/>
lorirritated stomachinto anatural and . <lb/></p> 

<p>of the system from sickness to health. <lb/></p> 

<p>&amp; Arr, Mººrººs, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>m undergoes the most important and <lb/></p> 

<p>fic in every disorder to which favy are <lb/>
1 against evil consequences. <lb/></p> 

<p>Pººvarrºs olº <lb/>
lood is in an impure state, let such <lb/></p> 

<p>rt with confidence to this powerful <lb/>
health and strength will be the result. <lb/></p> 

<p>risovºr Fort <lb/></p> 

<p>ſh- stone and Gravel. <lb/>
implaints, sº Becen 8 <lb/>
; Weakness, from whatars <lb/>
a of Urine. " sause, &amp;c., 8. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>words "Holloway, Eandon," are dis­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ºf directions around each box; which <lb/>
* Sold at the manufacto Pre<lb break="no"/>respectable Druggists and Dealers in <lb/>
2s., and 33s.-There is a considerable <lb/>
tions for use are affixed to each Box. <lb/></p> 

<p>QNUS EVERY THREE YEARS <lb/></p> 

<p>THE 5TNA <lb/></p> 

<p>URANCEQMPANY <lb/></p> 

<p>- (LIMI lºº, -<lb break="maybe"/>ital–One ºf illion Sterling. <lb/>
fices-Dub in-\-43 &amp; 4 Weper Sackville <lb/>
Elinhurgh–98 George's Airest. <lb/>
innilou – 17 &amp; 12 Copthill, R. C. <lb/>
eneral Mansser-Joha Inner, Esq. <lb/>
-cretery J. &amp; Fisher, Esq. <lb/></p> 

<p>nprecedensed success of the ETNA is the <lb/>
in.d, m, osing to its liberal dealings with <lb/>
à is a feet which strongly resommends the <lb/>
v to the .exple ef Nsº fºundland. <lb/>
*cºme of the Compsey ſºcia NEW PRE<lb break="no"/>A},t) N E is progressing at the rate of <lb/>
| pºr Annuts. <lb/>
in any dº not advocate high prominms. <lb/>
's imple s-aurity to all asurers. <lb/>
for losses shall be promptly and liberally <lb/></p> 

<p>ra irom cther offices can be attested free <lb/></p> 

<p>t". <lb/>
hy pryment of SIX years premiums sai <lb/>
WEN y-ars policy. <lb/>
x - Is THE exily ogwick wrºnch errºrs <lb/>
US EVERY ºr . REE FRAes to rollicºre <lb/>
tiolin; Rs haviºte º Lussks. <lb/>
ider-igned having been appointed Genera <lb/></p> 

<p>.x ewt undland for the above Company, <lb/>
•+ tº ºff-t insu' ances agai 1.0SS §§ <lb/>
F. HY FIRE on all descriptions ºf pre<lb break="no"/>tºur and reas inable rates, and begs leave. <lb/>
a share of the business of those having <lb/>
es tº effect. <lb/>
ters -hsil have prompt attention. <lb/></p> 

<p>for proposals and further informaties eas <lb/>
t the office of . <lb/></p> 

<p>i&amp;OBERT J. KENT, <lb/>
Solicitem, <lb/></p> 

<p>261 Duckworth-Sºreet St.John's, <lb/></p> 

<p>n. Rºm <lb/></p> 

<p>| N. <lb/>
E. N T * <lb/>
- V: <lb/>
aving and curing old wounds, sorts, M. <lb/>
wever inveterate. Few medicinet <lb/></p> 

<p>ºrand remedy not only cures in such <lb/>
is, as a proof it needs but a trial. <lb/></p> 

<p>prºciº-cºrrs. <lb/>
roughs, and colds, may be infallibly <lb/>
bbing this remedy twice a jay upon <lb/>
ates, and a cure quickly follows. <lb/></p> 

<p>EAST's, ETC. <lb/>
emedy is now in general use. In <lb/>
: Physicians regularly preseribe its <lb/></p> 

<p>n the chests of sailors and emigrants. <lb/></p> 

<p>SWIFºruit, rºtºrcks. º <lb/>
is Ointment will prove invaluable. <lb/>
n, and restores natural circulation. <lb/></p> 

<p>ETC., BTC. <lb/>
arts, of either sex, may be readily <lb/>
f this cooling and healing ointmeni. <lb/></p> 

<p>* Yotrºrrãº. <lb/></p> 

<p>ally cured by the joint <lb/>
the printed directions. <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>star eſ <lb/>
y iſ: mºst of the fºllowing tº rest <lb/></p> 

<p>re <lb/>
* Evil. Tic Dolourses, <lb/>
aa. Tightness ºr ºbsesſages the <lb/>
Chest, with dissuinyeſ Breathºg <lb/></p> 

<p>words "Hollowey, London,"atedls. <lb/>
the light. in every leaf of the book of <lb/>
actory of Professor Holloway, 244, <lb/>
Medicine, in pots at 1s.l.i.d., 2s. 8d., <lb/>
• saving by taking the larger alsº <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>\ <lb/></p> 

<p>e-crºsº ==== - - - - - - - - -\-\-\-\-\-\-\- -\-...-. -\-\-\-\-\-: Trº -\-\-\- ** =zººse:::::::::::::::::::::::: **-:****{-strºy: "…º.º.ºrººz - ºf º <lb/>
e. A s - -<lb break="maybe"/>- 6sº Yº q: , , º, o 3 m + 2 a. <lb break="no"/>Z <lb/>
º *** I'll ll ºil ºt, -\-\- -º-º: <lb/>
- - 3. ºr 'i tº <lb/>
wn -: *-: **** -": , ºr - - . * 143 <lb/>
- -\- - * ºr ..": ſº: ''s og .* º: ºf: ...f. <lb/>
- * 38. -\- t- - .. - -:: 4. i. º <lb/>
No. 6,568. . . . . St. John's, Wednesday, February 10, 1869, -1. <lb break="no"/>** -\-\-\-\- *** ..? wº ºf 32. º •. <lb/></p> 

<p>=-\-\-\- <lb break="no"/>Printed and Published every Tuesday gºd. Friday <lb/>
morning by Ely WARD DALTON SHEA, at his <lb/>
effice in Duckworth Sºº. Terms–One <lb/>
"Gºinea per annum, pnyable in advance. <lb/>
Advertisements not limited (AuctionSales and motº <lb/>
ºiº determine themselves excepted) are repeated, <lb/>
until ordered in writing to be withdrawn. , <lb/>
Fhis paper is filed, and may be seen free of charge <lb/>
2, #iºdſ. Pill and ointment Establishment, <lb/>
244, Strand. London. <lb/>
This paper is notissued to anySubsertber for a shorter <lb/>
ierm than siz months. <lb/></p> -->
 

<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head>

<p rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, February 4.</p>
    
    <p>
The House met pursuant to adjournment. <lb/></p> 

<p>Pursuant to the order of the day, and on motion <lb/>
of <persName ref="pers:GODD1">Mr. Godden</persName>, the House resolved itself into a <lb/>
Committee of the whole on the Address of Thanks <lb/>
in reply to His Excellency's speech. Mr. Knight in <lb/>
the chair. <lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName> had much pleasure in rising to sup<lb break="no"/>port the amendment which had been moved by his <lb/>
hon. friend, Mr. Parsons, to the second paragraph in <lb/>
        the Address of Thanks. The paragraph says:—  <lb/></p>
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>"We fully approve of the course taken by the <lb/>
Executive Government in issuing the Proclamation in <lb/>
June last, that relief in future would be confined to <lb/>
destitute widows and orphans, and to the sick and <lb/>
infirm poor. We believe this act was well timed, <lb/>
and we cordially hope and trust that the Executive <lb/>
may be successful in its efforts to suppress the de<lb break="no"/>moralizing system of able-bodiod relief." <lb/></p>
    </quote>
    <p>
This was a perfect echo of His Excellency's speech, <lb/>
while the amendment reads thus: "While we ad<lb break="no"/>mit the necessity of the large outlay under the head <lb/>
of relief for the able-bodied poor, we cannot refrain <lb/>
from expressing our disappointment of the injudici<lb break="no"/>ous mode in which such outlay was effected, and our <lb/>
regret that no remedial measures had been adopted <lb/>
by the Government to relieve the evils accruing to <lb/>
the poor from its sudden stoppage." Now he (Mr. <lb/>
R.) approved and endorsed every word contained in <lb/>
that amendment. We had been accused of bringing <lb/>
all our influence upon the Government to induce <lb/>
them to issue meal and molasses to the poor. It was <lb/>
however, well known that the opposition had brought <lb/>
no such pressure, they had no interestin bringing it, <lb/>
and none of that meal and molasses stuck to their <lb/>
hands or contributed to line their pockets. He well <lb/>
recollected how the hon, member, Mr. Shea, in his <lb/>
last great speech upon the tariff, paraded a letter <lb/>
signed by him (Mr. R,) and his colleagues, and en<lb break="no"/>deavoured to prove from it and to convince the <lb/>
country that we were the parties who had brought a <lb/>
pressure to bear upon the Government to induce <lb/>
and coerce them to issue this poor relief. But that <lb/>
letter should be placed side by side with the one <lb/>
which had been received by him (Mr. R.) from the <lb/>
Chairman of the Board of Works. In 1864, when <lb/>
this Amalgamated Government came into power, this <lb/>
Government that was the greatest curse to the coun<lb break="no"/>try, was going to work wonders—it was going to <lb/>
improve the condition of the people, stimulate en<lb break="no"/>terprise, and be a blessing to all. It was said that <lb/>
the hon. member Mr. Shea, and the hon. Receiver <lb/>
General left this side of the House purely to trample <lb/>
down all angry sectarian feelings. Well, we had a <lb/>
trail of them for four years and what had they done? <lb/>
When we look around can we see any evidence of <lb/>
progress or of administrative ability? No. Noth<lb break="no"/>ing but starvation among the people, as he had <lb/>
stated the other day, but which statement had been <lb/>
suppressed by the official reporters to this House. <lb/>
In 1864 then this unholy alliance was consummated, <lb/>
and before the session met we were summoned to <lb/>
attend a meeting in the office of the Colonial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary. We went there, and we were asked by the <lb/>
Premier, Mr. Carter, whether we would consent to <lb/>
an advance of £200, being made on account of our <lb/>
road grant to support the able-bodied poor in our <lb/>
district. He (Mr. R.) had said that he would not <lb/>
consent to sacrifice the industrious agriculturist for <lb/>
such a purpose. The hon, and learned Attorney <lb/>
General then said we sent for you to ask your per<lb break="no"/>mission, but if you do not give it we will <lb/>
do it without your sanction. We protested <lb/>
against such a proceeding, but it was of no avail. <lb/>
Last year when applications were made to us, we <lb/>
merely brought them under the notice of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, leaving the responsibility with them. He <lb/>
(Mr. R.) had addressed a communication to the hon. <lb/>
Colonial Secretary, relieving himself and his hon. <lb/>
colleagues from any responsibility, and placing that <lb/>
responsibility upon the shoulders of the Government, <lb/>
who were bound not to let any one starve. Here <lb/>
the hon. member read the communications he <lb/>
referred to, and commented upon them at consider<lb break="no"/>able length. Was there any evidence that he, or <lb/>
any of the Opposition, had coerced the Government <lb/>
into the lavish and extravagant expenditure that <lb/>
had been made? We had no desire to force the <lb/>
Government, we merely placed before them the <lb/>
positicn of the people, and refrained from telling <lb/>
or asking them to do anything. The members of <lb/>
the Government had a direct interest in fostering <lb/>
this system, of pauper relief, and but for it, their <lb/>
household Gods would come to nothing. There <lb/>
were men who came to us and said the Government <lb/>
will give us relief if you sanction it, and if we do not <lb/>
get it, it will be your fault, What then could we <lb/>
do? We were driven into the necessity of sending <lb/>
to the Government the communication that we did— <lb/>
a communication which has been twisted and <lb/>
tortured to suit the ends of the Executive. Here <lb/>
the hon member commented on the speech of the <lb/>
hon. member Mr. Shea last year in reference to this <lb/>
matter, and said that the issue of poor relief was <lb/>
what the Government desired and connived at. He <lb/>
referred to the issue of meal and molasses in the <lb/>
Eastern districts, and said it was made use of for the <lb/>
purpose of filling the pockets of members of the <lb/>
Executive, and not for the relief of the people. He <lb/>
charged certain of the Executive with selling meal <lb/>
to the Government at a price far above its market <lb/>
worth, and being full of Purser's figs, rotten and <lb/>
lumpy. He then referred to the permanent poor <lb/>
grant, contended that it was made the means of the <lb/>
vilest abuses and corruption, and that half the money <lb/> 
voted was not expended. The system, he said, was <lb/>
corrupt and rotten at the core. The Proclamation <lb/>
migut be a step in the right, direction, but it should <lb/>
not have been issued until the Government had in <lb/>
some way prepared the people for its reception, He <lb/>
would refer to the public accounts to show the <lb/>
robberies and jobberies that were contained therein. <lb/> 

<cb/>

The Government had taxed, bread and other neces<lb break="no"/>saries of life to such an extent as to leave the market <lb/>
without that active competition which was necessa<lb break="no"/>ry to equalise prices, and this was done in order to <lb/>
raise a revenue to meet their extravagance. They <lb/>
went in debt to the Union Bank to the amount of <lb/>
£70,000, and cared not bow the revenue went while <lb/>
that held, and then when the Bank called for pay<lb break="no"/>ment they had no means of responding, except by <lb/>
increased taxation. His side of the House had put <lb/>
forth their views, with regard to this taxation, but <lb/>
they were scouted, and they were told they were <lb/>
neither financiers nor politicians. What is the re<lb break="no"/>sult of their Tariff, why that His Excellency is ob<lb break="no"/>liged to acknowledge that the Revenue falls short of <lb/>
the Estimate. The Government claims credit for <lb/>
playing a bold and an honest policy in the matter of <lb/>
this proclamation, and that it was issued solely with <lb/>
a view to suppress able-bodied pauper relief, but <lb/>
they would not have adopted that course had not the <lb/>
Union Bank fightened the purse "strings." They <lb/>
make a virtue of necessity, and parade their virtues <lb/>
before the country. It is said St. John's absorbs <lb/>
the lion's share of Poor Relief, but it was well <lb/>
known that the people from all parts of the country <lb/>
crowd into St. John's. It was not the poor of St. <lb/>
John's who absorbed this Poor Relief. There were <lb/>
last winter in St. John's West not less than 75 out<lb break="no"/>port families, and they absorbed no less than £500 <lb/>
of the road grant of the district, which pronerly be<lb break="no"/>longed to the industrious agriculturist. The pro<lb break="no"/>clamation may have been good up to this, but if hon. <lb/>
gentlemen would visit the poor in their hovels, they <lb/>
would see an amount of misery which would soon <lb/>
convince them that it cannot be carried out in its <lb/>
integrity. He (Mr. R.) was directly opposed to the <lb/>
giving of relief to those who did not require it, but <lb/>
to these who were in danger of starving, relief <lb/>
should be given, though it took the last farthing in <lb/>
the public Exchequer. It matters not how the peo<lb break="no"/>ple were brought to want, they must not be allowed <lb/>
to perish. The Government won't do anything, all <lb/>
their affection, all their attention is centred in the <lb/>
one thing, they have mismanaged the public affairs, <lb/>
they have misappropriated the public funds, and feel<lb break="no"/>ing that they stunk in the nostrils of the people, <lb/>
they look to only one avenue of escape—Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, that is a new Amalgamation—an Amalgamation <lb/>
with Canada, which is 1000 miles away, with a <lb/>
people who are ignorant of the resources of the <lb/>
country, and yet are, so we are told, to do for us more <lb/>
than we can do for ourselves. He (Mr. R.) need <lb/>
not tell the House nor pruclaim to the country, all <lb/>
the wiles and tricks which had been played off in <lb/>
order to effect a change in the views of the people <lb/>
on this question. The other evening when his hon. <lb/>
colleague, (Mr. Talbot.) lightly touched on the <lb/>
question of Confederation, the hon. member for <lb/>
Placentia and St. Mary's, (Mr. Shea,) took him to <lb/>
task and then spoke for two hours on the very same <lb/>
subject. Had they on that side of the House no <lb/>
right to speak on the subject. Oh no! They were <lb/>
not honest, so it was said, and only hon. Mr Shea <lb/>
and a few other disinterested parties were entitled to <lb/>
speak. His colleague had also spoken of the necessity <lb/>
for economy, and hinted that a saving to the extent <lb/>
of £25,000 might be effected. This he (Mr. R.) <lb/>
believed also, and so did the people, yet it was cha<lb break="no"/>racterised as nonsense, balderdash, buncombe. We <lb/>
are told the public salaries amount to ouly £32,000 <lb/>
and asked how 25,000 can be saved out of that. <lb/>
The salaries may come to only £32,000, but the <lb/>
public expenditure amounted to 150,000. Will it be <lb/>
said that £25,000 cannot be saved out of that, and <lb/>
will not such a saving effect more benefit for the <lb/>
country than this wild scheme of Confederation. <lb/>
But we are not to touch the salaries of the fat officials. <lb/>
If the funds are not sufficient, the remedy is increased <lb/>
taxation. In their wild desire to maintain this posi<lb break="no"/>tion, they were like the man who killed the goose <lb/>
that laid the golden egg. They were in effect told <lb/>
that it was useless to save, that the country was <lb/>
going into Confederation, at least so they say. It <lb/>
was very evident that nothing could be expected from <lb/>
the Government, they were so absorbed by this one <lb/>
matter. They hope the matter will be discussed in a <lb/>
spirit of fair play, and that no clap-trap will be used. <lb/>
They are to have a monopoly of clap-trap, and no <lb/>
one was to interfere with them, or meet them with <lb/>
their own weapons. The question will come before <lb/>
the constituencies, and he (Mr. H.) hoped that all <lb/>
traitors will meet with traitors doom. The hon. <lb/>
member Mr. Shea had adduced the late election in <lb/>
Harbor Grace as a proof that the policy of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment was sustained by the people and merchants <lb/>
of Conception Bay, and said that the hon member <lb/>
Mr. Godden had been sent to this House to support <lb/>
that policy. There were two candidates, but neither <lb/>
of them in the addresses made any mention of the <lb/>
question of Confederation though it had been before <lb/>
the country for over four years. The election took <lb/>
place, and Mr. Godden was returned by a bare<lb/>
majority of 40 though the Government used all <lb/>
possible exertion, and the merehants all their influ<lb break="no"/>ence to secure his return, and this was the return <lb/>
which was so much boasted of. The hon. Mr Shea <lb/>
and the hon and learned Attorney General went to <lb/>
Quebec to hear what the other delegates had to say. <lb/>
They came back with what were called good terms, <lb/>
and every machinery was put in operation to accept <lb/>
them. The scheme came in for consideration, and <lb/>
was rejected by the House and people. A number <lb/>
of dodges were tried, dodge No. 1 was a dockyard <lb/>
which was to employ all the shipcarpenters, joiners <lb/>
&amp;c. &amp;c. Dodge No. 2 was a great nign road from St. <lb/>
John's to Placentia, which would absorb all the sur<lb break="no"/>plus labor of the Colony. No. 3 was a grand road <lb/>
from St. John's to Twillingate and Fogo, which <lb/>
would give employment to the Northern people. No. <lb/>
4 was steam, we were to have coastal, intercolonial, <lb/>
and direct steam, yet have got none of them. Last <lb/>
session the necessity for a new dodge and a Railway <lb/>
to Cape Race was got up. He (Mr R.) could not <lb/>
but admire the honesty of the hon and learned At<lb break="no"/>torney General who said it might as well be called <lb/>
a railway to the moon. <lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:CART5">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>—I aid not. I firmly <lb/>
believe in it now. <lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName>.—Then you have changed your <lb/>
opinions. He (Mr. R.) agreed, that it such a <lb/>
Railway were undertaken, it would be of benefit for <lb/>
the building of the Grand Trunk Railway and spend <lb/>
a great deal money on Canada. A notice of resolu<lb break="no"/>tion was placed on the paper, and there it remained <lb/>
until the rule of the House were suspended towards <lb/>
the close of the session, and then they wouid have <lb/>
pushed it through without fair discussion of it <lb/>
were it not for him (Mr R.) The resolutions were <lb/>
passed and sent to Canada, aud nothing had ever <lb/> 

<cb/>

been heard of them since. Does any man believe <lb/>
in the construction of this Railway? The capital <lb/>
was to come from Canada, yet the Canadians were <lb/>
not able to build their own public works, but had to <lb/>
go to the United States for money. Of course they <lb/>
had the report of a Canadian Engineer, Mr Fleming, <lb/>
who made the best of the matter, but it was well <lb/>
known how these reports were got up, especially <lb/>
when a Government wished for them. A new dodge <lb/>
is wanted this session, and he (Mr. R) would not be <lb/>
surprised if the hon member would produce a <lb/>
telegraph, authorising him to engage 800 or 1000 <lb/>
men for employment in Canada on some Railway or <lb/>
other. He (Mr. R) had enquired from a friend in <lb/>
Ottawa, for he too had friends there, what were the <lb/>
chances of our people getting employment there. <lb/>
(Here the hon gentleman read an extract from a <lb/>
letter alleged to be from Ottawa.) He asserted that <lb/>
the labor market of Canada was already overstocked, <lb/>
and if there was a demand for labor, that demand <lb/>
could very readily be supplied from the United States. <lb/>
From the very first this Confederation scheme had <lb/>
been supported by trickery and dodges and these <lb/>
dodges had been all so transparent as to render their <lb/>
exposure unnecessary. The hon. gentleman then <lb/>
commented at great length on the course which the <lb/>
Government had pursued with regard to Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. He denied that the time had come for disposing <lb/>
of the question. He denied that this House had <lb/>
power to entertain it. Let Canada propose to us <lb/>
some well defined terms as a basis for our consider<lb break="no"/>ation and then it will be high time for us to enter <lb/>
upon the discussion of the matter; we had no trade <lb/>
with Canada, Canada was now as tree to us and all <lb/>
British subjects as under Confederation it could <lb/>
possibly be. If Canadians fonnd it for their interest <lb/>
they could as well come here now with their capita <lb/>
as if the Union were an accomplished fact. A <lb/>
mere parchment Confederation would never be <lb/>
sufficient to induce capitalists to embark their money <lb/>
in enterprises which would result to the advantage <lb/>
of this colony. On the other hand Canada could <lb/>
offer no advantages to our labouring population. <lb/>
The labour market was already overstocked and <lb/>
were it not so, the facilities of communication with the <lb/>
United States, would effectually debar us from this <lb/>
benefit. The hon. member concluded a very lengthy <lb/>
speech by strong animad versions upon the policy of <lb/>
the Government in witholding seed potatoes from the <lb/>
poor of the Island. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:LITT3">Mr. LITTLE</persName> fully concurred with the amead<lb break="no"/>ment of his hon friend. Mr. Parsons, that is <lb/>
the Amendment moved in answer to that part <lb/>
of the Speech referring to the Proclamation of June <lb/>
last. Now, what was that proclamation? * * That <lb/>
owing to the gross imposition practised by undeserv<lb break="no"/>ing applicants for relief, the insufficiency of the only <lb/>
means available to the Government for confining <lb/>
relief within legitimate bonnds, the inadequacy of the <lb/>
revenue the extraordinary expenditure thus acca<lb break="no"/>sioned, &amp;c, &amp;c. It goes on to state that "hereafter <lb/>
relief will be confined to sick and infirm and to <lb/>
destitute widows and orphans," we find in the very <lb/>
wording of the Proclamation an admission by the <lb/>
Government of its own incapacity. They had made <lb/>
that incapacity a law, they had placarded it over the <lb/>
city, and out of their own mouths they stood con<lb break="no"/>demned. The Government do not dare to assert that <lb/>
there exists no necessity for this relief, they do not <lb/>
assert that members are not justifled in soliciting this <lb/>
relief, out the assertion is simply that Government <lb/>
had not sufficient machinery to carry out the details <lb/>
of the distribution in such a manner as to protect <lb/>
themselves from fraud and imposition. Was not the <lb/>
horest but unfortunate fisherman, the really deserving <lb/>
and who had lost his all by shipwreck, were not <lb/>
these entitled to the consideration of the Government? <lb/>
Do such cases really exist? Has that Proclamation <lb/>
been a panacea for all our evils? Has not pauper<lb break="no"/>isn been as rife in many localities as when that dis<lb break="no"/>tribution was taking place? Did Government put <lb/>
an addendum to to the Proclamation as to the subsitu<lb break="no"/>ion of any means by which the unfortunate poor of <lb/>
the country might be relieved? Not at all. Last <lb/>
year some £32,000 was expended and suddenly, <lb/>
without <choice><sic>ferewarning</sic><corr>forewarning</corr></choice>, without the substitution of any <lb/>
remedial measure, they throw broadcast this Procla<lb break="no"/>nation, proclaiming to the country that thro' the <lb/>
tarpitude ef their own officials, they are obliged to <lb/>
dose the Government chest, and rather than that <lb/>
fraud should be continued it is desirable that the peo<lb break="no"/>ple should die. The other day the hon. Attorney <lb/>
general had stated that it would have been unwise <lb/>
to purchase seed potatoes because of the high price <lb/>
and the shortness of the supply, and those who had <lb/>
not means to purchase would be constrained to do <lb/>
without then, And this was prudence, this was wis<lb break="no"/>dom. He must certainly condemn the mistaken <lb/>
policy of the Government in this respect. The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment were now feeling the effects of it and unless <lb/>
they were like a corporation without a soul to be <lb/>
damned or a body to be kicked, they must feel for <lb/>
the destitution which everywhere exists. Attempts <lb/>
had been made to afford relief through temporary <lb/>
establishments. Though he respected the motives <lb/>
which had induced benevolent men to enterprise <lb/>
these establishments,he could not see that any perma<lb break="no"/>nent good could posibly result from them. He <lb/>
agreed that it was the duty of every hon. member to <lb/>
use his best endeavours to extricate the country from <lb/>
its difficulties and it waa the intention of this party to <lb/>
        place belore the House their ideas on this subject— <lb/>
        ideas which would be endorsed throughout the length <lb/>
and breadth of the country. Government business <lb/>
should be conducted ou the same principles of econo<lb break="no"/>my which regulate the private affairs of men. He <lb/>
(Mr. L.) had much pleasure in expressing his sup<lb break="no"/>port of the amendment of the hon. member, Mr. <lb/>
Parsons. He did not find fault with an honest en<lb break="no"/>deavour on the part of the Government to suppress <lb/>
this fearful evil which is eating into the very, vitals <lb/>
of the country, but he censured their mode and man<lb break="no"/>ner of carrying into effect their intentions. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName> stood up to give his support to the <lb/>
amendment before the Chair, and not to enter at <lb/>
length upon the many subjects in the Address. Had <lb/>
this rule been followed this debate ought to have been <lb/>
finished last evening. The hon. member, Mr. Pin<lb break="no"/>sent, last evening had not merely attacked the reso<lb break="no"/>lution,but had gone into a debate upon his Excellen<lb break="no"/>cy's Speech and the various matters therein referred <lb/>
to, and which he very well knew would be subject to <lb/>
discussion as they came upsingly before the House. <lb/>
When the question of Confederation came formally <lb/>
before the House would be the proper time to ex<lb break="no"/>press opinions upon it, and look at it in all its bear<lb break="no"/>ings. But the hon. member Mr. Pinsent is not con<lb break="no"/>tent to wait—he must flash at once into everything, <lb/>
and must throw down the gauntlet to this side of the <lb/>

<cb/>

House. He says the Opposition have a right to <lb/>
point out a a remedy for existing evils. Well, he <lb/>
did so last spring when we asked for a grant for <lb/>
seed potatoes, but because that issue could not be <lb/>
turned to profitable account by members of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, because they could not make money out of <lb/>
it, it was refused. There had been thousands of <lb/>
acres prepared in anticipation that seed would be <lb/>
given, and the owners of them were now shivering <lb/>
with the cold, starving and dying, but you give them <lb/>
his Excellency's Proclamation, as much as to say to <lb/>
them, digest that if you can. One Executive Coun<lb break="no"/>cillor had sold meal to his (Mr. H.'s) district, and <lb/>
        forty barrels of it were so bad that the pigs would <lb/>
not eat them,and that was charged for at 33s.6d. per <lb/>
barrel, and was taken out of our road bill. Was it <lb/>
        not time indeed to put an end to a fraud like that? <lb/>
        You ask for a remedy. Why do you not send your is <lb/>
Surveyor General to open up the fine land about <lb/>
Torbay and Bay Bulls, and employ the people in <lb/>
clearing it? You could thus make a profit out of <lb/>
your lands and pay at the same time cash to the <lb/>
poor labourer. Look at, how the road money was <lb/>
misapplied. Go to St. Mary's and Placentia and <lb/>
see the vast sums that have been expended, and do <lb/>
you see any improvement? There was not an acre <lb/>
of land opened up. Go and see all the districts ex<lb break="no"/>cept his (Mr. H's), and the same state of things <lb/>
would be found. You talk of your resources. If a <lb/>
man goes into the wilderness of Canada he is helped <lb/>
by the Government either with implements or seed, <lb/>
and thus Canada has been raised to what she is now. <lb/>
Look at California, and see how her resources were <lb/>
developed. They were developed by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the day and hence she flourished and is <lb/>
what she is. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATToRNEY GENMENT</persName>—I suppose the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment made the gold? <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName>—The Government made the country <lb/> 
before the gold was discovered. What gold has your <lb/>
celebrated Geologist discovered? We have been <lb/>
paying here for four or five years £700 a year while <lb/>
        the people were starving, and what good had result<lb break="no"/>ed? The hon. member contended that the Geolo<lb break="no"/>gical Survey was a waste of public money and only <lb/>
added to the burdens of the country, and that if the <lb/>
seed potatoes had been furnished to the people last <lb/>
spring there would be an absence now of the starva<lb break="no"/>tion which was to be seen on every side. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:REND1">MR. RENDELL</persName>—The House had listened to a very <lb/>
long speech from the hon. member Mr. Renouf, and <lb/>
he (Mr. R.) had no doubt that the Government were <lb/>
well able to meet and refute the charges which had <lb/>
been made against them. There was a unanimous <lb/>
feeling throughout the country that poor relief to the <lb/>
able-bodied must be put down, and it was reasona<lb break="no"/>ble that when a man was in good bodily health and <lb/>
        able to do work, he had no right to claim support <lb/>
        from the Government for six months out of the year. <lb/>
If such a system as that which has heretofore exist<lb break="no"/>ed were to be continued, the country must financial<lb break="no"/>ly be ruined. We see the terrible effects that it has <lb/>
produced up to the present time, and no matter what <lb/>
        the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> believ<lb break="no"/>ed that it was utterly impossible for the financial <lb/>
condition of this colony to sustain the heavy burdens <lb/>
that was placed upon it. Last year we had a new <lb/>
tariff, a tariff which could not be defended but by <lb/>
the peculiar circumstances of this Colony, these cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances being purely exceptional, rendering it <lb/>
imperative that the liabilities of the Colony should be <lb/>
met; looking at the present tariff, from any other <lb/>
point of view, it was indefensible, and although he <lb/>
(Mr R) might have had something to do in fixing <lb/>
the rates upon certain articles, yet it had not his sup<lb break="no"/>port as a whole. He thought that this Government <lb/>
would be fully sustained by the public in the pro<lb break="no"/>clamation issued by them, that no relief would be <lb/>
        furnished to the able bodied poor. He was aware <lb/>
that much suffering did exist, and all must feel it <lb/>
deeply, and deeply deplore it. There was not a <lb/>
season passed when poor relief was distributed, but <lb/>
we found it subject to the grossest abuse and corrup<lb break="no"/>tion. He would say that in his own district, he had <lb/>
been disgusted at the way in which it had been <lb/>
abused. He knew one place where the test of an <lb/>
oath had been required, and it had been ascertain<lb break="no"/>ed that the party had actually removed a barrel of <lb/>
flour from his house to that of a neighbour, so that <lb/>
he might be in a position, as he erroneously supposed <lb/>
to satisfy his conscience by swearing that he had <lb/>
nothing in his House. Here there was a striking <lb/>
example of the terribly demoralizing effects of this <lb/>
system. The sick and infirm should of course be <lb/>
provided for, and he trusted that the spirit of chris<lb/>tain charity was not yet extinct, but that all were <lb/>
ready as far as their means would permit to relieve <lb/>
such cases. But relief to the able-bodied should be <lb/>
put down. At present great want was no doubt felt, <lb/>
but he believed that the people would be able to <lb/>
struggle through. In cases of course where such <lb/>
utter want existed that loss of life was to be feared, <lb/>
it was the duty of the Government as well as of every <lb/>
individual to prevent such a calamity. It was indeed <lb/>
difficult sometimes to understand the views and <lb/>
opinion of the opposition. At one time they support <lb/>
the action of the Government, and at another they <lb/>
turn round and denounce it. One thing, however, <lb/>
appeared to him (Mr R) to be perfectly clear. A <lb/>
Proclamation haſ been issued, and the people <lb/>
must abide by it. If the Government do not now <lb/>
carry out the Proclamation what will the people <lb/>
think? They will in the future regard all Proclama<lb break="no"/>tions of a like character and object as mere moon<lb break="no"/>shine. With reference to seed potatoes he (Mr R) <lb/>
could speak of the reeult in his own district of the <lb/>
refusal of the Government to furnish any. The <lb/>
fishery there had been by no means an abundant <lb/>
one, the people were not prosperous, and yet a <lb/>
greater breadth of land had been sown under potatoes <lb/>
this year than for many years past. He believed <lb/>
that all the really industrious succeeded in getting <lb/>
potatoes, and they who mostly claimad poor relief, <lb/>
he believed, had no gardens to plant potatoes even if <lb/>
given to them. After all, what was the extent of land <lb/>
that was cultivated in this colony? It was a mere <lb/>
nothing. He thought that in some way the people <lb/>
had lost the art as well as the habit of cultivating the <lb/>
soil. The present generation instead of, being <lb/>
habituated to it as their forefathers had been, <lb/>
neglected it altogether and trusted too much to the <lb/>
fisheries. It was idle now to tell the people that the <lb/>
cod fisheries alone could support them. He (Mr R.) <lb/>
did not believe it and no one intimately acquainted <lb/>
with the trade and circumstances of the colony would <lb/>
credit it. Some families where there are five or six <lb/>
men manage to do, as do also some who have large <lb/>
craft and means for prosecuting the fishery, and it is <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">[SEE LAST PAGE.]</p>

<pb n="5" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_5.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">5</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    <!-- IC, 2019-01-25, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>*. ...-a &lt; . . . . . . * * * ... * * * " " <lb break="no"/>T H E N E w F o UN D L AND ER..…-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-º <lb/>
4. N. • ** ***** - **** - . . . . . ." -\-\- - - + -\- - • , <lb/>
: v. - ". *…: <lb/>
- - - . hear that destitution prevailed in the locality <lb/>
-: x - - - - -\-\-\-\-\-\- - like the hon. to heal." p ity . <lb/>
* T *- - - ..." ersistent claimant for pauper relief for his Pistº; of Union, when they saw ºne" Referred to by the hon. member. large amount <lb/>
* * toosTINUED . "... meet . he has made all º party follow hi. viº and members, Mr. Korka and Mr. Readell, large of relief ... year conveyed thither and no re-<lb break="yes"/>hard work for *. . ... and wrong to i. bow their necks to his yoke. He, Mr. Pºwie, mercantile houses like Bidley's and Munn's, urn had ever been made. There was a supplying -\-&gt; <lb/>
It was therefore i ... cod fishery alone was );". the hon. member, Mr. Gien, credit for Baine, Johnston &amp; Co., and Tensier's, support- johan resident there and surely he when hé. <lb/>
the people to stippº Nºwhatevermoy have | . educating his party;" his skill in party discipline ing the measure. what interests had these receives the benefit of these poor men's services, <lb/>
The should in some substantial manner display his sympa. <lb/></p> 

<p>sufficient for their support. <lb/></p> 

<p>been the opposition given by his commercial assºciates | * be great indeed, when, in the º of three <lb/></p> 

<p>short days, he can so manipulate his ji.e., as to men except in the welfare of the country: . <lb/></p> 

<p>prosperity of the Colony would be beneficial to There is really no part of <lb/></p> 

<p>thy with their distress. <lb/></p> 

<p>...tº may have been tº vasiellºſiº. ... ...injusly eat their words. No man - this island so capable of sustaining a population: <lb/>
juppression of opinion ºn." 5. could .#... .."oºl. ii., is depression theirº. *. . jºnºia and st: *.*.*. == - <lb break="no"/>in deteronce to the views of persºn*** janºore ardently than did he hºº. ºl. Government too, on the question," jss the most fertile land in the country... There Printed and Published ever? <lb/></p> 


<p>the industrious man can find fish almost at his door. <lb/>
And yet that fertile land has been lying untilled and <lb/>
almost calling aloud for cultivation. It stands in <lb/>
cold contrast to the sterile land of the Northern <lb/>
districts, where the people are now sustaining them. <lb/>
jves." But the people of Piacentia would risk <lb/>
their lives upon the chance of what little sustain<lb break="no"/>ment they could get from the Government rather <lb/>
than exert themselves to their own permanent <lb/>
independence. Only last session there were three: <lb/>
tº and barrels of flour distributed among the <lb/>
people of that district through the wreck of the <lb/>
summer, and hardly a man of the locality but got a t <lb/>
... 'There sould not have been a single raan <lb/>
but must have been in a position to commence the " <lb/>
fishery infinitely superior to the men of other districts. <lb/>
The same pressure was last year attempted to be <lb/>
brought to bear upon the Government, although in <lb/>
addition to the flour so obtained, some #3900 worth <lb/>
... pauper Relief was distributed in the district. , <lb/>
He (hon. A.G.) had as much sympathy for the suf<lb break="no"/>fering poor as any man. He would gº tº, any legis <lb/>
timaº'extent to assist them. He hoped that the <lb/></p> 

<p>ºtic upon the great questiºn of Confedara<lb break="no"/>*...*. (Mr # or one . stood out boldly, feir, <lb/>
and square for it...He believed that there wer." <lb/>
jº himself did not much li; Confederation at <lb/>
first. They thought it would produce greatºr <lb/></p> 

<p>jmber, Mr. Little, and the gallan: Majºr, the <lb/>
Secretary of the Mendicity Work House: Why, his <lb/>
position there was 3. living testimony agains; peºpº. <lb/>
ism, and yet the Major loregoes that #. *.: <lb/>
- .*. The here, to become a mºre Pºp. agent. If ever tº: <lb/>
i. . so far a; *.*.*. º r; ºãS an honest act done by any Governmºnt, ºr by <lb/>
r <lb break="no"/>to it. But . jº more closely into the º' Party ºn this Colony, º it; ...it *o..". <lb/>
ºalter—to view it in all its aspects—and reflect upº of this º: i. *.i. 'a. st a <lb/>
the circumstances of this colony, a change cameº gained by 1i, ..." ld ". .# . by <lb/>
the spirit of our dream. and many who were at firs; starving lº. *...*. t &amp; Government <lb/>
strongly opposed to it are now at all events quiet ... unscrupulous demagºgue; agº". idered it was <lb/>
#. # is best to "accept the situation," make *::::: #. He, . É. consi i.i. ... <lb/>
- instead ... p.m. the duty, of ºvery fight tºº." man <lb break="no"/>the best .."ºś. less || munity to aid the Gºvernment in their honest. and <lb/>
| expensive 10 * - inº, endeavours to suppress so demoralizing." <lb/></p> 

<p>morning by Eu WARD 12. <lb/>
office in Duckworth S <lb/>
Guinca per annum, pnyalé <lb/>
dºer: ts not limited {4, <lb/>
rºkich defermline themselves <lb/>
until ordered in writing to <lb/>
its paper is fied, &amp;l mu º <lb/>
at Hodowa 's Pill and Oil <lb/>
244, Strand, London. <lb/>
zhip per is notissued to anyS <lb/>
term than six nantles. <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>HOUSE OF AS: <lb/></p> 

<p>d more suited to the condition of the + <lb break="no"/>3.". .. was the general idea that system. ...The Government deserve. * for <lb/>
{{ - y. ined by those connected with the com- resisting the pressure put upon them in this mate <lb/>
t was entertained by th9% - - jº theyºet credit for it. Every good and <lb/>
f this countr We had heard observations , and they g ed - y g <lb break="no"/>*. n the . men of Canada who had been generous citizen will aid the Government. by his <lb/>
; . as º schemers. He thought, that private i."; and cheer them " . their *::: <lb/>
i. ... the intelligent status ºf these men they | *. his quesº is nºw." the most vº <lb/>
.#.json with our ºwn...Lº. importance to the Colony. Our financial inºgº; <lb/>
would surely bear comp iſ admit that she was far in our social morality, almost our very as a <lb/>
ºilized community, depend upon the issue of this <lb/></p> 

<p>The House met pursuant to <lb/></p> 

<p>The holi. ATToRNEY GENE <lb/>
on this day fortuigh", he wº <lb/>
into comu.ttee of the Whol <lb/>
the Union of this Island w <lb/>
Gamala. <lb/></p> 

<p>ing at Canada we musº <lb/></p> 

<p>t <lb/></p> -->


<p rendition="simple:centre">[CONTINUED FROM FIRST PAGE.]</p>

<p>
    hard work for three men to make both end meet. <lb/>
    It was therefore idle and useless and wrong to lead <lb/>
    the people to suppose that the cod fishery alone was <lb/>
    sufficient for their support. Now whatever may have <lb/>
    been the opposition given by his commercial asspciates <lb/>
    and whatever may have been their vasicllation or <lb/>
    whatever suppression of opinion on the part of others <lb/>
    in deference to the views of persons on the other side <lb/>
    of the Atlantic upon the great question of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, he (Mr R) for one now stood out boldly, <choice><sic>feir</sic><corr>fair</corr></choice>, <lb/>
    and square for it. He believed that there were many <lb/>
    who like himself did not much like Confederation at <lb/>
    first. They thought it would produce greater <lb/>
    taxation, and hence so far as the majority of the <lb/>
    commercial body was concerned, they were opposed <lb/>
    to it. But as we came to look more closely into the <lb/>
    matter—to view it in all its aspects—and reflect upon <lb/>
    the circumstances of this colony, a charge came over <lb/>
    the spirit of our dream, and many who were at first <lb/>
    strongly opposed to it are now at all events quiet and <lb/>
    think that it is best to "accept the situation," make <lb/>
    the best terms we can, and get instead of our present <lb/>
    expensive local Government, something cheaper, less <lb/>
    cumbersome and more suited to the condition of the <lb/>
    Colony. This he believed was the general idea that <lb/>
    was entertained by those connected with the com<lb break="no"/>merce of this country. We had heard observations <lb/>
    made upon the public men of Canada who had been <lb/>
    stigmatised as polotical schemers. He thought, that <lb/>
    looking at the intelligent <hi rendition="simple:italic">status</hi> of these men they <lb/>
    would surely bear comparison with our own. Look<lb break="no"/>ing at Canada we must all admit that she was fair in <lb/>
    advance of us in wealth, in resources and general <lb/>
material prosperity. The public men may have <lb/>
anticipated too much, but they are not like us droop<lb break="no"/>ing in spirit and having no faith in the progress of <lb/>
their country. You never hear a Canadian that <lb/>
does not speak confidently and hopefully of his coun<lb break="no"/>try. He Mr R. wished that we could do the same. <lb/>
Their money may have been invested too early and <lb/>
too heavily in great public works, but they are now <lb/>
turning it to good account and the new Dominion is <lb/>
now beginning to reap the benefits. Reference had <lb/>
been made by the hon. member Mr Glen to the finan<lb break="no"/>cial condition of Canada and as he was some<lb break="no"/>what an authority in matters of finance, his <lb/>
opinion might have some effect. He told us <lb/>
yesterday that Canada was so bankrupt that <lb/>
if she had not been able to avail herself of the <lb/>
issue of Treasury notes, she would have been <lb/>
brought up by the round turn. It was simply in <lb/>
his (M. R's) opinion a sufficient answer to refer to <lb/>
the value of Canadian stock in the London market <lb/>
which was thus quoted in the "Times" of December <lb/>
last: <lb/></p>
    
    <p rendition="simple:centre">GOVERNMENT SECURITIES</p>
    
    <table>
        <row><cell>Canada.6 per cent. Jan. and July, 1877</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">107 1/2 to 108 1/2</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Do 6 per cent. Feb and Aug,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">105 to 107</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Do 6 per cent. March and Sept.</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">105 to 107</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Do 5 per cent. Jan. and July</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">95 to 96</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Do 5 per cent. inscribed stock</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">94 to 96</cell></row>
    </table>
    
    <p>
He thought that the gentlemen of the English Stock <lb/>
Exchange knew what they were about in money mat<lb break="no"/>ters, and the value of the Stock thus quoted should <lb/>
be a sufficient auswer to all the gloomy forebodings <lb/>
which hon. members opposite indulged in. In our <lb/>
present position we were now perfectly helpless and <lb/>
could do nothing of ourselves. Whatever might be <lb/>
said to the contrary, he thought that connection with <lb/>
the New Dominion would obtain for us benefits <lb/>
which could not get of ourselves if we remained <lb/>
out in the cold. He begged therefore to support the <lb/>
paragraph before the House. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KEAR1">Mr. KEARNEY</persName> was glad to hear that the <lb/>
question of the French Shore was drawing <lb/>
towards a settlement, which woull be favorable <lb/>
to the interests of the people of this country, <lb/>
and that his Excellency was prepared to issue <lb/>
licenses of search on that part of the island. <lb/>
He (Mr. K.) could not deny that the potatoe <lb/>
crop of last summer was a good one, but of <lb/>
what use was that to the thousands of poor <lb/>
people who had no seed, and were now perish<lb break="no"/>ing for the want of potatoes or other food? He <lb/>
did not want the Government to break through <lb/>
the Proclamation which they had issued, but he <lb/>
would he glad to see the people furnished with <lb/>
some employment which would enable them to <lb/>
earn their bread. If a ship, with a large num<lb break="no"/>ber of people on board, was known to be in <lb/>
distress, would there not be a great cry against <lb/>
any one who would refuse to render her all the <lb/>
assistance in his power? To allow them to <lb/>
perish for want of assistance would be a disgrace <lb/>
to the country; and could it not be as disgrace<lb break="no"/>ful, if not much more so to permit our own <lb/>
people to perish for want of timely aid? The <lb/>
people might have employment in preparing <lb/>
for the repairs of the roads, when the time <lb/>
comes. They might now be employed in the <lb/>
hauling of sand over the snow to such places as <lb/>
it will be required when the season opens. <lb/>
That is work which can be done now much <lb/>
better than in the summer. The people of St. <lb/>
John's might be employed in hauling building <lb/>
stone and ballast, which would always be valu<lb break="no"/>able, and which is in plenty on the South Side <lb/>
Hill. The people of Portugal Cove might be <lb/>
employed in repairing their breakwater and so <lb/>
giving them a place of refuge, and enabling <lb/>
them to give up their present miserable punt <lb/>
fishery. Witless Bay is a wild place, but there <lb/>
is a Fond on the east side of it and by cutting <lb/>
through a few yards of beach, it could be made <lb/>
available as a splendid harbor. To repair <lb/>
Toad's Cove Breakwater and finish the Stone <lb/>
Bridge at Brigus South, build a wooden bridge <lb/>
at Riverhead, Cape Broyle, and at Riverhead, <lb/>
Caplin Bay, would furnish employment, to a <lb/>
good many people in these localites. Again, <lb/>
the main beach at Ferryland might be staked <lb/>
and walled, so as to prevent the sand from <lb/>
entirely choking up the Pool. The Bar at <lb/>
Renews, of which he (Mr. K.) had so often <lb/>
spoken, might also be attended to. A great <lb/>
deal of property had been lost there for want of <lb/>
his recommendation being attended to. All <lb/>
these matters would give employment to the <lb/>
people; and he begged the Government to give <lb/>
employment to those who so sorely needed it, <lb/>
and not bring disgrace on the country by per<lb break="no"/>mitting any of its people to die of want. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:PROW1">Mr. PROWSE</persName> must say that the hon. member, Mr. <lb/>
        Hogsett, was the most consistent member of the <lb/>
        opposition on this question of the necessity for the <lb/>
        Proclamation. On the first day of the session he <lb/>
        and the gallant Major claimed all the credit of <lb/>
        having forced the Government into issuing the <lb/>
        Proclmation. The whole thing was thier work <lb/>
        and they were justly proud of the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
        of party discipline are strong <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> of the <lb/>
        opposition as death <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> is a <lb/>
        
        <cb/>
        
        persistent of claiment of pauper relief for his District, <lb/>
        and he has made all his party follow his views and <lb/>
        bow their necks to his yoke. He, Mr. Prowse, <lb/>
        gave the hon. member, Mr. Glen, credit for <lb/>
        "educating his party;" his skill in party discipline <lb/>
        must be great indeed, when, in the course of three <lb/>
        short days, he can so manipulate his followers as to <lb/>
        make them ignominously eat their words. No man <lb/>
        could oppose pauperism more vohemently or sustain <lb/>
        the Proclamtion more ardently than did the hon. <lb/>
        member, Mr. Little, and the gallant Major, the <lb/>
        Secretary of the Mendicity Work House. Why, his <lb/>
        position there was a living testimony against pauper<lb break="no"/>ism, and yet the Major foregoes that proud position <lb/>
        here, to become a mere pauper agent. If ever there <lb/>
        was an honest act done by any Government, or by <lb/>
        any party in this Colony, surely it was the issuing <lb/>
        of this Proclamation. No popularity could be <lb/>
        gained by it, and every harsh feeling amongst a <lb/>
        starving population could easily excited by <lb/>
        unscrupulous demagogues, against a Government <lb/>
        attempting it. He, Mr. Prowse, considered it was <lb/>
        the duty of every right thinking man in the com<lb break="no"/>munity to aid the Government in their honest and <lb/>
        sincere endeavours to suppress so demoralizing a <lb/>
        system. The Government deserve credir for <lb/>
        resisting the pressure put upon them in this mat<lb break="no"/>ter, and they get credit for it. Every good and <lb/>
        generous citizen will aid the Government by his <lb/>
        private charity, and cheer them on in their whole <lb/>
        work. This question is now of the most vital <lb/>
        importance to the Colony. Our financial integrity, <lb/>
        our social morality, almost our very existence as a <lb/>
        civilized community, depend upon the issue of this <lb/>
    trial. Pauperism with us is not an epidemic; it is <lb/>
a chronic disease; it ruins our credit, demoralizes <lb/>
our people, saps the energy of every man who <lb/>
once receives the pauper's dole, and utterly destroys <lb/>
those manly independent, feelings and those habits <lb/>
of selfreliance without which no people can pros<lb break="no"/>per. This demoralizing system has dried up <lb/>
the fountains of private charity in the outports. <lb/>
Everywhere government, meal has more or less <lb/>
choked up the springs of individual benevolence. <lb/>
He (Mr. P.) believed that no industrious, thrifty <lb/>
man need be a pauper in this country. Last fall he <lb/>
had been in the District of Ferryland. He travelled <lb/>
pver the worst road he had ever seen in Newfound<lb break="no"/>land, from Ferryland to Broad Cove, near Cape <lb/>
Bollard; and in Broad Cove he saw an example of <lb/>
what industry and thrift could, do. He stayed in <lb/>
Broad Cove with a man who had brought up a family <lb/>
of nine daughters and three sons, in plenty and com<lb break="no"/>fort. He fad acquired, by his own hard industry <lb/>
25 cows and 32 sheep. The had cleared land enough <lb/>
to support his stock. He had them ashore 148 qtlst <lb/>
fish, and during the month of November, he caught <lb/>
40 qis. more. He bought everything, at cash <lb/>
prices, and got the highest price for his fish. For <lb/>
30 years he had never owed a merchant a shilling. <lb/>
Now, how was it this man throve, whilst his neigh<lb break="no"/>bours in the same little harbor, with the wealth of the <lb/>
land around them, were miserable paupers? <lb/>
Of a laward day they lay in bed, whilst he worked <lb/>
at his land. When bait could not be got, they <lb/>
idled away their time ashore. He kept a stock of <lb/>
clam bait in the little stream that ran through his <lb/>
land, always ready for such an emergency. His <lb/>
daughters cured all his fish, made his bay and worked <lb/>
at everything on his farm. None in his house eat <lb/>
the bread of idleness. Consequently they were <lb/>
prosperous and contented, whilst in any of his neigh<lb break="no"/>bours were beggars. Everywhere in Newfoundland <lb/>
the same results can be seen. The independent man <lb/>
always makes a voyage. The dependent one is always <lb/>
behind. He (Mr.P.) never heard a good man in <lb/>
this country who did not denounce paper relief, and <lb/>
he regretted very much to see the present position <lb/>
of the hon. member, Mr. Renouf, on this question. <lb/>
Was it the duty of the opposition simply to denounce, <lb/>
abuse, and revile individual members of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment? He (Mr. P.) had heard pretty much the <lb/>
same speech from the hon member, Mr. Renouf, for <lb/>
the last four years, as to one delivered to dry. He <lb/>
could tell beforehand where the hon. member, Mr. <lb/>
Shea, would come in, where the Reciever General <lb/>
would be denounced, and where the late member <lb/>
for St. John's West, Mr. John Casey, would be <lb/>
flagellated. He knew the address and the prophe<lb break="no"/>sies of the members for St. John's West by heart. <lb/>
They were a couple of political Jeremians. They <lb/>
always prophesied evil things and they rejoiced <lb/>
now that evil days had come upon us. He (Mr. P.) <lb/>
considered it was the duty of every hon. mnember to <lb/>
this house to assist in every plan for whe regenera<lb break="no"/>tion on the country. He considered that the addres <lb/>
was a most reasonable address, and he was astonished <lb/>
at the opposition's finding fault with it. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName>.—Why did you not mention <lb/>
Reciprocity in the address? <lb/></p>
    
   <p> 
    <persName ref="pers:PROW1">Mr. PROWSE</persName>.—Because Confederation em<lb break="no"/>braced it. Reciprocity was a necessary appen<lb break="no"/>dix to Confederation. The only possible question <lb/>
that could arise on the address was as regards <lb/>
the first part of the paragraph on Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. If we agreed that the time was now <lb/>
arrived for us to consider terms, all the rest <lb/>
followed as a logical sequence, He (Mr. P.) <lb/>
regretted the position in which hon. members <lb/>
opposite wereplacing themselves on this question <lb/>
of union. In their hearts they were favourable <lb/>
to it, but out of deference to the prejudices of <lb/>
ignorance they were going to use it as a party <lb/>
question. Confederation, in this country, never <lb/>
ought to be a party question. It involves the <lb/>
interests of the whole eountry too deeply and <lb/>
too seriously to be treated in that way. The <lb/>
whole House should join in this address, should <lb/>
agree on the terms, and should be represented <lb/>
on the Delegation. Of course, it cannot be so <lb/>
if the paragraph is opposed, and the terms are <lb/>
only agreed to on one side. Confederation had <lb/>
not been fairly treated by its opponents in this <lb/>
country. Every prejudice had been unscrupu<lb break="no"/>lously stirred up against it. Fortunately the bleach<lb break="no"/>ing bones and ther oppressive taxation cry had <lb/>
been killed out by the incontrovertible logic of <lb/>
facts—but the Union of Ireland still remained, <lb/>
though there was not one point of similarity <lb/>
between the Union of Ireland and Confederation. <lb/>
The sore that rankled most in the breast of an <lb/>
Irishman, as regards that Union, was the un<lb break="no"/>fairness with which Roman Catholics had been <lb/>
treated. The land tenure never raised his in<lb break="no"/>dignation half so much as the Irish Church <lb/>
       Establishment and the Catholic disabilities. <lb/>
       Now, thanks to poor D'Arcy McGee, even the <lb/>
       prejudices of the Roman Catholics as regards <lb/>
       sectarian education have been repected. Not <lb/>
       one of the evils complained of under the Union <lb/>
       of Ireland exists under the Dominion of Canada. <lb/>
       He (Mr. P.) wished the Opposition would <lb/>
       <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>the course he had mentioned, for Con<lb break="no"/>federation must <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>. The country were <lb/>
       <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/> 

<cb/>

    of Union, when they saw men like the hon. <lb/>
    members, Mr. Rorke and Mr. Rendell, large <lb/>
    mercantile houses like Ridley's and Munn's, <lb/>
    Baine, Johnston &amp; Co., and Tessier's, support<lb break="no"/>ing the measure. What interests had these <lb/>
    men except in the welfare of the country. The <lb/>
    prosperity of the Colony would be beneficial to <lb/>
    them, its depression thier loss. The conduct of <lb/>
    the Government toom, on the question, tended to <lb/>
    inspire public confidence in their honesty and <lb/>
sincerity. They had not forced Confederation <lb/>
in any way. There had been no undue haste <lb/>
or precipitancy. Such a question should be <lb/>
calmly and carefully considered. The course of <lb/>
procedure under the British North American <lb/>
Act will give us all these safeguards. There <lb/>
must be an arrangement of terms first; then an <lb/>
address from the new House elected to accept <lb/>
terms, another address from the Dominion Par<lb break="no"/>liament, and, finally, the approval of the Queen <lb/>
in Council. <lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName> was not a little astonished at the <lb/>
course taken by the Government with reference <lb/>
to this question of Confederation. To the clause <lb/>
in the address which was under consideration <lb/>
the opposition had proposed an amendment, and <lb/>
he (Mr. H.) defied the Government to show <lb/>
that it contained anything which ignored the <lb/>
necessity for this Proclamation. It only went <lb/>
to say that the Proclamation would be a good <lb/>
course if it had been followed by that which <lb/>
was suggested, not only by the opposition, but <lb/> 
by the whole House, that is, if the people had <lb/>
been unabled to cultivate the potatoe crop, <lb/>
which He (Mr. H.) contented was every thing <lb/>
to the poor man. The hon. member for Ferry <lb/>
land. Mr. Glen, had given a barrel of seed <lb/>
potatoes to a man in his District. That man <lb/>
had seven children. He planted the barrel of <lb/>
potatoes. He had to sell his fish green, and in <lb/>
September commenced digging them for the <lb/>
support of himself, and his family.— <lb/>
They lived on them until October, when after <lb/>
all, they dug 15 barrels out of the ground. <lb/>
He (Mr. H.) did not attack the Proclamation. <lb/>
He was always for putting the people of the <lb/>
country on their own mettle. They, would <lb/>
then be independent and clear of all influence. <lb/>
It was the system he attacked, for it was made <lb/>
use of for party purposes, and not for the poor. <lb/>
On his side of the House they were willing to <lb/>
aid and assist in a strict superision of the relief. <lb/>
The poor should be relieved, which not at the <lb/>
expense of the industrious. He felt sure that <lb/>
no man in the House would permit a poor man <lb/>
to starve, no matter by what means starvation <lb/>
had been brought on him. He (Mr. H.) was <lb/>
not a pauper agent, and never would be one. <lb/>
        He had sought to teach his people that the surest <lb/>
        way to independence was to rely on themselves, <lb/>
and could now point to his district as the <lb/>
most independent in the island. This question <lb/>
of pauper relief was not a party question. It <lb/>
was one which they should deal with like men. <lb/>
He (Mr. H.) disagreed with the system as it is. <lb/>
The hon. and learaed Attorney General knew <lb/>
that he disagreed to the giving of the Road great <lb/>
to the able-bodied poor. The people didn't care <lb/>
where the relief comes from, so as they get it. <lb/>
It may have been well intended as a cheek, but <lb/>
it had been productive of more evil than any <lb/>
other scheme. It had stopped all public im<lb break="no"/>provement; and were those who tried to be in<lb break="no"/>dustrious to lose all the benefit of their exer<lb break="no"/>tions because others chose to be idle? For him<lb break="no"/>self he hoped that while the Government would <lb/>
cheek all imposition, they would allow no man <lb/>
to die. If there were a proper serveillance, <lb/>
the really poor would get relief, whilst the in<lb break="no"/>dolent, and those who did not require it, would <lb/>
not. He would not then travel into the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of Confederation. There will be a debate <lb/>
ween the clause referring to it comes up before <lb/>
them. When the terms were brought down <lb/>
he would be prepared to debate them, not in <lb/>
a factious spirit; but broadly, fairly,and square<lb break="no"/>ly on their merits. He would commit himself <lb/>
to no position until he had seen the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment programme. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:PROW1">Mr. PROWSE</persName> explained that the necessity for <lb/>
Poor Relief in his district was occasioned by the <lb/>
sudden withdrawal of a Mercantile Establishment to <lb/>
which the people had been in the habit of looking <lb/>
for their winter's subsistence. The outlay was <lb/>
almost entirely confined to the locality where this <lb/>
establishment was situated. The hon. member <lb/>
commented at considerable length on the demoraliz<lb break="no"/>ing effects of the issue of seed potatoes, which he <lb/>
characterized as an aggravation of chronic pauperism, <lb/>
and the very worst form of the pauper grant. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:OREI2">Mr. O'REILLY</persName> did not deny that the Government <lb/>
were entitled to great credit for having, thus far <lb/>
refrained from the issue of Poor Relief. He (Mr. <lb/>
O'R.) was member for an Outport district, where <lb/>
poverty and misery were peculiarly rife, and conse<lb break="no"/>quently he was intimately concerned in this matter. <lb/>
In his own district no less than six deaths from <lb/>
downright starvation had taken place; not from any <lb/>
epidemic disorder, not from the diseases incident to <lb/>
an inclement season, but from sheer hunger, and all <lb/>
these had occurred within a circuit of ten miles <lb/>
from Isle Valen. And these, he was assured, were <lb/>
not the only cases, for he was convinced that they <lb/>
must have since multiplied six fold. So far the <lb/>
Government had vindicated their own credit. By <lb/>
the contumacious imposition which had been practised <lb/>
they were goaded into the issue of this Proclamation, <lb/>
but having gone so far, he did not think that they <lb/>
should go any further. He could not shut his heart <lb/>
against the pitiful appeals of those whom he knew <lb/>
to be dying in his own district. The people had <lb/>
with difficulty tided over the inclemency of last <lb/>
winter. In the spring they were but scantily pro<lb break="no"/>vided for, they were alive, but they were naked and <lb/>
utterly unable to prosecute the fishery, with that <lb/>
energy which would secure them a subsistence for <lb/>
the winter. Under these circumstances poverty and <lb/>
        hunger were necessary results, and he now appealed <lb/>
        to the Government, and added his voice to the <lb/>
        numerous supplications for the issue of a little relief. <lb/>
        He felt the awkwardness of his position. Hitherto <lb/>
        he had been a consistent supporter of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, but he felt that he would be recreant to his <lb/>
        duty if he did not make this appeal to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and express his dissent from the wording of <lb/>
        the paragraph before the chair. <lb/></p> 
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> could not forbear to <lb/>
        <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> the remarks of the hon. <lb/>
        <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> He was surprised <lb/>
        
<cb/>

    to hear that destination prevailed in the locality <lb/>
        referred to by the hon. member. A large amount <lb/>
        of relief was last year conveyed thither and no re<lb break="no"/>turn had never been made. There was a supplying <lb/>
        merchant resident there and surely he, when he <lb/>
        recieved the benefit of these poor men's services, <lb/>
        should in some substantial manner display his sympa<lb break="no"/>thy with their distress. There is really no part of <lb/>
        this island so capable of sustaining a population as <lb/>
        the district of Placentia and St. Mary's. There <lb/>
        exists the most fertile land in the country. There <lb/>
        the industrious man can find fish almost at his door. <lb/>
        And yet that fertile land has been lying untilled and <lb/>
        almost calling aloud for cultivation. It stands in <lb/>
        cold contrast to the sterile land of the Northern <lb/>
        districts, where the people are now sustaining them<lb break="no"/>selves. But the people of Placentia would risk <lb/>
        their lives upon the chance of what little sustain<lb break="no"/>ment they could get from the Government rather <lb/>
        than exert themselves to their own permanent <lb/>
        independence. Only last session there were three <lb/>
        thousand barrels of flour distributed among the <lb/>
        people of that district through the wreck of the <lb/>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Summer</hi>, and hardly a man of locality but got a <lb/>
        barrel. There should not have been a single man <lb/>
        but must have been in a position to commence the <lb/>
        fishery infinitely superior to the men of other districts. <lb/>
        The same pressure was last year attempted to be <lb/>
        brought to bear upon the Government, although in <lb/>
        addition to the flour so obatined, some £3000 worth <lb/>
        of Pauper Relief was distributed in the district. <lb/>
        He (hon. A.G.) had as much sympathy for the suf<lb break="no"/>fering poor as any man. He would go to any legi<lb break="no"/>timate extent to assist them. He hoped that the <lb/>
Road money of the people might be preserved for <lb/> 
them, for a purpose which he had in view. He <lb/>
He wished to provide against, the necessity which <lb/>
compelled the poor to sell their greenfish at an <lb/>
enormous sacrifice, leaving then nothing for the <lb/> 
sustainment of their families, and it was with a view <lb/>
to the prevention of this state of things that he <lb/>
hoped to get the sustainment of hon. members in <lb/>
the course which he had marked out. From Twil<lb break="no"/>lingate every possible pressure was brought to bear <lb/>
upon the Executive. Petition after petition was <lb/>
sent in, and a grave responsibility devolved upon <lb/>
the Ministry. In a very short time all communica<lb break="no"/>tion with this district would be cut off by ice. <lb/>
Nevertheless the Government felt it to be their <lb/>
duty to resist these appeals, and the consequence <lb/>
was, that not only in this district, but in Bona vista <lb/>
and even in Trinity Bay, where it was found that <lb/>
the Government were resolute in their intentions, <lb/>
persons were found to come forward to the relief <lb/>
of the destitute. In his own district two Vigilance <lb/>
Committees had been appointed, and the people had <lb/>
taken upon themselves the task of assisting he dis<lb break="no"/>tressed. Hon members would find that if there <lb/>
were a proper resistance to all appeals, for a suffi<lb break="noi"/>cient length of time, the people of the country <lb/>
would be for the first time in a long series of years <lb/>
in a position of comparative independence. He <lb/>
(hon. A.G.) was well aware that individuals, for <lb/>
interested motives, attempted to get up an outcry as <lb/>
to the prevailing destitution, in order to force the <lb/>
Government into the issue of relief, that these agi<lb break="no"/>tators might profit by the large sales on meal and <lb/>
        molasses which would necessasily follow. The peo<lb break="no"/>ple themselves were well disposed and well con<lb break="no"/>ducted, and it any <hi rendition="simple:italic">emente</hi> should take place, it <lb/>
would be found, upon enquiry, that these interested <lb/>
parties were at the bottom of it. It would be very <lb/>
desirable that the really destitute should be relieved; <lb/>
but there can be no check against imposture, and the <lb/>
moment you begin the infernal system it becomes <lb/>
general, and you cannot distinguish between the <lb/>
impostor and the deserving poor. But there war, <lb/>
besides these difficulties, another and a paramount <lb/>
obstacle. The Colony has not the funds at its dis<lb break="no"/>posal sufficient to meet this demand. There had <lb/>
been the greatest care manifested to keep the ex<lb break="no"/>penditure within the Legislative grants; but still <lb/>
the drain upon the Revenue had been so enormous <lb/>
as to put it beyond the power of the Government, <lb/>
even if they had the desire, to renew the issue of <lb/>
relief. He (hon. A.G.) gave the hon, member, Mr. <lb/>
O'Rielly, credit for sincerity; but he could not <lb/>
help thinking that sufficient care had not been taken <lb/>
to impress upon the people the nature of this <lb/>
Proclamation. If that bad been effectually done, <lb/>
he did not believe that this pressure would have <lb/>
been brought to bear upon the hon member. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:OREI2">Mr. O'REILLY</persName> explained that though it was <lb/>
true that the people of the district obtained <lb/>
some 3000 barrels of flour from the wreck to <lb/>
which the hon. Attorney General alluded, yet <lb/>
this flour was scattered over some 5,000 peo<lb break="no"/>ple. A very small portion could be the share <lb/>
of any individual. It was wrong too to suppose <lb/>
that Placentia had received the whole of it. A <lb/>
large number of the people were at the time <lb/>
absent at St. Peter's, and thus received no <lb/>
benefit whatsoever from this distribution. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:RORK2">Mr. RORKE</persName>.—Although he had listened with <lb/>
great attention to the speeches of hon. gen<lb break="no"/>telemen opposite, he had been unable to come <lb/>
to any other conclusion than that they were <lb/>
a mere rehash of the same speechs which, <lb/>
for three or four sessions, we had been in <lb/>
the habit of hearing. The paragraph before <lb/>
the chair says that the proclamation has been <lb/>
well timed. It might be well timed, but he <lb/>
thought it would have been better timed had <lb/>
it been adopted 25 years ago. Had that <lb/>
been so, he believed that the distress now so <lb/>
universal would not have been the hundredth <lb/>
part of what is. He remembered the intro<lb break="no"/>duction of this system. He was personally <lb/>
aware of the imposture which was then at<lb break="no"/>tempted, imposture which had continued ever <lb/>
since, and he was firmly convinced that were <lb/>
it not for that proclamation the thing would <lb/>
never have come to an end. It might be <lb/>
    asked how the poor were to be relieved.— <lb/>
    As far as he could, he had assisted the desti<lb break="no"/>tute. God forbid that he should see the people <lb/>
starve, without extending to then a helping <lb/>
hand. But he could not forget the lesson which <lb/>
the Cotton Famine in England had taught <lb/>
wealthy people came forward and organised a <lb/>
fund by which the operatives of Lancashire <lb/>
were sustained against a pressure far worse <lb/>
than any we have ever experienced. He (Mr. <lb/>
R.) had looked to hon members opposite for a <lb/>
    display of sympathy for the poor struggling men. <lb/>
    Were hon members going to drag down such <lb/>
    men? The Government has been taunted on <lb/>
    account of the immense taxation which they <lb/>
    have been considered to impose. For his part <lb/>
    he (Mr. R.) had been one who had <lb/>
    assisted in imposing this taxation. To <lb/>
    him and many others who acknowledged <lb/>
the necessary for it, it had proved a better pill; <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">[SEE SECOND PAGE]</p>

    <!-- IC, 2019-01-25, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>Mr. GLEN gave antice th: <lb/>
would ask the hon. Colonial S <lb/>
of the amount expended by <lb/>
for relief of the able bodied po <lb/>
joistrict. viz.:<lb break="no"/>Amount expended by-L <lb/>
** " by Wm." <lb/>
tº a ** by M. w <lb/>
The following motices, give <lb/>
the ºssion, were accidentully <lb/>
of that day's proceedings: <lb/>
Mr. Taibor gave notice th <lb/>
would mºve that the salary <lb/>
Arms, shall not exceed the ºut <lb/>
Mr. Tºor also gave notice <lb/>
he would move tiiąt the report <lb/>
of the Jebates of the Ho <lb/>
ºd for, be discontinued. <lb/>
Air. TALBor also gave notice <lb/>
he will asz leave to uring in <lb/>
present office of Surveyor Gen <lb/>
for the Lat,d St rvices by. Sº <lb/>
duties of the Chairman of th: <lb/>
Pursuant to Order of the #23 <lb/>
sd itself into Committee of th <lb/>
dress of thanks, Mr. KNight it <lb/>
The fourth section of the <lb/>
read, as follows:<lb break="no"/>ºws are pleased to learn thi <lb/>
personal exºrtions in sudº' <lb/>
Wººd question of the Franch <lb/>
far successful that there is do <lb/>
b-ing arranged in a manº." <lb/>
irºs interested in it, and the <lb/>
ºd in Lord Carnarvon's despatc <lb/>
bºr, isé5, has been so far no <lb/>
cellency wil now be euabled t <lb/>
Jerain restr ctions for Mining <lb/>
in that locality." <lb/>
Hºn. Recºlvº Gºssean<lb break="no"/>in ſº world's history, and not <lb/>
ticular country. Sweep your ey <lb/>
we inhabit, you there obsery" " <lb/>
that must al...rm and surprise <lb/>
The very crust that envºº, <lb/>
sºns tº be worn out by tº <lb/>
cºntral fires. Haitliquake", to <lb/>
ºut and suddenly ºugºlph n <lb/>
ºn but man buuseif. Vulcanº <lb/>
these cultral fires, are lou: <lb/>
S. orals sweep the ocea" and <lb/>
argoles that carº "Pºº its b <lb/>
tile treasures and the men whe <lb/>
is circumscribe our view and re <lb/>
what do we see? The stalwar <lb/>
country ſleeing from its shurus, <lb/>
*re stricken with poverty and d <lb/>
self-reliance. Widows weeping <lb/>
who have been torn from then <lb/>
their sons who iave been untinº <lb/>
children looking in vain for,t <lb/>
never again return to caress the <lb/>
did not speak of these things <lb/>
foºtºring aespair. He still, sº <lb/>
the elements of wealth which it <lb/>
Her fisheries wore liable to be a <lb/>
New elements of wealth prete <lb/>
capitalists are anxious to explº <lb/>
as this we surely ought not to <lb/>
and teleper in impruti able an 1 <lb/>
That was why he spoke of thes <lb/>
l, stated these circumstances w <lb/>
every one acquainted with the <lb/>
Tº those who feel with the g <lb/>
tufferings of the pcople, it must <lb/>
as Representatives of the p <lb/>
trusted the serious cars of sea <lb/>
of the unsfºrtunes of the peo <lb/>
passionately to , the consider <lb/>
enable us to embody in Legi <lb/>
processes which will in some <lb/>
overwhelming afflictions. . Af <lb/>
which he hoped hon. gentleme <lb/>
exaggerated, he would enter <lb/>
the substantial matters containe <lb/>
speech. The first importan <lb/>
itself is the circumstance that <lb/>
aken upon themselves the resa <lb/>
His Excellancy to issue a Prº <lb/>
the issue, of Poor Relief to , <lb/>
infirm. He (hon. R. G.) had <lb/>
£ousequences of indiscriminate <lb/>
bodied poor. IIe had foreseei. <lb/>
the population of self-reliance, <lb/>
the peºple, and drag down <lb/>
the indus'rious men. ºf the I <lb/>
this subject had been repeated <lb/>
and their publication had sub <lb/>
and ultinately to the loss of <lb/>
le had the satisfaction of seei <lb/>
time every one recognized thi <lb/>
upon those principles which ht <lb/>
time laid dow; tı. In 1868 this <lb/>
nate relief reached its culmina <lb/>
nearly a quarter of a taillion <lb/>
expended, it was high time for <lb/>
its band. It required great h <lb/>
supporters of the Government <lb/>
sufive policy, and it was high <lb/></p> 

<p>hunger were necessary results, and he now appealed <lb/></p> 

<p>mitting any of its people to die of want. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Prowse must say that the hon. member, Mr. <lb/>
Hogsett, was the most censistent member of the <lb/>
opposition on this question of the lºssly for the <lb/></p> 

<p>: Establishment and the Catholic disabilities. <lb/>
'Now, thanks to poor D'Arcy McGee, even the <lb/>
prºjudices of the Roman Catholics as regards <lb/>
sºciarian education have been respected. Not <lb/></p> 

<p>jon. On the first day of ºn assion he "one of the evils complained of under the Union <lb/></p> 

<p>and the gallant Majºr claim. all the credit of <lb/></p> 

<p>of Ireland exists under the Ocm.nion of Canada. <lb/></p> 

<p>having forced the Government into issuing the He (Mr. P.) wished the Opposition would <lb/></p> 

<p>Proclamation. <lb/>
and they were just 3 1: Judo <lb/>
of party discipline, a * strº <lb/>
opposition is dea: , J . . ac 1. -\-\-\-\-" - " <lb/></p> 

<p>l, <lb/></p> 

<p>The whole thing was their work, <lb/>
ti.e. ex:ge:Mcle: <lb/>
i..., r vi ta: <lb/></p> 

<p>lic is a <lb/></p> 

<p>toy the course he had mentioned, for Con<lb break="no"/>derat. ,a ul is; co-a . 1. <lb/>
L. 1.- ..g to sº tie. "Yes -: *** * * Lt.- ... 3 <lb/></p> 

<p>cou ... y wº: e | <lb/></p> 

<p>to the Government, and added his voice to the <lb/>
numerous supplications for the issue of a little relief. <lb/>
He felt the awkwariness of his position. Hituerto <lb/>
he had been a consistent supporter of the Govern<lb break="no"/>tment, but he felt that he would be recreant to hfs <lb/></p> 

<p>auty if he did not make this appeal to the Govern­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ment, anu express his dissent from the wording of <lb/>
the paragrapu before. tae cuair. <lb/>
Hon. Attorney fºrm ºf could not forbear to <lb/>
u) is: - . . . . . .ie relia arres of t is 3 tº on. <lb/>
- ...its. ... ca. 3., wu, lie was surprised <lb/></p> 

<p>display of sympathy for the poor struggling me": <lb/>
Were hon members going to drag dowu su". <lb/>
men? The government has beea taunted on <lb/>
account of the immense taxation, which th9% <lb/>
have been constrained to inpose." Fºr his par% <lb/>
he (Mr. R.J. had been one whº haſ, <lb/>
assisted in imposing this taxation. ." <lb/>
him, and many others, who acknowledged <lb/>
was n.ºssily for it, it had proved a bitter Pº <lb/>
[see Szcusp PAG. J <lb/></p> 

<p>Matthey haidone so,and hon t <lb/>
one or two exceptions, had y <lb/>
to the necessity of the act. <lb/>
which attention is called is th <lb/>
£ghts of the French Süore. <lb/></p> 

<p>it. G.) had crossed the Atlan <lb/>
5t-terviews with the Juke of t <lb/>
made piciaises which he had <lb/></p>

<pb n="3" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-10_Page_3.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">3</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>

<p rendition="simple:centre">[CONTINUED FROM PAGE.]</p>
    
    <p>
and in many of the provisions by which it was <lb/>
        effected he would wish to see it sottened down— <lb/>
        If, then, this taxation should be continued, and <lb/>
continued it must be if Government should <lb/>
yield to the pressure of hon. members, the necessa<lb break="no"/>ry effect will be that the struggling man will be <lb/>
brought to a level with the pauper. But not <lb/>
one word of sympathy do we hear for this class, <lb/>
and not one word of sympathy for the supplying <lb/>
merchant, who, after losing principal and inter<lb break="no"/>est, upon the supplies he issues, loses the heavy <lb/>
duties which he has paid, and often, loses his <lb/>
capital into the bargain. He believed that <lb/>
all the evils of the country took their rise from <lb/>
the credit system, which bears as heavily as <lb/>
slavery upon the people, and which has brought <lb/>
ruin, not only to the supplying, but to the sup<lb break="no"/>plied. The faith between parties was broken <lb/>
down, and if the system could be done away <lb/>
with all classes would be benefitted. As to Con<lb break="no"/>federation, his (Mr. R's) sentiments were well <lb/>
known. He had besa favorable to it even <lb/>
before he became a member of this House, and <lb/>
he was still convinced that it would prove <lb/>
beneficial to the country. But he did not be<lb break="no"/>lieve that it would wipe away pauperism all at <lb/>
once. Even after Confederation became ac<lb break="no"/>complished. We should still have to contend <lb/>
with pauperism. But there was a growing <lb/>
opinion among all classes in favour of the <lb/>
scheme, and in his own district many of the <lb/>
leading men had come completely round, and <lb/>
many would accept Confederation even on the <lb/>
terms of the Quebec Convention. However, <lb/>
he merely touched upon this subject in passing. <lb/>
He was still of the opinion that a union with <lb/>
Canada upon equitable terms could not fail to <lb/>
prove advantageous to us. The matter before <lb/>
the chair was was upon which every hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber should express his opinion. For his part he <lb/>
gave his cordial adherence to the course adopt<lb break="no"/>ed by the Government in offering a resolute <lb/>
resistance to the resumption of pauper relief. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName>—The Government of Sir <lb/>
Hugh Hoyles gave more scope to Pauper <lb/>
Relief than any other Government, in this <lb/>
country. The Opposition were not the origi<lb break="no"/>nators of pauperism, and the population they <lb/>
represented was the best in Newfoundland. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:RORK2">Mr. RORKE</persName>—It was fifteen years old then. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>Mr. H. was not in the habit of telling lies. It <lb/>
was too much truth he told. It was because he <lb/>
told the truth that he evoked the hostility of <lb/>
hon. members and of other men. For the in<lb break="no"/>formation of the hon. member, Mr. Rorke, he <lb/>
would tell him that if the policy of Mr. Kent's <lb/>
government had been carried out he would <lb/>
not be dealing in pauper relief. It had not <lb/>
been chronic. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:BENN3">Mr. BENNETT</persName> wished to say a few words in <lb/>
sustainment of the position which the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had assumed upon the question of <lb/>
poor relief. He believed, and the Opposition <lb/>
or at least those of them who were candid and <lb/>
sensible men, would admit that in this matter <lb/>
the Government had been actuated by no <lb/>
political motive. The Government were as <lb/>
certain to be sustained in the course they had <lb/>
taken, by the intelligent and independent, as <lb/>
they were certain to receive the disapprobation <lb/>
        of all those who looked to then for support—<lb/>
        and as the latter class was far the more <lb/>
numerous one, they must of course expect <lb/>
that the disapprobation would be the greater. <lb/>
The Government were, however, sustained by <lb/>
conscious rectitude—by the knowledge that <lb/>
they had done what was right and proper. <lb/>
        He felt proud of the stand which the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had taken, for it was a noble one—<lb/>
        and had to be taken at some time. It was a <lb/>
matter of contention where and by whom <lb/>
the system of poor relief to the able-<lb break="yes"/>bodied had been introduced and who was to <lb/>
blame for it. He (Mr. B.) was too young a <lb/>
member of this Assembly to know himself, but <lb/>
        nothing was certain, it was <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> as that the very <lb/>
vitals of the country. He considered that it <lb/>
was stopped at a very good time, though for <lb/>
himself he must say that he would have desried <lb/>
to have seen it done some three years ago. It <lb/>
became plain to every man that sooner or later <lb/>
this system must have au end, and what time <lb/>
could be better for stopping it than when there <lb/>
wasa prospect of a fair fishery? That was the case <lb/>
last year. Last winter when poor relief was <lb/>
given out and the packet frozen up in Placentia <lb/>
Bay and the Ariel at the Northward he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) felt that it was indeed a trying <lb/>
time. Many families to the Westward <lb/>
supported themselves by Herrings, alone. <lb/>
He (Mr. B.) would indeed be sorry that the <lb/>
Government should let any man starve. This <lb/>
poor relief system was something like a man <lb/>
with a chronic desease. He meets a surgeon <lb/>
who says if the affected part is cut of you will <lb/>
live, otherwise you die. He submits to the <lb/>
operation. He keenly feels the cutting of the <lb/>
knife as it divided the tissues, sinews, and <lb/>
veins; but in a few days the anguish passes away; <lb/>
he is a new man and he blesses the surgeon who <lb/>
sould not have saved him without making him <lb/>
suffer for a time. The poor relief system bore the <lb/>
same analogy to the Government that the dis<lb break="no"/>ease did to the man. The people would no <lb/>
doubt suffer a little, but it was for their ultimate <lb/>
good. He had much pleasure in giving cordial <lb/>
support to paragraph before the chair. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The motion that the second paragraph be adop<lb break="no"/>ted, was then put and carried. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The Committee then rose, and reported pro<lb break="no"/>gress. To sit again to-morrow. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The House then adjourned until to-morrow <lb/>
at 8 o'clock. <lb/></p> -->


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-25, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

<!--<p>FRIDAY, February 6, <lb/></p> 

<p>The House met at 3 o'clock, pursuant to adjourn­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ment. <lb/>
Mr. Gººs complained that his speech of Weines: <lb/>
day fast bad not been properly regurºd; Talking <lb/>
of the poor relief he had said ºf be did not find su <lb/>
much liait witu tae Proclai...ºu as **** peech <lb/>
... tº;:h it was known was <lb/></p> 

<p>-: * <lb/>
. . . . . . . . ** <lb/></p> 

<p>; T H E N E w F o UN D L A N D E R. <lb/></p> 

<p>*º <lb/></p> 

<p>been given. Surely the Executive were aware, that <lb/>
such was not the case, that a great portion of the <lb/>
people could not provide themselves with subsistence <lb/>
for the coming winter. They were completely des: <lb/>
titute until the fish came—numbers had to go with<lb break="no"/>out food to catch fish for their daily food. It was <lb/>
cruel to say that these men should provide, for the <lb/>
coming winter. How could they do it? That part <lb/>
of the speech was heartless. Most of these had no <lb/>
seed potatoes and had to live on their neighbors. <lb/>
He had also mentioned a circumstance which occur<lb break="no"/>red in the East Indies and it was not reported. <lb/>
There was a famine there and those who perished <lb/>
numbered by thousands. A telegram was sent to <lb/>
the Imperial Government. The Secretary for India <lb/>
immediately replied, authorising the use of the pub: <lb/>
lic funds to any amount for that they should not <lb/>
permit any British subject to starve. The merchants <lb/>
subscribed £10,000 and telegraphed that that money <lb/>
could be used and more iſ required... Not only was <lb/>
that sum provided for, but seed for the rice crop was <lb/>
distributed for the next year, and men were employ<lb break="no"/>ed to bring water from a long way off, so that no <lb/>
second failure should happen. That was a paternal <lb/>
Government and he wanted to contrast it with ours, <lb/>
which was going to allow the people to starve. The <lb/>
Imperial Government would, he (Mr. G.) felt sure; <lb/>
be much annoyed if any people here were allowed <lb/>
to perish. With the Imperial Government whites <lb/>
were as good as black, and he believed the people <lb/>
who were starving in India were blacks. . None of <lb/>
this had been reported, while the hon... and learned <lb/>
member for Brigus was reported at such length that <lb/>
every one was afraid to read it. <lb/>
Messrs. Hogsett, Talbot, and Renouf also.com<lb break="no"/>plained that their speeches were neither fully nor <lb/>
correctly reported. <lb/>
HoN. A. Shea.—From the conduct of hon mem<lb break="no"/>bers opposite, a stranger visiting this. Assembly <lb/>
would have considerable difficulty in ariving at the <lb/>
conclusion that it was convened for the transaction <lb/>
of important public business. The last two hours <lb/>
have been frittered away with the most puerile <lb/>
miserable feelings as to the reports and the Reporters. <lb/>
were hon gentlemen so uncertain of their status in <lb/>
the opinion of the public that they had only to rely <lb/>
upon the clap-trap denunciations, of the reports: <lb/>
which session after session they had been uttering * <lb/>
Surely hon gentlemen whose position was no strong <lb/>
as theirs, could very well afford even to allow their <lb/>
remarks to go unreported. For his hon (Mr S) part <lb/>
he would be willing to make a bargain with hon <lb/>
gentlemen, if the Reporters would only agree to <lb/>
publish every word of what hon members opposite <lb/>
said, he would be quite content that the Government <lb/>
should go unreported. The character of the Op<lb break="no"/>position would then speak for itself, and the public <lb/>
would say these gentlemen constitute the Opposition <lb/>
and in Opposition they should be left. It appeared <lb/>
then that the leadership of the Opposition had been <lb/>
changed, and he had tº congratulate the Opposition <lb/>
on the announcement lately made by the hon <lb/>
meinber Mr. Glen,that they were now a united body. <lb/>
that they had discarded the hon member Mr Hogsett; <lb/>
they had found him doubtless an able and an ener<lb break="no"/>getic leader, a very ene, getic leader, but he was the <lb/>
Jonah of the lot, and they had discovered that it was <lb/>
necessary to throw him overboard. . Well, they had <lb/>
east the hon. member overboard,and he (hon Mr.S) <lb/>
did not dispute their discretion. . For the last four <lb/>
years they bad the repatation of being rather un<lb break="no"/>harmonious, and the causes of this discord he hon (A. <lb/>
S) would endeavour to trace. Sons two years ego <lb/>
ths hon member (Mr Hogsett) discovered that <lb/>
something not very creditable was said of him in <lb/>
one of the Halifax papers. -<lb break="maybe"/>MR. Hogserr-e Yes, and you wrote it. You <lb/>
are a scoundrel. You always were a scoundrel. <lb/>
The hon. the SPEAxsit—So long as I have the <lb/>
privilege of maintaining order in this House, I shall <lb/>
not allow expressions such as this to pass unmarked <lb/>
by my disapproval, and if there be any approach to a <lb/>
repetition of them I shall certainly take the chair and <lb/>
use such means as are at the disposal of the House to <lb/>
prevent the recurrence of unseeuly language or to <lb/>
punish it. <lb/>
Hon. A. Snza—It is an extraordinary fact that <lb/>
those persons who are most free with insolent obser<lb break="no"/>vations cannot bear te have the pickled rod applied <lb/>
to their bare backs, wriggling and twisting and <lb/>
burning, they exhibit a 'most uneasy consciousness of <lb/>
their punishment. To proceed. The hon, gentle<lb break="no"/>man want to Halifax to windicate his reputation, but <lb/>
before going he called upon him (hon. A Shea) for a <lb/>
note of recominendation. He (bon. A Shea) was no <lb/>
very anxious to give the hon. member a note, for <lb/>
there in a certain class of persons whom one does no; <lb/>
cale to recommend; but he did not want to refusé <lb/>
and he gave the hon. member a note of that kind <lb/>
which a man gives when he would rather let it alone <lb/>
On the faith of that note, and one from the hon, <lb/>
Attorney General, the hon, member got into good <lb/>
company with which he beeane so enamoured that <lb/>
though he had left here a violent Anti Confederate, <lb/>
in one short fortnight he returned a rabid Confede<lb break="no"/>rate and denounced his party. The bon. member <lb/>
was impatient of any delay in the matter of Con<lb break="no"/>federation and even in Halifax he had pledged his <lb/>
word that as leader of the opposition he would have <lb/>
the whole matter arranged and delegates would be <lb/>
forthwith despatched to the convention then about <lb/>
to sit in Loudon. After that the hon, meumber <lb/>
had a travelling fit, and in his absence <lb/>
a great many ugly things were said of him by his <lb/>
friends. When he returned, we had what is popu<lb break="no"/>larly termed "wigs on the green." He came in in a <lb/>
temper; he said ugly things of his friends, we had <lb/>
very disgracelul scenes nearly every day, and the <lb/>
propinquity of the parties suggested the necessity of <lb/>
the police. For that session the hoa gentleman was <lb/>
adrift, and no approach to union was inade. This <lb/>
time the hon member was the scape-goat, that was <lb/>
episode No. 1 illustrative of the exceeding harmony <lb/>
of this united party. The next year the hon, inem<lb break="no"/>ber Mr. Parsons was the scapegoat. They discovered, <lb/>
he thought that they discovered that that hon gene <lb/>
tleman had been "raising the wind" somewhere, <lb/>
and it was just about the time that the hon and gallant <lb/>
Major was scouting that military appointment of bis, <lb/>
and in fact they were all hunting together. As the <lb/>
story goes the hon member. Mr Parsons doubled <lb/>
them ºil; what he got they did not know, but they <lb/>
strongly suspected that it was some of the stuff with <lb/>
which people buy butter. They said that he had used <lb/>
his share and be should not hunt with them again<lb break="no"/>They made things very uncomfortable for him and, <lb/>
his desk was actually put up with a broom upon it <lb/>
and a label "For Salé." Ultimately, this came to <lb/>
an end, and this was episode No. 2 in the harmony <lb/>
of the party. The fact is, thºt though they are so <lb/>
few in number, this eterual itching for something <lb/>
which is got on that side of the House, makes them <lb/>
all so jealous that they are determined that not one <lb/>
shall get before another. The real understanding <lb/>
between them is,in effect,not even as good as it looks <lb/>
At the present time they are threatening, vengeance <lb/>
npon some one else; and this is the harmouious <lb/>
party headed by the hon member Air Glen. The <lb/>
ion" and veutrable geutleman had undertaxen an <lb/>
onerous duty, and it his tenure of office depended <lb/></p> 

<p>"e speech ' tº <lb/></p> 

<p>ipoſ. the preservation of order anong his part, , he <lb/>
3 that it world soon be given in in <lb/></p> 

<p>disgust. We have lis: <lb/>
and circumstances which led to th <lb/>
the former leader. <lb/>
He jºid now refer to the Speech of the hon. <lb/>
member, Mr. Renouf, delivered last cwening; a <lb/>
speech which had been very properly . <lb/>
terised by the hon. Membºr for Carbonear, i <lb/>
Rorke, as one containing merely." rehash of 8. <lb/>
the old utterances to which we had been ". <lb/>
ing for the past ſour years. It wº made up 9 <lb/>
his staple topics, topics, which with him never <lb/>
die out, and without which he would be utterly <lb/>
unable to make a speech. All knew, whº these <lb/>
topics were; the Amalgamated Government, <lb/>
Cºnfederation, the hon. Receiver General and <lb/>
himself, (hon. Mr. S.) the late Chairman of <lb/>
the Board of Works, Mr. Casey, occasionally <lb/>
because he was an absent mº, * * for a <lb/>
share of vituperative abuse. Now suppose the <lb/>
Government and those connected with it deserv<lb break="no"/>j iſ the abuse which the abundant vocabulary <lb/>
of the hon. member heaped upon them; sup<lb break="no"/>pose all the charges which he had made were <lb/>
perfectly true, suppose that we wire all of that <lb/>
abandoned character which he describes, how <lb/>
does all that affect the question under considera. <lb/>
tion One would imagine that after having <lb/>
spent four years in abusing us, without strength<lb break="no"/>ening or elevating his own party in the eyes of <lb/>
the public, and without injury to the Governs <lb/>
ment, the hon. member would have made an <lb/>
effort to produce something original. Why did <lb/>
he not consult his colleague, and ask him to <lb/>
suggest something to make a strong impression? <lb/>
But no, it was the old story of the blind horse <lb/>
tarning the mill, and the effusions of the hon. <lb/>
member were so nauseating that they only serve <lb/>
ed to put hon. gentlemen on this side of the <lb/>
Honse asleep. Certainly there were some <lb/>
allowances to be made for the feelings of <lb/>
irritation under which hon. gentlemen opposite <lb/>
aboured. They had now been in opposition <lb/>
eight or nine years; and four years ago, when <lb/>
the queſtion of Confederation came before the <lb/>
country, they had great hopes of doing something <lb/>
for themselves. They fell in with the strong <lb/>
and popular side. They took the flowing tide, <lb/>
and year after year expected to see the Govern: <lb/>
ment mak some talse step, by which they would <lb/>
walk into office. They thought that the gool <lb/>
time was near at hand, that the promised land <lb/>
was in view, when they would be called upou to <lb/>
enjoy the exquisite delight of seeing the hon. <lb/>
member. Mr. Hogsett, once more Attorney Geº<lb break="no"/>eral, and once more the protector of ther rights <lb/>
and liberties. Things, however, were lookin...: <lb/>
gloomy with them of late. The feeling that exist<lb break="no"/>ed so strong two or three years ago had under<lb break="no"/>gone a complete change. The tide was slackeu: <lb/>
ing, and from present appearances, they feared: <lb/>
that the grand objects to which they had been look<lb break="no"/>ing forward were not likely to be effected.T ley saw <lb/>
that public opinion was not what it had been; <lb/>
that Confederation was not now the dreaded <lb/>
bugbear it had becn considered. Lately, in tile <lb/>
district of Harbor Grace, the supposed stronghºld <lb/>
of the Anti-Confederates, an important election <lb/>
had tazen place, an election that had resulted in <lb/>
the return to this House of a gentleinan plºdged to <lb/>
support Confederation. This was indeed a death<lb break="no"/>blow to the hopes of hun- melub:rs opposite<lb break="no"/>They were now desirous of doing away with tile <lb/>
effect of that election, and say it turned on diffir<lb break="no"/>ent causes, that the hon. haember. Mr. Godden, <lb/>
never published his views of Confederation in his <lb/>
Address. Well, there was an old stager on the <lb/>
other side, who knew very well hºw the pulse of <lb/>
the district beat, an artful clever tellow, who knew <lb/>
well how to manipulate the people. Wn at was <lb/>
his course? In his Address he spoke of every <lb/>
subject but Confederation; because ile had before <lb/>
coulmitted himself to an opinio, upon it, and haul <lb/>
he again reterred to the question lae would have <lb/>
ruined his prospects. If he had believed that the <lb/>
Electors of that district were opposed tº Coufedera<lb break="no"/>tion, would he not have made use of it? Under <lb/>
all these circumstances, then, we were justified in <lb/>
regarding the result of this election as a duliberate <lb/>
expression of opinion upon the subject of Gouted<lb break="no"/>eration by the people of the district of Harbor <lb/>
Grace. Besides all this, we had the testimony of <lb/>
tue hon, member for Carbonear, Mr. Rorke, who <lb/>
was always consistent upon, this question. That <lb/>
election also proved that the people of that dis<lb break="no"/>trict were satisfied with the manner in which the <lb/>
affairs of the Colony had been managed by the <lb/>
present Government, that they desired to see Con<lb break="no"/>federation settled, and the Opposition kept; here <lb/>
they were, in the minority, where they were harm<lb break="no"/>less, and where, for ttie beaefit of the country, <lb/>
they should remain. They say, with the Governs <lb/>
ment, of all political imposters keep as clear of <lb/>
the roaring patriots, of those who roºr their flatu<lb break="no"/>lent rhetoric, day atter day, and whose only <lb/>
desire is to place themselves in positions of emolu<lb break="no"/>ment, Now what were we called upon to consi<lb break="no"/>der in the question before us? He would not <lb/>
contine himself merely to the paragraph betore <lb/>
the chair, but would refer also to the one which <lb/>
had been adopted last evening. The question of <lb/>
the condition of the poor necessarily raised ano<lb break="no"/>ther. How was that conditiou to be relieved, <lb/>
and what was the remedy? The doctrine of the <lb/>
Gºvernment was, that there was at present no <lb/>
substantial relief to be tound within ourselves, <lb/>
that that relief must coune trouſ an agency outside, <lb/>
who had the power and the means of doin: tor us <lb/>
what we could not do for ourselves. We inity be <lb/>
as capable as any men to conduct our own affairs, <lb/>
but the power to do 80 no longer re.mained with us. <lb/>
It was not a question, whether we were willing or <lb/>
able, but whether we had the power to effect any <lb/>
benefit for the country as, we are. This, than, <lb/>
was the doctrine upon which the Gºverument <lb/>
took its stand. What we wero laboriug under <lb/>
now was want of employinent for the people. If <lb/>
the labouring population had taeansot enplay<lb break="no"/>ument, ºwe would not bave, them now starving <lb/>
about our streets. Additional, means of eloploy. <lb/>
uleut, then, was what was needed, i'ile mercilants <lb/>
..here were not disposed to exteut' their trade. but, <lb/>
* the contrary, were very ºugh curtailing it. <lb/>
Tuut was of course tº.eir owu business, and they <lb/>
had a perfect right to do what they liked. Cue <lb/>
supply last year uad been a very meagra oue, and <lb/>
this year it would be less. Uuder tuess circum<lb break="no"/>§tance; the propositivu of savin.: £45,009 of our <lb/>
Civil Expeuditure, however laukable in itself, <lb/>
would ug useless as a modus of restoring tug <lb/>
Coultry to prosperity. It was idle to thiuk that it <lb/>
would have any etect. It was cett:uly wise aid pro<lb break="no"/>per that we should make all the reduction tuat was <lb/>
possible and consiste... wº.1 tie etective itsellarge <lb/>
of the public service - 13.1, tae proposal as it <lb/>
stood was easily compreheadej. ºf such ever <lb/>
were doue, tue oppositiou, it they got into <lb/>
power, would oila: u.ck tae present existing <lb/>
state of thing", so that their assumed patriotism <lb/></p> 

<p>a dethronement of <lb/></p> 

<p>th:44 ti-t likeli, in this instance, to deceive any <lb/>
oae. Ware hou. Inselbars 3.H, e...out 1 to b. <lb/></p> 

<p>ened in vain for the reason: | lieve that such a flimsy pretext would effect the . <lb/></p> 

<p>purpose they had in view? Look on the eos <lb/>
dition of the operative population, last ºpting. <lb/>
Hundreds of them could not obtain ºmploymant <lb/>
or supplies, and had to stow theinselves away <lb/>
in Labrador vessels, to endeavour to earn * <lb/>
precarious subsistence. What prospect, then <lb/>
was before us this spring 7 And what º: <lb/>
were at our disposal to free the streets from the <lb/>
starving and wretched creatures that would fill <lb/>
them? If then, we can do no good for this <lb/>
ouiselves, if we could find no employment for <lb/>
them, it is surely wise to seek assistance from <lb/>
those who are able to give it; and this was the <lb/>
course which the Government proposed to <lb/>
adopt. As we were likely to have a repetition <lb/>
of the state of things, which existed last sprint <lb/>
and as we were unable to obtain am Pag º: <lb/>
selves employment for the people, we <lb/>
thought it advisable to put ourselves in com.nu. <lb/>
nication with the Authorities in Canad, and <lb/>
obtain employment for our men on the Railway <lb/>
works that are progressing there. He (hon. M. <lb/>
S.) was happy to say that the efforts to affect: <lb/>
this had been successful,and iu the spring he would <lb/>
be prepared to enter into an agreement with and <lb/>
hire eight, hundred men ior this purpose. They <lb/>
would all be hired by, written agreement, and <lb/>
their wages would be paid thoughly, anu one mair <lb/>
could be received by their wives and families here. <lb/>
Tiley would be taken to Canada in a steamer,4a: <lb/>
at the end of the season would be sent back tº . <lb/>
their hounes, it they desired it. He would, then, <lb/>
leave it to the public to szy what ine effect bi º: <lb/>
would be. This, them, was what the Government <lb/>
had been doing while the opposition were roaring <lb/>
Take eight hundred men out of St. John's, and . <lb/>
would give employinent to all those wilora hained <lb/>
However, the opposition inigh; think lightly of i. <lb/>
he (hon. Mir. S.) would tell thea that wilen h; <lb/>
said he would be prepared to give employmentº, <lb/>
800 men, the public wºuld believe hiºn. * Was <lb/>
satisfied to leave tie matter to the good judge<lb break="no"/>ment of the people, and was assure, iſ wo iſ tº <lb/>
more than the sneers of the opposition to affects, <lb/>
good an arranketment. He periectly agreed with <lb/>
those who said that it was a misfortune that wº <lb/>
should be obliged tº send than away, but sureſ, <lb/>
that was better tuan keeping theiu here to ſº trye <lb/>
and their absence would be the insaus of icºn: <lb/>
ºhers get reasonablo wages ſor their gorvices. <lb/>
This, then, is a part of what we have been <lb/>
duing, and ... this is ...what we meant sy <lb/>
what opposition call selling the country by Con. <lb/>
federation. Here the hop. main her re-erred to <lb/>
a letter read by the hon, unsuber, Mr. Rºnouſ, <lb/>
and which he stated had cond trom Ottawa, <lb/>
adrising the people ot Newfoundland not to <lb/>
come there for enployment. He drew atteation <lb/>
to what he called the clumsy way in waich tus <lb/>
bon, member, Mr. Rinouf, sought tº effect his <lb/>
purpose, and pointed out that portion of it which <lb/>
stated that Biagrants were daily arriving flow <lb/>
Eurºp", as a co-tradiction the position which <lb/>
* hou. Imamber endeavoured to sustain, <lb/>
Tusrs was au idea abroad that it was the inter. <lb/>
ºut of the merehants to keep down the prica of <lb/>
labor. He (hon. Mr. S.) did not agree with <lb/>
that, or that such could be the interest of any <lb/>
class. If the people were not keo; employed. <lb/>
all the interests which depended on the iaborat <lb/>
must share his circulumstancos. There was as <lb/>
more sure sign of the state of any country that <lb/>
the condition of its laboring classes it might <lb/>
appear badly that the men shºuld go as J, <lb/>
but he (hea Mr. S.) doubted if the men then. <lb/>
selves would think so, or if they woull place <lb/>
taith in those who endeavored to persuade then <lb/>
to that offset. He hoped improved prospects <lb/>
in this country would enable them to return. <lb/>
No torne would be used; they could go or stay, <lb/>
just at it pleased them to do, The House had <lb/>
been treated to great dissertations on pauper <lb/>
relief, and on this paragraph in the address. <lb/>
He (hon. Mr. S.) really found it difficult to <lb/>
comprehend the views of hon. members op<lb break="no"/>posite. On the first day of the session the <lb/>
Government, Proclamation was highly eam. <lb/>
manded by , them, the only exception taken <lb/>
being that the Governmeat should have pro<lb break="no"/>vided seed potatoes. He (hon. Mr. S.) hardly <lb/>
ever knew of any benefit being derived from <lb/>
the issue of seed potatoes, and he had no faith in <lb/>
auth a course, for the seed potatoes were, in <lb/>
most cases, either eaten, or nover reached those <lb/>
for whom they were intended. However, last <lb/>
spring, the Government,in deference with wishes <lb/>
of the House, were prepared to issus them, and <lb/>
entered into correspondence with parties in the <lb/>
other Provinces,in order to ascertain terms, &amp;c. <lb/>
They found the prices asked were enormous, <lb/>
about 11s per barrel at the place of shipment, <lb/>
and one fourth ot then might be unfit for use <lb/>
on arrival here. No uuqualified guarantes to <lb/>
issue had been given by Lue Government, bu: <lb/>
ouly ºn intimation that if they could do so they <lb/>
would; and if it had been practicable,on reason. <lb/>
able conditions, it would have been done. The <lb/>
finances of the country were in such a condition <lb/>
that they cºuld not inske the necessary ad<lb break="no"/>vances, and they f. it that, under the circum<lb break="no"/>staucas, they shouli aba idon the idea. Was <lb/>
no one to be thougut of but those who had land? <lb/>
What do hon, members opposite propose to de <lb/>
for the fishermen? Their claims wer, equally <lb/>
good, yet hou, members did not propose that <lb/>
ºne shilling should be provided for them. <lb/>
Those wno had land ought to be in a position to <lb/>
provide their own seed potatoes, and be inde<lb break="no"/>pºndent of such aid irom the Government. <lb/>
The effect of ite Government's, refusal to buy <lb/>
was that the seed patotous came down for sale, <lb/>
and as the Governinent was not in the market, <lb/>
every indus;rious man was enabled to obtaia <lb/>
seed potatoes at a reasonal, rats. Every <lb/>
ºrrel that came was put in the ground. Tº <lb/>
Gºvernment could have do is no more. Ther <lb/>
*ight have given them to differeut people, but <lb/>
that was all. No inors woulſ have been plaut, <lb/>
ºd. ... Year after year the Govern ment had bºss <lb/>
**unted with this poor reliei. They world <lb/>
now give a tri.i to its suppression. They neau: <lb/>
to abide by tua Proclamation to its tulisst ex<lb break="no"/>tent. It was called for. It might be sºarp and <lb/>
ºvere to sojue, but it was a measura of cominoa <lb/>
justics and fair ply to the country at large­ <lb/></p> 

<p>The systein of pauper reliar was over a quarer <lb/></p> 

<p>ºf a c-utary oli, to that oa that score thºrs was . <lb/></p> 

<p>very little room for rº <lb/>
equally to blame. . The <lb/>
escaps his share of thºr <lb/>
and cowardly, and could <lb/>
the facts were before t <lb/>
Mr. S.) merely disclain <lb/>
member to lay the blame <lb/>
The dodge of denial had <lb/>
and so frequently and lo <lb/>
S.) would have believed i <lb/>
the contrary,and he had o <lb/>
duce to hou.member opp <lb/>
and convicted thens of ml <lb/>
that they had begged of <lb/>
issue Poor Relief, and th: <lb/>
tion relief had been issue. <lb/>
an attempt at some round <lb/>
nication, but the Governm <lb/>
mise anything but direct <lb/>
though hon. members mu <lb/>
the Government were in p <lb/>
munications, they disclaid <lb/>
attack the Government. <lb/>
would have the public to <lb/>
eould thus deny tileir own <lb/>
a tolerable good specimen <lb/>
and showed the result of ti <lb/>
§ear ss the Government. <lb/>
a statement of the expend <lb/>
bodied poor in the year 1 <lb/>
mambers read from the st. <lb/>
received by each district.) <lb/>
that with the exception of <lb/>
war, in proportion to P <lb/>
difference between any one <lb/>
8..John's having, as asual, <lb/>
anembrs oppºsite said the <lb/>
ble, that they did not force <lb/>
this expenditure. If they <lb/>
that the expenditure was <lb/>
was not sequired, why not <lb/>
ment and tell thein so, and <lb/>
it? They did not do so, b <lb/>
diture to go on, and <lb/>
jeast, became rasponsible. <lb/>
them to endeavor by m <lb/>
denial of their band writit <lb/>
responsibility, or fasten on <lb/>
pºor relief. Was not the <lb/>
Main expended with the co <lb/>
repre enta io is, from time <lb/>
mambers of that district 2 <lb/>
psaditure was not warrant <lb/>
these lion, members were r <lb/>
in not asking that it shonid <lb/>
(hon. Mr. S.) did not maa. <lb/>
did not best out the expe <lb/>
that the members had the <lb/>
they should not attempt to <lb/>
abil ty. The circumstanc <lb/>
tue system of poor relief, <lb/>
buost men to think that an <lb/>
down sh, uld be made. W <lb/>
the Proclamation was iss <lb/>
approved ot. Tuo old syst <lb/>
siſ down to one dead Îevel, <lb/>
try without an independe <lb/>
symptoms of a desirº to giv <lb/>
tion were now becoming ap <lb/>
Mr. Hogskrr —Nºt on out <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. SHEA.- Yes, * <lb/>
hon. leader ot the Oppositio, <lb/>
inhumau, and proclaimed his <lb/>
means to induce the Goverut <lb/>
and he is suitporteſt by hon, u <lb/>
Mr. HøgskºT.-\-No. <lb/>
Hon. Mr. SHEA.-Ynti chº <lb/>
made his state, neut. The attº <lb/>
induce the Guveruinent to ab <lb/>
on this imatter. Were there <lb/>
country who had a duty to di <lb/>
poor as well as the Govern <lb/>
3ountry was the relief of the <lb/>
Government. The systein ha. <lb/>
iu existence, and no doubt tº <lb/>
termination of it would bring <lb/>
in such a state of things it b <lb/>
all to lend a relping hand to <lb/>
was sorry to see that as yº <lb/>
John's did not come up to ti <lb/>
appear to appreciate the to <lb/>
the country is placed. This <lb/>
the neeessity of considering V <lb/>
not by Statüte compel all to <lb/>
to their taeans. He ſhon. M <lb/>
the hors. niemixer for Ferryla <lb/>
110 ntan would be allowed to <lb/>
arreat difficulties if the questio. <lb/>
opened again. The old abus' <lb/>
for it is a thing which contains <lb/>
elements and temptations to <lb/>
it would be matter of great re; <lb/>
of circumstances, the Governii <lb/>
pelled to yield. The Go, <lb/>
duty to perfºrm, and it was <lb/>
they were withou; a law to <lb/>
the poor. He knew there w <lb/>
great difficulties in the way <lb/>
Provisions of such a law, and <lb/>
Proportions of assessments, b <lb/>
for the Governiment any loug <lb/>
Juty of keeping the paupers. <lb/>
ºuths of hard suſtering, dit <lb/>
efore them, and he hoped all <lb/>
and contribute to tide the pêu'ſ <lb/>
*; think they would again <lb/>
*::::::::#; and if these tuou <lb/>
}. . the prospects of the <lb/>
#. ºugh improved. Oue <lb/>
solation was that in this criºl <lb/>
on our 9wn resources, as wºre <lb/>
claita *.*ny other people, I <lb/>
the Potaisión, we cºnti mak. <lb/>
people there. When the Nº. <lb/>
tailed, last year, and great iſ <lb/>
É. *uión;8t, the fisheru <lb/>
elt to ask for relief, but ſºle I, <lb/>
Flo and Quebec and tha cºº <lb/>
ent cities, ſurwarded £10,000 <lb/>
That was a practical proof ºt <lb/>
They had a claim, and they <lb/>
and funds were sent them, uſ, <lb/>
ºf dis;ribution telegraphed this <lb/>
&amp;uired, No doubt some would <lb/>
but call it what you will, <lb/>
**.xelcome here now?" w <lb/>
**sisting our people, but we <lb/>
ºld it would be or 'great dau <lb/>
Canada in forag paupérés. <lb/>
was expected to do all, and to <lb/>
No tuatiºn whº went ºw <lb/>
ºnent were to blame, a.d the <lb/>
to be cast on their should. <lb/>
logic of hon, gentl <lb/>
• gentlenipa d <lb/>
$xamine the question. Tws <lb/>
<lb break="no"/> </p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>