<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-01-27" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
    <title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-01-27">27 January 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-02-02"/>,
<date when="1865-02-06"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-02_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-02_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-06_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-06_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-11-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-02_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-02_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-02_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-02_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-06_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-06_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-06_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-06_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-02_Page_1.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    <fw type="dateline">St. John's, Thursday, February 2, 1865</fw>
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>

    <!-- IC, 2018-11-06, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->

<!--<p>s <lb/>
tail to procure Mrs. WINSLow's Sooth; <lb/>
upor children teething. This waſ. <lb/>
a the prescription of one of the be <lb/>
ians and nurses in the United sº <lb/>
used for thirty years with never failin <lb/>
success by millions, of mothers and ºf <lb/>
n the feeble infant cf one week old to t s <lb/>
nºt only relieves the child from pain, i. <lb/>
s the stomach and bowels, corrects acidit t º <lb/>
tone and energy to the whole system. # <lb/>
t instantly relieve Griping in the Bowels *­ <lb/>
ic. We believe it the best and surest remed, <lb/>
ld in all cases of Dissentery and Diarhº <lb/>
hether it arises from teething or any ºt. <lb/>
ull directions for use will accompany each <lb/>
one genuine unless the fac-simile of Curti, <lb/>
is on the outside wrapper. Price only 25 <lb/>
lottle. Sold by all Medicine Dealers. off. <lb/>
reet, New York, and 205 High Holbº <lb/></p> 

<p>ngland. <lb/>
MRS. WINSLOW, <lb/>
nced Nurse and Female Physician, presents <lb/>
ntion of mothers, her Soothing Syrup for <lb/>
ething, which greatly facilitates the process <lb/>
by softening the gums, reducing all infi. <lb/>
ill allay all pain and spasmodic action, and <lb/>
egulate the bowels. Depend upon it, m. <lb/>
I give rest to yourselves, and relief and <lb/>
our inſants. We have put up and sold this <lb/>
over thirty years, and can say, in confiden. <lb/>
ºf it what we have never boen able to sº <lb/>
r medicine—never has it failed in a single <lb/>
effect a cure, when timely used. Neº <lb/>
ºw an instance of dissatisfaction by any one <lb/>
t. On the contrary, all speak delighted <lb/>
*rations, and speaks in terius of commenda. <lb/>
magical effects and medical virtues. We <lb/>
is matter what we do now," after thirty <lb/>
ºrience, and pledge our reputation for the <lb/>
ºf what we here declare. In almost every <lb/>
i.ere the infant is suffering from pair and <lb/>
, relief will be found in fifteen or twenty <lb/>
ter the syrup is administered. Full direc. <lb/>
sing will accompany each bottle. Nons <lb/>
illess the ſac-simile of Curtis and Perkins, <lb/>
is on the outside wrapper. Sold by Drug. <lb/>
ghout the wºrld. ... Principal Office, 48 by <lb/>
', and 205 High Holboin, Engiand. Priºs <lb/>
hts per bottle. <lb/>
wing is as extract from a letter written by <lb/>
S Holme, Pastor of the Pierrepont-street <lb/>
*ich, Brooklyn, NY, to the "Journal and <lb/>
." Cincinnati, O., and speaks volumes in <lb/>
hat world-renowned medicine, Mrs. WINs. <lb/>
thing Syrup for Children Teething—" W. <lb/>
ertisement in your c lumns of Mrs. Wins. } <lb/>
ling Syrup. Now we never said a word in <lb/>
• patent medicine before in our life, but we <lb/>
iled to say to your readers that this is no <lb/>
we have tried it, and know it to be all i <lb/>
is probably one of the most successful <lb/>
ºf the day, because it in one of the best <lb/>
of your readers who have babies can't do <lb/>
iuy in a supply." <lb/>
J. DEARIN, St. John's, <lb/>
As ent for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>PHO E.W. H.W. F.H R4, <lb/>
- 4. *** *** wº. <lb/>
###tº $ºpºny. <lb/>
ird Street and Chering Cross, London. <lb/>
ESTA || || | SH ſº ty–1782 <lb/>
Thustº ES ANi DIRECTORS. <lb/></p> 

<p>irtou, Esq. Kirkman ix. Hodg: an Esq. <lb/>
<lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>ºpe, " i. i** - Horra, <lb/></p> 

<p>ston, " William J. Lancastor, " <lb/>
* Jºhn b. Mugen, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Fºser, " John Miasterman, Esq. M. P. <lb/></p> 

<p>ulter, " Jºhn Timnby Oxley tsa <lb/></p> 

<p>igodhart." George Stanley Reptor. " <lb/></p> 

<p>ºrdon, " |Benjamin Shºw, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>tº: " |Matthew Whiting, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Jgsor, " Franrik Wiison, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>8ECRETA Riks f <lb/></p> 

<p>William HARRIs Esq. <lb/>
GeoRGs',\ illiam LoveLL, Esq. <lb/></p> 

<p>ENIX FIRE OFFICE is confidently tº: <lb/></p> 

<p>i to the notice of the public—for the libera <lb/>
motitude with which all claims upon it are <lb/>
d paid- as well as for the almost unlimited <lb/>
ich it affords, comprising in addition to the <lb/>
ed Capital of the Coupany, the whole for <lb/>
umerous Proprietary. composed oſsomeº <lb/>
opulent gentlemen and Merchants in the <lb/></p> 

<p>goion. <lb/>
'ENIX CFFICF has carried on an exten­ <lb/>
ccessful busines: for upwards of seventy­ <lb/>
The duty paid by it to Government for <lb/>
in Great Briain and Ireland exceed <lb/>
terling per unnum. <lb/>
ind short time Insurances are undertaken <lb/>
ENIX Q9MPANY on almost every de­ <lb/>
risk, in Newfoundland at a moderate late <lb/>
which may be know on application to <lb/>
it their office, in St. John's, where policies <lb/>
ee of charge. <lb/>
W. &amp; G. RENDEI.L, <lb/>
Agents for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>'i'HE COLONIAL <lb/></p> 

<p>Assirance tompany <lb/></p> 

<p>EstarlishED 1846. <lb/>
AL, ONE MILLION STERLING. <lb/></p> 

<p>ge of Assuring before 25th: <lb/></p> 

<p>May 1863. <lb/>
IRD DIVISION OF PROFITS. <lb/>
the advantage of this year's entry to the <lb/></p> 

<p>ne, Proposals must be lodged at the Offies <lb/></p> 

<p>Newfoundland,or with one of the Agents <lb/>
25th May next. <lb/>
PARS BONUS will be allocated at the <lb/>
Profits in 1864 to Policies opened before <lb/>
the Books for the Present Year. <lb/></p> 

<p>ATER BY SPECIAL ACT of PARLIAMENT. <lb/></p> 

<p>Governor. <lb/>
iT HON. THE EARL OF ELGIN &amp; <lb/>
!)INE. Gover Nor-General of INDIA. <lb/>
ICE-\-5 GEORGESTREET, EDINBURGH <lb/>
Directors in St. John's, Newfoundland. <lb/>
O'Brien, Esq. Walter Grieve, Esq., <lb/>
Merchant. <lb/>
William Henry Mare, Esq. <lb/>
Adviser—Henry Hunt Stabb, M.D. <lb/>
tgent–Frederick J. Wyatt. <lb/>
'ION OF THE COMPANY. <lb/>
me of the Company............ £130,000. <lb/>
y have divided Profits on two occasions­ <lb/>
d 1859. <lb/>
£1000,opened in 1847,has beenincreased <lb/>
y the application of the Bonus; other <lb/>
proportion. - - 0. <lb/>
'd every five years; next division, in 186 <lb/></p> 

<p>* <lb/></p> 

<p>t <lb/></p> 

<p>'' <lb/></p> 

<p>¥ <lb/></p> 

<p>N <lb/></p> 

<p>th <lb/></p> 

<p>%. , <lb/></p> 

<p>F = (ſhe 3ienſmundlai <lb/></p> 

<p>se:= <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>No. 3,635. <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, Thursday, February 2, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>cº­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Printed and Published every Monday and Thursday <lb/>
mornings EDWARD DALTON SHEA, at his <lb/>
    Office in DUCKWORTH STREET—Terms–One <lb/>
Guinea per annum payable in advance.</p> 

<p>Advertisements not limited (Auction-sales and notice <lb/>
which determine themselves excepted) are repeated <lb/>
until ordered in writing to be withdrawn, and are <lb/>
charged for accordingly. <lb/></p> 

<p>This paper is filed, and may be seen, free of charge at <lb/>
Holloway's Pills and Ointment Establishment, 244 <lb/>
Strand, London. <lb/></p> 

<p>REPORT OF THE DELEGATES <lb/>
TO THE QUEBEC CONVENTION ON THE <lb/>
FEDERAL UNION of the BRITISH NORTH <lb/>
AMERICAN PROVINCES. <lb/></p>

<p>ST. JOHN'S, JANUARY 21st, 1865. <lb/></p>
    <p>
SIR,- <lb break="no"/>Having been honoured by the Government of this <lb/>
Colony with the appointment of Delegates to the <lb/>
General Colonial Convention at Quebec, on the sub­ <lb/>
ject of the Union of the British North America <lb/>
Provinces, we pr ded in the St ." St. <lb/>
George" on the 23rd September last, and arrived in <lb/>
due course at our destination. The Meeting was <lb/>
appointed to be held at Quebec on the 10th Octo­ <lb/>
ber, on which day the Belegates from the several <lb/>
Provinces met in the Parliament Buildings in that <lb/>
City. Canada was represented by the members of <lb/>
the Executive Council of that Province, twelve in <lb/>
number, Nova Scotia had five Delegates, New <lb/>
Brunswick seven, Newfoundland two and Prince <lb/>
Edward Island seven, the credentials of the Dele: <lb/>
gates from the Jower Provinces were handed in, and <lb/>
the Convention was then organized by electing Sir <lb/>
Etienne Tache, Premier of Canada, to be Chairman, <lb/>
and the several Provincial Secretaries and Mr. Shea <lb/>
to be Secretaries to the Convention. <lb/>
Sometime previously a Meeting took place at <lb/>
Charlottetown, of Delegates from Nova Scotia, <lb/>
New Brunswick and P.E. Island for the purpose <lb/>
of considering the question of a Legislative Union <lb/>
of these Provinces, and while so engaged, some <lb/>
members of the Canadian Government presented <lb/>
themselves with a proposal for the Union of all the <lb/>
Provinces, which was so far received, with favor that <lb/>
the consideration of the original question was sus­ <lb/>
pended, and the larger one entertained and discus­ <lb/>
sed. The Meeting then adjourned to Halffax, <lb/>
where the Delegates met shortly after and proceeded <lb/>
with their deliberations, which resulted in a resolu­ <lb/>
tion that a further Conference should be held at <lb/>
Querec, to which Newfoundland should be invited <lb/>
to send representatives. - <lb break="no"/>Though the subject had been fully discussed in all <lb/>
its general bearings at these earlier meetings, it was <lb/>
now necessary to treat it more specially in 1élation <lb/>
to the position the Colonies should respectively oc­ <lb/>
cupy in the contemplated Union, and moreover, the <lb/>
Newfoundland Delegates not having had the advan­ <lb/>
tage of being present at the previous meetings, it was <lb/>
suggested that an exposition of the whole question <lb/>
should be gone into on their account. This was <lb/>
agreed to and the business proceedings were accord­ <lb/>
ingly opened by the Hon. John A. McDonald, At­ <lb/>
torney General of Upper Canada, in an elaborate <lb/>
statement, showing the great benefits of combination <lb/>
to communities circumstanced as the British North <lb/>
American Colonies—drawn not only from the nature <lb/>
of things as respects the Provinces in their present <lb/>
state, in relation to each other, but fortified also by <lb/>
the experience of the working of the Union of the <lb/>
Canadas, and the more important example of the <lb/>
neighbouring States, which had become so great un­ <lb/>
der the Union they formed on their separation from <lb/>
the mother country. The necessity for Union was <lb/>
also shewn by Mr. McDonald, who considered it the <lb/>
policy clearly indicated by the Home Government, <lb/>
where it was justly felt that the time had arrived <lb/>
when the British North American Provinces should <lb/>
assume the position demanded by their numbers, <lb/>
wealth, extent of territory, and growing importance, <lb/>
and it was alone by a Union of the whole that they <lb/>
... could fit themselves for the great place now open to <lb/>
... them, and which the efforts of individual Provinces <lb/>
could never enable them to attain. <lb/>
In view of the framing of a constitution, the de­ <lb/>
feets of the American system were fully considered. <lb/>
Though the wisdom of the men who framed that con­ <lb/>
sutution, had been attested by its success for three <lb/>
quarters of a century, it still embraced principles <lb/>
which rendered it unable to bear the strain of the <lb/>
crisis which lately arose, furnishing a most instruc­ <lb/>
tive lesson at the present time. The admitted great <lb/>
defect of the Federal system of the United States is <lb/>
the weakness of the Executive, which compelled them <lb/>
in their day of trial to resort to the exercise of power <lb/>
unknown to the law, placing private and public liber­ <lb/>
ty at the mercy of arbitrary suthority. <lb/>
These was a very general feeling in the Confer­ <lb/>
ence that a legislative union would confer the great­ <lb/>
er advantages on the General Confederation, as the <lb/>
Government, under such a system, would possess <lb/>
larger authority and more commanding influence. <lb/>
But many difficulties presented themselves which de­ <lb/>
P. this view or its desired feasibility. The <lb/>
wer Canadians would not consent to any plan <lb/>
wheh placed their peculiar institutions beyond their <lb/>
immediate control; while it was also felt that public <lb/>
opinion(in the lower provinces was not ripe for the <lb/>
skºrenue change which the abrogation of their local <lb/>
legislatures would involve. <lb/>
These matters having been fully considered, the <lb/>
Colference decided as their first resolution, "That <lb/>
the best interest and present and future prosperity <lb/>
of British North America will be P. by a <lb/>
Federal Union under the Crown of Great Britain, <lb/>
provided such Union can be effected on principles <lb/>
just to the several Provinces. <lb/>
In the Resolutions adopted by the Conference to <lb/>
carry this Union into effect, care has been takeu to <lb/>
avoid the cause of weakness disclosed in the work­ <lb/>
jºg of the American Constitution. The General <lb/>
Government will be formed upon the principles of <lb/>
tº present colonial system. Executive Responsi­ <lb/>
§ility being maintained, while it will not, as in the <lb/>
inited States, be dependent, either for its organiza­ <lb/>
Šion,or nºnority, on the vºlition or acts of any of <lb/>
the local Gºvernments. The structure of these lat­ <lb/>
fºr bºdies is left in each case to the presentiocal <lb/>
legislatures to determine, and unifornič of pian not <lb/>
being necessary, they are severally left to frame <lb/>
such arrangements in tuis Icspect as the altered cir­ <lb/>
*istance and the peculiar condition of each pro­ <lb/>
Mince may seeia to render desirable. The powers of <lb/>
the General and Local Governmºs are defined so <lb/>
** Prevent any probable causes of conflict—all <lb/></p> 

<p>ceived in any part of the world where <lb/>
# been estab"shed. <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/>
! <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>powers of a general nature being vested in the Gen­ <lb/>
eral Government, and local questions being reserved <lb/>
for the subordinate bodies. <lb break="no"/>It was unanimously decided that the principle of <lb/>
Elective Councils should not be adopted in the new <lb/>
Constitution, and that the appointments should be <lb/>
for life, and should vest in the General Government, <lb/>
In the composition of this branch of the Legislature, <lb/>
the Lower Provinces have a larger representation <lb/>
than their due, if population alone were the govern­ <lb/>
ing consideration. For the purpose of this arrange­ <lb/>
ment it was proposed at the early meetings at Prince <lb/>
Edward Island and Halifax, that Upper and Lower <lb/>
Canada should each be made a section, and the Lower <lb/>
Provinces a third, with equal representation for each <lb/>
part. There was a differenee of opinion as to whe­ <lb/>
ther Newfoundland intended to be included in <lb/>
the number assigned to the Lower Provinces, but the <lb/>
Canadian Delegates, although maintaining that they <lb/>
had included Newfoundland in the arrangement, at <lb/>
length yielde" the point, and four additional members <lb/>
were added for this colony. "We may seem in this <lb/>
case to have received less that our relative right of <lb/></p> 

<p>Nova Scotia stand if the q were reg 1 with <lb/>
ical strictness. But it will easily be understood <lb/>
that unless such a large project as the Union of the <lb/>
Provinces, with the various and diverse interests it <lb/>
involves, were met in a spirit of fair compromise, no <lb/>
satisfactory general result could be arrived at, and in <lb/>
this instance the Delegates representing Upper Cana­ <lb/>
da, Nova Scotia and Newfoundland made a conces­ <lb/>
sion of extreme rights to the other Provinces,although <lb/>
in relation to the whole number, this colony has a <lb/>
larger share than would be signable by this rule. <lb/>
The principle of population alone governs the com­ <lb/>
position of the Lower House, which is to consist of <lb/>
196 members, eight being awarded as the portion of <lb/>
this colony. It will be seen that this number wou'd <lb/>
give us a full representation in the popular Branch, <lb/>
which is the influential and virtually governing Body <lb/>
in all Governments where the principles of Responsi­ <lb/>
ble Government prevail. <lb/>
The General Government is to assume the public <lb/>
debts of the several Provinces, on the equitable plan <lb/>
by which no one Province will be charged with more <lb/>
than its own obligations on this account. <lb/>
The surrender of the Customs Revenues to the <lb/>
General Government, embraces the condition that <lb/>
subsidies shall be made to the several Provinces for <lb/>
the support of their Local Institutions. In none of <lb/>
the Provinces is direct taxation held in favor, <lb/>
though in all but this colony, it prevails to <lb/>
a certain extent. We feel, however, that in <lb/>
this respect we could not consent to dis. <lb/>
turb our exceptional position, though a difficulty <lb/>
arose because of the insufficiency for our requiremerts <lb/>
of the pro rata amount of subsidy that was sufficient <lb/>
for the wants of the other Provinces. It was, how­ <lb/>
ever, agreed on, to avoid the necessity of resorting <lb/>
to direst taxation, to meet the deficiency of means in <lb/>
our case, that Newfoundland should receivea special <lb/>
subsidy of one hundred and fifty thousand dollars per <lb/>
annum, in consideration of the transfer to the General <lb/>
Government of the control of our ungranted and un­ <lb/>
occupied Crown Lands and Minerſ, and this ar­ <lb/>
rangement places the question of our means on a satis­ <lb/>
factory footing. <lb/>
The full .# explicit character of the report of the <lb/>
Conference, which we beg to annex, renders it unne­ <lb/>
cessary for us to go further into detail on this impor­ <lb/>
tant subject, which occupied the time of the Delegates <lb/>
for ten hours daily from the 19th to the 27th October, <lb/>
when our labours were brought to a termination and <lb/>
the report was unanimously agreed to. <lb/>
Men of all parties were presunt at the Conference <lb/>
from the various British North American Provinces, <lb/>
but the influence of local differences found no place <lb/>
in the deliberations. We feel warranted in asserting <lb/>
our belief that uo inquiry was ever conducted under <lb/>
a higher sense of the responsibility of the occasion, <lb/>
or with a more single desire to arrive at the best re­ <lb/>
sults for the great interests at stake. While it would <lb/>
be impossible to suppose that the report embodies <lb/>
every individual view of the Delegates on all the <lb/>
points it embraces, as a whole it was unreservedly <lb/>
adopted. It is the emanation of the best judgment <lb/>
of the Conference, unbiased by a wish for the undue <lb/>
advancement of party or sectional interests, and the <lb/>
spirit of calm discussion which pervaded the whole <lb/>
inquiry of which this report in the result, cannot fail <lb/>
to commend it to the earnest attention of all whose <lb/>
interests it affects. For ourselves, we have but to <lb/>
state that we affixed our signatures, as individuals, to <lb/>
that report with the full conviction that the welfare <lb/>
of the colony will be promoted by entering the Union <lb/>
it proposes, and that we cannot reject it without ag­ <lb/>
gravating the injurious consequences of our present <lb/>
insolation. <lb/>
We beg to annex a statement showing the amount <lb/>
and particulars of the charges from which this colony <lb/>
would be relieved under the Confederation, and the <lb/>
amount that would be available for the purposes of <lb/>
the Local Government. <lb/>
We have the honor to be Sir, <lb/>
Your most obedient servants, <lb/>
F. B. T. CARTER, <lb/></p> 

<p>A. SHEA, <lb/>
* EWHºoija ºž, AM ſº. <lb/>
CHARGES PAYABLE BY THE GENERAL <lb/>
GOVERNMENT. <lb/>
Governor and Secretary...... £2,280 <lb/>
Receiver General .. -\-\- - - 500 <lb/>
Customs Department. . . . . . . . . 7,625 <lb/>
Surveyor General .. -\- 400 <lb/>
Engineer... ....... - 150 <lb/>
Three Judges. . . . . . - 2,548 <lb/>
Interest on Debt... - 10,210 <lb/>
Postal Steam Servic - 5,150 <lb/>
Protection of the Fisheries.... 600 <lb/>
Post Office . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3,221 <lb/></p> 

<p>£35,71stg. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT. <lb/>
Iuterest on $25 per head on 130,000 in­ <lb/>
habitants, $3,250,000, at 5 per centum $162,500 <lb/></p> 

<p>80 cents per head on 130,000.... 1u4,000 <lb/>
Grant tor Surrender of Crown La &amp; 150,000 <lb/>
. $416,500 <lb/></p> 

<p>Less interest payable on Public Debt, <lb/>
£10,210 Sterling......... ........ 47,124 <lb/>
$369,376 <lb/></p> 

<p>January, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>representation, but so also would Upper Canada and <lb/></p> -->

<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, Jan. 27.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> and Members met in the Assembly <lb/>
Hall shortly before two o'clock. <lb/></p> 

<p>At two o'clock the Usher of the Black Rod delivered <lb/>
a message at the Bar from his Exceleney the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor, commanding the attendance of Mr. Speaker and <lb/>
the members in the Council Chamber. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName> and the members proceeded to the <lb/>
Council Chamber accordingly, and being returned. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> informed the House, that when in at<lb break="no"/>tendance on the Governor, his Excellency had been <lb/>
pleased to open the session with a speech, of which, <lb/>
for the sake of accuracy, he had obtained a copy, which <lb/>
he read to the House. (Published in Monday's <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">Newfoundlander</hi>. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName> rose to move the appointment of a <lb/>
select Committee to prepare the draft of an address in <lb/>
reply to the gracious speech with which his Excellency <lb/>
had been pleased to open the session. He (Mr. Wyatt) <lb/>
was sure they had all listened to the speech with par<lb break="no"/>ticular attention, as he was satisfied there would be but <lb/>
one opinion respecting it in that house and throughout <lb/>
the colony. His Excellency had addressed the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature for the first time since his assumption of the <lb/>
Government; and they must all feel gratified with the <lb/>
deep interest he manifested for the improvement of the <lb/>
country. He (Mr. Wyatt) felt he was ouly expressing <lb/>
the feeling of the House when he said they would give <lb/>
the most careful attention to all the suggestions of his <lb/>
Excellency, especially as these suggestions were for <lb/>
the benefit of the people whose representatives they <lb/>
were. They felt, with his Excellency, for the suffering <lb/>
to which so many of the people were reduced, arising <lb/>
from the failure of the seal fishery, last spring, the <lb/>
short catch in the shore cod-fishery, and the partial <lb/>
failure of the Labrador fishery. Having, in numerous <lb/>
instances, secured notining to sustain themselves and <lb/>
their families during the winter, a large number of the <lb/>
fishermen were in circumstances of deep distress, which <lb/>
the Government were doing all in their power to mit<lb break="no"/>igate. The system of relief which had grown up of <lb/>
<choice><sic>laate</sic><corr>late</corr></choice> years was one of which they all complained, and <lb/>
which was liable to many abuses; but still they must <lb/>
not suffer the people to starve. It was necessary, <lb/>
however, that the attention of the House shall be <lb/>
given to the subject of poor relief, with the view of <lb/>
checking the growing evil of pauperism. His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency suggested that they should give encouragement <lb/>
to the Mackerel and Bank fisheries, which were a <lb/>
source of profitable employment to the fishermen of <lb/>
other countries. The Bank fishery had been neglected <lb/>
for years, and with the present high price of fish there <lb/>
was every prospect of its proving remunerative. The <lb/>
Mackerel and Salmon fisheries were of great impor<lb break="no"/>tance, and should have every encouragment the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature could give them. His Excellency also directed <lb/>
their attention to the mineral resources of the Island, <lb/>
which there was reason to anticipate would furnish <lb/>
means of employment to a large number of our people, <lb/>
as well as a source of wealth to capitalists. He would <lb/>
now say a few words on a subject of the deepest impor<lb break="no"/>tance to the country, the proposed federation of the <lb/>
British North American Coionies. The Government <lb/>
had been invited last summer, to take part in a conven<lb break="no"/>tion, at Quebec to take this important question into <lb/>
consideration, and had appointed the hon. the Speaker <lb/>
of that house, and the hon member for Piacentia and St. <lb/>
Mary's, Delegates from this colony to the Convention. <lb/>
Although the Report of the proceedings of that Con<lb break="no"/>ference was not yet laid before the House, it had been <lb/>
made public through the newspapers, and he was satis<lb break="no"/>fied it had been read by every member of the House. <lb/>
They must all agree with his Excellency that the sub<lb break="no"/>ject was one of the deepest interest to the whole com<lb break="no"/>munity, and one which they ought to approach in a <lb/>
spirit of calm examination, with an earnest desire to <lb/>
come to such a conclusiod as would best promote the <lb/>
permanent interests of the colony. He (Mr. Wyatt) <lb/>
was aware that there was much difference of opinion <lb/>
it, this colony on the subject. Many considered the <lb/>
terms proposed for the admission of Newfoundland <lb/>
very favorable, while others were of a different opinion. <lb/>
It would be for the House, when the papers were laid <lb/>
before them, to weigh all that would be urged for and <lb/>
against the union. If, upon full consideration, it <lb/>
should be the opinion of the House that the decision <lb/>
should be referred to their constituents, he trusted <lb/>
that the matter would be fairly placed before those <lb/>
they represented. It was not a matter into which <lb/>
they should hastily rush, for they ought to bear in <lb/>
mind that the union once effected, it would be impos<lb break="no"/>sible to undo it, should they not find it to their ad<lb break="no"/>vantage. There were several other important subjects <lb/>
referred to in his Excellency's speech, to which the <lb/>
attention of the House would be directed in the course <lb/>
of the session, and which he (Mr. Wyatt) was satisfied <lb/>
would receive that careful attention to which their <lb/>
importance entitled them. In conclusion, he (Mr. <lb/>
Wyatt) would join in his Excellency's prayer that the <lb/>
Altnighty Ruler of all events would bless their labors, <lb/>
and those of the whole community, and render them <lb/>
more productive, and the country more prosperous <lb/>
than for many years past. He moved that a Select <lb/>
Committee be appointed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WHIT6">Mr. WHITEWAY</persName> had much pleasure in seconding <lb/>
the motion proposed by his honorable friend Mr. <lb/>
Wyatt. That gentleman had spoken truly when he <lb/>
said that the speech of his Exceitency the Governor <lb/>
referred to many matters of great interest and im<lb break="no"/>portance, as regards this country. But there was <lb/>
one subject alluded to in that speech, of paramount <lb/>
importance—that of the proposed Confederation of <lb/>
the British North American colonies. No one who <lb/>
had listened to the speech of his Excellency could but <lb/>
have been deeply impressed with the eminently en<lb break="no"/>lightened views it contained. The dignified tone, <lb/>
style and language of his Excellency represent him <lb/>
as one possessing all the characteristics essential in <lb/>
the Representative of Her most Gracious Majesty the <lb/>
Queen. His Excellency had been among us but a <lb/>
short time; but that period had been devoted to ac<lb break="no"/>quiring a thorough knowledge of the condition and <lb/>
requirements of the people. He had now given us <lb/>
the benefit of his inquiries. He had discovered evils, and <lb/>
he had not failed to suggest remedies. He had now <lb/>
discovered a great and growing evil which his prede<lb break="no"/>cessors had pointed at, but which no government had <lb/>
as yet had the hardihood to grapple with and eradi<lb break="no"/>cate, that abominable system as regards pauper re<lb break="no"/>liet, which existed in this country. The reinedy sug<lb break="no"/>gested by his Excellency was the only one which could <lb/>
be imployed to secure an economical administration <lb/>
of the paupar fund; that is the raising of that fund by <lb/>
direct taxion, and casting upon the tax payers them<lb break="no"/>selves, in every community, in duty of checking the <lb/>
expenditure; or, in others words, making each Dis<lb break="no"/>trict support its own paupers. He (Mr. Whiteway) <lb/>
 
<cb/>

regretted that the Bill brought in by the government, <lb/>
during the last session, having this object in view, <lb/>
had been withdrawn. The enormous annual drain <lb/>
from the general revenue for poor relief had stayed <lb/>
public improvements; and public buildings were going <lb/>
into decay, our roads were scarcely passable, and their <lb/>
was no new work in operation. He (Mr. Whiteway) <lb/>
was gratified to learn that there was an intention on <lb/>
the part of the government to introduce some measure <lb/>
calculated to resuscitate the Bank Fishery. It was <lb/>
much to be regretted that sufficient enterprise did not <lb/>
exist amongst us to induce an active competition with <lb/>
foreigners in this branch of the fisheries; and that <lb/>
we were satisfied to depend altogether upon our shore <lb/>
and Labrador fisheries. He believed that the people <lb/>
of this country would be much better off, if, instead <lb/>
of locating themselves upon the most extreme points <lb/>
of land, as they had done, upon the coast, and carry<lb break="no"/>ing on the fishery in small punts, as it were at their <lb/>
very doors, they had settled at the heads of the bays, <lb/>
where existed lands adapted for agricultural purposes. <lb/>
Then if they were provided with a larger class of fish<lb break="no"/>ing craft, large enough to proceed to the Banks, if <lb/>
necessary, one branch of the family might be employed <lb/>
in making agriculture an auxiliary to the fishery, <lb/>
during the absence of the fishermen, and upon <lb/>
their return, attend to the curing department. <lb/>
He (Mr. Whiteway) was glad to see a recommenda<lb break="no"/>tion to encourage agriculture. The best way, be be<lb break="no"/>haved, to accomplish this, was to make good roads to <lb/>
the country. No sooner is a good road made through <lb/>
a piece of good land, than we at once see a tilt spring <lb/>
up, then a potato plot is cleared. Next follows a <lb/>
cottage, and a little farm. Give the people facilities <lb/>
for communication, free grants of land, and agriculture <lb/>
will advance. It requires no bounty. There is every <lb/>
reason to believe that sheep may be kept to an unlimi<lb break="no"/>ted number upon our wild pasturage; but it seems to <lb/>
be the cry on all sides, that the dogs prove a great <lb/>
obstacle. He (Mr. Whiteway) regretted that, not<lb break="no"/>withstanding the strenuous efforts of one who had <lb/>
evinced a deep interest in agricultural improvement <lb/>
generally, and had accomplished much in that direction, <lb/>
Mr. Justice Robinson, his attempt to establish a joint <lb/>
stock company for the purpose of carrying out sheep <lb/>
farming on a large scale, had as yet come to nothing; <lb/>
not from lack of energy on the part of that gentleman, <lb/>
but because of the absence of that enterprising spirit <lb/>
among the people which induces a deviation from the <lb/>
old beaten track, and an embarking in new pursuits. <lb/>
The great and all-important subject of Education, it <lb/>
seemed, would be brought before the House during <lb/>
the present session. He (Mr. Whiteway) believed <lb/>
that in no colony of Great Britain was there so large <lb/>
an amonnt, in proportion to its population, appropri<lb break="no"/>ated oy the Government for educational purposes; but <lb/>
the benefits derived from it were not commensurate <lb/>
with the exuendiure. However, he did not agree <lb/>
with those who asserted that the money was thrown <lb/>
away, for it much good had been accomplished, a <lb/>
desire from improvement had been created, a taste for <lb/>
knowledge, and the people of the smallest settlement <lb/>
are now anxious to have their children taught, and the <lb/>
closing of their school would be viewed as a great <lb/>
deprivation, The idea of establishing a normal train<lb break="no"/>ing school for teachers was a good one, and, if carried <lb/>
out, would tend materially to improvement. The <lb/>
great want felt was for efficient teachers were obtained, <lb/>
they must be adequately paid, for men of attainments <lb/>
would not be satisfied with the small salaries which <lb/>
are now paid. In his (Mr. Whiteway's) opinion, they <lb/>
had now arrived when the Government may fairly say <lb/>
to the people of every locality where a school is re<lb break="no"/>quired, if you will subscribe or guarantee one half or <lb/>
one third, the government would provide the other <lb/>
half or two thirds of the teacher's salary; and it might <lb/>
be depended upon that there are few places in which <lb/>
to secure a good teacher, the people would not willing<lb break="no"/>ly lend their aid, for they now are feeling the advan<lb break="no"/>tages of having good schools. He (Mr. Whiteway) <lb/>
had frequently before, in his place in the house, spo<lb break="no"/>ken of the ruin which must ensue from the manner <lb/>
in which our salmon fisheries were prosecuted. In <lb/>
rivers heretofore prolific, scarce a salmon now was to <lb/>
be seen. He had seen a net stretched across a river <lb/>
from bank to bank, the salmon playing about below <lb/>
it, barred from getting into the river, and several sal<lb break="no"/>mon in the net, which had not been visited for two <lb/>
days. This, perhaps, was an isolated case, but those <lb/>
who had attended to the subject knew well that in <lb/>
prosecuting this fishery the most ruinous practices <lb/>
were followed. There is an excellent law upon our <lb/>
statute book relative to this subject, but it is nugatory, <lb/>
there being no police regulations to secure its being <lb/>
carried out. More and more it was becoming apparent <lb/>
how necessary was our establishment of some general <lb/>
supervision of the fisheries. The appointment of an <lb/>
able, educated and energetic man, as a general super<lb break="no"/>intendent of the fisheries, with a handsome salary, to <lb/>
secure the services of an efficient person, having at <lb/>
his command a steamer, for the purpose of visiting <lb/>
every part of the Island, during the summer, and in<lb break="no"/>vested with magisterial authority, to enforce the laws <lb/>
relative to the fisheries, was the only way this could <lb/>
be effected, and looking to the all importance of the <lb/>
subject, it was that for which, no matter what it might <lb/>
cost, should be the first money appropriated from the <lb/>
revenue; for the country was woolly dependent on <lb/>
the fisheries. The great question of Confederation <lb/>
was unquestionably the most important ever sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to the Legislature of this country; and the <lb/>
view of being united to a country so rich in resources <lb/>
as Canada, New Brunswick add Nova Scotia, and form<lb break="no"/>ing the nucleus of a great nation, was peculiary fas<lb break="no"/>cinating and attractive. That country possessed every <lb/>
internal resource uecessary to become great; and it <lb/>
required no prophetic spirit to foretel what she would <lb/>
be. Her unbounded forests, her vast mineral depos<lb break="no"/>its as yet put partially developed, her rich plains, <lb/>
    <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> for agricultural operation, her magnificent <lb/>
rivers intersecting every part of the county, and <lb/>
forming natural highways for the transport of her <lb/>
    produce, the safe and capacious <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> of Nova <lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick, afforded the means <lb/>
which required only sufficient population to raise her <lb/>
to the first rank, as a dependency, and in the course <lb/>
of years, the equal of the parent state. Was there <lb/>
anything wanting that nature had not bestowed in <lb/>
that country? Still it had been said that Canada <lb/>
wanted to tax Newfoundland to sustain her resources. <lb/>
Rich Canada abstracting from the barren island of <lb/>
Newfoundland, with 100,000 inhabitants one-thirtieth <lb/>
part of the whole population, a something to sustain <lb/>
her resources. The view was too absurd to need <lb/>
comment. But it was a matter that required grave <lb/>
consideration. When once we had embarked in con<lb break="no"/>federation thera was no return. We were bound for <lb/>
    ever. It should not be disposed of hastily, but be ap<lb break="no"/>proached in a spirit of calm deliberation and <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
enquiry. But when once a conclusion had been ar<lb break="no"/> 


<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-02_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>

rived at, when hon. gentlemen had formed their opi<lb break="no"/>nions, he tructed that each would fearlessly act, on <lb/>
these opinions, guided by his conscience to do what <lb/>
he conceived to be the most advantageos, for <lb/>
the public good, present and future. His Excellency <lb/>
referred to the Geological Survey, in which some pro<lb break="no"/>gress had been made, which was due to the efforts of <lb/>
the present administration; and by its results it had <lb/>
given us hopes that our mineral wealth was extensive. <lb/>
There were at present two copper mines in operation, <lb/>
which were affording employment and assistance to <lb/>
many, who, from the failure of the fisheries, and but <lb/>
for such timely aid, would be in great distress. The <lb/>
enterprising capitalists who were working these mines <lb/>
should be encouraged. Everything should be done by <lb/>
this House to assist parties who had thus invested <lb/>
their capital, as these gentlemen had done. He (Mr. <lb/>
Whiteway)referred to this matter, because he believed <lb/>
these parties had not received that consideration from <lb/>
the government to which they were entitled. He said <lb/>
this with regard to the postal communication. They <lb/>
had been compelled to employ special messengers to <lb/>
carry their mails, to maintain their communication <lb/>
with England, and this ought not to be. If a small <lb/>
amount were given for that purpose it would be well <lb/>
expended. He (Mr. W.) thought that all must coin<lb break="no"/>cide in the hope expressed by his Excellency relative <lb/>
to the laying of the Atlantic Telegraph Cable. He <lb/>
(Mr. Whiteway) never could refer to this subject with<lb break="no"/>out thinking of one who was its pioneer in this coun<lb break="no"/>try. He referred to Mr. F. N. Gisborne, who after <lb/>
connecting all the British North American Provinces, <lb/>
first conceived the idea of uniting this colony with <lb/>
the mother country by means of the Atlantic Tele<lb break="no"/>graph Cable. Nothing gave that gentleman greater <lb/>
pleasure now than looking <choice><sic>ferward</sic><corr>forward</corr></choice> to its successful <lb/>
completion next summer. He (Mr. Whiteway) would <lb/>
not detain the House any longer at present, as each <lb/>
matter referred to by his Excellency would individu<lb break="no"/>ally form a subject for discussion hereafter. He <lb/>
begged to second the motion for the appointment of a <lb/>
Select <choice><sic>Committea</sic><corr>Committee</corr></choice>. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. PARSONS—No person who had heard that <lb/>
speech but must agree that it was a masterly effort. <lb/>
It was the maiden speech of an able statesman who <lb/>
pandered to no party. There were suggestions in <lb/>
which he (Mr. Parsons) did not concur; but taken <lb/>
as a whole, it was the most practical opening speech <lb/>
to which the House had listened for a long time. It <lb/>
touched on many important subjects; and shadowed <lb/>
forth some things, which, if carried into effect, would <lb/>
be productive of incalculable benefit to the people of <lb/>
the country. His Excellency, during the short time <lb/>
he had been amongst us, appeared to have directed <lb/>
his attention to the wants of the country with an <lb/>
earnest desire to promote the best interests of the <lb/>
people over whom he had been appointed to rule. <lb/>
There were, however, suggestions in which he (Mr. <lb/>
Parsons) could not concur. His Excellency recom<lb break="no"/>mended that every district should be made to support <lb/>
its own poor. That appeared to be very reasonable; <lb/>
but when, from the failures of the fisheries, the people <lb/>
of many districts of the island were reduced to des<lb break="no"/>titution, there were few or none in those districts who <lb/>
were in a condition to contribute any thing for the <lb/>
support of their neighbours. He (Mr. Parsons) <lb/>
thought if his Excellency had gone farther with the <lb/>
subject of agriculture he would have pointed out the <lb/>
only means of raising the people above want. It was <lb/>
well known that the fisheries of the country were ina<lb break="no"/>dequate to sustain its increasing population, and that <lb/>
it was, their partial failure, for several <choice><sic>yearr</sic><corr>years</corr></choice> past, <lb/>
which had brought the people to their present state. <lb/>
No people were hardier or more energetic than the <lb/>
fishermen of this colony; but still, from unsuccessful <lb/>
fisheries, many of them were reduced to a <choice><sic>sthte</sic><corr>state</corr></choice> of <lb/>
absolute want. He (Mr. Parsons) had long urged <lb/>
upon successful governinents the necessity of giving <lb/>
proper encouragement to agriculture, as the only <lb/>
means of giving the people something to rely on. He <lb/>
would remind them that the immense sum of £30,000 <lb/>
had been annually voted by the House, and expended <lb/>
by the goverument in relieving the poor. Wound it <lb/>
not have been more beneficial it that sum, or a large <lb/>
portion of it, had been employed in the encouragement <lb/>
of agriculture, which would have placed many of its <lb/>
recipients above the degradation of poor relief? What <lb/>
permanent good arose from that expenditure? Did <lb/>
the government act in that paternal manner to be <lb/>
expected from them, in expending such a large sum? <lb/>
When public improvements were spoken of, we were <lb/>
told that the government had no money; and still we <lb/>
had this enormous pauper expenditure going on; and <lb/>
the only return we had was the making of a few bye­<lb break="yes"/>roads and the repair of a few unimportant bridges. <lb/>
Could any person persuade the people that the money <lb/>
was properly expended? If that money was expend<lb break="no"/>ded in the promotion of agriculture, or in stimulating <lb/>
the fisheries, would we not have a different result? <lb/>
Would the people be degraded, as now, by being <lb/>
compelled to come to the Chairman of the Board of <lb/>
Works and the Colonial Secretary to ask for pauper <lb/>
relief? When was it, until a few years ago, that the <lb/>
fishermen of the country came bowing to an official, <lb/>
sustained on the produce of the fishermen's labour, <lb/>
begging for a crumb of bread? When was it that a <lb/>
fisherman had to come to a mushroom official to beg <lb/>
a pittance of that which his own labour had produced? <lb/>
Few knew the reduced condition of the people of the <lb/>
country, whose toil had enriched the land. Let the <lb/>
money of the Treasury be thrown broadcast to those <lb/>
who wanted it, for it was by their toil that it came into <lb/>
The Treasury. The speech referred to the mackerel <lb/>
fishery and the Bank fishery; but how were the fisher<lb break="no"/>men to prosecute these fisheries without encourage<lb break="no"/>ment from the government? Give them the means <lb/>
out of that money which was their own. But it was <lb/>
best if they were enabled to cultivate the land; but <lb/>
from unsuccessful fisheries they were so reduced that <lb/>
the land remained uncultivated. If the Government <lb/>
enabled them to cultivate it, they would be relieved <lb/>
from the necessity of giving poor relief. The govern<lb break="no"/>ment had some years ago offered land free, with as<lb break="no"/>sistance in cultivation, and in building a dwelling­<lb break="yes"/>house, to any person who should settle upon it; and <lb/>
he (Mr. Parsons) had applied to the Surveyor-General <lb/>
to be intormed how many had availed of the offer, <lb/>
when it was stated that only one or two bad done so. <lb/>
But he had been told that thirty or forty had applied; <lb/>
but that they were sent from one official to another, <lb/>
and nothing actually done for them, that they had <lb/>
given up the hope of getting anything. The offer was <lb/>
a perfect delusion. The hon. member opposite sha<lb break="no"/>dowed forth a measure which seemed to interest him. <lb/>
much, the proposed federation of the colonies, which <lb/>
was to produce such beneficial results. He (M. <lb/>
Parsons) hoped it would be made a government mea<lb break="no"/>sure. He could not hear from hon. gentlemen favor<lb break="no"/>able to it what these resuls were to be. They were <lb/>
content to live on generalities. It was a very great <lb/>
thing in prospective; but, at all events, hon. members <lb/>
were not in a position to deal with it this session. He <lb/>
wished to know who authorised these gentlemen to <lb/>
proceed to Quebec and sign the resolutions of the <lb/>
Conference on behalf of the people of this colony, <lb/>
without the authority of the people. The hon. Premier <lb/>
forbore to take the constitutional course last session <lb/>
to obtain authority for sending delegates to the Char<lb break="no"/>lottetown Convention, to confer about a Legislative <lb/>
union of the Maritime Provinces. But it never en<lb break="no"/>tered into the minds of the people to unite with Ca<lb break="no"/>nada, a province so deeply sunk in debt, a union <lb/>

<cb/>

from which we could not derive any benefit. Canada <lb/>
was deeply sunk in debt, and wanted to be enabled to <lb/>
tax the people of the Maritime Provinces to improve <lb/>
their credit; and the Government came down very <lb/>
civilly to acquaint the House that a measure would <lb/>
pass the Imperial Parliament to give effect to the Re<lb break="no"/>solutions of the Conference. He (Mr. Parsons pro<lb break="no"/>tested against any proceeding in the matter this ses<lb break="no"/>sion, except to denounce it. They had experience <lb/>
in Ireland of the blighting effects of such unions. <lb/>
Such unions were productive of misery wherever <lb/>
they were carried into effect. The great O'Con<lb break="no"/>nell had been occupied half his life in the en<lb break="no"/>deavour to effect a repeal of the union of Ireland with <lb/>
England; and since the death of that great leader, the <lb/>
people were making constant efforts to get rid of the <lb/>
union, which was such a drawback on the prosperity of <lb/>
Ireland. He (Mr. Parsons) thought very few mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the house would consent to give up their coun<lb break="no"/>try to Canada, to tax us as they pleased. They would <lb/>
take our fisheries, lands and minerals, and what would <lb/>
they give us in return? Nothing tangible. It was all <lb/>
a delusion. He (Mr. Parsons) trusted the address <lb/>
would not be a mere echo of the speech. He would <lb/>
strike out the paragraph about poor relief. He trust<lb break="no"/>ed, especially when they came to the paragraph about <lb/>
the Quebec Conference, that they would not compro<lb break="no"/>mise the interests of the people until they went to a <lb/>
new election and had the views of the people on the <lb/>
subject. He did not feel at liberty to dispose of the <lb/>
matter now, and could only express his own senti<lb break="no"/>ments on the subject. He thought the proposed union <lb/>
was not at all calculated to benefit the people of this <lb/>
Colony, and so far as he was acquainted with their <lb/>
views, they were opposed to it. What the people <lb/>
wanted was remunerative employment in their own <lb/>
country. The government had expended £30,000 a <lb/>
year in poor relief. Let that money be expended in <lb/>
enabling the fishermen to cultivate the soil, and <lb/>
there would be but little poverty. The greater number <lb/>
of fishermen in the eastern portions of the district <lb/>
were possessed of land, but they had not the means <lb/>
of cultivation it. Why, in place of degrading them <lb/>
by pauper relief, did not the Government assist them <lb/>
to cultivate this land? They might easily be enabled to <lb/>
raise from 100 to 200 barrels of potatoes each, which <lb/>
would readily sell in this market is preference to the <lb/>
inferior potatoes coming from Prince Edward Island, <lb/>
and put those that raised them above want, for the <lb/>
man who had 200 barrels of potatoes required no <lb/>
relief from the Government. <lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:CASE2">MR. CASEY</persName>.—His Excellency the Governor was <lb/>
certainly entitled to the thanks of this House for the <lb/>
admirable speech with which he had opened the pres<lb break="no"/>ent session. It was new and refreshing, and quite a <lb/>
contrast to what we had been accustomed to His <lb/>
Excellency was evidently desirous of carrying out <lb/>
everything that was beneficial to the interests of the <lb/>
country. He (Mr. Casey) was pleased with His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency's reference to the road service; and agreed <lb/>
with him, that it should be a permanent institution in <lb/>
the country. The road grant was the only return <lb/>
which the people had for the heavy taxes they had to <lb/>
pay. Nothing tended so much to civilize a country as <lb/>
the opening of highways. Another subject of impor<lb break="no"/>tance was the Bank fishery, it was a matter of great <lb/>
moment that something should be done to increase <lb/>
our fisheries. When the shore fishery was unsuccess<lb break="no"/>ful, poverty was the certain result. Any legislation <lb/>
tending to benefit our fisheries must be regarded as a <lb/>
great boom, and ought to be carefully attended to. <lb/>
He (Mr. Casey) had heard an old experienced fisher<lb break="no"/>man, and one whose opinion on such matters should <lb/>
carry weight with it, assert that nothing tended so <lb/>
much to the injury of the fishery as the destruction of <lb/>
the roe of the fish. If such was the case, and we had <lb/>
reason to believe it was so, it was the duty of the <lb/>
Legislature to enact some law to prevent the destruc<lb break="no"/>tion. This country possessed great mineral resources, <lb/>
and it was high time that they were properly developed, <lb/>
and made the means of affording employment, and <lb/>
thus reducing the immense number of those who are <lb/>
recipients of pauper relief. He had been told that Mr. <lb/>
Bennett, the pioneer in all such matters, had lately <lb/>
entered largely and with considerable success into the <lb/>
working of mines to the Northward. No man deser<lb break="no"/>ved more the thanks of the people, for his liberality and <lb/>
enterprise in all matters tending to benefit this Colo<lb break="no"/>ny, than Mr. Bennett. There was another subject, <lb/>
namely poor relief, which had been referred to by his <lb/>
Excellency. Last session a Bill on the subject had <lb/>
been introduced by the government, to asses the dis<lb break="no"/>tricts fer the support, of the poor, but after sometime, <lb/>
it was dropped. He thought too that it was rightly <lb/>
withdrawn, and anything that in any way tended to <lb/>
increase taxes should be resisted by this House. All <lb/>
that the country required was successful fisheries, and <lb/>
it would soon rise like a Phoenix from its ashes, into <lb/>
the enjoyment of prosperity. He felt convinced that, <lb/>
with good fisheries, poverty would cease, and there <lb/>
would be no necessity for the immense drain now made <lb/>
on the public purse. But the all absorbing topic of <lb/>
the day was confederaton; a subject on which natu<lb break="no"/>rally, the people felt a deep interest. It was the duty <lb/>
of the Representatives of the people to let the public <lb/>
know what there opinions on the matter were. He <lb/>
considered that if we joined the Confederation, we <lb/>
would be doing this conntry a great wrong. We had <lb/>
already free institutions; and there was no Colony in <lb/>
which the principles of Governmental Responsibil<lb break="no"/>ity had worked better than in this. There was nothing <lb/>
to prevent, our young men from attaining elevated <lb/>
positions here now; and the rewards to be obtained <lb/>
should satisfy their ambition. He felt that there would <lb/>
be a great deal of ability brought to bear upon this <lb/>
question, and that matters would be put before the <lb/>
public in a plausible light. It was idle to suppose that <lb/>
if we joined this Confederation, we should be exempt <lb/>
from an increase of taxes. How were an Army and <lb/>
Navy for the Confederation to be supported? In four <lb/>
or five years hence we would have as much increased <lb/>
taxation as we received from Canada. (Here the hon <lb/>
member read an article from a Nova Scotia newspaper <lb/>
against Confederation.) <lb/></p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SHEA2">Mr. A. SHEA</persName>.—What paper is that? <lb/></p>
    
    
    <p>Mr. Casey—A highly influential and respectable <lb/>
        journal, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bull Frog</hi>.—Mr. Casey continued—No <lb/>
doubt the lawyers took a warm interest in the matter, <lb/>
having before their eyes Judgeships, Governorships, <lb/>
and other lucrative appointments. It would, no doubt, <lb/>
be a fortunate thing for them, when they were pocket<lb break="no"/>ing their salaries; but what substantial benefit was <lb/>
to be conferred on Newfoundland, was to him (Mr. <lb/>
Casey,) a mystery. He felt convinced few men would <lb/>
support such a sploitation of the rights of the people of <lb/>
this colony.</p>


    <p rendition="simple:centre">(<hi rendition="simple:italic">To be continued</hi>.)</p>
    
    <!-- IC, 2018-11-06, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->
    
<!--<p>Holloway's Prºs-Easy digestion.—These ad<lb break="no"/>mirable Pils cannot be too highly appreciated for the <lb/>
wholesome power they exert over aii disorders of the <lb/>
stomach, liver, bowels, and kidneys. They instanta<lb break="no"/>neously relieve and steadily work out a thorough cure, <lb/>
and its course dispel headache, bitiousness, flatulence <lb/>
and depression of spirits, i'i. wonderful to watch <lb/>
the flaily improvement of the complexion, as Hollo<lb break="no"/>**)'s Pills purify the blood and restore piumpness to <lb/>
the face, which had lost both flesh and colour. These <lb/>
Pills coinuine *y excellence desirable in a dome. <lb/>
***'. The must certain and beneficial results flow <lb/>
from the occasional use of thus regulating medicine; <lb/>
... Pºons in health, or when Ério. sedeutar r <lb/>
F., ne nº. 1 g....:. . . . - y <lb/>
*pations, will find it an invaluable apeiieut. <lb/></p> -->

</div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, Jannary 27.</p> 

<p>Observations of the Hon. R. J. PINSENT in moving <lb/>
    the Address in reply to His Excellency's Speech:— <lb/></p> 

        <p><persName ref="pers:PINS2">Hon. R. J. PINSENT</persName> rose to make a motion,—the <lb/>
usual one on an occasion of this kind—that a committee <lb/>
be appointed to prepare a reply to the very gracious <lb/>
speech with which the present session of the legislature <lb/>
has been inaugurated. He should not at this time <lb/>
ocuupy at very considerable length, the attention of the <lb/>
Council in discussing elaborately the many subjects <choice><sic>o</sic><corr>of</corr></choice> <lb/>
public concern which his Excellency the Governor <choice><sic>hadf</sic><corr>had</corr></choice> <lb/>
alluded to; nor devote himself to an analysis of the <lb/>
general affairs of the colony. These matters would come <lb/>
within the range of their deliberations at future and <lb/>
more fitting periods for discussion. At present he should <lb/>
confine his remarks to a summary review of the leading <lb/>
features of the Speech, preparatory to the motion he was <lb/>
about to make. He (Mr. P.) regarded the present as no <lb/>
common period in the history of the colony, viewing its <lb/>
depressed trade and the destitute gondition of the people, <lb/>
—the sad result of successive misfortunes and difficul<lb break="no"/>ties—a state of affairs which evoked the anxiety of all <lb/>
interested in the country's welfare. In this crisis Her <lb/>
Majesty had been pleased to appoint a new Governor to <lb/>
preside over our political destinies, in place of the <lb/>
venerable gentleman of whose very late decease we had <lb/>
just heard, after the attainment of a mature old age, and <lb/>
having spent many years of his life in honourable public <lb/>
service. In the gentleman who had been appointed to <lb/>
succeed him, so far as we could judge from our neces<lb break="no"/>sarily short and imperfect experience, Her Majesty's <lb/>
Government had made a very happy and fortunate selec<lb break="no"/>tion, and we have every reason to believe that the ad<lb break="no"/>ministration, of the colony affairs of the colony under his <lb/>
guidance will prove of that vigorous and judicious charac<lb break="no"/>ter which the circumstances of the country now demand. <lb/>
We recognize in him a ruler in the prime and vigor of <lb/>
physical and intellectual manhood, whose ability and <lb/>
education, general and official, were evidently of a high <lb/>
order, and who he (Mr. P.) believed possessed in con<lb break="no"/>nection with them those qualities of head and heart <lb/>
which adorn the high position he occupies, and fit him <lb/>
to fulfil its duties with honour to himself and with ad<lb break="no"/>vantage to the interests of the people whom he has been <lb/>
appointed to govern, He thought that in giving this <lb/>
expression to his own sentiments he was also expressing <lb/>
the feelings of his brother members and of the community <lb/>
in general. The language of his Excellency, in address<lb break="no"/>ing the legislature to-day, still further strengthened the <lb/>
evidence of his desire to promote the welfare of the <lb/>
country. That Speech was an able State document, as <lb/>
            well as chastely and eloquently expressed,—one adapted <lb/>
to the time and circumstances, and he (Mr. P ) could not <lb/>
conceive an occasion when it could afford him greater <lb/>
pleasure to propose the customary. Address than the <lb/>
present one. His Excellency first draws our attention <lb/>
to that subject of most material concern to us—the <lb/>
fisheries; and expresses his regret that misfortune and <lb/>
failure attended them. We cannot help deploring with <lb/>
his Excelleney those misfortunes, the cousequence in a <lb/>
great measure of physical laws which it is beyond our power <lb/>
to control. There was nothing that could relieve us and <lb/>
render our efforts successful in this respect but the mer<lb break="no"/>cy of God, and the renewed bounty of nature combi<lb break="no"/>ned with the exercise of increased exertion anu self-reli<lb break="no"/>ance upon the part of the people, a duty in which they <lb/>
should be encouraged by the legislature and assisted in <lb/>
the prosecution of their labours as far as may be practica<lb break="no"/>ble by judicious enactments. There was an old saying <lb/>
and an apt one,—"trust in God and keep your powder <lb/>
dry;" and as a rule it was, a very practical and judicious <lb/>
policy to follow in the general affairs of the world. <lb/>
Whatever means we have at our disposal calculated to <lb/>
contribute in any way to the general promotion of our <lb/>
resources, we should be culpable in neglecting to use in <lb/>
the manner and for the ends they were provided by a <lb/>
kind Providence. As a consequence of the failure of our <lb/>
            fisheries, that terrible incubus—pauper relief, has for <lb/>
years been expanding into gigantic proportions, destroy<lb break="no"/>ing the energy of the people and gradually but surely <lb/>
encroaching upon the resources of the country. His <lb/>
Excellency speaks of this subject in a practical aud com<lb break="no"/>prehensive way, but the difficulties of correcting it by <lb/>
legislation were in his (Mr. P.'s) mind of no ordinary <lb/>
character. Successive governments have endeavoured to <lb/>
apply a remedy, or at least to diminish its magnitude, but <lb/>
failure has attended their efforts. He hoped that the <lb/>
anticipation of his Excellency, with regard to the mitiga<lb break="no"/>tion of this evil and the settlement of some measure of <lb/>
practical reform, would be realized. The peutiliar circum<lb break="no"/>stances of the trade and of the people suggested peculiar <lb/>
difficulties; and the further circumstances, that the ques<lb break="no"/>tion is so often availed of in the legislature as well as <lb/>
out of doors,as political capital and for partisan purposes, <lb/>
presented another obstacle in the way of reform. He <lb/>
noped that the same vigour and discretion which had <lb/>
kept the expenditure for this service within the estimate <lb/>
for the past year would be brought successfully to bear <lb/>
upon the important and complicated question. As re<lb break="no"/>gards his Excellency's reference to the desirableness of <lb/>
prosecuting the mackerel and Bank cod-fiscery, he (Mr. <lb/>
P.) was not aware that the mackerel fisuery had so far <lb/>
improved as to be capable of prosecution witn advantage <lb/>
by the people of this country. Perhaps he was in error <lb/>
in the belief, but his impression was that the mackerel <lb/>
did not frequent our coast in sufficient quantities to make <lb/>
that fishery a profitable pursuit. Repecting the Bank <lb/>
fisnery, however, his opinion was very different. The <lb/>
suggestion of his Excellency on this subject was one con<lb break="no"/>taining much force, and he (Mr. P.) trusted that a mea<lb break="no"/>sure would be introduced giving eucouragement to those <lb/>
who may be inclined to participate in what he believed <lb/>
would prove a fruitful acquisition to the resources of the <lb/>
people and the trade of the colony. Many years ago the <lb/>
Bank fishery was prosecuted by our people with favour<lb break="no"/>able results, but some cause or other, perhaps fail<lb break="no"/>ure of prices or greater comparative success in other <lb/>
quarters, led to the abandonment. The circumstances <lb/>
of the country have since that period undergous very <lb/>
great alterations;—that disproportionate success which <lb/>
did away with our Bank fishery has ceased to exist, and <lb/>
the wants of the country demand a resort to other means <lb/>
of support than those which of late years have proved <lb/>
inadequate te the necessities of the people. This was a <lb/>
question of serious consideration for our merchants, plan<lb break="no"/>ters and fishermen. It was a tangible one, and was al<lb break="no"/>most certain to renumerate under judicious encourage<lb break="no"/>ment, those who undertake to carry it out. Agriculuure <lb/>
next engages his Excellency's consideration, aud of his <lb/>
interest in this subject the country has already had <lb/>
practical experience. The Agricultural Society was the <lb/>
first public body which addressed his Excellency after <lb/>
his arrival in the colouy. He (Mr. P.), as Vice-Presi<lb break="no"/>dent in the absence of the President of that body, had <lb/>
the honor of presenting its address, and his Excellency's <lb/>
reply evinced the cordial concern he felt in the promo<lb break="no"/>tion of this branch of our industrial occupatious. Much <lb/>
more might (he Mr. P. believed) be done in the exten<lb break="no"/>sion and maintenance of highways as a potent means <lb/>
towards the mast desirable end. Cultivation was an im<lb break="no"/>mediate cousequence of the construction of roads <lb/>
and the opening up of the country through their <lb/>
means. It was a wise suggestion on the part of his Ex<lb break="no"/>ellency that means should be taken to ensure a perma<lb break="no"/>nent
            legislative grant for the construction of roads, pla<lb break="no"/>cing it beyond the influence of chance of the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> of <lb/>
legislation; yet not preventing its extension when the <lb/>
means of the colony are sufficient to warrant greater ex<lb break="no"/>penditure. Roads were of the highest importance. Go <lb/>
where you will throughout the country,—wherever a <lb/> 
road is opened, there you find the cotter settling himself <lb/>
upon the soil; and though in the beginning his labours <lb/> 
seem of little account, they in due time become extended <lb/>
and bring comfort and support to the family of the poor <lb/>
man, adding to the improvement of the colony. In this <lb/>
connection the subject of sheep rearing deserves atten<lb break="no"/>tion. It was a matter that was likely to become a <lb/>
source of great benefit to the people in course of time, <lb/>
should it receive that liberal encouragement that it <lb/>
deserves. His Excellency also recommends the cultiva<lb break="no"/>tion of flax, in which he (Mr. P.) fully concurred. The <lb/>
practical suggestion respecting the improvement of the <lb/>
means of education, and particularly for the formation <lb/>
of Normal Schools to train teachers for the education of <lb/> 
the people, was one that merited serious attention; and <lb/>
we can't fail to approve of his Excellency's desire to <lb/>
promote it, as he trusted they should aid in doing. <lb/>
Unfortunately it happens that in Newfoundland the low <lb/>
standard of education amongst the masses of the people <lb/>
was owing, not so much to a deficiency of Schools, as to <lb/>
a careless and culpable negligence on the part of the <lb/>
people themselves to use tho educational privileges placed <lb/>
within their reach. We have Schools in many parts of <lb/>
the Island. Besides the institutions supported by Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, wonders had been done in the establishment <lb/>
of Schools by worthy Prelates and Ministers of religion; <lb/>
and very valuable aid was rendered by the Colonial <lb/>
Church and School Society in England, which has ex<lb break="no"/>pended annually, for many years, nearly £2,000 a-year <lb/>
towards educating the youth of the colony, erecting <lb/>
Schools, and providing efficient teachers, By these means <lb/>
the opportunities of education were brought to the doors <lb/>
of thousands who did not avail them. He (Mr. P.) <lb/>
should leave the discussion of his Excellency's recom<lb break="no"/>mendations upon the subject of the Salmon fishery to <lb/>
those legislators who were more conversant with the <lb/>
fisheries and better qualified to give a practical opinion <lb/>
upon it than he was. The Volunteer organization was a <lb/>
subject which appeared to have enlisted the particular <lb/> 
interest of his Excellency since his assumption of the <lb/>
<choice><sic>goverument</sic><corr>government</corr></choice>, and he suggeats measures for its contin<lb break="no"/>uance and extension. He (Mr. P.) entertained the <lb/>
opinion that in a country like this, the avocations <lb/>
of the people were of that peculiar character that the <lb/>
formation of a militia service could not prove practicable, <lb/>
therefore the best method of obtaining a local force was <lb/>
<choice><sic>bp</sic><corr>by</corr></choice> means of Volunteer companies;–they should be en<lb break="no"/>couraged and extended, as his Excellency suggests. The <lb/>
compilation and consolidation of the laws was a subject <lb/>
which had frequently occurred to his (Mr. P's.) mind, as <lb/>
he felt sure it had to many others, for years past, as a <lb/>
matter of great necessity. Any expense that would <lb/>
attend is effectuation would be amply repaid by the con<lb break="no"/>venience
and enlightenment so necessary a measure will <lb/>
afford, and he heartily coincided in this valuable sugges<lb break="no"/>tion in the Speech. With respect to the proposed <lb/>
Union of the British North American Colonies, he (M. <lb/>
P,) should reserve for the present any expression of <lb/>
opinion. In its official capacity this is the first time that <lb/>
question has been brought under the consideration of <lb/>
Council. We therefore know nothing of it beyond the <lb/>
allusion contained in the Speech from the Throne, and <lb/>
he should reserve its discussion until a more fitting <lb/>
            season;—after the reports and documents concerning it <lb/>
promised by his Excellency shall have been laid before <lb/>
the house. He (Mr. P.) was gratified to learn that the <lb/>
report of the efficient Geologist, Mr. Murray, who <lb/>
was employed last summer in surveying the min<lb break="no"/>eral lands of the country, has proved a highly satis<lb break="no"/>factory one. This was a subject which he (Mr. P) always <lb/>
felt a lively interest in, and had brought under the notices <lb/>
of the legislature nearly every Session since he had the <lb/>
honor of a seat in it. He always believed that our <lb/>
mineral deposits would one day prove a source of ines<lb break="no"/>timable wealth to the colony, and the terms in which his <lb/>
Excellency speaks of that Report foreshadow a prospec<lb break="no"/>tive and very valuable addition to our other branches of <lb/>
industry. We have already strong evidence of what <lb/>
may be anticipated, in the fact of the employment of <lb/>
foreign capital in the working of our mines, which he <lb/>
regarded as proof positive of the existence of substanţial <lb/>
grounds of hope. There was one subject referred to in <lb/>
the Speech which he (Mr. P.) regretted was not <lb/>
dealt with more explicitly,–that of coastal steam. That <lb/>
was a question of importance second to none, no even the <lb/>
roads, as regards the interests of the people; and he was <lb/>
sorry to see that difficulties had stood in the way of its <lb/>
being carried out so fully and efficiently, as was universally <lb/>
desired. We are assured the Government did is utmost <lb/>
to provide its more efficient establishment in accordance <lb/>
with the wishes and authority of the Legislature, but <lb/>
failed in their endeavours. He had no doubt the state<lb break="no"/>ment of his Excellency on this head was correct, and of <lb/>
course the legislature would be furnisned with a fuller <lb/>
explanation of the reason which prevented its accomplish<lb break="no"/>ment. He did not agree with those who opposed local <lb/>
Steam on the ground that there was not traffic sufficient <lb/>
to make the service remunerative or even self-supporting. <lb/>
He looked upon such an argument as false in principle <lb/>
and opposed to experience. Let the undertaking be <lb/>
established on an efficient basis, and it will in due time <lb/>
create a trade and business. We should not wait for <lb/>
traffic, but establish means for its encouragement. It <lb/>
had, however, another aspect,—the improving influence <lb/>
it would exercise upon the remote and isolated inhabitants <lb/> 
of the out-posts. This consideration should weigh equal<lb break="no"/>ly with the pecuniary one, in a subject of this nature, and <lb/>
he sincerely trusted that at no remote day local Steam <lb/>
would be placed upon more extended footing. In con<lb break="no"/>clusion he could not but join in the aspiration of his Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency, that "the Almighty Ruler of events may bless <lb/>
our labours and direct them for the good of the people <lb/>
whose interests are in our keeping, and crown our deli<lb break="no"/>berations with results promoting the good order, the <lb/>
peace, and the prosperity of the community to which we <lb/>
            belong." It was to us indeed a momentous period,— <lb/>
dark and gloomy one. Let us remember, however, <lb/>
that "the darkest hour precedes the brightest morn," <lb/>
and reflecting upon the difficulties we are now passing <lb/>
through, we may indulge a hope that they are the procur<lb break="no"/>sor of the dawn of happier and brighter days. He <lb/>
begged to move the appointment of a committee to <lb/>
prepare an Address in reply to his Excellency's Speech <lb/></p>
        
        <!-- IC, 2018-11-06, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day -->
        <!--<p>
MonDAY, January 30. <lb/>
The House met at 4 o'clock, <lb/>
Hon. E. MoRBIs, senior member, in the absence of hom <lb/>
Hon B. J. Pinsent, as chairman of the select com'' <lb/>
* Presented the draft of an Adirºs". reply to Hiſ <lb/>
Excellency the Governor's Speech; which was then read <lb/>
** time-to be read a second 'tiºn. to-morrow, and <lb/>
in the meantime printed, <lb/>
Hon R J PINskNT then gave notice of motion to sus<lb break="no"/>pend the 35th Rule of the House in reference to the <lb/>
Address, and the house adjourned until 4 o'clock tº: <lb/>
mºtow: TUESDAY, January 31! <lb/>
The House met at 4 o'clock. <lb/>
**:19asis, in the aosence of hon the Presides <lb/>
took the chair. -<lb break="maybe"/>9a motion of Hon R J Pinsent, the Address was read, <lb/>
**d time, and the 35th Rule of the je having. <lb/>
according to notice, been suspended, it was referred tº <lb/>
**mittee of the whole,_Hoa PGTEssº inj <lb/>
After some deliberations the several Sections wº <lb/>
adopted with a few verbal amendments, the committe'. <lb/>
ruse º *Ported, and the Address reaſia third time and <lb/>
passeu. <lb/>
* * then, on motion, ordered that it be engrosiº <lb/>
and presented to his Excellency the Governor by dep". <lb/>
tation of the whole house, <lb/></p> 

<p>The house then adjourned. ... — " <lb/></p> -->

        <!-- IC, 2018-11-09, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>i <lb/></p> 

<p>(Lºtt <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. <lb/>
THURSDA <lb/></p> 

<p>We have yet little ol <lb/>
in the proceedings <lb/>
branches the Address <lb/>
Throne has been ul <lb/>
Council it has passed. <lb/>
more discussed, and <lb/>
through committee. <lb/>
of a very salient ch <lb/>
point approaching th <lb/>
ence to Poor Relief <lb/>
recommended the pla <lb/>
the support of its owl <lb/>
and abandoned by th <lb/>
their reply to this sug <lb/>
nounce à clear nega <lb/>
application to the circ <lb/>
remarkable contradicti <lb/>
the same to the same, <lb/>
however, of course bro <lb/>
so this virtual amendm <lb/>
framers of the Address <lb/>
The Committee sat t <lb/>
ing one or two import: <lb/>
posed of when they rol <lb/></p> 

<p>MELANCHoly Acci <lb/>
lately befallen a poor <lb/>
ought to serve as a mo <lb/>
amongst us who are c <lb/>
of fire-arms. The fath <lb/>
a bird, but finding a d <lb/>
laid it up loaded in it <lb/>
unaware that the gun <lb/>
children, a little boy of <lb/>
and placed it for him oi <lb/>
his younger sister, was <lb/>
lying close to her. Th. <lb/>
when from some unluck <lb/>
charge and blew his po <lb/>
to the heartrending g <lb/>
Such a fearful example <lb/>
upon those who from th <lb/>
keep loaded guns in <lb/>
the reach of children. <lb/></p> 

<p>LATEST FR <lb/></p> 

<p>Richmond papers of <lb/>
that Wilmington was ev <lb/>
and that the Federals, 1 <lb/>
possession. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Augusta (Ga.) ( <lb/>
says that city " is fit, <lb/>
Carolina. It would at <lb/>
upon the people of tha. <lb/>
Untion aimy, and that <lb/>
tuing to save their fi <lb/></p> 

<p>Two blockade run <lb/></p> 

<p>into Fear River on th: <lb/>
was occupied by the Fº <lb/></p> 

<p>The Canadian Court <lb/>
U. S. Government, und <lb/>
Lake pirate Burleigh <lb/>
It is rumored that Je <lb/>
make submission to U. <lb/>
The Rebels recently <lb/>
down the North side of <lb/>
also a large land force. <lb/>
back by the Federals. <lb/>
The news of the failu <lb/>
pedition caused a rise <lb/>
land <lb/>
Gen. Hood has been <lb/>
Gen. Dick Taylor hs <lb/>
him. Gold 210. <lb/></p> 

<p>-º-E-º-º­ <lb/>
101ED,-\-On Sunday <lb/>
borne with meek subm <lb/>
Mary, eldest daughter <lb/>
years. <lb/>
At Trinity, on the <lb/>
tholomew Coleman, as <lb/>
At Bay Fortune, P. <lb/>
the 65th year of her a <lb/>
Wm. Underhay, Esq <lb/>
Militia of that Island. <lb/>
was sister to the propr <lb/>
At Halifax, N.S., or <lb/>
of diptheria, the infant <lb/>
- street. <lb/>
SMIIPPIAW tº <lb/>
<lb/> </p> 

<p>I <lb/>
Jan 27–Bianca, Wak <lb/>
Ktte, Scanlan, New Yº <lb/></p> 

<p>Jan 30–General Ros <lb/>
Iona, Muir &amp; Du: <lb/></p> 

<p>Ana (Sp) Rodriguez, <lb/></p> 

<p>Jan 31-Dart, Werge. <lb/></p> 

<p>Jan 23–Peerless, Eu <lb/>
25–Excelsior, Deme <lb/>
Swan, Cuba, A. Shea <lb/>
28 -Dart, W Indies. <lb/>
30-\-Julia Ellen, Port <lb/>
Arthur. Boston, Joh <lb/>
<lb/>Sales <lb/></p> 

<p>T}. <lb/>
(THURS <lb/></p> 

<p>At the <lb/></p> 

<p>The Property of * <lb/></p> 

<p>(for the <lb/>
Comprising tº <lb/>
25 Dozen Mle <lb/>
10 do. dº <lb/></p> 

<p>A lot of Supe <lb/>
A <lb/>
Herr <lb/></p> 

<p>Feb. 2. <lb/></p> 

<p>\ <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-06_Page_1.jpg"/> 
        <fw type="num">1</fw>
        <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
        
        <fw type="dateline">St. John's, Thursday, February 6, 1865</fw>

<!--<p>Notices. <lb/></p> 

<p>F= <lb/>
Mothers Mothers Tº <lb/></p> 

<p>procure Mrs. WINSLow" <lb break="maybe"/>children teething. s Soothin <lb/>
the prescription of one of the bes <lb/>
and nurses in the United States: <lb/>
for thirty years with never failiº rt <lb/>
. by millions of mothers alid chi. <lb/>
eeble infant of one week old to th. <lb/>
nly relieves the child from pain, b e <lb/>
tomach and bowels, corrects ji. <lb/>
ld energy to the whole system." <lb/>
tly relieve Griping in the Éowel, a. <lb/>
believe it the best and surest remed <lb/>
Il cases of Dissentery and Diarh. § <lb/>
it arises from teething or any j <lb/>
"ctions for use will accompany j <lb/>
fluine unless the fac-simile of Curtis <lb/>
he outside wrapper. Price only 25 <lb/>
Sold by all Medicine Dealers. Office <lb/>
'ew York, and 205 High Holbº <lb/></p> 

<p>S. WINSLow, <lb/></p> 

<p>Nurse and Female Physician, pr <lb/>
f mothers, her šj ..". <lb/>
which greatly facilitates the process <lb/>
|tering the gums, reducing all infia. <lb/>
v all pain and spasmodic action, and <lb/>
* the bowels. Depend upon it, m. <lb/>
F lest to yourselves, and relief and <lb/>
'ants. We have put up and sold this <lb/>
irty years, and can say, in confidence <lb/>
ºf we have never boea able to say <lb/>
cine-never has it failed in a singlé <lb/>
a cure, when timely used. Neº <lb/>
is ºnce of dissatisfaction by any ons <lb/>
the contrary, all speak delighted <lb/>
3, and speaks in tetus of commenda. <lb/>
- effects and medical virtues. We <lb/>
* ... what we do now," after thirty <lb/>
and pledge our reputation for the <lb/>
we here declare. In almost every <lb/>
* infant is suffering from pair and <lb/>
will be found in fifteen or twenty <lb/>
syrup is administered. Full direc. <lb/>
ill accompany each bottle. None <lb/>
he fac-simiſe of Curtis and Perkins <lb/>
the outside wrapper. Soº by Þº <lb/>
he world. Principal Office, 48 Dey <lb/>
205 High Ho-born, England. Price <lb/>
bottle. <lb/>
* *tract from a letter written by <lb/>
ne, Pāstor of the Pierrepont-street <lb/>
rooklyn, NY, to the "Journal and <lb/>
innati, O.. and speaks volumes in <lb/>
ld-renowned medicine, Mrs. WINs. <lb/>
vrup for Guildren Teething—" we <lb/>
ent in your c lurrns of Mrs. Wins­ <lb/>
rap... Now we newsr said a word in <lb/>
medicine before in our life, but we <lb/>
"y tº your readers that this is no <lb/>
* tried it, and know it to be alli <lb/>
*ably one of the most successful <lb/>
day, because it is one of the best <lb/>
readers who have babies can't do." <lb/>
a supply." <lb/>
. DE ARIN, St. John's, <lb/>
Agent for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>deºx FIRE; <lb/>
#86 ºpany. <lb/></p> 

<p>ret and Charing Cross, Londoa. <lb/>
4 H Lis HAE//-1782 <lb/>
'Tres an is pinkcroRs. <lb/>
risq. Kirkman D. Hodgº on Esq. <lb/>
" ... ºnes Hºrne, 44 <lb/>
William J. Lancaster, e. <lb/>
|Jºhn I). Magen, º <lb/>
-\- ſº Masterman,Esq. M., F. <lb/>
-\- 'ºhn Timohy oxley H tº <lb/>
tº ºverge Stanly Reptol, " <lb/>
|Bºsnin Shaw, ts <lb/></p> 

<p>. |..." Whiting, <lb break="maybe"/>ran is Wilson, º <lb/>
BEGRETARIES <lb/></p> 

<p>'ullax. HARRIs Esq. <lb/></p> 

<p>º tº LºvELL, Esq. <lb/>
FIRE OFFICE is confidently re­ <lb/>
* of the puishe—for the ºer. <lb/>
* with which all claims upon it are <lb/>
as well as for the almost uniº <lb/>
fords, ºuprising in aduuun to ſhe <lb/>
tal º the Cºmpany, the whole for <lb/>
* Prºprieta'y, composed of je <lb/>
it gentlemen and Merchants in the <lb/></p> 

<p>'. has "arried on an exten­ <lb/>
isines, for upwards of seventy­ <lb/>
ºnly, paid by it to Government fºr <lb/></p> 

<p>"eat Briain and 1 <lb/>
relan <lb break="maybe"/>Per Innºn. d exceed <lb/></p> 

<p>º Insurances are unde <lb/></p> 

<p>Q9MPANY on almost ...". <lb/>
Newfoundlaud at a moderaté rate <lb/>
; be know on application . <lb/>
office, in St. John's, where policies <lb/></p> 

<p>*arge. <lb/>
W. &amp; G. RENDEI.L, <lb/>
Adents for Merroundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>2 COLONIAL <lb/>
§ tº #: 4 - -<lb break="maybe"/>ºrante ü0 hpany <lb/>
ARLISHED E846. <lb/>
NE MILLION STERLING. <lb/>
Assuring before 25th <lb/>
May 1863. <lb/>
º PROFITS. <lb/>
*ge of this year's entry to th <lb/>
. must be lodged at #. §. <lb/>
. .." with one of the Agents <lb/>
º ..". º allocated at the <lb/>
564 to Policies <lb/>
ss for the Present º before <lb/>
* STECIAL Act of PARLIAMENT <lb/>
- Gºvernor. <lb break="maybe"/>Y. THE EARL OF ELGIN &amp; <lb/>
Governor-General of INDIA. <lb/>
iEORGE STREET, EDINBURGER <lb/>
* in St. John's, Newfoundland, <lb/>
, Esq. Walter Grieve, Esq., <lb/>
Merchant. <lb/>
n Henry Mare, Esq. <lb/>
-Henry Hunt Stabb, M.D. <lb/>
rederick J. Wyatt. <lb/>
OF THE COMPA NY. <lb/>
le Company... £130,000 <lb/>
livided Profits on two occasions— <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/></p> 

<p>ºpened in 1847,has beenincreased <lb/>
:pplication of the Bonus; other <lb/>
! 10n. <lb/></p> 

<p>iye years; next division in 1860. <lb/>
in any part of the world wher <lb/>
stablished, <lb/></p> 

<p>This waii; <lb/></p> 

<p>&amp; <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/>
No. 3,636. <lb/></p> 

<p>=­ <lb/>
inted and Published every Monday and Thursday <lb/>
mornings by Ely WARD DALTON SHEA, at his <lb/>
office in jūCKWORTH STREET-Terms–One <lb/>
Guinea per annº payable in advance. <lb/>
ãºrtisements not limited (Auction-sales and notices <lb/>
which determine themselves excepted) are repeated <lb/>
until ordered in writing to be withdrawn, and are <lb/>
charged for accordinglu. <lb/>
This paper is filed,and may be seen, free of charge at <lb/>
Followay's Pills and Ointment Establishmet, 244, <lb/>
Strand, London. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mºshop MscLoske y of New York <lb/>
ow THE SOCIETY OF ST. VINGENT <lb/>
DE PAUL. <lb/></p> 

<p>Respected Gentlemen ºf the Society of St. Vincent <lb/>
dº pºli-I am most happy to have the privilege of <lb/>
being present at this very interesting meeting of yout <lb/>
eneral conference, nºt only because it affords mº <lb/>
he opportunity of being made a witness of the extent <lb/>
and great respectability of your numbers, and to be: <lb/>
come also in some sort, more personally acquainted <lb/>
with you; but because it enables me besides to form a <lb/>
juster estima e of the progress and success of the great <lb/>
ºf good work of charity and religion in which you <lb/>
... iſ so zealously engaged. It needs, 1 trust, no <lb/>
words of mine tº give you the fullest assurance of the <lb/>
deep and lively interest which I feel in the welfare and <lb/>
rosperity of this excellent society. I trust that I <lb/>
estimate at its full worth, if it is really possible to es<lb break="no"/>timate it at its just, and full worth—the useful­ <lb/>
mess and importance ºf the Society of St. Wincent <lb/>
de Paul. I'conceive that one of the greatest bless<lb break="no"/>ings that can be enjoyed by any town, city, parish, or <lb/>
jºr-gation is to have established within it; precincts <lb/>
jºh or a conference of this society. , I cºn-evº <lb/>
it to be a source of especial happiness and benefit and <lb/>
blessing to all who are within the reach of its influ<lb break="no"/>ence-not only to the poor who become the objects <lb/>
of your charity, who arc relieved in their indigence <lb/>
aná want, not only to the sick and afflicted who re­ <lb/>
ºve from you words of consolation and temporal aid <lb/>
in alleviation of their sufferings, not only to the little <lb/>
thildren whom you rescue from vice and poverty, but <lb/>
ºbſessing also to the whole congregation and whole <lb/>
people where such a society exists, because the very <lb/>
&amp;ample which others, often not members of that so­ <lb/>
diety, have before their eyes—the beautiful example <lb/>
ºf seeing men devoting themselves so generously and <lb/>
so heroically to this work of relieving the distresses <lb/>
and the wants of their neighbors, of seeing them after <lb/>
a day of toil, when fatigue would invite them only to <lb/>
sit down and enjoy repose, to seek the comforts cf <lb/>
their own firesides, and the social peasures of their <lb/>
families, denying themselves all this, and going <lb/>
forth on their errands of mercy, perhaps on a <lb/>
Jold and bleak winter night, from house to house, <lb/>
from garret to cellar, dispersing their works of cha<lb break="no"/>rity. "I say this is a lessun to all who become the <lb/>
witnesses of it, and it is what must have in time, its <lb/>
effect upon their spiritual welfare. And it is, besides, <lb/>
I need of tell you, gentlemen of the St. Vincent de <lb/>
faul Society, a source of especial pleasure to those <lb/>
who are thus the members of these conferences, who <lb/>
are thus the dispensers of this charity, because it is <lb/>
for them one of the efficient means of gaining that <lb/>
for which you and I, and all of us, are laced here in <lb/>
this world-sanctification, and the salvation of our <lb/>
souls. I then repeat that I look upon the work, gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen, in which you are engag d as a work of reli<lb break="no"/>gion, as well as a work of charity; I look upon it as <lb/>
à great and holy work, in which you are made the <lb/>
atºiliaries of the ministers of Christ, in which you <lb/>
are made the co-workers in carrying out that great <lb/>
work, for which Christ came upon the earth and <lb/>
established and planted his Church, You knºw <lb/>
that in the early ages, in the very beginning, the <lb/>
charities of the faithful were generally dispensed <lb/>
by these who were appointed, by the apostles <lb/>
of their immediate successors for this work, and this <lb/>
privilege of being the dispensers of the charities of the <lb/>
Christians to their fellow-christian sufferers, was in<lb break="no"/>trusted chiefly to those who had consecrated, them<lb break="no"/>selves in religion—it was the work chiefly of the dea. <lb/>
cons of the "church, and in course of time as that <lb/>
church became spread out more widely over the face <lb/>
of he earth, then the provision was made in thºs: <lb/>
religious orders which sprung up on every side, filled <lb/>
with men who had themselves renounced the riches <lb/>
and pleasures of the world simply to devote themselves <lb/>
to the service of God and to the service of his poor­ <lb/>
because every service to the poor is especially a serº <lb/>
to God—and the convents and their inmates were the <lb/>
dispensers of charity to the poor and suffering of the <lb/>
church, and what came into the treasury of the <lb/>
church, out of what were the legitimate revenues of <lb/>
the church itself had its division, part for the ministry, <lb/>
part for the altar, part for some other purpose. but <lb/>
al-ays a share for the poor. In those days, too, taº <lb/>
were poor in the land, because we had the promise <lb/>
that we should always have the poor with us, but the <lb/>
promise was also given that we should have Christ <lb/>
Always with us, and Christ in his church never aban<lb break="no"/>doned the poor, but made that church instrumental <lb/>
for the relief of the indigent and suffering members ºf <lb/>
Jesus Christ, Bat when the time came that heresy <lb/>
made its innovations and attacks upon the church, <lb/>
and the time came when a false philosophy obtain<lb break="no"/>ed power in the minds of men, and the power <lb/>
ºf the Church was weakened, then in place of the <lb/>
ºnvents we had to have paupers, and workhouses and <lb/>
poorhouses, and state appropriations, and hºmº . <lb/>
pedien's, and conventions for the purpose of relieving <lb/>
these members of Jesus Christ.—But when the con<lb break="no"/>vents had to cease, and when those religious men who <lb/>
had been the dispensers of charity were scattered, their <lb/>
convents and institutions suppressed, and their num<lb break="no"/>bers becoming too small any longer to enable them <lb/>
to perform their work, then the Church gave its bles<lb break="no"/>sing to the devoted laymen of her bosom, and com<lb break="no"/>missioned them to go and do the work: and assosi<lb break="no"/>ations were formed in various parts among the laity <lb/>
and those no longer devoting themselves exclusively <lb/>
to a religious life to carry out the work, which as <lb/>
have said in the beginning, was a work, especially in<lb break="no"/>trusted to the Church, in the persons of the ministers <lb/>
and those who had entirely consecrated themselves to <lb/>
her service; and you are called upon, and you º <lb/>
permitted, and you have the Church's blessing 3 gº <lb/>
ºn and dº our work is not that a great honor * is <lb/>
not that a great privilege? And it is for jº: <lb/>
gentlemen of the Society of St. Vincent de Paul, <lb/>
to bear this always in mind that you are: real.y <lb/>
in a certain sense, missionaries of charity: and <lb/>
imissionaries, as I have said, also. of religion, <lb/>
because it is a well ascertained fact, that in <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, Monday, February 6, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>ity had taken such a deep hold of the hearts of the <lb/>
people, especially among the poor, and the igno<lb break="no"/>rant, and the unreflecting, that there has been <lb/>
nothing so poweriul to check the progress of infideity <lb/>
and bring back wandering minds to the practice of their <lb/>
religion as the influence of the society of St. Vincent <lb/>
de Paul. The members of that society in Paris can <lb/>
bear especial testimony to the Christian influence it <lb/>
has had in that immense city not merely in relieving <lb/>
want, not simply in alleviating distress, but often <lb/>
in planting the seeds of faith, in hearts that <lb/>
were calious and cold, and ignorant of God <lb/>
and of the interests of their immortal souls. <lb/>
I do not conceal from myself that you, in your mis<lb break="no"/>sion, must, at many times, have discouragements to <lb/>
encounter; you must have obstacles to meet, you must <lb/>
have temptations from time to time to abandon the <lb/>
work. You go among those poor people some imes <lb/>
after you have done all you could for them, and you <lb/>
will have, instead of words of thanks,it may be some<lb break="no"/>times hard words of rebuke and abuse; you may find, <lb/>
sometimes, your efforts not at all crowned with any <lb/>
success, and you go away discouraged, and ask what <lb/>
is the use of continuing in this wºrk. The more you: <lb/>
do for these people the less they seem to apprecate it, <lb/>
and derive benefit from it. But these are simply mo<lb break="no"/>mentary discouragements, and I will answer that the <lb/>
joys far exceed the little difficulties which you may <lb/>
have to experience. I will venture to say that the <lb/>
experience of almost each one of the members of this <lb/>
society present has been that, after going into these <lb/>
hovels of the poor, he has come away edified and in<lb break="no"/>structed, has come away amazed at the patient resig<lb break="no"/>nation with which many of them bow down their heads <lb/>
to that dispensation of Divine Providence which has <lb/>
consigned them to an almost hopeless, poverty during <lb/>
all the days of their lives, and while reciting their <lb/>
many sufferings and privations, still saying "God be <lb/>
praised," praising God and blessing God even for the <lb/>
seeming misery with which he seems to have visited <lb/>
them, showing how true it is, after all, that the virtu<lb break="no"/>ous poor are especially the members of Jesus Christ <lb/>
and the special objects of his love, and he knows how <lb/>
even to pour consolation into their hearts. It is this <lb/>
which will encourage and cheer you. I trust that you <lb/>
will go on increasing in the spirit of zeal and devotion. <lb/>
God will bless your work just in proportion as you <lb/>
enter into the true spirit .# St. Vincent de Panl him<lb break="no"/>self, and you will enter into that spirit also in the pro<lb break="no"/>portion as you will be faithful to observe all the rules <lb/>
and regulations that are laid down for you as members <lb/>
of the society. It is often with these associations as it <lb/>
is with the higher ones in 1eligious orders, that the <lb/>
rules may sometimes seem very insignificant, and yet <lb/>
the whole prosperity and strength and final success of <lb/>
the society depends upon the manner in which the <lb/>
rules will be observed, both in the spirit and in <lb/>
the letter. I am glad to learn from the testimony of <lb/>
your respected president, and from the very reverend <lb/>
vicar-general that you are growing up more to the mea<lb break="no"/>sure of your object; that you are beginning more fully to <lb/>
enter into the spirit of that work. In your conferences <lb/>
and your meetings there should be oue object kept in <lb/>
view; there should never be a looking outside of the <lb/>
legitimate objects of your association; there should <lb/>
be no motives or interests that are not directly <lb/>
connected with religion, or outside of the sim<lb break="no"/>ple work of attending to the poor, and dispensing this <lb/>
charity without fear, or favour, or prejudice,partiality, <lb/>
according to the best of your judgment, and solely for <lb/>
the greater honor and glory of God, and for the relief <lb/>
of the poor, and for the sanctification of your souls. It <lb/>
will be your last, and your consoling reflection, that, <lb/>
although you devote your time, after your hoºrs of <lb/>
daily toil to this work; that after all, while the day <lb/>
has been spent in laboring to earn the bread that per; <lb/>
ishes, the evening is spent in laying up that bread <lb/>
which perishes not—the bread of eternal life-and <lb/>
while theſlay is consecrated to laying up the treasures <lb/>
of this world, in your work in the Society of St. <lb/>
Vincent de Paul, you are laying up treasures in heaven <lb/>
where moth nor rust do not corrupt, and where thioves <lb/>
do not break in and steal. There it will remain forever, <lb/>
ane there when work is over, God will call you to re<lb break="no"/>ceive your reward; for every man shall be rewarded <lb/>
according lo his works. <lb/></p> 

<p>The address was listened to with the greatest inter<lb break="no"/>est. The members then knelt, and the Archbishop <lb/>
asked the blessing upon the society. <lb/></p> 

<p>-º-º-º­ <lb/></p> 

<p>A NEW ENTERPRISE.-The blockade runners car<lb break="no"/>rying cotton from Wilmington, Charleston and Mata­ <lb/>
moras to Nassau and Bermuda have been pretty <lb/>
closely watched of late by our armed vessels, and, in <lb/>
several instances were chased so sharply that they <lb/>
had to throw quantitities of cotton overboard. These <lb/>
vessels run always in a regular track after they get <lb/>
outside of the blockading ine, so that the ships com<lb break="no"/>ing from the West Indies with fruit have frequently <lb/>
found a rich harvest of cotton afloat, for which they <lb/>
occasionally sacrifice their cargo, perinitting, it to rot <lb/>
wnile they are gathering in the more valuable casſº­ <lb/>
ways of the blockade runners. Recently the rebels <lb/>
have been in the habit of ripping open the bales be<lb break="no"/>fore throwing them overboard, and thus the Sea, for <lb/>
miles in their track, is whitened with floating cotton. <lb/>
This was wo tempting an opportunity for Yankee en<lb break="no"/>terprise to overlook, and we understand that, a com<lb break="no"/>pany has been formed in this city which employs ves: <lb/>
sels to follow the path of the blockade runners, and <lb/>
pick up the cotton, and that they are making a think <lb/>
quite out of it. This certainly a new kind of maritime <lb/>
enterprise.—N. Y. Herald <lb/></p> 

<p>–- <lb break="maybe"/> </p> 

<p>Holloway's PiLLs.-Easy digestion.-These ad<lb break="no"/>mirable Pills cannot be too highly appreciated for the <lb/>
wholesome power they exert over aii disorders of the <lb/>
stomach, liver, bowels, and kidneys. They instanta<lb break="no"/>neously relieve and steadily work out a thorºugh gure, <lb/>
and its course dispel headache, biliousness, flatulence <lb/>
and depression of spirits. It is wonderful to watch <lb/>
the daily improvement of the complexion, as Hollo<lb break="no"/>way's Pills purify the blood and restore plumpnº tº <lb/>
the face, which had lost botn flesh and colour. These <lb/>
Pills combine every excellence desirable in a domestio <lb/>
remedy. The most certain and beneficial result: flow <lb/>
from the occasional use of this *:::::: medicine; <lb/>
even persons in health, or when ollowing sedentary <lb/>
occupations, will find it an invaluable aperient. <lb/></p> 

<p>A FINE Head of HAIR.—Nature's own diadem <lb/>
and title a dignity is to-day the coveted treasure of <lb/>
every person, as it was in olden time the pride of Ab­ <lb/>
salom and the strength of Samson. . It is the duty of <lb/>
all to cultivate the hair. You can do it and preserve <lb/>
it through lite by the use of Mrs. S. A. Allen's World's <lb/>
Hair Restorer and Zylobalsamum, or Hair, Dressing: <lb/>
Every Druggist sells them. J J Dearin Sole Agent <lb/>
for Newfoundland, to whom all orders must be ad­ <lb/></p> -->
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head> 

        <p rendition="simple:centre">(<hi rendition="simple:italic">Continued.</hi>)</p> 

<p rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, Jan. 27.</p>
        <p>
            <persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName>.—Since the last session of the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly a change has taken place in the representative of the <lb/>
Crown, and the House now before them the opening <lb/>
speech of the talented statesman appointed by Her <lb/>
Majesty to succeed the late Governor of this Colony. <lb/>
In that gracious speech there were several suggestions of <lb/>
very great importance to the Colony. ... He (Mr. Renouf) <lb/>
must say, we had not, for years, listened to such a <lb/>
speech. It was altogether free from party views. It did <lb/>
not betray a bias for any party. He was especially grati<lb break="no"/>fied by the first paragraph. He believed the governor <lb/>
was perfectly sincere, and from the spirit which his <lb/>
Excellency evinced since his arrival amongst us, and his <lb/>
genral deportment and affability of manner, he had <lb/>
produced a most favourable impression, towards him in <lb/>
the community. His Excellency regarded, the failure of <lb/>
the fisheries with deep regret. It had reduced many of <lb/>
the fishermen to severe distress. The suggestion to <lb/>
afford encouragement to the Bank and Mackerel <lb/>
fisheries, was most judicious. These fisheries lay, as it <lb/>
were, at our doors, and had been neglected for years, <lb/>
while our neighbours in the United States came upwards <lb/>
of a thousand miles to prosecute them, and found them <lb/>
renumerative. These fisheries were entitled to the <lb/>
special attention of the government; and in place of <lb/>
allowing the fishermen to depend upon the Treasury for <lb/>
a miserable pittance in the shape of pauper relief, they <lb/>
should be encouraged to embark in those fisheries, which <lb/>
could not fail to prove renumerative. It was time they <lb/>
should do something to stimulate the energies of the <lb/>
people, and direct their industry into profitable channels, <lb/>
—He (Mr. Renouf) was happy to find that the new <lb/>
Governor differed from his Council. His advisers held <lb/>
that roads would not pay. They were a mere con<lb break="no"/>venience. But his Excellency was so satisfied of the im<lb break="no"/>portance of roads, that he proposed to make permanent <lb/>
provision for them. His Excellency was satisfied they <lb/>
would pay, and that they were essential to civilization <lb/>
and progress. With regard to education, he (Mr. Re<lb break="no"/>nouf) agreed with his Excellency. But he must have <lb/>
been misinformed respecting normal schools, for we had <lb/>
them already. Arrangements were made for training <lb/>
teachers at St. Bcnaventure College, as well as at the <lb/>
Central School, and at the Church of England and <lb/>
Wesleyan Academies. But there was a necessity for <lb/>
making the schools throughout the colony nore efficient; <lb/>
especially in the outports. But to secure this provision <lb/>
much be made for more adequate renumeration to the <lb/>
            teachers.—For £25 a year, they could not get a teacher <lb/>
of ability and education, with permission to go six weeks <lb/>
to the fishery. If they expected to have competent <lb/>
teachers, they must provide them with sufficient emolu<lb break="no"/>ment. Reference was made in his Excellency's speech <lb/>
to the currency. He (Mr. Reuouſ) said there never was <lb/>
such a humbug as the present currency. It was a system <lb/>
most insuitable to the wants of our people. It was passed <lb/>
twelve months ago, and the copper currency had only <lb/>
been lately imported. In place of cents the government, <lb/>
it appeared, sent to England for half-pence which were <lb/>
substituted for the base copper coin previously in <lb/>
circulation. They could compet the government depart<lb break="no"/>ments to keep their accounts in dollars and cents; but <lb/>
the trade having declined to do so, the consequence to <lb/>
the working classes was the loss of four half pence on <lb/>
the shilling in their purchases They had to take these <lb/>
coppers at the rate of twenty to the shilling, and they <lb/>
would be received by retailers only at half pence; which. <lb/>
was a serious loss to the poor men; and he (Mr. Re<lb break="no"/>nouf) would like to know whether the officials of the <lb/>
Government were to make up the loss. The hon. <lb/>
member for Ferryland, Mr. Gen, introduced a Bill, some <lb/>
years ago, to regulate the currency, which, would not <lb/>
have effected any change in the rate at which the different <lb/>
coins passed current, and was all that was required to <lb/>
give us a sound currency. There was no desire in the <lb/>
community for the change effected by the present Act. <lb/>
There were no petitions from the Commercial body in <lb/>
support of it. His Excellency referred to the subject of <lb/>
poor relief. The present, Government, had expended <lb/>
£80,000 in poor relief within the past four years; and <lb/>
there was no guarantee that the money had gone to the <lb/>
deserving poor. What evidence was there that it was <lb/>
not applied for the sustentation of political influence in <lb/>
the Northern districts. We were told there was some <lb/>
improvement in the revenue. But what benefit would <lb/>
the people derive from it, after the loss of £2,000 on <lb/>
bogus bonds, taken at the Custom-house by the Receiver <lb/>
General, from men of straw. But when improvement <lb/>
in the reveuue was spoken of, why was there no mention <lb/>
of the Labrador? Was there no increase of revenue <lb/>
there? It was a subject of boasting last session, that <lb/>
some £1,300 had been collected on the coast of Labra<lb break="no"/>dor. He (Mr. Renouf) quite agreed with his Excellency; <lb/>
that encouragement suould be given to the Bank and <lb/>
Mackerel fisheries. 5,000 expended in bounties to these <lb/>
fisheries would be far preferable to wasting it in poor <lb/>
relief. But would that be given? No, the government <lb/>
would not spend a pound for the encouragement of the <lb/>
fishermen, from whom they derived all their means of <lb/>
support. Agriculture was referred to, which the go<lb break="no"/>vermment made loud professions of a desire to stimulate, <lb/>
and proposed to give free grants of land, and assist in <lb/>
its cultivation, but it resulted in nothing. Applicants <lb/>
were sent from one official to anotuer, and nothing was <lb/>
done for them. His Excellency referred to the <lb/>
raising of sheep, which would be followed by most <lb/>
beneficial results. The wool would furnish employ<lb break="no"/>ment to families in the manufacture of home pun. as <lb/>
was done in the neighbouring provinces. It was <lb/>
gratifying to learn that our usineral, resvurces, pro<lb break="no"/>mised to prove highly remunerative. They should not <lb/>
be sold to the Canadians. He (Mr. Renouf) was told <lb/>
by Mr. Bennett, the pioneer of mining enterprise in <lb/>
this Colony, before that gentleman left for England, <lb/>
that next year he would have a thousand men employed <lb/>
and would expend £50,000 in wages, which would be <lb/>
eminently beneficial to the Colony. It was said that <lb/>
if the Convention were carried out, the Canadians would <lb/>
work our minerals. But they did not work their own. <lb/>
The question of Confederation occupied an important <lb/>
position in his Excellency's speech and he (Mr. Re<lb break="no"/>nouf) must say that his Excellency was entitled to the <lb/>
thanks of the community for the promptitude with which <lb/>
he published the dispatch of Mr. Cardwell. He recei<lb break="no"/>ved in the morning, and the same evening it was made <lb/>
            public through the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Royal Gazette</hi>. The communication <lb/>
from the Colonial Ministry seemed somewhat of an inti<lb break="no"/>mation that he wished the Confederation carried into <lb/>
effect, but, at the same time, he respected the opinion <lb/>
of the people of these colonies, and maintained, a de<lb break="no"/>sire to force it upon them. His Excellercy told them <lb/>
of his having received a despatch from the Governor <lb/>
General of Canada, intimating that his Government <lb/>
would move an address to the Queen, requesting that an <lb/>
Act of the Imperial Parliament might be passed to give <lb/>


<cb/> 

effect to the resolutions of the Convention; "and he (Mr. <lb/>
Renouf) understood that information had been received <lb/>
here by telegraph, that the address had been passed by <lb/>
the Canadian House of Assembly by a large majority. <lb/>
But, at the same time, the members of this House, and <lb/>
the people out of doors, would have something to say <lb/>
in the matter. It must have been taken for granted, <lb/>
that the Delegates from the Maritime Provinces <lb/>
spoke of the views of the people, and, not merely their <lb/>
own. He (Mr. Renouf) did say that this House had <lb/>
no power to come to a decission on the matter. We <lb/>
should give no opinion on it this session. It was a new <lb/>
question to the House; and he did trust that no attempt <lb/>
would be made to bind this Colony until the people <lb/>
had time to give expression to their opinions on the <lb/>
subject. He did think it was well to send Delegates; <lb/>
but he must say that the resolutions adopted by the <lb/>
Delegates at the Conference were not such as he consid<lb break="no"/>ered for the advantage of Newfoundland to accept. As <lb/>
be would have an opportunity of expressing his views <lb/>
more fully when the several matters referred to in the <lb/>
speech would be submitted for the sanction of the House, <lb/>
he would not occupy more time at present; but would <lb/>
again express his gratification at the enlightened views so <lb/>
ably set forth in his Excellency's speech.</p>
            
<p><persName ref="pers:PROW1">Mr. Prowse</persName> was afraid the hon, gentlemen opposite <lb/>
had mot been in the path of progress during the recess; <lb/>
especially the hon. member, Mr. Renouf, had been drif<lb break="no"/>ting down into the slough of toryism, . He was fast rea<lb break="no"/>lizing that picture which a great wit had give nus of a Con<lb break="no"/>servative, who would not look upon the new moon, out <lb/>
of respect to that ancient and venerable institution the <lb/>
old moon; now his hon. friend would not look upon the <lb/>
bright shining faces of the new bright bronze halpennies <lb/>
out of respect to the old, beaten out buttons and ship <lb/>
coppers, to all the bastard currency we rejoiced in before. <lb/>
No, hon gentlemen did not want progress; no Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation for them, and one hon gentleman, <persName ref="pers:CASE2">Mr. Casey</persName>, used <lb/>
as an argument against the confederation scheme, as a <lb/>
proof, said he, how brilliantly Responsible Government <lb/>
has worked with us, and that we want no change. One <lb/>
party remained in office during the whole of one Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, and when the next party came in, they did the <lb/>
same. No wind of popular opinion was ever found strong <lb/>
enough to blow them out of office, certainly a most ex<lb break="no"/>traordinary proof of our fitness for representative en<lb break="no"/>lightened. He ( <persName ref="pers:PROW1">Mr. Prowse</persName> ) agreed with every word of <lb/>
praise which the hon gentlemen opposite had bestowed <lb/>
upon the able and eloquent speech just delivered by his <lb/>
Excellency; it was a matter of congratulation for the <lb/>
country, that Her Majesty had sent so able and distin<lb break="no"/>guished a Representative. His Excellency had taken a <lb/>
very clear view of the evils we were labouring under; he <lb/>
comprehended all the dangers which the giant evils of <lb/>
pauper relief exposed us to, and he (Mr. Prowse) con<lb break="no"/>sidered that the Government deserved the highest praise <lb/>
which we could bestow upon them, for the able way in <lb/>
wnich they had dealt with this question; the fact that <lb/>
in a year of unparalled detitution, they had kept the <lb/>
poor expenditure within the estimate, was, he considered <lb/>
the highest proof of their merit as an Executive. The <lb/>
excess of expenditure for shipwrecked crews they could <lb/>
not be blamed for it. It was the result of a fearful ca<lb break="no"/>lamity, which they could not reasonably have calculated <lb/>
on, and if in this battle with our great political enemy, <lb/>
pauperism, they have been powerless to subdue it, which <lb/>
sets at naught the efforts of our Priests and Ministers, <lb/>
and all the exertions of our various charitable Societies, <lb/>
they certainly have done all that could be done in grap<lb break="no"/>pling with what an emineut Ecclesiastical Authority has <lb/>
designated as our only great political, question.—We <lb/>
had heard Confederation spoken against by hon gentle<lb break="no"/>men who are opposed to it on the ground of increased <lb/>
taxation? but he would like to ask what else is there <lb/>
for us in the dim vista of the future but increased taxation. <lb/>
Will one good seal fishery, or one good codfishery pull <lb/>
up all the leeway you have lost? No, even with the <lb/>
best prospects, there is nothing before us but increased <lb/>
taxation, and that without corresponding improvements. <lb/>
Now, Sir, this is not the proper time to go into the mer<lb break="no"/>its of this great question of Confederation, but I will <lb/>
take this opportunity of expressing my opinion on the <lb/>
question. The hon member, Mr. Renouf, tells us that <lb/>
we ought not to express our opinion upon this question; <lb/>
he must grievously misapprehend the position of a Re<lb break="no"/>presentative here, when he says so., What are we here <lb/>
for but to express our opinons on all questions, coming <lb/>
before this Honse? And the man is a coward and a <lb/>
miserable driveller, unfit for his position as a representa<lb break="no"/>tive who shrinks from expressing his conscientious opinion <lb/>
on any question, who is frightened by the clamor of noisy <lb/>
    politicians-outside, or who is crushed under the weight <lb/>
of the mercantile influence which is arrayed against this <lb/>
question, and dares not express his opinion. He (Mr. <lb/>
Prowse) would take this opportunity of expressing his <lb/>
thanks to the Delegates, who so ably managed our inter<lb break="no"/>ests in the Conference at Quebec; no man can deny that <lb/>
they did well, and they have committed us to nothing. <lb/>
I should like to see a guarantee for direct and local <lb/>
stem, and I believe we will have it; and whilst, however, <lb/>
we are listening to all the reasons which must influence <lb/>
every one of us who is favorable to the scheme, I don't <lb/>
think we will have to search very deep into the motives <lb/>
or speculate widely to find out the reasons for their <lb/>
opposition. One, well salaried official candidly says if <lb/>
Confederation will increase my salary of £500 to £600. <lb/>
I am for Confederation. Every man who has anything <lb/>
to lose by the curtailed expenditure of our local Go<lb break="no"/>vernment and our local Legislature, all the <choice><sic>bost</sic><corr>best</corr></choice> of <lb/>
official vampires and small fry of newspapers and repor<lb break="no"/>ters are dead against it, and so are all those whose inter<lb break="no"/>ests as merchants will, as they fear, be affected, or whose <lb/>
trade will be turned into new; channels, or whose <lb/>
hatchets will be better ground now, but on the other <lb/>
hand, will any one believe that the six dollans a day for <lb/>
our Delegates and other leading gentlemen is sufficient <lb/>
inducement or bribe for them to sell their country; it is <lb/>
amusing to see the new born love which hon gentlemen <lb/> 
have for Mr. C. F. Rennett; a few years ago he was <lb/>
    in their opinion a narrow minded sectary, a one horse <lb/> 
politician, but now he is an angel of light. I agree with <lb/>
everything they say in his praise as a gentletuan and as <lb/>
as upright enterprising merchant, but I would be sorry <lb/>
to pin my faith to him as a politician, in this question. <lb/></p>

  <p><persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName> said that in his opinion the Delegates had <lb/>
done wrong in signing the report of the Conference. By <lb/>
doing so they had induced the British Government to <lb/>
suppose that Newfoundland was in favor of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, and the consequence was that a copy of Mr. Sard<lb break="no"/>well's despatch has been forwarded to His Excellency. <lb/>
By their unwise conduct our delegates had almost <lb/>
      succeeded in <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> us to the Confederation without our <lb/>
knowledge or consent. It would be charitable to sup<lb break="no"/>pose they did not know what they were doing; They <lb/>
were not sent there to sign this report, nor indeed to sign <lb/>
anything. They were sent merely to watch the pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings, and report them to this House. They had not <lb/>
received any commission from the people, but only from <lb/>
the Government. In any case, it was the duty of the <lb/>


<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-06_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">2</fw>

<fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw> 

Delegates, when they returned, to have given the <lb/>
public some information as to what had been done. <lb/>
They did not do so, however, and we have yet to learn <lb/>
what took place at that Conference: As for the benefits <lb/>
we were t receive by this Confederation, nothing <lb/>
could benefit the country so much as good fisheries and <lb/>
he (Mr. Glen) did not think the Confederation would <lb/>
bring the fish to, our shores. He must express his <lb/>
condemnation of the action of the Delegates in signing <lb/>
that report, which they had no business and were not <lb/>
authorised to do. Fortunately from the reading of the <lb/>
despatch, it was evident the British Government did <lb/>
not mean we should be coerced. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SHEA2">Mr.A. SHEA</persName>, said that at this late hour when the <lb/>
House was necessarily wearied, he would not trespass <lb/>
on their time, as he had intended, with any elaborate <lb/>
observations on the subject which at the present mo<lb break="no"/>ment naturally commanded the largest share of public <lb/>
attention. In the prominent place he held in relation. <lb/>
to this question, it would rationally be expected that <lb/>
he would be ready to go fully into the discussion; and <lb/>
the lateness of the hour alone induced him to forego <lb/>
their attention for the present. He must, however, <lb/>
express his regret that hon. gentlemen should have <lb/>
deemed it fitting to deal with the great question of <lb/>
Confederation as they had done in the remarks they <lb/>
offered to the House; for he had hoped that its mag<lb break="no"/>nitude and the great issues it involved would have <lb/>
secured for it that calm investigation of its real merits, <lb/>
which the welfare of the public so earnestly demands. <lb/>
This was not like the many ordinary subjects that <lb/>
came before them, and on which the course not very <lb/>
uncommon in that House, of unmeaning windy decla<lb break="no"/>mation, might do no great harm; but here, where the <lb/>
decision they might arrive at so deeply affected the <lb/>
whole interests of the country, it was of the last im<lb break="no"/>portance that reason and intelligence should guide <lb/>
thier deliberations to their ultimate result. For these <lb/>
reasons he was sorry to hear observations made that <lb/>
day which involved gross misrepresentations of the <lb/>
case, and seemed addressed rather to the passions and <lb/>
prejudices of the people, than to their sober and <lb/>
dispassionate judgment. Nor was he less surprised <lb/>
at the character of some of the logic that had been <lb/>
employed in the discussion. This colony was describ<lb break="no"/>ed as being in the lowest condition of pauperism, <lb/>
which caused an outlay of one-third of our revenue, <lb/>
and yet by those who thus painted our condition, we <lb/>
are told of the great eagerness of Canada to secure <lb/>
this prize, and of the great advantages we are to con<lb break="no"/>fer to our own detriment. Does not this mode <lb/>
of dealing with the subject show how little thought <lb/>
of relfection has been bestowed upon it by some who <lb/>
take upon themselves the task of instructing the mind <lb/>
of the public. The reasoning, public would demand <lb/>
some more thoughtful mode of inquiry in relation to <lb/>
this question. It should not be gone into hastily, and <lb/>
ample time must be given for its consideration, in <lb/>
order that no decision should be come to before the <lb/>
public were fully informed of its real nature, and its <lb/>
probable bearing upon our future interests: Various <lb/>
cries had been unfairly resorted to to prejudice the <lb/>
public mind. It was put forward as a strong ground <lb/>
of objection that the Union of Ireland with England <lb/>
had led to great evils in the former country, and <lb/>
hence the efforts of O'Connell for so many years to <lb/>
repeal the Union. Such arguments betray a lament<lb break="no"/>able ignorance of the grounds on which that great <lb/>
man based his agitation for Repeal. O'Connell sought <lb/>
repeal because the connection with England was not a <lb/>
Union in its true sense, because there was no equality <lb/>
of rights and privileges between the two countries, <lb/>
and the whole history of his life shows that all he de<lb break="no"/>sired was union with England, on terms that would <lb/>
have made Ireland her equal in all the conditions of <lb/>
fair partnership. But he was not going into the ques<lb break="no"/>tion at that late hour. The subject of taxation and <lb/>
the other points that had been raised would be dis<lb break="no"/>cussed at length when the matter was fairly before <lb/>
them, and when he had little doubt the many misre<lb break="no"/>presentations made on these subjects would be satis<lb break="no"/>factorily explained and disposed of. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
<persName ref="pers:KENT1">Mr. KENT</persName>—It appeared to him that those hon. <lb/>
gentlemen who had spoken so favorably of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernors speech were totally ignorant of the first prin<lb break="no"/>ciples of Responsible Government. They had praised <lb/>
the speech of the Governor without seeming to know <lb/>
at the same time that it was that of the leader of the <lb/>
government. All the rough edge of that speech had <lb/>
been so beautifully rubbed off that it showed his Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency to be a most accomplished master of English. <lb/> 
But he (Mr. Kent) would not indulge in the syco<lb break="no"/>phantic praises which his learned colleagues had so <lb/>
constitutionally bestowed on the speech of the Minis<lb break="no"/>try. These hon. gentlemen had worked themselves <lb/>
up into a parliamentary perspiration; and all in praise <lb/>
of the leader of the government. But for the refer<lb break="no"/>ence that had been made to the Atlantic Telegraph <lb/>
Cable, he (Mr. Kent) would say that it was like a <lb/>
lady's letter, the most important part of it was the <lb/>
postscript. With reference to the question of pauper <lb/>
relief, he believed that it was an ulcer in our social <lb/>
condition. The Government could have done a great <lb/>
deal to remedy this. They might have employed the <lb/>
people on public works, and thus reduced the number <lb/>
of recipients from the pauper fund; and for this grave <lb/>
omission they could offer no excuse. Now that the <lb/>
fisheries were a failure, they were obliged to open the <lb/>
public purse and distribute the money among the <lb/>
people. The suggestion in the speech that all relief <lb/>
should not come out of the public funds, was a very <lb/>
important one. He thought it was obligatory on the <lb/>
public generally to assist in the support of the poor. <lb/>
He believed that local assessment was the only way <lb/>
in with this could be accomplished. If the Bank <lb/>
and mackerel fisheries were to be encouraged by <lb/>
bounties, why were not the cod fisheries to be cared <lb/>
for also? Gradually, but slowly, the principles of <lb/>
Free Trade were permeating through France; and <lb/>
were we to retrograde, and resort to bounties for the <lb/>
extension of our fisheries? Would not the proper <lb/>
appropriation of the public monies in bounties, be to <lb/>
take the £30,000 that was uselessly squandered in <lb/>
pauper relief, and with it encourage the rearing of <lb/>
sheep and other graminivorous animals? He would <lb/>
advise the hon. Attorney General that he was running <lb/>
a tilt in this matter of bounties, but, like a drowning <lb/>
man, he would grasp at a straw. The suggestion in <lb/>
his Excellency's speech on the subject of Agriculture <lb/>
was an excellent one. Surely our climate was not less <lb/>
genial than that of Iceland. He (Mr. Kent) could see <lb/>
no reason why we should not raise flax extensively in <lb/>
this country. The suggestion was creditable to the <lb/>
Ministry and to his Excellency, as the head of it. The <lb/>
reference to a permanent Road Act, however, was <lb/>
certainly an extraordinacy one. He (Mr. Kent) <lb/>
would like to see any Premier attempt to bring in a <lb/>
permanent Road Bill, and make it a perennial spring <lb/>
of petty abstractions. If he (Mr. Kent) wanted to <lb/>
keep a party together he would not dare to propose <lb/>
such a thing. He might possibly, in carrying out its <lb/>
rovisions, leave out some delightful little locality, re<lb break="no"/>joicing in some peculiarly effloresent name, and the <lb/>
result would be an entire overthrow of his ministry. <lb/>
His Excellency the Governor appeared, on this point, <lb/>
to be in a blissful state baptismal innocence. <lb/>
With reference to the question of Steam communica<lb break="no"/>tion, he believed that it had been impossible for the <lb/>
Government to carry out their intentions by reason of <lb/>
the impoverished state of the Treasury. He trusted <lb/>
            that something would be done respecting the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Ellen <lb/>
Gisborne</hi>. There was one useful work which he (Mr. <lb/>

<cb/>

Kent) had to observe had been specially mentioned, <lb/>
and that was a breakwater at Portugal Cove. If that <lb/>
were accomplished it would be one of the greatest <lb/>
benefits that could be conferred upon the inhabitants <lb/>
of the district of Conception Bay. The question of <lb/>
education was a very delicate one to deal with. He <lb/>
(Mr Kent) did not understand what was meant by <lb/>
normal schools. He had been in the Magistrates' <lb/>
office the other day and he saw sixteen men sign there <lb/>
by making their mark. He considered that was a dis<lb break="no"/>grace to the country, and hoped the youth of the <lb/>
country would endeavour to take advantage of the <lb/>
benefits of education which were afforded them, and <lb/>
in some measure ameliorate their condition. With <lb/>
reference to the volunteers, he thought the Executive <lb/>
were too fightened about arming the fishermen of the <lb/>
country. He (Mr Kent) deeply regretted these un<lb break="no"/>fortunte distinctions. He was glad to hear that the <lb/>
revenue was a fair one, and hoped that when his hon <lb/>
colleague, Mr Renouf, looked into the public accounts <lb/>
he would find them satisfactory. He (Mr Kent) con<lb break="no"/>sidered the question of Confederation was one of no <lb/>
ordinary importance. If we were going to be recalci<lb break="no"/>trant in this matter the Home Government might <lb/>
withdraw the troops and we would lose the great ben<lb break="no"/>efit we derived from the protection they afforded us <lb/>
as well as from the expenditure on their account by <lb/>
the Imperial Government among us. He (Mr Kent) <lb/>
believed that if we kept on good terms with the Home <lb/>
Government they would extend to us for the next fifty <lb/>
years the aegis of their protection, Let us enter into <lb/>
the consideration of this matter calmly. Looking at <lb/>
the question in its commercial aspects, he (Mr Kent) <lb/>
considered that it must be of great advantage to this <lb/>
country. If we did not join in this confederation, <lb/>
Newfoundland might be met by a hostile tariff in every <lb/>
direction, for there was reason to apprehend that the <lb/>
Americans would terminate the reciprocity treaty. It <lb/>
might be said that we would still receive our flour and <lb/>
provisions from the United States; but if there was <lb/>
war between the United Kingdom and the United <lb/>
States, whence would we get them? How could they <lb/>
protect their fisheries if the British government were <lb/>
to tell them to set up for themselves? As to the cost <lb/>
of a navy, a navy was a very remote thing under this <lb/>
federation, because the British navy would, as now, <lb/>
give us all the naval protection we required. But if <lb/>
seamen were required for the British navy in time of <lb/>
war, it was evident we could supply them with men <lb/>
whose physical vigour and gallantry would reflect the <lb/>
highest credit on the service. As to the military ex<lb break="no"/>penditure of the Confederation, we were already <lb/>
ledged to contribute towards the military expenditure <lb/>
incurred for our defence, but as yet we had not been <lb/>
called upon for anything. Politically considered, he <lb/>
(Mr Kent) regarded the Confederation, as fraught <lb/>
with important benefits to this colony. Although he <lb/>
had been himself aparty to legislating for the existing <lb/>
representation in that House, still he must state his <lb/>
conviction that it was not such as was calculated to <lb/>
promote useful legislation or a feeling of harmony <lb/>
among the people of the colony. The representation <lb/>
was based on religious distinctions; and the two great <lb/>
religious denominations in the island being, so nearly <lb/>
balanced numerically,the consequence was that a slight <lb/>
advantage in one or two electoral districts gave a small <lb/>
numerical majority in that House to the representa<lb break="no"/>tives of one party or the other, and the effect of this <lb/>
was a constant struggle in that House for the posses<lb break="no"/>sion of power, to the retarding of useful legislation, <lb/>
and leading to the estrangement of parties in private <lb/>
life, and producing that otium theologicum, which was <lb/>
the bitterest of all hatreds. Viewed socially, federa<lb break="no"/>tion with the other provinces would be productive of <lb/>
great advantages. There was an expansive benevo<lb break="no"/>lence and an enlargement of views generated by amal<lb break="no"/>gamating with large and populous communities. Our <lb/>
isolation and contracted sphere of action was apt to <lb/>
operate injuriously in many respects, whereas union <lb/>
with the neighbouring provinces would produce in<lb break="no"/>creased intercourse, and an interchange of sentiments <lb/>
and hospitalities must result beneficially in many re<lb break="no"/>spects. He merely referred generally to these aspets <lb/>
of the question. When the subject was brought for<lb break="no"/>mally before the House he would be prepared to go <lb/>
more fully into its consideration. He was satisfied that <lb/>
great social, political and commercial advantages would <lb/>
accrue from it. He did say there was a great deal in <lb/>
the objection raised, that we ought to consult the con<lb break="no"/>sutuencies. He was pleased with the manner in which <lb/>
the question was brought before the public in the <lb/>
other colonies, where the supporters and opponents <lb/>
of confederation appeared at public meetings and fully <lb/>
set forth their views without introducing any clap-trap <lb/>
into their speeches. With respect to the Governor's <lb/>
speech, he (Mr. Kent) was very glad the ministry had <lb/>
advised his Excellency to lay such an unexceptionable <lb/>
speech before the House. With the prospect of soon <lb/>
appearing before their constituents they have appeared <lb/>
to have acted in accordance with the remark,that poli<lb break="no"/>ticians have four-years for sinning and one for repent<lb break="no"/>ing, previous to having to give an account of their <lb/>
conduct. He hoped they might so direct their legis<lb break="no"/>lation this session as to do something towards relieving <lb/>
the people from that deep despondency with which they <lb/>
are now pressed down. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
<persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr. TALBOT</persName> felt great pleasure in expressing his <lb/>
satisfaction with the speech from the throne; not only <lb/>
with the style of that able document; but with the im<lb break="no"/>portant practical suggestions it contained. He (Mr. <lb/>
Talbot) did not think it was the speech of the minis<lb break="on"/>try. It was not in accordance with the sentiments <lb/>
they had expressed in the House in former sessions, <lb/>
It must have been written by the Governor himself; <lb/>
and was a speech which did him very great credit— <lb/>
And judging by it, we might anticipate that his Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency would give great satisfaction in the adminis<lb break="no"/>tration of the Government of this Colony. There was <lb/>
one portion of it, that in reference to roads, recom<lb break="no"/>mending a permanent appropriation for their repair <lb/>
and extension, which was not in accordance with the <lb/>
sentiments of the ministry, for the Premier himself was <lb/>
opposed to roads. He (Mr. Talbot) was informed, <lb/>
although he never heard him say it himself, that the <lb/>
Premier had said, in his place in the House, that <lb/>
roads were only a convenierce, and would not pay for <lb/>
the outlay upon them. He (Mr. Talbot) thought a <lb/>
permanent Road Act would be very useful. They <lb/>
bould prevent the roads from falling into decay, by a <lb/>
permanent Act. During the last year they might be <lb/>
said to have no road grant at all, for the roads, equired <lb/>
such repairs, from the neglect of preceding years, and <lb/>
there were such large deductions for other purposes, <lb/>
that the whole grant in the St. John's district was <lb/>
required for repairs, and no new roads could be open<lb break="no"/>ed. With respect to education, he thought it was <lb/>
necessary to provide suitable renumeration for the <lb/>
teachers, but no training school was required. His <lb/>
Excellency must have been in error when he penned <lb/>
that recommendation. There was a training School <lb/>
for Catholic teachers in connexion with St. Bonaven<lb break="no"/>tore College, and he (Mr. Talbot,) believed arrange<lb break="no"/>ments were made in connection with the Protestant <lb/>
Academies for the training of teachers for the Protes<lb break="no"/>tant elementary schools.He did not, therefore, see why <lb/>
the Colony should be put to the expense of a separate <lb/>
training institution. With respect to the new Curren<lb break="no"/>cy Act, be thought the copper coinage introduced was <lb/>
not such as would give satisfaction to the country. He <lb/>
considered its result to the poor man was the loss of <lb/>
two pence on the shilling. The labourer on the <lb/>
wharves, who received them in payment of his wages <lb/>
            
        <cb/>    

at the rate of twenty half pence to the shilling, had <lb/>
afterwards to give them for ten pence at the shops <lb/>
where he purchased necessaries, for his family. He <lb/>
had to comply with the old custom which their legis<lb break="no"/>jor could not change. He (Mr. Talbot) was very <lb/>
much gratified to learn that the report of Mr. Murray, <lb/>
the geologist, was so favourable respecting our min<lb break="no"/>eral resources. It gave us reason to anticipate that <lb/>
valuable mines would be found which would furnish <lb/>
a source of employment, and prove remunerative to <lb/>
capitalists. The speech was unexceptionable, with the <lb/>
exception of the question of poor relief; and that was <lb/>
difficult one. We were so situated that, at present, <lb/>
we had no source of employment for any large portion <lb/>
of our people, except the fishery, and when that failed <lb/>
the people were reduced to want, and they had, no <lb/>
means in the outports of paying an assessment for their <lb/>
relief, for they were all dependent on the fishery. If <lb/>
the circumstances of the country were such that they <lb/> 
could make each district support their own poor, it <lb/>
would be a most desirable course, but he (Mr. Talbot) <lb/>
did not see how it could be done here. The next sub<lb break="no"/>ject in the speech was Confederation. It was a subject <lb/>
of very great importance, and ought not to be treated <lb/>
as a party question. He did not think it could be dis<lb break="no"/>posed of by the bandying of terms. It was too solemn <lb/>
a question to be so treated. It was one of life or death <lb/>
to the country. He had given it a great deal of con<lb break="no"/>sideration too, and after all he could not make up his <lb/>
mind upon it. There might be something in the ad<lb break="no"/>vantages pointed out by its supporters. He had re<lb break="no"/>garded it in the light of history and experience, and it <lb/>
struck him to be a measure calculated to prove fatal <lb/>
to the liberties of the country. He would like to see <lb/>
in it a measure calculated for relieving the country <lb/>
from pauperism which at present pressed it down. But <lb/>
he did declare he could not see in it any practical <lb/>
benefit calculated to lift the people from that state of <lb/>
poverty into which so many of them were plunged. <lb/>
And he solemnly declared he could not give it his <lb/>
adhesion. He could see some advantage in extended <lb/>
territory and a population of so many millians under <lb/>
one Government; but the question of our liberty was <lb/>
involved; and for liberty people have been ready to <lb/>
sacrifice every thing. People regarded liberty, as <lb/>
dearer than life itself. The proposed confederation <lb/>
appeared to him like people bartering away their liber<lb break="no"/>ty for a certain price. With respect to the Delegates <lb/>
appointed by the Government of this Colony, they <lb/>
were gentlemen of distinguished, talents, who he was <lb/>
satisfied, would do nothing which they considered to <lb/>
the prejudice of the Colony, or which would reflect <lb/>
discredit on themselves; but he could not concur in <lb/> 
the resolutions to which they were parties; and with <lb/>
regard to any decision on the question this session, he <lb/>
did say that if they decided upon a measure of such <lb/>
importance without consulting public opinion outside <lb/>
they would act most unconstitutionally. He (Mr. <lb/>
Talbot) was under the strongest impression that they <lb/>
had not the power to pass a measure for giving effect <lb/>
to these resolutions. They had been struggling for <lb/>
<choice><sic>twenry</sic><corr>twenty</corr></choice> years to secure a free <choice><sic>oonstitution</sic><corr>constitution</corr></choice> for the <lb/>
country, and would they put their liberties in jeopardy, <lb/> 
or give over to any country the power to trample upon <lb/>
them? He did say that he could see no good in it. <lb/>
As to free trade, we could have free commercial inter<lb break="no"/>course with the other Colonies without giving them <lb/>
the power to control our legislation. And as to open<lb break="no"/>ing a field for the enterprise of our young men, they <lb/>
could now proceed to ony of the colonies, and had <lb/>
free scope for their talents. Again, with respect to <lb/>
the manner in which these Delegates were sent, the <lb/>
question never had been brought before the House, <lb/>
and the proceeding was entirely that of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. After some further observations, the hon. <lb/>
member concluded by saying that he was decidedly <lb/>
pposed to the question of confederation being enter<lb break="no"/>tained this session. <lb/></p>
        
<p>
<persName ref="pers:CART5">The hon. Attorney GENERAL</persName> said he was much <lb/>
pleased with the manner, in which his Excellency's <lb/>
speech had been received by both sides of the House. <lb/>
He fully concurred in the very marked expression of <lb/>
satisfaction expressed by hon. members with that <lb/>
speech, and with the opinions expressed as to the emi<lb break="no"/>ment qualifications possessed by his Excellency for the <lb/>
exalted and responsible position to which he had been <lb/>
appointed by Her Most Gracious Majesty. There was, <lb/>
however, as was to be anticipated, some difference of <lb/>
opinion on several of the subjects referred to in that <lb/>
speech. The hon. member for St. John's East, <persName ref="pers:PARS1">Mr. <lb/>
Parsons</persName>, as was his usual practice, complained of the <lb/>
course followed by the Government, and expatiated <lb/>
in glowing terms on the results which would flow from <lb/>
a different policy shadowed forth by him, a policy of <lb/>
giving the public money to any who would receive it, <lb/>
to be expended in cultivating the soil, a policy of <lb/>
which the certain result would be to render all the <lb/>
recipients dependent upon government support. It <lb/>
was somewhat remarkable that although that hon. <lb/>
member had been upwards of twenty years in that <lb/>
House, and had been declaiming all that time about <lb/>
some comprehensive policy that would make abun<lb break="no"/>dance pervade the land, and banish want, and pauper<lb break="no"/>ism from our midst, yet he had never introduced a <lb/>
single measure to give effect to his own suggestions. <lb/>
With respect to the poor expenditure the hou. member <lb/>
had given free scope to his in agnation, and asserted <lb/>
that it was far larger than it had actually been. The <lb/>
hon. member for St. John's East, <persName ref="pers:KENT1">Mr. Kent</persName>, did <lb/>
object to some things in the speech, as was to be ex<lb break="no"/>pected from the leader of the opposition; but he ( <persName ref="pers:CART5">hon. <lb/>
A. Gen</persName>) could not but admire the good humour <lb/>
and wit with which the hon, member spoke in the <lb/>
house; except when he got into bad humour, and then <lb/>
he said things which he (hon A. Gen.) was sure he <lb/>
did not mean. He must say however, that he could <lb/>
not agree with the hon, member in some matters. He <lb/>
objected to the encouragement suggested by his Ex<lb break="no"/>cemency to the Bank, and mackeral fisheries. Now <lb/>
he (hon. A. Gen.) admitted that bounties, in the <lb/>
abstract, were objectionable. But in this case it was <lb/>
not proposed to give bounties to sustain an unprofit<lb break="no"/>able branch of business, but to give temporary en<lb break="no"/>couragement for the purpose of resuscitating a fishery <lb/>
which gave employment to the fishermen of other <lb/>
countries, but in which our fishermen did not at pre<lb break="no"/>sent engage; and which we had reason to believe <lb/>
would be, after a short time, not only self-sustaining, <lb/>
but a source of profitable employment to a large num<lb break="no"/>ber of our fishermen. Our fishermen had for many <lb/>
years past engaged only in the shore, and Labrador <lb/>
cod fisheries, which, we all regretted, had not baen so <lb/>
remunerative as could be wished. He did not think <lb/>
that there was any thing else to which his hon. friend <lb/>
had referred which required any observation. There <lb/>
was another matter, however, on which a good deal <lb/>
had been said on both sides of the House, on which <lb/>
he (hon. A. Gen.) would make a few observations. <lb/>
He referred to the proposed Confederation of the <lb/>
British North American Colonies. It was a matter of <lb/>
great importance and one equiring the gravest at<lb break="no"/>tention. it was one which would require them to <lb/>
take into consideration, not only the present condition <lb/>
of the colony and its relation to the parent state and <lb/>
the neighbouring colonies; but also the circumstances <lb/>
that might be anticipated to affect these relations in <lb/>
future years. It was <choice><sic>e</sic><corr>the</corr></choice> subject on which a great deal <lb/>
might be said and written on both sides. He would <lb/>
not at present go into the consideration of the ques<lb break="no"/>tion. The government were invited by that of Cana<lb break="no"/>da to take part in the deliberations at Quebec, and <lb/>
considered it their duty to the country to accept the <lb/>
    
    <cb/>

invitation. He concurred in the opinion <choice><sic>exprossed</sic><corr>expressed</corr></choice> <lb/>
by hon. members as to the zeal and ability with which <lb/>
the Delegates had discharged their duty; and he <lb/>
would take that opportunity of expressing his approv<lb break="no"/>al of the terms as respected <choice><sic>Newfaundland</sic><corr>Newfoundland</corr></choice>. He dif<lb break="no"/>fered from those who thought the Delegates should <lb/>
not have taken part in the discussions at the Confer<lb break="no"/>ence. Their instructions were not to do anything to <lb/>
bind this colony, as the subject had not been before <lb/>
the Legislature, and these instructions bad been com<lb break="no"/>plied with. But the course they had followed result<lb break="no"/>ed in arrangements which he (hon. Attorney General) <lb/>
considered it would be to our advantage to accept. <lb/>
He considered it was also their duty to sign the Re<lb break="no"/>port, by which the proceedings of the Conference <lb/>
were authenticated; and it must be gratifying to them <lb/>
all to learn the high <choice><sic>opiuion</sic><corr>opinion</corr></choice> entertained at the <lb/>
Conference, and by leading gentlemen in Canada, of <lb/>
the Delegates and the manner in which they had ac<lb break="no"/>quitted themselves. He should be expected to state <lb/>
the course which the Government intended to take <lb/>
respecting that matter. He deprecated any discus<lb break="no"/>sion of the matter until all the papers were laid be<lb break="no"/>fore the house, which, to save time, were now in the <lb/>
course of being printed, and would be laid on the table <lb/>
in a few days. Notice would be given of a day for <lb/>
taking the matter into consideration probably the 15th <lb/>
February, which would give hon. members three weeks <lb/>
to consider the documents on the subject, and the re<lb break="no"/>solutions to be proposed by the Government. There <lb/>
was no desire to press the decision of the House on <lb/>
the question with undue haste. He thought ample <lb/>
time should be given for its consideration, and concur<lb break="no"/>red with those who thought its importance entitled it <lb/>
to the gravest deliberation. He did trust that hon. <lb/>
members, after full consideration of the whole ques<lb break="no"/>tion, would come prepared to consider the resolutions <lb/>
with a full sense of the responsibility which devolved <lb/>
upon them, and whether they confirmed the resolu<lb break="no"/>tions or decided that we remain as we are, that they <lb/>
would be actuated by no motive except an earnest <lb/>
desire to promote the permanent interests of the coun<lb break="no"/>try in which they occupied the honourable and res<lb break="no"/>ponsible position of the peoples' representatives; and <lb/>
that their decision would be such as they could after<lb break="no"/>wards reflect upon with satisfaction. <lb/></p>
        

        
<p><persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName> wished to know whether it was the inten<lb break="no"/>tion of the Government to force the matter through <lb/>
the house this session? <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. Attorney GENERAL</persName>.—The Government <lb/>
never forced any matter through the House. They <lb/>
were always satisfied with submitting their views to <lb/>
the House, and accepting the decision of hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers upon them. <lb/></p>
        
<p><persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName>.—Was he to understand that the reso<lb break="no"/>lutions to be submitted by the Government would, as <lb/>
regsrds this Colony, affirm the report of the Confer<lb break="no"/>ence? <lb/></p>
        
<p><persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATToRNEY GENERAL</persName>.—Certainly. Such would <lb/>
be the effect of the resolutions, if concurred in by the <lb/>
House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName>.—The constitution was granted, not to <lb/> 
the House of Assembly, but to the people of New<lb break="no"/>foundland, and he (Mr. Glen) considered the people <lb/>
were entitled to be consulted before we came to a <lb/>
decision on the subject. <lb/></p>
        
<p><persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>.—The question would <lb/>
be submitted to the House, and it would be for hon. <lb/>
members to decide what course should be adopted. <lb/>
The government, were prepared to acquiesce in the <lb/>
decision of the House. <lb/></p>
        
<p>After some observations by Mr. Kent and Mr. <lb/>
Talbot, the motion for the appointment of a Select <lb/>
Committee to prepare the draft of an address in reply <lb/>
to his Excellency's speech was put and carried. <lb/></p>
        
<p>Ordered that Messrs. Wyatt, Whitewny, E. D. <lb/>
Shea, Winter, and Casey do form the committee. <lb/></p>
        
<p><persName ref="pers:CART5">The hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> gave notice that on <lb/>
Wednesday, the 15th February next, he will move the <lb/>
House into Committee of the whole on the subject of <lb/>
a Confederation of the North American Provinces. <lb/></p>
        
<p><persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName> gave notice that on to-morrow he will <lb/>
ask the hon. the Acting Colonial Secretary to lay on <lb/>
the table of the House a copy of all correspondence <lb/>
between the Government and that of Canada on the <lb/>
subject of Colonial Conſederation; also copy, of In<lb break="no"/>structions furnished the Delegates, Messrs. Shea and <lb/>
Carter, to the Quebec Convention, and the Report of <lb/>
the said Delegates. <lb/></p>
        
<p>Also to ask the hon. Acting Colonial Secretary for <lb/>
copy of correspondence from Dr. Stabb, Manager of <lb/>
the Lunatic Asylum, to the Government, in Decem<lb break="no"/>ber last, complaining of the visit of <choice><sic>inspectisn</sic><corr>inspections</corr></choice> made <lb/>
by the Representatives of St. John's West to that In<lb break="no"/>stitution twelve months ago. <lb/></p>
        
<p><persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr. TALBOT</persName> gave notice that on to-morrow he will <lb/>
ask the hon. Attorney General what arrangement has <lb/>
been made by the Government to provide Medical <lb/>
attendance for the St. John's Hospital in place of the <lb/>
late Dr. Rochford. <lb/></p>
        
<p>The House then adjourned until Monday at three <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/></p>
        
        <!-- IC, 2018-11-09, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>*memº <lb/></p> 

<p>T. <lb/></p> 

<p>(Lºtufoumiſmått. <lb/></p> 

<p>be the effect of the resolutions, if concurred in by the <lb/></p> 

<p>were entitled to be consulted before we came to a . <lb/></p> 

<p>pi <lb/></p> 

<p>is <lb/></p> 

<p>o <lb/></p> 

<p>t <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/></p> 

<p>in the nature of things, be o <lb/></p> 

<p>Lower Provinces, all pledge, <lb/>
ently of the force and influe: <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>f <lb/></p> 

<p>ki <lb/>
. be for purposes of local <lb/></p> 

<p>. to commit himself to <lb/></p> 

<p># jºments in the Prºby." <lb/>
informed portion of the publ <lb/></p> 

<p>in this respect. <lb/></p> 

<p>taxe <lb/></p> 

<p>discussing this point, to cr <lb/>
but this will be met, no dou <lb/>
are all before the Mouse. It <lb/>
ºuld act wisely in suspendi <lb/>
all the facts come before theu <lb/>
on one side or the other wili <lb/></p> 

<p>especially is argued from t <lb/>
Canada to be the natural en <lb/>
be influenced by a desire to i <lb/>
upon uš, <lb/>
for this opinion, it would be <lb/>
to keep aloof; but like most <lb/>
against Union, it rests on g <lb/></p> 

<p>alliance of the other Provin <lb/>
poses of her own; and we, <lb/>
hests, will adopt or reject i. <lb/>
purposes of our ºwn: W. <lb/>
men proceed on any other g <lb/>
interest, and the argument a <lb/>
Canada on this account is as: <lb/>
conduct of a man who reſu <lb/>
required merely because it sº <lb/>
it. It is for their own purp <lb/>
and Canada send us their foe <lb/>
our people,but do we reject 1 <lb/>
Trade of one whit the less v <lb/>
countries are guided by thei <lb/>
carrying it on P If then its <lb/>
join the Gunfederation, we wº <lb/>
spect we shall act on the st <lb/>
# the several Provinces as weli <lb/>
not be at the mercy of Cana' <lb/></p> 

<p>the common interests which <lb/>
well as we ourselves have in <lb/>
tion. <lb/>
interest to tax this colony ot <lb/>
any other injurious line of po <lb/>
by means of Confederation of <lb/>
fortunes with those of Cana <lb/></p> 

<p>dent that our loss is not her <lb/></p> 

<p>benefitted by our prosperity <lb/></p> 

<p>loser by the depression of an <lb/>
tion of which she forms so ſº <lb/>
mon sense and reason, and e <lb/></p> 

<p>of self-interest would prompt <lb/>
vative course of amelioratio <lb/></p> 

<p>jections; but as time goes of <lb/></p> 

<p>nd could be ever £8 <lb/></p> 

<p>ld be protected by <lb/>
oval from their own homes. <lb/>
the Delegates, and no one <lb/></p> 

<p>The bugbear now relied o <lb/>
, to which Confederation <lb/>
an attempt, in anticipatio <lb/></p> 

<p>f intelligent men. The que <lb/>
If any reasonable <lb/></p> 

<p>ºal existence. Canada unq <lb/></p> 

<p>the Delegates, for the 47 <lb/></p> 

<p>we have the great security <lb/></p> 

<p>If it could be made aſ <lb/></p> 

<p>with the affairs of this eulon <lb/>
colonies whose interests wer <lb/></p> 

<p>It is difficult to understand <lb/>
can fail to see the unreasoni <lb/></p> 

<p>fold the subject in all its asl <lb/></p> 

<p>true character will gradually <lb/></p> 

<p>to the intelligence of the co <lb/>
-\-\-4-seº <lb/></p> 

<p>Intelligence reached town <lb/>
bodies of Capt. John Burke, <lb/>
lost near Petty Harbor) and <lb/>
picked up there on Friday. <lb/>
ºrsrººmsºmº­ <lb/></p> 

<p>PASTORAL OF THE <lb/></p> 

<p>+JOHN THOM <lb/>
By the grace of God and fa <lb/>
Bishop of St. John's: <lb/>
To the Clergy and Laity 9 <lb/>
Benediction in t <lb/></p> 

<p>org, <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOII.N'S: <lb/>
MONDAY, FEBRUARY 6, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE Address in reply to the Governor's Speech has <lb/>
not yet passed through the Assembly, where it has <lb/>
been the subject of considerable discussion, especially <lb/>
as regards the absorbing question of Confederation. <lb/>
On Thursday the Delegates, Messrs. CARTER and <lb/>
SHEA, addressed the House at very considerable <lb/>
length in explanation of the question, and of the rea<lb break="no"/>sons which induced them to regard it with approval. <lb/>
We think no dispassionate man could have heard <lb/>
them without feeling they had made a strong case, <lb/>
and placed the subject in a clear and comprehensive <lb/>
light before the House. This, we believe, ras the <lb/>
impression they produced, and we do know that some <lb/>
who had been hostile to the measure were satisfied by <lb/>
the reasons put forward that not only might the coun<lb break="no"/>try safely adopt it, but that it would be unwise and <lb/>
suicidal to reject it. We regret that owing to the great <lb/>
imperfection of cur system of reporting, some days <lb/>
must elapse before these speeches are before the public <lb/>
in anything like completeness. <lb/>
The Militia scarecrow and the "bleaching of bones <lb/>
on the Canadian soil," have been pretty well laughed <lb/>
out of value for any further purposes of sensation. <lb/>
The Delegates showed that a Militia force could not <lb/>
be organized in this country, because the pursuits of <lb/>
our people were such as to take them from their homes <lb/>
during a great part of the year, and it would therefore <lb/>
be a mistake to rely on them, as in case of necessity. <lb/>
they would probably be absent. Canada has a frontier <lb/>
to defend, and she has a settled population. She has <lb/>
therefore the necessity for a Militia, and she has the <lb/>
means of creating it, both of which conditions are <lb/></p> 

<p>wanting in the case of this island. But if a Militia <lb/></p> 

<p># <lb/>
i <lb/>
3 <lb/>
# <lb/>
# <lb/>
} <lb/>
à <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>! <lb/></p>
<fw type="running">t MULLOCK ON 1 º he Lord</fw>
<fw type="num">3.</fw>
<fw type="num">DEARLY</fw>
<fw type="running">BELOWED BRETHRE!</fw> 

<p>Our Holy Father Pius IX. <lb/>
the Apostolic Chair to feedh <lb/>
teach and govern His Churc <lb/>
state of society in a great p <lb/>
beholding the grievous erro <lb/>
social edifice, has once more. <lb/>
an Encyclical letter dated 1) <lb/>
the Bishops and Pastors ofth <lb/>
flocks from the dangers of <lb/>
latitudinarianism. Although <lb/>
God, we are not in this cu <lb/>
moral pestilence, and the sin <lb/>
people has not been contamir <lb/>
ious teaching, still as men <lb/>
body of Christ—the Church­ <lb/>
suffers as we rejoice in her <lb/>
the gates of hell will never.] <lb/>
have the promise of her Divir <lb/>
we see His Vicar on earth su <lb/>
tions of the wičked; the prº <lb/>
legacy of the piety of former <lb/>
and priests in exile; conve <lb/>
desecrated; education, made <lb/>
sion; and secret societies sap <lb/>
of all morality—we would b <lb/>
we not deeply sympathise <lb/>
Holy Mother the Church. <lb/>
calls on all his childrer over <lb/>
in prayer before the Throne <lb/>
may be shortened," peace ré <lb/>
ºrror and infidelity subdued. <lb/></p> 

<p>^be made acceptable to God <lb/></p> 

<p>and humble hearts, he gran <lb/>
Plenary Indu gence of the J <lb/>
month in this year—the tim <lb/>
Rishop. Bowing with pro" <lb/>
of the Holy Father, we the <lb/>
ima Sunday, the 12th of Fº <lb/>
opening of the Jubilee in thi <lb/>
tinue till the 12th of March. <lb/>
will commence as goon as <lb/>
especially select this early <lb/>
have the opportunity of ob: <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>