<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-09" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1869-02-09">9 February 1869</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1869-02-17"/>
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2019-01-29">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2019-01-29">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_1.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">1</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">St. John's, Wednesday, February 17, 1869.</fw>

    <!-- IC, 2019-01-29, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->
<!--<p>onderful that the world has ever known. <lb/>
ſº, and in whateven shaps disease exists, <lb/>
ses equal to its subjection and cure. <lb/></p> 

<p>HE SrCº. <lb/>
one the IIousemold nextEdy of all nations. <lb/>
they attack the very Root of the complaint, <lb/>
lase, restore the drooping enorgies of the <lb/>
lynctionaar arronurios. <lb/>
HE STOMACH: <lb/>
what is the operation of thoſills? They <lb/>
fixed or irritated stomachinto a natural and <lb/>
|tate of the system from sickness to health. <lb/>
ER, AIIMIENTs. <lb/>
ystem undergoes the most important and <lb/>
ccific in every disorder to which they are <lb/>
feguard against evil consequences. <lb/></p> 

<p>NT) ºr MIETTERTTTEs or;" <lb/>
OOID. <lb/>
le blood is in an impure state, let snch <lb/></p> 

<p>resort with confidence to this powerful <lb/>
1 to health and strength will be the result. <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb break="no"/>Y ENTOWIN E-C-E­ <lb/></p> 

<p>*. laints §.i. Gravel. <lb break="no"/>Pr Uomplaints. econdary Symptons. <lb break="no"/>s Weakness, from thatever * <lb/></p> 

<p>ention of Urine, cause, &amp;c., a. <lb/></p> 

<p>the words "Holloway, London," are dis<lb break="no"/>k of directions around each box; which <lb/>
tº-º Sold at the manufactory of Pro<lb break="no"/>all respectable Druggists and Dealers in <lb/>
B., 22s., and 33s.-There is a considerable <lb/>
irections for use are affixed to cach Box, <lb/></p> 

<p>130NUS EVERY Tii REE YEARS <lb/></p> 

<p>THE FINA <lb/></p> 

<p>NSURANCE COMPANY <lb/></p> 

<p>- (LIMI.º.) -<lb break="maybe"/>Capital–One #illion Sterling. <lb/>
1 Offices-Dubin-\-46 &amp; 47 Upper Sackville <lb/>
Edinburgh–98 George's Street. <lb/>
London – 17 &amp; 1s Cornhill, E. C. <lb/>
General Manager—John Innes, #4. <lb/>
Secretary ...J. S. Fisher, Esq. <lb/></p> 

<p>le unprecedented success of the ETNA in the <lb/>
ed Kingdom, owing to its liberal dealings with <lb/>
publ 5 is a fact which strongly recomments the <lb/>
pany to the perple of Newfºundland. <lb/>
fe income of this Company is om NEw PRE<lb break="no"/>JMS AI.ONE is progressing at the rate -of <lb/>
,000 per Annum. <lb/>
he Cºmpany dº not advocate high preminms. <lb/>
offers ample security to all nsurers. <lb/>
aims for losses shall be promptly and liberally <lb/>
*:01. <lb/>
ransfers from other offices can be effected free <lb/>
harge. <lb/>
arties by payment of SIX years premiumscal <lb/>
e St.VEN years policy. <lb/>
: ETNA is ºil, only OFºrce wirich of rea <lb/>
Bosts if YERY T: REE YEARS To rolicy<lb break="no"/>HOLDERS HAVING No Loss E8. <lb/></p> 

<p>e underaigned having been appointed Genera <lb/>
at a* Newfoundland for the above Company, <lb/>
pared to effect Insurances against loss of: <lb/>
1AGE BY FIRE nm all descriptions of pro<lb break="no"/>at fair and reasºnable rates, and begs leave. <lb/>
licit a share ºf the business of those having <lb/>
ºnces to effect. <lb/>
orders shall have prompt attention. <lb/>
ºrms for proposals and further information ean <lb/>
ad at the 0::ite of <lb/></p> 

<p>It OBERT J. KENT, <lb/></p> 

<p>Solicitor. <lb/>
2281 Pºkºrº St.John's. <lb/>
- wn <lb/></p> 

<p>tºº.2 º º <lb/></p> 

<p>relieving and curing old wounds, sores, <lb/>
r however inveterate. Few medicines <lb/>
his grand remedy not only cures in such <lb/>
alysis, as a proof it needs but a trial. <lb/></p> 

<p>EONºrC+:EIT rs. <lb/>
ad coughs, and colds, may be infallibly <lb/>
l rubbing this remedy twice a day upon <lb/>
hetrates, and a cure quickly follows. <lb/>
EEAST's, ETC. <lb/>
ed. Remedy is now in general use. In <lb/>
, the Physicians regularly prescribe its <lb/>
Indin the chests of sailors and emigrants. <lb/>
D SWET.I.I.INTG-s. s <lb/>
d this Ointment will prove invaluable. <lb/>
i pain, and restores natural circulation. <lb/>
s, ETC., ETC. . <lb/>
we parts, of either sex, may be readily <lb/>
ise of this cooling and healing Ointment. <lb/>
j YCUTE:L. <lb/>
ectually cured by the joint agency of <lb/>
ng to the printed directions. gency <lb/></p> 

<p>intly in most of the following eases:­ <lb/></p> 

<p>1. Sore Heads. <lb/>
King's Evil. Tic Doloureur. <lb/></p> 

<p>ruptions. º or Wheezing on the <lb/></p> 

<p>3. Chest, with difficulty of Breathing <lb/></p> 

<p>the words "Holloway, London," aredis<lb break="no"/>f to the light, in every ieaf of the book of <lb/>
anufactory of Professor Holloway, 244, <lb/>
s in Medicine, in pots at 18.14d., 23.94. <lb/>
rable saving by taking the larger sizes <lb/></p> 

<p>... erty was not to be known. <lb/></p> 

<p>- ****-tºesnº-\-\-\-\-<lb break="maybe"/>ºf , -\- *::::::::::::::::::: -<lb break="maybe"/>£ººr. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºr * <lb/></p> 

<p>-\- - s- 34t. <lb/></p> 

<p>*-ºn- <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p># <lb/>
... $. <lb/>
:Tle ºr as .z-e # *­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ºr <lb/></p> 

<p>#. <lb/></p> 

<p>(ſhe 3ienfunmillantler,­ <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/>
# <lb/>
i <lb/></p> 

<p>-\-\- z lºgº - º <lb/>
* B = ** st. John's, Wednesday, February 17, 1869. - ** <lb/>
—— * <lb/></p> 

<p>3 speech. <lb/></p> 

<p>Printed and Published every Tuesday and Friday <lb/>
morning by EUWARD DALTON SHEA, at his <lb/>
office, in Duckworth STREET. Terms–One <lb/>
Guinea per annum, pnyable in advance. <lb/></p> 

<p>Advertisements not limited (Auction Sales and notices <lb/>
which determine themselves excepted) are repeated, <lb/>
until ºrdered in writing to be withdrawn; <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>rhis paper tº filed, and man be seen fee ºf hargé <lb/>
at Holloway's Pill and Ointment Establishment, <lb/>
244. Strand London. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>rais paper is notissued to any Subsertber for a shorter <lb/>
term than siz months. <lb/></p>--> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, Feb. 9. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
House met pursuant to adjournment. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
On motion of <persName ref="pers:GODD1">Mr. GODDEN</persName>, the House resolv<lb break="no"/>ed itself into Committee of the Whole on the <lb/>
Address of thanks, <persName ref="pers:KNIG2">Mr. KNIGHT</persName> in the chair. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:GODD1">Mr. GODDEN</persName> moved the adoption of the 4th <lb/>
section. <lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName>.—The section now before the <lb/>
House was one of the most vital importance to <lb/>
this country. It was important because it involv<lb break="no"/>ed a right which had seen conceded years ago, <lb/>
by the Imperial Government, which had been <lb/>
sanctioned by treaty, and which, only a few <lb/>
months ago, had been ignored by a Colonial <lb/>
Secretary of the name of Carnarvon. He (Mr. <lb/>
H.) contended that it was the most important <lb/>
clause in the Address. Before, however, he <lb/>
went into the consideration of the question <lb/>
he would refer to the whole of His Excellency's <lb/>
speech. Now he had heard hon. members <lb/>
speak of it as a glorious speech, as the most <lb/>
wonderful one which had ever been delivered by <lb/>
a Governor. It opened up such an expanse of <lb/>
view, and suggested so many remedies that all <lb/>
the Government members have fallen down on <lb/>
their knees and worshipped it. Well now, we <lb/>
have had a good deal said, session after session; <lb/>
about Outport Steam. The Surveyor General <lb/>
was a great supporter of Outport Steam. It <lb/>
would be in his opinion the panacea for every <lb/>
ill in Newfoundland. Every egg that would be <lb/>
laid, in Bonavista; every lobster that was <lb/>
caught along our coasts, every heifer that was <lb/>
at the Northward, were to find their way o <lb/>
the St. John's market by Outport Steam. Pov<lb break="no"/>erty was not to be know. Well, we have no <lb/>
steam consuunication now, and there was not <lb/>
a word about it in the speech. The little <lb/>
"Ariel" was lying in the harbor motionless. <lb/>
Now do the Government mean to abandon Out<lb break="no"/>port steam communication? Do they mean to <lb/>
forsake their first love. They were silent upon <lb/>
the subject, and are we then wrong in saying <lb/>
that they are a party of do-nothings who thus <lb/>
allow their own offspring to perish. Now that <lb/>
was the first omission in the speech. Now we <lb/>
had been paying for some years past seven or <lb/>
eight hundred a year for a Geological survey <lb/>
of the Island. Is there a single word about the <lb/>
exploration? No not one word. What did this <lb/>
show? Why that the Executive were lax in their <lb/>
duty in not knowing what their employee was <lb/>
about. There was not even a report from <choice><sic>thht</sic><corr>that</corr></choice> <lb/>
gentleman, and hence the Government are un<lb break="no"/>able to congratulate the country on the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture that had been made for this service. But <lb/>
the public had an opinion upon this matter, and <lb/>
that was that the Dominion Government were <lb/> 
in possession of that information which we <lb/>
should of right have. Leaving the Geological <lb/>
survey, he would now refer to the St. John's <lb/>
Hospital. There was not a man that entered <lb/>
that building but got infected with typhus <lb/>
fever. The matter had been brought before <lb/>
the Executive two years ago, and a promise had <lb/>
been made by the Government that it would be <lb/>
intended to, and yet it never had been. These <lb/>
were some of the dilemmas upon which we hang <lb/>
the Government. They bad left not a single <lb/>
monument, a mark of progress during their <lb/>
administration, except the mark which is ever <lb/>
seen in the lace of a man, fed upon Indian meal <lb/>
and molasses. The only promise which the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment made was the one they made to them<lb break="no"/>selves, to receive their salaries every quarter <lb/>
day. Here the hon. member referred to that <lb/>
portion of the Speech relative to the Reciprocity <lb/>
Treaty, and said that a more insulting paragraph <lb/>
had never been seen in a Governor's speech, <lb/>
addressed to a deliberative Assembly. We had <lb/>
got Reciprocal Free Trade bafore, and when <lb/>
there was no New Dominion, and we could get <lb/>
it again at the present moment. If we were <lb/>
merely in this House to obey Imperial behests, <lb/>
what was the use of a Representative form of <lb/>
Government, and telling the people that we <lb/>
could do this that and the other thing? This <lb/>
then was the great speech which after four years <lb/>
they had come down with, and expect the pub<lb break="no"/>lic to endorse. The time was not far distant <lb/>
when, the people would be fully alive to the <lb/>
way in which they had been deluded. The <lb/>
whole burden of this speech was Confederation, <lb/>
Confederation, Confederation. Then we <lb/>
come to the next insult that had been offered, <lb/>
and that was the clause referring to the French <lb/>
Shore. Here the hon member read the clause <lb/>
and continued. This House did not delegate <lb/>
His Excellency to go to England, any more than <lb/>
they did the hon. Receiver General. He went <lb/>
there of his own motion, and he botched the <lb/>
matter, and if he wishes now to throw dust in <lb/>
the eyes of the people, this House should meet <lb/>
him on the threshold, and put the public, or at <lb/>
least those of them, who may be inclined to <lb/>
invest money on that part of the coast, on their <lb/>
        <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>, before they place themselves in a position <lb/>

<cb/>

in which they cannot protect themselves, and in <lb/>
what His Excellency may not be able to help them, <lb/>
because he will be far away. If his Grace inform<lb break="no"/>ed His Excellency there was only one way in <lb/>
which it could be done with courtesy to the Go<lb break="no"/>vernor and to the Colony, and that did not appear <lb/>
to have been adopted. "I am informed" says <lb/>
his Excellency, that his Grace sees no reason <lb/>
why grants should not be sanctioned in the inte<lb break="no"/>rior of the island. Go where the good niggers go; <lb/>
where the aborogines used to dwell, long, long <lb/>
ago, and dig and delve,and when mines are found, <lb/>
you dare not bring your minerals to the sea shore. <lb/>
His Excellency goes on, "provided that no right <lb/>
is granted which will enable buildings to be erect<lb break="no"/>ed on the strand, or which would cause the French <lb/>
to apprehend any interruption to the full enjoy<lb break="no"/>ment by them of any of the privileges belonging <lb/>
to their Fishery rights." This was the grand <lb/>
boon, the great work accomplished by his Excel<lb break="no"/>lency during his four months' absence from the <lb/>
Colony. The matter stands exactly as it did last <lb/>
session. It is not one whith advanced. The <lb/>
French are just as secure in their rights, and the <lb/> 
difficulty of working mines by British subjects on <lb/>
British soil is as great as when that celebrated <lb/>
despatch to which his Excellency alludes was <lb/>
written. The policy indicated in that despatch is <lb/>
emphatically declared by his Excellency to be the <lb/>
policy of the British Government, and it we are <lb/> 
to believe his Excellency, it remained unaltered <lb/>
up to the time he left England. That despatch <lb/>
        read as follows:— <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">DOWNING STREET, <lb/>
    7th December, 1866. <lb/></p> 

<p>SIR.—I have had under my consideration your <lb/>
Despatch No. 116, of the 8th August, 1866, reporting <lb/>
your return from a visit to the South and West <lb/>
Coasts of Newfoundland, and communicating to me <lb/>
the impressions you derived from the journey. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
I have also received from you a more recent des<lb break="no"/>patch, enclosing a memorial from Mr. C. F. Bennett, <lb/>
who appears to have been engaged in searching for <lb/>
Minerals on the West Coast of Newfoundland. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Mr. Bennett does not see n to be fully aware that <lb/>
some of the conclusions which have been advocated <lb/>
from time to time by the British Government in <lb/>
relation to the French Shore, and to its neighboring <lb/>
waters, have never been admitted by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of France, and that it is the difference which <lb/>
has hitherto existed on these points between the two <lb/>
Governments which creates a difficulty in dealing <lb/>
with the Coasts of Newfoundland in the manner <lb/>
most calculated to develope the resources of the <lb/>
Colony. Her Majesty's Government much regret <lb/>
the unsettled state of this question, and the serious <lb/>
inconvenience to which this leads. But it would be <lb/>
a far graver evil to embroil the Government of Eng<lb break="no"/>land in a dispute with that of France on the grounds <lb/>
which a careful consideration of existing Treaties did <lb/>
not clearly justify. They are unable, therefore, to <lb/>
treat as decided questions which are really matter of <lb/>
controversy. They would, however, most readily <lb/>
re-open the negotiations with the French Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, which were broken off in 1861, if only satisfied <lb/>
that there were a reasonable prospect of bringing <lb/>
them to a successful termination. Meanwhile, pend<lb break="no"/>ing the settlement of the questions of French and <lb/>
British rights on the coast, I am unable to authorize <lb/>
the appointment of a British Magistrate on the so<lb break="no"/>called French Shore, nor have I any alternative but <lb/>
to instruct you, for the present, not to make any <lb/>
grants of land on that Coast. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
There is no doubt that the provisions of the exist<lb break="no"/>ing Treaties, as they stand, are ill adapted to meet <lb/>
the real exigencies either of the French Fishermen <lb/>
or of the Newfoundlaud Colonists; and might be <lb/>
greatly modified for the advantage of both parties. <lb/>
And I should gladly resume negotiations with a view <lb/>
to such a modification; but I think it necessary to <lb/>
add that any such negotiations must be attended <lb/>
with considerable difficulty, so long as it is liable to <lb/>
be disturbed by unforeseen objections on the part of <lb/>
the Colony. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">I have the honour to be, Sir, <lb/>
Your most obedient humble servant, <lb/> 
(Signed,)      CARNARVON. <lb/></p> 

<p>Governor Musgrave, &amp;c., &amp;2., &amp;c. <lb/></p> 

<p>That is the despatch which his Excellency tells us <lb/>
is kept intact, and that its principles still actuato <lb/>
the British Government. What does the Governor <lb/>
say "In anticipation of the formal agreement, <lb/>
which has been proposed to the French Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. I have been acquainted by His Grace the <lb/>
late Secretary of State that he approve; of the <lb/>
policy indicated in Lord Carnarvon's Despateh at <lb/>
the 7th December 1863, that no action should be <lb/>
taken which could in any way be construed into for <lb/>
interference with the French in their fishery rights. <lb/>
Was not that a re-echo of the despatch. Lord <lb/>
Cardarvon does not say that grants shall not be <lb/>
issued of the interior, but only that he his "no <lb/>
alternative but to instruct you tor the present not <lb/>
to make any grant of land on that coast." Was <lb/>
not that the Whole question between this Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture and the Imperial Government? What then <lb/>
has his Excellency done? What better position <lb/>
has he placed us in? He (Mr. H.) did not think <lb/>
he need point the House to the addresses and reso<lb break="no"/>lutions aud debates and the stern opposition given <lb/>
to the despatch of Lord Carnarvon. We are told <lb/>
we may go into the interior, but must not come <lb/>
near the coast. We might as well be told we could <lb/>
dig into the bowels of the earth like moles. Was <lb/>
this namby pamby speech, the only reply to <lb/>
house was to have to its resolutions and addresses? <lb/>
Common courtesy should at all events dictate an <lb/>
acknowledgment of the receipt of our despatches. <lb/>
How are we treated in this matter? So as to <lb/>
approach the Imperial Government with all due <lb/>
respect and with words of loyalty, but yet breath<lb break="no"/>ing our deep feelings of grievances on this subject. <lb/>
We sent home joint addresses, which went through <lb/>
the usual channel, and yet we have received no <lb/>
reply to them, at least from the only proper source <lb/>
from which the reply should come, that is to say <lb/>
from the office of the Secretary of State for the <lb/>
colonies. There had been no modification of the <lb/>
Carnarvon policy, it still stood out in bold relief <lb/>
    <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> the people of the Colony. Written <lb/>
not in letters of gold but of disgrace, and deeply <lb/>
imprinted in the minds of the people. It was non<lb break="no"/>sense to talk of issuing grants where the foot of <lb/>
no white man, not even our sainted Geologist <lb/>
had ever trod. Our people would perish there as <lb/>
certainly as they would in the wild woods of <lb/>
Canada, where they are to be sent to work at <lb/>
Railways. If hon. gentlemen, who call them<lb break="no"/>selves patriots and say they have the interest of <lb/>
the country at heart, can be content with such <lb/>
myths as these, all others could do was to pity <lb/>
them, to try to arouse them, aul if they cannot <lb/>
iupel them in a right direction, to appeal to the <lb/> 
people whose voice they must hear and whose <lb/>
    
    <cb/>

opinions they must respect. Though in the strug<lb break="no"/>gle between the French and English Governments, <lb/>
the French should have the best of it, was this <lb/>
House to ignore the rights of the people of the <lb/>
Colony? It the British Government commit a <lb/>
wrong, why let them. Let this House at all events <lb/>
discharge its duty to the people. Why should the <lb/>
House be called on to congratulate the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment or any delegate in a question which by <lb/>
his own acknowledgement is still open? The <lb/>
British Government is only about to submit terms <lb/>
to the French. Are thes terms agreed on be<lb break="no"/>tween them? Are they not still going on with <lb/>
negotiations. When we are still without that <lb/>
reply to which as a Representative body we are <lb/>
    entitled, are we to take the <hi rendition="simple:italic">ips dixit</hi> of any man <lb/>
who choses to go on a rambling excursion? This <lb/>
House is not dead yet, nor is the country killed <lb/>
out yet, neither are our representative institutions <lb/>
yet worn out, and though hon. gentlemen with <lb/>
large salaries may find it difficult to stem the dif<lb break="no"/>ficulties which surround them. Yet though poor <lb/>
as the people are, their skeleton forms will rise up <lb/> 
assert their rights, show their power and beat their <lb/>
opponents. The hon. and learned gentlemen con<lb break="no"/>cluded by moving the following amendment.— <lb/> 
[Here the hon member read the Amendment, and <lb/>
moved its adoption.] <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SHEA2">Hon. A. SHEA</persName>.—The matter before the chair <lb/>
had reference to a question of very great im<lb break="no"/>portance. He had no fault to find with the way <lb/>
in which the hon. and learned gentleman who <lb/>
spoke last treated it. But he (hon. Mr. S.) <lb/>
differed with him in his conclusions. To hear <lb/>
him, one would suppose that we were in a posi<lb break="no"/>ion to determine this question for ourselves. <lb/>
This question was a very old one, and had been <lb/>
matter of consijeration for almost every legisla<lb break="no"/>ture which had sat in the Colony. It is a matter <lb/>
on which the British Government alone can <lb/>
pronounce definitively. There were two par<lb break="no"/>ties concerned; and as far as could be seen by <lb/>
the correspondence, they had not arrived at any <lb/>
conclusions by which the exercise of their rights <lb/>
should be defined. It was well known that this <lb/>
was a subject which was always approached, <lb/>
with great tenderness by the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Fiance attached great importance to these, <lb/>
fisheries, and in the absence of any clear definition <lb/>
of their right, Great Britain was not in dispos<lb break="no"/>ed to a compromise which might laid to such a <lb/>
definition. The subject was brought before the <lb/>
House last session, and petitions to Parliament <lb/>
and to the Imperial Government were adopted. <lb/>
There was much difference of opinion as to the <lb/>
expediency of this course, and it was the opinion <lb/>
of many that it would not be wise to bring the <lb/>
matter before Parliament. Parliament, they <lb/>
thought, would be unwilling to take any ex<lb break="no"/>treme course in the matter, and the effect of <lb/>
elicisting the opinion of Parliament would be to <lb/>
relieve the Executive of the day from any res<lb break="no"/>ponsibility it might feel in view of the repre<lb break="no"/>sentations of this House. As the event shewed, <lb/>
they were justified in their anticipations. <lb/>
British statestmen say that they cannot proceed <lb/>
in the question with too much care, that the in<lb break="no"/>terests of the Empire are in a measure involved <lb/>
with it, and that they are not prepared to risk a <lb/>
war with France for its settlement. It was idle <lb/>
to suppose that the British Government would, <lb/>
for any interest of our jeopardise their good re<lb break="no"/>lations with France; and it would be unreasonable <lb/>
in one part to expect it. The result of our ap<lb break="no"/>plication was that it did not place the matter in <lb/>
any favourable light. There was not a man in <lb/>
Parliament who would support the Colonial <lb/>
view, for they all regarded the matter in an <lb/>
Imperial light, aad said it would be impolite <lb/>
and dangerous to carry out our views. It was <lb/>
a false move on our part to give them such an <lb/>
opportunity of pronouncing on the matter. It <lb/>
had been stated that his Excellency had no <lb/>
authority from this House to visit England and <lb/>
enter into negotiations on this matter. His <lb/>
Excellency was not responsible to this House, <lb/>
and did not for a moment suppose he was acting <lb/>
under its authority. It was by the special in<lb break="no"/>structions of the imperial Government he visited <lb/>
England. The Government supposed that one <lb/>
who took such a deep interest in the question, <lb/>
and had written so ably on it, would be of valu<lb break="no"/>able assistance in its settlement; and on that <lb/>
account and that alone, and independently of <lb/>
this House, he went home. He is not respon<lb break="no"/>sible to this House, nor is the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment responsible to this House, for the course <lb/>
they may pursue respesing this matter. The <lb/>
Imperial Government felt that we were largely <lb/>
interested in this matter, and they had exhibited <lb/>
every disposition to meet the views of the people <lb/>
of the Colony. But when asked to do that <lb/>
which would conflict with their policy towards <lb/>
France they demurred. It was perfectly <lb/>
idle to imagine that any consideration for our <lb/> 
interests would ever induce them to abandon <lb/>
their Imperial policy. He (hon. Mr. S.) did <lb/>
not say that we should lie down quietly and, as <lb/>
the expression was, "accept the situation." He <lb/>
thought it would be advisable to jog the memo<lb break="no"/>ry of the Imperial Government, to induce them <lb/>
to use every means consistent with their avowed <lb/>
policy, for the delimite settlement of our rights. <lb/>
Though we have not accomplished all we aimed <lb/>
at, nor obtained such a settlement of the ques<lb break="no"/>tion as would enable the Government to issue <lb/>
clear grants, we have nevertheless acquired a <lb/>
very in portant advantage, which would enable <lb/>
parties requiring tracts of land to obtain these <lb/>
lands, and work them virtually free from all <lb/>
these obstructions with which the letter of the <lb/>
law might seem to encumber them. This ad<lb break="no"/>vantage was owing entirely to the personal ex<lb break="no"/>ertions of the Governor, who had a this metter <lb/>
displayed an ability and a zaal which entiled <lb/>
him to the gratitude of every man who was in<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

terested in the welfare of the Colony. Under <lb/>
the authority obtained by His Excellency, <lb/>
power resides in him to issue grants of land, not <lb/>
exactly upon the sea coast, but more or less <lb/>
inland. No practical difficulty will obstruct the <lb/>
issue of three out of every four grants applied <lb/>
for on that shore. No Government could over <lb/>
turn the law of the treaties. No law could <lb/>
authorize the issue of any grants invading the <lb/>
occupation of any part of the sea coast which <lb/>
is reserved to the French; and such grants <lb/>
would necessarily be construed as an infraction <lb/>
of their treaty rights. Therefore, in an any <lb/>
grants that may be issued, a reservation will be <lb/> 
made against the erection of any buildings upon <lb/>
the sea coast, though it was not at all likely <lb/>
that parties would be necessitated to adhere to a <lb/> 
this condition, as the greater number of applica<lb break="no"/>tions are for land upon that part of the coast <lb/>
where the French do not fish; and where <lb/>
already British subjects reside, against the <lb/>
letter of the treaties, but altogether unobstruc<lb break="no"/>ted by the French. Already some very impor<lb break="no"/>tant grants have been issued to parties who, <lb/>
acquainted with the premises, are perfectly will<lb break="no"/>ing to take them with all the conditions. No <lb/>
doubt the subject would, in time, be satisfacto<lb break="no"/>rily dealt with, so that these things which we <lb/>
have now, by sufferance, would be confirmed as <lb/>
legal rights. Our proceedings of last year <lb/>
were doubtless perfectly well intended, but he <lb/>
(hon. Mr. S.) could not but repeat the opinion <lb/>
which he then expressed, that it was a grand <lb/>
mistake for us to go to the Imperial parliament. <lb/>
We merely enabled the Government of the day a <lb/>
to make a pronouncement that they would do <lb/>
nothing by which the Imperial relations with <lb/>
France might be disturbed. And it was unwise <lb/>
in us to call on a discussion which would neces<lb break="no"/>sarily have the effect of producing that expres<lb break="no"/>sion of opinion. This was no case in which <lb/>
Parliament would bring pressure upon the <lb/>
Government. It was a matter of international <lb/>
obligation, approached on all sides with great <lb/>
caution, and Parliament could not but approve <lb/>
of the course of reticence which the ministry <lb/>
adopted. He (hon. Mr. S.) could not see the <lb/>
necessity of introducing in the speech from year <lb/>
to year a mention of the Geological Survey, <lb/>
which has now become a mere matter of routine. <lb/>
As to the suspicion that the Report of the <lb/>
Geologist is better known in Canada than here <lb/>
it is most unfounded. Mr. Murray was a gen<lb break="no"/>tleman who had always most religiously respect<lb break="no"/>ed the obligatious which he owed to the local <lb/>
Government. He (hon. Mr. S.) was personally <lb/>
acquainted with the fact that in Cauada com<lb break="no"/>plaints were made of Mr. Murray's reticence, <lb/>
so that his intimate friends had sought from <lb/>
him (hon. Mr. S.) information on the common<lb break="no"/>est affairs. Sir W. Logan is Mr. Murray's <lb/>
superior, and his (Mr. Murray's) relations require <lb/>
him to report to Sir Willian in the first place. In <lb/>
that professional course which these proceedings <lb/>
require, they have to pass through his hands be<lb break="no"/>fore being communicated to us; and he (hon. <lb/>
Mr. S.) believed that they were just as religi<lb break="no"/>ously raspected as it he were the sworn servant <lb/>
of the Colony. Supposing however that this <lb/>
suspicion were correct, do we care that all the <lb/>
world should know our resources? Would it <lb/>
not, as a matter of fact, be hightly desirable that <lb/>
the attention of others should be directed to <lb/>
those resourses which, og ourselves, we cannot <lb/>
develop. He would not justify Mr. Murray <lb/>
if he were to allow Canada to anticipate us <lb/>
with this information; but wrong as it might be <lb/>
in him, the results could not be otherwise than <lb/>
advantageous to ourselves. The hon. member <lb/>
had referred to the introduction of the recipro<lb break="no"/>city question into the speech, and had comment<lb break="no"/>ed upon a remark of his (hon. Mr. S.) which <lb/>
was not open to dispute. When he referred to <lb/>
the subject he had said that it was incidentally <lb/>
introduced. That was perfectly true, but <lb/>
nevertheless the question aross as a matter of <lb/>
prominent consideration in connection with <lb/>
Coufederation. Reciprocity could not be ob<lb break="no"/>tained without the intervention of those agencies <lb/>
which under Confederation would be brought <lb/>
into play, at least until house members oppsite <lb/>
introduce that plan which has been heraldad <lb/>
with such a flourish of trumpets. We had <lb/>
had eleven years experience of recprocity; and <lb/>
we had found it greatly to our advantage. The <lb/>
proprosition of the hon. member, Mr. Glen, as <lb/>
to reciprocal duties, could hardly carry the <lb/>
slightest weight with it. We must know too <lb/>
that even if we were in a position to dispense <lb/>
with duties on the necessaries of life, it <lb/>
was only turo' the Imperial or the Dominion <lb/>
Government that we could obtain a renewal of <lb/>
the treaty. We were not in the position of a <lb/>
great negotiating power, and it we fancied so <lb/>
we should only place ourselves in the ridiculous <lb/>
position of the wiseacres ot Prince Edward <lb/>
islaud. Hon. gentleman ought to be ashamed <lb/>
of themselves to talk at this time of day of <lb/>
reciprocal duties of 5 per cent. Such terms <lb/> 
would never be proposed by the other Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, and the British GOvernment will permit <lb/>
no piebald policy. This allusion then had been <lb/>
properly iutroduced into the speech in the <lb/>
position it occupied, as an incidental matter <lb/>
powerfully bearing upon the main question. <lb/>
Independently of this, to his (hon. Mr. S's) <lb/>
mind, the main question had sufficient attrac<lb break="no"/>tions of its own. Reciprocity however is one <lb/>
of those things, which under Confederation <lb/>
    we are certain to gain, and it therefore occu<lb break="no"/>pied in the speech that place to which <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
    prominence and its importance <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> led <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> </p> 

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr. TALBOT</persName> approved of the amendment <lb/>
which had been put forward by the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber, M. Hogsett. It stated what was perfectly <lb/>
correct. Now the speech of his Excellency the <lb/>
Governor had been viewed in different lights. <lb/>
Some hon. members had praised it with no light <lb/>
praise, others had criticised it severely. So if he <lb/>
(Mr. T.) took a middle course, he thought he <lb/>
would be near the mark. It was by no means <lb/>
an extraordinary speech; but it was not wholly <lb/>
destitute of matters of considerable interest. It <lb/>
was one of those kind of speeches usually deliver<lb break="no"/>ed at the opening of each session of this House, <lb/>
fairly written, and fairly delivered. But in <lb/>
important matters there was an almost entire <lb/>
absence of decision, of a clearly defined policy; <lb/>
which we all must regard as not very comple<lb break="no"/>mantary to this House. A speech from the <lb/>
throne was always supposed to define a specific <lb/>
policy. Now in this speech there were references <lb/>
made to certain matters properly enough; but <lb/>
there was no course of policy defined for the <lb/>
Government to pursue. Now when the present <lb/>
Government came into power, a speech some<lb break="no"/>what similar to the present, one had been ad<lb break="no"/>dressed to this Assembly; and in that the <lb/>
Government did think it necessary to say what <lb/>
they intended to do, in order to restore the <lb/>
country from its deplorable condition, and to <lb/>
moving it forward in the career of improvement. <lb/>
The policy then put forth was the encouragement <lb/>
and improvement of Agriculture; and in per<lb break="no"/>suance of that a Bill was introduced and passed, <lb/>
having that end for its object,as well as the re<lb break="no"/>duction of pauperism. At the time this measure <lb/>
was under discussion, he (Mr. T.) had given <lb/>
it as his opinion that it would be productiv of no <lb/>
good. Well, the Bill was passed, came into <lb/>
operation,and we now find that it has been pow<lb break="no"/>erless to effect those results which the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment predicted, but which were never anticipated <lb/>
by this side of the House. Pauperism, so far <lb/>
from receding, had advanced; so far from being <lb/>
checked, it had been accelerated; so that our <lb/>
present position was really worse than when <lb/>
this great curative measure was so triumpuantly <lb/>
usherd in. Now that was one point which <lb/>
should be distinctly remembered. In that <lb/>
policy, then, Government had failed. Well, <lb/>
if we judge them by their failures, we cannot <lb/>
have much hope for their capacity to do any <lb/>
good. We had watchad carefully their pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings, and we had watched the operation <lb/>
and working of this measure with pecaliar cau<lb break="no"/>tion. He (Mr. T.) had taken the Government <lb/>
at its word. They said they were the greatest <lb/>
men in the country. He said granted. They <lb/>
said they would accomplish what had never <lb/>
been done before. He said granted. They <lb/>
said they possessed the collective wisdom of the <lb/>
country. He said granted. The said they <lb/>
were the Goliaths of this Colonial Parliament. <lb/>
He said granted. They said they were the only <lb/>
representatives of the public. He said grant<lb break="no"/>ed. They said they would never fail. He said <lb/>
doubtful. Well, all their sayings had come to <lb/>
nothiag, and his doubts had been verified. <lb/>
They were evidently impressed with the belief <lb/>
that it was impossible for any body of men to <lb/>
rule this country; because they would not and <lb/>
could not confess their own inability to do it, <lb/>
their own inability to grapple with the difficulties <lb/>
that surrounded them. They would doubtless <lb/>
assert that because they failed, it was impos<lb break="no"/>sible for others to succeed. Now what had <lb/>
they tried to do? Their first essay was to des<lb break="no"/>troy pauperism; and how did they try to effect <lb/>
that purpose? By saying to a pauper go into <lb/>
the woods and clear land,and for the first acre <lb/>
you clear we will give you $8, and for every <lb/>
one after the first, $9. This they said to a <lb/>
man without any means at his control, without <lb/>
being able to buy a loaf of bread, a pick-axe to <lb/>
work with, or the means to erect a dwelling to <lb/>
live in. At the time it was proposod he (Mr. <lb/>
T.) said it was impossible to succeed, as it was, <lb/>
that the Government must surely mean to do <lb/>
something more, must give them roads, must <lb/>
try to sustain them, or if not, we are only mock<lb break="no"/>ing the miseries of the poor. Well; the Bill <lb/>
had become, as he (Mr. T.) anticipated, a per<lb break="no"/>fect failure. But did they do anything else? <lb/>
Having failed in this instance, did they look <lb/>
around and see if they could devise any means <lb/>
that would be beneficial? Did they encourage <lb/>
those who had cultivated the land, but who, <lb/>
from poverty, were unable to work it? There <lb/>
were hundreds of acres of cultivated land which <lb/>
has been lying idle for years. Did they woo <lb/>
the people to recover it from its present wilder<lb break="no"/>ness state, and make their support dependent <lb/>
upon the culture of the soil? No. You <lb/>
made them believe they would get their <lb/>
support from you, and thus you <lb/>
degraded them. Pauperism increased, and pauper <lb/>
Relief expenditure increased. No effort was made <lb/>
to check it until the eleventh hour. He contended <lb/>
that when the Government desired to check this sys<lb break="no"/>tem, they should have done so by degrees, and not <lb/>
at one full bound. It would appear that the Premier <lb/>
felt his embarrassed situation, and his inability to <lb/>
stem the tide of corruption and malversation of the <lb/>
public funds. His only desire was to save himself, <lb/>
protect, if possible, his Government, and depend on <lb/>
luck for the result. The monster pauperism was <lb/> 
not to be killed but by one blow; but was to be <lb/>
gradually weakened. Then there was another evil <lb/>
quite sufficient to crush the country of itself, increased <lb/>
taxation. Their reasoning in support of that was <lb/>
that they could not support the people without <lb/>
facing additional burdens upon their backs. <lb/>
Your burdens, say they, are heavy, but we'll cure <lb/>
them by putting on heavier ones. Now would any <lb/>
one say that these two measures were calculated to <lb/>
benefit the county, though they were put forward <lb/>
for that purpose? They either did it for an evil <lb/>
purpose, or else because they were unabled to rule <lb/>
the country. We are told that this increase of taxa<lb break="no"/>tion was inevitable, and had been universally approv<lb break="no"/>ed of by the country. Here the hon. member refer<lb break="no"/>red at length to the late election at Harbor Grace,and <lb/>
contended that the question of Confederation had <lb/>
never been put to the people, who were perfectly <lb/>
indifferent whom they returned this session, knowing <lb/>
that the question would come before them for final <lb/>
decision at the general election. The fact that only <lb/>
one half of the electors votes, probed this. Then <lb/>

<cb/>

we had a new policy ushered in, the all abording <lb/>
one of Confederation. That was the policy that <lb/>
was shadowed forth in his Excellency's speech, two <lb/>
years ago, and every hon. member was aware of <lb/>
what then occurred. A paragraph had been smug<lb break="no"/>gled into the address, which it was afterwards <lb/>
    alleged affirmed the principle of Confederation.<lb/>
    Hon. members who had voted for it were in a state <lb/>
of great excitemant. They solemnly repudiated in <lb/>
    this House that they had intended to affirm any <lb/>
such principle. They'd clared that they were op<lb break="no"/>posed to Confederation on any terms, How men <lb/>
    then could so change their minds without any reason, <lb/>
    he (Mr. T.) was a loss to imagine. We are sur<lb break="no"/>rounded by the same circumstances now as we were <lb/>
    then. Yet we are told that those who had before <lb/>
    expressed their opinion to be that no circumstances <lb/>
    would justify Union with Canada, are now most <lb/>
anxious that very Union should be accomplished <lb/>
It was said, but he (Mr. T.) did not know whether <lb/>
    it was true or not, that the Government feel they <lb/>
    are in such a position that they cannot retrieve <lb/>
    themselves. They are in such a condition <lb/>
    of governmental misery, that they cannot <lb/>
    retrieve their position, and rather than give <lb/>
    way, rather than permit toher men to seize <lb/>
the helm, they would abandon the country and <lb/>
let it drift into a Union with Canada, provided <lb/>
only, that they should drift with it, and have the <lb/>
iron chest still with them. Next session, that was <lb/>
the last session, they had another speech, and <lb/>
    it was remarkable that the politics of the two <lb/>
former sessions were dropped, and the third <lb/>
    policy was a policy of taxation. We were told <lb/>
that the country was in a very bad state, Agricul<lb break="no"/>ture had effected no good. Confederation was <lb/>
    senuted, and Taxation only remained—and cer<lb break="no"/>tainly taxes were piled on. It was said this was <lb/>
    really a policy, and that its object was to prove to <lb/>
    the country that it would not be worse off by going<lb/>
    into Confederaion. One objection made to confe<lb break="no"/>deration was that the Canadian Tariff was very <lb/> 
high, and the policy was to make the tariff of the <lb/>
country as high as that of Canada, and thus remove <lb/>
that objection, and, as it proved, hon. gentlemen <lb/>
    opposite swallowed the bait. Did it strike them <lb/>
    that though the Tariff of the country may be pretty <lb/>
    much as is the Canadian Tariff, if we should be <lb/>
    confederated it will be kept as its present rate, if <lb/>
    not made higher, and we will have lost all control <lb/> 
over it. It may be asked how can we lessen it <lb/>
now? It never appears to strike hon. gentlemen <lb/>
that the expenditure could be brought down a little. <lb/>
    When it was proposed to increase taxation, the <lb/>
hon. gentlemen on his (Mr. T's.) side of the House <lb/>
suggested a reduction of the expenditure instead, <lb/>
but they were not listened to. In their simplicity <lb/>
they thought that by reducing the expenditure they <lb/>
would be able to avoid increased taxation, and do <lb/>
many, things which would tend to advance the <lb/>
interests of the country and the comfort of the <lb/>
    people. They fancied that it would well to act <lb/>
    as honest individuals surrounded by financial diffi<lb break="no"/>culties would to do, that is to retrench and live in a <lb/>
    less luxurious and expensive stylem and thus by <lb/>
    making income and expenditure square, get rid of <lb/>
difficulties and be independent. This is the fourth <lb/>
session, and they had again the old policy of the <lb/>
    second session, and were asked to adopt Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, as that was the only thing which would im<lb break="no"/>prove the condition of the country. Of course they <lb/> 
would have that question before them bye and bye. <lb/>
He (Mr. T.) was of opinion, and he thought the <lb/>
    country was of the same, that the only thing they <lb/> 
required was retrenchment. The public believed <lb/>
that the expenses are excessive, and that some <lb/>
    £20,000 or £30,000 a year, might easily be saved, <lb/>
and applied for the public benefit. Men in office <lb/>
    say, such a saving would be worth nothing, that it <lb/>
    would not give sixpence all round, and what good <lb/>
    would that effect? Why it would give £100,<lb break="no"/>000 to £120,000 in four years, and in a small <lb/>
community like this, if such a sum were judiciously <lb/>
and properly expended, there need not be a poor <lb/>
    man in the country. The people were now in a <lb/>
    transition state, from the time in which the fisheries <lb/>
    were able to support them for the whole year round, <lb/>
    to the time when they do not give sufficient for their <lb/>
    support during the summer. If that £100,000 were <lb/>
    avaliable now, it would be sufficient to tide them <lb/>
over their difficulties, and establish them in a course <lb/>
of industry which would render them prosperous and <lb/>
    happy. He (Mr. T.) believed that this saving <lb/>
    might be accomplished, at all events it was worth <lb/>
    trying, and if it failed, if being judiciously applied it <lb/>
    did not tide the people over the difficulties if it did <lb/>
not help to aid the fishermen in the establishing agricul<lb break="no"/>tural pursuits to aid the fisheries, then let us have <lb/>
Confederation or anything else. Before you take a <lb/>
step which will plunge you into irretrievable Union, <lb/>
    try it. It is better than parting with your libery <lb/>
    your poverty, and possibly with your lives. It was <lb/>
    not because people were surrounded by poverty <lb/>
    that they should part with their liberties and rights.<lb/>
    and link themselves to another country which had <lb/>
no sympathy with them. No country was so dis<lb break="no"/>cordant as Canada, which was made up of so many <lb/>
antagonistic elements and races. He (Mr. T.) <lb/>
    said it would be wise to pasuse and try all feasible <lb/>
    things before surrendering themselves in that way. <lb/>
    The question just before the House was that of the <lb/>
    French Shore rights. He had heard it said by <lb/>
some one on the Government benches, that we had <lb/>
gained a great privilege. He could not see it in <lb/>
that light or that they were one bit better off. The <lb/>
treaties remained exactly as they were. How then <lb/>
    was is possible to say that they were better off or <lb/>
    had more privledges than before? No conclusion <lb/>
    had yet been come to, so things remained as they <lb/>
    were last year, and ever since the treaties were <lb/>
made. The Government blundered most tremend<lb break="no"/>ously when they refused licenses two years ago. <lb/>
The same treaties existed then as now. No final <lb/>
    determination had been arrived at by the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion. Who refused to licenses? The Government <lb/>
    did, because directed to do so by the Secretary of <lb/>
    State for the Colonies. But he need not have <lb/>
    directed them at all, for the treaties were there to <lb/>
refer to. When the Secretary said they could not <lb/>
grant the licences, why did not the Government say <lb/>
they intended to do so without infringing on the <lb/>
fishery rights of the French? They did not do so, <lb/>
    and so neglected their duty. Now, when his <lb/>
    Excellency went home and said so, the Secretary <lb/>
    replied, Oh you may do that of course; it was <lb/>
    never intended that you should not do as you <lb/>
    pleased with the land; and we have the Government <lb/> 
gloritying themselves on the fact that they have <lb/>
    repaired their own blunder. It was a great privi<lb break="no"/>lege to be allowed to search on the land, and be <lb/>
at the same time told you must not erect buildings <lb/>
    on the French Shore. Where was the service doing, <lb/>
or what was precisely due to the Governor? The <lb/>
    proposed amendment simply embodied that which <lb/>
    he (Mr. T.) had said. The treaties were the diffi<lb break="no"/>culty, and they were still in existence. He felt <lb/>
much plessure in supporting the amendament. <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>
        Mr. PROWSE.— The hon. member for St. John's <lb/>
        West had just given them a dissertation on the art <lb/>
        of Government, but had been very reticent on <lb/>
        
        <cb/>
        
        the political moves of the opposition. The para<lb break="no"/>graph before the chair related to the French Shore <lb/>
        question and to it the opposition proposed an amend<lb break="no"/>ment. Regarding the question, an important move <lb/>
        had been made last session, inaugurated by the hon. <lb/>
        and learned leader of the opposition, who prepared a <lb/>
        series of resolutions, moved the House into Commit<lb break="no"/>tee, and not only got his resolutions passed, but had <lb/>
        peitions to the Queen, the Lords and the Commons <lb/>
        prepared, written in the very best text on the finest <lb/>
        of parchment. Not content with all this the hon. <lb/>
        and learned gentlemen personally superintended <lb/>
        the preparation of the tin case to carry home these <lb/>
        important documents. As first presented the <lb/>
        resolutions were such as it would not be cred<lb break="no"/>itable to the House to permit to be seen out<lb break="no"/>side. But all lent a hand, and they were licked <lb/>
        into shape, and yet all the credit og the whole <lb/>
        affair, tin box and all, devolved on the hon. and <lb/>
        learned mover. The amendment now proposed <lb/>
        was a natural addendum to the resolutions of <lb/>
        last sesstion. Other men, Governments, and <lb/>
        Legislatures had tried their hand at the affair, <lb/>
        but had not advanced it one bit; but when the <lb/>
        hon. and learned gentlemen took it up of <lb/>
        course, it was to be settled right off. Of course, <lb/>
        then, it was quite natural there should be a wall <lb/>
        of lamentation when, after all this exertion, the <lb/>
        result was nothing at all. It reminded him <lb/>
        (Mr. P.) of the question but by Mr. Jefferson <lb/>
        Brush to Martin Chuzzlewit, as to which of his <lb/>
        articles produced the greatest sensation in the <lb/>
        Court of St. James's. So with the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen opposite, they were quite surprised that <lb/>
        their great resolutions produced no effect. He <lb/>
        (Mr. P.) wanted to know who wrote that <lb/>
        amendment. It could not be the hon. member <lb/>
        for Ferryland, for he would make it shorter <lb/>
        and more succinct. The British Government <lb/>
        not only take no notice of the tin box resolu<lb break="no"/>tions and petitions, but they dare to approve of <lb/>
        Lord Carnarvon's policy. Why, it was a <hi rendition="simple:italic">casis <lb/>
            bclli</hi>, and if he (Mr. P.) were in opposition; he <lb/>
        would be for annexation after that. It was a 
        pity such a grand move should turn out a <hi rendition="simple:italic">fiasco</hi>. <lb/>
        There was another great movement yet to be <lb/>
        made. It had been two nights hatching, and <lb/>
        though they tried to shroud it in mystery, they <lb/>
        could not keep it quite, but let it out. He could <lb/>
        not then go into the question of what that move<lb break="no"/>ment wa to be. One thing struck him (Mr. P.) <lb/>
        after listening to the long speeches of hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers opposite. It was, what an uncommonly good <lb/>
        Government we have, when gentlemen blessed <lb/>
        with such lungs can find nothing so say against <lb/>
        it. Seed potatoes had been the stock subject of <lb/>
        the hon. and learned member for Harbor Main, <lb/>
        but he had changed his tastics to suit those of the <lb/>
        new leader, who did not approve of the problama<lb break="no"/>tion. That proclamation had produced, and <lb/>
        would produce, good results, and the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment intended carrying it out to its final end. If <lb/>
        hon. gentlemen opposite had the good of the <lb/>
        country at heart, they would return to their for<lb break="no"/>mer straightforward course respecting the pro<lb break="no"/>lamation.
    </p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName>.— No doubt that was a grand <lb/>
        display of elocution and statesman like abil<lb break="no"/>ity to which they had just listened from Daniel <lb/>
        Woodley Prowse, the wodden-headed represen<lb break="no"/>tative of the wooden-headed constituency of <lb/>
        Burego and LaPoile. Goodness help the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment when he was thier best man. It was <lb/>
        laughable in the extreme to hear him talk of the <lb/>
        hon. and learned member for Harbor Main, Mr. <lb/>
        Hogsett, a man who enjoyed the confidence of <lb/>
        the public of the country North, Southm East 
        and West. He (Mr. R.) regretted that, whilst <lb/>
        the hon. and learned member, Mr. Hogsett, <lb/>
        was packing up these tin cases, he did not pack <lb/>
        up the hon. and learned member for Burgee <lb/>
        and LaPoile in them. If he had been thus <lb/>
        packed off it would have rid the House of a <lb/>
        great nuisance. As for the amendment, he <lb/>
        (Mr. R.) held the same opinion as did his col<lb break="no"/>league, that the matter stood in the same posi<lb break="no"/>tion as it did before the resolutions and address<lb break="no"/>es were sent home. They had been told that <lb/>
        applicants for grants had recieved them, and <lb/>
        were prepared to go to work under the condi<lb break="no"/>tions contained in these grants. To his (Mr. <lb/>
        R's) mind they had no security, there was noth<lb break="no"/>ing before them to conclude that the matter <lb/>
        was so satisfactorily settled as to ally all anx<lb break="no"/>iety on the part of those who had discovered <lb/>
        minerals on that part of the island.— <lb/>
        They were told that a great deal had been <lb/>
        accomplished, and in the same breath that the <lb/>
        matter was still under discussion. The subject <lb/>
        was now recieveing the attention of Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's Government, and whilst the policy of <lb/>
        Lord Carnarvon is to be upheld, licenses to <lb/>
        search are to be issued. He (Mr. R.) contended <lb/>
        that a grant to work mines could be of no value <lb/>
        without a right to the use of the strand. A few <lb/>
        years ago private individuals in the course of <lb/>
        their explorations dsicovered valuable marbles <lb/>
        and other things. They then went to England <lb/>
        to endeavor to induce capitalists in invest. The <lb/>
        first enquiry made was also their title, and <lb/>
        although they were fully satisfied of the great <lb/>
        value of the minerals dsicovered, yet there being <lb/>
        no secure title, the capitalists refused to invest. <lb/>
        The question in fact remained as it was two <lb/>
        years ago. For the sake of argument, let us <lb/>
        assume that a grant has been issued. He to <lb/>
        whome the grant was made discovered minerals, <lb/>
        he commences operations, develops a valuable <lb/>
        mine, and has a number of people employed,
        he requires means of shipment, and has to bring <lb/>
        his minerals three or four mines to the strand, <lb/>
        when arrived there some Frenchmen comes and <lb/>
        says you are interfering with my fishery rights, <lb/>
        and although that may be said merely for the <lb/>
        sake of annoyance, he has to remove to one <lb/>
        side or the other; and no sooner is he <lb/>
        settled in the place to which he remo<lb break="no"/>ved than another Frenchman comes and <lb/>
        again says that he is interfering. <lb/>
        Of what use, then, were these licenses, when any <lb/>
        single fisherman might object to any erection being <lb/>
        made? We are aware that we, of ourselves, can do <lb/>
        nothing, that the Imperial Government would <lb/>
        never quarrel with France for us, and that if we <lb/>
        were confederated the voice of four millions of <lb/>
        
        <cb/>
        
        people would not effect what we cannot. Any one <lb/>
        who read the debates upon this question in the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Parliament must be struck with the entire <lb/>
        ignorance of the subject evinced by those who took <lb/>
        a part in that debate. We actually found a Minister <lb/>
        of the Crown saying that there should be mutual <lb/>
        concessions, that we should concede to the French <lb/>
        the right of fishing all along our coast. Did not <lb/>
        that show the Imperial authorities know nothing <lb/>
        at all about the matter? He considered that it <lb/>
        was a first subject of complaint that when we <lb/>
        sent petitions to the Imperial Government, we <lb/>
        should recieve no reply—He knew that it was <lb/>
        the usual course to send a reply in such cases; <lb/>
        and upon a matter of such vital importance be <lb/>
        thought it was right for us to express our views <lb/>
        as contained in the amendment. <lb/>
    </p>
    
    <p>
        The original motion was then put and carreid <lb/>
        on a division; <lb/>
    </p>
    
    <p>
        The Committee then rose and reported <lb/>
        progress. To sit again on Thursday. <lb/>
    </p>
    
    <p>
        The House adjourned till Thursday at 3 o'clocl.<lb/>
    </p>


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-30, Commented out below because it was easier to transcibe the text rather than reconstruct this -->

<!--<p>º <lb break="no"/>opposition. The para- people would not effect what "we Cannot. An <lb/>
graph before the chair related to the French Shore whº reºd the debates upon this question in the I. <lb/>
question and tº it the opposition proposed an amend:; perial Parliament must be strick with thi.". <lb/>
years ago, and every hon. member was aware of mant. Regarding the question, an impºrtant move Antire <lb/>
had heen made last session, inaugurated by the hon. a part in that debut... we actuily found a Mini <lb/>
glad into, the address, which it, was afterwards and learned leader of the opposition, who prepared a of the Crown saying that there should be º ſ <lb/></p> 

<p>petiti r s to the Qieen, the Lords an i the Commons <lb/>
this House that they had intended to affirm any prepared, writte in the very best text on the finest at all about the ºtter?"ife considered that ". . <lb/>
- content with all this tº hon was a first subject of 'sºlº."º." <lb/>
and learned, gentleman personally superintended sent, petitions to the Imperial Government wº <lb/>
then could so change their minds without any reason, the preparation of the tin case to carry home these should receive no reply -\-He knew that..." we <lb/>
As first presented the the usual course to senå a reply in º <lb/>
guided by the same iºnºwº we, ºre | resolutions were such as it woulf aot be cred- and upon, a matter of such vići impº. . º <lb/>
then. ..". are told . *. *...*.*.* itable to the House to primit to be seen ou <lb break="no"/>expressed their opinion to be that po circumstances - - - <lb break="no"/>. justify #. with Canada, are now most side. But all lent a hand, and they wºre lickad <lb/>
into shape, and yet all the credit of the whole | on . division: <lb/>
affair, tin box and all, devolved on the hon. and The Committee <lb/>
it was true or not, that the Government teel they learned mover. The amendment now proposed <lb/>
are in such a position that they cannot retr eve was a natural adden fun to the resolutions of Tue <lb/>
themselv's. They are in such a condition last session. Other men, Govern nents, and <lb/>
jº...": *... "...m. *: Legislatures had tried their h and at the affair, <lb/>
way, rather than permit other men to #. but had not advanced it one bit; but when the <lb break="no"/>hon. and learned gentleman took it up of Journment. <lb/>
course, it was to be settled right off. Of course, <lb/>
then, it was quite natural there should be a wall; itself into Committee of the Whole, on the furth <lb/>
of lamentation when, after all this exertion, tha: cºideration of the Address in reply tº: <lb/>
result w is uothing at all. <lb/>
it was remarkable that the policies of the two (Mr. P.) of the ques in put by <lb/>
Brush to Martin Chuzzlewit, as to which of his <lb/>
policy was a policy of taxation. We were told articles produced the greatest sensation in the time has nºw jeº... .", take action on th <lb/>
- So with the hon. gen- great question of Confederation; and we can ... <lb/>
tlemen opposite, they were quite surprised that | jour Excellency that we shall' gºve oil. . <lb/>
their great resolations produced uo effect. He <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>tainly taxes were piled on. It was said this was (Mr. P ) wanted to know who wrote that <lb/></p> 

<p>.# a policy. .. that its object was to prove to §. It coull not be the hon. member ..".ay. ..";" serve the interest, of <lb/>
the country that it would nº be worse ºff by going for Ferryland, for he would make it shorter the i.:*.* º º: of <lb/>
- - The British Government acceptable to all ci ove. <lb/>
deration was that the Canadian Tariff was very a ot only take no notice of the tin box resolu- i. to the ... "...º. ...: <lb/>
tion; and petitions, but they dare to approve of fia; approval and ratification of Her Mij. <lb/>
; Carnarvon's policy. <lb break="no"/>opposite swallowed the bait. Did it strike them | belli, and if he (Mr. P.) were in opposition; he <lb/></p> 

<p>; though the Tariff of the country º be pretty woull be for auuex . after º it was".!." .." . ºny.#... It was very desirabi, <lb/>
much as is the Qaºhaº, Tariff if we shºuld be | pity, such a grand wove sheuld turn out a fiasco. He did ..". i. #. .*.*. <lb/>
confederated it ſwill be *; as its *...*. rate,: There w is another great move.neat yet to be not think it ºis well to say . #".'. º". <lb/>
not made higher, and * will have ºf all, coºl made. It had tº ..., nights hatching, and the time has arrived, it must haveºlje. . . <lb/>
though they tried to shroud it in mystery, they thingprecedent to the fact that it was stated thataction <lb/>
could not keep it quite, but let it out. <lb/></p> 

<p>When it was proposed to increase taxation, the not then go into the question of what that move- <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>hon. º º: (Mr. T's.) side of the House ment .#. b+. §. thing struck him (Mr. P.) . ...'... º º understood ths <lb/>
suggested a reductiºn of , the expenditure instead, after listening to the loug speeches of hou. mem- no time ºil. *...". ...'. General, <lb/>
but they were not listened to. º their ...; bºrs opposite. It was, what au uncommonly good matter was, in the fir. ..". ... the <lb/>
tney, though that by dºing the expºnditure hºy Gover. wº have, when gentlemen blessed | people, who were tº be asked if they ...; <lb/>
with such lungs can find aothing so say against <lb break="no"/>it. Seed potatoes had been the stock subject of ºt, or in any way beyond that ºn. <lb/></p> 

<p>Wuy, it was a casus <lb/></p> 

<p>eople. Tuey fancied that it would be well to act the hon. and learned member tor Harbor Main <lb break="no"/>. *:::: individuals surrounded by financial diffi- but he had changed his tactics to suit those of th. i. .."; '. *...othing, and led people tº <lb/>
pºliº would to dº thº...ºneh and ſº in a new leader,who did not approve of the proclama- canvassed speculati i. * spoken of and <lb/>
less luxurious and expensive style, and thus, by tion. That proclamation had producei, and adopted i peculatively. this section be <lb/>
making income and expenditure square, get rid of ld prod y *dopted, it would, it appeared to him, assen <lb/>
would produce, good results, and the Govern- that which was not true. The elections were <lb/>
ment intended carrying it out to its final end. If *Ppreaching, and so it might be said that th; <lb/>
second session, and were asked to adopt Confedera. hou. gentlem in opposite had the good of the time had cºme when tue pe, le should be asked <lb/>
tion, as that was the ºnly thing which would ims | country at heart, they would return to their for- if they approved of the . le. At: <lb/>
provº the condition of the country. Of course they mer straightfoward course res? cling the pros the House could me: ... ...i. .º <lb/></p> 

<p>country was of the same, that the only thing they .* Bºoºº-No doubt that was a grand the pººl, i. thought that would be the proper <lb/>
- display of elocution , and statesman like abil- way to act, or a least that it ...".i <lb/>
ºy to which they had just lis ened from Dunlel accordance with the general uniºn. <lb/>
- Woodly Prowse, the wooden-healed represen- the hººd i.e., Attoraey General's prºmº <lb/>
Men in office |ºtive of the woolen-headed constituency of If this Paragraph be passed, it will b. º '. <lb/>
*...* a saving would he wºrºh ºthing, that if | Burgeo and LaPoile. Goodness help the Gov. me. for the considerº, uf the . <lb/>
º::::::::: *Wº:*::::::::::...º.º.º.º. º...". <lb/>
000 to £120,000 in %. years, and in a small laughabl; in the extrem, to hear hiin talk of the vions aſſi,mation of the principle. The wording <lb/>
hon. and learned member for Harbor Main, Mr. of the paragraph was not cle ir, and if ºbj <lb/>
Hogsett, a man who enjoyed the confidence of intendeſ tº Hºse should affirm the prin. <lb/>
man in the country. The people were now in a the public of the country North, South, East ºple, it ought to b, so expressed in c. º d <lb/>
transition state, from the time in which the fiſheries and Wast. He (Mr. R.) regretted that, wallst tlefillite language, Two years a. ºt §. 8th <lb/>
were able to support then for the wuole year round, the hou. and learned mºmber, Mr. Hogsett, mout attempted by a . infº. '... <lb/>
. .."..." . do not º i. º ... was packing up these tin cases, be did not pack | film ºil. principle, but the Hºuse retus . º <lb/>
support during the summer. If that *"... up the hon. and learned member for Burgee j after some consideration and difficulty, . <lb/>
If. he had been tius | hon. goutlemen opposi.e., the eſ use '... win. <lb/>
packed of it would have rid the House of a drawn and one of a doubtlulcharacter subsitual <lb/>
*Pºº. He (Mº...T.), believed that this saviug | #º ºuisanº-, As for the amendment, he After that it was said the Substituteu cl º <lb/>
might be accºmplished, as all events, it was worth (Mr. R.) held the same opiniod as did his col- atā, med the principle, and the present J. . <lb/>
"...º.º.º.º.º.º. league, that the matter stood in the same post-| Hºra, "whººp. # ...; <lb/>
did not tide the people over their difficulties, if it did |tion as it did before the resolutions and address- - irbor Gracur <lb/>
not help to aid the fishermen in establishing agricul- es. . sent home. They had been told that ºne did nºt intend to affirm the principle ºf aff, <lb/>
applicants for grants had received them, and le? It w - is tr <lb break="no"/>were perpared to go to work under the condi- i. be ſº."...","...º.º. # <lb/>
tº it. It is better than parting with your liberty, ºn contained in these grants. To his (Mr. words which mºner say sye, ſoº. ...; <lb/>
* Prºperty, and possibly with your lives. it was R's) mind they had no security, there was noth. implies an affirmation of the principi.". <lb/>
... .. *. by *. ing before them to conclude that the matter <lb/>
a u arº Wri their inderties and ti - - igſ. - * <lb/>
and #. to another country which had was so satisfactorily settled as to allay all. aux- first agi? None hitherto, but now we concur tº: <lb/>
iety on the part of those who had discovered it is time to take a.º."."fi. step should <lb/>
on that part of <lb/>
They . º that a great deal had been <lb/>
said it would be wise to pause and try all feasible accomplished, and in the same breath that the - -\-\- - - <lb break="no"/>things before jº. themselves in that way. matter was still under discussion. The subject i.",...;i...". º <lb/>
The question just before the House was that of the was now receiving the atteution of Her Ma. in so deceitul a manne; in it it a. nº. . iiis, <lb/>
French Snoré rights. He had heard it said by jesty's Government, and whilst the policy of (Mr. T's) approval, and he would be Very surry to <lb/>
Lord Carnarvon is to be upheld, licenses to <lb/>
search are to be issued. He (Mr. R.) contended <lb/>
that a grant to work mines could be of no value through, They are now asked to wheel aboutliko, <lb/>
was it possible to say that they were better off or without a right to the use of the strand. A few jiu grows,and say to-day what they roſasºit. <lb/>
. .. privileges than .. No †. years ago private individuals in the course of <lb/>
had yet been come, to, so things," as they their explorations discovered valuable marbles.: -. <lb break="no"/>were last, year, and . .; streatles . and other things. They then went to England #. º; ...". . <lb/>
made. The Government, biºlºred, mºst tremend" | to endeavor jug. capitalists in invest. The he (Air. T.) did not affirm ºe priº †. <lb/>
first enquiry made was as to their tile, and Froin all he had reflected upon it and ºn of it, he <lb/></p> 

<p>although they were fully satisfied of the great -<lb break="maybe"/>tion. Who refused the licenses? Tae-Government value of the minerals discovered, yet there j::::::::::::::"; ...; <lb/>
|; because directed to do so by the Becretary of no secure title, the capitalists refused to invest. aeant, and under ...'...". º <lb/>
State lor, the Colºnies. ...But lººd nº. have | The question in fact remained as it was two must go ºn is ºne ºn"...". plage, it <lb/>
directed them, at all, for the treaties were.there to years ago. For the sake of argument, ſet us -<lb break="maybe"/>assum that a graut has been issued. He to - • tº - -<lb break="maybe"/>whome the grant was made discovers minerals, §."..":... . *...*, #. <lb/>
he commences opercuous, developes a valuable principle of that Union such as they could approve. <lb/>
and so neglected their duty. Now, when his mine, and has a number of peºple employel, ut? He <lb/>
Excellency went home and said sº, the Secretary he requires ineans of shipment, and has to bring <lb/>
replied,. On you may do that ºf course; it was his minerals three or four miles to the stranurſ already united, and he (M.T. idº. et <lb/>
ºver, intºniº, º żº ... ... } when arrived there some Frenchman º' . principiº, and (; º;º: <lb/>
gº with tºº lºº.º.º. [... you are interfering with my fishery rights, tage, such a Union could be to the country. It <lb/>
and alºnough that may be said merely for the <lb/>
Iege to be allowed to search on the land, and be | Bake of annoyance, he has to remove to one was the ineauing of this Comfederation? Remove <lb/>
the other; and no sooner is he ſtºire". gliter, and what was iſ nºted, <lb/></p> 

<p>Frenchman comes and to Cauadal absolute power and control over our <lb/></p> 

<p>- + firls <lb/>
gº ºi nº. Herº ||........"... º. Tºjº. <lb/>
g - ght object, ...".":# in it all the glitzering colors you choose, but tº <lb/>
ºfur St , made? We are aware that we, of ourselves, can do | . . its reality, and that is wu.it it uneans. He <lb/>
Mº, Pºwse-The hoº: ºº sº...ohn's nothing, that the Imperial Government would ...; liberties because atter the jnº estao. <lb/>
West had just given them a dissertation on the art never quarrel with France for us, and nºt if we t <lb break="no"/>of Government, but had. been vary reticent on 1 were confederated the voic, bf fºur miſſiºns of <lb/></p> 

<p>ignoranse of the subject evinued by thos whº to k <lb/></p> 

<p>that show the Imperial airhorities knew nothing <lb/></p> 

<p>thought it was right for us to express our ºf <lb/>
as ºntained in the aimandment. widºs <lb/></p> 

<p>The original motion was then put and carried <lb/>
*A <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>then rose and <lb/>
prºgress. To sit again on Thursday. reported <lb/>
House adjourned till Thursday at 3 o'clock, <lb/></p> 

<p>a­ <lb/></p> -->


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-30, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

<!--<p>Thunspar, Feb. ii. <lb/>
The House met at 8 o'clock, pºin. i.". <lb/></p> 

<p>On motion of Mr. Goddsx, the House resolved <lb/></p> 

<p>to the <lb/>
of His Excellency, Mr. Knight in the ..." <lb/></p> 

<p>Qu motion of Mr. Goddes, the fifth sect; <lb/>
address was read as follows * section of the <lb/>
"We fully concur with your Excellency that the <lb/></p> 

<p>It reminded him <lb/>
Mr. Jefferson <lb/></p> 

<p>ºtentiºn to the consideration of our Udion wit, the <lb/>
Dominion of Canada, on such fair and equitable <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr., TALBor did not understand the sº <lb/>
which had just been read, and thought it was j <lb/></p> 

<p>H ld would be taken at some future time, which <lb/>
© Cou had now arrived. But he (Mr.T. ) was . ... <lb/></p> 

<p>this, Union. It had not been pit befºre tº people <lb/></p> 

<p>view which was given by caadidates, who in fact <lb/></p> 

<p>ous,and these conditions could be again referred to <lb/></p> 

<p>made a great row about it, and said tº º <lb/></p> 

<p>Was the House now asked to affirm that princi­ <lb/></p> 

<p>: Wils an advance towards its affirmation. Twº <lb/>
*** it, is titue to take action. What wº; tho' <lb/></p> 

<p>the islaud.- be to ultirin the principle, au. I until that be done. <lb/>
details and conditious cannot be considered. Wuy <lb/>
agt say distinctly that the time had come for the <lb/></p> 

<p>vote for it. There is a loophole left here for the <lb/>
supporters of the Governmºut, by which they may <lb/>
be caught by the uéck, and bound, as they pass' <lb/></p> 

<p>twº yea; ago. That was not treating then pro<lb break="no"/>perly. Their uttention shoulu be directed to the <lb/></p> 

<p>was deliºúly oppºsed to the principle, and diſ <lb/></p> 

<p>it were still in elabryo, aud, they did not see its <lb/>
working, tuere might be a doubt as to whether the <lb/></p> 

<p>(Mr. T.) said it was not. No unatter what. <lb/>
terms you propose, they cannot deviate troum the <lb/>
esseutial principles on, which, the ºolonies are: <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>would not make us better off, because from the: <lb/>
nature of things, it was itnpºssible it could. What. <lb/></p> 

<p>which he remo- ineaning? Just tiis, that by our own act wº giyê. <lb/></p> 

<p>destinies, øyer our liberties, auu propertiés and <lb/></p> 

<p>is interfering. -<lb break="maybe"/>fering. our lives. that is tie exact meaning of Contel­ <lb/></p> 

<p>lished, they would have no liberty to rulé thein<lb break="no"/>selves, and could, make no laws without tue *. <lb/></p> 

<p>*: <lb/>
* <lb/></p> 

<p>- irrºr *—hº <lb/></p> 

<p>tion of the Dominion; prºper: <lb/>
#Dominion Parliament cnuld tax <lb/>
and cºternally, to any amount they <lb/>
jause the same power could. <lb/>
*hen they pleased &amp;nd use their liv <lb/>
purposes, . Such was Confederatio <lb/>
iſ very nice thing tº congºttulate <lb/></p> 

<p>but he (M did not think the <lb/>
coutent with it. Was it wise or at <lb/>
up their right to legislate for them <lb/>
their property at the merey of a fo <lb/>
tax as they pleased, to submit tilº <lb/>
also, so that they might seize and <lb/>
from 18 to 60 years Ól age, to repº <lb/>
made upon them by the great Repu <lb/>
the dust will be raised and the pictu <lb/>
they...would be told that rhoºgh wr <lb/>
in ight be Confederation, per pse, <lb/>
derive advartages troºm it whic. <lb/></p> 

<p>balance all this; that new channe <lb/>
be opened, and the country raised <lb/>
civilization, that agriculture will <lb/>
and bloom in all the luxuriance it <lb/></p> 

<p>other Provinces, . He (Mr. T.) c. <lb/>
stand how Confederation was go <lb/>
this, and did not believe that the <lb/>
tkemselves really understo \d it <lb/>
Canada bind herselt on your parchit <lb/>
to promote our 30.htmei'ee, agricult <lb/>
factures? No, she could not do it, <lb/>
the law is already passed; Confed <lb/>
Hished, and she cannot give more <lb/>
already arranged amongst themse <lb/>
argu,ments advanced to prove the <lb/>
confederation had reference to Comi <lb/>
aud arrange.ments, and had nothil <lb/>
with the political aspect of the ques <lb/>
were to be benefited by an equal tar <lb/>
done by some Gouamercial ariange <lb/>
miues were tº be worked, it wou! <lb/>
capitalists and not by politicians; a. <lb/>
work them; not because we wer. <lb/>
but because they would be profitat, <lb/>
said that if we confederate we will <lb/>
flour, pork, &amp;c., tree of duty, Tbat <lb/>
ble argument. It certainly was s <lb/>
all these arguments the political <lb/>
Inixed up with comułercial matti <lb/>
question was blinked, so as to thr <lb/>
*yes of the people. These articles <lb/>
ºuty free by cominercial regulations. <lb/>
federation. Such was the ease betort", <lb/>
ht net to be so again? He (ºir. 'I <lb/>
show the knack by which the suppor <lb/>
eration attempted to blindiold the <lb/>
keep the political question in the bac <lb/>
drag forward a very different matter, <lb/>
duestion of commercial arrangements <lb/>
very strarge to nine, but perhaps it <lb/>
was innocent and not up to the tricke <lb/>
tral wisdom which sometimes maz <lb/>
livuse had in itself the power to <lb/>
pork, flour, &amp;c., free of dutv, but it <lb/>
...the country was in debt, and could <lb/>
He (Mr. T.) replied, let us retrench <lb/>
expenditure, and so be able to es: <lb/>
duties. Another argument was that wi <lb/>
ration we cannºt have reciprocity, W <lb/>
is ree procity? It simply mesn's th <lb/>
emption from duties of articles the <lb/>
sluce, of particular countries, on <lb/>
Was it not in our power to make suc <lb/>
MTo be sure it was Tuen what had <lb/>
to do with reciprocity? It was a se <lb/>
which shºuld be troited ot, its ow: <lb/>
Miot mixed up with the question of ( <lb/>
Politically, Coutederation inevit only <lb/>
should have the absolu.e control of t <lb/>
property and the lives of the people <lb/>
tie chałlenged a deliiai of th it. It <lb/>
what Coutederation inelant, then he <lb/>
of its meaning. He (Mr. T.) could <lb/>
though. W. <lb/></p> 

<p>w inust, it beenlet,have <lb/>
without it we cau't get on at all. W <lb/>
a cripp led state that willess 50.me <lb/>
coues, wild in thercy picks tº up, we <lb/>
we cutulut exist Uy uurselvu". B <lb/>
inent upsets the other arguinent, <lb/>
show that the great good of Guilfº <lb/>
be to save us fruiu uturselves. It liev <lb/>
occur to hon, geiſtleiuen \llitt aliy <lb/>
governing thu country cºulu be dev <lb/>
which they their seives adopted, aud <lb/>
1or the past four years, which W <lb/>
great many offices, and fill them <lb/>
many people, audi Inake large sular <lb/>
and tueu, lu order to get these 8 <lb/>
heavy taxes on bread, iluur, pork, &amp; <lb/>
because tust dues uot succeed, we mud <lb/>
as the country calliot be ruled by it <lb/>
But these hon, gentlemen go on the wi <lb/>
nation and flash and thundcr thre <lb/>
above. They can't walk upon terra fi <lb/>
mon people. If we ourselves by a lo <lb/>
Government cannot make the people <lb/>
surely no Government on this side the <lb/>
do it. When the ſimperial Governtnut <lb/>
affairs of the colony we well remel <lb/>
used to blunder. The general cry wº <lb/>
understand us. With self Governmei: <lb/>
we possessed everything negessary to <lb/>
perous. There are now some gentlem <lb/>
we ought to have another kick up <lb/>
selves under some other Smpire. <lb/>
history of this Confederation I I he <lb/>
were ſighting and squabbling among t <lb/>
in order to keep then quiet they: <lb/>
then was the first of Confederation. <lb/>
considerable Annexation party and th: <lb/>
shindy, not to says rabellion, which, <lb/>
quickly quelled. In the United Parli <lb/>
were equally divided and innumerable <lb/>
curred. That Confederation failed an <lb/>
years ago the leading men of both par <lb/>
the happy thought that if they could 4 <lb/>
Provinces to join them that they might <lb/>
make laws for them, they themselves <lb/>
very well. But all this time they neve <lb/>
Newfoundland could be benefitted by <lb/>
At last they united at Quebec, and the <lb/>
General, the present Sir Hugh W. Ho: <lb/>
to be travelling in Canada at the time, <lb/>
perhaps we would send up a couple on <lb/>
what they were doing there. The Cai <lb/>
men eaid they never thought of Newfou <lb/>
but, they would be very happy to r <lb/>
And so, without the appointment of ti <lb/>
the bon. Attorney General and the hon. <lb/>
sent up merely to watch the proceedin, <lb/>
vention. He (Mr. T.) would not go <lb/>
ceedings of that Convention, he would <lb/>
champaign bottles, and the various ſet <lb/>
they were invited, but the conciasion <lb/>
was that his two hon, friends were st <lb/>
by these elever Canadians and others ti <lb/>
the document which was the basis of C. <lb/>
Well, these hon, gentlemen came bal <lb/>
that they had done something of whic <lb/>
reason to be proud, There was no flo <lb/>
pets on their return, no guns fired, no <lb/>
awaiting them to exhibit these two wo <lb/>
aimiring gaze of their countrymen <lb/></p> 

<p>eame to this house and they end <lb/>
over to their views every man of jul <lb/>
country: They represented the thing <lb/>
eolours, they É. that it was <lb/></p> 

<p>thing for the country which could be a <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>