<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-13" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
    <title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-02-13">13 February 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-03-06"/>,
<date when="1865-03-09"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="3"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="3"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_3.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-03-09_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-03-09_Page_3.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-27">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="lyallg" when="2018-11-27">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_3"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_3.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-09_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-09_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-09_Page_3"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-09_Page_3.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_2.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER</fw>
<fw type="num">2</fw> <!-- GL, 2018-11-27, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day --> <!-- 

<p>: <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/>
f <lb/>
-<lb break="maybe"/><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>º: <lb/>
: <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>t <lb/></p> 

<p>ces had long and earnestly done; because it was always <lb/></p> 

<p>The new F o UN d LA N DE R <lb/></p> 

<p>- <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>explanation relieved the delegates from any suspicion of <lb/>
intentional neglect, but why should a matter of such <lb/>
grave importance be left open to doubt, or to the possi­ <lb/>
bility of injurious use of power P. Was this a positiºn <lb/>
to place before the country and ask its adhesion to *. It <lb/>
could never be assented to, until the amplest securities <lb/>
were given to guard us from the possibility of so unjust <lb/>
an imposition. The federal government proposes to <lb/>
raise a militia and naval service, and we are assured <lb/>
Newfoundlanders would be exempt from sharing the bur: <lb/>
then; but that argument had been very properly refuted <lb/>
by the hon gentie man (Mr. White) when he stated that <lb/>
when the necessity arose we should contribute our quota <lb/>
of mea and money to those services, and that if we enter <lb/>
the nationality it would be the duty of every man in the <lb/>
confederacy to come forward at the call of danger-and, <lb/>
more, that it was not likely any man capable of hearing <lb/>
arms would fail to aid in the defence of his country and <lb/>
his flag in the hour of need. There was one very serious <lb/>
objection to the project, and it applied equally to the <lb/>
other colonies as well as to ourselves;-it was that there <lb/>
is only a fixed and insufficient annual amount offered to <lb/>
them to carry on their local affairs. No matter how <lb/>
much our population increased,—no matter how rich our <lb/>
resources might prove to be, or how extensive our con­ <lb/>
tribution to the general exchequer, wa shall receive not <lb/>
one farthing beyond that sum estimated upon our pre­ <lb/>
sent population, -this was a most unsound and unfair <lb/>
principle. It is to be supposed that in the natural <lb/>
course of time and events our population will largely <lb/>
increase, our revenue perhaps become doubled, and no <lb/>
benefit accrue to us therefrom. It will be applied to <lb/>
railroads, to canals, to other public improvements in <lb/>
which the other colonies would participate, but not <lb/>
Newfoundland. What was to prevent an increased <lb/>
allowance per head with every decennial census * He <lb/>
considered the proposition, as it now stood, absurd and <lb/>
unsound, as a political principle at least, as much so as <lb/>
the idea of a maximum rate of taxation. There was a <lb/>
limit very soon arrived at, to the benefits we should derive <lb/>
from federal public works under favourable aspects, and all <lb/>
in which we could participate; once accomplished any in­ <lb/>
crease of our contribution to the federal exchequer must be <lb/>
for substantially Canadian objects. Cur fisheries, the chief <lb/>
source of our trade, are to be ceded to the control and <lb/>
management of the federal government, whose juris­ <lb/>
diction in everything would overide ours, and make it of <lb/>
course subservient to its policy, interests, or necessities. <lb/>
All these potent objections applied to the union of this <lb/>
colony with Canada, as she desires it, and it was his con­ <lb/>
viction that it should be forcibly remonstrated against to <lb/>
the imperial government:—lest pending our decision upon <lb/>
the question any action should be inadvertently taken <lb/>
by the British Parliament, to bind us to an agreement <lb/>
involving disastrous consequences. The question never <lb/>
had been a topic of serious public consideraton in the <lb/>
colony until very recently;-our public men had not <lb/>
made it their study as the statesmen of the other Provin­ <lb/></p> 

<p>generally believed that from any union of the Provinces, <lb/>
Newfoundland on account of her isolated position and <lb/>
different interests would be excluded, -that in fact she <lb/>
did not desire or require it. Canada has exhibited an <lb/>
almost indecent and suspicious hurry in the matter. We <lb/>
find that already a delegation has been sent to the Impe­ <lb/>
rial government to prepare it for the promotion of her <lb/>
views, fearing it would become the salutary action of ma­ <lb/>
turer consideration on the part of the other provinces. <lb/>
It would seem by the eclºt and favour in which those <lb/>
delegates were received by the British authorities, <lb/>
and by the tone of the English public journals, that they <lb/>
took it for granted that all the Colonies were satisfied, <lb/>
and favourable and anxious for the scheme; and it was <lb/>
not at all unlikely that our interests might be compro­ <lb/>
mised, either by compulsory acceptance or instant rejec­ <lb/>
tion did we not immediately express our objections. He <lb/>
regretted that he had detained the house so long at so <lb/>
late a period of the evening, but the importance of the <lb/>
question should be his justification. It will probably <lb/>
come under consideration at a future period, and perhaps <lb/>
this debate may tend to shorten any that will then take <lb/>
place, He had no objection to the petition, but he thought <lb/>
it might have been more expressive; and he must repeat <lb/>
his conviction, that no matter how often the country <lb/>
migh be appealed to, it would never consent to confeder. <lb/>
ation on the terms proposed. This was no novel view <lb/>
of his, such was his conviction months ago. He had <lb/>
expressed it publicly in another place, long before a <lb/>
a public or commercial meeting had been suggested, <lb/>
or the result of such a preceeding had been thought of, <lb/>
and he had discovered no good reason to induce a change <lb/>
in his opinions. <lb/>
(To be continued.) <lb/>
*-as-s <lb/></p> 

<p>HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY. <lb/></p> 

<p>THURspAY, FER. 9. <lb/>
The house met at three o'clock. <lb/>
Mr. KENT presented a petition from the Right Rev. <lb/>
IJr. Mullock, Roman Catholic Bishop of St. John's, <lb/>
which was received and read, setting forth that he had <lb/>
accidently learned that a Bill ſor the registration of <lb/>
births, marriages and deaths had been before the house <lb/>
and had passed a second reading, imposing duties and <lb/>
penalties on the Roman Catholic Clergy, who are in <lb/>
nowise officials of the Government, salaried or other­ <lb/>
wise; that while petitioner believed the principle of <lb/>
the bill to be a step in the way of civilisation, still he <lb/>
considered it unjust that, without notice to the parties <lb/>
concerned,penalties and duties should be imposed upon <lb/>
them, that petitioner and his clergy will willingly allow <lb/>
the government registrar, under certain limitations, <lb/>
access to the parochial registries of baptisms and mar­ <lb/>
riages, but respectfully decline to become the unpaid <lb/>
officials of the government, under penalties; and pray­ <lb/>
ing that the house would not pass the bill in its present <lb/>
form. <lb/>
Mr. KENT, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
table, said the petition had reference to the fifth, sixth, <lb/>
fifteenth and concluding sections of the bill. His Lord­ <lb/>
ship Dr Mullock and his clergy were not willing to be <lb/>
compelled by law to make to the Government, under <lb/>
penalties, the returns provided for by that bill. They <lb/>
were not officials of the Governinent, and if a law were <lb/>
passed compelling them to make returns as to the man­ <lb/>
ner in which they administered the rites of the Church <lb/>
of which they were ordained clergymen, they consid­ <lb/>
ered it would be tantamount to a penal enactment. IIe <lb/>
(Mr Kent) thought the hon leader of the Government <lb/>
should have been more cautious in drawing up the bill <lb/>
—he should have trusted for the success of such a mea-! <lb/>
sure more to moral influence than to any penal enact- | <lb/>
ment lie (Mr Kent) had looked over the Irish act <lb/>
for the registration of births, marriages and deaths, and <lb/>
he did not see that it contained a single penal enact­ <lb/>
ment, notwithstanding that there was an established | <lb/>
church in that country, whose clergy were more amen­ <lb/>
able to the Government than those of a Church having <lb/>
no connection with the state. He was perfectly satis­ <lb/>
fied the leader of the Government would take the <lb/>
matter into consideration, and so modify the provisions <lb/>
of the measure as to remove its objectionable features. <lb/>
The law should be so framed as not to excite the con­ <lb/>
scientious fear or alarm of any clergyman whatever. <lb/>
In Ireland, he ſound the registration was entirely car­ <lb/>
ried out by laymen. <lb/>
Mr. Talbot was satisfied the leader of the Govern­ <lb/>
ment would, in committee on that bili, meet the wishes <lb/>
of the Right Rey Bishop and his clergy. <lb/>
... Mr ResocF-That bill, in its present shape, would <lb/>
imposo onerous duties, under penalties, upon clergy­ <lb/></p> 

<p>men who received no stipend whatever from the Gov­ <lb/>
ernment. <lb break="no"/>Mr KAvANAGH hail great pleasure in stupporting <lb/>
the prayer of that petition, and trusted the leader of <lb/>
the Government would so modify the measure as to <lb/>
render it acceptable to all. <lb/>
Mr Casey was sure it never was the intention of the <lb/>
learned Attorney General to impose penalties on the <lb/>
Catholic clergy under that bill. The duties of the <lb/>
Catholic clergy were most arduous. They had scarcely <lb/>
any leisure; and to impose additional duties upon them <lb/>
would be highly improper. He was satisfied that, in <lb/>
committee, the hon leader of the Government would <lb/>
remove what was considered objectionable in the bill. <lb/>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/>
Mr Moore presented a petition from Thomas Dwyer <lb/>
and others, of Upper Island Cove, which was received <lb/>
and read, praying for a grant to complete a road in <lb/>
that locality. <lb break="no"/>Mr RENöur presented a petition from John White <lb/>
and others, of Petty Harbour, which was received and <lb/>
read, praying for a grant to deepen the gut there. <lb/>
Mr Resour, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
table, would heartily support its prayer. The petition­ <lb/>
ers were entitled to every consideration from the Gov­ <lb/>
ernment, and he trusted that matter would receive <lb/>
that consideration to which its importance, entitled it. <lb/>
Mr CAsex supported the prayer of the petition. <lb/>
When the wind blew from the North East the petition­ <lb/>
ers had very great difficulty in mooring their boats. If <lb/>
any money should be granted this session for break­ <lb/>
waters, he considered injustice would be done to the <lb/>
etitioners if their claim should not also be attended to. <lb/>
#. had not often asked anything from the Govern­ <lb/>
ment; they had supported themselves without asking <lb/>
for poor relief, except a few this year. <lb/>
Mr TALBot quite agreed with his hon colleagues <lb/>
that that was an important petition. These people were <lb/>
industrious, and suffered great inconvenience and loss <lb/>
from the want of proper shelter for their boats. IIe <lb/>
trusted that petition would not be overlooked. The <lb/>
people were entitled to consideration. <lb/>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/>
Mr E D SHEA gave notice that on to-morrow he <lb/>
would ask the hou'Acting Colonial Secretary to lay on <lb/>
the table a copy of the report of the Commander of <lb/>
H.M.S. Medea of the fisheries at Labrador. <lb/>
On motion of the hon ATToRNEY GENERAL, pur­ <lb/>
suant to order of the day, the house resolved itself into <lb/>
committee of the whole on the bill for the registration <lb/>
: births, marriages and deaths—Mr. Barron in the <lb/>
Chair. <lb/>
Hon. ATToRNEY GENERAL–The object of that bill <lb/>
was to provide information as to the gradual growth <lb/>
of population in this colony, and also to form a public <lb/>
record by which the rights of parties in matters of in­ <lb/>
heritance might be established. Registers of births, <lb/>
marriages and deaths were kept as a matter of record <lb/>
in almost all civilized countries, and it might be con­ <lb/>
sidered a reproach to us that hitherto we had no <lb/>
enactment for such public records being kept. Statis. <lb/>
tical information on that subject was also now consi­ <lb/>
dered a matter of great importance, and governments <lb/>
bestowed great a tention on the collection of such <lb/>
statistics, which enabled them to judge of the prºgress <lb/>
of population and the sanitary state of the people; and <lb/>
to some extent of their comfort and social condition. <lb/>
The present bill was an attempt, and he must admit, <lb/>
an imperfect attempt, to provide such a record. To <lb/>
rovide such a system of registrition as existed in the <lb/>
§. Kingdom might at present be too expensive. <lb/>
But an attempt ought to be made, and when that <lb/>
bill should have gone through committee, and they <lb/>
had experience of its working, its imperfections could <lb/>
be remedied by suosºq ent le: slation. The greatest <lb/>
difficulty he apprehended would be found in our po­ <lb/>
pulation being so scattered, so that there would be a <lb/>
difficulty in sendºng tie required inform stion to the <lb/>
proper utficer. He did not cons d-r that in the exist­ <lb/>
ing circuinstances of the colony any money could be <lb/>
sppropriated towards giving effect to that measure. <lb/>
IIe thought the Stipendiary Magistrates would be <lb/>
willing to act as Regis' rars; and where there were no <lb/>
Stipeudiary Magistrates the Governor in Council <lb/>
would appoint Registrars. When the sections of the <lb/>
bill objected to in the pet tion presented by the hon. <lb/>
member for St. John's East (Mr. Kent) came to be <lb/>
considered, the objections to them would be taken up, <lb/>
and he hoped the matter would be satisfactorily ar­ <lb/>
ranged. He concurred with the hon member that the <lb/>
co-operation of all was necessary to the proper working <lb/>
of the measure, and hoped that in a matter of so <lb/>
much importance to their own people, the aid of the <lb/>
Roman Catholic clergy would be readily given to <lb/>
carry out that registration efficiently. <lb/>
Mr. Kent, bad great pleasure in supporting the <lb/>
principle of the bill. It was as creditable to the hon. <lb/>
Attorney General as was the information and research <lb/>
which he had brought to-bear on the question. The <lb/>
increase of population was shown by the births, and <lb/>
the sanatory condition of the people by its rate of <lb/>
mortality. And these were matters upon which it was <lb/>
very necessary that we should be informed. Indeed <lb/>
statistical information of every description was highly <lb/>
desirable. He was surprised by recent information <lb/>
procured at the instance of one of the Judges of our <lb/>
Supreme Court, that 1500 sheep had been destroyed <lb/>
at Brigus and its vincinity by dogs in five years. Did <lb/>
not that fact show that it was necessary to remove the <lb/>
cause of this destruction P The same principle applied <lb/>
to this measure. Every one speaks of our healthy <lb/>
climate, but the idea was only a speculative one, for <lb/>
we had no statistical information as to the mortality. <lb/>
In the United Kingdom, every thing was accurately <lb/>
known, and the bills of mortality in London were <lb/>
regularly published once a week. He (Mr. Kent) <lb/>
thought that the proper persons to carry out the pro­ <lb/>
visions of this measure were the Stipendiary, Magis­ <lb/>
trates, and he trusted that us we progressed in mate­ <lb/>
rial prosperity, we might be able to allow them some <lb/>
small compensation for their services in the matter. <lb/>
lie could fancy that they might be very profitably <lb/>
employed in collecting all kinds of statistical informa­ <lb/>
tion, and especially with reference to agriculture. And <lb/>
they certainly ought not to object to perform this <lb/>
duty which would occupy but a small portion of their <lb/>
time. Our position was in many instances an ano­ <lb/>
maly. In the other colonies they cannot see any ne— <lb/>
cessity for salaried magistrates over the whole country <lb/>
as we had here. He was very glad to see that the <lb/>
hon the Attorney General saw the propriety of omit­ <lb/>
ting the two sections in this bill already referred to. <lb/>
He was certain when that hon gentleman evinced <lb/>
such a desire to propitiate the gºod wishes of hon <lb/>
members on this side of the house, that from them <lb/>
he would receive no factious or violent opposition in <lb/>
the public business. <lb/>
Mr. WHITEway had great pleasure, in supporting <lb/>
this bill. But he did not think that the outport ma­ <lb/>
gistrates should he saddled with these new daties <lb/>
without being in some way paid for their services. At <lb/>
present their salaries were hardly sufficient to keep <lb/>
them from starvation. It was very true that in some <lb/>
parts of the island they had very littie to do; but in <lb/>
other places to his (Mr. Whiteway's) own knowledge <lb/>
they had a great, amount of duty to perform, and <lb/>
their time was fully oxeupied. It should also be re­ <lb/>
memºered that these gentlemen were nºt unfiequently <lb/>
the Deputy Surveyors, and were often called away <lb/>
forty or fifty miles from their homes for the purpose <lb/></p> 

<p>be not to pass it all, as we had no guarantee that it <lb/></p> 

<p>of surveying land for which service they received but <lb/>
trifling remuneration. Last winter the Magistrate at <lb/></p> 

<p>Fogo was occupied for nearly two months on business <lb/>
apart from his office, occasioned by the number of <lb/>
wrecked sealers that had to seek shelter there. We <lb/>
could not find gentlemen in this country who could <lb/>
afford to work without remuneration, a fact of which <lb/>
we had sufficient evidence when we found three Con­ <lb/>
tingency Bills thrown out in the Legislative Council, <lb/>
becausehon gentlemen repressnting out higher classes <lb/>
refused to give two or three hours of their time, once <lb/>
or twice a week, to the service of the country, without <lb/>
remuneration. He was sorry to see this additional <lb/>
duty imposed on the Magistrates without some little <lb/>
fee to remunerate them for their service. <lb/>
Mr. Renouf hoped that the eloquent speech of the <lb/>
hon member for Fogo would be reported. He (Mr. <lb/>
Renouf) thought the object of the bill was a good <lb/>
one. These Magistrates had very little to do, and <lb/>
they might be very usefully employed in collecting the <lb/>
information necessary to the successful carrying out <lb/>
of this measure. He (Mr. Renouf) thought their <lb/>
salaries were amply sufficient for the duties they had <lb/>
to perform. That measura would not entail much <lb/>
additional labor, and he considered that they were <lb/>
certainly the proper persons to be entrusted with the <lb/>
carrying out of the provisions of that bill: <lb/>
r. E. D. SHEA regarded the principle of that <lb/>
bill as unobjectionable. It would certainly have the <lb/>
effect of procuring very useful information. We <lb/>
should now know more of that interesting locality <lb/>
Goat's Cove than we knew before. Hon members <lb/>
would be able to ascertain the number of its inhabi­ <lb/>
tants, and whether Mr King was in reality monarch <lb/>
of all he surveyed in that quarter. But joking apart, <lb/>
he considered the measure a very useful one, and the <lb/>
only difficulty in his mind was that it would not be <lb/>
carried out efficiently, because there was no provision <lb/>
for remunerating the parties who were to perform the <lb/>
work. It seemed to be thought,however, that theStipen­ <lb/>
diary Magistrates would be only too glad to take upon <lb/>
themselves this extra duty. They enjoyed so many <lb/>
of the blessings of civilization in these outports, their <lb/>
position there was such a happy one, that they would <lb/>
feel that they were bound to make some return for all <lb/>
the numerous advantages they reaped. It had been <lb/>
said that they were in some districts rarely called <lb/>
upon to adjudicate upon a case. He (Mr. Shea) <lb/>
thought that fact spoke trumpet-tongued in their fa­ <lb/>
vour. Did it not show the great moral influence <lb/>
which their presence exercised?. It was not right that <lb/>
they should now be burdened with extra duties of an <lb/>
onerous character, without one shilling compensation. <lb/>
He did not see why they should be more patriotic and <lb/>
disinterested than other officials. Then many of these <lb/>
gentlemen had to perform the duties of Poor Commis­ <lb/>
sioners, and if they were not paid for that they should <lb/>
be, for a more arduous and disagreeable duty he (\lr. <lb/>
Snea) could not conceive. It was not fair for the <lb/>
Government to impose these additional duties on these <lb/>
gentlemen merely because they had the power to do <lb/>
so. Looking at the provisions for carrying out the <lb/>
present measure, he did not think that the Govern­ <lb/>
ment could reasonably expect that the duties would <lb/>
be efficiently performed. But beyond the Magistrates, <lb/>
the Government were to appoint Registrars. These <lb/>
men, of course, would be paid; or was it contempla<lb break="no"/>ted that all were to do the work from pure unsullied, <lb/>
unmixed patriotism? He (Mr. Shea) very much feared <lb/>
that this attempt at economy was not a very wise pro­ <lb/>
ceeding. He did not wish to pred.ct failure. He <lb/>
merely expressed the fears which he really entertained. <lb/>
He hoped that there would be some inducement held <lb/>
out to these gentlemen, of some small remun-ration <lb/>
—otherwise we could not have much confidence in the <lb/>
successful working of that measure. <lb/>
Mr. TALBot.—No one would take an interest in <lb/>
any business if he was not paid for it. If the Govern. <lb/>
ment employed Registrars they would be compelled to <lb/>
pay them. And what would be the necessary, result <lb/>
with the Magistrates? . They would become jealous <lb/>
of the Registrars, and of course their work would be <lb/>
inefficiently performed. The best plan would be to <lb/>
pay all or none. He (Mr. Talbot) must contess that <lb/>
his opinion was, considering the modus operandi to be <lb/>
pursued, that this measure would result in failure, in <lb/>
fact become totally inoperative. The best way would <lb/></p> 

<p>would be carried into effect; and the Act would be <lb/>
mere waste paper and an incumbrance to the statute <lb/>
book. The Roman Catholic clergy would not consent <lb/>
to discharge the duties that were to be imposed on <lb/>
them. Besides, there were private reasons, which <lb/>
could never be known that would prevent them. They <lb/>
would not act as tha officials of any government, paid <lb/>
or unpaid. If the government passed the bill in its <lb/>
present form it would be a penal act. The church <lb/>
and state could never run together in parallel lines <lb/>
in all things, and you could, nºt fºrce them. There <lb/>
were certain things connected with births and marrin­ <lb/>
ges, that they could not tell you of. As citizens, they <lb/>
would be bound, but as Ministers of religion, you <lb/>
would not get anything out of them. Whenever their <lb/>
principles came in contact with the state, they were <lb/>
bound to resist. Therefore this bill would be altoge­ <lb/>
taer a nu:lity. If the government made it incumbent <lb/>
on mothers, fathers, brothers and sisters, to give the <lb/>
notices required by this bill, where was the necessity <lb/>
for requiring the clergymen, to do so? With these <lb/>
observations he supported the principle of the measure <lb/>
though he did not see how it was possible for this act <lb/>
to be carried into effect. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon ATTorney GENERAt.-If he was not mista­ <lb/>
ken marriages must be registered under the marriage <lb/>
act. <lb/>
Mr. KENT.-But clergymen were not bound to <lb/>
make returns. <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon ATToRNEY GENERAL believed they were. <lb/>
The SPEAKER considered that it was of great import­ <lb/>
ance that there should be a registration of births and <lb/>
marriages. The measure applied to all, an i it was a <lb/>
duty that they owed to their own people, as it was of <lb/>
the utmost importance that such registers should be <lb/>
correctly kept, as they might involve rights of proper­ <lb/>
ty and the peace of families, and serious loss and <lb/>
damage might result from the want of that evidence <lb/>
which, in the lapse of time, such registers only could <lb/>
furnish. In this country no great loss had yet takea <lb/>
place from the want of public registers although he <lb/>
was aware there had been some. We were increasing, <lb/>
and with an increase of population and accumulatios <lb/>
of property, it was of the utmost importance that we <lb/>
should have a correct registry of marriages and births. <lb/>
A registry of deaths was also necessary. He had fre­ <lb/>
quent applications from England and Ireland as to the <lb/>
deaths of persons, and the time of such deaths. With <lb/>
regard to penalties, it there was any objection, he did <lb/>
not see that it was necessary to press that. It became <lb/>
a moral duty, and he took it for granted all clergy­ <lb/>
me would be ready and willing to assist in securing <lb/>
accurate registers. In Lower Canada there was a sys­ <lb/>
tem of public registration, duplicate registers being <lb/>
kept by ail clergymen, one of which was at the end <lb/>
of each year deposited with the Clerk of the Court, <lb/>
and the Roman Catholic clergy were the first named in <lb/>
the Act.—(Here bon Speaker read the first section <lb/>
of the Act of Lower Canada.) He thought it was the <lb/>
duty of all clergymen to assist in carrying out such a <lb/>
necessary measure. As to the penalties, he did not <lb/>
suppose they would come to much, but he did not <lb/>
think any clergymen would refuse to give the neces­ <lb/>
Bary returns. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. KENT.-It was, no doubt of importance both as <lb/></p> 

<p>statistical information, that there should be a corre <lb/>
registry of births, marriages and deaths. But wh ct <lb/>
the petition of the Right Revd. Dr. Mullock º <lb/>
to was that the Catholic clergy should, under penal. <lb/>
ties, be bound to make returns to the governm. <lb/>
which he regarded as a species of penal legislation. <lb/>
Mr Prowse was surprised that there should be any' <lb/>
difficulty about furnishing information which was. <lb/>
sidered necessary in all civilised and progressive Coun. <lb/>
tries. He did say that if in that bill there was anything <lb/>
which touched the religious feeling of the Right R. <lb/>
Dr. Mullock, he (Mr Prowse) would not be a party t; <lb/>
its enactment, for however valuable the information <lb/>
might be, religiºus feelings must be held sacred; a. <lb/></p> 

<p>be the last to infringe them....But such registers wº <lb/>
very much required, and he(Mr Prowse) trusted the <lb/>
would be a willingness to assist in having them accº. <lb/>
ately made up. <lb/>
Mr TALBor—It was customary in all Catholic cours <lb/>
tries to º in the churches public registers of mat. <lb/>
riages and births, and whenever courts of justice re. <lb/>
quired extracts from them as matter of evidence, acces <lb/>
to them was allowed. But there were no public reg­ <lb/>
isters of marriage here at all, because marriages wº <lb/>
not performed in the churches. But there was a reg <lb/>
istry kept of baptisms and marriages, and the Bishº <lb/>
had no objection to allow it to be copied if the gover. <lb/>
ment required it. <lb/>
Hon ATToRNEY GENERAL–It seemed to be con. <lb/>
sidered objectionable that the bill should impose a duty <lb/>
for which there was no compensation. He had no ob. <lb/>
jection to dispense with the 5th section of the Bill. But <lb/>
he could not say the same respecting the 6th. It was <lb/>
the section on which he relied for securing a correct <lb/>
registry of marriages. It provided that in addition tº <lb/>
what clergymen were bound by law to do, they should <lb/>
send a copy of their registry at the end of the year to <lb/>
the Colonial Secretary's office. This object was to <lb/>
rocure in a condensed form what was now recorded <lb/>
in all the churches and chapels in the island. He quitº <lb/>
agreed with the Speaker that it was not a matter <lb/>
which any clergyman would object to, when the im: <lb/>
portance of the object was considered. <lb/>
Mr KENT—But it was to be done under a penalty. <lb/>
IIon Attorney. GENERAL–As to the penalty, it <lb/>
that was the objection, there would not be much diffi. <lb/>
culty about it. These sections might as well be passed <lb/>
over for further consideration, and the other sections <lb/>
of the bill proceeded with. <lb/>
The seventh section was then read and adopted. <lb/>
The remaining sections were read servatim and <lb/>
adopted, and the committee rose and the chairman re­ <lb/>
ported progress and asked leave to sit again. To sit <lb/>
again to-morrow, <lb/>
On motion of the hon Attorney General, pursuant <lb/>
to order of the day, the house resolved itself into Com­ <lb/>
mittee of the whole on the Coroners' Bill, Dr Winter <lb/>
in the chair. <lb/>
The hon Attorney General explained the object of <lb/>
the bill, and the present state of the law, after which <lb/>
its several sections were read and adopted, down to the <lb/>
section authorizing the Goveonor in Čouncil to fix the <lb/>
fees under the measure, on which there was some dis. <lb/>
cussion, when the committee rose and the chairman <lb/>
reported progress. To sit again to-morrow. <lb/>
On motion of the hon Attorney General, pursuant <lb/>
to order of the day, the house resolved itself into com. <lb/>
mittee of the whole on the bill to provide for wives and <lb/>
children deserted by their husbands and parents, and <lb/>
. parents deserted by their children, Mr. Wyatt in the <lb/>
chair. <lb/>
The hon Attorney General having explained the <lb/>
object of the bill, several sections were read and adopt-, <lb/>
ed, with soune amendments. The committee then rose . <lb/>
and the chairman reported progress. To sit againto­ <lb/>
morrow. <lb/>
The house then adjourned until to-morrow at three <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/>
FRIDAY, Feb. 10, <lb/>
The house met at three o'clock. <lb/>
Pursuant to order of the day, on motion of the hon <lb/>
Attorney GENERAL, the house resolved itself into a <lb/>
Committee of the whole on the 3ill to continue the <lb/>
punishment of Banishment in certain cases, Mr Now. <lb/>
lan in the chair. <lb/>
The several sections of the Bill were read and <lb/>
adopted, and the committte rose and the Chairman <lb/>
reported the Bill with some amendments, <lb/>
Ordered to be engrossed and read a third time to. <lb/>
morrow. <lb/>
Pursuant to order of the day, on motion of the kon <lb/>
Attorney General the house resolved itself into a <lb/>
Committee of the whole on the Bill to make provis. <lb/>
ion for the recovery of Penalties becoming due on the <lb/>
ºut- of certain Recognizances, Mr. Rorke in the <lb/>
chair. <lb/>
The several sections of the Bill were read and adop­ <lb/>
ted, and the committee rose and the Chairman repor­ <lb/>
ted the Bill with some amendment. Ordered to be <lb/>
engrossed and read a lhird time to-morrow. <lb/>
Pursuant to the order of the day, on motion of the <lb/>
hon ATToksey GENERAL, the House resolved itself <lb/>
into a Committee of the whole on the Bill to enable <lb/>
courts of Law to give relief against adverse claims <lb/>
made upon persons having no interest in the subject <lb/>
of such claims, Dr Winter in the chair. <lb/>
The several sections of the biºl were read and adop­ <lb/>
ted with some amendments, an i the committee rose <lb/>
and the chairman reported the Bill with some amend. <lb/>
ments. <lb/>
Ordered to be engrossed and read a third time on <lb/>
Monday next. <lb/>
The house then adjourned until Monday at thres <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/>
--> <p rendition="simple:right">Monday, Feb. 13.</p> 

<p>The house met at three o'clock.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:KENT1">The hon RECEIVER GENERAL</persName> laid on the table of <lb/>
the house a return showing the duties that would be <lb/>
payable upon our imports for 1863 under the tariff of <lb/>
Canada, as asked for by the hon member for St. <lb/>
John's West, Mr. Renouf. A similar return for <lb/>
1864, was in the course of preparation at the cus<lb break="no"/>tom-house, and would be laid on the table when com<lb break="no"/>pleted.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. Wyatt</persName> presented a petition from Robert <lb/>
Thorburn, and other member of the Commercial <lb/>
Society of St. John's, which was received and read, <lb/>
setting forth, that petitioners had been informed that <lb/>
the subject of a confederation of the British North <lb/>
American Provinces, based on certain resolutions <lb/>
adopted at a convention of delegates from each of the <lb/>
Provinces, held at Quebec in the month of October <lb/>
last, was to be brought forward at an early day for the <lb/>
consideration of the house; that petitioners were of <lb/>
opinion that a step involving such momentous conse<lb break="no"/>quences as the union of this colony with the neigh<lb break="no"/>bouring North American Provinces, should not be <lb/>
essayed until some further time had been allowed for <lb/>
the collection of information and statistics, and for the <lb/>
consideration of the subject by the constituencies of <lb/>
the several electoral districts, and by the inhabitants <lb/>
generally, many of whom had not yet heard that such <lb/>
a confederation was contemplated; that any union, <lb/>
to be mutually beneficial, must be founded upon a <lb/>
uniformity of interests and objects, and that, so far as <lb/>
the limited information of petitioners extended, no <lb/>
such uniformity existed between Canada and this <lb/>
Colony; that the Canadas, being essentially manufac<lb break="no"/>turing and agricultural countries, have always pursued <lb/>
a protective policy, while Newfoundland, which pro<lb break="no"/>duces few, and must import most of the necessaries <lb/>
<!--

<p>f <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>he was satisfied the leader of the Government would y <lb/></p> 

<p>p <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>s <lb/></p> 

<p>#. <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/>
! <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>? <lb/></p> 

<p>... in navment of which <lb/>
of .." ...'. be benefite <lb/>
. jing that the house <lb/>
tº. fledge either the Go <lb/>
i. to the proposed uniſh <lb/>
jºin obtained which will clear <lb/>
for the advantage of this colon <lb/>
niy has been affºrded of consu <lb/>
important measure. , <lb/>
Mr Wyarr, in moving tha <lb/>
table, woull make a few obser <lb/>
... signed by, most of the le. <lb/>
john's, now in the cºnntry, an <lb/>
afforded, he was satisfied that <lb/>
...y others who were not fe" <lb/>
was based on resolution: adop <lb/>
...; the commercial Society, c <lb/>
tion of that questiºn. There <lb/>
je at the meeting, and hº <lb/>
that gentleman had afterwards <lb/>
tion. He mentioned that to <lb/>
the question: The Commerc. <lb/>
º, feel gratified at the receptiº <lb/>
tions. §. very long ago the <lb/>
tion to the government as to <lb/>
ºted upon, and the revenue <lb/>
iderable loss, which would h <lb/>
that recommendation been act. <lb/>
might appear to have emanuſ <lb/>
colony; but it ºxpressed the <lb/>
ºmber of all classes. The tº <lb/>
munity, and fishermen, agreed <lb/>
not to be settled in the existin <lb/>
Time should be given for its 90 <lb/>
for the friends of confederatio <lb/>
be beneficial to the country f <lb/>
mation had yet been furnished <lb/>
appear to be such sº would li <lb/>
their present constitution as * <lb/>
represented himself a constit <lb/>
thºusand. It would not be fai <lb/>
sulting them, tº decide upon <lb/>
tion, which might be afterwar <lb/>
1Its own opinion was that if wº <lb/>
ration with Canada, Newfound <lb/>
and before he would give a v <lb/>
that house, to pledge his con <lb/>
and see them, and learn their <lb/>
the prayer of that petition w <lb/>
merely asked for time; and hº <lb/>
its prayer wouli be acceded to. <lb/>
that the petition came in rather <lb/>
but so early as the 6th Dece <lb/>
dressed to the Government by <lb/>
ber of Commerce, asking for <lb/>
were informed, in reply, that th <lb/>
in possession of further info <lb/>
published in the newspapers <lb/>
mature consideration it was de <lb/>
of the Commercial Society, an <lb/>
petition now presented, which <lb/>
ceive at the hands of hon mem <lb/>
was entitled to. It was signed <lb/>
sented the greater portion of the <lb/>
and if it could be shown them tº <lb/>
benefit of the colony to enter i <lb/>
they wouid readily become p. <lb/>
then they would oppose it, Th <lb/>
go hand in hand with the fishe <lb/>
were identical. It had been sai <lb/>
had their private place, where <lb/>
He denied that. They had <lb/>
motives to any parties.—They <lb/>
question decided on its merits. <lb/>
(To be contin <lb/>
<lb break="no"/>Holloway's Oi NTMENT AN <lb/>
emption from sores, ulcers,bad <lb/>
most diseases of the skin, will <lb/>
persevering use of these admir <lb/>
may be implicitly relied on in <lb/>
regard to sex or the duration of <lb/>
way's Ointment and Pills are un <lb/>
indolent ulcerations of the legs <lb/>
other applications and consign <lb/>
of pain and death. No risk or <lb/>
the use of Holloway's medical <lb/>
allays pain, smarting, and itcl <lb/>
from foul mattor, represses prol <lb/>
es the growth of good health; <lb/>
ultimately form a sound surface <lb/></p> 

<p>ſºufºu. <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOH, <lb/>
MONDAY, MARCI <lb/></p> 

<p>The debate in the Assembly on <lb/>
yet closed, though the argum" <lb/>
husted. The scheme has no <lb/>
through and through—all its few <lb/>
bare, and we feel assured that a <lb/>
ed it with intelligent and impar <lb/>
cided in favour of its adoption <lb/>
are glad to perceive that with a <lb/>
industrious opponents have been <lb/>
real point against it, or in any w <lb/>
sition of antagonism they have <lb/>
of delusions with which they at <lb/>
very soon worked through and <lb/>
have been unable to replace eve <lb/>
and have had no other choice <lb/>
picking up the scattered fragmen <lb/>
and flinging them back aga, <lb/>
facts and argument. It has bee <lb/>
have noticed the discussion that <lb/>
tence of our opponents has been <lb/>
Union had come to us from a nº <lb/>
°rnment whose first object was <lb/>
*elves at our utmost cost. Cana <lb/>
nancial straits, and saw no me <lb/>
*vailable to her as a raid upon u <lb/>
*eeming as we so notoriously <lb/>
Prosperity! Hence the cry of <lb/>
hence the discovery of the trea <lb/>
... our independent legislation.": <lb/>
* not in the same breath, proc. <lb/>
thus put the case, that we are <lb/>
Pay our deb's, and that we are p <lb/>
of pauperism compared to whic <lb/>
the neck would be an endurable <lb/>
Pendent legislation" to which we <lb/>
at all hazards, is admittedly th <lb/>
Possible, and we by no means d­ <lb/>
believe it to be powerless to meet <lb/>
exigencies of the country. U. <lb/>
done good service, and if not to <lb/>
*ach, at least to an appreciable <lb/></p> 

<p>l <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="3" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_3.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER</fw>
<fw type="num">3</fw> <!-- 

<p>rmation, that there should be a <lb/>
hs, . and deaths. But what <lb/>
the Right Revd. Dr. Mullock objected <lb/>
Catholic clergy should, under pe. <lb/>
to make returns to the governme. <lb/>
rded as a species of penal le islation. <lb/>
was surprised that there should be any' <lb/>
furnishing information which was . <lb/>
try in all civilised and progressive coºl <lb/>
ty that if in that bill there was anything <lb/>
the religious feeling of the Right R. <lb/>
; (Mr Prowse) would not be . party tº <lb/>
ior however valuable the informati. <lb/>
sus feelings must be held sacred; and <lb/>
the leader of the Government would <lb/>
fringe them, But such registers wer. <lb/>
tired, and he(Mr Prowse) trusted ther. <lb/>
ingness to assist in having them accur. <lb/></p> 

<p>correct <lb/></p> 

<p>It was customary in all Catholic couns <lb/>
the churches public registers of mar. <lb/>
is, and whenever courts of justice re­ <lb/>
from them as matter of evidence, access <lb/>
owed. But there were no public reg­ <lb/>
!e here at all, because marriages were <lb/>
n the churches. But there was a reg. <lb/>
ptisms and marriages, and the Bishº <lb/>
i to allow it to be copied if the govern. <lb/>
t. <lb/>
: EY GENERAL–It seemed to be con­ <lb/>
nable that the bill should impose a duty <lb/>
was no compensation. He had no ob. <lb/>
ise with the 5th section of the Bill. But <lb/>
v the same respecting the 6th. It was <lb/>
which he relied for securing a correct <lb/>
iages. . It provided that in addition to <lb/>
were bound by law to do, they should <lb/>
heir registry at the end of the year to <lb/>
cretary's office. This object was to <lb/>
ſidensed form what was now recorded <lb/>
aes and chapels in the island. He quite <lb/>
: Speaker that it was not a matter <lb/>
:yman would object to, when the im­ <lb/>
Ibject was considered. <lb/>
Put it was to be done under a penalty. <lb/>
EY GENERAL–As to the penalty, it <lb/>
ection, there would not be much diffi­ <lb/>
These sections might as well be passed <lb/>
consideration, and the other sections <lb/>
eded with. <lb/>
•ection was then read and adopted. <lb/>
ng sections were read servatim and <lb/>
e committee rose and the chairman re­ <lb/>
and asked leave to sit again. To sit <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/>
the hon Attorney General, pursuant <lb/></p> 

<p>ſay, the house resolved itself into Com­ <lb/>
Iole on the Coroners' Bill, Dr Winter <lb/></p> 

<p>rney General explained the object of <lb/>
present state of the law, after which <lb/>
ºns were read and adopted, down to the <lb/>
ing the Goveonor in Council to fix the <lb/>
leasure, on which there was some dis­ <lb/>
the committee rose and the chairman <lb/>
's. To sit again to-morrow. <lb/>
the hon, Attorney General, pursuant <lb/>
ſay, the house resolved itself into com­ <lb/>
ole on the bill to provide for wives and <lb/>
I by their husbands and parents, and <lb/>
ted by their children, Mr. Wyatt in the <lb/></p> 

<p>orney General having explained the <lb/>
several sections were read and adopt­ <lb/>
àendments. The committee then rose <lb/>
ºn reported progress. To sit again to­ <lb/></p> 

<p>in adjourned until to-morrow at three <lb/></p> 

<p>FRIDAY, Feb. 10. <lb/>
it at three o'clock. <lb/>
ider of the day, on motion of the hon <lb/>
ERAL, the house resolved itself into a <lb/>
e whole on the Bill to continue the <lb/>
Banishment in certain cases, Mr Now­ <lb/></p> 

<p>sections of the Bill were read and <lb/></p> 

<p>e committte rose and the Chairman <lb/>
! with some amendments, <lb/>
engrossed and read a third time to­ <lb/></p> 

<p>der of the day, on motion of the kon <lb/>
il the house resolved itself into a <lb/>
: whole on the Bill to make provis­ <lb/>
"ry of Penalties becoming due on the <lb/>
lin Recognizances, Mr. Rorke in the <lb/></p> 

<p>'tions of the Bill were read and adop­ <lb/>
mittee rose and the Chairman repor­ <lb/>
80me amendment. Ordered to be <lb/>
*d a lhird time to-morrow. <lb/>
* order of the day, on motion of the <lb/>
: ENERAL, the House resolved itself <lb/>
of the whole on the Bill to enable <lb/>
give relief against adverse claims <lb/>
is having no interest in the subject <lb/>
r Winter in the chair. <lb/>
stions of the bill were read and adop­ <lb/>
aendments, an i the committee rose <lb/>
: reported the Bill with some amend­ <lb/></p> 

<p>engrossed and read a third time on <lb/>
n adjourned until Monday at three <lb/></p> 

<p>MoxDAY, Feb. 13. <lb/></p> 

<p>at three o'clock. <lb/>
:WER GENERAL laid on the table of <lb/>
'I .."; the duties that would be <lb/>
imports for 1863 under the tariff of <lb/></p> 

<p>for by the hon member for St. <lb/>
r. Renouf. A similar return for <lb/>
course of preparation at the Cus­ <lb/>
ould be laid on the table when com­ <lb/></p> 

<p>resented a petition from Robert <lb/>
her members of the Commere, ak <lb/>
ºn's, which was received and read, <lb/>
petitioners had been informed that <lb/>
onfederation of the British North <lb/>
Ces, based on certain resolutions <lb/>
ntion of delegates from each of the <lb/>
Q lebec in the mºnth of October <lb/>
ight forward at an early day for the <lb/>
le house; that petitioners were o <lb/>
involving such momentous conse­ <lb/>
on of this colony with the neigh­ <lb/>
merican Provinces, should not be <lb/>
• further time had been atlowed for <lb/>
formation and statistics, and for the <lb/>
le subject by the constituencies of <lb/>
al districts, and by the inhabitants <lb/>
whom had not yet heard that such <lb/>
was contemplated; that any unior, <lb/></p> 

<p>eneficial, must be founded upon a 9". <lb/></p> 

<p>ests and objects, and that, so far as <lb/>
nation of petitioners extended, no <lb/>
existed between Canada and this <lb/>
Canadas, being essentially manufac: <lb/>
ural countries, have always pursued <lb/>
, while Newfoundland, which pro­ <lb/>
st import most of the necessaries <lb/></p> 

<p>e=­ <lb/></p> 

<p>e==T= <lb/></p> 

<p>• *: ment of which she exports her own <lb/></p>--> of life, in payment of which sh exports her own <lb/>
produce, will ever be benefited by a free trade policy; <lb/>
and praying that the house would take no action to <lb/>
bind or pledge either the Government of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature to the proposed union, until information has <lb/>
been obtained which will clearly demonstrate it to be <lb/>
for the advantage of this colony, nor until an opportu<lb break="no"/>nity has been afforded of consulting the people on this <lb/>
important measure.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr WYATT</persName>, in moving that ths petition lie on the <lb/>
table, would make a few observations. That petition <lb/>
was signed by most of the leading merchants of St. <lb/>
John's, now in the country, and if an opportunity were <lb/>
afforded, he was satisfied that it would be signed by <lb/>
many others who were not resident in the capital. It <lb/>
was based on resolutions adopted at a special meeting <lb/>
of the Commercial Society, called for the considera<lb break="no"/>tion of that question. There was only one dissenting <lb/>
voice at the meeting, and he (Mr. Wyatt) believed <lb/>
that gentleman had afterwards withdrawn his opposi<lb break="no"/>tion. He mentioned that to show the unanimity on <lb/>
the question. The Commercial body had no reason <lb/>
to feel ratified at the reception given to their peti<lb break="no"/>tions. Not very long ago they made a recommenda<lb break="no"/>tion to the government as to bonds, which was not <lb/>
acted upon, and the revenue, had since suffered con<lb break="no"/>siderable loss, which would have been avoided had <lb/>
that recommendation been acted upon. That petition <lb/>
might appear to have emanated from a class in the <lb/>
colony; but it expressed the opinions of an immense <lb/>
number of all classes. The merchants, trading com<lb break="no"/>munity, and fishermen, agreed that that question ought <lb/>
not to be settled in the existing House of Assembly. <lb/>
Time should be given for its consideration; and it was <lb/>
for the friends of confederation to prove that it would <lb/>
be beneficial to the country generally. So far as infor<lb break="no"/>mation had yet been furnished, its advantages did not <lb/>
appear to he such as would induce them to give up <lb/>
their present constitution as a separate colony. He <lb/>
represented himself, a constituency of nine or ten <lb/>
thousand. It would not be fair to them without con<lb break="no"/>sulting them, to decide upon entering the confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, which might be afterwards a matter of regret. <lb/>
His own opinion was that if we entered into confede<lb break="no"/>ration with Canada, Newfoundland would be nowhere, <lb/>
and before he would give a vote on the question in <lb/>
that house, to pledge his constituents, he would go <lb/>
and see them, and learn their opinions respecting it, <lb/>
the prayer of that petition was very moderate. It <lb/>
merely asked for time; and he (Mr. Wyatt) trusted <lb/>
its prayer wouli be acceded to. It might be objected <lb/>
that the petition came in rather late, on that question; <lb/>
but so early as the 6th December a letter was ad<lb break="no"/>dressed to the Government by direction of the Cham<lb break="no"/>ber of Commerce, asking for information; and they <lb/>
were informed, in reply, that the Government were not <lb/>
in possession of further information than had been <lb/>
published in the newspapers of the town. After <lb/>
mature consideration it was decided to have a meeting <lb/>
of the Commercial Society, and the result was the <lb/>
petition now presented, which he trusted would re<lb break="no"/>ceive at the hands of hon members that attention it <lb/>
was entitled to. It was signed by those who repre<lb break="no"/>sented the greater portion of the wealth of the colony; <lb/>
and if it could be shown them that it would be for the <lb/>
benefit of the colony to enter into the Confederation, <lb/>
they would readily become parties to it. But until <lb/>
then they would oppose it.- They were determined to <lb/>
go hand in hand with the fishermen. Their interests <lb/>
were identical. It had been said that the merchants <lb/>
had their private place, where they attacked others. <lb/>
He denied that. They had no desire to impute <lb/>
motives to any parties.—They desired to see that <lb/>
question decided on its merits. <lb/></p> 

<p>(<hi rendition="simple:italic">To be continued</hi>)</p> <!-- 

<p>Holloway's OINTMexT AND Pills.-Certain ex­ <lb/>
emption from sores, ulcers,bad legs, piles, fistulas, and <lb/>
most diseases of the skin, will be shortly cured by the <lb/>
persevering use of these admirable remedies. They <lb/>
may be implicitly relied on in all such cases without <lb/>
regard to sex or the duration of the malady. Holo­ <lb/>
way's Ointment and Pills are unspeakably precious in <lb/>
indolent ulcerations of the legs which often resist all <lb/>
other applications and consign the sufferer to the bed <lb/>
of pain and death. No risk or inconvenience attends <lb/>
the use of Holloway's medicaments. The Ointment <lb/>
allays pain, smarting, and itching, cleanses the sore <lb/>
from foul matter, represses proud flesh, and encourag <lb/>
es the growth of good healthy granulations which <lb/>
ultimately form a sound surface. <lb/></p> 

<p>ū; ºutnumbmer. <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOH.W.?.S.: <lb/>
MONDAY, MARCH 6, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>The debate in the Assembly on Confederation is not <lb/>
yet closed, though the argument in completely ex­ <lb/>
husted. The scheme has now been investigated <lb/>
through and through-all its features and details laid <lb/>
bare, and we feel assured that all who have consider­ <lb/>
edit with intelligent and impartial minds have de­ <lb/>
cided in favour of its adoption by the colony. We <lb/>
are glad to perceive that with all their efforts its most <lb/></p> 

<p>industrious opponents have been unable to make one <lb/></p> 

<p>real point against it, or in any way to sustain the po­ <lb/>
sition of antagonism they have assumed. The stock <lb/>
of delusions with which they at first opposed it was <lb/>
very soon worked through and broken up, yet they <lb/>
have been unable to replace even this sort of material <lb/>
and have had no other choice than to flºunder on, <lb/>
picking up the scattered fragments of their old supply <lb/>
and flinging them back against a solid wall of <lb/>
facts and argument. It has been observed by all who <lb/>
have noticed the discussion that the foundation pre­ <lb/>
tence of our opponents has been that the proposal of <lb/>
Union had come to us from a needy and crafty Gov­ <lb/>
*rnment whose first object was to aggrandize them­ <lb/>
*elves at oar utmost cost. Canada was indeed in fi­ <lb/>
nancial straits, and saw no means of extrication so <lb/>
"ailable to her as a raid upon us in Newfoundland, <lb/>
*eming as we so notoriously are with wealth and <lb/>
Prosperity! Hence the cry of oppressive taxation, <lb/>
*nce the discovery of the treasure we possess in <lb/>
..our independent legislation." It is at the same time, <lb/>
iſ not in the same breath, proclaimed by those who <lb/>
thus put the case, that we are at present unable to <lb/>
Pay our deb's, and that we are pressed down by a load <lb/>
ºf pauperism compared to which a mill-stone round <lb/>
the reck would be an endurable burthen. The "inde. <lb/>
Pendent legislation" to which we are asked to cling <lb/>
**ll hazards, is admittedly the best that has been <lb/>
Pºsible, and we by no means depreciate it when we <lb/>
believe it to be powerless to meet the present material <lb/>
*igencies of the country. Unquestionably it has <lb/></p> 

<p>done good service, and if not to the full extent of its <lb/>
**h, at least to an appreciable degree. <lb/></p> 

<p>But it can­ <lb/></p> 

<p>There was only one dissenting f <lb/></p> 

<p>-º <lb/></p> 

<p>not supply the void of short fisheries, it cannot pro­ <lb/>
duce means for developing our dormant resources—it <lb/>
cannot of itself create that employment and food which <lb/>
our people so urgently need. That a Union with pros­ <lb/>
perous communities gives best promise of these advan­ <lb/>
tages, we think has been made sufficiently clear; and <lb/>
on such grounds alone,even if there were no other in­ <lb/>
ducements, it is the measure which this colony should <lb/>
most anxiously desire. At all events, it is for those <lb/>
who dispute this view, to cast about and suggest some <lb/>
more feasible and efficient means of relieving the ne­ <lb/>
cessities that bow the country down. It is not <lb/>
enough to deny the value of Confederation, and at <lb/>
this point stand stock still, as our opponents in the <lb/>
case seem to think. The demand for some endeavour <lb/></p> 

<p>in some direction is not to be ignored. Remain as we <lb/></p> 

<p>are we cannot, if we would—the resources on which <lb/></p> 

<p>we have hitherto relied have long since warned us of <lb/>
their insufficiency, and new ones must be found if the <lb/></p> 

<p>population are not to fly the land. The question <lb/>
therefore is, if Confederation be not acceptable, what <lb/></p> 

<p>is to be the alternative proposition? We have <lb/>
looked to those who so vehemently denounce on <lb/></p> 

<p>one side to point to something of which they might <lb/>
expect approval on the other—but so far, blank repu­ <lb/></p> 

<p>diation has seemed to them to discharge all the duty <lb/></p> 

<p>they owe the country. This, however, is a course <lb/>
which we apprehend will, on reflection, find few ap­ <lb/>
provers—it its fatuity is not made plain by the <lb/>
state of things around us now, some amongst us must <lb/></p> 

<p>have heads much harder to penetrate than we think <lb/>
they are at all likely to prove. <lb/></p> 

<p>-º-º-º-º-º­ <lb/>
In the Canadian Assembly a test vote to continue de­ <lb/>
bate on Confederation to exclusion of all other busi­ <lb/>
ness, has been carried by a vote of 63 to 26—this vir. <lb/>
tually disposing of the question. In the Legislative <lb/>
Council the debate was terminated by a majority of <lb/>
45 to 15 votes. <lb/></p> 

<p>In our own Assembly there is a majority in favour <lb/>
of the measure, though it is agreed to refer it to the <lb/>
constituencies. <lb/></p> 

<p>-º-º-º-º­ <lb/></p> 

<p>On Friday night last the wind veeredöfrom north-east <lb/>
to south-west, and having moved the ice off, the <lb/>
greater number of the sealers got out on Saturday— <lb/>
yesterday most of the others followed, some few yet <lb/>
remaining in port. <lb/></p> 

<p>sº-º-º­ <lb/>
Trinity Bay, February 25th, 1865." <lb/>
[To THE EDITOR of THE NEWFoundLANDER.] <lb/>
SIR-Ishall feel obliged by your giving insertion;in <lb/>
the columns of your journal to the following noble con­ <lb/>
duct on the part of Mr. Richard Rockwood, of Heart's <lb/>
Content:—On a day last week several persons went <lb/>
out from that place to the ice in search for seals; <lb/>
towards the aſternoon the wind sprung up from the <lb/>
S.E. a strong breeze; all the punts had returned before <lb/>
the height of the gale, with the exception of two, <lb/>
and it happened that the crews of them were <lb/>
seven in number. Mr. Rockwood, on seeing no ap­ <lb/>
pearance of them coming in late in the day, immediate­ <lb/>
ly fitted out a cod-seine skiff, with eight hands, to search <lb/>
for the missing men. After being out some time they <lb/>
came up with one of the punts, having four men on <lb/>
board, in a sinking state, and were just in time to save <lb/>
them from a watery grave. No trace whatsoever could <lb/>
be got of the other punt's crew. But Mr. Rockwood <lb/>
was not deterred from making further search. Next <lb/>
morning the same boat and crew were fitted out at Mr. <lb/>
Rockwood's sole expense to proceed to the ice and <lb/>
search in every direction for them. After being out <lb/>
all day no trace could be got of them. However, I <lb/>
feel happy to say that they reached the other shore <lb/>
(Heart's Ease) quite fatigued, but were most kindly <lb/>
treated there by the school-teacher of that place, and <lb/>
have since returned to their families all well. <lb/>
Such conduct as this on the part of Mr. Rockwood <lb/>
deserves to be recorded, it goes to prove that he under­ <lb/>
stands the .# and knows how to practice the <lb/>
Divine precept of charity. And if such feelings were as <lb/>
well understood by those who are in a much higher walk <lb/>
in life in this country, and practised by them when op­ <lb/>
portunity offers, it would go in a great measure to calm <lb/>
down that asperity offeeling that, I feel sorry to say, has <lb/>
lately sprung up amongst us. <lb/>
A SOUTH-SHORE MAN. <lb/>
P.S.—Your journal is much sought after here lately <lb/>
owing to the sound and statesmanlike views on Confed­ <lb/>
eration in your editorials. Many persons here, who <lb/>
are really anxious for the future welfare of this country, <lb/>
begin to cheer up, and say there is some hope for it now <lb/>
when they see an amalgamation of the principal worth, <lb/>
and intelligence of our Legislature combining on this <lb/>
matter for the general good. Persons here think that <lb/>
if pamphlets, with both sides of the question, were <lb/>
distributed through the * previous to the gene­ <lb/>
ral election, it would be well. <lb/></p> 

<p>Notices. <lb/></p> 

<p>All parties ordering the <lb/>
"Victory" Cook Stove <lb/>
For the Newfoundland trade, will piease do so through <lb/>
Mr. GEo. GBAR, sole Proprietor of the same. <lb/></p> 

<p>BOWERS, PRATT &amp; Co., <lb/>
2nd Jan., 1865. 169, Congress-street, Boston. <lb/>
Feb. 27. (1 y.) <lb/></p> 

<p>Life Assurance. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºr Big <lb/>
Scottish Provident Institution, <lb/>
HEAD-OFFICE: <lb/>
EDINBURGH. <lb/>
Th's Office tenders superior advantages, assuring a <lb/>
greatly larger Assurance for the same premium, and <lb/>
eventually, to good lives, as large additions as where <lb/>
the usual high rate of premium is charged. <lb/>
A comparison of its tables of rates and profits and <lb/>
general conditions, can be confidently asked. <lb/>
Agent at Saint John's, <lb/></p> 

<p>J. O. FRASER. <lb/>
(6 m.) <lb/></p> 

<p>'LO BE LET, <lb/>
That commodious SHOP, WARE­ <lb/>
ROOMS, extensive STORE and <lb/>
WATERSIDE PREMISES, lately <lb/>
occupied by Messrs. WILLIAM THoMA's <lb/>
&amp; Co., in all respects admirably suited <lb/></p> 

<p>for a large mercantile business. <lb/>
Apply to <lb/>
F. B. T. CARTER. <lb/>
Feb. 27. 4.i. <lb/></p> 

<p>Feb. 27. <lb/></p> 

<p>T H E N E W F O U N D L A N D E R. <lb/></p> 

<p>Notice. Notices. <lb/>
* YTTY #TTTRIFTTº <lb break="no"/>A GENERALTMEETING a certain number of persons of the same age in the <lb/>
OF THE second, third; or fourth periods of five years respec­ <lb/></p> 

<p>... COLONIAL <lb/>
Life Assurancº ('ompany <lb/></p> 

<p>WAS HELD WITH IN THR <lb/>
COMPANY'S OFFICE, 5, GEORGE STREET, <lb/>
El)INBURGH, <lb/>
OW THURSDAY THE 151'H OF DECEMBER, <lb/>
TO RECEIVE THE <lb/>
Report by the Board of Directors <lb/>
on THE <lb/>
INVESTIGATION OF THE COMPANY"S <lb/>
AFFAIRS AND DIVISION OF <lb/>
PROFITS, AS AT 25Th <lb/>
MAY, 1864. <lb/></p> 

<p>George Moſs, Esq., Advocate, sheriff of stiling. <lb/>
shire, and Professor of Scots Law in the University of <lb/>
Edinburgh, in the Chair, <lb/></p> 

<p>- THE PROFITS REALISED <lb/>
During the period from 25th May 1859 to 25th May <lb/>
1864, ascertained in the manner now explained, amount <lb/>
to the large sum of £73,581, 19s, sterling, and the <lb/>
following statement will show how this result is de­ <lb/>
rived from the calculations:<lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>FUNDS invested, per statement <lb/>
submitted, after deduction of all <lb/>
claims against the Company out­ <lb/>
standing, . . . . . . . . . ... . . . . . . . . . $504,694 14 li <lb/>
LIABILITIES. <lb/>
1. With Profits, <lb/>
2. Without Profits, <lb/>
3. Other Classes of <lb/></p> 

<p>£221,154 15 3 <lb/>
82,665 17 10 <lb/></p> 

<p>Assurances, 1,807 9 0 <lb/>
4. Annuities, 30,201 19 3 <lb/>
5. Company whose <lb/>
business Was <lb/>
transferred, 15,407 14 7 <lb/>
351,237 15 11 <lb/>
-\- -<lb break="maybe"/>prºduct. 153,456 19 0 <lb/></p> 

<p>Capital Stock, #20,000 0 0 <lb/>
Guarantee Fund, 70,000 0 0 <lb/>
-\-&gt; 90,000 0 0 <lb/></p> 

<p>Remains, .... £63,456 19 0 <lb/>
Add sum divided annually among <lb/>
the Proprietors since 1859,hrought <lb/>
into account at this investigation, 10,125 0 0 <lb/>
Total Profits of period, from 25th <lb/></p> 

<p>May 1859 to 25th May, 1864 273,581. 19 0 <lb/></p> 

<p>DIVISION OF PROFITS. <lb/>
The directors propose to divide the above sum of <lb/>
£73,581, 19s, sterling, in the following proportions, <lb/>
between the Policy-holders and the Shareholders:— <lb/>
To the Policy-holders, #53,022 3 1 <lb/>
To the Shareholders since last In­ <lb/></p> 

<p>vestigation, 10,125 0 0 <lb/>
To the Guarantee Fund, 10,000 0 0 <lb/>
273,147 3 1 <lb/></p> 

<p>The sum of £33,022, 3-, 1.d. sterling, apportioned <lb/>
to Policy-holders, will give them an Annual Bonus of <lb/>
#1 10s. sterling per cent. for each year since last In­ <lb/>
vestigation, or for each year the Policy has existed in <lb/>
the case of those which may have been opened since <lb/>
25th May 1859, and the Directors are happy to be able <lb/>
to continue this rate, which was that given at the last <lb/>
Investigation in 1859. They have on this occasion <lb/>
again given the subject of Division of Profits with <lb/>
reference to the different classes of risks their most <lb/>
serious attention; but after reviewing it carefully, and <lb/>
hearing the views of the Actuary on the subject, they <lb/>
are satisfied that the addition of a reversionary sum <lb/>
for each premium paid is as fair a method in the <lb/>
circumstances of the case as could be adopted. <lb/>
Before concluding, the Directors think it necessary <lb/>
to ask your particular attention to the Statements <lb/>
referred to in a previous part of this Report, relating <lb/>
to the Mortality of the Company, as bearing more par­ <lb/>
ticularly on the rates charged for Assurance. <lb/>
The Directors have been frequently urged to re­ <lb/>
duce their Itates for various climates, and they have, <lb/>
as they were bound to do, given these appeals their <lb/>
most serious consideration; but afer we'ghing well <lb/>
the arguments brought forward, and studying with <lb/>
much care the results of their own mortality,they have <lb/>
come to the conclusion that they have not sufficient <lb/>
data to authorise their making the proposed reduction. <lb/>
There is no doubt that other Offices are transacting <lb/>
business at lower Premiums, in many places, and <lb/>
prove formidable rivals to the Company, but that is <lb/>
not an argument taken by itself which has any influ­ <lb/>
ence with your Directors, as they are satisfied that the <lb/>
Col nial Rates, as far as present reliable knowledge <lb/>
extends, are fair and equitable. But as soon as they <lb/>
are satisfied, by the result of sound observation, that <lb/>
these rates are unduly in excess, they will promptly <lb/>
give the Assured the benefit. Small Institutions, <lb/>
making large rates of Interest on compara ively small <lb/>
sums, locally invested, and restricting their operations <lb/>
to a narrow circle, may transact business on lower <lb/>
Rates, trusting to the fortunate continuance of such <lb/>
results during the lives of the Assured, but with these <lb/>
Institutions the lyirectors do not place themselves in <lb/>
petiti They have their local advantages, and <lb/>
may be preferred by those more especially who can <lb/>
take part in their management and watch over their <lb/>
local proceedings. But in the case of any one who <lb/>
looks forward with prudent anxiety to the future, long <lb/>
deferred as the lifetime of an individual may be, the <lb/>
Uolonial seek a preference as standing on a wider <lb/>
basis, their character and position being as well known <lb/>
and recognised in every British Colony as in Edin­ <lb/>
burgh, London, or Dullin. <lb/>
In coming to the resolution not to reduce Rates, <lb/>
the Directors have proceeded on the advice of their <lb/>
Actuary, and the Investigation into the Company's <lb/>
Mortality has been the basis of that resolution... It <lb/>
would be prematura to publish these curious and in­ <lb/>
structive results, as the Directºrs are anxious to add <lb/>
to their experience before giving them to the world, <lb/>
but it may be st.ted that the proportion which the <lb/>
actual nuclber of Deaths bore to the expected number <lb/>
had increased very consideratly during the period of <lb/>
five years from 1859 to 1864, beyond that exhibited <lb/>
during the periºd of thirteen years from 1846 to 1859 <lb/>
—in Great Britain, in America, in the East Indies <lb/>
(civil life.) in Ceylon, and in the West Indies—shcw­ <lb/>
ing that the Mortality increases rela ively in a greater <lb/>
degree as a Company advances in age,' that is to say, <lb/>
the Mortality among lives which have been conn cted <lb/>
with the Company for ten, fifteen, or twenty years. <lb/>
will be increasingly greater than among lives of the <lb/>
same age in the first five years of their connection with <lb/></p> 

<p>the Company or otherwise, that the mortality among <lb/></p> 

<p>tively, after joining the Institution, will have gradual­ <lb/>
ly increased, affºrding less favourable results as we <lb/>
recede from the period at which the lives were ac­ <lb/>
cepted, <lb/>
It is on these grounds that the Directors have de­ <lb/>
clined tº reduce their Rates. These Rates were <lb/>
originally adopted after much study and much inquiry. <lb/>
No Institution has had access to better sources of <lb/>
information than the Colonial, and the Directors have <lb/>
determined not to run any hazard for the purpose of <lb/>
popularity or to swell their amount of business. <lb/>
These are the results of the Investigation, and the <lb/></p> 

<p>Directors hope they may now return to the chord first <lb/></p> 

<p>struck as the key-note of their Report, and repeat their <lb/></p> 

<p>congratulations on the success which has attended the <lb/></p> 

<p>Uompany's operations during the last five years, as <lb/></p> 

<p>well as during the whole period of the Company's <lb/>
existences <lb/></p> 

<p>By Order of the Directors, <lb/>
WILL. TúOS. THOMSON, <lb/></p> 

<p>- Actuary. <lb/>
D, CLUNIE GREGOR, <lb/>
Secretary, <lb/>
Edinburgh, 15th December, 1864. <lb/></p> 

<p>NEW FOUND LAND. <lb/>
HEAD OFFICE, ST, JOHN'S. <lb/>
L. O'Brien, Esq., Merchant I Wm. Hegry Mare, Esq. <lb/>
Augustus W. Harvey, Esq., Mershant. <lb/>
Medical Adviser—Henry Hunt Stabb, M. D. <lb/>
Agent, F. J. WYATT. <lb/>
February 24. <lb/></p> 

<p>SPECIAL INTIMATION. <lb/></p> 

<p>The BENEFITs of Life Assurance with tº <lb/>
SMALLEST OUTLAY, <lb/>
combined with the FULLEST SECURITY. <lb/></p> 

<p>This desirable object has been attained by the Policy­ <lb/>
holders of the <lb/></p> 

<p>Life.Association of Scotland <lb/></p> 

<p>By means of its Allocation of Profit in Cash towards <lb/>
the Annual Reduction of the Premiums payable for the <lb/>
Policies, the older Policy-holders paying at present <lb/>
only 12s. 6d. (instead of 20s.) per £1 of the Premiums; <lb/>
and by the following <lb/>
REGULATION FOR FURTHER DIMINISHING <lb/>
OUTLAY FOR LIFE ASSURANCE. <lb/>
Until the time when the premiums may be expected <lb/>
to be reduced by the application of profits, the Assured <lb/>
for £500 or upwards, may leave unpaid a considerable <lb/>
portion (one-third or one-fourth) of the premiums re­ <lb/>
cessary to keep the policy in force. The unpaid part <lb/>
is allowed to remain in the hands of the Assured as <lb/>
long as he pleases, and he is not asked to pay interest <lb/>
thereon; but the amount, with accumulated interest, <lb/>
will be deducted from the sum assured at death, New <lb/>
Entrants thus at once commence with <lb/>
PAYMEN IS MUCH BELOW THE TABULAR <lb/>
RATES, <lb/>
and continue to make such reduced payments for six <lb/>
years, when they become entitled to reduction of the <lb/>
premiums by the application of Profits. They will, <lb/>
nevertheless, receive the same benefits and the same <lb/>
share of profit, as if the full premiums had been paid. <lb/>
Pr. sent outlay is also further diminished by means of <lb/>
the Association's <lb/>
INCREASING POLICIES <lb/></p> 

<p>n which the sums Assured shall increase by the meret <lb/>
lapse of time to double the original amount, withou <lb/>
corresponding increase of premium i, and, under the <lb/>
Participating Class, the premiums will be reducible by <lb/>
application of Profits. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Policies do Not Contain several of the Res­ <lb/>
TRIOTIons commonly imposed on Assured Lives, and <lb/>
conter on the Policy-holders unusual and important <lb/>
facilities and privileges. <lb/>
fºr ENTRANTs on or before 5TH APRIL <lb/>
will secure a decided advantage over later Entrants <lb/>
at the Division of brofit. <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>NEWFO UN HyLAND BRANCH. <lb/></p> 

<p>HEAL) () FFICE.-ST. JOHN'S. <lb/>
DIRECTORS: <lb/>
H, K. Dickinson, Esq. Hon. James Cormack. <lb/>
obert Grieve, Esq. <lb/>
Agent and Secretary.....................E. L. JARWIS. <lb/>
St. John's, 27th Feb., 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>NEW ARRIVALS 1 <lb/>
Per Glance, <lb/></p> 

<p>American l'arlor Gothic GRATES, <lb/></p> 

<p>Which will be sold cheap for cash. <lb/></p> 

<p>GEO. GEAR. <lb/>
L169 &amp; 349 WATER-STREET.] <lb/>
(2 wks.) <lb/></p> 

<p>Feb. 27. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Subscriber <lb/></p> 

<p>Having bewn appointed Agent for the sale of <lb/>
Chilson's Ranges, <lb/></p> 

<p>Samples of the same can be seen at his Establishment, <lb/>
349 Water-Street. <lb/>
GEO. GEAR. <lb/></p> 

<p>Feb. 27. <lb/>
Athenæuth Lectures. <lb/></p> 

<p>rivKHE Annual Course of Lectures at this Institute <lb/>
will ſommence on MONDAY the 16th January, a. <lb/>
the Temperance Hali. <lb/>
March 6—Henry H. Stahb, Esq., M D —Subject <lb/>
—A 'pect of Life—European and Coloniut <lb/>
March13–Rev. D. McRae—Subject–Tennyson. <lb/>
March 20–Rev.J.Phelps—"Realings from Merchan <lb/>
of Veiivce <lb/>
March 27—Rev. John Maze–Subj-ct <lb/>
Othere will be announced in due course. Fech <lb/>
Lecture will commence at 8 o'clock,-Doors open at <lb/>
quarter past Seven. <lb/>
Season Ticket to admit two............5 s. 6d. <lb/>
S ason Ticket to admit one............23. 6;. <lb/>
Admission to single Lecture............U. 6d. <lb/>
Tickets for the course will be furnished to Members <lb/>
of the insulute on payment of their Subscription. <lb/>
D. W. PROWSE, <lb/></p> 

<p>Secretary. <lb/></p> 

<p>(3m.) <lb/></p> 

<p>January 5. <lb/></p> 

<p>164 Barrels <lb/>
New Prime PORK, <lb/></p> 

<p>per "Era," Just recived i y <lb/></p> 

<p>P &amp; T. HEARx. <lb/>
Jan. 26 <lb/></p> 

<p>- - -<lb break="maybe"/>-\- t <lb/></p> 

<p>ºil. <lb/>
| <lb/>
i. <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>* <lb/></p> 

<p>º: <lb/>
. <lb/></p> 

<p>f <lb/>
&amp; <lb/>
<lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>-º <lb/>
: <lb/>
º <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/>
: <lb/></p> 

<p>* <lb/>
º <lb/></p> 

<p>* <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/></p> 

<p>-\-5, <lb/>
*: <lb/></p> 

<p>§: <lb/></p> 

<p>* <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/>
#.º <lb/></p> 

<p># <lb/>
<lb break="no"/>.. <lb/></p> 

<p># <lb/></p> 

<p>&amp; <lb/>
&gt; <lb/>
sºy <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-09_Page_2.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
<fw type="num">2</fw> <div type="section"> <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head> <p rendition="simple:right">Monday, Feb. 13–<hi rendition="simple:italic">Continued</hi>.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SHEA2">SHEA</persName> - What new matter was that which we <lb/>
had now from the Commercial body? That was not <lb/>
the petition which was on the table of the Commercial <lb/>
Room on Saturday. The petition, however, was a <lb/>
very proper one, as were the hon gentleman's obser<lb break="no"/>vations also. But notwithstanding it was a class pe<lb break="no"/>tition to conserve their own interests. But he might <lb/>
ask whether the interests of the merchants were iden<lb break="no"/>tical with those of the people at large in this matter <lb/>
Their object was to amass as speedily as possible the <lb/>
means to leave the country and live elsewhere. If <lb/>
they had had thefr wish there would not have been a <lb/>
mile of road in the colony. They objected to all tax<lb break="no"/>ation, Was this the first time they petitioned the <lb/>
house? Did we not find that Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was opposed by the commercial body, and that <lb/>
some of them left the country on account of its being <lb/>
introduced? They had suddenly become free traders. <lb/>
If they had their own way the colony would not have <lb/>
had representative institutions to this day. When free <lb/>
trade with the United States was proposed, it had not <lb/>
more determined opponents than the commercial <lb/>
body. The petitioners were very respectable men. <lb/>
He admitted their respectability, but he must repeat <lb/>
that was a class petition. The petition stated that <lb/>
Canada pursued a protective policy—so did the United <lb/>
States. It said we would benefit by a free trade po<lb break="no"/>licy. He (Mr. Shea) agreed with the petitioners. <lb/>
But when free trade was proposed none were more vio<lb break="no"/>lently opposed to it than the petitioners. They <lb/>
seemed now to have an extraordinary fit of alarm. <lb/>
Who told them, or any person else that the question <lb/>
of confederation would be forced through this session? <lb/>
Not a single word was uttered since the commence<lb break="no"/>ment of the session by any supporter of confederation <lb/>
to show that there was <lb/>
through the house. There was nothing he (Mr. S.) <lb/>
would deprecate more than to force the matter without <lb/>
affording full time for its consideration. If there had <lb/>
been a general concurrence of opininion on the ques<lb break="no"/>tion in the house and throughout the country, and if <lb/>
the neighbonring colonies had proceeded with it, it <lb/>
would have been perfectly legitimate to dispose of the <lb/>
matter this session. But in the divided state of pub<lb break="no"/>lic opinion such a course was never thought of. These <lb/>
gentlemen were unnecessarily alarmed. He did say <lb/>
that the supporters of confederation in the house were <lb/>
too deeply impressed with a sense of their responsibi<lb break="no"/>lity, and the duty which they owed to the country, to <lb/>
press the matter hastily. They knew that however <lb/>
successful it might prove, those who took an active <lb/>
part in carrying a measure of that kind would get <lb/>
very little thanks for it, while they would be subject<lb break="no"/>ed to blame by all who might be disappointed. The <lb/>
hon member said the recommendation from the Cham<lb break="no"/>ber of Commerce was not attended to when they sug<lb break="no"/>gested that the Customs' duties should be made pay<lb break="no"/>able in cash. And the government were right in nct <lb/>
attending to them. He said it was an attempt on the <lb/>
part of the men of wealth to crush the middleman. <lb/>
Customs' bonds had been in use for over thirty years, <lb/>
and until a recent case no loss was sustained by the <lb/>
revenue through them. It was a legitimate case for <lb/>
that house to interfere to sustain the industrious man <lb/>
of good character and limited means. Some persons <lb/>
had signed two petitions on that subject, one for and <lb/>
one against the payment of the duties in cash. The <lb/>
subject would probably come up again, and we would <lb/>
then have an opportunity of discussing the benefit to <lb/>
the rising importers by the present system. It would <lb/>
appear that the petitioners had already made up their <lb/>
minds on the question of faderation, that it would <lb/>
ruin the country. It was not the introduction of Ca<lb break="no"/>nadian capital in our trade, or the active competition <lb/>
of Canadian merchants and traders that alarmed them. <lb/>
The hon member who presented the petition said <lb/>
they had applied to the government for information. <lb/>
But he (Mr. Shea) did not see what right these gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen, however respectable, had to information from <lb/>
the government beyond other parties. The Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture were the only parties entitled to priority of infor<lb break="no"/>mation. The prayer of the petition, however, could <lb/>
easily be complied with. Delay was the proper <lb/>
course under existing circumstances,with the opinions <lb/>
of the people throughout the country, as well as in <lb/>
the Legislature, so much divided, it would be most <lb/>
improper and unjust to press the question to a deci<lb break="no"/>sion. That was a conclusion which would have been <lb/>
arrived at if that petition had not been presented.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:MARC3">Mr. MARCH</persName>.-You might search all over the <lb/>
world without finding men occupying a leading posi<lb break="no"/>tion having so much property involved as the mer<lb break="no"/>chants of Newfoundland, highly educated and <lb/>
with a perfect knowledge of our trade and resources. <lb/>
Last Saturday he witnessed what he never before had <lb/>
observed in his life, high and low mixed together to <lb/>
consider this great question. He thought, when men <lb/>
had sustained such heavy losses as our merchants had <lb/>
suffered last year and some years preceding they were <lb/>
entitled to much credit for the way in which they had <lb/>
acted towards the planters and fishermen. He would <lb/>
say now, as he had frequently said before, that there <lb/>
were no men in the world moie liberal in giving away <lb/>
their substance to fustain the fishermen and trada of <lb/>
the country. And were these the men to he sneered <lb/>
at when they came to this house with such a reasona<lb break="no"/>ble petition on that important question? The hon. <lb/>
member said they went away when they realised for<lb break="no"/>tunes. But if they did, did they not leave their re<lb break="no"/>presentatives behind them? The house he (Mr. March) <lb/>
had been connected with for years, had £180,000 <lb/>
afloat last year, and he need not say that they sus<lb break="no"/>tained a loss by the year's business. And the fisher­ <lb/>
men bad come to understand who were their friends, <lb/>
and who eame forward to sustain them. Who would <lb/>
give the supplies a few weeks hence,for the seal fishery? <lb/>
He trusted in Proaidvince smiling on the energies of <lb/>
the hardy men who were proceeding to the ice; and <lb/>
if they were successful,they would bring in abundance. <lb/>
The hon member said he would give time for the con<lb break="no"/>sideration of that question. But if he could have car<lb break="no"/>ried if he would have pressed it througe the house. <lb/>
But he now found that public opinion was excited <lb/>
aganst him, and therefore he said its decision ought <lb/>
to be postponed until next year. But, were these his <lb/>
sentiments from the first? He (Mr March) said nothing <lb/>
should be done hastily until the people had time <lb/>
to consider it. That was a solemn momentous ques<lb break="no"/>tion, and be felt grateful that that petition had come <lb/>
in. There never was a better feeling than now be<lb break="no"/>tween the several classes of the community. The <lb/>
fishermen could not exist without the merchants, and <lb/>
the laerchants' profits were 1ealized from the labour <lb/>
of the fishermen, and both seemed to be more con<lb break="no"/>vinced of their mutual degendauce than at any former <lb/>
period.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA2">Mr. SHEA</persName>—The hon member has made a mistate<lb break="no"/>ment which he (Mr. Shea) would not allow to pass <lb/>
uncontradicted. Who authorised aim to say that if <lb/>
he (Mr. Shea) had his way the measure would be <lb/>
passed this season?</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:MARC3">Mr. MARCH</persName>-Yourself. You said you would dis­ <lb/>
pose of it, and if your constituents did not like it,they <lb/>
might reject you at the hustings.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA2">Mr SHEA</persName>—The hon member did not understand the <lb/>
question. He (Mr Shea) felt the responsibility of the <lb/>
question too much to do anything of the kind. From <lb/>
the very first he said it was too serious a question to be <lb/>
        

<cb/>
        
        disposed of without due consideration, and that he did <lb/>
not desire that it should be carried by a narrow majority. <lb/>
What he said was that these were his opinions on the <lb/>
question, and if his constituents did not like these opin<lb break="no"/>ions they must choose a representative whose opinions <lb/>
they approved, not that he would carry it without con<lb break="no"/>sulting them. He (Mr Shea) would state his opinions <lb/>
when he went before them, fairly and openly, and <lb/>
would submit himself to their vote; but his opinions <lb/>
were his own. He did not blame the merchants for <lb/>
leaving the country; but he did say that their interests <lb/>
were not identical with those of the people of this coun<lb break="no"/>try, who intended to remain in it and make it the home <lb/>
of their children. He regretted the merchants did not <lb/>
remain permanently, and direct their attention to those <lb/>
improvements which occupied the attention of merchants <lb/>
in other places. That question must be settled by those <lb/>
who were able to instruct the people on its merits. A great <lb/>
question like that, requiring cool and careful investi<lb break="no"/>gation, was not to be disposed of by clamour. It <lb/>
should be approached calmly and carefully. The best <lb/>
minds and clearest intellects in the country were re<lb break="no"/>quired to elucidate it.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:WHIT6">Mr. WHITEWAY</persName>—This question of confederation <lb/>
had worked wonders. On every occasion heretofore, <lb/>
the hon member Mr March strongly advocated the <lb/>
rights of the fishermen, and now for the first time in <lb/>
his life he appears as the apologist of the merchants. <lb/>
Such a course however was unnecessary, for nothing <lb/>
had been said that he (Mr W) was aware of, disres<lb break="no"/>pectful to that body. The hon gentleman had said that <lb/>
this great and important question ought not to be in<lb break="no"/>fluenced by clamour. But he (Mr W) believed that it <lb/>
was the clamour of that hon member and others like <lb/>
him which had induced the commercial body to send <lb/>
that petition to this house, hon members had gone forth <lb/>
and made the grossest misrepresentation of what had <lb/>
been stated here. He (Mr W) never heard the hon. <lb/>
member for Placentia and St. Mary's, Mr. Shea, say <lb/>
that he would force this matter through this session. <lb/>
Such a course he believed was never contemplated. <lb/>
The question was entirely new to this country. It had <lb/>
been under the consideration of the other colonies for <lb/>
years past, but we had never interested ourselves in it, <lb/>
and until the past autumn the question had never been <lb/>
submitted to us. It was only ſately that we acquired <lb/>
any satisfactory information on the subject. The peti<lb break="no"/>tion just presented to the House was entitled to all the <lb/>
consideration which the hon member, Mr Wyatt, asked <lb/>
for it. And he (Mr W) felt convinced that every pe<lb break="no"/>tition, no matter from whom it emanated, would always <lb/>
meet with due consideration in that assembly. But <lb/>
this was avowedly a class petition, and as such should <lb/>
be cautiously dealt with, for unfortunately the gentle<lb break="no"/>men who had signed this petition were apt to change <lb/>
their opinions, and in support of what he stated, he <lb/>
(Mr W) had merely to refer to the action of the Com<lb break="no"/>mercial Society in 1863, when they passed a resolution <lb/>
as to advisability of paying all duties in cash and doing <lb/>
away with the Bond system. The resolution which was <lb/>
sent to the hon Receiver General was as follows:–</p>
    
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>"That it is advisable, and recommended by this So­ <lb/>
ciety, that, in future, all duties be paid in cash, and <lb/>
that H. M. Government be informed of this Resolution, <lb/>
in order to take any steps they may think advisable <lb/>
thereon." </p></quote>
    
    <p>
Shortly after this resolution was received by the Re<lb break="no"/>ceiver General, a petition, which he (Mr. W) would <lb/>
read, was addressed to his Excellency the Governor in <lb/>
Council, as follows:— </p>
    
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>
"We, the undersigned Merchants and Importers of <lb/>
St. John's, having been given to understand that the <lb/>
Commercial Society have passed the following Resolu­ <lb/>
tion, viz: </p>
        
        <p>
"That it is the opinion of the Commercial body that <lb/>
all duties should be payable in cash, with the view of <lb/>
its being sent to the Executive for action thereon, beg <lb/>
leave to express our dissent therefrom. </p>
        
        <p>
"By allowing importers to give Bond for Duties <lb/>
amounting to over £40 sterling (which formerly was <lb/>
£25) is a great accommodation to the trade, and con<lb break="no"/>siderable advantage to the revenue, as in case all duties <lb/>
were made payable in cash, the outports, with the ex<lb break="no"/>ception of Harbour Grace (and this is a great consid<lb break="no"/>eration) could not possibly pay their duties in cash.</p>
        
        <p>
"We, therefore, humbly submit these our opinions, <lb/>
and trust that as the revenue has not hitherto (so far <lb/>
as we know) sustained any loss from the manner in <lb/>
which duties have been paid, according to law, there <lb/>
will be no alteration made, unless, on a full investiga<lb break="no"/>tion, it be found advantageous to the country gen<lb break="no"/>erally." </p>
        
    </quote>
    
    <p>
This petition was signed by Messrs. Job, Brothers &amp; <lb/>
Co., and by fifty other importers, and was sufficient to <lb/>
show that unanimity did not prevail amongst the mer<lb break="no"/>cantile community upon public questions, any more <lb/>
than in other quarters. Now this petition was present<lb break="no"/>ed to the Legislature, praying for the continuance of <lb/>
the Bond system, and was actually signed by men who <lb/>
had voted for the resolution, and who were members <lb/>
of the Commercial Society. When he (Mr W) saw <lb/>
that only two years ago these gentlemen changed their <lb/>
opinions in so short a time as two days, this House <lb/>
should certainly pause, and not hastily act according to <lb/>
the prayer of that petition. It might be that in a day <lb/>
or two we should have another petition from the same <lb/>
gentlemen with a prayer in favor of confederation. <lb/>
They say that all the country wants is time, and that in <lb/>
the abstract they were in favor of it. But was it right <lb/>
to set up class against class in this matter? Was it all <lb/>
pure philanthropy that animates these gentlemen "to <lb/>
scatter their supplies of hard cash,"—to use the lan<lb break="no"/>guage of Mr March? Did they not hope for an ample <lb/>
return for the capital which they had invested here in <lb/>
trade? He wondered that the hon member, Mr March <lb/>
who was so fond of quoting Scripture had forgotten the <lb/>
text applicable in this case, that he did not exclaim, <lb/>
"Does Job serve God for naught?" Did the merchants <lb/>
expest no return? He (Mr W) always understood <lb/>
that no action of a definite nature was to be taken on <lb/>
this question this session. There was never an inten<lb break="no"/>tion of forcing it. Therefore this petition was unneces<lb break="no"/>sary and uncalled for, as it only prayed for what the <lb/>
house had determined on long ago.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName> was glad to hear the assertion of the hon <lb/>
member, Mr Whiteway, that there was no intention of <lb/>
forcing this question. But this change had been effected <lb/>
by the voice of public opinion, and by the stand which <lb/>
he (Mr Glen) and his hon colleagues had taken in the <lb/>
matter. It was their intention to have forced it; and <lb/>
that was the opinion which he (Mr Glen) held in com<lb break="no"/>mon with every right thinking man in the community. <lb/>
When they found that it would have been impossible to <lb/>
carry it, they tried a measure which was very nearly <lb/>
successful. They said you are only required to affirm <lb/>
the principle, and we will go to the country on it. That <lb/>
desire had been persisted in until last Friday. He (Mr <lb/>
Glen) considered that it was necessary that they should <lb/>
be carefully and vigilantly watched yet. He had asked <lb/>
the hon Attorney General for a copy of his resolution <lb/>
a fortnight ago. Why had it not been laid before the <lb/>
house? It was not treating this house with proper re<lb break="no"/>spect, and tended to a continuance of that alarm which <lb/>
existed in the public mind. The hon member, Mr Kent, <lb/>
when Premier, always had his resolutions before the <lb/>
House in ample time to discuss then. The only object <lb/>
which he (Mr Glen) had in opposing the matter was <lb/>
that he did not wish it to be decided until they went to <lb/>
the country.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KENT1">Mr. KENT</persName> said that when the question of Confede<lb break="no"/>ration had first come before the house, he had ex<lb break="no"/>pressed his opinion in favor of it, but he had at the <lb/>
same time stated that rothing should be done without <lb/>
submitting it at first to the people. He was of that <lb/>
opinion stil. The Merchants had an undoubted con<lb break="no"/>stitutional right to petition this House, and when it <lb/>
was considered how respectably that petition was <lb/>
signed, he felt that it would receive every considera<lb break="no"/>tion to which it was entitled. It was a petition which <lb/>
would have no weight with the country at large. He <lb/>
thought that the condition of the people of this coun<lb break="no"/>try was very similar to that of Ireland; both countries <lb/>
had but one branch of industry to rely upon. In Ire<lb break="no"/>land Agriculture was the staple industry, and the <lb/>
people had to contend against the landlords, who <lb/>
were the most powerful and influential class. Here <lb/>
we were limitted to the fisheries. The merchants pos<lb break="no"/>sessed the capital, and could make what terms with <lb/>
the people they liked. If we could call up other <lb/>
pursuits to relieve our fisheries, we could create <lb/>
sources of employment which would render our ope<lb break="no"/>rative population independent of the fisheries, and the <lb/>
consequence would be an increased measure of mate<lb break="no"/>rial prosperity. Whether Confederation would da <lb/>
this or not, he (Mr. Kent) was not prepared to say. <lb/>
It was entirely for the consideration of the people.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:RORK1">Mr RORKE</persName> was not in the House when this discus<lb break="no"/>sion began, but he had seen the petition and consider<lb break="no"/>ed it was a very reasonable one. It was a most mo­ <lb/>
mentous question, although it should have been di<lb break="no"/>vested of all the acerbity which characterises political <lb/>
movements. He was sorry that that had not been al<lb break="no"/>together the case. He was not aware that it was the <lb/>
intention of the Government to have forced this mat<lb break="no"/>ter through this session. He was surprised to find <lb/>
hon gentlemen opposite changing their opinions about <lb/>
the merchants so very quicklv. They consider them <lb/>
even honest good men; well truth will out, and he <lb/>
was glad to hear such acknowledgments from them. <lb/>
He would not detain the House at present, but he <lb/>
trusted that when the mutter came to be fully and <lb/>
properly discussed, hon gentlemen would approach it <lb/>
in a calm and proper spirit.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:PROW1">Mr. PROWSE</persName>.—The petition before the House was <lb/>
undoubtedly a class petition, but it emanated from a <lb/>
class whose respectability and influence necessarily <lb/>
gave it great weight. Looking at all the circumstan<lb break="no"/>ces surrounding this question, he (Mr P) could not <lb/>
but regard that petition as premature. Taking up <lb/>
the speeches of the delegates as published, and also <lb/>
the strong expression of opinion from other hon mem<lb break="no"/>bers of this house, could not the movers of this Peti<lb break="no"/>tion see that it was not the intention of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to force this question through this house, this <lb/>
session? The assertions of hon members on this <lb/>
point could not have been stronger. The petition, he <lb/>
had no doubt, was well meant, but it was uncalled for <lb/>
and unnecessary, and there had been nothing in the <lb/>
speeches of hon members of this house, to warrant <lb/>
the alarm which appeared to be so universal amongst <lb/>
a certain class, and of which this petition had been the <lb/>
result. The hon member, Mr. March, deprecates the <lb/>
use of claptrap, and yet the hon gentleman actually <lb/>
talked of selling the country to the French Canadians. <lb/>
Could there be any viler or more obnoxious claptrap <lb/>
than that? Had not hon gentlemen stated that the <lb/>
Councilors were to receive £100) a year? Did they <lb/>
not know that to be false? Of course they did—It <lb/>
was a gross perversion of the truth, and they who <lb/>
uttered it knew they were stating what was false. Was <lb/>
not that claptrap? If men were guilty of wilful per<lb break="no"/>version of the truth, they were guily of claptrap, <lb/>
and failed in their duty to their country and to their <lb/>
constituents. He (Mr P.) had great respect for the <lb/>
petition just presented, but there was no occasion for <lb/>
it. There was no desire to press this matter on eith<lb break="no"/>er side of the house. It merely asked for what the <lb/>
Legislature had already determined on, and was <lb/>
therefore in his (Mr P's.) opinion premature.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName> could not but express his delight at <lb/>
the remarks of the hon member for Placentia and St. <lb/>
Mary's, Mr Shea, that there was no desire to press <lb/>
this matter through the house this session. However <lb/>
this side of the house owed the hon the delegates <lb/>
nothing. It was only on account of the manly stand <lb/>
taken by him (Mr. R.) and colleages that that <lb/>
had taken place, Up to Friday last, they were per<lb break="no"/>sistent in their determination to press this matter. <lb/>
What dip the refusal to give the resolution shew? <lb/>
Simply that we were to be taken by surprise, and <lb/>
this matter forced upon us. Now what a wonderful <lb/>
change had come over these gentlemen. They found <lb/>
that by dodging, they could not carry this question, <lb/>
and new with an assumed magnanimity they assure <lb/>
this house. that they never had any desire to press <lb/>
this question, or even have the principle affirmed by <lb/>
a mere majority. The action which we had taken in <lb/>
this matter was precisely the same which hon members <lb/>
in the other colonies had pursued. He thought that <lb/>
the petition before the house was a very respectable <lb/>
one. Every man had a right to petition this house, <lb/>
whether he were a prince or beggar. This petition <lb/>
dictated no terms, it merely asked for time to give it <lb/>
proper consideration. Was that an unreasonable <lb/>
request? Certainly not. He (Mr R.) was not in the <lb/>
house when this petition was presented, but he had <lb/>
heard the observations which the hon member, Mr. <lb/>
Shea, had made upon it, and he thought them most <lb/>
insulting and irrelevant to the subject before the <lb/>
house. He (Mr. R.) had the highest respect for the <lb/>
merchants who embarked their capital in the trade of <lb/>
the country, thus giving employment to the operative <lb/>
population. Could the Canadian merchants do more <lb/>
for us than our own did at present? He (Mr. Renouf) <lb/>
doubted whether they could afford us any benefit <lb/>
whatever. Capital and labour went hand in hand; <lb/>
and would we not rather see twelve mercantile houses <lb/>
rise in commercial prosperity than one should fall?<lb/>
Was it not a well known fact, that Mr. Walter Grieve <lb/>
had lost more than £20,000 during the last two years; <lb/>
was it not impossible for us to live without the mer<lb break="no"/>chants? He (Mr Renouf) was glad that this House <lb/>
had determined that this question of Confederation <lb/>
should be settled by the people. He considered that <lb/>
they were the proper persons to deal with it, and, <lb/>
therefore, could not endorse the opinion of Mr Prowse, <lb/>
that they were too wooden-headed to understand it. <lb/>
All that we contended for was that we had not the <lb/>
power delegated to us to definitively settle this mat<lb break="no"/>ter without appealing to the peºple, Will hon gen<lb break="no"/>tleman guarantee to us that they will not take a vote <lb/>
in this matter? If so the country would be perfectly <lb/>
satisfied. Then we would be able to believe them. <lb/>
We would have to watch them carefully still. </p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName> could not agree with hon members <lb/>
when they said that this petition was premature. The <lb/>
Commercial Society had good reason to believe that <lb/>
it was the intention of hon members to press the mat<lb break="no"/>ter this session, and thus pledge the country. They <lb/>
had not before them at present that statistical infor<lb break="no"/>mation which was necessary to induce them to give <lb/>
their consent to any hasty legislation on the subject. <lb/>
They had before them the opinion of the hon Atty. <lb/>
General that his resolutions, if passed, would pledge <lb/>
the country, and for ever settle the subject of Confe<lb break="no"/>deration. He thought that they had a perfect right <lb/>
to present this petition. They wished that this mat<lb break="no"/>ter should be carefully and attentively, considered, <lb/>
and that the people of the country should have ample <lb/>
time to discuss it. He did not think that the Com<lb break="no"/>mercial Society, when they asked to be furnished with <lb/>
information, and with copies of the documents re<lb break="no"/>ceived, had asked for anything that was unfair or im<lb break="no"/>proper. The merchants had a deeper stake in the<lb/>
        
        <cb/>

interests of the country than any member in this <lb/>
House. With reference to the statement of the hon <lb/>
member for Twillingate and Fogo, Mr. Whiteway, <lb/>
about signing double petitions, all he (Mr Wyatt) <lb/>
could say in the matter was that those who required <lb/>
it were not members of the Commercial Society.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr.Talbot</persName> supported the prayer of the petition, <lb/>
out of deference to the opinions of so respeciable a <lb/>
body of men. One would think, however, that they <lb/>
were only a preel of niggars. He did not agree with <lb/>
the eulogiums that had been passed on that body <lb/>
by so many honourable gentlemen. They were no <lb/>
doubt, a very worthy set of men, but he did not think <lb/>that they had done so much for the country, that we <lb/> 
should be alarmed and frightened by this petition,<lb/>
and hold up our hand and exclaim "oh! the Com<lb break="no"/>mercial body have petitioned the House." No one<lb/>
objected more to claptrap then he (Mr. Talbot) did<lb/>
he liked to take up every question, hold it up to the<lb/>
light, and see what was it. He did not think that <lb/>
their action in this matter was entirely for the benefit <lb/>
of the fishermen. They were the ones who reaped all <lb/>
benefit of the earnings of the fishermen. Their profits <lb/>
were immense, indeed it would be difficult to ascer<lb break="no"/>tain their limits. It was admitted, however, that they <lb/>
would not stop there if by the process of grinding, <lb/>
they could grind anything more out of them before <lb/>
they left the country to spend their money elsewhere.<lb/>
They had certainly a perfect right to do this. There <lb/>
was then no great compliment between the fishermen <lb/>
and the merchants. They certainly do not bring<lb/>
their capital to this country; a few might have done <lb/> 

so, but, as a general rule it was all made here. They <lb/>

make their money and spend it elsewhere, and leave <lb/>
the country as denuded as if a shilling had never been <lb/>
earned in it. If the merchants, after having made <lb/>
their money, settled down in this country and ex<lb break="no"/>tended their business, it would be one of the happiest <lb/>
countries in the world. Had the merchants ever es<lb break="no"/>tablished factories over the country to afford employ<lb break="no"/>ment to the people when the fisheries were over? <lb/>
No, therefore we see so much destitution and suffer<lb break="no"/>ing. He (Mr. Talbot) was opposed to confederation, <lb/>
as it was at present. He would like it if in reality it <lb/>
was confederation. He would however, like to see <lb/>
some beneficial result that would flow from it.</p>
    
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CASE2">Mr.CASEY</persName> was of opinion that the petition from the <lb/>
Commercial Society was as much entitled to respect <lb/>
as that from any other society in the country. It <lb/>
was foolish for hon gentlemen to say that the interest <lb/>
of the merchants was not the interest of the fishermen. <lb/>
Their interests were bound up together, when the one <lb/>
was successful, both were benefitted. His (Mr. <lb/>
Casey's) opinion on this matter was not altered. How<lb break="no"/>ever, he would refrain from making any observations <lb/>
upon this great question until the 15th of the month. <lb/>
He thought the petition was in very good time, and <lb/>
deserved the earnest and thoughtful consideration of <lb/>
every member of this house.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Mr. E. D. SHEA</persName>.—It was very stale common <lb/>
place to say that this petition was entitled to respect. <lb/>
It was unnecessary for non gentlemen to have taken <lb/>
so much trouble to prove what every one admitted. <lb/>
That petition was the result of misconception. It <lb/>
had been represented to the merchants and overy one <lb/>
interested in the matter that it was the determination <lb/>
of this house to pass this matter the present session. <lb/>
Had it not been universally expressed that there was <lb/> 
no such intention, so often did hon gentlemen declare <lb/>
that they did not believe it. It was of course neces<lb break="no"/>sary for them to make up a case, so that we might <lb/>
appear as traitors, and they as the saviours of the <lb/>
country.They had no other way of lifting themselves<lb/>
up into a little popularity. It was perfectly true <lb/> that the hon. Attorney General had said that if the <lb/>
resolution which he intended to prepare were passed, <lb/>
it would pledge the country. But did he not also say <lb/>
that he would place it on the table of that house for <lb/>
hon members to deal with it as they pleased. If so, <lb/>
how could it be contended that there was a desire to <lb/>
press the matter during this session? It was all very <lb/>
well for hon. gentlemen to say they disliked claptrap. <lb/>
But how could they get on without it? Did they not <lb/>
now find it very useful to serve their purposes? This <lb/>
petition only asked for what the house had already <lb/>
determined to give—ample time for the fullest enqui<lb break="no"/>ry to be had and the question thoroughly tested. If <lb/>
confederation were then adopted every one would be <lb/>
satisfied. </p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KENT1">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> wished to make a few <lb/>
observations on some remarks that had fallen from <lb/>
the hon. member for Trinity, Mr. Wyatt, to the effect <lb/>
that the Government had not treated the Commercial <lb/>
Society with that respect to which they were entitled. <lb/> The Government were only too happy at all times to <lb/>
furnish the Commercial body with any information <lb/>
that it was in their power to afford and which would <lb/>
be proper for them to give. It was the duty of the <lb/>
Government in the present matter to lay the docu<lb break="no"/>ments which it had first before the Legislature. There <lb/>
had been an application to be furnished with all docu<lb break="no"/>ments on this subject, and they were told that the <lb/>
Government at the time were possessed of none that <lb/>
were not already in the public papers. Despatches <lb/>
that were received afterwards, were with the Report <lb/>
of the Delegates, laid before the house. These docu<lb break="no"/>ments had been furnished to the Chamber of Com<lb break="no"/>merce. It was, however, only right and proper that <lb/>
the representatives of the people should have them <lb/>
first. He (hon. Attorney General) thought that the <lb/>
Commercial Society had nothirg to complain of. It <lb/>
had certainly been his intention to lay before this <lb/>
house a Resolution which, if carried, would have de<lb break="no"/>finitively settled the question, and if the other Co<lb break="no"/>lonies had entered this Confederation now, he should <lb/>
have felt bound to place the matter before the house <lb/>
this session for adoption or rejection.—Now, how<lb break="no"/>ever, there was no necessity for such a course. He <lb/>
would, however, say that in this proceeding the de<lb break="no"/>legates were in no way responsible. Entirely with him<lb break="no"/>self must that responsibility rest.</p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KAVA1">Mr. KAVANAGH</persName> presented a petition from Martin <lb/>
Kough and others of Quidi Vidi, and from Daniel <lb/>
Keeffe and others of Pouch Cove, which were several<lb break="no"/>ly received and read, praying for grants to complete <lb/>
roads in these localities.</p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that these petitions lie on the table.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName> gave notice that, on to-morrow, he <lb/>
would ask the Chairman of the Board of Works for<lb/>
copy of contracts for supplies for distressed fishermen <lb/>
emploed on the public works, also return of amount <lb/>
paid for such supplies to 31st ult.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr. TALBOT</persName> gave notice that, on to-morrow, he <lb/>
would ask the chairman of the Board of Works for for <lb/>
copies of tenders for supplying the several public <lb/>
Institution with provisions and other necessaries for <lb/>
the curent year, together with a return of the names <lb/>
of those whose tenders were accepted by the govern<lb break="no"/>ment.</p>
    
    <p>Also, that, on to-morrow, he would ask the Sur<lb break="no"/>veyor General to lay on the table of the House a <lb/>
statement of the number of acres of Crown Land <lb/>
disposed of to purchasers during the last four years, <lb/>
distinguishing the number of acres in each year, the <lb/>
electoral districts in which they are situated, the <lb/>
names of purchasers, and the quantity purchased by <lb/>
each respectively,  and the number of acres brought <lb/>
under cultivation by each purchaser; also a statement <lb/>
of the description of crops produced on these lands <lb/>
respectively, of the pecular characteristics of the soil, <lb/>
        
        

<!--<p>Jºſºn <lb/></p> 

<p>It was of course neces.; <lb/>
r <lb/>
: <lb/></p> 

<p>dorse the project of Confed. <lb/>
members composing this majorit <lb/></p> 

<p>consideration. <lb/>
good, but objected to details; an <lb/>
Pressed decided hostility to the <lb/>
are the characteristics of the two <lb/>
... position is but imperfectly underst <lb/>
"* to numbers—the compactn. <lb/>
the one side, and the pieball and <lb/>
ºther, forming material elements i <lb/></p> 

<p>ºf the people and secure their enla <lb/></p> 

<p>wº <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. J.O.H. <lb/>
THURSDAY, MARſ <lb/></p> 

<p>The long continued debate o <lb/>
-seatnytërminated on Mout. <lb/></p> 

<p>of the Attorxey General <lb/>
leaves the question open until t <lb/>
ºn it at the next election, someti <lb/>
º, Though the Resolution expres: <lb/>
question, the discussion called <lb/></p> 

<p>Assembly in explicit torms, and <lb/>
that a majority of the House (, <lb/></p> 

<p>sity of certain modifications in t <lb/></p> 

<p>. Resolutions; but the exceptions <lb/>
acter that may easily be met, a <lb/></p> 

<p>of any such difficulty as would <lb/></p> 

<p>members from the support of th <lb/></p> 

<p>as the opinion of the present II. <lb/>
clearly declared itselfin favor &amp; <lb/>
eration. <lb/>
} But when we look at the ch: <lb/></p> 

<p>- ind of the opposition the measur <lb/></p> 

<p>nouncement in its favor acquires <lb/>
The approvers of Confederation <lb/></p> 

<p>4. their opinions that it meant <lb/>
* the people, and the advance o <lb/>
ty; they spoke with the evidenc <lb/></p> 

<p>in their tone and bearing, and th <lb/></p> 

<p>on the public mind is admitted of <lb/></p> 

<p>ñents, on the other hand, were u <lb/>
tion, and for the most part only a <lb/>
Some of them <lb/></p> 

<p>*eir respective status and influe <lb/>
i Though under all the circums <lb/></p> 

<p>Parties as thus correctly described <lb/>
"ethink there can be no rationald <lb/>
ºf the Unionists will be material <lb/>
*ject again comes on for further <lb/></p> 

<p>*e. The progress the questi, <lb/></p> 

<p>betokens its growing acceptance, <lb/>
Present condition of the colony th <lb/>
Provement it holds out cannot fail <lb/></p> 

<p>! My <lb/>
No doubt our future action on <lb/>
ºpeniant in some measure on the <lb/></p> 

<p>- taken by Nova Scotia and New I. <lb/>
*sion of these Provinces is indispe <lb/>
tion of a Confederacy, and their n. <lb/>
*ntly of essential importance. <lb/></p> 

<p>"btedly, a sufficient amount of . <lb/>
* result for the present at least n <lb/>
3 the resistance of either would a <lb/>
f *omplishment of the object. <lb/>
}* all the provisions of so large <lb/>
* variety of interests can have <lb/></p> 

<p>*Husted in all its parts as not to le <lb/></p> 

<p>. *ven where the plan as a who, <lb/></p> 

<p>*ded; and from such causes h <lb/></p>
    
    
    
    <p><lb break="no"/>and of the average distance of <lb/>
        of from the sea shore, in eac <lb/>
        lso similar statements in ref <lb/>
        immediately preceding 1861. <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>Excellency the Governor, pre <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>liowing documents­ <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>t Gonsolidated statement of <lb/>
        ºf the poor for the year 1864. <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>ordered that these docume <lb/>
        should be alarmed and frightened by this petition. . . The hon Colonial, SEcBet <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>Excellency the Governor, pºt <lb/>
        tatement of the number of tri. <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>he liked to take up every question, hold it up to th: Ordered that this dºcument <lb/>
        : On motion of the hon AT1 <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>severally r-ad a third time an <lb/>
        The bill to continue the pu: <lb/>
        in certain cases. <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>alties becoming due upon upon <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>against adverse claims made u <lb/>
        interest in the subject of such <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>Whiteway take these bills to t <lb/>
        for concurrence. <lb/>
        ºf . On motion of the hon. A to <lb/>
        to order of the day, the hou <lb/>
        committee of the whole on th <lb/>
        of the bill to provide for the <lb/>
        marriages and deaths, Mr. Bar <lb/>
        ; On motion of the hon Attor <lb/>
        of the hill passed over when <lb/>
        were read seriatum and adopt <lb/>
        ments, and the cominittee rose <lb/>
        ported the bill with amendmeld <lb/>
        concurred in. Third reading <lb/>
        ; On motion of the hon Attor: <lb/>
        to order of the day, the hou <lb/>
        committee of the whole on th: <lb/>
        of the bill to make provision f <lb/>
        deserted by their husbands and <lb/>
        deserted by their children, Mir <lb/>
        . .; 0.1 m tion of the hon Att. <lb/>
        maining sections of the bill w <lb/>
        with some amendments, and t <lb/>
        the chairman reported the <lb/>
        ; which were read and concurre <lb/>
        morrow. <lb/>
        ' ' Mr. MooRE gave notice <lb/>
        would ask the hon Colonial: <lb/>
        what-aurangement had been ma <lb/>
        * for the steam packet <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>o'clock. <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>The hon Receives GENER <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>Financial Secretary's Conso <lb/>
        enditure under Rºad Aot 27 <lb/>
        Report of Cashier of Newf <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>riel to the north and west d . <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>uant to order of the day, t <lb/>
        The bill to make provision f <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>ecognisances. <lb/>
        The bilt to enable courts <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>The bill to regulate the office <lb/>
        Ordered that the hon Attu <lb/></p> 
    
    <p>ay. <lb/>
        The house then adjourned un <lb/></p> -->
    

<pb n="3" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-09_Page_3.jpg"/> 

<fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER</fw>
        
        <fw type="num">3</fw>


and of the average distance of these lands so disposed<lb/> 
    of from the sea shore, in each electoral district, and<lb/>
    also similiar statements in reference to the four years<lb/>
    immediately preceding 1861.</p>
        
        <p>
            The <persName ref="pers:BEMI1">Hon Receiver GENERAL</persName>, by command of his<lb/>
            Excellency the Governor, presented to the house the<lb/>
            following documents-</p>
        
        <p>
            Consoldiated statement of expenditure for the relief<lb/>
            of the poor for the year 1864.</p>
    
    <p>
        Financial Secretary's Consolidated Statement of ex<lb break="no"/>penditure under Road Act 27th Vic., cap. 3.</p>
    
    <p>Report of Cashier of Newfoundland Savings' Bank.</p>
        
        <p>Ordered that these documents lie on the table.</p>
        
        <p>The hon COLONIAL SECRETARY, by command of his<lb/>
            Excellency the Governor, presented to the house a<lb/>
            statement of the number of trips made by the steamer<lb/>
            <hi rendition="simple:italic">Ariel</hi> to the north and west during the past season.</p>
    
    <p>
        Ordered that this document be on the table.</p>
    
    <p>
        On motion of the <persName ref="pers:CART5">hon ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>, pur<lb break="no"/>suant to order of the day, the following Bills were<lb/>
        severally read a third time and passed-</p>
    <p>The bill to continue the punishment of banishment<lb/>
        in certain cases.</p>
    
    <p>The bill to make provision for the recovery of pen<lb break="no"/>alties becoming due upon upon the forfeiture of certain<lb/>
recognisances.</p>
    
    <p>
        The bill to enable courts of law to grant relief<lb/>
        against advers claims made upon persons having no<lb/>
        interest in the subject of such claims.</p>
    
    <p>The bill to regulate the office and duties of coroners.</p>
    
    <p>Ordered that the hon Attorney General and Mr.<lb/>
        Whiteway take these bills to the Legislative Council<lb/>
        for concurrence.</p>
    
    <p>On motion of the <persName ref="pers:CART5">hon. Attorny General</persName>, pursuant<lb/>
        to order if the day, the house resolved itself into<lb/>
        committee of the whole on the further consideration<lb/>
        of the bill to provide for the registration of births,<lb/>
        marriages and deaths, Mr. Barron in the chair.</p>
    
    <p>
        On motion of the <persName ref="pers:CART5">hon. Attorny General</persName> the sections<lb/>
        of the bill passed over when the committee last sat<lb/>
        were read <hi rendition="simple:italic">seriatum</hi> and adopted, with some amend<lb break="no"/>ments, and the committee rose and the chairman re<lb break="no"/>ported the bill with amendments, which were read and<lb/>
        concurred in. Third reading to-morrow.</p>
    
    <p>
        On the motion of the <persName ref="pers:CART5">hon. Attorny General</persName>, pursuant<lb/>
        to order of the day, the house resolved itself into<lb/>
        committee of the whole on the further consideration<lb/>
        of the bill to make provision for wives and children<lb/>
        deserted by their husbands and parents, and of parents<lb/>
        deserted by their children, Mr Wyatt in the chair.</p>


    <p>On motion of the <persName ref="pers:CART5">hon. Attorny General</persName>, the re<lb break="no"/>maining sections of the bill were read and adopted,<lb/>
        with some amendments, and the committee rose and<lb/>
        the chairman reported the bill with amendments,<lb/>
        which were read and concurred in. Third reading to-<lb break="yes"/>morrow.</p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:MOOR3">Mr. MOORE</persName> gave notice that on to-morrow he<lb/>
        would ask the hon Colonial Secretary, if any, and<lb/>
        what arrangement had been made to provide a suitable<lb/>
        teamer for the steam packet service in Conception<lb/>
        Bay.</p>
    
    <p>The house then adjourned until to-morrow at three<lb/>
        o'clock.</p>
    
        

<!--<p>ngate and Fogo, Mr. Whiteway, <lb/>
"la petitions, all he (Mr Wyatt; <lb/>
atter w is that those who required <lb/>
rs of the Commercial Society. <lb/>
ported the prayer of the petition, <lb/>
the opinions of so respeciable a <lb/>
a would think, however, that they <lb/>
of niggars. He did not agree with <lb/>
it had been passed on that body <lb/>
irable gentlemen. They were no <lb/>
by set of men, but he did not think <lb/>
so m ich for the country, that we <lb/>
and frightened by this petition, <lb/>
nd and exclaim " oh! the Com­ <lb/>
petitioned the House." No one <lb/>
ºptrap then he (Mr.Talbot) did; <lb/>
every question, holi it up to the <lb/>
t was it. He did not think that <lb/>
s matter was entirely for the benefit <lb/>
They were the ones who reaped all <lb/>
gº of the fishermen. Their profits <lb/>
sed it would be difficult to ascer­ <lb/>
was admitted, however, that ther <lb/>
are if by the process of grinding, <lb/>
ything more out of them before <lb/>
y to spend their money elsewhere. <lb/>
a perfect right to do this. Tners <lb/>
oupliment between the fishermen <lb/>
They certainly do not bring <lb/>
ountry; a few might have dons <lb/>
rule it was all made here. They <lb/>
nd spend it elsewners, and leave <lb/>
.ded as if a shilling had never been <lb/>
merchants, aſter having made <lb/>
ed down in this country and ex­ <lb/>
s, it would be one of the happiest <lb/>
ºld. Had the merchants ever es­ <lb/>
ver the country to afford employ­ <lb/>
when the fisheries were over? <lb/>
•e so much destitution and suffer­ <lb/>
, , ) was opposed to confederation, <lb/>
He would like it if in reality it <lb/>
He would however, like to see <lb/>
it that would flow from it. <lb/>
opinion that the petition from the <lb/>
was as much entitled to respect <lb/>
her society in the country. It <lb/>
gentlemen to say that the interest <lb/>
not the interest of the fishermen. <lb/>
bound up together, when the one <lb/>
h were benefit.e J. His (M'. <lb/>
this matter was not altered. How­ <lb/>
in from making any observations <lb/>
tion unil the 15th of the month. <lb/>
tion was in very good time, and <lb/>
and thoughtful consideration of <lb/>
3 house. <lb/>
.A.—It was very stale common <lb/>
petition was entitled to respect. <lb/>
tor non gentlemen to have taken <lb/>
prove what every one admitted. <lb/>
he result of misconception. It <lb/>
I to the m-rchants and every one <lb/>
ter that it was the deterinitiation <lb/>
this matter the present session. <lb/>
wersally expressed that there was <lb/>
as otten as we declared there was <lb/>
often did hon gentlemen declare <lb/>
-lieve it. It was of course neces. <lb/>
ke up a case, so that we might <lb/>
and they as the saviours of the <lb/>
other way of lifting themselves <lb/>
pularity. xu was ºwn secuy, ºw­ <lb/>
ey Gºneral hul said that if th: <lb/>
intended to prepare were passed, <lb/>
country. But did he not also say <lb/>
it on the table of that house for <lb/>
il with it as they pleased. If so, <lb/>
tended that there was a desire to <lb/>
ing this session?. It was all very <lb/>
men to say they disliked claptrap. <lb/>
get on without it? Did they not <lb/>
ful to serve their purposes 9 this <lb/>
for what the house had already <lb/>
ample time for the fullest enqui­ <lb/>
e question thoroughly tested. If <lb/>
hen adopted every one would be <lb/></p> 

<p>ENERAL wished to make a few <lb/>
e remarks that had fallet, from <lb/>
Trinity, Mr. Wyatt, to the effect <lb/>
had not treated tha Commercis I <lb/>
yect to which they were entitled. <lb/>
e only too happy at all times to <lb/>
rcial body witu any information <lb/>
ower to afford and which would <lb/>
to give. It was the Juty of the <lb/>
present matter to lay the dºcu­ <lb/>
rst before the Leglelature. There <lb/>
bn to be furnished with all docu­ <lb/>
rt, and they were told that the <lb/>
me were possessed of none that <lb/>
the public pipers. Despatches <lb/>
terwards, were with the Report <lb/>
before the house. These docu­ <lb/>
nished to the Chamber of Com­ <lb/>
ºver, only right and proper that <lb/>
ºf the people should have them <lb/>
»rney General) thought that the <lb/>
ad nothurg to complain of. It <lb/>
is intention to lay before this <lb/>
nich, if carried, would have de­ <lb/>
question, and if the other Co­ <lb/>
is Confederation now, he shouli <lb/>
ice the matter before the house <lb/>
tion or rejection.—Now, how­ <lb/>
e 'essity for such a course. He <lb/>
that in this proceeding the de­ <lb/>
, responsible. Entirely with him­ <lb/>
ability rest. <lb/>
-titiºn lie on the table. <lb/>
resented a petition from Martin <lb/>
Quidi Wldi, and from Daniel <lb/>
'ouch Cove, which were several­ <lb/>
praying for grauts to complete <lb/>
t's. <lb/></p> 

<p>petitions lie on the table. <lb/>
notice that, on to morrow, be <lb/>
an of the Board of Works for a <lb/>
Fupplies for distressed fishermen <lb/>
c works, also return of amount <lb/>
to 3ist ult. <lb/>
notice that, on to-morrow, he <lb/>
man of the Board of Works for <lb/>
supplying the several public <lb/>
sions and other necessaries for <lb/>
ther with a returu of the names <lb/>
| were accepted by the govern­ <lb/></p> 

<p>morrow, he would ask the Sur­ <lb/>
on the table of the Huu.e. a <lb/>
mber of acres of Crown Land <lb/>
sers during the last four years, <lb/>
nber of acres in each year, the <lb/>
which they are situated, the <lb/>
and the quantity purchased by <lb/>
1 the number of acres brought <lb/>
**ch purchaser; also a statement <lb/>
crops produced on these lands <lb/>
ular characteristics of the soil, <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>jo similar statements in reference to the four years <lb/>
immediately preceding 1861. <lb break="no"/>*... non Réceives Gesekat, by command of his <lb/>
Excellency the Governor, presented to the house the <lb/>
fºllowing documentº- - -<lb break="maybe"/>{jidated statement of expenditure for the relief <lb/>
of the poor for the year 1864. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Financial Secretary's Consolidated Statement of ex­ <lb/>
náture under Rºad Aºi 27th Vic...ca9. 3. <lb/>
Report of Cashier of Newfºundland Savings' Bank. <lb/>
Ordered that these documents lie on the table. <lb/>
º, hon Colonial SecBetaby, by command of his <lb/>
Excellency the Governºr, presented to the house a <lb/>
ºatement of the nºimber of trips made by the steamer <lb/></p> 

<p>pº <lb/></p> 

<p>Ariel to the north and west daring the past season. <lb/></p> 

<p>Özdered that this document lie on the table. <lb/>
on motion of the hon, ATTobsºy GENERAL, pur­ <lb/>
want to order ºf the day, the following Bills were <lb/>
severally rºad a third time and passed- <lb break="no"/>The bill to continue the punishment of banishment <lb/>
in certain cases. <lb break="no"/>The bill to make provision for the recovery of pen­ <lb/>
alties becoming due upon upon the forfeiture of certaiu <lb/>
recognisances. <lb break="no"/>The bill to enable courts of law to grant relief <lb/>
against adverse claims made up ºn persons having no <lb/>
fºrest in the subject of such claims. <lb/>
The bill to regulate the office and duties of coroners, <lb/>
ordered that the hon. Attorney General and Mr. <lb/>
whiteway take these bills to the Legislative Council <lb/>
for concurrence: <lb/>
on motion of the hon. Attoruey General, pursuant <lb/>
to order of the day, the house resolved itself into <lb/>
committee of the whole on the further consideration <lb/>
ºf the bill to provide for the registration of births, <lb/>
marriages and deaths, Mr. Barron in the chair. <lb/>
on motion of the hon Attorney General the sections <lb/>
of the bill passed over when the committee last sat <lb/></p> 

<p>were read seriatum and adopted, with some amend­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ments, and the committee rose and the chairman re: <lb/>
rted the bill with amendments, which were read and <lb/>
£oncurred in. Third reading to-morrow. <lb/>
on motion of the hon Attorney General, pursuant <lb/>
to order of the day, the houso resolved itself into <lb/>
committee of the whole on the further consideration <lb/>
ºf the bill to make provision for wives and children <lb/>
4.ierted by their husbands and parents, and of parents <lb/>
deserted by their children, Mr. Wyat in the chair. <lb/>
on mºtion of the hon Attorney General, the re­ <lb/>
maining sections of the bill, were read and adopted, <lb/>
with sºme amendments, and the committee rose and <lb/>
the chairman reported the bill with amendments, <lb/>
which were read and concurred in. Third reading to­ <lb/>
morrow. <lb/>
Mr. MooRE gave notice that on to-morrow he <lb/>
would ask the hon Colonial Secretary, if any, and <lb/>
what arrangement had been made to provide a suitable <lb/>
teamer for the steam packet service in Conception <lb/></p> 

<p>Bay. <lb/>
The house then adjourned until to-morrow at three <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/></p> -->

<!--<p>it may be therefore that we shall not lose any advan­ <lb/>
whole matter is new, will well bear examination, and <lb/></p> 

<p>doubts that it bespeaks the future destiny of the Pro­ <lb/>
vinces; but it is still well that we learn and become <lb/>
beforehand as well informed as possible of the nature <lb/>
of the system by which we are to be governed here­ <lb/>
after. <lb/>
<lb break="no"/>The Rev. Mother of the Convent of Mercy begs <lb/>
gratefully to acknowledge the receipt of Three Pounds <lb/>
from Thomas GLEN, Esq. for the relief of the Poor. <lb/></p> 

<p>-º- <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>We regret to learn that intelligence has been receiv­ <lb/>
ed by telegraph of the death of D. S. Rennie, Esq; <lb/>
brother of W. F. Rennie, Esq., of this town, and <lb/>
brother-in-law of the hon. the Attorney General. Mr. <lb/>
Rennie has for several years past resided in England, <lb/>
—Express of Tuesday. <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>ATIMENAEUM. <lb/></p> 

<p>At a meeting of this Institute held at the Temper­ <lb/>
ance Hall, March 7, 1865, Hon. N. SrABB. President, <lb/>
in the chair, the following Report was unanimously <lb/>
adopted:­ <lb/></p> 

<p>The Committee of the St. John's Athenaeum in pre­ <lb/>
senting their fourth Annual Report, regret that they <lb/>
are unable to congratulate the subscribers on the <lb/>
financial condition of the Institute during the past <lb/>
year. On the 31st December, 1864, the balance <lb/>
against the Society amounted to £109; this unfortu­ <lb/>
nate state of things has arisen chi fly from two causes: <lb/>
the loss of the annual grant from the Legislature, and <lb/>
the great expense incurred by the Institute in keeping <lb/>
up the Museum—this collection has cost since 1861 no <lb/>
less than £112 10s, in rent alone. The responsibility <lb/>
of sustaining it was cast upon this Society, by the <lb/>
amalgamation of the St. John's Library and Reading <lb/>
Room, the Young Mens' Institute, and the Mechan­ <lb/>
ics' Institute into the Athenaeum. These Institutions <lb/>
had made arrangements which the Committee of this <lb/>
Society had to carry out entirely for the public benefit. <lb/>
aad from which no money return was ever, realised, <lb/>
and when the Committee attempted to sell the Mu­ <lb/>
seum collection, they were forced, in deference to the <lb/>
strong expression of public feeling manifested on that <lb/>
occasion, to forego the attempt. They therefore con­ <lb/>
sider that as they have borne the expense of sustain­ <lb/>
ing the Museum entirely for the public benefit, they <lb/>
should be indemnified by the Local Legislature for <lb/>
the great loss they have sustained by retaining it for <lb/>
public use. In the last session of the House a peti­ <lb/>
tion was presented, and an address to both branches <lb/>
of the Legi was carried, praying for the annual <lb/></p> 

<p>Últ ſtufulimitmer. <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOH.W'S: <lb/>
THURSDAY, MARCH 9, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>The long continued debate on Confederation in our <lb/>
areeravºſvěriminated on Mouday last uy the adoption <lb/></p> 

<p>of the Attorney GENERAL's Resolution, which <lb/>
leaves the question open until the country pronounces <lb/>
on it at the next election, sometime in the present year. <lb/>
Though the Resolution expresses no opinion on the <lb/>
question, the discussion called forth the views of the <lb/>
Assembly in explicit terms, and we are enabled to state <lb/>
that a majority of the House (sixteen to thirteen) en­ <lb/>
dorse the project of Confederation. Some of the <lb/>
members composing this majority suggested the neces­ <lb/>
sity of certain modifications in the terms of the Quebec <lb/>
Resolutions; but the exceptions taken are of a char­ <lb/>
acter that may easily be met, and cannot be the cause <lb/>
of any such difficulty as would alienate one of these <lb/>
members from the support of the measure. As far then <lb/>
as the opinion of the present House is concerned, it has <lb/>
clearly declared itself in favor of the proposed Confed­ <lb/>
tration. <lb/>
But when we look at the character of the support <lb/>
and of the opposition the measure has received, the pro­ <lb/>
nouncement in its favor acquires additional significance. <lb/>
The approvers of Confederation were clear and decided <lb/>
ºn their opinions that it meant progress, the elevation <lb/>
ºf the people, and the advance of the common prosper­ <lb/>
|ity; they spoke with the evidence of conviction marked <lb/>
in their tone and bearing, and the effect they produced <lb/>
on the public mind is admitted on all sides. The oppo­ <lb/>
ºuts, on the other hand, were uncertain of their posi­ <lb/>
tion, and for the most part only asked for time for fuller <lb/>
consideration. Some of them thought the principle <lb/>
good, but objected to details; and two or three only ex­ <lb/>
Pressed decided hostility to the scheme. When such <lb/>
*the characteristics of the two parties, their relative <lb/>
Pºsition is but imperſectly understood by the mere refer­ <lb/>
* to numbers—the compactness and confidence on <lb/>
the one side, and the piebald and indecisive tone of the <lb/>
*forming material elements in any just estimate of <lb/>
their respective status and influence. <lb/>
Though under all the circumstances the position of <lb/>
*ties as thus correctly described is highly satisfactory, <lb/>
"think there can be norational doubt that the strength <lb/>
º Unionists will be materially increased when the <lb/>
subject again comes on for further discussion in the next <lb/>
* The progress the question has already made <lb/>
*tokens its growing acceptance, and especially in the <lb/>
*ent condition of the colony the fair prospect of im­ <lb/>
Pºvement it holds out cannot fail to impress the mass <lb/>
of º people and secure their enlarged support. <lb/>
No doubt our future action on the question must be <lb/>
*pendant in some measure on the course that may be <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>mus <lb/></p> 

<p>ºn by Nova Scotia and New Brunswick. The ad­ <lb/>
jº" of these Provinces is indispensable to the forma­ <lb/>
* ºf a contederacy, and their movements are conse­ <lb/>
ºnly of essential importance. There is in both, un­ <lb/>
ºbtedly, a sufficient amount of antagonism to make <lb/>
|*result for the present at least more or less doubtful, <lb/></p> 

<p>w §the resistance of either would unquestionably delay <lb/></p> 

<p>*complishment of the object. It is not supposable <lb/></p> 

<p>l -\- <lb break="no"/>"all the provisions of so large a scheme operating <lb/></p> 

<p>** variety of interests can have been so accurately <lb/></p> 

<p>. ºuted in all its parts as not to leave room for objec­ <lb/>
"even where the plan as a whole may be favorably <lb/></p> 

<p>*rded; and from such causes hesitation and delay <lb/></p> 

<p>grant, but without effect. The Committee would re­ <lb/>
commend that the same course should be adopted this <lb/>
session, and they trust that all the members of the <lb/>
Institute will use their influence with the members of <lb/>
the Assembly and the Executive to obtain that com­ <lb/>
pensation which, under the circumstances, the Com­ <lb/>
mittee deem the Achenaeum is fairly entitled to. <lb/>
The Committee again desire to express their thanks <lb/>
to the lecturers for this season. Hitherto the course <lb/>
of lectures this winter has had marked success, .the <lb/>
amount afready realized being £22 5s, for only eight <lb/>
lectures, while last year £25 17s. 9d. was the whole <lb/>
amount received for the course, <lb/>
Last year the Library was increased by the add tion <lb/>
of thirty new books; this year, owing to the financial <lb/>
condition of the Institute, they have been unable to <lb/>
add more than six. As many complaints have been <lb/>
made in regard to books being kept over the time al­ <lb/>
lowed, the Committee notified the public that in fu­ <lb/>
ture the fines would be more rigorously enforced. <lb/>
Owing to the depressed condition of the colony du­ <lb/>
ring the past year, the Committee deemed it perfectly <lb/>
impracticaule to carry out their design of erecting a <lb/>
new building for the purposes of the Institute. They <lb/>
trust, however, that with renewed prosperity they <lb/>
may be enabled to complete so necessary an under­ <lb/>
taking for the moral and intellectual advancement of <lb/>
the community. <lb/>
All which is respectfully subm'tted. <lb/>
NICHOLAS STAB.B. President. <lb/>
D. W. PROWSE, Secretary. <lb/>
St. John's, Marck 7, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>The election of Officers for the ensuing year then <lb/>
took place, when the following gentlemen were duly <lb/>
elected by bailot: — <lb/>
PRESIDENT: <lb/>
Hon. Nicholas Stabb, re-elected, <lb/>
vice-PRESIDENTS: <lb/>
Hon. R. J. Pinsent, re-elected. Hun. R. Kent, elected. <lb/>
Curators: <lb/>
Museum. Apparatus. <lb/>
F. J. Wyatt, Esq. E. L. Moore, Esq. <lb/>
secret A RY: <lb/>
D. W. Prowse, E q., re-elected. <lb/>
Coxixiittee: <lb/>
C.T.Ryland, Esq.,re-elected James Fox, Esq., elected <lb/>
James Baird, Esq., " Geo. Lash, Esq., re-elected <lb/>
John Bow ing. Esq., " Wm. Bºyd, Esq., " <lb/>
John Meehan, Esq., " Henry Bevins, Esq., " <lb/>
D. Sclater, E-q., eiected. <lb/></p> 

<p>ST: JOHN'S MECHANICS' SOCIETY". <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, March 3rd, 1865. <lb/>
The officers and Committee of the St. John's <lb/>
Incorporated Mechanic-'Sºciety for the past year have <lb/>
much pleasure in announcing this its Thirty-Eighth <lb/>
Annual report with a statement of its affairs. <lb/>
The Society,accompanied by the Ayalon Band, had <lb/>
the honour of attending on the 25th June last at the <lb/>
laying of the Cornar Sºone of the new Church of St. <lb/>
Patrick—His Lordship Right Rev. Dr. Mullock who <lb/>
officiated, grariousy condescended to think the Society <lb/>
for being present. <lb/>
It is a source of much gratification to refer to the <lb/>
continued prosperity and success of this Society.' <lb/>
Your Cºmmittee have expended during the past <lb/>
yer according to the Society, for <lb/></p> 

<p>Sick Benefits and Death, £24 18 0 <lb/>
Incidental Expenses 28 4 10 <lb/>
Total £53 2 10 <lb/></p> 

<p>Actual Worth, £1000 0 0 <lb/></p> 

<p>In conformity with the rules the Society walked in <lb/>
procession at the funeral of the widow of a deceased <lb/>
brother member. <lb/>
During the past year three new members were ad­ <lb/>
mitted. <lb/>
Your Committee cannot close this Report without <lb/>
favourably alluding to the harmony and goºd feeling <lb/>
existing among its members,and expressing a hope that <lb/>
it may long continue to uphold among them. <lb/>
In conclusion, your Committee have to thank the <lb/></p> 

<p>present year, but a hitch in either Nova Scotia or New <lb/>
Brunswick would necessarily postpone final action, and <lb/></p> 

<p>tage by the delay our Legislature has agreed to. The <lb/></p> 

<p>in any interest should not be urged hastily. No one <lb/></p> 

<p>The Report is respectfully submitted on behalf of <lb/>
the Officers and Committee. <lb/>
R. TTRELEGAN, Secretary. <lb/>
The following Resolutions were the unanimously <lb/>
carried­ <lb/>
Resolved —That a vote of thanks is due to the <lb/>
President, Valentine Merchant, Esq., for his exertions <lb/>
in the Society's welfare, by discharging the trust <lb/>
assigned to him to the entire satisfaction of the Body. <lb/>
Resolved,—That the thanks of this Society are <lb/>
hereby tendered to the Officers for the zeal they dis­ <lb/>
played on all occasions in the discharge of their res­ <lb/>
pective duties. <lb/>
The Society having proceeded to the election of <lb/>
Officers for the ensuing year, when the following was <lb/>
the result: — <lb/>
Mr. John Maher, <lb/>
John Power, <lb/></p> 

<p>elected President <lb/></p> 

<p>re-elected Vice-President <lb/></p> 

<p>Charles Conway, - - <lb break="no"/>John W. #.; Eastern District. <lb/></p> 

<p>Thomas Walsh <lb break="no"/>Andrew §:...d.; Western District. <lb/></p> 

<p>seal. Fishery. <lb/>
List of Wessels cleared for the Scal Fishery—1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>Outfit 1865–43 vessels–5,445 tons—2,231 men. <lb/>
Ditto 1864–43 vessels—5,347 tons—2,209 men. <lb/></p> 

<p>- Tog <lb/></p> 

<p>TJosFPITT MULLINGs, <lb/>
Authorized Broker, H. M. C. <lb/></p> 

<p>Custom-House, St. John's, 7th March, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>Increase—none 22 <lb/></p> 

<p>1)IED,-\-On Tuesday last, Jonathan, eldest son of <lb/>
Mr. W. T. Parsons, aged 18 years. His funeral will <lb/>
take place to-day (Thursday) at 3 o'clock, p.m., when <lb/>
friends are requested to attend <lb/></p> 

<p>Auction Sale. <lb/></p> 

<p>To be Sold by Auction. <lb/></p> 

<p>On THURSUAY, the 2) h A.:ril next, at 11 o'clock, <lb/>
ON THE PREMISES, <lb/></p> 

<p>The remaining Lea-ehold interest of <lb/></p> 

<p>Messrs. J. B. Barnes &amp; Co., <lb/></p> 

<p>ſn the premises in Water Street, lately occupied in <lb/>
part by the said Messrs. J. B. BARNEs &amp; Co., and <lb/>
in part now held by Mr. John Tarehin, being twenty <lb/>
one years unexpired from the 20.h of August next. <lb/>
Ground rent one hundred and eighty pounds sterling <lb/>
per annum. <lb/>
All required information may be obtained up on ap­ <lb/>
plication at the Saving's Bank: <lb/>
By order of the Directors. <lb/>
EDWARD MORRIS, <lb/></p> 

<p>March 9. Cashier. <lb/></p> 

<p>Life Assurance. <lb/></p> 

<p>- trix: <lb/>
Scottish Provident Institution, <lb/>
HEAD-office: <lb/></p> 

<p>EIJINBUH.GII. <lb/>
This Office tenders superior advant ges, assuring a <lb/>
greatly larger Assurance ior the same premium, and <lb/>
eventually, to good lives, as large additiºns as where <lb/>
the usual high rate of premium is charged. <lb/>
A comparison of its tabies of rates and profits and <lb/>
general conditions, can he confidently asked. <lb/>
Agent at Sain' J hn's, <lb/></p> 

<p>J. O. FRASER. <lb/></p> 

<p>members for their regular attendance on all occasions; <lb/></p> 

<p>*&gt; <lb/></p> 

<p>Fab, 27, (6 m.) <lb/></p> 

<p>A:l parties ordering the <lb/>
"Victory" Cook Stove <lb/>
Fºr the Newfºundland trade, can obtain them only <lb/>
through Mr. Geo. GEAR, sole Proprietor of the same. <lb/>
: ** - BOWERS, PRATT &amp; Co.. <lb/>
2nd Jan., 1865. 169, Congress-street, Buston. <lb/>
Feb. 27. (1 y.) <lb/>
'IO BE LET, <lb/>
That commodious SHOP, WARE­ <lb/>
1:00 MS, extensive STORE and <lb/>
WATERSIDE PREMIISES, lately <lb/>
occupied by Messrs. WILLIAMTHoyas <lb/>
&amp; Co., in all respects admirably suited <lb/></p> 

<p>i: <lb/>
| <lb/></p> 

<p>f <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>sº <lb/>
-\-\-;:-Fº­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Wm. Mul owny, º 1st Assistant for a large mercantile business. <lb/></p> 

<p>Richard Hanley, -\- 2nd ** Apply to -\- <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Wm. McGrath st 1st Treasurer F. B. T. CARTER, <lb/></p> 

<p>John %. -\-; tº Feb. 27 4i. <lb/></p> 

<p>Wm. Kelly, -\- 3r tº <lb/></p> 

<p>Richard ºn. t- Secretary. NEW ARRIVALS I <lb/>
YISITING OFFICERS. Per Glance, <lb/></p> 

<p>American Parlor Gothic GRATES, <lb/>
Which will be sold cheap for cash. <lb/></p> 

<p>GEO. GEAR. <lb/>
L169 &amp; 349 WATER-STREET.] <lb/></p> 

<p>(2 wics. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Subscriber <lb/></p> 

<p>Feb. 27. <lb/></p> 

<p>Wessels, MASTERs. Tons. MEN. <lb/>
L. O'Brien &amp; Co. Having been appointed Agent for the sale of <lb/>
Francis Gallishuo 133 65 *L - º <lb/>
Margaret Ann Nurse 44 20 Chilson's Ranges, <lb break="no"/>Meteor Goss 128 Gº | Samples of the same can be seen at his Establishment, <lb/>
James Henry Geary 127 tº 349 Water-Street. <lb/>
W. Grieve &amp; Co. - GEO. GEAR. <lb/>
§ { Halern 222 68 Feb. 27. (3m.) <lb/>
Wolf (s) Skinner 210 70 <lb/>
Brooking &amp; Co. º sº ºn&amp; <lb/>
Ariel; c. . . . Athenæum Lectures. <lb/>
- Stephen March. <lb break="no"/>Corsair March 112 50 Th; Annual Course of Lectures at this institute <lb/>
-\- -\-\-\- McBride &amp; Kerr. will Commence on MONDAY the 16th January, at <lb/>
. º..." #. ld º 50 the Temperance Hall. <lb/>
enny Lin ransile 6 <lb/>
y Stabh, Row &amp; Co. 1 March13–Rev. D. McRae—Subject–Tennyson. <lb/>
Sarah Grace Burke 103 40 March 20–Rev.J.Phelps—"Realings from Merchant <lb/>
George English 80 37 _ of Venice <lb/>
Leader Gearan 125 50 March 27—Rev. John Maze—Subject:-An Arch­ <lb/>
Prima Donna Silvey 125 53 deacon. <lb/>
Job Brothers &amp; Co. Othere will be announced in due course. Each <lb/>
Kate Cumming Cummins 184 63 | Lecture will commence at 8 o'clock,-Doors open at <lb/>
Charles Snow 86 44 quarter past Seven. <lb/>
Bertha White 257 84 Season Ticket to admit two............5s. 0d. <lb/>
Mary Jane Connors 51 21 Seascu Ticket to admit one. 2s. 6d. <lb/>
Baine, Johnston &amp; Co. Admission to single Lecture............').s. 6]. <lb/>
Bloodhound (s) Graham 153 70 Tickets for the course will be furnished to Members <lb/>
Qspray (8) Gulliford 176 70 of the Institute on payment of their Subscription. <lb/>
Gipsy Gosse 133 60 D. W. PROWSE, <lb/>
Guitar Duff 113 64) Jan 5. Secretary <lb/>
Noel Martin 135 60 <lb break="no"/>Primrose Bank Curtin 78 40 SPECIAL INTIMATION. <lb/>
- &amp;, L.Tessier. <lb break="no"/>Brisk Morris 127 60 The BENEFITS of Life Assurance with the <lb/>
K. McLea &amp; Sons, SMALLEST OUTLAY <lb/>
Fleetwing Rogers 142 55 -: -<lb break="maybe"/>Rebecca. Hudson 96 50 combined with the FULLEST SECURITY. <lb/>
Nightingals Mullow <lb break="no"/>g &amp; bº. 136 56 This desirable object has been attained by the Policy­ <lb/>
Fanny Bloomer Jackman 126 55 holders of the ºr <lb/>
Margaret Jackman 14ſ, 55 - ..oz.a., f: <lb/>
Racer Noseworthy 85 30 Li fe.Association of Scotland <lb/>
Afton Feehan 131 55 | By means of its Allocation of Profit in Cash towards <lb/>
Isabella Ryan 140 60 the Annual Reduction of the Premiums payable for the <lb/>
Giraffe Lynch 164 52 | Policies, -the older Policy-holders, paying at present <lb/>
Muir &amp; Duder, only 12s. 6d. (instead of 20s) per £1 of the Premiums; <lb/>
Superior Mºrris 68 29 and by the following <lb/>
Seamew Culbert 112 54 REGULATION FOR FURTHER INIMINISHING <lb/>
A. Goºdridge &amp; Sons. OUTLAY FOR LIFE ASSURANCE. <lb/>
Bessie Goodridge 143 60 Uztil the time when the premiums may be expected <lb/>
Goodridge &amp; Kelligrew. to be reduced by the application of profits, the Assured <lb/>
Reindeer Macarthy 147 55 for £500 or upwards, may leave unpaid a considerable <lb/>
P. Rogerson &amp; Son. portion (one-third or one-fourth) of the premiums re­ <lb/>
Elizabeth Percey 152 60 cessary to keep the policy in force. The unpaid part <lb/>
Jessie Taylor 142 60 is allowed to remain in the hands of the Assured as <lb/>
Glance Pike 142 55 long as he pleases, and he is not asked to pay interest <lb/>
Clift, Wood &amp; Co. thereon; but the amount, with accumulated interest, <lb/>
Brothers Winsor 134 53 will be deducted from the sum assured at death, New <lb/>
R. Q'Dwyer. Entrants thus at orce commence with <lb/>
Chedabucto Cole 83 30 PAYMENIS MUCH BELOW THE TABULAR. <lb/></p> 

<p>RATES, <lb/>
and continue to make such reduced payments for six <lb/>
years, when they become entitled to reduction of the <lb/>
premiums by the application of Profits. They will, <lb/>
nevertheless, receive the same benefits and the same <lb/>
share of profit, as if the full premiums had been paid­ <lb/>
Present outlay is also further diminished by means of <lb/>
the Association's <lb/></p> 

<p>INCREASING POLICIES <lb/>
n which the sums Assured shall increase by the meret <lb/>
lapse of time to double the original amount, withou <lb/>
corresponding i of premium; and, under the <lb/>
Participating Class, the premiums will be reducible by <lb/>
application of Profits. <lb/>
The Policies do Not CoNTAIN several of the RES­ <lb/>
TRICTIons commonly impºsed on Assured Lives, and <lb/>
conſer en the Policy-holdirs unusual and important <lb/>
facilities and privileges. <lb/>
IF ENTRANTs on or before 5TH APRIL <lb/>
will secure a decided advantage over later Entrants <lb/>
at the Division of Profit. <lb/></p> 

<p>NEWFC} UN tº LAND BRANCH, <lb/>
HEAL) () FFICE –ST. JOHN'S. <lb/>
Di Rectors: <lb/>
H. K. Dickinson, E-q | Hon. James Cormack. <lb/>
Robert Grieve, Esq. <lb/>
Agent and Secretary.....................E. L. JARVIS, <lb/>
March 7 <lb/></p> 

<p>LAN CASHIRE <lb/>
- - - t <lb/>
Insurance Company. <lb/>
FIRE AND LIFE. <lb/>
CAPITAL TWO MILLION'S STERLING!. <lb/>
Head Office: Exchange-Street, Manchester. <lb/>
Board of director:8: <lb/>
John Todd, Esq., Chairman. <lb/>
Wifiam H. Bradley, E.g. William Pilkington, Esq., <lb/>
John Clegg, Esq. Blackburn <lb/>
B. Darbyshire, Esq., Liv-|Joseph Schofeld, Esq. <lb/>
erpool. N. Shelmerdine, Et q. <lb/>
Alexander Ewing E-q., James Smith, Leq., Liver­ <lb/>
Glasgow. pool. <lb/>
Samuel H tºgreaves, Esq James Wagsteff, Esq., Lon­ <lb/>
John K, owles, E-q. don, <lb/>
J. Robinson Kay, Eeq., Edward War,klyn, Esq. <lb/>
Bury Barton Wood, Esq. <lb/>
J. Schofield Meyson, E-q <lb/>
Gecrge Stewart, Genera' Manager. <lb/>
E. J. J.A.RWIS, <lb/>
Agent for New oundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>Jan. 30. <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>3. <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/>
| <lb/></p> 

<p>† <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/></p> 

<p>§ <lb/></p> 

<p>+ <lb/></p> 

<p>#.#:+ <lb/></p> 

<p>º: <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p>-->

</div>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>