<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-14" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
    <title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-02-14">14 February 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-03-16"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-03-16_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-03-16_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-27">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-11-27">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-16_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-16_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-16_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-16_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-16_Page_1.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">St. John's, Thursday, March 16, 1865.</fw>

    <!-- IC, 2018-11-27, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>Notice. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mothers Motherji <lb/></p> 

<p>rocure Mrs. WIN º <lb/>
children º". <lb/>
tº prescription of one of th <lb/>
hd nurses in the United State <lb/>
F thirty Years with never º <lb/>
s by millions of mothers alid Ing, <lb/>
able infant of one week old chi. <lb/>
ly relieves the child from i." tha <lb/>
ºmach and bowels, corrects acid: <lb/>
d energy to the whole system ity, <lb/>
tly relieve Griping in the Bowel. It <lb/>
believe it the best and Rurest . and <lb/>
leases of Dissentery and jº <lb/>
it arises from teething or an ſea in <lb/>
Actions for use will sº other <lb/>
}nuine unless the fac-simile jº. <lb/>
the outside wrapper. Price º: <lb/>
Sold by all Medicine Dealers. #. <lb/>
New York, and 205 High Høi. <lb/></p> 

<p>d. <lb/>
!.S. WINSLOW, <lb/>
Nurse and Female Physicia <lb/>
of mothers, her §§. §." <lb/>
#, which greatly facilitates th: . or <lb/>
oftening the gums, reducing aſ; <lb/>
lay all pain and spasmodi. action, a <lb/>
ite the bowels. Depend upon it." nd <lb/>
We rest to yourselves, and reſt. <lb/>
inſants. We have put up and sold . <lb/>
thirty years, and can say, in confide 18 <lb/>
*hat we have never boea able to . <lb/>
*dicine—never has it failed in a sin # <lb/>
it a cure, when timely used. N. <lb/>
instance of dissatisfaction by any . <lb/>
On the contrary, all speak deſign; <lb/>
ºns, and speaks in terms of comm. <lb/>
ſical effects and medical virtues, wº. <lb/>
Autter "what we do now," after th; <lb/>
ºe; and pledge our reputation for º <lb/>
hat we here declare. In almost ... <lb/>
she inſant is suffering from pair º <lb/>
lief wiłł be found in fifteen or twent <lb/>
the ºyrup is administered. Fºll 3. <lb/>
f will accompany each bottle. Nons <lb/>
ss the ſac-simile of Curtis and Perkins <lb/>
on the outside wrapper. sold by Drug. <lb/>
. ..". a.º. Office, 48; <lb/>
in igh Ho-be, - <lb break="no"/>per bottle. in, England. Priº, <lb/>
ºff is an extract from a letter writt <lb/>
Holme, Pastor of the tº. <lb/>
h; Brooklyn, NY, to the "Jºurnal and <lb/>
Cincinnati, O., and speaks volumes in <lb/>
wºrld-renowned medicine, Mrs. WI <lb/>
ºg Syrup for Children Teething—" W. <lb/>
*nt in your c lumns of Mrs. Wins. <lb/>
# Syrup. Now we never said. word in <lb/>
ºtent medicine before in ºr life, but w; <lb/>
to say, tº your readers that this is no <lb/>
*"e, tried it, and know it to be all t <lb/>
probably one of the most successful <lb/>
the day, because it is one of the best <lb/>
*ºur readers who have babies ºn'. do <lb/>
} in a supply " <lb/>
J. DEARIN, St. John's, <lb/>
-\-\- Arent for N-wfoundard. <lb/>
*11t) EN IX F.I.R.A. <lb/>
"Hijet 4% -\-\-\-<lb break="maybe"/>fillite ºpiily. <lb/>
<lb break="no"/>Street and Charing Cross, London. <lb/>
ſº S1 A B/, /S//ſ, 19–1732 <lb/>
ritus'TF Es AN, DIREoro Rs. <lb/>
ºn, Esq. (Kirkman D. Hodg on Esq. <lb/>
ºpe, Jºnes Horne, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>William J. Lancaster, <lb/>
Jºhn I). Magen, <lb/></p> 

<p>; it <lb/></p> 

<p>-er, " J.In Masternan, Esq. M. P. <lb/>
r, " ºbu Tunolly oxley | 84 <lb/>
that tº G, ºrge Sta' ley Repto -<lb break="maybe"/>ºn, " |Benjamin Shaw, <lb/>
... [atthew. Whiting, "I <lb/>
*or, " Fran is Wilson, <lb/>
thscreta Ries <lb/>
William Harris Esq. <lb/>
Gronge \ ulian, tº y ELL, Fºsq. <lb/></p> 

<p>NIX FIRE offic; i. confi <lb/>
...he notice of the public—for ..". <lb/>
"titude with which all claims upon it are <lb/>
paid-as well as for the almost unlimited <lb/>
it affords, *prising in addition to the <lb/>
Capital of the Cºmpany, the whole for <lb/>
"ºils Proprieta y. composed oſsºm <lb/>
* Rentlemºn and Merchants in tº <lb/>
NIX QFFICE has warried on an exten <lb/>
sful busines for upwards of seventy<lb break="no"/>The duty paid by it to Government fºr <lb/>
.9eat Briain and iº". <lb/>
º, per innurn. <lb/>
*...º.º. Insurances are undertake <lb/>
Ix COMPANY on i..."...". <lb/>
ºn Newfoundland aſ a jº <lb/>
ich may bo know on application to <lb/>
ºr otive, in St. John's, wº. policies <lb/>
ºf charge. <lb/></p> 

<p>W. &amp; G. RENDE1.L, <lb/>
49ents for Vermonºid. <lb/></p> 

<p>HE COLONIAL <lb/>
- º * -<lb break="maybe"/>Slifºliº U0ilpally <lb/>
-<lb break="maybe"/>STARLISHED 1846. <lb/>
ONE MILLION STERLING. <lb/>
of Assuring before 35th <lb/>
May 1863. <lb/></p> 

<p>DIVISION OF PROFITS. <lb/>
advantage of this year's entry to the <lb/>
*** must be lodged at the office <lb/>
fºundland,or with ºf the Agents <lb/>
. May next. <lb/>
ºš will be allocated at the <lb/>
.#64 to Policies opened before <lb/>
ouks for the Present Year. <lb/></p> 

<p>* Sºcial Act of parliament. <lb/></p> 

<p>r opernor. <lb/></p> 

<p>(ON THE EARL of ELGIN &amp; <lb/>
-\- Goykºnon-GENERA. of INDIA. <lb/>
* GEORGESTREET, EDINBURGH <lb/></p> 

<p>* in St. John's, Newfoundland. <lb/>
ºn, Esq. Walter Grieve, Esq., <lb/>
Merchant. <lb/></p> 

<p>am Henry Mare, Esq. <lb/>
*...Henry Hunt staši, M. D. <lb/>
-Frederick J. Wyatt. -<lb break="maybe"/>| OF THE Coirp ANy. <lb/>
the Company......... gigo,000 <lb/>
divided Profits on tºojºng­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ºpened in 1847,has beenincreased <lb/>
ºpplication of the Bonus; other <lb/>
rtion. <lb/>
five years; next division in 1860. <lb/>
*d in any part of the world what <lb/>
n established <lb/></p> 

<p>A <lb/></p> 

<p>=<lb break="no"/>*...;-as­ <lb/></p> 

<p>(ſhe 3ienſuumillander, <lb/></p> 

<p>ings by EI)WARI) 1)ALTON SHEA, at his <lb/></p> 

<p>3. . DUCKWORTH STREET-Terms One <lb/>
%inea per annum payable in advance. <lb/></p> 

<p>Advertisements not limited (Auction-sales and notices <lb/>
ºffich determine themselves excepted) are repeated <lb/></p> 

<p>until ordered in writing to be withdrawn, and sre <lb/>
charged for accordinglu. <lb/></p> 

<p>This paper is filed,and may be seen, free of charge at <lb/>
Holloway's Pills and Ointment Establishmet, 244, <lb/>
strand. London. <lb/></p> 

<p>are­ <lb/>--> 
    
    
<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head>

<p rendition="simple:right">Tuesday, Feb. 14.</p>
<p rendition="simple:centre">(Continued.)</p> 

<p>On motion of the <persName ref="pers:CART5">hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>, pursuant <lb/>
to order of the day, the house resolved itself into com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the whole on the consideration of the confedera<lb break="no"/>tion of the British North American Provinces, Mr. Knight <lb/>
in the chair.</p> 

    <p><persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>.—The resolution which he <lb/>
proposed to submit for the consideration of the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, was one which proposed to postpone until after <lb/>
the meeting of the next House of Assembly the considera<lb break="no"/>tion of the important question of the federation of the <lb/>
North American Colonies. The documents received by <lb/>
the Government on this subject had been submitted to <lb/>
the house at the opening of the session; and he had then <lb/>
given notice of certain resolutions which he intended <lb/>
under the directions of the Secretary of State's despatch, <lb/>
to submit to the house with the view of either adopting <lb/>
or rejecting the report of the Quebec conference. From <lb/>
the first, however, there was no idea of making this a <lb/>
government or party question, but to submit it as one on <lb/>
which the house was to pronounce a deliberate judgment <lb/>
after fully weighing all the considerations by which it was <lb/>
surrounded. He thought it objectionable, if the other <lb/>
colonies adopted the Union at once, that we should <lb/>
allow the matter to lie over, and if we afterwards decided <lb/>
that confederation was for our advantage, should have to <lb/>
knock at the door, twelve or eighteen months after the <lb/>
confederacy was organized, asking for what we were now <lb/>
entitled to accept. It appeared, however, that this win<lb break="no"/>ter, the other colonies, or at least some of them, would <lb/>
postpone the decisions of the mater; and as there was <lb/>
an almost unanimous a desire expressed, not only in the <lb/>
house, but by the public at large, from some of whom <lb/>
petitions had been laid before the house, that the ques<lb break="no"/>tion should here be postponed for further consideration, <lb/>
he had decided not to submit the resolutions he had at <lb/>
first designed, but to substitute that now before the <lb/>
committee, for the postponement of any decision upon it <lb/>
until after a new election had taken place, and the ques<lb break="no"/>tion had been fully discussed by the constituences. <lb/>
With regard to the history of the question of confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, it would be doubtless in the recollection of some <lb/>
hon members that the late Governor General of Canada, <lb/>
Sir Edmund Head, in his closing address to the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature of that Province, had recommended it on the con<lb break="no"/>aideration of the members of the Legislature and of the <lb/>
people of the Province. He (hon A. Gen.) recollected <lb/>
very well the effect which that speech produced at the <lb/>
time. It excited considerable sensastion, not only in the <lb/>
colonies, but also in England. I was not at all favora<lb break="no"/>bly viewed at the Colonial office, and a despatch was <lb/>
sent out, which was on the journals of the House, re<lb break="no"/>questing that it should not be discussed, nor delegates <lb/>
appointed for its consideration, unless with the sanction <lb/>
of the nome Government. In the course of time, how<lb break="no"/>ever, the question came to be regardel more favourably. <lb/>
It was taken up in the Legislature of Nova Scotia, and <lb/>
certain resolutions were adopted, which the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor was requested to transmit to the Secretary of <lb/>
State for the Colonies. These resolutions were sent out <lb/>
to the several colonies, with a dispatch from the late <lb/>
Duke of Newcastle, which was recorded on our journals, <lb/>
which showed a considerable change of opinion on the <lb/>
part of Her Majesty's Government on that question. <lb/>
Nothing further was done in the matter until in 1864 <lb/>
resolutions were passed by the Legislatures of Nova <lb/>
Scotia, New Brunswick and Prince Edward Island, pro<lb break="no"/>posing a Legislative union of the maritime provinces, and <lb/>
authorising the appointment of delegates to consider the <lb/>
question. These delegates met at Charlottetown, when <lb/>
delegates for the government of Canada attended, and <lb/>
after there had been some discussion of the question of <lb/>
the proposed Legislative union, the Canadian delegates <lb/>
suggested in place of it the larger question of a federal <lb/>
union of the provinces, which umet the approval of the <lb/>
Conference; and it was decided to meet at Quebec for <lb/>
its consideration, and that an invitation should be sent <lb/>
to the government of this colony to send delegates to the <lb/>
conference at Quebec. Hon members would have learnt <lb/>
from the papers laid on the table of the house the course <lb/>
adopted by the government. The question had not been <lb/>
under the consideration of the Legislature, but they con<lb break="no"/>sidered that in a matter of so much importance, it was <lb/>
their duty to respond to the invitation and appoint <lb/>
delegates to the conferense, with instructions to consider <lb/>
and discuss the propositious that might be submitted to <lb/>
the Conference, but to do nothing committing this <lb/>
Colony. In accordance with the course adopted in the <lb/>
other Colonies, and as the most fitting in itself, as this <lb/>
was not a party question hut one afficting materially the <lb/>
interests of the whole people, delegates were appointed <lb/>
from the two parties represented in that House, the hon <lb/>
the Speaker, from the government side, and the hon <lb/>
member tor Placentia and St. Mary's, Mr. Shea, a leading <lb/>
member of the opposition. The delegates met at Quebec <lb/>
on the 10th of October, and the conference was in session <lb/>
for some weeks, and the result of their deliberations was <lb/>
the report laid on the table of the house. It had been <lb/>
said that the delegates from this Colony, not being <lb/>
appointed by authority of the Legislature, had no right <lb/>
to sign the report; and that in consequence of the report <lb/>
being signed by all the delegates, the Colonial Secretary <lb/>
had sent out his dispatch signifying his approval of the <lb/>
repest. He (hon Attoruey General) did not concur in <lb/>
that view. The delegates from this island, having very <lb/>
properly taken part in the proceedings of the conference, <lb/>
and approving of the resolutions adopted, he conceived <lb/>
that they acted properly in signing the report, which <lb/>
was nothing more than certifying the resolutions. <lb/>
And as to the observation that the Colonial Secretary was <lb/>
misled, the hon members who were of that opinion were <lb/>
entirely mistaken. The Colonial Secretary, from the <lb/>
correspondence which had taken place between this Go<lb break="no"/>vernmentand that of Canada, and which was transmitted to <lb/>
him before the Conference met, was fully aware of the <lb/>
limited authority of the Delegates from this Colony, and <lb/>
of the instructions under which they acted, and <lb/>
could not have been misled or influenced in this respect, <lb/>
as the hon member for Ferryland, Mr. Glen, supposed. <lb/>
It had also been objected that the Delegates, after their <lb/>
return, neglected to convene public meetings for the dis<lb break="no"/>Sussion of the question, as was done in some of the other <lb/>
colonies. He (hon Attorney General) did think that it <lb/>
    
    <cb/>
    
    would be highly improper for any officers of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, as the Delegates were to adopt such a course. <lb/>
They were not delegates from any popular body. They <lb/>
reported to the government, and it was not to the people, <lb/>
but to the Legislature, as representing the whole of the <lb/>
people of the colony, that the report should be submit<lb break="no"/>ted for to them they were responsible. There was nothing <lb/>
in the conduct of the delegates, from the beginning to <lb/>
the end of the proceedings, but what was not only unex<lb break="no"/>ceptionable, but most commendable. They discharged <lb/>
their duty in such a manner in the opinion of those best <lb/>
capable of judging, the ablest men of the other provinces, <lb/>
as to have reflected the highest credit on themselves <lb/>
and on the colony they represented. With respect to <lb/>
the report of the conference, it was a matter of satisfac<lb break="no"/>tion that for months past it had undergone such full <lb/>
discussion that we are all familarised with its conclusions. <lb/>
It was the result of the delibereations of the ablest men <lb/>
in the provinces, upon a question of the highest impor<lb break="no"/>tance which had occupied public attention in the other <lb/>
provinces for years. The report had been transmitted <lb/>
to Her Majesty's Government, and, after mature consid<lb break="no"/>eratin, a dispatch was transmitted expressing a general <lb/>
approval of the decision arrived at by the conference. <lb/>
The question had been fully discussed by the public and <lb/>
in the mother country, in the other provinces, and in <lb/>
this colony and by statesmen on both sides of the At<lb break="no"/>lantic; and there was now very little new left for him <lb/>
to say on the subject. He did not intend to go into the <lb/>
statistics of the question, nor to recapitulate the arguments <lb/>
previously used by other and abler writers and speakers <lb/>
upon the subject; but having to vote upon it, he consid<lb break="no"/>ered it necessary to state the reasons which influenced <lb/>
his mind in coming to a conclusion upon a subject of such <lb/>
grave importance, a vote upon which, either one side <lb/>
or the other, cast so great a responsibility upon those <lb/>
with whom the adoption, or rejection of this project <lb/>
would rest. He recollected that, seven or eight years <lb/>
ago, when the question was first mooted by the Governor <lb/>
General, he (hon A. Gen) did not view it very favourably. <lb/>
It appeared to him, upon a merely passing consideration, <lb/>
to involve an increase of expediture for a general govern<lb break="no"/>ment and local governments and legislatures, without as <lb/>
he then apprehended, any corresponding advantage. But <lb/>
when it come before him as a practical question, upon <lb/>
which serious action was to be taken, and be came to view <lb/>
it in its relation not merely to the present circumstances <lb/>
of this colony, but also in regard to the future, he found <lb/>
that he had made a very great mistake in regarding it as <lb/>
a question of which the decision was to be influenced <lb/>
entirely by pecuniary considerations. On the contrary, it <lb/>
involved numerous important considerations of a social, <lb/>
political, moral and commercial character, requiring the <lb/>
closest attention. It was one that should be studied under <lb/>
the lights of history and experience, and with a regard to <lb/>
all those circumstances, that tended to promote he wealth <lb/>
of nations and the progress and prosperity of a people, <lb/>
and the wellfare, moral, political, and social of society. <lb/>
And although, in some respects, in having relation to the <lb/>
future, the question must be regarded as somewhat of a <lb/>
speculative character, yet here, as in private life, where <lb/>
our future conduct is necessarily so often determined by <lb/>
speculative reasoning based on what we believe to be sub<lb break="no"/>sisting facts, we might come to a conclusion very satis<lb break="no"/>factory and convincing to our minds, without being able <lb/>
to transfer that conviction to the minds of others with all <lb/>
the certainty of mathematical demonstration or the un<lb break="no"/>answerable logic of a sum in arithmetic. And viewing<lb/>
this question with regard to the considerations to which <lb/>
he had referred, looking at it in every light, and taking <lb/>
into account all that had been spoken and written against <lb/>
it, he had arrived at the conclusion that the proposed <lb/>
Confederation should by all ineans be entered into; as <lb/>
he subscribed most heartily to the sentiment expressed <lb/>
in the first paragraph of the report of the Convention, <lb/>
that such an union would largely promote the welfare <lb/>
and advantage of all the Colonies. A consideration that <lb/>
powerfully influenced his mind with regard to this pro<lb break="no"/>posal, was the contrast that might fairly be instituted <lb/> 
between what Newfoundland now was and what she <lb/>
might be under Confederation. At present we were an <lb/>
insignificant fishing settlement, with a population of a <lb/>
hundred and twenty or a hundred and thirty thousand, <lb/>
with no resources at present available beyond our fisheries <lb/>
and those insufficient for the support of our people, a <lb/>
large proportion of whom were dependent for four <lb/>
months in the year upon pauper relief supplied from the <lb/>
public revenue. These fisheries evidently, if not decli<lb break="no"/>ning, at least not increasing in productiveness with our <lb/>
increasing numbers, and for sometime past furnishing very <lb/>
inadequate support to those engaged in their prosecution. <lb/>
And supposing the fisheries to improve, and that we <lb/>
should have the average prosperity of the past still such <lb/>
improvement merely sufficed for the comfortable <lb/>
maintenance of the people for the time, and offered <lb/>
no means of supporting any great increass of our <lb/>
present numbers, even if our mineral resources <lb/>
turned out as productive as we hoped; so that we <lb/>
could have no prospect of becoming anytning but a small <lb/>
colony, of little influence or power in any respect, and of <lb/>
no note, importance, or consideration, which, should the <lb/>
protection of Great Britain be withdrawn, must fall a <lb/>
prey to the first power that might chose to take posses<lb break="no"/>sion of the Island. Was that a state which it could be <lb/>
satisfactory to ourselves, or to those who misht come <lb/>
after us to contemplate? On the other hand, what might <lb/>
we be under confederation? We were invited to join a <lb/>
Confederation which, in half a century, would be second <lb/>
to no power on the face of the earth, with a population, <lb/>
at present numbering four millions, stretching from the <lb/>
Atlantic to the Pacific, and which would number fifty <lb/>
millions within the life time of some of our children; <lb/>
with a country abounding with resources, such as could <lb/>
not fail, in the hands of an energetic people, to place us <lb/>
        in the first rank amongst the nations of the earth,—a <lb/>
Confederation whose commerce would cover every sea, <lb/>
whose flag would be respected in every quarter of the <lb/>
globe, and which should take place in the great family <lb/>
of nations, second to none, in influence, in wealth, in <lb/>
power, in resources, in all that tended to illustrate and <lb/>
magnify the position and standing of a people. When <lb/>
he (hon A. Gen.) contrasted this with, Newfoundland <lb/>
out of the confederation, with its 130,000 inhabitants <lb/>
subsisting by the fisheries on its cost, and the limited <lb/>
mineral resources which the island was known to possess, <lb/>
be considered it was a duty we owed to ourselves and <lb/>
to posterity to accept the invitation extended to us. <lb/>
True, these considerations were not such matters as <lb/>
could be measured by pounds, shillings and pence. <lb/>
Nevertheless they were such as powerfully influenced <lb/>
nations as well as individuals, in their ordinary conduct. <lb/>
There were other things of value in this life for both, <lb/>
besides dollars and cents; and as in private life were <lb/>
found individuals ready to pay for rank, station and <lb/>
influence, so among nations, the last shilling in the <lb/>
exchequer would be expended, and the last man sent to <lb/>
fight, with the object of maintaining the national honor <lb/>
and preserving the character and position of the common<lb break="no"/>wealth, When, therefore, we turned to the considera<lb break="no"/>
        
        <cb/>
        
tion of great national questions, such as this was, surely <lb/>
there were other matters to be regarded besides the mere
pecuniary aspect of the matter. But the British Go<lb break="no"/>vernment regarded the union as a matter which, with <lb/>
this object, we ought to go into. It was will then, that <lb/>
we should consider the consequences of opposing their <lb/>
wishes in this matter. The question of the defence of <lb/>
the colonies was one which had undergone a good deal <lb/>
of discussion of late years, and many statesmen were of <lb/>
opinion that the colonies cost Great Britain more than <lb/>
they were worth; and maintained that it was high time <lb/>
that we should do something for our own defence. But <lb/>
it should not be overlooked that the question for our <lb/>
consideration was not <hi rendition="simple:italic">whether we should go into the <lb/>
confederation or remain as we are at present</hi>—but <lb/>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">whether the confederation being formed, as it undoubtelly <lb/>
would be, by the other provinces, we were prepared to take <lb/>
he consequences of remining out of it</hi>. He (hon A. Gen.) <lb/>
spoke without other means of information than were <lb/>
open to all, but he did say that looking at the dispatches <lb/>
from Her Majesty's Government, the part they had taken <lb/>
in this matter, the debates in Parliament, the aricles <lb/>
in semi-official organs at home, and the speeches and <lb/>
writings of leading statesmen and writers in England, <lb/>
it was too plain in his judgement, for controversy, that <lb/>
Great Britain would require the colonies to contributed <lb/>
to their own defence, to a much greater extent than they <lb/>
had hitherto done; and that was nothing but what was <lb/>
reasonable; and a few years ago dispatches were received <lb/>
on the subject, expressing the opinions of statesmen at <lb/>
home, which the British Government regarded as a mat<lb break="no"/>ter which ought to be carried out; and he would ask, if <lb/>
we were called upon in this colony, could we refuse? It <lb/>
must be recollected that our admission to responsible <lb/> 
government was as part of the North Ameriean Colonies. <lb/>
It was conceded to us, because it had been previously <lb/>   
granted to the other provinces; not simply because we <lb/>
were fit for it, but because we came within a principle, <lb/>
which, having been applied to the other North American <lb/>
colonies, must also be applied to us. Now supposing <lb/>
confederation carried out, and that the other provinces <lb/>
went into it and made the suggested provision for the <lb/>
defence of the confederated provinces; and that we re<lb break="no"/>mained out, in what lignt would we be regarded by the <lb/>
government and people of England? They would take <lb/>
no interest in us, because we would be outside the con<lb break="no"/>federated provinces, subject in our management to <lb/>
wholly different principles, and would be regirded as a <lb/>
people whose interest were of very little concern, and <lb/>
who, having thrown away the advantages offered to them, <lb/>
could be worked upon oily as wilful and wayward <lb/>
children. And what, then, could we expect, but that we <lb/>
should be handed over to some subordinate at the Colonial <lb/>
office, to receive very little of that attention which we <lb/>
now experience. We might find, in time, the ships of <lb/>
war now employed for our defence sent elsewhere, and <lb/>
the troops stationed here withdrawn; and attention given <lb/>
to those who were more careful to comply with the <lb/>
wishes of the British Government. It must be recollec<lb break="no"/>ted that we had pledge ourselves to contribute to our <lb/>
own defence; a resolution to that effect was recorded <lb/>
on our journals some sessions ago, in reply to a dis<lb break="no"/>patch from the home government. Now that was a <lb/>
serious matter, if we should resolve to remain in our <lb/>
present isolation. He (hon A. Gen.) recollected the <lb/>
time when a whole regiment was considered necessary <lb/>
for our protection, and two or three ships of war. We <lb/>
would undoubtedly require so mething more than a few <lb/>
volunteer companies, and hon members who said so much <lb/>
about increased taxation, should recollect that the cost of <lb/>
a single regiment involved a far larger expenditure <lb/>
than Canada would take from us; and that would <lb/>
be the necessary consequence of standing out <lb/>
against confederation. It had been stated that <lb/> 
Great Britain would never abandon Newfoundland, <lb/>
on account of her geographical position. This <lb/>
seemed a whim a childish delusion. If Newfoundland was <lb/>
of so much importance, why was it not made a naval <lb/>
station, in preference to pestilence striken Bermuda, and <lb/>
Halifax, which had always been naval stations? While <lb/>
immense sums were expended on the citidel at Halifax, <lb/>
so as to remier is impregnable, this place was neglected, <lb/>
and only two or three forts defending the narrows re<lb break="no"/>paired, to render them tenable, and Armstrong guns pla<lb break="no"/>ced in them. Halifax had a capacious harbor, not liable <lb/>
to be closed by ice, and situated within 12 hours by <lb/>
steam of one entrance to the gulf of St. Lawrence and <lb/>
and 18 hours of the other, and within 12 hours of the <lb/>
United States; and the harbor of Louisburg, which was <lb/>
also free from ice, was situated between the two entran<lb break="no"/>ces to the Gulf. It was folly to talk of the advantages <lb/>
of our position, situated about 600 miles away from the <lb/>
probable scene of action, as compared with Halifax or <lb/>
Louisburg—If we were considered of so much importance <lb/>
to Great Britain, why was there so little expended on <lb/>
our fortifications? And of whatever importance we <lb/>
might now be to Great Britain, when the confederation <lb/>
of the colonies was carried out what would our importance <lb/>
then be? It we declined to enter into the confederation <lb/>
we would not be longer regarded by the other Colonies <lb/>
as a sister colony, but as one which had declined com<lb break="no"/>plying with the recommendation of the parent state, and <lb/>
refused all association with them, We should have no <lb/>
claim upon their sympathy or support, should we be <lb/>
threatened witn an other French convention, and their <lb/>
markets would be closed to on produce by prohibitory <lb/>
du ies. The opponents of confederation had been asked, <lb/>
again and again what our position would be, seperated <lb/>
from the confederation, and no satisfactory reply had been <lb/>
given. As to the question—what were the in material ad<lb break="no"/>vantages of confederation; it seemed to him (hon A. <lb/>
Gen) that there were in any. With regard to our public <lb/>
men, it opened up a field wortny of their ambition. Let <lb/>
the hon member for Ferryland, Mr. Gen, consider the <lb/>
enlarged sphere of advancement which confederation <lb/>
opened up to him, if sent up as a member to the House <lb/>
of Commons, where talent must take the lead whether it <lb/>
came from Newtowndland or Vancouver; and where he <lb/>
would have an opportunity, one day, of discussing some <lb/>
important question affecting the interests of Columbia, <lb/>
and on another, one involving those of New Brunswick, <lb/>
while on a third those of the great Suskatchewan valley <lb/>
would be taken up; and the compensation, when, his <lb/>
talents and experience placed his services in demand as <lb/>
a minister of the Crown, would be in proportion to the <lb/>
importance of his position; while the height of his ambi<lb break="no"/>tion in Newfoundland was to be Receiver General, at <lb/>
4,500 a-year. At the same time he might have an op<lb break="no"/>portunity of benefiting his Newfoundiand constituents <lb/>
and the Island generally, by the promotion of extensive <lb/>
public works, while at present he was laudably endea<lb break="no"/>vouring to promote the interests of the fishermen by ur<lb break="no"/>ging the construction of a breakwater at Tota's Cove. <lb/>
Was it no object to many in public life to have such <lb/>
prospects as this before them?—Surely it suould stimu<lb break="no"/>late the youth of the country to have the prospect before <lb/>
them of attaining to a position in public life, such as <lb/>
none of the colonies could offer while they continued in <lb/>
their present fragmentary condition. Surely there was

<cb/>
        
something more elevating and enabling in such prospects <lb/>
than the narrow party struggles of our present colonial <lb/>
politics could offer. But it was not merey to politicians <lb/>
that confederation offered a field worthy of their ambition. <lb/>
It must benefit young men in all the professinns. <lb/>
They had before them an enlarged field for their exer<lb break="no"/>tions, and proportionally larger prizes to stimulate these <lb/>
exertions in the professions of law and medicine. And <lb/>
it must be supposed that, in the course of time, there <lb/>
would be an army and an navy, in which our youth <lb/>
would have an opportunity of rising to eminence. And <lb/>
while his hon friend the member for Ferryland might <lb/>
be Home Minister or Receiver General of Canada, why <lb/>
might not the hon and gallant member for St. John's <lb/>
West attain the rank of Field Marshal Renouf? It would <lb/>
give a stimulous to the exertions of our young men in all <lb/>
        the professions; taking <hi rendition="simple:italic">excelsior</hi> as their motto, they <lb/>
would press forward in every art and science, and ulti<lb break="no"/>mately many would attain an eminence to which few in <lb/> 
the Colonies at present aspired. Than as to the commer<lb break="no"/>cial advantages of confederation. Look at our herring fish<lb break="no"/>ry, for instance, at present langhishing. Was it nothing <lb/>
to have such a market as Canada which in a few years <lb/>
would take all we could <choice><sic>produc</sic><corr>produce</corr></choice>? Her own population, in <lb/>
place of being our rivals in the fisheries would find more <lb/>
congenial and more profitable employment in the cultiva<lb break="no"/>tion of her prolific soul, exchanging her produce for those <lb/>
of our fisheries, was there nothing in this, that we had a <lb/>
country before us to go to, if we could not find congenial <lb/>
occupation here. And if when Canada was carrying out <lb/>
large public works we were united with her, was it to <lb/>
be assumed that none of these would be constructed <lb/>
here. And would not those carried out elsewhere afford <lb/>
employment to many of our citizens and labourers? <lb/>
Take, for instance, the extension of the Grand Trunk <lb/>
Railroad from Canada to the harbor of Halifax. Would <lb/>
not many of our people go to Nova Scotia and New <lb/>
Brunswick, and find employment upon that important <lb/>
national work? And would not this relieve the fisher<lb break="no"/>ies from he pressure of a surplus? Did we not know <lb/>
that bands of Irish reapers, crossed the Channel every <lb/>
year, and cut down the harvests of England and the <lb/>
South of Scotland, while many of the Scottish highland<lb break="no"/>ers found similar employment in the midland counties, <lb/>
and both carried home ample wages, which added <lb/>
materially to the comforts of the succeeding winter? <lb/>
We must remember that one of the results of confed<lb break="no"/>eration would be increased communication with the <lb/>
different provinces, of the confederacy. It might be <lb/>
said that the provinces, were open to our people now, <lb/>
but the work was not there now. Nor were they open <lb/>
in the same way as they would be when we became one <lb/>
people. There were some who now went to the other <lb/>
colonies and succeeded, but they were those who conques<lb break="no"/>ted difficulties. Certain travellers in the interior of <lb/>
Africa lately found a Scotchman there occupying an <lb/>
important position under one of the kings of Abysinia. <lb/>
Natives of the British islands were to be found making <lb/>
their way occasionally in Turkey, China, and other <lb/>
foreign countries, but these were the few exceptions of <lb/>
men of extraordinary ability and enterprise, who would <lb/>
push their way any where and in spite of all obstacles. <lb/>
But what would they find if the other colonies and this <lb/>
were one country? Our people, under confederation <lb/>
would pass from one country to another, as they now <lb/>
come from the outports to St. John's. And our shares <lb/>
of the general revenue remaining for public works would <lb/>
doubtless be expended in this Colony, and afford em<lb break="no"/>ployment to our people. Would not the union of the <lb/>
provinces induce such intercourse as to give sufficient <lb/>
employment to the proposed line of steamers between <lb/>
this port and Canada; and would not that give facilities <lb/>
and offer inducements for travelling, increasing our <lb/>
social intercourse with each other largely; and would <lb/>
not that be to our advantage, and would the commer<lb break="no"/>cial intercourse thereby promoted be of no benefit, if <lb/>
capitalists were induced to visit us, and engage in work<lb break="no"/>ing our mines, or establishing manufactures? Why <lb/>
should not a citizen of Quebec in place of going to work <lb/>
the copper mines at Lake Superior, come to this island, <lb/>
which was less distant then Lake Superior, while the <lb/>
facilities from sending the ore to market were much <lb/>
greater? Now he had to come to a foreign country, <lb/>
whose laws were different from those of Canada. But <lb/>
make both the same country, and it would be merely a <lb/>
question of profit and private preference. It had been <lb/>
said, as regards Canada, that we would derive the same <lb/>
advantages commercially, from free trade between the <lb/>
colonies as from a union. While the advantages would <lb/>
be limited, under a fee trade treaty, we could have no <lb/>
guarantee for their permanency. A treaty between the <lb/>
two colonies might be terminated at any time by the <lb/>
caprice of either party, while a union with Canada would <lb/>
be permanent. It had been stated that seeing the <lb/>
proposals for confederation arose from the strife of <lb/>
parties in Canada, the same difficulties might again occur, <lb/>
and we would be involved in them. But no such conse<lb break="no"/>quences could arise from confederation; and the working <lb/>
of the union could not be disturbed while it continued in <lb/>
existence. Another consequence of confederation would <lb/>
be our greater security from foreign aggression. It was <lb/>
said we might expect the protection of Great Britain to <lb/>
be continued under any circumstances. He had referred <lb/>
to the conditions to be exacted from us in this respect, <lb/>
but while it might be a question how we would stand <lb/>
with Great Britain if we kept out of the confederation, <lb/>
there could be no question that if we were into it we <lb/>
would have the protection of Great Britain and of the <lb/>
confederation also, and these two in close alliance, <lb/>
after a few years at all events, could withstand the world <lb/>
in arms. But then, we were told of the heavy military <lb/>
expenditure to which we would be subject. But only a <lb/>
very moderate military expenditure would be required at <lb/>
first, and why should we not have both an army and a <lb/>
navy when we gained strength and the ability to main<lb break="no"/>tail them without their being burdensome to the coun<lb break="no"/>try? Let us recollect also that as we often suffered <lb/>
from the fluctuations to which our fisheries expose us, <lb/>
and our people are sometimes reduced to extreme <lb/>
destitution, if we contribute to a common treasury, <lb/>
and if poverty, from the failure of the fisheries, <lb/>
overtake our people, there will be means available <lb/>
for warding off starvation. At present we have at <lb/>
the same time, wide spread poverty and reduced means <lb/>
for its relief, and we cannot apply to the neighbouring <lb/>
colonies, to whose treasuries we contributed nothing in <lb/>
our prosperity; and if we applied to Great Britain, we <lb/>
would be referred to our own resources. But if we <lb/>
were one people, we could go to Canada and ask relief <lb/>
for our impover shed population from the common <lb/>
treasury. Then, if we looked to the history of other <lb/>
countries, where small communities had become united <lb/>
into powerful states, we would find something in the <lb/>
light which history threw on this question. He (hon <lb/>
Attorney General) Bad always been of opinion that there <lb/>
could be no question of history being in favour of con<lb break="no"/>federation. In this house, for the first time, he had <lb/>
heard that position questioned. It did seem to him, <lb/>
however, that history was favourable to the union of <lb/>

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-16_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">2</fw>
        
        <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>

small states into larger. But he would not take a wide <lb/>
field to sustain his views, nor would he go across the <lb/>
Atlantic to find example, it was not long since Nova <lb/>
Sexia and Cape Breton were separate Provinces; and <lb/>
every one who knew the history of these Provinces, <lb/>
knew they had advanced more rapidly since the union <lb/>
than they did in the same length of time when separated. <lb/>
About twenty years ago, a few residents <lb/>
in Cape Breton got up an agitation for a dissolution of <lb/>
the union, but it was frowned down by the thinking <lb/>
people throughout the Province. New Brunswick and <lb/>
Nova Scotia were at one time united, and subsequently <lb/>
separated, and the statesmen of both Provinces were so <lb/>
satisfied of the advantages of their being reunited, that a <lb/>
conference was held at Charlottetown last summer to <lb/>
devise the means for a legislative union of these Provin<lb break="no"/>ces and Prince Edward Island, which was terminated by <lb/>
the proposition from Canada for the more extensive union <lb/>
now under consideration. If, however, all this can be <lb/>
        said in favour of <hi rendition="simple:italic">confederation</hi>, what has been urged on <lb/>
the other side? Confederation, like all questions in<lb break="no"/>volving great changes, and affecting important interests, <lb/>
had met considerable opposition, and it was well <lb/>
that it should be so, for it was not desirable to change, <lb/>
except for some great advantage, and the more such <lb/>
a matter was opposed, the more thoroughly would its <lb/>
details be examined. Some opposed confederation, <lb/>
doubtless, from interested motives, either because <lb/>
they saw in it pecuniary loss to themselves, or a les<lb break="no"/>sening of their personal, social, or political importance, <lb/>
some doubtless, from conscientious motives. He (hon <lb/>
Attorney General) did not mean to attribute interested <lb/>
motives to any of those who differed from him, but their <lb/>
existence ought not to be overlooked, and every objection <lb/>
should be carefully weighed, and, if possible, removed. <lb/>
If this were not practicable, and should well-founded <lb/>
objections preponderate, the union snauld be abandoned. <lb/></p> 

<p>He (hon Attorney General) would briefly refer to the <lb/>
objections urged against the proposed confederation. <lb/>
It had been objected, that in going into the union, we <lb/>
were giving up our independence—our right to inde<lb break="no"/>pendent legislation. Every savage entering society <lb/>
gave up a portion of his independence, but did he lose <lb/>
by the change? True, if we went into confederation, <lb/>
we would give up a portion of our present control of <lb/>
our affairs. But he did think that we would <choice><sic>bs</sic><corr>be</corr></choice> well <lb/>
quit of it. What was the history of this colony since <lb/>
we had a local Legislature? It was not one on which <lb/>
we could look with satisfaction. Why, since 1832 we <lb/>
were violently agitated, every four years, with party <lb/>
strife, aggravated by the rancour of religious differ<lb break="no"/>snces; and our representatives came together excited <lb/>
by the bitterest feelings towards each other. And <lb/>
after they met, the object of one party in that House <lb/>
was to hold on to office, and of the other to turn them <lb/>
out; and, in the nearly equal division of parties which <lb/>
prevailed, it was found that neither the one party nor <lb/>
the other could do much for the promotion of the <lb/>
public good. If the strife of parties should have a <lb/>
narrower scope and have less bitterness, as the objects <lb/>
coutended for would have less importance, from the <lb/>
concession of power to be made to the general govern<lb break="no"/>ment, would it not be a great benefit to the commu<lb break="no"/>nity? On the other hand, if we gave up some power <lb/>
which we at present held, would we not nave an equi<lb break="no"/>valent in the shire we should receive in the general <lb/>
government? Another objection urged against going <lb/>
into a Confederation with Canada, was that she had <lb/>
a local debt of over sixty millions of dollars, which the <lb/>
confederation must assume. But of what importance <lb/>
was that debt, as compared with the resources of that <lb/>
magnificent province? If she had a large debt, she <lb/>
had the public works for the construction of which the <lb/>
greater portion of it was incurred. Our debt could <lb/>
not be diminished; and what had we to represent a <lb/>
large portion of it, but the pauperism resulting from <lb/>
the failure of our fisheries? But, it is said, we would <lb/>
be subject, by the union to a large increase of taxa<lb break="no"/>tion. He did not intend to go into the question of <lb/>
the tariff. He would leave that to those who had <lb/>
studed that part of the subject more particularly, and <lb/>
were more competent to deal with it than he was. He <lb/>
would, however, make one or two general observa<lb break="no"/>tions upon this point. In the first place, much use <lb/>
had been made, on the other side, of a Customs' <lb/>
return showing that the Canada tariff was, in many <lb/>
aspects, higher than our own, and was one which, if <lb/>
applied to us, would, as alleged, increase our taxation <lb/>
30 or 40 per cent. and it had been said in argument, <lb/>
    with reference to the return,—"See how much more <lb/>
you will pay for this article, and how much more for <lb/>
that." With as little reason and logical force might <lb/>
    he (hon A Gen) take up the same return, and point<lb break="no"/>ing to the other articles, say,—"See how much less, <lb/>
under confederation, you will ply for some other <lb/>
articles, your grog, for instance, you will get for little <lb/>
or nothing. You will pay no duty on lines, twines <lb/>
and fishery materials, £c.." But in <choice><sic>trath</sic><corr>truth</corr></choice>, neither one <lb/>
side nor the other of such an argument, affected the <lb/>
point really at issue. He considered that nothing, <lb/>
or or against the union, could be drawn from con<lb break="no"/>trasting the tariff of the two countries, and for this <lb/>
plain reason, that the Canada tariff, being framed for <lb/>
Canada alone, was wholly inapplicable, in many par<lb break="no"/>ticulars, to the very different commercial interests of <lb/>
tne lower provinces; and the first thing which the <lb/>
united Legislature would have to attend to, would be <lb/>
to frame such a tariff (very different from the present) <lb/>
as would suit the general interest, and not the trade <lb/>
of Canada alone. It seemed to him, therefore, to be <lb/>
a waste of time to discuss the effect of the existing <lb/>
tariffs on this question. Further, let it be noticed, on <lb/>
the question of increased taxation under the union, <lb/>
that as by the rapid growth of the other provinces in <lb/>
population and wealth, the area of taxation would <lb/>
increase rapidly year by year, and as (the expense of <lb/>
governing 20,000 people being very little more than <lb/>
that of governing 1O,000) the taxation would not in<lb break="no"/>creass with the numbers of the tax-payers, the actual <lb/>
burden ot taxation, on each individual, would year by <lb/>
year, be lessening. In this advantage we should <lb/>
share, not by our own growth, but by the growth of <lb/>
the other provinces, so that, under this union, we <lb/>
would have this result, which we could never have out <lb/>
of it, namely, that the larger it became, the more <lb/>
would the burden of taxation be lessened to out <lb/>
stationary population, to be, spread over the increasing <lb/>
population of the sister colonies. Let the clamourers <lb/>
about increased taxation ponder over this a little. <lb/>
Further he (hon A Gen) would ask, having regard <lb/>
to the present condition of this colony, with is debt <lb/>
in spite of the most rigid economy on the part of the <lb/>
government, increasing, year by year, how long it will <lb/>
be, remaining as we are, before our own tariff rises to <lb/>
the highest figure of that of Canada. We must pay <lb/>
our debts, and pay the necessary cost of government, <lb/>
support our starving poor, and sustain the public <lb/>
credit, with what means (our present revenue being <lb/>
insufficient) but by increased taxation? It has been <lb/>
rising for years past. It is now 11 1/2 pet cent., and is <lb/>
yet insufficieut. How long will it us before, of our <lb/>
own accord, and from sneer necessity, we lay on our <lb/>
prople duties beyond wnat our most excited alarmists <lb/>
fear trom the union? On the other hand, supposing, <lb/>
for the sake of argument, that we do pay more duties <lb/>
under the union than we are at present subjected to, <lb/>
of what importance will that be to our people, it, as <lb/>
we assume, by the opening of other fields ot labour, <lb/>
and by means of the older advantages to spring to <lb/>
them from the union, their ability to hear further tax<lb break="no"/>ation is increased in an equal or greater proportion? <lb/>
Will we not, in effect, benefit by the change? To put <lb/>

<cb/>

this idea in figures, what did it matter to a man if you <lb/>
increased his taxation 5 per cent., if, at the same time, <lb/>
you increased the value of his labour 10 or 15 per <lb/>
cent? But supposing further, the Canadian tariff of <lb/>
20 per cent., retained on the importation of manufac<lb break="no"/>tured goods, as was feared by the anti-confederates, <lb/>
was it to be supposed that the same amount of duty <lb/>
<choice><sic>wyull</sic><corr>would</corr></choice> be received as would now be produced by that <lb/>
rate of duty? No such thing. The effect would be a <lb/>
change of trade, not increased taxation paid by our <lb/>
people. In place of British manufactures, they would <lb/>
use articles produced in Canada and the other provin<lb break="no"/>ces, where they now manufactured extensively, and <lb/>
which manufactures would be largely imported here,and <lb/>
would pay no duty at all. At present our merchants im<lb break="no"/>ported British manufactured goods to suppl your wants; <lb/>
but, under confederation, they would find it to their <lb/>
advantage to import from Canada, by which our peo<lb break="no"/>ple would be very much benefited, by being sup<lb break="no"/>plied, at a lower price, with articles as good, and <lb/>
sometimes very much better than those they get now. <lb/>
Those of our merchants whose capital was employed <lb/>
in the manufacture or importation of British goods, <lb/>
would, for a time, suffer by the change, but the people <lb/>
at large would benefit, and we are here to legislate, <lb/>
not for the benefit of the few, but of the many, doing <lb/>
no unnecessary damage, nevertheless, to any interest <lb/>
in the community. It had been objected that Canada <lb/>
imports largely of manufactured goods from England. <lb/>
But for the same reason that the wealthy citizens of <lb/>
London wore French kid gloves, French silks and <lb/>
such like foreign articles, at a higher price than the <lb/>
better articles manufactured at home; and he did not <lb/>
think the importation of British manufactured goods <lb/>
into Canada, to the extent of 15 or 16 millions of dol<lb break="no"/>lars, was very large after all for a population of about <lb/>
three millions, especially when we took into consider<lb break="no"/>ation what went over the border, on account of the <lb/>
tariff of the United States being so much higher than <lb/>
that of Canada. It was idle to suppose that there <lb/>
should be such extensive manufactures in Canada, un<lb break="no"/>less the people consumed the goods. We knew they <lb/>
manufactured largely. He (hon A. Gen) would say <lb/> 
that it seemed to him treating this important matter <lb/>
in a very unworthy way, to limit it to our present cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances. We were legislating for future genera<lb break="no"/>tions, for all time to come, for posterity principally; <lb/>
and it was a contracted view to take of such a ques<lb break="no"/>tion, to raise objections to the existing tariff of Canada, <lb/>
which might change from year to year, and was a con<lb break="no"/>sideration of so temporary a character; and he must <lb/>
say, moreover, that he deprecated the tone and man<lb break="no"/>ner in which the motives and the conduct of our Can<lb break="no"/>adian friends had been treated by those opposed to <lb/>
the union. They had, in the most open and candid <lb/>
manner, stated their own desire for confederation and <lb/>
their reasons for it. They concealed nothing, but <lb/>
placed the proposal on the broad ground that the <lb/>
scheme would be for the advantage of the other pro<lb break="no"/>vinces as well as of the Canadas. We had the assur<lb break="no"/>ance of the Governor General, referred to in his Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency's speech, that there was no desire on the part <lb/>
of the Canadian ministry to fasten their tariff upon us. <lb/>
And yet the Canadian advocates of confederation had <lb/>
been spoken of as being influenced solely by a desire <lb/>
    to get hold of <hi rendition="simple:italic">this fine Island, and turn it and its <lb/>
valuable resources and wealthy population</hi> to their own <lb/>
profit and advantage by means of the proposed union. <lb/>
Certainly if these were the feelings with which we are <lb/>
to regard our Canadian brethren, the less we have to <lb/>
do with them the better. But he (non A. Gen) did <lb/>
not feel so. He regarded the proposal for a union in <lb/>
the same light as in private life he would regard the <lb/>
offer of partnership, upon fair and legitimate terms, <lb/>
from a wellthy and influential firm, of high character, <lb/>
unlimited resorces, large means and extens we credit, <lb/>
to a small trader living in his neighbourhood, without <lb/>
any prospect of becoming anything beyond a small <lb/>
trader, but whose alliance was sought simply because <lb/>
the latter had some advantages of position, water priv<lb break="no"/>ileges, or the like, which the other desired. In the <lb/>
present case we were the small trader, Canada the <lb/>
wealthy, prosperous one, and as in private life, such <lb/>
an offer would be accepted with alacrity, so should we <lb/>
gladly accede to the proposal now made to us. It had <lb/>
been objected that Canada would draw us into war <lb/>
with the United States. If Canada should be drawn <lb/>
into war, we knew that whether we had confederation <lb/>
or not, we could not avoid taking part in it, for it <lb/>
would be a war between Great Britain and the United <lb/>
States, in which all the colonies would be involved. <lb/>
It was said that Canada had an extensive frontier <lb/>
which it would require a large force to defend. But <lb/>
if Canada had an extensive frontier, that of her neigh<lb break="no"/>bour was equally extensive, and it would soon be a <lb/>
question which was the stronger. It we looked to the <lb/>
history of Canada we would find how she on former <lb/>
occasions held her own against great odds; and we <lb/>
all knew that she was prospering more rapidly in pop<lb break="no"/>ulation and material property than the adjoining States <lb/>
of the neighbouring republic. He would again observe <lb/>
that we are not legislating merely for the present, but <lb/>
for future generations; and we know that a few years <lb/>
would place Canada on an equality, in this respect, <lb/>
with her southern neighbour; and in connection with <lb/>
this branch of the subject it should not be forgotten <lb/>
that we wonld under it be much better able to resist <lb/>
successfully the encroachments of France upon our <lb/>
fishing grounds than we are at present. Now we dare <lb/>
not even arrest a French craft trespassing on our <lb/>
waters lest the act should excite the ill-will of our <lb/>
allies. Under confederation what would hinder our <lb/>
strictly enforcing our treaty rights with that nation? <lb/>
It was objected that the details in the terms of Con<lb break="no"/>federation ware not such as were in some respects sat<lb break="no"/>isfactory. No document ever drawn up could be re<lb break="no"/>garded as perfect; but it seemed to him that there <lb/>
would be a difficulty in arranging terms that on the <lb/>
whole would be less objectionable. As to the question <lb/>
of taxation, it could not be shown that a high tariff of <lb/>
duties would be more acceptable to the people of Can<lb break="no"/>ada, New Brunswick or Nova Scotia, than to those of <lb/>
this colony; and as to the appropriation of the revenue <lb/>
for objects of public utility, we would all be represent<lb break="no"/>ed in the Federal House of Cemmons, as each separ<lb break="no"/>ate district in Newfoundland was in the House of <lb/>
Assembly of this colony, where we could not give a <lb/>
shilling to one district but all the others claimed an <lb/>
equal share. So we would be represented in both <lb/>
branches of the Federal Legislature where our repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives would look out for the interests of New<lb break="no"/>foundland. It should be recollected that the General <lb/>
Government would be composed of representatives of <lb/>
Canada and all the other provinces and colonies of the <lb/>
Confederation, and that they would feel board to con<lb break="no"/>sult the wishes and to promote the prosperity of all. <lb/>
He believed these statesmen would deal fairly with us <lb/>
as they expected we should do with them. The report <lb/>
of the conference showed an amount of political saga<lb break="no"/>city and judgment which must satisfy us that the <lb/>
statesmen from whom it emanated were men of no <lb/>
common minds; and he would be slow indeed to find <lb/>
fault with the resolutions. Objection had been taken <lb/>
to the phase in the representation allowed to us. But <lb/>
the representation was based on a fair principle. Was <lb/>
it unfair that we should have a small representation <lb/>
when our numbers woull not entitle us to more? <lb/>
Would a confederation based on injustice in this par<lb break="no"/>ticular be likely to be permanent? As to the division <lb/>
of the funds drawn from our revenue, the general gov<lb break="no"/>ernment assumed a certain portion of our expenditure <lb/>
and took the whole of our Customs' revenue, and in <lb/>

<cb/>

return they gave us an annual allowance which was <lb/>
larger than the average of what we had for years <lb/>
past, applicable to the branches of expenditure which <lb/>
we were to continue to bear. It was objected that <lb/>
this revenue would not increase with our increasing <lb/>
population. But we received an amount which was <lb/>
adequate to all our wants. And was it not better that <lb/>
we should have a certain allowance from the general <lb/>
funds, which would not fall, than to have to depend <lb/>
upon a revenue liable to such fluctations as we ex<lb break="no"/>perienced at present; and supposing our population <lb/>
were to increase, it must be from new sources of em<lb break="no"/>ployment, which would create additional wealth, and <lb/>
there would be a corresponding reduction in cer<lb break="no"/>tain portions of our expenditure. But supposing that <lb/>
our revenue should not be sufficient tho meet an emer<lb break="no"/>gency, and that we required a larger amount, had we <lb/>
not the general government and Legislature to appeal <lb/>
to? <lb/>
</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName>.—But they said the confederate gov<lb break="no"/>ernment would give a specific sum, and no more; for <lb/>
whatever more we might require we must resort to <lb/>
direct taxation, <lb/></p> 

    <p><persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ArTTORNEY GENERAL</persName>.—Yes, as a general <lb/>
rule, it was so; but if any special emergency arose, we <lb/>
might fairly go to them, and our claim would, there <lb/>
can be no doubt, be favorably considered. It was ob<lb break="no"/>jected that the General Government and Legislature <lb/>
were invested with large powers of taxation. But how <lb/>
could a confederation be formed without such powers? <lb/>
How could we form a confederation which we expect<lb break="no"/>ed to be permanent, and to become, in the course of <lb/>
time, large and powerful, without such powers of taxa<lb break="no"/>tion? Large powers were necessary to sustain nation<lb break="no"/>al existence. Some exigency might arise, when, for the <lb/>
preservation of our nationality, great efforts must be <lb/>
made, and the exercise of extensive powers resorted <lb/>
to. Lastly, there was a consideration of much im<lb break="no"/>portance, which must not be overlooked in the discus<lb break="no"/>sion of this object. It had already been put in this <lb/>
House, in the shape of a question, but it had received <lb/>
no satisfactory reply—What did those who opposed <lb/>
confederation—who were disposed to reject the ad<lb break="no"/>vantages now offered to them, propose as the means <lb/>
whereby they would, in the absence of Confederation, <lb/>
raise the country from its present depression? Were <lb/>
they prepared to take the helm, and find means and <lb/>
ways by which our psople were to be elevated from <lb/>
poverty and demoralization to comfort and indepen<lb break="no"/>dance? Look at our present position. Struggle as <lb/>
we may, even with a fair revenue, we cannot keep <lb/>
from going into debt every year for our current ex<lb break="no"/>penditure. This past year, the casualty of a North <lb/>
East wind blowing for a few weeks in the spring of <lb/>
the year occasioned us a debt of nearly £4,000. It was <lb/>
answered:—"Oh let us have good fisheries, and we <lb/>
are all right." But in the first place, who is to com<lb break="no"/>mand these good fisheries, and secondly, suppose we <lb/>
ad them, what does the history of the colony show? <lb/>
That when we had good fisheries, we never laid by <lb/>
for a rainy day, or paid off a shilling of debt; but, <lb/>
on the contrary, got deeper into debt every year, <lb/>
whether, the fisheries were bad or good. The best <lb/>
that could happen to us was an alternation of series <lb/>
of good and bad fisheries. And what would be the re<lb break="no"/>sult of this, judging from experience? As time rolled <lb/>
on, our debt increasing year by year,white our resourc<lb break="no"/>es were diminishing, and a third of our population, <lb/>
for a third of the year, were in a starving condition. <lb/>
The end of all this it was not difficult to discover— <lb/>
certain, inevitable national bankruptey; and if so, <lb/>
where was the hope, in our present is lated state, <lb/>
for the future of Newfoundland? Go into confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, and these evils are, to a great extent, cer<lb break="no"/>tainly mitigated; and, as we contend, prospects are <lb/>
held out to us and our children of a state of things <lb/>
raised far, in every respect, socially, politically and <lb/>
commercially, above our present condition. It has <lb/>
been said—"Better bear the ills we have than <lb/>
change for others that we know not of," and that by <lb/>
entering into confederation, it might be "out of the <lb/>
frying pan into the fire." But this is a mistake of <lb/>
those who say thus. We are in the fire already; and <lb/>
unless we make a desperate effort for our own relief, <lb/>
we shall shortly have nothing of us remaining but a <lb/>
heap of ashes. He (hon A Gen) did see nothing before <lb/>
the country, if this proposal was rejected. He said it <lb/>
to the house and he said it to the country. That was <lb/>
not a matter for the present time, but for the future. <lb/>
Sations did not grow to maturity in a few years. Gen<lb break="no"/>erations passed away before the result of changes came <lb/>
to maturity. But that confederation would come, and <lb/>
it was for us now to consider it; and he did say that <lb/>
as he would not hesitate to embark in it all he was <lb/>
worth himself, so he would recommend the same <lb/>
course to others. We had not had many years of <lb/>
legislation, and while we had the opportunity, it ap<lb break="no"/>peared to him that it was a duty we owed to the coun<lb break="no"/>try to take advantage of the offer now made to us, and <lb/>
to embrace, a change which, in his judgment, would <lb/>
lead on to fortune. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:SHEA2">Mr. SHEA</persName>—Did the hon gentleman mean, when he <lb/>
spoke of the large powers of taxation reserved to the <lb/>
General Government, that they could resort to direct <lb/>
taxation? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> –Certainly. The power <lb/>
was necessary, it should be, where the constitution <lb/>
was a written one. It was a power the exercise of <lb/>
which might be essential to the very existence of the <lb/>
confeceration. But as it was also reserved to the local <lb/>
Legislatures as a means for the defrayal of their local <lb/>
expenses, it was evident, he thought, except perhaps <lb/>
in the matter of excise on spirits, which might be re<lb break="no"/>garded as part of the Customs' laws, it was a power to <lb/>
be exercised by the General Government only in ex<lb break="no"/>treme cases. The hon gentleman then moved the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing resolution:—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>,—That having under their serious and most <lb/>
deliberate consideration the proposal for the forma<lb break="no"/>tion of a Federal Union of the British North Amer<lb break="no"/>ican Provinces, upon the terms contained in the <lb/>
Report of the Convention of Delegates held at Quebec <lb/>
on the 10th October last,—the Despatch of the Right <lb/>
Honorable the <choice><sic>Sec etary</sic><corr>Secretary</corr></choice> of State for the Colonies, <lb/>
dated Dec. 3, 1864—the observations of His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency the Governor in relation to this subject in his <lb/>
opening Speech of the present Session—and the <lb/>
Report of the Newfoundland Delegates, this Com<lb break="no"/>mittee are of opinion, that having regard to the <lb/>
comparative novelty and very great importance of <lb/>
this project, it is desirable that, before a vote of the <lb/>
Legislature is taken upon it, it should be submitted <lb/>
    to the consideration of the people at large—particu<lb break="no"/>larly as the action of the other Provinces does not <lb/>
appear to require that it should be hastily disposed <lb/>
of and as (the present being the last Session of this <lb/>
Assembly) no unreasonable delay can be occasioned <lb/>
by this course; and they therefore recommend that <lb/>
a final determination upon this important subject be <lb/>
deferred to the next meeting of the Legislatire. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. KENT</persName> rose with great pleasure to second the <lb/>
resolution which the hon Attorney General had just <lb/>
proposed. Nothing could be fairer than that resolu<lb break="no"/>tion. It was in perfect accordance with, the views of <lb/>
the mercantile body and the desire of the people of <lb/>
this town as expressed in the petition which had been <lb/>
presented to this house. That certainly was the most <lb/>
important question that had over been brought before <lb/>
that legislature, and it carried, would result in a poli<lb break="no"/>tical and govermental revolution. That resolution <lb/>
in question reminded him (Mr. Kent) of an anecdote <lb/>
he once read of an old Quaker lady who said that there <lb/>

<cb/>

were three things in this world which she could never <lb/>
understand. The first was why little boys threw <lb/>
stones at the apple trees to bring down the apples, <lb/>
when if they only waited until the apples were ripe <lb/>
they would drop of the trees; the second was why <lb/>
people should persist in going to war to be killed, <lb/>
when if they remained at home, they would certainly <lb/>
die in due course; and the third was why young gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen should run after young ladies, when it they <lb/>
only waited, the young ladies would run afer them. <lb/>
(Laughter.) Now the spirit of the resolution was in <lb/>
perfect accordance with the theory of the Quaker lady, <lb/>
Our adhesion to confederation was a foregone conclu<lb break="no"/>sion, and only required time definitely to settle it. He <lb/>
(Mr. Kent) felt that it was impossible for him to ela<lb break="no"/>borate this subject in the masterly manner in which <lb/>
the hon Attornny General treated it. The learned <lb/>
Premier had brought to bear on this question the <lb/>
stores of a richly cultivated mind, and the result of <lb/>
the study and refiection which he had bestowed upon <lb/>
it, he had this day given to this House. And he (Mr. <lb/>
Kent) must say that an abler discourse he never lis<lb break="no"/>tened to. It was creditable to the people that they <lb/>
had taken this normal view of the great question, and <lb/>
to see they did not give up the advantage they pos<lb break="no"/>sessed for that which they regarded as entirely theo<lb break="no"/>retical and not calculated to ameliorate the condition <lb/>
of the country. He (Mr. Kent) was perfectly satis<lb break="no"/>fied with this delay. It would enable the quesion to <lb/>
be more closely, <choice><sic>iavestigated</sic><corr>investigated</corr></choice> by the country at <lb/>
    large, and he had no doubt that the fears which seem<lb break="no"/>ed to be at present entertained would disappear, <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
the mist before the morning sun. It was not fair to <lb/>
argue this question as if there w is no change in our <lb/>
condition. Our relative condition, and connection <lb/> 
with the mother country was greatly altered. If we <lb/>
refused to enter into this confederation, would we not <lb/>
have the in difference of the mother country, on one <lb/> 
side, and the antipathy of the Federal Union on the <lb/> 
other? And then, when we were met, as we assured<lb break="no"/>ly would be, by a hostile tariff in their ports, what <lb/>
wonld be our condition? Their strength would be <lb/>
our weakness. In 1861 there was a select conmittee <lb/>
appointed by the Imperial Parliament, to enquire and <lb/>
report upon the military expenditure of the Colonies, <lb/> 
and in the evidence taken befose it, Mr. Gladstone <lb/>
recorded the following opinion: "[ would almost <lb/> 
venture to say, without speaking of cases in which <lb/>
    circumstances are altogether peculiar, <hi rendition="simple:italic">that no commu<lb break="no"/>nity which is not primarily charge with the ordinary <lb/>
business of its own defence, is really, or can be, in the <lb/>
full sense of the word, a free community</hi>. The privi<lb break="no"/>lege of freedom and the burdens of freedom are ab<lb break="no"/>solutely associated together; to bear the burden is as <lb/>
necessary as to enjoy the privilege, in order to form <lb/>
that character which is the great ornament of all free<lb break="no"/>dom itself." Here was an opinion that it was neces<lb break="no"/>sary for the peservation of its freedom, that every <lb/>
country should pay for its own military defences. <lb/>
Surely the military defences of Canada ought not to <lb/>
frighten us, especially when we reflected on her al<lb break="no"/>most boundless resources, and mercantile wealth. <lb/>
But the retantion of the colonies by the parent state <lb/>
since the establish ment of free trade, seems to be of <lb/>
secondary consideration altogether; and in supporting <lb/>
this he (Mr. Kent) would quote the language of <lb/>
Lord Grey, use I in his evidence before the committee <lb/> 
already referred to. "In the last century the po<lb break="no"/>session of colonies, of which the trade was to be mo<lb break="no"/>nopolised by the mother country, was believed to be a <lb/>
source of wealth to a nation. Hence to wrest from <lb/>
each other their colonial possessions, was regarded by <lb/>
European nations as an object of great importance; <lb/>
and it was regarded almost a sufficient object for a <lb/>
war, to capture one or two sugar colonies. But it is <lb/>
now generally understool that monopolising the trade <lb/>
of colonies is contrary to the true interest of both <lb/>
parties, and that nothing, therefore, is gained by con<lb break="no"/>quering colonies for this purpose." Hon. gentlemen <lb/>
who had spoken adverse to this question, said that we <lb/>
were going to abandon the British flag. Such an as<lb break="no"/>sertion was a palpable absurdity. But our present <lb/>
position was in his (Mr. Kent's) estimation, tanta<lb break="no"/>mount to it, for it tended to alineate the affections of <lb/>
the British people from us. He was glad to see the <lb/>
alarm which this question had created. It showed the <lb/>
value which the people placed on our representative <lb/>
form of government; and he believed that the success<lb break="no"/>ful working of our present form of government, in<lb break="no"/>stead of being an argument against Confederation, was <lb/>
in favour of it. It had been a normal school for us, <lb/>
and had fitted our public men for occupying a high <lb/>
platform in the great confederation which he believed <lb/>
would, in the future, be an influential and powerful <lb/>
nation. He (Mr. Kent) saw no hope for this country <lb/>
if she remained in her present position. The late go<lb break="no"/>vernment had been compelled to consolidate a debt of <lb/>
some £45,00), an i he believed that the present would <lb/> 
be compelled to the same, and so on witn every suc<lb break="no"/>ceeding government, until we stood on the brink of <lb/>
national insolvency. This question of Confederation <lb/> 
had been so ably argued that he (Mr. Kent) had no <lb/>
intention of saying anything further on it. The mat<lb break="no"/>ter was to go before the country for the people to ne<lb break="no"/>gative or adopt as they pleased, and he only trusted <lb/>
that whatever might he the conclusion arrived at, it <lb/>
would be the one best adopted for promoting the sub<lb break="no"/>stantial welfare of the country. <lb/></p> 

<p>The committee then rose, and the chairman report<lb break="no"/>ed progress—to sit again to-morrow. <lb/></p> 

<p>The house then adjourned until three o'clock to-<lb break="yes"/>morrow. <lb/></p> 


    <!-- IC, 2018-11-27, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>ſº §Itufmmitmer. <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOH.W.?.S.: <lb/>
THURSDAY, MARCH 16, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>We have frequently referred to the necessity of great<lb break="no"/>er attention to Agriculture on the part of our popu<lb break="no"/>lation, and to the large benefits they forfeit by their <lb/>
neglect of this important resource. One of the <lb/>
mist valuable elements of the pursuit is the rearing <lb/>
of Sheep, and for this, it is universally admitted, we <lb/>
possess in Newfoundland peculiar facilities and advant<lb break="no"/>ages; yet, strange to tell, in spite of these induce<lb break="no"/>ments, the want of employment and a wide-spread <lb/>
pauperism make up our unvarying and incessant cum<lb break="no"/>plaint. While we have to deplore this degrading <lb/>
anomaly of our condition, it is at least somewhat satis<lb break="no"/>factory to observe that public attention is at last being <lb/>
aroused to the demand for remedial effort, and <lb/>
it is due to the Agricultural Society to say that <lb/>
this appears to be chiefly the result of their <lb/>
persistent and most laudable endeavours. This <lb/>
Body have long devoted themselves in good ear<lb break="no"/>nest to inquiries the object of which has been to <lb/>
awaken our people from their permicious supineness <lb/>
on the subject, and to impress them with a conviction <lb/>
that to this cause they owe much of that want <lb/>
and miserable dependance waich have been their lok <lb/></p> 

<p>disappear, ºr—-<lb break="maybe"/></p> 

<p>3 <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/></p> 

<p>t <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/>
\ <lb/></p> 

<p># <lb/></p> 

<p>% <lb/></p> 

<p>d. <lb/></p> 

<p>} <lb/>
A. <lb/></p> 

<p>. <lb/></p> 

<p>e­ <lb/></p> 

<p>In pursuance of their wise º <lb/>
short time since, applied <lb/>
procure return" from the <lb/>
island of the number. of <lb/>
which have for a certain n <lb/>
troyed by those ferocious p <lb/>
amongst us have been st <lb/>
indispensable helps to th <lb/>
evidence thus brought t <lb/>
us to some effective measure <lb/>
strous evil we are cherishi <lb/>
be to our lasting shame. In <lb/>
to the Legislature by the S <lb/>
we have the truly alarming: <lb/>
last five years there have be <lb/>
this Island 4,136 sheep, <lb/>
228 goats, and in view d <lb/>
fice of food and means of <lb/>
lature is prayed to interpose <lb/>
that relief and protection wh <lb/>
so loudly and imperatively c <lb/>
canno: permit onrselves to dº <lb/>
such an appeal will now <lb/>
1)ifficulties may be pleaded <lb/>
may stand in the way, but r <lb/>
fºr a-laund that such obstacl <lb/>
foot, and that the industry o <lb/>
this cause shall be rescued fr <lb/>
lated to new snd vigorous exe <lb/>
in these late warnings a clea <lb/>
have actually lost, but of the <lb/>
have possessed, had the <lb/>
since removed, for the numbe <lb/>
in spite of such danger bears <lb/>
which we should have counte <lb/>
ror of their destruction. We <lb/>
an incalculable supply of goo <lb/>
with it an amount of occup <lb/>
manufacture of wool, which w <lb/>
saved many hundreds of poor <lb/>
and worse calamities. But Ł <lb/>
mined now that, as far as <lb/>
there shall be an end of the <lb/>
present staring us in the face <lb/></p> 

<p>[to THE EDITOR OF THE <lb/>
Sir, I make it a rule to <lb/>
accuracies in the reports of m <lb/>
in the papers published da <lb/>
words attributed to me in the <lb/>
in reporting observations of <lb/>
March 7th, are so grossly in <lb/>
myself bound to deny that I e <lb/>
further, that my observations <lb/>
cellency the Governor had a <lb/>
cy. The subject was the pres <lb/>
tion from the Catholics of Car <lb/>
ment of I)irectors to the Gram <lb/>
cality. The Daily N. we repor <lb/>
* The board was denied the n <lb/>
so that it might proceed to <lb/>
met and appointed a teacher; <lb/>
lency appointed two Protesta <lb/>
done for the purpºse of crew <lb/>
in the country" Nuw, Sur, t <lb/>
misrepresentation is that it is <lb/>
tent on can be gathered from <lb/>
manner in treating the subj. <lb/>
ing His Excellency the Gº <lb/>
I complained that h's name w <lb/>
appear that His Excellency <lb/>
the appointments to the Carl <lb/>
and to verify my statements. <lb/>
the Royal Gazette the annou <lb/>
pointmeuts, all b the Gover <lb/>
exception of the appointment <lb/>
mar School, which are annon <lb/>
the Governor alone. And I <lb/>
publication as tending to lead <lb/>
on the part of the Catholics v <lb/>
to a subject about which t <lb/>
excited. This, with past pro <lb/>
public to comprehend how a <lb/>
hood of Editors are that I sh <lb/>
Excellency the Governor. <lb/>
I am, Sir, <lb/></p> 

<p>Yo <lb/></p> 

<p>-º-º: <lb/></p> 

<p>1) Ifd,—At Spaniard's Bay <lb/>
lingering illness, in the 77th <lb/>
liain Gosse, an old and respe: <lb/></p> 

<p>On Monday last, after a <lb/>
with Christian resignation to <lb/>
the beloved wife of Mr. ( <lb/>
years. Her funeral wili take <lb/></p> 

<p>Holloway's OINTMENT <lb/>
emption from sores, ulcers,bu <lb/>
most diseases of the skin, wi <lb/>
perseyering use of these adm <lb/>
ºnay be iufºu...', -\-1:...i <lb/>
regard to sex or the duration <lb/>
way's Ointmant and Pills are <lb/>
indolent ulcerations of the 1. <lb/>
ºther applications and consi. <lb/>
of pain and death. No risk <lb/>
the use of Holloway's med, <lb/>
allays pain, smarting, and 1 <lb/>
from foul matter, represses jº <lb/>
es the growth of good heal <lb/>
ultimately form a sound surf <lb/>
-º­ <lb/></p> 

<p>THE Gloay of A Woy <lb/>
HAIR.—Marriage is the goal <lb/>
and nothing aids in the ma <lb/>
coveted, like a splendid he <lb/>
of Mrs. S. A. Allen's Wor <lb/>
Zylobalsamum, or Hair Dres <lb/>
act directly on the roots of t <lb/>
natural nourishinent required <lb/>
them. J. J. Dearin Soie A <lb/>
to whom all orders must be a <lb/></p> 

<p>SHIPPING INTA <lb/></p> 

<p>ENTEaF. <lb/>
March 10-Florence, Pattle, <lb/></p> 

<p>ston &amp; Co <lb/>
cLeal <lb/></p> 

<p>March 14–Florence, Carri <lb/>
Johnston &amp; Co. <lb/>
Loadi: <lb/>
March 9–Georgina, barbad. <lb/>
*—Balclutha, West Indies, <lb/>
13-Tiger, Portugal, K. Mc <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>