<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-21" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
    <title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-02-21">21 February 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-03-02"/>,
    <date when="1865-03-20"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>,
    <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-03-02_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-03-02_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
    <item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-03-20_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-11-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-02_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-02_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-02_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-02_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
    <surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-20_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-20_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-02_Page_1.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">St. John's, Thursday, March 2, 1865.</fw>

    <!-- IC, 2018-11-13, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>Notices. <lb/></p> 

<p>£rs: Mothers Mother <lb/></p> 

<p>T tail to procure Mrs. WIN s!!! <lb/>
ºup, for, children teething. Thi <lb/>
tiºn is the prescription ºf One . Yºlº <lb/></p> 

<p>ysicians and nurses in the United sº º <lb/></p> 

<p>in used for thirty years with 8: i. <lb/>
ind success by miſſions of j i. <lb/>
!om the feeble infant ºf one we . *id tº <lb/></p> 

<p>It not only relieves the child ... toº. <lb/>
*orrects as: º: <lb/></p> 

<p>ates the stomach and bowels, <lb/>
es tºne and energy to the wh idiº <lb/>
lost in ºnly relieve Griping *. stem. <lb/></p> 

<p>Solic. We believe it the es: and sure <lb/></p> 

<p>Forld in all cases of Dissentery and i. #| || <lb/></p> 

<p>h, whether it arises from teet <lb/></p> 

<p>- - - hin <lb break="no"/>Full directions for use will 8 or anyo <lb/></p> 

<p>- acc <lb break="no"/>. None genuine unless the , *pany ºf <lb/></p> 

<p>- - - c-simi <lb/>
inºis ºn the outside wrapper. #: <lb/>
y?; <lb/></p> 

<p>"...bottle. Sold by all Medicine D. <lb/>
Street, New York * Healers. 0 <lb/>
, England. , ork, * 205 High <lb/>
MRS. WINSLOW, <lb/></p> 

<p>herienced Nurse and Female Physician <lb/></p> 

<p>attention of mothers, her Soothing §. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Cur, <lb/></p> 

<p>Holbº <lb/></p> 

<p>a teething, which greatly facilitates the º <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>ing, by softening the gums, rejºi <lb/>
-will allay all pain and spasmodi. <lb/>
to regulate the bowels. Depend upon i. <lb/>
will give rest to yourselves, and refit. <lb/></p> 

<p>to your infants. We have put up and soldſº <lb/>
y, in confideºſ <lb/></p> 

<p>for over thirty years, and can sa <lb/>
uth of it what we have never boea abi. t <lb/>
other medicine—never has it failed .. */ <lb/>
besto effect a cure, when timely used. R. <lb/>
º know an instance of dissatisfaction by a. -<lb break="maybe"/>sed it. On the contrary, all speak deli º <lb/>
tº operations, and speaks in terms of ºf <lb/>
fits magical effects and medical virtues. º <lb/>
in this matter "what we do now," after º <lb/></p> 

<p>experience. and pledge our reputation for | <lb/></p> 

<p>hent of what we here declare. " In a -<lb break="maybe"/>ce where the infant is suffering #: <lb/>
º: relief will be found in fifteen or twent <lb/>
es after the syrup is administered. Fºll º: <lb/>
for using will accompany each boº. Nº. <lb/></p> 

<p>me unless the ſac-simile of Curtis and Perkim, <lb/></p> 

<p>York, is on the outside wrapper. sold ºbj <lb/>
"N". . #. É. 3. º <lb/>
- and 205 High Holborn, Engi º <lb/>
|:5 cent. per .* rn, England. På. <lb/></p> 

<p>t; Chºº Brooklyn, NY, to the "Journal and . <lb/>
ager," Cincinnati, ()., and speaks volumes in: <lb/></p> 

<p>Southing Syrup for Children Teething—" W. <lb/></p> 

<p>$oothing Syrup. Now we never said. wordin <lb/>
of a patent medicine before in our life, but we <lb/>
mpelled to say to your readers that this is nº <lb/>
g-we have tried it, and know it to be all i <lb/>
It is probably one of the mºst successſd <lb/></p> 

<p>* ºf your readers who have babies can', i. <lb/></p> 

<p>han lay in a supply." <lb/>
J. DEARIN, St. John's, <lb/></p> 

<p>| 25. Agent for Newfoundland <lb/></p> 

<p>-\-\-. - 1 -<lb break="maybe"/>Straité Coºpºny. <lb/>
mbard Street and Charing Cross, Loni, R. <lb/>
ESTABLISHEp—1782 <lb/></p> 

<p>coura ºggsfi...— . . <lb/>
and vilified Irish character, it did so, by É <lb/>
a grain of wit with a pack of extravagance, <lb/>
pnd ridicule. Like many other things of the <lb/>
ad better be allowed to rest in oblivion, the <lb/>
n undisguised caricature has passed in Bri<lb break="no"/>t should not be allowed to drag out a puny <lb/>
n colonial taste. When a dance or song, <lb/>
of national custom or charac er is intended <lb/>
ght on the stage, it should either be pro<lb break="no"/>n or not at all. Truth and justice demand <lb/>
he movements, dress, and demeanour of <lb/>
ag forward to dance an Irish jig, in char­ <lb/></p> 

<p>as it is seen in Ireland, their dancing is <lb/>
professes to be, but a caricature that might <lb/>
compared to monkey antics as to a national <lb/>
The majority of the Irish people who are <lb/>
•e lovers of the jig and other lively dances, <lb/>
ferent from all other people, if it can be <lb/>
at at the time they should wish to appear <lb/>
dacent," they dress themselves in as un<lb break="no"/>ragged a manner as possible, to attend a <lb/>
home circle, or at a cross road, a fair or a <lb/>
Such being presumable only within the <lb/>
Lunatic Asylum, or in the drunkerſ revels <lb/>
alians, why represent Irish character in <lb/>
e? No matter how good the motives of <lb/>
g part may be—and to person is farther <lb/>
cting the purity of their intentions' than I <lb/></p> 

<p>the risible muscles of the majority of the <lb/>
till it is unjustifiable to make a* Punch and <lb/>
my national custom or costume, and pass <lb/>
cal unbecoming pranks off as national <lb/>
tics. <lb/>
nd his cauðeen are old acquaintances; but <lb/>
le daughter of Erin could not recognise a <lb/>
resemblance in the type exhibited on the <lb/>
estion. The innate modesty and reserve, <lb/>
riend and foe give her credit, would bring <lb/>
&amp; blush to her cheek; and well might she <lb/>
If I'm to be caricatured so the age of <lb/>
gone, and good taste and self-respect have <lb/>
ng with it." <lb/>
mances into which the character of a clown <lb/>
in enters, the audience are amused by whim<lb break="no"/>ind they admire as much the abilities of the <lb/>
º, in his own way, as any other, because <lb/>
role. But it is a graat mistake to suppose <lb/>
ineation of the character of any class in any <lb/>
juires only grimaces, pranks, uproar, and <lb/>
y then exhibit the Irish peasant besmeared <lb/>
pound of these ingredients as a ground for <lb/>
s of low wit and paltry ludicrousness? <lb/>
lim a monopoly if such a character is sº <lb/></p> 

<p>3,643. <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, Thursday, March 2, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>- &gt; <lb/></p> 

<p>fiº; <lb/></p> 

<p>following is an extract from a letter wri;: <lb/>
- r writtenby! <lb/>
v J S Holme, Pastor of the Pººj º <lb/></p> 

<p>ºf that world-renowned medicine, Mr. WINs. <lb/></p> 

<p>advertisement in your cºlumns of Mrs. Wi.; <lb/></p> 

<p>"es of the day, because it is one of the hº <lb/></p> 

<p>PHOEN EX FIRA, . t <lb/></p> 

<p>ot exhibit that "step" of the "light fan- \ <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>W <lb/>
10 matter what effect such an exhibition may. # <lb/></p> 

<p>ing?'—the Yorkshire clod-hopper, Dutch <lb/>
cotch gaberlungie should be allowed tº <lb/>
Plays in general depict respectable, eº; <lb/>
•cently comic, phases of lite. 'Why shoul <lb/>
d manners form an exception? Anjuse" <lb/>
y kind, wo merit the approbation of those <lb/>
obation is worth having, should be kept <lb/>
imate bºunds; and I appeal to any un<lb break="no"/>d that gives the question a moment's coº <lb/>
f the usual style of exnibiting the Iris <lb/>
Irish gentleman of the zij or new school. <lb/>
, rollicking, reckless manaer, is not inº?". <lb/>
eal and low P Now, the Highland Fiº <lb/>
ognised as a national dance, is alway" <lb/></p> 

<p>3 <lb/>
i <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/></p> -->

<head rendition="simple:centre">MR. A. SHEA'S SPEECH ON <lb/>
CONFEDERATION IN THE <lb/>
HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY ON <lb/>
TUESDAY, 21st FEBRUARY.</head> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SHEA2">Mr. A. SHEA</persName> said he did not intend to offer any <lb/>
practical objection to the resolution embodying as it <lb/>
did the views of the public generally on this important <lb/>
subject; but he felt, nevertheless, that in the interest <lb/>
of the public it was in its present shape open to some <lb/>
objection. His opinion was that the resolution the <lb/>
House should adopt was one affirming the principles <lb/>
contained in the Report of the Quebec Conference, <lb/>
but at the same time providing that their decision <lb/>
should be subject to the expression of public opinion <lb/>
at the next general election. He felt this was the <lb/>
course the House should adopt, because on such a re<lb break="no"/>solution there would be a division, and every member <lb/>
of the House would then stand before the constituen<lb break="no"/>cies in an intelligible light, while the present Resolu<lb break="no"/>tion being one on which no division can take place, the <lb/>
public are without that security at the next elections <lb/>
which a clear avowal of the opinions of members would <lb/>
afford and which may now be avoided by any who de<lb break="no"/>sire to return to the House under false pretences. He <lb/>
thought therefore for the protection of the public that <lb/>
it would have been desirable to submit a more definite <lb/>
proposition than was contained in the Resolution ba<lb break="no"/>fore them. Before proceeding farther he would refer <lb/>
to a discussion that had been had in another place on <lb/>
this subject in which some very extraordinary assump<lb break="no"/>tions were made the groundwork of the argument. The <lb/>
question had been dealt with as one by which it was <lb/>
designed to set up the Markets of Canada against <lb/>
those of the United States and to impose disabilities <lb/>
on our trade with the latter. He (Mr. Shea) was at <lb/>
a loss to know where the warrant had been found for <lb/>
such a conclusion, which only serves to show how little <lb/>
the subject was comprehended by those who can so <lb/>
express themselves. There was nothing in the pro<lb break="no"/>posed Confederations by which the ports of the United <lb/>
States would be rendered less open than at present to <lb/>
our commerce, and no one would deprecate more than <lb/>
he (Mr. Shea) any attempt by fiscal regulations to <lb/>
force trade from the channels in which it naturally <lb/>
flowed. Men of business should be left free to resort <lb/>
to those places in which their convenience or their in<lb break="no"/>terest was best consulted, and these sound principles <lb/>
were not contravened by any thing contemplated in <lb/>
the Report agreed to at Quebec. No doubt since the <lb/>
time when that Report was adoptod, the United States <lb/>
Government have given notice for the repeal of the <lb/>
Reciprocity Treaty, and it may be imagined that the <lb/>
abrogation of that measure would induce a resort to a <lb/>
retaliatory policy by the Government of the Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. Now it was believed in well-informed circles <lb/>
that the repeal of that Treaty was not a necessary con<lb break="no"/>sequence of the notice that had been given, and he <lb/>
Mr. Shea) was strongly disposed to share this opinion. <lb/>
The conclusion which that notice expresses was ar<lb break="no"/>rived at under the influence of irritation caused <lb/>
by the conduct of the St. Alban's raiders who <lb/>
escaped into Canada, and were believed to have <lb/>
received sympathy there, and it is therefore not un<lb break="no"/>reasonable to suppose that before the expiration of <lb/>
the twelve months to which the notice extends the <lb/>
public mind of America will view the subject in a <lb/>
calmer and more just light, and will see how little of <lb/>
legitimate connexion there is between the transaction <lb/>
at which they have taken unfounded umbrage, and a <lb/>
business treaty which has been an operation for some <lb/>
years past to the mutual advantage of the parties con<lb break="no"/>cerned. But should it be otherwise, and that the <lb/>
notice given in petulance is carried into effect by re<lb break="no"/>pesling the treaty, then he had authority for asserting <lb/>
that as far as Canada is concerned her leading men in <lb/>
accordance with the approved course of British legis<lb break="no"/>lation would deprecate, a recourse to a retaliatory <lb/>
policy. It would be seen then how little grounds there <lb/>
were for the apprehensions that our free trade Colo<lb break="no"/>nial policy would be disturbed, or our present satis<lb break="no"/>factory relations be injuriously affected by the opera<lb break="no"/>tions of the Government of the proposed Confederation. <lb/>
He had listened with much interest to the very able <lb/>
and logical speech of the learned Attorney General <lb/>
yesterday, but he did not entirely agree with his hon <lb/>
and learned friend as to the speculative character of <lb/>
the question they were considering. This measure of <lb/>
Confederation does not belong to the class of untried <lb/>
or novel experiments. All the principal countries of <lb/>
the world are the result of combinations of small <lb/>
states for purposes of defence, security, and common <lb/>
advancement. When we look at England up to the <lb/>
time of the Heptarchy and after the combination of <lb/>
these little kingdoms under one Crown, we have a <lb/>
signal illustration of the effects of Confederation in <lb/>
promoting the power, and general prosperity of a <lb/>
people. In her early days weak, and disjointed, <lb/>
the several little States at war with each other, or <lb/>
harrassed or overrun by some foreign invader, they <lb/>
made but little progress. But since they became one <lb/>
under a settled Government the result of their com<lb break="no"/>bined suffrages, though England has known of those <lb/>
vicissitudes from which no nation can be exempt, her <lb/>
career has been one of steady advancement, culmi<lb break="no"/>nating at the present day in the proud position she <lb/>
holds, foremost amongst the nations of the earth. <lb/>
Then we have her Union with Scotland from which <lb/>
both countries have derived such signal advantages. <lb/>
The Union of England and Ireland had been referred <lb/>
to as an example of the injurious effects of combina<lb break="no"/>tions, and efforts had been made to work on the tra<lb break="no"/>ditional prejudice which that event had justly in<lb break="no"/>spired, to create a hostile feeling to the present mea<lb break="no"/>sure. They have read the history of that transaction <lb/>
to little purpose who assert that it has any features in <lb/>
common with the just terms on which the Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation of these colonies is proposed to be formed. At <lb/>
the time of that Union, Ireland was a conquered <lb/>
country, and force and fraud were employed to bring <lb/>
about the so-called Union. Nor were its conditions <lb/>
less unjust than the agencies by which it was effected. <lb/>
The representation given to Ireland in the British <lb/>
Parliament was about one-half of what she was enti<lb break="no"/>tled to on fair grounds, and from this representation <lb/>
the Catholics who formed five-sixths of the population <lb/>
were entirely excluded by the continuance of the <lb/>
Penal Laws. It were idle to enumerate the inequali<lb break="no"/>ties and injustice which marked this connexion which <lb/>
scarcely established any bond but that which exists <lb/>
between the taskmaster and the slave. Every one <lb/>
acquainted with the history of O'Connell's life knows <lb/>
that his agitation for a Repeal of the Union was <lb/>
grounded on the fact that the conditions of a fair <lb/>
Union were not found in the relations between Eng<lb break="no"/>land and Ireland, and that it was not so much the <lb/> 
Repeal of the Union he sought as the acquisition of <lb/>

<cb/> 

equal rights and privileges, the concession of which <lb/>
he hoped to extort from the fears of the British Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment which that agitation was more likely than <lb/>
any other to call up. The whole tenor of his speeches <lb/>
shows that a Union with England based on terms of <lb/>
equality and general equity would have found him a <lb/>
willing supporter. What analagy then, said Mr. <lb/>
Shea, can be drawn between a Union such as I have <lb/>
correctly described, and the proposed combination of <lb/>
these British North American Provinces where the <lb/>
just rights of all are alike respected, and the condi<lb break="no"/>tions of honorable partnership upheld. And even as <lb/>
respects the Irish Union, reveal has now no advocates, <lb/>
for the policy of the British Government has of late <lb/>
years become less anti-social, and the efforts of the <lb/>
leading Irishmen is now being directed to the attain<lb break="no"/>ment of those practical reforms which would promote <lb/>
the social and material advancement of the country <lb/>
which there is a growing disposition in England to <lb/>
advance. In the history of France we have another <lb/>
example of the power of Confederation to further the <lb/>
greatness and prosperity of a country. The vast Em<lb break="no"/>pire which existed in the days of Charlemagne fell to <lb/>
pieces under the rule of his feeble successors who di<lb break="no"/>vided the Empire, and granted provinces to the high <lb/>
nobility, completing the feudal system under which <lb/>
the country became so dismembered, that in one <lb/>
hundred years after the death of that great monarch <lb/>
the crown had but two provinces and some sinall dis<lb break="no"/>tricts remaining under its control. France ceased to <lb/>
be a real European Power until partly by marriages <lb/>
and treaties, and by the accession of the great Henry <lb/>
IV., those fiefs were again united to the central state, <lb/>
and under the policy of Richlieu and Mazarin was <lb/>
brought to be the leading Power of Europe during <lb/>
the reign of Louis XIV. Spain owed her greatness <lb/>
to the union of the several petty kingdoms and coun<lb break="no"/>tries under the crowns of Arragon and Castile, which <lb/>
became themselves united by the marriage of Ferdi<lb break="no"/>nand and Isabella. From the time of this union <lb/>
Spain increased her power and wealth until she be<lb break="no"/>came the Empire of Philip II., which was the great<lb break="no"/>est and most powerful in the world. It was the <lb/>
dreams of Universal Empire on the part of Charles, <lb/>
followed by the mad amoition of his son Pnillip; to <lb/>
dominate the seas, that involved the exhausting con<lb break="no"/>sequences which ultimately led to the decline of <lb/>
Spanish power and influence. It would be tedious, <lb/>
and to no necessary purpose that I should pursue the <lb/>
history of these examples which shows that Confed<lb break="no"/>eration of weak States means security and progress, <lb/>
and the consequent advancement of the people whose <lb/>
interests they embrace. But if we turn to more re<lb break="no"/>cent times we find argument no less striking and <lb/>
instructive. We have but to look at the United <lb/>
States to see what Confederation has done there. <lb/>
The fact of the marvellous advancement of the <lb/>
people and the power of the country cannot be <lb/>
denied, nor can it be attributed to any other cause <lb/>
than the Confederation of the States; but then it is <lb/>
said see what the country has come to now, alleging <lb/>
that the civil war is a consequence of Confederation, <lb/>
No reasoning can be more fallacious, nor can we sup<lb break="no"/>pose it is offered in seriousness <choice><sic>b</sic><corr>by</corr></choice> men of competent <lb/>
judgment. The civil war is a war of Slavery and was <lb/>
long since forboded as the inevitable issue of such an <lb/>
anomaly in a country where free Institutions prevail; <lb/>
and even though the North and South should be <lb/>
severed as the result of the civil war the fact will not <lb/>
militate against the principle of Confederation, but is <lb/>
simply an evidence of the incompatibility of Slavery <lb/>
with the working of free Institutions. To prove that <lb/>
combination has failed in the case of the United <lb/>
States it must be shown that the several States are <lb/>
anxious to return to their original separate condition <lb/>
of what is termed "independent" existence. This <lb/>
desire he apprehended it would be somewhat <lb/>
difficult to discover, though proofs of the <lb/>
opposite character were found in the history <lb/>
of that Country. The new communities that <lb/>
grow up in the outskirts of the States have their <lb/>
probationary stage, and become entitled to admission <lb/>
into the Union when that time has passed. Do we ever <lb/>
find them unwilling to enter when the time arrives? <lb/>
On the contrary they avail themselves of what they <lb/>
justly esteem the privilege of merging their weak ex<lb break="no"/>istence into the strong power of which they then be<lb break="no"/>come a part, sharing in the prosperity and protection <lb/>
which the connexion ensures. He (Mr. Shea) would <lb/>
now come to a more familiar case in which the bless<lb break="no"/>ings of Confederation had been strikingly exemplified. <lb/>
Since the Union of the Canadas about twenty years <lb/>
since they have more than doubled in wealth and pop<lb break="no"/>ulation, they have established their railway system <lb/>
and their other great public works by which the coun<lb break="no"/>try has been opened up to settlement and cultivation. <lb/>
That union was effected by the influence of the Brit<lb break="no"/>ish Government against powerful sectional resistance <lb/>
in the colony, but the result triumphantly established <lb/>
the wisdom of the measure. The Union has no firmer <lb/>
supporters than those who most stoutly opposed its in<lb break="no"/>itiation, and who now frankly acknowledge the false <lb/>
views which influenced their course. They see a <lb/>
career of progress consequent on the Union which was <lb/>
impossible under their former divided state, and are <lb/>
desirous of extending the principle to the Maritime <lb/>
Provinces in order to enlarge its sphere of operations <lb/>
for the benefit of the whole. In all the cases he had <lb/>
quoted it must be remarked as the result of these sev<lb break="no"/>eral Confederations that nowhere was there a desire to <lb/>
return to the separate existence out of which they <lb/>
sprung. Can any argument so strongly prove the va<lb break="no"/>lue of the principle as this determination to uphold it, <lb/>
shown by all countries that have tasted its effects: <lb/>
—Now, if ever a country was so placed as to <lb/>
require the aid of others, it is this colony. With a <lb/>
population of but 130,000 scattered over many hundred <lb/>
miles of sea coast our condition manifestiy points to <lb/>
the necessity of co-operation with others whose alliance <lb/>
    will give as a <hi rendition="simple:italic">status</hi> which in our isolated state <lb/>
we cannot attain. We have proved our want <lb/>
of power to effect any object above the ordinary <lb/>
routine. We have seen pauperism setting us at de<lb break="no"/>fiance, and all our necessarily feeble efforts have been <lb/>
futile for its correction. We have resources fully ade<lb break="no"/>quate to the support of the population, and they remain <lb/>
idle from our inability to place them within the reach <lb/>
of the people, whose condition so loudly calls for <lb/>
increased employment. In this position of affairs <lb/>
we present a strong case for the necessity of combina<lb break="no"/>tion with those who have the power to aid as, and <lb/>
whose interest it would be to promote our prosperity. <lb/>
But it is said by those who cannot resist the principle <lb/>
in the abstract, and who yet would oppose this mea<lb break="no"/>sure by any means, that the peculiarities of our circum<lb break="no"/>stances and the want of identity of interest with the <lb/>
other provinces, and our different pursuits render the <lb/>
proposition inapplicable to us. It appeared to him that <lb/>
logically to carry out the views of those who so object <lb/>
that tailors and shoemakers, and all the other trades, <lb/> 
    
    <cb/>

should each form distinct and separate communities <lb/>
apart from those whose pursuits were different. To <lb/>
his mind the variety of pursuits formed the strongest <lb/>
reason why communities should confederate; because <lb/>
this caused the exchange of productions and supplying <lb/>
their mutual necessities, the interests of all were con<lb break="no"/>ceived by the association. But when we look to other <lb/>
Confederations do we find no difference in their <lb/>
pursuits? what can be more diverse than the trades <lb/>
atd avocations of the people in different parts of the <lb/>
United States? Have we not the manufacturing and <lb/>
the agricultural and various other interests in England, <lb/>
and even the fisheries of Scotland are combined with <lb/>
these under one Government and we have not found <lb/>
that the diference in the pursuits of the people have <lb/>
militated, against their common prosperty. John <lb/>
Stuart Mill, one of the profoundest thinkers of the <lb/>
day, in speaking of the conditions necessary for the <lb/>
beneficial Confederation of States says "the strongest <lb/>
of all is identity of political antecedents; the possession <lb/>
of a national history, and consequent community of <lb/>
recollections; collective pride and humiliation, plea<lb break="no"/>sure and regret, connected with the same incidents in <lb/>
the past." Have we not these essentials in strict <lb/>
accord with those Provinces with whom we propose <lb/>
to confederate, and when we consider the experience <lb/>
on which such views are founded, how small is the <lb/>
weight that should attach to objections that are <lb/>
thus so strikingly rebutted. From a fair and careful <lb/>
consideration of the case presented in the <lb/>
Quebec Resolutions, it would he thought be diffi<lb break="no"/>cult to dispute their beneficial application to this <lb/>
Colony, more especially in the circumstances <lb/>
in which it, now stands, when almost any change <lb/>
must be an improvement to the labouring population. <lb/>
But a pregnant question now presents itself, have we <lb/>
the unqualified power to decide our own destiny in <lb/>
this respect. It would be idle to suppose that the <lb/>
meeting at Quebec was not inspired by the Impe<lb break="no"/>rial Government. No one who has paid any de<lb break="no"/>gree of attention to the tone of British opinion re<lb break="no"/>garding these Colonies for some years past, can have <lb/>
failed to see that a change in the relations they held <lb/>
to the Mother Country was surely coming about. It <lb/>
became a mere question of time when we obtained <lb/>
Responsible Government, and with it virtual indepen<lb break="no"/>dence in the Government of these Colonies. We ac<lb break="no"/>quired the right to legislate; so that our tariffs became <lb/>
hostile to the commercial interests of E gland, and <lb/>
with this exercise of independence it was not unna<lb break="no"/>tural that the question should be asked, why should <lb/>
they be called on to sustain those whose legislation <lb/>
for their own selfish ends was marked by this un<lb break="no"/>friendly spirit. This feeling has been gaining strength <lb/>
for some time, but the events taking place in America <lb/>
for the past four years, seem to have brought it to the <lb/>
mind of the British Government, not only as a ques<lb break="no"/>tion of right, and justice, but in regard to the <lb/>
sterner consideration of the practicability of ex<lb break="no"/>isting means for the defence of the British <lb/>
North American Provinces. Thy evidently see <lb/>
that so many disjointed States, with each its se<lb break="no"/>parated organization and right of independent action, <lb/>
could not offer the necessary effective resistance to <lb/>
attack from the American States which in the course <lb/>
of events might probably arise, and they have con<lb break="no"/>cluded that in order to the affective apolication of <lb/>
Imperial aid, these Provinces should combine and be <lb/>
one for purposes of defence, moved by one central <lb/>
authority under the direction of which their combined <lb/>
strength, backed by the influence of England, would <lb/>
present an imposing front, and induce an invader to <lb/>
pause in his aggressive designs. The Government <lb/>
feel that the combination of these Provinces is the <lb/>
condition alone on which they can be upheld in con<lb break="no"/>nexion with the mother country, and in view of all <lb/>
the considerations that surround this grave question, <lb/>
shall we be told it must be dealt with by legard to <lb/>
its effects in adding a halfpenny a yard to the price <lb/>
of calico. Can we doubt that the proposed Confede<lb break="no"/>ration is the explession of the settled views of British <lb/>
policy, and we may be thankful that when its advent <lb/>
is inevitable, the arrangement itself is one that has <lb/>
the approving testimany of experience. But this is <lb/>
evidently but a part of a more extended application <lb/>
of the principles of Confederation which has forc<lb break="no"/>ed itself on the attention cf the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. In the fall of 1863, a number of Russian <lb/>
ships were stationed at New York the mission of which <lb/>
was not then known. It has since come to light that <lb/>
as at that time the interference of England in Polish <lb/>
affairs was not thought improbable, these ships were <lb/>
held in readiness to proceed to Australia and destroy <lb/>
the principal towns of these colonies, if that interfer<lb break="no"/>ence took place. The circumstance brings into strong <lb/>
light the necessity of giving to the outlying dependen<lb break="no"/>cies of the Crown a greater degree of inherent strength, <lb/>
and the measures now proposed for the B. N. A. Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces will doubtless also be carried out for the Aus<lb break="no"/>tralian group, which are also warned of the danger of <lb/>
relying solely on England for their protection. But he <lb/>
had heard the strange argument advanced, that if we <lb/>
in this colony refuse to unite we shall become a pet <lb/>
Province and the seat of a Naval Station. We had <lb/>
not heard the reasoning by which this conclusion was <lb/>
arrived at, but it was somewhat novel to find reward <lb/>
waiting on those who pursued a course of senseless <lb/>
contumacy and resistance. Will our refusal to confed<lb break="no"/>erate make Halifax less eligible than before in point <lb/>
of geographical position? Will its harbor, at all times <lb/>
accessible, be then divested of its attractions in our <lb/>
favor? It was strange that such groundless assertions <lb/>
could receive any countenance amongst even the least <lb/>
enlightened, but they show the nature of the opposi<lb break="no"/>tion got up against the proposal for Union. We deceive <lb/>
ourselves in supposing that we have any value in the <lb/>
eyes of Great Britain that would induce a favorable <lb/>
exceptional policy in our case. It is not with us now <lb/>
as in times of old, when this colony was a nursery for <lb/>
seamen for the British navy, and when it was valuable <lb/>
on that account. England has now no need for us in <lb/>
that respect, and our people being resident, have no <lb/>
great desire to try their fortunes in the naval service <lb/>
of the country. But it is asserted that the British <lb/>
Government never intended that this island should <lb/>
form part of the Confederation and that our move<lb break="no"/>ments are entirely gratuitous. The evidence, however, <lb/>
is clear on this point against those who offer this objec<lb break="no"/>tion. In 1862 when the other colonies passed Resolu<lb break="no"/>tions for the consideration of the question of Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, we had not moved in the matter at all, and yet <lb/>
a copy of these Resolutions was forwarded here by the <lb/>
Secretary of State, and our attention invited to them, <lb/>
showing clearly the intention of the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment that we should not remain outside of any plan <lb/>
that might be agreed on for the Union of these Colo<lb break="no"/>nies. Their intentions in this respect are therefore <lb/>
not left to conjecture, while it might easily have been <lb/>
supposed that a uniform policy for these Provinces <lb/>

<cb/>

would be insisted on. He hoped he had shown that <lb/>
the principle itself was desirable and tended to pro<lb break="no"/>gress; that even if less desirable, it was in view of all <lb/>
fair reasoning, the inevitable destiny of the Provinces; <lb/>
and that it was the evident design of the Imperial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment that this colony should form part of the pro<lb break="no"/>posed Confederation. He would now go into the con<lb break="no"/>sideration of the leading objections urged against the <lb/>
scheme, and most prominent amongst these is the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of Taxation. There is no word more vague in <lb/>
its signification than that of taxation. In the sense in <lb/>
which it is used by those who employ it to get up a <lb/>
hostile cry in the present case, it is an abstraction from <lb/>
the means of the people for which they receive no re<lb break="no"/>turn. Against taxation of this character people natur<lb break="no"/>ally rebelled, and the Legislature should also set its <lb/>
face with equal resolution. But there was another kind <lb/>
of taxation which signified pot oppression, but progress <lb/>
and public advantage, and which nurtured and pro<lb break="no"/>moted the prosperity of the people. We see high rates <lb/>
of taxation in many prosperous countries, as in <lb/>
England for example, and in Canada, whose <lb/>
taxes had been so much spoken of there was to <lb/>
his mind no part of the administration of affairs in <lb/>
that country which spoke more highly of the states<lb break="no"/>manlike sagacity of her public men than the system <lb/>
of taxation by which the resources of the country have <lb/>
been brought into life, and their value enhanced, giv<lb break="no"/>ing to the people ten-fold means for paying the taxes <lb/>
imposed upon them. As compared with our wretch<lb break="no"/>ed system, under which but a fractional part is devot<lb break="no"/>ed to purposes of public usefulness, the taxation of <lb/>
Canada stands out in remarkable contrast. He would <lb/>
be but too glad to see the way clear for a very large <lb/>
increase of our present taxation. He regretted that <lb/>
there was no public undertaking similar to those <lb/>
on which public money had been expended in Canada <lb/>
—undertakings which opened up their resources and <lb/>
permanently enlarged the means for the employment <lb/>
of their industry. This fruitful expenditure was what <lb/>
we stood so much in need of and taxation for such a <lb/>
purpose instead of being the hated thing as it is often <lb/>
popularly and ignorantly regarded, would be beneficial <lb/>
and invigorating in its results. If the nature of our <lb/>
resources were such as would justify the application <lb/>
of fifty thousand pounds in this manner in the present <lb/>
year, an immediate stimulus would be given to the <lb/>
labour of the people besides bringing within reach <lb/>
permanent sources of employment which would make <lb/>
the payment of the consequent taxation a much ligh<lb break="no"/>ter burthen then is now imposed. But there are many <lb/>
taxes applying to us at the present, time which we <lb/>
apparently treat with unconcern, and which are far <lb/>
more oppressive than those to which the hostility of <lb/>
some members of the house is directed. Who can <lb/>
measure the taxes imposed by privation and want from <lb/>
which so many of our people are suffering, the waste <lb/>
of physical and mental vigour,and of the general cor<lb break="no"/>ers of life, with the sure prospect of decrepitude and <lb/>
imbecility in the coming generation, if the settled <lb/>
physiological laws are not to be set aside in our case. <lb/>
The escape from such taxes might well engage <lb/>
the attention we bestow on our very minor and <lb/>
imaginary ills. We then have the taxes which pov<lb break="no"/>erty in our midst must necessarily entail on every one <lb/>
who has a shilling to spare for the relief of the dis<lb break="no"/>tressed. We have the taxes which owners of pro<lb break="no"/>perty feel in times like the present, when empty <lb/>
houses and bad tenants are unfortunately too well <lb/>
known, operating far more severely than any taxation <lb/>
which Confederation could cause. The Canadian <lb/>
Tariff is assumed to be that which would be applied <lb/>
to the future Confederation. He (Mr. Shea) would <lb/>
admit for the sake of argument that such was to be <lb/>
the case as far as its general provisions could apply; <lb/>
though those whose authority was better than his <lb/>
thought a reduced scale of duties would bring <lb/>
sufficient revenue for the wants of the new Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. In 1864 an increase had been made <lb/>
in the Canadian Tariff on certain articles, but <lb/>
as this had been done for special purposes, and <lb/>
as these new taxes would he remitted in the present <lb/>
Session; the Delegates had not dealt with this excep<lb break="no"/>tional Tariff, but had adopted that of 1863 as a basis <lb/>
of calculation. The duties in Canada on ready made <lb/>
clothing, leatherware, &amp;c.; are higher than thuse im<lb break="no"/>posed by our Tariff. It would be rementered that <lb/>
two years ago a Petition was presented to the House <lb/>
under very imposing circumstances; calling attention. <lb/>
to the necessity of increasing the duties on these des<lb break="no"/>criptions of goods for the protection, of our artizans. <lb/>
Very great stress was laid on the subject aid its im<lb break="no"/>portance urged by hon members of the House, as a <lb/>
proposal from which much public benefit must arise. <lb/>
These hon. gentlemen had now the opportunity pre<lb break="no"/>sented by the Canadian Tariff of giving effect to their <lb/>
views, and yet strangely enough they are now most <lb/>
loud in condemning the terms of that Tariff in this <lb/>
respect. Was it merely for some temporary purpose <lb/>
the views of the Petition were advocated, or how is <lb/>
it that we have the singular spectacle of men repudi<lb break="no"/>ating their own opinions on the first occasion that <lb/>
has offered of carrying then into effect? He (M. Shea) <lb/>
had no faith in the views on which that petition was <lb/>
based, nor did he believe that any legislation of the <lb/>
House could afford the petitioner the relief they sought <lb/>
for, and he referred to the circumstances only to show <lb/>
the inconsistency of hon members and the small amount <lb/>
of reliance that can be placed on those who do not act <lb/>
on fixed principles and settled habits of thought and <lb/>
action. But though duties on soune articles are higher <lb/>
in Canada than here, the tariff of Canada is not pro<lb break="no"/>tective in its objects as has been asserted. Mr. Howe <lb/>
in writing to Mr. Adderly, in Dec. 1862, says:—In <lb/>
none of the Provinces have protective or discrimminating <lb/>
duties ever been imposed. It is true that the import <lb/>
duties of Canada are rather high, but it can be shown <lb/>
that all the duty raised is actually required to pay <lb/>
the interest on the debts of the Province, to carry out <lb/>
public improvements and to provide for its Civil List." <lb/>
Mr. Howe is an impartial authority, though the facts in <lb/>
themselves are plain enough and need no voucher. It <lb/>
had been already shown that the aggregate amount of <lb/>
the revenues of the several provinces, calculated by <lb/>
their present tariff, would be sufficient for the wants of <lb/>
the Confederation, and in assuming the Canadian Tariff <lb/>
of 1863 as a groundwork of calculation for the whole, it <lb/>
was evident that he was putting the case in its worst <lb/>
aspect for the purpose he had in view. This Canadian <lb/>
Tariff would give, in the first instance, a larger Reve<lb break="no"/>nue than we had at present, but a fair examination of <lb/>
it would show that we should receive a full equivalent <lb/>
for the increased amount. By our own Tariff in 1863 <lb/>
we received £94,413, and the imports of that year <lb/>
would give £135,000 if the Canadian Tariff were in <lb/>
force, being an increase of a little over £40,000. But <lb/>
from this amount there would be a considerable sum <lb/>
to deduct for account of goods that would come in free <lb/>
from Canada and the other Provincer if Confedera<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-02_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">2</fw>
<fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>

tion took place. There was, for instance, the article <lb/>
of Bread, which, by the strict application of the Cana<lb break="no"/>dian Tariff, forms an item of Revenue to the amount <lb/>
of £7894, which is not exempted by that Tariff at <lb/>
present, merely because it is not an article of importa<lb break="no"/>tion there, and consequently escaped their attention. <lb/>
This, of course, would be free under the general Tariff, <lb/>
but supposing for the sake of argument that its reten<lb break="no"/>tion were senselessly persisted in, the effect then <lb/>
would be to shut the article out, and oblige us to get <lb/>
our supplies from the local bakeries, which are quite <lb/>
capable of furnishing all we want. He put this, of <lb/>
course, as an extreme and most improbable case, but he <lb/>
would deprecate any such tax on Bread, for while our <lb/>
local bakeries did good service in breaking down the <lb/>
Hamburg monopoly, he would be sorry to see the <lb/>
monopoly placed in their hands. Then there was the <lb/>
article of Kerosene Oil which paid £120, which after <lb/>
Confederation would come free from Canada. Ale and <lb/>
Porter pay £507 by our Tariff, and by the Canadian <lb/>
they would pay £799. As considerable supplies would <lb/>
of course come from Canada under a free Tariff, he <lb/>
would assume the future duty under this head at <lb/>
£300, leaving £499 to go to the account of abate<lb break="no"/>ments. The article of leatherware was most import<lb break="no"/>ant. By our tariff it paid in 1863 £5628, and by the <lb/>
Canadian it would have been £12791. The leather <lb/>
manufactures are amongst the most extensive in Ca<lb break="no"/>nada, and as the articles can be got there, as appeared <lb/>
by the statement of the hon. member for Carbonear, <lb/>
on as good terms as from England, we should doubt<lb break="no"/>less receive a considerable amount of our supply from <lb/>
Canada under the new arrangement. He did not wish <lb/>
however to overstate the case in any way, but he did <lb/>
not think he was open to the charge when he estimat<lb break="no"/>ed that two-fifths of the import would be from that <lb/>
country, which would be an abatement of £5000 from <lb/>
the sum the Canadian Tariff would produce from our <lb/>
import of this article. Soap gives £645 under our <lb/>
Tariff, and would pay £1760 by the Canadian. As <lb/>
soap is largely manufactured in the other Provinces <lb/>
he assumed that one-half our import would be from <lb/>
them, reducing the Revenue by the sum of £880. <lb/>
Candles pay £467, and by the Canadian Tariff £849, <lb/>
would be realised. Here he estimated that the reve<lb break="no"/>nue would remain as it is with us, leaving £382 to be <lb/>
deducted from the calculation of the Canadian Tariff. <lb/>
He confined himself to the articles on which he felt <lb/>
no question could be raised as to the justness of his <lb/>
estimate, rejecting all those which, though they will <lb/>
probably come into more or less extent under a free <lb/>
Tariff, cannot be purchased at the English price, and <lb/>
on which consequently, though no duty would be <lb/>
paid, the purchaser would have little or no advantage. <lb/>
He had not taken into account either, the article of <lb/>
Tobacco, which comes in now from Canada in compe<lb break="no"/>tition with Tobacco from the United States, but as it <lb/>
it is subject to an excise, he felt he could not claim <lb/>
it as a free import, though doubtless this restriction <lb/>
will be removed to enable Canada to supply the <lb/>
Lower Provinces. The woollens and furniture and <lb/>
other Canadian goods, he had not taken into account, <lb/>
though these articles would, to some <choice><sic>exteut</sic><corr>extent</corr></choice>, advan<lb break="no"/>tageously find their way here; neither had he made <lb/>
any abatement for the short comings of Revenue, as <lb/>
    compared with the <hi rendition="simple:italic">pro rata</hi> increase of taxation <lb/>
which in cases like the present all experience shows <lb/>
to be necessary. The sums he had estimated however <lb/>
amounted to £17182—which would make the Reve<lb break="no"/>nue actually payable in 1863 under the Canadian <lb/>
Tariff £118,000. That however was the result of <lb/>
account of one year only. He would now deal with <lb/>
an average of years, and though five years was the <lb/>
term usually employed in such cases; still as the last <lb/>
four had been unproductive Tariffs, he would in the <lb/>
present instance take the average of the past ten <lb/>
years as a fairer criterion for the present purpose. <lb/>
He found that this gave an average Revenue of £100,<lb break="no"/>000, on which the Canadian Tariff would make an in<lb break="no"/>crease of £42857. Taking the estimates he had made <lb/>
for account of abatements by reason of the import of <lb/>
free goods from the other Provinces, it would give <lb/>
    £18086, making the <choice><sic>nett</sic><corr>net</corr></choice> <choice><sic>Revonue</sic><corr>Revenue</corr></choice> £124,771 as the <lb/>
annual produce of the Canadian Tariff it applied to <lb/>
our Imports for the past ten years. Against this we <lb/>
had to set off the sum of £112,000 guaranteed by the <lb/>
Resolutions at Quebec. Then there was the Steam <lb/>
Communication between Newfoundland and England <lb/>
and Canada, which would be reasonably estimated <lb/>
at £10,000 a year. We had besides a second Postal <lb/>
Steamer which would cost £4000 a year, and the cost <lb/>
of the Minerelogical Survey £500, making £126 500 a <lb/>
year. He invtied the most careful examination and scru<lb break="no"/>tiny of his statements, and did not doubt, they would <lb/>
commend themselves to condid and dispassionate <lb/>
minds as being the result of a careful and reasonable <lb/>
consideration of the case. He believed he had un<lb break="no"/>derstated the probable import of free goods from the <lb/>
other Provinces, and he had little doubt that before <lb/>
the measure was five years in operation, owing to the <lb/>
increase of the free list, the revenue payable by this <lb/>
colony would be less than at the present time. Of <lb/>
the capabilities of Canada to supply a good part of <lb/>
our wants, we have evidence in the following state<lb break="no"/>ment of her manufactures, which are every day ex<lb break="no"/>tending, and to which a great stimulus would be given <lb/>
by opening the trade of the lower Provinces for their <lb/>
free Iulport:— <lb/></p>
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>
"To commence with the manufacture of lumber. <lb/>
Canada contains over two thousand saw mills, and in <lb/>
one year cut nearly eight hundred million feet of lum<lb break="no"/>ber She has over two hundred distilleries and <lb/>
breweries, which last year produced over nine million <lb/>
gallons of spirits and malt liquors, yielding an excise <lb/>
duty of over seven hundred thousand dollars. These <lb/>
breweries and stills consumed over one million six <lb/>
hundred thousand bushels of grain and malt. There <lb/>
are at least one thousand flour, grist and oat mills in <lb/>
this country; two hundred and fity carriage factories <lb/>
—perhaps more; quite two hundred foundries; one <lb/>
hundred and fifty carding mills; one hundred and <lb/>
thirty woollen factories, and five hundred tanneries. <lb/>
Other and less important factories are numberless. <lb/>
In speaking of the crops of Canada only millions can <lb/>
be used, Canada produces annually between twenty<lb break="no"/>five and thirty milions bushels of wheat; twelve <lb/>
millions bushels of pease; forty millions bushels of <lb/>
oats; over a million and a half tons of hay; thirteen <lb/>
million bushels of buckwheat; twenty-eight million <lb/>
bushels of potatoes; nearly twenty million bushels of <lb/>
turnips; kills thirty million pounds of beef; shears <lb/>
five and a half million pounds of wool; kills four mil<lb break="no"/>lion pounds of pork; and makes forty-two to forty-five <lb/>
million pounds of butter." <lb/></p>
    </quote>
    <p>
It must be borne in mind. that though the Tariff of <lb/>
Canada may be upheld in its general features, it was <lb/>
framed for Canada alone,and cannot be expected to be <lb/>
closely adapted to the Lower Provinces, which were <lb/>
not in the view of its framers. It would therefore <lb/>
necessarily undergo revision, as stated to him by <lb/>
Mr. Galt, "in deference to the circumstances of <lb/>
the Lower Provinces." But let us imagine the <lb/>
extreme case that Canada had the power, and forced <lb/>
on the Lower Provinees a measure of oppressive tax<lb break="no"/>ation, must we not see that such a course would de<lb break="no"/>feat itself—that in a country like this with a long <lb/>
line of coast offering such facilities for illicit traffic, <lb/>
the Revenue would be but partially collected, and the <lb/>
law would be wanting in that mortal support on which <lb/>
all laws are dependant for their successful operation. <lb/>
Can we rationally suppose that the Confederation <lb/>
would be governed by men so deficient in statesman<lb break="no"/>ship as to legislate in disregard of the circumstances <lb/>
        
        <cb/>

and feelings of the people their measures would affect. <lb/>
It requires but little reflection to satisfy a thinking <lb/>
mind of the groundless nature of such apprehensions <lb/>
and of the ample guarantees we have against the im<lb break="no"/>position of heavy taxation. The Provinces were not <lb/>
entering on this scheme with the idea that they <lb/>
would be so many distinct antagonisms, requiring <lb/>
each to guard themselves against the encroaching <lb/>
spirit of the rest; but on the contrary, they propose <lb/>
to come together for purposes of mutual co-operation <lb/>
which all stand in need of, and which can only be <lb/>
secured by a course of action in which the just <lb/>
rights of all are respected, and upheld. The <lb/>
common Interests of the Lower Provinces at least <lb/>
are acknowledged by all who speak on this <lb/>
subject, and their views on the question of taxation <lb/>
would necessarily be identical. If Canadian statesmen <lb/>
had the wish will any one assert that they would have <lb/>
the power to press taxation against the combined <lb/>
resistance of the Lower Provinces. Experience gives <lb/>
as no warrant for assuming that an attempt could be <lb/>
made so hostile to the spirit and genius of represen<lb break="no"/>tative combinations, but such strange argument had <lb/>
been used in relation to this question that ever, such <lb/>
remote and almost impossible contingencies it became <lb/>
necessary to examine and rebut. He had shown the <lb/>
utter fatility of such legislaticn if it were enacted, but <lb/>
in the case he had imagined the weight of public <lb/>
opinion throughout the confederacy would come to <lb/>
the support of those against whom oppression was <lb/>
directed and the influence would be such as no Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment would be able to resist. But he would go <lb/>
further, and suppose such a measure accomplished we <lb/>
should still have the security that lies in an appeal to <lb/>
the Imperial Government to whom all the legislation <lb/>
of the Confederation must be sent for approval. He <lb/>
would now refer to the question of the General <lb/>
Expenditure to show that it would be sufficiently <lb/>
provided for by combining the present revenues <lb/>
of the Provinces; and the extended application <lb/>
of something like the scale of Canadian duties of 1863 <lb/>
would give a surplus sufficient to provide for the new <lb/>
requirements. [Mr. Shea here read the statement as <lb/>
inserted below.] The sum of one million of dollars <lb/>
was set down for purposes of defence. He knew many <lb/>
persons thought this an insufficient amount, but they <lb/>
were of a class who made that one of many objections. <lb/>
When this estimate was made in Canada an engineer <lb/>
officer was there sent out by the Imperial Government <lb/>
to report on this question, and he (Mr. Shea) pre<lb break="no"/>sumed the Canadian Government knew something of <lb/>
that officer's opinion when this sum was set down as <lb/>
sufficient. Besides the statements of men acting under <lb/>
a sense of the responsibility of their official position <lb/>
must assuredly be taken as better evidence than the <lb/>
notions of incompetent and irresponsible opponents <lb/>
of the whole scheme. It is constantly being asserted, <lb/>
with the air of unanswerable argument, that in the <lb/>
railways and public works of Canada we have no inter<lb break="no"/>est. The objection takes that special view that char<lb break="no"/>acterises so much of the argument offered against the <lb/>
whole measure. In every improvement that facilitates <lb/>
trade and cheapens the means of transport in those <lb/>
countries we are connected with by cominercial rela<lb break="no"/>tions, we have an interest. We have an interest in <lb/>
the railways of Spain, which have improved the means <lb/>
of communication in that country, and which have <lb/>
done more than all other causes to sustain the high <lb/>
prices of our staple produce for the past few years. <lb/>
We have an interest in the railways in the United <lb/>
States, which lessen the cost of carriage from the in<lb break="no"/>terior to the seaboard, of those articles of commerce <lb/>
which we import from that country. The railways in <lb/>
Brazil are also of consequence to us in increasing the <lb/>
means of transporting our fish to parts of that country <lb/>
that were before inaccessible, and enhancing its con<lb break="no"/>sumption and value. But in the proposed Intercolonial <lb/>
Railway to Halifax we have interests of a more direct <lb/>
and significant kind. The present state of our relations <lb/>
with America is not so satisfactory as to render a rup<lb break="no"/>ture with that country a very improbable contingency. <lb/>
It is most wise then for all <choice><sic>eircumstanced</sic><corr>circumstanced</corr></choice> as we are to <lb/>
consider the position in which we should be placed in <lb/>
that event. At present we receive nearly all our sup<lb break="no"/>plies of food from the States, and for five months of <lb/>
the year the river of St. Lawrence is frozen. War <lb/>
with the States during this time when navigation is <lb/>
suspended would cut us off from all our ordinary sup<lb break="no"/>plies of food. It is in this view that the Railway to <lb/>
Halifax becomes so important and gives an answer to <lb/>
those who ask us what interest we have in its <lb/>
construction. It would be the means of saving us from <lb/>
want if England and the United States were at war, <lb/>
by establishing a communication between Canada and <lb/>
the seaboard through British Territory. The people <lb/>
of this country might be starving, while the granna<lb break="no"/>ries of Western Canada were full-stored with wheat, <lb/>
unless the Railway communication with Halifax were <lb/>
established. This is no new view of the subject, for <lb/>
it was urged by Mr. Howe, in 1862, when he said that <lb/>
"the Intercolonial Railway being finished, we shall <lb/>
not only control the telegraphic and postal communi<lb break="no"/>cation of the Western States, but secure to the people <lb/>
of Great Britain at all seasons a steady supply of <lb/>
breadstuffs, should unhapily the ports of the United <lb/>
States, in war, be closed against them." We have too <lb/>
another interest in the prosecution of these public <lb/>
works. They will give a great impetus to labour du<lb break="no"/>ring their construction, and this cannot take place so <lb/>
near to ourselves without affecting its value in this <lb/>
country. He knew that on another point much stress <lb/>
had been laid for want he felt of a full consideration of <lb/>
the circumstances. It was objected that without re<lb break="no"/>gard to the future increase of our population and re<lb break="no"/>venue, the amount of the contribution we are to re<lb break="no"/>ceive from the General Revenue is fixed. It will be <lb/>
seen that such a stipulation as this was necessery <lb/>
in the interest of the smaller Provinces. They <lb/>
cannot be expected to grow in population so as to <lb/>
keep pace with the increase of the larger Provinces, <lb/>
especially Upper Canada, where population must grow <lb/>
rapidly not only from its inherent attractiveness, but <lb/>
from a great exodus from the States which has com<lb break="no"/>menced, to escapeſrom the ruinous taxation which the <lb/>
war will impose on that country. It the question <lb/>
of local subsidies were left open, the Revenues would <lb/>
be absorbed by Canada, and increased taxation for <lb/>
general purposes would then become necessary. No <lb/>
better check could have been devised to guard against <lb/>
excessive taxation, and while even should our popu<lb break="no"/>lation increase no material increase of our Local Ex<lb break="no"/>penditure for the immediate purposes of Government <lb/>
would become necessary. The larger sum would then be <lb/>
at the disposal of the General Government for general <lb/>
purposes for our fair proportion of which we should <lb/>
have our undoubted claim. The objection then that <lb/>
the amount for local purposes <choice><sic>ss</sic><corr>as</corr></choice> limited may come <lb/>
with some reason from the larger and more growing <lb/>
provinces but the argument is strange here seeing that <lb/>
the arrangement conseves the icterests of colonies <lb/>
such as this where no relative increase of population <lb/>
can reasonably be expected to take place. He felt <lb/>
that in any fair view of this subject the rate of <lb/>
taxation at the onset would be the maximum for many <lb/>
years to come, and until some great change of cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances and relations should take place. The rate <lb/>
of taxation per head in Canada is now Two dollars <lb/>
and forty cents, while in the United States in 1860, <lb/>
prior to the war, the rate was but One dollar and <lb/>
sixty-five cents, shewing that he wants of a country <lb/>
do not keep pace with a great increase of population, <lb/>
such as may be expected for the Confederation. He <lb/>
had heard the statement frequently made, that the <lb/> 

<cb/>

advocates of this change had not been able to point <lb/>
out the specific ways in which this colony would be <lb/>
benefitted by Confederation. He did not think a spe<lb break="no"/>cification of particular advantages necessary to estab<lb break="no"/>lish their case. When they were able to refer to his<lb break="no"/>tory and experience, and show by that testimony that <lb/>
such combinations have worked well, they were justi<lb break="no"/>fied in the conclusion that we might safely adopt it. <lb/>
This was far better evidence to sustain their position <lb/>
than any opinions of anticipated beliefits which were <lb/>
necessarily more or less speculative, and could more <lb/>
easily be disputed by men of adverse views. But <lb/>
though he did not consider this course necessary, <lb/>
he still had no objection to offer to the Committee <lb/>
some opinions he had formed as to its probable deve<lb break="no"/>lopments. The establishment of Steam Communica<lb break="no"/>tion would bring us into close contact with the other <lb/>
Provinces, especially Canada, making our people <lb/>
known to them and they to us, and thus creating <lb/>
those relations from which mutual advantages would <lb/>
assuredly result. We should become better acquaint<lb break="no"/>ed with the circumstances of those Colonies, and with <lb/>
the means they afford for the extension of our trade, <lb/>
and our middle classes would thus have opportunities <lb/>
for business transactions which they never can at<lb break="no"/>quire while confined to our local resources. It is the <lb/>
invariable consequence of Steam communication to <lb/>
promote trade, and create new means for its enlarge<lb break="no"/>ment, and a slight consideration of our circumstances <lb/>
and those of the Sister Colonies, must show that we <lb/>
shall be no exception to this admitted rule. Then we <lb/>
have often boasted, and justly too, of the commanding <lb/>
position of the harbor of St. John's, and we have made <lb/>
great, but unsuccessful efforts to attract to it the at<lb break="no"/>tention to which we think it is entitled as a prominent <lb/>
Atlantic port. Is it at all unreasonable to suppose <lb/>
that when we become united to Canada, the advan<lb break="no"/>tages it offers as a half-way house for their ships, <lb/>
will not be recognised when brought to their notice <lb/>
by us, and the very probable result will be the es<lb break="no"/>tablishment of a Dock capable of taking up ships of <lb/>
the largest size, which will not only make it, a port <lb/>
of refuge for the crippled. Canadian ships, but will <lb/>
caused to be generally visited by vessels in distress, <lb/>
much to their safely and convenience and the profit <lb/>
of our tradesmen and labourers? This project was <lb/>
brought before the house by Mr. Newman some two <lb/>
years since, and he [Mr. Shea] felt it had not re<lb break="no"/>ceived the attention it really deserved. Our Post <lb/>
Office arrangements being under the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment our Post roads would claim their attention and <lb/>
then we might reasonably hope to see the roads to <lb/>
Trepassey and Placentia completed, and be freed from <lb/>
the reproach suggested in the petition of the Com<lb break="no"/>mercial Society that the question of Confederation <lb/>
now three months before the country has not yet been <lb/>
heard of by the great bulk of our outport population. <lb/>
There is also the great post road being opened to the <lb/>
Twilingate district which would be completed in a <lb/>
reasonable time, but if left to local means who can <lb/>
name a day sufficiently distant that will see it finished. <lb/>
We all believe the Bultow fishing on the Banks to be <lb/>
most injurious to our interest and it has often been <lb/>
contended that it was a mode of fishing repugnant to <lb/>
the terms of the treaty, and we have remonstrated on <lb/>
this point but in vain. As a part of the Confederation the <lb/>
remonstrance would come from four millions of people <lb/>
and could not so easily be disregarded. So also with <lb/>
regard to any matter on, which we felt aggrieved, <lb/>
our representations would so longer be those <lb/>
of a weak uninfluential community, but the voice of a <lb/>
powerful state whose just complaints would command <lb/>
attention and redress. These he contended were advan<lb break="no"/>tages of no mean order, nor were they such as might <lb/>
not reasonably be expected. Then when he looked <lb/>
to the great growing agricultural population of Upper <lb/>
Canada, it seemed to him to that quarter we might <lb/>
confidently look for the means of bringing our Her<lb break="no"/>ring fishery into active development. To do this we <lb/>
must have unbroken communication by water with <lb/>
Western Canada, and here we are brought to see one <lb/>
of the advantages to this country from the improve<lb break="no"/>ment of the Canal system, in waich in which it had <lb/>
been asserted we had no interest. It would hardly <lb/>
be credited elsewhere that we have on our coasts at <lb/>
certain seasons, herrings in illimitable quantities, and <lb/>
yet we have also a want of employment for the people <lb/>
and extensive pauperism. There is evidently some <lb/>
grave defect in our economic arrangements, or these <lb/>
facts could not co-exist. It does not appear to suit <lb/>
the interest of our Merchants to prosecute this <lb/>
fishery, though the Americans carry on the trade to <lb/>
some extent in Fortune Bay to their profit, no doubt, <lb/>
and much to the advantage of our people in that <lb/>
locality. It is evident it will never, acquire the im<lb break="no"/>portance it should have but through the agency of <lb/>
strangers who in their own country may see the means <lb/>
of bringing this fish into extensive cousumption, and <lb/>
he saw no more likely field of operations than amongst <lb/>
the great agricultural population of Upper Canada <lb/>
when our increased intercourse brought our capabili<lb break="no"/>ties in this respect more clearly before them. These <lb/>
seemed to him to be a few of the benefits that would <lb/>
arise, but when they looked at the result of the calcu<lb break="no"/>lations often before made as to the operation of great <lb/>
changes, they would find even where general success <lb/>
attended those measures it has often been in ways that <lb/>
had not been predicted. It was so with the Railway <lb/>
system of England, and with the Commercial Treaty <lb/>
with France, both great and both satisfactory <lb/>
in other respects than had been foretold. He certainly <lb/>
augured much advantage to this country from the fact <lb/>
that Canada had a great interest in our prosperity, <lb/>
apart from the general principle that would lead her <lb/>
to promote the welfare of every member of the Con<lb break="no"/>federation. But from the circumstances that we pro<lb break="no"/>duce so little in this colony, our imports of Canadian <lb/>
produce would probably be larger than those of any of <lb/>
the Lower Provinces and as good customers, her inter<lb break="no"/>est in our welfare is assured even on the most selfish <lb/>
grounds. On the question of the general powers of <lb/>
taxation of all kinds which are to be given to the gen<lb break="no"/>eral Government the fears of many persons had been <lb/>
excited, owing to their partial and imperfect considera<lb break="no"/>tion of this portion of the plan. The rights of levying <lb/>
Duties of Customs is given to the General Parliament, <lb/>
and Direct Taxation is reserved for the Local Legis<lb break="no"/>latures. Over both these is given to the General <lb/>
Legislature a sort of sovereign right which must neces<lb break="no"/>sarily reside in a Body to which such large powers and <lb/>
responsibilities are confided, and which in this case can <lb/>
only be possessed by means of direct provision, the <lb/>
Constitution being a written one, and therefore confer<lb break="no"/>ring no authority but what is expressly given. This <lb/>
power over us is held by the Imperial Government at <lb/>
the present time, and the Government of the United <lb/>
States possess the same right of taxation in regard to <lb/>
all the separate States. But it must be taken and <lb/>
construed in connexion with the special powers of tax<lb break="no"/>ation the are reserved, for it would be a mockery to <lb/>
give the Local Legislatures the right of Direct Taxa<lb break="no"/>tion, if as in a general rule or in ordinary circumstan<lb break="no"/>ces the right could be set aside by the controlling Body. <lb/>
No fair reading of these several stipulations can lead <lb/>
to any other conclusion than that the taxation <lb/>
of houses, and property of that kind, belongs <lb/>
as at present to the Local Government, and cannot <lb/>
be applied except by their agency, and that practically <lb/>
our position is not changed in this respect. None of <lb/>
the Provinces would give to the General Government <lb/>
an authority that could otherwise operate, for this <lb/>
power of direct taxation is an inherent right in the <lb/> 
    
   <cb/> 
    
local bodies, and should not be aleniated. In case of <lb/>
great emergency or danger where the lives of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple and all they hold most dear were put in peril, <lb/>
then the general power would be exercised for the <lb/>
preservation of the interests at stake, and in view of <lb/>
such emergencies the wisdom and necessity of clothing <lb/>
the Government with full authority must be apparent. <lb/>
In the United States where this power exists, he <lb/>
(Mr. Shea) had not been able to find that it was ever <lb/>
exercised until the breaking out of the present war <lb/>
when necessity brought it into operation, and when <lb/>
that power had it not been provided, would have been <lb/>
exercised as were many others without any constitu<lb break="no"/>tional authority. And so in the present case, if it were <lb/>
omitted in the propose constitution, and that at any <lb/>
future time an exigency arose demanding its exercise <lb/>
the General Government in the interests of the people <lb/>
would be compelled to usurp the authority as was <lb/>
done by President Lincoln, whose course was so fully <lb/>
justified by his recent election. How much wiser <lb/>
then to provide as is here proposed for all possible <lb/>
contingencies when the power is in the hands of a <lb/>
Responsible Government rather than leave the <lb/>
country exposed to a resort to authority unknown <lb/>
to the Constitution which involves dangers of <lb/>
a grave character. As regards the burthens the <lb/>
federation would entail, an army and navy are <lb/>
held out in prominent relief, and the alarm of tax <lb/>
payers is sought to be excited. He had already on a <lb/>
former occasion explained his views on this head, and <lb/>
they are not changed by farther consideration. The <lb/>
Colonies are expected to assist themselves, but no <lb/>
intention exists of placing on them so great a bur<lb break="no"/>then as an army and navy would create. While we <lb/>
are dependencies manifestly unable to sustain so great <lb/>
an obligation, its imposition would be opposed to all <lb/>
sense of justice, and the relation we hold to the <lb/>
mother country. No doubt the day will come when <lb/>
the Confederation will, from its increase of population <lb/>
and wealth, necessarily cease to be a Dependency <lb/>
and with the best wishes of the Mother Country <lb/>
from which these Colonies would never voluntarily <lb/>
separate, an independent national position will be as<lb break="no"/>sumed. When that time does arrive, an army and <lb/>
navy, and the other obligations of national existence <lb/>
will doubtless become necessarry, and the Country <lb/>
will have the ability to sustain these burthens. But <lb/>
at present we have no need to deal with such conside<lb break="no"/>rations. Mr. Mill, the great writer he had already <lb/>
quoted, though belonging to the school that holds <lb/>
the Colonies of light value to England, yet ad<lb break="no"/>mits, that "as the Mother Country claims the <lb/>
privilege, at her sole discretion, of taking mea<lb break="no"/>sures or pursuing a policy which may expose them <lb/>
to attack, it is just that she should undertake a con<lb break="no"/>siderable portion of their Military Defence even in <lb/>
time of peace; the whole of it so far as it depends on a <lb/>
standing Army." That this is the view entertained by <lb/>
        H.M. present Government is evident from the follow<lb break="no"/>ing paragraph in Mr. Cardwell's Despatch— <lb/></p>     
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>"A very important part of this subject is the ex<lb break="no"/>pensa which may attend the working of the Central <lb/>
and the Local Governments. Her Majesty's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment cannot but express the earnest hope that the <lb/>
arrangements which may be adopted in this respect <lb/>
may not be of such a nature as to increase, at least in <lb/>
any considerable degree, the whole expenditure, or to <lb/>
make any material addition to the taxation, and there<lb break="no"/>by retard the internal industry, or tend to impose <lb/>
new burdens on the commerce of the country." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>These words would be an idle mockery if it were con<lb break="no"/>templated to impose on the Confederation the heavy <lb/>
obligation an Army and Navy would involve. We may <lb/>
therefore conclude that the just and equitable policy <lb/>
which leaves this charge for the present at least with <lb/> 
the Imperial, Government is that it is proposed to <lb/>
follow, and that we need not indulge in any serious <lb/>
apprenensions on this account. The plan of the Con<lb break="no"/>federation embraces little of what is new. Its pro<lb break="no"/>moters were alive to the wisdom of framing the mea<lb break="no"/>sure by regard to the approved nature of the old <lb/>
foundations on which they designed that this super<lb break="no"/>structure should mainly test. The slight variance it <lb/>
presents to the British model are those alone which <lb/>
the circumstances rendered necessary, and its whole <lb/>
character is testified by the unanimous voice <lb/>
of the British nation. But in considering the <lb/>
question of its adaptation to our condition, it may <lb/>
not be amiss that we should further consider the results <lb/>
of our present system as regards taxation and expend<lb break="no"/>iture. He had referred to the various kinds of taxation <lb/>
and shown that only was oppressive from which the <lb/>
people at large derived little or no benefit. When he re<lb break="no"/>flected on the character of our expenditure the injus<lb break="no"/>tice of the present system of taxation became striking<lb break="no"/>ly apparent. Of the sum of one hundred thousand pounds <lb/>
    sterling we raise, the following is the appropriation:—<lb/>
    Salaries, £23,539; Printing, &amp;c., £2100; Poor Hos<lb break="no"/>pitals, &amp;c., £17,454; Post-office, £3280; Pensions, <lb/>
£2,170; Ferries, £380; Steam, 5.150; Protection of <lb/>
Fisheries and sundries £2,500; R-pairs of Buildings, <lb/> 
£750; Supplies of Guis, &amp;c., £1,400; Education, <lb/>
    £13,625; Interest on Debt, £10,210; Contingencies: <lb/>
    of legislature, £6,000; Sundries, £2000; Roads, <lb/>
£10,000. It will he seen how small a portion of this <lb/>
Expenditure is for any purpose of improvement by <lb/>
which the condition of the people would be improved. <lb/>
The Education Grant, from a variety of causes, gives <lb/> 
no corresponding benefit, and the Road Grant which <lb/> 
the people value most, is only made when all <lb/>
other services are provided for, and is not to <lb/>
be relied, on as an annual grant. Nor did <lb/>
he see that our existing Constitution was ca<lb break="no"/>pable of working out much better results. He <lb/>
trusted all these various reflections would be dwelt on <lb/>
by the people in a calm and inquiring spirit, so that <lb/>
when the time came for final decision on this most <lb/>
important question they would be enabled to come <lb/>
to the conclusion most in accord with the progress <lb/>
of society and the conservation of the common inter<lb break="no"/>est of the people of this country. <lb/> </p>
    
    <!-- IC, 2018-11-13, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>Comparative Statement of Canadian and Newfound. <lb/>
land Tariff as applied to our Imports in 1863, and <lb/>
Jor the past ten years, with the equivalent offered <lb/>
under Confederation. <lb/>
1863. <lb/>
Revenue by Canadian Tariff 2135,032 14 3 <lb/>
Do. Newfoundland Tariff, 94,513 19 2 # <lb/>
£40,518 15 1 } <lb/>
E8TIMATED ABATEMENT8. <lb/>
Bread £7,894 0 0 <lb/>
Kerosene Oil 127 10 0 <lb/>
Ale and Porter 499 0 0 <lb/>
Soap 880 0 0 <lb/>
Leatherware 5,000 0 0 <lb/>
Candles 382 0 0 <lb/>
"..."; 2,400 o 0 <lb/>
£17,182 10 0 <lb/>
–-\-" <lb/>
Nett Reyenue 1863 £117,850 4 * <lb/></p> 

<p>e Revenue, 10 years <lb/>
increase *: <lb/>
Tariff <lb/></p> 

<p>Averag <lb/>
verage. <lb/>
Canadian <lb/></p> 

<p>Average abatements <lb/></p> 

<p>dia <lb/>
average producedana <lb/>
Nett CoNTRA <lb/>
Amount gu" anteed by Resol <lb/>
Conference <lb break="no"/>Steam between Newfoundlan <lb/>
England and Canada <lb/>
nd Postal Steamer <lb/>
#jºi Survey <lb/></p> 

<p>-º-º-º<lb break="no"/>Financial position of <lb/>
LIABILIT <lb/></p> 

<p>Interest on Debt <lb/>
SUBSIDIES­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Canada . <lb/></p> 

<p>Nova Scotia. <lb/></p> 

<p>New Brunswick <lb/></p> 

<p>Newfoundland <lb/></p> 

<p>P. E. Island <lb/>
GENERAL, EXPENDITURE. <lb/></p> 

<p>Administration of Justice <lb/>
Civil Government <lb/>
Legislative Expences <lb/>
I)efence <lb/>
Public Works, &amp;c., <lb/>
Steam <lb/>
Collection Revenue <lb/>
Miscellaneous <lb/></p> 

<p>ASSET3. <lb/>
Canada kevenue <lb/>
Nova Scotia <lb/>
New Brunswick <lb/>
Newfoundland <lb/>
P. E. Island <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Lºt #itufºu <lb/>
ST. JOH <lb/>
THURSDAY, MAR <lb/></p> 

<p>-<lb break="maybe"/>(ſ <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/>The last few days have witness <lb/>
and activity in our thoroughfar <lb/>
the Sealers for their annual <lb/>
Wolf went out of port on Tues <lb/>
one of the fleet jet gone. Th <lb/>
and only awaiting a favorable <lb/>
out of their track. The outfit fi <lb/></p> 

<p>is somewhat larger than that of <lb/>
-º-º­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ERitatuxt.—In last sentenc <lb/>
Lenten Pastoral of the Rt. 1 <lb/>
words should be, "The Holy <lb/>
for gaining the Jubilee will no <lb/>
of the Easter duty, for the pre <lb/>
the indulgence of the Jubilee, t <lb/>
Communion." <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>The following letter appear <lb/></p> 

<p>Harbon GR <lb/>
SiR,-A friend has recently <lb/></p> 

<p>a letter in your issue of the <lb/>
perhaps had escaped my noti <lb/>
ported to be unfavorable toGo <lb/>
forbids me to say what I thi <lb/>
of your correspondent, who t. <lb/>
ledge or concurrence, proclait <lb/>
to be my sentiments on this <lb/>
also prematurely to give publi <lb/>
may entertain for or a <lb/>
Newfoundland with Canad <lb/>
sure you that whenever the <lb/>
those amongst whom Provide <lb/>
quire my ho-tility to this or <lb/>
to affect them injuriously, I sh <lb/>
it openly and in my own nam <lb/>
by proxv. In the meantime <lb/>
refuse insertion to any commi <lb/>
me political or other views, til <lb/>
to do so by attaching to then <lb/>
lure. , <lb/></p> 

<p>Faithfully 5 <lb/></p> 

<p>To the Editor of the day-boo <lb/>
Sl <lb/></p> 

<p>—e— <lb/>
(ro THE EDIroR of THE <lb/></p> 

<p>SIR,-\-I was in hopes the <lb/>
entirely disappeared—all part <lb/>
being thoroughly ashamed of <lb/>
ed in the affair. But it see <lb/>
people, headed by an excitabl: <lb/>
master, and a couple of gallan: <lb/>
to stili keep the affair before t <lb/>
now engaged in the holy work <lb/>
ment to discharge a poor const <lb/>
is simply an excess of duty—d. <lb/>
able desire of preserving tº <lb/>
in his lºve ef letter-writing, a <lb/>
extraordinary talent for conv <lb/>
way, he stated in a letter to t <lb/>
(what he was told upon, as <lb/>
authority) in such a way as <lb/>
magistrate and others to think <lb/>
tion he so much deplored and <lb/>
ºnly the talk of the grog-shop, <lb/>
lani youths over their cups <lb/>
traitors. There was conside; <lb/>
ing iſ. at Port-dc-Grave, b <lb/>
to kill the Fenians or sea-birds <lb/>
ºnce of opinion at Port-de<lb break="no"/>However, Air. Editor, I trust <lb/>
*ot gº so far as to discharge tº <lb/>
*able, and thereby make him a <lb/>
time to come. A severe repr.In <lb/>
his-lettel-writing propensities, <lb/>
his style of composition. <lb/>
Your obedient se <lb/></p> 

<p>Feb. 27th, 1865. <lb/>
**m. <lb/></p> 

<p>pied,—On Friday evening <lb/></p> 

<p>sinful iſlness, Mary, the belº, <lb/>
º Purchase." y: <lb/></p>-->

    
    
    <pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-20_Page_1.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    
</div>
    <div type="debate">
    
    <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head>
    
    <p rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, Feb. 21.</p>
        <p>The house met at three o'clock. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
        The hon RECIEVER GENERAL, by command of his <lb/>
        Excellency the Governor, presented to the house a return <lb/>
        of the duties collected at Harbor Grace in the years <lb/>
        1862 '3 and '4. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
        Ordered that this document lie on the table. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
        <persName ref="pers:RORK1">Mr. RORKE</persName> presented a pretition from Wm. Burke <lb/>
        and others, of Victoria Village, near Carbonear, which <lb/>
        was received and read, praying for a grant to complete <lb/>
        the road through that settlement. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
        Ordered that the petion lie on the table. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
        <persName ref="pers:KAVA1">M. KAVANAGH</persName> presented a petition from Gregory <lb/>
        Duggan and others, of Broad Cove, which was received <lb/>
        and read, praying for a grant to complete the road join<lb break="no"/>ing the Portugal Cove road. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
        Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
        On motion of the hon ATTORNEY GENERAL, pursuant <lb/>
        to order of the day, the house resolved itself into com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the whole on the further consideration of the <lb/>
        confederation of the British North American Provinces. <lb/>
        Mr. Knight in the chair. <lb/></p>
            
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:RORK1">Mr. RORKE</persName> said he rose to say a few words on this <lb/>
        important subject of confederation. He regarded the <lb/>
        subject in two aspects, political and commercial, Some <lb/>
        of the supporters of the latter seemed to forget the for<lb break="no"/>mer. All who had paid attention to the proceedings in <lb/>
        the Imperial Parliament, and the progress of public <lb/>
        opinion in England, of late years, must be aware that the <lb/>
        question of the military expenditure in the colonies had <lb/>
        received a good deal of attention, and was the cause of <lb/>
        much complaint, and that Her Majesty's Government <lb/>
        were pressed to have recourse to every means of its <lb/>
        reduction. That question of confederation, which was <lb/>
        taken up in the neighbouring Provinces, and to which <lb/>
        they were invited to become parties, offered an oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of effecting such reduction; and we saw, by the <lb/>
        despatch of Mr. Cardwell, that it was strongly recom<lb break="no"/>mended to us by Her Majesty's Government. We had <lb/>
        therefore to consider it as a measure which the home go<lb break="no"/>vernment desired to see carried out. By the confedera<lb break="no"/>tion of the colonies, they would form a powerful commu<lb break="no"/>nity, and the Imperial Government would be gradually <lb/>
        relieved from a considerable, portion of the existing <lb/>
        military evpenditure. It had been said that Great <lb/>
        Britain would still continue our plesent protection to us, <lb/>
        and that we might, therefore, remain out of the con<lb break="no"/>federation. He (Mr. Rorke) did not consider the matter <lb/>
        in that light. If we declined to accept the terms offered <lb/>
        to us, he apprehended the British Government would <lb/>
        not act towards us as they had hitherto done. It had <lb/>
        been stated that the statesmen of Canada desired to have <lb/>
        this Colony, and the other maritime Provinces, for the <lb/>
        purpose of aiding in the defence of Canada. He did not <lb/>
        concur in that. Canada was a populous and powerful <lb/>
        and prosperous country, and better able to defend her<lb break="no"/>self than we were. Then as to the commercial aspect <lb/>
        of the question; many apprehended that we would be <lb/>
        subjected to a much larger annunt of taxation than we <lb/>
        now paid; but when we come to consider the position <lb/>
        we would be in, he did not see much to apprehend <choice><sic>rom</sic><corr>from</corr></choice> <lb/>
        increased taxation. People were apprehensive that the <lb/>
        tariff of Canada would be adopted by the confederate <lb/>
        Government and Legislature. But supposing the tariff <lb/>
        of Canada were applied to our imports, he did not consi<lb break="no"/>der that it would produce so much revenue as was sup<lb break="no"/>posed. By that tariff, books, lines, seines, nets, salt and <lb/>
        canvas were admitted duty free, which were articles of <lb/>
        large consumption in the fisheries. There were other <lb/>
        articles which came in at a duty not exceeding our pre<lb break="no"/>sent tariff. A large quantity of goods were imported now <lb/>
        which we had no business to use; and which had been <lb/>
        the cause of three fourths of the poverty under which <lb/>
        Newfoundland now suffered; and if increased duties <lb/>
        would be the means of reducing the consumption of such <lb/>
        goods, he (Mr. Rorke) would say that it would be a <lb/>
        great benefit to the country. But respecting the in<lb break="no"/>creased duty on manufactured goods; so far as regarded <lb/>
        our operative population, he did not apprehend the <lb/>
        revenue would be increased by them. Look at Canada. <lb/>
        He found there manufactures of the articles we required, <lb/>
        which, under confederation, would come in duty free. <lb/>
        These manufactures had much increased of late years, <lb/>
        and now manufactures from the United States were com<lb break="no"/>ing in, on account of the distracted state of the country, <lb/>
        occassioned by the war, and its enormous taxation. They <lb/>
        had extensive woollen manufactures, manufactures of <lb/>
        boots and shoes, and the manufactures of leather were <lb/>
        very extensive. Canada had long been noted for its <lb/>
        superior saddlery, which was not, however, of extensive <lb/>
        demand here. But Canada leather was a good <lb/>
        article, and our consumption of leatherware was large. <lb/>
        He (Mr. Rorke) had samples of boots and shoes, from <lb/>
        Quebec, last fall, and he had compared them with our <lb/>
        imports from England and other countries, and found <lb/>
        them very much superior to what we were in the habit <lb/>
        of receiving from America, and fully equal to the Eng<lb break="no"/>lish, while the prices were moderate. Their leather and <lb/>
        their castings were of as good a description as what came <lb/>
        from England, and fully as cheap. He had no doubt <lb/>
        that many other articles were produced in Canada that <lb/>
        would suit us, and which would all come in duty free. <lb/>
        We all knew that when people were put to it, they <lb/>
        readily actommodated themselves to circumstacces. We <lb/>
        need not, therefore, be apprehensive that there would be <lb/>
        any great difficulty in substituting the Canadian manufac<lb break="no"/>ture for the British. He did not, therefore, apprehend <lb/>
        that our taxation would, on the whole, be higher than <lb/>
        now, and he believed that our fishermen would in many <lb/>
        instances get better articles than they used now, and <lb/>
        equally cheap. Flour and provisions were also abun<lb break="no"/>dant and cleap in Canada, and, when the Grand Trunk <lb/>
        Railway was completed to Halifax, could be received by <lb/>
        us all the year round. This was an age of change, and <lb/>
        the confederation of small states into larger was occuring <lb/>
        yearly, in Europe. He thought, taking the whole matter <lb/>
        into consideration, that Confederation would ultimately <lb/>
        prove beneficial. He did not anticipate any immediate <lb/>
        benefit, nor did he suppose we would suffer any detri<lb break="no"/>ment, for he believed we would find that the revenue on <lb/>
        the articles we would receive duty free would balance <lb/>
        the increase duty on the others; and then Canada <lb/>
        offered an unlimited market for our pickled fish, while <lb/>
            Confederation would secure us against the imposition of <lb/>
            any duty upon it. We were also promised steam com<lb break="no"/>
    
    <cb/>
    
 munication both with England and with Canada, and <lb/>
        when that was accomplished, he believed it would work <lb/>
        a greater benefit to this country than could, at present, <lb/>
        be estimated. But some hon members were apprehensive <lb/>
                that the federal parliament would tax our fish and oil.— <lb/>
        That could easily be guarded against, and he believed if <lb/>
        delegates were sent to England on the subject, we would <lb/>
        get other concessions. We were not similar to the <lb/>
        other provinces, and that would be taken into considera<lb break="no"/>tion. It was his firm belief that Confederation would <lb/>
        ultimately be of great benefit. He did not desire to <lb/>
        influence others, but it was his belief that it would work <lb/>
        beneficially for this country, and, therefore, he had much <lb/>
        pleasure in supporting the resolutions moved by the hon <lb/>
        leader of the government. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
        (Here followed the speech of Mr. Shea which has been <lb/>
        already published in this Journal) <lb/></p>
    
    
    
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>