<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-15" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1869-02-15">15 February 1869</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1869-02-19"/>,
<date when="1869-02-24"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_3.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2019-01-10">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2019-01-10">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_3"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_3.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_2.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2019-01-10, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

<!--<p>*= <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>"I h E. N. F. W. Fo UN D i. A N D E R. <lb/></p> 

<p>- - º: ams-e<lb break="no"/>never intended that it should be regarded in th which was so perfeet <lb/>
light. We ..º. you and º: country .;: §. #. S.) *.*. <lb/></p> 

<p> y" -\-\- <lb break="no"/>if terms avorable to the interests of thº' tº: part ºn the **. "º. <lb/>
ºnnot be agreed to. Why, the hon member ºf: have it to say that it fell to his <lb/>
Glen, sayif we get terms satisfactory, he was real, part, however humble, in so im; <lb/>
That plan had met with the a <lb/></p> 

<p>to go in for Confederation, and yet the hon membe: <lb/>
would debar us by his proceeding from *taining leading men of England of all po <lb/></p> 

<p>would never be until the Dominion had been either <lb/>
natured into strength and power, and declared its <lb/>
will so tº be, or until Great Britain had elected to <lb/>
throw off the burthen of Colonial depaudencies. <lb/>
At present an alliance with the United States could <lb/>
only be faught with enormous public debt and tax-<lb break="maybe"/>a'ion amounting to an annual burthen of $30 per <lb/>
head. The hon and 'earned member then proceed­ <lb/></p> 

<p>tion means employment. While the abstruse argu<lb break="no"/>ment of hon. memners opposits might be thrown <lb/>
away, the peoplewould be able understand when they <lb/>
were spoken to in this manner. The only thing hop. <lb/>
members opposite had done was to endeavour tº <lb/>
mystify the people. If their real opinions were worth <lb/>
anything the people must go without them. On the <lb/>
question of terms he (Mt. O'R) should be prepared to <lb/></p> 

<p>gallery knew that it mattered very little to him and <lb/>
to the country whether the prosent five or six office<lb break="no"/>holders or the same number of gentlemen from the <lb/>
other side were in the enjoyment of place and e no<lb break="no"/>lument, but such a man was quite capable of unuer: <lb/>
standing, and hon members might depend upon it <lb/>
the public were intelligent enough to distinguish <lb/></p> 

<p>t <lb/></p> 

<p>between what were earnest solid arguments and the <lb/>
tactics of politics. The hon, and learned member, <lb/>
Mr. Hogsett, supports this amendment of Mr. <lb/>
Talbot's and reproaches the hon, member for Harbor <lb/>
Grace with not speaking to the motion, and not <lb/>
giving expression to his views. He (Mr. P.) could <lb/>
3. understand that a young member but a few <lb/></p> 

<p>'s in this House, and who had never entered the did not directly force it. He deprecated the -\- - -<lb break="maybe"/># *. might be inuisposed to deliver inconsistency º hot members who, in the 'saine some hon member opposite to enlighten , the were acceptable or not. He could not, therefors, J.; sº a subject? A test like that, tile q <lb/>
himself of frequent speeches; but he was at a loes speech, spoke of Britain as a cruel stepmother, and House upon the question before ºne chair. agree to this paragraph being amended, and be 'i º well versed in the suience of <lb/>
to cºnceive hºw the charge of suppression of his then laided alliance with it as sº mugſ, preferable | He had expected to bar some vigºrºs ºuen could not agree to the amend mºnt, bºause it son- # whose integrity aud impartial <lb/>
opinions could be made against the hon member, to closer connection with the sister Colonies. He upon this all important, question of Confedera | tained a statement that was untrue. The question of: doubted, who look calmly on fr <lb/>
who had expressed himsel; so clearly and decisively argued that oar vºice in the Daminion Councils |tion. It wºuld appear that there was not much Contederation had never been rejected by this Legis. § and say that this system of Gov. <lb/></p> 

<p>on the first day of the session, and about whose <lb/>
views upon this address there could be no mistake, <lb/>
as it bore his, (Mr. Godden's) maine at the foot of <lb/>
it, as Chairman ct the Committee that drew it up. <lb/>
lion. mambers say, with an asunption of grave sin<lb break="no"/>cerity, let us educate and inform the people on this <lb/>
question. This was the very course the Govern<lb break="no"/>inent side proposed to take, and was engaged in <lb/>
urging; and this was the tenor of its resolution, <lb/>
while the terms of the amendment are calculated, <lb/>
and, as he believed, designed to prevent the very <lb/>
education aud information they professed to be, so <lb/>
anxious about, The opposition will not allow usif,they <lb/>
can help it. to inform the people. Tae hon inem<lb break="no"/>ber for St. John's West, Mr. Talbot, contends that <lb/>
we are in a position to help ourselves, to develop <lb/>
our own resources and industries. He asserts this <lb/>
and uttery fails to prove it. But, he adds, does <lb/>
Canada sºy she will help us, that she will come <lb/>
down with a sum of money for the improvemennt of <lb/>
this country? Now lie (wir. P.) took up the hon. <lb/>
member on his own grouad, und replied that is just <lb/>
one of the things we want to find out, by adopting <lb/>
course proposed in the addess. That hon. meinber <lb/>
again says, how are we get out of our isolation, an <lb/>
into the current of civilization by confederating? <lb/>
We shall b2, and remain an Island, says he, unless <lb/>
some convulsion of nature throws us into the maia <lb/>
land of Canada. He (Mr. P.) thought and believed, <lb/></p> 

<p>with every man who had cºmmon sense to under- to go again before the country upou in efinite step should be taken by this House before an appeal could never arise in. this case. But assuming lot good would this collatry <lb/>
stand what they were talking about, that the very speculation, to be in a position to assail the govern- was made to the country at the next general election. argument sake that it did, he (hon Mr S) knew of: tue exponditure in Cauada o <lb/>
fact of our being an Island and renote from our ment as having offered nothing preferable to the Upon inotion the Committee then rose, reported | lºw countries that had been sold that had not been . ife (no 1. Mr. S ) replied ti <lb/>
neighbours, was the very reason for Quebec Conveu'ion, and then to be in a position to progress, and asked leave to sit again on Monday. the gainers. Look at Louisiana when she was pur-: advauc th - l - t b t <lb/>
desiring efficient and speedy means of deal with the matter themselves, without submitting The House then adjourned unil Monday at 3 chased by, the United States Iron France—that was u06 tº value of lab ºr i <lb/>
trade and intercourse, and by , such means their own future plans to the country. He concluded o'clock. a sale, and unoney paid to it, and see how prosperous . try, and, tuat would by must <lb/>
Louisiana had been since. Had she not been a; tue laboring classes; an i though <lb/></p> 

<p>and their consequences, we should get into the <lb/>
more ample current of civilization. As it was. he <lb/>
doubted if we had the means to continue local <lb/>
steam flself. We had already begun to feel the <lb/>
first truits of Confederatiºn, tºy the tact that an <lb/>
opportuuity would be afforded to 800 heads of <lb/>
tāmilies, it employment could not be got here, to <lb/>
obtain Railway work in Canuda the coming suin<lb break="no"/>mer, steamcrs taking theim and bringi g then <lb/>
back, it they chose to return. That was a sun.ill <lb/>
example of what univn would do. The union ut <lb/>
the two Capadas was cited as an unfortunate oilu. <lb/>
True, there had been some political disaffection, <lb/>
but the material progress of those file countries <lb/>
had not been interrupted, in population, public <lb/>
wºrks, railways, &amp;c. It showed how little our <lb/>
people need care about the political changes, iſ the <lb/>
substautial blessings of lile were to ſlow <lb/>
from the proposed union. The hon. and learned <lb/>
luetmber ticu proceeued to 8how that so fur irutu <lb/>
its being the fact, as Mr. Tilbot had said, that Sir <lb/>
liugh Hoyles had uo been favourable to Confe<lb break="no"/>deration, he, Sir Hugh, hud been the very strºng<lb break="no"/>est advocate of it, and would have adopted tie <lb/>
Quebec sclieme without hesitatiou, but for the less <lb/>
buld policy of his ussociates and tile ineumbers of <lb/>
the House in general. Here Mr. Pinseut cited <lb/>
at considerable length from the speech of Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General Hoyles in 1865, a speech whicu he <lb/>
designated us out of the most powertul ever ut<lb break="no"/>tured here upon the subject. Tilat speech was in <lb/>
connection with the oily Resolution ever passed <lb/>
by this House in tie unatter of Gouiederation, and <lb/>
the closing language oi that Resulution, prop sel <lb/>
by Mr. Høyles, secuuded by the present Receiver <lb/>
General, Mr. Kent, then in oppositivu, and curried <lb/>
unanimously, was " that a linul determination <lb/>
upon this importunt subject be deterra 1 until <lb/>
the next session of the Legislature." The <lb/>
session there reterred to was the first <lb/>
session of this very preseut Parlialuent, so that <lb/>
if that resulution had been acted upon, as it unight, <lb/>
in all consistency have been, the question now <lb/>
before us, for consideration oily, migut have been <lb/>
finally determined turce years ago, without any <lb/>
further appeal. But on account of the desire <lb/>
generally expressed, that it should not be so <lb/>
ficted upou, but that butter terms should it possi<lb break="no"/>ble, be secured, and the conditious ascertained <lb/>
for the inſurinution of the Jeople, and a promise <lb/>
of the premier that there should be uo final deter<lb break="no"/>mination until the inuproved terms had been first <lb/>
submitted to the people, ſor these reasons a <lb/>
course, the one now being pursued, was taken. <lb/>
Here Mr. Pinsent read a long extruct ſroul, as h <lb/>
said, the finest speech, and that was say great <lb/>
deal, ever delivered by Mr. Reuout in the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly, in which, in 1965, he supported Mr. Hoyles's <lb/>
resolution, and poiuted out in turcible terms the <lb/>
propriety of taking the course now proposed by <lb/>
the governunent, belore sending the question to <lb/>
the people, also extracts troºm jr. Glen's speeches <lb/>
of that time to the same effect, and part of ºn <lb/>
editorial from the Patriot printed by the hon. mem. <lb/>
bºr, Mr. Parsons, in Roman letters, which could <lb/>
alumust be read from the gallery, to the effect that <lb/>
no sane than could for 3 inoment think of rejecting <lb/>
the consºlºition of equitable terms. He (Air. P.) <lb/>
never could bring himself to believe in the sincerſ <lb/>
ity of Mr. Parsons's subsequent opposition. It <lb/>
must have been irom fearola loss of that 1. opularity <lb/>
of which he was so fond, and which he so de<lb break="no"/>servºlly enjoyed; but that hon, member would <lb/>
do wisely now in turning with the tide, which had <lb/>
evidently set the other way. The hou. member <lb/>
(Mr. Pinsent) then showsd that there was to fail <lb/>
comparison to be mºde with the Irish uniou, some <lb/>
of the terms of which every liberlly tuiuded man <lb/>
now condemned and eudeavoured to remove. <lb/>
There were no objections of that kind to Confeder. <lb/>
ich conteumplated perfect equality, and <lb/></p> 

<p>il atºl religious liberty in its highest uevelop<lb break="no"/>meut. Would jute Iligent men be deluded by the <lb/>
prºposal to take...off all duties ou the staple <lb/>
accessaries of life this session, as a partial <lb/>
alleviatiosi of the burtheus of the people, when <lb/>
the finaucial eoudition of the gov and the <lb/>
state of the people were sush its they now ure, aul <lb/>
with a debt cousiderably exceeding half a million <lb/>
ºf dollars tº be redeemed in tour or five years? <lb/>
Iſºn: members whº suggested such neºs <lb/>
must be aware of their iupossibility, and the <lb/>
ºpiº, and rºiu which must bºonju. <lb/>
on their adoption as we now are, while by an alli<lb break="no"/>ance with the Dominion those objects they so <lb/></p> 

<p>press what he considered to be essential conditions, <lb/></p> 

<p>ded to argue that if the policy of the Statesmen of <lb/>
Great Britain to annex this Island and the sister <lb/>
Provinces, was Confederation, this was a strong addi<lb break="no"/>tional reason for submitting to it, and he pointed out <lb/>
several modes in which an indirect pressure might <lb/>
be bronght to bear upon us, even if the parent state <lb/></p> 

<p>would be fairly potent. It was not to be sup <lb/>
that all the rest were to be banded against us. <lb/></p> 

<p>not the voice of the hon and learned member for <lb/>
Harbor Main of considerable weight and in<lb break="no"/>portance in this H usef And it bore the same <lb/>
relation to its numbers as our number of Repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives would to the Central Parliament. <lb/>
The Lon. member proceeded to take up other <lb/>
objections and positions put from the other side, <lb/>
argued that the amen ment was unfounded in fact, <lb/>
inconsistent in itself, and opposed to the principles <lb/>
hon. gentlemen opposite contended tor. He uſged <lb/>
that the course propose i by the address, far from <lb/>
being any interference with the rights of the people, <lb/>
was what the country was anxiously looking for, <lb/></p> 

<p>that it might know en what to decide. Meinhers <lb/>
on this side of the House proposed to take the <lb/>
proper preparatory measures before submitting the <lb/>
question o the people. They were prepared to <lb/>
stani or fall by their policy. He felt that they <lb/></p> 

<p>were candidly and honestly discharging their <lb/>
duty to their constituents. If they were rejected, <lb/></p> 

<p>when the basis of terms was submitted, then the <lb/>
consequences lay with the people; and their present <lb/>
Representatives would have acquitted themselves of <lb/>
the grave responsibility of rejecting or dangerously <lb/>
delaying this measnre. He gathered from the <lb/>
course proposed by the other side, from the very <lb/>
language of their aimendment, that their policy was <lb/></p> 

<p>by again sunn ng up the adva.tages to be derived <lb/>
fron union, and describing the nobler character of <lb/>
that new political and cominercial life into which we <lb/>
shall have entered under Confederation. ... . <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Rexocri-Notwi.listin ling the bitter <lb/>
scolding which the Opposition had just received, <lb/>
he would not be deterrid from suppoiling the <lb/>
amendment of the hon. member, Mr. Talbºt. <lb/>
The hon. member who had just spoken. and <lb/>
taxed this side of the House with inconsisten<lb break="no"/>cies, should have recollected the old adage rela: <lb/>
tive to the peculiar liability of those who lived <lb/>
in giass houses. In 1865 the hon, ºnember was <lb/>
in the Legislative Council, and had there given <lb/>
notice that he would move the following <lb/>
lesulutions:- a <lb/></p> 

<p>First,-\-That for Newfoundland to enter into a 'Con. <lb/>
federation of the British North American Coloniasupon thc <lb/>
terms, proposed in the Report of the Quebec Couference, <lb/>
would bºiletrimental to the best interests of this Uology, <lb/></p> 

<p>and ought to be resisted. -<lb break="maybe"/>Secaud, That a humble Address be transaitted to itſer <lb/></p> 

<p>Majesty, einnødying the yiews of the Legislative Council <lb/>
upon tili-subject, with their reasoils for the adoption of <lb/>
thuse wit.ws. <lb/></p> 

<p>Third," Tuata Select Con-uittee of this House be ap<lb break="no"/>poin.ed to draft ille said Address. <lb/>
But us uv further record was to be found of this <lb/>
lesolution, all must conclule what was known <lb/>
to be the case, th it the ho - member thought <lb/>
better to abandon it. Iu 1866, he give another <lb/>
notice, which he also dropped like a hot potatoe. <lb/>
"hen this is the man who talks to us of inconsis<lb break="no"/>teacies. IIe says we have do le nothing to raise <lb/>
luc country. But what has he doue?. -Last <lb/>
year we had his great bill for the reduction of <lb/>
the public expenditure, which never even went <lb/>
to a second reading. Then there was his pain<lb break="no"/>pulet upon Confederation. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Committee then rose, and the Chairman <lb/>
reported progres". To sit again tu-nurrow. <lb/></p> 

<p>Tue Lionse tuea adjunrned until 3 o'clock, <lb/>
to-inos row. <lb/></p> 

<p>FRIDAY, Feb. 12. <lb/>
The House met pursuant to adjournment. <lb/>
order of THE DAY. <lb/>
Committee of the Whole on Address. Mr. Knight <lb/>
in the Chair. <lb/>
The paragraph relating to Confederation having <lb/>
been real, <lb/>
Mr. O'RIELLY said, So much had been said on <lb/>
this matter, and so many diverse opinions offered, <lb/>
that the subject might be well said to be worn <lb/>
threadbare. While hon. members accused each <lb/>
other of inconsistency he at least could lay claim to <lb/>
consistency upon this question, and if he could <lb/>
not point to, any record of lengthy arguments <lb/>
which he had employed, he could at least flatter <lb/>
himself that he had no shifts or backslidings to ac<lb break="no"/>count for. His position was still precisely the same <lb/>
as that which he and his hon. colleagues had assumed <lb/>
at the hustings in '65, with this difference, however, <lb/>
that whatever difficulties he had then seen in the <lb/>
way had now entirely disappeared. The confederate <lb/>
cause had been gaining ground over all the Island, <lb/>
and though the Confederate party were continuing <lb/>
faithful to their pledge, that the question should be <lb/>
submitted to the cous ituencies, public opinion from <lb/>
Cape John to Caºe Ray, was calling aloud for a <lb/>
change. The principle of Confederation was now <lb/>
under discussion: "Who denied the principle P <lb/>
To use the joint language of the hon, and gallant <lb/>
Mijor, and the hon. member, Mr. Talbot, " the <lb/>
highest and most gifted minds acknowledge the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple". There was not the beginning of a differ<lb break="no"/>ence with regard to the principle between hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers on this and on the other side. Hon. members <lb/>
ite were all confed and the only differ­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ence, between them was upon matters of detail. <lb/>
Surely then upon the question of details hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers could well give over their party differences. <lb/>
As to terms there were few hon. members who would <lb/>
be more difficult to please than himself, and <lb/>
when the debate upon the subject came on <lb/>
he should be prepared to conteuil that express <lb/></p> 

<p>unanimity as to the <lb break="no"/>as the hon member, Mr º says that it means <lb/>
employument for th; people. <lb/>
º . meantug § hin (Mr P.J. and was one <lb/>
which wou'd hardy be ſound in any dictionery. It <lb/>
that were really the meaning of it-it it, would <lb/>
procure that, the Opposition would hailConfederation <lb/>
with one voice. <lb/>
would be placed upon it <lb/>
abroad from this colony to seek employment because <lb/>
we had it within our own borders. <lb break="no"/>to transport 800 of our stalwart fishermen into the <lb/>
wilds of Canada. <lb/>
give them better employment than Canada could <lb/>
afford them. What I expatriate the hardy natives <lb/>
of this-colony and make them seek employment <lb/>
amongst strangers? Why it was a policy that no <lb/>
parental Government would entertain. -\-\-<lb break="maybe"/>mamber then proceeded to show that we had within <lb/>
ourselves resources which if fostered and developed <lb/>
by the Government were more than sufficient for our <lb/>
population. <lb/>
question of Confederation before the House now was <lb/>
a breach of laith on the part of the Governin-n , <lb/>
that there was no evidence before this House that <lb/></p> 

<p>against Confederation, and coutended that <lb/>
opinion of the people was the same now, and that no <lb/></p> 

<p>no one would attempt to deny that he was an out<lb break="no"/>spoken Confederate, but he should always be jºalous <lb/>
of this country's interests in connection with the <lb/>
question of terms. <lb/></p> 

<p>After some remarks from Mr. Hogsºrt, ... <lb/>
Mr. PARsons said that he had been waiting for <lb/></p> 

<p>meaning of the word. <lb/></p> 

<p>Weil, that certainly <lb/></p> 

<p>Bit he feared no such meaning <lb/>
We do not want to go <lb/></p> 

<p>We did not want <lb/></p> 

<p>We would keep then here and <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon <lb/></p> 

<p>He considered the bringing of this <lb/></p> 

<p>the public desired any change. He referred to the <lb/>
Petitions which had been presented former sessions <lb/>
the <lb/></p>--> 

<p rendition="simple:right">Monday, Feb. 15.</p>
    
    <p>
The House met pursuant to adjournment. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Upon motion of the <persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>, <lb/> 
the House resolved itself into a Committee of the <lb/>
whole on the Address of Thanks.—Mr. Knight in <lb/>
the Chair. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">hon. the SPEAKER</persName> said that he considered it <lb/>
to be his duty, occupying the position of Speaker of <lb/>
this House, to refer to certain remarks contained in <lb/>
        the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chronicle</hi> of this morning, in which he had been <lb/>
charged with uttering language derogatory to Mr. C <lb/>
F Bennett. He must contradict that statement, and <lb/>
call upon the House to endorse what he now said, <lb/>
that he neither directly nor inferentially referred to <lb/>
Mr. Bennett. He had done so he would have been <lb/>
guilty of a violation of the rules of this House, and <lb/>
he thought all would do him the justice to say that <lb/>
since he had the honor of presiding here he had al<lb break="no"/>ways endeavoured to sustain the dignity of the <lb/>
House and adhere to the rules governing our de<lb break="no"/>bates. Had the remarks in this paper merely refer<lb break="no"/>red to himself personally, he would have deemed <lb/>
them unworthy of notice, but when they referred to <lb/>
his position as the Speaker of this House, he con<lb break="no"/>sidered that in recognition of that duty which he <lb/>
owed to that office and to this House, he was bound <lb/>
to take notice of this matter and contradict it. He <lb/>
would again declare that he had neither directly nor <lb/>
inferentially referred to Mr. Bennett in the speech <lb/>
which he had made. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>The hon. Receiver General, Mr. Prowse, and the <lb/>  
Colonial Secretary also sustained the assertion of the <lb/>
hon. and learned Speaker, and bore testimony to the <lb/>
dignity with which he had always upheld his posi<lb break="no"/>tion. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        The <persName ref="pers:KENT1">RECIEVER GENERAL</persName> remarked that the offi<lb break="no"/>cial Reports were confirmatory of what the Speaker <lb/>
had declared. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr. TALBOT</persName> could not say whether the words had <lb/>
been used or not, but he denied that the official <lb/>
Reports were any authority upon the matter. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName> was glad to see that every one read the <lb/>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chronicle</hi>, it shewed that it was the true exponent of <lb/>
public opinion. He thought that it was carrying this <lb/>
matter too far when he heard that the Editor of the <lb/>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chronicle</hi> had been ejected from the Clerk's room by <lb/>
the order of the Speaker. The Opposition were <lb/>
attacked in the most outrageous manner every day, <lb/>
but they paid no attention to it. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The <persName ref="pers:SHEA2">hon. A. SHEA</persName> was sorry that the hon. and <lb/>
learned Speaker had taken the trouble to occupy <lb/>
a moment of time with a matter so paltry. Suppose <lb/>
he had said Mr. Bennett was the Head Centre of the <lb/>
Anti-Confederates? What then? Was that gentle<lb break="no"/>man ashamed of being so called? What then was <lb/>
there in it that any man should feel thin skinned <lb/>
about? But the hon, the Speaker had never men<lb break="no"/>tioned Mr. Bennett's name. How then could he <lb/>
have spoken disrespectfully of him?. He (Mr S) <lb/>
had referred to Mr. Bennett in this House and <lb/>
would do so again when he deemed it uecessary, but <lb/>
he had never spoken disrespectfully of him. He <lb/>
was sorry any importance had been attached to this <lb/>
matter. He would now refer to the paragraph be<lb break="no"/>fore the Chair, This section then affirmed that the <lb/>
time had arrived for considering this question of <lb/>
Confederation, so that it might be referred to the <lb/>
various constituencies. Now the hon. member Mr, <lb/>
Talbot the other evening in a speech of considerable <lb/>
length, denied this. He (Mr. S.) admitted that the <lb/>
hon. member had discussed the matter with a great <lb/>
deal of ability and in language that was certainly <lb/>
entitled to respect, and he made this admission <lb/>
freely and readily, altho' both in the premises and <lb/>
conclusions of the hon. member he entirely dis<lb break="no"/>agreed. The hon. member had asserted that the <lb/>
time had not arrived for dealing with this question, <lb/>
and that this House had no authority to deal with it, <lb/> 
He thought that the time had fully arrived for this <lb/>
question to be considered, and further, that was <lb/>
in accordance with the existing state of <lb/>
opinion. Why, what was the reproach that had been <lb/>
uttered against us time after time? That we did <lb/>
not bring down the terms, so that the people might <lb/>
be fully instructed upon them, and now, with a <lb/>
strange and marvellous inconsistency, they tell us <lb/>
that we have no right to go into the discussion and <lb/>
investigation of those very terms, for which they had <lb/>
so often asked. Now how would it be possible for us <lb/>
    to go into the discussion of terms, unless we assented <lb/>
    to the section before the chiair. There was not a <lb/>
    man in this House, who might not vote for this <lb/>
    Section, and when the terms are brought down with <lb/>
    perfect honesty and consistency dissent from any or <lb/>
        <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>. Hon members opposite had twisted this <lb/>
        <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>, and the Government had <lb/> 
    
    <cb/>
    
    never intended that it should be regarded in that <lb/>
    light. Were merely tell you and the country by this <lb/>
        section that we will enquire into the matter, and see <lb/>
        if terms favorable to the interests of this Colony <lb/>
        cannot be agreed to. Why the hon member Mr <lb/>
        Glen, says if we get terms satisfactory, he was ready <lb/>
        to go in for Confederation, and yet the hon member <lb/>
        would debar us by his proceeding from ascertaining <lb/>
    what were satisfactory terms or not. It could not be <lb/>
too well known, he thought, that no proceeding was <lb/>
contemplated by this House by which this question <lb/>
would be finally determined. We simply desired to <lb/>
show the country what the terms were—so that they <lb/>
might give them earnest consideration, and be in a <lb/>
position at the general election to say whether they <lb/>
    were acceptable or not. He could not, therefore, <lb/>
    agree to this paragraph being amended, and he <lb/>
    could not agree to the amendment, because it con<lb break="no"/>tained a statement that was untrue. The question of <lb/>
    Confederation had never been rejected by this Legis<lb break="no"/>lature or by the country, because it had never been <lb/>
submitted to either. This House would certainly be <lb/>
open to censure it it permitted such a statement to go <lb/>
unchallenged. Hon members opposite a few years <lb/>
ago, when there was a paragraph in the address <lb/>
relative to Confederation, said, if you pass it, you <lb/>
affirm the principle of Confederation. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment declared at the time that that was not a right <lb/>
interpretation to place upon it, as the section was one <lb/>
which pronounced no opinion, and went merely for <lb/>
delay. But so assured were they that it affirmed the <lb/>
principle of Confederation, that they proposed an <lb/>
amendment to it. (Here the hon member read the <lb/>
same.) Now if that amendment had been carried, <lb/>
the hon member would have been borne out in his <lb/>
statement that the question had been rejected. But <lb/>
the fact was, that that amendinent had been igno<lb break="no"/>miniously rejected by a majority of eighteen to six. <lb/>
How then could it be said that the Quebec scheme <lb/>
had ever been rejected by this House. Now he (Mr <lb/>
S) did not claim that thut majority aſfirined the <lb/>
principle of Contederation, he merely claimed that it <lb/>
rejected the amendment against the principle. His <lb/>
was indeed somewhat surprised that the hon member <lb/>
Mr Talbot should deal with so important a question <lb/>
in the manner he had. The clap trap about our <lb/>
lives and liberties was not worthy that gentleman's <lb/>
position or ability. Then he appeals to the natives <lb/>
        not to sell their country. That question of <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
    could never arise in this case. But assuming for <lb/>
    arguement sake that it did, he (hon Mr S) knew of <lb/>
    few countries that had been sold that had not been <lb/>
        the gainers. Looks at Louisiana when she was pur<lb break="no"/>chased by the United States from France—that was <lb/>
    a sale, and money paid for it, and see how prosperous <lb/>
    Louisiana had been since. Had she not been a <lb/>
    gainer by that sale? He merely referred to this <lb/>
in reference to the question which had been raised, <lb/>
and to shew that selling a country was not after all <lb/>
so terrible a thing, but was a proceeding by which <lb/>
many countries had been benefitted. The hon <lb/>
member then referred to Irish encumbered estates <lb/>
Act, and shewed the advantages it had conferred, <lb/>
regarding it in the light of a forced sale. The hon <lb/>
meuber Mr Talbot tells us that the Irish Union was <lb/>
caused by bribery, and that some three millions were <lb/>
spent for that purpose. Well, that was true. But <lb/>
who was it that received that money? Why the <lb/>
opposition, who then occupied that position in the <lb/>
Irish Parliament which hon gentlemen opposite do <lb/>
here. It was to purchase their woes that this money <lb/>
had been spent. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LITT3">MR. LITTLE</persName>.—Are you going to give us some. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SHEA2">Hon. Mr. SHEA</persName> –Don't let the hon. member's <lb/>
mouth water too soon, He would not have hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen opposite indulge in extravagant expectations <lb/>
of what might happen here. The Union of Ireland <lb/>
was an exception and was not one that should be <lb/>
quoted. That was a Union between people not, on <lb/>
an equality. It was a Union of a dominant race <lb/>
with a slavish and enthralled one. It was the Union <lb/>
of men who enjoyed civil and religious rights with <lb/>
men who had neither the one nor the other, was it <lb/>
then anything surprising that the dominant class <lb/>
should regard the others as slaves and treat them so? <lb/>
But were the same conflicting elements to be found <lb/>
here? Had we not all civil and regious liberty? <lb/>
Were we not all upon the same footing? Were we <lb/>
not equal in the eye of one Government and it uni<lb break="no"/>versal laws? Would the hon gentleman say that the <lb/>
Union of the States was a failure? Canadian Union <lb/>
he says was a failure. Where does the hon. member <lb/>
get his facts for making such a statement? <lb/>
The result to the country was great prosperity. <lb/>
He had not then a hand the statistics of popu<lb break="no"/>lation, produce, &amp;c., but he knew that they <lb/>
showed sufficient to justify the assertion that the <lb/>
Union of the two Provinces had proved a succes. <lb/>
Was the fact that the people of England last <lb/>
year demanded a new Reform Bill any proof <lb/>
that the bill of 1832 was a failure? No it only <lb/>
showed that the time for further changes had <lb/>
some, and just so with the question of Union. <lb/>
The time for change came, and when the ques<lb break="no"/>tion which had agitated the Lower Province, <lb/>
was ripe for settlement, Canada could scarcely <lb/>
believe that Nova Scotia, the cradle of Union, <lb/>
would turn its back on its own offspring. It was <lb/>
stated that the Delegates had condemned the <lb/>
Quebec Resolutions. Such was not the case, <lb/>
neither the hon. and learned Attorney General <lb/>
nor he (hon. Mr. S.) had ever said so. They <lb/>
never entertained such opinions as would justify <lb/>
them in saying so. Having regard to the time <lb/>
of its origin, he denied that it was a plan which <lb/>
deserved condemnation. It was most favorably <lb/>
received, and commended the admiration of the <lb/>
ablest and most intelligent men in England. <lb/>
It had since then been slightly modified, but <lb/>
how? Was it not by making concessions all <lb/>
round, on the one side as well as the other? <lb/>
The result of monetary consessions would be <lb/>
that while we might get more money for our <lb/>
own immediate purposes, we would not be <lb/>
benefited to the full extent supposed, because <lb/>
to the extent of the increase received we lessen <lb/>
the money which would remain in the hands of <lb/>
the General Government for general purposes. <lb/>
The only changes made as yet were monetary <lb/>
ones. The framework and character of the <lb/>
constitution, the powers of the general and local <lb/>
governments, are still the same as adopted in <lb/>
Quebec, so that in these principal points those <lb/>
resulutions remain intact. In one other point <lb/>
only was any change made, and that was by the <lb/>
British Government in the number of Senators, <lb/>
so as to provide for the happening at any time <lb/>
of a deadlock in the Government. <lb/>
    As to the objections <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>. The only <lb/>
    ones raised by the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>, were that the people <lb/>
    would be <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> more than was fair, and that <lb/>
they would not recieve enough. To no other <lb/>
    <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> plan was any objection raised, and <lb/>
    <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> it would be <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> to raise objections <lb/>


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-10, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>were incapable of forming an of <lb/></p> 

<p>examine into the matter, for them. <lb/></p> 

<p>should leave the country, but he <lb/></p> 

<p>they blind and inchpable of form <lb/>
Not one ct them but spoke in <lb/>
Constitution as framed at Quebe <lb/>
that a significant fact, which migh <lb/>
the minds of some who ought to <lb/></p> 

<p>lated to advance the interests a <lb/>
prosperity of these Colouies, sh <lb/>
and great weight with men whº <lb/>
and knowledge of such matters i <lb/>
so large. He did not mean to <lb/>
gen lemen should not exercise the <lb/>
on the subject. The duty and the <lb/>
ity with them, and they were bou <lb/></p> 

<p>all, what was Confederatiou? It <lb/>
that four or five provinces, havin <lb/>
tutions and laws, aud owing: <lb/>
common sovereign, should unite f <lb/>
mon benefit. Those who advocate <lb/>
sition believed that Union would <lb/>
beneficial results than isolation. <lb/>
by the exam, le of the Uuited <lb/>
believed that such a Union w <lb/>
genural prosperity and give stabil <lb/>
that in co-operation each would <lb/>
which individually they eould no <lb/>
his (hon. Mr. S's.) mind, Confede <lb/>
inereased mºans of anployin ºut. <lb/>
that the want of which was most <lb/>
now 7 Rumployment. It had bee <lb/></p> 

<p>tlerive such direct advantages as <lb/>
Prºvinces, yet those which we in <lb/>
will have. Here was a practical <lb/>
he said. He was authorised to eu, <lb/>
to work at the putlie works in Can <lb/>
not the taking of tuese 800 men of <lb/>
where they new wand ºr up an I d <lb/>
to work but auable to find it, adva. <lb/>
of labor? He did not speak for ad <lb/>
pose, and would not be so toolhard <lb/>
an assertion which could be contra <lb/>
išt of My next. IIa agreed that <lb/>
toº.uue that the pºpulation shouli º <lb/>
go away, but it wºuld be a greated <lb/>
to have theta reimain here in the sº <lb/>
as they were in last year. No <lb/>
give him (huu Mr. S.) greater pi <lb/>
*ual the state of the comu.ry sueuld <lb/>
to enable these inea to stay at uulu <lb/>
lºad a greater interest in seeing the <lb/>
iſloyed than lie had, tuat they suu. <lb/>
purchasers and not as begg us. Wuj <lb/>
the yield to any in uls desire to sº <lb/>
prosperous Aud happy: Xot one <lb/>
who would be eugºg.u by utia woul <lb/>
uext winter, for uail their wages w. <lb/>
here for theia. Wuile tui.gs were <lb/>
sed in the country, he (uoi Air. S.) <lb/>
this as a godseud. He looked <lb/>
beginning of a system which wou <lb/>
country from tuture deterioration <lb/>
of laour. The tact shows that is la <lb/>
here, it will be taken up tor the ot. <lb/>
If we have Coufederation, we will <lb/>
Steamers with Quebee and Me. <lb/>
would enable the people tº go a <lb/>
kilnº. In this country the labor q <lb/>
derlios all others, aud snything wi <lb/>
advance the interests of the lab <lb/>
also tended to the advance of the <lb/>
the country at large. All that was <lb/>
a well employed people, and then <lb/>
would be contented aud happy. <lb/></p> 

<p>look on it as at all desirable that <lb/></p> 

<p>desirable that when they were so be <lb/>
should have some backdoors. Iſe <lb/></p> 

<p>ed to lear it said that our men <lb/>
for this work, Any man who will <lb/>
going, will acknowiadge that no flu. <lb/>
men ever left any port. Lie had <lb/>
any counplaint of the insu on the Te <lb/>
aud did not think the wo <lb/>
Rilway was any harder. Nor did <lb/>
had been inputsu to them by the <lb/>
themselves their friends, that were <lb/>
** to ſurget those whom they had <lb/>
He thought differeutly of them, a <lb/>
them to be possessed of <lb/>
which attached then tu those wº <lb/>
aud legitimate claims on them. 0 <lb/>
any of them chose to relaxis away,it <lb/>
it would be better for them, they w <lb/>
in doing so. They would have the <lb/>
coming home it they chose to c. <lb/>
could be no compulsion, Those wh <lb/>
go would go as volunteers. He c <lb/>
stand that such matters as these w <lb/>
tasteful to those who were inter ste <lb/>
down the value of labor. Last yes <lb/>
wers in such a wretched condition <lb/>
*** glad to ship on any terms. <lb/></p> 

<p>desired to perpetuats that stat <lb/></p> 

<p>would, of course, be dissati, fled wi <lb/></p> 

<p>tempt to disturb it. He thougut th <lb/>
ºf the question which they were no <lb/>
*g, * might with propriety sp. <lb/></p> 

<p>Charles Fox Bennet, who requi. <lb/></p> 

<p>much desire to accomplish wifi be eflected. As to - - - - <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>th - …" the fisheries. Exception had been taken to the bond so often asked. Now how would it be possible for us a deadlock in the Goveralasat. <lb/></p> 

<p>§§.#º"..."; º ... [fide character of the telegram received by his hon. to go into the discussion of terms, unle; we area:ed As ſo tº objectious arged. Tug ou!y number of men to work his mines, a <lb/>
ulluion, there There was not a * "ourse, try and get them at as low <lb/></p> 

<p>* no such present probability, and if <lb/></p> 

<p>Yere tº be its it.: fate, #. who i. <lb/>
Annexation tendencies as ºn mºre likely to <lb/>
turther their designs by promoting that, the first <lb/></p> 

<p>step to further American unity, Tsi, consumns. <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/></p> 

<p>**league offering employment to 800 or 1,000 people. <lb/>
He might sately say that all that scepticism was to be <lb/>
found within the doors of this House. Those persons <lb/>
who were most to be affected by it had full faith in <lb/></p> 

<p>* *:­ <lb/></p> 

<p>is reality and tº regarded it as a prac i <lb/>
- - - - - - . -<lb break="maybe"/>-: 2. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>to the section before the chair. <lb/>
man, in this House, who might not vote for this <lb/>
Seetion, and when the terms are breught down with <lb/>
Perſect bonesty and consisteney dissent from any or <lb/></p> 

<p>s Jºosie had twisted this <lb/></p> 

<p>oues raised by ºue Aatis, were that the people <lb/>
would be .azed more thau was fair, und tist <lb/></p> 

<p>:a: 327:2.4.1% had: <lb/></p> 

<p>tury would not receive enough. To do oths: <lb/>
2. - i... plan was any objection raised, aud <lb/>
certailly if no.1! be uillical, to raise o jictious <lb/></p> 

<p>P*itle. He was, of course, right, <lb/>
his interests and the interests of <lb/></p> 

<p>wers directly opposed to each other, <lb/></p>-->




<pb n="3" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_3.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">3</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2019-01-10, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>er intended that it should be regarded in that <lb/>
t. We merely tell you and the country by this <lb/>
tion that we will enquire into the matter, and see <lb/>
terms favorable to the interests of this Colony <lb/>
not be agreed to. Why, the hon member ºf: <lb/>
ºn, say: if we get terms satisfactory, be was read <lb/>
to in for Confederation, and yet the hon member <lb/>
ld debar us by his proceeding from *taining <lb/>
at were satisfactory terms or not. It could not be <lb/>
well known, he thought, that no proºeding was <lb/>
templated by this House by which this question <lb/>
ld be finally determined. We simply desired to <lb/>
* the country what the terãº were-so that they <lb/>
by give them earnest consideration, and be in 4 <lb/>
tion at the general election to say whether they <lb/>
e acceptable or no. He could not, thereford, § <lb/>
ee to this paragraph being amended, and bº <lb/>
id not agree to the amend ment, because it cou<lb break="no"/>ed a statement that was untrue. The question of <lb/>
tederation had never been rejected by this Legis. <lb/>
re or by the country, because it had never been <lb/>
unitted to either. This House would certainly be <lb/>
to censure it it permitted such a statement to go <lb/>
uallenged. Hon members opposite a few years <lb/>
when there was a paragraph in the address <lb/>
tive to Contederation, said, if you pass it, you <lb/>
in the principle of Confederation. The Gaveral <lb/>
t declared at the time that that was not a right <lb/>
rpretation to place upon it, as the section was one <lb/>
ch pronounced no opinion, and went inerely for <lb/>
y. But so assured were they that it affirmed the <lb/>
ciple of Confederation, that they proposed an <lb/>
udulent to it. . (Here the hon member read the <lb/>
'.) Now if that amendment had been carried, <lb/>
boa member would have been borne out in his <lb/>
ement that the question had been rejected. But <lb/>
fact was, that that amendipent had been igno<lb break="no"/>ously rejected by a majority of eighteen to six, <lb/>
then could it be said that the Quebec scheme <lb/>
ever been rejected by this House. Now he ( yir <lb/>
did not claim that that majority aſfirined the <lb/>
ciple of Conlederation, he merely claimed that it <lb/>
a'ed the amendment against the principle. He <lb/>
indeed somewhat surprised that the hon ineinder <lb/>
Talbot should de l with so important a question <lb/>
be nanner he had. The clap trap about our <lb/>
and liberties was not worthy that gentleman', <lb/>
tion or ability. Then he appeals to the natives <lb/>
to sell their country. Túat question of sal, <lb/>
d never, arise in this case. But assuming lor <lb/>
inent sake that it did, he (hon Mr S) know of <lb/>
countries that had been sold that had not been <lb/>
gainers. Look at Louisiana when she was pur<lb break="no"/>ed by the U.ited States from France—that was <lb/>
e. and uoney paid to it, and see bow prosperous <lb/>
siana had been since. Had she not been a <lb/>
ºr by that sale 2 He mergiy referred to this <lb/>
elereuce to the question which had been raise.I. <lb/>
to shºw that selling a country was not after ali <lb/>
ºrrible a thing, but was a proceeding by whicu <lb/>
y countries had been benefitted. The hon <lb/>
ber then referred to Irish encumbered estates <lb/>
and shºwed the advantages it had conferred, <lb/>
rding it in the light of a forced sale. The hom <lb/>
bºr Mr Talbot tells us that the Irish Union was <lb/>
*d by bribery, and that sons three millions were <lb/>
t ior that purpose. Weii, that was true. But <lb/>
was it that received that money? Why the <lb/>
unition, who then occupied that position in the <lb/>
Parliament which hon gentlemen opposite'du <lb/>
it was to purchase their vo.e. that this money <lb/>
been spent. <lb break="no"/>a ſºrrº-Are you gºing tº give assimº. <lb/>
on. Mr. ShkA-1}on't let the hon. member', <lb/>
b water too sºon, lie would not have hon. gen, <lb/>
in oppositº indulge in extravagant expectations <lb/>
at might happen here. 'ſue Um on of Irelani <lb/>
an exception and w s got one that should be <lb/>
'd, That was a Union between people not, on <lb/>
quality. It was a Union of a dominant race <lb/>
a slavish and enthralled one. It was the Union <lb/>
en who enjoyed civil an i religious rights with <lb/>
who had nulthur the one nor the other, was it <lb/>
anything surprising that the dopinant cl, s <lb/>
ld regard the otliurs as slaves and treat then a r <lb/>
were the same conflicting eleueurs to be foun.i <lb/>
* Had we not all civil and re igious liberty? <lb/>
e we not all upon the same loo, ing 7 Were we <lb/>
qual in the eye of one Government and it un<lb break="no"/>ſlºw: * Would the honºgantleman say that the <lb/>
n of the States was a fal:ure? Canadian Union <lb/>
ye was a ſailure Where does the hon. member <lb/>
his facts for making such a statement 7 <lb/>
result to the country was great prosperiy. <lb/>
ad not then at hand the sta istics of popu. <lb/>
us, produce, &amp;c., but be knew that they <lb/>
ed sufficient to justify the assertiou that the <lb/>
n of the two Provinces had proved a success. <lb/>
tle fact, taut the people of England last <lb/>
damanded a new Itºform Bill any proof <lb/>
the bill of 1832 was a failure? No it only <lb/>
ed that the time for further changes had <lb/>
º, and just so with the question of Union. <lb/>
time for change cam', and when the ques. <lb/>
which had agitated the Lower Provinces, <lb/>
ripe for settlement, Canada could searcely <lb/>
vs that Nova Scotia, the cradle of Union, <lb/>
tura its back on its own offspring. It was <lb/>
d that the Delegates had condemned the <lb/>
buc Resolu ions. Such was not tua case, <lb/>
ºr the hou, and learned Attorney-General <lb/>
* (hon. Mr. S.) had ever said so. They <lb/>
entertained such opinions as would justity <lb/>
in saying so. Having regard to the time <lb/>
ºrigiu, he denied that it was a plan which <lb/>
v'd condemuation. It was most favorably <lb/>
vud, and coun inded the admiration of the <lb/>
", aud most intelligent men in. England. <lb/>
d since then been slightly nod fied, but <lb/>
Was it not by making concessions all <lb/>
l, on the out side as well as the other? <lb/>
result of monetary consessions would by <lb/>
whºle we might get more money for our <lb/>
insumediate purposes, w; would not be <lb/>
ited to tiss ful extent supposed, because <lb/>
* extent of thu increase received we lessen <lb/>
oney which would remain in the hauds of <lb/>
reberal Government for general purposes. <lb/>
uly cuangas made as yet were nonetary # <lb/>
The frauework acd character of the <lb/>
tution, the powers of the general and local <lb/>
nineuts, are suit the as us as adopted in <lb/>
c. *o that in these principal points those <lb/>
tious remain intact. In one other puia <lb/>
as any change made, and that was by the <lb/>
u Government in the number of Senators, <lb/>
to provide fur the lappeulug at any time <lb/>
deadlock in the Government. <lb/>
o the objectious urged. Tue ouly <lb/>
raised by tué Antis, were that the people <lb/>
be ºxed more thau was fair, and that <lb/>
would not receive enough. To uo other <lb/>
... plan was any objection raised, aud <lb/>
ve ºil.lical to raise o jittivus <lb/></p> -->

to a plan which was so perfect in all its parts. <lb/>
He (hon. Mr. S.) had taken a very humble <lb/>
part in the great work; but he was proud to <lb/>
have it to say that it fell to his lot to take any <lb/>
part, however humble, in so important a work. <lb/>
That plan had met with the approval of the <lb/>
leading men of England of all politics, and were <lb/>
they blind and incapable of forming an opinion? <lb/>
Not one of them but spoke in praise of the <lb/>
Constitution as framed at Quebec, and was not <lb/>
that a significant fact, which might well influence <lb/>
the minds of some who ought to feel that they <lb/>
were incapable of forming an opinion on such <lb/>
a subject? . A test like that, the opinions of men <lb/>
well versed in the science of Government, <lb/>
whose integrity and impartiality cannot be <lb/>
doubted, who look calmly on from a distance, <lb/>
and say that this system of Government calcu<lb break="no"/>lated to advance the interests and secure the <lb/>
prosperity of these Colonies, should have due <lb/>
and great weight with men whose experience <lb/>
and knowledge of such matters is by no means <lb/>
so large. He did not mean to say the hon. <lb/>
gentlemen should not exercise their own reason <lb/>
on the subject. The duty and the responsibility <lb/>
lay with them, and they were bound to see and <lb/>
examine into the matter, for themselves. After <lb/>
all, what was Confederation? It simply meant <lb/>
that four or five provinces, having similar insti<lb break="no"/>tutions and laws, aud owing allegiance to a <lb/>
common sovereign, should unite for their com<lb break="no"/>mon benefit. Those who advocated this propo<lb break="no"/>sition believed that Union would lead to more <lb/>
beneficial results than isolation. Enlightened <lb/>
by the example of the United States, they <lb/>
believed that such a Union would promote <lb/>
general prosperity and give stability to all, and <lb/>
that in Co-operation each would find benefits <lb/>
which individually they could not obtain. To <lb/>
his (hon. Mr. S's.) mind, Confederation meant <lb/>
increased means of employment. What was <lb/>
that the want of which was most severely felt <lb/>
now? Employment. It had been asked what <lb/>
good would this country derive from <lb/>
the expenditure in Canada on Railways. <lb/>
He (hon. Mr. S.) replied that it would <lb/>
advauce the value of labor in this coun<lb break="no"/>try, and that would be most beneficial to <lb/>
the laboring classes; and though we may not <lb/>
derive such direct advantages as will the other <lb/>
Provinces, yet those which we most require we <lb/>
will have. Hare was a practical proof of what <lb/>
he said. He was authorised to engage 800 men <lb/>
to work at the public works in Canada. Would <lb/>
not the taking of these 800 men off our streets, <lb/>
where they now wanderr up and down, willing <lb/>
to work but unable to find it, advance the value <lb/>
of labor? He did not speak for any party pur<lb break="no"/>pose, and would not be so foolhardy as to make <lb/>
an assertion which could be contradicted by the <lb/>
1st of May next. He agreed that it was a mis<lb break="no"/>furtune that the population should be required to <lb/>
go away, but it would be a greater misfortune <lb/>
to have them remain here in the same position <lb/>
as they were in last year. Nothing would <lb/>
give him (hon Mr. S. ) greater pleasure than <lb/>
that the state of the country should be sush as <lb/>
to enable these men to stay at home. No man <lb/>
had a greater interest in seeing the people em<lb break="no"/>ployed than he had, that they should come as <lb/>
purchasers and not as beggers. Why then should <lb/>
he yield to any in hid desire to see the people <lb/>
prosperous aud happy? Not one of the 800 <lb/>
who would be engaged by him would be paupers <lb/>
next winter, for all their wages would be kept <lb/>
    here for them. While <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> were so depres<lb break="no"/>sed in the country, he (hon Mr. S.) considered <lb/>
this as a godsend. He looked on it as the <lb/>
beginning of a system which would save this <lb/>
country from future deterioration in the value <lb/>
of laour. The fact shows that if labor be law <lb/>
here, it will be taken up for the other colonies. <lb/>
If we have Confederation, we will have regular <lb/>
Steamers with Quebec and Montreal, which <lb/>
would enable the people to go away in bad <lb/>
time. In this country the labor question un<lb break="no"/>derlies all others, and anything which tended to <lb/>
advance, the interests of the laboring classes <lb/>
also tended to the advance of the interests of <lb/>
the country at large. All that was needed was <lb/>
a well employed people, and then the country <lb/>
would be contented and happy. He did not <lb/>
look on it as at all desirable that the people <lb/>
should leave the country, but he did think it <lb/>
desirable that when they were so badly off they <lb/>
should have some backdoors. Iſe was surprsis<lb break="no"/>ed to hear it said that our men were not fit <lb/>
for this work. Any man who will see the men <lb/>
going, will acknowledge that no finer body of <lb/>
men ever left any port. He had never heard <lb/>
any complaint of the man on the Telegraph line, <lb/>
and did not think the work on the <lb/>
Rilway was any harder. Nor did he fear, as <lb/>
had been imputed to them by those who call <lb/>
themselves their friends, that were so degraded <lb/>
as to forget those whom they had left behind. <lb/>
He thought differently of them, and believed <lb/>
them to be possessed of social qualities <lb/>
which attached then to those who had good <lb/>
and legitimate claims on them. Of course, if <lb/>
any of them chose to remain away, if they thought <lb/>
it would be better for them, they would be right <lb/>
in doing so. They would have the means of <lb/>
coming home if they chose to come. <choice><sic>Theore</sic><corr>There</corr></choice> <lb/>
could be no compulsion. Those who wished to <lb/>
go would go as volunteers. He could under<lb break="no"/>stand that such matters as these would be dis<lb break="no"/>tasteful to those who were interested in keeping <lb/>
down the value of labor. Last year the men <lb/>
were in such a wretched condition that they <lb/>
were glad to ship on any terms. Those wuo <lb/>
desired to perpetuate that state of things <lb/>
would, of course, be dissatisfied with ant at<lb break="no"/>tempt to disturb it. He thought that in view <lb/>
of the question which they were now consider<lb break="no"/>ing, he might with propriety speak of Mr. <lb/> 
Charles Fox Bennet, who required a large <lb/> 
number of men to work his mines, and would, of <lb/>
course, try and get them at as low a rate as <lb/>
possible. He was, of course, right, but in that <lb/>
his interests and the interests of the people <lb/>
were directly opposed to each other. He (hon. <lb/>

<cb/>

Mr. S.) was glad Mr. Bennett had these mines <lb/>
to work, and wished there were more like <lb/>
mines in the country. To say that Mr. Bennet <lb/>
entered into these speculations for the benefit <lb/>
of the people was arrant nonsense. He enter<lb break="no"/>ed into it as a commercial matter, solely for <lb/>
his own benefit. This was no matter of reproach <lb/> 
to him, for it was the spirit of all commercial <lb/>
speculations. If the demand of labor be stimulat<lb break="no"/>ed, all those who give employment will feel it, <lb/>
for they will have to pay increased wages. He <lb/>
mentioned these matters incidentally. It, however, <lb/>
came in, as an argument, stronger than any <lb/>
force of rhetoric. A stimulus of the kind was <lb/>
not needed to procure a majority favourable to <lb/>
Confederation. The minds of the people had <lb/>
come to the conclusion that the time had come <lb/>
when the question should be taken up. The <lb/>
hon. member, Mr. Talbot, had spoken of his <lb/>
preference of a commercial union before a <lb/>
political union. The present measure com<lb break="no"/>prehended both. He would see, on relfection, <lb/>
that even if practicable, a commercial union <lb/>
would be of very little advantage. How was <lb/>
    it to be had? There must be consenting par<lb break="no"/>ties on both sides, and would Canada be will<lb break="no"/>ing to consent to such a <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> proposition as <lb/>
we could make? How could we enter into a <lb/>
commercial treaty for any purpose, the effect <lb/>
of which would to deprive us of the power to <lb/>
legislate with regard to the matter it referrd to? <lb/>
The former treaty with the United States was not <lb/>
made with us, but through the agency of the other <lb/>
Provinces. What we required here was employment, <lb/>
and the opening up of the resources of the country, <lb/>
and a commercial union would not do that for is. <lb/>
We hoped to have our mining interests brought into <lb/>
life and activity, and no commercial union would do <lb/>
that. He hoped the day was not far distant when <lb/>
the Bay of Islands, Porteau Port, and the other <lb/>
parts of the Western Shore will be filled with flou<lb break="no"/>rishing settlements. Commercial union would not <lb/>
do that, but political union would, for it would give <lb/>
us that which is now so much needed, steam commu<lb break="no"/>nication with these extern Districts. Last year, <lb/>
after the fisheries had closed, value to the extent of <lb/>
£100,000 was shipped form Bay of Islands, and of <lb/>
that £5,000 did not belong to us, because we had no <lb/>
steam communication, and that we cannot have <lb/>
except we form part of the Dominion. When the <lb/>
United States resolved to from a union, were they <lb/>
content with a mere commercial union? Did they <lb/>
not form a political union, believing it to be the best <lb/>
way of advancing their interests at home and abroad? <lb/>
And have not the results justified that belief, while <lb/>
a commercial unoin alone would have left them <lb/>
thirteen separate  and  independent States. <lb/>
Could any of the United States separately treat <lb/>
with Foreign countries? And was it not by <lb/>
their combined and concentrated authority that <lb/>
they were enabled to have weight with diplo<lb break="no"/>matists abroad? Suppose we could effect a <lb/>
Commercial Treaty with Canada. To his (hon. <lb/>
Mr. S's.) mind, it would be a bald, naked, in<lb break="no"/>operative document, not worth the parchment <lb/>
upon which it would be written. If, on the <lb/>
other hand, we combined with Canada, we would <lb/>
instantly possess these commercial advantages; <lb/>
bread, flour, pork, butter, and all the Canadian <lb/>
manufactures would be aduitted duty free. <lb/>
Besides this, with a creditable liberality, they <lb/>
had agreed to allow breadstuffs from the United <lb/>
States to come in free. These advantages <lb/>
comprehend what no more commercial treaty <lb/>
could obtain for us. Look again at the effect <lb/>
of Confederation upon our foreign relations. <lb/>
Here was Spain, where a revolution was going <lb/>
on, which must necessarily have the effect of <lb/>
liberalizing her institutions, and lead her rules <lb/>
to the cousideration and acceptance of treaties <lb/>
with foreign powers. Look at Cuba and Brazil, <lb/>
which are, after Spain, our most important <lb/>
markets. The Dominion Government have <lb/>
treaty making powers, and can it be doubted <lb/>
that seeing the desire of Spain to extend her <lb/>
trade, they will take steps to place their com<lb break="no"/>mercial arraugements with Spain upon a proper <lb/>
footing? Already they are contemplating a <lb/>
commercial treaty with Brazil. We cannot <lb/>
possibly obtain a participation in these advan<lb break="no"/>tages without the co operation of the Dominion <lb/>
Government. At present we know that Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will not look with any great favour upon <lb/>
us, should we refuse to join the Confederation; <lb/>
and it is only by an authority greater than <lb/>
ourselves that we can secure these treaty priv<lb break="no"/>leges. He (hon. Mr. S.) urged these argu<lb break="no"/>ments on purely abstract grounds. He would <lb/>
not take notice of the assertions of hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers opposite as to the interference with our <lb/>
lives and liberties. This was simply a bread <lb/>
and butter question. The hon. member, Mr. <lb/>
Hogsett, had asked where would we be if Con<lb break="no"/>federation were accomplished, with 8 members <lb/>
out of 194, as if the other 186 members must <lb/>
necessarily be antagonistic to our interests. <lb/>
Now looking at the United States, which pre<lb break="no"/>sent an analogous case, did we find that less <lb/>
consideration was accorded to the smallest State <lb/>
of the Union than to the wealthy and extensive <lb/>
State of New York? These 8 men would be <lb/>
equal to 27 in the British House of Commons, <lb/>
and when we considered that a compact body of <lb/>
27 men would, in many cases, be sufficient to <lb/>
overturn a Government, we must come to the <lb/>
conclusion that our numbers are not so insigni<lb break="no"/>ficant. If it could be shown to him that the <lb/>
interests of Upper and Lower Canada were <lb/>
adverse to our, he would say, by all means, <lb/>
let us keep clear of this Confederation. But <lb/>
    what was the fact? We produce <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> or <lb/>
nothing but fish and oil. We want food and <lb/>
clothes. Canada can give us nearly all that we <lb/>
require in that respact. If than we were pros<lb break="no"/>perous, we should be good costomers. If not, <lb/>
they could gain notning by oppressing us. <lb/>
Would it, then, be for their interest to damage <lb/>
us, who would be good customers, and who <lb/>
would probably spend our surplus means in <lb/>
the purchase of their productions? In fact it <lb/>
must be palpable that it would be for their in<lb break="no"/>terest to promote our welfare, and that from <lb/>
mere selfish considerations, by which all men <lb/>
and all countries must be more or less actuated. <lb/>
It had been asserted that at the present moment <lb/>
we could import nothing from Canada. This <lb/>

<cb/>
    
was not the fact. We could now import from <lb/>
    Canada <hi rendition="simple:italic">via</hi> Boston, as cheaply as in the month <lb/>

of November. Our importations would <lb/>
be made by means of screw steamers, and <lb/>
thro' the Banking facilities which would be <lb/>
afforded, extended means of importation would <lb/>
be given, so that even, at an extra cost, it <lb/>
would suit our importers better to deal with <lb/>
Canada. No man could now import from the <lb/>
United States without money on the spot or credit <lb/>
on London. The Banking system which would be <lb/>
established would enable men who in this market <lb/>
would get credit for £1000, and who could not <lb/>
now import from the United States, through not <lb/>
having credits in London,to import from Canada <lb/>
upon the same terms as it they were purchasing <lb/>
in this market. He (Mr. S.) had always said <lb/>
that we could not allow any of our markets to <lb/>
be shut up. We must be at liberty to buy in <lb/>
the Canadian or American market as it suited out <lb/>
purpose. When hon. members say that you <lb/>
can purchase more cheaply in the American <lb/>
than in the Canadian market, they are not correct. <lb/>
At times you can purchase more cheaply in the <lb/>
one market, at times in the other. When you <lb/>
consider that a large quantity of wheat grown in <lb/>
Canada is exported to the United States, was <lb/>
it likely that you could purchase more cheaply <lb/>
there than at the fountain head? It had been <lb/>
stated that this question was brought forward <lb/>
because the Government were in difficulties. <lb/>
Hon. members knew well that he had from <lb/>  
the other side of the House spoken as strongly <lb/> 
in favour of Union as he had ever spoken. He <lb/>
had no changes of sentiment to atone. The <lb/>
late leader, Sir Hugh W. Hoyles, and the pre<lb break="no"/>sent hon Attorney General were quite <lb/>
as pronounced in their opinions. They <lb/>
held to their opinions on this <lb/>
great question, confident that it would <lb/>
ultimately find its way to public acceptance. It <lb/>
was idle to assert that the substitution of one <lb/>
Government for another could effect any radical <lb/>
change. The Government could, it they thought <lb/>
proper, sit down and fold their arms, and no <lb/>
rational man would admit the probability of <lb/> 
their being disturbed. But they had an inter<lb break="no"/>est in the welfare of the country, and they felt <lb/>
it a duty to announce their opinions, that in <lb/>
Confederation alone did the hope of redemption <lb/>
and regeneration of the country lie. If hon. <lb/>
members opposite knew that they were correct <lb/>
in their assertions as to the state of public <lb/>
opinion, why did they not urge on the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to its own destruction? Hon. members <lb/>
on this side were prepared to give their consti<lb break="no"/>uencies an opportunity of putting other men in <lb/>
thier places. Could hon. members opposite, by <lb/>
any artificial means, supply the vacuum created <lb/>
by the withdrawal of capital from the country? <lb/>
The only remedy for our evils was capital, and <lb/>
consequent employment of the people, and he <lb/>
(hon. Mr. S.) had yet to learn that the people <lb/>
    were so <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> as willingly to remain in their <lb/>
present degraded state, and that they would not <lb/>
enterprise any change rather than that the pre<lb break="no"/>sent state of things should continue. <lb/></p> 

    <p rendition="simple:centre">(To be Continued.)</p>
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2019-01-10, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->
    
<!--<p>his own benefit. This was no matter of reproach be giveſ, so of importation woul <lb/></p> 



<p>that. He hoped the day was not far distant whº as <lb/>
the Bay of Islands, Port-au-Port, and the other had <lb/></p> 

<p>the purchase of their producious * In fact it! was imp <lb/>
Lincoln. <lb/></p> 

<p>* not the fact. We could now import from <lb/>
Canada via Boston, as cheaply as in the month <lb/>
importations wouli <lb/>
screw steamers, and <lb/></p> 


<p>No m in could now import from the <lb/></p> 

<p>He (Mr. S.) had always said <lb/></p> 

<p>When you <lb/></p> 


<p>Tuo <lb/></p> 



<p>( to be Continued.) <lb/></p> 

<p>== <lb/></p> 

<p>Úſt ſtufimlmer. <lb/>
Sr. joiſts. <lb/>
FRIDAY, FEBRUARY 19, 1869. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Couſederation clause of the Assembly's Ad<lb break="no"/>dress in reply to the Governor's speech, having been <lb/>
treaty making powers, and can it be doubled carried on Tuesday evening by the large number of <lb/>
eighteen against eight votes, it now remains for the <lb/>
trade, they will take steps to place their com— | H. to enter upon the consideration of the terms <lb/>
on which they think the colony shoald join the <lb/>
Union, leaving the constituencies to decide the <lb/>
question. These terms will be submitted by the <lb/>
Government on Monday, and we have no doubt, <lb/>
they will be such as will command general accoptance. <lb/></p> 

<p>We are glad to be informed that the petition got <lb/></p> 

<p>up against the return of Mr. Grieve, as member for <lb/>
Greenock, has been pronounced by the Court <lb/>
"frivolous and vexatious." The whole cost of this <lb/>
He would proceeding is to be borne by the opposing candidate, <lb/></p> 

<p>Ir, Christie, <lb/></p> 

<p>We learn with deepest and most sincere regret of <lb/>
he death of the Honourable James Cornack, <lb/></p> 

<p>merchant, which took place at Bay Roberts on <lb/>
Thursday evening, after a protracted illness. Gar <lb/>
feeling on the occasion will be shared far and near <lb/>
in this community, for no man stood higher in the <lb/>
estimation of all who knew him for thorough goodness <lb/>
consideration was accorded to the smallest State of heart and an all-pervading integrity of character. <lb/>
He was for many years an honoured member of the <lb/>
Legislative Council; and when the announcement <lb/>
of his demise was made in that Chamber and in the <lb/>
Assembly to-day, in each branch ware uttered just <lb/>
and cordial tributes of the regard and esteem in <lb/>
which he was universally held, both Houses suspend<lb break="no"/>ing their sittings in sorrowfal respect to his meanory. <lb/>
May be rest in the peace of the just, and may the <lb/>
Great Cousolar pour healing balm into the wounds of <lb/>
that bereſt home circle where he will be so long and <lb/>
so achingly missed an i in ourned. <lb/></p> 

<p>== <lb/></p> 

<p>BY TFLEGRAPH. <lb/>
TO THE COMMERCIAL Rooyi, <lb/>
New Yoex Feb. 12. <lb/>
President Jºhnsºn has pardoned Dr. Mºiſ, who <lb/>
i iu the iastiau of Presid <lb/>
- New York, Feb. 14. <lb/>
A despatch from 0:tawa says it was thought that <lb/></p> 

<p>an organ-retion ba'i peet, orimei to re-lue Whelaºs <lb/>
:. from the authorities. Several seizures made <lb/>
to-day. <lb/></p> 

<p>Sº TENDERS will be received at <lb/>
this 9thce, until Noon, on Monday <lb/>
the 22nd Instant, from persons willing to <lb/>
ºnter into . Contracts for the following <lb/>
Army Services, for one year from the 1st <lb/>
April 1869. <lb/>
Baking Bread from Government <lb/>
Flour; <lb break="no"/>Cartage &amp; IIospital Supplies. <lb/>
The Tenders to be marked on the out<lb break="no"/>side "Tenders for Baking Bread, &amp;c." ac<lb break="no"/>cording to the service tendered for, and <lb/>
must be addressed to the Senior Commis<lb break="no"/>sariat Officer. <lb/>
The Tenders for Bread <lb/>
to express in words at length the quantity <lb/>
proposed to be returned for every 100 lbs <lb/>
of Flour delivered to the Contractor. <lb/>
The Contractor for Bread <lb/>
to have the option of baking of Bread on <lb/>
his own premises, or at the Government <lb/>
Bake-house. <lb/>
The Contractor's Premises <lb/>
to be, at reasonable hours, open to inspec<lb break="no"/>tion by an Officer of the Commissariat, or <lb/>
persons acting for him. <lb/>
The Tenders for Cartage <lb/>
to state the rate of hire for single or <lb/>
double Horse-Carts, separately; for Horses <lb/>
with Harness and Driver, each, and for <lb/>
Horses and Drivers without Harness, each, <lb/>
by the day and per trip, in sterling <lb/>
money. <lb break="no"/>Tenders for IIospital Supplies <lb/>
to express the prices in words as well as <lb/>
in figures, in Sterling. "As a guide to <lb/>
persons desirious of tendering, the follow<lb break="no"/>ing is a list of the various articles and pro<lb break="no"/>bable quantities which may be used during <lb/>
the year," viz,<lb break="no"/>Flour......... 30|Mustard...... " 6 <lb/>
Mutton......" 3UU|P tº 3. <lb/>
Mutton Chops" 5"|Vinegar.....pints 24 <lb/>
Potatoes ....." 1500|Essence of Beef lbs.100 <lb/>
Vegetables—viz — Cinnamon....." I <lb/>
Turnips, Carrots, Celery|Mølasses.... qets 6 <lb/>
Onions, Cabbage, &amp;c. Wine, Port.. pints 250 <lb/>
as required by Medical Wine,Sherry " 10 <lb/>
F...lbs 600|Porter, Eng btls 300 <lb/>
100 Porter, Năd.. " 24 <lb/>
20|Ale, English, ": <lb/>
160|Ale, Nfd º <lb/></p> 

<p>Żºłrandy...... gals 2 <lb/>
900|Gin.... pints * 5 <lb/>
200|Rum...... l 1. <lb/></p> 

<p>... gili. <lb/>
19|Soap, hard, for per<lb break="no"/>59 sonal use... lbs . <lb/></p> 

<p>150|Soap,hard,coarse" 60 <lb/>
150|Soap,sof ... " 150 <lb/></p> 

<p>85th Soda........ ... " 120 <lb/>
50|Scouring Sand bus 10 <lb/>
6|Whiting......... lbs 6 <lb/></p> 

<p>50|Bath Bricks.... No 1 <lb/>
Black Lead..... lbs 6 <lb/>
-\-\-\-\-\- Windsor Soap. " 4 <lb/>
Deliveries of the above to be made at the <lb/>
Hospital daily, in such quantities as may <lb/>
be demanded by the Senior Medical Officer. <lb/>
The conditions of the foregoing Contracts <lb/>
may be ascertained and any further infor<lb break="no"/>mation obtained, on application at this <lb/>
office, during the hours for transacting <lb/>
public business, <lb/>
Satisfactory Securities will be required <lb/>
for the due fulfilment of each of the fore<lb break="no"/>going Contracts, and each party tendering <lb/>
must give the names of two persons of <lb/>
bona fide property, willing to become <lb/>
securities for the performance of the Con<lb break="no"/>tract, in the sum of £100 sterling for Bak<lb break="no"/>ing Bread, £100 sterling for Cartage, £25 <lb/>
sterling for Hospital Supplies. <lb/>
Accounts when amounting to Fifty <lb/>
Pounds Sterling and upwards will be paid <lb/>
by a Bill on Her Majesty's Treasury, but <lb/>
when under that sum, by a cheque on a <lb/>
Local Bank. <lb/>
Commissariat, Newfoundland, <lb/>
St. John's 15th Feb., 1869. <lb/>
A. FULFORD ADAMS, <lb/>
A. C. G. <lb/></p> 

<p>[N.B. The forms of Tender for the Contract <lb/>
for Timber have been altered to admit of the <lb/>
Contractor claiming a higher price for small <lb/>
orders, . Two prices will be admitted, one for <lb/>
orders for one of 500 feet super of one inch <lb/>
plank or its equivalent and upwards, the other <lb/>
jor orders for less than one load.] <lb/>
SEALEP TENDERS. in Duplicate, will be <lb/>
received at this Office until Noon on WED. <lb/>
NESDAY, the 24th instant, from persons will. <lb/>
ing to enter into a Contract for the supply of <lb/></p> 

<p>TIMBER, &amp;c., <lb/></p> 

<p>for the Royal Engineer Department, for a <lb/>
period of Two years from the 1st of April <lb/>
noxt. <lb/>
This Contract may be terminable after the <lb/>
expiration of Twelve months, on three monthſ, <lb/>
nºtice; frºm the first, of the month, being <lb/>
given by either of the Contracting Parties. <lb/>
The respective Schedules, with the condition: <lb/>
of Contract may be seen at the Office of the <lb/>
Qommanding. Hoyal Engineer, from whom <lb/>
forms of Tenders and further ºf ornation can <lb/>
be obtained, <lb/>
The Tenders to express the prices at per <lb/>
cent. above or below the rates named in the <lb/>
Schedule, in Army Sterling, and to be addres<lb break="no"/>sed to the Senior Commissariat officer. <lb/>
Security to the amount of £100 Sterling <lb/>
will be required for the due fulfilment of thº <lb/>
Contract. <lb/>
Payment will be made Quarterly in Bills on <lb/>
Her Majesty's Treasury, at par, for accounts, <lb/>
properly certified, amounting to £50 a.º. wp<lb break="no"/>wards, and by cheque on a Lºcal Back if un<lb break="no"/>der that sum. <lb/>
Commissariºit, Newfoundland; <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/></p> 

<p>No change in Gºld. <lb/></p> 

<p>Styloan s 15ſ, February, 1869, <lb break="no"/>* A, #6Bo ADA yº <lb/>
4. Q. Q <lb/></p> 

<p>:T­ <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_1.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">St. John's, Wednesday, February 24, 1869.</fw>


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-10, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>-\-\-\-\-\-\- ºr-\-\-tºº-\-&gt; <lb/></p> 

<p>rful that the world has ever known. <lb/>
ná in whateven share disease exists, <lb/>
equal to its subjection and cure. . . <lb/></p> 

<p>ºf sIC-K. . . . ." <lb/>
the Housemoto REMEDY of all nations. <lb/>
attack the very poor of the complaint, <lb/>
ºre the drooping energies of the <lb/>
Nerſonaar REFORMATION-\-<lb break="maybe"/></p> 

<p>2 sºror/C.A.C.E. <lb/>
is the operation of the Pills? They <lb/>
ºriațăstomachinto anatural and <lb/>
of the system from sickness to health. . <lb/>
* ALTT.IMIENTS<lb break="no"/>m undergoes the most important and <lb/>
icin every disorder to which they are <lb/>
ard against evil consequences. <lb/></p> 

<p>5 TIMEFU=ITIEs of <lb/>
|-i-º­ <lb/></p> 

<p>lood is in an impure stato, let such <lb/>
ºf with confidence to this powerful <lb/>
health and strength will be the result. <lb/></p> 

<p>+-ISTOWN. FO:ER. <lb/></p> 

<p>fl. stone and §:... <lb/></p> 

<p>onplaints. secondary Symptons. <lb/>
implaints 5. . Thatever <lb/></p> 

<p>wn of Urine, - cause, &amp;c., <lb/></p> 

<p>words tº Hºlloway, London," are dis<lb break="no"/>of directions around each box; which <lb/>
*...* Solà at the manufactory of Pro<lb break="no"/>respectable Druggists and Dealers in <lb/>
22s., and 33s.-There is a considerable <lb/>
tions for use are affixed to cach Box. " <lb/></p> 

<p>ONUS EVERY THREE YEARS <lb/></p> 

<p>THE ETNA <lb/></p> 

<p>URANCE COMPANY <lb/></p> 

<p>(LIAIARP, -<lb break="maybe"/>pital—One Million Sterling: <lb/>
ºffices—Dublin-46 &amp; º: Sackville <lb/>
ºdinburgh–98 George's Street. <lb/>
*"...º.º., E. c. <lb/>
eneral Manager—John Innes, Esq. <lb/>
ecretary J. S. Fisher, Esq. <lb/>
nprecedented success of the ETNA in the <lb/>
Kingdom, owing to its liberal dealings with <lb/>
is is a fact which strongly recºmmends the <lb/>
y to the people of Newfoundland. <lb/>
come ºf his company from NEW PRE. <lb/>
ALONE is progressing at the rate of <lb/>
per Annum. - -<lb break="maybe"/>ompany do not advocate high preminms. <lb/>
rs ample security to all nsurers. ... <lb/></p> 

<p>s for '... shall be piomptly and liberally <lb/></p> 

<p>fers from other offices can be effected free <lb/>
e <lb/></p> 

<p>by payment of Six years premium can <lb/>
VEN years policy. <lb/>
in A is Tlib only Ogwick, which of FER <lb/>
sus "EYERY Tim REE YEARs to Policy<lb break="no"/>. HoldeRS HAVING No Lussks. <lb/></p> 

<p>ndersigned having been appointed General <lb/>
* Newfoundland for the above Company, <lb/>
ed to effect Insurances against LOSS Olk <lb/>
;B BY FIRE on all descriptions of pro<lb break="no"/>fair and reasonable rates, and begs leave<lb break="no"/>a share of the business of those having <lb/>
cs to effect. <lb/>
Jers shall have prompt attention. <lb/>
for proposals and ſurther information ean <lb/>
t the oſfice of -<lb break="maybe"/>ROBERT J. KENT, <lb/>
Solicitor. <lb/>
No. 261 Duckworth-Street St. John's. <lb/></p> 

<p>6m <lb/></p> 

<p>owever inveterate. Few medicine: <lb/>
grand remedy not only cures in such <lb/>
is, as a proof it needs but a trial. <lb/></p> 

<p>DISTC+ETTIS. <lb/>
soughs, and colds, may be infallibly <lb/>
bbing this remedy twice a day upon <lb/>
ates, and a cure quickly follows. <lb/></p> 

<p>EAST's, ETC. <lb/>
temedy is now in general use. In <lb/>
• Physicians regularly prescribe its <lb/>
a the chests of sailors and emigrants. <lb/></p> 

<p>s"Wriºr, I.TINTG.S. º <lb/>
his Ointment will prove invaluable. <lb/>
im, and restores matural circulation. <lb/></p> 

<p>ET.C., ETC<lb break="no"/>arts, of either sex, may be readily <lb/>
f this cooling and healing Ointment. <lb/></p> 

<p>E" ºrot TTEC<lb break="no"/>|aily cured by the joint agency of <lb/>
o the printed directions <lb/></p> 

<p>Peº- -<lb break="maybe"/>ieving and curing old wounds, sº <lb/></p> 

<p>y in most of the following cases:<lb break="no"/>Soro Heads. <lb/>
F's Evil. Tic Doloureux. <lb/>
ons, Tightness or Wheezing on the * <lb/>
* - Cheat, with difficulty of Breathing <lb/></p> 

<p>words " Holloway, London," are dis<lb break="no"/>the light, in every leaf of the book of <lb/>
factory of Professor Holloway, 244, <lb/></p> 

<p>Medicine, in pots at 18.1%d., 2s. 9d., <lb/>
le saving by taking the larger sizese <lb/></p> 

<p>No. 6,572. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºr. ..." <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, Wednesday, February 21, 1869. <lb/></p> 

<p>Printed and Published every Tuesday and Friday <lb/>
morning by EDWARD DALTON SHEA, at his <lb/>
Office in Duckwor:Tit STREET. Terns—One <lb/>
Găinea per annum, pnyable in advance. <lb/>
Advertisements not limited (Auction Sales and notices <lb/>
which determine themselves excepted) are repeated, <lb/>
until ordered in writing to be withdrawn. <lb/>
is paper is filed, and mºw be seen free of charge <lb/>
at Holloway's Pill and Ointment Establishment, <lb/>
244. Strand. London. . . <lb/>
This paper is not issued to any Subsertber for a shorter <lb/>
term than siz months. <lb/></p> 

<p>Thouse of Asseyibly. <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p>--> 

</div>
    <div type="debate">
        
        <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head>
    

<p rendition="simple:right">MONDAY, Feb. 15.</p>
        
        <p rendition="simple:centre">[CONTINUED]</p>
        
        <p>
            <persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName>.—The hon. gentleman had <lb/>
made a very lengthy and elaborate speech to <lb/>
show the people that Coufederation was the best <lb/>
thing for their interest, and that the exportation <lb/> 
of 800 men before the 10th of May would be <lb/>
the beginning of the blessings of Confederation. <lb/>
He (Mr. H.) might admit that for an old and <lb/>
overpopulated country, emigration might be a <lb/>
good thing, but who would assert it with regard <lb/>
to a colony which had capacities for supporting <lb/>
3,000,000 of people? If no bettar argument <lb/>
for Confederation than this could be found, the <lb/>
case must be a bad one. From day to day <lb/>
our people are leaving our shores, and going <lb/>
under the Government of the stars and stripes. <lb/>
It this Dominion be what they say, why don't <lb/>
emigrants remain there? Do they do so? No, <lb/>
they go to the United States. Was the Do<lb break="no"/>minion independent? Why, 14 or 15 Bills passed <lb/>
last year, had been ignored by the Imperial <lb/>
Government. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA2">Hon. Mr. S</persName>.—I heard of one. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName> could name them. The fact <lb/>
was that the Yankees would have us before the <lb/>
good times spoken of would over arrive. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
            <persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName>.—There was no evidence before <lb/>
the House that the people were in favour con<lb break="no"/>federation. In fact all the evidence pointed out <lb/>
the contrary. Hon. members representing Out<lb break="no"/>ports had ample opportunity, during the past <lb/>
five years to have got up petitions in favour of <lb/>
it, had the people approved of the measure—<lb/>
And had they approved of it? We might be as<lb break="no"/>sured that there would have been some effort made <lb/>
to prepare these petitions. The hon member, Mr. <lb/>
Pinsent, had lately visited his district, and read them <lb/>
a lecture on Confederation. Had he been <choice><sic>autho<lb break="no"/>thorised</sic><corr>authorized</corr></choice> by the people to sustain it? If we look at <lb/>
the mother country we find that in all great, mea<lb break="no"/>sures the public mind was always consulted, and <lb/>
that legislation was controlled by it. Some three <lb/>
years ago a petition had been presented by Mr. <lb/>
Wyatt against Confederation. He (Mr. R.) had the <lb/>
honor of presenting one of a similar character, and <lb/>
with a similar object, from the District of Placentia. <lb/>
Last year he had been entrusted with one from the <lb/>
monster meetting which had been held in the Fisher<lb break="no"/>men's Hall. Surely, then, if the people were in <lb/>
favour of it, where was the evidenue that would <lb/>
prove that the Government was correct and the op<lb break="no"/>position wrong. If the people viewed the matter <lb/>
in the same light that we are told, how is it that that <lb/>
opinion is not expressed by any petition before this <lb/>
House? It was indeed easy to say that a change <lb/>
had come over their minds. But we want something <lb/>
more than mere assertion—something more taugible, <lb/>
while there existed before this House the many post<lb break="no"/>tive assurances and evidence that the people did not <lb/>
desire us to take any action upon this important <lb/>
question. The hon. Attorney General, when he <lb/>
went to Burin in 1865, told the electors that his in<lb break="no"/>dividual views inclined to the principle of Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. Indeed, he only inclined to the principle in <lb/>
1865, whereas, in 1864 he was unequivocally in favor <lb/>
of it, and signed the Quebec Resolutions. He had <lb/>
pledged himself while in Canada to use his utmost <lb/>
endeavours to carry Confederation, upon the basis <lb/>
of the Quebec Resolutions. Why did he not hpn<lb break="no"/>estly ten the people of Burin he was in favor of Con<lb break="no"/>federaion, and upon these terms, and not to have <lb/>
hoodwinked and deceived them as he did. (Here <lb/>
the hon member referred to the Year Book of <lb/>
1868, and read from it certain passages relative to <lb/>
the sittings of the delegates. In 1884, and their pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings in Canada. Why, then, had not the <lb/>
            hon. Attorney General <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> told the people that <lb/>
he had signed the Quebec scheme, and that be <lb/>
would stand or fall by it? Oh, no. He knew very <lb/>
well, had be done so he would not now be in the po<lb break="no"/>sition he was. He had to eat humble pie when he <lb/>
went to Burin. He then promised them that there, <lb/>
should be no legislation upon, the matter without <lb/>
consulting the people, and yet be now proposes <lb/>
take action upon it without the consent of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple. Perhaps, however, it is true that the hon. <lb/>
Attorney General is not going back to Burin, and <lb/>
thus can afford to violate his plighted faith. Well <lb/>
the Receiver General went to the hustlings in 1853 <lb/>
and he also was forced to pocket Confederation and <lb/>
to eat humble pie. He had cast his eyes up to <lb/>
Heaven and had solemnly asserted that he would <lb/>
do nothing upon the matter without consulting his <lb/>
constituents. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
            <persName ref="pers:KENT1">Hon. RECEIVER GENERAL</persName>—I made no such de<lb break="no"/>claration. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
<persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName>.—Would refer to the hon. member's <lb/>
memory. Here the hon. Imember read an account <lb/>
of proceedings attending the elections of 1865. He <lb/>
then proceeded to read the address of himself and <lb/>
his colleague, Mr. Talbot, to the elector in that <lb/>
year, and commented upon the speech pf the At<lb break="no"/>torney General in which they had been accused <lb/>
of eating their own words. He contended that <lb/>
they had distinctly in this audress told the people <lb/>
that they were opposed to Confederation, as they <lb/>
were now. He contended further that they had <lb/>
truly foretold what had come to pass. That the <lb/>
malgamated Government was corrupt, had increas<lb break="no"/>ed the civil expenditure and the taxes, and added <lb/>
to the burdens of the people, that there exces<lb break="no"/>sive taxation had killed out the middle man, and <lb/>
that the short issue of supplies to the fishermen <lb/>
the past year was to be attributed to the increase <lb/>
of taxation which precluded the man of merely <lb/>
moderate means from competing with the more <lb/>
wealthy importers, who thus had a monopoly and <lb/>
could charge what they liked. Then the great <lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> was the <lb/>
            
            <cb/>

exportation of 800 men to Canada. This was to <lb/>
            produce quite a <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> among the labourers <lb/>
and increase their wages. They had received no <lb/>
instructions to bind the Legislature of the country, <lb/>
but when they signed the Resolutious they bound <lb/>
themselves to urge the principle and the terms <lb/>
on the people. The hon, and learned Attorney <lb/>
General and the hon. Mr. Shea would say that they <lb/>
approved of them but that it was subject to the <lb/>
approval of the people, but when the British <lb/>
Government saw that all had signed the document <lb/>
was it at all wonderful that they should conclude <lb/>
that all were in favour of Confederation? It was <lb/>
said that the House did not reject the principle <lb/>
that he (Mr. R) asserted that it did. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the day was afraid to lay the principle <lb/>
before the House for discussion, but substituted <lb/>
that very mild Resolution by the accepting of <lb/>
which the House and country virtually rejected <lb/>
the Quebec scheme. A great deal had been said <lb/> 
about the influence our representatives would <lb/>
have in the Dominion Parliament. In the last <lb/>
session the members from the Lower Provinces <lb/>
were opposed to the proposed tariff, but they might <lb/>
as well have held their tongues. It was passed in <lb/>
spite of them, and not a Canadian member gave <lb/>
them any assistance. It was also said that Lower <lb/>
Canadian sympathies and feelings would go with <lb/>
the Maritime Provinces. It might be so when <lb/>
Upper and Lower Cauada disagreed amongst them<lb break="no"/>selves, but when the question was Canadian they <lb/>
would be found united. The hon. member, Mr. <lb/>
Shea, referred to the case of Rhode Island, which <lb/>
has only one member in the House of Representit<lb break="no"/>tives. Though such was the case she was repre<lb break="no"/>sented in the Senate equally wiyh New York or <lb/>
any other State in the United States. In the Senate <lb/>
all the States were represented alike. Was <lb/>
such the case in the Dominion? There <lb/>
was no analogy between the constitutions. <lb/>
In the Dominion the arrangements were made so <lb/>
that Canada should always have a majority. Con<lb break="no"/>federation for our benefit indeed! It was never so <lb/>
intended. The Imperial Government were always <lb/>
anxious for it, simply that Imperial taxpayers might <lb/>
be relieved from the expenditure of troops in these <lb/>
            Colonies. They heard a great deal of reciprocity—<lb/>
            that we cannot have reciprocity without Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. They had yet to learn that the United States <lb/>
were disposed to establish reciprocity. From all <lb/>
that he (Mr. R.) could learn they were not at all <lb/>
disposed to re-establish it. When they heard hon. <lb/>
gentlemen opposite praise Reciprocity it should be <lb/>
remembered that at one time they were its bitterest <lb/>
enemies. It was strange how men would wheel <lb/>
round when they had an object in view. In 1864 <lb/>
they saw that no benefit whatever could be derived <lb/>
from Reciprocity, while to-day they are enamored <lb/>
with it. The hon member, Mr. Shea, took his (Mr. <lb/>
R's.) hon. colleague, Mr.Talbot, to task because he <lb/>
had said that it was possible to have Reciprocity <lb/>
without Confederation. He (Mr. R.) agreed with <lb/>
his hon. colleague. What was to prevent their <lb/>
having Reciprocity without Confederation? The rea<lb break="no"/>son was said to be because we cannot afford to strike <lb/>
£32,000 off our taxes. It could be had by striking <lb/>
£30,000 a year off official robbery, jobbery and <lb/>
extravagance, The hon. membr, Mr. Shea, says <lb/>
the salaries come to only £32,000 a year, and asks <lb/>
how could £30,000 be struck off that. But the <lb/>
public expenditure of last year citus to £170,000, <lb/>
and off that the hon. members of the opposition <lb/>
            proposed to strike £30,000, would not the saving <lb/>
of that sum be preferable to selling the country, <lb/>
to deporting 800 men to work in the wilds of <lb/>
Canada? The Government was puzzled to know <lb/>
how it could be done, but at the proper time they <lb/>
would be shown how to do it. Do they <lb/>
increase the taxes when, in other countries <lb/>
the revenue falls short of the expenditure? <lb/>
No. They reduce the expenditure; and that is, <lb/>
ought, and shall be the duty of the Government of <lb/>
this country. By a system of rigid economy they <lb/>
could have reciprocity, and every other, advan<lb break="no"/>tage, and need not be obliged to surrender the coun<lb break="no"/>try into the hands of strangers. Hon. gentlemen <lb/>
ask where is Mr. Howe. He (Mr. R.) was free to <lb/>
admit that that hon. gentleman was the great anti-<lb break="yes"/>Confederate leader in Nova Scotia. It would appear <lb/>
now that he was President of the Executive Council <lb/>
of the Dominion, but does that show that he had <lb/>
deserted his colors? Nova Scotia was in a differ<lb break="no"/>ent position from ours; she had been sold by her repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives; but he (M. R.) and his colleage's would <lb/>
take care that no such thing suould happen here. <lb/>
Canadian gold brought the majority against Con<lb break="no"/>federation in the Nova Scotia Assembly down to <lb/>
a minority, and so Confederation was carried <lb/>
there. When the people saw how affairs stood <lb/>
they got up hundreds of petitions, and sent Mr. <lb/>
Howe and a delegation to England to represent <lb/>
the true facts of the case. A second time did Mr. <lb/>
Howe go to Englaud, but he found the people <lb/>
there so absorbed by the question of Reform that <lb/>
he could not get his case fairly heard. Howe <lb/>
fought the battle well, and yielded only when he <lb/>
saw how little the people at home cared for <lb/>
Colonial as distinguish from Imperial interests. <lb/>
The hon. member, Mr. Shea, said it was the desire <lb/>
of the mother country that these Colonies should <lb/>
Cenfederate, all that she knew what was best <lb/>
for us. He (Mr. R.) denied it. They were the <lb/>
best judges of their own interests, and had no <lb/>
occasion to refer to those who evidently knew <lb/>
very little about them, and cared less. It was <lb/>
said that the cry of "bleaching bones" had been <lb/>
abandoned. Was it indeed? That it had a mean<lb break="no"/>ing was sufficiently proved by the fact that in 1835 <lb/>
the Canadian Conferderates, in pointing out the ad<lb break="no"/>vantages of union with the Lower Provinces, urged <lb/>
that Newfoundland would supply 30,000 of the <lb/>
            best seamen that ever trod the deck of a <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb break="no"/>wer. Now suppose men were required, was <lb/>
it to be supposed that the Newfoundland fisher<lb break="no"/>men would be exempted? They would have to go <lb/>
and some of their bones would be bleaching. <lb/>
A good deal was said about the present Chief <lb/>
Justice having been favourable to Confederation <lb/>
He, it was said, cited the case of the Irish reaper <lb/>
going to England to reap the harvest, and return<lb break="no"/>ing home with money in both pockets. Crossing <lb/>
the Channel was one thing. It could be done in <lb/>
            a few hours. But Quebec was 1,000 miles away, <lb/>
            and how could our poor labouresr travel up, and <lb/>
            down that distance? There was no analogy be<lb break="no"/>tween the cases. It was said that adter Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion we would have steam, Coastal and inter-<lb break="yes"/>provincial and that when labour was scarce <lb/>
            here, our people could go to the other Provinces <lb/>
            in search of it. They were also told that after <lb/>
            Confederation the land would flow with milk and <lb/>
            honey. How did the two notions stand together? <lb/>
            The people were leaving the country; but they <lb/>
            went to the United States, and not to Canada. <lb/>
            Would that be the case if Canada offered the <lb/>
            greater advantages? The Canadians <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
        
        have to seek employment in the United States <lb/>
      <choice><sic>ave</sic><corr>have</corr></choice>, even those who come to Canada from Eng<lb break="no"/>land have frequently to cross the border. The <lb/>
Government saw they did not increase the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture, that it was now actually less than in former <lb/>
years. It that be the case, how comes the increas<lb break="no"/>ed tariff of 1833, 1837, and 1868? Surely if the ex<lb break="no"/>penditure was less,there was no reason to increase <lb/>
the tariff. They ask where are our means of <lb/>
giving employment? The public gave to them <lb/>
the largest revenue any Government here ever had, <lb/>
yet where was there any evidence that that revenue <lb/>
was applied for the benefit of the people? Let <lb/>
the people exercise their legitimate authority, and <lb/>
return men who will carry out the wishes of the <lb/>
people, and with similar means the people would <lb/>
be made contented and happy. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
The hon. gentleman concluded a lengthy speech <lb/>
by stating that he had some further remarks to <lb/>
make, which he woull reserve for another <lb/>
occasion. <lb/></p>
        <!-- Commented out as not relevant to the debate
        <p>
The <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">hon. COLONIAL SECRETARY</persName> would wish <lb/>
to make an observation with regard to the fuel <lb/>
of the Lunatic Asylum, to the expens of which <lb/>
the hon. member Mr. Renouf had adverted. If <lb/>
the hon. member would refer to the journals <lb/>
for 1868, he would find that the cost of fuel for <lb/>
that year is £200 less than the cost for 1867. <lb/>
In 1867 it was considered advisable to purchase <lb/>
a cargo of coal, a considerable quantity of which <lb/>
remained on hand for 1868, thus lessening the <lb/>
expenses of that year. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
The Committee then rose, reported progress, <lb/>
and asked leave to sit again. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
The House then adjourned till to-morrow, at <lb/>
3 o'clock. <lb/></p> 


IC, 2019-01-10, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

<!--<p>I'uesday, Feb. 16. <lb/></p> 

<p>The House met at three o'clock, pursuant to <lb/>
adjournment. <lb/></p> 

<p>O.1 motion of Mr. Goddex, the House re<lb break="no"/>solved itself into Co.n.mittee of the Wuole on <lb/>
the ſur her consideraion of the address in reply <lb/>
to his Excellency's speech, Mr. KNIGHT in the <lb/>
chair. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. LITTLE thought that too much time had <lb/>
been spent in the discussing a question which in <lb/>
reality was not before the chaur, and that that <lb/>
which really was before the chair had been dis<lb break="no"/>cussed in a manner calculated to distract the at. <lb/>
tention of the liouse, and consume time which <lb/>
ought to be devoted to other purposes. Every <lb/>
species of argument had been used, and a gen<lb break="no"/>eral desise to rush to the front in the cause cf <lb/>
Confederation had been exhibited, though that <lb/>
question was not before the House. Tue Goy<lb break="no"/>crument could not deuy but that it was their <lb/>
own supporters who first promoted this unne<lb break="no"/>cessary discussion, whicu cousumed the time <lb/>
and mouey of the country. His (Mr. L'-) idea <lb/>
was that tué discussion should be conſiued to <lb/>
each section as it presented itself. The section <lb/>
now under consid ration was that which pro<lb break="no"/>posed immediate legislation on the question of <lb/>
Contederation, or at least that the Liouse should <lb/>
now euter into the discussion of that q lestion. <lb/>
Iſe concurred with all uis lieurt in tue latter <lb/>
part of the umºudunest proposed by the hon. <lb/>
in-mber, Mr. Taluo, not oily because of his <lb/>
(Mr. L's) pledge to uis constituents, but prin: <lb/>
cipally because this Lºgislature was not elected <lb/>
for the purpose of definitely binding the country <lb/>
on the subject of Coufederation. Even the hon, <lb/>
and l arned leader of the Governme it himself <lb/>
was not sent Lere by his cous ituents with full <lb/>
power to deal with the questiou. In plain lan<lb break="no"/>guage, he toll the people that the m tier would <lb/>
be referred to them betose any action would be <lb/>
taken on it; and he (Mº. L.) did not doubt but <lb/>
that the hou. and learned geutlemau wouli <lb/>
keep his promise. In limine, the moment assent <lb/>
is given to the principle or a measure and its <lb/>
deta is are takeu up for cousideratiod, it id em<lb break="no"/>bodied in resolutious and passed by tuis House, <lb/>
from that unomeut the approval of the country <lb/>
to that principle becomes a tuere bag telle. <lb/>
He (Mr. L.) understood that the course pro<lb break="no"/>posed by the Government was to discuss the <lb/>
principle a ud the terns together, and by a re. <lb/>
solution of this IIouse make the acceptance of <lb/>
these terms a solemn act of the Lºgislature,then <lb/>
to send a delegation to the G ºvernment of <lb/>
t-e Domiuion, asking their asseut to these <lb/>
terms, a d it they be accepted by thein, then <lb/>
to dissolve the Lºgislature aud sºud hou. mem<lb break="no"/>bars to their constituencies for approval <lb/>
of thcir course of action, and uot ſor ac<lb break="no"/>ceptance or rejection of the principle of <lb/>
Uoutederation. It that by the course <lb/>
by watc l it is proposed to accomplished a gigan<lb break="no"/>tic scheme, for the amelioratiou of the country's <lb/>
ils, it is taking a very bad in ºus for the , ac<lb break="no"/>complishment of that end, Taey were not there <lb/>
to 1 gislato on the question of Coated 3ration, <lb/>
and lie, for oue, was returned to oppose it in <lb/>
i tue chºpe iu wuich it was first presented to <lb/>
{ i le cºuntry. .ie would oppose both terms aud <lb/>
* resolution 14 the presaut alouse, because other<lb break="no"/>| wise ue woulſ we ſale to his coustituents. The <lb/>
prese it L gi-liture was i.igagã 13, of deallug <lb/>
with thm ºtter, because it had not been clºthed <lb/>
with tue a-ceºsary powers by the people, who <lb/>
aloue can couler thea. I., a mattei of this sort <lb/>
be cousidered taat all should act together,sinking <lb/>
all party and personal interests, when the right: <lb/>
vi s.4-goveru.nent were about to oe transferrel <lb/>
to s.rangels, and the dearest interests of the <lb/>
peo.12 to be sacrificed. The uatter has ben <lb/>
suijaei or discussion in taa, Hºus" balcre, and <lb/>
the House had set its face against the principle <lb/>
aud tue teru-, as elapoiled in the Q 12iec <lb/>
schem. Tuat do one could dely. Petitious <lb/>
were presented to this Ilois* against tie intro<lb break="no"/>duction of that scheme, add yet hon, gentlemen <lb/></p> 

<p>- -\-Tº <lb/></p> 

<p>have to seek employment in the United Sºtes, ered to discuss the principle and to bind tieſ <lb/></p> 

<p>country. Such was not the case. It would be . <lb/>
a breach of faith to attempt it, and those who, <lb/>
attempted it will find that the dig of reckoning" <lb/>
will come, when they will appear before their <lb/>
taskmasters, who will assurelly bring them to <lb/>
account for their faithlessness. He (Mr. L.) , <lb/>
would have no reason to four meeting his coi<lb break="no"/>stituents,for he would observe his pledge to the n, <lb/>
which was that in the first instance the ques-" <lb/>
tion of Confederation and its term should be, <lb/>
submittel to the people. Should they at , <lb/>
the polls declare in favour of it, then <lb/>
he would be happy to carry out their <lb/>
desires to the bast of his ability. <lb/>
until then he would vote against both, unless <lb/>
it were made a condition that unless the people <lb/>
adopted them they should not be heli to bind <lb/>
the country. He did not regard legislative action <lb/>
on such a matter as mere lip service or proform: <lb/>
work. After passing resolutions as proposed, <lb/>
the question would become ore of man, not of <lb/>
measures. Rially the conduct of the Gºvera<lb break="no"/>ment with regard to this matter w is suffixie it <lb/>
to excite suspicion in the minds of honest men<lb break="no"/>Way have they not long ago com? dowa with <lb/>
the proposed terms? Why do they keep then <lb/>
back * Why herald the very shadow of Gonfe<lb break="no"/>deration with such speeches as, had been heard? <lb/>
Why not in these speeches deal with factº in- " <lb/>
stead of theories? He thought the amonds. <lb/>
ment before the chair w is a very prop ºr one, <lb/>
ani woull give it his support, for the reasons' <lb/>
which he had already expressed. To these: <lb/>
reasons and that opinion he would <lb/>
adhere. He had given his opinio 1 as shortly <lb/>
as he coull. IIa would, so far as his p wer <lb/>
enabled him, opposs the passini; of any resolu<lb break="no"/>tions respecting the principle or term of <lb/>
Confederation, because the matter should first <lb/>
be laid before the people, who know best what <lb/>
was for their own interest. t <lb/>
Mr. Prowse had much pleasure in listeding " <lb/>
to the hon. and learned member who had just <lb/>
sooken, though he (Mr. P.) differed with his <lb/>
views. He (Mr. P.) considered that the whola. <lb/>
question of Confederation rested on the terms. <lb/>
Hon. gentlemen opposite, aal all blessed with <lb/>
the highest and most gifted minds, admitted that' <lb/>
the principle was one which could not be gain-. <lb/>
said. There was no man would go so far as to <lb/>
say we would not haveConfederation on anyterms." <lb/>
To go to the bustings with the naked question <lb/>
of principle would have no me uing, but to go' <lb/>
with the principle accompanied by the terms <lb/>
was what they could very easily understand. Ha, <lb/>
agreed with the hon, and learned member for <lb/>
Harbor Main that the people should decide the <lb/>
question for themselves. How could the terms <lb/>
be placed before them? These mus' first be <lb/>
discussed and agreed to; and they ought to be <lb/>
agreed to by every member in the House. He <lb/>
(Mr. P.) considered that the terms should be <lb/>
fair and equitable, and suited to tax interests ot" <lb/>
the Colony. It woul! also have to be considered <lb/>
whether they would be accepted by tha' <lb/>
Dominion Government. If they were, then <lb/>
they would be submitted to the people.... It they <lb/>
do not accept them then they fall to the ground; <lb/>
b it if they do accept them, then both this Lºgis<lb break="no"/>lature and that of the Dominion will have to <lb/>
a dress the Queen in Council praying H ºr ap-? <lb/>
proval of the matter. Tuo hon, and learned, <lb/>
member for Harbor Maiu said that the couduct <lb/>
of the Government, was calculated to excite * <lb/>
suspicion. He (Mr. P.) considered that the ' <lb/>
conduct of the Governinout had been all through <lb/>
as ſair and open and above board as . it could: <lb/>
possibly be, The hon, gen:l in in did not say, <lb/>
in what way their conduct was suspicious. Had: <lb/>
they accelerated or pushed on the question, or: <lb/>
forced it in any way? Iid (Mr. P.) had noth<lb break="no"/>ing to do with the Goverainent, and merely gave <lb/>
his own opinions on the course of eventº, as <lb/>
ady cther independant inémber would. The <lb/>
Government looked on the matter as a mast, <lb/>
grave and important one, and they progeolvd <lb/>
slowly and calmly with it, just as it should be.' <lb/>
lie supposed that in duo tune the terms would <lb/>
be brought down. They could thea be discussel <lb/>
and criticised aud cuvassed, There was a titas <lb/>
when Coafederation was a small child in thº? <lb/>
House, and when it had a great' <lb/>
many . enemies quite ready to strangle it, butz <lb/>
now it had growu up and acquired considerable" <lb/>
strength, and those who before tried to strangla <lb/>
it are glad to help it along, Lie (Mr. P.). <lb/>
could recollect when the luajarity against Cou<lb break="no"/>federation, both inside and outside of the House, <lb/>
was very large, but the m jority was even larger <lb/>
the other way uow. Tuls was too importiuſ a <lb/>
question for mere tricks of par y, and it was <lb/>
criminal for any ſaan to be politically dishonest <lb/>
about it. He had placed his views ou record in <lb/>
1895, and to these views he still adhered. He<lb break="no"/>thea believed that as the majority was so large <lb/>
against it, it would be a long time before it was <lb/>
settled. However, lie aow believed that the <lb/>
time to settle it had come. He ageed with <lb/>
the hon, and learned member for Hiroor Main, <lb/>
that this House coall not make any final settle<lb break="no"/>ment respec.ingtime tertas, Tuaº was the province <lb/>
of the peºple aud a proviso to that efect should <lb/>
be inserted in the resolutions. He (Mr. P.J." <lb/>
did not like to see tile uſtair way in wutc., this <lb/>
q1...stion of Confederation was dealt with, both <lb/>
inside and outside of the House. Every man <lb/>
wao speaks in favor of Confederation hair agaia <lb/>
aid agaia to fight against some exploded idea or <lb/>
other. The * bleacuing boaes" idea was so far <lb/></p> 

<p>opposite say that th; L-gislature were empow-l ſeieration disdained tº use it any mors. The <lb/></p> 

<p>gone that even the great head contre of Con- '' <lb/></p> 

<p># <lb/></p> 

<p># <lb/>
; <lb/></p>
-->
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>