<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-17" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1869-02-17">17 February 1869</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1869-02-24"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2019-01-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2019-01-07">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER</fw>
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2019-01-07, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day -->

<!--<p>f <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>Union of Ireland was also brought forward in <lb/>
eloquent terms, what possible contestion was <lb/>
there between the Union of Ireland and this <lb/>
guestion of Confederation?, Hon. gentiemen <lb/>
#ºvery well that it had none, and it was <lb/>
sowardly, mean and dastardly thus to appeal to <lb/>
the passions and prejudices of the peopl-. His <lb/>
District had suºred a great deal by the with­ <lb/>
drawal of local steam, The withdrawal, how <lb/>
ever was unavoidable, for in the present cºndi­ <lb/>
tion of the colony the subsidy could not be afford­ <lb/>
si. He thought that local steam shoull b2.4 <lb/>
sine, ºa Won of Confederation. They would <lb/>
then have something better thaa the dirty tub <lb/>
hey used to have, and wouli also have batter <lb/>
than the present tub ic Conception Bay. He <lb/>
Ener that the hon. member for S. John's had <lb/>
tried and were trying to stir up a feeling agº inst <lb/>
confederation, but he balieved that his(Mr.P") <lb/>
constituents were favorable to it on good terms <lb/>
He hoped these good terms would be gºt, and <lb/>
that if not none other would be accepted. He <lb/>
had often in that House triel to procure the <lb/>
erection of a Light House in his district, but <lb/>
had failed. Las: summer representations on the <lb/>
matter were made to the Dominiou Government <lb/>
and without hesitation they sent down a steamer; <lb/>
had a survey held and the site agree; on, and <lb/>
the building will commence at once. There was <lb/>
aarnest of one of the benefits of Confederation. <lb/>
The speeches on this question were sº long that <lb/>
the subject was nearly worn threadbare, but <lb/>
there was one importan; matter which was <lb/>
only slightly, if at all glanced at. That was <lb/>
the power given to the Dominion Palliament to <lb/>
negotiate commercial treaties, which would <lb/>
aftect this country in the matters of the French <lb/>
shore and the Spanish trade. H3 had been <lb/>
told that the Dominion was endeavoring to es­ <lb/>
tablish a free trade with the Spanish West <lb/>
India Islands, and that it will be accomplished <lb/>
so soon as the affairs of Spain are settled. New­ <lb/>
foundland had a very great interest in that <lb/>
matter. The differential duty against foreign flºgs <lb/>
had op d very prejudicially to our i <lb/>
This àuty had been the means of prohibiting our <lb/>
fish being carried in English bottoms to Spain, <lb/>
and it had been maintained by the interest <lb/>
which a few Blediterranean ship-owners poss <lb/>
sessed at the Cortes. With the new Govern­ <lb/>
ment the flºg duty wonlil be taken away,aud our <lb/>
commercial rel, tions with Spain would, through <lb/>
the influence of the Dominiou be placed upon a <lb/>
much fairer footing than at prosent. It was of <lb/>
the greatest possible importance tº u; that ºur <lb/>
interests should be represented at Madrid. The <lb/>
produce of Swaden, and Holland had, through <lb/>
the influence of their respective Ministers, been <lb/>
brought into great demand in tºº, Spanish <lb/>
market. Spain consumed annually 900,0004 le. <lb/>
of codfish, and of this we did not send them one­ <lb/>
fourth, hiring been cut out by the Swedish <lb/>
fish. Petitions and memorials sent year after <lb/>
year to the Colouial office had all proved una­ <lb/>
wailing to remove the invidious obstacles against <lb/>
which we had to contend, and our only cuance <lb/>
of success lay in the power conferred upon the <lb/>
idominion, of making commercial treaties and <lb/>
sending an accredited minister to these Courts. <lb/>
He (Air. P.) had referred to this point because <lb/>
he knew something of it personally. He trust­ <lb/>
ed when the real questiou came down,the terms <lb/>
and bona fide conditions of Conſederation, they <lb/>
will receive that calm and dispassionate coasi­ <lb/>
deration to which they were entitled. <lb/>
The hon. Colonial Secretany should have <lb/>
taken no part in the debate, did he not consider <lb/>
it the duty of every hon member to express his <lb/>
opinions on the important, matters, belore the <lb/>
ciair, For his (hou C. S's) part, he was tied <lb/>
by no pledges, but felt himself perfectly free to <lb/>
déal with the question of Confederation and, to <lb/>
give publicity to the views which he had <lb/>
always held. When the question was first <lb/>
brought into notice,though we had a genial tariff <lb/>
and ºverything in our favour, he had been of <lb/>
opinion that we could not ally ourselves to the <lb/>
neighbouring Colonies without being benefitted <lb/>
He had regarded Newfoundland as a poor family <lb/>
invited to cast in her lot with half a dozen <lb/>
families in comfortable circumstances, and he <lb/>
had beon persuaded that such a union cºuld not <lb/>
but rebound to her advantage. In 1865 he had <lb/>
before his constituents avowed his seutiments, <lb/>
aud he had told them that whenever the question <lb/>
came up for consideration he would wu.e in <lb/>
favour of it. If then they had disapproved of <lb/>
his sentiments they need not have elected him: <lb/>
He should now vote in favour of the Address, and <lb/>
if in this he was running counter to the opinions <lb/></p> 

<p>of his district they were perfectly, free tº elect <lb/></p> 

<p>another man. We could not but regard this <lb/>
quastion of unior as one fraught with impora <lb/>
tance, as it must affect the weal or woe of the <lb/>
country for all time to come. The <lb break="no"/>o the matter could not without prejudice to the <lb/>
community be longer delayed. Delay would <lb/>
not only be cowardly but suicidal as, regurded <lb/>
the interests of the Country and those who <lb/>
were charged with the protection of those inter­ <lb/>
ests. He believed the country demanded, a <lb/></p> 

<p>decision at the hands of this House, uud that || <lb/></p> 

<p>seven-tenths of the people of the Island, were iu <lb/>
favour of a change. Should then that change be <lb/>
such as would continue us in our present posi­ <lb/>
tion as a luiserable fishing dependency? Qe <lb/>
should it be such as woull unito us with a <lb/>
Dominion growing in wealth and importance <lb/>
every day? With reference to the subject of <lb/>
Reciprocity,though every hop.membº adulitted <lb/>
its advantges, there was a variety ºf opinions. <lb/>
Hon gentlemen on this side agreed with his <lb/>
Excellency, that separated from the Dominion <lb/>
we should be in no position to ensure to our­ <lb/>
selves the banefits of reciprocal free trade, while <lb/>
hon, gentlemen opposits contended that lºck <lb/>
procity might be brought abour by a reductiºn <lb/>
of the civil expenditure. With this latter view <lb/>
he (non, C.S.), could not concur. Wherever <lb/>
there was a useless expenditure or a useless <lb/>
'office ie: it be roaqved. But, refranch, as we <lb/>
might he cºnsidered it, utterly impossible to <lb/>
obtain all the begains from such a policy as <lb/></p> 

<p>... their and if toey could succeed in <lb/></p> 

<p>. . .ent before us cæstituents, if they disapprowed <lb/></p> 

<p>*** <lb/></p> 

<p>hon. members opposite contemplated, and though <lb/>
these benefits might be obtained, he considered <lb/>
that they would bear no compariso...!? those <lb/>
growing out of confederation. He (hon: 3. S.) <lb/>
had understood the hop. member, Mr. Little, to <lb/>
say that it was the intention of the Government <lb/>
to adopt by resolution the saction of this colony <lb/>
º, whº terms of Confederation. He (hoa. C. S.), <lb/>
id not understaad it so. If this were so." <lb/>
question would be definitely settled. T./ <lb/>
measure could act be tested at the general <lb/>
election and the election, would be a question <lb/>
not of measures bat of mea. The hon. taember <lb/>
was throwing dust in the eyes of his coustituency, <lb/>
and endeavouring to shirk the responsibility <lb/>
which was incumbent upon him, leaving himself <lb/>
free to accept Confederation as a foregone º <lb/>
clusion, while it was in reality undecided and hº <lb/>
might in hones'y oppose it. He (ºn. C. S.) <lb/>
considered that the time had arrived when wº <lb/>
should acº like rational creatures. We could <lb/>
not remain blind to the decleusion of the means <lb/>
of employment and deaf to the appeals of misºry <lb/>
and distress. The resources on which the <lb/>
people haſ trusted did not keep Peº with the <lb/>
increase of population. He did not mean tº <lb/>
say that Coatederation would have the effect of <lb/>
bringing fish to our shores,but he regarded it as <lb/>
a means to an end, and that end the gradual but <lb/>
unceasing and certain improvement of the con­ <lb/>
dit on of the country. It would be needless for <lb/>
him to express in detail his views upon this sub, <lb/>
ject, for abler hands had already dealt with it in <lb/>
all its bearings. He hoped that the terms tº <lb/>
which this House would assant would be such <lb/>
as would prove advantageous to the country, <lb/>
that there would be no difficulty in obtaising <lb/>
their appoval at the hands of the General Gov; <lb/>
ernment, and that before long Newfoundland <lb/>
would b: an integral part of the Confederacy. <lb/>
Mir, Giles.-Hon. members opposite seemed to <lb/>
be trying to educate the people ºn the subject of <lb/>
Confjºtion, before the terms &amp;ame down. He <lb/>
only rose to make a relaark upon the speech of the <lb/>
hon. Recover General, which was a very able and <lb/>
o ive speech. "But the lion, gentleman had <lb/>
sºd matters which were not facts,tending to delude <lb/>
the people. This statement could not arise from <lb/>
the ignorance of the hon. gettleman. If the state­ <lb/>
men had come from the hou. member, Mr. Pinsent, <lb/>
he (Mr. G.) would not have taken, the slightest <lb/>
notice of it,for he did not consider that that hon, gº­ <lb/>
tlemaa was quite au fait at figures. The honºe­ <lb/>
ceiver General had stated that our expenditure <lb/>
ºnder Confederation would be $315,000 and the <lb/>
grant from the Dominion $416,000, so that $100,000 <lb/>
would annually be left for roads. Now the Dom ni­ <lb/>
on did not grant us $416,000, so the fact stated was <lb/>
not correct. The amount of the Dominion subsidy <lb/>
was sºč9,000, so that there was a difference of <lb/>
$47,000 against the Colony. That statement ºf the <lb/>
hon, gantleman had gone, forth to the world, had <lb/>
been extensively read, and coming forth with the <lb/>
prestige of his high character, it must have taken <lb/>
effect. The hon. gentieman should have been more <lb/>
guarded. If the Confederate cause were a good <lb/>
une, it would not require misstatements to support <lb/>
it. The hon, member, Mr. Pinsent, seemed to be <lb/>
trimming his wings for a ſlight to Ottawa, and when <lb/>
bya and bye the ugly rush for situations came (for <lb/>
tàers would be an ugly rush), the bon. member if he <lb/>
tailed in getting a high legil position * Attorney <lb/>
General or Sºlicitor General, after the display <lb/>
which he had made the other day, would be § <lb/>
Justified in looking for the post of Finance Minister. <lb/>
He (M.G.) had stated a few days ago that the <lb/>
Dºminion was in difficulties, and that to save theº­ <lb/>
sºlves from insoºveccy, they had to issue $5,000,000 <lb/>
in Treasury notes. The hon member, Mr. Rendell, <lb/>
had said that that could not be, as their debentures <lb/>
were at a premium in London. The hon. Maember <lb/>
should recºlect that at that time parties in England <lb/>
Juli not ge; more than 1% per ceil. for their money, <lb/>
on account of the excessive supply of gold, ºppºse <lb/>
the Dominion Government had thrown this $5,000; <lb/>
ood of debentures into the London market, would <lb/>
hey have been saleable? Certainly not. Tae <lb/>
Domini were just as i as our <lb/>
ºn Gºvernment. These Treasury notes would have <lb/>
to be called in, and a crash would come. Though <lb/>
they were a Government of great abilities, they were <lb/>
ecºlºs Goveranent. iie (Air. G.), coald not <lb/>
see the expediency of one bankrupt #overnment <lb/>
going into partnership with another. <lb/>
†e fºod. Receiver GExERAL maintained the <lb/>
accuracy of his statement. The subsily ºf hº Dos <lb/>
miniºn Government would audant to $416,509 and <lb/>
under the Resolutions which were to be brought in, <lb/>
the Government would look for a yet larger grant­ <lb/>
Mr. Gººs.-The Dominion Government deducts <lb/>
the interest on the debt from the subsidy­ <lb/>
Hon. Receiver GeseRAL.-Yes, but that I have <lb/>
charged under the expenditure: Ile (hon. R.G.) <lb/>
was mused by the anxiety of bon. members oppo. <lb/>
site." In Nova Scotia Confederation was carried <lb/>
without an appeal to the constituencies. In Now: <lb/>
foundland the Legislature are determined that the <lb/>
constituencies shalfbe consulted, and because tha, <lb/>
very conditions which were denied to Nova Scotia <lb/>
are granted to Newfoundland, Newfoundland: <lb/>
forsoºth, is the most aggrieved country in the wºrld <lb/>
He was "astonished tº near the hon, member, Mr <lb/>
Little,talk of legislating upon Confederation. A sim: <lb/>
ple resolutions is not legislation as leg t requires <lb/>
£he concurrence of the three estates of Parliaueut. <lb/>
We pass resolutions exp anatory of the details upon <lb/>
which we would recommend the constituencies to <lb/>
accept the Union, and after having these conditions <lb/>
asseåted o by the General Gayernment, we go to <lb/>
the constituencies and say "Look calmly into the <lb/>
question, see the condition of the country and say <lb/>
heter or not we shall remain as we are: if sº, <lb/>
sweep from the bustings "hosº mºn who have ill­ <lb/>
advised yeu, but if you cousider they are honest <lb/>
adopt these terms and go into the Union." Hon. <lb/>
members opposite were Enrowing dusk in the eyes of <lb/></p> 

<p>getting into power, they would carry ºut the neas are <lb/>
if ºeneration, Tnºt was the meaning of the <lb/>
phrase," men and not measures." He was perfectly <lb/>
ºished aſ the hon. member. Mr. Glen, saying <lb/>
that he (hon. B.G.) was gality of aciº to delude <lb/>
the people. He was here to instrue: the people as <lb/>
far as his powers and his position went and was: <lb/></p> 

<p>of him, they coald reject him, and end his political <lb/>
influence. - * * * <lb/>
Mr. Resour contended that the figures of the hon <lb/>
Receiver General were false, and that the hon <lb/>
member, Mr. Glen, was correct. Tae Hoa, nº <lb/>
tº alºna, we would have to provide $315,990 <lb/>
for various services, Hs (Mr. B.) held in his <lb/>
hand a statement which proved that we should have <lb/>
to provide $360,000. Here was sº errºr of$45,000. <lb/>
ºiscensuedus expet-ditºre under Confederation, <lb/></p> 

<p>T H E N E W F 9 UN P <lb/></p> 

<p>insni; he had odered to every Boman Catholic <lb/></p> 

<p>L. A. N. D. E. R. <lb/>
- - - - - , <lb/>
Receiver General, could not amºnt tº less than <lb/>
$37,000; for provision for coastal steam woul <lb/>
i... ... be maje. He denied that the hºs Re­ <lb/>
ºver General represented the views of his con­ <lb/>
situalits or of the Roman Catholic population. <lb/>
The hon. Receiver GENERAL said, that the best <lb/>
reply to this remark was º he had received <lb/>
irº tie Right Revd. Dr. Mullock, which he read <lb/></p> 

<p>fºllows – - <lb break="no"/>K. My dear Mr. Kent, I was delighted with your <lb/>
peech in to-day's N.infoundlander. It is argumen­ <lb/>
tàtive, convincing, and will do a great deal or goo i. <lb/>
Praying for God continue y.º. in good health. <lb/>
I remain, yours sincerely, <lb/>
f J. T. AltJLLOCK. <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon. John Kent. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Resour.—Hon. gentlemen, on this side <lb/>
had the highest regard for Dr.Mullock, but this <lb/>
. . .aaººr which should be left to the people. <lb/>
H. members on this side had fought the bat lº <lb/>
of the people through good and through evil <lb/>
report, and as lºng, us...hº. had the honor ol <lb/>
occupying seats in the House, they would repre­ <lb/>
jºief districts independent of any influence: <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. BRENNAN.—Where was," gº deal of <lb/></p> 

<p>Trº <lb/></p> 

<p>On motion that the said report be received <lb/>
Mr. Parsons moved and Mr. GLEx seconº <lb/>
the following amendment to the second para­ <lb/>
graph of the address:­ <lb/>
While we admit the necessity lor the largs <lb/>
outlay under the head of relief of the able bodi. <lb/>
poor, we cannot refrain from expressing our dis <lb/>
approval of the injudicious mode in which such <lb/>
outlay was effected, and our regret, that no <lb/>
remedial measures had been adopted by the <lb/>
Government to relieve the evils accruing to the <lb/>
poor from its stoppage. <lb/>
The amendment was put and lost on a divi. <lb/>
sion,-Years, aſssrs silen, lioisºtt, Parsons, <lb/>
Breansn, Kearney, Little, Talbot, AI jor và <lb/>
Renouf, Nays—Hous Attorney General': <lb/>
Colºnial Secretary, Receiver General, A. Shea, <lb/>
the Surveyor General, Mesrs Raudell, Klight, <lb/>
Burton, Oakley, Evans, Bar.nett, Prº <lb/>
Pinsent, Barron. O'Rielly, Green, Goddau <lb/>
ICavanagh. <lb break="no"/>Mr. Hogs ETT then moved in amendment <lb/>
seconded, by Mr. TALB T, that the fourth <lb/></p> 

<p>conflictisg opinions abºut C: <lb/>
worth of potatoes would cause the people of St. <lb/>
Mary's Bay to be independent, iastead o! pay­ <lb/>
ing it to a Geologist, Waere was the property <lb/>
di.overed by thºr Geologis; 7 Not the full of <lb/>
his (Mr. B's) ſist. There was plenty of flags <lb/>
which ought to be used for drains about Torbay. <lb/>
The pipes cost a great deal of money, that catue <lb/>
from across the Åtlantic Ocean. A gentleman <lb/>
said to him (Mr. B.) that they were a gº! <lb/>
deal cheaper than the square drain. "A" <lb/>
they?', said he (Mr. B.), "Oh yes," said tº <lb/>
gentleman "that is what they have in Lso.idon." <lb/>
* Are you going to tell ms " said he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
" that they are cheaper when the money go; <lb/>
across the ocean and will never return." <lb/>
Whereas, iſ the money was spent in time country <lb/>
it would be like a weaver's shuttle, no sooner <lb/>
out of one hand than into the other. Have the <lb/>
flags at each side, lay it and sover it with thrº <lb/>
feet of earth, and it will last as long as the <lb/>
south Side hill. Our people were not here <lb/>
accustomel to heavy labour. The Rilway <lb/>
work in Canada was tha hardest work that <lb/>
could be. He considered that annexation would <lb/>
be more beneficial to Newfoundland as far <lb/>
as its encouragement of labour was concerned, <lb/>
than Confederation. <lb break="no"/>Mr. KEARNEY considered the subjeet before <lb/>
the chair was the most important that <lb/>
could come before this House. It was <lb/>
well known that he was returned to this <lb/>
House pledged to oppose Confederation: <lb/>
In case, however, the government, intended <lb/>
sending delegates to Canada, to adjust tº <lb/>
terms of Confederation, he hoped they would <lb/>
not forget this side of the House. The hon. <lb/>
member then referred at considerable length to <lb/>
the supply system, and the detrimental effects <lb/>
produced by the fisherinea being compelled to <lb/>
seil their fish green, for food. Iſe reterred to <lb/>
some cases of extortion. He drew particular <lb/>
attention to the great want and poverty that ex­ <lb/>
isted among the people, and appealed to the <lb/>
government not to allow the people to starve. <lb/>
Mr. HogserI thought that he had said every­ <lb/>
thing that was necess try upon the paragraph <lb/>
before the chair, and the amendmen; which had <lb/>
been proposed. It appeared, however, that the <lb/>
hon, Receiver General had been hatching an <lb/>
egg, and wanted to lay it. He (Mr. ii.) had <lb/>
been told that the lion. Receiver General had <lb/>
flung a let er in the faces of the opposition: <lb/>
which he alleged he had received from the Right <lb/>
Rev. Dr. Mullock. Now he (Mr. H) could <lb/>
not see why that Right Revd. Prelate's name <lb/>
should be dragged batore this House, and used <lb/>
as a meaus of utimidating aud coutrolling that <lb/>
independ of action which this side of the <lb/>
House possesses. Did the hon Receiver General <lb/>
think to whip us into line by a letter of that <lb/>
description? Did we see any . Protestan: gen­ <lb/>
tleman in this House dragging in his Bishop's <lb/>
name before the House, and making it the sub­ <lb/>
ject of debate? Why, the very fact of so violat­ <lb/>
ing the pivacy of that communication shows <lb/>
that the hon Receiver General would, if it suited <lb/>
his purpose, betray Dr. Mullock to-morrow. <lb/>
The hon Receiver General had received that <lb/>
letter in compliment to the speech which he de­ <lb/>
livered, and he now hurls it before this House <lb/>
as an evidance that he was the champion of the <lb/>
Catholic interests of this country. Why, the hon <lb/>
Receiver General killed more Catbolics, and <lb/>
is answerable for more Catholic blood than <lb/>
any man that ever stepped upou our shores. <lb/>
II6 drags his Bishop's nauma, now before this <lb/>
House to be the scofiag and sport of those <lb/>
who did not agree with him in his religiou: <lb/>
views, in order to cover his owo insulenee and <lb/>
cowardice. There was one Bishop in this country <lb/>
if his faith, who had given the hon Receiver <lb/>
General character and staadiug in the com­ <lb/>
munity, and yet he ungratefully abased him. <lb/>
How often had he (Mr. H.) heard him wag <lb/>
his tongue against his Bishop? Why, it the <lb/>
Right Revd. Dr. Mullock associated with the <lb/>
Receiver General, he would lower his position <lb/>
anido injury to his sacred character. The oppo­ <lb/>
sition knew their Bishop and resp cted him,and <lb/>
when he was attacked they would defend niin­ <lb/>
They would not go behind his back to traduce <lb/></p> 

<p>when the Receiver Geuel alforget he was a Catho­ <lb/>
lic and a Christian. He (Mr. H.), warned him <lb/>
not again to drag the name of ºuat oxalted <lb/>
individual before this iiouse. It was only <lb/>
cowards and knaves who would do such a thing. <lb/>
lie (Mr. H.) had got up merely . to give, ex­ <lb/>
pression is these views. Let him go and put <lb/>
nis head in a padding bag, forswear politics; <lb/>
and do penance tor the wrong; that he had done <lb/>
that great and good man, his Bishop, and the <lb/>
floan Cape John to Cºpa Bay: <lb/>
The paragraph was heu adopted. <lb/>
On motion of Mr. Goddes, the Countrittee <lb/>
then rose, and the Glauria in reported that the <lb/>
Committee haſ passed the addross without <lb/></p> 

<p>him. It he (AIr.H.) thought proper to show || <lb/></p> 

<p>the service. <lb/></p> 

<p>graph be exp i, and the foilowing sub-; <lb/>
jiu-jin lieu ther ºf: - ng sub-; <lb/>
In reference -to the French shore question, <lb/>
we ſail to discover in your Excelleusy's speech <lb/>
any thing that relievs this im, ortant in ther <lb/>
from the difficulties which surrounded it on <lb/>
the occasion of the address of the Legislature <lb/>
in the past session; and whilst we recognisa <lb/>
your Excellency's conduct in a desire to bring <lb/>
this subject to a satisfactory conclusion, we <lb/>
cannot but regret that no reply has been <lb/>
made to the resolutions and petitions of thi <lb/>
Legislature, and that the policy indicated in <lb/>
lord Carnarvon's despatch of the 7th D8. <lb/>
cember, 1866, is approved of by the la • <lb/>
Secretary of State for the Colonies. <lb/>
The amendment was put and lost on a <lb/>
similar division to the foregoing. <lb/>
Mr. 'Taleot then moved, in amendment, <lb/>
seconded by M jor Renouſ, that the sixth pits. <lb/>
graph be expunged, ald the following substitut­ <lb/>
ed in lieu thereof:­ <lb/>
with regard to the question of Confederation, <lb/>
we beg respectfully to esserve that the only <lb/>
scheme having reference to this matter which <lb/>
has been submitted to our consideration wit <lb/>
that Knowd by the name of the Q i-buc Resoli. <lb/>
tions, and that scheine has already been reje"el <lb/>
by the Legislature and the country i, and ** <lb/>
further take leave to express to your Excellowey <lb/>
our conviction and desire that a subject of <lb/>
such vital importance to the liberties of the <lb/>
country should be submitted to the decision <lb/>
of the people at the polls, before any further <lb/>
action be taken upon it by the Legislature. <lb/>
The ameadmaut was put and lost, oil a <lb/>
similar division to the foregoing- <lb break="no"/>The original motion was then put all <lb/>
carried. <lb break="no"/>ordered that tho address be read a third <lb/>
time to-morrow. <lb/>
The House than aljourned till to-morrºw, <lb/>
at 3 o'clock. <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> -->

<p rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, Feb. 17</p>
    
    <p>
The House met at 3 o'clock. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
On motion of <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GODDEN</persName>, pursuant to order <lb/>
of the day, the address to his Excellency the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor, in reply to his speech at the opening of the <lb/>
session, was read a third time and adopted, as <lb/>
        follows:— <lb/></p>
    
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">To His Excellency Anthony Musgrave Esq. Governor <lb/>
and Commander-in-Chief in and and over the Island <lb/>
of Newfoundland and its Dependencies.</hi> <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    <p>MAY IT PLEASE YOUR EXCELLENCY,— <lb/></p> 

<p>We, the Commons House of Assembly of Newfound<lb break="no"/>land, beg to thank Your Excellency for the gracious <lb/>
Speech with which you have been pleased to open <lb/>
the present Session of the Legislature, and for the <lb/>
uniform courtesy which has marked your intercourse <lb/>
with the House of Assembly during your Administra<lb break="no"/>tion of the Government. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
We fully approve of the course taken by the <lb/>
Executive Government in issuisg the Proclamation in <lb/>
June last, that relief in future would be confined to <lb/>
destitute widows and orphans, and to the sick and <lb/>
infirm poor. We believe this act was well tuned, and <lb/>
we cordially hope and trust that the Executive may <lb/>
be successful in its efforts to suppress the demoraliz<lb break="no"/>ing system of able-bodied pauper relief. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
We thank You Excellency for the promise that <lb/>
the Public accounts for the year 1863, will be shortly <lb/>
laid before us. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>We are pleased to learn that Your Excellancy's <lb/>
personal exertions in endeavoraing, to settle the <lb/>
vexed question of the French Shore, have been so far <lb/>
successful that there is now a prospect of its being <lb/>
arranged in a manner advantageous to both parties <lb/>
interested in it, and that the policy indicated in Lord <lb/>
Carnarvon's despatch of 7th December, 1866, has <lb/>
been so far modified that Your Excelleucy will now <lb/>
be enabled to issue Grants unier certain restrictions <lb/>
for Mining and other purposes in that locality. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The new statutory provisions which Your Excel<lb break="no"/>lency suggests, with regard to Licenses for Cutting <lb/>
Timber, shall receive our careful attention. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
We fully concur with Your Excellency that the <lb/>
time has now arrived for us to take action on the <lb/> 
great question of Confederation; and we can assume <lb/>
Your Excellency that we shall give our earnest <lb/>
attention to the consideration of or Union with the <lb/>
Dominion of Canada, or such fair and equitable <lb/>
        terms as may be <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> to serve the interests of <lb/>
the Colony, be approved of by the Government of the <lb/>
Dominion, and which we trust may prove acceptable <lb/>
to all classes of the people, when submitted to the <lb/>
constituencies, and also recieve the final approval <lb/>
and ratification of Her Majesty. <lb/></p>
        
<p>The Contract entered into by Your Excellency <lb/>
with Messrs. Inman &amp; Co., for the Conveyance of <lb/>
the Mails between St. John's and Halifax, has been <lb/>
so far carried out in a satisfactory manner. The new <lb/>
arrangement with regard to the detention of the <lb/>
Steamer St. John's has been a great conveniance <lb/>
to the Public, and the Boats are admirably suited to <lb/> 
the service. <lb/></p>

<p>
    Ordered that the adress be presented to his <lb/>
    Excellency the Governot by the speaker and the <lb/>
    whole House. <lb/>
</p>

<p>
    The hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL informed the <lb/>
    House that his Excellency would recieve the <lb/>
    Speaker and the whole House with the address on <lb/>
    Friday next, at 12 o'clock. <lb/>
</p>
    <p>
        The House adjourned until Friday, at 11 <lb/>
        o'clock. A.M. <lb/>
    </p>


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-07, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

<!--<p>- Fardar, Feb. 19­ <lb/>
The House met at 11 o'clock, A. M. <lb break="no"/>At 12 º'clock the SPzazzº aud the whole . <lb/>
House proceeded to Government House... <lb/>
presented to his Excellengy the address." reply; <lb/>
to his opening speech, and being returned, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>instead of $3,000, the ambie assuagd by the hoà. <lb/></p> 

<p>anaudan int. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºnformed the House that while º i <lb/></p> 

<p>* <lb/></p> 

<p>nce on his Excellency. the <lb/>
a º: House, he had pres <lb/>
jiency the aid. of thanks, is <lb/>
£xcelleney the made the follºwing <lb/>
Mr. Speaker º; Gentlemen of the a <lb/>
of Assembly. - <lb break="no"/>I receive your 'Address with much g <lb/>
am glad to be assured of approval oft <lb/>
by the Governº with regari to th <lb/>
nºtifying that G ment refief woul <lb/>
ºnfined to destitue widows and epha: <lb/>
and infirm poº. I am satisfied that s <lb/>
to this course is essential to the future <lb/>
the wholo community. it is the intere <lb/>
the duty, of all those who can render <lb/>
more necessitous of their fellow citizº <lb/>
...it the Government in their eſt. <lb/>
§ºlony of the vicious system which <lb/>
aralyzed all healthy energy. and so #. <lb/>
# prºdence among large numbers of it <lb/>
er Majesty's Government will lear <lb/>
tion that yºu are prepared to take, <lb/>
question of Uniºn with the Dominiu <lb/>
ºnd I have no doubt that Pºu will be <lb/>
sº terms of arrangement for tºpuſ. <lb/>
acceptable to the Government of the #2 <lb/>
ºnatºrially conducive to the interests of <lb/>
In this case the good sense of, the cºnſ. <lb/>
scarcely permit them to withold the <lb/>
such an arrangement; and its ratific <lb/>
Majesty may confidently be an icipate. <lb/>
Mr. Hyatt asked and ob lea <lb/>
for the remainder of the sessiº: <lb/>
The Hon. AtroſtNky G&amp;Sºłat. <lb/>
was sure that all had heard, with º: <lb/>
melancholy intelligeneº which had Î <lb/>
ceived,et the death of the H ºn. J AM <lb/>
All who knew him respected him. <lb/>
sº long time engaged in the busiuess <lb/>
and perhaps no where would his 1. <lb/>
ãº tº than in the locality whe <lb/>
S. res.ded. He had for many. Yº <lb/>
high public position, as * Legislativ <lb/>
and i. strict attention to his duties: <lb/>
the approbation of all liº (hou. A. <lb/>
that this House would testify its rest <lb/>
for his ºmily, by adjourning <lb/>
He therefore uoved that the 1 <lb/>
ru, out of respect to the me not <lb/>
L. C., of whose <lb/>
tºs ºust been received, and in token <lb/>
esteem in which the ºeuºsºl jº <lb/>
iºd, ºud of the sympathy ſult by tie­ <lb/>
his widow and family. <lb/>
Mr. Gies begged to second the <lb/>
1a non, Mr. Corinaek was a wºrk!' <lb/>
ºne whose lyss we must all deeply dº <lb/>
was but right that we siloui i thus i <lb/>
merits, and gay a triuute of respect <lb/>
tº ºry. <lb/>
T.s Hoa, Reservkº GENERAL <lb/>
plºts, d to see unsuºpºsiº" <lb/>
fouse to respect the tilemury ºf a gº <lb/>
had been alike all honor to his nº <lb/>
adopted country, in every relation 0: <lb/>
is "had beam placeu. He hºl <lb/>
honorable merchant, and had <lb/>
service to the people of , the <lb/>
which he had so loug resided, a <lb/>
a large columercial business. <lb/>
ais worth was well known, util...h6 <lb/>
fºrt and happiness anongst all a <lb/>
whom h9 would now be deeply. In <lb/>
political sphere lic had discarged tº <lb/>
tagly to himself. Ile (hon. Rºº..." <lb/>
self fast approaching the ", Herº inſi <lb/>
and thus he the mºre dueply lult til <lb/>
which the country Hul sustained, lº <lb/>
public inau and a good titº, winil. <lb/>
injuried the loss of a valued ind, ºt <lb/>
Mr. Hogsgrº fully participated in <lb/>
of nom, geuileiau. The duº of su <lb/>
ºne nor. James Gormack was a lo <lb/>
community at large lºl. <lb break="no"/>Mr. Fissºst migh, under ordid <lb/>
stances, not have given woº <lb/>
to clings which mig 't be *w <lb/>
'by slence, particularly *, * <lb/>
iſ which agº. gentlemen who had <lb/>
referred to the deceased gettle's <lb/>
had poculiar reasons for uut alloy <lb/>
sion to pass without exprº re! <lb/>
part to one, the rocollection of: <lb/>
associated with his earliest years, <lb/>
had ever possessed a warm it <lb/>
regard, and who, besides th; as <lb/>
private life, had been tor souey." <lb/>
ſue.mber in the cº-ordinate braudu <lb/>
lature, the Legislative Council, <lb/>
could therefore speak of the develº <lb/>
tleman, in both his public and priº <lb/>
of lite, from intim tº experience. <lb/>
ed both most worthily,and his gen <lb/>
urbane mauners, and liveral j <lb/>
him endeared and respected by all <lb/>
pleasure of his acqua at incº: For ti <lb/>
he (Mr. P.) could not do othº". <lb/>
open expressiou to his sympathy <lb/>
gºntinº, family, and public * <lb/>
memory of the deceased.: <lb/>
The House than adjourned unti <lb/>
3 o'clock, <lb/></p> 

<p>Mox DAY <lb/></p> 

<p>The IIouse met, and adjourue! <lb/>
atterward, to attend the tutºral ot, <lb/>
JAMES Cottºmack.: <lb/></p> 

<p>Úſt ſtufiml: <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOLIN'S <lb/>
WEDNESDAY, FEBRUARY <lb/>
rº­ <lb/>
Tar Government propositions as to <lb/>
which they think this colony should <lb/>
federation were introduced for discº <lb/>
mittee of the Assembly yesterday by <lb/>
torney General; Mr. Glen, the hon. <lb/>
Mr. Hog.ett followed, when the Com <lb/>
the debate was a journed to to-day. <lb/>
These torms (for which we have n <lb/>
tenao to-day), are in the first place <lb/>
nion Government shall defray &amp; sum <lb/>
our public exponditure, being the * <lb/>
penses of thoso departments of " <lb/>
assume contrºl, Governor, Judges <lb/>
Office, Light Houses, Surveyor Geni <lb/>
In addition to this sum of <lb/>
would be Assets applicable to local <lb/>
poses <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>