<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-06" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
    <title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-02-06">6 February 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-02-16"/>.
<date when="1865-02-20"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="2"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-16_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-20_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-20_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
    <change who="lyallg" when="2018-11-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-16_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-16_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-20_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-20_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-20_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-20_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-16_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    <fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <!-- GL, 2018-11-13, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day --> 

<!--<p>before the matter came to be fully discussed, to place it. <lb/>
before the public in a proper light sº that nº on: might, <lb/>
jºken at a disadvantage. Was it right that hon geº­ <lb/>
tlemen should endeavor to prejudice the public mind in <lb/>
tne way in which they had tried to do. They come in <lb/>
here with garbled statements—statements entirely incor­ <lb/>
*...* and in that not a shadow of foundation, fºr assertion, <lb/>
and omit to mention the all fishery naterials, such as <lb/>
fines, twines, nets, &amp;c., were admitted, duty free. They <lb/>
tell as that we should have called a public meeting. But <lb/>
there was no objection by them on their return, to go <lb/>
before the public. He (Mr. Shea) was responsible to no <lb/>
ºne but his constituency for his conduct; he was nºt ap­ <lb/>
pointed by the public, and he did not see how any injury <lb/>
ãould have resulted by reason of their not calling a pub­ <lb/>
lic meeting. We had no desire to force, the matter <lb/>
thus; we wanted the fillest investigation and we rightly <lb/>
deemed that the proper place for that investigation was <lb/>
this House, where face to face, and before the public the <lb/>
matter could be carafully and boldly enquired into. <lb/>
The public had nothing to do with what the delegates <lb/>
said at the Conference. They had to do with their <lb/>
Acts and nothing more. He insisted that some hon <lb/>
members had been there to witness the proceedings of <lb/>
that Conference; it would have done them good, they <lb/>
would have witnessed an exhibition of high tones, feel­ <lb/>
ing and patriotism, for which they would have been <lb/>
uttered unprepared. What other cause could have been <lb/>
adopted than the one pursued. These Resolutions would <lb/>
have been only waste paper without the signatures of the <lb/>
Telegates to authenticate them. Then we were to receive <lb/>
no manufactures from Canada because Canada imported <lb/>
largely from England herself. The arguanent was a <lb/>
false and unfounded one, As well might you say that <lb/>
we cant import from England because Englaid imports <lb/>
largely from France. He (Mr. Shea) knew of a manu­ <lb/>
factory at Toronto which actually imported chairs to <lb/>
England. Canada was great and rich in all the elemenis <lb/>
of meterial prosperity. It was a bad thing, to see mo­ <lb/>
ney so easily obtained here. It was an evidence of the <lb/>
unfortunate state of the country. We had great accumu­ <lb/>
lations of idle money and a deal of pauperism. When <lb/>
he (Mr. Shea) was in Canada he had been ashamed tº be <lb/>
compelled to state that we spent £20,000 in poor relief. <lb/>
We know pauperism to be incident to all places, but it <lb/>
was not paid out of the public money as it was done <lb/>
here. Had we not *e extreme wealth at one end pau­ <lb/>
perism at the other, and was a state things, which hon. <lb/>
genlemen would desire to perpetuate. The hon gentle­ <lb/>
man continued at great length, replying to each argument <lb/>
put forward by the hon member Mr. Renouf. <lb/>
On motion of Mr. Wyatt, the Committee rose, and <lb/>
the Chairman reported progress. To sit again on Mon­ <lb/>
day. -<lb break="maybe"/>#h. House then adjourned until Monday at three <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/>-->
    
    
<head rendition="simple:right">MONDAY, Feb. 6.</head>
    
    <p>
The House met at three o'clock.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName> presented a petition from George <lb/>
Bridle, Gaoler at Greenspond, which was received <lb/>
and read, praying for an increase of salary.</p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName>, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
table, would express a hope that its prayer would be <lb/>
favourably considered by the house. The petition<lb break="no"/>er's salary was altogether inadequate. </p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">The SURVEYOR GENERAL</persName> supported the prayer of <lb/>
the petition. It was gay a few years ago that he <lb/>
(Sur. Gen.) succeeded in securing the petitioner any <lb/>
salary as gaoler, although he had long discharged the <lb/>
duties. It was the smallest salary of any gaoler in <lb/>
the Island. He trusted he would be put on the <lb/>
same footing as the other outport gaolors.</p>
    
    <p>
Order that the petition lie on the table.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:PARS1">Mr. PARSONS</persName> presented a petition from Jacob <lb/>
Bradbury, of Torbay, which was received and read, <lb/>
praying for compensation for damage done to his <lb/>
house by lightning in August last.</p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:PARS1">Mr. PARSONS</persName>, in moving that the petition lie on <lb/>
the table, said the destruction of property by <choice><sic>light<lb break="no"/>ing</sic><corr>lightning</corr></choice> was of rare occurrence in this country. In this <lb/>
instance the property, which the petitioner had ac<lb break="no"/>cumulated by years of industry was suddenly destroy<lb break="no"/>ed by a visitation of providence. He (Mr. Parsons) <lb/>
trusted the house would make him some allowance, <lb/>
to enable him to retrieve his loss.</p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table.</p>
    
   <p> 
       <persName ref="pers:PARS1">Mr. PARSONS</persName> also presented petitions from James <lb/>
Brown and others, of Torbay, and from Jacob <lb/>
Bradbury and others, of the same place, which were <lb/>
severally received and read, praying for grants to <lb/>
open and complete roads in these localities.</p>
    
    
    <p>
Ordered that these petitions lie on the table.</p>
    
    <p>
On motion of <persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName>, pursuant to order <choice><sic>o</sic><corr>on</corr></choice> <lb/>
the day, the house resolved itslf into Committee of <lb/>
the whole, on the further consideration of the address <lb/>
in reply to his Excellency's speech, Mr. KNIGHT in <lb/>
the chair.</p>
    
<p>    
<persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Mr. E. D. SHEA</persName> said he had listened with a good <lb/>
deal of attention to the observations of the gentlemen <lb/>
who differed from him on the subject of confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, as he was desirous of discovering what their <lb/>
objections were, and whether they had any weight, <lb/>
that he might modify the opinions he had already <lb/>
formed, if he found himself in any degree mistaken. <lb/>
But he had heard nothing to induce him to modify <lb/>
his views. In saying that, he did not attribute to <lb/>
these hon. members any lack of zeal and energy in <lb/>
the discussion of that question. They had laboured <lb/>
hard to find arguments in support of their views, <lb/>
only it appeared to him that they expended so much <lb/>
labour in the endeavour to make the worse appear <lb/>
the better reason. He (Mr. Shea) believed the <lb/>
more that question was discussed, the more would <lb/>
public opinion be influenced in its favour. He had <lb/>
observed a good deal of inconsistency in the observa<lb break="no"/>tions of hon members in opposition to that measure. <lb/>
They asserted at one time that Canada desired to <lb/>
get held of us that she might victimise us for her <lb/>
own ends, and then that Canada thought of us at the <lb/>
eleventh hour. If the latter assertion was the correct <lb/>
one, it showed how really indifferent Canada was <lb/>
whether we joined in the confederation or not. Then <lb/>
it had been urged that the securities of Canada are <lb/>
depressed, while ours are at a premium, from which <lb/>
it was inferred Canada is not in a sound financial <lb/>
condition. But it did not follow, because money <lb/>
was in demand in a country, and the rate of interest <lb/>
high, that it was not in a prosperous condition. The <lb/>
very reverse was frequently the case. It by no <lb/>
means indicated a sound state of the money market, <lb/>
that the rate of interest was low. What was the <lb/>
present state of the labour market in this colony? <lb/>
Why 400 able bodied men were at present employed <lb/>
by the Board of Works at 6s a week, paid in provi<lb break="no"/>sions. Why was that? Because there was no de<lb break="no"/>mand for labour; and the same rule which applied <lb/>
to labour applied with equal force to the state of the <lb/>
money market. Then the hon. member for St. <lb/>
John's East, Mr. Parsons, told us not to be anxious <lb/>
about our defence from foreign aggression, for <lb/>
England and France had such a deep interest in the <lb/>
protection of this, country, that they would see to <lb/>
our defence. He (Mr. Shea) did not see hoy we <lb/>
could have much confidence in the protection of <lb/>
France. It seemed to him to be somewhat like the lamb <lb/>
relying on the wolf for protection. We paid a large <lb/>
sum annually for the protection of our fisheries against <lb/>
French encroachments, and why should we do this, <lb/>
if the French felt such a deep interest in us? And <lb/>
a few years ago we were in great excitement on ac<lb break="no"/>count of a convention between England and France <lb/>
on the subject of our Fisheries, by which our inter<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>
        
ests were sacrificed to France; and now the hon. <lb/>
member told us to rely upon the protection of <lb/>
France. Again, it was said that while the supporters <lb/>
of confederation spoke of the openings in Canada <lb/>
for their children, they had no regard to the interests of <lb/>
the fishermen's children. If we regarded the present <lb/>
state of our operative population, they would ap<lb break="no"/>pear to have the deepest interest in that ques<lb break="no"/>tion. What had our legislation been for several <lb/>
years past, but unsuccessful efforts to raise the la<lb break="no"/>bouring classes from their depressed condition? <lb/>
And what had we accomplished but to join with the <lb/>
Receiver General in Jeremiads over the distressed <lb/>
state of the country, without being able to strike out <lb/>
anything to relieve the general distress? We have <lb/>
now come to such a state of depression that we can <lb/>
proceed no further, and it was our solemn duty to <lb/>
consider whether this proposed confederation offer<lb break="no"/>ed any means of relieving the people. No mat<lb break="no"/>ter that the feelings of those whose interests were <lb/>
involved in this discussion were excited against the <lb/>
measure, still it was our duty to enter earnestly into <lb/>
its consideration. It looked to him as a providential <lb/>
interposition that these calamities had come upon us, <lb/>
as if to force us to look beyond precarious fisheries <lb/>
with the view of finding some means of relieving the <lb/>
general distress; and that federation seemed to meet <lb/>
    the case. What was the state of the country at <lb/>
present? Why a third of our population are not <lb/>
half fed. What did we see in our streets? Those <lb/>
who once were in comfortable circumstances reduc<lb break="no"/>ed to the deepest, penury, suffering from that want <lb/>
which blanches the cheek, palsies the limbs, and <lb/>
makes the young suddenly old. And we <lb/>
were told to rely upon our fisheries to remedy <lb/>
this. We had relied upon them from year to year, and <lb/>
our circumstances were becoming worse. Some years <lb/>
we had good fisheries, but the good was not so much <lb/>
to the fishermen as to the capitalists who realized <lb/>
fortunes out of the fisheries and then left the coun<lb break="no"/>try. He (Mr. Shea) did not blame them for leav<lb break="no"/>ing a country in which there was such frequent and <lb/>
deep destitution. He merely referred to the fact and <lb/>
system, if system it might be called. Our fisheries <lb/>
at their best were only sufficient to keep the heads <lb/>
of the labouring people over water for the season in <lb/>
which they were productive, experience had shown <lb/>
they left to the sons of toil ao permanent fruit. <lb/>
Again, they had not kept pace with the progress of po<lb break="no"/>pulation,and that was the difficulty we had to meet. <lb/>
We want other employment for our people besides the <lb/>
fisheries. Would confederation give such employment? <lb/>
He (Mr. Shea) believed it would. One of its first <lb/>
results would be a line of weekly steamers between <lb/>
this port and one in Canada. These steamers must <lb/>
cause an increase of trade, which would give in<lb break="no"/>creased employment; and anything that gave in<lb break="no"/>creased employment must benefit the people gener<lb break="no"/>ally. It would also put an end to our isolation, <lb/>
and with increased <choice><sic>interconrse</sic><corr>intercourse</corr></choice> would come the <lb/>
opening up of new resources and an increase of our <lb/>
trade. It was said that we wished to drive the peo<lb break="no"/>ple from the country. No such thing. We wish to <lb/>
make the country worth their living in; to provide <lb/>
employment for the labouring classes, and <lb/>
so to promote their comfort as to make <lb/>
the country worth calling their home. What <lb/>
do we find now? That many of our best fish<lb break="no"/>ermen and mechanics are fleeing the country. The <lb/>
only part of the country from which we did not at <lb/>
present hear the wall of distress, was that where a <lb/>
in market was created by reciprocity with the United <lb/>
States; and in the prospect of the free trade treaty <lb/>
being abrogated, it behoved us to endea<lb break="no"/>vour to secure a new vent for our exports <lb/>
in lieu of that trade. The only means by which <lb/>
we could see our pauperism put an end to <lb/>
was by providing increased employment for our peo<lb break="no"/>ple, and extended markets for our produce. Could <lb/>
we retain our people permanently if they could bet<lb break="no"/>ter their circumstances by leaving the country? Large <lb/>
numbers were leaving, and many of those who re<lb break="no"/>named did so because they had not the means of go<lb break="no"/>ing away. If the Government were to charter two <lb/>
or three vessels to carry emigrants to Canada or <lb/>
Nova Scotia, they would have applications from <lb/>
more than they could accommodate. Again, with <lb/>
regard to the educated classes. There was no field <lb/>
for many of them here; and under confederation <lb/>
they would find a fine field in such a growing commu<lb break="no"/>nity as that of Canada. But it was said why not go <lb/>
there now? They would be regarded only as aliens. <lb/>
But with confederation of the Provinces we would <lb/>
become one people, and with our representatives in <lb/>
both houses of the Federal Legislature, they would <lb/>
have influential friends whose aid they would be en<lb break="no"/>titled to rely upon to forward their views. A fur<lb break="no"/>ther effect of confederation would be to allay those <lb/>
ascerbities of religious and political differences, which <lb/>
were the bane, of small communities. Our public <lb/>
men would have larger questions to grapple with, <lb/>
and in the choice of representatives to the federal <lb/>
parliament, talent and integrity would be regarded <lb/>
more than creed or faction. But it was said by hon. <lb/>
gentlemen beside him that confederation might suit <lb/>
the other colonies, but that it was unsuitable for us. <lb/>
They say that Archbishop Connolly's letter had no <lb/>
reference to our circumstances, and was unsuitable <lb/>
for Newfoundland, although it might be very well <lb/>
for Nova Scotia and New Brunswick. If these gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen were at liberty to quote Nova Scotia newspa<lb break="no"/>pers of little or no influence, got up metely to set <lb/>
forth the views of interested parties opposed to con<lb break="no"/>federation, why might not we quote the opinions of <lb/>
so distinguished and talented a Prelate as Arch<lb break="no"/>bishop Connolly? And if confederation would bene<lb break="no"/>fit Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, why would it <lb/>
not also benefit us? But he (Mr. Shea) maintained <lb/>
it would benefit us still more. These countries were <lb/>
prosperous now, while we were the reverse. We <lb/>
had the same need of protection that they had, and <lb/>
we had the sad necessities of our people besides. And <lb/>
if the opinions of Archbishop Connolly were not to be <lb/>
quoted here, what would hon, gentlemen say to the <lb/>
opinions of Dr. Mullock? They could not say <lb/>
that they were not applicable to our circumstances, <lb/>
and he was most favourable to confederation.— </p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CASE2">Mr. CASEY</persName>—You have no right to introduce the <lb/>
name of the Rt. Rev. Dr. Mullock here.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Mr. SHEA</persName>.—His opinion is already published, <lb/>
and he has no objection to his name being <lb/>

<cb/>
    

the continuance of the troops, for there was no de<lb break="no"/>sire on the part of the Imperial Government to with<lb break="no"/>draw them, if we only evinced a wish to adopt such <lb/>
measures as would aid in the defence of the coun<lb break="no"/>try. Did we not know that the people of England, <lb/>
of all parties, looked favourably on confederation, as <lb/>
that which would raise us into national importance? <lb/>
It was a foregone conclusion with the Imperial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, as was evident from Mr. Cardwell's dis<lb break="no"/>patch. What was the reception of Mr. Brown the <lb/>
other day, when he went home from Canada? He <lb/>
was visited and feted by the highest in the land, <lb/>
by many to whom he was previously unknown, and <lb/>
who would have been unacquainted with him for a <lb/>
long time to come, had he not represented the idea <lb/>
of Confederation. Now he (Mr. Shea) would ask, <lb/>
what condition we should be in if we remain <lb/>
in our isolation, and a French convention were again <lb/>
to be entered into? Would we be in a condition to <lb/>
claim the assistance of the confederated provinces? <lb/>
Or could we unaided successfully oppose the in<lb break="no"/>fluence of France with the Imperial Government? <lb/>
These were serious considerations. They were con<lb break="no"/>siderations which we could not afford lightly to dis<lb break="no"/>miss. His (Mr. Shea's) belief was that the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of Confederation would sooner or later be forced <lb/>
upon us. We might stave it off for a time. But the <lb/>
tendency of the age was for the union of small states <lb/>
into larger ones. It was said we proposed to give <lb/>
up our self government. We gave up nothing worth <lb/>
retaining. Self-government was the best system we <lb/>
could have, but it would not make up for short fish<lb break="no"/>eries and a starving population. We would still <lb/>
have self-government on a larger scale, for we were <lb/>
to have a voice in the General Government and <lb/>
Legislature of the union in proportion to our <lb/>
population, while, our local government for <lb/>
merely local affairs was to be as much our <lb/>
own as now. We were told that we gave up <lb/>
our fisheries to be legislated for by Canada. But <lb/>
the fisheries were still to be under local control, by <lb/>
a special stipulation, while their protection would be <lb/>
effectually carried out under the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. It was said we gave up our Crown lands and <lb/>
mines. We merely gave up the right of legislating <lb/>
for them, in return for a valuable consideration. We <lb/>
received £37,500 a year for them. Much had been <lb/>
said about out mineral wealth; but of what value <lb/>
were our mines, while they were not worked? And <lb/>
was it not well known that we had neither capital nor <lb/>
enterprise to work them? And when we were of<lb break="no"/>fered such a valuable consideration for them by par<lb break="no"/>ties who had both capital and enterprise, would it not <lb/>
be folly to decline such an advantageous offer?— <lb/>
Could it be doubted that the Federal Government, <lb/>
which proposed to pay such a price for our Crown <lb/>
lands and mines, would be induced to improve them, <lb/>
in order to have a return for their outlay?</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. Renouf</persName>.-We would not receive as much from <lb/>
the Federal government as we would be called upon <lb/>
to pay. Our Customs duties would amount to £140,<lb break="no"/>000 a year, while we would only receive altogether <lb/>
£112,000.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Mr. E. D. SHEA</persName>.—The hon member assumed that <lb/>
the present Canadian tariff would be retained by the <lb/>
Federal Government. Now we had the assurance <lb/>
of Lord Monck, as well as of Mr. Galt that the Can<lb break="no"/>adian tariff would not be that of the Confederation, <lb/>
but a reduced tariff. Our present revenue, for years <lb/>
past, had been only from £90,000 <choice><sic>ta</sic><corr>to</corr></choice> £100,000, and <lb/>
we were to receive £112,000. But supposing we <lb/>
should have the Canadian tariff, it did not follow <lb/>
that the revenue should increase in accordance with <lb/>
the increased duties levied. Assuming that we are <lb/>
paying 13 per cent now, and that the duties should <lb/>
be raised to 15 per cent, what was that compared <lb/>
with what our people are suffering now? We were <lb/>
suffering taxation in its worst shape, the taxation of <lb/>
pauperism. As to an increase from 13 to 15 per<lb break="no"/>cent.. what was that, if the country were rendered suf<lb break="no"/>ficiently prosperous to bear it? Let us have another <lb/>
        year or two of such fisheries as we have had for <lb/>
several years past, and no other resource opened up <lb/>
for the employment of our people, or for the enter<lb break="no"/>prise of our merchants, and what taxation should we <lb/>
be able to pay? Taxation was a relative con<lb break="no"/>sideration—it will be heavy or otherwise, ac<lb break="no"/>cording to the ability of our people to endure it. <lb/>
We were now taxed over 13 percent upon the whole of <lb/>
our duty-paying imports, and what did we get out of it? <lb/>
Only the defraying of our civil expenditure and the <lb/>
support of our poor; and the poor were not half fed, <lb/>
and it could not be otherwise, while we had such ina<lb break="no"/>dequate means of relief. And we had also to consider <lb/>
the deterioration, moral and physical, that must <lb/>
result from this perpetuated pauperism—trans<lb break="no"/>mitting not alone its inherent debasement and <lb/>
demoralization, but the worst bodily diseases that <lb/>
could afflict a people. We had not had a road grant <lb/>
worth naming for years past; but he must remind <lb/>
the house that under confederation we would have <lb/>
an annual road grant of from £12,000 to £15,000, <lb/>
which would be under the control of the local gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and Legislature, and would not be liable as <lb/>
now to be given, withheld or reduced according as we <lb/>
had successful fisheries or the reverse. This itself <lb/>
would be a permanent source of employment for a <lb/>
number of our people, which would not be subject to <lb/>
curtailment at the time they would most require it. <lb/>
He (Mr. Shea) did not know that there would be <lb/>
any increase of taxation. He saw nothing to induce <lb/>
him to believe that there would be any necessity to <lb/>
have any material increase. Hon gentlemen antici<lb break="no"/>pated that we would be under the necessity of having <lb/>
recourse to direct taxation on property in the island. <lb/>
But were not proprietors worse taxed now,in the de<lb break="no"/>privation of those rents which the depressed circum<lb break="no"/>stances of many of our people rendered them unable <lb/>
to pay? If we should have the Canadian tariff, under <lb/>
confederation, the area of taxation would be nar<lb break="no"/>rowed, because we would have a considerable impor<lb break="no"/>tation of the manufactures of Canada, of wedlens, lea<lb break="no"/>ther and other articles which would come in duty <lb/>
free. Hon members might sneer at that, but we know <lb/>
that in Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, where they <lb/>
knew the manufacturing capabilities of Canada better <lb/>
than we do, it was made an argument against Con<lb break="no"/>federation that they would be flooded with Canadian <lb/>
manufactures, to the injury of their own. To listen <lb/>
to the objections to confederation urged by some hon <lb/>
members, one would suppose that Newfoundland was <lb/>

urged to come into the confederation because we <lb/>
 were so important that they could not get on without <lb/>
        
us. He (Mr Shea).did not depreciate our resources. <lb/>
Our fisheries were the most important, the position of <lb/>
the Island also, as the key to the Gulf and to the <lb/>
river St. Lawrence was of great value as a strategic <lb/>
position in the event of war. But the world could, <lb/>
however, get on without us —and so could the con<lb break="no"/>federation. He had lately read some observations <lb/>
in a Canada newspaper, in which it was stated that <lb/>
Newfoundland had made an excellent bargain, but if <lb/>
we were dissatisfied with it, we might remain out of <lb/>
the Confederation. Hon gentlemen said they were <lb/>
dissatisfied with confederation; but if they rejected <lb/>
that, what would they suggest to better the condition <lb/>
of our people? </p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CASE2">Mr. CASEY</persName>-Better legislation than we had of late <lb/>
years.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Mr. E. D. SHEA</persName>-Would any legislation of ours <lb/>
give food to the people or find then employment? <lb/>
He did not desire to press the final decision of the <lb/>
question this sesson. Let the constituents, by all <lb/>
    
    
<cb/>

means, be sonsulted; but before we call on them for <lb/>
their opinions, let hon members express their own ; <lb/>
and let the country give the final verdict upon them. <lb/>
He thought that was the right course, and that any<lb break="no"/>thing short of it would be a shirking of the question <lb/>
We were here to deliberate, and not as mere dele<lb break="no"/>gates. As to what was the duty of members to their <lb/>
constituents, he would quote the opinion of Burke, <lb/>
whose opinions on constitutional questions were ad<lb break="no"/>mitted by, all parties to be entitled to the greatest <lb/>
weight, Here the hon member quoted from a speech <lb/>
by Burke to his constituents at Bristol, as follows:­</p>
    
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>
"It ought to be the happiness and glory of a repre<lb break="no"/>sentative, to live in the strictest union, the closest <lb/>
correspondence, and the most unreserved communica<lb break="no"/>tion with his constituents. Their wishes ought to <lb/>
have great weight with him, their opinions high re<lb break="no"/>spect, their business unremitting attention. It is his <lb/>
duty to sacrifice his repose, his pleasures, his satis<lb break="no"/>factions, to theirs; and above all, to prefer their inter<lb break="no"/>ests to his own. But his unbiassed opinion, his mature <lb/>
judgment, his enlightened conscience, he ought not to <lb/>
sacrifice to any man, or to any set of men living. <lb/>
These he does not derive from your pleasure; no, nor <lb/>
from the law and the constitution. They are a trust <lb/>
from Providence, for the abuse of which he is deeply <lb/>
answerable. Your representative owes you, not his <lb/>
industry only, but his judgment, and he betrays, in<lb break="no"/>stead of serving you, if he sacrifices it to your opinion." </p>
    </quote>
    
    <p>
It was our duty as representatives to give our Constitu<lb break="no"/>ents the benefit of our judgment; and they <choice><sic>wound</sic><corr>would</corr></choice> af<lb break="no"/>terwards exercise their judgment upon their represen<lb break="no"/>tatives, and reject us, if they were not satisfied with <lb/>
our conduct. The question was prejudged by some <lb/>
hon. members, and it was our duty to express our de<lb break="no"/>liberate opinion upon it, after that cool and calm con<lb break="no"/>sideration which its importance to the country, to its <lb/>
people, and to those who would come after us impera<lb break="no"/>tively demanded. Let no hon. member shrink from <lb/>
the responsibility of his position. Let all speak out <lb/>
in the face of the country and let the constituencies<lb/>
afterwards say whether they will accept or reject the <lb/>
terms of the proposed Confederation.</p>
    
    <p rendition="simple:centre">
        (<hi rendition="simple:italic">To be continued</hi>.)</p> 


    <!-- GL, 2018-11-13, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 
    
    
<!--<p>LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL, <lb/></p> 

<p>Monday, February 13. <lb/>
The House met at 4 o'clock. <lb/>
Hon N. STABB laid on the table of the house the: <lb/>
following documents— <lb/>
Estimate for defraying part of the public expendi­ <lb/>
ture of the colony for 1865. <lb/>
Statement showing the aggregate amount of the <lb/></p> 

<p>public debt of the colony on the 31st December, 1834, <lb/></p> 

<p>and the years in which the several portions of it are <lb/>
repayable. <lb/>
Financial statement of the affairs of the colony for <lb/>
the year 1865. <lb/>
Consoliuated account current of the receipts and <lb/>
payments for the year ended 31st December, 1864. .. <lb/>
Detailed statement of salaries of Stipendiary Mugis­ <lb/>
trates, Clerks of the Peace, Constables and Jailors in. <lb/>
the outports. <lb/>
Hon. P. G. TESSIER presented a petition from the <lb/>
Cºmmercial Society of St. John's, an important and <lb/>
influential body, he said, representing the greater <lb/>
portion of the trad ng interests of the colony, and en­ <lb/>
titled to the fullest cºnsideration at the hands of the: <lb/>
legislature. The object of this petition was to pray <lb/>
this honorable house that when the subject of the <lb/>
Confederation of the Colonies comes before it for de­ <lb/>
liberation, it will not take definite action upon the: <lb/>
matter until such information shall have been obtain­ <lb/>
ed as will clearly demonstrate that it would be to the <lb/>
advantage of Newfoundland to euter into the proposed. <lb/>
Colonial Union. He should merely present the Peti­ <lb/>
tion, that it be ſaid upon the table of the house. <lb/>
ORDER OF THE DAY. <lb/>
Hon. R. J. PINsent notice to move, <lb/>
First—That for Newfoundland to enter into a Con­ <lb/>
federation of the British North American Colonies <lb/>
upon the terms proposed in the Report of the Q lebec. <lb/>
Conference, would be detrimentil to the best interests <lb/>
of the colony, and ought to be resisted. <lb/>
Second,-That a humble Address be presented to her <lb/>
Majesty, embodying the views of the Legislative Coun­ <lb/>
cil upon this subject, with their reasons for the adop­ <lb/>
tion of those views. <lb/>
Third-That a select committee of this house bs. <lb/>
appointed to prepare the said Address, <lb/>
Hon. R. J. PINSENT said, that as the hon gentleman <lb/>
§. Tessier) has just presented a petition from the <lb/>
Sommercial Society, a most important and influential <lb/>
body, upon the same subject and of a similar character <lb/>
to that emoraced in his (Mr. P's) notice of motion,and <lb/>
as a rule of the house prevents the reading of that <lb/>
petition, or any action being taken on it to-day, he <lb/>
(Mr. P.) would not proceed with his motion, but pass, <lb/>
it over for the present. He did not desire that a <lb/>
question of so much momen:ous concern should be: <lb/>
entered into until it had received the fullest consider­ <lb/>
ation before hand; and when we shall have heard this <lb/>
petition read, and more deliberately examined the <lb/>
documents relating to the matter, we may be in a <lb/>
better position to discuss it. There can be no doubt. <lb/>
that the feeling of a large majority of the people was <lb/>
opposed to the terms of the proposed confederation, as <lb/>
regards this colony, and he must express his own opin­ <lb/>
ion that they were highly objectionable in many material <lb/>
respects. The motive, then, which prompted him <lb/>
(Mr. P.) to move in the muter was that this view <lb/>
might be expressed by the Council, and the reasons <lb/>
for it made known by address to the Jimperial Gov­ <lb/>
frnment. The decision of this house upon such reso­ <lb/>
lutions as he(Mr. P.) had given notice of would not. <lb/>
affect the main question of confederation or non-con­ <lb/>
federation, but would go to point out the salient fea<lb break="no"/>tures of objection to it, in the form in which it has <lb/>
been offered to us. He presumed it would not be <lb/>
denied that this house has an independent right to de­ <lb/>
clare its opinions upon public questions, irrespective <lb/>
of outside influences of any kind, and it was not <lb/>
bound to await the result of action in any quarter. <lb/>
We have no constituencies to consult, no country to: <lb/>
appeal to, to regulate the course of action we should <lb/>
pursue, and are consequently in a position to give an <lb/>
untrammelled opinion on questions of a public char­ <lb/>
acter. Hon. members of this bouse possess con­ <lb/>
siderable stake in the country, and are deeply inter­ <lb/>
ested in its present and future welfare; and being <lb/>
unswayed by personal or party motives in their legis­ <lb/>
lative action, it was only just to expect from them a <lb/>
dispassionate consideration of such important sub­ <lb/>
jects as this. However, as the petitiou just presented <lb/>
confirms what appears to be the general view, that <lb/>
anything like decisive action upºn it should be delay: <lb/>
ed, he would not press his motion, but await until the: <lb/>
matter has received more ample consideration. <lb/>
Hon E. MoRBIs—Do you mean to let it staad upon <lb/>
the minutes? <lb/>
Hon. R. PINSENT—Yes, for the present. <lb break="no"/>Hon. E. Morals—It does seem a most extraordin <lb/>
ary proceeding. And notwithstanding the hon and-\-<lb break="yes"/>learned gentlemau's statement, the resolutions on that <lb/>
notice aſ motion do not in the smalles, degree corres­ <lb/>
pond witn the petition just presented to a the Cordº <lb/>
mercial, Society. The merchanis' petition was, * <lb/>
reasunable, a moderatº, and molest one, aid torned 2. <lb/>
marked contrast to the spirit and claracter of tae Iloils­ <lb/></p> 

<p>gentleman's no:ice of motion,-one of the most Prº* <lb/></p> 

<p>. <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>ſ <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/>
tºl <lb/>
| <lb/>
g <lb/>
i <lb/>
| <lb/>
# <lb/>
t . <lb/>
: 1 <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/>
<lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>tuous proceedings he <lb/>
: ...?the country. He <lb/>
that the hon and learned g <lb/>
contrary to his usual correct <lb/>
objectionable a notice befor <lb/>
thought the house would be r <lb/>
dignity and its honor did it a <lb/>
to pass unnoticed; The hon <lb/>
can't forget that he was chair <lb/>
mittee appointed to prepare t <lb/>
his Excelleney the Governor, <lb/>
up that Address; and what d <lb/>
ºe consideraion of the Conf. <lb/>
Hon R. J.PINSENT-There <lb/>
chair, and there is no necessit <lb/>
Hón E. MoRRIS-You are <lb/>
the matter so easily as you in <lb/>
Hon. the PRESIDENT-I <lb/>
learned gentleman withdrew h <lb/>
Hon E. MoRRIS-No, he <lb/>
intention to pos pone it, and <lb/>
oring to prove the moderate: <lb/>
Jailing of the shelter of the n <lb/>
out of the dilemma into which <lb/>
plunged him by this opportu <lb/>
paragraph of the Address w <lb/>
quote: when interrupted, run: <lb/>
"The question of Confederal <lb/>
ican Colonies is one which hal <lb/>
been submitted for our consis: <lb/>
the further information with <lb/>
to be furnish;d, and we assu <lb/>
we shall approach the conside <lb/>
of the Report of the Delegat <lb/>
Jency refers, impressed with t <lb/>
the proposition, and in a sp <lb/>
and careful enquiry" <lb/>
–Coad any thing be imagin <lb/>
assurance of the house to his <lb/>
that the snbject should be ap <lb/>
ealm consideration and car <lb/>
hasty manner in which the h <lb/>
with this rash and ill-judged <lb/>
actually handed in on the san <lb/>
apers having reference to th <lb/>
were laid upon the table, an <lb/>
were printed for the use of ho <lb/>
thing but complimentary to t <lb/>
rtedly, and he (Mr M.) felt tº <lb/>
construed into a compiiment <lb/>
Governor, after the deliberate <lb/>
that it would examine the qu <lb/>
fully. Now, if the hon an <lb/>
reconsider his proceeding in t <lb/>
thought he would, by consu <lb/>
corum of the Chamber, be <lb/>
notice from the record book, <lb/>
quite sure that the hon gentl <lb/>
never would, bring it forwar <lb/>
being fully aware of the aver <lb/>
munity upon the subject. <lb/>
Hon. the l'iteside.NF-I] <lb/>
however this discussion is irr <lb/>
Hon. E. Morris—Then w <lb/>
to remain on the minutes P. <lb/>
Hon R. J. PINSENT rose: <lb/>
he had not expected, when h <lb/>
to postpone his motion, that <lb/>
Morris, would have started <lb/>
mor so readily have rushed in <lb/>
and unnecessary. It was <lb/>
(Mr.P.) after simply express <lb/>
the subject matter of the not <lb/>
desire to postpone it in con <lb/>
appeared to prevail in the C <lb/>
it would be advisable to allow <lb/>
tunity for consideration of tº <lb/>
to any thing approaching a <lb/>
view has received further co­ <lb/>
tation of the Commercial Si <lb/>
the hon gentleman is so sent <lb/>
dignity of the house as h. <lb/>
aurely it would not have t <lb/>
from him a display of a little <lb/>
has exhibited on this occasi. <lb/>
He (Mr. P.), believed the re. <lb/>
show that he (Mr P.) had a <lb/>
spirit towards hon members <lb/>
agree with them: but the sa <lb/>
be pointed at to prove that <lb/>
sions did agitate the Cham! <lb/>
man who is now so ready to <lb/>
tion frcm the honor and dig. <lb/>
prominent part in them. The <lb/>
and te (Mr P.), did not des <lb/>
them now. He (Mr P.) on <lb/>
hon gentlenºan should hesita <lb/>
censor to his brother member <lb/>
cffice that did not suit him, <lb/>
becoming grace. Ile (Mlr P <lb/>
he was delighted to see that <lb/>
be inspired by the infusion <lb/>
and the house may at letst t <lb/>
of mution as being the unex <lb/>
from that usual insipidity <lb/>
character of our debates. I <lb/>
that the hon gentleman's (M <lb/>
oratorical powers are again i <lb/>
that hon gentleiman is disp, <lb/>
(Mr P) was prepared to take <lb/>
him in the discussion of this <lb/>
Inay choose: <lb/>
Hon. E. MoRRI5 would r. <lb/>
man's proceeding, without br <lb/>
the house. If those resolutiº <lb/>
and the question disposed of <lb/>
templated by the hon Gentlet <lb/>
to compromise the house and <lb/>
Hon. the PRE8ident.—'t <lb/>
of order. Hon Gentlemen tr <lb/>
tunity to discuss the questio <lb/>
5688 lon. <lb/>
Hon. N. STABB, in reply t <lb/>
before the house a return st <lb/>
importa ſur 1863, and the at <lb/>
thereon, with a comparative <lb/>
amount of duties said import <lb/>
to iſ levied under the Canad <lb/>
The house then adjourned <lb/></p> 

<p>Holloway's Oint MENT . <lb/>
of Hope.—If there be one de <lb/>
ledge superior to all others <lb/>
means of preserving or re <lb/>
which existeace is a mocker <lb/>
loway's twin medicaments s <lb/>
tum. In all diseases they <lb/>
purify the blood, from whicn <lb/>
must inevitably be renewed. <lb/>
friction, relaxes, penetrates, <lb/>
lating aad wholesome influe <lb/>
lying organs. In this way <lb/>
and kidneys, can be effective <lb/>
ed, especially if Holloway' <lb/>
taken to aid in thework of pu <lb/></p> 

<p>SAFE AND SubE.—You c. <lb/>
neither time nur sickness <lb/>
you use MR. S. A. Allex <lb/>
and Zylooalsamum, or Hair <lb/>
equalled for restoring. invi <lb/>
dressing the hair. Every 1, <lb/>
Dearin, Sole Agent for N. <lb/></p> 

<p>dºmes <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-20_Page_1.jpg"/> 

<fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER</fw>
    
    <fw type="dateline">St. John's, Monday, February, 20, 1865.</fw>
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    
    <!-- GL, 2018-11-13, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day --> 
    
    
<!--<p>Notices. <lb/></p> 

<p>-<lb break="maybe"/><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Mothers . . Mothers: ": <lb/>
procure Mrs. WINSLow's Soothin <lb/>
ºr children teething. This valuable <lb/>
the prescription of one of the best <lb/>
and nurses in the United States; it <lb/>
for thirty years with never failing­ <lb/>
ess by millions of mothers and chi­ <lb/>
feeble infant of one week old to the <lb/>
only relieves the child from pain, but <lb/>
stomach and bowels, corrects acidity, <lb/>
and energy to the whole system. It <lb/>
intly relieve Griping in the Bowels and <lb/>
He believe it the best and surest remedy <lb/>
all cases of Dissentery and Diarhoea in <lb/>
ºr it arises from teething or any other <lb/>
rections for use will accompany each <lb/>
renuine unless the fac-simile of Curtis <lb/>
the outside wrapper. Price only 25 <lb/>
. Sold by all Medicine Dealers. Office, <lb/>
New York, and 205 High Holborn <lb/></p> 

<p>d. <lb/>
*S. WINSLOW, <lb/></p> 

<p>Nurse and Female Physician, presents <lb/>
of mothers, her Soothing Syrup for <lb/>
g, which greatly facilitates the process <lb/>
oftening the gums, reducing all infia­ <lb/>
ay all pain and spasmodic action, and <lb/>
ite the bowels. Depend upon it, mo <lb/>
ce rest to yourselves, and relief and <lb/>
nfants. We have put up and sold this <lb/>
hirty years, and can say, in confidence <lb/>
hat we have never boea able to say <lb/>
licine—never has it failed in a single <lb/>
: a cure, when timely used. Never <lb/>
instance of dissatisfaction by any one <lb/>
in the contrary, all speak delighted <lb/>
ins, and speaks in terms of commenda­ <lb/>
cal effects and medical virtues. We <lb/>
itter "what we do now," after thirty <lb/>
e. and pledge our reputation for the <lb/>
at we here declare. In almost every <lb/>
he infant is suffering from pair and <lb/>
ef will be found in fifteen or twenty <lb/>
e syrup is administered. Full direc­ <lb/>
will accompany each bottle. None <lb/>
the fac—simile of Curtis and Perkins, <lb/>
n the outside wrapper. Sold by Drug­ <lb/>
t the world. Piincipal Office, 48 Dey <lb/>
d 205 High Holborn, England. Price <lb/>
er bottle. <lb/>
is an extract from a letter written by <lb/>
olme, Pastor of the Pierrepont-street <lb/>
Brooklyn, NY, to the "Journal and <lb/>
ncinnati, O., and speaks volumes in <lb/>
orld-renowned medicine, Mrs. WINS­ <lb/>
Syrup for Children Teethink—"...We <lb/>
-mºnt in your c lumns of Mrs. Wins­ <lb/>
syrup. Now we never said a word in <lb/>
ºnt medicane before in our life, but we <lb/>
o say 'to your readers that this is no <lb/>
ºve tried it, and know it to he all i <lb/>
probably one of the most successful <lb/>
e day, because it is one of the best <lb/>
our readers who have babies can't do <lb/>
in a supply." <lb/>
J. DEARIN, St. John's, <lb/>
Agent for Newfoundiand. <lb/>
HOEN LX FA 1: E <lb/></p> 

<p>-\- *, w 4. <lb/>
ance Čoſſipaay. <lb/>
treet and Charing Cross, London. • <lb/>
STA BLISH ſº D–1782 <lb/>
RUSTFE8 an I DreecroftS. <lb/>
n, Esq. (Kirkman D. Hodg on Esq. <lb/>
9, " James Horne. -\-<lb break="maybe"/>|wiſham J. Lancaster, * <lb/>
|John D. Alaxen, -\-<lb break="maybe"/>J.,hn Masternan, Esq. M. P. <lb/>
John Timohy Uxley sti <lb/>
George Stanley Reptol. " <lb/>
Benjamin Shaw, 4­ <lb/>
Matthew Whiting, sº <lb/>
Franºis Wilson, <lb/>
sECRETARIE8 <lb/></p> 

<p>William Ha'this Esq. <lb/>
George WillIAM LovELL, Faq. <lb/>
IX FIRE OF FICE is confidently re­ <lb/>
the notice of the public—for the libera <lb/>
titude with which all claims upon it are <lb/>
lid–as well as tor the almost unlimited <lb/>
it affords, couprising in addition to the <lb/>
apital of the Cempany, the whole for <lb/>
ºrous Proprieta'y, composed of som <lb/>
lent gentlemen and Merchants in the <lb/></p> 

<p>*n. <lb/>
IX ſhFFICE has carried on an exten <lb/>
sful business for upwards of seveuty­ <lb/>
ae duty paid by it to Government for <lb/>
Great Briain and Ireland exceed <lb/>
ng per sºuntrunk. <lb/>
short time Insurances are undertaken <lb/>
[X COMPANY on almost every de­ <lb/>
, in Newfoundland at a moderate rate <lb/>
ich may be know on application to <lb/>
weir office, in St. John's, where policies <lb/></p> 

<p>ºf charge. <lb/>
&amp; G. RENDEI.L, <lb/>
Agents for Neurroundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>"HE COLONIAL <lb/></p> 

<p>*A* g. 4 * º <lb/>
SSūrāšić0 ióläjälly <lb/>
ºst ARL1sfied 1846. <lb/>
, ONE MILLION STERLING. <lb/>
: of Assuring before 25th <lb/>
May 1863. <lb/>
...) TMVISION OF PROFITS. <lb/>
e advantage of this year's entry to the <lb/>
Proposals must be lodged at the Offiee <lb/>
awfoundland, or with one of the Agents <lb/>
th May next. <lb/>
RS BöNUS will be allocated at the <lb/>
fits in 1364 to Policies opened before <lb/>
Books for the Present Year. <lb/>
ED BY SPECIAL ACT OF PARLIAMENT. <lb/></p> 

<p>Governor. <lb/>
HON, THE EARL OF ELGIN &amp; <lb/>
NE. Goveuxor-General, of INDIA. <lb/>
3.5 GEORGESTREET, EDINBURGH <lb/>
rectors in St. John's, Newfoundland. <lb/>
3rien, Esq. Walter Grieve, Esq., <lb/>
Merchant. <lb/>
Tlliam Henry Mare, Esq. <lb/>
ibiser—Henry Hunt Stabb, M.D. <lb/>
nt–Frederick J. Wyatt. <lb/>
UN OF THIE COMPANY. <lb/>
of the Company............ £130,000 <lb/>
have divided Profits on two occasions" <lb/>
; 859. <lb/>
.000,opened in 1847,has beenincreased <lb/>
the application of the Bonus; oth" <lb/>
roportion. <lb/>
very five years; next division in 1860. <lb/>
ceived in any part of the world whº <lb/>
a been established <lb/></p> 

<p>cº <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>* . <lb/>
*** <lb/></p> 

<p>No. 3637. º St. John's, Monday, February, 20, 1865. º: <lb/></p> 

<p>Printed and Published every *:::: and Thursday <lb/>
Pºrnings by Elºw ARD DALTQN. SHEA, at his <lb/>
office in DUCKWORTH STREET-Terms–One <lb/>
guinea per annum payable in advance. <lb/></p> 

<p>Advertisements not limited (Auction-sales and notice. <lb/>
ºch determine themselves excepted) are repeated <lb/>
until ordered in writing to be withdrawn, and are <lb/>
charged for accordingly. <lb/></p> 

<p>gîis paper is filed,and may be seen, fre",ºf charge ºf <lb/>
Hºlloway's Pills and Ointment Establishmet, 244, <lb/>
Strand, London. <lb/></p> 

<p>A Cough,' 'Cold," or Irritated Throat <lb/>
If allow-d to progress, results in Serious Pulmonary <lb/>
and Bronchial affections, ošentime, incurable. <lb/>
Brown's Bronchial Troches. <lb/>
Reach directly the affected parts, and give almost in­ <lb/>
stant relief. In Bronchins, Asthma, and Catarrh they <lb/>
are hene isial. Obrain, only the genuine Brown's <lb/>
Bronchial 'roches which have proved their effi acy by <lb/>
a test of many years . Among tesimonials aesingew <lb/>
their efficacy are leers from E H Chaplin, D.), N. Y. <lb/>
York; He rv Ward Be'cher, Brooklyn, N.Y.; New <lb/>
willis, New York; Hon C A Phelps, President, Man <lb/>
senae'; Dr. G F Biglow, Big-low. Boston; Prof Ed­ <lb/>
ward North, Blinon, N.Y., Surgeons in the Army and <lb/>
othels of eminºnce. <lb/>
Bronchitis, Coughs, Asthma, <lb/>
And all disorders of the Throa and Lungs are relieved <lb/>
by using "Brown's Bronchial Troches."—"I have beeh <lb/>
afflicted with bronchitis during the paat winter, and <lb/>
found no relefuntil I found your Bronchial Troches. <lb/>
G. H. Gardner, Principal of Ruger's Female Institute, <lb/>
N Y"—"Almost ins'ant relief in the distressing labor <lb/>
of breathing peculiar to Asthma. Itev A C Eggle­ <lb/>
ton, New York,"—" It gives me great pleasure to cer; <lb/>
ify to the efficacy of your Bronchial Troches, in and <lb/>
affection of the ſhroat and voice, induced by public <lb/>
singing. They have suited my case exactly ralieving <lb/>
my Throat and clearing my yoice so that I could sing <lb/>
with eage. T Ducharme, Choriser French Parish <lb/>
church, Montreal."—"When somewhat hoarse from <lb/>
cold or over exertion in public speaking, I have uni­ <lb/>
formly found Brown's Troches afford relief. Henry <lb/>
Wilkes, D D Pastor of Zion Church; Montreal." <lb/>
iłrown's Bronchial Troches <lb/>
Are compounded as to reach directly the seat of the <lb/>
disease and give almost instant relief. <lb/>
The Troches are offered with the fullest confidence <lb/>
in their efficacy; they have been thoroughly tested,and <lb/>
maintain the good reputalion they have justly acquired: <lb/>
For Public Speakers, Sungers, Military Officers, and <lb/>
those who over-tax the voice, they are useful in reliev­ <lb/>
ing an Irritated Throat, and will render articulation <lb/>
easy. To the soldier exposed to sudden changes in the <lb/>
weather they will give promp relief in Coughs and <lb/></p> 

<p>colds, and can be carried in the pocket to be taken as <lb/></p> 

<p>occºsion requires. Solà at 25 cents a box. <lb/>
Coughs and Colds. <lb/>
Sudden changes of climate are sources of Pulmona" <lb/>
Bronchial and Āsthuna ic affections, Experience having <lb/>
proven that simple remedies often act speedily and cer­ <lb/>
isinly when tºken in the early stages of the disease, <lb/>
recourse should at once be had to " Brown's Bronchial <lb/>
Troches," or Lozenges. Few are aware of the import­ <lb/>
ance of checking a cough, or "common cold," in the <lb/>
first stage. That which in the beginning would yield <lb/>
to a mild remedy, if neglected, soon attacks the Lungs <lb/>
º, Brown's Bronchial Troches," or Cough Lozenges <lb/>
allay irritation which induc's coughing, having a direct <lb/>
influence on the effected pars. As there are imitations <lb/>
be sure to obtain the genuine. Sold by all dealers in <lb/>
Medicine, at 25 cents a box. <lb/>
J. J. DEA RIN, St. John's, <lb break="no"/>April 25° Agent for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>New Goods. New Goods. <lb/></p> 

<p>º - * Nº. <lb/></p> 

<p>P. Jordán &amp; Sºils, <lb/>
180 [WATER-STREE T] 222 <lb/>
N returning thanks to their numerous customers in <lb/>
St. John's and the Outports for the very largé <lb/>
patronge at all times given them, beg to state that <lb/>
they have just received per steamer St. Andrew from <lb/>
Glasgow, Titania and Portia frºm Liºpºl, a large <lb/></p> 

<p>supply of BRITISH MANUFACTURED <lb/></p> 

<p>O O D S , <lb/>
riz —Broad Cloths, Doeskins, Buck­ <lb/>
skins, Tweeds, and a variety of other <lb/>
fancy TROWSERINGS, <lb/>
of the newest patterns.—They would particularly is <lb/>
vite attention to their <lb break="no"/>Tweeds and ſancy Trowserings <lb/>
which they are prepared to sell at very low prices. <lb/>
a L S o: <lb/>
coatings, Petershams, Beavers <lb break="no"/>Pilot Cloths, Raised and Plain Whitney: <lb/>
Sealskins, &amp;, , , , , e. -<lb break="maybe"/>WESTINGS-plain and fancy. <lb/>
An] are now making up from the above new Stock an <lb/>
extensive assortment of <lb/></p> 

<p>C},OT:; ING, <lb/></p> 

<p>which they can recommend, and will sell at the lowest <lb/>
possible prices. <lb/>
Gentlemens' Shirts, Fronts and lars <lb/>
Neckties, Silk Squares and Pocket Handkerchiefs <lb/>
Cloth and Glazed Caps ard Hats <lb/>
And a large variety of <lb/></p> 

<p>Dress STUFFS. <lb/></p> 

<p>viz:—Coburgs, Aipaccas, Orleans, Circassians <lb/>
Mohairs, and W inseys <lb/>
Ladies Steel and Quited Skirts <lb/>
shawls, Scarfs and Hosiery <lb/>
inens, Hollands, Diaper Table Cloths <lb/>
oil cloths, Towellings, Regattas <lb/>
sheetings, Moleskins. Blay Calicoes <lb/>
white Shirings and Linings <lb/>
Blankets, Sheets; Quilts and Counterpanes <lb/>
Swanskins, Flannels, Lamas <lb/>
Serges and Baizes. <lb/>
Womens, Girls, and Childrens' Eid, Cloth, <lb/>
and Leather <lb/>
rºw <lb/>
H3 O O. T S , <lb/>
Mens' Wellingtºn, Dºck, Haif boots an i Shoes' <lb/>
And a lot of India flubber Ware. <lb/>
The whole of the above stock will be sold at the <lb/>
gmailest remunerative prices. <lb/>
Sept 15, 3m. <lb/></p> 

<p>Prunella <lb/></p> -->
<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">Monday, Feb. 6.</p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">(Continued.)</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:PROW1">Mr. Prowse</persName> –I must congratulate the House, Sir, on <lb/>
the calm and impartial spirit in which this great question <lb/>
of Confederation has been discussed here already. The <lb/>
mere debate of the question has produced some benefi<lb break="no"/>cial results; already the old land marks of party have <lb/>
been destroyed by it.—The lion and the lamb have learnt <lb/>
to lie down together. We find the hon member, Mr. <lb/>
Glen, in double harness with Mr. C. F. Bennett, the <lb/>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Ledger</hi> and the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Patriot</hi>, newspapers hand in hand; <lb/>
and a still more wonderful and affecting sight, the mer<lb break="no"/>chants, whom hon gentlemen opposite have spent their <lb/>
life time in denouncing as the grinders and oppressors <lb/>
of the poor, have now formed a solemn league and <lb/>
covenant with their natural enemies the radicals. Is <lb/>
there not something suspicious in the fact that for once, <lb/>
at least, the merchants have united as one man on this <lb/>
question? It has been said that we have no right to <lb/>
quote the opinion of the Right Rev. Dr. Connolly or <lb/>
of his Lordship Dr. Mulock; but I tell hon gentleman <lb/>
that when every sort of misrepresentation has gone forth <lb/>
to the world, when people who ought to have known <lb/>
better; talk outside doors of a thousand a year to Coun<lb break="no"/>cillors and Members of Parliament, when such villainous <lb/>
perversions of facts as the bones of our militia bleaching <lb/>
on the borders of Canada, have been promulgated far <lb/>
and wide, we have a right to tell the mass of the people, <lb/>
who won't trouble themselves to investigate the question, <lb/>
or who possibly cannot understand it in all its various <lb/>
bearings, that their spiritual teachers, in whom they have <lb/>
the most implicit confidence, are favorable to this great <lb/>
project. And I think, sir, when the people knew this, <lb/>
it will take all the demagogues and all the stump <lb/>
orators both inside this House and out of it, to make the <lb/>
people believe that men of such, character and such ac<lb break="no"/>knowledged ability as Dr. Mullock and Dr. Connolly, <lb/>
went to sell either this country or Nova Scotia to these <lb/>
Dutch Canadians, as the hon member Mr. March; has <lb/>
called them, Great political capital is expected to be <lb/>
made out of that we are selling the country to Canada, <lb/>
that we want to separate Newfoundland from the mother <lb/>
country. Now the hon member Mr. March, and every <lb/>
one else who make such statements, must know that they <lb/>
are false. One of the leading principles of the scheme <lb/>
of Confederation is to bind the Colonies more closely to <lb/>
Great Britain; and I <choice><sic>beliefe</sic><corr>believe</corr></choice> this was one of the primary <lb/>
objects which animated every delegate at that Confer<lb break="no"/>ence. We shall certainly be joined to England in a <lb/>
different way, if their great idea is carried out. We shall <lb/>
no longer be so many straggling helpless dependencies. <lb/>
We shall be joined as one strong united country, an en<lb break="no"/>lightened British Statesmen with us to be. Like all other <lb/>
great political questions, this is one which in its very <lb/>
nature is theoretical and to a certain extent problema<lb break="no"/>tical in its effects. You cannot, by any means at your <lb/>
disposal, reduce it to a matter of pounds, shillings and <lb/>
pence. You cannot guage and assay all its advantages <lb/>
and disadvantges, by any array of figures, or the most <lb/>
elaborate statement of hard facts. You must reason on <lb/>
it from the established rules of political philosophy. <lb/>
You must bring to bear upon it the light of that ex<lb break="no"/>perience which history teaches us in the annals of other <lb/>
countries; or are we so peculiarly situated, so singuar <lb/>
in our character as a civilized country, that the political <lb/>
principles which have produced certain results in other <lb/>
lands will not do so here? The union of England and <lb/>
Scotland in 1707, was as much opposed as this one we <lb/>
are now discussing. What arguments could be used than <lb/>
to shew <choice><sic>on</sic><corr>an</corr></choice> Orkney man; or an inhabitant of the <lb/>
Western Islands, that the union would benefit them? <lb/>
How could the railways in the South of Scotland, or its <lb/>
increased wealth be of any advantage to a poor island <lb/>
separated so many miles of sea from the main land; <lb/>
but, I ask, has not the union done so? Is there an <lb/>
island belonging to the two kingdoms, however barren <lb/>
or remote, that has not benefitted in an amazing degree <lb/>
by the connection between England and Scotland? <lb/>
Look at the union of Upper and Lower Canada. We <lb/>
have not the repelling circumstances of race and lan<lb break="no"/>guage to contend with. We have none of those strong <lb/>
arguments of diversity of religion, language and nationa<lb break="no"/>lity, which were used against that union. But what has <lb/>
been the result, both in Upper and lower Canada ? <lb/>
Twenty-three years ago Montreal contained 41,000 inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants. Now, when its suburbs, it numbers 108,000. Last <lb/>
year upwards of 2000 new houses were built there. <lb/>
Everywhere, sir, both in Europe and Anerica, the same <lb/>
invariable results have flown from union; but perhaps <lb/>
the strongest arguments we can deduce from history in <lb/>
favor of union, is the result of disunion as shown by its <lb/>
effects on Spain. Does any one who reads history be<lb break="no"/>lieve that Spain would now be a second rate power in <lb/>
Europe, if Philip the Second had planted his capital on <lb/>
the banks of the magnificent Tagus, instead of on that <lb/>
wretched ghost of a river, the <choice><sic>Manzanres</sic><corr>Manzanares</corr></choice>. But, say hon <lb/>
gentlemen, tells us what benefits we are to derive from <lb/>
Confederation, and we will give in out adherence to it. <lb/>
These gentlemen can find no arguments, no reason what<lb break="no"/>ever in the able and logical speeches of both the Speaker <lb/>
and the hon Mr. Shea. No, sir, the logic and the elo<lb break="no"/>quence of Gladstone would be wholly unavailing with such <lb/>
men. Local prejudice, local obstinacy, and local stupidi<lb break="no"/>ty have always been the greatest obstacles in the way of <lb/>
progress. It has always been so. Wit, indignation, elo<lb break="no"/>quence, the most forcible logic sustained by a long train <lb/>
of unanswerable arguments, are wholly unavailing to <lb/>
penetrate the wooden headed obstinacy of the local mind. <lb/>
Logic and arguments all fall back like blunted arrows, <lb/>
from the impenetrable walls of obstinate ignorance. But, <lb/>
sir, in considering this question we ought to take into <lb/>
account the present Colonial policy of Great Britain. <lb/>
Now, sir, this policy is settled and fixed. It is not con<lb break="no"/>fined to any one Ministry, or one party. From the ex<lb break="no"/>treme opinion of Professor Godwin Smith, to the con<lb break="no"/>servative views of Lord Stanley, all point in the same <lb/>
direction. All enlightened British statesmen tell you, in <lb/>
the plainest terms, that English tax-payers won't submit <lb/>
much longer to bear burdens for the Colonies, which the <lb/>
Colonists ought to bear themselves. And what do they <lb/>
tell you in the matter? Why, in plain terms, it is just <lb/>
this—" Gentlemen, we approve of this scheme of Confed<lb break="no"/>eration. We want you to get strong. We want you to <lb/>
be united. We won't cast you off. We feel bound; in <lb/>
honor, to protect you." But supposing you don't take <lb/>
this advice, and you preter remaining out in <lb/>
the cold, do you suppose that England, with <lb/>
her colonies all over the world, will still hug you to <lb/>
her heart, as the brightest jewel in the Crown? Does <lb/>
any sensible man believe she will? No, you will be left <lb/>
       to shut for yourselves, and a miserable shift it will be. <lb/>
And do you also believe, if you remain out of the Con<lb break="no"/>federation, and the Reciprocity Treaty is rescinded, that <lb/>
the other Colonies, who are competitors with you in the <lb/>
fisheries, will not tax your produce? The great obsti<lb break="no"/>cal, however, to this measure, is increased taxation. The <lb/>
Canadian tariff, as we are told, will be much heavier than <lb/>
    


<cb/>
    
our own, and that though the £112,000 given us by the <lb/>
Confederate Government is a good sum, the Canadian <lb/>
tariff will give us a revenue of £140,000 or even a great <lb/>
deal more. Now, sir, we have the statement of Lord <lb/>
Monck and also of Mr. Galt, that the Federal tariff will <lb/>
be lowered instead of raised; and as every one acquain<lb break="no"/>ted with political economy knows, in increased tariff does <lb/>
not...necessarily mean increased revenue, but in many <lb/>
cases has quite the contrary effect. But, sir, I contend <lb/>
that we will have more than £112,000. Local, direct, <lb/>
and intercolonial steam is virtually promised to us, and <lb/>
that is at least £10,000 more. One of the first effects <lb/>
of Confederation will be the reduction of your Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive contingencies. These are now £7000, and, at least, <lb/>
we ought to save £3000 a year; here, when the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly is reduced to half, and the Council abolished. But <lb/>
over and above the money saved, I consider that if Con<lb break="no"/>federation will only put an end to the sectarian and poli<lb break="no"/>tical differences which are such a bane to our community; <lb/>
if it will only put down the small fry of newspapers and <lb/>
petty politicians, who help to fan the flames of religious <lb/>
strife, and who fatten like political vultures upon our <lb/>
local sectarian differences, if Confederation will only do <lb/>
this, as I trust, in time, that it will, I, for one, will hail <lb/>
it as the greatest boon that could ever be conferred upon <lb/>
this Colony. As regards the giving away of our wild <lb/>
lands, I look upon the $37,000 a year as a gift; and, sir, <lb/>
I consider that the money is the least part of the benefit. <lb/>
The General Government must do something to meet the <lb/>
opposition, when enquiries are made as to what the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment has done to develop these lands in Newfound<lb break="no"/>land, for which they pay such a tremendous price. And <lb/>
this must eventually be of the greatest benefit to us. It <lb/>
must bring capital to our shores, and that capital should <lb/>
be welcomed amongst us, no matter where it comes from, <lb/>
whether it is French or American, aye or even Turkish <lb/>
capital, Sir, I have no desire to press this matter <lb/>
through the House with undue haste. The longer the <lb/>
question is discussed the greater will be the number of <lb/>
adherents to Confederation. Let us have the voice of <lb/>
the country upon this question Let each member de<lb break="no"/>clare his honest opinion up in it, openly and candidly; <lb/>
and then let our constituencies deal with us as they <lb/>
think proper. On such a momentous topic, fir, no mem<lb break="no"/>ber of this House should be silent; none should meanly <lb/>
shirk a question involving such tremendous consequences; <lb/>
none should give a silent vote. My own honest convic<lb break="no"/>tion is, that with local and direct steam assured to us, <lb/>
and such other more favourable terms, as of course we <lb/>
must try to get, Confederation with the British North <lb/>
American Provinces, under ail the circumstances of our <lb/>
present condition, would be highly beneficial to this colo<lb break="no"/>ny. I am still open to conviction that my conclusions are <lb/>
wrong; but I have heard nothing as yet from the oppo<lb break="no"/>nents of the scheme which would induce me to change <lb/>
my opinion, I want to know from them how they in<lb break="no"/>tend to deal with pauperism. I must confess, with all <lb/>
respect for their ability and sincerity; that I vainly <lb/>
believe they would not grapple with this giant evil half <lb/>
so efficiently as the present leader of the government has <lb/>
done. There is scarcely another politician in the country <lb/>
who has more strenously endeavoured to put it down; <lb/>
and yet he has failed, and even with good fisheries, fail<lb break="no"/>ures in this respect will be the lot of every party that <lb/>
rules in this Colony; unless some radical change takes <lb/>
place in its condition. I must congratulate this House, <lb/>
sir, that at last we have a topic to discuss which will raise <lb/>
us to above the low dead level of our petty local squab<lb break="no"/>bles, and, I trust, sir, that we will discuss it in a spirit <lb/>
worthy of its vast importance to ourselves and to our <lb/>
children.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. Wyatt</persName> desired to make a few observations <lb/>
before this question was put. The Address in reply <lb/>
to the speech of his Excellency the Governor had <lb/>
now been before the house tor a week. He deeply <lb/>
regretted that the debate on this question of confeder<lb break="no"/>ation had been so premature, as a day had been set <lb/>
apart for its full discussion. Now he would ask hon <lb/>
gentleman if they had approached this subject in that <lb/>
spirit of calm enquiry which had been recommended by <lb/>
his Excellency? Had they not gone so far as to impute <lb/>
personal motives to the hon delegates, for the manner in <lb/>
which they supported the question. He (Mr. Wyatt) <lb/>
believed the delegates had done their duty fairly and <lb/>
honestly. They reflected credit on Newfoundland; and <lb/>
were in his opinion, entitled to the fullest consideration <lb/>
from this house.—They had not departed from their <choice><sic>in<lb break="no"/>eractions</sic><corr>interactions</corr></choice>, and had in no way pledged the country. The <lb/>
question now came before the representatives of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple to confirm or reject, as they deemed proper. It was <lb/>
one of grave responsibility, and should be referred to the <lb/>
people, who had the greatest interest in the matter. He <lb/>
was sorry to hear the hon the Speaker's attack upon the <lb/>
merchants, because he (Mr. Wyatt) believed that we had <lb/>
nothing to consider on the subject except that which <lb/>
would promote the prosperity of the fishermen and what <lb/>
conduced to the prosperity of one, necessarily did the <lb/>
same with the other. He believed that the merchants <lb/>
did everything in their power to benefit the fisherinen of <lb/>
the country, and there could be no doubt that ultimately <lb/>
they would reap the benefit. Of course, the merchants <lb/>
required a fair return for their capital. He thougnt, <lb/>
therefore, that the remarks of the hon the Speaker were <lb/>
uncalled for. He (Mr. Wyatt) knew that it is the settled <lb/>
determination of the merchants not to let this matter <lb/>
pass too hastily. He throughly appreciated the praises <lb/>
which were given to the merchants by some hon members <lb/>
opposite. These praises, at this time, accorded very well <lb/>
with their past conduct. Who was it that always raised <lb/>
the cry against the merchants, about taken the life-blood <lb/>
from the people? Not hon members opposite. He <lb/>
could assure these hon members that the merchants per<lb break="no"/>fectly understood them, the hon member for Burgeo and <lb/>
        LaPoile, Mr. Prowse must have a <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> at the merchants. <lb/>
Now he (Mr. Wyatt) would ask him who was it that <lb/>
gave him a seat in this house? Was it not entirely <lb/>
owing to mercantile influences? He (Mr. Wyatt) would <lb/>
simply suggest that the question of confederation should <lb/>
not be further gone into at present, until the 15th, when <lb/>
every hon member of this house would no doubt, be fully <lb/>
prepared to discuss it.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> had already spoken on this matter, and <lb/>
did not now intend to occupy the time of the house in <lb/>
again going into it. But as one hon member for Bona<lb break="no"/>vista, Mr. Wyatt, had made some allusion to the position <lb/>
which, he had taken on this question he felt it his duty <lb/>
to reply to him. Like Corporal Trim, the hon member <lb/>
felt compelled to stand up for his company. He (the <lb/>
Speaker) came into that house as an independent mem<lb break="no"/>ber, and he would now express independently his op<lb break="no"/>ions, uninfluenced by any man or any set of men. But <lb/>
when in private and privileged places, personal motives <lb/>
        were attributed to him, he could not be banned if <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
privilege, though not private peace, he should endeavour <lb/>
somewhat to return the compliment. He (the Speaker) <lb/>
did not intend to make any personal attack upon the<lb/>
merchants Had he ever done anything to injure the <lb/>
capital of the country? Had he ever supported them, <lb/>
and among the members of the commercial body he knew <lb/>

<cb/>
    
    none that were not his personal friends. But he (the <lb/>
Speaker must give it as his deliberate opinion, that the <lb/>
supplying system was ruinous to the best interests of <lb/>
the country. It was a reckless system, and tended to <lb/>
throw great numbers upon the Government for support <lb/>
during the winter? It tended generally to demoralize <lb/>
the fishermen. It was well known that the outharbour <lb/>
merchants and planters were made a prey, of by the <lb/>
piratical boats that went from St. John's, and obtained <lb/>
from the fishermen, frequently, in the night time, the <lb/>
fish that they should have turned in to their supplying <lb/>
merchant. It was this want of mutual confidence be<lb break="no"/>tween the merchant and fisherman that occasioned, in a <lb/>
great degree, such improper proceedings, Then we saw <lb/>
that our leading merchants engaged in a branch of trade <lb/>
which should be left in the hands of the middle classes. <lb/>
If you went up Water Street, you would find them sel<lb break="no"/>ling hairbrushes, lavender water, groceries, and such <lb/>
articles. He thought these things should be imported by <lb/>
the merchants, and sold to the retail shopkeepers, who <lb/>
would be enabled to do a very good business by such a <lb/>
course of dealing. But how could these hope to prosper, <lb/>
when the merchant, who was the importer, <lb/>
was also the retailer? These were his (the <lb/>
Speaker's) true sentiments, and he would always utter <lb/>
them. Now the merchants, as a general rule, were sel<lb break="no"/>dom united. But on this question of confederation they <lb/>
seemed to stand wonderfully together. What is the ne<lb break="no"/>cessary inference to be drawn from this? If the people <lb/>
found a number of lawyers putting their heads together <lb/>
and particularly anxious for the carrying of any measure, <lb/>
what would be said? "What's up now I wonder?" <lb/>
Every man, whether planter, merchant or fisherman, <lb/>
would naturally have his own opinion on the subject, <lb/>
and so long as that opinion was maintained without as<lb break="no"/>cribing personal interest or motive -o those who thought <lb/>
differently, so long would he (the Speaker) respect such <lb/>
opinions, so held.</p>
    
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName>.—There had been a great deal said about <lb/>
the distress and misery of the people; but there was <lb/>
not a single argument put forward to shew us how con<lb break="no"/>federation would ameliorate our condition, or in any <lb/>
way confer any substantial benefit upon us. It was well <lb/>
known that we lived entirely by our fisheries, and how <lb/>
confederation was going to benefit them he Mr. <lb/>
Glen was utterly at a loss to conceive. Not being able <lb/>
to convince us on this point, hon gentleman had resorted <lb/>
to threats, and have told us that unless we join in this <lb/>
confederation, Great Britain will withdraw her protec<lb break="no"/>tion from us, leave us to our own resources, and to the <lb/>
mercy of two powerful neighbours. He (Mr. Glen) did <lb/>
not believe a word of it. It was simply absurd, and <lb/>
resorting to such an argument only shewed how weak <lb/>
was the cause which non gentlemen advocated. No <lb/>
disappointment could possibly have come of it, if that <lb/>
Report had not been signed by the delegates. It was <lb/>
well know that the British Navy had been supplied with <lb/>
men from our shores, and it was these hardy fishermen <lb/>
who had won for Britain the supremacy of the ocean. <lb/>
Could we not appeal then on that point? Did hon gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen remember what the Earl of Chatham said about <lb/>
Newfoundland? He said sooner than a rock should be <lb/>
taken from Newfoundland by a foreign power, he would, <lb/>
make it the cause of war with the whole world. He <lb/>
(Mr. Glen) believed that England would do so now. It <lb/>
was said that we were to have direct steam. That cer<lb break="no"/>tainty would be a benefit. But he (Mr. Glen) did not <lb/>
see that stipulated for in the Report of the Conference. <lb/>
It we were to have it, it should be there. But the <lb/>
General Government would not give us enough to pay <lb/>
our working expenses. What a miserable position we <lb/>
were placed in. They tell us that we are to receive <lb/>
£10,000 for steam. They might just as well say £20,<lb break="no"/>000. One would be just as visionary as the other.—It <lb/>
looked very much like the story of the Frenchman whose <lb/>
book-keeper told him that he was worth £20,000, but <lb/>
when he put his hand in his pocket he found he was not <lb/>
worth a cent. The hon member for Burgeo and La <lb/>
Poile had used as an argument the union between Eng<lb break="no"/>land and Scotland. No one doubted that that was bene<lb break="no"/>fical, though it had been obtained through treachery. <lb/>
Scotland after the union was enabled to trade with Eng<lb break="no"/>land's Colonies, and had the protection of the English <lb/>
fleet wherever she went. Could Canada do that for <lb/>
Newfoundland? She could do neither the one nor the <lb/>
other. In his (Mr. Glen's) opinion, she would have hard <lb/>
work enough to protect herself in a few years, without <lb/>
thinking of us. He would say nothing futuor on the <lb/>
matter now, but leave it until the 15th, when it would <lb/>
be more fully discussed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Mr. E. D. Shea</persName>.—The hon member, Mr. Glen, had <lb/>
entirely mistaken what he (Mr. Shea) had said. When <lb/>
he spoke of the numbers of people likely to go to Canada <lb/>
and seek employment there, he meant our unfortunate <lb/>
poor, not our mechanics and other trades people, who <lb/>
are, comparatively speaking, better off. But the hon <lb/>
member, Mr. Glen, was determined not to believe any <lb/>
thing, he (Mr. Shea) was fully convinced that if con<lb break="no"/>federation was carried out and all the benefits which were <lb/>
spoken of were fully realized, the hon member, Mr. Glen, <lb/>
would still adhere to his state of unbelief. He says <lb/>
" can you gaarantee the benefits which you say con<lb break="no"/>federation will counter?" He (Mr. Shea) could as much <lb/>
guarantee them as the hon member, Mr. Glen, could <lb/>
guarantee good fisheries. He (Mr. Shea) thought that <lb/>
it was a great mistake, that the <choice><sic>prople</sic><corr>people</corr></choice> should be so <lb/>
entirely confined to the fisheries. They relied too ex<lb break="no"/>clusively upon them, and that was the bane of the <lb/>
country. The great mistake was that hon gentlemen<lb/>
supposed we were dealing, in this matter, with a govern<lb break="no"/>ment opposed to us. Did they really apprehend that, the <lb/>
people of Canada were opposed to us? If they enter<lb break="no"/>tained such views they must reject common sense and <lb/>
reason. He (Mr. Shea) argued on the presumpuon that <lb/>
we were to have steam. That should be secured to us, <lb/>
and it it were not sufficiently secured at present, let it be <lb/>
made so before the bargain is concluded. As hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber, had referred to the <choice><sic>lester</sic><corr>letter</corr></choice> of His Lordship Dr. <lb/>
Mullock. He (Mr. Shea) must say that the only infer<lb break="no"/>ence to be drawn from that letter was that his Lordship <lb/>
was in favour of confederation. Could it be thought by <lb/>
any reasoning being that confederation would be <choice><sic>bene<lb break="no"/>cial</sic><corr>beneficial</corr></choice> to the educated, and injurious to the lower orders? <lb/>
Had his Lordship been opposed to confederation would <lb/>
he not have gived his opinion upon it? He showed by <lb/>
his letter that he was heart and soul for it; but simply <lb/>
abstains from offering an opinion upon its commercial <lb/>
results. We have been told that we had no right to deal <lb/>
with the question now. We had a perfect right to do <lb/>
so, and the country demanded it of us. We would be <lb/>
shrinking from our duty if we did not do it. Let us <lb/>
send the matter before the country, not without our <lb/>
expression of opinion upon it. He (Mr. Shea) saw no <lb/>
other course that could be properly pursued. He was <lb/>
opposed to the carrying of the measure at present. Let <lb/>
all the people he fairly and properly consulted. The <lb/>
hon member, Mr. Casey, said that if we entered this <lb/>
confederation, Canada would be sure to tax us. He (Mr.<lb/>
    Shea) thought far differently. Canada would be more
    



<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-20_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER</fw> 

<fw type="num">2</fw>

likely to treat us with greater consideration, when she <lb/>
found that our interests were identical with her own; <lb/>
and that we were prepared to share their burdens. It <lb/>
was desirable that the public mind should be thoroughly <lb/>
informed on this great question, at the earliest oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity, and he (Mr. Shea) therefore did not agree with <lb/>
hon gentlemen when they said that this debate was pre<lb break="no"/>mature. It was the duty of the Legislature to take up <lb/>
the matter as early as possible. He did not grudge the <lb/>
time that had been spent in its discussion,as he believed <lb/>
it had been turned to very useful account.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CASE2">Mr. CASEY</persName>.—No person who had listened atten<lb break="no"/>tively to the observations of hon members, who had <lb/>
addressed the house on that subject could fail to notice <lb/>
the anxiety of the supporters of the Confederation to <lb/>
carry that question through the house, notwithstand<lb break="no"/>ing the very general feeling against it. They had <lb/>
failed, however, to convince him (Mr. Casey) that the <lb/>
Confederation would be of the slightest benefit to the <lb/>
inhabitants of Newfoundland. He saw nothing what<lb break="no"/>ever staring us in the face but taxation and ruin, if we <lb/>
consented to that proposal. What similarity was there <lb/>
between our pursuits and those of Canada? None <lb/>
whatever. Here we were a little kingdom in our<lb break="no"/>selves, and if war should arise, we would be protected <lb/>
by the army and navy of Great Brftain. Did not Mr. <lb/>
Brown of Toronto state that one of the first objects <lb/>
of the Confederation would be to provide for the <lb/>
military defence of Canada? And did not the dele<lb break="no"/>gates, before the conference broke up, consent to the <lb/>
expenditure necessery for that purpose? Where was <lb/>
the means for that? Newfoundland had until lately <lb/>
sufficient to meet her own expenditure, but could not <lb/>
furnish the means of paying troops for the defence of <lb/>
Canada. But we were stricken down, for the time, <lb/>
by bad fisheries. He trusted, however, that Provi<lb break="no"/>dence would again smile upon us; and with the return <lb/>
of prosperty we would have sufficient revenue for our <lb/>
requirements, and the people themselves would frown <lb/>
down pauperism. After the introduction of Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government, a determined effort should have <lb/>
been made to put down the demoralisation of pauper<lb break="no"/>ism. He did not see why so much had been expended <lb/>
of late years. It certainly was not because the people <lb/>
could not do without it. The present Government <lb/>
sent poor relief east, west, north and south, and de<lb break="no"/>moralized the people by their lavish expenditure. <lb/>
Under pretence of relieving the poor,they sent a large <lb/>
        quantity of Indian <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> to Harbor Grace, where it was <lb/>
not required. Something was said by the hon member <lb/>
for Ferryland, Mr. Shea, about a large sum being ex<lb break="no"/>pended for the protection of the fisheries. He Mr.Casey <lb/>
had read carefully the reports of the persons sent to <lb/>
protect the fisheries, and he could see nothing in them <lb/>
to satisfy him that their services were necessary. But <lb/>
he would like to know, if we were to enter into this <lb/>
confederation, how the Canadian navy was to give us <lb/>
protection? It would take time to form such a navy <lb/>
as would protect the maritime provinces; and where <lb/>
was the money to come from? It was from the navy <lb/>
of Briain that we were to look for protection. The <lb/>
hon member said also that our operative population <lb/>
would benefit by the union. He (Mr. Casey) did not <lb/>
see that. When the question of Free Trade was agi<lb break="no"/>tated, the people expected that they would get bread <lb/>
and flour for nothing. But it was found that bread <lb/>
and flour were as dear as before we had the treaty. <lb/>
We were told that when confederation was carried out <lb/>
we were to have a line of steamers from this port to <lb/>
Toronto. He had looked carefully over the papers, <lb/>
and he could see nothing about these steamers. He <lb/>
would like to have something more than mere rumour <lb/>
on that matter. He granted the steamers would be <lb/>
a benefit, if we got them. We were told that the <lb/>
educated youth of the country had not a field here; <lb/>
but that they would have a fine field in Canada after <lb/>
confederation was carried out. But did not our youth <lb/>
proceed to Canada and Australia now, and did not <lb/>
many of them do well in these countries, without con<lb break="no"/>federation? The brothers of the hon the Speaker had <lb/>
done so, and he (Mr. Casey) was happy to learn that <lb/>
they had prospered. If the youth of the country could <lb/>
not find employment in their native land to their <lb/>
long, and had the enterprise to go elsewhere, he <lb/>
(Mr. Casey) would admire them for it. But they cer<lb break="no"/>tainly did not require confederation to secure success. <lb/>
A great deal of stress was laid upon the letter of Arch<lb break="no"/>bishop Connolly. Certainly no person who knew that <lb/>
distinguished prelate, either personally or by reputa<lb break="no"/>tion, but would pay the greatest attention to his <lb/>
opinions. But it did not follow, because he considered <lb/>
that confederation would benefit Nova Scotia, that it <lb/>
would prove beneficial to Newfoundland. The opin<lb break="no"/>ion of the Right Revd. Dr. Mullock was also referred <lb/>
to. He (Mr. Casey) d.d not know what Dr. Mul<lb break="no"/>lock's opinions were on the question of confederation, <lb/>
but he did know that hon members were not always <lb/>
so ready to quote the opinions of that gifted prelate <lb/>
in support of their views. Reference had been made to <lb/>
the reception given to Mr. Brown in England. But <lb/>
Garibaldi was also feted in <choice><sic>Englond</sic><corr>England</corr></choice>; and the Duke of <lb/>
Sutherland seat his yacht for him. But the sensible <lb/>
people of England made the country too hot for him, <lb/>
and he had to retire without the ovation he had an<lb break="no"/>ticipated. We were told the local Legislature would <lb/>
still be retained for the management of our local af<lb break="no"/>fairs; but would any person tell bim that the tenden<lb break="no"/>cy would not be to do away with the local Legislature <lb/>
altogether? Ten years hence we would have no local <lb/>
legislature in the maritime provinces, if confederation <lb/>
was carried. Then we were told that we would re<lb break="no"/>ceive $150,000 a year for our Crown lands and miner<lb break="no"/>als; and ten years hence it might be found that our <lb/>
mineral resources were worth a great deal more. It <lb/>
was not when a geological survey of the country was <lb/>
undertaken, which promised in the opinion of the <lb/>
geologist employed, to show that we had valuable <lb/>
minerals, that we should thus give away our Crown <lb/>
lands and mines, for what, after all, was our own <lb/>
money, for we should not receive by any means as <lb/>
much in the whole as we would be taxed under the <lb/>
tariff of Canada. It was not fair that we should come <lb/>
to any decision on that question this session. The <lb/>
members of the present house were not elected for any <lb/>
such purpose. Confederation was not thought of <lb/>
when they were elected. Let them go to the country, <lb/>
which he (Mr. Casey) hoped would not be until the <lb/>
fall, and let the people say whether they wished for <lb/>
confederation or not. Reference had been made to <lb/>
the sympathy of the other Colonies when the French <lb/>
        
convention of 1847 came out, and it was stated that <lb/>
            the convention was in a great measure detested <lb/>
            through that sympathy. He admitted that we ought <lb/>
            to be forever grateful for the sympathy we then ex<lb break="no"/>perienced; but that was no reason why we should now <lb/>
            enter into another convention against our interests. <lb/>
            It was said also that such was the anxiety on that <lb/>
            question that property was very much depreciated; <lb/>
            but property was never so much depreciated as now, <lb/>
            owing to a succession of bad fisheries. He (Mr.Casey) <lb/>
            denied that the delegates were justified in signing the <lb/>
            resolutions drawn up by the Conference. He (Mr. <lb/>
        Casey) found that the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Daily Telegraph</hi>, a good au<lb break="no"/>thority, charged the Delegales with acting illegally in <lb/>
            that proceeding. That journal said those who formed <lb/>
            the Conference at Quebec for the purpose of arranging <lb/>
            the terms of a Convention, had no authority for what <lb/>
            they did.-The union hetween England and Ireland <lb/>
            had been referred to, and it was stated that Scotchmen <lb/>
            went up to England and obtained situations, and that <lb/>
            Irishmen went also. But did not history tell us that <lb/>
            the Irishmen who did so sold themselves, bddy and <lb/> 
    
    <cb/>


soul, to the British Government? The result of the <lb/>
union between England and Ireland was most disas<lb break="no"/>trous to Ireland, and such would be the effect with re<lb break="no"/>gard to that Confederation, if carried into effect, New<lb break="no"/>foundlanders not yet in being would curse the day that <lb/>
their country was made over to Canada. —Need he <lb/>
(Mr. Casey) go one step further to show the results of <lb/>
this Confederation, if entered into? In the other <lb/>
provinces, where there might be some beneft derived <lb/>
from Confederation, there was much opposition by <lb/>
many, and by some of the most influential of the <lb/>
newspapers. (Here the hon member read several <lb/>
extracts from Canada and Nova Scotia newspapers.) <lb/>
These were the organs of public opinion in the neigh<lb break="no"/>bouring provinces, and they showed any thing but <lb/>
unanimity of sentiment in favour of the proposed <lb/>
union. Many of the leading citizens of Halifax were <lb/>
also opposed to it, although if any city would benefit <lb/>
by it. It must be Halifax, which was to be the colonial <lb/>
terminus of the Grand Trunk Railway. He (Mr. <lb/>
Casey) would say again that it was not competent for <lb/>
the present House of Assembly to dispose of that ques<lb break="no"/>tion, and hon members ought not to consent to it, if <lb/>
they had the interest of the country at heart.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName>.—Hon members stated that we would <lb/>
have a larger revenue under confederation than we <lb/>
have now. But we would also have much heavier <lb/>
taxation. By a return prepared at the Custom-house, <lb/>
and of which, therefore, the accuracy would not be <lb/>
questioned, it was shown that the Canadian tariff, ap<lb break="no"/>plied to our imports, would give a revenue of £140,<lb break="no"/>000 a year, while all we would receive under confed<lb break="no"/>eration was £132,000, and no increase for the future, <lb/>
whatever, the increase of our population might be. <lb/>
And for this we would be required to give them our <lb/>
Custom-houses, Government house, our Crown lands, <lb/>
with all our valuable mineral resources, and the power <lb/>
to make laws, for the Governor General could disallow <lb/>
any Act passed here. Now, he (Mr. Renouf) would <lb/>
ask hon members, were we to sell our country for <lb/>
£132,000 a year? For his part he would not do so, <lb/>
We could wait and see what Providence would do for <lb/>
us. We did not yet know what our resources are. <lb/>
Our minerals are not yet developed. He regretted <lb/>
that the late government did not institute a geologi<lb break="no"/>cal survey when they had an abundant revenue. Could <lb/>
Canada do more to settle our Crown lands and devel<lb break="no"/>op our mineral resources than Newfoundland could <lb/>
do? We could have a thorough geological survey, <lb/>
if we should borrow the money for the purpose, and if <lb/>
valuable minerals were discovered, there would be <lb/>
no difficulty in fortning a Company prepared to work <lb/>
them. Mines must be worked by private enterprise <lb/>
and private capital. Government could not do it to <lb/>
advantage no matter what their means might be. We <lb/>
were told that Mr. Galt had no desire to raise the <lb/>
tariff; and who was Mr. Galt?. He was but one man, <lb/>
and he could not speak for a central government not <lb/>
yet in existence. He might promise that it would not <lb/>
be increased. But promises made under such circum<lb break="no"/>stances were not reliable. We know it was promised <lb/>
to Ireland, when the union was carried, that Catholic <lb/>
emancipation would follow, and it was not until twen<lb break="no"/>ty eight years after, that it was carried in the Imperial <lb/>
Parliament. Could we have any confidence, consider<lb break="no"/>ing what the expenditure of the Federal Government <lb/>
must inevitably, be that Mr. Galt's promises would <lb/>
be better kept? He (Mr. Renouſ) hoped every hon. <lb/>
member of that, house would exercise his unbiassed <lb/>
judgment in that matter, and not suffer himself to be <lb/>
influenced by the supporters of Confederation on eit<lb break="no"/>her side of the house, to believe that the cry of taxa<lb break="no"/>tion was a shadow. The question of taxation was no <lb/>
shadow, but was a substance, and one which would <lb/>
come home to every elector in the Colony. The peo<lb break="no"/>ple of Newfoundland were not less intelligent than <lb/>
those of others countries, and were not to be misied <lb/>
by mere professions of economy, which the sightest <lb/>
reflection must show them could not be realized. Then <lb/>
we we were told that we would not be called upon to <lb/>
furnish a militia. The object of the conference at <lb/>
Quebec was a milotary convention, and not commer<lb break="no"/>cial; and if Federation were carried out, England <lb/>
would say—"You have now the resources of a great <lb/>
country ; provide for your own defence. So long as <lb/>
you were struggling colonies we defended you, but <lb/>
now you are able to do for yourselves." Now the <lb/>
existing tariff of Canada would all £40,507 to our <lb/>
Customs revenue. But that tariff would only allow <lb/>
a million of dollars for military, and nothing for naval <lb/>
expenditure. He (Mr Renouf) would be prepared to <lb/>
show, when the question came up for discussion on <lb/>
the 15th, that the Federal government would require <lb/>
two millions of dollars more than the Canadian tariff <lb/>
would produce. And how was that to be raised ? <lb/>
Why by raising the tariff; by imposing additional <lb/>
burdens upon the people. He did not desire to <lb/>
see the matter passed so hastily. He saw no occasion <lb/>
to force this question, as it was of the utmost impor<lb break="no"/>tance that, the matter should be fully investigated, <lb/>
and placed in all its aspects before the country. He <lb/>
(Mr. Renouf) disclaimed saying anything against <lb/>
the merchants of Newfoundland. He always had the <lb/>
greatest respect for them, and considered <lb/>
their interest identical with those of the fisher<lb break="no"/>men. So, it would appear that our joining in <lb/>
this Confederation was entirely to be attributed to the <lb/>
Hon the Attorney General, and that it was through <lb/>
his influence that we were not left out in the cold. <lb/>
But what right had the hon the Attorney General to <lb/>
take upon himself so great a responsibility! Where, <lb/>
he (Mr. Renouf) would ask, was the official dispatch <lb/>
ot the Governor General of Canada? Had that been <lb/>
borked? It seemed to him that our delegates had <lb/>
received a piper's invitation, for there had evidently <lb/>
been no desire or intention to ask Newfoundland at <lb/>
first. Our delegates say that they did not commit us. <lb/>
He (Mr. Renout) agreed with the opinion of the hon <lb/>
member, Mr. Glen, that they had. They signed that <lb/>
Report on behalf of this country, and had it been pos<lb break="no"/>sible for them to have bound us they would have done <lb/>
so. And yet they were invested with no authority <lb/>
from this Legislature. They were not the delegates <lb/>
of the people, and did not represent their wishes or <lb/>
ours, nor aid they even conserve the interest of this <lb/>
Colony. The wily Canadians were too much for them. <lb/>
They saw what a capital opportunity it was for them <lb/>
to get hold of us, and endeavour to relieve themselves <lb/>
of the difficulties that were pressing them down. It <lb/>
was taken for granted in Canada that our delegates<lb/>
represented the feelings of the people of this Island. <lb/>
But they say, they only bound themselves. Who, he <lb/>
(Mr. Renouf) would ask, would have to pay their ex<lb break="no"/>penses? He presumed the country would pay the <lb/>
piper, and that we should very soon hear something <lb/>
about it in this House. Our position was very differ<lb break="no"/>ent from that of the other provinces. We had no <lb/>
large body of agricultural settlers here as tney had. <lb/>
In the other Colonies gentlemen sold out of the Army <lb/>
and Navy; purchased estates and settled down to the <lb/>
cultivation of the soil; and thus a good society was <lb/>
formed. Here it was far different. The merchant, <lb/>
as soon as he had made a fortune, left the country and <lb/>
enjoyed his wealth elsewhere. Our isolation was <lb/>
complete, and if we entered this Confederation it would <lb/>
be just the same. Besides, would not Canada have <lb/>
the benefit of our taxation? And what good were we <lb/>
to receive in return? Could we receive our flour and <lb/>
provisions from Canada? During six months of the <lb/>
year the navigation of the St. Lawrence was stopped <lb/>
by a barrier of ice that could never be removed. <lb/>
Would there be a cheaper mode of conveyance <lb/>
    
    
    <cb/>


after we were confederated than now? Then it had <lb/>
been said that our tradespeople and operatives could <lb/>
go to Canada and during a great part of the year <lb/>
receive large wages, and return here in comfort <lb/>
to their families. This was certainly very nice <lb/>
in theory, but he doubted if it could be practical<lb break="no"/>ly realised. Would not these people have to pay <lb/>
their passages, and would not that swallow up the <lb/>
greater part of their earnings? Besides, were the <lb/>
operative population better paid in Canada than they <lb/>
are here? Certainly not. As regarded the cod <lb/>
fishery, Canada has her own, and could supply her <lb/>
own wants; and therefore there would be no market <lb/>
for our fish there. What increased population <lb/>
could Confederation bestow upon the people of this <lb/>
Colony If Canada possesses such great resources, how <lb/>
was it that in the great exodus that took place <lb/>
here lately, not one in every hundred went to, Cana<lb break="no"/>da? If she offered so fine a field for our educated <lb/>
young men, how was it that none of them faced there? <lb/>
But if this Confederation were passed, he (Mr. Renouf) <lb/>
supposed that all the Canadian offices would be filled <lb/>
by Newfoundlanders. Did hon gentlemen really desire <lb/>
to impose upon this house and the country by such <lb/>
clap-trap. But after all, supposing that the sons of <lb/>
our wealthy people were really benefitted, what was to <lb/>
become of the sons of the fishermen and the trades<lb break="no"/>men? But these delegates well knew that, if this <lb/>
question was passed this session they would be well <lb/>
rewarded for it. Most likely they would have an <lb/>
audience of Her Most Gracious Majesty, and then it <lb/>
would be—"Rise, Sir Frederick B. T. Carter–Rise, <lb/>
Sir Ambrose Shea." This would be the result. But <lb/>
this question should not be affirmed this session. The <lb/>
people were the judges, and to them it should be sub<lb break="no"/>mitted. </p>
    
    <p>
The question that the section be adopted was then <lb/>
put and carried.</p>
    
    <p>
The remaining sections of the address were then <lb/>
read seriatim and adopted, and the Committee rose <lb/>
and the Chairman reported the address without <lb/>
amendment. </p>
    
    <p>
On motion of <persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName> the address was then <lb/>
read a third time and passed—to be presented to his <lb/>
Excellency the Governor by Mr. Speaker and the <lb/>
whole house. </p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> informed the House that his Excel<lb break="no"/>lency would receive the address at three o'clock to<lb break="no"/>morrow.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CART5">The hon ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> gave notice that on <lb/>
to-morrow he would move for leave to bring in Bills <lb/>
for the Registration of Births, Marriages and Deaths <lb/>
in this Colony—For regulating the appointment of <lb/>
Coroners—For the banishment of Criminal Offenders <lb/>
-For the maintenance of deserted wives and children <lb/>
-For the recovery of forfeited recognizances, and for <lb/>
the amendment of the law of Interpleader.</p>
    
    <p>
The House then adjourned until three o'clock; to<lb break="no"/>morrow. <lb/></p> 


    <!-- GL, 2018-11-13, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 


<!--<p>THE Noblest AMbition –It has been well remarked <lb/>
by an American poet, that "no gift however beautiful— <lb/>
no success, however brilliant—should be placed above <lb/>
the skill and talents which can relieve a single pang, and <lb/>
the self-devotion which lays then at the feet of the <lb/>
humblest fellow-creature." Judged by this rule, Profes­ <lb/>
sor Hollow ty, of whom the world his heard so much <lb/>
during the last twenty years, occupies a high position. <lb/>
His life seems to have been devoted to the aileviation of <lb/>
suffering, and his desire to benefit his fellow-creatures <lb/>
appears to have been seconded by an amount of natural <lb/>
talent and acquired skill seldom combined in one indivi. <lb/>
dual. The practical result of this combination has oeen <lb/>
the production of two remedies knºwn throughout the <lb/>
world as Holloway's Pills an Hollow ly's Ointment, <lb/>
wnich, if any value can be attached to human ºcstimony, <lb/>
have left all other devices of science far behind in the <lb/>
great work of relieving pain, strengthening the constitution <lb/>
and prolonging life. <lb/>
In bitious is ºrders especially, the Pills have been won­ <lb/>
derfully etic scious, and for that reason, they are a most <lb/>
important me ulc.ne in the country, where bºutous fewer <lb/>
and all the varieties of liver complaint are u fortunately <lb/>
so common. We learn from persons subject to buious <lb/>
attacks in the Spring and Faii, who have resorted to <lb/>
these Pils as a preventive, that they have never failed <lb/>
to save theim from such periodical affection; waile we <lb/>
have also the strongest possible testimony in their favour <lb/>
frºm individuals who have taken them in the worst stages <lb/>
of liver disease. Long before we haſ an opportunity to <lb/>
judge of their value from home testimony, ine medical <lb/>
journals and the daily press of Europe had referred to <lb/>
them in terms of praise. It gives us pleasure to say that <lb/>
our own experience confirins and v ºrities the statem ºuts <lb/>
derived from foreign sources. Not being conversant <lb/>
witu the pailosopny of medical science, we cannot enter <lb/>
into a learned exposition of the modus operan li of Hol­ <lb/>
loway's Pills in blious cases, but shall rest content <lb/>
with saying, that under the influence of the remedy the <lb/>
skin and the whites of the eyes soon lose their yellow <lb/>
tinge, the pain in the right side disappears, the appetite <lb/>
return, the digestion improves, and the pnysicial strength <lb/>
of the invalid is restored. Professor Holloway, who has <lb/>
made pnysiology and pathology his study for a quarter <lb/>
of a century, has given scientific whys an i was refores <lb/>
for their curative effects; we simply state that they fulfil <lb/>
the promises df the inve.1:or—a fact that has never been <lb/>
questioned, we believe, by those who have given them a <lb/>
fair trial,—h'ushington Commonwealth. <lb/>
<lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>SAFE AND SURE.-You cannot be bald or grey, and <lb/>
neither time nor sickness can blemish your hair, if <lb/>
you use MRs. S. A. Allex's World's Hair testorer <lb/>
and Zylooalsamum, or Hair Dressing. They are un­ <lb/>
equaled for restoring, invigorating, beautifying and <lb/>
dressing the hair. Every Druggist sells them." J. J. <lb/>
Dearin, Sole Agent for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>Újtjitſuſumātūtt. <lb/></p> 

<p>mere trick, for obvious purposes, of those who wished <lb/>
it ill. But the plain and simple resolution now belors <lb/>
us terminates all anxiety and trickery too, as far as <lb/>
this subject is concerned; and the certainty that the <lb/>
country will have abundant time for the fullestiny. <lb/>
tigation, will, we do trust, dispose all thinking men <lb/>
to take it up with a calm fixed purpose to get at its <lb/>
real merits. Those who desire this end should guard <lb/>
against the error, so fatal to just conclusions, of <lb/>
singling out any one particular feature of a scheme <lb/>
which may strike them as faulty,and on this fragment. <lb/>
ary evideoce, deciding against the whole. Neither <lb/>
will it do to seize upon any cant "cry" such, for ex. <lb/>
ample, as that of increased taxes—at once to make up <lb/>
one's mind that this cry is true because some people <lb/>
bawl it luntily; or that if not devoid of truth, it ne­ <lb/>
cessarily represents increased evils without a particle <lb/>
of compensation. All such modes of regarding the <lb/>
subject are utterly fallacious, and of course can lead <lb/>
to nothing but the most perverse, ignorant miscon. <lb/>
ceptions. If we are in earnest in wishing to estimate <lb/>
correctly its bearings upon"our interests.we must view <lb/>
the question as a whole,and inquire by careful and un­ <lb/>
biassed examination whether all that it is proposed to <lb/>
us to relinquish in the way of local control and local <lb/>
revenue, will not be fully compensated for in the ma­ <lb/>
terial and social advantages to arise to our people <lb/>
from close connection with our prosperous and pro­ <lb/>
gressive neighbours, and by the pecuniary contribu­ <lb/>
tions guaranteed to us in lieu of our present receipts. <lb/>
It is only by this abstract mode of analysing the case, <lb/>
and by dismissing the delusions of class crotchsts and <lb/>
prejudices, that our people can ever hope to possess <lb/>
themselves of the sort of information reliable for their <lb/>
guidance; and to this end time and leisure will now <lb/>
no doubt contribute the aid of their important <lb/>
agencies. <lb/>
REPORT OF THE BENE VOLEVT IRISH <lb/>
SOCIETY FOR THE YEAR ENDING <lb/>
17th FEBRUARY, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>ORPHAN Asylum, <lb/>
17th February, iss...} <lb/>
The fifty-ninth Anniversary Moeting of the Bene­ <lb/>
volent Irish Society was held this day, Hon. Edwago <lb/>
MoRkis, President, in the chair. <lb/>
The Rev. David Q')onnell proposed by T.S.Dwyer, <lb/>
Esq., seconded by Michael Rice, Esq., was unani. <lb/>
mously elected a member of the Society:­ <lb/>
The following gentlemen were elected by ballot, <lb/>
members of the Societv, viz., <lb/>
Mr. Patrick Kelly, proposed by Mr. Walter Irwin, <lb/>
seconded by Mr. Vºliam Dou: ney. <lb/>
Captain Philip Cleary, proposed by Mr. M. Birney, <lb/>
seconded by John Casey, Esq., M.H.A. <lb/>
Mr. James Kavanagh, proposed by Mr. John Walsh, <lb/>
seconded by Mr. William Doutney. <lb/>
The minutes of the last quarterly and intervening <lb/>
meetings having been read over and confirmed, the <lb/>
roll was called, and the sum of £31 17, 3d, was <lb/>
collected. <lb/>
The Treasurer reported the gross amount expended <lb/>
during the year for Teachers' salaries, improvements, <lb/>
repairs, &amp;c., as £465, 16s. 8d., and the gross receipts <lb/>
from all sources at £637 19s. 9 i... leaving a balanc, <lb/>
to the credit cf the Society of £172 3s. 1d. <lb/>
The Chairmat of the School then laid his report of <lb/>
the condition of the Schools and industrial depart­ <lb/>
ment upon the table, which, upon motion of John W. <lb/>
Nugent, Esq., seconded by Patrick Brazil, Esq., was <lb/>
received and adopted. The report is as follows:–<lb break="yes"/>Report of the Orphan Asylum School Committee for <lb/>
the year ending 17th of February, 1865. <lb/>
Your Committee in presenting their usual Annual <lb/>
Report of the Department committed to their care, <lb/>
regret they cannot congratulate the Society upon any <lb/>
improvement whatever in the Schools during the latt <lb/>
year, the attendance being only the same in number <lb/>
and frequently very irregular. <lb/>
Your Committee have given the subject their ear­ <lb/>
nest attention, and have endeavoured by every possi­ <lb/>
ble means to ascertain why advantages such as the <lb/>
Institution holds forth are not gladly availed of by <lb/>
those ſor whose benefit such a large sum is annually <lb/>
expended, but have failed to discover the cause, it <lb/>
is, however, believed, and expressed by many, that <lb/>
owing to the late disastrous fisheries, and the poverty <lb/>
consequent thereon, children are not in a condition tº <lb/>
attend school, the want of necessary clothing, &amp;c., <lb/>
being the general answer to all enquiries ºn the <lb/>
subject. <lb break="no"/>It has been stated also that much indifference exist, <lb/>
to the advantages of education amongst the class for <lb/>
whose benefit the Schools were established, and such <lb/>
certainly appears to be the case to a great extent; but <lb/>
when your Committee look back to those years when <lb/>
the Schools were presided over by the Christian <lb/>
Brothers, they find the number of children in ºund. <lb/>
ance to be more than the building could well accom­ <lb/>
modate, the roll presenting a list of over six hundred <lb/>
names. From this it would naturally appear that <lb/>
could the Society again secure the services ºf a com­ <lb/>
munity of some relgious teaching order, the Schools <lb/>
would again be filled. <lb/>
Your ºommittee do not question the ability of the <lb/>
Present Teachers in referring to the years when the <lb/>
Christian Brothers had the cºre of those Departments, <lb/>
but they do so to show the confidence which our com: <lb/>
munity then had, and no doubt would again have, in <lb/>
the advantages to be gained by having such men, not <lb/>
alºne in acquiring a superior education, but whose <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOH.W.? S: <lb/>
MONDAY, FEBRUARY 20, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>It is probable that the Attorney General's resolution <lb/>
on the question of Colonial Union will come under <lb/>
consideration in the Assembly to-day. Under all the <lb/>
circumstances we think this resolution embodies a wise <lb/>
and judicious course. The idea, however erroneous, <lb/>
thet it was conteiaplated to press the matter of Con­ <lb/>
federation to a precipitate issue, had tended to disturb <lb/>
many minds; and in this unsettled state, vague ap­ <lb/>
prehension of a 1 sorts of possible and impossible mis­ <lb/>
chiefs seemed to have usurped the place of dispassion­ <lb/>
ate inquiry.Those who permitted themselves to be thus <lb/>
influenced have been for the time rendered insapable <lb/>
of anything like correct appreciation of a matter which <lb/>
only presented to them causes of alarm; and even <lb/>
were it practicable, the attempt to carry the uneasure <lb/>
against such a feeling would have been an act of great <lb/>
rashness, involving special injustice to the object it­ <lb/>
self. We have already shown that no such proceed­ <lb/>
ing was intended by the friends of Confederation, <lb/></p> 

<p>and that the attribution of this course to them was a <lb/></p> 

<p>wouli tend so nuch to improve and fix the <lb/>
mºrals of the rising generation. <lb/>
The Teacher of the Upper School, Mr. Thomas <lb/>
McGrath, in November last tendered his resignation, <lb/>
Whiº was laii before a meeting of your Committee <lb/>
by the hon, the President, when it was decided that <lb/>
such resignation be received and Mr. McGrath duly <lb/>
notified thereof. His letter and the reply of the Com­ <lb/>
mittee are now laid upon the table. Under these cir­ <lb/>
* Your Committee would respectfully suggest <lb/>
that the pupils in the upper be removed to the ºver <lb/>
school under the care of Brother Francis Grace until <lb/>
such time as the Society can make other satisfactory <lb/>
*angements, or be enabled to carry out their desire <lb/>
ºf procuring teachers of the Order of the Christian <lb/>
#rothers, in endeavouring to accomplish which His <lb/>
Lºrdship the Patron of the Society is kindly using his <lb/>
strong influence. <lb/>
The School Fees for the year amount to £2 13s. 9d. <lb/>
The Report of the Industrial Department now laid <lb/>
upon the table, shews a falling off in the amount of <lb/>
wºrk done in comparison with late years. This is <lb/>
wholly attributable to the failure of the fisheries, there. <lb/>
buing very little demand for nets or net-mending, <lb/>
However, although the Department has not been able <lb/>
*...* its expenses, the balance to its debit is <lb/>
trifling. <lb/>
The Committee have also to report that what new <lb/>
nets were made during the past year have been pur­ <lb/>
chased at the current market value by Messrs. Laur­ <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/></p> 

<p># <lb/>
; <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>ſ: <lb/>
% <lb/>
;: * <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>ence O'Brien &amp; Co., who de <lb/>
this as on former occasions. <lb/>
Your Committee have muc <lb/>
that the Ball held in the Soc <lb/>
isit under the patronage of <lb/>
tended, and after paying all e <lb/>
able surplus which was voted <lb/>
stall: at the late Bazaar in ai. <lb/>
now in course of erection, an <lb/>
£20 1s. 4d. was handed over <lb/>
for that purpose. .. <lb/>
It was the intention of you <lb/>
ther improve the ground of <lb/>
other and a better description <lb/>
those already panted, but tº <lb/>
to carry out their wishes, hu <lb/>
mend that object to the atten <lb/>
The stone wall and paling . <lb/>
the eastward of the building <lb/>
tion, and vour Committee wº <lb/>
be rebuilt the coming season <lb/>
attention to the eastward end <lb/>
lery in front. The tower als <lb/>
a small sum will be required <lb/>
The property of the Societ <lb/>
schools is insured in the sum <lb/>
Respectfully submitted on <lb/></p> 

<p>WIL <lb/>
HEN <lb/></p> 

<p>Tde Chairman of Charity t <lb/>
which, upon motion of M <lb/>
seconded by John Casey, Esq <lb/>
and adopted. The report is <lb/>
Report of Chairman of Comº. <lb/>
culing 17th February, 18 <lb/>
I beg leave to report that t <lb/>
placed in the hands of the C <lb/>
distribution was, in accordan <lb/>
the Sºciety, expended in the <lb/>
was distributed to such object <lb/>
accredited tickets of the mem <lb/>
Annexed is a statement of <lb/>
ture, particulars of which will <lb/>
book of the cymmittee now o <lb/>
service of any memner wishin <lb/>
M[Chi <lb/></p> 

<p>The President then said th <lb/>
consideration was the vote for <lb/>
lated the Society on its pres: <lb/>
dition, and Irwing their attº <lb/>
of repairs, &amp;c., which existed <lb/>
grounds of the Society, sug: <lb/>
of giving to the utmºst extent <lb/>
the relief of the great distress <lb/>
isted, they should yet be guit. <lb/>
Society, and that as it appear <lb/>
those best acquainted with th: <lb/>
not in the present instance vo <lb/>
that course should be adopted. <lb/>
by J. W. Nugent, Esq., se. <lb/>
Esq., M.H.A., and <lb/>
Resolved,— That the sum of <lb/>
placed in tue hands of the Cu <lb/>
of Charity, to be distributed <lb/>
resºlution passed at the last <lb/>
After which the report of ti, <lb/>
was by the Presid'n' sub utte <lb/>
them, on in to 1 of Joan V. <lb/>
by Michael Stafford, E q., rec <lb/>
report is as follows:­ <lb/>
Report of the Presilent and tº <lb/>
Irish Society for the year q. <lb/></p> 

<p>We beg in the first place t. <lb/>
upon the attainment of this it. <lb/>
The first lunportant proceet. <lb/>
our last report, was its celeb! <lb/>
1)ay. Many of your me nber <lb/>
the occasion. subscribed the <lb/>
and Twenty-n ne Pounds as . <lb/>
the cost of the pi la s of the <lb/>
now in course of erection, an <lb/>
on that day in processivu, an <lb/>
together with a short addre, <lb/>
Right Rev. Dr. Mullock, wh <lb/>
pointment, at the foot of the <lb/>
chapel at River-head, from <lb/>
reply to the address, thanki <lb/>
setiments which it express <lb/>
purse as a " Inagn.ficent dona <lb/>
visited the Convent at itiver­ <lb/>
ed through the town to the <lb/>
attended the Sacred Ceremon <lb/>
evening a considerable nual <lb/>
guests dined at the Orphan A <lb/>
On the 29th of March a hi. <lb/>
the Society, was held in our I, <lb/>
which were applied by the cer <lb/>
in aid of the i3azaar for St. P <lb/>
On the 26th June the Socié: <lb/>
Mechanics and Total Abstitieſ <lb/>
the hand of St. Bonaventure's <lb/>
cession to be present at the lº <lb/>
of St. Patrick's ('hurch, which <lb/>
ed by His Lordship Dr. Mullu <lb/>
occasion to many thousands a <lb/>
On the 29th November a s, <lb/>
to consider the condition of ti <lb/>
of which is contained in the re. <lb/>
and Uommittee of the O. A. S <lb/>
to refer the Society. At tº <lb/>
formally voted the use of the U <lb/>
Building to the Catholic Instit <lb/>
its course of lectures. * <lb/>
A special meeting was held <lb/>
prepare an address to Chief Ju <lb/>
then about tº leave the countr <lb/>
was decide 1 that as it was prot <lb/>
would soon retire altogether fri <lb/>
be premature at that meeting <lb/>
the President was authorized <lb/>
this purpose when his retire <lb/>
place and transmit a suitable aſ <lb/>
The Society has gra'efully tº <lb/>
tinued liberal assistance of the <lb/>
Schools and Industrial Depart <lb/>
The building is sill insured <lb/>
rance Company for £1200. <lb/>
The report of the Chairman <lb/>
O. A. S. hool will be found to <lb/>
tion regarding that Departme: <lb/>
the treasurer will czhibit thi <lb/>
finanoes show ng the revenue! <lb/>
3:637 19s. 9s., and the expenſ <lb/>
Six new members were adu <lb/>
and four of our associates we <lb/>
of death—all esteemed and <lb/>
Fogarty, Patrick Fina, John I <lb/>
The late John Little, Esq., <lb/>
corded in the list of our depar <lb/>
for many years a prominent in <lb/>
and for several of the last yet <lb/>
Vice-President. He had ei <lb/>
Society by his unceasing atten <lb/>
by irreproachable and exempl. <lb/>
and a citizen, and on the part <lb/>
pectfully tender to his family <lb/>
with them in their sorrow for <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>