<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-06" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-03-06">6 March 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-05-01"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-12-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-12-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_1.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLADNER.</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">St. John's, Monday, May 1, 1865.</fw>
    
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2018-12-11, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

<!--<p>T­ <lb/></p> 

<p>otice. <lb/></p> 

<p>— <lb/>
TMothers T. Māºri <lb/></p> 

<p>procure Mrs. WINSLow" ... * * <lb/>
...iº.". ...; <lb/>
the prescription of one of tº ". <lb/>
and nurses in the United State est: <lb/>
for thirty years with never fa º it <lb/>
ºss, by millions of mother, sº §: <lb/>
|eeble infant of one week old . -<lb break="maybe"/>bly relieves the child frº.º. <lb/>
ſtomach and bowels, oorrect; .# <lb/></p> 

<p>ind energy to the whole System ity, <lb/></p> 

<p>ntly relieve Griping in the Bower, It <lb/></p> 

<p>e believe it the best and sures: re, and <lb/>
all cases of Dissentery and Diarh ned <lb/></p> 

<p>*r it arises from teething or any º -<lb break="maybe"/>rections for use will *çeompanve er <lb/>
tenuine unless the fac-simil: of C º <lb/>
the outside wrapper. Price ...'. <lb/>
* Sold by all Medicine Dealers. §. <lb/>
New York, and 205 High H. <lb/></p> 

<p>hd. <lb/>
RS. WINSLOW, <lb/></p> 

<p>Nurse and Female Physician <lb/>
of mothers, her sº. §.". <lb/>
ig, which greatly facilitates th: ... <lb/>
softening the gums, reducing all infi s <lb/>
|lay all pain and spasmodic actiºn a º <lb/>
ate the bowels. Depend upon it." . <lb/>
iye rest tº yourselves, and reliº. <lb/>
inſants. We have put up and jã this <lb/>
| thirty years, and can say, in conſ. <lb/>
what we have never boea able to . <lb/>
edicine—never has it failed in sº <lb/>
et a cure, when timely used. Never <lb/>
R instance of dissatisfaction by any ong <lb/>
un the contrary; all speak delighted <lb/>
ions, and speaks in tenuis of commenda. <lb/>
#ical effects and medical virtue. We <lb/>
batter "what we do now," after thirty <lb/>
nce. and pledge our reputation for the <lb/>
that we here declare. In almost every <lb/>
# the infant is suffering from pair and <lb/>
slief will be found in fifteen or twenty <lb/>
the syrup is administered. Full dire: <lb/>
# will accompany, each bottle. None <lb/>
iss the fac-simile of Curtis and Perkin, <lb/>
on the outside wrapper. Sold by prºg: <lb/>
put the world ... Principal Office, 48 Dey <lb/>
and 205 High Ho-born, England. Price <lb/>
per bottle. -<lb break="maybe"/>ng is an extract from a letter written by <lb/>
Holme, Pastor of the Pierrepont-stres: <lb/>
*h, Brooklyn, N Y, to the "Journal and <lb/>
Cincinnati, O., and speaks volumes in <lb/>
world-renowned medicine, Mrs. WINs. <lb/>
ng Syrup for Children Teething—"We <lb/>
isement in your cºlumns of Mrs. Wins<lb break="no"/>g Syrup. Now we never said a word in <lb/>
atent medicine before in our life, but we <lb/>
1 to say to your readers that this is no <lb/>
have tried it, and know it to be all i <lb/>
* probably one of the most successful <lb/>
the day, because it in one of the best <lb/>
your readers who have bahies can't do <lb/>
y in a supply." <lb/>
J. DEARIN, St. John's, <lb/>
Agent for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>PHOENIX FIRE <lb/></p> 

<p>º * 5. r <lb/>
raitce Cºpany. <lb/>
i Street and Charing Cross, London. <lb/>
ESTABLISHED–1782 <lb/>
TRU8TH 88 ANI, DIRECTOR8. <lb/>
ton, Esq. Kirkman D. Hodgº on Esq. <lb/>
ºpe, " .Jaines Horne, -6 <lb/></p> 

<p>rt, " William J. Lancaster, " <lb/>
" John D. Magen, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>ser, " John Mºgterman, Esq. M. P. <lb/>
ler, " John Timohy Oxley sq; <lb/>
odhant" |George Stanley keptor. " <lb/>
ion, " Benjamin Shaw, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>* Matthew Whiting, 44 <lb/>
Fran is Wilson, <lb/></p> 

<p>8R crººrº RIEs <lb/></p> 

<p>WiLLIAM HARRIs Esq. * <lb/>
George William Lowell, Esq. <lb/>
NIX FIRE UFFICE is confidently re<lb break="no"/>o the notice of the public—for the liberu <lb/>
|vtitude with which all claims upon it are <lb/>
paid- as well as for the almost unlimited <lb/>
tº it affords, comprising in addition to the <lb/>
Capital of the Cempany, the whole for <lb/>
us Proprieta y, composed oſsom <lb/>
pulent gentlemen and Merchants in the <lb/></p> 

<p>orm. <lb/></p> 

<p>NIX OPFICF has carried on an exten <lb/>
'ssful business for upwards of seventy<lb break="no"/>| The duty paid by it to Government for <lb/></p> 

<p>n Great Hºri ain and Ireland exceed <lb/>
rling per annum. <lb/>
| short time Insurances are undertaken <lb/>
NIX COMPANY on almost every de<lb break="no"/>sk, in Newfoundland at a moderate rate <lb/>
hich may be know on application to <lb/>
their office, in St. John's, where policies <lb/>
of charge. <lb/></p> 

<p>W. &amp; G. RENDEI.L, <lb/>
Agents for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE COLONIAL <lb/></p> 

<p>4 - -<lb break="maybe"/>SSIrance Ú0hpāilf <lb/>
Estarlished 1846. <lb/>
L, ONE MILLION STERLING. <lb break="no"/>e of Assuring before 25th <lb/></p> 

<p>May 1863. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>D IDIVISIt)N OF PROFITS. <lb/>
he advantage of this year's entry to the <lb/>
. Proposals must be lodged at the Offie" <lb/>
tewfoundland, or with one of the Agent" <lb/>
5th May next. <lb/>
RS BöNUs will be allocated at the <lb/>
ofts in 1864 to Policies opened before <lb/></p> 

<p>* Books for the Present Year. <lb/>
ER BY special act of PARLIAMENT. <lb/></p> 

<p>Governor. -<lb break="maybe"/>HON.THE EARL OF ELGIN &amp; <lb/>
NE. Governor-General, of INDIA. <lb/>
E-\-5 GEORGE STREET, EDINBURGH <lb/>
irectors in St. John's, Newfoundland. <lb/>
Brien, Esq. Walter Grieve, Esq., <lb/>
Merchant. <lb/>
William Henry Mare, Esq. <lb/>
ldviser—Henry Hunt Stabb, M. D. <lb/>
ent–Frederick J. Wyatt. -<lb break="maybe"/>'ON OF THE COMPANY. <lb/>
e of the Company............ £130,000 <lb/>
have divided Profits on two occasions­ <lb/></p> 

<p>1000,opened in 1847,has been increased <lb/></p> 

<p>the application of the Bonus; otbed <lb/>
Iroportion. -<lb break="maybe"/>avery five years; next division in 186". <lb/>
sceived in any part of the world whº <lb/>
e been established <lb/></p> 

<p>3lenſuumillander, <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, Monday, May 1, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>- Pubºished every Monday and Thursday <lb/></p> 

<p>*::::::::::::::::ºsiº <lb/>
2..."; fluck WoRTH STREET-Terms one <lb/>
Guinea per annº payable in advance. -<lb break="maybe"/>jºrtisements not limited (Auction-sales end notices <lb/></p> 

<p>A. #ich determine themselves excepted) are repeated <lb/>
j ordered in writing to be withdrawn, and are <lb/>
charged for accordingly. <lb/></p> 

<p>This paper is filed,and may be seen free of charge at <lb/>
ºilovay's Pill and Ointment Establishment, 24% <lb/></p> 

<p>grand, London. <lb/>
== <lb/>
SPECIAL IN TIMATION. <lb/>
The BENEFITS of Life Assºanee with the <lb/>
SMALLE87' 0UT LAY, <lb/>
ombined with the FULLEST SECURITY, <lb/></p> 

<p>is desirable object has been attained by the Policy <lb/>
This desira º holders of the <lb/></p> 

<p>Life.Association of Scotland <lb/></p> 

<p>By means of its Alocation of Profit in Cash towards <lb/>
º, Annual Reduction of the Premiums payable for the <lb/>
Policies, the older Policy-holders paying at present <lb/>
only 12s. 6d. (instead of 20s ) per £1 of the Premiums; <lb/>
and by the fºllowing <lb/>
REGULATION FOR FURTHER PIMINISHING <lb/>
OUILAY FOR LIFE ASSURANCE. <lb/></p> 

<p>Urtil the time when the premiums may be expected <lb/>
to be reduced by the application of prºfits, the Assured <lb/>
for £500 or upwards, may leave unpaid a cons derabie <lb/></p> 

<p>ortion (one-third or one-fourth) of the premiums re<lb break="no"/>sensary to keep the policy in force. . The unpaid part <lb/>
is allowed to remain in the hands of the Assured as <lb/>
long as he pleases, and he is not asked to pay interest <lb/>
thereon; but the amount, with accumulated interest, <lb/>
will be deducted from the sum assured at death, New <lb/>
Entrants thus at once commence with <lb/>
PAYMEN IS MUCH BELOW THE TABULAR <lb/></p> 

<p>RATES, <lb/>
and continue to make such reduced payments for six <lb/>
years, when they become entitled to reduction of the <lb/>
premiums by the applica:ion of Profits. They will, <lb/>
nevertheless, receive the same benefits and the same <lb/>
Share of profit, as if the full premiums had been paid. <lb/>
Present outlay is also further diminished by means of <lb/>
the Associations <lb/>
INCREASING POLICIES <lb/></p> 

<p>in which the sums Assured shall increase by the mere <lb/>
lapse of time to dowble the original amount, without <lb/>
corresponding increase of premium; and, under the <lb/>
Participating Class, the premi will be reducible by <lb/>
appliea'ion of Profits. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Policies do Not Contain several of the Res<lb break="no"/>raictions commonly imposed on Assured Lives, and <lb/>
couler wm the Policy-holders unusual and important <lb/>
liabilities and privileges. <lb/></p> 

<p>tº-entrants on or before 5TH APRIL <lb/>
will secure a decided advantage over later Entrants <lb/>
at the Division of brofit. <lb/></p> 

<p>NEWFG UN i) LAND BRANCH. <lb/>
HEAL) () FFICE.-ST. JOHN S. <lb/>
prºtectors: <lb/>
H. K. Dickinaon, Esq. Hon. James Cormack. <lb/>
Robert Grieve, Esq. <lb/>
Agent and Secretary.....................E. L. JARWIS. <lb/>
March 7 <lb/>
TH: Company carrying on business as wercurants <lb/>
in Greenwrk, under the firm of KERR &amp; <lb/>
McRRide, and in Newfoundland under the firm of <lb/>
McBride &amp; H ERR, was dissolv-d on the 20th day of <lb/>
February, 1865, of mutual cel.sent of the subscribers, <lb/>
only partners thereof. <lb/>
All debts due by the dissolved Company will he paid <lb/>
by the Company carrying ºn business in Greenock <lb/>
under the firm of R. K. Mct;Ride &amp; Co. and in New<lb break="no"/>ſoutſiland under the firm of Michride &amp; Co.—to whom <lb/>
the Stock of the dissolved concern has been transfer<lb break="no"/>red, and who are tº carry on the business in future for <lb/>
their own behoof; and they are also author.z-d to <lb/>
receive payment of, and tº discharge all debts due to, <lb/>
the dissolved concern. <lb/>
Greenock, 1st March, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>ROBERT KERR. <lb/>
JAMES McIBRIDE. <lb/>
PEl Elt MctiltiDE, <lb/>
Thos KING, Witness. <lb/>
Charles Shannon, Witness. <lb/>
March 23. 1 m. <lb/></p> 

<p>*AN CASHIRE <lb/>
Insurance Company. <lb/></p> 

<p>FIRE AND life. <lb/></p> 

<p>CAPITAL TRWO MILLION'S STERLING. <lb/>
Head Office: Exchange-Street, \lanchester. <lb/>
Board of LIRECTORs: <lb/>
- John Todd, Esq., Chairman. <lb/>
William H. Bradley, Esq. William Pilkington, Esq., <lb/>
John Clegg, Esq. Blackburn. <lb/>
• Darbyshire, Esq., Liv-Joseph Schofield, Esq. <lb/>
erpool. N. Shelmerdine, Esq. <lb/>
Alexander Ewing Esq., James Smith, Esq., Liver­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Glasgow pool. <lb/>
Şamuel Hargreaves, Esq. James Wagstaff, Esq., Lon<lb break="no"/>John Knowles, Esq. don <lb/></p> 

<p>J. Robinson Kay, Esq., Edward Wanklyn, Esq. <lb/>
Bury. Barton Wood, Esq. <lb/>
J. Schofield Mayson, Esq <lb/>
George Stewart, General Manager. <lb/>
E. I. JARWIS. <lb/>
Agent for Newfoundland. <lb/>
<lb break="no"/>Royal ARTillery.—Holloway's Ointment and <lb/>
Pills-A sej, ant in the Royal Artillery, writes, on <lb/>
December 12th, 1862, fom Poonamattee, Madras <lb/>
Presidency, that his right lg, from the arxie to the <lb/>
Falſ, was a quagmire of disease and corruption; that <lb/>
he was on the hoptal roll for twelve mºnths, with<lb break="no"/>Rut any improvement in his case; that he, as a forlorn <lb/>
ope, resolved to try Holloway's celebrated Ointment <lb/>
and Pills. These soon gave ease, expe led the end <lb/>
umours from the limb, healed the apparently incura<lb break="no"/>tle sore, and restored him to sound health. <lb/></p> 

<p>-º­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Everything In Season. That grey hairs are hon<lb break="no"/>ºrable in old age is a proverbial matter; but are <lb/>
they so in youth P Mrs. S. A. Allen's World<lb break="no"/>Har Restorer and Zylobalsamum, or Hair Dressing, <lb/>
** suited to both young and old, they restore grey <lb/>
hair to its youthful color, giving the roots the natural <lb/>
tourisment. They renew, preserve and increase the <lb/>
§rowth. Every 1)ruggist sells them. J. J. Dearin, <lb/></p> 

<p>House of ASSEMBLY. <lb/></p> 

<p>- - - THURSDAY, March 2. <lb/>
Mr. Evans did not know that he could say much on <lb/>
this important question which had not been said by hon <lb/>
members who had already addressed the House on the <lb/>
subject. Still he considered it his duty to state his <lb/>
opinions upon... a question of such deep importance, in<lb break="no"/>volving as it did the present and future destinies of the <lb/>
country. He fully concurred in the course proposed in <lb/>
the resolution before the chair. . The question ought to <lb/>
be fully considered by the constituencies previous to any <lb/>
decision being come to upon it in that House; and he <lb/>
cordially concurred in the views of the hon leader of the <lb/>
Government in that respect. The interests of this Is. <lb/>
land, in all time coming, were involved in the decision <lb/>
that would be come to, and therefore too much consi<lb break="no"/>deration could be giv. n to the question. After the most <lb/>
careful consideration of all that "had been advanted on <lb/>
both sides in that debate, he must say that the opinions <lb/>
he had previously formed were strengthened—that the <lb/>
weight of evidence and arguments was in favour of Uon. <lb/>
federaticm. So far from believing that Confederation <lb/>
would weaken the ties which bind us to the parent state, <lb/>
he considered that these ties would thereby be strength. <lb/>
en-d. He (Mr. Evans) would be no party to any pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings which he believed calculated to separate this <lb/>
Colony, from Great Britain; but he believed that in <lb/>
supporting Confeueratiºn he was prolonging, if not per<lb break="no"/>petrating the connection. The Confederacy would at <lb/>
once become a powerful state, while its progress in popu<lb break="no"/>lation and the development of material resources, judg<lb break="no"/>ing by the past, must be such as, in half a century <lb/>
hence, would place us in the very first position on this <lb/>
side of the Atlantic. At the same time, with the gener<lb break="no"/>ous assistance of the mother country, and the <lb/>
protection which her navy would afford to our fisheries <lb/>
and commerce, we would have no cause for anxiety as to <lb/>
the aggression of any foreign power, either in Europe <lb/>
or America. As to the ability of the Confederation to <lb/>
repel invasion, should it be attempted, he need only <lb/>
refer to the history of the revolutionary war of the <lb/>
United States. The thirteen United Coſol.ies, with a <lb/>
§. under the present population of British <lb/>
orth America, and with fewer material resources, suc<lb break="no"/>cessfully resisted all the efforts of the mother country <lb/>
to retain them under her dominion; and if they could <lb/>
do that, notwithstanding that at the commencement of <lb/>
the struggie England held military possession of the <lb/>
country, would we not be sufficiently powerful to r-pel <lb/>
foreign aggression, when we had the military and naval <lb/>
protection of ur at Britain combined with our own <lb/>
efforts P But what could the isolated Provinces of <lb/>
British North America do for their own defence, were <lb/>
they to be now attacked by an enemy? Would it be <lb/>
possible for them to combine for the purpose P. It was <lb/>
well known that such coulbination, without union, would <lb/>
be impracticable. What could our populotion of 130,<lb break="no"/>u00, scattered along such an extent of cºast, do fºr <lb/>
their own protection? We have neither the influence <lb/>
nor the power to command that respect which we would <lb/>
enjoy as a component portion of a 'Confederacy num<lb break="no"/>bering four millions, and which a few years would raise <lb/>
to four times that number, with a territory stretching <lb/>
from the Atlantic to the Pacific. And as to the means <lb/>
of defrºying our civil expenditure, and promoting educa<lb break="no"/>tion and the extension of roads, our means under ("on<lb break="no"/>federation would be fully as ample as now; while, if <lb/>
we gave up a certain portion of our independent legisla<lb break="no"/>tion, we would be adinitted to lexislate to the same ex<lb break="no"/>tent, for the Confederacy, through our representatives <lb/>
in the Federal House of Cominons, We did not so <lb/>
much part with our power of legislation as we combined <lb/>
with tue other British Colonies to legislate in common <lb/>
for objects of common interest. He cer ainly felt some<lb break="no"/>what alarmed at the learned Doctor's long array of <lb/>
figures; and if he thought there was any danger of a <lb/>
reduction in the number of members allotted to us, he <lb/>
would say, that it would be well to guard by an <lb/>
express stipulation against such a contingency. But <lb/>
he did not think we should ohject to the number <lb/>
of members assigned to us. e were fairly con<lb break="no"/>sidered, on the basis of population, and considering <lb/>
the ability and success with wrich our 19elegates sis<lb break="no"/>tained our interests at the Conference at Quebec, he felt <lb/>
no anxiety as to our interest being properly attended to <lb/>
in the Federal Parliament, provided the constituencies <lb/>
exercise proper judgment in the selection of rep -<lb break="maybe"/>tives; and any increase in their number would certainly <lb/>
not facilitate the selection of suitable representatives. <lb/>
Besides, as had been remarked by the hon and learned <lb/>
member for Fogo, Mr. Whiteway, the other provinces <lb/>
are interested in the fisheries, in common with ourselves, <lb/>
and Canada especially had for some time past bestowed <lb/>
great aitention upon her fisheries, although of minor <lb/>
importance compared with ours He did not apprehead <lb/>
that it would be disadvantageous to us to surrender our <lb/>
ungranted Crown Lands witnout mines and minerals to <lb/>
the General Government. He was of opinion that the <lb/>
apprehensions of hon members on that suºject were <lb/>
groundless. The General Government would have no <lb/>
interest except to render our Crown lands available for the <lb/>
public benefit; and they would be as open to us for settle<lb break="no"/>ment as they are now. If our mineral resources are as <lb/>
valuable as they are represented, it was only <lb/>
necessary that they should be known to secure abundance of <lb/>
capital to work them; and it would not be denied that a <lb/>
thorough geological survey of the Island would be more <lb/>
effectively carried out by the General Government than <lb/>
by our own unaided efforts. With respect to the ques <lb/>
tion of the tariff, he did see some difficulty, but he cul<lb break="no"/>sidered it by no means insurmountable; and considering <lb/>
the liberal manner in which the representation of our <lb/>
Delegates were met at the Uonlerence, he was satisfied <lb/>
every consideration would be extended to us. If the <lb/>
existing Canadian tariff were applied to our imports, we <lb/>
might at first be more highly taxed than now... But the <lb/>
hou ber, for Piacentia and St. Mary's Mr. Shea, <lb/>
had shown that we would soon have an importation of; <lb/>
Canadian gºods, which of course would come in ºi <lb/>
free i and from what the ben member for Carbonear, Mr. <lb/>
Rorke stated as to the quality and prices of the samples of <lb/>
Canadian leather, boots, shoes, and other articles ne rad <lb/>
from Quebec, last fall, there was no reason to doubt that <lb/>
we would find it for our advantage to import Canada <lb/>
manufactured laather te a considerable extent j and he <lb/>
agreed with hon members who anticipated toat we would <lb/>
siso import Canadian woollens, to souns extent. He was <lb/>
also satisfied that the union would lead to the estaufism<lb break="no"/>ment of local manufactures. But these changes would be <lb/>
only of gradual introduction; and in the mean<lb break="no"/>time, it ought to be arranged that we should <lb/>
not be required to contribute more to the general reve<lb break="no"/>nue, accoiding to population, than the other colonies. <lb/>
The hon member for Ferryland, Mr. Glen, objected that <lb/>
there were no sip:ulations in the Resolutions agailst an <lb/>
export duty upon fish and oil. He (Mr. Evans) did not <lb/>
think any such stipulations neeessary, for he was perfect­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Solº Agent for Nerioundland, to whom all orders <lb/>
tnust bu addressed. <lb/></p> 

<p>ly satisfied that the General Government would not at<lb break="no"/>tempt it. There was no export duty on fish and oil ſron <lb/></p> 

<p>any of the British North American Colonies now; but <lb/>
there was an export duty on timber from New Rruns. <lb/>
wick, in lieu of stumpage, and upon Coal and other min. <lb/>
erals in Nova Scotia, in lieu of Royalty; and the stipu. <lb/>
lation in the Resolutions, that there should be no export <lb/>
duty on these, was simply because, as a portion of the <lb/>
Crown lands revenue, they belonged to Nova Scotia and <lb/>
New Brunswick respectively, and they found it most <lb/>
ºnvenient in these provinces to collect the revenue upon <lb/>
them by an export duty. But he (Mr. Evans) did not <lb/>
believe the General Government would attempt to 1m<lb break="no"/>É. any export duties, which was contrary to the en<lb break="no"/>ightened spirit of modern commercial legislation. The <lb/>
hon reember also eomplained of the Canadian tariff as <lb/>
protective while our interests lay in the direction of Free <lb/>
Trade; and also that Freneh saught fish was admitted <lb/>
into Canada, duty free, and would also come in here un<lb break="no"/>der the Canadian tarif. But the Canadian tariff would <lb/>
not be adopted by the Federal Legislature without modi<lb break="no"/>fication, even if the existing import duties under it should <lb/>
be retained. The Federal tariff would, of course, be <lb/>
adapted to the local requirements of the several Colonies. <lb/>
He did not look upon the proposed Confederation as <lb/>
the submission of this Colony to a hostile country which <lb/>
would pay little regard to our interests, but an "alliance <lb/>
with sister Colonies, for the promotion of our mutual <lb/>
interests, which could only be done by the general Le<lb break="no"/>gislature carefully considering the wants and wishes of <lb/>
tue several Confederated Colonies.—of course steam <lb/>
communication with the United Kingdom and with Cana<lb break="no"/>da, was indispensible to the beneficial operation of the <lb/>
union. The steamers for Canada should call at some of <lb/>
the ports of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick on the <lb/>
Gulf of St. Lawrence. This would open up a valuable <lb/>
trade with these Colonies; and in return for our imports <lb/>
frºm them, they would be good customers for our "her<lb break="no"/>rings and other fishery products. He hoped the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would erect an additional number of Lighthouses <lb/>
on our south wratern Coast, along what was the highway <lb/>
to the Gulf of the river St. Lawrence. Confederation <lb/>
would give us a uniform currency, as well as a uniform <lb/>
tariff, and it could not be denied that both would prove <lb/>
advantageous in our business relations with the other <lb/>
colonies. It has been urged that our commercial inter<lb break="no"/>course with the other Colonies is limited. But the coin<lb break="no"/>merce of British North America, though extensive now, <lb/>
can only be said to be in its infancy; and as population <lb/>
increased, the demands for the products of our fisheries <lb/>
in the other colonies would increase still more rapidly, for <lb/>
Agriculture and other pursuits would, no doubt occupy <lb/>
the attention of their people to a large extent; and we <lb/>
right anticipate supplying them to a much greater ex<lb break="no"/>tent than now with the produce of our fisheries. It <lb/>
had been objected that theie is no uniformity of interests <lb/>
between Canada and this Colony, that we are a fishing <lb/>
community, while Canada is an agricultural, lumbering <lb/>
and manufacturing country. But for that very reasun <lb/>
he considered that we would be of the greater advantage <lb/>
to each other. We would be good customers for the <lb/>
flour, pork and butter of Canada, and also, he believed <lb/>
for Canadian manufactures, while Canada would affori <lb/>
us an extensive market for our herrings and some other <lb/>
articles of which we had an unlimited supply of very <lb/>
superior quality; and he had not the least doubt that as <lb/>
population increase i in Canada and the North Western <lb/>
territory, the demand for the products of our fisheries fºr <lb/>
these markets would exceed any thing at present antici<lb break="no"/>pa'ed. With the modifications in the resolutions to <lb/>
which he had referred, he was of opinion that the pro<lb break="no"/>popose 1 union would operate beneficially for Newfound<lb break="no"/>iand. The present condition of a large portion of <lb/>
our operative population was most distressing; and <lb/>
it was our bounden duty to devise some means fºr <lb/>
their relief. Hitherto they had derived but little benefit <lb/>
from the immense treasures drawn from our waters. In <lb/>
years of prosperous fisheries they were comfortable; but <lb/>
when the catch was short, partly, no doubt, from impro<lb break="no"/>vidence, but chiefly from the precarious nature of their <lb/>
occupaion, large numbers were reduced to destitution. <lb/>
It was admitted on all hands that other occupations <lb/>
hesides the fisheries, must be provided for a considera<lb break="no"/>ble number of our people, or that they must émigrate: <lb/>
and as this proposal of union appeared to open up to us <lb/>
a prospect beneficial to our operative population, as calcu<lb break="no"/>lated to provide them with increased employment. be <lb/>
thought we would be recreant to our duty to the country <lb/>
if we did not take it into serious cousideration. The <lb/>
hon. ber fur B , Mr. Wyatt, said our interests <lb/>
would be attended to on the other side of the water, <lb/>
better than by any delegation from this Colony; but he <lb/>
( ir. Evans) did mean to disparage the efforts of gentle: <lb/>
men in England interested in this Colony, when he said <lb/>
he would be surry to see the protection of our constitu<lb break="no"/>tional rights entrusted to any person not responsiole to <lb/>
the people of the country, and he did think that in a <lb/>
matter of such vital importance it was essential to the <lb/>
protection of our interests that we should be represented <lb/>
at the final passing of the Imperial Act, by Deegates <lb/>
thoroughly informed as to our interests, and the wants <lb/>
and wishes of the constituencies of the colony. It would <lb/>
appear, however, that a final conclusion will not be come <lb/>
to on the subject by some of the other colonies, and <lb/>
therefore the members returned to the next House of <lb/>
Assembly would have an opportunity of considering the <lb/>
whole question, with the great advantage of being furnish<lb break="no"/>ed with the views of the constituencies upon it, and be<lb break="no"/>ing fully informed as to the cºurse, taken by the Legisla<lb break="no"/>tures of the other coionies. He (Mr. Bwans) would not <lb/>
longer occupy the time of the house. He looked upºn <lb/>
Confederation, on fair ter.ns, as calculated to be eminently <lb/>
beneficial to this Colony. With the two or three mod.<lb break="no"/>fications of the resolutions, to which he had referred, and <lb/>
which, he believed, could be easily accomplished, he <lb/>
considered it would result beneficially to the country, and <lb/>
would greatly promote the prog.ess of its people, souially <lb/>
commercially and politically. <lb/>
on motion of non arro.txey General, the committee <lb/>
then rose, and the Charinaa reporteu progress. To sit <lb/>
agala to-mºrrow. <lb/>
Mr. PABsoss gave notice that, on Thursday next, he <lb/>
would ask leave to bring in a Biu to urovide for the <lb/>
election of a Light-house va Cape St. Francis. <lb/>
Mr. Resoup gave no ice that, ou to-norrow, he would <lb/>
ask toe Acting Colonial Secretary what action has been <lb/>
taken by the Gºvernment to furnish the B.itism Norta <lb/>
American Association of London, witn Parliamentary, <lb/>
statistical and other documentary information relating to <lb/>
this Island, the character of such documents, if auy, <lb/>
sent since the reception by the Covernmeut of the circu<lb break="no"/>lar and rules of the said Association, dated 1st March, <lb/>
1862 Also, for a statement, showing the localities of <lb/>
the Pillar letter boxes in tais town, how often they a <lb/>
empited of their contents, the number of newspapers and <lb/>
letters deposited in these boxes for town aud *†. <lb/>
delivery, ºne British North American Provinces, fireat <lb/>
Britain and Ireland, and foreign Countries, with, thº<lb break="no"/>amount of revenue drawn from the said Pillar boxes, <lb/>
from date of establishmelt to the end of February last. <lb/>
The House trea, adjauraed until to-uorrow at three <lb/></p> -->

<p rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, March 6.</p>
    
    <p>
The house met at three o'clock. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:EVAN2">Mr. EVANS</persName> presented a petition from James Harvey <lb/>
and others, of Burin, which was received and read, <lb/>
praying that he may be compensated for making a road <lb/>
there. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">SURVEYOR GENERAL</persName> presented a petition from <lb/>
David Candow and others, of King's Cove and settlements <lb/>
adjacent, which was received and read, praying for a grant <lb/>
to complete the road between that settlement and <lb/>
Bonavista. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName> presented a petition from Robert Raymond <lb/>
and other, of the Goulds, which was received and <lb/>
read, praying for a grant to open a road to Shoal Bay. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName> also presented a petition from John H. <lb/>
McKie, of Bay Bulls, which was received and read set<lb break="no"/>ting forth that he had filled the office of Stipendiary <lb/>
Magistrate and Preventive Officer of Customs at that <lb/>
place, for the last 53 years, and praying for a retiring <lb/>
allowance sufficient to support him in his old age. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName>, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
table, would observe that he believed that the claims of <lb/>
the petitioner to liberal consideration would be recogni<lb break="no"/>zed on both sides of the house. He was now eighty-one <lb/>
years of age, and had served the colony for fifty-three <lb/>
years, and there never was a complaint of the manner <lb/>
in which he discharged his duties. He found it neces<lb break="no"/>sary, on account of his increasing infirmities, to resign <lb/>
his offire some months ago, and the Government granted <lb/>
him tile usual allowance of half salary, on his retire<lb break="no"/>ment, being £75 a year; which was the same as was <lb/>
given to other retiring magistrates who had been only 7 <lb/>
or 8 years in office. The Goverment however, consented <lb/>
to the matter being brought before the house, that his <lb/>
claim to an increased allowance, on account of his long <lb/>
services, might he considered by hon members. He <lb/>
(Mr. Glen) intended to propose in committee on supply, <lb/>
that the retiring allowance be made £100 a year, with <lb/>
which the petitioner would be perfectly satisfied. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Mr. E. D. SHEA</persName>.—The manner in which that claim <lb/>
came before the house entitled it to the most favourable <lb/>
consideration by hon members on both sides. The pe<lb break="no"/>titioner had spent a long life in the public service. He <lb/>
had given great satisfaction, and his character for integri<lb break="no"/>ty stood high; and while the government, adopted the <lb/>
usual course in the matter, they marked their apprecia<lb break="no"/>tion by suggesting that his claim should be brought be<lb break="no"/>fore the house for special consideration. He (Mr. Shea) <lb/>
was satisfied hon members on both sides of the house <lb/>
would readily assent to the very moderate increase <lb/>
which would be proposed, that the retiring allowance to <lb/>
their venerable gentleman be increased from £75 to £100 <lb/>
a year. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA2">Mr. A. SHEA</persName> fully agreed in all that had been said <lb/>
respecting the services of the petitioner. He had known <lb/>
that gentleman for many years, and he would only ob<lb break="no"/>serve that his conduct publicly and privately had secu<lb break="no"/>red him the respect of all to whom he was known. He <lb/>
had given the country the service of a long life, and he <lb/>
(Mr. Shea) had no doubt that house would take the same <lb/>
view of the case as the government had done; that his <lb/>
long services fully entitled him to the very moderate in<lb break="no"/>crense of his retiring allowance suggested by the hon <lb/>
member who presented the petition. In the appointment <lb/>
of the gentleman who succeeded him, the government <lb/>
had selected a worthy man an old and respectable resi<lb break="no"/>dent; and it was highly creditable to them to have selec<lb break="no"/>ted for the office a gentleman so eminently qualified, <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:LEAM2">Mr. LEAMON</persName> presented a petition from Edward <lb/>
O'Keefe and others, of Brigus, which was received and <lb/>
road, praying for a grant to erect a public wharf there. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:LEAM2">Mr. LEAMON</persName>, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
table, would observe that it was on a subject of great <lb/>
importance to the community. All the wharves at Bri<lb break="no"/>gus were owned by private parties; mostly by planters, <lb/>
who did not care to have them made use of for the public <lb/>
accommodation; and in the fall of the year especially, <lb/>
much inconvenience was experienced when the Concep<lb break="no"/>tion Bay Steamer arrived, in landing and embarking <lb/>
passengers and goods. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">SURVEYOR GENERAL</persName> presented a petition from <lb/>
Samuel Evans and others, of Greenspond, which was <lb/>
received and read, praying for a grant to build a bridge <lb/>
between that Island and Ship Island; also a petition <lb/>
from John White and others, of Greenspond, which was <lb/>
received and read, praying that no further grant be made <lb/>
to construct the bridge between that Island and Ship <lb/>
Island. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName> had great pleasure in supporting the <lb/>
prayer of the latter of these petitions. The former he <lb/>
would oppose, as the bridge prayed for would ruin the <lb/>
harbor, if erected. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that these petitions lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Mr. E. D. SHEA</persName> presented a petition from Michael <lb/>
Hayes and others, of Brigus South, which was received <lb/>
and read, praying for a grant to repair the bridge to the <lb/>
Island there. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:WINT1">Dr. WINTER</persName> presented petitions from James Verge <lb/>
and others, of Trinity, from Michael Murphy and others, <lb/>
of Trinity Harbor, from A. H. Cole and others, of <lb/>
British Harbor, from James Werge and others, of Plate <lb/>
Cove, from A. W. Bremner and others, Trinity South <lb/>
Side, and from Thomas Lawler and others, of British <lb/>
Harbor, whicn were severally received and read, pray<lb break="no"/>ing for grants to repair and complete roads in these <lb/>
localities. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that these petitions lie on the table. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. WINTER also presented a petition from B. Sweet<lb break="no"/>land and others, of King's Cove, which was received and <lb/>
read, praying for the appointment of a keeper of the <lb/>
half-way house between Trinity and King's Cove; also <lb/>
a petition from Alexander Bremner and others, Con<lb break="no"/>missioners of the public wharf at Catalina, which was <lb/>
received and read, praying for an additional grant for its <lb/>
competion. <lb/></p> 

<p>Ordered that these petitions lie on the table. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WINT1">Dr. WINTER</persName> gave notice that, on to-morrow he would <lb/>
move an address to his Excellency the Governor in <lb/>
Council, on the petition from the Commissioners for the <lb/>
erection of a public wharf at Catalina; also that he would <lb/>
ask the Surveyor General to lay before the house an <lb/>
estimate of the expense of erecting a bleakwater at <lb/>
Grates Cove. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LEAM2">Mr. LEAMON</persName> gave notice that he would, on to-morrow, <lb/>
move an address to his Excellency the Governor on the <lb/>
petition of the inhabitants of Brigus, for a grant to erect <lb/>
    a <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> wharf there. <lb/></p> 

<p>The hun Acting Colonial Secretary, by command of <lb/>
his Excellency, the Governor, presented to the house the <lb/>
report of the Board of Works for the year 1864, with <lb/>
accompanying documents relating to the various services <lb/>
under control of the Board. <lb/> </p>  

<p>Ordered that these documents lie on the table. <lb/></p>
  
  
<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-05-01_Page_2.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. KENT</persName> presented a petition from John O'Con<lb break="no"/>nor and others, Roman Catholic inhabitants of Car<lb break="no"/>bonear, which was received and read, setting forth, <lb/>
that petitioners, during the last twenty-two years, had <lb/>
a majority in the Board of Commissioners of the Car<lb break="no"/>bonear Grammar School, that whenever a vacancy oc<lb break="no"/>urred in the said Board, by the death or resignation <lb/>
of any member, the Government heretofore always <lb/>
observed the rule of giving the Roman Catholis a <lb/>
Preponderating influence, according to the well under<lb break="no"/>stood intention of the Legislature when the law for <lb/>
establishinent of the said Institution was enacted; that <lb/>
petitioners are aware that in the month of January, <lb/>
1864, the surviving members of the Board applied to <lb/>
the then Governor in Council, to fill the places at the <lb/>
Board vacant by the death of Joseph Ryan, Esq., a <lb/>
Roman Catholic, William Bemister, Esq., a Protest<lb break="no"/>ant, and Richard McCarthy, a Catholic; and as no <lb/>
reply was received to the application, and as a recent <lb/>
appointment of two Protestants has been made, with<lb break="no"/>out any reference to the existing members of the <lb/>
Board, thereby giving the Protestants a prepoaderance <lb/>
in the management of the school, petitioners beg <lb/>
leave to state that the regard they said appointment as <lb/>
an infringement of their rights as Roman Catholics; <lb/>
and praying that that the house would adopt such <lb/>
measures as they may deem fit, to reinstate petition<lb break="no"/>ers in the rights and priivileges which they so long <lb/>
enjoyed in the management of the Carbonear Gram<lb break="no"/>mar School. <lb/></p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. KENT</persName>, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
table, said it related to a subject which he had fancied <lb/>
had been definitely settled a quarter of a century ago. <lb/>
The complaint which he had now to make to the <lb/>
house, and to which that petition referred, was occa<lb break="no"/>sioned by religious dissensions, and he, therefore, re<lb break="no"/>gretted that he was the medium of the matter being <lb/>
placed before the country, more particularly now at a <lb/>
period of our history when it was hoped that all religi<lb break="no"/>ous discord in educational subjects had <choice><sic>beeu</sic><corr>been</corr></choice> done <lb/>
away with, and when we were all to be sent about our <lb/>
business, and to appeal to the country in order to <lb/>
secure a fresh return. He (Mr. K.) thought that at a <lb/>
period like this the Ministry ought to be particularly <lb/>
cautious not to impress the mind of the country that <lb/>
they were acting with feelings of partiality towards <lb/>
one class—a course which must tend to the spread of <lb/>
acrimonious feelings and religious dissensions. He <lb/>
(Mr. K) regretted it more particularly at this time, <lb/>
when we are going to lose the services of the talented <lb/>
leader of the Government. For he (Mr. K) fully <lb/>
believed that if the hon Attorney General hid been <lb/>
made acquainted with the circumstances of this case, <lb/>
and the cause of this complaint, he would very soon <lb/>
have checked the sectarian tendencies of those by <lb/>
whom he was surrounded. In 1843, Mr. Barnes, in <lb/>
moving the second reading of the Education Bill, <lb/>
quoted the following protests of the Roman Citnolics <lb/>
and Protestants on the system that at the time exist- <lb/>
"As His Excellency is well aware, the cause of con<lb break="no"/>ficting opinions in Ireland was, as long as the system <lb/>
of which the foregoing resolution is in substance the <lb/>
same, and formerly adopted by the Kildare Street So<lb break="no"/>ciety, in Schools, and we are sure His Excellency is <lb/>
aware that we, professing the Roman Catholic religion <lb/>
cannot countenance or support a system which has <lb/>
been condemned, not only by the superiors of the <lb/>
Irish Catholic Church, but by his Most Gracious Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's enightened Government. <lb/></p>
    
    
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>
"We must further submit to Hs Excellency's supe<lb break="no"/>rior judgment the situation the foregoing resolution <lb/>
will place us in as Roman Catholios, and waich we are <lb/>
sure he will see that we have no aftemative left, if he <lb/>
should be pleased to accept our resignation, as we <lb/>
would not conscientiously remain as members of a <lb/>
Board of Education whose object is to divert the pub<lb break="no"/>lic moneys granted for elementary education, into re<lb break="no"/>ligious or sectarian purposes. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>"We beg also to inform. His Excellency that prior <lb/>
to the passing of this resolution, we repeatedly and <lb/>
solemnly told the Board, that if they adopted it, we <lb/>
had no alternative left but to request His Excellency <lb/>
would be pleased to withdraw his approvol of the same <lb/>
thereby preventing it from becoming a Bye-law, or if <lb/>
he should approve of it, to accept our resignations, and <lb/>
which solicitations appeared to be quite useless, and <lb/>
which was the cause of our withdrawal from the Board <lb/>
before the conclusion of the meeting. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
"We are quite satisfied His Excellency will view <lb/>
our conduct in a favoravle light, in withdrawing from <lb/>
a Board that cannot have our support, if such a line of <lb/>
policy is continued; but, on the contrary, must be <lb/>
conscientiously discouraged by us. <lb/></p>
        
<p rendition="simple:centre">We have, &amp;c.,</p>
        
        <table>
            <row><cell>(Signed)</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">DENIS MACKIN,</cell></row>
            <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">CHARLES DALTON,</cell></row>
            <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">PETER BROWN,</cell></row>
            <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">JAMES POWER,</cell></row>
        </table>
        
        <p>
"Under those circumstances, we, the only Protest<lb break="no"/>ant members present at the meeting, have found it im<lb break="no"/>practicable to perform the important duties assigned to <lb/>
us. And therefore beg leave, as the only alternative, <lb/>
to tender to His Excellency the Governor, our resig<lb break="no"/>nation and to lament the existence of a law that pre<lb break="no"/>vents us the free exercise of our judgment upon a <lb/>
measure involving the best interests of the com<lb break="no"/>munity. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">We have, &amp;c.,</p>
        
        <table>
            <row><cell>(Signed)</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">BURT, Episcopal Missionary,</cell></row>
            <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">J. PICKAVAUT, Wesleyan Missionary,</cell></row>
            <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">THOMAS RIDLEY,</cell></row>
            <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">JOHN STARK,</cell></row>
            <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">WILLIAM STERLING.</cell></row>
        </table>
        
        <p>The Honorable the Colonial Secretary.' <lb/></p>
</quote>
    
    
<p>The Education Act of 1863 put an end to all these <lb/>
sectarian disputes, and its provisions had been found <lb/>
to be so fair, so equitable, and so just, that the edu<lb break="no"/>cational vote had always been granted without one <lb/>
word of complaint being offered. The two Grammar <lb/>
Schools in the district of Conception Bay, at Harbor <lb/>
Grace and Carbonear, had been established for the <lb/>
purpose of giving a superior education to the youth of <lb/>
the higher classes, and at the time of the passing of <lb/>
the Bills, there was a tacit understanding that the ma<lb break="no"/>jority of the Board of Commissioners of Harbour <lb/>
Grace should be Protestant, and that in Carbonear, <lb/>
where the majority of the people were Catholics, the <lb/>
Board should nave a Catholic najority. Throughout <lb/>
the past twenty-one years, through different forms <lb/>
and classes of governments, this rule had been strictly <lb/>
followed, until now, for the first time, that it has been <lb/>
changed. Now what has there been to justify this? If <lb/>
the Protestants of Carbonear felt aggrieved at the <lb/>
conduct of the Directors there, they could send their <lb/>
children to Harbor Grace, as the Catholics of Harbour <lb/>
Grace could send their children to Carbonear. It had <lb/>
been stated that a petition had been sent in to His <lb/>
Excellency the Governor, a few days ago. He (Mr. <lb/>
K.) would ask whether it had been prevented? Had <lb/>
it been suppressed? He appealed to the hon Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General, whether he was to receive an answer or <lb/>
not? <lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> –Certainly not, without <lb/>
a proper notice being first given. <lb/></p>
        
        <p><persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. KENT</persName> —When the character of the Government <lb/>
was affected by this question, was it possible that they <lb/>
would get rid of answering on a mere matter of form? <lb/>
What he said was that these parties stated that a peti<lb break="no"/>tion was sent to his Excellency the Governor, and was <lb/>
he (Mr K) to let it so abroad, that the present Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, in order to carry out their own section <lb/>
views, had that petition suppressed? Why were these

<cb/>

vacancies in the Board not filled up immediately? <lb/>
What necessity was there to leave it without a quo<lb break="no"/>srum for twelve months, unless there had been some <lb/>
sectarian conspiracy to change the character of the <lb/>
School? What satisfactory answer could the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment give the country relative to this movement? <lb/>
Four of the Board there, being a quorum, appoint a <lb/>
teacher. The Government wait until he is appointed, <lb/>
and then they appoint two Protestant Directors to the <lb/>
Board. The Chairman, who had resigned, resumes <lb/>
his place, and actually questions the legality of the act <lb/>
of the Board, the incompleteness of which was itself <lb/>
occastioned by the remissness of the Government. <lb/>
Look, then, at the manner in which the Government <lb/>
endeavored to throw the odium of their act upon the <lb/>
Governor. Since the introduction of Responsible <lb/>
Government, all appointments were made by his Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency in Council. Did they wish to escape from <lb/>
the turnitude of their proceeding by throwing the res<lb break="no"/>ponsibility in this case upon his Excellency? (The <lb/>
hon. gentleman here read the form of announcement in <lb/>
            the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi>) It there was any mismanagement of the <lb/>
school, why was it not properly remedied? Why was <lb/>
not the teacher dismissed? He (Mr. K.) contended <lb/>
that perfect faith should be kept with the people of <lb/>
Carbonear, and no act should be permitted to derange <lb/>
what existed for a quarter of a century. Now, he <lb/>
would ask the Attorney General to allow that nomina<lb break="no"/>tion of the teacher to continue. Would he, in the <lb/>
eleventh hour, and when we were on the eve of a gen<lb break="no"/>eral election, allow that good faith to be violated <lb/>
which had existed so long? Now that he was going <lb/>
to retire from politicil life, would he not preserve the <lb/>
rights of the Catholics, not only of Carbonear, but of <lb/>
the whole country? <lb/></p> 

<p>The <persName ref="pers:CART5">hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> sincerely deprecated <lb/>
in common with the hon member for St. John's East, <lb/>
Mr Kent, the existence of any sectarian feeling, whe<lb break="no"/>ther in the district of Conception Bay or elsewhere. <lb/>
He must say, however, that in his humble judgment, <lb/>
if any such feelings were produced they could only be <lb/>
attributed to hon member, Mr Kent, and his some<lb break="no"/>what unreasonable pretensions. That Grammar school <lb/>
at Carbonear had been a reproach to that town for <lb/>
years, and a constant source of trouble and annoyance <lb/>
to the Government. Constant complaints had been <lb/>
made as to the total inefficiency and worthlessness of <lb/>
that school, and that the money which was expended <lb/>
was entirely thrown away. It was not agreeable to be <lb/>
compelled to say anything that would reflect on the <lb/>
character of the dead, but it was absolately necessary <lb/>
that under certain circumstances the truth should not <lb/>
be coucealed. It was a notorious fact that for years <lb/>
that school had been in such a condition, owing to the <lb/>
conduct of the Principal, that few persons sent their <lb/>
children to it. In fact the money given for its Sup<lb break="no"/>port, was merely for the education of two or three <lb/>
pupils who attended. Now hon gentlemen knew this <lb/>
to be true, and also that one denomination had, at <lb/>
their own expense, to provide a school, so that their <lb/>
children might not be deprived of the benefit of edu<lb break="no"/>cation. Not only was that notorious, but it had come <lb/>
before the Legislature last session when a petition <lb/>
was presented to the House praying that an enquiry <lb/>
should be had into the working of that Grammar <lb/>
School. A similar petition had been presented to the <lb/>
Government, who directed an enquiry to be made, but <lb/>
which led to no satisfactory result. It seemed that <lb/>
the Commissioners, or a majority of them, were dis<lb break="no"/>posed to uphold the all condition of affairs, and so the <lb/>
school continued to be a reproach to the Board of <lb/>
Directors. Now in his (hon A Gen's) opinion, it made <lb/>
to difference who these Directors were. Whether <lb/>
they were Protestant or Catholic they should have <lb/>
made some effort to place the school in some state of <lb/>
efficiency. Things continued this way until the death <lb/>
of the late Master of the school, when it was consider<lb break="no"/>ed that a fitting opportunity had arrived to place the <lb/>
school under proper management. The Consequence <lb/>
was that one party made application for the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of two Roman Catholic Directors, another for <lb/>
two Protestants, while a third party applied to have <lb/>
the grant divided, and to put an end to the difficulty, <lb/>
without giving any cause of dissatisfactoin to either <lb/>
party. Under these circumstances, and seeing these <lb/>
conflicting opinions, the Government would not act in <lb/>
the matter, and addressed a letter to the Commission<lb break="no"/>ers, telling them to do nothing until the subject was <lb/>
brought before the Legislature, unless the people of <lb/>
Carbonear so settled it themselves as to enable the <lb/>
Government to deal with it satisfactorily to all parties. <lb/>
Recently, however, the Board, acting in direct opposi<lb break="no"/>tion, to the orders of the Government, appointed a <lb/>
teacher from one of the Common Board schools with<lb break="no"/>out showing any regard to the wishes of these who <lb/>
were as much interested in the welfare and efficiency <lb/>
of the school as themselves. The information which <lb/>
the Government had of this proceeding was communi<lb break="no"/>cated to them by the Chairman of the Board. He <lb/>
was requested to call a meeting relative to the quar<lb break="no"/>ter's salary that was due the late master, and after <lb/>
that had been settled they suddenly proposed to him <lb/>
that he should resign. He was taken by surprise, and <lb/>
they passed a vote depriving him of his position as <lb/>
Chairman, and immediately proceeded to appoint an<lb break="no"/>other master. The Chairman having recovered from <lb/>
his surprise, and refused to contenance their proceed<lb break="no"/>ings, declined remaining any longer at the meeting. <lb/>
Notwithstanding this, the three other gentlemen, in <lb/>
defiance of law appointed this master and regularly <lb/>
installed him in office. When this was reported to the <lb/>
Government they wrote to Carbonear stating that <lb/>
such proceedings could not be countenanced, and in <lb/>
order to prevent similar occurrences until the matter <lb/>
could be fully considered and disposed of by the Leg<lb break="no"/>islature, two persons were appointed to fill up the <lb/>
vacaicies in the Board, one being an official of the <lb/>
Government in whom they had perfect confidence. <lb/>
These then were the proceedings which the Gover<lb break="no"/>ment adopted, and which they were quite prepared to <lb/>
defend and justify, and of which they were ready to <lb/>
take the responsibility. The hon member, Mr Kent, <lb/>
had presented a petition from the Roman Catholics of <lb/>
Carbonear. That however was but one side of the <lb/>
story. No doubt now the Protestants, seeing what <lb/>
    was done, should <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> themselves,and we would have <lb/>
a petition from then stating their views in the matter. <lb/>
If any sectarian strive on any way resulted from the  <lb/>
occurrences, it would be produced by the curious ob<lb break="no"/>servations of the hon member, and the unreasonable <lb/>
previsions of the petitioners. It mignt be true that <lb/>
the majority of the population of Carbonear weee <lb/>
    Roman Catholic at the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> this school was estab<lb break="no"/>lished; but he (hon A Gen) had yet to learn that <lb/>
when that majority was changed, the Board should not <lb/>
    be hanged with them. His <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> of the matter was, <lb/>
that when this school was established there was a <lb/>
majority of Roman Catholics in the population of Car<lb break="no"/>bonear, and consequently here was a majority on the <lb/>
Board. The same principle was recognised at Harbour <lb/>
Grace where the circumstances were the reverse and <lb/>
the Protestants had the majority when the Grammar <lb/>
School was established. But if in the course of time <lb/>
the majority came to be the other way, he regarded <lb/>
the principle that governed all these things as applica<lb break="no"/>ble to a Board, the Protestants having the majority <lb/>
    and consequently the largest interest in the effciency <lb/>
    of the school, should have the majority on the Board <lb/>
    alos. Would it not be manifestly unfair and unjust <lb/>
    that if the Roman Catholics so decreased that only <lb/>
    one or two of their children attended this school, they <lb/>
    should <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> by their majority retain the control and <lb/>
    
    <cb/>
    

management of it? The school was for the benefit of <lb/>
the community, which was clearly shewn by the fact <lb/>
that the Board was a general one. But the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment was not made so much on that accounts as to <lb/>
prevent this Board from any further intermeddling <lb/>
with the school till the matter was settled by the Leg<lb break="no"/>islature. The hon member, Mr Kent, says that by <lb/>
the Act one of these schools was to be Protestant and <lb/>
the other Catholic, and that a tacit understanding <lb/>
was entered into to that effect. He (hon Attorney <lb/>
General) could not agree to any such tacit under<lb break="no"/>standing. With whom and by whom had it been <lb/>
made? It did not appear on the record, and therefore <lb/>
it could not be taken into consideration. The hon <lb/>
member must also consider that other people have <lb/>
rights to conserve as well as the class he represents; <lb/>
and they would not readily yield them. The govern<lb break="no"/>ment were only desirous of occupying a neutral posi<lb break="no"/>tion and of doing equal justice to both parties. He <lb/>
was glad that some action was taken so that the matter <lb/>
might be fairly considered and disposed of. <lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:RORK1">Mr. RORKE</persName> regretted that the hon member for St. <lb/>
John's East, Mr. Kent, should have imparted any<lb break="no"/>thing of a sectarian character to the question before <lb/>
the house; indeed, from the tone and temper of the <lb/>
hon member, it was evident that his feelings on that <lb/> 
question were of a vindictive nature. He (Mr. R) had <lb/>
no intention of following such a course; but would <lb/>
merely state what had occurred on the establishment <lb/>
of the Carbonear Grammar School in 1843. He had <lb/>
a conversation with Mr Munn, who was at that time <lb/>
a member of the Legislature, and, he had told him <lb/>
(Mr R.) that there had been a tacit understanding <lb/>
that, as the majority of the people in Harbor Grace <lb/>
were Protestants, they should have a Protestant ma<lb break="no"/>jority in the Board of Directors of their school, and as <lb/>
the majority of the population in Carbonear were <lb/>
Roman Catholics, the same principle would be alopted <lb/>
there, and the majority on the Board would be Roman <lb/>
Catholics. But he (Mr. R) did not, neither did Mr <lb/>
Munn, understand that such an arrangement was to <lb/>
be binding upon them for all time to come, no matter <lb/>
how the relative numbers of the several Religious <lb/>
denominations might have changed. If the Protes<lb break="no"/>tants in Carbonear now were in the majority, they <lb/>
should certainly not be governed by a Catholic ma<lb break="no"/>jority on the Board of Directors of that school. The <lb/>
hon member, Mr Kent, had stated that this institution <lb/>
had worked harmoniously. He (Mr. R) must correct <lb/>
that statement. He had been one of the Directors of <lb/>
this school, and when the first meeting was held to <lb/>
take into consideration the appointment of a Master, <lb/>
the Board found that the Rev. Mr. Gleeson had <lb/>
already entered into an agreement with the late Mr. <lb/>
O'Donovan for the office. Mr O'Donovan arrived and <lb/>
the school went on very well until it was found neces<lb break="no"/>sary to apply some of the fees to the repairs of the <lb/>
School house and other incidental expenses, and then <lb/>
there was found an unwillingness on the part of Mr. <lb/>
Hanrahan, to state what the arrangement was that <lb/>
had been entered into with the Principal. It then <lb/>
came out that the Directors had no control over the <lb/>
fees, as they had been guaranteed to the Master. This <lb/>
difficulty always arose at the meetings of the Board, <lb/>
when it was found necessary to make any repairs or <lb/>
additions to the School house. They found that in<lb break="no"/>stead of their being the masters of the Principal, he <lb/>
was theirs and that they were unable to exercise any <lb/>
control over him. Mr. O'Donovan was a man of <lb/>
considerable attachments, was well qualified for the <lb/>
office of teacher, and everything went on satisfactorily <lb/>
for about ten years. He (Mr. R) had resigned his <lb/>
office as Director, as soon as he saw that the Board <lb/>
were powerless. The School had declined rapidly <lb/>
until not more than two or three children attended it. <lb/>
It was very natural, then, for the Protestants of the <lb/>
district to feel themselves aggrieved. Yet they re<lb break="no"/>mined silent, fearing that they would be changed with <lb/>
indulging in sectarian feelings which the hon member, <lb/>
Mr. Kent, had imputed to them. It was only within <lb/>
the past two or three years that they had petitioned <lb/>
this House. He (Mr. K) had presented two petitions <lb/>
on this subject before and he had now another. The <lb/>
Petition which he now held in his hand showed a <lb/>
desire on the part of the Protestants to prevent any <lb/>
further ill feeling, by having the grant divided. He <lb/>
did not see anything particular in the selection of this <lb/>
session for making this application. The circumstan<lb break="no"/>ces of this institution had forced it upon the in<lb break="no"/>habitants of Carbonear, to do something to remedy <lb/>
the evil, that existed. They were determined to <lb/>
have their rights, and would fearlessly insist upon <lb/>
them. <lb/></p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SHEA2">Mr. A. SHEA</persName> fully participated in the feelings of <lb/>
regret expressed by the hon member for St. John's <lb/>
East, Mr. Kent, at the introduction of a question <lb/>
calculated to call up those animosities and dissntions <lb/>
which we ought all to endeavour to repress. He had <lb/>
listened very attentively to the observations of the hon <lb/>
Attorney General and of the hon member for Carbo<lb break="no"/>near, Mr. Rorke; but he could not see that they had <lb/>
in any way made out a justification for the course <lb/>
which had been pursued. The hon Attorney General <lb/>
first justified the course that had been followed by <lb/>
saying that the majority on the population of Carbo<lb break="no"/>near were now Protestants. How was that ascertained? <lb/>
Certainly not by the last census, if it was discovered <lb/>
then, why was not this change effected at that time, <lb/>
and why did the Government wait for this convenient <lb/>
opportunity to carry out their views? The hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber, Mr Kent, had put the matter very fairly, when <lb/>
he stated that these schools in Harbor Grace and <lb/>
Carbonear had been intended as an offset to each other, <lb/>
and that the arrangement was not based upon the <lb/>
small and narrow grounds that were now suggested. <lb/>
In order to get out of this difficulty, hon gentlemen <lb/>
would now endeavour to divide the grant. Were they <lb/>
prepared to divide the grant in Harbour Grace, or the <lb/>
general grant throughout the Island? Did they <lb/>
imagine they could stop here, after accomplishing a <lb/>
certain work to suit their own purposes? Of all men <lb/>
he was surprised to hear this proposal from the hon <lb/>
member for Carbonear, Mr. Rorke. We all knew what <lb/>
was the state of society in the district of Conception <lb/>
Bay, a few years back. Did hon gentlemen wish, by <lb/>
pursuing such a course of conduct as they had com<lb break="no"/>menced, to call again into existence there sectarian <lb/>
animosities, especially at a period like this, when we <lb/>
all had hoped that they had been buried for ever? <lb/>
This legislation would make the Roman Catholics feel <lb/>
that they were d prived of their rights. The effect of <lb/>
such proceedings on the general welfare, the peace of <lb/>
society, and good governement, ought not to be over<lb break="no"/>looked. Upon a sensitive point like this, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should be careful to avoid any intermedlling; <lb/>
for the effect of it would be to destroy the interests of <lb/>
Roman Catholic's, so far as the education of their <lb/>
children was concerned, and the natural result would <lb/>
be to produce a very extensive feeling of distrust and <lb/>
uneasiness on the part of the people. If an incomplete <lb/>
man had been placed in that school, his place should <lb/>
have been supplied by a properly qualified Master. Had <lb/>
the government any gratitude now that they would <lb/>
get an efficient teacher? Injustice is done to us, and <lb/>
yet we are told that we are the cause of it. He (Mr <lb/>
S.) knew that some parties had their mind fixed on <lb/>
this subject for some time past. The hon member, <lb/>
Mr Rorke, had been influenced by those whose de<lb break="no"/>signs no right thinking man would countenance. <lb/>
Would there be no others who would sympathise <lb/>
with the people of Carbonear on this act of injustice? <lb/>
You desire now to entirely change the character of the <lb/>

<cb/>

school, and make it so that the Roman Catholics of <lb/>
Carbonear can feel no possible interest in it. This was <lb/>
not the way to remedy the evil.Is it because there had <lb/>
been a slight change in the population, the denomina<lb break="no"/>tional character of this School was to be changed? <lb/>
Supposing another change took place to-morrow, was <lb/>
this institution to be a bone of contention for ever. The <lb/>
Board in Harbor Grace was constituted on the same <lb/>
principle; and we never had any complaint of its work<lb break="no"/>ing. It would have been easy to have remedied this mat<lb break="no"/>ter leaving unchanged the character of the school. He <lb/>
(Mr. S.) feared that the consequences of legislation <lb/>
would have a range far beyond what was contemplat<lb break="no"/>ed, and might have a great effect upon the next elec<lb break="no"/>tion. If the Roman Catholics of Carbonear felt that <lb/>
they were to be ostracised in this way, and excluded <lb/>
from the privledges they were enjoying, there could <lb/>
be no doubt but that it would be attended with serious <lb/>
consequences all over the Bay. The people could not <lb/>
tamely submit to such palpable injustice. Depend <lb/>
upon it, the Roman Catholics of Conception Bay were <lb/>
not put down yet. They may make an attempt to <lb/>
gain back what they have lost. He (Mr. S.) was <lb/>
speaking the language of society and reason, and <lb/>
hoped hon gentlemen would sell and seriously con<lb break="no"/>sider the matter, and not sow the seeds of religious <lb/>
animosity among the people. <lb/>
</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:RORK1">Mr. RORKE</persName> did not see any force in the remarks <lb/>
of the hon member of Placentia and St. Mary's, <lb/>
Mr. Shea. He says that the Roman Catholics are <lb/>
only asking for their rights. Well, that was all that <lb/>
the Protestants were looking for, on thier part. There <lb/>
was a Grammar,school in Carbonear, and a sum of <lb/>
£200 was annually paid for its support, and yet the <lb/>
Protestant part of this community recieved no benefit <lb/>
from it. Was that a state of things that should be <lb/>
permitted to continue? There was no other way to <lb/>
remedy the evil than dividing the grant. <lb/>
</p> 
    
<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">The hon RECEIVER GENERAL</persName> thought that much <lb/>
irrelevant matter had been intriduced into that dis<lb break="no"/>cussion. No one was better acquired with the state <lb/>
of things that existed in Carbonear relative to the <lb/>
Garmmar school than he was himself except the hon <lb/>
member, Mr. Rorke. He (hon R. Gen) saw no <lb/>
way in which these sectarian feelings and animosities <lb/>
which the hon member, Mr. Shea, had referred to, <lb/>
could be prevented, but by dividing the grant. The <lb/>
house had had petitions presented to it, praying for a <lb/>
division of the grant, as the school had become <lb/>
wholly inoperative, and the money  that was granted<lb/>
for its support was entirely  thrown away. He (hon. <lb/>
R. Gen) did not see that the Roman Catholic inter<lb break="no"/>est would be injuriously affected by their being in the <lb/>
minority on the Board, any more than the Protes<lb break="no"/>tants would be if placed in a similar position. He <lb/>
conceived that the people had only to blame them<lb break="no"/>selves for the present state of the school. He did<lb/>
not think that the threats of the hon member for <lb/>
Placentia and St. Mary's were in wery good taste. <lb/>
The Protestants of Conception Bay knew how to <lb/>
insist upon what they considered to be their rights <lb/>
as well as the Roman Catholics; and they would not <lb/>
permit an insult to pass unnoticed. He (hon R Gen) <lb/>
had some acquantance with the working of that Gram<lb break="no"/>mar school. For years it had been an abortion. Both <lb/>
the Protestants and Roman Catholics had been dis<lb break="no"/>satisfied with it, and were desirous of remedying the <lb/>
evils which they saw existed; and recently the Pro<lb break="no"/>testants had employed a Master of their own, at a <lb/>
salary of £100 a year.—He had yet to learn that this <lb/>
school was to be regarded in a different light from a <lb/>
Commercial school. He was always impressed with <lb/>
the view that they were upon the same basis.–During <lb/>
the past twenty or thirty years there had been an inm<lb break="no"/>mense change in the population of Carbonear. There <lb/>
had been a considerable decrease in the number of <lb/>
Roman Catholics, and a large, increase among the <lb/>
Protestants. What was right in 1843, would not be <lb/>
regarded as right or just in 1865. The hon member <lb/>
for St. John's East, Mr. Kent says the Carbonear <lb/>
school, was established as an offset to the one at Har<lb break="no"/>bour Grace, and that the arragenment must be satis<lb break="no"/>factory to both towns. What could be more absurd <lb/>
than to suppose a Protestant youth gang from Car<lb break="no"/>bonear to Harbor Grace, and a Catholic youth from <lb/>
Harbor Grace to Carbonear, to attend school? As the <lb/>
Protestants were in the majority at Carbonear, it was <lb/>
only right they should have the majority on the Board <lb/>
of that Grammar School. The division of the grant <lb/>
was certainly the best way to put an end to the diffi<lb break="no"/>culty. In his (hon R. General's) opinion, nine tenths <lb/>
of the people of Carbonear, not only would agree to <lb/>
it, but strongly desired it. It was the hon member, <lb/>
Mr. Kent, and his friends, who were endeavoring to <lb/>
raise a sectarian feeling. But he (hon Receiver Gen<lb break="no"/>eral) felt assured that if any possible mischief result<lb break="no"/>ed from their doing so, the Protestants of Carbonear <lb/>
were well able to take care of themselves. He, how<lb break="no"/>ever, did not, in any way, anticipate that the peace <lb/>
and harmony of the own would be affected by this <lb/>
Grammar school grant being divided. <lb/></p>

    
    
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2018-12-12, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->
    
    <!--<p>ot <lb/></p> 

<p>consequences all over the Bay. <lb/></p> 

<p>tam, ly submit to such palpabl <lb/>
upon it, the Roman Catholics of <lb/>
not put down yet. <lb/>
gain back what they have lost. <lb/>
speaking the language of sobriety and reason <lb/>
hºped hon gettlemen would well and seriousl <lb/>
sider the matter, and rot sow the <lb/>
animosity among the people. <lb/></p> 



<p>Protestant part of the community regiº nºbºnº <lb/>
from it. Was that a state of thing; that shjºli º <lb/>
permitted to cºntinue?. <lb/>
remedy the evil than dividing the gra <lb/></p> 

<p>irrelevaat matter had been introluceſ intº that dis.: <lb/>
cussion. <lb/>
ºf thirgs that existed in Carbonear relatiº to <lb/>
Grammar school than he was hims ºf <lb/>
member, Mr. Rorke. <lb/>
way in which these sectarian feelings <lb/>
which the hon member, Mr. Shea, <lb/></p> 

<p>gould be prevented, but by divid ng <lb/></p> 


<p>iſ, but strongly desired it. <lb/>
Mr. Kent, <lb/>
raise a sect <lb/>
eral) felt as-ur, d that <lb/>
ed from their doing so, the Protestants of Carbonesr <lb/>
were well able to take -<lb/>ev'r, did not, ºn a'y <lb/>
and harmony of whº own <lb/></p> 

<p>Grammar schºol grant being <lb/></p> 

<p>- *** - Tº <lb/></p> 


<p>*­ <lb/></p> 

<p>=st <lb/></p> 

<p>e outport localities. <lb/>
º: . property' will | <lb/>
. how general the feeling m <lb/>
*. t it was worse thin idle to <lb/>
last t .. the special object of thi <lb/>
ing ". food for ferocious dogs. <lb/>
be to clearly still from a few statis <lb/>
. d has been the pursuit of s <lb/>
stun; as compared with its progr <lb/></p> 

<p>his was <lb/>
h <lb/>
the i. <lb/>
be changed? <lb/>
Hºrrow, was <lb/>
for ever, The <lb/>
on tha. <lb/>work. <lb/>
$ mit. <lb/></p> 

<p>3. <lb/>
a <lb/>
m <lb/>
8. <lb/></p> 

<p>have reºpediéd thi <lb/></p> 

<p>lou - -\-\-\-\-<lb/>(\lº S) feared that the consequences of . islati Cu ith its barren soil, its in <lb/>
would havé à range far beyond what was º; leeland, . not more than half <lb/>
ed, and might have a great effect upon the next j populatio 1832 the <lb/>
tion. If the Roman Cathºlics of Uarbon. felt .. land. As far back as <lb/></p> 

<p>they were to be os' racised in this way, and º: | it a million of sheep and 40,0 <lb/>
from the privileges they were enjºying, there co, º º; hº it exported a million p <lb/>
be no doubt but that it would be aſſadº ºil..." and ght from the <lb/></p> 

<p>- erious <lb/>
The p-ople • uld not <lb/>
*...**i.e. p-pº <lb/>
-\-\- Conception Bay wers <lb/>
They may make an attempt to <lb/>
He (wſr. S.) was <lb/></p> 

<p>and <lb/>
Cum. <lb/>
seeds of º: <lb/></p> 

<p>oves wrou <lb/>
.. work of the female <lb/>
own homes. Twenty-five years <lb/>
1857, we see by our census that un <lb/>
were but 9570 sheep agains: 500, <lb/>
only 12 000 head cattle against th <lb/>
tiº Icelanders in 1832. We have <lb/>
recent, years. but there can be n <lb/>
they producible, the revelation wo <lb/>
our shame for the backwarlºs. a <lb/>
ends of our people as regards this <lb/>
agricultural industry. <lb/>
Let us hope however that these <lb/>
of such a country as Iceland, of <lb/>
here where cur advantages are sc <lb/>
he quite thrown away. We have 0 <lb/>
inducement of this example, and <lb/>
urged to exertion by the necessities <lb/>
who cannot be supported by the fis <lb/>
years have most painfully but coi <lb/>
strated. Our first step however in <lb/>
indicated, must be the removal of <lb/>
which have hitherto presented the <lb/>
the way. Let the people at once; <lb/>
have sucrified heretofore, mike u <lb/>
at all events to have done with suc <lb/>
fully cry quits for ever with the <lb/>
loss and want. They should ren. <lb/>
police in this respect light and eas <lb/>
themselves in an effort tending so <lb/>
to their 8wn great profit. Th: sl: <lb/>
reflection must suffice to show that <lb/>
awake to a sense of our true inter <lb/>
and to atone for past shortcomines <lb/>
full the means and opportunities <lb/>
—palpably within the reach of our po <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Rokkº did not see any force in the remarks <lb/>
member for Plicentia and St. Mary', <lb/></p> 

<p>Well, that was a'l that <lb/>
on their part. There <lb/>
and a sum of <lb/></p> 

<p>There was no other way to <lb/>
nt. <lb/> </p> 

<p>.*.*.*.csiºn GENERAt thought that mº, <lb/></p> 

<p>No one was better acq inted with the stats <lb/>
h the . <lb/>
except the hon <lb/>
He (hon R. Gen) say". <lb/>
an! animosities, <lb/>
had referred to, <lb/>
the grant. The <lb/>
it, praying for a <lb/></p> 

<p>that was granted <lb/>
thrºwn away. He (hon. <lb/></p> 

<p>people had only to blame them. . . <lb/>
the present state of the school. H., it <lb/></p> 

<p>eir rights, <lb/>
and they wºuld not <lb/>
pass unnoticed. He (non R Gº) -\-4-\-\-\-<lb/>antance wib the working of that Grim. THE Seal, rs are dropping in day b. <lb/>
with saving trips; and though u <lb/>
| are soune far short of this, and <lb/>
ships, yet the average res it thun <lb/>
statement in the Day-Book, is a fa <lb/>
of the vessels yet out are favoura', <lb/>
the end of last week the published <lb/>
the following:—Number of vess <lb/>
Johns, 46, number of sewls, 84,352 <lb/>
16 vessels, 31, i11 seals; at Carbon <lb/>
seals; at Cu irs, 3 v. ss ls and <lb/>
number of seals, 125,135; averag. <lb/>
<lb/> </p> 

<p>[To Tiis EDIToſt of Tile New <lb/></p> 

<p>; and recently the Pro. <lb/></p> 

<p>- He haſ yet to learn that this <lb/></p> 

<p>He was always impress-d with <lb/></p> 

<p>Jeruºla decrease in the number of <lb/></p> 

<p>What was righ; in 1843, would hotº <lb/>
The hon member | <lb/>
Kent says the Carooner <lb/></p> 

<p>SIR,-\-I beg to call the attention of <lb/>
the propriety of havin; the wur <lb/>
dogs in St. John's carried out in <lb/>
Crowded streets are not the place <lb/>
marks men to fire guns, and even <lb/>
crowded there is always a liabili <lb/>
demands grea' cºre. Rut it is a <lb/>
tho town, the dogs that do mºst hº <lb/>
The work is all right and proper, <lb/>
thing r, quiring jn gºn, nº and dis <lb/>
of those who execute it, test the <lb/>
the public whose interest they <lb/>
acco int let there be any risk ru" <lb/>
life, and in shooting the dogs, th <lb/>
take good aim for vital parts, not <lb/>
'mals in the legs and sath ºl.c <lb/>
necessary torture. These t ing <lb/>
already, and I hope a hint may h; <lb/>
Yours obedien <lb/></p> 

<p>and that the urrangement must bºsºn. <lb/>
both towns Wuat cºuld be more absurd <lb/>
h going frem ('ar. <lb/>
Cathºlic youth from <lb/>
to attend schooi º As the <lb/>
majority at Carbonear, it was <lb/>
- ave the majority on the Board <lb/>
that Grammar School. The division of the grant <lb/></p> 

<p>(hon R. General's) ºp'nion, nine tenths <lb/>
the people of Carbonear, not only would agree to <lb/>
It was the hon member, <lb/>
* his friends, who were eqdeavouring tº <lb/>
ºrian ſeeling. But he (hon Receiver Gen. <lb/>
if any possible mischief result. <lb/></p> 

<p>ſ <lb/></p> 

<p>care of themselves. He, how<lb break="no"/>way. anticipate that the peace <lb/></p> 

<p>woild be affected by this <lb/>
divided. <lb/></p> 



<p>to <lb/></p> 

<p>You desire now to entirely change the character of the <lb/></p> 

<p>tº v <lb/></p> 

<p>* * **, *... ... saw is... ... ..º. <lb/></p> 

<p>(Lt }} <lb/>
-<lb/>3' Sº <lb/>
"-\-\-\-\- <lb/>We are glad tº observe that the police are actively <lb/></p> 

<p>whº really desires to see the progress and advancel <lb/>
civilization of our people. We are not unmindful of <lb/>
the inveterate prejudice to be encountered in this work º <lb/>
—that unrea soning tenacity with which so many of the 4 <lb/>
Pºpulation have clung to their dogs and persuaded <lb/>
themselves that these brutes were a mainstay of their <lb/>
support. But we cannot help hoping that this folly <lb/>
has now, to a great extent, yielded to the teachings of <lb/>
experience. At the time that dogs were of their ul<lb break="no"/>most value to the poor man in this country, there is <lb/>
no doubt that value was much overrated when the <lb/>
cost of their keep and of their mischief was considered. <lb/>
But now that they are comparatively so little used itſ " <lb/>
the hauling of firewood, they can, for the most part, f <lb/>
rendºr no possible return to their owners for the <lb/>
expense of feeding; and when it is rememb-red tha!. <lb/>
a good part of the ſeed of dogs consists of articles i. <lb/>
for human food, this expense cannot be lightly *: <lb/>
mated. Therefore if it were but for this reason alone; sal rºad. <lb/>the poor man ought to be glad to rid himself ºf a <lb/>
useless and costly idicumbrance. But when, we, come: <lb/></p> 

<p>reference to the destruction of sheep and cattle, ind: <lb/>
he prohibition it has imposed upon sheep raising in <lb/>
'Newfoundland, we cannot ſail to see bow insensatº <lb/>
has been this peculiarity. We pnblished a short time <lb/></p> 

<p>,-()n Thursday last <lb/>
St. Paul's Church, lia-bor Grace, <lb/>
Jones, John Row Mabiu, ſº q., <lb/>
Fºuny Jane, eldest daughter of <lb/>
Brºwn, Esq., of Harb ºr Grace. <lb/>
-** <lb/>
191EU.-i), Tuursday aftern <lb/>
Keuzie, wife of Mr John McL. <lb/>
daughter of the Revd. L. Mcle. <lb/></p> 

<p>ww.xfºwo, J <lb/>
Ufºlutiſtint. ' <lb/>
ST. Jöm.yºs. <lb/>
* Monio Ay, Mºy i, 'rº. <lb/></p> 

<p>8 years. <lb/>
**ged in the abatement of the dog-nuisance. In <lb/>
*is effort they ought to receive the countenance and Sales by Au <lb/>
support of every well wisher of the colony,of every man TIIIST) <lb/></p> 

<p>(MONDAY) at 1 <lb/>
At the 8to: <lb/></p> 

<p>IRobt. Alsop <lb/></p> 

<p>[NORTH-s: <lb/></p> 

<p>The IResidue of <lb/></p> 

<p>As per Pºlº, <lb/></p> 

<p>May 1. <lb/>
Governmen <lb/></p> 

<p>THE Mukºng and Repa <lb/>
f,0A1)S, will be let <lb/>
DAY next, the 4th irst, at <lb/>
Road towards Brennan and <lb/>
fººd bridge road up the hill. <lb/>
To open and make the <lb/>
(near Bro kfleid) to th: ºla <lb/>
Black Mush road, from 0 <lb/></p> 

<p>towarus Caul's farm, whár, <lb/>
JRepairs of Cld Piaceutia <lb/>
To repair road from Bay <lb/></p> 

<p>bor road. east of Gregory (; <lb/>
Repair of cross road': <lb/></p> 

<p>Walker's and others, <lb/>
Heavy Tree road. <lb/>
Church road, by *. Sh <lb/></p> 

<p>: '4 -<lb/>| Making the road on the <lb/></p> 

<p>try to count the cost.of our stupid, dog fancy by . <lb/></p> 

<p>ince a Government return which showed that during: y o <lb/>
he last five years there had been 4313 sheep, 82 | <lb/></p> 

<p>cows, 7 horses, and 228 gºats destroyed in the island Board of Works, 28th Apri <lb/></p> 

<p>by dogs, *nd this return was incomplete, for it did nº - is. . . . <lb/></p>-->
    
    
     

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>