<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-09" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
    <title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-02-09">9 February 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-03-06"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-27">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-11-27">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="002" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-03-06_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>

    <!-- IC, 2018-11-27, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>explanation relieved the delegates from any suspicion of <lb/>
intentional neglect, but why should a matter of such <lb/>
grave importance be left open to doubt, or to the possi<lb break="no"/>bility of injurious use of power P. Was this a positiºn <lb/>
to place before the country and ask its adhesion to *. It <lb/>
could never be assented to, until the amplest securities <lb/>
were given to guard us from the possibility of so unjust <lb/>
an imposition. The federal government proposes to <lb/>
raise a militia and naval service, and we are assured <lb/>
Newfoundlanders would be exempt from sharing the bur: <lb/>
then; but that argument had been very properly refuted <lb/>
by the hon gentie man (Mr. White) when he stated that <lb/>
when the necessity arose we should contribute our quota <lb/>
of mea and money to those services, and that if we enter <lb/>
the nationality it would be the duty of every man in the <lb/>
confederacy to come forward at the call of danger-and, <lb/>
more, that it was not likely any man capable of hearing <lb/>
arms would fail to aid in the defence of his country and <lb/>
his flag in the hour of need. There was one very serious <lb/>
objection to the project, and it applied equally to the <lb/>
other colonies as well as to ourselves;-it was that there <lb/>
is only a fixed and insufficient annual amount offered to <lb/>
them to carry on their local affairs. No matter how <lb/>
much our population increased,—no matter how rich our <lb/>
resources might prove to be, or how extensive our con<lb break="no"/>tribution to the general exchequer, wa shall receive not <lb/>
one farthing beyond that sum estimated upon our pre<lb break="no"/>sent population, -this was a most unsound and unfair <lb/>
principle. It is to be supposed that in the natural <lb/>
course of time and events our population will largely <lb/>
increase, our revenue perhaps become doubled, and no <lb/>
benefit accrue to us therefrom. It will be applied to <lb/>
railroads, to canals, to other public improvements in <lb/>
which the other colonies would participate, but not <lb/>
Newfoundland. What was to prevent an increased <lb/>
allowance per head with every decennial census * He <lb/>
considered the proposition, as it now stood, absurd and <lb/>
unsound, as a political principle at least, as much so as <lb/>
the idea of a maximum rate of taxation. There was a <lb/>
limit very soon arrived at, to the benefits we should derive <lb/>
from federal public works under favourable aspects, and all <lb/>
in which we could participate; once accomplished any in<lb break="no"/>crease of our contribution to the federal exchequer must be <lb/>
for substantially Canadian objects. Cur fisheries, the chief <lb/>
source of our trade, are to be ceded to the control and <lb/>
management of the federal government, whose juris<lb break="no"/>diction in everything would overide ours, and make it of <lb/>
course subservient to its policy, interests, or necessities. <lb/>
All these potent objections applied to the union of this <lb/>
colony with Canada, as she desires it, and it was his con<lb break="no"/>viction that it should be forcibly remonstrated against to <lb/>
the imperial government:—lest pending our decision upon <lb/>
the question any action should be inadvertently taken <lb/>
by the British Parliament, to bind us to an agreement <lb/>
involving disastrous consequences. The question never <lb/>
had been a topic of serious public consideraton in the <lb/>
colony until very recently;-our public men had not <lb/>
made it their study as the statesmen of the other Provin­ <lb/></p> 

<p>generally believed that from any union of the Provinces, <lb/>
Newfoundland on account of her isolated position and <lb/>
different interests would be excluded, -that in fact she <lb/>
did not desire or require it. Canada has exhibited an <lb/>
almost indecent and suspicious hurry in the matter. We <lb/>
find that already a delegation has been sent to the Impe<lb break="no"/>rial government to prepare it for the promotion of her <lb/>
views, fearing it would become the salutary action of ma<lb break="no"/>turer consideration on the part of the other provinces. <lb/>
It would seem by the eclºt and favour in which those <lb/>
delegates were received by the British authorities, <lb/>
and by the tone of the English public journals, that they <lb/>
took it for granted that all the Colonies were satisfied, <lb/>
and favourable and anxious for the scheme; and it was <lb/>
not at all unlikely that our interests might be compro<lb break="no"/>mised, either by compulsory acceptance or instant rejec<lb break="no"/>tion did we not immediately express our objections. He <lb/>
regretted that he had detained the house so long at so <lb/>
late a period of the evening, but the importance of the <lb/>
question should be his justification. It will probably <lb/>
come under consideration at a future period, and perhaps <lb/>
this debate may tend to shorten any that will then take <lb/>
place, He had no objection to the petition, but he thought <lb/>
it might have been more expressive; and he must repeat <lb/>
his conviction, that no matter how often the country <lb/>
migh be appealed to, it would never consent to confeder. <lb/>
ation on the terms proposed. This was no novel view <lb/>
of his, such was his conviction months ago. He had <lb/>
expressed it publicly in another place, long before a <lb/>
a public or commercial meeting had been suggested, <lb/>
or the result of such a preceeding had been thought of, <lb/>
and he had discovered no good reason to induce a change <lb/>
in his opinions. <lb/>
(To be continued.) <lb/>
*-as-s <lb/></p> -->

<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, FEB. 9.</p>
    
    <p>
The house met at three o'clock.</p>
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KENT1">Mr. KENT</persName> presented a petition from the Right Rev. <lb/>
Dr. Mullock, Roman Catholic Bishop of St. John's, <lb/>
which was received and read, setting forth that he had <lb/>
accidently learned that a Bill ſor the registration of <lb/>
births, marriages and deaths had been before the house <lb/>
and had passed a second reading, imposing duties and <lb/>
penalties on the Roman Catholic Clergy, who are in <lb/>
nowise officials of the Government, salaried or other<lb break="no"/>wise; that while petitioner believed the principle of <lb/>
the bill to be a step in the way of civilisation, still he <lb/>
considered it unjust that, without notice to the parties <lb/>
concerned, penalties and duties should be imposed upon <lb/>
them, that petitioner and his clergy will willingly allow <lb/>
the government registrar, under certain limitations, <lb/>
access to the parochial registries of baptisms and mar<lb break="no"/>riages, but respectfully decline to become the unpaid <lb/>
officials of the government, under penalties; and pray<lb break="no"/>ing that the house would not pass the bill in its present <lb/>
form. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KENT1">Mr. KENT</persName>, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
table, said the petition had reference to the fifth, sixth, <lb/>
fifteenth and concluding sections of the bill. His Lord<lb break="no"/>ship Dr Mullock and his clergy were not willing to be <lb/>
compelled by law to make to the Government, under <lb/>
penalties, the returns provided for by that bill. They <lb/>
were not officials of the Governinent, and if a law were <lb/>
passed compelling them to make returns as to the man<lb break="no"/>ner in which they administered the rites of the Church <lb/>
of which they were ordained clergymen, they consid<lb break="no"/>ered it would be tantamount to a penal enactment. He <lb/>
(Mr Kent) thought the hon leader of the Government <lb/>
should have been more cautious in drawing up the bill <lb/>
—he should have trusted for the success of such a mea<lb break="no"/>sure more to moral influence than to any penal enact<lb break="no"/>ment lie (Mr Kent) had looked over the Irish act <lb/>
for the registration of births, marriages and deaths, and <lb/>
he did not see that it contained a single penal enact<lb break="no"/>ment, notwithstanding that there was an established <lb/>
church in that country, whose clergy were more amen<lb break="no"/>able to the Government than those of a Church having <lb/>
no connection with the state. He was perfectly satis<lb break="no"/>fied the leader of the Government would take the <lb/>
matter into consideration, and so modify the provisions <lb/>
of the measure as to remove its objectionable features. <lb/>
The law should be so framed as not to excite the con<lb break="no"/>scientious fear or alarm of any clergyman whatever. <lb/>
In Ireland, he ſound the registration was entirely car<lb break="no"/>ried out by laymen. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Mr. Talbot was satisfied the leader of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would, in committee on that bill, meet the wishes <lb/>
of the Right Rev Bishop and his clergy. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        Mr RENOUF—That bill, in its present shape, would <lb/>
impose onerous duties, under penalties, upon clergy<lb break="no"/>
<cb/>
men who received no stipend whatever from the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KAVA1">Mr KAVANAGH</persName> had great pleasure in supporting <lb/>
the prayer of that petition, and trusted the leader of <lb/>
the Government would so modify the measure as to <lb/>
render it acceptable to all. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CASE2">Mr CASEY</persName> was sure it never was the intention of the <lb/>
learned Attorney General to impose penalties on the <lb/>
Catholic clergy under that bill. The duties of the <lb/>
Catholic clergy were most arduous. They had scarcely <lb/>
any leisure; and to impose additional duties upon them <lb/>
would be highly improper. He was satisfied that, in <lb/>
committee, the hon leader of the Government would <lb/>
remove what was considered objectionable in the bill. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:MOOR3">Mr MOORE</persName> presented a petition from Thomas Dwyer <lb/>
and others, of Upper Island Cove, which was received <lb/>
and read, praying for a grant to complete a road in <lb/>
that locality.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr RENOUF</persName> presented a petition from John White <lb/>
and others, of Petty Harbour, which was received and <lb/>
read, praying for a grant to deepen the gut there. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr RENOUF</persName>, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
table, would heartily support its prayer. The petition<lb break="no"/>ers were entitled to every consideration from the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, and he trusted that matter would receive <lb/>
that consideration to which its importance, entitled it. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Mr CASEY supported the prayer of the petition. <lb/>
When the wind blew from the North East the petition<lb break="no"/>ers had very great difficulty in mooring their boats. If <lb/>
any money should be granted this session for break<lb break="no"/>waters, he considered injustice would be done to the <lb/>
etitioners if their claim should not also be attended to. <lb/>
They had not often asked anything from the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment; they had supported themselves without asking <lb/>
for poor relief, except a few this year. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr TALBOT</persName> quite agreed with his hon colleagues <lb/>
that that was an important petition. These people were <lb/>
industrious, and suffered great inconvenience and loss <lb/>
from the want of proper shelter for their boats. He <lb/>
trusted that petition would not be overlooked. The <lb/>
people were entitled to consideration. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Mr E D SHEA</persName> gave notice that on to-morrow he <lb/>
would ask the hon Acting Colonial Secretary to lay on <lb/>
the table a copy of the report of the Commander of <lb/>
        H.M.S. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Medea</hi> of the fisheries at Labrador. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
On motion of the hon <persName ref="pers:CART5">ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>, pur<lb break="no"/>suant to order of the day, the house resolved itself into <lb/>
committee of the whole on the bill for the registration <lb/>
of births, marriages and deaths—Mr. Barron in the <lb/>
Chair. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> –The object of that bill <lb/>
was to provide information as to the gradual growth <lb/>
of population in this colony, and also to form a public <lb/>
record by which the rights of parties in matters of in<lb break="no"/>heritance might be established. Registers of births, <lb/>
marriages and deaths were kept as a matter of record <lb/>
in almost all civilized countries, and it might be con<lb break="no"/>sidered a reproach to us that hitherto we had no <lb/>
enactment for such public records being kept. Statis<lb break="no"/>tical information on that subject was also now consi<lb break="no"/>dered a matter of great importance, and governments <lb/>
bestowed great a tention on the collection of such <lb/>
statistics, which enabled them to judge of the progress <lb/>
of population and the sanitary state of the people; and <lb/>
to some extent of their comfort and social condition. <lb/>
The present bill was an attempt, and he must admit, <lb/>
an imperfect attempt, to provide such a record. To <lb/>
provide such a system of registrition as existed in the <lb/>
United Kingdom might at present be too expensive. <lb/>
But an attempt ought to be made, and when that <lb/>
bill should have gone through committee, and they <lb/>
had experience of its working, its imperfections could <lb/>
be remedied by subsequent legislation. The greatest <lb/>
difficulty he apprehended would be found in our po<lb break="no"/>pulation being so scattered, so that there would be a <lb/>
difficulty in sending the required information to the <lb/>
proper officer. He did not consider that in the exist<lb break="no"/>ing circuinstances of the colony any money could be <lb/>
appropriated towards giving effect to that measure. <lb/>
He thought the Stipendiary Magistrates would be <lb/>
willing to act as Registrars; and where there were no <lb/>
Stipendiary Magistrates the Governor in Council <lb/>
would appoint Registrars. When the sections of the <lb/>
bill objected to in the petition presented by the hon. <lb/>
member for St. John's East (Mr. Kent) came to be <lb/>
considered, the objections to them would be taken up, <lb/>
and he hoped the matter would be satisfactorily ar<lb break="no"/>ranged. He concurred with the hon member that the <lb/>
co-operation of all was necessary to the proper working <lb/>
of the measure, and hoped that in a matter of so <lb/>
much importance to their own people, the aid of the <lb/>
Roman Catholic clergy would be readily given to <lb/>
carry out that registration efficiently. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KENT1">Mr. KNET</persName> had great pleasure in supporting the <lb/>
principle of the bill. It was as creditable to the hon. <lb/>
Attorney General as was the information and research <lb/>
which he had brought to bear on the question. The <lb/>
increase of population was shown by the births, and <lb/>
the sanatory condition of the people by its rate of <lb/>
mortality. And these were matters upon which it was <lb/>
very necessary that we should be informed. Indeed <lb/>
statistical information of every description was highly <lb/>
desirable. He was surprised by recent information <lb/>
procured at the instance of one of the Judges of our <lb/>
Supreme Court, that 1500 sheep had been destroyed <lb/>
at Brigus and its vincinity by dogs in five years. Did <lb/>
not that fact show that it was necessary to remove the <lb/>
cause of this destruction? The same principle applied <lb/>
to this measure. Every one speaks of our healthy <lb/>
climate, but the idea was only a speculative one, for <lb/>
we had no statistical information as to the mortality. <lb/>
In the United Kingdom, every thing was accurately <lb/>
known, and the bills of mortality in London were <lb/>
regularly published once a week. He (Mr. Kent) <lb/>
thought that the proper persons to carry out the pro<lb break="no"/>visions of this measure were the Stipendiary, Magis<lb break="no"/>trates, and he trusted that us we progressed in mate<lb break="no"/>rial prosperity, we might be able to allow them some <lb/>
small compensation for their services in the matter. <lb/>
He could fancy that they might be very profitably <lb/>
employed in collecting all kinds of statistical informa<lb break="no"/>tion, and especially with reference to agriculture. And <lb/>
they certainly ought not to object to perform this <lb/>
duty which would occupy but a small portion of their <lb/>
time. Our position was in many instances an ano<lb break="no"/>maly. In the other colonies they cannot see any ne<lb break="no"/>cessity for salaried magistrates over the whole country <lb/>
as we had here. He was very glad to see that the <lb/>
hon the Attorney General saw the propriety of omit<lb break="no"/>ting the two sections in this bill already referred to. <lb/>
He was certain when that hon gentleman evinced <lb/>
such a desire to propitiate the good wishes of hon <lb/>
members on this side of the house, that from them <lb/>
he would receive no factious or violent opposition in <lb/>
the public business. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:WHIT6">Mr. WHITEWAY</persName> had great pleasure, in supporting <lb/>
this bill. But he did not think that the outport ma<lb break="no"/>gistrates should he saddled with these new duties <lb/>
without being in some way paid for their services. At <lb/>
present their salaries were hardly sufficient to keep <lb/>
them from starvation. It was very true that in some <lb/>
parts of the island they had very littie to do; but in <lb/>
other places to his (Mr. Whiteway's) own knowledge <lb/>
they had a great, amount of duty to perform, and <lb/>
their time was fully occupied. It should also be re<lb break="no"/>membered that these gentlemen were not unfrequently <lb/>
the Deputy Surveyors, and were often called away <lb/>
forty or fifty miles from their homes for the purpose <lb/>
of surveying land for which service they received but <lb/>
trifling remuneration. Last winter the Magistrate at <lb/>
 
 <cb/>

Fogo was occupied for nearly two months on business <lb/>
apart from his office, occasioned by the number of <lb/>
wrecked sealers that had to seek shelter there. We <lb/>
could not find gentlemen in this country who could <lb/>
afford to work without remuneration, a fact of which <lb/>
we had sufficient evidence when we found three Con<lb break="no"/>tingency Bills thrown out in the Legislative Council, <lb/>
because hon gentlemen <choice><sic>repressnting</sic><corr>representing</corr></choice> out higher classes <lb/>
refused to give two or three hours of their time, once <lb/>
or twice a week, to the service of the country, without <lb/>
remuneration. He was sorry to see this additional <lb/>
duty imposed on the Magistrates without some little <lb/>
fee to remunerate them for their service. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName> hoped that the eloquent speech of the <lb/>
hon member for Fogo would be reported. He (Mr. <lb/>
Renouf) thought the object of the bill was a good <lb/>
one. These Magistrates had very little to do, and <lb/>
they might be very usefully employed in collecting the <lb/>
information necessary to the successful carrying out <lb/>
of this measure. He (Mr. Renouf) thought their <lb/>
salaries were amply sufficient for the duties they had <lb/>
to perform. That measura would not entail much <lb/>
additional labor, and he considered that they were <lb/>
certainly the proper persons to be entrusted with the <lb/>
carrying out of the provisions of that bill. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SHEA1">Mr. E. D. SHEA</persName> regarded the principle of that <lb/>
bill as unobjectionable. It would certainly have the <lb/>
effect of procuring very useful information. We <lb/>
should now know more of that interesting locality <lb/>
Goat's Cove than we knew before. Hon members <lb/>
would be able to ascertain the number of its inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants, and whether Mr King was in reality monarch <lb/>
of all he surveyed in that quarter. But joking apart, <lb/>
he considered the measure a very useful one, and the <lb/>
only difficulty in his mind was that it would not be <lb/>
carried out efficiently, because there was no provision <lb/>
for remunerating the parties who were to perform the <lb/>
work. It seemed to be thought, however, that the Stipen<lb break="no"/>diary Magistrates would be only too glad to take upon <lb/>
themselves this extra duty. They enjoyed so many <lb/>
of the blessings of civilization in these outports, their <lb/>
position there was such a happy one, that they would <lb/>
feel that they were bound to make some return for all <lb/>
the numerous advantages they reaped. It had been <lb/>
said that they were in some districts rarely called <lb/>
upon to adjudicate upon a case. He (Mr. Shea) <lb/>
thought that fact spoke trumpet-tongued in their fa<lb break="no"/>vour. Did it not show the great moral influence <lb/>
which their presence exercised? It was not right that <lb/>
they should now be burdened with extra duties of an <lb/>
onerous character, without one shilling compensation. <lb/>
He did not see why they should be more patriotic and <lb/>
disinterested than other officials. Then many of these <lb/>
gentlemen had to perform the duties of Poor Commis<lb break="no"/>sioners, and if they were not paid for that they should <lb/>
be, for a more arduous and disagreeable duty he (Mr. <lb/>
Shea) could not conceive. It was not fair for the <lb/>
Government to impose these additional duties on these <lb/>
gentlemen merely because they had the power to do <lb/>
so. Looking at the provisions for carrying out the <lb/>
present measure, he did not think that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment could reasonably expect that the duties would <lb/>
be efficiently performed. But beyond the Magistrates, <lb/>
the Government were to appoint Registrars. These <lb/>
men, of course, would be paid; or was it contempla<lb break="no"/>ted that all were to do the work from pure unsullied, <lb/>
unmixed patriotism? He (Mr. Shea) very much feared <lb/>
that this attempt at economy was not a very wise pro<lb break="no"/>ceeding. He did not wish to predict failure. He <lb/>
merely expressed the fears which he really entertained. <lb/>
He hoped that there would be some inducement held <lb/>
out to these gentlemen, of some small remuneration <lb/>
—otherwise we could not have much confidence in the <lb/>
successful working of that measure. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr. TALBot</persName>.—No one would take an interest in <lb/>
any business if he was not paid for it. If the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment employed Registrars they would be compelled to <lb/>
pay them. And what would be the necessary, result <lb/>
with the Magistrates? They would become jealous <lb/>
of the Registrars, and of course their work would be <lb/>
inefficiently performed. The best plan would be to <lb/>
pay all or none. He (Mr. Talbot) must confess that <lb/>
        his opinion was, considering the <hi rendition="simple:italic">modus operandi</hi> to be <lb/>
pursued, that this measure would result in failure, in <lb/>
fact become totally inoperative. The best way would <lb/> 
be not to pass it all, as we had no guarantee that it <lb/>
would be carried into effect; and the Act would be <lb/>
mere waste paper and an incumbrance to the statute <lb/>
book. The Roman Catholic clergy would not consent <lb/>
to discharge the duties that were to be imposed on <lb/>
them. Besides, there were private reasons, which <lb/>
could never be known that would prevent them. They <lb/>
would not act as the officials of any government, paid <lb/>
or unpaid. If the government passed the bill in its <lb/>
present form it would be a penal act. The church <lb/>
and state could never run together in parallel lines <lb/>
in all things, and you could, not force them. There <lb/>
were certain things connected with births and marria<lb break="no"/>ges, that they could not tell you of. As citizens, they <lb/>
would be bound, but as Ministers of religion, you <lb/>
would not get anything out of them. Whenever their <lb/>
principles came in contact with the state, they were <lb/>
bound to resist. Therefore this bill would be altoge<lb break="no"/>ther a nullity. If the government made it incumbent <lb/>
on mothers, fathers, brothers and sisters, to give the <lb/>
notices required by this bill, where was the necessity <lb/>
for requiring the clergymen, to do so? With these <lb/>
observations he supported the principle of the measure <lb/>
though he did not see how it was possible for this act <lb/>
to be carried into effect. <lb/></p> 

    <p><persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>.—If he was not mista<lb break="no"/>ken marriages must be registered under the marriage <lb/>
act. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:KENT1">Mr. KENT</persName>.—But clergymen were not bound to <lb/>
make returns. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CART5">The hon ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> believed they were. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> considered that it was of great import<lb break="no"/>ance that there should be a registration of births and <lb/>
marriages. The measure applied to all, and it was a <lb/>
duty that they owed to their own people, as it was of <lb/>
the utmost importance that such registers should be <lb/>
correctly kept, as they might involve rights of proper<lb break="no"/>ty and the peace of families, and serious loss and <lb/>
damage might result from the want of that evidence <lb/>
which, in the lapse of time, such registers only could <lb/>
furnish. In this country no great loss had yet taken <lb/>
place from the want of public registers although he <lb/>
was aware there had been some. We were increasing, <lb/>
and with an increase of population and accumulatios <lb/>
of property, it was of the utmost importance that we <lb/>
should have a correct registry of marriages and births. <lb/>
A registry of deaths was also necessary. He had fre<lb break="no"/>quent applications from England and Ireland as to the <lb/>
deaths of persons, and the time of such deaths. With <lb/>
regard to penalties, it there was any objection, he did <lb/>
not see that it was necessary to press that. It became <lb/>
a moral duty, and he took it for granted all clergy<lb break="no"/>men would be ready and willing to assist in securing <lb/>
accurate registers. In Lower Canada there was a sys<lb break="no"/>tem of public registration, duplicate registers being <lb/>
kept by all clergymen, one of which was at the end <lb/>
of each year deposited with the Clerk of the Court, <lb/>
and the Roman Catholic clergy were the first named in <lb/>
the Act.—(Here bon Speaker read the first section <lb/>
of the Act of Lower Canada.) He thought it was the <lb/>
duty of all clergymen to assist in carrying out such a <lb/>
necessary measure. As to the penalties, he did not <lb/>
suppose they would come to much, but he did not <lb/>
think any clergymen would refuse to give the neces<lb break="no"/>sary returns. <lb/></p> 

    <p><persName ref="pers:KENT1">Mr. KENT</persName>.—It was, no doubt of importance both as <lb/>
    regarded the rights of property and for necessary
    
<cb/>

statistical information, that there should be a correct <lb/>
registry of births, marriages and deaths. But what <lb/>
the petition of the Right Revd. Dr. Mullock objeced <lb/>
to was that the Catholic clergy should, under penal<lb break="no"/>ties, be bound to make returns to the government, <lb/>
which he regarded as a species of penal legislation. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:PROW1">Mr PROWSE</persName> was surprised that there should be any <lb/>
difficulty about furnishing information which was con<lb break="no"/>sidered necessary in all civilised and progressive coun<lb break="no"/>tries. He did say that if in that bill there was anything <lb/>
which touched the religious feeling of the Right Rev <lb/>
Dr. Mullock, he (Mr Prowse) would not be a party to <lb/>
its enactment, for however valuable the information <lb/>
might be, religious feelings must be held sacred; and <lb/> 
he was satisfied the leader of the Government would <lb/>
be the last to infringe them. But such registers were <lb/>
very much required, and he (Mr Prowse) trusted there <lb/>
would be a willingness to assist in having them accur<lb break="no"/>ately made up. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr TALBOT</persName>—It was customary in all Catholic coun<lb break="no"/>tries to keep in the churches public registers of mar<lb break="no"/>riages and births, and whenever courts of justice re<lb break="no"/>quired extracts from them as matter of evidence, access <lb/>
to them was allowed. But there were no public reg<lb break="no"/>isters of marriage here at all, because marriages were <lb/>
not performed in the churches. But there was a reg<lb break="no"/>istry kept of baptisms and marriages, and the Bishop <lb/>
had no objection to allow it to be copied if the govern<lb break="no"/>ment required it. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> –It seemed to be con<lb break="no"/>sidered objectionable that the bill should impose a duty <lb/>
for which there was no compensation. He had no ob<lb break="no"/>jection to dispense with the 5th section of the Bill. But <lb/>
he could not say the same respecting the 6th. It was <lb/>
the section on which he relied for securing a correct <lb/>
registry of marriages. It provided that in addition to <lb/>
what clergymen were bound by law to do, they should <lb/>
send a copy of their registry at the end of the year to <lb/>
the Colonial Secretary's office. This object was to <lb/>
procure in a condensed form what was now recorded <lb/>
in all the churches and chapels in the island. He quite <lb/>
agreed with the Speaker that it was not a matter <lb/>
which any clergyman would object to, when the im<lb break="no"/>portance of the object was considered. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KENT1">Mr KENT</persName>—But it was to be done under a penalty. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> –As to the penalty, if <lb/>
that was the objection, there would not be much diffi<lb break="no"/>culty about it. These sections might as well be passed <lb/>
over for further consideration, and the other sections <lb/>
of the bill proceeded with. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The seventh section was then read and adopted. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        The remaining sections were read <hi rendition="simple:italic">servatim</hi> and <lb/>
adopted, and the committee rose and the chairman re<lb break="no"/>ported progress and asked leave to sit again. To sit <lb/>
again to-morrow. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
On motion of the <persName ref="pers:CART5">hon Attorney General</persName>, pursuant <lb/>
to order of the day, the house resolved itself into Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the whole on the Coroners' Bill, Dr Winter <lb/>
in the chair. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The hon Attorney General explained the object of <lb/>
the bill, and the present state of the law, after which <lb/>
its several sections were read and adopted, down to the <lb/>
section authorizing the Goveonor in Council to fix the <lb/>
fees under the measure, on which there was some dis<lb break="no"/>cussion, when the committee rose and the chairman <lb/>
reported progress. To sit again to-morrow. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
On motion of the <persName ref="pers:CART5">hon Attorney General</persName>, pursuant <lb/>
to order of the day, the house resolved itself into com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the whole on the bill to provide for wives and <lb/>
children deserted by their husbands and parents, and <lb/>
for parents deserted by their children, Mr. Wyatt in the <lb/>
chair. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The <persName ref="pers:CART5">hon Attorney General</persName> having explained the <lb/>
object of the bill, several sections were read and adopt<lb break="no"/>ed, with some amendments. The committee then rose <lb/>
and the chairman reported progress. To sit again to-<lb break="yes"/>morrow. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The house then adjourned until to-morrow at three <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/></p>
    
    <!-- IC, 2018-11-27, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
    
    <!--<p>
FRIDAY, Feb. 10, <lb/>
The house met at three o'clock. <lb/>
Pursuant to order of the day, on motion of the hon <lb/>
Attorney GENERAL, the house resolved itself into a <lb/>
Committee of the whole on the 3ill to continue the <lb/>
punishment of Banishment in certain cases, Mr Now. <lb/>
lan in the chair. <lb/>
The several sections of the Bill were read and <lb/>
adopted, and the committte rose and the Chairman <lb/>
reported the Bill with some amendments, <lb/>
Ordered to be engrossed and read a third time to. <lb/>
morrow. <lb/>
Pursuant to order of the day, on motion of the kon <lb/>
Attorney General the house resolved itself into a <lb/>
Committee of the whole on the Bill to make provis. <lb/>
ion for the recovery of Penalties becoming due on the <lb/>
ºut- of certain Recognizances, Mr. Rorke in the <lb/>
chair. <lb/>
The several sections of the Bill were read and adop<lb break="no"/>ted, and the committee rose and the Chairman repor<lb break="no"/>ted the Bill with some amendment. Ordered to be <lb/>
engrossed and read a lhird time to-morrow. <lb/>
Pursuant to the order of the day, on motion of the <lb/>
hon ATToksey GENERAL, the House resolved itself <lb/>
into a Committee of the whole on the Bill to enable <lb/>
courts of Law to give relief against adverse claims <lb/>
made upon persons having no interest in the subject <lb/>
of such claims, Dr Winter in the chair. <lb/>
The several sections of the biºl were read and adop<lb break="no"/>ted with some amendments, an i the committee rose <lb/>
and the chairman reported the Bill with some amend. <lb/>
ments. <lb/>
Ordered to be engrossed and read a third time on <lb/>
Monday next. <lb/>
The house then adjourned until Monday at thres <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/>
Monday, Feb. 13. <lb/>
The house met at three o'clock. y <lb/>
The hon Receiver General iaid on the table of <lb/>
the house a return showing the duties that would be <lb/>
payable upon our imports #. 1863 under the tariff of <lb/>
Qanada, as asked for by the hon member for St. <lb/>
John's West, Mr. Renouf. A similar return for <lb/>
1864, was in the course of preparation at the cus<lb break="no"/>..." and would be laid on the table when com<lb break="no"/>pitted. <lb/>
Mr. Wyatt presented a petition from Robert <lb/>
Thorburn, and other member of the Commercai <lb/>
Society of St. John's, which was received and read, <lb/>
setting forth, that petitioners had been informed that <lb/>
the subject of a confederation of the British North <lb/>
American Provinces, based on certain resolutions <lb/>
adopted at a convention of delegates from each of the <lb/>
Provinces, held at Quebec in the month of October <lb/>
las, was to be brought forward at an early day for the <lb/>
consideration of the house; that petitioners were of <lb/>
92inion that a step involving such momentous conse<lb break="no"/>quences as the union of this colony with the neigh<lb break="no"/>bouring North American Provinces, should not be <lb/>
essayed until some further time had been allowed for <lb/>
the collection of information and statis:ics, and for the <lb/>
consideration of the subject by the constituencies of <lb/>
the several electoral districts, and by the inhabitants <lb/>
generally, many of whom haſ not yet heard that such <lb/>
a confederation was contemplated; that any unior, <lb/>
to be mutually beneficial, must be founded upon &amp; P <lb/>
uniformity of interests and objects, and that, so far as <lb/>
the limited information of petitioners extended, no <lb/>
such uniformity existed between Canada and this <lb/>
Colony; that the Canadas, being essentially manufac: <lb/>
turing and agricultural countries, have always pursued <lb/>
* protective policy, while Newfoundland, which pro­ <lb/></p> 

<p>regarded the rights of property and for necessary <lb/></p> 

<p>duces few, and must import most of the necessaries <lb/></p> 

<p>f <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>he was satisfied the leader of the Government would y <lb/></p> 

<p>p <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>s <lb/></p> 

<p>#. <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/>
! <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>? <lb/></p> 

<p>... in navment of which <lb/>
of .." ...'. be benefite <lb/>
. jing that the house <lb/>
tº. fledge either the Go <lb/>
i. to the proposed uniſh <lb/>
jºin obtained which will clear <lb/>
for the advantage of this colon <lb/>
niy has been affºrded of consu <lb/>
important measure. , <lb/>
Mr Wyarr, in moving tha <lb/>
table, woull make a few obser <lb/>
... signed by, most of the le. <lb/>
john's, now in the cºnntry, an <lb/>
afforded, he was satisfied that <lb/>
...y others who were not fe" <lb/>
was based on resolution: adop <lb/>
...; the commercial Society, c <lb/>
tion of that questiºn. There <lb/>
je at the meeting, and hº <lb/>
that gentleman had afterwards <lb/>
tion. He mentioned that to <lb/>
the question: The Commerc. <lb/>
º, feel gratified at the receptiº <lb/>
tions. §. very long ago the <lb/>
tion to the government as to <lb/>
ºted upon, and the revenue <lb/>
iderable loss, which would h <lb/>
that recommendation been act. <lb/>
might appear to have emanuſ <lb/>
colony; but it ºxpressed the <lb/>
ºmber of all classes. The tº <lb/>
munity, and fishermen, agreed <lb/>
not to be settled in the existin <lb/>
Time should be given for its 90 <lb/>
for the friends of confederatio <lb/>
be beneficial to the country f <lb/>
mation had yet been furnished <lb/>
appear to be such sº would li <lb/>
their present constitution as * <lb/>
represented himself a constit <lb/>
thºusand. It would not be fai <lb/>
sulting them, tº decide upon <lb/>
tion, which might be afterwar <lb/>
1Its own opinion was that if wº <lb/>
ration with Canada, Newfound <lb/>
and before he would give a v <lb/>
that house, to pledge his con <lb/>
and see them, and learn their <lb/>
the prayer of that petition w <lb/>
merely asked for time; and hº <lb/>
its prayer wouli be acceded to. <lb/>
that the petition came in rather <lb/>
but so early as the 6th Dece <lb/>
dressed to the Government by <lb/>
ber of Commerce, asking for <lb/>
were informed, in reply, that th <lb/>
in possession of further info <lb/>
published in the newspapers <lb/>
mature consideration it was de <lb/>
of the Commercial Society, an <lb/>
petition now presented, which <lb/>
ceive at the hands of hon mem <lb/>
was entitled to. It was signed <lb/>
sented the greater portion of the <lb/>
and if it could be shown them tº <lb/>
benefit of the colony to enter i <lb/>
they wouid readily become p. <lb/>
then they would oppose it, Th <lb/>
go hand in hand with the fishe <lb/>
were identical. It had been sai <lb/>
had their private place, where <lb/>
He denied that. They had <lb/>
motives to any parties.—They <lb/>
question decided on its merits. <lb/>
(To be contin <lb/>
<lb break="no"/>Holloway's Oi NTMENT AN <lb/>
emption from sores, ulcers,bad <lb/>
most diseases of the skin, will <lb/>
persevering use of these admir <lb/>
may be implicitly relied on in <lb/>
regard to sex or the duration of <lb/>
way's Ointment and Pills are un <lb/>
indolent ulcerations of the legs <lb/>
other applications and consign <lb/>
of pain and death. No risk or <lb/>
the use of Holloway's medical <lb/>
allays pain, smarting, and itcl <lb/>
from foul mattor, represses prol <lb/>
es the growth of good health; <lb/>
ultimately form a sound surface <lb/></p> 

<p>ſºufºu. <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOH, <lb/>
MONDAY, MARCI <lb/></p> 

<p>The debate in the Assembly on <lb/>
yet closed, though the argum" <lb/>
husted. The scheme has no <lb/>
through and through—all its few <lb/>
bare, and we feel assured that a <lb/>
ed it with intelligent and impar <lb/>
cided in favour of its adoption <lb/>
are glad to perceive that with a <lb/>
industrious opponents have been <lb/>
real point against it, or in any w <lb/>
sition of antagonism they have <lb/>
of delusions with which they at <lb/>
very soon worked through and <lb/>
have been unable to replace eve <lb/>
and have had no other choice <lb/>
picking up the scattered fragmen <lb/>
and flinging them back aga, <lb/>
facts and argument. It has bee <lb/>
have noticed the discussion that <lb/>
tence of our opponents has been <lb/>
Union had come to us from a nº <lb/>
°rnment whose first object was <lb/>
*elves at our utmost cost. Cana <lb/>
nancial straits, and saw no me <lb/>
*vailable to her as a raid upon u <lb/>
*eeming as we so notoriously <lb/>
Prosperity! Hence the cry of <lb/>
hence the discovery of the trea <lb/>
... our independent legislation.": <lb/>
* not in the same breath, proc. <lb/>
thus put the case, that we are <lb/>
Pay our deb's, and that we are p <lb/>
of pauperism compared to whic <lb/>
the neck would be an endurable <lb/>
Pendent legislation" to which we <lb/>
at all hazards, is admittedly th <lb/>
Possible, and we by no means d<lb break="no"/>believe it to be powerless to meet <lb/>
exigencies of the country. U. <lb/>
done good service, and if not to <lb/>
*ach, at least to an appreciable <lb/></p> 

<p>l <lb/></p>
-->
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>