<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-11" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1869-02-11">11 February 1869</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1869-02-17"/>,
<date when="1869-02-19"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="3"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_3.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2019-01-30">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2019-01-30">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_3"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_3.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_2.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER</fw>


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-30, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->

<!--<p>* Mr. TALBYT approved of the amendment <lb/>
which had been put forward by the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber, lir. Hogsett. It stated what was perfectly <lb/>
currect. Now the speech of his Excellency the <lb/>
Governor had been viewed in different lights. <lb/></p> 

<p>Some hon. members had praised it with no light alleged affirmed the principle of Confederation. series of resolutions, moved the House intº C5 units concessions, that we should conced. ... tº. Fre <lb/>
Hon. members who had voted for it were in a state | tee, and not only gºt his resolutions passed. but had the right of fishing all along our coast. Did . <lb/></p> 

<p>praise, others had criticised it severely. So if he <lb/>
(Mr. T.) took a middle course, he thought he <lb/>
would be near the mark. It was by no means <lb/>
an extraordinary speech; but it was not wholly <lb/>
destitute of matters of considerable interest. It <lb/></p> 

<p>was one of those kind of speeches usually deliver- he (Mr. T.) was a loss to imagine. We are sur- import unt documents. <lb/></p> 

<p>ed at the opening of each session of this House, <lb/>
fairly written, and fairly delivered. But in <lb/>
important matters there was an almost entire <lb/>
absence of decision, of a clearly defined policy; <lb/>
which we all must regard as not very compi<lb break="no"/>mantary to this House. A speech from the <lb/>
throne was always supposed to define a specific <lb/>
policy. Now in this speech there were references <lb/>
made to certain matters properly enough; but <lb/>
there was no course of policy defined for the <lb/>
Government to pursue. Now when the present <lb/>
Government came into power, a speech some<lb break="no"/>what similar to the present, one had been ad<lb break="no"/>dressed to this Assembly; and in that the <lb/>
Government did think it necessary to say what <lb/>
they intended to do, in order to restore the <lb/>
country from its deplorable condition, and to <lb/>
moving it forward in the career of improvement. <lb/>
The policy then put forth was the cncouragement <lb/>
and improvement of Agriculture; and in per<lb break="no"/>suance of that a Bill was introduced and passed, <lb/>
having that end for its object,as well as the re<lb break="no"/>duction of pauperism. At the time this measure <lb/>
was under discussion, he (Mr. T.) had given <lb/>
it as his opinion that it would be productiv of no <lb/>
good. Well, the Bill was passed, came into <lb/>
operation,and we now find that it has been pow<lb break="no"/>crless to effect those results which the Govern— <lb/>
ment predicted,but which were never anticipated <lb/>
by this side of the House. Pauperism, so far <lb/>
from receding, had advanced; so far from being <lb/>
checked, it had been accelerated; so that our <lb/>
present position was really worsé than when <lb/>
this great curative measure was so triumpuantly <lb/>
usherd in. Now that was one point which <lb/>
should be distinctly remembered. In that <lb/>
policy, then, Government had failed. Well, <lb/>
if we judge them by their failures, we cannot <lb/>
have much hope for their capacity to do any <lb/>
good. We had watchad carefully their pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings, and we had watched the operation <lb/>
and working of this measure with pecaliar cau. <lb/>
tion. He (Mr. T.) had taken the Government <lb/>
at its word. They said they were the greatest <lb/>
men in the country. He said granted. They <lb/>
said they would accomplish what had never <lb/>
been done before. He said granted. They <lb/>
said they possessed the collective wisdom of the <lb/>
country. He said granted. The said they <lb/>
were the Goliaths of this Colonial Parliament. <lb/>
He said granted. They sail they were the only <lb/>
ropresentatives of the public. He said grant<lb break="no"/>ed. They said they would never fail. Jie said <lb/>
dcubtful. Well, all their sayings had come to <lb/>
nothiag, and his doubts had been verified. <lb/>
They were evidently impressed with the belief <lb/>
that it was impossible for any body of men to <lb/>
rule this country; because they would not and <lb/>
could not cºnfess their own inability to do it, <lb/>
their own inability to grapple with the diſficulties <lb/>
that surrounded them. They would doubtless <lb/>
assert that because they failed, it was impos<lb break="no"/>sible for others to succeed. Now what had <lb/>
they tried to do? Their first essay was to des<lb break="no"/>troy pauperism; and how did they try to effect <lb/>
that purpose? By saying to a pauper go into <lb/>
the woods and clear land,and for the first acre <lb/>
you clear we will give you $8, and for evory <lb/>
one after the first, $9. This they said to a <lb/>
raan without any means at his control, without <lb/>
being able to buy a loaf of bread, a pick-axe to <lb/>
work with, or the means to erect a dwelling to <lb/>
live in. At the time it was proposod he (Mr. <lb/>
T.) said it was impossible to succeed, as it was, <lb/>
that the Government must surely mean to do <lb/>
something more, must give them roads, must <lb/>
try to sustain them, or if not, we are only mock<lb break="no"/>ing the miseries of the poor. Well; the Bill <lb/>
had become, as he (Mr. T.) anticipated, a per<lb break="no"/>fect failure. But did they do anything else? <lb/>
Having failed in this instance, did they look <lb/>
sround and see if they could devise any ineans <lb/>
that would be beneficial? Did they encourage <lb/>
those who had cultivated the land, b t who, <lb/>
from poverty, were unable to work it? There <lb/>
were hundreds of acres of cultivated land which <lb/>
has been lying idle for years. Did they woo <lb/>
the people to recover it from its present wilders <lb/>
ness state, and make their support dependent <lb/>
upon the culture of the soil? No. You <lb/>
made them believe they would get their <lb/>
support from you, and thus you <lb/>
degraded them. Pauperism increased, and pauper <lb/>
Relief expenditure increased. . No effort , was made <lb/>
to check it unsil tha eleventh hour. He contenued <lb/>
that when the Government desired to check this sys<lb break="no"/>tem, they should baye done so by degrees, and not <lb/>
at one full bound. It would appear that the Premier <lb/>
felt his émbarrassed situation, and his inability to <lb/>
stem the tide of cérruption and malversation of the <lb/>
public funds. Elis only desire was to save himself, <lb/>
rotect, if possible, his 'Government, and depend on <lb/></p> 

<p>not to be killed out by one blow; but was to be <lb/>
gradually yeakened. Then there was anotuer evil <lb/>
quite sufficient to crush the country of itself,increased <lb/>
taxation. Their reasoning in support of tual was <lb/>
that they could not support the people without <lb/>
lacing additional burthens upon their backs. <lb/>
§. burdens, say they, are heavy, but we'll cure <lb/>
them by putting on heavier ones. Now would any <lb/>
one say that these two measures were calculated to <lb/>
lieuefit the county, though they were put forward <lb/>
for that purpose? They either did it ior an evil <lb/>
$ºufocse, or else because they were unabled to rule <lb/>
the country. . We are told that this increase of taxa. <lb/>
tion was inevitable,and had been universally approv<lb break="no"/>ed:ot by the cóuatry. Here the hon. member refer<lb break="no"/>red at length to the late election at Harbor Grace,and <lb/>
sentended that the question of Confederation had <lb/>
gº been put to the people, who were perfectly <lb/>
indifferent whom they returned this session, knowing <lb/>
'hat the question would coins before them" for fin. <lb/>
decision at the general election. The fact that only <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>one of Confederation. That was the policy that <lb/>
was shadowed forth in his Excellency's speech, two <lb/></p> 

<p>what then occurred. A paragraph had been smug­ <lb/></p> 

<p>of great excitemant. They solemnly repudiated in <lb/></p> 

<p>such principle. They d clared that they were ogs of parchment. Not <lb/>
posed to Confederation on any terms, How men <lb/></p> 

<p>anxious that very Union should be accomplished <lb/>
It was said, but he (Mr. T.) did not know whether <lb/></p> 

<p>the helm, they would abandon the country and <lb/>
let it drift into a Union with Canada, provided <lb/>
only, that they should drift with it, and have the <lb/>
iron chest still with them. Next session, that was <lb/>
the last session, they had another speech, and <lb/></p> 

<p>former sessions were dropped, and the third <lb/></p> 

<p>ture had effected no good. Confederation was <lb/>
senuted, and Taxation only remained—and cºr­ <lb/></p> 

<p>into Confederaion, Ole objection, age to Conte- and more succinct. <lb/></p> 

<p>high, and the policy was to make the tariff of the <lb/>
country as high as that of Canada, an I thus renove <lb/>
that objection, and, as it proved, hon., gentlemen <lb/></p> 

<p>over it. It may be asked how can we lessen it <lb/>
now? It never appears tº attike hon, gentlemen <lb/>
that the expenditure could be brought down, a little. <lb/></p> 

<p>would be able to avoid increased taxation, and do <lb/>
many, things which would tend to advance the <lb/>
interests of the country and the comfort of the <lb/></p> 

<p>difficulties and be independent. I'ais is the fourth <lb/>
session. and they had again the old policy of the <lb/></p> 

<p>would have that question before them bye, and bye. clamation. <lb/>
He (Mr. T.) was of opinion, and he thought the <lb/></p> 

<p>required was retrenchment. The public believed <lb/>
that the expenses are excessive, and that some <lb/>
#20,000 or £30,000 a year, might easily be saved. <lb/>
and applied for the public henefit. <lb/></p> 

<p>coulºunity like this, if such a sum were judiciously <lb/>
and properly expended, there need not be a poor <lb/></p> 

<p>over their difficulties, and establish them in a course <lb/>
of industry which would render them prosperous and <lb/></p> 

<p>tural pursuits to aid the fisheries, then let Tus have <lb/>
Gonfederation or anything else. Before you take a <lb/>
step which will plunge you into irretrievable Union, <lb/></p> 

<p>no sympathy with the u. No country was so dis- ls <lb/>
cordautas Canada, which was made up of so many | ** <lb/>
antagonistic elements and races. He (Mr. T.) <lb/></p> 

<p>some one on the Government benches, that we had <lb/>
gained a great privilege. He could not see it in <lb/>
that light or that they were one bit better off. The <lb/>
treaties remained exactly as they were. How then <lb/></p> 

<p>ously when tuey refused licenses two years ago. <lb/>
The same treaties existed then as dow. No final <lb/>
determination had been arrived at by the Conven­ <lb/></p> 

<p>refer to. When the Secretary said they could not <lb/>
grant the licences, why did not the Government say <lb/>
tney intended, to do so. without, infringing on the <lb/>
fishery rights of the French? They did not do so, <lb/></p> 

<p>gloritying themselves on the tact that they have <lb/>
repaired their own blunder. It was a great privi­ <lb/></p> 

<p>at the same time told you must not erect buildings side or <lb/>
or what was precisely due to the Gºvernor? Tº jved than another <lb/>
Pºdkºninº ºpy.º.º.º. again says that <lb/>
Me (Alr. †. had said. Tue treatles were the diffi, º <lb/></p> 

<p>much plessure in supportag the anundament. <lb/></p> 

<p>*nºkali of the electors voted, proved ini. Theſ, <lb/></p> 

<p>- $. <lb/></p> 

<p>we had a new policy fisharedin, the, all absording the. political moves of the <lb/></p> 

<p>that the country was in a very bad state, Agricuſ. | Court of S. James's. <lb/></p> 

<p>b: - ºnent. -\-\-<lb break="maybe"/>ºlº.º.ºuld be ºn tº dº." |...}. them. <lb/></p> 

<p>on-tae French Shore, Where was the service dou", settled in the place <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb break="no"/>opposition. The para- people would not effect what "we Cannot. An <lb/>
graph before the chair related to the French Shore whº reºd the debates upon this question in the I. <lb/>
question and tº it the opposition proposed an amend:; perial Parliament must be strick with thi.". <lb/>
years ago, and every hon. member was aware of mant. Regarding the question, an impºrtant move Antire <lb/>
had heen made last session, inaugurated by the hon. a part in that debut... we actuily found a Mini <lb/>
glad into, the address, which it, was afterwards and learned leader of the opposition, who prepared a of the Crown saying that there should be º ſ <lb/></p> 

<p>petiti r s to the Qieen, the Lords an i the Commons <lb/>
this House that they had intended to affirm any prepared, writte in the very best text on the finest at all about the ºtter?"ife considered that ". . <lb/>
- content with all this tº hon was a first subject of 'sºlº."º." <lb/>
and learned, gentleman personally superintended sent, petitions to the Imperial Government wº <lb/>
then could so change their minds without any reason, the preparation of the tin case to carry home these should receive no reply -\-He knew that..." we <lb/>
As first presented the the usual course to senå a reply in º <lb/>
guided by the same iºnºwº we, ºre | resolutions were such as it woulf aot be cred- and upon, a matter of such vići impº. . º <lb/>
then. ..". are told . *. *...*.*.* itable to the House to primit to be seen ou <lb break="no"/>expressed their opinion to be that po circumstances - - - <lb break="no"/>. justify #. with Canada, are now most side. But all lent a hand, and they wºre lickad <lb/>
into shape, and yet all the credit of the whole | on . division: <lb/>
affair, tin box and all, devolved on the hon. and The Committee <lb/>
it was true or not, that the Government teel they learned mover. The amendment now proposed <lb/>
are in such a position that they cannot retr eve was a natural adden fun to the resolutions of Tue <lb/>
themselv's. They are in such a condition last session. Other men, Govern nents, and <lb/>
jº...": *... "...m. *: Legislatures had tried their h and at the affair, <lb/>
way, rather than permit other men to #. but had not advanced it one bit; but when the <lb break="no"/>hon. and learned gentleman took it up of Journment. <lb/>
course, it was to be settled right off. Of course, <lb/>
then, it was quite natural there should be a wall; itself into Committee of the Whole, on the furth <lb/>
of lamentation when, after all this exertion, tha: cºideration of the Address in reply tº: <lb/>
result w is uothing at all. <lb/>
it was remarkable that the policies of the two (Mr. P.) of the ques in put by <lb/>
Brush to Martin Chuzzlewit, as to which of his <lb/>
policy was a policy of taxation. We were told articles produced the greatest sensation in the time has nºw jeº... .", take action on th <lb/>
- So with the hon. gen- great question of Confederation; and we can ... <lb/>
tlemen opposite, they were quite surprised that | jour Excellency that we shall' gºve oil. . <lb/>
their great resolations produced uo effect. He <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>tainly taxes were piled on. It was said this was (Mr. P ) wanted to know who wrote that <lb/></p> 

<p>.# a policy. .. that its object was to prove to §. It coull not be the hon. member ..".ay. ..";" serve the interest, of <lb/>
the country that it would nº be worse ºff by going for Ferryland, for he would make it shorter the i.:*.* º º: of <lb/>
- - The British Government acceptable to all ci ove. <lb/>
deration was that the Canadian Tariff was very a ot only take no notice of the tin box resolu- i. to the ... "...º. ...: <lb/>
tion; and petitions, but they dare to approve of fia; approval and ratification of Her Mij. <lb/>
; Carnarvon's policy. <lb break="no"/>opposite swallowed the bait. Did it strike them | belli, and if he (Mr. P.) were in opposition; he <lb/></p> 

<p>; though the Tariff of the country º be pretty woull be for auuex . after º it was".!." .." . ºny.#... It was very desirabi, <lb/>
much as is the Qaºhaº, Tariff if we shºuld be | pity, such a grand wove sheuld turn out a fiasco. He did ..". i. #. .*.*. <lb/>
confederated it ſwill be *; as its *...*. rate,: There w is another great move.neat yet to be not think it ºis well to say . #".'. º". <lb/>
not made higher, and * will have ºf all, coºl made. It had tº ..., nights hatching, and the time has arrived, it must haveºlje. . . <lb/>
though they tried to shroud it in mystery, they thingprecedent to the fact that it was stated thataction <lb/>
could not keep it quite, but let it out. <lb/></p> 

<p>When it was proposed to increase taxation, the not then go into the question of what that move- <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>hon. º º: (Mr. T's.) side of the House ment .#. b+. §. thing struck him (Mr. P.) . ...'... º º understood ths <lb/>
suggested a reductiºn of , the expenditure instead, after listening to the loug speeches of hou. mem- no time ºil. *...". ...'. General, <lb/>
but they were not listened to. º their ...; bºrs opposite. It was, what au uncommonly good matter was, in the fir. ..". ... the <lb/>
tney, though that by dºing the expºnditure hºy Gover. wº have, when gentlemen blessed | people, who were tº be asked if they ...; <lb/>
with such lungs can find aothing so say against <lb break="no"/>it. Seed potatoes had been the stock subject of ºt, or in any way beyond that ºn. <lb/></p> 

<p>Wuy, it was a casus <lb/></p> 

<p>eople. Tuey fancied that it would be well to act the hon. and learned member tor Harbor Main <lb break="no"/>. *:::: individuals surrounded by financial diffi- but he had changed his tactics to suit those of th. i. .."; '. *...othing, and led people tº <lb/>
pºliº would to dº thº...ºneh and ſº in a new leader,who did not approve of the proclama- canvassed speculati i. * spoken of and <lb/>
less luxurious and expensive style, and thus, by tion. That proclamation had producei, and adopted i peculatively. this section be <lb/>
making income and expenditure square, get rid of ld prod y *dopted, it would, it appeared to him, assen <lb/>
would produce, good results, and the Govern- that which was not true. The elections were <lb/>
ment intended carrying it out to its final end. If *Ppreaching, and so it might be said that th; <lb/>
second session, and were asked to adopt Confedera. hou. gentlem in opposite had the good of the time had cºme when tue pe, le should be asked <lb/>
tion, as that was the ºnly thing which would ims | country at heart, they would return to their for- if they approved of the . le. At: <lb/>
provº the condition of the country. Of course they mer straightfoward course res? cling the pros the House could me: ... ...i. .º <lb/></p> 

<p>country was of the same, that the only thing they .* Bºoºº-No doubt that was a grand the pººl, i. thought that would be the proper <lb/>
- display of elocution , and statesman like abil- way to act, or a least that it ...".i <lb/>
ºy to which they had just lis ened from Dunlel accordance with the general uniºn. <lb/>
- Woodly Prowse, the wooden-healed represen- the hººd i.e., Attoraey General's prºmº <lb/>
Men in office |ºtive of the woolen-headed constituency of If this Paragraph be passed, it will b. º '. <lb/>
*...* a saving would he wºrºh ºthing, that if | Burgeo and LaPoile. Goodness help the Gov. me. for the considerº, uf the . <lb/>
º::::::::: *Wº:*::::::::::...º.º.º.º. º...". <lb/>
000 to £120,000 in %. years, and in a small laughabl; in the extrem, to hear hiin talk of the vions aſſi,mation of the principle. The wording <lb/>
hon. and learned member for Harbor Main, Mr. of the paragraph was not cle ir, and if ºbj <lb/>
Hogsett, a man who enjoyed the confidence of intendeſ tº Hºse should affirm the prin. <lb/>
man in the country. The people were now in a the public of the country North, South, East ºple, it ought to b, so expressed in c. º d <lb/>
transition state, from the time in which the fiſheries and Wast. He (Mr. R.) regretted that, wallst tlefillite language, Two years a. ºt §. 8th <lb/>
were able to support then for the wuole year round, the hou. and learned mºmber, Mr. Hogsett, mout attempted by a . infº. '... <lb/>
. .."..." . do not º i. º ... was packing up these tin cases, be did not pack | film ºil. principle, but the Hºuse retus . º <lb/>
support during the summer. If that *"... up the hon. and learned member for Burgee j after some consideration and difficulty, . <lb/>
If. he had been tius | hon. goutlemen opposi.e., the eſ use '... win. <lb/>
packed of it would have rid the House of a drawn and one of a doubtlulcharacter subsitual <lb/>
*Pºº. He (Mº...T.), believed that this saviug | #º ºuisanº-, As for the amendment, he After that it was said the Substituteu cl º <lb/>
might be accºmplished, as all events, it was worth (Mr. R.) held the same opiniod as did his col- atā, med the principle, and the present J. . <lb/>
"...º.º.º.º.º.º. league, that the matter stood in the same post-| Hºra, "whººp. # ...; <lb/>
did not tide the people over their difficulties, if it did |tion as it did before the resolutions and address- - irbor Gracur <lb/>
not help to aid the fishermen in establishing agricul- es. . sent home. They had been told that ºne did nºt intend to affirm the principle ºf aff, <lb/>
applicants for grants had received them, and le? It w - is tr <lb break="no"/>were perpared to go to work under the condi- i. be ſº."...","...º.º. # <lb/>
tº it. It is better than parting with your liberty, ºn contained in these grants. To his (Mr. words which mºner say sye, ſoº. ...; <lb/>
* Prºperty, and possibly with your lives. it was R's) mind they had no security, there was noth. implies an affirmation of the principi.". <lb/>
... .. *. by *. ing before them to conclude that the matter <lb/>
a u arº Wri their inderties and ti - - igſ. - * <lb/>
and #. to another country which had was so satisfactorily settled as to allay all. aux- first agi? None hitherto, but now we concur tº: <lb/>
iety on the part of those who had discovered it is time to take a.º."."fi. step should <lb/>
on that part of <lb/>
They . º that a great deal had been <lb/>
said it would be wise to pause and try all feasible accomplished, and in the same breath that the - -\-\- - - <lb break="no"/>things before jº. themselves in that way. matter was still under discussion. The subject i.",...;i...". º <lb/>
The question just before the House was that of the was now receiving the atteution of Her Ma. in so deceitul a manne; in it it a. nº. . iiis, <lb/>
French Snoré rights. He had heard it said by jesty's Government, and whilst the policy of (Mr. T's) approval, and he would be Very surry to <lb/>
Lord Carnarvon is to be upheld, licenses to <lb/>
search are to be issued. He (Mr. R.) contended <lb/>
that a grant to work mines could be of no value through, They are now asked to wheel aboutliko, <lb/>
was it possible to say that they were better off or without a right to the use of the strand. A few jiu grows,and say to-day what they roſasºit. <lb/>
. .. privileges than .. No †. years ago private individuals in the course of <lb/>
had yet been come, to, so things," as they their explorations discovered valuable marbles.: -. <lb break="no"/>were last, year, and . .; streatles . and other things. They then went to England #. º; ...". . <lb/>
made. The Government, biºlºred, mºst tremend" | to endeavor jug. capitalists in invest. The he (Air. T.) did not affirm ºe priº †. <lb/>
first enquiry made was as to their tile, and Froin all he had reflected upon it and ºn of it, he <lb/></p> 

<p>although they were fully satisfied of the great -<lb break="maybe"/>tion. Who refused the licenses? Tae-Government value of the minerals discovered, yet there j::::::::::::::"; ...; <lb/>
|; because directed to do so by the Becretary of no secure title, the capitalists refused to invest. aeant, and under ...'...". º <lb/>
State lor, the Colºnies. ...But lººd nº. have | The question in fact remained as it was two must go ºn is ºne ºn"...". plage, it <lb/>
directed them, at all, for the treaties were.there to years ago. For the sake of argument, ſet us -<lb break="maybe"/>assum that a graut has been issued. He to - • tº - -<lb break="maybe"/>whome the grant was made discovers minerals, §."..":... . *...*, #. <lb/>
he commences opercuous, developes a valuable principle of that Union such as they could approve. <lb/>
and so neglected their duty. Now, when his mine, and has a number of peºple employel, ut? He <lb/>
Excellency went home and said sº, the Secretary he requires ineans of shipment, and has to bring <lb/>
replied,. On you may do that ºf course; it was his minerals three or four miles to the stranurſ already united, and he (M.T. idº. et <lb/>
ºver, intºniº, º żº ... ... } when arrived there some Frenchman º' . principiº, and (; º;º: <lb/>
gº with tºº lºº.º.º. [... you are interfering with my fishery rights, tage, such a Union could be to the country. It <lb/>
and alºnough that may be said merely for the <lb/>
Iege to be allowed to search on the land, and be | Bake of annoyance, he has to remove to one was the ineauing of this Comfederation? Remove <lb/>
the other; and no sooner is he ſtºire". gliter, and what was iſ nºted, <lb/></p> 

<p>Frenchman comes and to Cauadal absolute power and control over our <lb/></p> 

<p>- + firls <lb/>
gº ºi nº. Herº ||........"... º. Tºjº. <lb/>
g - ght object, ...".":# in it all the glitzering colors you choose, but tº <lb/>
ºfur St , made? We are aware that we, of ourselves, can do | . . its reality, and that is wu.it it uneans. He <lb/>
Mº, Pºwse-The hoº: ºº sº...ohn's nothing, that the Imperial Government would ...; liberties because atter the jnº estao. <lb/>
West had just given them a dissertation on the art never quarrel with France for us, and nºt if we t <lb break="no"/>of Government, but had. been vary reticent on 1 were confederated the voic, bf fºur miſſiºns of <lb/></p> 

<p>ignoranse of the subject evinued by thos whº to k <lb/></p> 

<p>that show the Imperial airhorities knew nothing <lb/></p> 

<p>thought it was right for us to express our ºf <lb/>
as ºntained in the aimandment. widºs <lb/></p> 

<p>The original motion was then put and carried <lb/>
*A <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>then rose and <lb/>
prºgress. To sit again on Thursday. reported <lb/>
House adjourned till Thursday at 3 o'clock, <lb/></p> 

<p>a­ <lb/></p> -->

<p rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, Feb. 11. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The House met at 8 o'clock, pursuant to ad<lb break="no"/>jourment. <lb/></p> 

<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:GODD1">Mr. GODDEN</persName>, the House resolved <lb/>
    itself into Committee of the Whole, on the further <lb/>
    consideration of the Address in reply to the speech <lb/>
    of His Excellency, <persName ref="pers:KNIG2">Mr. KNIGHT</persName> in the Chair. <lb/></p> 

<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:GODD1">Mr. GODDEN</persName>, the fifth section of the <lb/>
    address was read as follows:— <lb/></p>
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>
"We fully concur with your Excellency that the <lb/>
    time has now arrived for us to take action on the <lb/>
    great question of Confederation; and we can assure <lb/>
    your Excellency that we shall give our earnest <lb/>
attention to the consideration of our Union with the <lb/>
Dominion of Canada, on such fair and equitable <lb/>
    terms as many be calculated to serve the interests of <lb/>
    the Colony, be approved of by the Government of <lb/>
    the Dominion, and which we trust may prove <lb/>
    acceptable to all classes of the people, when sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to the constituencies, and also recieve the <lb/>
fianl approval and ratification of Her Majesty."</p> 
</quote>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr. TALBOT</persName> did not understand the section <lb/>
    which had just been read, and thought it was involv<lb break="no"/>ed in a good deal of mystery. It was very desierable <lb/>
    that such a matter should not be misunderstood. <lb/>
    He did not agree that the time had arrived, and did <lb/>
    not think it was well to say so. If it be said that <lb/>
    the time has arrived, it must have reference to some<lb break="no"/>thing precedent to the fact that it was stated that action <lb/>
    would be taken at some future time, which time <lb/>
    had now arrived. But he (Mr. T.) was not aware <lb/>
    that such had ever been said. If he understood the <lb/>
    assurance of the hon. and learned Attorney General <lb/>
    no time could arrive to this present House, for the <lb/>
    matter was, in the first place, to be referred to the <lb/>
    people, who were to be asked if they approved of
this, Union. It had not been put before the people <lb/>
    In that light, or in any way beyond that general <lb/>
view which was given by candidates, who in fact <lb/>
    bound themselves to nothing, and led people to <lb/>
    believe that it was a mere question spoken of and <lb/>
    canvassed speculatively. If this section be <lb/>
    adopted, it would, it appeared to him, assert <lb/>
    that which was not true. The elections were <lb/>
    approaching, and so it might be said that the <lb/>
    time had come when the people should be asked <lb/>
    if they approved of the principle. After that <lb/>
the House could meet and state certain conditi<lb break="no"/>ons,and these conditions could be again referred to <lb/>
    the people, he thought that would be the proper <lb/>
    way to act, or at least that it would be in <lb/>
    accordance with the general understanding of <lb/>
    the hon. and learned Attorney Genereal's premise. <lb/>
    If this paragraph be passed, it will be an agree<lb break="no"/>ment for the consideration of the conditions, <lb/>
    which would be a strong presumption of a pre<lb break="no"/>vious affirmation of the principle. The wording <lb/>
    of the paragraph was not clear. and if it be <lb/>
    intended that the House should affirm the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple, it ought to be so expected in clear and <lb/>
    definite language. Two years ago, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment attempted by a clause in the address to <lb/>
    affirm the principle, but the House refused, and <lb/>
    after some consideration and difficulty, amongst <lb/>
    hon. gnetlemen opposite, the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> was with<lb break="no"/>drawn, and one of a doubtless characters substituted. <lb/>
    After that it was said the substituted clause <lb/>
    affirmed the principle, and the present Judge <lb/>
    Hayward, who then represented Harbor Grace <lb/>
made a great row about it, and said that he for <lb/>
    one did not intend to affirm the principle at all. <lb/>
    Was the House now asked to affirm that princi<lb break="no"/>ple? If we look at this paragraph, and ask if <lb/>
    such be the case, we are met by a conclusion of <lb/>
    words which neither says yes nor no. It certainly <lb/>
    implies an affirmation of the principle. That <lb/>
was an advance towards its affirmation. We <lb/>
agree it is time to take action. What was the <lb/>
    first act? None hitherto, but now we concur that <lb/>
    it is time to take action. The first step should <lb/>
    be to affirm the principle, and until that be done, <lb/>
    details and conditions cannot be considered. Why <lb/>
    not say distinctly that the time had come for the <lb/>
    affirmation of the principle and consideration of <lb/>
    details? The section implied that affirmation, but <lb/>
    in so deceitful a manner that it did not meet his <lb/>
    (Mr. T's) approval, and he would be very sorry to <lb/>
vote for it. There is a loophole left here for the <lb/>
supporters of the Government, by which they may <lb/>
be caught by the neck, and bound as they pass <lb/>
    through. They are now asked to wheel about like <lb/>
    jim crows, and say to-day what they refused to say <lb/>
    two years ago. That was not treating them pro<lb break="no"/>perly. Their attention should be directed to the <lb/>
    precise point, and they should not be asked to <lb/>
    proceed with their eyes bandaged. For himself, <lb/>
    he (Mr. T.) did not affirm the principle at all. <lb/>
    From all he had reflected upon it and seen of it, he <lb/>
    was decidedly opposed to the principle, and did <lb/>
    not think Union would, under all its circumstances, <lb/>
    prove beneficial, and they then knew what Union <lb/>
    meant, and under what leading principles they <lb/>
    must go in. If the Union had not taken place, if <lb/>
    it were still in embryo, and they did not see it <lb/>
    working, there might be a doubt as to whether the <lb/>
    principle was good or not. But now that the <lb/>
    Union was established, the question was—Is the <lb/>
    principle of that Union such as they could approve <lb/>
    of? He (Mr. T.) said it ws not. No matter what <lb/>
    terms you propose, they cannot deviate from the <lb/>
    essential ptinciples on which the Colonies are <lb/>
    already united, and he (Mr. T.) did not approve <lb/>
    of those principles, and do not see what advan<lb break="no"/>tage such a Union could be to the country. It <lb/>
    would not make us better off, because from the <lb/>
    nature of things, it was impossible it could. What <lb/>
    was the meaning of this Confederation? Remove <lb/>
    all the glare and glitter, and what was its naked <lb/>
    meaning? Just this, that by our own act we give <lb/>
    to Canada absolute power and control over our <lb/>
    destinies, over our liberties, and properties and <lb/>
    our lives. That is the exact meaning of Confed<lb break="no"/>eration. Throw what dust you like about it, put <lb/>
    in it all the glittering colors you choose, but take <lb/>
    it in its reality, and that is what it means. He <lb/>
    said liberties, because after the Union was estab<lb break="no"/>lished, they would have no liberty to rule them<lb break="no"/>selves, and could make no laws without the sec<lb break="no"/></p> 

    <!-- IC, 2019-01-30, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>tion of the Dominion; prºper: <lb/>
#Dominion Parliament cnuld tax <lb/>
and cºternally, to any amount they <lb/>
jause the same power could. <lb/>
*hen they pleased &amp;nd use their liv <lb/>
purposes, . Such was Confederatio <lb/>
iſ very nice thing tº congºttulate <lb/></p> 

<p>but he (M did not think the <lb/>
coutent with it. Was it wise or at <lb/>
up their right to legislate for them <lb/>
their property at the merey of a fo <lb/>
tax as they pleased, to submit tilº <lb/>
also, so that they might seize and <lb/>
from 18 to 60 years Ól age, to repº <lb/>
made upon them by the great Repu <lb/>
the dust will be raised and the pictu <lb/>
they...would be told that rhoºgh wr <lb/>
in ight be Confederation, per pse, <lb/>
derive advartages troºm it whic. <lb/></p> 

<p>balance all this; that new channe <lb/>
be opened, and the country raised <lb/>
civilization, that agriculture will <lb/>
and bloom in all the luxuriance it <lb/></p> 

<p>other Provinces, . He (Mr. T.) c. <lb/>
stand how Confederation was go <lb/>
this, and did not believe that the <lb/>
tkemselves really understo \d it <lb/>
Canada bind herselt on your parchit <lb/>
to promote our 30.htmei'ee, agricult <lb/>
factures? No, she could not do it, <lb/>
the law is already passed; Confed <lb/>
Hished, and she cannot give more <lb/>
already arranged amongst themse <lb/>
argu,ments advanced to prove the <lb/>
confederation had reference to Comi <lb/>
aud arrange.ments, and had nothil <lb/>
with the political aspect of the ques <lb/>
were to be benefited by an equal tar <lb/>
done by some Gouamercial ariange <lb/>
miues were tº be worked, it wou! <lb/>
capitalists and not by politicians; a. <lb/>
work them; not because we wer. <lb/>
but because they would be profitat, <lb/>
said that if we confederate we will <lb/>
flour, pork, &amp;c., tree of duty, Tbat <lb/>
ble argument. It certainly was s <lb/>
all these arguments the political <lb/>
Inixed up with comułercial matti <lb/>
question was blinked, so as to thr <lb/>
*yes of the people. These articles <lb/>
ºuty free by cominercial regulations. <lb/>
federation. Such was the ease betort", <lb/>
ht net to be so again? He (ºir. 'I <lb/>
show the knack by which the suppor <lb/>
eration attempted to blindiold the <lb/>
keep the political question in the bac <lb/>
drag forward a very different matter, <lb/>
duestion of commercial arrangements <lb/>
very strarge to nine, but perhaps it <lb/>
was innocent and not up to the tricke <lb/>
tral wisdom which sometimes maz <lb/>
livuse had in itself the power to <lb/>
pork, flour, &amp;c., free of dutv, but it <lb/>
...the country was in debt, and could <lb/>
He (Mr. T.) replied, let us retrench <lb/>
expenditure, and so be able to es: <lb/>
duties. Another argument was that wi <lb/>
ration we cannºt have reciprocity, W <lb/>
is ree procity? It simply mesn's th <lb/>
emption from duties of articles the <lb/>
sluce, of particular countries, on <lb/>
Was it not in our power to make suc <lb/>
MTo be sure it was Tuen what had <lb/>
to do with reciprocity? It was a se <lb/>
which shºuld be troited ot, its ow: <lb/>
Miot mixed up with the question of ( <lb/>
Politically, Coutederation inevit only <lb/>
should have the absolu.e control of t <lb/>
property and the lives of the people <lb/>
tie chałlenged a deliiai of th it. It <lb/>
what Coutederation inelant, then he <lb/>
of its meaning. He (Mr. T.) could <lb/>
though. W. <lb/></p> 

<p>w inust, it beenlet,have <lb/>
without it we cau't get on at all. W <lb/>
a cripp led state that willess 50.me <lb/>
coues, wild in thercy picks tº up, we <lb/>
we cutulut exist Uy uurselvu". B <lb/>
inent upsets the other arguinent, <lb/>
show that the great good of Guilfº <lb/>
be to save us fruiu uturselves. It liev <lb/>
occur to hon, geiſtleiuen \llitt aliy <lb/>
governing thu country cºulu be dev <lb/>
which they their seives adopted, aud <lb/>
1or the past four years, which W <lb/>
great many offices, and fill them <lb/>
many people, audi Inake large sular <lb/>
and tueu, lu order to get these 8 <lb/>
heavy taxes on bread, iluur, pork, &amp; <lb/>
because tust dues uot succeed, we mud <lb/>
as the country calliot be ruled by it <lb/>
But these hon, gentlemen go on the wi <lb/>
nation and flash and thundcr thre <lb/>
above. They can't walk upon terra fi <lb/>
mon people. If we ourselves by a lo <lb/>
Government cannot make the people <lb/>
surely no Government on this side the <lb/>
do it. When the ſimperial Governtnut <lb/>
affairs of the colony we well remel <lb/>
used to blunder. The general cry wº <lb/>
understand us. With self Governmei: <lb/>
we possessed everything negessary to <lb/>
perous. There are now some gentlem <lb/>
we ought to have another kick up <lb/>
selves under some other Smpire. <lb/>
history of this Confederation I I he <lb/>
were ſighting and squabbling among t <lb/>
in order to keep then quiet they: <lb/>
then was the first of Confederation. <lb/>
considerable Annexation party and th: <lb/>
shindy, not to says rabellion, which, <lb/>
quickly quelled. In the United Parli <lb/>
were equally divided and innumerable <lb/>
curred. That Confederation failed an <lb/>
years ago the leading men of both par <lb/>
the happy thought that if they could 4 <lb/>
Provinces to join them that they might <lb/>
make laws for them, they themselves <lb/>
very well. But all this time they neve <lb/>
Newfoundland could be benefitted by <lb/>
At last they united at Quebec, and the <lb/>
General, the present Sir Hugh W. Ho: <lb/>
to be travelling in Canada at the time, <lb/>
perhaps we would send up a couple on <lb/>
what they were doing there. The Cai <lb/>
men eaid they never thought of Newfou <lb/>
but, they would be very happy to r <lb/>
And so, without the appointment of ti <lb/>
the bon. Attorney General and the hon. <lb/>
sent up merely to watch the proceedin, <lb/>
vention. He (Mr. T.) would not go <lb/>
ceedings of that Convention, he would <lb/>
champaign bottles, and the various ſet <lb/>
they were invited, but the conciasion <lb/>
was that his two hon, friends were st <lb/>
by these elever Canadians and others ti <lb/>
the document which was the basis of C. <lb/>
Well, these hon, gentlemen came bal <lb/>
that they had done something of whic <lb/>
reason to be proud, There was no flo <lb/>
pets on their return, no guns fired, no <lb/>
awaiting them to exhibit these two wo <lb/>
aimiring gaze of their countrymen <lb/></p> 

<p>eame to this house and they end <lb/>
over to their views every man of jul <lb/>
country: They represented the thing <lb/>
eolours, they É. that it was <lb/></p> 

<p>thing for the country which could be a <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="3" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-17_Page_3.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">3</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-31, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>people would not effect ºt"ws cannot. Any on <lb/>
wing read the debates upon this ion in th: . <lb/>
*erial Parliament must be strick with the jº.<lb break="no"/>ignoranee of the subject evinced by those whº . <lb/>
part in that debate. We actułly found a Mimi. <lb/>
if the Crown saying that there should be". <lb/>
Concessions, that we should concede to the F. <lb/>
he right of fishing all along our coast. Did . <lb/>
hat show the Imperial airhorities knew ºth. <lb/>
all about the matter? Iſe, considered º'"; <lb/>
as a first subject of complaint that <lb/>
ºnt, petitions to the Imperial Government w <lb/>
hould receive no reply -\-He knew that it ". <lb/>
he usual course to send a reply in such cases. <lb/>
ad upon, a matter. of such vital imporan. i. <lb/>
nought it was right for us to express our widws <lb/>
*i. . . an andment. <lb/>
:e original motion was then put an <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>9t;T division; p d carried, <lb/>
he Committee then rose and re <lb/>
ºgrees. To sit again on Thursday. ported <lb/>
The House adjourned till Tuursday at 3 o'clock. <lb/></p> 

<p>THunsdar, Feb. 11. <lb/>
The House met at 8 o'clock, parsuant to ada <lb/>
&gt; *rnment. <lb/>
Qº. taction of Mr. Godbºx. the House reso:ver <lb/>
elf into Committee of the Whole, on the #. <lb/>
sideration of the Address in reply to the speech <lb/>
º *.*.*. Mr. KNIGHT in the Chair. <lb/>
ºn motion of Mr. Goddes, the fifth sect; <lb/>
*dress was read as follows:- ection of the <lb/>
"We fully concur with your Excellency that the <lb/>
ae, has now arrived for us to take actiºn on the <lb/>
at question of Confederation; and we can assure <lb/>
* Excellency that we shall give our **arnest <lb/>
tention to the consideration of our U.ion wi b the <lb/>
"minion of Canada, on such fair and equitable <lb/>
rms as may be calculated to serve the interests of <lb/>
* Colony, be approved of by the Governº: of <lb/>
Dominion, an which we trust may prove. <lb/>
*pable, ſo all classes of the people, when sº, <lb/>
ºted to the consti, ncies, and also receive the <lb/>
sl approval and ratification of Her Majºsty." <lb/>
Mr. TALBor did not unierstand the section <lb/>
ich had just been read, and thought it was invoy. <lb/>
in a good deal of mystery. It was very desirable <lb/>
t such a matter snout: not be misunderstood. <lb/>
did not agree that the time had arrived, and did <lb/>
v thuk it was well to say so. It it be said that <lb/>
time has arrived, it must have reference to 8oine<lb break="no"/>agprecedent to the fact that it was stated thataction <lb/>
aid be taken at some future time, which jº <lb/>
I now arrived. But he (Mr.T. ) was not aware <lb/>
t such had ever been said. If he understood the <lb/>
urance of the hon, and learned A torney General, <lb/>
time could arrive to this present House, for the <lb/>
tºr was, in the first place, to be reierred 3 tº <lb/>
pº, who were tº be asked if they approved of <lb/>
Union. It had not been pit before tº pºople <lb/>
'hat, light, or in any way beyond that genera! <lb/>
* whiun was given by candidates, who ºn tº <lb/>
nil them:ºlves to nothi.g, and ſed people to <lb/>
ºve that it was a mere question spoken ºf and <lb/>
wassed., speculatively. If this section be <lb/>
pled, it would, it appeared to hi m, assert. <lb/>
which was not true. The elections were <lb/>
rºaching, aud so it might be said that the <lb/>
* had coine when the people should be asked <lb/>
*y approved of the principle. After that <lb/>
House could meet and state certain conditi, <lb/>
and these conditions could be again referred to <lb/>
people, he thought that would be the proper <lb/>
to act, or a least that it would by in <lb/>
ordance with the general understanºling of <lb/>
h94-and learned Attorney Gºneral's pro mise." <lb/>
*P*graph be pºssed, it will be an agree<lb break="no"/>$ for the consideration of the couditions, <lb/>
sh would be a stroug presumption of a pre<lb break="no"/>* alliamation of the principle. The wordlug <lb/>
* Paragraph was ubt 'cle ºr, and if it be <lb/>
"del that the House should affirm the prin<lb break="no"/>* it ought to b; so expressed in clear aud <lb/>
its language. Two years ag, the Govern. <lb/>
attempted by a clausu in the address to: <lb/>
* the Piuciple, but the iſ use retused, ani <lb/>
Souie Gunglderativu and difficulty, ºulongst <lb/>
goatluinen Opposiºr the ci use was withs <lb/>
nand one of a doubtulcharacter subsituted. <lb/>
r that it was Baid the substituteu clause <lb/>
ae: the principie, and the present Judge. <lb/>
ward, who then represented Harbor Grieur <lb/>
* * gudat row about it, and said that he fºr <lb/>
ºd lºt intend to affirm the principle at aii. <lb/>
the House now asked to affirm that princi<lb break="no"/>it we look at this pºvetgripil, and ask if <lb/>
be , the case, we are met by a cou usion of <lb/>
3 which usiºner says yes nurſuo. It certainly <lb/>
*s all, affirmation of the principle. Tºt. <lb/>
uh alyānue towards its atllrºnationi. "We <lb/>
it is time to take action, What was the <lb/>
":1% None hithertº, but now we concur that: <lb/>
time to take action. The first step should, <lb/>
"Iliriº the principle, anºi until that bºnº <lb/>
s uſid conditious culiuot be considered. Wuy <lb/>
y distinctly that the tune had come for the <lb/>
"tion of the principle and consideratiºn of <lb/>
** The section ingfied that affirmation, but <lb/>
ºcellºul tº ºkkuner ill tº it did not useet uis, <lb/>
S) approval, aud he would be very sorry to <lb/>
ºr it. There is a loophole left here for the <lb/>
ºs ºf the Governmºut, by which they may <lb/>
£ht by the neck, and bound as they pass, <lb/>
:n. They are now asked to wheel about like: <lb/>
*Wºund say to-day what they refused to say <lb/>
"...ago. That was not treating then pro<lb break="no"/>Their attention should be directed to the <lb/>
*... point, and they should not be asked to: <lb/>
d with their eyes bindaged. For himself, <lb/>
º, T.) dº nºt affirm the principle at aii. <lb/>
ll lie had reflected upon it amuseum of it, he <lb/>
ciueuly opposed to the principle, and diſ. <lb/>
tº Ullion would, under all its circuviust'inces, <lb/>
l, and tuey then kuew win it Unioni <lb/>
and under wuat leading principles they <lb/>
*:ti. It tue iſnion h; ot takºu place, it <lb/>
still in elubryº, aud, they did not see its <lb/>
#, there might be a doubt as to whether the <lb/>
!e Wits guud or not. But now that the <lb/>
was established, the question was—is time' <lb/>
* of that Uniou such as they could approve. <lb/>
• (Mr. T.) Sug it was not, No unatter what. <lb/>
9u prufºuse; they cannut deviate troºm the <lb/>
•l principles on which the Colonies are' <lb/>
uuºted, and lie (Mr. uid, hot approve: <lb/>
priuchºles, and did not see what advau-<lb break="maybe"/>ich &amp; Uuion could be to the country. It $ <lb/>
not make us better oft, because from the: <lb/>
ºf things, it was impossible it could. Wºmat. <lb/>
g of this Conteueration? Reinovº <lb/>
&amp;lare audgli aud what was its naked: <lb/>
** Just tiis, that by our own act we give <lb/>
da absolute power and control over our <lb/>
ºr ºver Qur liberties, and properités and <lb/>
S. ...That is tie exact meaning of Contel<lb break="no"/>Turow what dust you line about it, put <lb/>
the glitteriug cutors you caoose, but take: <lb/>
reality, and that is what it incans. He <lb/>
erties, because alter the Union was estab<lb break="no"/>uty would have no liberty to rulé theins <lb/>
ad could, make no laws wººthout tue **. <lb/></p> 

<p>#-\-<lb break="maybe"/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>TTHETNF, w Fou NDT, ND R. <lb/></p> 

<p>*-: *** * * * &gt; <lb/></p> 

<p>** r , . <lb/></p>--> 

<p>tion of the Dominion; property, because the <lb/>
Dominion Parliament could tax them internally <lb/>
and externally, to any amount they pleased; lives <lb/>
because the same power could take our people <lb/> 
when they pleased and use their lives for their own <lb/>
purposes. Such was Confederation. It would be <lb/>
a very nice thing to congratulate themselves on, <lb/>
but he (Mr. T.) did not think the people would be <lb/>
content with it. Was it wise or advisable to yield <lb/>
up their right to legislate for themselves, to place <lb/>
their property at the mercy of a foreign power to <lb/>
tax as they pleased, to submit their lives to them <lb/>
also, so that they might seize and take every man <lb/>
from 18 to 60 years of age, to repel any attempts <lb/>
made upon them by the great Republic? Of course, <lb/>
the dust will be raised and the picture painted, and <lb/>
they would be told that though what he had said <lb/>
    might be Confederation, <hi rendition="simple:italic">per ipse</hi>, yet we would <lb/>
derive advantages from it which would counter <lb/>
balance all this; that new channels of trade will <lb/>
be opened, and the country raised in the scale of <lb/>
civilization, that agriculture will be awakened, <lb/>
and bloom in all the luxuriance it exhibits in the <lb/>
other Provinces. He (Mr. T.) could not under<lb break="no"/>stand how Confederation was going to effect all <lb/>
this, and did not believe that the Confederates <lb/>
themselves really understood it either. Would <lb/>
Canada bind herself on your parchment agreement <lb/>
to promote our commerce, agriculture and manu<lb break="no"/>factures? No, she could not do it, for remember <lb/>
the law is already passed; Confederation estab<lb break="no"/>lished, and she cannot give more than has been <lb/>
already arranged amongst themselves. All the <lb/>
arguments advanced to prove the advantages of <lb/>
confederation had reference to Commercial treaties <lb/>
and arrangements, and had nothing at all to do <lb/>
with the political aspect of the question. If trade <lb/>
were to be benefited by an equal tariff, it could be <lb/>
done by some Commercial arrangements. If our <lb/>
mines were to be worked, it would be done by <lb/>
capitalists and not by politicians; and they would <lb/>
work them; not because we were confederated, <lb/>
but because they would be profitabie. It will be <lb/>
raid that if we confederate we will have our bread <lb/>
flour, pork, &amp;c., free of duty. That was a plausi<lb break="no"/>ble argument. It certainly was strange that in <lb/>
all these arguments the political question was <lb/>
mixed up with commercial matters. The real <lb/>
question was blinked, so as to throw dust in the <lb/>
eyes of the people. These articles could be made <lb/>
duty free by commercial regulations, without Con<lb break="no"/>federation. Such was the case before, and why should <lb/>
it not to be so again? He Mir. T.) wanted to <lb/>
show the knack by which the supporters of Confed<lb break="no"/>eration attempted to blindfold the people. They <lb/>
keep the political question in the back ground, and <lb/>
drag forward a very different matter, that is the <lb/>
question of commercial arrangements. It appeared <lb/>
very strarge to aim, but perhaps it was because he <lb/>
was innocent and not up to the tricks, the labyrin<lb break="no"/>tial wisdom which sometimes mazes one. That <lb/>
House had in itself the power to admit bread, <lb/>
pork, flour, &amp;c., free of duty, but it would be said <lb/>
the country was in debt, and could not afford it. <lb/>
He (Mr. T.) replied, let us, retrench, reduce the <lb/>
expenditure, and so be able to strike off these <lb/>
duties. Another argument was that without Confede<lb break="no"/>ration we cannot have reciprocity. Why not? What <lb/>
is reciprocity? It simply means the mutual ex<lb break="no"/>emption from duties of articles the peculiar pro<lb break="no"/>duce of particular countries, on mutual terms. <lb/>
Was it not in our power to make such terms now? <lb/>
To be sure it was. Then what had Confederation <lb/>
to do with reciprocity? It was a separate matter, <lb/>
which should be treated on its own merits, and <lb/>
not mixed up with the question of Confederation. <lb/>
Politically, Confederation meant only that Canada <lb/>
should have the absolute control of the libery, the <lb/>
property and the lives of the people of this Colouy. <lb/>
He challenged a denial of thit. It that was not <lb/>
what Confederation meant, then he was ignorant <lb/>
of its meaning. He (Mr. T.) could see the truth <lb/>
though. We must, it seemed, have Confederation; <lb/>
without it we can't get on at all. We are in such <lb/>
a crippled state that unless some other country <lb/>
comes, and in mercy picks us up, we are gone for <lb/>
we canuot exist by ourselves. But that arga<lb break="no"/>ment upsets the other argament, for it goes to <lb/>
show that the great good of Confederation will <lb/>
be to save us from ourselves. It if ever appears to <lb/>
occur to hon. gentlemen that any other mode of <lb/>
governing the country could be devised, but that <lb/>
which they themselves adopted, and have pursued <lb/>
for the past four years, which was to make a <lb/>
great many offices, and fill them with a great <lb/>
many people, and make large salaries for them, <lb/>
and then, in order to get these salaries, put on <lb/>
heavy taxes on bread, flour, pork, &amp;c., and then, <lb/>
because tust does not succeed, we must Confederate, <lb/>
as the country cannot ue ruled by its own people. <lb/>
But these hon. gentlemen go on the wings of imagi<lb break="no"/>nation and flash and thunder through the realms <lb/>
above. They can't walk upon terra firuma like com<lb break="no"/>mon people. If we ourselves by a local system of <lb/>
Government cannot make the people comfortable, <lb/>
surely no Government on this side the Atlantic can <lb/>
do it. When the Imperial Government managed the <lb/>
affairs of the colony we well remember how they <lb/>
used to blunder. The general cry was they don't <lb/>
understand us. With self Government we thought <lb/>
we possessed everything necessary to make us pros<lb break="no"/>perous. There are now some gentlemen who think <lb/>
we ought to have another kick up and place our<lb break="no"/>selves under some other Empire. What was the <lb/>
history of this Confederation! The two Canadas <lb/>
were fighting and squabbling among themselves, and <lb/>
in order to keep then quiet they were united. This <lb/>
then was the first of Confederation. There was a <lb/>
considerable Annexation party and they got up a big <lb/>
shindy, not to say a rebellion, which, however, was <lb/>
quickly quelled. In the United Parliament parties <lb/>
were equally divided and innumerable deadlocks oc<lb break="no"/>curred. That Confederation failed and four or five <lb/>
years ago the leading men of both parties hit upon <lb/>
the happy thought that if they could get the other <lb/>
Provinces to join them that they might tax them and <lb/>
make laws for them, they themselves would get on <lb/>
very well. But all this time they never dreamt that <lb/>
Newfoundland could be benefitted by the scheme. <lb/>
At last they united at Quebec, and the then Attorney <lb/>
General, the present Sir Hugh W. Hoyles, happened <lb/>
to be travelling in Canada at the time, and he said <lb/>
perhaps we would send up a couple of men to see <lb/>
what they were doing there. The Canadian gentle<lb break="no"/>men said they never thought of Newfoundland at all, <lb/>
but they would be very happy to meet our men. <lb/>
And so, without the appointment of this Assembly, <lb/>
the hon. Attorney General and the hon. A. Shea were <lb/>
sent up merely to watch the proceedings of the Con<lb break="no"/>vention. He (Mr. T.) would not go into the pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings of that Convention, he would not count the <lb/>
champaign bottles, and the various fetes to which <lb/>
they were invited, but the conclusion of the matter <lb/>
was that his two hon, friends were so bamboozled <lb/>
by these clever Canadians and others that they signed <lb/>
the document which was the basis of Confederation. <lb/>
Well, these hon. gentlemen came back, conscious <lb/>
that they had done something of which they had no <lb/>
reason to be proud. There was no flourish of trum<lb break="no"/>pets on their return, no guns fired, no triumphal car <lb/>
awaiting them to exhibit these two worthies to the <lb/>
admiring gaze of their countrymen. Well, they <lb/>
came to this house and they eadeavoured to bring <lb/>
over to their views every man of influence in the <lb/>
country! They represented the thing in glowing <lb/>
colours, they declined that it was the grandest <lb/>
thing for the country which could be accomplished,

<cb/>

they felt the breath of fame already on their cheeks, <lb/>
saw in vision the statues to be erected to their <lb/>
memory 50 years hence, But alas! alas! for the <lb/>
bright visions of their world! No sooner did this <lb/>
    House entered into the consideration of the scheme <lb/>
and condemned it, than these two hon. gentlemen <lb/>
said it would never do and they would never assent <lb/>
to it. They declared they would never accept Con<lb break="no"/>federation on the terms which they had solemnly <lb/>
signed in conclave. They turned their backs upon <lb/>
their signatures and accounted for them by some <lb/>
obfuscation of the brain from which at the time they <lb/>
suffered. They want to persuade us now that they <lb/>
have in hand some other scheme, and if that were <lb/>
condemned by the country these hon. gentlemen <lb/>
would be ready to condemn it themselves. Will <lb/>
they never cease to bamboozle us with the concoc<lb break="no"/>tion of new schemes? He (Mr. T.) supposed that <lb/>
they fancied that some of their many schemes must <lb/>
take, and, then the country might sink or swim. <lb/>
They would proceed to Canada, enthrone themselves <lb/>
in high places, and look down from their lofty emi<lb break="no"/>mences and say, "We are sorry for you but we <lb/>
couldn't do more for you." And doubtless the peo<lb break="no"/>ple would say so too. Confederation would not <lb/>
lighten the burdens of our people nor relieve their <lb/>
wants. Assist the people while they are in their <lb/>
    transition state—while they are on the isthmus pass<lb break="no"/>ing from the ocean of adversity to the ocean of pros<lb break="no"/>perity—and then you will have done your duty to <lb/>
them, but till you shall have done that all the con<lb break="no"/>federations you can go into will be unavailing. It <lb/>
had been circulated in the nowspapers that Nova <lb/>
Scotia had accepted the situation. She had found <lb/>
that she could not extricate herself from it except at <lb/>
the cannon's mouth and so she had determined to <lb/>
make the best of a bad bargain. And so because <lb/>
she can't get rid of it it has been concluded that she <lb/>
is well pleased with it. One might as well say that a <lb/>
man with an incurable sore who had given up all <lb/>
hope of its eradication, was well pleased with his <lb/>
malady. The Nova Scotian and Irish unions were <lb/>
both accomplished by the corruption of the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of the people who in common parlance <lb/>
sold their country. But in Ireland and in Nova <lb/>
Scotia too the peoples' hands were clean. The peo<lb break="no"/>ple never sanctioned the sales of their countries, our <lb/>
hon. members, however, if they can carry our their <lb/>
plans, will coerce the people themselves into selling <lb/>
their country. But the people see the plan and will <lb/>
not be tricked. Surely then hon. members should <lb/>
pause in their headlong career. Let them strike <lb/>
down the enormous expenditure and lighten the <lb/>
burdens of the people. Let them not follow that <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">ignis futuus</hi> of Confederation—that fluttering thing <lb/>
which must prove illusive to them. He (Mr. T.) <lb/>
would ask them to lay aside their ambition and allow <lb/>
their bosoms to swell with fuelings of humanity, <lb/>
turning their attention to such legislation as would <lb/>
conduce to the benefit of the people of the country. <lb/>
If you do less or more, it you attempt to carry Con<lb break="no"/>federation you will get yourselves into a turmoil from <lb/>
which you will find it difficult to escape. Beware of <lb/>
the damage of striking down the liberties of a people. <lb/>
You may trifle with the liberties and freedom of the <lb/>
people, but depend upon it they will not suffer such <lb/>
to be done. The people value liberty, and do not <lb/>
then sell it for a mess of potage. He feared that the <lb/>
already trespassed too long upon the House. His <lb/>
desire was to show that we should not adopt this <lb/>
section as it stood. Its language was too vague. <lb/>
If we adopt i,. we adopt the principle of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. This the Government could not do without <lb/>
belieing their former pledges to the country; with this <lb/>
view, then he would put forward the following <lb/>
amendment: <lb/></p>
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>
" That the only terms upon which we have been <lb/>
asked to go into Confederation are those of the <lb/>
Quebec resolutions, which have been rejected by the <lb/>
House and the country. We therefore submit that <lb/>
in accordance with the pledge given by the <lb/>
Premier, no further action be taken until the <lb/>
principle of Confederation be submitted to the <lb/>
people." <lb/></p>
    </quote>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:CART5">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>—The gentlemen on <lb/>
the other side of the House, known as Her Majesty's <lb/>
Opposition, had just put their best leg foremost, and <lb/>
had selected their man to nake a speech upon this <lb/>
occasion. That hon gentleman was certainly not a <lb/>
bad actor. He was able to take his part in a play <lb/>
        with most men. He had a good deal of the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
element in his nature. He (hon. A G) was led to <lb/>
believe that the speech which had just been delivered <lb/>
had been recently recited before the whole party, <lb/>
and unanimously approved of by them. That special <lb/>
notice had been given that he was selected to play <lb/>
this part; there had been a full attendance, and the <lb/>
recitation had been deemed excellent. It was re<lb break="no"/>ceived with wonder and admiration, that any man <lb/>
could express all these pretty things which the hon. <lb/>
member undertook to do. Their advice to him had <lb/>
been, whatever you do, don't indulge in argument, <lb/>
because you know we hon metmbers of the West end <lb/>
have already committed ourselves to an opinion upon <lb/>
the matter. Draw off their attention from that. <lb/>
Be as illogical as you can, and if you only succeed in <lb/>
drawing off the attention of the Government from <lb/>
that, we may be able yet to outwit them and <lb/>
possibly leap into their seats. But he (A G) would <lb/>
inform them that they would find their mistake. <lb/>
The Government thoroughly understood and was <lb/>
prepared for them, but hardly appreciated soundly <lb/>
of their tactics. His observations were too trans<lb break="no"/>parent to succeed in influencing the mind of any <lb/>
man, or to carry any weight with them. He (hon <lb/>
A G) found a difficuly in meeting the observations of <lb/>
the hon member, because he felt that in doing so he <lb/>
was only buffetting with the wind. If the hon <lb/>
member had put forth any facts or given us any <lb/>
data, he (hon A G) could easily meet him. The hon <lb/>
member however, had failed to do that, and had <lb/>
merely indulged in a lot of clap-trap and in some <lb/>
old Irish songs, and thinks that such a serious and <lb/>
important matter of this kind should be turned off by <lb/>
a proceeding ouly worthy of men sitting down over a <lb/>
glass of grog. He (hon A G) had been a little sur<lb break="no"/>prised because he had not before been aware of the <lb/>
versatility of the hon member. If the object of the <lb/>
hom member was merely to excite mirth, his success <lb/>
had been very indifferent. But more that one old <lb/>
song was required in the discussion of so important a <lb/>
subject as the present. One could imagine that the <lb/>
hon member had entertained a hatred tor Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion during his whole life, that he had never ex<lb break="no"/>pressed an opinion favorable to it, and that what he <lb/>
now says must carry conviction to every unwilling <lb/>
mind. He was playing his part so that be might it <lb/>
possible get into power and enjoy some of the sweets <lb/>
and emoluments of other. He was trying a popu<lb break="no"/>larity dodge. He says "will you give up your <lb/>
liberty, your lives, and property to Canada?" <lb/>
Why one would fancy from such expressions that <lb/>
Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, and Canada, had no <lb/>
liberty, no property, and no lives? The hon member <lb/>
must recollect that long before we had Responsible <lb/>
Government, that boom had been conferred upon <lb/>
Canada, that Nova Scotia and New Brunswick had <lb/>
also received it before us, and yet one would fancy <lb/>
from the argument of the hon member that they had <lb/>
given up everything that Britons valued, and when <lb/>
these Colonies had Confederated and were impressed <lb/>
    that it was for their interest and good, could we have <lb/>

<cb/>

any doubt upon our minds that we would enjoy with <lb/>
them the same benefits and advantages which they <lb/>
of present possess? Why, what was the object of <lb/>
Confederation? Was it not the consolidation and <lb/>
strengthening of British interests? Was it not the <lb/>
consolidation of liberty itself? Here when disunited, <lb/>
each separate Parliament was making laws adverse <lb/>
to the interests of each other. We had different <lb/>
tariffs, a different currency, different laws, yet all <lb/>
expressing to be governed by the constitution of <lb/>
Great Britain. This then was seen and with one <lb/>
desire we met together in full liberty and freedom to <lb/>
prepare a measure which had been commended by <lb/>
British statesmen on all sides and as having emanated <lb/>
from enlightened men and statesmen. When that <lb/>
measure went before the British Parliament, was it <lb/>
advocated only by one side? All–whatever you <lb/>
might call them, Radicals, Conservatives, or Whigs, <lb/>
praised and sustained it as a measure which they believ<lb break="no"/>ed was calculated to alvance the prosperity of all the <lb/>
colonies together. Newfoundland has hitherto been <lb/>
isolated from the outer world, and according to the <lb/>
hon member, it was to remain so. Were we to be cut <lb/>
off from all civilized countries? Were we to stand <lb/>
still or retrograde that we should, never enjoy the <lb/>
advantages and progress of civilization? But the <lb/>
hon member would find that the people would be no <lb/>
longer cajoled by his absurdities uttered here merely <lb/>
for the purpose of being tuned to political purposes <lb/>
on the hustings. Would they prevent the people <lb/>
from having more extended employment, from <lb/>
earning a fair days wages and keep then within the <lb/>
present narrow, area of employment? That may <lb/>
please hon members opposite, who might chuckle to <lb/>
see the people in the streets unemployed, wretched and <lb/>
starving. Oh! says the hon member, will the Canadians <lb/>
        erect manufactories for us,—who were erecting <lb/>
manufactories now? Who was giving remunerative <lb/>
labor to the people? Was the hon member doing <lb/>
it? Would talk do it? Did he believe that we <lb/>
possessed any means to alleviate their distresse, or <lb/>
to remove burdensome taxation? Relieve it? No? <lb/>
and be never did believe it, and there were no man <lb/>
now in this House more in favour of Confederation, <lb/>
than the hon. member Mr. Talbot and his colleague, <lb/>
Mr. Renouf, and they had recorded their opinions <lb/>
upon the question. These two gifted minds is they <lb/>
styled theirs to be, were four years ago in favour of <lb/>
Confederation, and in a celebrated address which <lb/>
they published, they had stated their opinions upon <lb/>
the subject. Had they changed since then? Have <lb/>
they had to recant? Have they been converted by <lb/>
the hon. member Mr. Glen? Have they by the <lb/>
hon. member Mr. Hogsett, who all along was in favor <lb/>
of Confederation, and who now says we shall know <lb/>
his opinion at the proner time? What however, <lb/>
did these two gifted minds say? Here was their <lb/>
celebrated letter addressed to the electors of St. <lb/>
John's on the 6th of November 1865, in which they <lb/>
state. "It is true that the principle of Amalgamation <lb/>
like that of Confederation, cannot be a subject of con<lb break="no"/>troversy. The highest, the most gifted minds ac<lb break="no"/>knowledge it." It is in the details, that is to say in <lb/>
the application of the principle all the danger lies." <lb/>
These highest and most gifted minds ackknowledge <lb/>
then that there can be no controversy upon the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of Confederation. But now we find the hon. <lb/>
member Mr. Talbot getting up and moving a resolu<lb break="no"/>tion repudiating the doctrine which he paraded in <lb/>
1865 as the emanation of one of the most enlightened <lb/>
minds, either aluong us, or any where else. Now <lb/>
what is the question before the chair. That this <lb/>
House will at a proper time take into consideration <lb/>
the details—thus perfectly coinciding with the views <lb/>
of the hon member. Here in their address they <lb/>
insisted on what should be done, and what we are <lb/>
about to do, and yet now they repudiate their own <lb/>
words. They say "you rejected the question of <lb/>
Confederation." He (A. G.) would ask, when? He <lb/>
denied that such had over been done by this House, <lb/>
and when the amendinent of the Solicitor General <lb/>
had been put forward, the hon member himself con<lb break="no"/>ceived it to be in favour of Confederation, and said <lb/>
that it could be viewed in no other light than as an <lb/>
admission of the principe, if so, the question was <lb/>
not rejected, but confirined, and this the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber admitted at the time. Agin he says, we, the <lb/>
delegates, were not authorised to go to Canada to <lb/>
take any part, but merely to speak. The delegates <lb/>
had been fully authorised to enter into the discussion <lb/> 
of the question, but not to bind this colony, and that <lb/>
they never, had professed to do. We had resereved <lb/>
to the local legislature the final determination of the <lb/>
matter, and on their arrival had declared what he <lb/>
(A. G) had always declared and now repeated, that <lb/>
nothing could or would be definitely settled until the <lb/>
question went before the various constituencies at a <lb/>
general election, for them to pronounce upon it. But <lb/>
he had never said that he would not take any action <lb/>
upon it. Hon. gentlemen would have been called <lb/>
upon to discuss this question long ago before this <lb/>
House, but for the position which one of the other <lb/>
colonies had assumed. Nova Scotia was turbulent. <lb/>
The great anti-confederate leader Howe, had stirred <lb/>
up the country, in one of the phrases peculiar to this <lb/>
House, from its centre to its circumference. He had <lb/>
told the people that Confederation had been carried <lb/>
unconstitutionally, because it had not been submitted <lb/>
to them—and he opposed then what he had been <lb/>
supporting his, whole life. Since then he had gone <lb/>
to Canada, and was now a Cabinet Minister of the <lb/>
New Dominion. Now what did this prove, not merely <lb/>
that he was in favour of Confederation as a principle, <lb/>
but that he believed it would be of immense advan<lb break="no"/>tage to his native country. Now, however, it might <lb/>
be alleged against Dr. Tupper, that he acted impru<lb break="no"/>dently in not submitting the question to the constitu<lb break="no"/>encies, yet no one can doubt that he was actuated <lb/>
by the purest patriotism, and that justice will yet <lb/>
be done him and his memory by his fellow citizens. <lb/>
whose material interests he had so admirably pro<lb break="no"/>moted. Mr. Howe was now reaping the faits of <lb/>
Dr. Tupper's planting and nursing. But oh! says <lb/>
the hon. member Mr. Talbot, the people are being <lb/>
bribed from Canada, as they were bribed in Ireland. <lb/>
Where was the evidence of bribery here? If the <lb/>
hon member has made use of the expression as a hint <lb/>
or suggestion, he (hon. A G) would say that they <lb/>
had no money to give him or any body else. But <lb/>
after all, on whose side was secret service money <lb/>
used? Did not Nova Scotia in its Anti-Parliament <lb/>
votes $50,000 secret service money for the purpose <lb/>
of repealing the Union if possible. And woould any <lb/>
man doubt that the opposition <choice><sic>wonld</sic><corr>would</corr></choice> follow the ex<lb break="no"/>ample of Mr. Howe at any moment that they <lb/>
thought it was their advantage to do so. <lb/>
And if, when we go to the people at the next election <lb/>
would the opposition not be the first to carry the <lb/>
question of Confederation it they got the majority? <lb/>
Then it is again atteged that we are to be taxed. <lb/>
Unfortunately we were able to tax ourselves. He <lb/>
did not think that the people of Canada were more <lb/>
in love with taxation than we were and whatever <lb/>
attempt would be made to tax them heavily they <lb/>
would no doubt raise their voice against it. Look <lb/>
at their tariff and compare it with our own and see <lb/>
how much more favourable it was than our present <lb/>
one is or likely to be. Under the Canadian tariff <lb/>
there was scarcely an article used in the prosecuting <lb/>
of the fisher as that was not excepted from taxation, <lb/>
besides food of all kinds. Then with regard to internal <lb/>
    
    <cb/>
    
taxation the hon. member had evidently not read <lb/>
the Union Act or he woull not hare exhibited the <lb/>
ignorance he did. Internal-taxation he would find <lb/>
could only be imposed by the local legislatures of <lb/>
each colony. The only power the Dominion had <lb/>
was over the import tax and this brought him to the <lb/>
question of taxing our exports. This was hardly <lb/>
possible; they could not impose an export tax on one <lb/>
particular colony—they would make it general if they <lb/>
did so, and in that view we would be no worse off <lb/>
than our neighbours; but apart from this, an export <lb/>
tax was a doctrine that had long singe bean exploded <lb/>
and was opposed by every sound political economist, <lb/>
and was not likely to occur under British rule. This <lb/>
question of Confederation then had never bean sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to this House and was never rejected by it. <lb/>
The question would be snbmitted to the people at <lb/>
the polls, but in the mean time we have a perfect <lb/>
right to express our opinion upon it. Surely when <lb/>
we went before the people with certain terms, that <lb/>
was the time for them to examine them. Without <lb/>
terms being agreed to, in order to submit them to <lb/>
the people, we could do nothing, Why the hon. <lb/>
member Mr. Glen, the leader of the opposition has <lb/>
truly declared that the question was one purely of <lb/>
terms. Then what is it we now propose? Why <lb/>
the very course which the hon. members Messrs Talbot <lb/>
and Renouf advocated and which is also approved of <lb/>
by their venerable leader Mr. Glen. But there was <lb/>
        one remedy besides Confederation,—Put us, say Her <lb/>
Majesty's opposition, into power, let us get into the <lb/>
saddle and ride the house and all will then be right <lb/>
and fair, there will then be no pauperism, no more <lb/>
depression, all will go on straight, prosperous, and <lb/> 
smoothed. We however think that we are just as well <lb/>
able to manage the affairs of this country as the <lb/>
gentlemen composing Her Majesty's opposition. <lb/>
We say that in all humility. We have heard no <lb/>
grand scheme from them for the benefit of the country <lb/>
altho' they had been talking here for the past three <lb/>
or four years to the extent of their long powers. <lb/>
But he (A G) understood now there was something <lb/>
hatching, an egg was being laid that would contain <lb/>
everything that was necessary tor the happiness and <lb/>
prosperity of the people. What was this great secret <lb/>
that they would not unbosom? Who had concocted <lb/>
it? Who had the credit of its paternity? Why was <lb/>
he not pointed out? and why did he not stand up <lb/>
and declare I am the man. <lb/></p> 

    <p>MR. GLEN—Ecce homo. <lb/></p>
    
    <p rendition="simple:centre">[TO BE CONTINUED.]</p> 
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2019-02-04, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>*=-g <lb/>
The Mail Steamer City of Hatifar arrived from <lb/>
Halifax yesterday afternoon. Her English papers <lb/>
are to the 30th ult, but local telegraphic advices <lb/>
give news later than present mail dates. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Address in reply to the Governor's opening <lb/>
speech passed through Committee in the Assembly <lb/>
last evening—third reading to–day. The discussions <lb/>
bf the last three or four days were exclusively <lb/>
upon that clause of the Address which affirm d <lb/>
the duty of immediate Legislative decision as <lb/>
to the terms on which the Colony ought to <lb/>
become a part of the Union. The Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion moved an amendment to the effect that the <lb/>
Quebec Convention had been already rejected, and <lb/>
that the question be postponed until after next <lb/>
general election. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>The amendment was scouted as so trans<lb break="no"/>parent a fraud deserved to be; and the <lb/>
Confederation clause was carried by a vote of <lb/>
eighteen against eight members: <lb/></p> 

<p>It is pleasing to be able to refer to another <lb/>
amongst the few instances of those who having been <lb/>
connected with this country occasionally remember <lb/>
its poor. The Rev. W. J. Newman, of Dartmouth, <lb/>
has through Mr. Pinsent, Q. C., contributed twelve <lb/>
pounds towards the relief of the destitute—seven of <lb/>
which have been given to the St. John's Association, <lb/>
and the remainder to similar s elsewl <lb/></p> 

<p>Maits per City of Halifaz will be closed on <lb/>
Friday, 19th inst., at 9 A.M.; late letters received <lb/>
until half past 9. <lb/></p> 

<p>- . PASSENGER84 <lb/>
Per City of Halifaz from Halifax.-Mrs. º: <lb/>
George #. Greer, John Crane, and 1 Corporal B. Å. <lb/></p> 

<p>BY TELEGRAPH. <lb/>
TO THE COMMERCIAL Rooyt. <lb/>
• -º-º: <lb/>
flönbos, Feb. 10. <lb/>
The Conservatives afe filaking preparations for 4 <lb/>
vigorous opposition, in Parliament. <lb/>
Taord Cairns will replace Lord Malmesbury as <lb/>
their leader in the House of Lords. <lb/>
Gladstone proposes to abolish University tests. <lb/>
Orrawa, Fab. 11. <lb/>
Whelan was thrged at eleven o'clock to-day. He <lb/>
was dressed in black; with a green necktie. He <lb/>
slept soundly last night, appeared perfectly calm, <lb/>
and prepared for death. The proceedings passed; <lb/>
quietly. His last words were "inay God sava Irelan <lb/>
and save my soul." <lb/>
New York, Feb. 1.-Gºld 1s5. <lb/>
Loxdox, Feb. 11. <lb/>
A banquet was given tº the Ministry this morning <lb/>
at Fishmonger's Hill, Mr. Gladstons made a speech <lb/>
in which he reviewed the progress alrea;ſy mide in <lb/>
carrying into effect the resolves for the dišestablish<lb break="no"/>ment of the Irish Church, and declared his intention <lb/>
of proceeding speedily, and prudently, encouraged <lb/>
by constitutional knowledge; by the Queen who as<lb break="no"/>sociates herself with the interestá and aiſections of the <lb/>
people; by the character and ability of biº colleagues, <lb/>
by the favorable judgment of the country, and by the <lb/>
justice of the cause: <lb/>
Mr. Bright also addreſsed the company, he cºn: <lb/>
de:uned the profuse expenditures of past years, an <lb/>
urged the necessity ºn the part of the House of being <lb/>
more positive and decided on the question of econoºty. <lb/>
The House of Lords met to-day, but without trans<lb break="no"/>acting any business of importance, and adjourned to <lb/>
the 16th<lb break="no"/>Loxpox, Feb. 12, <lb/>
A Paris despatch days 23 Carlists who were at<lb break="no"/>tempting to class the frontier yesterday wers arrest. <lb/>
ed by a body of the French Corps of OJserva.iom. <lb/>
and sent to Bayonne. <lb/>
Active nogotiations are now being carried on with: <lb/>
a view of obtaining permission that a Nuncio of tha <lb/>
Pope should be allowed to represent B2na at the <lb/>
Court of Qaeen Victoria. Mr. Gladstone is said to. <lb/>
to be entirely favourable to the preject. <lb/>
Moxºrreal, Fab, 12. <lb/>
Whelan's body was buried within the precinets of <lb/>
the jail this forenoon, <lb/></p> 

<p>-* <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_1.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">St. John's, Friday, February 19, 1869.</fw>
    
    <!-- IC, 2019-02-04, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>* * <lb/>
* * * *... s.ſ: it. <lb/>
**::: *, *:: tº <lb/></p> 

<p>ºwever inveterate. Few medicines <lb/></p> 

<p>grand remºdy ºut oily eurºs in such <lb/></p> 

<p>is, as a proof it needs but a trial. <lb/>
: <lb/></p> 

<p>teving and curing old wounds, sores, | <lb/></p> 

<p>OTTC HETI." IS. <lb/>
coughs, and colds, may be infallibly <lb/>
Łbrig this remedy twice a day upon <lb/>
atcs, and a cure quickly follows, <lb/>
E.A.ST.G, ETC. <lb/>
emedy is now in general use Ia <lb/>
Physicians regularly preseribe its <lb/>
the chests of sailors and emigrants. <lb/>
ºw ET, LIISTG-S. º: <lb/>
is Ointment will prove invaluable. <lb/>
n, and restores natural circulation. <lb/>
ETC., ETC. <lb/>
arts, of either sex, may be rendily <lb/>
this cooling and healing Qintment. <lb/>
F. YoUTEC. <lb/>
illy cured by the joint agency of <lb/>
the printed directions. <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>$ore IIcads. <lb/>
s Evil. Tic Doloureux. <lb/>
08, ". or Wheezing on the <lb/>
- Chest, with difficulty of Brenthug <lb/></p> 

<p>... -\- .-\-\-\-\- t <lb/>
in mºst of the following cases:<lb break="no"/>| <lb/>
| <lb/></p> 

<p>words "Holloway. London," are dis<lb break="no"/>the light, in every leaf of the book of <lb/>
retory of Professor Holloway, 244, <lb/>
Medicine, in pots at 18.1%d., 28.9d.,' <lb/>
e saving by taking the larger sizes, <lb/></p> 

<p>Mººrººzerº <lb/></p> 

<p>H, I F E <lb/>
£iatiºn ºf $69tland. <lb/></p> 

<p>NEW FOUNDſ..AND BRANCII. <lb/>
... pirºkºto RB: <lb/>
K. Dickinson, E q., Hoà J. Cormack, , <lb/>
R. Grieve. Esq. <lb/>
"dical Oſłicer, Docior W. C. Simms. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºº:: <lb/></p> 

<p>raual income of this Associaticn is now <lb/>
wards of ... " <lb/></p> 

<p>:6230,000 Sterling. <lb/>
"cumulated Fund in 1866, <lb/></p> 

<p>! stg" <lb/>
• A-ºrances in force in 1867, enjointed <lb/>
228 stg. - -<lb break="maybe"/>*iness, is coniucted under two separate <lb/>
n:-, ºr classes of Assurance. <lb/>
ho prefer Life Assurance, at the stnallett <lb/>
sistent with security,+should examino the <lb/></p> 

<p>her <lb/>
£LASS A. <lb/>
ho desire their share of Profi's applied in <lb/>
the sums' assured—eith the option of an <lb/>
provision for their old age- without affect <lb/>
ºn assured, are rejerred to the usual bene <lb/></p> 

<p>CLASS B, <lb/></p> 

<p>Class A one half or one fourth of the first <lb/>
prºminius may remain ungaid. Interest <lb/>
that at 5 per cent, being required to be <lb/></p> 

<p>amounted to <lb/></p> 

<p>ºises in this Class amºng the first series of <lb/>
ºrs, have rised to, 373 pe. cent, of hºir <lb/>
tºl are payab e in Čast, and not at death. <lb/>
!. 'hº profi - are all-il to the policy, and <lb/>
until inz at the te of 4 per cen; each <lb/>
* Anount insured. The resulta of this <lb/>
ite att-ntion of every, one seeking for <lb/></p> 

<p>it-ºrt. <lb break="no"/>proposals, and full information may be <lb/></p> 

<p>a, , lying to -_-_<lb break="no"/>E. m., JAltwis. <lb/>
Tºšº: <lb/></p> 

<p>**ś 5. #. <lb/>
- Mºs tº <lb/></p> 

<p>il that ſhe world has ºver known. <lb/>
in wastEven stars disease crists, <lb/>
tal to its subjection and cure." <lb/>
SICE. * "s <lb/>
o Household menfedy of all nations. <lb/>
tack the very loor of the complaint, <lb/>
store the drooping energies of the <lb/>
tionaky REFORMATios. <lb/>
sºciº-A-CIE * <lb/>
s the operation of the Pills? They <lb/>
irritated stom.ich into a natural and <lb/>
tho system from sickness to health. <lb/></p> 

<p>A TTIMIENTTS. <lb/>
indergoes the most important and <lb/>
u every disordor to which they are <lb/>
i against evil consequences. " <lb/></p> 

<p>civiliº'UºTTIES OF <lb/></p> 

<p>i is in an impure state, let such <lb/>
with confidencs to this powerful <lb/>
ith and strength will be the result. <lb/></p> 

<p>... as <lb/></p> 

<p>Nowy-N Foº, <lb break="no"/>Stone and Gravel. <lb/>
Secondary Symptons. <lb/>
Weakness, iron, sinatever <lb/></p> 

<p>-<lb break="maybe"/>- bause, &amp;c., a. <lb/>
| <lb/></p> 

<p>aints. <lb/>
Urine. <lb/>
is " Fºlloway, London," are dis<lb break="no"/>- - -\- *...* * * <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>réctions around, each box;, which <lb/>
Sold at ille, i.enufactory, ºf. Pro<lb break="no"/>octable Druggists, and Dealers, In, <lb/>
, and 33s.-\-Tucre is a considerablº º <lb/>
s for use are ºffixed to each Tºrº. <lb/></p> 

<p>§ <lb/></p> 

<p>** <lb/></p> 

<p># <lb/>
: <lb/></p> 

<p>as - *-**** A. <lb/>
(ſ <lb/>
t *: <lb/></p> 

<p>No. 6,571. <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, Friday, February 19, <lb/></p> 

<p>I869. <lb/></p> 

<p>- - - -\-\-\-\- - - <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Printed and Published ºvery Tuesday and Friday <lb/>
morning by Ely WARI) DALTON SHEA, at his <lb/>
2 office in Duckwoºd STREET. Terms–One <lb/>
g ºnea per annum, pngable in advance. . . . . <lb/>
Advertisements hot limited (Auction Sales and notices <lb/>
ºch determine themselves excepted) are repeated, <lb/>
until ordered in writing to be withdrawn. <lb/>
This paper tº filed, and may be seen free of charge <lb/>
... 'Hºlloway's Pill and Ointment Establishment, <lb/>
244. Sirand. London. <lb/>
This paper is notissued to any Subsertber for a shorter <lb/>
term than six months. <lb/></p> 

<p>== <lb/></p> -->
    
</div>
<div type="debate">

<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">Thursday, Feb. 11. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">[CONTINUED.] <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CART5">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>.–No new offices had <lb/>
been created by his Government, but many hundreds <lb/>
of pounds of the civil expenditure had been saved <lb/>
Compare the civil list now with what it had been at <lb/>
the commencement of Responsible government, and it <lb/>
would be found to be lower, in the number and <lb/>
amount of official incomes. Hon. members, say why <lb/>
don't the Government do this, though in all parts of <lb/>
the world employment was given to the people with<lb break="no"/>out any demand being made on the Government? <lb/>
In Spain, where a revolution had just taken place, <lb/>
the first act of the patriots who led it was to decree <lb/>
that the corrupt system pursued by former Spanish <lb/>
Governments, of giving employment to the people <lb/>
on public works, instead of inciting private enterprise, <lb/>
should cease. He (hon A G) said that when this <lb/>
country united with the Dominion, and had the <lb/>
benefit of free trade, and a uniform tariff and curren<lb break="no"/>cy, it must tend to increase that commercial prospers<lb break="no"/>ity on which so much of the future of this country <lb/>
depends. Was a small country like this, with such a <lb/>
restricted trade as it has, likely to create large com<lb break="no"/>mercial relations with any other country? Was it <lb/>
likely to have they advantages of reciprocity? Did <lb/>
hon. gentlemen suppose that Great Britain would <lb/>
enter into a treaty for Newfoundland alone, or that <lb/>
Canada would do it for her, when she did not form <lb/>
part of the Dominion? If then, Newfoundland stays <lb/>
out, and the Dominion enters into a new Reciprocity <lb/>
Treaty, will not Nova Scotia have all the advantages <lb/>
which will flow from the fish trade? If Canada <lb/>
should impose a duty on our articles of export, would <lb/>
it not place us in a worse position? And, if we do not <lb/>
join her she, must treat as she would any foreign <lb/>
power. With every possible encouragement given <lb/>
to the cultivation of the soil, it was found that the <lb/>
people were, but very little better off than before. <lb/>
Under the Act for the encouragement of Agriculture, <lb/>
some $2000 had been paid, aud within three or four <lb/>
years free grants for close on 9000 acres had been <lb/>
sued, and yet notwithstanding all this cultivation, <lb/>
the people did not appear any better off. There <lb/>
was a gentleman who took a great deal of interest in <lb/>
the affairs of the colony, who had lately written a <lb/>
great deal in the papers, and was well known as one <lb/>
of the strongest anti-confederate in the country.<lb/>
He (hon A G) had a high regard for that gentleman, <lb/>
and would be sorry to say anything disrespectful of <lb/>
him, when he asked that gentleman what it was that <lb/>
would be of benefit to the country, he replied <lb/>
that it lay with the Government, and on being asked <lb/>
in what respect, replied "to propose an arrangement <lb/>
or the prosecution of the fisheries, that there was no <lb/>
aw to regulate it, and that without such a law the <lb/>
country could not prosper. He was then asked "what <lb/>
regulation he would propose," and replied, that <lb/>
"codnets, codseines and bultows should be abolished <lb/>
and the people made to go on with the hook and line <lb/>
Now he (hon A G) would ask if it was at all likely <lb/>
the people would agree to such a proposal? Those <lb/>
who had seines and nets would be opposed by those <lb/>
who had not, and vice versa, in fact no unamnity <lb/>
would be found to exist. The journals of the House <lb/>
were loaded with evidences, taken upon that very <lb/>
subject, yet it would be found that scarcely two <lb/>
paties were agreed in their views on it. Under <lb/>
such circumstances, how was it possible for the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to propose any measure on the subject? <lb/>
One would imagine that the use of these articles, <lb/>
was confined to this country, but such was <lb/>
not the case, for they were also used in England, <lb/>
Norway and other countries; and further, it was <lb/>
found that where laws for the regulation of the <lb/>
fisheries had been framed, they were since repealed. <lb/>
He (hon A G) put that forward as the course of <lb/>
action suggested to the Government by that gentle<lb break="no"/>man, but it was evident to all that such a course <lb/>
could not be pursued, with any hope of success. If <lb/>
cheap Government be what is wished for, there was <lb/>
no more likely way of obtaining it than by joining <lb/>
the Confederacy. If we do, then instead of our <lb/>
Legislature costing as it does some $24,000 a year, <lb/>
it need not cost more than $6000, and then in that <lb/>
one item alone $18,000 a year might be saved. <lb/>
Further, instead of having our present expenses and <lb/>
diliculties in raising a revenue, we would have one <lb/>
more certain than tuat which was now raised, and <lb/>
our labors need not extend beyond its appropriation. <lb/>
This might be considered as going into the terms. <lb/>
but he merely mentioned it incideutally, so that hon <lb/>
members who spoke of reduction of expenditure <lb/>
mght see that all they could effect now would not <lb/>
equal what could easily be doue under the new <lb/>
system. He feared he was taking the matter up too <lb/>
seriously, and speaking on it in a way which hon <lb/>
gentlemen opposite did not expect. Their desire evi<lb break="no"/>dently was that it should be taken up in a serio-comic <lb/>
way, as had been done by the hon member, Mr. <lb/>
Talbot, who sung a good song and endeavoured to <lb/>
laugh it all out. The (hon A G) had not heard any; <lb/>
thing advanced by the other side which one could <lb/>
well lay hold of to answer. All that was said, was <lb/>
about as substantial as the wind that whistles by a <lb/>
man's ears. The hon member had played round and <lb/>
about the matter, but had carefully avoided touching <lb/>
it just, as if he desired to lead people off the tru: <lb/>
scent. He was uncommonly adroit, and had played <lb/>
his part well, and if he did make a hit now and then, <lb/>
did it in a most inoffensive way. The hon gentleman <lb/>
had however made some mistaken statements. For <lb/>
instance; he said the Quebec Resolutions had <lb/>
been rejected. Now such was not the case. <lb/>
For in 1865 the present Chief Justice, then the <lb/>
leader of the Government, carstully avoided in<lb break="no"/>troducing the Quebec Resulutions, and said that <lb/>
as they were not agreed among themselves in <lb/>
the other provinces, and moreover, us the gen<lb break="no"/>eral elections were near at hand, it would be <lb/>
recipitate to submit the matter to the House <lb/>
    
    <cb/>
    
then, and that it ought to be left to the people. <lb/>
That was what was now proposed to be done. <lb/>
They had the advantage of the Quebec Reso<lb break="no"/>lutions, and from the changes which had since <lb/>
then taken place, and from lapse of time and <lb/>
more mature consideration, their minds were <lb/>
now more prepared for a review of their posi<lb break="no"/>tion respecting this matter. He (hon. A.G.) <lb/>
knew that when the hon. member, Mr. Talbot, <lb/>
was returned to the House, he was about as fa<lb break="no"/>vourable to union as any other man. The hon. <lb/>
gentleman might have changed his mind since <lb/>
then, but he could not change the expressions <lb/>
used in his celebrated letter. He (hon. A. G.) <lb/>
would (and he considered he was quite in order <lb/>
in so doing) refer to a letter lately published in <lb/>
one of the local papers by the hon. member <lb/>
for Ferryland, Mr. Glen, the leader of the op<lb break="no"/>position. There is what he says, "It is for<lb break="no"/>tunate for the country that there are men in the <lb/>
Legislature of some practical sense—men who <lb/>
have fought the battle of confederation faith<lb break="no"/>fully for the past four years, and who will con<lb break="no"/>tinue to fight it faithfully as they heretofore have <lb/>
done, having the true interests of their country <lb/>
solely in view." "Fought the battle of Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation," not its opponents, and that from the lead<lb break="no"/>er of the opposition. The same practical <lb/>
men are still fighting the battle of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. Surely no man would deuy that so clear-<lb break="yes"/>headed a man as the hon. member for Ferryland <lb/>
could not be so obfuscated as to suppose people <lb/>
would believe he meant the anti-confederates <lb/>
by these words. He did not. He was a Con<lb break="no"/>federate on the 11th of January last. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName>.—No, Never was. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>.—And four days <lb/>
after, being brought to task by an authority to <lb/>
which he was willing to submit, he recanted <lb/>
and ate his own words. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName>.—It was those blackguard printers <lb/>
left out the anti. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>.—To show that <lb/>
such was not the case, that there could be no <lb/>
doubt but he intended to give all the praise to the <lb/>
Confederates, he says "the fact is, and there can <lb/>
be no doubt about the matter, that Mr. Bennett is <lb/>
afraid it we join the Union that the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment will make him 'disgorge' the ten hun<lb break="no"/>dred thousand acres of land so shamefully given <lb/>
him by an Irresponsible Government, to the injury <lb/>
of the people of Newfoundland. That is the sole <lb/>
reason of Mr. Bennett's opposition to Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion—nothing more or less." That was the only <lb/>
reason why the hon. member was, so opposed to <lb/>
Mr Bennett. If he agreed with him, why should <lb/>
he condemn Mr. Bennett in the way be did. He <lb/>
(hon. A. G.) had road enough to show what the <lb/>
hon. member's views on the subject then were, and <lb/>
of course, unless he had changed his mind, like <lb/>
as others did, be must be a Confederate still. He <lb/>
(hon. A. G.) had been accused of signing he <lb/>
Quebec Resolutions. He did sign them, and both <lb/>
he and his hon. friend, Mr. Shea felt that they had <lb/>
doue that which would greatly tend to the advance<lb break="no"/>ment of the material interests of the country. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName>.—When the seventh clause of <lb/>
this reply was moved, it was only natural to <lb/>
expect that the mover of is would, on so im<lb break="no"/>portant a question as that of Confederation, have <lb/>
explained his views and told the House what <lb/>
his constituents thought of it. The more so as <lb/>
the election whcih placed that hon. gentleman in <lb/>
the House was pointed to by the Government <lb/>
as a triumph of the principles of Confederation. <lb/>
But no, the hon. member had not the pluck to <lb/>
say what the opinions of Harbor Grace were; <lb/>
it was left for the opposition to combat this <lb/>
paragraph as they pleased without one, word <lb/>
of explanation from the other side, until the <lb/>
hon and learned Attorney General spoke. Wny <lb/>
was it that the supporters of the Government, <lb/>
that even the great Confederate gun to which <lb/>
the hon. member? Mr. Shea, so triumphantly <lb/>
pointed, did not come forward and support, those <lb/>
principies which the opposition and the country <lb/>
were asked to adopt. Did the hon. and learned <lb/>
Attorney General canvas the <choice><sic>princaple</sic><corr>principle</corr></choice> while <lb/>
the House is asked to adopt? Did he bring <lb/>
forward any argument in support of it? Not <lb/>
one. He invites them to meet the mater on <lb/>
fair, equitable, and logical grounds, and yet he <lb/>
styles the speech of the hon. member, Mr. <lb/>
Talbot, an old song, and instead of bottling for <lb/>
the principle, seeks to throw ridicule on the man <lb/>
who fights against it and endeavours to show <lb/>
that it is inapplicable to Newioundland. Such <lb/>
is the course of conduct pursued by one of the <lb/>
Ministry towards one of the most important <lb/>
questious that ever came before the country, a <lb/>
question, which involved the destinies of the <lb/>
country for centuries to come. Was that the <lb/>
way in which such an all absorbing question <lb/>
should be treated? His Excellency says that <lb/>
the time has arrived when we should take the <lb/>
matter into our serious consideration. We are <lb/>
not here to consider that question, because the <lb/>
public never delegated us to do so. He could <lb/>
appeal to the records, and to the speech ot the <lb/>
hon. member, Mr. Shea, who took a leading <lb/>
part on this question. In 1865, when the late <lb/>
Premier brought the matter before the House <lb/>
of that day, that hon. members found fault with <lb/>
the way in which it was put, because it was not <lb/>
made a question to come fairly and broadly be<lb break="no"/>fore the people. (Here the hon. and learned <lb/>
gentlemen read extracts from the speech of hon. <lb/>
Mr. Shea, delivered in 1865, when the Resolu<lb break="no"/>tion of the hon. and learned leader of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment was before the House.) It had <lb/>
been said just now that the Quebec resolu<lb break="no"/>tions were never rejected, if they were not so <lb/>
in terms, they were at all events impliedly <lb/>
rejected by the course which the hon. gentleman <lb/>
then took. In 1865 they were a raid to adopt <lb/>
    
    <cb/>
    
the principle and the hon. member, Mr. Shea, <lb/>
charged them with being so. The Government <lb/>
did not adopt the principle and no hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber went to the country on it, by none was it <lb/>
made a falling point at the hustings. What is <lb/>
Confederation? It means the giving up of that <lb/>
control over our own affairs which we now <lb/>
enjoy. Can we say that the people of the <lb/>
country have come to the determination of <lb/>
doing that. Could he (Mr. H.) or any other <lb/>
hon. member say that their constituents had <lb/>
come to the conclusion that they were willing to <lb/>
give up the constitution which they now had <lb/>
and band their rights over to any other power? <lb/>
Can they possibly come to that conclusion <lb/>
before the matter is put fairly before them? Is <lb/>
it because the country was in a condition of <lb/>
temporary misery, and things were not as they <lb/>
used to be, that we should sell that for which we <lb/>
had so long fought? Was it because some <lb/>
difficulties were on us we should "fly from the <lb/>
ills we have to those we know not of." They <lb/>
had fought for responsible Government, which <lb/>
meant self-government, and is it because they <lb/>
found a little difficulty in working it out and <lb/>
looked more after their own interests than after <lb/>
those of the country? Hence that iustitution <lb/>
which was the boast of every British subject, <lb/>
and which made the British people what they <lb/>
are, was to be given up and handed over to the <lb/>
Cauadians. It may be that the country had <lb/>
not derived such great advantages from Responsi<lb break="no"/>ble Government as was expected, but would any <lb/>
intelligent man be coatent to give it up and go <lb/>
back to the days of that Government which was <lb/>
only responsible to the Imperial authorities. There <lb/>
was no nation nor no race of men without its dif<lb break="no"/>ficulties,but were they on that account to take <lb/>
their hats in their hands and go and beg of any <lb/>
other country to take theia under their protec<lb break="no"/>tion? If when the people of the country <lb/>
thoroughly understood the question, they would <lb/>
say they were content to yield up their <lb/>
rights, then he (Mr. H.) would deal with the <lb/>
terms. He was not afraid to say that his mind <lb/>
had undergone various changes on this subject. <lb/>
Every mind which viewed it calmly must have <lb/>
these changes, for it was a grave question, one <lb/>
which involved the rights and liberties of the <lb/>
country. He as well as others might <lb/>
have been caught with the glare and <lb/>
glitter of the statement that they were about to <lb/>
become part of a great nation. But were they <lb/>
to form part of a great nation. He (Mr. <lb/>
H.) was inclined to think so once, but when he <lb/>
found that the Imperial Government interfered <lb/>
with the action of the Parliament of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion, he concluded that the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had its paw on them as well as on the <lb/>
smallest of its colonies. Even with our own <lb/>
modicum of liberty, could we not if uncontrol<lb break="no"/>led raise a revenue which the people would not <lb/>
feel. There was money every day leaving our <lb/>
shores which was not taxed, and which was <lb/>
received by persons who did not contribute <lb/>
one cent towards the improvement of the town. <lb/>
No, all these taxes were left to fall on the un<lb break="no"/>fortunate tenant, who had to pay the taxes <lb/>
from the sweat of his labour. We tried to tax <lb/>
those absentees but were prevented and told we <lb/>
could not, because they paid taxes at the other <lb/>
side. We were told the Dominion Go<lb break="no"/>vernment would help us in this respect.— <lb/>
Don't they know that the important ques<lb break="no"/>tion of the French Shore was pending, and <lb/>
have they shown any desire to assist us? <lb/>
They are a mere Colony, subject to the veto of <lb/>
the Colonial office and to all that official blunder<lb break="no"/>ing which has done so much to retard Colonial <lb/>
progress, to the ignorance of men who apply <lb/>
audiquated principles to the circumstances of the <lb/>
present day. Though we were told thus, the <lb/>
Dominion would be ruled over by a Prince of the <lb/>
blood, and that it would have the coutrol of its <lb/>
own affairs, it is to-day as much in leading strings <lb/>
as it was twenty years ago. If Newfoundland <lb/>
then, were to become a part of the Dominion, it <lb/>
would be doubly subservient, not only to the <lb/>
Imperial interests, but also to the veto of the <lb/>
Dominion itself. Why should our poverty be <lb/>
assigued as a reason for driving us into Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation? Had the Canadians ever made us an offer? <lb/>
Was it in the power of Canada to relieve the Col<lb break="no"/>ony? Supposing the Dominion to be a success; <lb/>
would they undertake to feed our starving people? <lb/>
No, but they point us to the glories of the future, <lb/>
to that day when they will be a great nation, and <lb/>
able to meet the world in arms. Can our people <lb/>
afford to live on that glorious vista? Will not the <lb/>
hon. Attorney General admit that the nationality <lb/>
of Dominion is a purely speculative question? <lb/>
Why did the United States purchase Russian <lb/>
America? Simply because she is drawing her lines <lb/>
closely around British interests, on this side the <lb/>
Atlantic. What guarantee could be given that the <lb/>
Dominion would exist, with the power of the Ameri<lb break="no"/>can Republic on the other side? Great Britain <lb/>
is reducing her war estimates by a million pounds. <lb/>
She will constrain the Colonies to defend themselves <lb/>
What possible chance could these Colonies have of <lb/>
defending themselves against the formidable power <lb/>
of the United States? The hon. Attorney General <lb/>
had said that the tariff of the Dominion would be <lb/>
equalised. Surely the hon. gentleman was aware <lb/>
that Nova Scotia and New Brunswick are fully two <lb/>
centuries ahead of us, and a tariff which would be <lb/>
suitable for them would press very heavily on us <lb/>
Thus they might be able to contribute to the expense <lb/>
of an army and Navy, Newfoundland would be pow<lb break="no"/>erless to do so. It is true, that in relation to our <lb/>
means, we have contributed more wealth to Britain <lb/>
than any Colony ou this side the Atlautic; and <lb/>
        yet we cannot outain our <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> territorial right, <lb/>
        through the ignorant <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> of British officials. <lb/>
And could it be doubled that if we should join the <lb/>
Dominion they would be as powerless to secure us <lb/>
our rights as we oursleves are to-day? The hon. <lb/>
member, Mr.Shea, said, in a former speech of his, <lb/>
"but a pregnant question now presents itself" <lb/>
Have we the unqualified power to decide our own <lb/>

<cb/>

destinies? It would be idle to suppose that the <lb/>
meeting at Quebec was not inspired by the Impe<lb break="no"/>rial Government." He [Mr. H.) contended that <lb/>
the Imperial Government would never drive us into <lb/>
the Dominion. While Great Britain could keep her <lb/>
power on these seas, Newfoundland would be pro<lb break="no"/>tected, and we should not be constrained to submit <lb/>
to an oppressive tariff, imposed, not for local but for <lb/>
national purposes. What possible effect could the <lb/>
representation of eight men have in a Parliament of <lb/>
194? Dr. Tupper, in Halifax, had expressed in con<lb break="no"/>versation with him, (Mr. H.) the very same ideas <lb/>
as hon. gentlemen opposite seem to have, that the <lb/>
people of Nova Scotia were too ignorant to be con<lb break="no"/>sulted on this question. Let the hon. member Mr. <lb/>
Shea, or any other hon. gentleman go before his <lb/>
constituents and explain to them that by their assent <lb/>
to Confederation they are giving up their control <lb/>
over their Revenues, and there was not a constituen<lb break="no"/>cy in the Island which would return them. Often <lb/>
questions of vital importance must necessarily arise, <lb/>
as to the manner of local Goverminent, and the dis<lb break="no"/>tribution of districts. Like harlequins in a panto<lb break="no"/>mime, are we going to jump through a hoop before <lb/>
we know where we are? This house was never <lb/>
assembled to decide upon this question. The late <lb/>
Attorney General knew the responsibility, and he <lb/>
shirked it. By the Resolutions brought in by him, <lb/>
it was solemnly declared that it is desirable, before <lb/>
a vote be taken upon this question that it should be <lb/>
submitted to the people. The question, then, had <lb/>
never been submitted to the people, and he (Mr. H.) <lb/>
contended that that submission must be a condition <lb/>
precedent to any action upon the matter. We don't <lb/>
know what effect our affirmation of the principle <lb/>
might have upon the Imperial Government. Where <lb/>
you undertake to settle the destinies of a people <lb/>
without submitting the question to them, it will be <lb/>
found that they have sufficient resistance to expel <lb/>
the men who commit so unconstitutional an act. <lb/>
He (Mr. H.) heartily supported the Resolution <lb/>
before the chair. He would never assent to a radi<lb break="no"/>cal change of our Constitution until the whole ques<lb break="no"/>tion were fairly and honestly put before the people, <lb/>
to be received or rejected by them. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:PINS2">Mr. PINSENT</persName> could not conceive anything clearer <lb/>
or more explicit than the language of the address. <lb/>
Here it was unmistakeably declared that whatever <lb/>
action might be taken by hon. members would not <lb/>
necessarily bind their constituencies. Hon. members <lb/>
appeared as representatives, to stand or fall by the <lb/>
views which they might now express. If rejected <lb/>
by their constituents, no harm can possibly be done <lb/>
to the people,for this action is altogether preliminary; <lb/>
and by no means binding upon the country. What <lb/>
then was the amendment which hon. members oppo<lb break="no"/>site opposed to this reply? [Here the hon. member <lb/>
read the amendment.] <lb/></p>
    
    <p>Why, on the very face of it, there appeared a fatal <lb/>
inconsistency. Hon. members assert that the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Resolutions have been rejected by the people, <lb/>
and in the next breath they tell us that the people <lb/>
have never had the matter submitted to them. Now <lb/>
either the question has been submitted to the people <lb/>
or it has not. If it have been submitted to then, <lb/>
the best proof of its acceptance is the overwhelming <lb/>
majority which here support it. If it had not been <lb/>
submitted to the people, then the statement that they <lb/>
have rejected the principle must necessarily be false. <lb/>
We had been told that the Quebec Resolutions have <lb/>
been condemned. As a matter of fact, exception <lb/>
has been taken to them, but there are many who <lb/>
would accept Confederation on these terms, rather <lb/>
than not have it at all. He (Mr. P.) did not, how<lb break="no"/>ever, go so far as that. He had frequently taken <lb/>
exception to some of the terms. The hon. member, <lb/>
Mr.Talbot, says "Let us ask, the people if under <lb/>
certain circumstances they will accept this change." <lb/>
That was the very course which by this address the <lb/>
House was asked to pursue. How can we other<lb break="no"/>wise arrive at the conditions of Confederation upon <lb/>
which we are to go to the people? No two mem<lb break="no"/>bers have precisely the same views upon the subject; <lb/>
and it is evident that we must have some broad and <lb/>
unmistakeable platform upou which to take our <lb/>
stand. We had been told that the Canadians would <lb/>
have complete control over our properties, our liber<lb break="no"/>ties and our lives. Now hon. members must recol<lb break="no"/>lect that Confederation once accomplished, we shall <lb/>
all become Canadians, and Canada cannot injure us, <lb/>
without an equal, nay a larger amount of injury to <lb/>
herself. What have we to dread with regard to <choice><sic>onr</sic><corr>our</corr></choice> <lb/>
property? A law to affect us must necessarily <lb/>
affect the other provinces, and was it to be supposed <lb/>
that they would enterprise any suicidal policy, that <lb/>
they would legislate to the injury of their property, <lb/>
which is so infinitely superior to ours? How were <lb/>
our liberties, then, to be affected? Let us see first <lb/>
what we understand by the expression. The culmi<lb break="no"/>nation of our liberties appeared to be the power of <lb/>
returning a certain number of representatives to this <lb/>
Assembly. This consummation of liberty was cer<lb break="no"/>tainly not a subject for any great congratulation; <lb/>
and when hon. gentlemen opposite considered that <lb/>
the people had returned to office men so unworthy <lb/>
as the present Ministry, they surely must consider <lb/>
the liberty as of very small account. How, then, <lb/>
were our liberties to be affected? We should still <lb/>
continue to return representatives and though they <lb/>
would be fewer in number, if they had within them <lb/>
any sentiments of pride, they would rejoice in having <lb/>
a voice in the large and extensive affairs of the <lb/>
Dominion. Our liberties would, in fact, be vastly <lb/>
extended, and wa should move in a grander, wider <lb/>
and nobler sphere. But how were our lives to be <lb/>
effected? Were hon. gentlemen going to resurrec<lb break="no"/>tionise the bugbear of the bleaching bones? We <lb/>
should live under equal laws, and no man would be <lb/>
decapitated in Newfoundland for a crime which <lb/>
was not so punishable in other parts of the Dominion. <lb/>
But we were threatened that if war with America <lb/>
should arise, our people would be carried away to <lb/>
fight. The prospect of such a war was very remote. <lb/>
He believed it would never be. But it is should <lb/>
take place, or any similar catastrophe, were we not <lb/>
in as much peril as if we were a part of the Dominion, <lb/>
while less capable of defence? And if the time of <lb/>
danger should come, was there any man to unpa<lb break="no"/>triotic as to say that he would leave to <lb/>
others the defence of his house, his family and <lb/>
his household gods? The day has gone by <lb/>
when the public placed faith in such spurious <lb/>
alarms, or were to be frightened by them, and when <lb/>
they hear this and such like arguments addressed to <lb/>
then, and when they bear questions of the highest <lb/>
gravity made the opportunity for attack and recri<lb break="no"/>mination, he believed they suspected the lot of them, <lb/>
and regarded the executive and the opposition as <lb/> 
engaged in nothing but a fight for office; but any <lb/>
intellident man who listened to then from the <lb/>


<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-19_Page_2.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>


    <!-- IC, 2019-02-04, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>- - º: ams-e<lb break="no"/>never intended that it should be regarded in th which was so perfeet <lb/>
light. We ..º. you and º: country .;: §. #. S.) *.*. <lb/></p> 

<p>section that we will enquire into the matter, and y" -\-\- <lb break="no"/>if terms avorable to the interests of thº' tº: part ºn the **. "º. <lb/>
ºnnot be agreed to. Why, the hon member ºf: have it to say that it fell to his <lb/>
Glen, sayif we get terms satisfactory, he was real, part, however humble, in so im; <lb/>
That plan had met with the a <lb/></p> 

<p>to go in for Confederation, and yet the hon membe: <lb/>
would debar us by his proceeding from *taining leading men of England of all po <lb/></p><p>
did not directly force it. He deprecated the <lb break="maybe"/># *. might be inuisposed to deliver inconsistency º hot members who, in the 'saine some hon member opposite to enlighten , the were acceptable or not. He could not, therefors, J.; sº a subject? A test like that, tile q <lb/>
himself of frequent speeches; but he was at a loes speech, spoke of Britain as a cruel stepmother, and House upon the question before ºne chair. agree to this paragraph being amended, and be 'i º well versed in the suience of <lb/>
to cºnceive hºw the charge of suppression of his then laided alliance with it as sº mugſ, preferable | He had expected to bar some vigºrºs ºuen could not agree to the amend mºnt, bºause it son- # whose integrity aud impartial <lb/>
opinions could be made against the hon member, to closer connection with the sister Colonies. He upon this all important, question of Confedera | tained a statement that was untrue. The question of: doubted, who look calmly on fr <lb/>
who had expressed himsel; so clearly and decisively argued that oar vºice in the Daminion Councils |tion. It wºuld appear that there was not much Contederation had never been rejected by this Legis. § and say that this system of Gov. <lb/></p> 
<p>tion means employment. While the abstruse argu<lb break="no"/>ment of hon. memners opposits might be thrown <lb/>
away, the peoplewould be able understand when they <lb/>
were spoken to in this manner. The only thing hop. <lb/>
members opposite had done was to endeavour tº <lb/>
mystify the people. If their real opinions were worth <lb/>
anything the people must go without them. On the <lb/>
question of terms he (Mt. O'R) should be prepared to <lb/></p> 

<p>with every man who had cºmmon sense to under- to go again before the country upou in efinite step should be taken by this House before an appeal could never arise in. this case. But assuming lot good would this collatry <lb/>
stand what they were talking about, that the very speculation, to be in a position to assail the govern- was made to the country at the next general election. argument sake that it did, he (hon Mr S) knew of: tue exponditure in Cauada o <lb/>
fact of our being an Island and renote from our ment as having offered nothing preferable to the Upon inotion the Committee then rose, reported | lºw countries that had been sold that had not been . ife (no 1. Mr. S ) replied ti <lb/>
neighbours, was the very reason for Quebec Conveu'ion, and then to be in a position to progress, and asked leave to sit again on Monday. the gainers. Look at Louisiana when she was pur-: advauc th - l - t b t <lb/>
desiring efficient and speedy means of deal with the matter themselves, without submitting The House then adjourned unil Monday at 3 chased by, the United States Iron France—that was u06 tº value of lab ºr i <lb/>
trade and intercourse, and by , such means their own future plans to the country. He concluded o'clock. a sale, and unoney paid to it, and see how prosperous . try, and, tuat would by must <lb/>
Louisiana had been since. Had she not been a; tue laboring classes; an i though <lb/></p> 

<p>il atºl religious liberty in its highest uevelop<lb break="no"/>meut. Would jute Iligent men be deluded by the <lb/>
prºposal to take...off all duties ou the staple <lb/>
accessaries of life this session, as a partial <lb/>
alleviatiosi of the burtheus of the people, when <lb/>
the finaucial eoudition of the gov and the <lb/>
state of the people were sush its they now ure, aul <lb/>
with a debt cousiderably exceeding half a million <lb/>
ºf dollars tº be redeemed in tour or five years? <lb/>
Iſºn: members whº suggested such neºs <lb/>
must be aware of their iupossibility, and the <lb/>
ºpiº, and rºiu which must bºonju. <lb/>
on their adoption as we now are, while by an alli<lb break="no"/>ance with the Dominion those objects they so <lb/></p> 

<p>press what he considered to be essential conditions, <lb/></p> 
--> 



gallery knew that it mattered very little to him and <lb/>
to the country whether the prosent five or six office-<lb break="yes"/>holders or the same number of gentlemen from the <lb/>
other side were in the enjoyment of place and eno<lb break="no"/>lument, but such a man was quite capable of under<lb break="no"/>standing, and hon members might depend upon it <lb/>
the public were intelligent enough to distinguish <lb/>
between what were earnest solid arguments and the <lb/>
tactics of politics. The hon. and learned member, <lb/>
Mr. Hogsett, supports this amendment of Mr. <lb/>
Talbot's and reproaches the hon, member for Harbor <lb/>
Grace with not speaking to the motion, and not <lb/>
giving expression to his views. He (Mr. P.) could <lb/>
quite understand that a young member but a few <lb/>
days in this House, and who had never entered the <lb/>
    Building before, might be indisposed to deliver <lb/>
    himself of frequent speeches; but he was at a loss <lb/>
    to concieve how the charge of suppression of his <lb/>
    opinions could be made against the hon member, <lb/>
    who had expressed himself so clearly and decisively <lb/>
on the first day of the session, and about whose <lb/>
views upon this address there could be no mistake, <lb/>
as it bore his, (Mr. Godden's) name at the foot of <lb/>
it, as Chairman of the Committee that drew it up. <lb/>
Hon. mambers say, with an asumption of grave sin<lb break="no"/>cerity, let us educate and inform the people on this <lb/>
question. This was the very course the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment side proposed to take, and was engaged in <lb/>
urging; and this was the tenor of its resolution, <lb/>
while the terms of the amendment are calculated, <lb/>
and, as he believed, designed to prevent the very <lb/>
education aud information they professed to be so <lb/>
anxious about, The opposition will not allow us if, they <lb/>
can help it, to inform the people. The hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber for St. John's West, Mr. Talbot, contends that <lb/>
we are in a position to help ourselves, to develop <lb/>
our own resources and industries. He asserts this <lb/>
and uttery fails to prove it. But, he adds, does <lb/>
Canada say she will help us, that she will come <lb/>
down with a sum of money for the improvemennt of <lb/>
this country? Now he (Mr. P.) took up the hon. <lb/>
member on his own ground, and replied that is just <lb/>
one of the things we want to find out, by adopting <lb/>
course proposed in the addess. That hon. member <lb/>
again says, how are we get out of our isolation, an <lb/>
into the current of civilization by confederating? <lb/>
We shall be, and remain an Island, says he, unless <lb/>
some convulsion of nature throws us into the main<lb break="no"/>land of Canada. He (Mr. P.) thought and believed, <lb/>
        with every man who had common sense to under<lb break="no"/>stand what they were talking about, that the very <lb/>
        fact of our being an Island and remote from our <lb/>
        neighbours, was the very reason for <lb/>
        desiring efficient and speedy means of <lb/>
        trade and intercourse, and by such means <lb/>
and their consequences, we should get into the <lb/>
more ample current of civilization. As it was, he <lb/>
doubted if we had the means to continue local <lb/>
steam itself. We had already begun to feel the <lb/>
first traits of Confederation, by the fact that an <lb/>
opportunity would be afforded to 800 heads of <lb/>
families, if employment could not be got here, to <lb/>
obtain Railway work in Canada the coming sum<lb break="no"/>mer, steamers taking them and bringing them <lb/>
back, it they chose to return. That was a small <lb/>
example of what union would do. The union of <lb/>
the two Canadas was cited as an unfortunate one. <lb/>
True, there had been some political disaffection, <lb/>
but the material progress of those fine countries <lb/>
had not been interrupted, in population, public <lb/>
works, railways, &amp;c. It showed how little our <lb/>
people need care about the political changes, if the <lb/>
substautial blessings of life were to flow <lb/>
from the proposed union. The hon. and learned <lb/>
member then proceeued to show that so far from <lb/>
its being the fact, as Mr. Talbot had said, that Sir <lb/>
Hugh Hoyles had not been favourable to Confe<lb break="no"/>deration, he, Sir Hugh, had been the very strong<lb break="no"/>est advocate of it, and would have adopted the <lb/>
Quebec scheme without hesitation, but for the less <lb/>
bold policy of his associates and tile members of <lb/>
the House in general. Here Mr. Pinsent cited <lb/>
at considerable length from the speech of Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General Hoyles in 1865, a speech which he <lb/>
designated us out of the most powerful ever ut<lb break="no"/>tured here upon the subject. That speech was in <lb/>
connection with the only Resolution ever passed <lb/>
by this House in the matter of Confederation, and <lb/>
the closing language of that Resulution, proposed <lb/>
by Mr. Hoyles, seconded by the present Receiver <lb/>
General, Mr. Kent, then in opposition, and carried <lb/>
unanimously, was "that a final determination <lb/>
upon this importunt subject be deferred until <lb/>
the next session of the Legislature." The <lb/>
session there reterred to was the first <lb/>
session of this very present Parlialuent, so that <lb/>
if that resulution had been acted upon, as it might, <lb/>
in all consistency have been, the question now <lb/>
before us, for consideration only, might have been <lb/>
finally determined three years ago, without any <lb/>
further appeal. But on account of the desire <lb/>
generally expressed, that it should not be so <lb/>
ficted upon, but that better terms should it possi<lb break="no"/>ble, be secured, and the conditious ascertained <lb/>
for the information of the people, and a promise <lb/>
of the premier that there should be no final deter<lb break="no"/>mination until the improved terms had been first <lb/>
submitted to the people, for these reasons a <lb/>
course, the one now being pursued, was taken. <lb/>
Here Mr. Pinsent read a long extract from, as he <lb/>
said, the finest speech, and that was say great <lb/>
deal, ever delivered by Mr. Reuouf in the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly, in which, in 1865, he supported Mr. Hoyles's <lb/>
resolution, and pointed out in forcible terms the <lb/>
propriety of taking the course now proposed by <lb/>
the government, before sending the question to <lb/>
the people, also extracts from Mr. Glen's speeches <lb/>
of that time to the same effect, and part of an <lb/>
    editorial from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Patriot</hi> printed by the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>er, Mr. Parsons, in Roman letters, which could <lb/>
almost be read from the gallery, to the effect that <lb/>
no sane man could for a moment think of rejecting <lb/>
the consideration of equitable terms. He (Mr. P.) <lb/>
never could bring himself to believe in the sincer<lb break="no"/>ity of Mr. Parsons's subsequent opposition. It <lb/>
must have been from fear of a loss of that popularity <lb/>
of which he was so fond, and which he so de<lb break="no"/>servedly enjoyed; but that hon. member would <lb/>
do wisely now in turning with the tide, which had <lb/>
evidently set the other way. The hon. member <lb/>
(Mr. Pinsent) then showed that there was no fall <lb/>
comparison to be made with the Irish union, some <lb/>
of the terms of which every liberlly minded man <lb/>
now condemned and endeavoured to remove. <lb/>
    There were no objections of that kind to Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, which contemplated perfect equality, and <lb/>
    civil and religious liberty in its highest develop<lb break="no"/>ment. Would intelligent men be deluded by the <lb/>
    proposed to take off all duties on the stable <lb/>
    necessities of life this session, as a partial <lb/>
    alleviation of the burthens of the people, when <lb/>
    the financial condition of the government and the <lb/>
    state of the people were such as they now are, and <lb/>
    with a debt considerably exceeding half a million <lb/>
    of dollars to be redeemed in four or five years? <lb/>
    Hon. members who suggested such measures <lb/>
    must be aware of their impossibility, and the <lb/>
    bankruptcy and ruin which must be consequent <lb/>
    on their adoption as we now are, while be an alli<lb break="no"/>ance with the Dominionthose objects they so <lb/>
    much desire to accomplish will be effected. As to <lb/>
    the probability of the future absorption by the <lb/>
    United States of the Canadian Dominion, there <lb/>
    was no such present probability, and if such <lb/>
    were to be its ultimate fate, those who hold <lb/>
    Annexation tendencies are much more likely to <lb/>
    further their designs by promoting that, the first <lb/>
    step to further American unity. This consummation <lb/>
    
<cb/>

would never be until the Dominion had been either <lb/>
natured into strength and power, and declared its <lb/>
will so to be, or until Great Britain had elected to <lb/>
throw off the burthen of Colonial dependencies. <lb/>
At present an alliance with the United States could <lb/>
only be faught with enormous public debt and tax<lb break="no"/>ation amounting to an annual burthen of $30 per <lb/>
head. The hon and learned member then proceed<lb break="no"/>ded to argue that if the policy of the Statesmen of <lb/>
Great Britain to annex this Island and the sister <lb/>
Provinces, was Confederation, this was a strong addi<lb break="no"/>tional reason for submitting to it, and he pointed out <lb/>
several modes in which an indirect pressure might <lb/>
be brought to bear upon us, even if the parent state <lb/>
    did not directly force it. He deprecated the <lb/>
    inconsistency of hon. members who, in the same <lb/>
    speech, spoke of Britain as a cruel stepmother, and <lb/>
    then landed alliance with it as so much preferable <lb/>
    to closer connection with the sister Colonies. He <lb/>
    argued that our voice in the Dominion Councils <lb/>
would be fairly potent. It was not to be supposed <lb/>
that all the rest were to be banded against us. Was <lb/> 
not the voice of the hon and learned member for <lb/>
Harbor Main of considerable weight and in<lb break="no"/>portance in this House? And it bore the same <lb/>
relation to its numbers as our number of Repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives would to the Central Parliament. <lb/>
The hon. member proceeded to take up other <lb/>
objections and positions put from the other side, <lb/>
argued that the amendment was unfounded in fact, <lb/>
inconsistent in itself, and opposed to the principles <lb/>
hon. gentlemen opposite contended for. He urged <lb/>
that the course proposed by the address, far from <lb/>
being any interference with the rights of the people, <lb/>
was what the country was anxiously looking for, <lb/>
that it might know on what to decide. Members <lb/>
on this side of the House proposed to take the <lb/>
proper preparatory measures before submitting the <lb/>
question to the people. They were prepared to <lb/>
stand or fall by their policy. He felt that they <lb/>
were candidly and honestly discharging their <lb/>
duty to their constituents. If they were rejected, <lb/>
when the basis of terms was submitted, then the <lb/>
consequences lay with the people; and their present <lb/>
Representatives would have acquitted themselves of <lb/>
the grave responsibility of rejecting or dangerously <lb/>
delaying this measnre. He gathered from the <lb/>
course proposed by the other side, from the very <lb/>
language of their amendment, that their policy was <lb/>
    to go again before the country upon indefinite <lb/>
    speculation, to be in a position to asail the govern<lb break="no"/>ment as having offered nothing preferable to the <lb/>
    Quebec Convention, and then to be in a position to <lb/>
    deal with the matter themselves, without submitting <lb/>
    their own future plans to the country. He concluded <lb/>
by again summing up the advantages to be derived <lb/>
from union, and describing the nobler character of <lb/>
that new political and cominercial life into which we <lb/>
shall have entered under Confederation. <lb/> </p>

    <p><persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName>.—Notwithstanding the bitter <lb/>
scolding which the Opposition had just received, <lb/>
he would not be deterred from supporting the <lb/>
amendment of the hon. member, Mr. Talbot. <lb/>
The hon. member who had just spoken and <lb/>
taxed this side of the House with inconsisten<lb break="no"/>cies, should have recollected the old adage rela<lb break="no"/>tive to the peculiar liability of those who lived <lb/>
in glass houses. In 1865 the hon. member was <lb/>
in the Legislative Council, and had there given <lb/>
notice that he would move the following <lb/>
        resolutions:— <lb/></p> 

    <p>First,—That for Newfoundland to enter into a Con<lb break="no"/>federation of the British North American Colonies upon the <lb/>
terms, proposed in the Report of the Quebec Couference, <lb/>
would be detrimental to the best interests of this Colony, <lb/>
and ought to be resisted. <lb/></p>
    
    
    <p>Second,—That a humble Address be transmitted to Her <lb/>
Majesty, embodying the views of the Legislative Council <lb/>
upon this subject, with their reasons for the adoption of <lb/>
those views. <lb/></p> 

    <p>Third,—That a Select Committee of this House be ap<lb break="no"/>pointed to draft the said Address. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
But as no further record was to be found of this <lb/>
resolution, all must conclule what was known <lb/>
to be the case, that the hon. member thought <lb/>
better to abandon it. In 1866, he give another <lb/>
notice, which he also dropped like a hot potatoe. <lb/>
Then this is the man who talks to us of inconsis<lb break="no"/>tencies. He says we have done nothing to raise <lb/>
the country. But what has he done? Last <lb/>
year we had his great bill for the reduction of <lb/>
the public expenditure, which never even went <lb/>
to a second reading. Then there was his pam<lb break="no"/>phlet upon Confederation. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Committee then rose, and the Chairman <lb/>
reported progres. To sit again to-morrow. <lb/></p> 

<p>The House then adjourned until 3 o'clock, <lb/>
to-morrow. <lb/></p> 



    <!-- IC, 2019-02-04, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

<!--<p>FRIDAY, Feb. 12. <lb/>
The House met pursuant to adjournment. <lb/>
order of THE DAY. <lb/>
Committee of the Whole on Address. Mr. Knight <lb/>
in the Chair. <lb/>
The paragraph relating to Confederation having <lb/>
been real, <lb/>
Mr. O'RIELLY said, So much had been said on <lb/>
this matter, and so many diverse opinions offered, <lb/>
that the subject might be well said to be worn <lb/>
threadbare. While hon. members accused each <lb/>
other of inconsistency he at least could lay claim to <lb/>
consistency upon this question, and if he could <lb/>
not point to, any record of lengthy arguments <lb/>
which he had employed, he could at least flatter <lb/>
himself that he had no shifts or backslidings to ac<lb break="no"/>count for. His position was still precisely the same <lb/>
as that which he and his hon. colleagues had assumed <lb/>
at the hustings in '65, with this difference, however, <lb/>
that whatever difficulties he had then seen in the <lb/>
way had now entirely disappeared. The confederate <lb/>
cause had been gaining ground over all the Island, <lb/>
and though the Confederate party were continuing <lb/>
faithful to their pledge, that the question should be <lb/>
submitted to the cous ituencies, public opinion from <lb/>
Cape John to Caºe Ray, was calling aloud for a <lb/>
change. The principle of Confederation was now <lb/>
under discussion: "Who denied the principle P <lb/>
To use the joint language of the hon, and gallant <lb/>
Mijor, and the hon. member, Mr. Talbot, " the <lb/>
highest and most gifted minds acknowledge the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple". There was not the beginning of a differ<lb break="no"/>ence with regard to the principle between hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers on this and on the other side. Hon. members <lb/>
ite were all confed and the only differ­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ence, between them was upon matters of detail. <lb/>
Surely then upon the question of details hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers could well give over their party differences. <lb/>
As to terms there were few hon. members who would <lb/>
be more difficult to please than himself, and <lb/>
when the debate upon the subject came on <lb/>
he should be prepared to conteuil that express <lb/></p> 

<p>unanimity as to the <lb break="no"/>as the hon member, Mr º says that it means <lb/>
employument for th; people. <lb/>
º . meantug § hin (Mr P.J. and was one <lb/>
which wou'd hardy be ſound in any dictionery. It <lb/>
that were really the meaning of it-it it, would <lb/>
procure that, the Opposition would hailConfederation <lb/>
with one voice. <lb/>
would be placed upon it <lb/>
abroad from this colony to seek employment because <lb/>
we had it within our own borders. <lb break="no"/>to transport 800 of our stalwart fishermen into the <lb/>
wilds of Canada. <lb/>
give them better employment than Canada could <lb/>
afford them. What I expatriate the hardy natives <lb/>
of this-colony and make them seek employment <lb/>
amongst strangers? Why it was a policy that no <lb/>
parental Government would entertain. -\-\-<lb break="maybe"/>mamber then proceeded to show that we had within <lb/>
ourselves resources which if fostered and developed <lb/>
by the Government were more than sufficient for our <lb/>
population. <lb/>
question of Confederation before the House now was <lb/>
a breach of laith on the part of the Governin-n , <lb/>
that there was no evidence before this House that <lb/></p> 

<p>against Confederation, and coutended that <lb/>
opinion of the people was the same now, and that no <lb/></p> 

<p>no one would attempt to deny that he was an out<lb break="no"/>spoken Confederate, but he should always be jºalous <lb/>
of this country's interests in connection with the <lb/>
question of terms. <lb/></p> 

<p>After some remarks from Mr. Hogsºrt, ... <lb/>
Mr. PARsons said that he had been waiting for <lb/></p> 

<p>meaning of the word. <lb/></p> 

<p>Weil, that certainly <lb/></p> 

<p>Bit he feared no such meaning <lb/>
We do not want to go <lb/></p> 

<p>We did not want <lb/></p> 

<p>We would keep then here and <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon <lb/></p> 

<p>He considered the bringing of this <lb/></p> 

<p>the public desired any change. He referred to the <lb/>
Petitions which had been presented former sessions <lb/>
the <lb/></p> 

<p>- Monday, Feb. 15. <lb/>
The House met pursuant to adjournment. <lb/>
Upon motion of the Hou. ArroRNEY GENERAL, <lb/></p> 

<p>the House resolved itself into a Committee of the <lb/>
whole on the Address of Thanks.-Mr. Knight in <lb/>
the Chair. <lb/>
The hon. the SPEAKER said that he considered it." <lb/>
to be his duty, occupying the position of Speaker of <lb/>
this House, to refer to certain remarks contained in <lb/>
the Chronicle of this morning, in which he had been <lb/>
charged with uttering language derogatory to Mr. G <lb/>
F Bennett. <lb break="no"/>call upon the House to endorse what he now said, <lb/>
that he neither directly nor inferentially referred to <lb/>
Mr. Bennett. <lb/>
guilty of a violation of the rules of this House, and <lb/></p> 

<p>He must contradict that statement, and <lb/></p> 

<p>Had he done so he would have been <lb/></p> 

<p>he thought all would do him the justice to say that <lb/>
since he had the honor of pre # <lb/>
ways endeavoured to sustain the dignity of the <lb/>
House and adhere to the rules governing our de<lb break="no"/>bates. Had the remarks in this paper mºrely refer<lb break="no"/>- red to himself personally, he would have deemed <lb/>
them unworthy of notice, but when they referred to <lb/>
his position as the Speaker of this House, he con<lb break="no"/>sidered that in recognition of that duty which he <lb/>
owed to that office and to this House, he was bound <lb/>
to take notice of this matter and contradict it. <lb/>
would again declare that he had neither directly nor <lb/>
inferentially referred to Mr. Bennett in the speech <lb/>
... which he had made. <lb/></p> 

<p>ig here he had al­ <lb/></p> 

<p>He <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon. Receiver General, Mr. Prowse, and the <lb/></p> 

<p>Colonial Secretary also sustained the assertion of the <lb/>
hon. and learned Speaker, and bore testimony to the <lb/>
dignity with which he had always upheld his posi­ <lb/></p> 

<p>tion. <lb/>
The Receiver GENERAL remarked that the offi<lb break="no"/>cial Reports were confirmatory of what the Speaker <lb/>
had declare <lb/>
Mr. TALBor could not say whether the words had <lb/>
been used or not, but he denied that the official <lb/>
Reports were any authority upon the matter. <lb/>
GLRN was glad to see that every oné read the <lb/>
Chronicle, it shewed that it was the true exponent of <lb/>
public opinion. He thought that it was carrying this <lb/>
unatter too far when he heard that the Editor of the <lb/>
Chronicle had been ejected from the Clerk's room by <lb/>
the order of the Speaker. The Opposition were <lb/>
attacked in the most outrageous manner every day, <lb/>
but they paid no attention to it. <lb/>
Tue hon. A. SBEA was sorry that the hon. and <lb/>
learned Speaker had taken the trouble to occupy <lb/>
a moment of time with a matter so paltry. Suppose <lb/>
he had said Mr. Bennett was the Head 3.nº ºthe <lb/>
Anti-Confederates? What then Was that gentle<lb break="no"/>man ashamed of being so called? What then was <lb/>
there in it that any man should feel thin skinned <lb/>
about? But the hon, the Speaker had never men<lb break="no"/>tioned Mr. Bennett's name. How then could he <lb/>
have spoken disrespectfully of him?. He (Mrs) <lb/>
had referred to Mr. Bennett in this House and <lb/>
would do so again when he deemed it uecessary, but <lb/>
he had never spoken *... of him. He <lb/>
was sorry any importance had been attached to this <lb/>
matter. He would now refer to the paragraph be<lb break="no"/>fore the Chair, This section then affirmed that the <lb/>
time had arrived for considering this question of <lb/>
Confederation, so that it might be referred to the <lb/>
various constituencies. Now the hon. member Mr, <lb/>
Talbot the other evening in a speech of considerable <lb/>
length, denied this. He (Mr. S.) admitted that the <lb/>
hon. member had discussed the matter with a great <lb/>
deal of ability and in language that was certainly <lb/>
entitled to respect, and he made this admission <lb/>
freely and readily, altho' both in the premises and <lb/>
conclusions of the hon. member he entirely dis<lb break="no"/>agreed. The hon, member had asserted that the <lb/>
time had not arrived for dealing with this question, <lb/>
and that this House had no authority to deal with it, <lb/></p> 

<p>He thought that the time had fully arrived for this <lb/>
question to be considered, and further, that was <lb/>
in accordance with the existing state of <lb/>
opinion, Why, what was the reprºach that had been <lb/></p> 

<p>public <lb/></p> 

<p>uttered against us time after time 2 That we did <lb/></p> 

<p>not bring down the terms, so that the people might <lb/>
be fully instructed upon them, and now, with a <lb/>
strange and marvellous inconsistency. they tell us <lb/>
that we have no right to go into the discussion and <lb/>
provision should be made for the encouragement of investigation of those very terms, for which they had <lb/></p> 

<p>what were satisfactory terms or not. It could not be <lb/>
too well known, he thought, that no proceeding wº <lb/>
contemplated by this Liouse by which this question <lb/>
would be finally determined. We simply desired tº <lb/>
show the country what the terms were—so that they <lb/>
might give them earnest consideration, and be in 4 <lb/>
position at the general election to say whether they <lb/></p> 

<p>lature or by the country, because it had never bºss <lb/>
submitted to either. This House would certainly be <lb/>
open to censure it it permitted such a statement to go <lb/>
unchallenged. Hon alembers opposite a few years <lb/>
ago, . when there was a paragraph in the address <lb/>
relative to Confederation, said, if you pass it, you <lb/>
affirm the principle of Confederation. The Goveral <lb/>
ment declared at the time that that was not a right <lb/>
interpretation to place upon it, as the section was oils <lb/>
which pronounced no opinion, and went ºuerely for <lb/>
delay. But so assured were they that it affirmed the <lb/>
principle of Confederation, that they proposed an <lb/>
amendment to it. (Here the hon member read the <lb/>
same.) Now if that amendment had been carried, <lb/>
the hoa member would have been borne out in his <lb/>
statement that the question had been rejected. But <lb/>
the fact was, that that amendinent had been igno, <lb/>
iminiously rejected by a majority of eighteen to six, <lb/>
How then could it be said that the Quebec scheus <lb/>
had ever been rejected by this House. Now he ſ \ir <lb/>
S) did not claim that thut majority aſfirined the <lb/>
principle of Contederation, he merely claimed that it <lb/>
rejected the amendment against the principle. His <lb/>
was indeed somewuat surprised that the lion member <lb/>
Mr Talbot should deal with so important a question <lb/>
in the nanner he had. The clap trap about our <lb/>
lives and liberties was not worthy that gentleman', <lb/>
position or ability. Then he appeals to the natives <lb/>
not to sell their country. Tuat question of sals <lb/></p> 

<p>gainer by that sale He merely referred to this <lb/>
in reference to the question which had been raisel, <lb/>
and to shew that selling a country was not atter <lb/>
so terrible a thinx, but was a proceed.ng by which <lb/>
many countries had been benefitted. " The hon <lb/>
meuber then referred to Irish encumbered estates <lb/>
Act, and shewed the alivantages it had conferred, <lb/>
regarding it in the light of a forced sale. The hº <lb/>
meuber Mr Talbot tells us that the Irish Union was <lb/>
caused by bribery, and that sons three millions wers <lb/>
spent lor.that purpose. Well, that was true. But <lb/>
who was it that received that money? Why the <lb/>
ºpposition, who then occupied that position in the <lb/>
Irish Parliament which hon gentlemen oppone'd, <lb/>
huts. It was to purchase their woes that this ujuuy <lb/>
had been spent. <lb/></p> 

<p>Ma. Lºrree.—Are you going to give as sºmé. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. Shka–Don't let the hon. member, <lb/>
mouth water too soon, Île would not have hon, gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen oppositº indulge in extravagant expectations <lb/>
of what might happen here. The Un or of Irelani <lb/>
was an exception and was not one that should b, <lb/>
quoted, ...That was a Union between people not, on <lb/>
an equality. It was a Union of a dominant race <lb/>
with a slavish and enthralled one. It was the union <lb/>
of men who enjoyed civil an I religious rights with <lb/>
men who had nuthur the one nor the other, was it <lb/>
then anything surprising that the dominant cle, <lb/>
should regard the otbers as slaves and treat thea of <lb/>
But were the same conflicting eleucots to be ſouni <lb/>
here 2 Had we not all civil and regious liberty? <lb/>
Were we not all upon the same looting 7 were as <lb/>
not equal in the eye of one Govern ment and it un<lb break="no"/>Mersal laws? Would the hon gentleman say that the <lb/>
Union of the States was a falºre? Janadian Union <lb/>
he says was a ſailure Where does the hon. member <lb/>
get his facts for making such a statement? <lb/>
The result to the country was great prosperiy. <lb/>
He had not then a hand the sta istics of popu, <lb/>
lition, produce, &amp;c., but he knew that they <lb/>
showed sufficient to justify the assertion that the <lb/>
Union of the two Provinces had proved a succes, <lb/>
Was the fact that the people of England last <lb/>
year demanded a new Bºforin Bill any proof <lb/>
th it the bill of 1832 was a failure? No iſ otly <lb/>
showed that the time for further changes had <lb/>
some, and just so with the question of Union. <lb/>
The time for change cam', and when the ques. <lb/>
tion which had agitated the Lower Province', <lb/>
was ripe for settlement, Canada could searcely <lb/>
believe that Nova Scotia, the cladle of Union, <lb/>
would tura its back on its own offspring. It was <lb/>
stated that the Delegates had condemned the <lb/>
Quebec Resolu ions. Such was not tua case, <lb/>
neither the hon. and learned Attorney Gaueral <lb/>
nor he (hon. Mr. S.) had ever said so. They <lb/>
never eutertained such opinions as would justily <lb/>
them in saying so. Having regard to the time <lb/>
ºf its origiu, he denied that it was a plan which <lb/>
deserv'd coudemuation. It was most lavorably <lb/>
received, and coun vided the admiration of the <lb/>
ablest and most intelligent men in England. <lb/>
It had since then been slightly nod fied, but <lb/>
how? Was it not by making concessions all <lb/>
round, on the oue silio as well as the other? <lb/>
The result of monetary consessions would by <lb/>
that whºle we might get more money for our <lb/>
own immediate purposes, we would act be <lb/>
benefited to tug fu.j extent supposed, because <lb/>
to the extent of the increase received we lessen <lb/>
the money which would remain in the hauds of <lb/>
he General Government for general purposes. <lb/>
The ouly changes made as yet were nonetary <lb/>
ones. The framework and eharacter of the * <lb/>
constitution, the powers of the general and local <lb/>
governunauts, are sull the same as adopted in <lb/>
Quebec, so that in these principal points thusa <lb/>
resulutions remain intact. In one other poia <lb/>
ºly was any change made, and that was by the <lb/>
British Government in the number of Seators, <lb/>
*2 as to provide for the happeuiug at any tina <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>were incapable of forming an of <lb/></p> 

<p>examine into the matter, for them. <lb/></p> 

<p>should leave the country, but he <lb/></p> 

<p>they blind and inchpable of form <lb/>
Not one ct them but spoke in <lb/>
Constitution as framed at Quebe <lb/>
that a significant fact, which migh <lb/>
the minds of some who ought to <lb/></p> 

<p>lated to advance the interests a <lb/>
prosperity of these Colouies, sh <lb/>
and great weight with men whº <lb/>
and knowledge of such matters i <lb/>
so large. He did not mean to <lb/>
gen lemen should not exercise the <lb/>
on the subject. The duty and the <lb/>
ity with them, and they were bou <lb/></p> 

<p>all, what was Confederatiou? It <lb/>
that four or five provinces, havin <lb/>
tutions and laws, aud owing: <lb/>
common sovereign, should unite f <lb/>
mon benefit. Those who advocate <lb/>
sition believed that Union would <lb/>
beneficial results than isolation. <lb/>
by the exam, le of the Uuited <lb/>
believed that such a Union w <lb/>
genural prosperity and give stabil <lb/>
that in co-operation each would <lb/>
which individually they eould no <lb/>
his (hon. Mr. S's.) mind, Confede <lb/>
inereased mºans of anployin ºut. <lb/>
that the want of which was most <lb/>
now 7 Rumployment. It had bee <lb/></p> 

<p>tlerive such direct advantages as <lb/>
Prºvinces, yet those which we in <lb/>
will have. Here was a practical <lb/>
he said. He was authorised to eu, <lb/>
to work at the putlie works in Can <lb/>
not the taking of tuese 800 men of <lb/>
where they new wand ºr up an I d <lb/>
to work but auable to find it, adva. <lb/>
of labor? He did not speak for ad <lb/>
pose, and would not be so toolhard <lb/>
an assertion which could be contra <lb/>
išt of My next. IIa agreed that <lb/>
toº.uue that the pºpulation shouli º <lb/>
go away, but it wºuld be a greated <lb/>
to have theta reimain here in the sº <lb/>
as they were in last year. No <lb/>
give him (huu Mr. S.) greater pi <lb/>
*ual the state of the comu.ry sueuld <lb/>
to enable these inea to stay at uulu <lb/>
lºad a greater interest in seeing the <lb/>
iſloyed than lie had, tuat they suu. <lb/>
purchasers and not as begg us. Wuj <lb/>
the yield to any in uls desire to sº <lb/>
prosperous Aud happy: Xot one <lb/>
who would be eugºg.u by utia woul <lb/>
uext winter, for uail their wages w. <lb/>
here for theia. Wuile tui.gs were <lb/>
sed in the country, he (uoi Air. S.) <lb/>
this as a godseud. He looked <lb/>
beginning of a system which wou <lb/>
country from tuture deterioration <lb/>
of laour. The tact shows that is la <lb/>
here, it will be taken up tor the ot. <lb/>
If we have Coufederation, we will <lb/>
Steamers with Quebee and Me. <lb/>
would enable the people tº go a <lb/>
kilnº. In this country the labor q <lb/>
derlios all others, aud snything wi <lb/>
advance the interests of the lab <lb/>
also tended to the advance of the <lb/>
the country at large. All that was <lb/>
a well employed people, and then <lb/>
would be contented aud happy. <lb/></p> 

<p>look on it as at all desirable that <lb/></p> 

<p>desirable that when they were so be <lb/>
should have some backdoors. Iſe <lb/></p> 

<p>ed to lear it said that our men <lb/>
for this work, Any man who will <lb/>
going, will acknowiadge that no flu. <lb/>
men ever left any port. Lie had <lb/>
any counplaint of the insu on the Te <lb/>
aud did not think the wo <lb/>
Rilway was any harder. Nor did <lb/>
had been inputsu to them by the <lb/>
themselves their friends, that were <lb/>
** to ſurget those whom they had <lb/>
He thought differeutly of them, a <lb/>
them to be possessed of <lb/>
which attached then tu those wº <lb/>
aud legitimate claims on them. 0 <lb/>
any of them chose to relaxis away,it <lb/>
it would be better for them, they w <lb/>
in doing so. They would have the <lb/>
coming home it they chose to c. <lb/>
could be no compulsion, Those wh <lb/>
go would go as volunteers. He c <lb/>
stand that such matters as these w <lb/>
tasteful to those who were inter ste <lb/>
down the value of labor. Last yes <lb/>
wers in such a wretched condition <lb/>
*** glad to ship on any terms. <lb/></p> 

<p>desired to perpetuats that stat <lb/></p> 

<p>would, of course, be dissati, fled wi <lb/></p> 

<p>tempt to disturb it. He thougut th <lb/>
ºf the question which they were no <lb/>
*g, * might with propriety sp. <lb/></p> 

<p>Charles Fox Bennet, who requi. <lb/></p> 

<p>much desire to accomplish wifi be eflected. As to - - - - <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>th - …" the fisheries. Exception had been taken to the bond so often asked. Now how would it be possible for us a deadlock in the Goveralasat. <lb/></p> 

<p>§§.#º"..."; º ... [fide character of the telegram received by his hon. to go into the discussion of terms, unle; we area:ed As ſo tº objectious arged. Tug ou!y number of men to work his mines, a <lb/>
ulluion, there There was not a * "ourse, try and get them at as low <lb/></p> 

<p>* no such present probability, and if <lb/></p> 

<p>Yere tº be its it.: fate, #. who i. <lb/>
Annexation tendencies as ºn mºre likely to <lb/>
turther their designs by promoting that, the first <lb/></p> 

<p>step to further American unity, Tsi, consumns. <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/></p> 

<p>**league offering employment to 800 or 1,000 people. <lb/>
He might sately say that all that scepticism was to be <lb/>
found within the doors of this House. Those persons <lb/>
who were most to be affected by it had full faith in <lb/></p> 

<p>* *:­ <lb/></p> 

<p>is reality and tº regarded it as a prac i <lb/>
- - - - - - . -<lb break="maybe"/>-: 2. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>to the section before the chair. <lb/>
man, in this House, who might not vote for this <lb/>
Seetion, and when the terms are breught down with <lb/>
Perſect bonesty and consisteney dissent from any or <lb/></p> 

<p>s Jºosie had twisted this <lb/></p> 

<p>oues raised by ºue Aatis, were that the people <lb/>
would be .azed more thau was fair, und tist <lb/></p> 

<p>:a: 327:2.4.1% had: <lb/></p> 

<p>tury would not receive enough. To do oths: <lb/>
2. - i... plan was any objection raised, aud <lb/>
certailly if no.1! be uillical, to raise o jictious <lb/></p> 

<p>P*itle. He was, of course, right, <lb/>
his interests and the interests of <lb/></p> 

<p>wers directly opposed to each other, <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>