<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-16" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1869-02-16">16 February 1869</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1869-02-24"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2019-01-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2019-01-17">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_1.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">St. John's, Wednesday, February 24, 1869.</fw>



    <!-- IC, 2019-01-17, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->
    
    
<!--<p>-\-\-\-\-\-\- ºr-\-\-tºº-\-&gt; <lb/></p> 

<p>rful that the world has ever known. <lb/>
ná in whateven share disease exists, <lb/>
equal to its subjection and cure. . . <lb/></p> 

<p>ºf sIC-K. . . . ." <lb/>
the Housemoto REMEDY of all nations. <lb/>
attack the very poor of the complaint, <lb/>
ºre the drooping energies of the <lb/>
Nerſonaar REFORMATION-\-<lb break="maybe"/></p> 

<p>2 sºror/C.A.C.E. <lb/>
is the operation of the Pills? They <lb/>
ºriațăstomachinto anatural and <lb/>
of the system from sickness to health. . <lb/>
* ALTT.IMIENTS<lb break="no"/>m undergoes the most important and <lb/>
icin every disorder to which they are <lb/>
ard against evil consequences. <lb/></p> 

<p>5 TIMEFU=ITIEs of <lb/>
|-i-º­ <lb/></p> 

<p>lood is in an impure stato, let such <lb/>
ºf with confidence to this powerful <lb/>
health and strength will be the result. <lb/></p> 

<p>+-ISTOWN. FO:ER. <lb/></p> 

<p>fl. stone and §:... <lb/></p> 

<p>onplaints. secondary Symptons. <lb/>
implaints 5. . Thatever <lb/></p> 

<p>wn of Urine, - cause, &amp;c., <lb/></p> 

<p>words tº Hºlloway, London," are dis<lb break="no"/>of directions around each box; which <lb/>
*...* Solà at the manufactory of Pro<lb break="no"/>respectable Druggists and Dealers in <lb/>
22s., and 33s.-There is a considerable <lb/>
tions for use are affixed to cach Box. " <lb/></p> 

<p>ONUS EVERY THREE YEARS <lb/></p> 

<p>THE ETNA <lb/></p> 

<p>URANCE COMPANY <lb/></p> 

<p>(LIAIARP, -<lb break="maybe"/>pital—One Million Sterling: <lb/>
ºffices—Dublin-46 &amp; º: Sackville <lb/>
ºdinburgh–98 George's Street. <lb/>
*"...º.º., E. c. <lb/>
eneral Manager—John Innes, Esq. <lb/>
ecretary J. S. Fisher, Esq. <lb/>
nprecedented success of the ETNA in the <lb/>
Kingdom, owing to its liberal dealings with <lb/>
is is a fact which strongly recºmmends the <lb/>
y to the people of Newfoundland. <lb/>
come ºf his company from NEW PRE. <lb/>
ALONE is progressing at the rate of <lb/>
per Annum. - -<lb break="maybe"/>ompany do not advocate high preminms. <lb/>
rs ample security to all nsurers. ... <lb/></p> 

<p>s for '... shall be piomptly and liberally <lb/></p> 

<p>fers from other offices can be effected free <lb/>
e <lb/></p> 

<p>by payment of Six years premium can <lb/>
VEN years policy. <lb/>
in A is Tlib only Ogwick, which of FER <lb/>
sus "EYERY Tim REE YEARs to Policy<lb break="no"/>. HoldeRS HAVING No Lussks. <lb/></p> 

<p>ndersigned having been appointed General <lb/>
* Newfoundland for the above Company, <lb/>
ed to effect Insurances against LOSS Olk <lb/>
;B BY FIRE on all descriptions of pro<lb break="no"/>fair and reasonable rates, and begs leave<lb break="no"/>a share of the business of those having <lb/>
cs to effect. <lb/>
Jers shall have prompt attention. <lb/>
for proposals and ſurther information ean <lb/>
t the oſfice of -<lb break="maybe"/>ROBERT J. KENT, <lb/>
Solicitor. <lb/>
No. 261 Duckworth-Street St. John's. <lb/></p> 

<p>6m <lb/></p> 

<p>owever inveterate. Few medicine: <lb/>
grand remedy not only cures in such <lb/>
is, as a proof it needs but a trial. <lb/></p> 

<p>DISTC+ETTIS. <lb/>
soughs, and colds, may be infallibly <lb/>
bbing this remedy twice a day upon <lb/>
ates, and a cure quickly follows. <lb/></p> 

<p>EAST's, ETC. <lb/>
temedy is now in general use. In <lb/>
• Physicians regularly prescribe its <lb/>
a the chests of sailors and emigrants. <lb/></p> 

<p>s"Wriºr, I.TINTG.S. º <lb/>
his Ointment will prove invaluable. <lb/>
im, and restores matural circulation. <lb/></p> 

<p>ET.C., ETC<lb break="no"/>arts, of either sex, may be readily <lb/>
f this cooling and healing Ointment. <lb/></p> 

<p>E" ºrot TTEC<lb break="no"/>|aily cured by the joint agency of <lb/>
o the printed directions <lb/></p> 

<p>Peº- -<lb break="maybe"/>ieving and curing old wounds, sº <lb/></p> 

<p>y in most of the following cases:<lb break="no"/>Soro Heads. <lb/>
F's Evil. Tic Doloureux. <lb/>
ons, Tightness or Wheezing on the * <lb/>
* - Cheat, with difficulty of Breathing <lb/></p> 

<p>words " Holloway, London," are dis<lb break="no"/>the light, in every leaf of the book of <lb/>
factory of Professor Holloway, 244, <lb/></p> 

<p>Medicine, in pots at 18.1%d., 2s. 9d., <lb/>
le saving by taking the larger sizese <lb/></p> 

<p>No. 6,572. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºr. ..." <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, Wednesday, February 21, 1869. <lb/></p> 

<p>Printed and Published every Tuesday and Friday <lb/>
morning by EDWARD DALTON SHEA, at his <lb/>
Office in Duckwor:Tit STREET. Terns—One <lb/>
Găinea per annum, pnyable in advance. <lb/>
Advertisements not limited (Auction Sales and notices <lb/>
which determine themselves excepted) are repeated, <lb/>
until ordered in writing to be withdrawn. <lb/>
is paper is filed, and mºw be seen free of charge <lb/>
at Holloway's Pill and Ointment Establishment, <lb/>
244. Strand. London. . . <lb/>
This paper is not issued to any Subsertber for a shorter <lb/>
term than siz months. <lb/></p> 

<p>Thouse of Asseyibly. <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Moxoay, Feb. 15. <lb/>
- [costIsued 1 <lb/>
Mr. Hogsett.-The hon. gentleman had. <lb/>
made a very lengthy and eliborate speech to <lb/>
show the pecple that Cou'ederation was the best <lb/>
thing for their interest, and th–t the exporta'iou <lb/></p> 

<p>of 80 men before the 10th of May would be <lb/></p> 

<p>the beginning of the blessings of Confederation. <lb/>
He (Mr. H.) might admit that for an old and <lb/>
overpopulated country, eiagration night be a <lb/>
good thing, but who would assert it with regard <lb/>
to a col my which had capacities for supporting <lb/>
3,000,000 of peopl;? If no bettar argument <lb/>
for Confederation than this could be found, the <lb/>
case must be a bad one. From day to day <lb/>
our people are leaving our shores, and going <lb/>
uuler the Government of the stars and stripes. <lb/>
It this Dominion be what they say, why don't <lb/>
emigrants remain there? Do they do so? No, <lb/>
they go to the United States. Was the DJ<lb break="no"/>miſſion independent? Why, 14 or 15 Bill passed <lb/>
1 st year, haſ been ignored by the Imperial <lb/>
Gowel liment. <lb/>
Hon. Mr. S.—I heard of one. <lb/>
Mr. Hogsºrt could name them. The fact <lb/>
was that the Yankees woull have us before the <lb/>
good times spoken of would over arrive. <lb/>
Mr. Renouf.-There was no evidence before <lb/>
the House that the people were in favour con<lb break="no"/>federation. In fact all the evidence pointed o it <lb/>
the contrary. Hon. members representing Out<lb break="no"/>ports had ample opportunity, during the pas; <lb/>
five years to have got up petitions in favour of <lb/>
it, had the people approved of the measure<lb break="no"/>And had they approved of it? We might be as<lb break="no"/>sured that there would have been some elfort made <lb/>
to prepare these petitions. The hon upmber, Mr. <lb/>
rinsent, had lately visited his district, and read them <lb/>
a lecture ou Confed-ration. Had he been author <lb/>
thorised by the people to sustain it? If we look at <lb/>
the mother country we find that in all great, inea<lb break="no"/>sures the public mind was always consulted, and <lb/>
that legislation was controlled by it. Sºme three <lb/>
years ago a petition had been presented by Mr. <lb/>
W, at against Confederation. He (Mr. B.) had the <lb/>
honor of presenting one of a similar character, and <lb/>
with a similar object, from the District of Placeutia. <lb/>
Last year he had been entrusted with one irgin the <lb/>
monster luecting which had been held in the Fisher<lb break="no"/>men's 11all. Surely, tºlen, if the people were in <lb/>
favour of it, where was the evidenue that would <lb/>
prove that the Government was correct and the op<lb break="no"/>position wrong. If the people viewed the matter <lb/>
in the same light that we are told, how is it that that <lb/>
opinion is not expressed by any petition before this <lb/>
liouso? It was indeed easy to say that a clºnge <lb/>
had come over their miuds. But we want somethºg <lb/>
more than mere assertion—sounctbing more taugible, <lb/>
while there existed before this Hous: the many post<lb break="no"/>tive assurances and evidence that the peºple did not <lb/>
desire us to take any action upon this importunt <lb/>
question. The hon. Attorney General, when he <lb/>
went to Burin in 1865, told the electors that his in<lb break="no"/>dividual views inclined to the principle of Confeder<lb break="no"/>*tion. Indeed, he only inclined to the principle in <lb/>
1865, whereas, in 1864 he was unequivocally in layor <lb/>
of it, and signed the Quebec Resolutions. He had <lb/>
pledged himself while in Canada to use his utino?" <lb/>
&amp;ndeavours to carry Confederation, upon the basis <lb/>
of the Quebec Resolutions. Why did he not h ºn<lb break="no"/>estly ten the people of Burin he was in favor of Cun<lb break="no"/>federaion, and upon these terus, and not to have <lb/>
hºudwinked and deceived them as he did. (Here <lb/>
the hon member referred to the Year Book of <lb/>
1868, and lead from it certain passages relative to <lb/>
the situngs of the delegates. In 1884, and their prº<lb break="no"/>ceedings in Canada.j Why, then, had nºt the <lb/>
hon. Attorney General mantu ly told the people that <lb/>
he had signed the Q lege'; sche me, and that be <lb/>
would stand or fall by it? .9a, no. He knew very <lb/>
well, had be done so he would not now be in the 99<lb break="no"/>sition he was. IHe had to eat bumble pie wuen he <lb/>
went to Burin. He then proulised them that ther, <lb/>
should be no legislation upon, the matter witho. <lb/>
consulting the people, and yet be now proposes <lb/>
take action upon it without the conselt, ºf the peº" <lb/>
pie. Perhaps, however, it is true that the lion. <lb/>
Attorney General is not going back to Buriº, all <lb/>
thus can afford to violate is plighted faith. Well: <lb/>
the Receiver General went to the hustings in 1853. <lb/>
and he also was forced to pouket Confederation and <lb/>
to eat huabia pie. He had cas. his eyes up tº <lb/>
leaven and had solemnly asser ed til it he would <lb/>
do nothing upon the matter without consulting his <lb/>
constituents. <lb/>
lion. Receiven Geseawl—I made no such de<lb break="no"/>claration. <lb/>
Mr. Resour.—would refer to the hon. member's <lb/>
memory. Liure the hon. Inetuber read in account <lb/>
ul proceedings atteuding the elections vilsöö. Hº <lb/>
then proceeded to read the address of hºuself tº <lb/>
$his colleague, Mr. Talbot, to the elector in tº <lb/>
year, and commented upon the speech ul the *. <lb/>
turney General in which they had been arcuºl <lb/>
ºf eating their own words. He cuntended lººk <lb/>
they had distinctly ill tuis audress told the peºple <lb/>
at they were opposed tº Coutederation; its tº <lb/>
were ugw. He cou:euted further. that they had, <lb/>
truly toretold what had culme to pass. That tº . <lb/>
lus!gaulated Goveruineut was corrupt, had incº<lb break="no"/>ed the civil expenditure and the taxes, and tul<lb break="no"/>to tºe burdens of the people, that there ex <lb/>
sive taxation had killed out the middle tuan, aud <lb/>
that the short issue of supplies to tue, fishermen <lb/>
the past year was to be āūributed to the in-ereºis <lb/>
of tºxation which precluded the man of merely <lb/>
lºoderate aeans trum competing with the murº <lb/>
weally iuporters, who tuus uad: monopoly kid <lb/>
$ould charºe what they liked. . Then the grºit <lb/>
:=dw-yº fºcadº Rºi i.; i.e: "...is was tº <lb/></p> 

<p>. <lb/>
exportation of 800 men to Canada. This was to <lb/>
produce quite a macusing among the lithoutrers <lb/>
attd increase their wages. They had received no <lb/>
instructions to bind the Iregislatºre or the country. <lb/>
but when they sioned the Resolutious they bound <lb/>
themselves to urge the principle and the terms <lb/>
on the people. The lion, and learned Attorney <lb/>
General and the hon. Mr. Shea would say that they <lb/>
approved of then but that it was subject to , the <lb/>
approval of the people, but when the British <lb/>
Government saw that all had signed the document <lb/>
was it at all wonderful that they should cunclude <lb/>
that all were in favour of Confederation? It was <lb/>
said that the House did not r-ject the principle <lb/>
that he (Mr. R, asserted that it did. The Gover:-\-<lb break="maybe"/>ment of the day was afraid to lly the principle <lb/>
before the House for discussion, but substituted <lb/>
that very mild Resolution by the accepting of <lb/>
which the House and country virtually rejected <lb/></p> 

<p>| the Quebec scheme, ...A great deal had been said <lb/></p> 

<p>about the influence our representatives would <lb/>
have in the Dominiou Parliament. In the last <lb/>
session the members from the Lºwer Provinces <lb/>
were opposed to the proposed târiff, out they might <lb/>
as well have held their tongues. It was passed in <lb/>
spite of them, and not a Canadian wiember gave <lb/>
them any assistance. It was also said that Lower <lb/>
Cºnadiai, sympathies and feelings would go with <lb/>
the Maritime Provinces. It might be so when <lb/>
Upper and Lower Cauada disagreed amongst the ul<lb break="no"/>selves, but when the question was Canadiau they <lb/>
would be found united. The lion. member, Mr. <lb/>
Shea, referred to the case of Rhode Island, which <lb/>
has only one member in the House of Representit<lb break="no"/>tives. Though such was the case she was repre<lb break="no"/>sented in the Senate equally wi.h New York or <lb/>
any other State in the United States. In the Selºte <lb/>
alſ the States were represented alike. Was <lb/>
such the case in the Dominion? There <lb/>
was no analogy between the constitutions <lb/>
In the Dominion the arrangements were inade so <lb/>
that Canada should always...have a majority. Con<lb break="no"/>federation for our benefit indeed! It was never so <lb/>
intended. The Imperial Government were always <lb/>
anxious for it, si upy that Imperial taxpayers might <lb/>
be relieved from the expend-ture of troops in these <lb/>
Colonies. They heard a great deal of reciprocity<lb break="no"/>that we cannot have reciprocity without Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. They had yet to learn that the United States <lb/>
were disposed to establish reciprocity. From all <lb/>
that he (Mr. R.) could learn they were not at all <lb/>
disposed to re-establish it. When they heard hon. <lb/>
gentlemen opposite praisº Reciprocity it should be <lb/>
remembered that at one time they were its bitterest <lb/>
enemies. It was strange how men would wheel <lb/>
round when they had an object in view. In 1864 <lb/>
they saw that no benefit whatever could be derived <lb/>
from Reciprocity, while to-day they are enamored <lb/>
with it. The non member, Mr. Shea, took his (Mr. <lb/>
R's.) hon. colleague, Mr.Talbot,to task because he <lb/>
had said that it was possible to have Reciprocity <lb/>
without Confederation. He (Mr. R.) agreed with <lb/>
his hon, colleague. . What was to prºvent tueir <lb/>
having Reciprocity without Confederation? The rºa<lb break="no"/>son was said to be because we cannot afforu to strike <lb/>
£32,000 off our taxes. . It could be had by striking <lb/>
£30,000 a year off official robbery, jobbery und <lb/>
extravagance, The hou. membr, Mr. Shea, says <lb/>
the salaries come to only £32,000 a year, and asks <lb/>
how could £30,000 be strick off thit. But the <lb/>
public expenditure of last year citus to £170,000, <lb/>
and off that tug hol. inemvers of the opposition <lb/>
proposed to strike C30,000, would not the Suving <lb/>
of that sum be preterable to selling the cou try, <lb/>
to deporting 8.J.), luen to work in tile wilds of <lb/>
Canada? The Government was puzzled to know <lb/>
how it could be dune, but at the proper tiune they <lb/>
would be shown how to do it. DJ they <lb/>
increase the taxes when, in other countries <lb/>
the revenue falls short of the expenditure? <lb/>
No. They reduce the expenditure; and that is, <lb/>
ought, and shall be the duty of the Goverument of <lb/>
this coun-ry. By a system of rigid economy they <lb/>
could have reciprocity, and every other, advan <lb/>
tagu, and need not be obliged to surrender the count <lb/>
try into the hands of strangers. Hon. gentlemen <lb/>
ask where is Mr. Howe. He (Mr. R.) was free to <lb/>
admit that that hon. gentleman was the great anti<lb break="no"/>Confederate leader in Nova Scotia. It would appear <lb/>
now that he was President of the Executive Council <lb/>
of the Louinion, but does that show that he had <lb/>
deserted his colors? Nova Scotia was in a differs <lb/>
ent position from ours;she had been solº by her repre: <lb/>
so ſtatives; but he (M. R.) and his colleagu's would <lb/>
take care that lio such thing suould happen here. <lb/>
Uanadian gol.I brought the in jority a rainst Con<lb break="no"/>teleration in the Njya Scotia Assembly down to <lb/>
a minority, and so Coutederation was carried <lb/>
there. Wheu the people saw how air irs stood <lb/>
tney got up huudrels of ºtitions, and sent Mr. <lb/>
Ilove and a delegation to Elzland to represent <lb/>
the true facts of the case. ... second time did Mr. <lb/>
Liowego to Euglaud, but he touild the people <lb/>
there so absurved by the question of Retorm that <lb/>
hu could not get his case fairly heard. IIowe <lb/>
tought the bat.le well, and yielded only when he <lb/>
saw how little the people at hotne, cºlled for <lb/>
Colonial as distinguish irom Imperial interests. <lb/>
The hon. member, Mr. Snea, said it was the desire <lb/>
of the mother country tuat these Colonies shºuld <lb/>
Centederate, all that she knew w.lat was best <lb/>
tor us. IIe KMr. R.) denied it. They were, the <lb/>
best judges of their owd interests, and, hiſ no <lb/>
occasion to reter to those who evidently knew <lb/>
very little about them, and cared les:... It was <lb/>
said that the cry of "bieachin: bou had been <lb/>
abandone i. Was it indeed? That it had it ingº <lb/>
ing was suffixiently proved by the lact that in 1333 <lb/>
tº Canadian Conferiºrites, in pointin: out the ad: <lb/>
vautages of union with the Lºwer Provinces, urged <lb/>
that Newfoundiand would supply 39.099 of the <lb/>
best seamen triat ever trud the deck of 4 in ºu-ºº: <lb/>
wer. Now suppose ineu were reguired, wº <lb/>
it to be supposed that the Newloundit d fisher" <lb/>
inen would be exempted? They would have tº #9, <lb/>
and some of their doues would be bleachi.i.4: <lb/>
A good deal was said about the present ºntº <lb/>
Ju-lice having been lavourable tº Guntederation<lb break="no"/>ife, it was said, cited the cise of the Irish reaper? <lb/>
gºing tº Eagland to reap the baryºt, atlu returl<lb break="no"/>5.ºf hone with money in both poekºs. º 'º' <lb/>
tº Giannel was one thing. It could be done º' <lb/>
a few hours. But Q lebec was 1,000 in is tº: <lb/>
and nº could our ºr ſabourers travel up ** <lb/>
down tº it distance? There was nº anºlº <lb/>
º, ºne cºsts, it was said that after Confederº <lb/>
tº we wºuld have steam, Coastal aud intº <lb/>
provincial and that: wheti labour, º.º.º. <lb/>
fºre, our peºple could go to the 9thºr ºvº. <lb/>
in search of it. They were also told tudº. * <lb/>
Čoned ration the land would flow with, inilk an: <lb/>
home. ii., diſtue two notions stand Pºet. <lb/>
The people were leaving the country; bº.º. <lb/>
wjº tºniº S.ates, and not tº Canal+. <lb/>
Woºij tº be the case if Canada ottered the <lb/></p> 

<p>greater aivaa-ºº: T-\- C...]...::"...n?: as <lb/></p> 

<p>ave, even thºse who corne to Canada from E ig <lb/>
land have frequently to cross the border. The <lb/>
Government saw they did not increase tºle expendi<lb break="no"/>ture. that it was now actually less than in former <lb/>
years. It that be the case, how comes the increas<lb break="no"/>ed tariff of 1833, 1837, and 1868? Surely if the ex<lb break="no"/>penditure was less,there was no reason to increase <lb/>
the tariff. They ask where are our means of <lb/>
giving employment? The public gave to them <lb/>
the largest revenue any Governament here ever had, <lb/>
yet where was there any evidence that that revenue <lb/>
was applied for the beliefit of the people? Let <lb/>
the people exercise their legitimate authority, and <lb/>
return men who will carry out the wishes of the <lb/>
people, and with similar means the people would <lb/>
be made contented and hugpy. <lb/>
The hon. gentleman concluded a lengthy speech <lb/>
by stating that he ai some further remarks to <lb/>
make, which he woull reserve for another <lb/>
occasion. <lb/>
The hom. Colonial Secretary would wish <lb/>
to make an observation with regard to the fuel <lb/>
of the Lunatic Asylum, to the expens of which <lb/>
the hou, member Mr. Renout had adverted. If <lb/>
the hon. member would refer to the journals <lb/>
ſor 1868, he would fi id that the cost of fuel for <lb/>
that year is £200 less than the cost for 1867. <lb/>
In 1867 it was considered advisable to purchase <lb/>
a cargo of coal, a considerable quantity of which <lb/>
remained on hand for 1868, thus lessening the <lb/>
expenses of that year. <lb/>
The Committee then rose, reported progress, <lb/>
and asked leave to sit again. <lb/>
The House then adjourned till to-morrow, at <lb/>
3 o'clock. <lb/></p> -->

<p>TUESDAY, Feb. 16. <lb/></p> 

<p>The House met at three o'clock, pursuant to <lb/>
adjournment. <lb/></p> 

<p>On motion of <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GODDEN</persName>, the House re<lb break="no"/>solved itself into Committee of the Whole on <lb/>
the further consideraion of the address in reply <lb/>
to his Excellency's speech, Mr. KNIGHT in the <lb/>
chair. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LITT3">Mr. LITTLE</persName> thought that too much time had <lb/>
been spent in the discussing a question which in <lb/>
reality was not before the chaur, and that that <lb/>
which really was before the chair had been dis<lb break="no"/>cussed in a manner calculated to distract the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the House, and consume time which <lb/>
ought to be devoted to other purposes. Every <lb/>
species of argument had been used, and a gen<lb break="no"/>eral desise to rush to the front in the cause of <lb/>
Confederation had been exhibited, though that <lb/>
question was not before the House. The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment could not deny but that it was their <lb/>
own supporters who first promoted this unne<lb break="no"/>cessary discussion, which consumed the time <lb/>
and mouey of the country. His (Mr. L's) idea <lb/>
was that the discussion should be confined to <lb/>
each section as it presented itself. The section <lb/>
now under consideration was that which pro<lb break="no"/>posed immediate legislation on the question of <lb/>
Confederation, or at least that the House should <lb/>
now enter into the discussion of that question. <lb/>
He concurred with all his heart in the latter <lb/>
part of the amendment proposed by the hon. <lb/>
member, Mr. Talbo, not only because of his <lb/>
(Mr. L's) pledge to his constituents, but prin<lb break="no"/>cipally because this Legislature was not elected <lb/>
for the purpose of definitely binding the country <lb/>
on the subject of Confederation. Even the hon. <lb/>
and learned leader of the Government himself <lb/>
was not sent here by his constituents with full <lb/>
power to deal with the question. In plain lan<lb break="no"/>guage, he told the people that the matter would <lb/>
be referred to them before any action would be <lb/>
taken on it; and he (Mr. L.) did not doubt but <lb/>
that the hon. and learned geutleman would <lb/>
    keep his promise. In <hi rendition="simple:italic">limine</hi>, the moment assent <lb/>
is given to the principle or a measure and its <lb/>
details are taken up for cousideration, and em<lb break="no"/>bodied in resolutious and passed by this House, <lb/>
from that moment the approval of the country <lb/>
    to that principle becomes a mere <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>. <lb/>
He (Mr. L.) understood that the course pro<lb break="no"/>posed by the Government was to discuss the <lb/>
principle and the terms together, and by a re<lb break="no"/>solution of this House make the acceptance of <lb/>
these terms a solemn act of the Legislature, then <lb/>
to send a delegation to the Government of <lb/>
the Dominion, asking their assent to these <lb/>
terms, and if they be accepted by them, then <lb/>
to dissolve the Legislature and send hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers to their constituencies for approval <lb/>
of their course of action, and not for ac<lb break="no"/>ceptance or rejection of the principle of <lb/>
Confederation. If that be the course <lb/>
by which it is proposed to accomplished a gigan<lb break="no"/>tic scheme, for the amelioration of the country's <lb/>
ils, it is taking a very bad in means for the ac<lb break="no"/>complishment of that end. They were not there <lb/>
to legislate on the question of Coafederation, <lb/>
and he, for oue, was returned to oppose it in <lb/>
the shape in which it was first presented to <lb/>
the country. He would oppose both terms and <lb/>
resolution in the present House, because other<lb break="no"/>wise he would be false to his coustituents. The <lb/>
present Legislature was incapable of dealing <lb/>
with the matter, because it had not been clothed <lb/>
with the necessary powers by the people, who <lb/>
    alone can <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> them. In a matter of this sort <lb/>
be considered that all should act together, sinking <lb/>
all party and personal interests, when the rights <lb/>
    pf <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> government were about to be transferred <lb/>
to strangers, and the dearest interests of the <lb/>
people to be sacrificed. The matter has been <lb/>
    subject of discussion in <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>, House before, and <lb/>
the House had set its face against the principle <lb/>
and the terms, as emploied in the Quebec <lb/>
scheme. That no one could deny. Petitions <lb/>
were presented to this House against the intro<lb break="no"/>duction of that scheme, add yet hon, gentlemen <lb/>
opposite say that the Legislature were empow<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

ered to discuss the principle and to bind the <lb/>
country. Such was not the case. It would be <lb/>
a breach of faith to attempt it, and those who, <lb/>
attempted it will find that the day of reckoning <lb/>
will come, when they will appear before their <lb/>
taskmasters, who will assurelly bring them to <lb/>
account for their faithlessness. He (Mr. L.) <lb/>
would have no reason to four meeting his con<lb break="no"/>stituents, for he would observe his pledge to them, <lb/>
which was that in the first instance the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of Confederation and its term should be, <lb/>
submitted to the people. Should they at <lb/>
the polls declare in favour of it, then <lb/>
he would be happy to carry out their <lb/>
desires to the bast of his ability <lb/>
until then he would vote against both, unless <lb/>
it were made a condition that unless the people <lb/>
adopted them they should not be held to bind <lb/>
the country. He did not regard legislative action <lb/>
    on such a matter as mere lip service or <hi rendition="simple:italic">proformx</hi> <lb/>
work. After passing resolutions as proposed, <lb/>
the question would become ore of man, not of <lb/>
measures. Really the conduct of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment with regard to this matter was sufficient <lb/>
to excite suspicion in the minds of honest men. <lb/>
Wny have they not long ago come down with <lb/>
the proposed terms? Why do they keep them <lb/>
back? Why herald the very shadow of Confe<lb break="no"/>deration with such speeches as had been heard? <lb/>
Why not in these speeches deal with facts in<lb break="no"/>stead of theories? He thought the amend<lb break="no"/>ment before the chair was a very proper one, <lb/>
and woull give it his support, for the reasons <lb/>
which he had already expressed. To these <lb/>
reasons and that opinion he would <lb/>
adhere. He had given his opinion as shortly <lb/>
as he could. He would, so far as his power <lb/>
enabled him, opposs the passing of any resolu<lb break="no"/>tions respecting the principle or term of <lb/>
Confederation, because the matter should first <lb/>
be laid before the people, who knew best what <lb/>
was for their own interest. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:PROW1">Mr. PROWSE</persName> had much pleasure in listening <lb/>
to the hon. and learned member who had just <lb/>
<choice><sic>sooken</sic><corr>spoken</corr></choice>, though he (Mr. P.) differed with his <lb/>
views. He (Mr. P.) considered that the whole <lb/>
question of Confederation rested on the terms. <lb/>
Hon. gentlemen opposite, and all blessed with <lb/>
the highest and most gifted minds, admitted that <lb/>
the principle was one which could not be gain<lb break="no"/>said. There was no man would go so far as to <lb/>
say we would not have Confederation on any terms. <lb/>
To go to the bustings with the naked question <lb/>
of principle would have no meaning, but to go <lb/>
with the principle accompanied by the terms <lb/>
was what they could very easily understand. He <lb/>
agreed with the hon. and learned member for <lb/>
Harbor Main that the people should decide the <lb/>
question for themselves. How could the terms <lb/>
be placed before them? These must first be <lb/>
discussed and agreed to; and they ought to be <lb/>
agreed to by every member in the House. He <lb/>
(Mr. P.) considered that the terms should be <lb/>
fair and equitable, and suited to tax interests of <lb/>
the Colony. It would also have to be considered <lb/>
whether they would be accepted by the <lb/>
Dominion Government. If they were, then <lb/>
they would be submitted to the people. If they <lb/>
do not accept them then they fall to the ground; <lb/>
but if they do accept them, then both this Legis<lb break="no"/>lature and that of the Dominion will have to <lb/>
address the Queen in Council praying Her ap<lb break="no"/>proval of the matter. The hon. and learned <lb/>
member for Harbor Main said that the couduct <lb/>
of the Government was calculated to excite <lb/>
suspicion. He (Mr. P.) considered that the <lb/>
conduct of the Governmentt had been all through <lb/>
as fair and open and above board as it could <lb/>
possibly be. The hon. gentleman did not say <lb/>
in what way their conduct was suspicious. Had <lb/>
they accelerated or pushed on the question, or <lb/>
forced it in any way? He (Mr. P.) had noth<lb break="no"/>ing to do with the Government, and merely gave <lb/>
his own opinions on the course of events, as <lb/>
any other independant member would. The <lb/>
Government looked on the matter as a most, <lb/>
grave and important one, and they proceeded <lb/>
slowly and calmly with it, just as it should be. <lb/>
He supposed that in due time the terms would <lb/>
be brought down. They could then be discussed <lb/>
        and criticised and <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>, There was a time <lb/>
when Confederation was a small child in the <lb/>
House, and when it had a great <lb/>
many enemies quite ready to strangle it, but <lb/>
now it had grown up and acquired considerable <lb/>
strength, and those who before tried to strangle <lb/>
it are glad to help it along. He (Mr. P.) <lb/>
could recollect when the majority against Con<lb break="no"/>federation, both inside and outside of the House, <lb/>
was very large, but the majority was even larger <lb/>
the other way now. This was too important a <lb/>
question for mere tricks of party, and it was <lb/>
criminal for any man to be politically dishonest <lb/>
about it. He had placed his views on record in <lb/>
1895, and to these views he still adhered. He <lb/>
then believed that as the majority was so large <lb/>
against it, it would be a long time before it was <lb/>
settled. However, he now believed that the <lb/>
time to settle it had come. He ageed with <lb/>
the hon. and learned member for Harbor Main, <lb/>
that this House could not make any final settle<lb break="no"/>ment respecting the terms. That was the province <lb/>
of the people and a proviso to that effect should <lb/>
be inserted in the resolutions. He (Mr. P.) <lb/>
did not like to see the unfair way in which this <lb/>
question of Confederation was dealt with, both <lb/>
inside and outside of the House. Every man <lb/>
who speaks in favor of Confederation had again <lb/>
and again to fight against some exploded idea or <lb/>
other. The "bleaching bones" idea was so far <lb/>
gone that even the great head centre of Con<lb break="no"/>federation distained to use it any more. The <lb/>
    </p> 

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>


<p>Union of Ireland was also brought forward in <lb/>
eloquent terms, what possible contestion was <lb/>
there between the Union of Ireland and this <lb/>
guestion of Confederation? Hon. gentlemen <lb/>
knew very well that it had none, and it was <lb/>
cowardly, mean and dastardly thus to appeal to <lb/>
the passions and prejudices of the people. His <lb/>
District had suffered a great deal by the with<lb break="no"/>drawal of local steam, The withdrawal, how<lb break="no"/>ever was unavoidable, for in the present condi<lb break="no"/>tion of the colony the subsidy could not be afford<lb break="no"/>ed. He thought that local steam shoull be a <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine Qua Non</hi> of Confederation. They would <lb/>
then have something better than the dirty tub <lb/>
they used to have, and would also have better <lb/>
than the present tub in Conception Bay. He <lb/>
knew that the hon. member for St. John's had <lb/>
tried and were trying to stir up a feeling against <lb/>
confederation, but he believed that his (Mr. P's) <lb/>
constituents were favorable to it on good terms. <lb/>
He hoped these good terms would be got, and <lb/>
that if not none other would be accepted. He <lb/>
had often in that House tried to procure the <lb/>
erection of a Light House in his district, but <lb/>
had failed. Last summer representations on the <lb/>
matter were made to the Dominion Government <lb/>
and without hesitation they sent down a steamer, <lb/>
had a survey held and the site agreed on, and <lb/>
the building will commence at once. There was <lb/>
earnest of one of the benefits of Confederation. <lb/>
The speeches on this question were so long that <lb/>
the subject was nearly worn threadbare, but <lb/>
there was one important matter which was <lb/>
only slightly, if at all glanced at. That was <lb/>
the power given to the Dominion Parliament to <lb/>
negotiate commercial treaties, which would <lb/>
aftect this country in the matters of the French <lb/>
shore and the Spanish trade. He had been <lb/>
told that the Dominion was endeavoring to es<lb break="no"/>tablish a free trade with the Spanish West <lb/>
India Islands, and that it will be accomplished <lb/>
so soon as the affairs of Spain are settled. New<lb break="no"/>foundland had a very great interest in that <lb/>
matter. The differential duty against foreign flags <lb/>
had operated very prejudicially to our interests. <lb/>
This duty had been the means of prohibiting our <lb/>
fish being carried in English bottoms to Spain, <lb/>
and it had been maintained by the interest <lb/>
which a few Mediterranean ship-owners pos<lb break="no"/>sessed at the Cortes. With the new Govern<lb break="no"/>ment the flag duty would be taken away, and our <lb/>
commercial relations with Spain would, through <lb/>
the influence of the Dominion be placed upon a <lb/>
much fairer footing than at present. It was of <lb/>
the greatest possible importance to us that our <lb/>
interests should be represented at Madrid. The <lb/>
produce of Sweden, and Holland had, through <lb/>
the influence of their respective Ministers, been <lb/>
brought into great demand in the Spanish <lb/>
market. Spain consumed annually 900,000qds. <lb/>
of codfish, and of this we did not send them one-<lb break="yes"/>fourth, hiring been cut out by the Swedish <lb/>
fish. Petitions and memorials sent year after <lb/>
year to the Colonial office had all proved una<lb break="no"/>vailing to remove the invidious obstacles against <lb/>
which we had to contend, and our only chance <lb/>
of success lay in the power conferred upon the <lb/>
Dominion, of making commercial treaties and <lb/>
sending an accredited minister to these Courts. <lb/>
He (Mr. P.) had referred to this point because <lb/>
he knew something of it personally. He trust<lb break="no"/>ed when the real question came down, the terms <lb/>
    and <hi rendition="simple:italic">bona fide</hi> conditions of Confederation, they <lb/>
will receive that calm and dispassionate consi<lb break="no"/>deration to which they were entitled. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The hon. <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">COLONIAL SECRETARY</persName> should have <lb/>
taken no part in the debate, did he not consider <lb/>
it the duty of every hon member to express his <lb/>
opinions on the important matters, before the <lb/>
chair. For his (hon C. S's) part, he was tied <lb/>
by no pledges, but felt himself perfectly free to <lb/>
deal with the question of Confederation and to <lb/>
give publicity to the views which he had <lb/>
always held. When the question was first <lb/>
brought into notice, though we had a genial tariff <lb/>
and everything in our favour, he had been of <lb/>
opinion that we could not ally ourselves to the <lb/>
neighbouring Colonies without being benefitted. <lb/>
He had regarded Newfoundland as a poor family <lb/>
invited to cast in her lot with half a dozen <lb/>
families in comfortable circumstances, and he <lb/>
had been persuaded that such a union could not <lb/>
but rebound to her advantage. In 1865 he had <lb/>
before his constituents avowed his sentiments, <lb/>
and he had told them that whenever the question <lb/>
came up for consideration he would vote in <lb/>
favour of it. If then they had disapproved of <lb/>
his sentiments they need not have elected him. <lb/>
He should now vote in favour of the Address, and <lb/>
if in this he was running counter to the opinions <lb/>
of his district they were perfectly free to elect <lb/> 
another man. We could not but regard this <lb/>
quastion of union as one fraught with impor<lb break="no"/>tance, as it must affect the weal or woe of the <lb/>
country for all time to come. The settlement <lb/>
of the matter could not without prejudice to the <lb/>
community be longer delayed. Delay would <lb/>
not only be cowardly but suicidal as, regarded <lb/>
the interests of the Country and those who <lb/>
were charged with the protection of those inter<lb break="no"/>ests. He believed the country demanded a <lb/>
decision at the hands of this House, and that <lb/>
seven-tenths of the people of the Island were in <lb/>
favour of a change. Should then that change be <lb/>
such as would continue us in our present posi<lb break="no"/>tion as a miserable fishing dependency? Or <lb/>
should it be such as would unite us with a <lb/>
Dominion growing in wealth and importance <lb/>
every day? With reference to the subject of <lb/>
Reciprocity, though every hon. member admitted <lb/>
its advantges, there was a variety of opinions. <lb/>
Hon gentlemen on this side agreed with his <lb/>
Excellency, that separated from the Dominion <lb/>
we should be in no position to ensure to our<lb break="no"/>selves the benefits of reciprocal free trade, while <lb/>
hon. gentlemen opposite contended that Reci<lb break="no"/>procity might be brought about by a reduction <lb/>
of the civil expenditure. With this latter view <lb/>
he (hon, C.S.), could not concur. Wherever <lb/>
there was a useless expenditure or a useless <lb/>
office let it be removed. Bu, retrench as we <lb/>
might he considered it, utterly impossible to <lb/>
obtain all the benefits from such a policy as <lb/>
    
    <cb/>
        
hon. members opposite contemplated, and though <lb/>
these benefits might be obtained, he considered <lb/>
that they would bear no comparison to those <lb/>
growing out of confederation. He (hon. C. S.) <lb/>
had understood the hon. member, Mr. Little, to <lb/>
say that it was the intention of the Government <lb/>
to adopt by resolution the saction of this colony <lb/>
to the terms of Confederation. He (hon. C. S.) <lb/>
did not understaad it so. If this were so the <lb/>
question would be definitely settled. The <lb/>
measure could not be tested at the general <lb/>
election and the election, would be a question <lb/>
not of measures but of men. The hon. member <lb/>
was throwing dust in the eyes of his coustituency, <lb/>
and endeavouring to shirk the responsibility <lb/>
which was incumbent upon him, leaving himself <lb/>
free to accept Confederation as a foregone con<lb break="no"/>clusion, while it was in reality undecided and he <lb/>
might in honesty oppose it. He (hon. C. S.) <lb/>
considered that the time had arrived when we <lb/>
should act like rational creatures. We could <lb/>
not remain blind to the decleusion of the means <lb/>
of employment and deaf to the appeals of misery <lb/>
and distress. The resources on which the <lb/>
people had trusted did not keep pace with the <lb/>
increase of population. He did not mean to <lb/>
say that Confederation would have the effect of <lb/>
bringing fish to our shores, but he regarded it as <lb/>
a means to an end, and that end the gradual but <lb/>
unceasing and certain improvement of the con<lb break="no"/>dition of the country. It would be needless for <lb/>
him to express in detail his views upon this sub<lb break="no"/>ject, for abler hands had already dealt with it in <lb/>
all its bearings. He hoped that the terms to <lb/>
which this House would assant would be such <lb/>
as would prove advantageous to the country, <lb/>
that there would be no difficulty in obtaining <lb/>
their appoval at the hands of the General Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, and that before long Newfoundland <lb/>
would be an integral part of the Confederacy. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName>.—Hon. members opposite seemed to <lb/>
be trying to educate the people on the subject of <lb/>
Confederation, before the terms came down. He <lb/>
only rose to make a remark upon the speech of the <lb/>
hon. Reciever General, which was a very able and <lb/>
argumentative speech. But the hon, gentleman had <lb/>
stated matters which were not facts, tending to delude <lb/>
the people. This statement could not arise from <lb/>
the ignorance of the hon. gettleman. If the state<lb break="no"/>ment had come from the hon. member, Mr. Pinsent, <lb/>
he (Mr. G.) would not have taken the slightest <lb/>
        notice of it, for he did not consider that that hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman was quite <hi rendition="simple:italic">au fait</hi> at figures. The hon. Re<lb break="no"/>ceiver General had stated that our expenditure <lb/>
under Confederation would be $315,000 and the <lb/>
grant from the Dominion $416,000, so that $100,000 <lb/>
would annually be left for roads. Now the Domini<lb break="no"/>on did not grant us $416,000, so the fact stated was <lb/>
not correct. The amount of the Dominion subsidy <lb/>
was $369,000, so that there was a difference of <lb/>
$47,000 against the Colony. That statement of the <lb/>
hon. gantleman had gone, forth to the world, had <lb/>
been extensively read, and coming forth with the <lb/>
prestige of his high character, it must have taken <lb/>
effect. The hon. gentleman should have been more <lb/>
guarded. If the Confederate cause were a good <lb/>
one, it would not require misstatements to support <lb/>
it. The hon, member, Mr. Pinsent, seemed to be <lb/>
trimming his wings for a flight to Ottawa, and when <lb/>
bye and bye the ugly rush for situations came (for <lb/>
there would be an ugly rush), the hon. member if he <lb/>
failed in getting a high legal position as Attorney <lb/>
General or Solicitor General, after the display <lb/>
which he had made the other day, would be fully <lb/>
justified in looking for the post of Finance Minister. <lb/>
He (M.G.) had stated a few days ago that the <lb/>
Dominion was in difficulties, and that to save them<lb break="no"/>selves from insolveccy, they had to issue $5,000,000 <lb/>
in Treasury notes. The hon. member, Mr. Rendell, <lb/>
had said that that could not be, as their debentures <lb/>
were at a premium in London. The hon. member <lb/>
should recollect that at that time parties in England <lb/>
could not get more than 1.5 per cent. for their money, <lb/>
on account of the excessive supply of gold. Suppose <lb/>
the Dominion Government had thrown this $5,000,<lb break="no"/>000 of debentures into the London market, would <lb/>
they have been saleable? Certainly not. The <lb/>
Dominion Government were just as insolvent as our <lb/>
own Government. These Treasury notes would have <lb/>
to be called in, and a crash would come. Though <lb/>
they were a Government of great abilities, they were <lb/>
a reckless Government. He (Mr. G.) could not <lb/>
see the expediency of one bankrupt Government <lb/>
going into partnership with another. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The Hon. <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">RECIEVER GENERAL</persName> maintained the <lb/>
accuracy of his statement. The subsidy of the Dom<lb break="no"/>minion Government would amount to $416,500 and <lb/>
under the Resolutions which were to be brought in, <lb/>
the Government would look for a yet larger grant. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
            <persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName>.—The Dominion Government deducts <lb/>
the interest on the debt from the subsidy. <lb/></p>
            
    <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. RECIEVER GENERAL</persName>.—Yes, but that I have <lb/>
charged under the expenditure. He (hon. R.G.) <lb/>
was amused by the anxiety of hon. members oppo<lb break="no"/>site. In Nova Scotia Confederation was carried <lb/>
without an appeal to the constituencies. In New<lb break="no"/>foundland the Legislature are determined that the <lb/>
constituencies shall be consulted, and because the <lb/>
very conditions which were denied to Nova Scotia <lb/>
are granted to Newfoundland, Newfoundland, <lb/>
forsooth, is the most aggrieved country in the world. <lb/>
He was astonished to hear the hon. member, Mr <lb/>
Little, talk of legislating upon Confederation. A sim<lb break="no"/>ple resolutions is not legislation, as legislation requires <lb/>
the concurrence of the three estates of Parliament. <lb/>
We pass resolutions expanatory of the details upon <lb/>
which we would recommend the constituencies to <lb/>
accept the Union, and after having these conditions <lb/>
assented to by the General Government, we go to <lb/>
the constituencies and say "Look calmly into the <lb/>
question, see the condition of the country and say <lb/>
whether or not we shall remain as we are: if so, <lb/>
sweep from the bustings of those men who have ill-<lb break="yes"/>advised yet, but if you cousider they are honest <lb/>
adopt these terms and go into the Union." Hon. <lb/>
members opposite were throwing dust in the eyes of <lb/>
    there constituents, and if they could succeed in <lb/> 
getting into power, they would carry out the measure <lb/>
if Confederation. That was the meaning of the <lb/>
phrase, "men and not measures." He was perfectly <lb/>
astonished at the hon. member, Mr. Glen, saying <lb/>
that he (hon. R.G.) was guilty of acts to delude <lb/>
the people. He was here to instruct the people as <lb/>
far as his powers and his position went, and when <lb/>
    he went before his constituents, if they disapproved <lb/>
of him, they could reject him, and end his political <lb/>
influence. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
<persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName> contended that the figures of the hon <lb/>
Receiver General were false, and that the hon <lb/>
member, Mr. Glen, was correct. The hon. member <lb/>
had said we would have to provide $315,000 <lb/>
for various services. He (Mr. R.) held in his <lb/>
hand a statement which proved that we should have <lb/>
to provide $360,000. Here was an error of$45,000. <lb/>
The Miscellaneous expensiture under Confederation, <lb/>
        instead of $3,000, the amount assumed by the hon. <lb/>
        
        <cb/>

Receiver General, could not amount to less than <lb/>
$37,000; for provision for coastal steam would <lb/>
have to be made. He denied that the hon. Re<lb break="no"/>ciever General represented the views of his con<lb break="no"/>stituants or of the Roman Catholic population. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The hon. <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">RECIEVER GENERAL</persName> said, that the best <lb/>
reply to this remark was a letter he had received <lb/>
from the Right Revd. Dr. Mullock, which he read <lb/>
        as follows— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"My dear Mr. Kent, I was delighted with your <lb/>
    speech in to-day's <hi rendition="simple:italic">Newfoundlander</hi>. It is argumen<lb break="no"/>tative, convincing, and will do a great deal of good. <lb/>
Praying for God continue you in good health. <lb/></p>
    
    <p rendition="simple:centre">
I remain, yours sincerely, <lb/></p>
    <p rendition="simple:right">
J. T. AltJLLOCK. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>The hon. John Kent. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName>.—Hon. gentlemen, on this side <lb/>
had the highest regard for Dr.Mullock, but this <lb/>
was a matter which should be left to the people. <lb/>
Hon. members on this side had fought the batle <lb/>
of the people through good and through evil <lb/>
report, and as long as they had the honor of <lb/>
occupying seats in the House, they would repre<lb break="no"/>sent their districts independent of any influence. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREN1">Mr. BRENNAN</persName>.—There was a great deal of <lb/>
conflicting opinions about Confederation. £700 <lb/>
worth of potatoes would cause the people of St. <lb/>
Mary's Bay to be independent, instead of pay<lb break="no"/>ing it to a Geologist. Where was the property <lb/>
discovered by that Geologist? Not the full of <lb/>
his (Mr. B's) fist. There was plenty of flags <lb/>
which ought to be used for drains about Torbay. <lb/>
The pipes cost a great deal of money, that came <lb/>
from across the Atlantic Ocean. A gentleman <lb/>
said to him (Mr. B.) that they were a great <lb/>
deal cheaper than the square drain. "Are <lb/>
they?" said he (Mr. B.), "Oh yes," said the <lb/>
gentleman "that is what they have in London." <lb/>
"Are you going to tell me" said he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
"that they are cheaper when the money goes <lb/>
across the ocean and will never return." <lb/>
Whereas, if the money was spent in time country <lb/>
it would be like a weaver's shuttle, no sooner <lb/>
out of one hand than into the other. Have the <lb/>
flags at each side, lay it and cover it with three <lb/>
feet of earth, and it will last as long as the <lb/>
South Side hill. Our people were not here <lb/>
accustomed to heavy labour. The Rilway <lb/>
work in Canada was tha hardest work that <lb/>
could be. He considered that annexation would <lb/>
be more beneficial to Newfoundland as far <lb/>
as its encouragement of labour was concerned, <lb/>
than Confederation. <lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:KEAR1">Mr. KEARNEY</persName> considered the subject before <lb/>
the chair was the most important that <lb/>
could come before this House. It was <lb/>
well known that he was returned to this <lb/>
House pledged to oppose Confederation. <lb/>
In case, however, the government, intended <lb/>
sending delegates to Canada, to adjust to <lb/>
terms of Confederation, he hoped they would <lb/>
not forget this side of the House. The hon. <lb/>
member then referred at considerable length to <lb/>
the supply system, and the detrimental effects <lb/>
produced by the fishermen being compelled to <lb/>
sell their fish green, for food. He referred to <lb/>
some cases of extortion. He drew particular <lb/>
attention to the great want and poverty that ex<lb break="no"/>isted among the people, and appealed to the <lb/>
government not to allow the people to starve. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName> thought that he had said every<lb break="no"/>thing that was necessary upon the paragraph <lb/>
before the chair, and the amendment which had <lb/>
been proposed. It appeared, however, that the <lb/>
hon. Receiver General had been hatching an <lb/>
egg, and wanted to lay it. He (Mr. H.) had <lb/>
been told that the Hon. Receiver General had <lb/>
flung a letter in the faces of the oppositions <lb/>
which he alleged he had received from the Right <lb/>
Rev. Dr. Mullock. Now he (Mr. H) could <lb/>
not see why that Right Revd. Prelate's name <lb/>
should be dragged bafore this House, and used <lb/>
as a means of itimidating and controlling that <lb/>
independance of action which this side of the <lb/>
House possesses. Did the hon Receiver General <lb/>
think to whip us into line by a letter of that <lb/>
description? Did we see any Protestant gen<lb break="no"/>tleman in this House dragging in his Bishop's <lb/>
name before the House, and making it the sub<lb break="no"/>ject of debate? Why, the very fact of so violat<lb break="no"/>ing the pivacy of that communication shows <lb/>
that the hon. Receiver General would, if it suited <lb/>
his purpose, betray Dr. Mullock to-morrow. <lb/>
The hon Receiver General had received that <lb/>
letter in compliment to the speech which he de<lb break="no"/>livered, and he now hurls it before this House <lb/>
as an evidance that he was the champion of the <lb/>
Catholic interests of this country. Why, the hon <lb/>
Receiver General killed more Catholics, and <lb/>
is answerable for more Catholic blood than <lb/>
any man that ever stepped upou our shores. <lb/>
II6 drags his Bishop's name, now before this <lb/>
House to be the scoffing and sport of those <lb/>
who did not agree with him in his religious <lb/>
views, in order to cover his own insolence and <lb/>
cowardice. There was one Bishop in this country <lb/>
if his faith, who had given the hon Receiver <lb/>
General character and standing in the com<lb break="no"/>munity, and yet he ungratefully abused him. <lb/>
How often had he (Mr. H.) heard him wag <lb/>
his tongue against his Bishop? Why if the <lb/>
Right Revd. Dr. Mullock associated with the <lb/>
Receiver General, he would lower his position <lb/>
and do injury to his sacred character. The oppo<lb break="no"/>sition knew their Bishop and respected him, and <lb/>
when he was attacked they would defend him. <lb/>
They would not go behind his back to <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
him. If he (Mr. H.) thought proper to show <lb/>
when the Receiver General forget he was a Catho<lb break="no"/>lic and a Christian. He (Mr. H.) warned him <lb/>
not again to drag the name of that exalted <lb/>
individual before this House. It was only <lb/>
cowards and knaves who would do such a thing. <lb/>
He (Mr. H.) had got up merely to give ex<lb break="no"/>pression is these views. Let him go and put <lb/>
his head in a padding bag, forswear politics; <lb/>
and do penance for the wrongs that he had done <lb/>
that great and good man, his Bishop, and the <lb/>
insult he had ordered to every Roman Catholic <lb/>
from Cape John to Cape Ray. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The paragraph was then adopted. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
On motion of <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GODDEN</persName>, the Committee <lb/>
then rose, and the Chairman reported that the <lb/>
Committee had passed the address without <lb/>
    amendment <lb/></p> 

<cb/>

<p>On motion that the said report be received <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:PARS1">Mr. PARSONS</persName> moved and <persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName> seconded <lb/>
    the following amendment to the second para<lb break="no"/>graph of the address:— <lb/></p>
    
    <p>While we admit the necessity for the large <lb/>
outlay under the head of relief of the able bodied <lb/>
poor, we cannot refrain from expressing our dis<lb break="no"/>approval of the injudicious mode in which such <lb/>
outlay was effected, and our regret, that no <lb/>
remedial measures had been adopted by the <lb/>
Government to relieve the evils accruing to the <lb/>
poor from its stoppage. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        The amendment was put and lost on a divi<lb break="no"/>sion,—Yeahs, Messrs Glen, Hogsett, Parsons, <lb/>
Brennan, Kearney, Little, Talbot, Major <lb/>
Renouf; Nays—Hons Attorney General <lb/>
Colonial Secretary, Receiver General, A. Shea, <lb/>
the Surveyor General, Mesrs Randell, Knight, <lb/>
Burton, Oakley, Evans, Barnett, Prowse <lb/>
Pinsent, Barron. O'Rielly, Green, Goddeu <lb/>
Kavanagh. <lb/></p>
        
        <p><persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName> then moved in amendment <lb/>
seconded, by <persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr. TALBOT</persName>, that the fourth <lb/>
            paragraph be expunged and the following sub<lb break="no"/>stituted in lieu thereof:— <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
In reference to the French shore question, <lb/>
we fail to discover in your Excelleusy's speech <lb/>
any thing that relievs this important matter <lb/>
from the difficulties which surrounded it on <lb/>
the occasion of the address of the Legislature <lb/>
in the past session; and whilst we recognise <lb/>
your Excellency's conduct in a desire to bring <lb/>
this subject to a satisfactory conclusion, we <lb/>
cannot but regret that no reply has been <lb/>
made to the resolutions and petitions of this <lb/>
Legislature, and that the policy indicated in <lb/>
Lord Carnarvon's despatch of the 7th De<lb break="no"/>cember, 1866, is approved of by the late <lb/>
Secretary of State for the Colonies. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The amendment was put and lost on a <lb/>
similar division to the foregoing. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr. TALBOT</persName> then moved, in amendment, <lb/>
        seconded by <persName ref="pers:RENO1">Major Renouf</persName>, that the sixth para<lb break="no"/>graph be expunged, and the following substitut<lb break="no"/>ed in lieu thereof:— <lb/></p>
    
    <p>With regard to the question of Confederation, <lb/>
we beg respectfully to observe that the only <lb/>
scheme having reference to this matter which <lb/>
has been submitted to our consideration with <lb/>
that known by this name of the Qeubec Resolu<lb break="no"/>tions, and that scheme has already been rejected <lb/>
by the Legislature and the country; and we <lb/>
further take leave to express to your Excelleney <lb/>
our conviction and desire that a subject of <lb/>
such vital importance to the liberties of the <lb/>
country should be submitted to the decision <lb/>
of the people at the polls, before any further <lb/>
action be taken upon it by the Legislature. <lb/></p>
        
        <p>
The amendment was put and lost, on a <lb/>
similar division to the foregoing. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>The original motion was then put and <lb/>
carried. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>Ordered that the address be read a third <lb/>
time to-morrow. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The House than adjourned till to-morrow, <lb/>
at 3 o'clock. <lb/></p> 


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-17, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

<!--<p>WEDNEsday, Feb. 17 <lb/>
The House met at 3 o'clock. <lb/>
Öº mºon of Mr. &amp; poss, pursus it tº or r <lb/>
of the day, the address to his Excelle ov, tº Gº: <lb/>
ernor, in reply to his speech at the ope i zºol th9 <lb/>
session, was read a third tilt- ar.d allop.e. 1, as <lb/>
follows:<lb break="no"/>To His Excellency Anthony Musgrave Bººgoº, <lb/>
and commºdºr in-chief.ii and our the Island <lb/>
of Newfoundlani and its Devendencies. <lb/></p> 

<p>MAY IT Prºasiſ. Youtt ExCELLENCY,­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ºve, the Commonstionse of Assem ly of N-wfoun!" <lb/>
land, beg to thank Your Excellency for the grºcioli <lb/>
Speech with which you have been pleased to opst <lb/>
the present Session of the Legislature, an 1 for the <lb/>
uniform cºurtesy which has marked your intercouris <lb/>
with the House of Assembly during your Adminºr" <lb/>
tion of the Government. <lb/>
We fully approve of the course taken by tº <lb/>
Executive Gºvernment in issuisg the Proclamation in <lb/>
June last, that relief in future would be confinal tº <lb/>
destitute widows and orphans, and to the sick anº <lb/>
infirm poor. We believe this act was well tuned, and <lb/>
we cordially hope and trust that the Executive ºf <lb/>
be successful in its efforts to suppress the demoral" <lb/>
ing systeum of able-bodied pauper relief. <lb/>
Wé thank You Bºilency'ſor the promise tº <lb/>
the Public accounts for the year 1863, will be short" <lb/>
laid before us, <lb break="no"/>We are pleased to learn that Your Excellancy's <lb/>
personal exertions in endeavoraing, to settle º <lb/>
vexed question of the French Shore, lave been sofar <lb/>
successful that there is now a prospact of its bº <lb/>
arranged in a manner advantageous to boº, Pº <lb/>
intºed in it, and that the policy indicated in ſº <lb/>
Carnarvon's despatch of 7th December, 186% º <lb/>
been so far modified that Your Excelleucy will nº": <lb/>
be enabled to issue Grants unier certain rºº riºt" <lb/>
for Mining and other purposes in that logºſity. <lb/>
The new statutory provisions which Your Excal. <lb/>
lency suggests, with regard to Licenses for Out", <lb/>
Timber, guill receive our careful atten ion. <lb/>
We fully concur with Your Excellency tha' tº <lb/>
time has now arrived for us to take action on tº <lb/></p> 

<p>great question of Confederation; and we can *. <lb/>
ºcellency that we shall give our ear" <lb/>
attention to the consideration of or Union with ºf <lb/>
j, of Canada, or such fir and equº; <lb/>
terms as may be cateuiated to serve the intereº <lb/>
the Colony, be approve i of by the Govern cent of this <lb/>
Dominion, and which we trust may prove acceptable <lb/>
ºil classes of the people, when "submitted ºf <lb/>
jail."...iº, the final approval <lb/>
and ratification of Her Majesty. <lb break="no"/>The contract entered intº by Your Excellº, <lb/>
with Riessrs. Inman &amp; Co., for the Conveya" o! <lb/>
the Miº, between St. John's and Hallax, his hº <lb/>
º, a carried out in a satisfactory.manner. Thº." <lb/>
arrangement with regard to the detention. of the <lb/>
stºriº St. John's has been a great conve?".] <lb/>
... ºi...ºft. Bºtºre admirably inited" <lb/></p> 

<p>f <lb/></p> 

<p>ºn that the address be presented tº * <lb/>
E. ºriency the Governor by the speaker and * <lb/>
whole House. -<lb break="maybe"/>ºn Arrowser General informed." <lb/>
Hºuse that his Excellency would receiyo." <lb/>
speaker and the wuole House with the addre" 05: <lb/>
Friday next, at 12 o'clock. <lb/>
†ng House thea ajjurited until Friday, at it. <lb/></p> 

<p>u'clock. A. M. <lb/></p> 

<p>- Fardar, Feb. 19<lb break="no"/>The House met at 11 o'clock, A. M. <lb break="no"/>At 12 º'clock the SPzazzº aud the whole . <lb/>
House proceeded to Government House... <lb/>
presented to his Excellengy the address." reply; <lb/>
to his opening speech, and being returned, <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>instead of $3,000, the ambie assuagd by the hoà. <lb/></p> 

<p>anaudan int. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºnformed the House that while º i <lb/></p> 

<p>* <lb/></p> 

<p>nce on his Excellency. the <lb/>
a º: House, he had pres <lb/>
jiency the aid. of thanks, is <lb/>
£xcelleney the made the follºwing <lb/>
Mr. Speaker º; Gentlemen of the a <lb/>
of Assembly. - <lb break="no"/>I receive your 'Address with much g <lb/>
am glad to be assured of approval oft <lb/>
by the Governº with regari to th <lb/>
nºtifying that G ment refief woul <lb/>
ºnfined to destitue widows and epha: <lb/>
and infirm poº. I am satisfied that s <lb/>
to this course is essential to the future <lb/>
the wholo community. it is the intere <lb/>
the duty, of all those who can render <lb/>
more necessitous of their fellow citizº <lb/>
...it the Government in their eſt. <lb/>
§ºlony of the vicious system which <lb/>
aralyzed all healthy energy. and so #. <lb/>
# prºdence among large numbers of it <lb/>
er Majesty's Government will lear <lb/>
tion that yºu are prepared to take, <lb/>
question of Uniºn with the Dominiu <lb/>
ºnd I have no doubt that Pºu will be <lb/>
sº terms of arrangement for tºpuſ. <lb/>
acceptable to the Government of the #2 <lb/>
ºnatºrially conducive to the interests of <lb/>
In this case the good sense of, the cºnſ. <lb/>
scarcely permit them to withold the <lb/>
such an arrangement; and its ratific <lb/>
Majesty may confidently be an icipate. <lb/>
Mr. Hyatt asked and ob lea <lb/>
for the remainder of the sessiº: <lb/>
The Hon. AtroſtNky G&amp;Sºłat. <lb/>
was sure that all had heard, with º: <lb/>
melancholy intelligeneº which had Î <lb/>
ceived,et the death of the H ºn. J AM <lb/>
All who knew him respected him. <lb/>
sº long time engaged in the busiuess <lb/>
and perhaps no where would his 1. <lb/>
ãº tº than in the locality whe <lb/>
S. res.ded. He had for many. Yº <lb/>
high public position, as * Legislativ <lb/>
and i. strict attention to his duties: <lb/>
the approbation of all liº (hou. A. <lb/>
that this House would testify its rest <lb/>
for his ºmily, by adjourning <lb/>
He therefore uoved that the 1 <lb/>
ru, out of respect to the me not <lb/>
L. C., of whose <lb/>
tºs ºust been received, and in token <lb/>
esteem in which the ºeuºsºl jº <lb/>
iºd, ºud of the sympathy ſult by tie<lb break="no"/>his widow and family. <lb/>
Mr. Gies begged to second the <lb/>
1a non, Mr. Corinaek was a wºrk!' <lb/>
ºne whose lyss we must all deeply dº <lb/>
was but right that we siloui i thus i <lb/>
merits, and gay a triuute of respect <lb/>
tº ºry. <lb/>
T.s Hoa, Reservkº GENERAL <lb/>
plºts, d to see unsuºpºsiº" <lb/>
fouse to respect the tilemury ºf a gº <lb/>
had been alike all honor to his nº <lb/>
adopted country, in every relation 0: <lb/>
is "had beam placeu. He hºl <lb/>
honorable merchant, and had <lb/>
service to the people of , the <lb/>
which he had so loug resided, a <lb/>
a large columercial business. <lb/>
ais worth was well known, util...h6 <lb/>
fºrt and happiness anongst all a <lb/>
whom h9 would now be deeply. In <lb/>
political sphere lic had discarged tº <lb/>
tagly to himself. Ile (hon. Rºº..." <lb/>
self fast approaching the ", Herº inſi <lb/>
and thus he the mºre dueply lult til <lb/>
which the country Hul sustained, lº <lb/>
public inau and a good titº, winil. <lb/>
injuried the loss of a valued ind, ºt <lb/>
Mr. Hogsgrº fully participated in <lb/>
of nom, geuileiau. The duº of su <lb/>
ºne nor. James Gormack was a lo <lb/>
community at large lºl. <lb break="no"/>Mr. Fissºst migh, under ordid <lb/>
stances, not have given woº <lb/>
to clings which mig 't be *w <lb/>
'by slence, particularly *, * <lb/>
iſ which agº. gentlemen who had <lb/>
referred to the deceased gettle's <lb/>
had poculiar reasons for uut alloy <lb/>
sion to pass without exprº re! <lb/>
part to one, the rocollection of: <lb/>
associated with his earliest years, <lb/>
had ever possessed a warm it <lb/>
regard, and who, besides th; as <lb/>
private life, had been tor souey." <lb/>
ſue.mber in the cº-ordinate braudu <lb/>
lature, the Legislative Council, <lb/>
could therefore speak of the develº <lb/>
tleman, in both his public and priº <lb/>
of lite, from intim tº experience. <lb/>
ed both most worthily,and his gen <lb/>
urbane mauners, and liveral j <lb/>
him endeared and respected by all <lb/>
pleasure of his acqua at incº: For ti <lb/>
he (Mr. P.) could not do othº". <lb/>
open expressiou to his sympathy <lb/>
gºntinº, family, and public * <lb/>
memory of the deceased.: <lb/>
The House than adjourned unti <lb/>
3 o'clock, <lb/></p> 

<p>Mox DAY <lb/></p> 

<p>The IIouse met, and adjourue! <lb/>
atterward, to attend the tutºral ot, <lb/>
JAMES Cottºmack.: <lb/></p> 

<p>Úſt ſtufiml: <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOLIN'S <lb/>
WEDNESDAY, FEBRUARY <lb/>
rº<lb break="no"/>Tar Government propositions as to <lb/>
which they think this colony should <lb/>
federation were introduced for discº <lb/>
mittee of the Assembly yesterday by <lb/>
torney General; Mr. Glen, the hon. <lb/>
Mr. Hog.ett followed, when the Com <lb/>
the debate was a journed to to-day. <lb/>
These torms (for which we have n <lb/>
tenao to-day), are in the first place <lb/>
nion Government shall defray &amp; sum <lb/>
our public exponditure, being the * <lb/>
penses of thoso departments of " <lb/>
assume contrºl, Governor, Judges <lb/>
Office, Light Houses, Surveyor Geni <lb/>
In addition to this sum of <lb/>
would be Assets applicable to local <lb/>
poses <lb/></p>
-->
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>