<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-08" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
    <title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-02-08">8 February 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-02-27"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-27_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="lyallg" when="2018-11-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-27_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-27_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-27_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER</fw>



<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">Wednesday, Feb. 8. </p>
    
    <p>
The house met at three o'clock. </p>
    
    <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">The hon. RECEIVER GENERAL</persName>, by command of his <lb/>
Excellency the Governor, presented to the house the <lb/>
following documents- </p>
    
    <p>Statement of assets and liabilities of the colony on <lb/>
the 31st December, 1864. </p>
    
    <p>Financial Secretary's statement of expenditure, for <lb/>
each particular service, for the year, 1864.</p>
    
    <p>
Consolidated account of goods imported for the <lb/>
year ending 31st December, 1864.</p>
    
    <p>
Receiver General's statement of accounts, Treasury <lb/>
Department, for the year 1864.</p>
    
    <p>
Statement of public debt 31st December, 1864.</p>
    
    <p>
Financial statement of the affairs of the colony for <lb/>
the year 1865. </p>
    
    <p>Estimate for defraying the civil expenditure of the <lb/>
Colony for the year 1864.</p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">The hon. RECEIVER GENERAL</persName>, in moving that these <lb/>
documents lie on the table, regretted that he could <lb/>
not invest this subject with the interest which at<lb break="no"/>taches to the annual statements of the distinguished <lb/>
statesman who is at present finance minister of Eng<lb break="no"/>land, or even those of the hon member for Ferryland, <lb/>
Mr. Glen, when that hon gentleman was Receiver <lb/>
General, with an overflowing exchequer. He (hon. <lb/>
R. Gen.) would, however, endeavour to make his <lb/>
statements as explicit as possible, and while he re<lb break="no"/>gretted that he could not refer to an expansion of <lb/>
trade or an improved condition of the people during <lb/>
the past year, he could show some increase of revenue <lb/>
and the strictest economy in the public expenditure. <lb/>
The revenue for the past year, from all sources, was <lb/>
£106,415 17s., being an increase of £4,356 17s 6d. <lb/>
on that of the preceding year. The increase on the <lb/>
Customs' duties was £4,415 9s 9d, of which £1,921 <lb/>
11s 1d was in the outports. The Light dues for the <lb/>
       
       
past year amounted to £4,953 7s 1d, being a de<lb break="no"/>crease of £263 9s 9d. The amount of Customs' <lb/>
duties received at St. John's was £81,861 5s 8d; at <lb/>
Twillingate, #160 18s; at Fogo, £1,052 7s 9d; at <lb/>
Greenspond, £1290 11i 4d; at Trinity and Catalina, <lb/>
£1,133 1s 9d; at Hant's Harbor, £55 5s 1d; at <lb/>
Carbonear, £696 05 5.d.; at Harbor Grace, £11,942 <lb/>
65 1d; at Bay Roberts, £6 13s 1d; at LaManche, <lb/>
3:303 14s 5d; at Burin, £308 12s; at La naline, <lb/>
        £53 12s 5d; at St. Lawrence, £40 4s 6d; at Har<lb break="no"/>bor Breton, £374 3s 11d; at English Harbor, £66 <lb/>
4s 3d; Pushthrough, £59 9s 1d; Gaultois, £689 <lb/>
18s 7d; Burgeo, £147 17 4d; LaPoile £1,185 10s <lb/>
        11d; Channel, £437 19s; Labrador, £1,112 2s. 11d. <lb/>
There was a decrease on the duties collected at La<lb break="no"/>brador of £210 7 9d as compared with the previous <lb/>
year, which was accounted for by the circumstance <lb/>
that molasses and several other articles for consump<lb break="no"/>tion on the Labrador were purchased, duty paid, in <lb/>
St. John's, there being no advantage to those having <lb/>
establishments there in importing those articles from <lb/>
any other piace, now that the payment of duties could <lb/>
not be evaded. There was a considerable increase on <lb/>
the duties collected at Harbor Grace, which might be <lb/>
accounted for partly by the extension of the business <lb/>
of that port, but principally by the opening by <lb/>
Messrs. Ridley &amp; Sons of a branch establishment at <lb/>
Rose Blanche, for which the importations were at <lb/>
Harbor Grace, the goods being afterwards sent coast<lb break="no"/>wise. As it might be a matter of interest to hon. <lb/>
members to be informed upon what articles there was <lb/>
an increase, and on what a decrease of duties, he <lb/>
would read the details. On ale and porter there was <lb/>
an increase of £200 11s 11d; on butter £60 19s 8d; <lb/>
cheese £3 16 4d; chocolate and cocoa £28 14s 8d; <lb/>
cigars £1 15s 8d; coals £1,313 4s 6d; coffee, £47 <lb/>
6s 3d; confectionary £23 2s 1d; teathers £51 16s; <lb/>
fruit (90,831 lbs.) £567 143 1d; molasses (147,233 <lb/>
gals.) £1,533 14s 2d; pork, £6 18, 7d; brandy, gin, <lb/>
and whiskey, (44.18 1/2 gals.) £1,104 11s 3d; rum. <lb/>
(10,744 1-2 gals.) £1641 14s 9d; sugar unrefined <lb/>
        (2230cwt 1qr 91b) £916 6s 5d, bastard £4 10 7d; <lb/>
wine in bottles £29 11s; not in bottles (1126 gals.) <lb/>
£281 10s; port, madeira, burgundy and sherry (326 <lb/>
        gals.) £35 13s 9d; goods paying 51-2 per cent. and <lb/>
        advalorem, £705 12s 11d. The total increase was <lb/>
        £8,459 4s 8d. There was a decrease on the follow<lb break="no"/>ing articles–bacon and hams, £15 5s 7d; biscuit, <lb/>
        £238 6s 9d; oatmeal and Indian meal £1 12s 4d; <lb/>
salt (5,688 1-2 tons) £142 4s 2d; cordials (1,701 1-2 <lb/>
        gals.) £255 4s 6d; sugar, refined (630 cwt 3qrs <lb/>
11lbs) £416 7s 2d; tea, sonchong, congou, &amp;c., <lb/>
        £52 13s other sorts, £69 5s 5d; the total quantity <lb/>
short imported being 6,483 lbs.; tobacco (107,135lbs) <lb/>
        £1,473 2s 5d; vinegar £16 14s 2d; claret and other <lb/>
wines (989 1-2 gals.) £154 10s 91; goods not enu<lb break="no"/>merated or described, £210 0s 10d., the total de<lb break="no"/>crease being £3,045 7s 11d., which being deducted <lb/>
from increase, leaves a gross increase of £5,413 17s <lb/>
7d on the year. He regretted to state that notwith<lb break="no"/>standing the prevalence of distress amongst the op<lb break="no"/>erative population, arising from the short fisheries of <lb/>
the past year, there was an increase of over £3000 on <lb/>
spirits and wines, ale and porter. It was certairly <lb/>
deserving of the most serious consideration that in <lb/>
such a year as the past, with starvation staring hun<lb break="no"/>dreds in the face, the seal fishery almost a total fail<lb break="no"/>ure, and the cod fishery not much better, there should <lb/>
have been such an alarming incresse in the consump<lb break="no"/>tion of intoxicating liquors, and that two-ninths <lb/>
of our whole revenus should be derived from the du<lb break="no"/>ties on these liquors. The statement of assets and <lb/>
liabilities of the colony exhibits a balance against the <lb/>
colony on the 31st Dec. last, of £36,899 0s 2d against <lb/>
£32 616 17s 10d, on the 31st Dec., 1863, being <lb/>
an increase, during the past year, of £3,482 2s. 4d. <lb/>
The increase is easily accounted for. Votes were <lb/>
passed in committee on supply last session, not inclu<lb break="no"/>ded in the estimate, amounting to £900, and the ex<lb break="no"/>penditure for shipwrecked erews, occasioned by the <lb/>
disasters of the seal fishery, exceeded the estimate by <lb/>
£3,103, 17s 5d. and some accounts were slightly <lb/>
overdrawn while the revenue was only £4254, in ex<lb break="no"/>cess of its estimated amount. The public debt account <lb/>
showed an increase of £4 446 17s 2d, caused by the <lb/>
issuing of Debentures under the St. John's Sewerage <lb/>
Act, for £5,000, and some small amounts under the <lb/>
St. John's Rebuilding Act, from the aggregate of <lb/>
which there remained to be deducted £733 9s 10d <lb/>
debentures paid off. The amount of the funded debt <lb/>
on the 31st December last was £177,261 18s 4d <lb/>
The Financial statement for the present year was made <lb/>
out in dollars and cents. The revenue was estimated <lb/>
at the same amount as last year, which he (hon R. <lb/>
Gen.) hoped would be realized, the estimate being <lb/>
$492,509, while the expenditure was estimated at <lb/>
$480,958, 86. The only increase of salaries was £10 <lb/>
to the High Constable at Harbor Grace, and £20 to <lb/>
the General Superintendent of Police, for which ad<lb break="no"/>dresses passed the house last session, Provision was <lb/>
made for the expenses of a general election, the con<lb break="no"/>tinuing of the geological survey, the erection of a <lb/>
Government store and workshop, for which the neces<lb break="no"/>sity had been experienced in years past; and $48,150 <lb/>
for the road service. It would be recollected that at <lb/>
the close of last session an addressed passed both <lb/>
houses for the payment of the cost of uniforms for <lb/>
Captain Renoni's Company of Rifle Volunteers, and <lb/>
that subsequently petitions were presented from the <lb/>
Captains of the other Companies for similar grants. <lb/>
The government had decided on leaving the whole <lb/>
question to the house and a sum of $5,000 was insert<lb break="no"/>ed in the estimate towards meeting that outlay, <lb/>
        
        
        <cb/>


should it be passed by the house. The sum of $46,<lb break="no"/>000 was sit down for the permanent and casual poor. <lb/>
In some districts the road grant was now being antici<lb break="no"/>pated to relieve the distress now prevailing, as it was <lb/>
evident that the circumstances of the coiony would <lb/>
not admit of any increase in the poor vote, without <lb/>
a corresponding diminution of the road grant, which <lb/>
would be obviously unjust to those districts not requir<lb break="no"/>ing more that a moderate amount of poor relief. As <lb/>
some of the hon members opposite, since the opening <lb/>
of the session, had recourse to the stale charge so <lb/>
frequently refuted, that the government had recourse <lb/>
to the excessive issue of poor relief in certain districts <lb/>
to sustain their political influence, he (hon R. Gen.) <lb/>
would refer to the abstract of poor expenditure as <lb/>
furnished by the Stipendiary Poor Commissioner, and <lb/>
now laid on the table, which was, for the several dis<lb break="no"/>tricts, as follows:- </p> 



<table>
    <row><cell>St. John,'s</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Cy £4,141 16 4</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Ferryland</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">622 5 10</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Bay de Verds</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">556 13 10</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Brigus</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">802 0 11</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Bonavista</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">951 19 3</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Carbonear</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">300 5 10</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Trinity</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">653 4 10</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Twiligate and Fogo</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">693 14 6</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Harbor Maine</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">317 19 3</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Harbor Grace</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">604 5 4</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Placentia and St. Mary's</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">619 16 2</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Labrador</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">23 0 0</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Burin</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">664 7 3</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Fortune Bay</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">15 18 4</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Burgeo and LaPoile</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">237 14 1</hi></cell></row>
    <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">£11,205 2 2</cell></row>
    <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Stg. £9,711 1 10</cell></row>
 
</table>
    
<p>
In those districts represented by hon members on <lb/>
the opposition side of the house, with a population of <lb/>
49,424, the expenditure was within a fraction of 2s. <lb/>
4d. per head, for every man woman and child, while <lb/>
in the districts represented by hon members on this <lb/>
side, with a population of 68,880, the expenditure <lb/>
was a fraction over 1s. 6d. per head. So much for <lb/>
the correctness of the charges made by hon members. <lb/>
Before sitting down, he (hon. R. Gen.) conceived it <lb/>
his duty to refer to some observations which had been <lb/>
made on a former day by the hon member for St. <lb/>
John's West, Mr. Renouf, respecting certain Cus<lb break="no"/>toms' Bonds taken for duties on goods imported, on <lb/>
which a Newfoundland jury had given an adverse <lb/>
verdict, and respecting which, so far as he could learn, <lb/>
he had reason to believe the Judges of the Supreme <lb/>
Court were divided in opinion, The matter had been <lb/>
referred to on two or three occasions by the hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber, with no lack of vituperative charges against him <lb/>
(hon R. Gen.) for, inattention to the duties of his <lb/>
office. If the hon member had the interests of the <lb/>
colony at heart so much as he professed, he would <lb/>
have attached the blame to the system which had pre<lb break="no"/>vailed in the Customs department for the past thirty <lb/>
years, and expressed his satisfaction at its being <lb/>
changed—that signing blank bonds, a practice fraught <lb/>
with most disastrous consequences, and liable to abuse <lb/>
any time. It was matter of congratulation that this <lb/>
system had been terminated, although it might involve <lb/>
a loss to the colony of £2,000 or more. This, of <lb/>
course, was a matter of uncertainty, as there were <lb/>
legal points yet to be decided. But he (hon R. Gen.) <lb/>
might call in question the sincerity of the hon member, <lb/>
when he affected to deprecate the loss, as calculated <lb/>
to lessen the means available for many improvements <lb/>
of urgent necessity, Was not the hon member glad <lb/>
that he had the opportunity of a fling at the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and especially at the Receiver General? And <lb/>
he (hon R. Gen.) was bold to say that the immunity <lb/>
which the Reveiver General's accounts had hitherto <lb/>
received at the hon member's hands. was because they <lb/>
were beyond his fault flnding ability. He (hon R. <lb/>
Gen.) had been charged by the hon member with in<lb break="no"/>attention to the duries of his office, because bonds <lb/>
with what he termed worthless names to them, had been <lb/>
taken for duties. Whilst he (non R. Gen.) would be <lb/>
the last person in the house, to question the right of <lb/>
any hon member to criticise the acts, of any public <lb/>
officer, and would readily concede that right in his <lb/>
own case, he merely demanded that the criticism <lb/>
should be fair. In the continuance of a practice <lb/>
which existed when Captain Spearman was at the head <lb/>
of the Customs' department, and was continued under <lb/>
the hon members opposite, Mr. Kent and Mr. Glen, <lb/>
while their attention to the duties of their office was <lb/>
never questioned, and was not more marked than his <lb/>
(hon R. Gen's.) he could not be considered by any <lb/>
disinterested person to have acted negligently; and <lb/>
he would ask these hon gentlemen whether the prac<lb break="no"/>tice of signing blank bonds, to be afterwards filled up, <lb/>
did not exist when they had charge of the Customs' <lb/>
department>?</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. Kent</persName>-Yes.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName>-Such a practice existed in the Custom <lb/>
house in his time.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon Receiver GENERAL</persName> thanked these hon gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen for their admissions. Both outside and inside <lb/>
the house parties had charged the loss to his (hon R. <lb/>
Gen's.) neglect. With respect to the sureties to these <lb/>
bonds, whatever change might have taken place in <lb/>
their circumstances previous to the bonds coming to <lb/>
maturity they were regarded at the time of signing <lb/>
as carrying on a safe business and perfectly solvent, <lb/>
importers to a considerable extent. and paying a con<lb break="no"/>siderable amount of duties. He (hon. R. Gen) was <lb/>
sensible that a large amount of responsibility rested on <lb/>
the Receiver General in respect to bonds. But there <lb/>
were times when other and equally important duties <lb/>
called him away from his office; and was the business <lb/>
of the country to sand still, or were parties giving <lb/>
bonds to wait his return? In such cases all must <lb/>
depend upon the discretion of the Assistant Collector. <lb/>
Without wishing to shirk responsibility, or thrusting <lb/>
on , the shoulders of that gentleman responsibility <lb/>
which he (hon R. Gen ) should alone bear, he would <lb/>
ask the hon members opposite, his predecessors in <lb/>
office, whether all the bonds taken in their time were <lb/>
submitted for their approval? </p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. KENT</persName> and <persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName>.—No.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon Receiver GENERAL</persName> thanked the hon mem<lb break="no"/>bers. But the authorities of the Custom house were <lb/>
not infailable any more than the Managers and Di<lb break="no"/>rectors of our Banks. They were liable to be mistaken <lb/>
as to the circumstances of parties signing bonds. <lb/>
When these bonds were presented with the names of <lb/>
parties of whose solvency there was not a whisper of <lb/>
suspicion, to reject the bonds was virtually to cause <lb/>
that suspicion, which might injure parties of whose <lb/>
integrity there was no question. Between the duty <lb/>
of protecting the revenue, and avoiding the doing of <lb/>
any injury to the commercial standing of business <lb/>
men, the Receiver General and Assistant Collector <lb/>
were placed in a position of great delicacy and res<lb break="no"/>ponsibility. But in case of the bonds in question the <lb/>
question was not, as to the solvency of the sureties, <lb/>
but as to the validity of bonds signed in blank, and <lb/>
afterwards, filled up. Several of the Sureties were <lb/>
men of undoubted means. That was not the place to <lb/>
discuss the legality or illegality of bonds signed in <lb/>
blank; and he (hon R. Gen.) had no desire to re<lb break="no"/>mark on the wart of prudence or honor of the parties <lb/>
to these transactions, who signed blank bonds to be <lb/>
passed at the Custom-house for duties, and then re<lb break="no"/>pudiate their responsibility. He could not sufficiently <lb/>
express his cond-mation of their conduct. The prac<lb break="no"/>tice of signing blank bonds bad prevailed for over <lb/>
        
        <cb/>

thirty years, and was the rule, not the exception with <lb/>
respect to the bonds given during the whole of that <lb/>
time. It had now, however, been put an end to, and <lb/>
although the course now adopted might be attended <lb/>
with inconvenience to many in the trade, whose honor <lb/>
is above suspicion, yet the necessity of protecting the <lb/>
revenue rendered it imperative to adopt the precau<lb break="no"/>tions now in use, by which it would be impossible for <lb/>
the sureties to a bond to deny their liability. He <lb/>
moved that the documents lie on the table.</p>
    
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. Renouf</persName>.-The duties collected at the Labra<lb break="no"/>dor in 1863 amounted to £1,325 10s 81., and there <lb/>
was last year a falling off of £210 7s 9d. He was <lb/>
not at all astonished at that. He told the govern<lb break="no"/>ment at the time they were passing their Labrador <lb/>
Bill that it would prove a failure. But the medsure <lb/>
was not passed for the purpose of revenue, but to <lb/>
make places for their own friends. Where was the <lb/>
necessity for sending a Judge to the Labrador, for the <lb/>
purpose of administering justice? Why, his own <lb/>
report showed that he had hardly any cases to try. But <lb/>
the object was to give a salary to one of their friends. <lb/>
Was it not in accordance with the advice of the Fish<lb break="no"/>ery Commissioner that the duties were imposed, and <lb/>
was not a relative of his employed in their collection? <lb/>
We were told that the first year was a year of experi<lb break="no"/>ment, and that the duties would be larger next year, <lb/>
that there was a difficulty in getting to the Labrador <lb/>
coast the first year on account of the ice. But in <lb/>
place of an increase there was a deficiency last year. <lb/>
The measure had turned out to be a complete failure. <lb/>
The Receiver General endeavoured to account for the <lb/>
deficiency by stating that a large quantity cf dutia<lb break="no"/>ble goods had been purchased in this market for the <lb/>
Labrador. He (Mr. Renouf) would take the figures, <lb/>
and not a mere assumption, and the fixures showed <lb/>
a decrease in the amount of duties. It was high time <lb/>
that the system should be put an end to, by which the <lb/>
colony was put to a loss of £2,000. It was time it <lb/>
should be abolished. It was somewhat surprising that <lb/>
the loss should have taken place under the present <lb/>
Receiver General. His predecessors in the Custom <lb/>
house lost nothing. It no doubt arose from his neg<lb break="no"/>ligence. It was no cause of rejoicing that such a loss <lb/>
incurred; but we would rejoice if the Receiver Gen<lb break="no"/>eral told us that he would pay a portion of the loss. <lb/>
It appeared that £3500 had been expended for the re<lb break="no"/>lief of shipwrecked sealing crews; and all that money <lb/>
was expended in the northern bays; all among the <lb/>
constituents of the hon members opposite. When the <lb/>
detailed accounts were laid before the house we would <lb/>
find who benefited by that large expenditure. He (Mr. <lb/>
Renouf) was told of the crew of one vessel having re<lb break="no"/>ceived £240 to bring them from Twillingate to Har<lb break="no"/>bor Grace. When the Receiver General said the poor <lb/>
expenditure was kept within the estimate, he might <lb/>
takeſ 2,500 of this sum and add it to that expenditure. <lb/>
He believed the flnating debt agains: the Colony was <lb/>
stated to be £36,000. That balance had been ac<lb break="no"/>cumulated by the present Government, who boasted <lb/>
of their economy and practised extravagance. It ap<lb break="no"/>peared that the superintendent of the police at Har<lb break="no"/>bor Grace received an advance of £10. That was a <lb/>
small sum for Harbor Grace, but it must get some<lb break="no"/>thing. He (Mr. Renouf) was not aware that an ad<lb break="no"/>dress passed the house for that sum. He was sur<lb break="no"/>prised that something had not been done for Carbon<lb break="no"/>ear. But the hon member for Carbonear understood <lb/>
it, and had taken up the claim of the police there. <lb/>
It appeared that the poor expenditure in the district <lb/>
of Fortune Bay had been only £15. But poor relief <lb/>
had found its way to the Larbrador coast, and the <lb/>
small sum of £23 had been expended there for a com<lb break="no"/>mencement. The economical government had extend<lb break="no"/>ed the system of poor relief.. The merchants on the <lb/>
Labrador said, if they were to be taxed for the pur<lb break="no"/>poses of Newfoundland, let the Government provide <lb/>
relief for their poor, as well as in Newfoundland.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KENT2">Hon. Receiver GENERAL</persName>.-Some years before <lb/>
the present government came into office a supply o <lb/>
provisions was sent to St. George's Bay, which paid <lb/>
no revenue to this colony. He did not blame the <lb/>
late government for that. It was a question of human<lb break="no"/>ity. After the fire of 1846, the people of the United <lb/>
States, Nova Scotia, Canada, and other places sent <lb/>
relief to the sufferers here, and the munificent sum <lb/>
£30,000 stg was given by the British Government for <lb/>
their relief. The expenditure ot the Labrador was <lb/>
for the relief, aged, and infirm persons, who were una<lb break="no"/>ble to earn their own subsistence.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:MARC3">Mr. MARCH</persName>-In every subject that came before <lb/>
the house he would always tell the truth, and oppose <lb/>
what was wrong. The Government had acted wisely, <lb/>
jusly and honestly in the collection of duties at the <lb/>
Labrador. He was aware that Judge Sweetland had <lb/>
given great satisfaction in the discharge of his duties. <lb/>
He was spoken of by the people in the highest terms. <lb/>
The collection of duties was a great protection to our <lb/>
own traders. It was a movement in the right direc<lb break="no"/>tion. The expenditure at Labrador in poor relief was <lb/>
occasioned by a case of great urgency and distress. <lb/>
it was to save life, and was to be attributed to the <lb/>
Rev. Mr. Botwood, who had, on his own credit pro<lb break="no"/>cured over £20 worth of provisions. He (Mr. March) <lb/>
intended to stand up and demand a fair proportion of <lb/>
the public money for Labrador. It was right that the <lb/>
people who lived there should receive it. They were <lb/>
taxºd and were entitled to some return for schools, <lb/>
roads, and other improvements.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr. Talbot</persName> did not think that the Government <lb/>
were entirely free from blame in this matter of the <lb/>
Customs bonds, though he did not see that any par<lb break="no"/>ticular blame attached to the hon the Receiver Gene<lb break="no"/>ral.There was evidently something wrong in the whole <lb/>
system; and if so it was the duty of the Government <lb/>
to correct it, and more particularly when they boast <lb/>
of intending to correct all the evils in the system of <lb/>
their predecessors. Now it appeared to him (Mr. <lb/>
Talbot) that they improved nothing, and that they had <lb/>
acted even worse in these matters than the former <lb/>
Government. Again, they shewed themselves less <lb/>
capable than their predecessors of guarding against <lb/>
and preventing any disagreeable results which might <lb/>
arise from the course which they were pursuing. In <lb/>
that view of the matter then the Receiver General was <lb/>
equally to blame with the Government. The late <lb/>
Government saw that the system was a bad one, and <lb/>
they therefore kept a strict watch upon it. The pres<lb break="no"/>ent Government did not exercise the same prudence <lb/>
and caution; and it had worked perniciously, and the <lb/>
country are the sufferers. Then with reference to the <lb/>
collection of duties at the Labrador; had it not been <lb/>
a total failure? It was undertaken in a spirit of mere <lb/>
persecution, and like all persecutions, had failed. Who <lb/>
but the present Government would have thought of <lb/>
pursuing men into a wild savage country, run to from <lb/>
civilised society, and merely for the purpose of grind<lb break="no"/>ing a tax out of them? This was the grand stroke of <lb/>
policy upon which the Government had so prided <lb/>
themselves. He (Mr. Talbot) would like to ask the <lb/>
hon Receiver General what constable it was at Harbor <lb/>
Grace who had received an increase of £10 to his <lb/>
salary? He did not see anything to prevent the <lb/>
Carbonear constables from being placed on the same <lb/>
footing. There was no economy in thus giving men <lb/>
small salaries. They were always discontented, and, <lb/>
as a natural consequence of that discoutent, would do <lb/>
their work in an inefficient manner.</p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. KENT</persName> was not prepared to enter into a criti<lb break="no"/>cal, examination of the accounts just laid upon the <lb/>
table by the hon Beceiver Geueraſ. But he saw in <lb/>
them, at the first glance, nothing upon which to con<lb break="no"/>


<cb/>
        
gratulate the country, especially in view of the lament<lb break="no"/>able fact that they represented a total loss of over<lb/>
£60,000 to the country. He found an importation of <lb/>
£20,000 worth of spirits—taking them at their first <lb/>
cost-paying, duties to the amount of £12,000, to <lb/>
which might be added, as a natural consequence, an <lb/>
expenditure of £35,000 for poor relief. Such a state <lb/>
of things was indeed lamentable. It represented an <lb/>
amount of extravagant dissipation, and of resulting <lb/>
poverty, which was alarming, and which could excite <lb/>
none other than the most fearful apprehensions with <lb/>
regard to the future of the country.</p>
    
    <p>
Ordered the documents lie on the table. </p> 

    <p rendition="simple:centre">(<hi rendition="simple:italic">To be continued</hi>.)</p>
    
    <p>[The "continuation" does not appear to have been published in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Newfoundlander</hi> and is not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation Debates</hi> Collection]</p>
    
    
    <!-- GL, 2018-11-13, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 
<!--Újt ſtufºumlumºr. <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOHN'S: <lb/>
MONDAY, FEBRUARY 27, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE ArroRNEY GENERAL's Resolution postponing <lb/>
to next session any definite action on the subject of <lb/></p> 

<p>Confederation, has been under discussion in the Atº $. <lb/></p> 

<p>sembly since this day week, and yet remains undis. <lb/>
posed of. There have been some admirable speeches <lb/>
in favour of the proposed change-particularly those <lb/>
of the ATToRNEY GENERAL and Mr. A. SHEA, which <lb/>
were most able and convincing expositions, and as far <lb/>
as we have heard, they yet remain wholly unanswered <lb/>
on the other side of the case. This protracted in­ <lb/>
quiry and examination of the whole question cannot <lb/>
but prove instructive to the public mind, and the re. <lb/></p> 

<p>sult in a short time, we have no doubt, will be a gents . <lb/></p> 

<p>ral concurrence of opinion in favour of Colonial <lb/>
Union. <lb/></p> 

<p>We have no space to-day for any lengthened ob. <lb/>
servations. <lb/></p> 

<p>tº-The Society of St. Vincent de Paul gratefully as: <lb/>
knowledge the receipt of Thirty Pounds Twelve Shil. <lb/>
lings and Seven Pence, the pett proceeds of the St. <lb/>
Bonaventure College Theatricals. <lb/></p> 

<p>[To THE EDIroR of THE NEWPOUNDLANDER) <lb/></p> 

<p>SIR-If the demand on your space is not too <lb/>
pressing I shall feel obliged by your giving insertion <lb/>
to the following remarks, with reference to the Ama­ <lb/>
teur Theatricals at the Fishermen's Hall: <lb/></p> 

<p>To the members of the Amateur Company the pub­ <lb/>
lic are indebted for a considerable source of amuse­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ment; and the receipts being devoted to the relief of <lb/></p> 

<p>the poor, should, irrespective even of other reasons, <lb/>
commend them to the kindest consideration of the <lb/>
community. <lb/>
The last performance for the season came off last <lb/>
night; and I feel great pleasure in saying that the <lb/>
first and principal part of the Entertainment r dºcted <lb/>
great credit on the players. The characters were well <lb/>
sustained throughout, and the s age business, which <lb/>
was of no usual character, very well manged. <lb/>
It is much more difficult, no doubt, to provide in­ <lb/>
terludes and afterpieces wholly unobject on ble, than <lb/>
the dramatic pieces performed first. This narrowness <lb/>
of selection, a desire on the part of the audience for <lb/>
provocatives of laughter, whether it be wit, ridicula, <lb/>
or burlesque, and the not unusual practice of players <lb/></p> 

<p>endeavouring to draw a good house by pandering a, <lb/></p> 

<p>littie to the taste of the frivolous or ignorant, often <lb/>
make interludes and afterpieces more foolish than <lb/></p> 

<p>funny, more tirerome than amusing, and sometimes <lb/>
offensive and disgusting. So iong as the British stage 4: <lb/>
found it could make capital by representations of a <lb/></p> 

<p>distorted and vilified Irish characer, it did so, by . <lb/>
mixing up a grain of wit with a pack of extravagance, <lb/>
buffoonery and ridicule. Like many other things of the <lb/>
past that had better be allowed to rest in oblivion, the <lb/>
day of such undisguised caricature has passed in Bri­ <lb/>
tain, and it should not be allowed to drag out a puny <lb/>
existenee in colonial taste. When a dance or song, <lb/>
illustrative of national custom or charac er is intended <lb/>
to be brought on the stage, it should either be pro­ <lb/>
perly given or not at all. Truth and justice demand <lb/>
this. If the movements, dress, and demeanour of <lb/>
those coming forward to dance an Irish jig, in char­ <lb/>
acter, do not exhibit that "step" of the "light fan­ <lb/>
tastic toe," as it is seen in Ireland, their dancing is <lb/>
not what it professes to be, but a caricature that might <lb/>
as well be compared to monkey antics as to a national <lb/>
diversion. The majority of the Irish people who are <lb/>
known to he lovers of the jig and other lively dances, <lb/>
must be different from all other people, if it can be <lb/>
supposed that at the time they should wish to appear <lb/>
"mate and dacent," they dress themselves in as un­ <lb/>
couth and ragged a manner as possible, to attend a <lb/>
dance in a home circle, or at a cross road, a fair or a <lb/></p> 

<p>wedding. Such being presumable only within the <lb/></p> 

<p>walls of a Lunatic Asylum, or in the drunked revels <lb/>
of Bacchanalians, why represent Irish character in <lb/>
such a guise? No matter how good the motives of <lb/></p> 

<p>those taking part may be—and no person is farther <lb/>
from suspecting the purity of their intentions than I <lb/></p> 

<p>am—and no matter what effect such an exhibition may <lb/>
have with the risible muscles of the majority of the <lb/>
audience, still it is unjust fiable to make a* Punch and <lb/>
Judy" of any national custom or costume, and pass <lb/>
such farcical unbecoming pranks off as national <lb/>
characteristics. <lb/></p> 

<p>Paddy and his caubeen are old acquaintances; but <lb/>
certainly the daughter of Erin could nºt recognise a <lb/></p> 

<p>shadow of resemblance in the type exhibited on the <lb/>
night in question. The innate modesty and reserve, <lb/>
for which friend and foe give her credit, would bring <lb/>
the burning blush to her cheek; and well might she <lb/>
exclaim, "If I'm to be caricatured so the age of <lb/></p> 

<p>chivalry is gone, and good taste and self-respect flaws <lb/></p> 

<p>expired along with it." <lb/>
In performances into which the character of a clown <lb/>
or barlequin enters, the audience are amused by whim­ <lb/>
sicalities; and they admire as much the abilities of the <lb/>
comic actor, in his own way, as any other, because <lb/>
such is his role. But it is a great mistake to suppose <lb/>
that the delineation of the character of any class in any <lb/>
country requires only grimaces, pranks, uproar, and <lb/>
frolic. Why then exhibit the Irish peasant besmeare <lb/>
with a compound of these ingredients as a ground for: <lb/>
a few specks of low wit and paltry ludicrousness?: <lb/>
Why give him a monopoly if such a character is so <lb/>
wastly amusing?'—the Yorkshire clod-hopper, Dutch <lb/>
boor, and Scotch gaberlungie should be "allowed to <lb/>
participate. Plays in general depict respectable, eº; <lb/>
citing, or decently comic, phases of lite. 'Why shoul <lb/>
Irish life and manners form an exception? Amuseº <lb/>
ments of any kind, to merit the approbation of thos" <lb/>
whose approbation is worth having, should be kept <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/></p> 

<p>! <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>f <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>!. <lb/></p> 

<p>e-e <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>gone through in a prºper in <lb/>
ºostume; and why must an il <lb/>
in irish character be brought <lb/>
akin to the freaks of a ragg <lb/>
child of Eve <lb/>
Unfortunately Bacchus has <lb/>
tries, though in different pi <lb/>
ould assume that the neare <lb/>
Hººge to the brawls and revi <lb/>
truer the character of any cla <lb/>
that "too much af one thing i <lb/>
I hope the public taste will be <lb/>
maxim as to discountenance <lb/>
done or unreal, be it ever so <lb/>
I am aware that unfavot <lb/>
always gives annoyance. Ti <lb/>
# can say is, that if it is, po <lb/>
to be distasteful, my criticism <lb/>
only read in a similar spirit to <lb/>
written. I freely give the pa <lb/>
credit they deserve, and that <lb/>
at the same time, I feel bound <lb/>
unwarrantable buriesque and <lb/>
people whose character, self-re <lb/>
for the memory of their ence <lb/>
majority of this community <lb/>
as their own. <lb/>
I must apologise, Mr.-Edito <lb/>
on your valuable space; but <lb/>
ter and dictator, to a great ex <lb/>
be discharging a part of its <lb/>
the subject under public notic <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, February, 24th, <lb/></p> 

<p>LENTEN PASTORAL 01 <lb/>
D.R. MUL. <lb/></p> 

<p><lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>+ JOHN THOM <lb/></p> 

<p>£y the grace of God and fa. <lb/>
y Bishop of St John's: <lb/></p> 

<p>To the Clergy and Laity of <lb/>
w Benediction in the Lord <lb/></p> 

<p>'pearly Beloved baeth Rex <lb/></p> 

<p>Our Holy Mother the Ch <lb/>
us in this peculiarly acceptabl <lb/>
Lord our God in fasting a <lb/>
mourning, for he is gracious <lb/>
and rich in mercy,"—Joel 2. <lb/>
ance is set apart that by a true <lb/>
and mortification, we may pu <lb/>
btains of sin we have contract. <lb/>
and turn aside the arrow ot <lb/>
cri mes bawe provoked. The t <lb/>
as the great Indulgence of the <lb/>
Holy Father, and commenced <lb/>
12th of February, has opened <lb/>
mercy to sinners. Tne solem: <lb/>
sanctified by the example of o <lb/>
tised by the Apostles, and h, <lb/>
the earliest ages of the Church <lb/>
for body and soul. By it we <lb/>
sensual indulgences, motify <lb/>
and rekindle in our hºnrts thm <lb/>
Practice then, dearly belºved <lb/>
i'ius demanded by the Church <lb/>
ance, prayer and fasting. Atte <lb/>
avocations permit you at th <lb/>
Mass and the evening instruct: <lb/>
around you and offer up the R <lb/>
every night give alms accord, <lb/>
the fasting and abatinence of ti <lb/>
of the poor, and thus prepare <lb/>
tion of the heavenly banquet º <lb/>
The Holy Communion you mak <lb/>
will not satisfy the obligation <lb/>
the precept of the Churon and <lb/>
Jubilee, each requires a separ <lb/>
calmer and more just light, <lb/>
legitimate connexion there it <lb/>
at which they have taken u <lb/>
business treaty which has be <lb/>
years past to the mutual adv <lb/>
cerned. But should it be <lb/>
notice given in petulance is <lb/>
pealing the treaty, then he <lb/>
that as far as Canada is conc <lb/>
accordance with the approve <lb/>
lation would deprécate, a <lb/>
policy. It would be seen the <lb/>
were for the †. <lb/>
nial policy would be disturº <lb/>
factory relations be injuriou <lb/>
tions of the Government of th <lb/>
He had listened with much <lb/>
and I gical speech of the tº <lb/>
yesterday, but he did not en <lb/>
and learned friend as to the <lb/>
the question they were consi <lb/>
Confederation does not belo, <lb/>
or novel experiments. All t <lb/>
the world are the result o <lb/>
states for purposes of defen <lb/>
advancement. When we lºw <lb/>
time of the Heptarchy and <lb/>
these ſittle kingdoms unde <lb/>
signal illustration of the eff <lb/>
promoting the power, and <lb/>
people. In her early day <lb/>
the several little States at <lb/>
harrassed or overrun by so <lb/>
made but little progress. H <lb/>
urder a settled Government <lb/>
bined suffrages, though Eng <lb/>
vicissitudes from which no t <lb/>
career has been one of ste <lb/>
nating at the present day in <lb/>
holds, foremost amongst th <lb/>
Then we have her Union v <lb/>
both countries have derived <lb/>
The Union of England and <lb/>
to as an example of the inj <lb/>
tions, and efforts had been <lb/>
ditional prejudice which t <lb/>
spired, to create a hostile f <lb/>
sure. They have read the <lb/>
to little purpose who assert <lb/>
common with the just term <lb/>
*tion of these colonies is pi <lb/>
the time of that Union, <lb/>
country, and force and frau, <lb/>
about the so-called Union. <lb/>
less unjust than the agencie <lb/>
The representation given <lb/>
Parliament was about one­ <lb/>
tled to on fair grounds, an <lb/>
the Catholics who formed f <lb/>
were entirely excluded b <lb/>
Penal Laws. It were idle <lb/>
ties and injustice which m: <lb/>
scarcely established any be <lb/>
between the taskmaster <lb/></p> 

<p>within legitimate bºunds; and I appeal to any ºn ...; acquainted with the histor <lb/>
biassed mind that gives the question a moment's toº. 4, that his agitation for a <lb/>
sideration, if the usual style of exhibiting the Irish: rounded on the fact tha <lb/>
peasant or Irish gentleman of the old or new school, inion were not found in ti <lb/>
in a coarse, rollicking, reckless manaer, is not intºn. land and Ireland, and that <lb/>
sistent, unreal and low * Now, the Highland Fiº Repeal of the Union he so <lb/>
which is recognised as a national dance, is slº" <lb/></p> 

<p>: <lb/></p> 

<p>t <lb/></p> 

<p>} 2: <lb/></p> 

<p>lºm <lb break="no"/> </p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>