<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-01" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
    <title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1865-02-01">1 February 1865</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1865-02-09"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-09_Page_1.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1865-02-09_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-11-09">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-09_Page_1"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-09_Page_1.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1865-02-09_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-09_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="1" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-09_Page_1.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>
    <fw type="running">St. John's, Thursday, February 9, 1865.</fw>
    
    <!-- IC, 2018-11-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->

<!--<p>Notices. <lb/></p> 

<p>Iothers . . Mothers . . . <lb/>
brocure Mrs. WINSLow's Soothin <lb/>
children teething. This valuable <lb/>
he prescription of one of the best <lb/>
nd nurses in the United States; it <lb/>
r thirty years. with never failing­ <lb/>
is by millions of mothers and chil­ <lb/>
eble infant of one week old to the <lb/>
ly relieves the child from pain, but <lb/>
bmach and bowels, corrects acidity, <lb/>
d energy to the whole system. It <lb/>
tly relieve Griping in the Bowels and <lb/>
believe it the best and surest remedy <lb/>
| cases of Dissentery and Diarhoea in <lb/>
it arises from teething or any other <lb/>
Betions for use will accompany each <lb/>
nuine unless the fac-simile of Curtis <lb/>
he outside wrapper. Price only 25 <lb/>
Sold by all Medicine Dealers. Office, <lb/>
New York, and 205 High Holborn <lb/></p> 

<p>S. WINSLOW, <lb/></p> 

<p>Nurse and Female Physician, presents <lb/>
5f mothers, her Soothing Syrup for <lb/>
, which greatly facilitates the prºcess <lb/>
|ftening the gums, reducing all infia­ <lb/>
ly all pain and spasmodic action, and <lb/>
e the bowels. Depend upon it, mo <lb/>
e rest to yourselves, and relief and <lb/>
fants. We have put up and gold this <lb/>
irty years, and can say, in confidence <lb/>
hat we have never boen able to say <lb/>
icine—never has it failed in a single <lb/>
a cure, when timely used. Never <lb/>
instance of dissatisfaction by any one <lb/>
the contrary, all speak delighted <lb/>
ns, and speaks in terms of commenda­ <lb/>
al'effects and medical virtues. . We <lb/>
iter what we do now," after thirty <lb/>
E. and pledge our reputation for the <lb/>
...t we here declare. <lb/>
me infant is suffering from pair and <lb/>
ºf will be found in fifteen or twenty <lb/>
a syrup is administered: Full direc. <lb/>
will accompany each bottle. None <lb/>
the fac-simile of Curtis and Perkins, <lb/>
the outside wrapper. Sold by Drug­ <lb/>
the world. Plincipal Office, 48 Dey <lb/>
205 High Holborn, England. Prics <lb/>
Fr bottle. <lb/>
is an extract from a letter written by <lb/>
me, Pastor of the Pierrepont-street <lb/>
Brooklyn, N Y, to the "Journal and <lb/>
cinnati, O., and speaks volumes in <lb/>
ºrld-renowned medicine, Mrs. WIN3­ <lb/>
syrup for Children Teething—i.We <lb/>
ment in your cºlumns of Mrs. Wins­ <lb/>
yrup. Now we never said a wordin <lb/>
it medicine before in our life, but we <lb/>
, say to your readers that this is no <lb/>
we tried it, and know it to be all i <lb/>
nobably one of the most successful <lb/>
day, because it is one of the best <lb/>
ur readers who have babies can't do <lb/>
m a supply." <lb/>
J. DEARIN, St. John's, <lb/>
Agent for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>IOENIX FIRE <lb/>
auce Coºpally. <lb/>
treet and Charing Cross, London. <lb/>
TABLISHEij–1782 <lb/></p> 

<p>USTEES AND DIRECTORS. <lb/></p> 

<p>, Esq. (Kirkman D. Hodgº on Esq. <lb/>
" James Horne, &amp; 6 <lb/>
| William J. Lancaster, * <lb/>
* John D. Magen, º <lb/>
, " John Masterman,Esq. M., P. <lb/>
" John Timohy Oxley tsº <lb/></p> 

<p>lartº George Stanley Reptol. " <lb/></p> 

<p>, " Benjamin Shaw, º <lb/>
* Matthew Whiting, 46 <lb/></p> 

<p>º, " (Fransis Wilson, 66 <lb/>
sECRETARIES <lb/></p> 

<p>Witliam HARRIs Fsq. <lb/>
George William LoveLL, Faq. <lb/>
* FIRE OF FICE is confidently re­ <lb/>
he notice of the public—for the libera <lb/>
tude with which all claims upon it are <lb/>
ld ... as well as for the almost unlimited <lb/>
affords, comprising in addition to the <lb/>
upital of the Cºmpany, the whole for <lb/>
rous Proprieta y, composed of som <lb/>
tent gentlemen and Merchants, in the, <lb/></p> 

<p>ºl. <lb/>
1X 0FFICE has warried on an exten <lb/>
ful business for upwards of seventy­ <lb/>
e duty paid by it to Government for <lb/>
Great Briain and Ireland exceed <lb/>
ng per unnum. <lb/>
hort time insurances are undertaken <lb/>
X COMPANY on almost every de­ <lb/>
un Newfoundland at a moderate rate <lb/>
ch may be know on application to <lb/>
eir office, in St. John's, where policies <lb/>
f charge. <lb/>
W. &amp; G. RENDEI.L, <lb/>
Avents for Newfoundland. <lb/></p> 

<p>HE COLONIAL <lb/>
ºr * <lb/>
Sliraſº Č0:1)ally <lb/>
st ARLISHED 1846. <lb/>
ONE MILLION STERLING, <lb/>
of Assuring before 25th <lb/>
May 1863. <lb/>
DIVISION OF PROFITS. <lb/>
advantage of this year's entry to the <lb/>
roposals must be lodged at the Offie&amp; <lb/></p> 

<p>wfoundland,or with one of the Agents <lb/>
h May next. § <lb/>
:S BÖNUS will be allocated at the <lb/>
ts in 1864 to Policies opened before <lb/>
3ooks for the Present Year. <lb/>
is BY SPECIAL Act of PARLIAMENT. <lb/>
Governor. <lb/>
HON. THE EARL OF ELGIN &amp; <lb/>
E. Gover NoF-GENERAL OF INDIA. <lb/>
-5 GEORGESTREET, EDINBURGH <lb/>
ºctors in St. John's, Newfoundland. <lb/>
rien, Esq. Walter Grieve, Esq., <lb/>
Merchant. <lb/></p> 

<p>'lliam Henry Mare, Esq. $', <lb/></p> 

<p>iwiser—Henry Hunt Stabb, M.D. <lb/>
it—Frederick J. Wyatt. <lb/>
JN OF THE COMPANY. <lb/>
of the Company......... e130,000 <lb/>
§ divided Profits on two occasions." <lb/>
100,0pened in 1847,has beenincreased <lb/>
he application of the Bonus; othek <lb/>
oportion. <lb/>
very five years; next division in 1860. <lb/>
eived in any part of the world whº <lb/>
een established. <lb/></p> 

<p>In almost every . <lb/></p> 

<p>No. 3,637. <lb/></p> 

<p>St. John's, Thursday, February 9, 1865. <lb/></p> 

<p>- nd Puhlished every Monday and Thursda <lb/>
*...º.º. SHEA. at . <lb/>
tº judgwoº."-0." <lb/>
ºnnea per annº payable in advance. <lb/>
jºrtisements not limited (Auction-sales and notices <lb/>
*†ich determing themselves excepted) are repeated <lb/>
jordered in writi: to be withdrawn, and are <lb/>
charged for accordinglu. <lb/>
this paper is filed,and may be seen, free ºf chargº <lb/>
Hºlloway's Pills and Ointment Establishmet, 244, <lb/>
grand, London. <lb/></p> 

<p>*Toºse of Assembly.T <lb/></p> 

<p>Monday, Jan. 30. <lb/></p> 

<p>The House met at three o'clock. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Mr. WYATR, from the select Committee to prepare <lb/>
an address in reply to his Excelleney's speech, resented <lb/>
the draft of an address, which was read a first time. <lb/></p> 

<p>reading to-morrow­ <lb/></p> 

<p>sº gave notice that, on to-morrow, he would <lb/>
move the suspensiºn of the Rules of the House with re­ <lb/>
ference to that address. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>The hon. RECEIVER GENERAL gave notice that, on <lb/>
tomorrow, he would move the appointment of a select <lb/>
...mmittee on the Contingencies of the House. <lb/></p> 

<p>Colonial Secretary tº lay on the table copies of corres­ <lb/>
...nce with the Government of Canada, and other <lb/>
...ts relative to the Federal Union of the Provin­ <lb/></p> 

<p>*Hon. Arronney GENERAL-The documents were in <lb/>
the course of being printed, and would be laid on the <lb/>
... as soon as they could be gºt ready. <lb/>
º, RENOUF, pursuant to notice, asked the hon. <lb/>
Acting Colonial Secretary to lay on the tible 9f the <lb/>
#. A copy of the letter of Dr. Stabb, Superintend. <lb/>
ent of the Lunatic Asylum, complaiting of the visit of <lb/>
inspection by the members for the division of St. John's <lb/>
west to that Institution. <lb/>
†. Hon. ArroRNEY GENERAL was sorry that the <lb/>
government could not comply with the request of the <lb/>
ºn member, for a copy of the le ter referred to in his <lb/>
notice, in which he assumed that some reference was <lb/>
...tº himself and the other members for St. John's <lb/>
**... it must be obvious that if the confidential com­ <lb/>
mºtions of the officers of the Government were to be <lb/>
made public, unuch detriment to the public service would <lb/>
be the inevitable result. <lb/>
M. iºnour.—Was the letter marked confidential? <lb/>
tiºn. ArrorNEY GENERAL-It was a , matter of no <lb/>
importance whether it was marked confidential or not. <lb/>
I, was fºom an officer of the government. <lb/>
Mr. Renouf.-That officer, it appeared, could do as <lb/>
he pleased. He had the sole control of an institution, <lb/>
ºmies from the town, in which there were over 10% <lb/>
pauperiumates, and which cost the colony £4,000 a year; <lb/>
...hºn the members for the Western ſivision of St. <lb/>
. John's, in the discharge of their duty to their constitu­ <lb/>
ents, made a visit of inspectiºn to that institution, it <lb/>
appeared that this official complained to the Executive <lb/>
ºwing done so, and now when they applied for <lb/>
a cony of his letter, they were refused. The reason was <lb/>
j. Dr. Stabb had a brother in the Executive <lb/>
Çºmºl, who supported him in all his proceeding". <lb/>
The hon, ATTokNEY GENERAL was very sorry to see a <lb/>
feeling tranifested towards, a gentleman who was not <lb/>
present in that House to defend himself. If the hom <lb/>
memºer were amenable to the government, and if any <lb/>
charges were made against him by the Physician of the <lb/>
imatic Asylum, it would be the duty of the government <lb/>
tº communicate a copy of such charges to him, to give <lb/>
him an opportunity of meeting them. But it was ob­ <lb/>
viously improper to furnish a gentleman entirely uncon­ <lb/>
nºted with the government with a confidential commº­ <lb/>
i.on from an officer of that government, even if he <lb/>
was mentioned in it. He (hon. A. Gen.) did not sºy <lb/>
whether such was the case in this instance or not. He <lb/>
might inform the hon, member, that it was no part of his <lb/>
º duty as member for St. John's West, to visit the <lb/>
umatic Asylum. If he went there, it was in private <lb/>
capacity, as any other citizen might go. . He (hon. A. <lb/>
Gün) did not say that it was not proper for him to do <lb/>
so, idio inform himself respecting the management of <lb/>
that institution and every other public institution ºn the <lb/>
colony; and if he, or any ºther member had any <lb/>
charges to make respecting the management of this <lb/>
Asylum, or any other institution under the control of <lb/>
the government, they would be prepared at once to <lb/>
institute an inquiry. <lb/>
S. ºoº-Was certainly surprised that any doei. <lb/>
ment should be thus refused to be laid before this <lb/>
Hºuse. He would ask the hon. Attorney, General <lb/></p> 

<p>... Resour pursuant to notice, asked the Acting <lb/></p> 

<p>by Dr. Stabb in a most cringing manner. He took <lb/>
them through the whole building, and actually asked <lb/>
them into his private apartments. There was no insti­ <lb/>
tution that required more supervision than that one.-\-<lb break="yes"/>And had the representatives of the people, who voted <lb/>
the supplies for its support, no right to visit it P. <lb/>
After some further discussion, in which Mr. Renouf, <lb/>
the hons. Attorney and Receiver General, and Mr. <lb/>
Talbot took part, the matter was dropped. <lb/>
The house then adjourned until Tuesday at three <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/>
TUESDAY, Jan. 31. <lb/>
The house met at three o'clock. y <lb/>
Mr. GLEN presented a petition from Gregory Morris <lb/>
and other inhabitants of Witless Bay, which was received <lb/>
and read, praying that a certain cove in Witless Bay <lb/>
º be reserved as a place of 'refuge for their fishing <lb/>
craft. <lb/>
Mr. Gien, in moving that the petition lie on the table, <lb/>
would observe that Witless Bay was much exposed to <lb/>
easterly gales, which proved very destructive to fishing <lb/>
craft; and the cove in question was the only place where <lb/>
they could take shelter. It was, therefore, of great im­ <lb/>
portance to the people that it should be reserved for their <lb/>
use. An endeavour was now made to claim it as private <lb/>
property, and he thought it was the duty of the govern­ <lb/>
ment to interfere for the public interest. <lb/>
Hon ATToRNEY GENERAL, in seconding the motion <lb/>
for the petition lying on the table, would state that the <lb/>
hom member showed him the petition previous to the pre­ <lb/>
seating it to the House; and had pointed out to him the <lb/>
proper course in the matter. It was not a matter for <lb/>
the Government to interfere. Let the petitioners prefer <lb/></p> 

<p>an indictment at the Quarter Sessions for the district. <lb/></p> 

<p>There was a number of them, and the expense would be <lb/>
trifling. They could then have it tried whether any pri­ <lb/>
vate party had any right of property in that cave. <lb/>
Mr. KENT.-Fishery rights throughout the colony <lb/>
should be preserved inviolate. It was obviously of the <lb/>
utmost importance to the petitioners, for the safety of <lb/>
their fishing craft, the cove in question should not pass <lb/>
into private hands. What were the Attorney General <lb/>
and Surveyor General paid such magnificent salaries for, <lb/>
if they were not to look after the public interests * <lb/>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/>
on motion of Mr. WYATT, pursuant to order of the <lb/>
day, the address in reply to the Governor's speech was <lb/>
read a second time. <lb/>
Mr. Wyatt moved, pursuant to notice, that the <lb/>
rules of the house oe suspended in reference to the ads <lb/>
dress. <lb/>
Mr. KENT—The address embraced matters of great <lb/>
importance It would be well to proceed in the reg­ <lb/>
ult course, and not have it committed until to-mor­ <lb/>
IoW. <lb/>
Hon Attorney GENERAL-The address being an <lb/>
echo of the speech, as was usual with such documents, <lb/>
there were several paragra hs on which there would be <lb/>
no difference of opinion. They might proceed with these, <lb/>
and let that on which hon members might wish, for dis­ <lb/>
cussion lie over until to-murrow. <lb break="no"/>The motion was put and carried. <lb/>
On motion of Mr. WYATT, the House resolved itself <lb/>
into Committee of the whole on the address, Mr. KNIGHT <lb/>
in the chair. <lb/>
The first and second sections of the address were read <lb/>
serialim and adopted. Ine third section was read refer­ <lb/>
ring to the subject of poor relief. <lb/>
Mr. WYArr moved that the section be adopted, <lb/>
Mr. E. 1). Shea said that paiagraph was not in ac­ <lb/>
cordance with the speech, which recominended assess­ <lb/>
ment in the several districts for the support of the poor. <lb/>
In the reply the Government swallowed their own words <lb/>
and deprecated his Excellency's suggestion. They said <lb/>
there were difficulties in the way of its adoption. He <lb/>
(Mr. Shea) congratulated the Government on their con­ <lb/>
version to the views of the opposition on that question. <lb/>
The matter was fully discussed last session. The sound­ <lb/>
ness of the principle was admitted on this side, but we <lb/>
said it was not applicable to the circumstances of this <lb/>
colony; and that paragraph of the address virtually said <lb/>
the same thing. Å Bill was brought in last session pro­ <lb/>
viding for assessment in certain districts, Hon members <lb/>
on this side expressed their views fully on the subject, in <lb/>
opposition to that measure, and some members on the <lb/>
Government side of the House coincided with them, and <lb/>
the Bill was consequently withdrawn. And now, while <lb/>
the Governor was advised to recommend having recourse <lb/>
to assessment, the Government tell him that such a course <lb/>
is impracticable in this Colony. He (Mr. Shea) did say <lb/>
that piragraph was a distinct and clear and unmistaka­ <lb/>
able amendment on the Governor's speech, proceeding <lb/>
from the Government, or at all events, from members <lb/></p> 

<p>whether that document had been marked confidential or <lb/>
not He (Mr. R) considered that he had a perfect <lb/>
right to ask for that document in his official capacity as a <lb/>
j ºf this House. He (Mr. R.) would briefly <lb/>
explain the circumstances of this case. He understood, <lb/>
with his hon colleague Mr. 'I'albot, that a letter had been <lb/>
with to the Executive by the Superintendent of, the <lb/>
insic Asylum, complaining of the ontº of three <lb/>
hon members of that house, who, in discharge of their <lb/>
duty as custodians of the public, hº visited that institu­ <lb/>
tion twelve months previously. On that oººººoºººy <lb/>
had met the Superintendant who complained of itſuess, <lb/>
and was unable to accompany them through the building. <lb/>
—He (Mr. Renouf) must say that as far as the eye could <lb/>
discover, every thing was in the most perfect order­ <lb/>
they had been well satisfied with the result of their visit, <lb/>
and regarded the state of the institution º credit to the <lb/>
Superintendent. What then was this letter written for, <lb/>
and especially twelve months after this visit ". made 2 <lb/>
H. go there That letter reſºlº º <lb/>
his (Mr. Remours) haracter, and, he had a .g. š. <lb/>
it. He had applied to the hon Colonial Seº, to <lb/>
ascertain whether it was really in existence or not. That <lb/></p> 

<p>years back grave complaints had been made against Dr. <lb/>
Sabb, and that the Governor had said that it he wº <lb/>
guity of the charges alleged against him, he was not fit <lb/>
to be any longer the Superintendent of that institution? <lb/>
The resºrt wis that Loºtors Carson and Rochtorº were <lb/>
appointed to supervise the working of that institution. <lb/>
Åid now, because the West End memº, jº deep <lb/>
interest in the unfortunate inmates of the Asylum. Wºº <lb/>
they to be made the subject of complaint." the govern. <lb/>
ment, and his twelve months after their visit P Alu <lb/>
when he, no doubt, was anticipating anothºr visit, he <lb/>
ºples to the government for hoerty to exclude members <lb/>
frºm visiting the Asylum. What was ule cause of this 2 <lb/>
—was there any great party going on there at that <lb/>
time Any extensive decorations to be put up?–Last <lb/>
session great fault was found with the extravaganº of <lb/>
that insitution. But Doctor Stabb had a brother in the <lb/>
Executive, and they were mesmerised by his influence. <lb/>
Tº lette did not deter the members for St. Jonn's <lb/>
West from making their visit, when they were received <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>- g the confid of the Gov <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Mr. KENT.—The centripetal and the centrifugal forces <lb/>
of the Government had in this matter been acting in di­ <lb/>
rect opposition to each other. The hon the leader of the <lb/>
Government had last year endeavoured to force the Poor <lb/>
Law Bill down the throats of his supporters, but they <lb/>
were reluctant to swallow the pill. He was realizing the <lb/>
position of all leaders. His supporters were restive, They <lb/>
were kicking in harness, and the hon gentlemen experi­ <lb/>
enced the diffiulty of driving four in hand-Could any­ <lb/>
thing be more strong or more emphatic than the advice <lb/>
given them from the throne on this subject, advice <lb/>
sanctioned by the leader of the Government and the <lb/>
Executive P What did it mean P. That the present <lb/>
system should be discontinued, as it, led to imposition <lb/>
and eurruption in its worst forms. . At present it was a <lb/>
boon, a premium, instead of a relief. This was no new <lb/>
matter. Last year the Government introduced their <lb/>
Poor Law Bill and held it aloft, as high as Caesar ever <lb/>
held his Commentaries; and were to stand or fall by it. <lb/>
But the supporters of the Ministry, would nº sustain <lb/>
them in passing it, and it was withdrawn. The same <lb/>
proposition was now a second ume laid before the Legs­ <lb/></p> 

<p>gentisman did not deny it, and said that the non: Attor- lature, a committee was appointed tº prepºrº an aduress <lb/>
ley General would give him (Mr. Renouf) a copy of the ſ in accordance with the views of the Executive; and they <lb/>
leter.—Did not hor: gentlemen remember that some actually give that proposition a direct negative. <lb/></p> 

<p>They <lb/>
say that though the principle is a perfectly sound one, <lb/>
we are not in a position at present to apply it. They <lb/>
acknowledge the pauper relief is an ulcer in our social <lb/>
system, and yet they would not vote for any measure that <lb/>
ºuld tend to allegiate it, and improve our condition. <lb/>
was the learned Doctor aware that when he signed that <lb/>
Report he was passing a direct censure upon the Go­ <lb/>
vernment Hè (MF. Kent) would ask hon gentleme; <lb/>
opposite whether they intended to support toº address 2 <lb/>
Were they to have two sets of opinions, if this were <lb/>
an ordinary case, he (Mr. Kent) would not mind it. <lb/>
But it was a matter that plunged the countly deeper in <lb/>
debt, year after year. It was sapping, the vital energies <lb/>
of the country; and never was this House so strongly <lb/>
called upon to renunciate its opinions as at present: But <lb/>
the committee had given the question the go-bye. and <lb/>
the Ministry sat in a state of coma, whilst a directºº. <lb/>
ive was given to the proposition of the Eºcuº. W nat <lb/>
did he Executive members say to it?. Were they <lb/>
satisfied with themenace-" Eat thy pudding slave and <lb/></p> 

<p>hold thy tongue."? If they were desirous of playing the <lb/>
part of spirit rappers, let them sehd for the Davenport <lb/>
brothers, to relieve them from their present state ºf <lb/>
embirrasment. They certainly were in an unenviable <lb/>
position, and he would let them enjoy ther fame. He <lb/></p> 

<p>(Mr. Kent) did not begrudge it to them. <lb/></p> 

<p>a Mr. TALBOT-That paragraph required some attention. <lb/>
He must observe that it was not at all what he would <lb/>
expect to be the language emploved in addressing the <lb/>
Governor. The address was in perfect contrast to the <lb/>
elegant and classical language of his Excellency's speech. <lb/>
With respect to that paragraph, he might observe that it <lb/>
was not respectful towards his Excellency for the Gos <lb/>
yernment to address him in that manner, after advising <lb/>
him to recommend assessment for relieving the able: <lb/>
baſſad poor. But the address altogether was not such <lb/>
as should have emanated from the Select Cºmmittee <lb/>
acting in unison with the Government. He (Mr. Tal­ <lb/>
bot) would take a fisherman from the streets, and he <lb/>
wºuld draw '. a more suitable reply than that address. <lb/>
One of those fishermen whom the members of the govern­ <lb/>
mºnt would trample upon, would produce a document <lb/>
couched in a style superior to that address. And as to <lb/>
the Governmeut already departing from the course <lb/>
announced the other day in his Excellency's speech; it <lb/>
was to him (Mr. Talbot) no matter of surprise; for, it <lb/>
was well known that their chief object was to preserve <lb/>
their places; and if they found their supporters would <lb/>
not sustain them in the matter of assessment, they were <lb/>
ready to abandon it, as they did the poor Bill last session. <lb/>
The Government were becoming more infatuated every <lb/>
year. If they diff-red in opinion from the Governor, it <lb/>
was their duty to resign, and make room for others who <lb/>
would give his Excellency reliable advice respecting the <lb/>
actual wants and circumstances of the Colony, The <lb/>
sound principle was to assess the districts for the sup­ <lb/>
port of the poor, but he (Mr.Talbot) had no hope that <lb/>
the present, government would have the manliness to <lb/>
grapple with the growing evil of pauperism, and bring <lb/>
in a measure in opposition to the wishes of some of their <lb/>
influential supporters. <lb/>
Mr. Prows; was delighted to find that the hon mem­ <lb/>
ber who had just sat down, had became a convert to his <lb/>
Excellency's views on the subject of poor relief. But he <lb/>
(Mr. Prowse) would like to see the hon member set <lb/>
forth these views to his constituents. They were sound <lb/>
and correct views; and he (Mr. Prowse) rejoiced to see <lb/>
them enunciated by his Excellency. He (Mr. Prowse) <lb/>
expressed these views last year, and he held them still, <lb/>
whatever difficulty there might be in giving, effect to <lb/>
them in this Colony. He (Mr. Prowse) would like to <lb/>
hear every hon member of that House who had opinions, <lb/>
express them openly. He recollected that in conversa­ <lb/>
tion with the hon member, a few days ago, he expressed, <lb/>
in glowing language, his admiration of Confederation <lb/>
But because certain parties out of doors were opposed to <lb/>
it, he dared not give it his support in that House. The <lb/>
fiſhermen would find by-and bye who were there friends. <lb/>
They would not be misled by interested parties to be­ <lb/>
Hºwe that their interests would be sacrificed by confed­ <lb/>
eration, and that the object of its supporters was to sell <lb/>
Newfoundland. There was a certain amount of clamour <lb/>
raised amongst a class of the population on the subject <lb/></p> 

<p>some time, which orcasioned great inconvenience to the <lb/>
people in the heighbourhood, and especially to ths <lb/>
children in attending school. <lb/>
(medered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/>
Mr. WYATT gave notice, that on to-morrow, he woult <lb/>
ask the hon Acting Colonial Secretary for a return <lb/>
showing the number of voyages made by the steamer <lb/>
Arel, to the Westward and Northward, during the year <lb/>
1864, dates of departure from St. John's, and dates of <lb/>
return; also particulars of ports called at, and time of <lb/>
arrival and departure from these ports. <lb/>
Mr. LEaxos presented a petition from John Harley <lb/>
and others of Cap in Cove, South Side of Port-de Grave, <lb/>
which was received and read, praying for a grant to <lb/>
make a road to that settlement. <lb/>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. a <lb/>
Mr. Kent presented a petition from Michael Wade, <lb/>
of Fiat Rock, which was received and read, praying for <lb/>
a grant to open a road from the main road to his farm. <lb/>
Mr. KEST, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
table, would observe that it referred to a matter of very <lb/>
great importance, to the progress of agriculture in the <lb/>
Colony. His Excellency | <lb/>
their attention the importance of the road service, as <lb/>
well as the encouragement of agriculture, Agriculture <lb/>
could not progress without roads, and if they desired tº <lb/>
see a prosperous agricultural population, it was essential <lb/>
that they should be provided with the means of access <lb/>
to their land, and of bringing their produce to market­ <lb/>
It was admited on both sides that the fisheries alone <lb/>
were not sufficient to sustain our increasing population, <lb/>
therefore it became their imperative duty to igive every. <lb/>
facility to those who directed their attention, to other <lb/>
industrial pursuits, The petitioner had peculiar claims <lb/>
which ought not to be overlooked. <lb/>
Mr. Pºsons had much pleasure in supporting the <lb/>
prayer of that petition. He had long been the advocate <lb/>
of agricultural improvement: . This country had great <lb/>
agricultural capabilities, whichhad hitherto been vºy <lb/>
much neglected. No person, who had witnessed the <lb/>
oxhibition of agricultural produce in the front of the <lb/>
building in the month of October could have any doubt <lb/>
on the subject. We had extensive tracts, of most fertile <lb/>
land in the interior, which had not yet been rendered <lb/>
accessible for cultivation. He need only refer to the <lb/>
narrative of Mr. Cormack of his journey across the <lb/>
island. He passed over fine plains with grºss five of <lb/>
six feet high, on which numerous herds, ºf deer found <lb/>
pasturage. In addition to our prºlific fisheries, which <lb/>
for a few seasons had partially failed, and our valuable <lb/>
mineral resources, we had tracts of land which could not <lb/>
be surpassed in fertility, and which required only the <lb/>
fostering hand of a paternal government tº give due en­ <lb/>
couragement and assistance for their cultivation, when <lb/>
they would be occupied by a hardy and industrious pºp": <lb/>
lation. It was not the miserable and degrading dole of <lb/>
the pauper that our people required to sustain them. <lb/>
Give them aid to cultivate the soil, and roads to render <lb/>
their lands accessible, and the able bodied would main­ <lb/>
tain themselves in comfort. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. MARCH concurred in the views of the hon mem­ <lb/>
ber who had just sat down respecting the importance of <lb/></p> 

<p>af pauper relief; and, in *1 the <lb/>
Jared not express his views ºn that question. He (Mr. <lb/>
Prows) must say that he had great respect fºr the hon <lb/>
members's ability, but he had very little respect for his <lb/>
courage. <lb/>
tion. Arronxex GENERAL did not think that hon <lb/>
gentleman distinctly understood the meaning of the <lb/>
passage in either the speech or the reply. They had <lb/>
certainly not expressed themselves as if they understood <lb/>
..m."when the Poor Law Bill was introduced last <lb/>
session, these two hon gentlemen opposed, it with all <lb/>
their might. The Bill was withdrawn for further const­ <lb/>
deration, and up to the present time the opinions of the <lb/>
hon gen lemen were thought to be the same as they <lb/>
expressed last session. He was glad that such a happy <lb/>
charge had come over the spirit of their dream. It <lb/>
would appear, from the observations of these hon <lb/>
gentlemen, that however distaseful a measure might be <lb/>
ãuring the administratiºn of one Governor, it was a <lb/>
highly desirable and beneficial one under another. Here <lb/>
ºñía actually a formal recantation of the heterodox <lb/>
principles expressed by hon members last session; <lb/>
#."ºnorabé meuber, Mr. Kent, openly avowed <lb/>
that he had been mistaken. He believed now <lb/>
that the only way to remedy the existing evils of the <lb/>
system of pauper relief was by assessment. He, (hon <lb/>
Åitorier General) was pleased to see the hon gentleman <lb/>
in such a frank and manly way, acknowledged his <lb/>
is... " The hon members object to the address <lb/>
because they say it does not gº sº far as the speech. <lb/>
He (Attorney General) did nºt think it was open to any <lb/>
such aspersion. Undoubtedly there were obstacles to <lb/>
every useful measure, even tº Confederation.—There <lb/>
was not one act, unless it might be some measure of a <lb/>
common place character, that conduced to the remedying <lb/>
of any evils, or aimed at any important improvement, <lb/>
jiàº a first present difficulties to its being cºrried <lb/>
... ." But when difficulties were in the way of any <lb/>
measure, the benefits of which were in the future, no <lb/>
i.biºmas impossible for small mind, to comprehend <lb/>
how they were to be overcome. The address said <lb/>
simply that we entirely assented to the principle, but <lb/>
ºthere were certain difficulties in, the way of its <lb/>
successful application, which we would endeavour by <lb/>
... ºnsideration to overcome, and conter upon the <lb/>
country so desirable a, bººk ºf the address had said <lb/>
jº 'were insuperable difficulties in the wº, then . <lb/>
would have been open to the construction put, Pºº º <lb/>
by hon members opposite. it was all very well for hon <lb/>
gentlemen to endeavour tº mistify and confuse. The <lb/>
thing was perfectly understood. Difficultles did exist, <lb/>
..ºh. H. cºuld not shut their eyes to their exis­ <lb/>
tence. He was glad, nowever, to **** many hon. <lb/>
gentlemen now in favour of the measure, and he felt <lb/>
isfied that the paragraph in question would be adopted <lb/>
as it stood in the address. <lb/>
The motion for the adoption of the section, was then <lb/>
put and carried. -<lb break="maybe"/>ºr. Committee then rose and the Chairman reported <lb/>
gress. To sit again to-morrow. <lb/>
The House ºnen adjourned unul Wednesday at 3 <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/>-->
    
    <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head>
    
<p rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, Feb. 1.</p>
    
<p>The House met at 3 o'clock.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:KAVA1">Mr. KAVANAGH</persName> presented a petition from F. Fitzgerald <lb/>
and others, of Forbay, which was received and read, <lb/>
praying for a grant to make a road from thence to <lb/>
Beaullen. <lb/></p>
    
<p>Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName> presented a petition, from Thomas Fish <lb/>
Parker and others, of Middle Bill Cove, which was <lb/>
received and read, praying for a grant to build a bridge <lb/>
over the river at Anthony's Gut. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName>, in moving that, the petition lie on the <lb/>
<choice><sic>able</sic><corr>table</corr></choice>, would observe that the bridge has been down for <lb/>
    
    <cb/>
    
some time, which orcasioned great inconvenience to the <lb/>
        people in the heighbourhood, and especially to ths <lb/>
        children in attending school. <lb/></p>
    <p>
        Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName> gave notice, that on to-morrow, he would <lb/>
        ask the hon Acting Colonial Secretary for a return <lb/>
        showing the number of voyages made by the steamer <lb/>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Ariel</hi>, to the Westward and Northward, during the year <lb/>
        1864, dates of departure from St. John's, and dates of <lb/>
        return; also particulars of ports called at, and time of <lb/>
        arrival and departure from these ports. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:LEAM2">Mr. LEAMON</persName> presented a petition from John Harley <lb/>
        and others of Cap in Cove, South Side of Port-de Grave, <lb/>
        which was received and read, praying for a grant to <lb/>
        make a road to that settlement. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. KENT</persName> presented a petition from Michael Wade, <lb/>
        of Fiat Rock, which was received and read, praying for <lb/>
        a grant to open a road from the main road to his farm. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. KENT</persName>, in moving that the petition lie on the <lb/>
        table, would observe that it referred to a matter of very <lb/>
        great importance, to the progress of agriculture in the <lb/>
        Colony. His Excellency the Governor, had urged upon <lb/>
        their attention the importance of the road service, as <lb/>
        well as the encouragement of agriculture, Agriculture <lb/>
        could not progress without roads, and if they desired to <lb/>
        see a prosperous agricultural population, it was essential <lb/>
        that they should be provided with the means of access <lb/>
        to their land, and of bringing their produce to market. <lb/>
        It was admited on both sides that the fisheries alone <lb/>
        were not sufficient to sustain our increasing population, <lb/>
        therefore it became their imperative duty to give every <lb/>
        facility to those who directed their attention, to other <lb/>
        industrial pursuits, The petitioner had peculiar claims <lb/>
        which ought not to be overlooked. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <persName ref="pers:PARS1">Mr. PARSONS</persName> had much pleasure in supporting the <lb/>
        prayer of that petition. He had long been the advocate <lb/>
        of agricultural improvement. This country had great <lb/>
        agricultural capabilities, which had hitherto been very <lb/>
        much neglected. No person who had witnessed the <lb/>
        exhibition of agricultural produce in the front of the <lb/>
        building in the month of October could have any doubt <lb/>
        on the subject. We had extensive tracts, of most fertile <lb/>
        land in the interior, which had not yet been rendered <lb/>
        accessible for cultivation. He need only refer to the <lb/>
        narrative of Mr. Cormack of his journey across the <lb/>
        island. He passed over fine plains with grass five or <lb/>
        six feet high, on which numerous herds of deer found <lb/>
        pasturage. In addition to our prolific fisheries, which <lb/>
        for a few seasons had partially failed, and our valuable <lb/>
        mineral resources, we had tracts of land which could not <lb/>
        be surpassed in fertility, and which required only the <lb/>
        fostering hand of a paternal government to give due en<lb break="no"/>couragement and assistance for their cultivation, when <lb/>
        they would be occupied by a hardy and industrious popu<lb break="no"/>lation. It was not the miserable and degrading dole of <lb/>
        the pauper that our people required to sustain them. <lb/>
        Give them aid to cultivate the soil, and roads to render <lb/>
        their lands accessible, and the able bodied would main<lb break="no"/>tain themselves in comfort. <lb/></p> 
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:MARC3">Mr. MARCH</persName> concurred in the views of the hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber who had just sat down respecting the importance of <lb/>
agriculture. He never was so convinced on the subject <lb/>
as last summer. He touched in at one settlement on the <lb/>
French shore, where one man had 50 sheep, and another <lb/> 
had 11 milch cows, and these persons had no complaint <lb/> 
of poverty. And it was well known that the land on the <lb/>
French shore was comparatively barren compared with <lb/>
the other parts of Newfoundland. On his return from <lb/>
the Labrador he met with that eminent statesman Mr. <lb/>
Howe, who had done so much to promote the progress of <lb/>
Nova Scotia. That gentleman spoke in the highest <lb/>
terms of the fine land which he had seen up the Bays, <lb/>
and along the streams flowing into them. Nearly the <lb/>
whole of that land was unoccupied. The people had <lb/>
settled on the head-lands, for the convenience of <lb/> 
prosecuting the fishery in punts, and were located in <lb/> 
the vicinity of the poorest land for cultivation. Yet, <lb/>
we saw that excellent vegetables were raised here. <lb/>
Mr. Howe saw at once the mistake which had been <lb/>
committed. He said if the people went up into these <lb/>
Bays, where there was fine land and fine timber they <lb/>
might have large craft, and come down to follow the fish<lb break="no"/>ery wherever the fish were to be found, and have their <lb/>
firms at home, to fall back upon, where they could raise <lb/>
much of the produce necessary for our consumption. In <lb/>
place of importing cattle from Prince Edward Island and <lb/>
Nova Scotia, they might have thousands of cattle in these <lb/>
Bays, which would find a ready market in St. John's, <lb/>
with millions of sheep, which would furnish them with <lb/>
both food and clothing. He (Mr. March) had hope for <lb/>
this country yet, He did not despair of seeing it raise <lb/>
again to prosperity. If we have a good seal fishery thin <lb/>
spring, and he did, hope providence would again smile <lb/>
upon us, we would ston, see industry revive, and the <lb/>
merchants would give out supplies with their accustomed <lb/> 
liberality, as no other merchants in the world would do. <lb/>
There were one spring, no fewer than 680,000 seals <lb/> 
brought in, an i with favourable winds, there was reason <lb/>
to anticipate a good fishery this spring, for but few seals <lb/>
had been taken last year. He would not put it at the <lb/>
highest rate; but assuming that there would be 400,000 <lb/> 
seals taken; at 10s each, they would be worth £200,000 <lb/> 
If we had a fair cod-fishery we might calculate on a mil<lb break="no"/>lion quintals. There had been considerably more in <lb/>
some seasons. Fish would be worth a pound a quintal. <lb/>
It was now worth 26s., and there would be none in the <lb/> 
market when the new fish came in. This exclusive of <lb/>
the cod oil, the salmon and the herrings, gave us £1,-<lb break="yes"/>
200,000 for a population of 130,000, besides the produce <lb/>
of Agriculture; and if our people were assisted by the <lb/>
government and by the merchants to go up into these <lb/>
fine Bays, we would soon have a prosperous agricultural <lb/>
population. There was Mr. Tilly, who was so comfort<lb break="no"/>able with his family in Hants' Harbor. That venerable <lb/>
and respected gentleman was far seeing. He saw that <lb/>
in fishery would be liable to failures, and as population <lb/>
was increasing, that some other means of support would <lb/>
become necessary; and he went up into Random Sound <lb/>
at the head of Trinity Bay, where here was as fine a <lb/>
soil as in the land of Goshen. He and his sons had cul<lb break="no"/>tivated a fine tract of land there, where they raised <lb/>
abundance of produce, while they attended to the fishery <lb/>
in the height of the season. One year lately they raised <lb/>
sufficient wheat to make 35 barrels of flour, and this <lb/>
year Mr. Tilly had such fine turnips that one of them <lb/>
could not be put into a flour barrel. Several other fa<lb break="no"/>milies had been induced to follow Mr. Tilly's example, <lb/>
and with the same industry would soon be comfortable. <lb/>
Now with all this we had our minerals, There was no coun<lb break="no"/>try that possessed more valuable resource than this island, <lb/>
and though we had for some years severe distres amongst <lb/>
our people, yet when it, passed away it would be, the <lb/>
means of doing us good; and after all, if Providence <lb/>
afflicted us with a failure of the fisheries, we were exempt <lb/>
from the scourge of war, which was desolating the United <lb/>
States, our government had met the crisis with much <lb/>
energy and judgment, and no person was allowed to <lb/>
person of want; and with the protection of the noble <lb/>

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1865-02-09_Page_2.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">2</fw>
        
        <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>

British government we would yet see brighter days. He <lb/>
felt proud of being a British subject, and desired no other <lb/>
connection. It was not the rule of a race of French and <lb/>
Dutch Canadians that he would substitute for the liberty <lb/>
we now enjoyed under the best government in the world. <lb/>
He (Mr. March) had every confidence in the leader of <lb/>
the present government, but he wished more had been <lb/>
done to settle the people in those fine Bays where the <lb/>
land was so productive, and where there was abundance <lb/>
of manure from the sea weed that washed up on the <lb/>
beaches, and grass grew higher than a man's head. It <lb/>
was only now that we were coming to know the capabili<lb break="no"/>ties of our country, and he hoped that the hardships we <lb/>
had gone through would render our people more careful <lb/>
to husband their means when prosperity returns, and to <lb/>
invest them in those agricultural improvements which <lb/>
would be an inheritance to their children. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Ordered that the petition lie on the table. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
On motion of <persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. Wyatt</persName>, pursuant to order of the day, <lb/>
the House resolved itself into Committee of the whole on <lb/>
the addrass in reply to his Excellency's speech, <persName ref="pers:KNIG2">Mr. <lb/>
KNIGHT</persName> in the chair. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
On motion of <persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. Wyatt</persName>, the next section of the ad<lb break="no"/>dress in reference to education, was read. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName> moved that the section be adopted. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:TALB3">Mr. TALBOT</persName> —The Governor in his speech had refer<lb break="no"/>red to Education and to the necessity of establishing a <lb/>
training school. There were already two or three such <lb/>
schools in existence here, and it was very remarkable <lb/>
that his Excellency the Governor was not aware of it. <lb/>
Why did not his constitutional advisers inform him of <lb/>
it? He (Mr. Talbot) was aware of their existence, and <lb/>
they were provided according to the principle of the Edu<lb break="no"/>cation Act, on the denominational basis—The Roman <lb/>
Catholics had one and the Protestants had two or three, <lb/>
and he (Mr. Talbot) had yet to learn that they were not <lb/>
satisfactory, or that they did not fully answer the purpose <lb/>
for which they were established. He could positively <lb/>
assert that the Roman Catholic one was as good and <lb/>
efficient as it was possible to establish. It was in con<lb break="no"/>nection with St. Bonaventure College, and was placed in <lb/>
charge of a teacher eminently fitted by the excellent <lb/>
training he had himself received at the Dublin training <lb/>
        Institution, to train young men for teachers.—There <lb/>
were always from six to nine pupils under a course <lb/>
of training in this college, and he (Mr. Talbot) presu<lb break="no"/>med that it was the same with the Protestant institu<lb break="no"/>tions; and that the most satisfactory results were attain<lb break="no"/>ed. And was it proposed now to establish another <lb/>
school, in the place of one which could not possibly be <lb/>
excelled? What, therefore, could be the motive for <lb/>
suggesting the establishment of a Normal School? If <lb/>
it was intended that a central training School for all <lb/>
religious denominations should be established, it would <lb/>
be necessary that a school-house should be built for <lb/>
the purpose, and a staff of teachers employod; and <lb/>
thus a very large amount of unnecessary expense would <lb/>
be incurred, thus reducing the general grant now given <lb/>
for Educational purposes.—The only thing which he (Mr. <lb/>
Talbot) saw that would be beneficial was to increase <lb/>
the grant, so as to provide adequate salaries for the <lb/>
teachers. The great eivil in this country was that the <lb/>
teachers did not receive that compensation for their ser<lb break="no"/>vices to which they were entitled, or which would ren<lb break="no"/>der them satisfied with their position. It was <lb/>
not worth training them, if they only received a paltry <lb/>
£25 a year. Let hon members just reflect for one <lb/>
moment on that subject. You give a liberal education <lb/>
to these young men who are designed for teaching in the <lb/>
outports. You raise them intellectually and morally, <lb/>
instil into their minds a laudable ambition, and then you <lb/>
send them to the Outports on the pitiful stipend of £25 <lb/>
a year. Under this system the great difficulty was in <lb/>
retaining the services of these teachers. In the out<lb break="no"/>ports they found young men in mercantile establishments, <lb/>
intellectually far their inferiors, and yet receiving <lb/>
salaries double the amount they received. Hence they <lb/>
become dissatisfied with their position, and on the first <lb/>
opportunity they give it up and seek for employment in <lb/>
which they may receive adequate return for their services. <lb/>
The least salary such men should get was he (Mr. Talbot) <lb/>
would say, £80 a year, with whateyer else they were able <lb/>
to make. That would render them satisfied with their <lb/>
positions; and being satisfied, they would remain and <lb/>
do their work well. Unless this change was effected, it <lb/>
would be useless to incur expense in further training <lb/>
teachers, for the better educated our young men became, <lb/>
the less inclined would they be settler permanently in the <lb/>
outports on such starving salaries as they at present <lb/>
received. The second point which he (Mr.Talbot) would <lb/>
refer to, was the proposition to compel the people to <lb/>
contribute to the support of their schools. The principle <lb/>
was a sound and unexceptionable one; but he was satis<lb break="no"/>fied it would not work well. It was notorious that in <lb/>
some of the Outports the people were so indifferent to <lb/>
education, that they would do without a school forever <lb/>
rather than contribute one penny to its support. The <lb/>
Inspectors had loudly complained of the indifference of <lb/>
the parents, who in many instances did not send their <lb/>
children to school at all; while others only sent them <lb/>
when they could not employ them at home. But surely <lb/>
if the people were unwilling to contribute to the support <lb/>
of their schools, you would not, on that account, take <lb/>
away from them the blessings of education altogether. <lb/>
Aid Education as much as you can, foster it, improve it, <lb/>
but do not strike at the root of the present system, and <lb/>
sweep it away altogether. He (Mr. Talbot) felt it neces<lb break="no"/>sary to make these observations, in anticipation of any <lb/>
Bill that might be introduced on the subject. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. KENT</persName> was perfectly satisfied the leader of the <lb/>
government would do nothing to disturb the denomi<lb break="no"/>national arrangements which we all knew tended very <lb/>
much to allay the sectarian feeling with at one time <lb/>
ran so high in the country,and under which education <lb/>
has made some progress. The duty of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment consisted in supplying the nueans for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of education, and exercising a severe surveillance <lb/>
over its expenditure, but to leave the carrying it out, <lb/>
especially as respected the religious feelings of the <lb/>
people, to parents aud pastors; and if they had the <lb/>
means to increase the grant, parents and all who were <lb/>
interested in education would not object. He knew <lb/>
nothing else that was required. As to the govern<lb break="no"/>ment setting up a normal school for the training of <lb/>
teachers for all denominations in the colony, he did not <lb/>
believe it would be attempted. He agreed entirely <lb/>
with the hon. member, Mr. Talbot, that unless suffi<lb break="no"/>cient emolument were provided for the teachers, any <lb/>
improvement would prove nugatory, as the teachers <lb/>
would be dissatisfied when they saw others, perhaps <lb/>
inferior to them in attainments, in the enjoyment of <lb/>
much more ample salaries. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CART5">The hon. ATTRRNAY GENERAL</persName> was satisfied that <lb/>
when the measure proposed to be introduced by the <lb/>
government was submitted to hon members, it would <lb/>
prove satisfactory to both sides of the House. With <lb/>
Reference to the expense of the proposed formal school, <lb/>
he did not think any additional expenditure would re<lb break="no"/>sult from its establishment. There could be no doubt <lb/>
whatever that a normal school was one of the first ne<lb break="no"/>cessities of an educational system for the training of <lb/>
those who were to teach the people. Teachers who <lb/>
were uneducated could not instruct others. The reports <lb/>
of the Inspectors and of the Boards of Education <lb/>
showed the necessity of a better instructed class of <lb/>
teachers than many of those now employed, and the <lb/>
experience of all who were acquainted with the state <lb/>
of our elementary schools sustained that view. The <lb/>
hon. member opposite objected to any interference <lb/>
with the existing arrangements for the training of <lb/>
Roman Catholic teachers. He said they had a training <lb/>
school already. The hon gentleman also objected to <lb/>

<cb/>

the salaries provided for the teachers. But still he <lb/>
admitted that notwithstanding the inadequate salaries, <lb/>
young men came to be trained, and the Boards com<lb break="no"/>manded the services of parties, after being trained, <lb/>
although their emoluments were certainly much les <lb/>
than it was desirable they snould be. This showed <lb/>
that it was not necessary to inerease the grants to ena<lb break="no"/>ble the Boards to secure the services of efficient teach<lb break="no"/>ers. The hon member was mistaken when he said we <lb/>
had training schools already. The hon member re<lb break="no"/>ferred to the arrangements for training Roman Catho<lb break="no"/>lic teachers in St. Bonaventure College. The Educa<lb break="no"/>tion Act provided for the training there, and in seve<lb break="no"/>ral Protestant institutions. But it was found that the <lb/>
teachers trained in these institutions were inefficient, <lb/>
and it was thought expedient to have a normal school, <lb/>
in which the training of the teachers might be con<lb break="no"/>ducted. Last summer circulars were sent to the sev<lb break="no"/>eral outports, and to the head of the Colonial and Con<lb break="no"/>tinental Church Society, and important information <lb/>
had thus been obtained which would be laid before <lb/>
the House. It was not a training school only that <lb/>
was required. Several of the Boards were in the habit <lb/>
of keeping large sums of money unemployed. Reform <lb/>
was necessary in that respect. The limits of the Edu<lb break="no"/>cation districts were not found so convenient as was <lb/>
desirable. There were also some other improvements <lb/>
required, and an arrangement had been entered into <lb/>
by the Government for the supply of a uniform set of <lb/>
school books at a cheaper rate than they could be pro<lb break="no"/>cured by depending on the book-sellers for their im<lb break="no"/>portation. That should be provided for by law. With <lb/>
respect to the normal school, there was an appropria<lb break="no"/>tion under the existing Act for the training of teach<lb break="no"/>ers at the several Protestant institutions. It was <lb/>
thought that the training could be made more efficient <lb/>
by combining the money thus expended in one sum; <lb/>
and that it would be sufficiant for the maintenance of <lb/>
a normal school. They did not propose to interfere <lb/>
<choice><sic>wish</sic><corr>with</corr></choice> the existing denominational arrangements. From <lb/>
the opinions expressed by those who might be consi<lb break="no"/>dered as expressing Roman Catholic opinion, they <lb/>
appeared to be satisfied with the system of training <lb/>
which they had already at St. Bonaventure College, <lb/>
and they would not be interfered with, and the appro<lb break="no"/>priations for training Protestant teachers would be <lb/>
combined for the support of a Protestant normal school. <lb/></p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. KENT</persName>—Would any portion of the Roman Ca<lb break="no"/>tholic grant be touched? <lb/></p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>—Not without the con<lb break="no"/>sent of the Roman Catholic members. <lb/></p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:KENT2">Mr. KENT</persName>—They might do what they pleased with <lb/>
their own. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The motion that the section be adopted was then <lb/>
put and carried. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The several sections of the address down to that in <lb/>
        reference to the currency were <choice><sic>aead</sic><corr>read</corr></choice> <hi rendition="simple:italic">seriatim</hi> and <lb/>
adopted. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The section respecting the currency having been read, <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:WYAT1">Mr. WYATT</persName> moved that it be adopted. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName> said the measure introduced by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, and passed the session before last, was un<lb break="no"/>doubtedly a good one. But in order to perfect the <lb/>
arrangements it should be made compulsory on the <lb/>
merchants and all engaged in the trade of the country <lb/>
to keep their accounts in dollars and cents. At pre<lb break="no"/>sent there was a good deal of misunderstanding and <lb/>
discontent among poor people relative to the copper <lb/>
currency, as they were under the impression that they <lb/>
lost two pence on every shilling. It was absolutely <lb/>
necessary that it should be made incumbent on the <lb/>
trade to keep their accounts in accordance with the <lb/>
provisions of the Act, otherwise we would have to <lb/>
go back to the old system of pounds, shillings and <lb/>
pence. <lb/></p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. Attorney GENERAL</persName> –The observations of <lb/>
the hon memner were well worthy of the attention and <lb/>
serious consideration of the Government and the <lb/>
Legislature. The law, however, had only been a few <lb/>
weeks in operation. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>The motion was then put and carried. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
Some othar sections, down to the 11th, on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject of confederation, were read seriatim and adopted. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        The Committee then rose, and the Chairman report<lb break="no"/>ed progress.—To sit again to-morrow. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:RENO1">Mr. RENOUF</persName> gave notice that on to-morrow he <lb/>
would ask the Acting Colonial Secretary to lay on the <lb/>
table of the House a copy of tenders, notice and <lb/>
agreement, for the hire of the vessel to carry the <lb/>
Commissioner of Fisheries, Judge, and Collector of <lb/>
Revenue to the coast of Labrador in 1864. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The house then adjourned until Thursday at three <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/></p>
    
    <!-- IC, 2018-11-09, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
    
    <!--<p>
THURSDAY, Feb. 2. <lb/>
The House met at three o'clock. <lb/>
On motion of Mr. WYATT, pursuant to order of the <lb/>
day, the House resolved itself into Committee of the <lb/>
whole on the further consideration of the address in <lb/>
reply to his Excellency's speech at the opening of the <lb/>
session, Mr KNIGHT in the chair. <lb/>
Mr WYATT said the next section for consideration <lb/>
was the 11th, in reference to the confederation of the <lb/>
Colonies. He moved that the section be read. <lb/>
The motion was put and carried, and the section <lb/>
was read as follows:–<lb break="yes"/>"The subject of the proposed Confederation of the <lb/>
British Nora American Provinces is one of the great­ <lb/>
est interest and unpo'tance, and we concur with your <lb/>
Excellency that it should be approached in a spirit of <lb/>
calm enquiry, keeping in view, as well the present, as <lb/>
the probable future offects on the people of this <lb/>
Colony." <lb/>
The SPEAKER said he had not hitherto had an op­ <lb/>
Portunity of making any observations respecting his <lb/>
Excellency's speech; and perhaps it was scarcely ne­ <lb/>
cessary for him to say anything regarding a speech <lb/>
which was so very satisfactory to hon gentlemen on <lb/>
both sides of the House. For the first time-since he <lb/>
(the Speaker) thad the honor of a seat in that House. <lb/>
had he heard the members on the opposition side <lb/>
praise the speech from the throne. Hon members on <lb/>
the opposition benches indorsed in complimentary <lb/>
language the important practical suggestions of his <lb/>
Excellency's speech. It was evident, however, that <lb/>
these hon gentleinen, in their ignorance of constitu­ <lb/>
tion: Isages, regarded the speech as emanating from <lb/>
the Governor himself, and not the embodiment of the <lb/>
poiicy of his constitutional advisers; and it was not <lb/>
until that experienced parliamentary tactician, the <lb/>
hon member for St. John's East, Mr Kent, set these <lb/>
hon members right, that tary became aware that they <lb/>
were bestowing the most unqualified commendation <lb/>
upon the policy of his (the Speaker's) hon friend, the <lb/>
leader of the government. One hon member said it <lb/>
was a parliamentary fiction that the speech was the <lb/>
speech of the ministry. He (the Speaker) must say <lb/>
hat this was novel constitutional doctrine emanating <lb/>
ſºom a professed admirer of responsibie government. <lb/>
Next day, however, there was some attempt to find <lb/>
fault, but it was so feeble that it was not entitled to <lb/>
notice. He (the Speaker) did say the members of the <lb/>
Government had reason to congratulate themselves <lb/>
upon this unqualified indorsation of their policy by <lb/>
the opposition. With respect to his Excellency's <lb/>
*peech, he (the Speaker) would observe that he had <lb/>
listened to few speeches couched in more elegant lan: <lb/>
guage, and he must congratulate the House" and the <lb/>
ºuntry upon the choice Her Majesty had made of a <lb/>
Gºvernor of so much ability and intellectuality, to <lb/>
administer the affairs of this ancient and loyal colony. <lb/></p> 

<p>H.s Excellency came here in the pr.ne of life, aud he <lb/>
must have been highly appreciated by uer Alyesty, <lb/></p> 

<p>Government when he was appointed to such a high <lb/>
and responsible office as the government of this im­ <lb/>
portant dependancy of the Crown. There was soarcely <lb/>
a subject of public interest in the colony which was <lb/>
not referred to in that speech. The subject of pauper­ <lb/>
ism occupied a prominent place. There was scarsely <lb/>
a session but they bad to take that question into con­ <lb/>
sideration. Poverty, in one part of the island or <lb/>
another, was almost of annual recurrence, showing the <lb/>
necessity of providing some other means of subsistence <lb/>
for the people besides precarious fisheries. There <lb/>
were no people who worked harder or toiled more <lb/>
incessantly than did many of the fishermen of this <lb/>
colony, or who poured more wealth into the treasury <lb/>
of their employers, while, at the same time, they were <lb/>
subject to the recurrence of seasons of wide spread <lb/>
destitution. Some remedy was required to reach this <lb/>
evil, and if any remedy was devised, it must come <lb/>
from this House, for it would not come from those <lb/>
who profited by the fishermens' toil: The encourage­ <lb/>
ment of the Bank and Mackerel fisheries, and the <lb/>
promotion of agriculture were calculated to prove most <lb/>
beneficial in furnishing profitable employment to our <lb/>
people and thus improving their circumstances. But <lb/>
the question which chiefly engrosse I public attention <lb/>
was that referred to in the section just read. He (the <lb/>
Speaker) would act with impartiality in regard to that <lb/>
matter. It was a question on which he had no party <lb/>
views to subserve. He came to its decision fearlessly <lb/>
and independently, and cared for no clamour raised <lb/>
by interested parties cut of doors; and he did say that <lb/>
he would discuss it without feeling. It was a matter <lb/>
which had agitated the country for some months, and <lb/>
was the most important question which could occupy <lb/>
the attention of the Legislature. A day was fixed for <lb/>
the discussion of that question; and he (the Speaker) <lb/>
would not now anticipate what he might then have to <lb/>
say on the subject. But having had the honour of <lb/>
being appointed one of the delazates to the confer­ <lb/>
ence held on this subject at Qiubec, he would be ex­ <lb/>
pected tº take the earliest opportunity of entering into <lb/>
explanations respecting the proceedings of that con­ <lb/>
ference. When he considered that there were partias <lb/>
out of doors who, from interested motives, were desir­ <lb/>
ous of defeating the object of that conference, and <lb/>
when we found them indulging in such clap-tran with <lb/>
a view to excite a clamour against the proposed con­ <lb/>
federation, charging the Delegates with selling the <lb/>
country, as if there were in his mind or in that of the <lb/>
gentleman associated with him any desire except to <lb/>
promote the best interests of their native land—when <lb/>
he found such calumnies resorted to he would take that <lb/>
opportunity to nake a few observations. His co-delegate <lb/>
and himself had not been pitchforked into the country. <lb/>
They had not traded on the interests of the penaº, <lb/>
They went to the Conference with an earnest resolu­ <lb/>
tion to benefit their native land to the utmost of their <lb/>
ability, feeling the deep responsibility of the duties <lb/>
they had undertaken. They were de ermined to d, <lb/>
nothing which, in their opinion, would be calculated <lb/>
to prejudice the country in which they had such a <lb/>
deep interest. And who should feel a deeper interest <lb/>
in the prosperity of Newfoundland than they did P <lb/>
Both natives of the Island, in which all their interests <lb/>
centred, was it to be supposed that either of them <lb/>
would do anything calculated to prejudice the true <lb/>
interests of their country? He (the Speaker) ex­ <lb/>
pected to spend his life in the country, and he did <lb/>
not anticipate any personal advantage from the pro­ <lb/>
posed federation, farther than it would promote the <lb/>
prosperity of the land of his nativity and the home of <lb/>
his children. If was said they were giving away the <lb/>
fisheries. Now those who said so knew it was not <lb/>
true. They knew that the people of all British North <lb/>
America had the same interest in the fisheries as we <lb/>
have. But at the conference it was stipulated, which <lb/>
was readily conceded, that we should reserve the <lb/>
power to make such enactments as might be necessay <lb/>
for the protection of the fisheries. Again, it was said <lb/>
we were destroying the liberties of the people. He was <lb/>
surprised to hear such a statement put forward. Would <lb/>
any person have his fiberty curtailed by taking up his <lb/>
residence in Great Britain, in Nova Scotia, New Bruns­ <lb/>
wick, or Canada? These countries all had responsible <lb/>
government before we had it. And it was the very first <lb/>
decision come to at the Conference that with a view <lb/>
to the perpetuation of our connection with the mother <lb/>
country, and the promotion of the best interests of the <lb/>
people, the model of the British government should <lb/>
be followed, so far as circumstances would permit, the <lb/>
Government being vested in Her Most Gracious <lb/>
Majesty and administerod by her representative in <lb/>
accordance with the well understood principles of the <lb/>
British constitution. He (the Speaker) was surprised <lb/>
when he heard yesterday a member of that II»use sny <lb/>
that he wanted to be British, and not to be ruled by <lb/>
French or Dutch Canadians—what an absurdity our <lb/>
British connection would be guaranteed by an Act of <lb/>
the Imperial Parliament. With responsible govern­ <lb/>
ment, the ministry of the day responsible to the people <lb/>
not merely of Canada, but also of New Brunswick, <lb/>
Nova Scotia, Newfoundland, and Prince Edward <lb/>
Island, would not our liberties be as well secured as <lb/>
at present, and our British connection perpetuated for <lb/>
ages to come 2 Again, we were told of the establish­ <lb/>
ment of a militia, as if the people were to be marched <lb/>
to the frontier of Canada to repel invasion from that <lb/>
province. When he found gentlemen, from whom <lb/>
better might be expected, getting up clap-trap of that <lb/>
kind, he regarded it as the best evidence that they <lb/>
had nothing substantial to urge against the proposel <lb/>
confederation. Where was there anything in the reso­ <lb/>
lutions to indicate any such purpose P. How could we <lb/>
have a militia force in this Colony. Our fishermen, <lb/>
from the very nature of their occupation, could not be <lb/>
organized into a militia. During the summer season <lb/>
the greater number of them were absent from their <lb/>
homes prosecuting the fishery. It was only amongst <lb/>
an agricultural population that a militia could be or­ <lb/>
ganized. But, he (the Speaker) would ask, whether <lb/>
every man of right feeling in the country would not be <lb/>
ready to arm in defence of his family and his home <lb/>
and the land of his nativity or adoption, should the <lb/>
necessity arise? The triumphs of the British navy <lb/>
were not achieved without ine powerful aid of the <lb/>
fishermen of Newfoundland, and we had now a body <lb/>
of fishermen who in valour and physical vigour were <lb/>
not inferior to their aucestors, and who were as ready <lb/>
to defend their country as any class of Her Majesty's <lb/>
subjects. There might be some legislation with res­ <lb/>
pect to the Volunteers, but he (the Speaker) was cer. <lb/>
tain that Britain would continue to use the protection <lb/>
of her troops, and that the navywould not be with­ <lb/>
drawn. He had authority for saying that all that the <lb/>
statesmen of Great Britain required was that the <lb/>
people of the colonies should show a disposition to <lb/>
protect themselves, and that protection which had <lb/>
hitherto been accorded them would not only be con­ <lb/>
tinued, but increased But it was said "you are going <lb/>
to bind us to Canada." Now we had heard that sai <lb/>
by persons who had never seen Canada, who had <lb/>
never been out of this Colony; and perhaps it would <lb/>
be as well for some of them to travel a littie and visit <lb/>
that magnificent province, as well as Nova Scotia and <lb/>
New Brunswick, which were advancing so rapidly in <lb/>
material prosperity, and in all that tended to make a <lb/>
peºple great and respected. How many had emigra­ <lb/>
ted from this Colony to Canada, and found ther a <lb/>
home where their industry was rewarded with Compe­ <lb/>
tence for themselves and their families? But we were <lb/>
to be united, not merely to Canada, but to Nova <lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick, and in the Legislature of <lb/>
tue uon we would all be represented accord.ag to <lb/></p> 

<p>T-mm­ <lb/></p> 

<p>our population. It was a treaty, which, if carried Out <lb/>
would give us all one great country, extending from <lb/>
the Atlantic to the Pacific, in whose onwariº. <lb/>
and prosperity we wonld participate, and whose glor <lb/>
and renown would be the inheritance of your child. <lb/>
Our alliance was not to be with Canada alone, but alsº <lb/>
with Nova Scotia and New Branswick. These Coun­ <lb/>
tries were all more prosperous than we are, for it must <lb/>
be admitted that we are at the lowest point of depres. <lb/>
sion. It was useless to talk of the 600,000 seals, or <lb/>
the 400,000 that we are to have this spring. Would. <lb/>
one successful seal fishery reestablish our prºsperity? <lb/>
But hon gentlemen would retain their isolation. jã <lb/>
they recollect 1857, two years after the establishment <lb/>
of responsible government, when a convention waº <lb/>
entered into with France, giving away our best fishi. <lb/>
grounds, and when a few hours after the Convention <lb/>
was made public here, property was depreciated 40 <lb/>
per cent? What did we do then? Did we contemn tº <lb/>
aid of Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, and Canada? No, <lb/>
but a deputation was appointed.consisting of the hº <lb/>
member for St. John's East, Mr. Kent, and himself <lb/>
(the Speaker) to proceed to these provinces, whose all <lb/>
liance some hon, members would now contemn, and <lb/>
we received their warmest sympathy and cooperation <lb/>
to defeat that convention, which, if carried into effect, <lb/>
would have transferred our most valuable fisheries tº <lb/>
the French. , What was the result P-Out came thaci. <lb/>
cular dispatch of the Colonial Minister, announcing <lb/>
that the convention was withdrawn. Hon. member. <lb/>
said we would never again have such a convention, <lb/>
But how did they know P Was not the influence of <lb/>
France as potent at Downing Street now as then? <lb/>
And were not our proceedings vigillantly watched by <lb/>
the emissaries of the French Emperor?' And would <lb/>
not our isolation, if we persisted in it, give the desired <lb/>
opportunity of endeavouring to obtain frem the Bri. <lb/>
tish Government what it has long been his polic) to <lb/>
secare? And supposing the convention of 1857 should <lb/>
be renewed, what were we to do? Would we send tº <lb/>
the neighbouring Provinces P. If we did, they would <lb/>
most likely reply—" We assisted you once, and when <lb/>
subsequently we proposed a federation which would || <lb/>
have secured the protection of your interests in all <lb/>
time coming, you refused to become parties to it. You <lb/>
may now protect yourselves." But the union was ob. <lb/></p> 

<p>º <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>2. <lb/></p> 

<p>jected to on the plea of increased taxation, Could any <lb/>
hon member recollect when, a few years ago, the <lb/>
great leader of the opposition to this confederation <lb/>
proposed to lay an export duty on fish and oil? And <lb/>
now he came forward, as the professed friend of the <lb/>
fisherman, to oppose the union on the plea of increas. <lb/>
*... taxation. ... And how much would they be taxed? <lb/>
Would they feel 2, 3, or 4 per cent over the present <lb/>
taxation * Were they not sufficiently taxed aired)? <lb/>
Pid they not receive their supplies at an advance of <lb/>
50 or 63? Did not the fishermº at present get dour <lb/>
imported, duty free, under the reciprocity treaty,and <lb/>
was there any reduction in their accounts in conse. <lb/>
quence? But we must bear in mind that a notice has <lb/>
been given to abrogate the reciprocity treaty, and <lb/>
with it we would lose our free trade with the other <lb/>
colonies, for we could not expect, if we refused to join <lb/>
in this confederation, that the other provinces wºuld <lb/>
continue the admission of our produce duty free. But <lb/>
under this confederation, not only the products of the <lb/>
fisheries and of agriculture, but also the manufacture. <lb/>
of the several provinces would pass duty free from one <lb/>
to the other. Now, Canada, New Brunswick, and <lb/>
Nova Scotia were extensive" in manufacturing, and <lb/>
the very articles required by our fisherinen were m <lb/>
nufactured in these provinces at a cheaper rate. Let <lb/></p> 

<p>this convention be carried out, and food and clothing <lb/></p> 

<p>for our fisherman would be brought in duty-free from <lb/></p> 

<p>the neighbouring provinces. Again, they should <lb/>
support this confederation on account of their children. <lb/></p> 

<p>Was there no regard for them P Waat future was # <lb/>
there for any young man brought up in this country <lb/>
If his object was to engage in commercial pursuits, <lb/>
where was he to get his flaining P. How were we to: <lb/>
get a mercantile education for many of our sons, with <lb/>
the importations which were annually made from <lb/>
išritain P. Some must go to another country, and <lb/>
where were they to go to, with the British provinces <lb/>
broken up into fragments P To the United States? <lb/>
Every feeling of patriotism dictated that they should <lb/>
remain under the British flag. Supposing they now <lb/>
went to Canada, who were they to apply to P 'But it <lb/>
we formed part of the same country, they would find <lb/>
our members there, and if we were careful in their: <lb/>
selection, they would be such as would make them. <lb/>
selves felt, limited as was the number to which our <lb/>
population entitled us. Our young men could apply <lb/>
to these members, whose interest would oe made avail. <lb/>
able to forward their views. Look at Scotland, for in­ <lb/></p> 

<p>stance. How many went from Scotland, and on appli. <lb/></p> 

<p>cation to their members in the Imperial Parliament, <lb/></p> 

<p>got appointments, which enabled them by the prope: <lb/></p> 

<p>exercise of their talents to rise to eminence P And he <lb/></p> 

<p>(the Speaker) was aware that many young men who t <lb/></p> 

<p>came over to England from Ireland, were equally suc- º <lb/>
cessful, through the influence of the Irish members. <lb/>
And it would be the same under this convention, <lb/>
while, at the same time, the recommendation of of our <lb/>
Representatives, to whom they might be known, or <lb/>
bring introductions, would be influential in procuring <lb/>
situations for our young men in mercantile establisa. <lb/>
ments. There was abundance of room in the neigh­ <lb/>
bouring Provinces for all our young men who might <lb/>
not find employment here, for hundreds of years to <lb/>
come. Then were we not in a state of the deepest <lb/>
depression 2 And what would raise as from it so <lb/>
effectually as union with the neighbouring provinces? <lb/>
How often have we heard the wish expressed for year, <lb/>
past for union with these provinces P And now when <lb/>
we had the opportunity, many amongst us would <lb/>
prefer isolation. The financial arrangements entered <lb/>
into would give a batter revenue than we had on the <lb/>
average of the last ten years, securing sufficient means <lb/>
tor the road service, so much complained of, as being <lb/>
inadequately provided for. We wauld also be provided <lb/>
with direct steam communication at the expense of . <lb/>
the Federal Government, as well as steam communi­ <lb/>
cation with Canada, which, no doubt, would induct <lb/>
the visits of capitalists, and stimulate enterprise, <lb/>
leading to competition, which, while it would benefit <lb/>
the community, was not, perhaps, desired by some. <lb/>
But although it might be the means of reducing profits, <lb/>
anything that would promote employment must prove <lb/>
beneficial to the working classes. Ít was said they <lb/>
were giving away the Urown lauds and the minerals <lb/>
of the island. From the clamour raised by some <lb/>
gentlemen on this subject, one would unagine thº' <lb/>
the Canadians were to send down a number of vessels <lb/>
with pickaxes and snovels to carry away the land. It <lb/>
would be a rather arduous task to take away the rock <lb/>
of this Island—to take away even Chain rock, and at <lb/>
for Signal Hill, who was to attempt its removal But <lb/>
what did we want? What had we been wishing ſo; <lb/>
years P Did we not want our wild lands improved? <lb/>
Who was to do it? Was it not wel, to induce the peopl" <lb/>
who were willing to pay so handsomaly for them,t) iſ } <lb/>
prove them, so as to tepay them for their outlay? Wº <lb/>
knew we were to get a handsome sum for the surreº." <lb/>
der of our Crown lands, and we also knew that * <lb/>
render them productive of revenue a large expendituº <lb/>
would be involved in surveys, and the working . <lb/>
our mines, which would be all for our benefit, whi" <lb/>
there could be no interference with local enº <lb/>
prise, for the lands were as available to us as to º <lb/>
9-her portion of the Confederation, and local * <lb/>
ists had greater facilities than those who came troº <lb/></p> 

<p>§ <lb/></p> 

<p>* <lb/></p> 

<p>- - ...,ntieſ <lb/>
ustance. But our own capital is, with the excep" <lb/></p> 

<p>of Mr. Bennett, had hit <lb/>
age in mining operatiº <lb/>
tº our mines should b <lb/>
ital, as with British or A <lb/>
little of either had co <lb/>
Canadian capitalists to <lb/>
not failito prove advant <lb/>
they did not come, wº. <lb/>
resent. The sum of $ <lb/>
to receive for our Crowl <lb/>
Again, so me hon memb <lb/>
about providing empl <lb/>
establishing factories. <lb/>
economically, should be <lb/>
prise, and the best mean <lb/>
rovide an extended ma <lb/>
the Confederation woul: <lb/>
sumers, a number which <lb/>
with our extensive watel <lb/>
could offer inducements <lb/>
establish manufactures, <lb/>
American market was <lb/>
tion. We had a large <lb/>
Island for whom everyt <lb/>
Confederation was carri <lb/>
of depriving some of on <lb/>
tions they had occupied <lb/>
all know how difficult i <lb/>
give up that from which <lb/>
importance. They knew <lb/>
who traded on the passic <lb/>
ple to submit to an arral <lb/>
pations wonld be gone. <lb/>
pect of it, and therefore <lb/>
the interests of the peop <lb/>
that is to be, and increas: <lb/>
they regard their own pr <lb/>
are ready to sacrifice the <lb/>
Our House of Assembly <lb/>
importance, and ought a <lb/>
in numbers. Subjects ol <lb/>
occupy the attention of ti <lb/>
tomed to deal with, and <lb/>
much less important that <lb/>
past. But we ought all <lb/>
not private and person <lb/>
beneficial result of Conſ. <lb/>
ascerbity of feeling whic <lb/>
contests would be done a <lb/>
past there had been a co <lb/>
tween the two religious p <lb/>
tion is divided, and elect <lb/>
tº be carried in certain d <lb/>
deprecated. With Conf <lb/>
to return to the federal i <lb/>
men, and those who po <lb/>
public confidence, irres <lb/>
gentlemen wish to see e! <lb/>
oration would bring laig <lb/>
attention of politicizns. <lb/>
community who traded o <lb/>
wanted a relative provi <lb/>
pointment for him, not o <lb/>
said—"it is our right as <lb/>
that the wuy to promote <lb/>
service? Wnen we wer. <lb/>
our Crown lands it appe <lb/>
gave the Telegraph Uom <lb/>
for the express purpose tº <lb/>
the Com; any, sº far as h <lb/>
hgen unable to induce a s <lb/>
lands; and now we were <lb/>
lands for a large anni <lb/>
likely to get them setti <lb/>
giving the Canadians t <lb/>
pleasure. The power of <lb/>
ceded to the General Paº <lb/>
be representatives from <lb/>
supposed that the other <lb/>
love with taxation that iſ <lb/>
ue from Newfoundlan <lb/>
heavily 2 There would <lb/>
whole Confederation an <lb/>
some said there ought t <lb/>
should not be required t <lb/>
amount. The result of: <lb/>
that as population adva <lb/>
ment was in a condition <lb/>
still be called on for cur <lb/>
excess of what we woul <lb/>
then tariff. There was a <lb/>
the subject of taxation, <lb/>
Canada desired to get <lb/>
squeeze out of us the m <lb/>
large revenue. The ver <lb/>
were those who oppose. <lb/>
tutional government he <lb/>
was granted after consiſ <lb/>
tended that the *iouse <lb/>
taxation, and the then { <lb/>
having declared that out <lb/>
er of taxation. With r <lb/>
no reason to apprehend <lb/>
would propose a high la <lb/>
with being taxed higher <lb/>
And when he spoke of <lb/>
must admit that he had <lb/>
and he lost his office fol <lb/>
back to the days of irr <lb/>
back to the tunes prece: <lb/>
the country had made <lb/>
disasters. But he was <lb/>
tion we would find such <lb/>
sent contemplated. Al <lb/>
and prosperous country <lb/>
munication by steam, v <lb/>
isola iun which had so <lb/>
then if our import duti <lb/>
than now, we would ha <lb/>
One word more on a <lb/>
good deal of misapprel <lb/>
been a colcession to tº <lb/>
get, by which these Pi <lb/>
the necessity of havit <lb/>
The misapprehension <lb/>
the following section o <lb/>
euce defining the powe <lb/>
make laws for "the i <lb/>
ties of Customs on I <lb/>
Exports of Timber, I <lb/>
Suwn Lumber, and of <lb/>
It was inferred from th <lb/>
ted to impose an ex <lb/>
and that the Delegate <lb/>
stipulated from their <lb/>
But the other Provinc <lb/>
besides the articles e <lb/>
these were especially <lb/>
tia and New Brunswic <lb/>
them, which they are: <lb/>
territorial revenue, <lb/>
exported is cut on the <lb/>
retained by the Provi <lb/>
ence, the government <lb/>
years ago, discontinu <lb/>
substituting for it an <lb/>
samu way in Nova Sc <lb/>
Royalty on Coal and <lb/>
payable at the Cust <lb/>
referred to merely p <lb/>
should retain that rew <lb/>
them. But as to imp <lb/></p> 

<p>I-m­ <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>