<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-19" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNLLA">Newfoundland Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1869-02-19">19 February 1869</date>, Newfoundland Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNLLA"> <editor>Edward Dalton Shea</editor>.
<title>The Newfoundlander</title>.
<date when="1869-02-24"/>.
<pubPlace>St. Johns, Newfoundland</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Edward Dalton Shea</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="3"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_3.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2019-01-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2019-01-07">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_3"> <graphic url="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_3.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="2" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_2.jpg"/> 
    
    <fw type="num">2</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER</fw>


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-07, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
    
<!--<p>f <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>Union of Ireland was also brought forward in <lb/>
eloquent terms, what possible contestion was <lb/>
there between the Union of Ireland and this <lb/>
guestion of Confederation?, Hon. gentiemen <lb/>
#ºvery well that it had none, and it was <lb/>
sowardly, mean and dastardly thus to appeal to <lb/>
the passions and prejudices of the peopl-. His <lb/>
District had suºred a great deal by the with­ <lb/>
drawal of local steam, The withdrawal, how <lb/>
ever was unavoidable, for in the present cºndi­ <lb/>
tion of the colony the subsidy could not be afford­ <lb/>
si. He thought that local steam shoull b2.4 <lb/>
sine, ºa Won of Confederation. They would <lb/>
then have something better thaa the dirty tub <lb/>
hey used to have, and wouli also have batter <lb/>
than the present tub ic Conception Bay. He <lb/>
Ener that the hon. member for S. John's had <lb/>
tried and were trying to stir up a feeling agº inst <lb/>
confederation, but he balieved that his(Mr.P") <lb/>
constituents were favorable to it on good terms <lb/>
He hoped these good terms would be gºt, and <lb/>
that if not none other would be accepted. He <lb/>
had often in that House triel to procure the <lb/>
erection of a Light House in his district, but <lb/>
had failed. Las: summer representations on the <lb/>
matter were made to the Dominiou Government <lb/>
and without hesitation they sent down a steamer; <lb/>
had a survey held and the site agree; on, and <lb/>
the building will commence at once. There was <lb/>
aarnest of one of the benefits of Confederation. <lb/>
The speeches on this question were sº long that <lb/>
the subject was nearly worn threadbare, but <lb/>
there was one importan; matter which was <lb/>
only slightly, if at all glanced at. That was <lb/>
the power given to the Dominion Palliament to <lb/>
negotiate commercial treaties, which would <lb/>
aftect this country in the matters of the French <lb/>
shore and the Spanish trade. H3 had been <lb/>
told that the Dominion was endeavoring to es­ <lb/>
tablish a free trade with the Spanish West <lb/>
India Islands, and that it will be accomplished <lb/>
so soon as the affairs of Spain are settled. New­ <lb/>
foundland had a very great interest in that <lb/>
matter. The differential duty against foreign flºgs <lb/>
had op d very prejudicially to our i <lb/>
This àuty had been the means of prohibiting our <lb/>
fish being carried in English bottoms to Spain, <lb/>
and it had been maintained by the interest <lb/>
which a few Blediterranean ship-owners poss <lb/>
sessed at the Cortes. With the new Govern­ <lb/>
ment the flºg duty wonlil be taken away,aud our <lb/>
commercial rel, tions with Spain would, through <lb/>
the influence of the Dominiou be placed upon a <lb/>
much fairer footing than at prosent. It was of <lb/>
the greatest possible importance tº u; that ºur <lb/>
interests should be represented at Madrid. The <lb/>
produce of Swaden, and Holland had, through <lb/>
the influence of their respective Ministers, been <lb/>
brought into great demand in tºº, Spanish <lb/>
market. Spain consumed annually 900,0004 le. <lb/>
of codfish, and of this we did not send them one­ <lb/>
fourth, hiring been cut out by the Swedish <lb/>
fish. Petitions and memorials sent year after <lb/>
year to the Colouial office had all proved una­ <lb/>
wailing to remove the invidious obstacles against <lb/>
which we had to contend, and our only cuance <lb/>
of success lay in the power conferred upon the <lb/>
idominion, of making commercial treaties and <lb/>
sending an accredited minister to these Courts. <lb/>
He (Air. P.) had referred to this point because <lb/>
he knew something of it personally. He trust­ <lb/>
ed when the real questiou came down,the terms <lb/>
and bona fide conditions of Conſederation, they <lb/>
will receive that calm and dispassionate coasi­ <lb/>
deration to which they were entitled. <lb/>
The hon. Colonial Secretany should have <lb/>
taken no part in the debate, did he not consider <lb/>
it the duty of every hon member to express his <lb/>
opinions on the important, matters, belore the <lb/>
ciair, For his (hou C. S's) part, he was tied <lb/>
by no pledges, but felt himself perfectly free to <lb/>
déal with the question of Confederation and, to <lb/>
give publicity to the views which he had <lb/>
always held. When the question was first <lb/>
brought into notice,though we had a genial tariff <lb/>
and ºverything in our favour, he had been of <lb/>
opinion that we could not ally ourselves to the <lb/>
neighbouring Colonies without being benefitted <lb/>
He had regarded Newfoundland as a poor family <lb/>
invited to cast in her lot with half a dozen <lb/>
families in comfortable circumstances, and he <lb/>
had beon persuaded that such a union cºuld not <lb/>
but rebound to her advantage. In 1865 he had <lb/>
before his constituents avowed his seutiments, <lb/>
aud he had told them that whenever the question <lb/>
came up for consideration he would wu.e in <lb/>
favour of it. If then they had disapproved of <lb/>
his sentiments they need not have elected him: <lb/>
He should now vote in favour of the Address, and <lb/>
if in this he was running counter to the opinions <lb/></p> 

<p>of his district they were perfectly, free tº elect <lb/></p> 

<p>another man. We could not but regard this <lb/>
quastion of unior as one fraught with impora <lb/>
tance, as it must affect the weal or woe of the <lb/>
country for all time to come. The <lb break="no"/>o the matter could not without prejudice to the <lb/>
community be longer delayed. Delay would <lb/>
not only be cowardly but suicidal as, regurded <lb/>
the interests of the Country and those who <lb/>
were charged with the protection of those inter­ <lb/>
ests. He believed the country demanded, a <lb/></p> 

<p>decision at the hands of this House, uud that || <lb/></p> 

<p>seven-tenths of the people of the Island, were iu <lb/>
favour of a change. Should then that change be <lb/>
such as would continue us in our present posi­ <lb/>
tion as a luiserable fishing dependency? Qe <lb/>
should it be such as woull unito us with a <lb/>
Dominion growing in wealth and importance <lb/>
every day? With reference to the subject of <lb/>
Reciprocity,though every hop.membº adulitted <lb/>
its advantges, there was a variety ºf opinions. <lb/>
Hon gentlemen on this side agreed with his <lb/>
Excellency, that separated from the Dominion <lb/>
we should be in no position to ensure to our­ <lb/>
selves the banefits of reciprocal free trade, while <lb/>
hon, gentlemen opposits contended that lºck <lb/>
procity might be brought abour by a reductiºn <lb/>
of the civil expenditure. With this latter view <lb/>
he (non, C.S.), could not concur. Wherever <lb/>
there was a useless expenditure or a useless <lb/>
'office ie: it be roaqved. But, refranch, as we <lb/>
might he cºnsidered it, utterly impossible to <lb/>
obtain all the begains from such a policy as <lb/></p> 

<p>... their and if toey could succeed in <lb/></p> 

<p>. . .ent before us cæstituents, if they disapprowed <lb/></p> 

<p>*** <lb/></p> 

<p>hon. members opposite contemplated, and though <lb/>
these benefits might be obtained, he considered <lb/>
that they would bear no compariso...!? those <lb/>
growing out of confederation. He (hon: 3. S.) <lb/>
had understood the hop. member, Mr. Little, to <lb/>
say that it was the intention of the Government <lb/>
to adopt by resolution the saction of this colony <lb/>
º, whº terms of Confederation. He (hoa. C. S.), <lb/>
id not understaad it so. If this were so." <lb/>
question would be definitely settled. T./ <lb/>
measure could act be tested at the general <lb/>
election and the election, would be a question <lb/>
not of measures bat of mea. The hon. taember <lb/>
was throwing dust in the eyes of his coustituency, <lb/>
and endeavouring to shirk the responsibility <lb/>
which was incumbent upon him, leaving himself <lb/>
free to accept Confederation as a foregone º <lb/>
clusion, while it was in reality undecided and hº <lb/>
might in hones'y oppose it. He (ºn. C. S.) <lb/>
considered that the time had arrived when wº <lb/>
should acº like rational creatures. We could <lb/>
not remain blind to the decleusion of the means <lb/>
of employment and deaf to the appeals of misºry <lb/>
and distress. The resources on which the <lb/>
people haſ trusted did not keep Peº with the <lb/>
increase of population. He did not mean tº <lb/>
say that Coatederation would have the effect of <lb/>
bringing fish to our shores,but he regarded it as <lb/>
a means to an end, and that end the gradual but <lb/>
unceasing and certain improvement of the con­ <lb/>
dit on of the country. It would be needless for <lb/>
him to express in detail his views upon this sub, <lb/>
ject, for abler hands had already dealt with it in <lb/>
all its bearings. He hoped that the terms tº <lb/>
which this House would assant would be such <lb/>
as would prove advantageous to the country, <lb/>
that there would be no difficulty in obtaising <lb/>
their appoval at the hands of the General Gov; <lb/>
ernment, and that before long Newfoundland <lb/>
would b: an integral part of the Confederacy. <lb/>
Mir, Giles.-Hon. members opposite seemed to <lb/>
be trying to educate the people ºn the subject of <lb/>
Confjºtion, before the terms &amp;ame down. He <lb/>
only rose to make a relaark upon the speech of the <lb/>
hon. Recover General, which was a very able and <lb/>
o ive speech. "But the lion, gentleman had <lb/>
sºd matters which were not facts,tending to delude <lb/>
the people. This statement could not arise from <lb/>
the ignorance of the hon. gettleman. If the state­ <lb/>
men had come from the hou. member, Mr. Pinsent, <lb/>
he (Mr. G.) would not have taken, the slightest <lb/>
notice of it,for he did not consider that that hon, gº­ <lb/>
tlemaa was quite au fait at figures. The honºe­ <lb/>
ceiver General had stated that our expenditure <lb/>
ºnder Confederation would be $315,000 and the <lb/>
grant from the Dominion $416,000, so that $100,000 <lb/>
would annually be left for roads. Now the Dom ni­ <lb/>
on did not grant us $416,000, so the fact stated was <lb/>
not correct. The amount of the Dominion subsidy <lb/>
was sºč9,000, so that there was a difference of <lb/>
$47,000 against the Colony. That statement ºf the <lb/>
hon, gantleman had gone, forth to the world, had <lb/>
been extensively read, and coming forth with the <lb/>
prestige of his high character, it must have taken <lb/>
effect. The hon. gentieman should have been more <lb/>
guarded. If the Confederate cause were a good <lb/>
une, it would not require misstatements to support <lb/>
it. The hon, member, Mr. Pinsent, seemed to be <lb/>
trimming his wings for a ſlight to Ottawa, and when <lb/>
bya and bye the ugly rush for situations came (for <lb/>
tàers would be an ugly rush), the bon. member if he <lb/>
tailed in getting a high legil position * Attorney <lb/>
General or Sºlicitor General, after the display <lb/>
which he had made the other day, would be § <lb/>
Justified in looking for the post of Finance Minister. <lb/>
He (M.G.) had stated a few days ago that the <lb/>
Dºminion was in difficulties, and that to save theº­ <lb/>
sºlves from insoºveccy, they had to issue $5,000,000 <lb/>
in Treasury notes. The hon member, Mr. Rendell, <lb/>
had said that that could not be, as their debentures <lb/>
were at a premium in London. The hon. Maember <lb/>
should recºlect that at that time parties in England <lb/>
Juli not ge; more than 1% per ceil. for their money, <lb/>
on account of the excessive supply of gold, ºppºse <lb/>
the Dominion Government had thrown this $5,000; <lb/>
ood of debentures into the London market, would <lb/>
hey have been saleable? Certainly not. Tae <lb/>
Domini were just as i as our <lb/>
ºn Gºvernment. These Treasury notes would have <lb/>
to be called in, and a crash would come. Though <lb/>
they were a Government of great abilities, they were <lb/>
ecºlºs Goveranent. iie (Air. G.), coald not <lb/>
see the expediency of one bankrupt #overnment <lb/>
going into partnership with another. <lb/>
†e fºod. Receiver GExERAL maintained the <lb/>
accuracy of his statement. The subsily ºf hº Dos <lb/>
miniºn Government would audant to $416,509 and <lb/>
under the Resolutions which were to be brought in, <lb/>
the Government would look for a yet larger grant­ <lb/>
Mr. Gººs.-The Dominion Government deducts <lb/>
the interest on the debt from the subsidy­ <lb/>
Hon. Receiver GeseRAL.-Yes, but that I have <lb/>
charged under the expenditure: Ile (hon. R.G.) <lb/>
was mused by the anxiety of bon. members oppo. <lb/>
site." In Nova Scotia Confederation was carried <lb/>
without an appeal to the constituencies. In Now: <lb/>
foundland the Legislature are determined that the <lb/>
constituencies shalfbe consulted, and because tha, <lb/>
very conditions which were denied to Nova Scotia <lb/>
are granted to Newfoundland, Newfoundland: <lb/>
forsoºth, is the most aggrieved country in the wºrld <lb/>
He was "astonished tº near the hon, member, Mr <lb/>
Little,talk of legislating upon Confederation. A sim: <lb/>
ple resolutions is not legislation as leg t requires <lb/>
£he concurrence of the three estates of Parliaueut. <lb/>
We pass resolutions exp anatory of the details upon <lb/>
which we would recommend the constituencies to <lb/>
accept the Union, and after having these conditions <lb/>
asseåted o by the General Gayernment, we go to <lb/>
the constituencies and say "Look calmly into the <lb/>
question, see the condition of the country and say <lb/>
heter or not we shall remain as we are: if sº, <lb/>
sweep from the bustings "hosº mºn who have ill­ <lb/>
advised yeu, but if you cousider they are honest <lb/>
adopt these terms and go into the Union." Hon. <lb/>
members opposite were Enrowing dusk in the eyes of <lb/></p> 

<p>getting into power, they would carry ºut the neas are <lb/>
if ºeneration, Tnºt was the meaning of the <lb/>
phrase," men and not measures." He was perfectly <lb/>
ºished aſ the hon. member. Mr. Glen, saying <lb/>
that he (hon. B.G.) was gality of aciº to delude <lb/>
the people. He was here to instrue: the people as <lb/>
far as his powers and his position went and was: <lb/></p> 

<p>of him, they coald reject him, and end his political <lb/>
influence. - * * * <lb/>
Mr. Resour contended that the figures of the hon <lb/>
Receiver General were false, and that the hon <lb/>
member, Mr. Glen, was correct. Tae Hoa, nº <lb/>
tº alºna, we would have to provide $315,990 <lb/>
for various services, Hs (Mr. B.) held in his <lb/>
hand a statement which proved that we should have <lb/>
to provide $360,000. Here was sº errºr of$45,000. <lb/>
ºiscensuedus expet-ditºre under Confederation, <lb/></p> 

<p>T H E N E W F 9 UN P <lb/></p> 

<p>insni; he had odered to every Boman Catholic <lb/></p> 

<p>L. A. N. D. E. R. <lb/>
- - - - - , <lb/>
Receiver General, could not amºnt tº less than <lb/>
$37,000; for provision for coastal steam woul <lb/>
i... ... be maje. He denied that the hºs Re­ <lb/>
ºver General represented the views of his con­ <lb/>
situalits or of the Roman Catholic population. <lb/>
The hon. Receiver GENERAL said, that the best <lb/>
reply to this remark was º he had received <lb/>
irº tie Right Revd. Dr. Mullock, which he read <lb/></p> 

<p>fºllows – - <lb break="no"/>K. My dear Mr. Kent, I was delighted with your <lb/>
peech in to-day's N.infoundlander. It is argumen­ <lb/>
tàtive, convincing, and will do a great deal or goo i. <lb/>
Praying for God continue y.º. in good health. <lb/>
I remain, yours sincerely, <lb/>
f J. T. AltJLLOCK. <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon. John Kent. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Resour.—Hon. gentlemen, on this side <lb/>
had the highest regard for Dr.Mullock, but this <lb/>
. . .aaººr which should be left to the people. <lb/>
H. members on this side had fought the bat lº <lb/>
of the people through good and through evil <lb/>
report, and as lºng, us...hº. had the honor ol <lb/>
occupying seats in the House, they would repre­ <lb/>
jºief districts independent of any influence: <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. BRENNAN.—Where was," gº deal of <lb/></p> 

<p>Trº <lb/></p> 

<p>On motion that the said report be received <lb/>
Mr. Parsons moved and Mr. GLEx seconº <lb/>
the following amendment to the second para­ <lb/>
graph of the address:­ <lb/>
While we admit the necessity lor the largs <lb/>
outlay under the head of relief of the able bodi. <lb/>
poor, we cannot refrain from expressing our dis <lb/>
approval of the injudicious mode in which such <lb/>
outlay was effected, and our regret, that no <lb/>
remedial measures had been adopted by the <lb/>
Government to relieve the evils accruing to the <lb/>
poor from its stoppage. <lb/>
The amendment was put and lost on a divi. <lb/>
sion,-Years, aſssrs silen, lioisºtt, Parsons, <lb/>
Breansn, Kearney, Little, Talbot, AI jor và <lb/>
Renouf, Nays—Hous Attorney General': <lb/>
Colºnial Secretary, Receiver General, A. Shea, <lb/>
the Surveyor General, Mesrs Raudell, Klight, <lb/>
Burton, Oakley, Evans, Bar.nett, Prº <lb/>
Pinsent, Barron. O'Rielly, Green, Goddau <lb/>
ICavanagh. <lb break="no"/>Mr. Hogs ETT then moved in amendment <lb/>
seconded, by Mr. TALB T, that the fourth <lb/></p> 

<p>conflictisg opinions abºut C: <lb/>
worth of potatoes would cause the people of St. <lb/>
Mary's Bay to be independent, iastead o! pay­ <lb/>
ing it to a Geologist, Waere was the property <lb/>
di.overed by thºr Geologis; 7 Not the full of <lb/>
his (Mr. B's) ſist. There was plenty of flags <lb/>
which ought to be used for drains about Torbay. <lb/>
The pipes cost a great deal of money, that catue <lb/>
from across the Åtlantic Ocean. A gentleman <lb/>
said to him (Mr. B.) that they were a gº! <lb/>
deal cheaper than the square drain. "A" <lb/>
they?', said he (Mr. B.), "Oh yes," said tº <lb/>
gentleman "that is what they have in Lso.idon." <lb/>
* Are you going to tell ms " said he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
" that they are cheaper when the money go; <lb/>
across the ocean and will never return." <lb/>
Whereas, iſ the money was spent in time country <lb/>
it would be like a weaver's shuttle, no sooner <lb/>
out of one hand than into the other. Have the <lb/>
flags at each side, lay it and sover it with thrº <lb/>
feet of earth, and it will last as long as the <lb/>
south Side hill. Our people were not here <lb/>
accustomel to heavy labour. The Rilway <lb/>
work in Canada was tha hardest work that <lb/>
could be. He considered that annexation would <lb/>
be more beneficial to Newfoundland as far <lb/>
as its encouragement of labour was concerned, <lb/>
than Confederation. <lb break="no"/>Mr. KEARNEY considered the subjeet before <lb/>
the chair was the most important that <lb/>
could come before this House. It was <lb/>
well known that he was returned to this <lb/>
House pledged to oppose Confederation: <lb/>
In case, however, the government, intended <lb/>
sending delegates to Canada, to adjust tº <lb/>
terms of Confederation, he hoped they would <lb/>
not forget this side of the House. The hon. <lb/>
member then referred at considerable length to <lb/>
the supply system, and the detrimental effects <lb/>
produced by the fisherinea being compelled to <lb/>
seil their fish green, for food. Iſe reterred to <lb/>
some cases of extortion. He drew particular <lb/>
attention to the great want and poverty that ex­ <lb/>
isted among the people, and appealed to the <lb/>
government not to allow the people to starve. <lb/>
Mr. HogserI thought that he had said every­ <lb/>
thing that was necess try upon the paragraph <lb/>
before the chair, and the amendmen; which had <lb/>
been proposed. It appeared, however, that the <lb/>
hon, Receiver General had been hatching an <lb/>
egg, and wanted to lay it. He (Mr. ii.) had <lb/>
been told that the lion. Receiver General had <lb/>
flung a let er in the faces of the opposition: <lb/>
which he alleged he had received from the Right <lb/>
Rev. Dr. Mullock. Now he (Mr. H) could <lb/>
not see why that Right Revd. Prelate's name <lb/>
should be dragged batore this House, and used <lb/>
as a meaus of utimidating aud coutrolling that <lb/>
independ of action which this side of the <lb/>
House possesses. Did the hon Receiver General <lb/>
think to whip us into line by a letter of that <lb/>
description? Did we see any . Protestan: gen­ <lb/>
tleman in this House dragging in his Bishop's <lb/>
name before the House, and making it the sub­ <lb/>
ject of debate? Why, the very fact of so violat­ <lb/>
ing the pivacy of that communication shows <lb/>
that the hon Receiver General would, if it suited <lb/>
his purpose, betray Dr. Mullock to-morrow. <lb/>
The hon Receiver General had received that <lb/>
letter in compliment to the speech which he de­ <lb/>
livered, and he now hurls it before this House <lb/>
as an evidance that he was the champion of the <lb/>
Catholic interests of this country. Why, the hon <lb/>
Receiver General killed more Catbolics, and <lb/>
is answerable for more Catholic blood than <lb/>
any man that ever stepped upou our shores. <lb/>
II6 drags his Bishop's nauma, now before this <lb/>
House to be the scofiag and sport of those <lb/>
who did not agree with him in his religiou: <lb/>
views, in order to cover his owo insulenee and <lb/>
cowardice. There was one Bishop in this country <lb/>
if his faith, who had given the hon Receiver <lb/>
General character and staadiug in the com­ <lb/>
munity, and yet he ungratefully abased him. <lb/>
How often had he (Mr. H.) heard him wag <lb/>
his tongue against his Bishop? Why, it the <lb/>
Right Revd. Dr. Mullock associated with the <lb/>
Receiver General, he would lower his position <lb/>
anido injury to his sacred character. The oppo­ <lb/>
sition knew their Bishop and resp cted him,and <lb/>
when he was attacked they would defend niin­ <lb/>
They would not go behind his back to traduce <lb/></p> 

<p>when the Receiver Geuel alforget he was a Catho­ <lb/>
lic and a Christian. He (Mr. H.), warned him <lb/>
not again to drag the name of ºuat oxalted <lb/>
individual before this iiouse. It was only <lb/>
cowards and knaves who would do such a thing. <lb/>
lie (Mr. H.) had got up merely . to give, ex­ <lb/>
pression is these views. Let him go and put <lb/>
nis head in a padding bag, forswear politics; <lb/>
and do penance tor the wrong; that he had done <lb/>
that great and good man, his Bishop, and the <lb/>
floan Cape John to Cºpa Bay: <lb/>
The paragraph was heu adopted. <lb/>
On motion of Mr. Goddes, the Countrittee <lb/>
then rose, and the Glauria in reported that the <lb/>
Committee haſ passed the addross without <lb/></p> 

<p>him. It he (AIr.H.) thought proper to show || <lb/></p> 

<p>the service. <lb/></p> 

<p>graph be exp i, and the foilowing sub-; <lb/>
jiu-jin lieu ther ºf: - ng sub-; <lb/>
In reference -to the French shore question, <lb/>
we ſail to discover in your Excelleusy's speech <lb/>
any thing that relievs this im, ortant in ther <lb/>
from the difficulties which surrounded it on <lb/>
the occasion of the address of the Legislature <lb/>
in the past session; and whilst we recognisa <lb/>
your Excellency's conduct in a desire to bring <lb/>
this subject to a satisfactory conclusion, we <lb/>
cannot but regret that no reply has been <lb/>
made to the resolutions and petitions of thi <lb/>
Legislature, and that the policy indicated in <lb/>
lord Carnarvon's despatch of the 7th D8. <lb/>
cember, 1866, is approved of by the la • <lb/>
Secretary of State for the Colonies. <lb/>
The amendment was put and lost on a <lb/>
similar division to the foregoing. <lb/>
Mr. 'Taleot then moved, in amendment, <lb/>
seconded by M jor Renouſ, that the sixth pits. <lb/>
graph be expunged, ald the following substitut­ <lb/>
ed in lieu thereof:­ <lb/>
with regard to the question of Confederation, <lb/>
we beg respectfully to esserve that the only <lb/>
scheme having reference to this matter which <lb/>
has been submitted to our consideration wit <lb/>
that Knowd by the name of the Q i-buc Resoli. <lb/>
tions, and that scheine has already been reje"el <lb/>
by the Legislature and the country i, and ** <lb/>
further take leave to express to your Excellowey <lb/>
our conviction and desire that a subject of <lb/>
such vital importance to the liberties of the <lb/>
country should be submitted to the decision <lb/>
of the people at the polls, before any further <lb/>
action be taken upon it by the Legislature. <lb/>
The ameadmaut was put and lost, oil a <lb/>
similar division to the foregoing- <lb break="no"/>The original motion was then put all <lb/>
carried. <lb break="no"/>ordered that tho address be read a third <lb/>
time to-morrow. <lb/>
The House than aljourned till to-morrºw, <lb/>
at 3 o'clock. <lb/></p> 

<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>WEDNEsday, Feb. 17 <lb/>
The House met at 3 o'clock. <lb/>
Öº mºon of Mr. &amp; poss, pursus it tº or r <lb/>
of the day, the address to his Excelle ov, tº Gº: <lb/>
ernor, in reply to his speech at the ope i zºol th9 <lb/>
session, was read a third tilt- ar.d allop.e. 1, as <lb/>
follows:­ <lb/>
To His Excellency Anthony Musgrave Bººgoº, <lb/>
and commºdºr in-chief.ii and our the Island <lb/>
of Newfoundlani and its Devendencies. <lb/></p> 

<p>MAY IT Prºasiſ. Youtt ExCELLENCY,­ <lb/></p> 

<p>ºve, the Commonstionse of Assem ly of N-wfoun!" <lb/>
land, beg to thank Your Excellency for the grºcioli <lb/>
Speech with which you have been pleased to opst <lb/>
the present Session of the Legislature, an 1 for the <lb/>
uniform cºurtesy which has marked your intercouris <lb/>
with the House of Assembly during your Adminºr" <lb/>
tion of the Government. <lb/>
We fully approve of the course taken by tº <lb/>
Executive Gºvernment in issuisg the Proclamation in <lb/>
June last, that relief in future would be confinal tº <lb/>
destitute widows and orphans, and to the sick anº <lb/>
infirm poor. We believe this act was well tuned, and <lb/>
we cordially hope and trust that the Executive ºf <lb/>
be successful in its efforts to suppress the demoral" <lb/>
ing systeum of able-bodied pauper relief. <lb/>
Wé thank You Bºilency'ſor the promise tº <lb/>
the Public accounts for the year 1863, will be short" <lb/>
laid before us, <lb break="no"/>We are pleased to learn that Your Excellancy's <lb/>
personal exertions in endeavoraing, to settle º <lb/>
vexed question of the French Shore, lave been sofar <lb/>
successful that there is now a prospact of its bº <lb/>
arranged in a manner advantageous to boº, Pº <lb/>
intºed in it, and that the policy indicated in ſº <lb/>
Carnarvon's despatch of 7th December, 186% º <lb/>
been so far modified that Your Excelleucy will nº": <lb/>
be enabled to issue Grants unier certain rºº riºt" <lb/>
for Mining and other purposes in that logºſity. <lb/>
The new statutory provisions which Your Excal. <lb/>
lency suggests, with regard to Licenses for Out", <lb/>
Timber, guill receive our careful atten ion. <lb/>
We fully concur with Your Excellency tha' tº <lb/>
time has now arrived for us to take action on tº <lb/></p> 

<p>great question of Confederation; and we can *. <lb/>
ºcellency that we shall give our ear" <lb/>
attention to the consideration of or Union with ºf <lb/>
j, of Canada, or such fir and equº; <lb/>
terms as may be cateuiated to serve the intereº <lb/>
the Colony, be approve i of by the Govern cent of this <lb/>
Dominion, and which we trust may prove acceptable <lb/>
ºil classes of the people, when "submitted ºf <lb/>
jail."...iº, the final approval <lb/>
and ratification of Her Majesty. <lb break="no"/>The contract entered intº by Your Excellº, <lb/>
with Riessrs. Inman &amp; Co., for the Conveya" o! <lb/>
the Miº, between St. John's and Hallax, his hº <lb/>
º, a carried out in a satisfactory.manner. Thº." <lb/>
arrangement with regard to the detention. of the <lb/>
stºriº St. John's has been a great conve?".] <lb/>
... ºi...ºft. Bºtºre admirably inited" <lb/></p> 

<p>f <lb/></p> 

<p>ºn that the address be presented tº * <lb/>
E. ºriency the Governor by the speaker and * <lb/>
whole House. -<lb break="maybe"/>ºn Arrowser General informed." <lb/>
Hºuse that his Excellency would receiyo." <lb/>
speaker and the wuole House with the addre" 05: <lb/>
Friday next, at 12 o'clock. <lb/>
†ng House thea ajjurited until Friday, at it. <lb/></p> 

<p>u'clock. A. M. <lb/></p>--> 

<p rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, Feb. 19</p>
    
    <p>
The House met at 11 o'clock, A. M. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>At 12 º'clock the SPEAKER and the whole <lb/>
House proceeded to Government House, and <lb/>
presented to his Excellengy the address in reply <lb/>
to his opening speech, and being returned, <lb/> </p>
    
    <p>The SPEAKER informed the House that while at <lb/> </p>


    <!-- IC, 2019-01-07, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->
<!--<p>; <lb/></p> 

<p>| <lb/></p> 

<p>instead of $3,000, the ambie assuagd by the hoà. <lb/></p> 

<p>anaudan int. <lb/></p> 

<p>ºnformed the House that while º i <lb/></p> 

<p>* <lb/></p> 

<p>nce on his Excellency. the <lb/>
a º: House, he had pres <lb/>
jiency the aid. of thanks, is <lb/>
£xcelleney the made the follºwing <lb/>
Mr. Speaker º; Gentlemen of the a <lb/>
of Assembly. - <lb break="no"/>I receive your 'Address with much g <lb/>
am glad to be assured of approval oft <lb/>
by the Governº with regari to th <lb/>
nºtifying that G ment refief woul <lb/>
ºnfined to destitue widows and epha: <lb/>
and infirm poº. I am satisfied that s <lb/>
to this course is essential to the future <lb/>
the wholo community. it is the intere <lb/>
the duty, of all those who can render <lb/>
more necessitous of their fellow citizº <lb/>
...it the Government in their eſt. <lb/>
§ºlony of the vicious system which <lb/>
aralyzed all healthy energy. and so #. <lb/>
# prºdence among large numbers of it <lb/>
er Majesty's Government will lear <lb/>
tion that yºu are prepared to take, <lb/>
question of Uniºn with the Dominiu <lb/>
ºnd I have no doubt that Pºu will be <lb/>
sº terms of arrangement for tºpuſ. <lb/>
acceptable to the Government of the #2 <lb/>
ºnatºrially conducive to the interests of <lb/>
In this case the good sense of, the cºnſ. <lb/>
scarcely permit them to withold the <lb/>
such an arrangement; and its ratific <lb/>
Majesty may confidently be an icipate. <lb/>
Mr. Hyatt asked and ob lea <lb/>
for the remainder of the sessiº: <lb/>
The Hon. AtroſtNky G&amp;Sºłat. <lb/>
was sure that all had heard, with º: <lb/>
melancholy intelligeneº which had Î <lb/>
ceived,et the death of the H ºn. J AM <lb/>
All who knew him respected him. <lb/>
sº long time engaged in the busiuess <lb/>
and perhaps no where would his 1. <lb/>
ãº tº than in the locality whe <lb/>
S. res.ded. He had for many. Yº <lb/>
high public position, as * Legislativ <lb/>
and i. strict attention to his duties: <lb/>
the approbation of all liº (hou. A. <lb/>
that this House would testify its rest <lb/>
for his ºmily, by adjourning <lb/>
He therefore uoved that the 1 <lb/>
ru, out of respect to the me not <lb/>
L. C., of whose <lb/>
tºs ºust been received, and in token <lb/>
esteem in which the ºeuºsºl jº <lb/>
iºd, ºud of the sympathy ſult by tie­ <lb/>
his widow and family. <lb/>
Mr. Gies begged to second the <lb/>
1a non, Mr. Corinaek was a wºrk!' <lb/>
ºne whose lyss we must all deeply dº <lb/>
was but right that we siloui i thus i <lb/>
merits, and gay a triuute of respect <lb/>
tº ºry. <lb/>
T.s Hoa, Reservkº GENERAL <lb/>
plºts, d to see unsuºpºsiº" <lb/>
fouse to respect the tilemury ºf a gº <lb/>
had been alike all honor to his nº <lb/>
adopted country, in every relation 0: <lb/>
is "had beam placeu. He hºl <lb/>
honorable merchant, and had <lb/>
service to the people of , the <lb/>
which he had so loug resided, a <lb/>
a large columercial business. <lb/>
ais worth was well known, util...h6 <lb/>
fºrt and happiness anongst all a <lb/>
whom h9 would now be deeply. In <lb/>
political sphere lic had discarged tº <lb/>
tagly to himself. Ile (hon. Rºº..." <lb/>
self fast approaching the ", Herº inſi <lb/>
and thus he the mºre dueply lult til <lb/>
which the country Hul sustained, lº <lb/>
public inau and a good titº, winil. <lb/>
injuried the loss of a valued ind, ºt <lb/>
Mr. Hogsgrº fully participated in <lb/>
of nom, geuileiau. The duº of su <lb/>
ºne nor. James Gormack was a lo <lb/>
community at large lºl. <lb break="no"/>Mr. Fissºst migh, under ordid <lb/>
stances, not have given woº <lb/>
to clings which mig 't be *w <lb/>
'by slence, particularly *, * <lb/>
iſ which agº. gentlemen who had <lb/>
referred to the deceased gettle's <lb/>
had poculiar reasons for uut alloy <lb/>
sion to pass without exprº re! <lb/>
part to one, the rocollection of: <lb/>
associated with his earliest years, <lb/>
had ever possessed a warm it <lb/>
regard, and who, besides th; as <lb/>
private life, had been tor souey." <lb/>
ſue.mber in the cº-ordinate braudu <lb/>
lature, the Legislative Council, <lb/>
could therefore speak of the develº <lb/>
tleman, in both his public and priº <lb/>
of lite, from intim tº experience. <lb/>
ed both most worthily,and his gen <lb/>
urbane mauners, and liveral j <lb/>
him endeared and respected by all <lb/>
pleasure of his acqua at incº: For ti <lb/>
he (Mr. P.) could not do othº". <lb/>
open expressiou to his sympathy <lb/>
gºntinº, family, and public * <lb/>
memory of the deceased.: <lb/>
The House than adjourned unti <lb/>
3 o'clock, <lb/></p> 

<p>Mox DAY <lb/></p> 

<p>The IIouse met, and adjourue! <lb/>
atterward, to attend the tutºral ot, <lb/>
JAMES Cottºmack.: <lb/></p> 

<p>Úſt ſtufiml: <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOLIN'S <lb/>
WEDNESDAY, FEBRUARY <lb/>
rº­ <lb/>
Tar Government propositions as to <lb/>
which they think this colony should <lb/>
federation were introduced for discº <lb/>
mittee of the Assembly yesterday by <lb/>
torney General; Mr. Glen, the hon. <lb/>
Mr. Hog.ett followed, when the Com <lb/>
the debate was a journed to to-day. <lb/>
These torms (for which we have n <lb/>
tenao to-day), are in the first place <lb/>
nion Government shall defray &amp; sum <lb/>
our public exponditure, being the * <lb/>
penses of thoso departments of " <lb/>
assume contrºl, Governor, Judges <lb/>
Office, Light Houses, Surveyor Geni <lb/>
In addition to this sum of <lb/>
would be Assets applicable to local <lb/>
poses <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="3" facs="final/images/lgNLLA_1869-02-24_Page_3.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">3</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE NEWFOUNDLANDER.</fw>

    <!-- IC, 2019-01-07, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>| <lb/>
On motion that the said report be received <lb/>
r. Parsons moved and Mr. Glex second. <lb/>
a ſollºwing amendment to the second P:tra­ <lb/>
aph of the address:­ <lb/>
While we admit the necessity for the large <lb/>
tlay under the head of relief of the able bodii <lb/>
jor, we cannot refrain fron expressing our uis <lb/>
}proval of the injudicious mode in whic, su. <lb/>
tlay was effected, and our regret that: no <lb/>
medial measures had been adjpted by the <lb/>
ºvernment to relieve the evils accruing to thi <lb/>
or from its stoppage. <lb/>
The anendment was put and lost on a divi. <lb/>
in, -Years, uſesrs ºlen, liogsett, Parson, <lb/>
readen, Kearney, Little, Talbot, Mºjº. <lb/>
nouf: , Nays-Hons . Attorney General' <lb/>
lºnial Secretary, Receiver General, A. Shea, <lb/>
• Surveyor General, Mesrs Raudell, Kigº <lb/>
rton, Oakley, Evans, Bar.nett, Proº." <lb/>
nsent, Barron. O'Rielly, Green, Goddau <lb/>
vausgh. <lb break="no"/>Mr. Hogsfºr then moved in amend ment <lb/>
oaded by Mr. TALB ºr, that the fourth <lb/>
*graph be expunged, and the following sub­ <lb/>
uted in lieu thereof:­ <lb/>
A reference to the French shore question, <lb/>
ſal to discover in your Excelleusy's speech <lb/>
thing that r-lievs this important in iter <lb/>
in the difficulties whic' surrounded it on <lb/>
occasion of the address of the Legislature <lb/>
the past session; and whilst we recognise <lb/>
is Excellency's conluct in a desire to bring <lb/>
# subject to a satisfactory conclusion, we <lb/>
not but regret that no reply has been <lb/>
de to the resolutions and petitions of this <lb/>
:islature, and that the policy indicated ia <lb/>
rd Caruarvon's despatch of the 7th De. <lb/>
a'yer, 1866, is approved of by the las <lb/>
retary of State for the Colonies. <lb/>
The amendment was put and lost on a <lb/>
ilar division to the foregoing. <lb/>
Mr. TALBor then moved, in amendment, <lb/>
ºnded by AI jor Renouſ, that the sixth para­ <lb/>
ph be expunged, ald the following substitut­ <lb/>
.nlisu thereof:­ <lb/>
With regard to the question of Confederation, <lb/>
beg respectfully to exserve that the oily <lb/>
eme having reference to this matter which <lb/>
been submitted to our consideration w is <lb/>
t knowd by the name of the Q -bec Resol 1. <lb/>
is, and that scheine has already been reje"el <lb/>
the Legislature and the country; and we <lb/>
her take leave to express to your Excelleucy <lb/>
conviction and desire that a subject of <lb/>
a vital importance to the liberties of the <lb/>
ntry should be submittel to the decision <lb/>
he poople at the polls, before any further <lb/>
ºn be taken upon it by the Legislature. <lb/>
he ameidmaut was put and lost, oil a <lb/>
lar division to the foregjing. <lb/>
'hs original motion was then put aul <lb/>
*ied. <lb/>
}rdered that the address be read a third <lb/>
e to-tnorrow. <lb/>
The Hºuse then a journed till to-marrow, <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/></p> 

<p>WEDNESDAr, Feb. 17 <lb/>
10 house met at 3 o'clock. <lb/>
1 not.oil of Mr. G ºdds N, pursuit at t y ord or <lb/>
tº day, thº ad iress to his Excelle,ow t tº Goy­ <lb/>
ºr, in reply to his speech at the ope inz of the <lb/>
ion, was read a third tims and allop.e. 1, as <lb/>
ºws <lb break="no"/>As Excellency Anthony Musgrave Esq. Govern ºr <lb/>
and Commander-in-Chief.in an 2 over the Island <lb/>
of Newfoundlani and its Devendencies. <lb/>
* If PL:Asº. Yout 12xcellºscy, <lb/>
e, the Commons iſonse of Assem ly of N-wfoun l­ <lb/>
bug to think Your Excellency fºr the gracious <lb/>
ºch with witch you bawe been pleased to opet <lb/>
"rosent Sussion of the Legislature, an 1 for the <lb/>
ºrm cºurtesy which has marked your intercourss <lb/>
the House of Assembly during your Admin stra. <lb/>
of the Government. <lb/>
* fully approve of the course taken by the <lb/>
eutive Governinent in issuisg the Proclamation in <lb/>
last, that reliei in future would be confined to <lb/>
tute widows and orphans, and to the sick and <lb/>
n poor. We believe this act was well timed, and <lb/>
ordially hope and trust that the Executive may <lb/>
accessful in its efforts to suppress the demorauz, <lb/>
ysteus of able-bodied pauper relief. <lb/>
9 thank Your Exc-llency for the promise that <lb/>
'ublic accounts for the year 1868, will be shortly <lb/>
before us, <lb break="no"/>e are pleased to learn that Your Excellency's <lb/>
onal exertions in endeavoraing to settle tº <lb/>
i question of the French Shore, Lave been sofar <lb/>
*ial that there is now a prospect of its being <lb/>
'ged in a manner advantageous to both partiu: <lb/>
ested in it, and that the Policy indicated in Lord <lb/>
arvon's despatch of 7th December, 1866, has <lb/>
so far modified that Your Excelleucy will now <lb/>
abled to issue Grants under certain r s rictious <lb/>
£uning and other purposes in that locality. <lb/>
is new statutory provisions which Your Excal­ <lb/>
suggests, with regard to Licenses for Cutting <lb/>
ter, suill receive our careful attunion <lb/>
a fully euncur with Your Excellency that the <lb/>
has now arrived for us to take action ou thé <lb/>
question of Confederation; and we can assure <lb/></p> 

<p>collency that we shall give our earnes: <lb/>
ºuon to the consideration of our Uniºn with the <lb/>
inion of Canada, on such fair and ogntablº <lb/>
s as may be caſeulated to serve the interests." <lb/>
olony r be approved of by the Govern cent of the <lb/>
inion, and watch we trust may prove acceptable <lb/>
classes of the peºple, when submitted to thº <lb/>
tuencies, aud also receive the final approval <lb/>
ratification of Her Majesty. <lb/>
* Contract entered into by Your Excellency. <lb/>
:lessrs. Inman &amp; Co., for the Conveyance o <lb/>
laiis between St. John's and Halifax, has been <lb/>
t carried out in assisiactory.manner. The nº <lb/>
gement with regard to the detention of the <lb/>
uer in St. John's bas been a great convealeucº! <lb/>
• Public, and the Boats are admirably suited to" <lb/>
*:rvºice. <lb/>
iered that the address be presented tº hiº <lb/>
Ilency the Governor by the speaker and the <lb/>
6 tivusov <lb break="no"/>e hou. Arronner General informed the <lb/>
•e that, his Excellency wo.itſ receive the <lb/>
wer aud the whole House with the address on <lb/>
•y utzt, at 12 o'clock. <lb/>
&amp; House thea ajºurned until Friday, at 11 <lb/>
Jk. A. M. <lb/></p> 

<p>- FRIDAY, Feb. 19­ <lb/></p> 

<p>6 House met at 11 o'clºck, A. M. <lb/>
12 o'clock the SPEAks; and the whol: <lb/>
e proceeded to Government House, and <lb/>
nted to his Excellency the address in reply <lb/>
s openius; speech, and being returned, <lb/>
• Sesake; informed the Hºuse that while tº <lb/></p> 

<p>e <lb/></p>--> 

<p> atendance on his Excellency the Governor, at <lb/>
Government House, he had presented to his <lb/>
Excellency the address of thanks, to which his <lb/>
    Excellency the made the following reply:— <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker and Gentlemen of the Honorable House <lb/>
of Assembly.</hi> <lb/></p>
    
    <p>I receive your Address with much gratification. I <lb/>
am glad to be assured of approval of the course taken <lb/>
the Government, with regard to the Proclamation <lb/>
noyifying that Government relief would in future be <lb/>
confined to destitue widows and <choice><sic>ophans</sic><corr>orphans</corr></choice> and the sick <lb/>
and infirm poor. I am satisfied that strict adherence <lb/>
to this course is essential to the future well, being of <lb/>
the whole community. It is the interest, no less then <lb/>
the duty, of all those who can render any aid to the <lb/>
more necessitous of their fellow citizens, by doing so <lb/> 
to assist the Government in their effort to rid the <lb/> 
Colony of the vicious system which has hitherto <lb/>
paralyzed all healthy energy, and so greatly promoted <lb/>
imprudence among large numbers of its population. <lb/></p> 

<p>Her Majesty's Government will learn with saisfac<lb break="no"/>tion that you are prepared to take action on the <lb/> 
question of Union with the Dominion of Canada; <lb/>
and I have no doubt that pou will be able to settle <lb/>
such terms of arrangement for this purpose as will be <lb/>
acceptable to the Government of the Dominion, while <lb/>
materially conducive to the interests of this Colony. <lb/>
In this case the good sense of the constituencies can <lb/>
scarcely permit them to withold their approval of <lb/>
such an arrangement: and its ratification by Her <lb/>
Majesty may confidently be anticipated. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HYATT</persName> asked and obtained leave of absence <lb/>
for the remainder of the session. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The <persName ref="pers:CART5">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> then said he <lb/>
was sure that all had heard with deep regret the <lb/>
melancholy intelligence which had just been re<lb break="no"/>ceived, of the death of the Hon. JAMES CORMACK. <lb/>
All who knew him respected him. He had been <lb/>
a long time engaged in the business of the colony, <lb/>
and perhaps no where would his loss be more <lb/>
deeply felt than in the locality where he had so <lb/>
long resided. He had for many years occupied a <lb/>
high public position as a Legislative Councillor, <lb/>
and his strict attention to his duties had me with <lb/>
the approbation of all. He (hon. A.G.) was sure <lb/>
        that this House would testify its respect and sym<lb break="no"/>pathy for his <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>, by adjourning until Monday <lb/>
next. He therefore moved that the House do now <lb/>
adjourn, out of respect to the memory of the Hon. <lb/>
James Cormack, M. L. C., of whose death news <lb/>
has iust been received, and in token of the high <lb/>
esteem in which the deceased gentleman was <lb/>
held, and ot the sympathy felt by this House with <lb/>
his widow and family. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:GLEN1">Mr. GLEN</persName> begged to second the mition. The <lb/>
late hon. Mr. Cormack was a worthy gentleman, <lb/>
one whose loss we must all deeply deplore, and it <lb/>
was but right that we should thus recognise his <lb/>
merits, and pay a tribute of respect to his me<lb break="no"/>mory. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. RECIEVER GENERAL</persName> was indeed <lb/>
pleased to see this disposition on the part of the <lb/>
House to respect the memory of a gentleman who <lb/>
had been alike an honor to his native and his <lb/>
adopted country, in every relation of life in which <lb/>
he had been placed. He had been an <lb/>
honorable merchant, and had done much <lb/>
service to the people ot the locality in <lb/>
which he had so long resided, and carried on <lb/>
a large commercial business. Commercially <lb/>
his worth was well known, and he diffused com<lb break="no"/>fort and happiness amongst all about him, by <lb/>
whom he would now be deeply missed. In his <lb/>
political sphere he had discharged his duty credi<lb break="no"/>tably to himself. He (hon. R. G.) was now him<lb break="no"/>self fast approaching the "sere and yellow leaf," <lb/>
and thus he the more deeply felt the deprivation <lb/>
which the country had sustained, is the loss of a <lb/>
public man and a good citizen, while he privately <lb/>
mourned the loss of a valued and attached friend. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HOGS1">Mr. HOGSETT</persName> fully participated in the feelings <lb/>
of hon. gentlemen. The death of such a man as <lb/>
the hon. James Cormack was a loss which the <lb/>
community at large felt. <lb/></p>
        
<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. PINSENT</persName> might, under ordinary circum<lb break="no"/>stances, not have given voal expression <lb/>
to feelings which might be as well evidenced <lb/>
by silence, particularly after the apt manner <lb/>
in which hon. gentlemen who had preceded him <lb/>
referred to the deceased gentleman. But he <lb/>
had peculiar reasons for not allowing the occa<lb break="no"/>sion to pass without express reference on his <lb/>
part to one, the recollection of whom had been <lb/>
associated with his earliest years, for whom he <lb/>
had ever possessed a warm friendship and <lb/>
regard, and who, besides the associations of <lb/>
private life, had been for some years a brother <lb/>
member in the co-ordinate branch of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, the Legislative Council. He (Mr. P.) <lb/>
could therefore speak of the deceased non-gen<lb break="no"/>tleman, in both his public and private relations <lb/>
of life, from intimate experience. He discharg<lb break="no"/>ed both most worthily, and his genial disposition, <lb/>
urbane mauners, and liberal mind, had made <lb/>
him endeared and respected by all who had the <lb/>
pleasure of his acquaintance. For these reasons <lb/>
he (Mr. P.) could not do otherwise than give <lb/>
open expression to his sympathy, with the hon. <lb/>
gentleman's family, and public tribute to the <lb/>
memory of the deceased. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
The House then adjourned until Monday at <lb/>
3 o'clock. <lb/></p>
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2019-01-07, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->
    <!--<p>
Moxdar, Feb. 23. <lb/>
The House met, and adjºurue 1 innediately <lb/>
a'terwards to atteud the fuujral of the late Joa. <lb/></p> 

<p>JAMEs CoRMAck. <lb/></p> 

<p>Çº juſtmliºtt. <lb/></p> 

<p>ST. JOHN'S: <lb/>
W.E.D.NESDAY, FEBRUARY 24, 1869. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE Government propositions as to the terms on <lb/>
which they think this colony should enter into Con­ <lb/>
federation were introduced for discussion in Com­ <lb/>
mittee of the Assembly yesterday by the Hon. At­ <lb/>
torney General; Mr. Glen, the hon. Mr. Shea, and <lb/>
Mr. Hogett followed, when the Committee rose and <lb/>
the debate was a journed to to-day. <lb/>
These terms (for which we have not room in cr­ <lb/>
tenuo to-day), are in the first place that the Domi­ <lb/>
mion Government shall defray a sum of $208,462 of <lb/>
our public expenditure, being the salaries and ex­ <lb/>
penses of thoso departments of which they would <lb/>
assume control, Governor, Judges, Customs, Post <lb/>
Office, Light Houses, Surveyor Goneral, &amp;c. &amp;c. <lb/></p> 

<p>In addition to this sum of $20S,462 <lb/>
would be Assets applicable to local pur­ <lb/>
poses $408,922 <lb/></p> 

<p>T.H.E. N E wif o un D LAND E R. -\-\-\- * - &gt; * *-*. . . . . . . -\-&gt; <lb/></p> 

<p>"Together with...the just claims of this colony for <lb/>
other charges and - of like charact <lb/>
with those borne or made by the Dominion with <lb/>
reference to the other provinces." <lb/></p> 

<p>The public debt and liabilities to be assumed by <lb/>
the Dominion Government. <lb/>
No tax to be levied on our exports unless a similar <lb/>
one be laid on all the staple products of the other <lb/>
provinces. <lb/></p> 

<p>Domition Government to assume the charge for <lb/>
interest on £50,000 of Water Company's Stock. <lb/>
Oceanic, Colonial and Coastal Steam Communica­ <lb/>
tion to be provided by the Government of the <lb/>
Dominion. <lb/>
No final arrangement until an appeal be made to <lb/>
the people at next gennral election. <lb/>
In connection with these proposed terms, is a plan <lb/>
of a future constitution on a reduced scale, abolishing <lb/>
the Legislative Council, reducing the number of <lb/>
representatives to fifteen, and largely decreasing <lb/>
allowances for salaries &amp;c. Tais would bring the <lb/>
future expenditure for these services down to <lb/>
$245,810, which being defrayed from the above <lb/>
stated sum applicable to local purposes, viz., <lb/>
$408,922, would leave an annual balance available <lb/>
for roads and other public improvements of abou t <lb/>
$163,112. <lb/>
We think the opinion of the country will infallibly <lb/>
be that these terms comprise a most equitable <lb/>
arrangement, and that the colony should not hesitate <lb/>
to ratily it. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>The remains of the Honble. James Cormack <lb/>
were brought here for interment on Monday last by <lb/>
the S. eamer Lizzie, which arrived about four o'clock. <lb/>
The body was met at Messrs. Baine Johnston &amp; <lb/>
Co's. premiscs, by the members of the Council and <lb/>
Assembly, the Benevolent Irish Society, and a vast <lb/>
concourse of citizens, who accompanied it to its <lb/>
final resting place in Belvidere Cemetery. <lb/></p> 

<p>REPORT OF THE BENEWOLENT IRISEI <lb/>
SOCIETY FOR THE YEAR ENDING <lb/>
17th FEBRUARY, 1869. <lb/>
ORPHAN Asyluyt School, <lb/>
February 17th, 1869. <lb/>
The Sixty-third Anniversary Meeting of the <lb/>
Benevolent Irish Society was held here this day. <lb/>
There being but few members present, owing to the <lb/>
inclemency of the weather, the meeting was adjourn­ <lb/>
ed to Friday, the 19th current, to be then here <lb/>
holden. <lb/>
ORPHAN Asylux School, <lb/>
February 19th, 1869. <lb/>
The adjourned Anniversary Meeting of the Bene­ <lb/>
volent Irish Society was held here this day. IIon. <lb/>
Edward Morris, President, in the chair. <lb/>
M. O'Regan, *† being proposed and seconded <lb/>
was admitted by ballot a member of the Society. <lb/>
The Minutes of the last quarterly meeting were <lb/>
read over and confirmed, the roll was called, and the <lb/>
sum of £59 12s. 11d. collected. <lb/>
The Treasurer reported the gross amount expend­ <lb/>
ed during the year, for Teachers' salaries, improve­ <lb/>
ments. &amp;c., &amp;c., as £515 15s 2d, and the gross re­ <lb/>
ceipts from all sources £675 9s 10d, leaving a <lb/>
balance to the credit of the Society, irresp.ctive of <lb/>
the day's collection, of £159 14s 8.1, but subject to <lb/>
claims for Teachers' salaries now due. Tue Report <lb/>
was on motion received and adopted. <lb/>
The Chairman of the School Committee then read <lb/>
his Report of the condition of the Schools and the <lb/>
Industrial Department, which was as follows: <lb/>
Report of the Committee of the Orphan 4.sylum­ <lb/>
Schoo's, for the year ended, February 17th 1869. <lb/>
Your Committee, in resigning the trust reposed in <lb/>
them for the past year, beg respectfully to submit <lb/>
the following Report t­ <lb/>
That the daily attendauce in both Schools shows <lb/>
an increase over the preceding two or three years; <lb/>
still your Committee regret that the attendance is <lb/>
not such as the Siciety night expect from the large <lb/>
amount expended in their support, but this non­ <lb/>
attendance unay in some degree be attributed to the <lb/>
extreme poverty of the times. <lb/>
The Industrial Department, as the Syciety will <lb/>
observe from the returns laid on the table, has not <lb/>
been able to meet the expenses attending in; still tie <lb/>
balance is trilling, and your Committee hºpe that the <lb/>
advautages derived by the youth; therein, engaged, <lb/>
n Nett making and mending, and the relief to poor <lb/>
families from their earnings, will, on the whole, <lb/>
prove satisfactory to the Society: <lb/>
Your Committee beg to state that the expenditure <lb/>
in the way of improvement or repairs the past year <lb/>
has been trifling, and only what was absolutely <lb/>
necessary to keep the Building water-tight, and this <lb/>
your Committee believe. will scarcely be possible <lb/>
much longer, as the wood-work is so decayed in <lb/>
many places, it will not bear repair; the Conmittee <lb/>
would, therefore, urge upon the Society the necessity <lb/>
of adding to the Building Fund as largely as inay be <lb/>
convenient, so as to be able, as soon as possible, to <lb/>
commence the erection of a suitable Hall, <lb/>
The Nett-work forwarded to the Paris Exhibition <lb/>
has been returned in good condition, and your Com­ <lb/>
mittee are pleased to state that, although no mark of <lb/>
distinction has accompanied them, they are led to <lb/>
believe from correspondence received from persons <lb/>
who were present at the great Exhibition, and in­ <lb/>
terested in the welfare of Newfoundland, that they <lb/>
ranked equal to most of the Net work exhibited <lb/>
there. <lb/>
All the Nets made in the Industrial Department <lb/>
during the past year, have been taken by Mass, a <lb/>
L. O'Brien k Co. at the current price, as heretofore, <lb/>
and your Committee have only to reiterate, that the <lb/>
thanks of the Society are pre-aminently due to that <lb/>
Firm for its continued interest in their affairs. <lb/>
The pro serty of the Society in connection with <lb/>
the Schools is insured as heretofore. <lb/>
Your Committee in conclusion would report that <lb/>
the wall around the Society's property will in usuy <lb/>
places require pointing during the ensuing sun ner, <lb/>
and the covering plank suſ pailing on 4ht to be <lb/>
puttied and painted to prevent decay and preserve <lb/>
the respectable appearance of the property, and re <lb/>
to nmend that sufficient funds be reserved for that <lb/>
urpusq. <lb/>
iº spectfully submitted on behalf of the Cºmmittee, <lb/>
Ws. DOJ INEY. <lb/>
Chairman O.A. School. <lb/>
M. BERNEY, <lb/>
Secretary 0-A. School <lb/>
This Report was on motion received and adopted. <lb/>
The chairman of Charity then presented his Be­ <lb/>
port, showing that the monies placed in his hands <lb/>
isd been expended in accordance with the desire; <lb/></p> 

<p>of thesociety. It was then proposed by Michael <lb/></p> 

<p>Riº, Esq., seconded by william F. Walsh, Esq., <lb/></p> 

<p>and unanimously resolved,—That the sum of £ii) <lb/>
he placed in the bands of the Chairman and Com­ <lb/>
mittee of Charity for distribution amongst the poor, <lb/>
to be expeuded as usual in the purchase of pro­ <lb/>
visions. <lb/>
After which the Annual Report of the President <lb/>
and offizers was submitted to the Society, and by <lb/>
them, 9, motion of Michael Stafford, Esq., second­ <lb/>
ºl by Michael Power, Esq.. received and adopted:–<lb break="yes"/>Report of the Presulent and qfixers of the Banevo­ <lb/>
tent Irish Society for the year ending 17th Febru­ <lb/>
ary, 1869. <lb/>
Our first pleasing duty is to congratulate the <lb/>
Society upon the attainment of this its Sixty-third <lb/>
anniversary. <lb/>
The Society celebrated the anniversary of St. <lb/>
Patrick by the usual procession to the Cathedral, <lb/>
where they attended the sacred ceremonies of the <lb/>
day, and were accommodated with seats within the <lb/>
rails of the high altar; after mass they callel to pay <lb/>
their respects upon his Lordship the Right Rev. Dr. <lb/>
Mullock, who received them in the spacious library <lb/>
of the Episcopal residence. <lb/>
The Society's vote of One hundred pounds for <lb/>
the relief of the poor was expended in the purchase <lb/>
of bread, which was distributed by the Committee <lb/>
of Charity as effectively as was possible. <lb/>
At the quarterly Meeting in May last the Society <lb/>
decided upon the purchase of a Debenture for Fifty <lb/>
pounds, with funds which had been provided to <lb/>
augment the building-fund, which was accordingly <lb/>
done by the Treasurer, an i there is now accumulated <lb/>
towards that object Two hundred and fifty pounds <lb/>
in Debentures of the colony. <lb/>
On, the 31st August the Society received Five <lb/>
P.": in aid of its funds, through F. J. Wyatt, <lb/>
sq., M.H.A., from Horatio Bland, Esq., a native <lb/>
of this country, who made a visit here after an ab­ <lb/>
sence of forty-six years. The Treasurer, on the <lb/>
part of the Society, acknowledged the donation. <lb/>
... We have to renew our acknowledgements of the <lb/>
liberal assistance given by the Legislature towards <lb/>
the Schools and the Industrial Department. <lb/>
The Building continues to be insured for One <lb/>
thousand pounds sterling. <lb/>
The Report of the Chairman of the Orphan Asy­ <lb/>
lum School will afford full information as to the <lb/>
condition of the Schools, and the accounts of the <lb/>
Treasurer will exhibit the state of our funds, shew­ <lb/>
ing that the expenditure for the year has been £515 <lb/>
15s 2d, and the recei, its £675 9s 10d. <lb/>
Eighteen new members were added to the Society's <lb/>
roll juring the past year, <lb/>
We have to record the death of three of our mem­ <lb/>
bers during the past year, of Mr. William Flinn and <lb/>
Mr. Richard Delahunty, two old and respected mem­ <lb/>
bers, and also of the Very Rev. Kyran Walsh, W.G., <lb/>
and late Parish Priest of Harbor Main, who had long <lb/>
. a leading and highly esteemed member of our <lb/>
00IV. <lb/>
Our year of office having now terminated, we re­ <lb/>
sign our positions, tendering to all the members our <lb/>
sincere thanks for the support which we have <lb/>
uniformly receive i, and the order aud decorum <lb/>
which have been always observed. <lb/>
We beg to subscribe ourselves. <lb/>
EDWARD MORRIS, <lb/>
President. <lb/>
HENRY W. BORN, <lb/>
Secretary, <lb/>
The hon. Robert Kent, aſter a ſew pertinent <lb/>
reinarks on the many acts ºf kindness done the <lb/>
Society by the late Thomas Holdsworth Brooking, <lb/>
E q proposell the following resolution, witieh being <lb/>
seconded by Richard Howley, Esq., was unanimoisy <lb/>
assed: <lb/>
Resolved,—That this Society deeply sympathise <lb/>
with the family and relations of the late Thoma <lb/>
Holdswor h Brooking, Esq., upon the death of that <lb/>
gentleman, who for very miny years acted gratuitous­ <lb/>
ly as the agent of this Sºciety in Londot. <lb/>
The following resolutions were then passed <lb break="no"/>1. Resolved,— That thu expression of our warmes: <lb/>
gratitude is due to the Legis sture for its muniticult <lb/>
grant in support of the Institution. <lb/>
2. Resolved.—That the thanks of the Society are <lb/>
due und hereby tenderod to his Lordship the Right <lb/>
Rev. Dr. Mullock for his his patro rails and support <lb/>
in promotion of the objects of the Societv. <lb/>
3. Resolve l,— that the Chairman and Committee <lb/>
of the Orphan Asylum 8:hool are entitled to . the <lb/>
thanks of the Society for their efficient imanagement <lb/>
of that department. <lb/>
4. Itesolved,—That the proprietors of the public <lb/>
journals who publish the reports and other matters <lb/>
of the Society, gratuitously, are entitled to our <lb/>
thanks. <lb/>
Balloting for Oficers for the ensuing year resulted <lb/>
as tullows:­ <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Edward Morris re-elected President <lb/>
Jonn Casey, Esq. -\- Vice President <lb/>
Thos. S. Dwyer -\- 1st Assistant W.P. <lb/>
Michael J. O'Mara -\- 2nd assistant V.P <lb/>
Wm. P. Walsh elected Treasurer. <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>Henry W. Born re-elected Secretary. <lb/>
Wm. Doutney -\- Chairuman O.A.S. <lb/>
Michael Rice -\- Chairinan Charity <lb/>
James Calinan -\- chairiuan Review <lb/>
&amp; Correspondence <lb/></p> 

<p>Michael Berney tº Secretary (). A S <lb/></p> 

<p>HENRY W. BORN, <lb/>
Secretary <lb/>
<lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>BYTELEGRAPH. <lb/>
TO THE COMMERCi.A.L. ROOM. <lb/></p> 

<p>-\-<lb break="maybe"/>Loxpox, Feb. 16th. <lb/>
The formal opening of Parliament, which was <lb/>
postponed inst year by the resianation of the Dis. <lb/>
raeli Ministry, took place this afternoon. The mein­ <lb/>
bers of the House of Connions were suminoued to <lb/>
attend at the Bar of the Chanber of the Peers, to <lb/>
hear the Royal Speech. The Q ſeen was not preseut <lb/>
and the speech was read by the Lord Chancellor. <lb/>
The Queen assures the Lords and Commons that <lb/>
at present the relations of Great Britain with loreign <lb/>
Powers, are on an ex-el-nt footing. The hostil.ties <lb/>
which threatenel to break out in the East have been <lb/>
prevented by the Conterence of the Grea F, wer; at <lb/>
Paris. The hope is expressed gºat the negalia.iors <lb/>
with the United S'ates w łł place on a firmer and <lb/>
mors durahle basis the friendships which sliquid exist <lb/>
betweeu Bagland and the U.ed States. The con­ <lb/>
tinued supp.ession of the writ of Hate's Corpazia <lb/>
regarded as unnecessary. The ecclesiastical arrange­ <lb/>
ments for Ireland are to be considered by Parliament. <lb/>
Her Mjesty is persuaded that a caretai regard will <lb/>
be had to the idterests involved and the welfare of <lb/>
religion, and that through the application of the <lb/>
principles of equal justice to the question before <lb/>
theim, Parliam ºut will secure the individual feeling <lb/>
of the people of Ireland on the side of loyalty aud <lb/>
haw, efface the memory of past coutentions, and cherish <lb/>
the sympathies of an affections' people. <lb/>
New York, Feb. 16. <lb/>
An immense mass meeting ot citizens in favor of <lb/>
freedom of Ireland and the 'iberation of American <lb/>
citiz-as held prisoners by England, took place last <lb/></p> 

<p>- Ottawa, Feh. 19. <lb/></p> 

<p>Whelan's confession was to the effect that he was <lb/>
one of a gang of three who plotted Megee's mur­ <lb/>
der; that his duty wus to watch McGee; that he <lb/>
dogged his victim's steps on the night of the mur­ <lb/>
der, and when he left the Parliament House he ran <lb/>
across the Parliament Square into the vacant lot <lb/>
opposite Mrs. Trotter's, where it will be remember­ <lb/>
ed footsteps like his were discovered. Here he gave <lb/>
the signal of McGee's approach, and one of his ac­ <lb/>
complices fired the fatal'shot. He said that both of <lb/>
them would yet be known, but steadily refused to <lb/>
give their names. <lb/></p> 

<p>MARRISD.—On January 5th, at St. John's Cathes <lb/>
dral by the Right Rev. the Lord Bishop of Rupert­ <lb/>
Land, assisted by the Wen. Archdeacon McLean, the <lb/>
Rev W. C. Pinkham, formally of St. John's, New­ <lb/>
foundland, now of St. Agustine College, and Canter­ <lb/>
bury, England, now Incumbent of St. James to Jane <lb/>
Ann, second daughter of Wm. Drever, Esq., <lb/>
Merchant. <lb/></p> 

<p>DIED —On Monday afernoon, the 15th inst. <lb/>
after a short illness Mr George Stevers, a native of <lb/>
Devonshire, England, in the 81st year of his age. <lb/>
At Halifax, N. S., on Tuesday, 9', inst., Mrs. <lb/>
A. G. Rutherford, late of Newfoundland, age 1 <lb/>
53 years, <lb/>
At Bay Roler's, on Thursday last the Hon. James <lb/>
Cormack, Member of the Legislative Council, aged <lb/>
61 years—R. I. P.. <lb/>
On Sunday morning last, Jane, the beloved wife <lb/>
of Mr Gilbert Withycombe, aged 75 years, <lb/>
On Sundry evening, after a protracted illness, <lb/>
which she bore with truly christian patience and re­ <lb/>
siguation to the Divine will, Eliza Mary Rose, eldest <lb/>
daughter of Dr. J. J. Dearin, aged 23 years. IHer <lb/>
funeral will take place on to-morrow (Thursday) <lb/>
evening, at four o'clock. Friends and acquain­ <lb/>
tances of the family are requested to attend. <lb/>
The death of this truly amiable young lady will <lb/>
long be felt by the suffering poor of this community. <lb/>
Her many virtuous and º, Christian qualities, her <lb/>
humility and self denial, were conspicuous in all her <lb/>
walks through life, and endeared her to all who had <lb/>
the pleasure of her acquaintance. <lb/></p> 

<p>The St. Vincent de Paul Society <lb/></p> 

<p>Reg to invite the attention of the Public to their <lb/>
STOCK OF <lb/></p> 

<p>H O S E. /* <lb/></p> 

<p>now for sale at the Old Factory. <lb/>
Feb 24, 3i, <lb/></p> 

<p>THE NEW YORK <lb/>
Łife insiſtance Coſſipahy <lb/>
Capital—$12,000,000. <lb/></p> 

<p>Offlies, Nos. 112 and 114 Broadway. <lb/></p> 

<p>This Company is one of the oldest in America, <lb/>
having been ghartered in 1841, and cominenced busi­ <lb/>
ness in May 1845. During the twenty-three years <lb/>
of its existence, it has issued policies upon the lives <lb/></p> 

<p>More than 57,000 persons, <lb/></p> 

<p>And paid in losses to the families, and representa; <lb/>
tives of those who have deceased while members of <lb/></p> 

<p>thu Coupany, <lb/>
" $5,000,000 <lb/></p> 

<p>Special care in the selection of its risks, strict econ­ <lb/>
omy, and a safe and iudicious investºnent of its <lb/>
Fun:ls emphitically characterise the management of <lb/></p> 

<p>Luis Coupar: <lb/>
* Trustees. <lb/></p> 

<p>Morris Franklin, President of the New York Life <lb/>
Insurance Co. <lb/>
John M. Nixon, (Doremus &amp; Nixon, Dry Goad.) 45 <lb/>
Wa'ren St <lb/>
David Dows, (David Dows &amp; Co. Flour Aterchants) <lb/>
20 Smith St <lb/>
Isaac C. Keadill, Union Buildings, corner of Willian <lb/>
and Pine Sts <lb/>
Daniel 8 Miller, (late Diter, Miller &amp; Co. Graçars.) <lb/>
II*nry IQ Bogert, (Bogert &amp; Kneeland) 49 Willian <lb/>
St <lb/>
John L. Rogers, (late Wyeth, Rogers &amp; Co. Impor­ <lb/>
ters) 54 William St <lb/>
John Mai's, (Merchant) 20 South S4 <lb/>
Wtu H Appleton, (Appleton &amp; Co, Puvlishers) 93 <lb/>
Grand St <lb/>
Robert B Collins, (Collins &amp; Lºrothers, Stationers) <lb/></p> 

<p>106 Leonard St <lb/>
Willian Barton, (Bunker) 33 Wall St. <lb/>
Win A Booth (Booth &amp; Elgar) 95 Front St <lb/>
George A Osgood (Banker) 33 Broad St <lb/>
Henry Bowers, (Bowers, Beecznan &amp; Bradlord Jr. <lb/>
Dry Goods) 59 Leonard St <lb/>
Charles L Anth ºny, (Anthony &amp; Hall, Dry Goole) <lb/>
66 Leonard St <lb break="no"/>Sanford Cobb, President Eagle Fire Insurance Co. <lb/>
71 Wail St. <lb/>
Elwari Martin, (Cragin &amp; Co, Provisions) 400 <lb/>
West Twelfth St <lb/>
Fºlwin Hoyt, (Hoyt, Spragues &amp; Co. Dry Goods) <lb/>
50 Park Place <lb/>
Lewis F Battellé, (late Battells &amp; Benwick) 162 <lb/></p> 

<p>From St <lb/>
H B Claflin (H. B. Claflu &amp; Co Dry Goods) cornet <lb/>
Church &amp; Worth St <lb/>
MORRIS FRANKLIN, <lb/>
UT resident, <lb/>
WiLLIAM*I. BEE43, <lb/>
Wite. Prea. and Actuary, <lb/>
Medical Examiners for Newfoundland. <lb/>
11a. Trixi.28 Cnowdy, <lb/>
W. C. Sixtsis, Mi u <lb/>
PREsco.TT 251E:S3W, <lb/>
General Agent. <lb/></p> 

<p>Feb 19 <lb/></p> 

<p>- Ex City of Halyaz. <lb/>
100 Barrels ºſess and Paiue Mess <lb/></p> 

<p>P G I: R iſ <lb/></p> 

<p>z-Equal to any ever imported. <lb/>
... " -Arº­ <lb/>
153 Casks Prime Canada <lb/></p> 

<p>B J T T E R. <lb/></p> 

<p>12o.º sale: BY -<lb break="maybe"/>- A. SBEA. <lb/></p> 

<p>night. Alayof Hai, presided. <lb/></p> 

<p>Feb. 24. 2*, <lb/></p> 

<p>i <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>