<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_BC_1871-03-28"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1871-03-28">28 March 1871</date>, Canadian Confederation with British Columbia</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>Norman Ward and Pamela Hardisty</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2007"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="286"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_277.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_278.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_279.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_280.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_281.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_282.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_283.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_284.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_285.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_286.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-10-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_277">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_277.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_278">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_278.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_279">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_279.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_280">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_280.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_281">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_281.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_282">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_282.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_283">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_283.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_284">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_284.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_285">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_285.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_286">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_286.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="277" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_277.jpg"/>
          <fw type="dateline">March 28, 1871</fw>  <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">277</fw>
            
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS</head>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>Tuesday, March 28, 1871</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>
<div type="section">

            <p>
     <emph>The SPEAKER</emph> took the chair at 3 o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prayers</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

 </div>  
 <div type="section">           

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     AFTER ROUTINE 
     <lb/></head>
   
<p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>SAULT STE. MARIE RAILWAY</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SIMP2">Mr. SIMPSON</persName> introduced a Bill to incorporate the Sault Ste. 
     <lb/>
     Marie Railway and Bridge Company, and it received first reading. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>
   <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     MANITOBA ELECTIONS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> referred to the return of the Writs from 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba, and asked if it was the intention of the Government to 
     <lb/>
     refer the matter to a special Committee to report on them to the 
     <lb/>
     House. Under the peculiar circumstances attending the election, 
     <lb/>
     some such precaution should be taken. In order to maintain the 
     <lb/>
     purity of this House and prevent the intrusion of those not entitled 
     <lb/>
     under Imperial Acts to sit here, he thought it was the responsibility 
     <lb/>
     of the Government to indicate their position, and that of those 
     <lb/>
     elected in Manitoba. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-E. CARTIER</persName> said the Government did not 
     <lb/>
     intend to take any such action until the newly elected candidates 
     <lb/>
     should arrive from Manitoba or until objections should be urged to 
     <lb/>
     their taking their seats in the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>
            <div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">
     QUEBEC HARBOUR 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Hon. Mr. LANGEVIN</persName> introduced a Bill to provide for the 
     <lb/>
     improvement and management of the Harbour of Quebec. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     * * * 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">
     ADMISSION OF BRITISH COLUMBIA 
     <lb/>
     
            </head>


            <p><persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-E. CARTIER</persName> moved that the House go 
     <lb/>into Committee to consider a series of resolutions respecting the 
     <lb/>admission of British Columbia into Union with Canada. This 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <cb/>
           
            <p>
     subject, he said, was one which required few words to introduce it. 
     <lb/>
     Its importance was recognized by all. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Who would have thought twelve years ago when British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia was erected into a colony by Lord Lytton that it should 
     <lb/>
     form in so short a time a portion of Canada. It was due to the 
     <lb/>
     foresight and statesmanship of that great literary man that he should 
     <lb/>
     quote from a speech of his, delivered in 1858, in which this great 
     <lb/>
     union was foretold. He was now quoting from the prorogation 
     <lb/>
     speech delivered on the 2nd August, 1858. It said: "The Act to 
     <lb/>
     which Her Majesty's assent for the establishing of the Colony of 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia was originally required in consequence of the 
     <lb/>
     recent discoveries of gold in that district, but Her Majesty hopes 
     <lb/>
     that this new Colony on the Pacific may be but one of several in a 
     <lb/>
     greater state of progress, by which Her Majesty's Dominions in 
     <lb/>
     British North America may be ultimately peopled in an unbroken 
     <lb/>
     chain from the Atlantic to the Pacific by loyal subjects of Her 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's Crown." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Could the present movement have been more clearly foretold? 
     <lb/>
     Since 1858 the scheme of Confederation had made great strides 
     <lb/>
     toward completion. He (Hon. Sir George-E. Cartier) regretted the 
     <lb/>
     absence of the hon. member for Shefford on this occasion. That 
     <lb/>
     gentleman had often complained that this country was advancing 
     <lb/>
     too slowly, and said that the Dominion would advance more rapidly 
     <lb/>
     if placed on an independent footing. But, if the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Shefford was present today, he could not charge the Ministry with 
     <lb/>
     having been idle since they had brought about the union of all 
     <lb/>
     British North America since they had assumed office. While in 
     <lb/>
     London with his (Hon. Sir George-E Cartier) colleagues, at a dinner 
     <lb/>
     where several literary men were present, he mentioned to Lord 
     <lb/>
     Lytton, who was not then in office, that the Confederation scheme 
     <lb/>
     was one of the principal objects which had brought him to England. 
     <lb/>
     Lord Lytton replied, "I presume that you have come not merely to 
     <lb/>
     see that the British North American Atlantic Provinces should be 
     <lb/>
     united. I hope you look forward to the greater Confederation which 
     <lb/>
     will reach to the Pacific Ocean." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     He (Hon. Sir George-E. Cartier) would now come to the Bill 
     <lb/>
     itself. It was before the House, and they could examine it for 
     <lb/>
     themselves. He invited the freest and fullest discussion on each and 
     <lb/>
     every clause, but he would remind them that the Bill was in the 
     <lb/>
     nature of a treaty, and consequently the Government would insist 
     <lb/>
     upon the adoption of those terms as adopted in British Columbia<lb break="no"/>that the amendment of one paragraph or one item of those terms 
     <lb/>
     would defeat the whole project. He took this early opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     informing the House of the fact. British Columbia had decided to 
     <lb/>
     accept the Bill without amendments, though several members of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature of that colony had shown a disposition to amend the 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="278" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_278.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">278</fw><fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">March 28, 1871</fw>
            <p>
     measure in some of its parts. The necessity of accepting this Bill as 
     <lb/>
     it stood must be apparent to all. The population of British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     was set down at 60,000, and it was certainly not below that number, 
     <lb/>
     if the Indians and Chinese were included as well as the white. The 
     <lb/>
     customs duty collected under the tariff of the colony amounted to 
     <lb/>
     $350,000, which would give about twice as much per head for the 
     <lb/>
     population as was collected in the Dominion. Each inhabitant of 
     <lb/>
     Canada was supposed to contribute $3 to the Revenue per year, 
     <lb/>
     while each inhabitant of the colony contributed nearly twice that 
     <lb/>
     amount. It might be said that the tariff was higher than ours, but it 
     <lb/>
     was not so much so as to make this difference if the population 
     <lb/>
     were not there. The House would therefore, admit that the 
     <lb/>
     Government did not err in estimating the population at 60,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The delegates of British Columbia wished to have the subsidy 
     <lb/>
     placed at 80 cents per head for a population of 120,000, but on 
     <lb/>
     being informed that it would be impossible to obtain the assent of 
     <lb/>
     Parliament to such terms they allowed the population to put at 
     <lb/>
     60,000. This was an opportune time to admit the colony into the 
     <lb/>
     union, for it was desirable to extend the Confederation to the Pacific 
     <lb/>
     as soon as possible, and on economical grounds it was advisable to 
     <lb/>
     admit the colony into the Dominion before the increase of 
     <lb/>
     population could increase the subsidy to a very large rate. Then 
     <lb/>
     with respect to the clause providing for provisions it must be 
     <lb/>
     remembered that British Columbia was a Crown colony. Under it 
     <lb/>
     several officers were appointed for life, and they should be 
     <lb/>
     provided for. The colony had laterally adopted responsible 
     <lb/>
     Government which was to commence from the date of the union, so 
     <lb/>
     that no future charges of this kind need be expended in the future. 
     <lb/>
     There were very few such pensions to be provided for; the majority 
     <lb/>
     of them would be employed under the Federal Government. Then, 
     <lb/>
     with respect to the tariff, it was provided that they should retain 
     <lb/>
     their own tariff, which was higher than ours, till the completion of 
     <lb/>
     the Pacific Railway. No inconvenience need be anticipated from it, 
     <lb/>
     and under the peculiar circumstances of the case it was necessary to 
     <lb/>
     allow them to retain it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Item eleven, relating to the construction of the Pacific Railway, 
     <lb/>
     would no doubt provoke discussion. There were various unfounded 
     <lb/>
     rumours with respect to this. It was not the intention of the 
     <lb/>
     Government to construct the road, but it would be undertaken by 
     <lb/>
     companies to be assisted mainly by land grants. It was not the 
     <lb/>
     intention of the Government to burden the exchequer much to 
     <lb/>
     obtain this railway. While this clause was under discussion between 
     <lb/>
     the delegates and the Government it was proposed by the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     that the colony should hand over a forty mile strip of land towards 
     <lb/>
     the construction of the railway. That would be 24,000 square miles 
     <lb/>
     of land, or 50,360,000 acres of land, not merely agricultural land, 
     <lb/>
     but mineral land. Placing that land at $1 per acre, it would be equal 
     <lb/>
     to a grant of$50,360,000 towards the construction ofthe railway. It 
     <lb/>
     was proposed to give the colony $100,000 per annurn, which, 
     <lb/>
     placing the interest at 5 per cent, would be the annual interest on the 
     <lb/>
     value of 2,000,000 acres of land, leaving the remainder to be used 
     <lb/>
     by this Government. The railway, starting from Nipissing, would be 
     <lb/>
     about 2,500 miles, 700 of which would pass through Ontario. They 
     <lb/>
     did not expect to get entirely the 20 mile grant on each side of the 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
           
   
           
     road, but they expect to get from the Ontario Government every 
     <lb/>
     alternate lot on each side of the line for that 700 miles. That would 
     <lb/>
     give 9,000,000 acres of land from the Ontario Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Starting from Lake Nipissing it would connect with the Ontario 
     <lb/>
     system of railway and with the Quebec system of railway through 
     <lb/>
     the Ottawa Valley. They were prepared to give it to any company 
     <lb/>
     which would undertake the construction of the line, with a capital of 
     <lb/>
     twenty-five millions of dollars, which with interest at 5 per cent, 
     <lb/>
     would represent $1,500,000 per annurn. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Sherbrooke had recently remarked that the certain increase of 
     <lb/>
     receipts from customs and excise was at the rate of 5 per cent per 
     <lb/>
     year. At that rate, taking the customs at $10,000,000, the increase 
     <lb/>
     would be $500,000, and on excise, taking the receipts at 
     <lb/>
     $5,000,000, $250,000. That would give a total from these two 
     <lb/>
     sources alone to meet $1,500,000 per annurn, a sum of $750,000. 
     <lb/>
     He knew it would be argued that this railway would cost between 
     <lb/>
     one and two hundred millions of dollars, if not more. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:RYMA1">Mr. RYMAL</persName>: How much do you estimate the cost at? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> would compare it with the 
     <lb/>
     American Pacific Railway, which from Omaha to the Pacific was 
     <lb/>
     1,775 miles in length. That railway was aided by land and money 
     <lb/>
     grants, and cost $50,000,000. The Canadian Pacific Railway would 
     <lb/>
     be about 700 miles longer. Yet he would place the cost at double 
     <lb/>
     the rate of the American Pacific Railway, and the utmost cost that 
     <lb/>
     could be incurred would be $100,000,000. But whatever it would 
     <lb/>
     cost, he would assure the House that there would be no taxation on 
     <lb/>
     the country more than existed at present. (Cheers) A certain portion 
     <lb/>
     of the public lands had been reserved for the Indians, and the only 
     <lb/>
     guarantee that was necessary for the future good treatment of the 
     <lb/>
     Aborigines was the manner in which they had been treated in the 
     <lb/>
     past. Now, having glanced at the provisions of the Bill he would 
     <lb/>
     call the attention of the House to the fact that while our neighbours 
     <lb/>
     had taken sixty years to extend their borders to the Pacific, the 
     <lb/>
     young Dominion would have accomplished it inside of ten years. 
     <lb/>
     And look at the importance of the extension. We need a seaboard 
     <lb/>
     on the Pacific if ever this Dominion was to be a powerful nation in 
     <lb/>
     the future, and what more convenient time could there be for this 
     <lb/>
     union than at the present time? He concluded by an allusion to the 
     <lb/>
     splendid position which England had attained by the development 
     <lb/>
     of her marine power, and that even Prussia, notwithstanding the 
     <lb/>
     triumphs she had lately won, must be content to take a second place 
     <lb/>
     beside the great maritime power of England. The hon. Baronet 
     <lb/>
     resumed his seat amid loud cheers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOLT1">Mr. BOLTON</persName> said that the House was hardly prepared to enter 
     <lb/>
     on the discussion till it heard from the Finance Minister a statement 
     <lb/>
     respecting the financial results of the matter now submitted to the 
     <lb/>
     House. It was mainly as a financial measure that the House would 
     <lb/>
     have to consider this measure. The Minister of Militia had stated 
     <lb/>
     that this railway was to involve no new burdens on the taxpayers. 
     <lb/>
     The House was entitled to hear, from the greatest financial 
     <lb/>
     authority in the House, a statement showing how that would 
     <lb/>
     have to be reached without involving additional burdens on 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="279" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_279.jpg"/>
         <fw type="dateline">March 28, 1871</fw>   <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">279</fw> 
            
     taxpayers. This was a question that met the House <hi rendition="simple:italic">in limine</hi>, and 
     <lb/>
     should be explained by the Finance Minister. 
     <lb/>
            </p>  
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HINC1">Hon. Sir FRANCIS HINCKS</persName> had not expected at this early 
     <lb/>
     period to go into the financial aspect of the question. As to the 
     <lb/>
     railroad, the idea had been that it could be constructed by a 
     <lb/>
     liberal land grant and liberal money subsidy. It was not expected 
     <lb/>
     to bring this subject forward this session. But various plans 
     <lb/>
     would be considered and proposed to capitalists, including land 
     <lb/>
     grants. The money change was estimated at one million to a 
     <lb/>
     million and a quarter dollars per annum, which would not 
     <lb/>
     involve additional Dominion taxation. No capitalists were likely 
     <lb/>
     to survey the road at their own expense. Government thought it 
     <lb/>
     necessary that they should assume the responsibility for survey 
     <lb/>
     and location of line, this expenditure to be afterwards made by 
     <lb/>
     first charge in the road. The charges to the Dominion in 
     <lb/>
     connection with British Columbia were estimated at $460,000 a 
     <lb/>
     year, and the revenue from all sources about $360,000 leaving 
     <lb/>
     an annual charge of about $100,000 upon Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HINC1">Hon. Sir FRANCIS HINCKS</persName> in reply to Mr. Jones, of Leeds 
     <lb/>
     North and Grenville North, said the road would cost about one 
     <lb/>
     hundred millions of dollars. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GALT1">Hon. Sir A.T. GALT</persName> said the admission of British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     into the Union was desirable to all parties, the only question 
     <lb/>
     being as to the terms upon which it was to be based. He was 
     <lb/>
     willing within two restrictions to accept any terms with this 
     <lb/>
     object. The first involved the avoidance of the violation of any 
     <lb/>
     constitutional rights of the people of that colony, and the second 
     <lb/>
     the abstaining from the imposition of onerous burdens on the 
     <lb/>
     people of Canada. In view of the many important public or 
     <lb/>
     natural works claiming our attention, it behoved us to guard 
     <lb/>
     carefully against unduly augmenting the demands upon our 
     <lb/>
     resources. Not only had railways and canals and other works to 
     <lb/>
     be provided for, but the defence of the country, according to 
     <lb/>
     past contracts and legislation. Now there was no doubt that the 
     <lb/>
     union of this colony and the Dominion would be productive of 
     <lb/>
     little benefit-would probably, but prove a source of fruitless 
     <lb/>
     expense unless it could be also united by means of a good 
     <lb/>
     railway communication. That was why a railway had been made 
     <lb/>
     one of the terms of the compact. But its conditions necessarily 
     <lb/>
     required consideration. We should have to take care not to 
     <lb/>
     cripple the powers and means of the Local Government by those 
     <lb/>
     conditions, in regard to future enterprises. While it was 
     <lb/>
     desirable a road to our Western territory and through the colony 
     <lb/>
     should be made for the settlement of that vast region, the Local 
     <lb/>
     Government should not be deprived of the means of securing 
     <lb/>
     works of local value and promise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The object of the House then should be the creation of this 
     <lb/>
     needed communication in conditions not antagonistic to British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia local improvements, without provisions for which we 
     <lb/>
     could not expect it to enter the Union. The resources of that 
     <lb/>
     country naturally presented themselves to our notice in this 
     <lb/>
     connection. What were they? A reliable authority in British 
     <lb/>
           
           <cb/>
             
   
          
     Columbia lately stated the population at 10,000 whites and 
     <lb/>
     40,000 Indians. Now these aborigines should not be placed on 
     <lb/>
     an equal footing with the whites for the purpose of framing the 
     <lb/>
     financial basis of the Union. They could not be regarded as the 
     <lb/>
     equals of the whites for revenue purposes at least. The imports 
     <lb/>
     and exports also deserved our notice. The exports were 
     <lb/>
     principally furs, lumber and some gold and coal. The imports 
     <lb/>
     included articles dutiable in Canada, besides breadstuffs and 
     <lb/>
     such like commodities, from which the bulk of the revenue was 
     <lb/>
     derived. In 1867 the total amount was estimated at $537,000, of 
     <lb/>
     which the customs yielded $350,000. The Dominion would 
     <lb/>
     receive this, the remainder arising from excise and amounting to 
     <lb/>
     over $150,000 falling to the Colony. The present terms of the 
     <lb/>
     Union were considerably less advantageous to Canada than the 
     <lb/>
     former both as regards the railway and other matters. Before it 
     <lb/>
     was left optional with us when we should commence the work, 
     <lb/>
     which, however, was to be completed within a reasonable 
     <lb/>
     period, but the subsequent conditions required the 
     <lb/>
     commencement of the road within two years and its completion 
     <lb/>
     within ten. We might have finished the work within ten years, 
     <lb/>
     but were not compelled to do it. The cost of the road would be 
     <lb/>
     very great, one hundred million being the Government estimate, 
     <lb/>
     and a considerable proportion of this amount must come from 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion exchequer. The present engagement as to time 
     <lb/>
     was much beyond what British Columbia asked at first, and in 
     <lb/>
     the second place the road was rendered more burdensome from 
     <lb/>
     the extension to Nipissing, further than at first spoken of The 
     <lb/>
     present terms were enormously more burdensome to Canada 
     <lb/>
     than the former. The estimated revenue from Columbia was 
     <lb/>
     $386,000, and payments by Dominion $536,226 apart from 
     <lb/>
     indirect engagements. But this revenue from British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     depended upon maintenance of its tariff. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The result was that the colony would receive $150,000 to 
     <lb/>
     $170,000 a year from Canada for Union, including in trade 
     <lb/>
     guarantee for the works at Esquimault. He would not object to 
     <lb/>
     that price for a political union, and did not think it too great an 
     <lb/>
     equivalent for valuable lands extracted from the colony for the 
     <lb/>
     railway. But there were other conditions of a serious and 
     <lb/>
     objectionable nature in view ofour circumstances and prospects. 
     <lb/>
     He objected to the hands of the country being tied as to the 
     <lb/>
     period within which the Dominion should commence and 
     <lb/>
     complete the railway. As it was, after the British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     delegates came to Ottawa, Canada's obligations became 
     <lb/>
     enormously enhanced. 1f the colonists did not command this 
     <lb/>
     condition as compensation for the reduction of the estimate of 
     <lb/>
     population from 120,000 to 60,000, or to provide means needed 
     <lb/>
     for local purposes, why should our Government have voluntarily 
     <lb/>
     assumed this serious obligation not at first proposed. He 
     <lb/>
     deprecated interference with one of the principles of our 
     <lb/>
     constitution, namely, representation by population, by these 
     <lb/>
     resolutions. He indicated the evils of admitting colonies or 
     <lb/>
     territories on the footing ofpresent members of Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The American territorial system presented an attractive 
     <lb/>
     contrast with ours in this respect. If not admitted till they 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="280" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_280.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">280</fw>  <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">March 28, 1871</fw>
          

     reached a certain stage of growth and development, they would 
     <lb/>
     have certain local works completed not necessary to be assumed 
     <lb/>
     by the Dominion. At present, to admit such Provinces as British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia we had to depart from this principle of representation 
     <lb/>
     by population to give the people proper representation, and 
     <lb/>
     frame the financial basis of our Union to enable to newcomers 
     <lb/>
     to carry on the Government, and other enterprises. One 
     <lb/>
     important object for us was to avoid incurring obligations 
     <lb/>
     oppressive to our people, who numbered but four millions. By 
     <lb/>
     these resolutions they were threatened with a very grave 
     <lb/>
     responsibility in regard to the early commencement and 
     <lb/>
     completion of the Pacific Railway. He was certainly opposed to 
     <lb/>
     terms of this kind, however desirous of extending the Union and 
     <lb/>
     meeting the wishes of British Columbia. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Cheers</hi>.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> referred to the remarks of the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Sherbrooke as to the difference between the 
     <lb/>
     requests made by British Columbia, and what was proposed to 
     <lb/>
     be granted by the Government. He said the only difference was 
     <lb/>
     as regards the communication, it being decided that there should 
     <lb/>
     be a guarantee for the specific time of ten years, which would 
     <lb/>
     allow ample time for the construction of the Railway, and the 
     <lb/>
     Government had thought it better to limit the matter to ten years 
     <lb/>
     instead of making a guarantee in perpetuity. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The member for Sherbrooke had stated that all British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia asked for was a coach road connecting Fort Garry 
     <lb/>
     with the Government roads of British Columbia and an 
     <lb/>
     expenditure of a million dollars a year on a railway, and that the 
     <lb/>
     proposition submitted by the Government was less favourable to 
     <lb/>
     Canada. He entirely dissented from the hon. member on that 
     <lb/>
     matter, on these grounds. When the road had been proposed it 
     <lb/>
     had been found from enquiry and investigation that from the 
     <lb/>
     high cost of labour and other charges that would have to be met 
     <lb/>
     in constructing such a road within the stated time of three years, 
     <lb/>
     that the cost would be very heavy, very heavy indeed, and in 
     <lb/>
     addition to this it was coupled with a proposition that a railway 
     <lb/>
     should be built as soon as practicable, and that there should be 
     <lb/>
     an annual expenditure from the commencement of a million of 
     <lb/>
     dollars. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Under these circumstances the Government had held that any 
     <lb/>
     expenditure on a coach road was useless, and one that was not 
     <lb/>
     required, inasmuch as all the traffic would be taken by the 
     <lb/>
     railway as soon as completed. Taking this view therefore the 
     <lb/>
     Government had at once dissented from the proposition of 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia, and would not agree to it. The Government 
     <lb/>
     had also considered it unwise to consent to an annual 
     <lb/>
     expenditure of a million of dollars from the commencement 
     <lb/>
     without having any particulars as to the difficulties that would 
     <lb/>
     be met with, and had rather preferred that the whole work 
     <lb/>
     should be undertaken in a reasonable specified time,—as they 
     <lb/>
     thought a proper survey should be made, and the work then 
     <lb/>
     completed as speedily as possible. Then again the propositions 
     <lb/>
     of British Columbia had been changed in respect of 
     <lb/>
     representation in the Dominion House of Parliament. Reverting 
     <lb/>
           
           <cb/>
            

                 to the matter of the railway, he said the House had heard that it 
     <lb/>
     was estimated that the money grant necessary to construct the 
     <lb/>
     railway, in addition to the land grant, would amount to l and a 
     <lb/>
     quarter millions per annum, but it must not be understood that 
     <lb/>
     the expenditure of that sum of money was involved in the 
     <lb/>
     proposition before the House. That proposition was simply to 
     <lb/>
     admit British Columbia into the Dominion and connect her with 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion system of railways, and it must be remembered 
     <lb/>
     that the agreement entered into by the delegates at the 
     <lb/>
     conferences at Quebec and London, was that the six Provinces 
     <lb/>
     should be brought together, and also that the Red River country 
     <lb/>
     and British Columbia should also be included in the 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Such was the agreement, and happily, part had been 
     <lb/>
     accomplished, for notwithstanding all the trouble, all the 
     <lb/>
     anxiety, and all the difficulties that had arisen in connection 
     <lb/>
     with the North West, he believed the conviction from one end of 
     <lb/>
     the country to the other was that that country had been acquired 
     <lb/>
     on very favourable terms. Well the next thing after getting 
     <lb/>
     possession, was how to utilize it, and how could it be utilized? 
     <lb/>
     Surely not by building coach roads, not by simply improving the 
     <lb/>
     communication by water, no—the North West could only be 
     <lb/>
     used to advantage by means of a railway running to the foot of 
     <lb/>
     the Rocky Mountains, and the Government would not be doing 
     <lb/>
     its duty to the Dominion unless it projected that work. It was 
     <lb/>
     well known on the most reliable information, that in the valley 
     <lb/>
     of the Saskatchewan and the Red River there was a tract of 
     <lb/>
     Prairie Land, immense in extent, and magnificent in character, 
     <lb/>
     and how could immigration be conducted to that country, how 
     <lb/>
     could supplies be carried to settlers, how could the produce of 
     <lb/>
     that country be brought to a market unless there was a railway, 
     <lb/>
     and he did not hesitate to say that it had been the deliberately 
     <lb/>
     expressed opinion of the House and the country, that as soon as 
     <lb/>
     the country was acquired, a railway must be built to the foot of 
     <lb/>
     the Rocky Mountains. Believing this to be the determination of 
     <lb/>
     the Government and the country, the delegates from British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia came and submitted a proposition that that Railway 
     <lb/>
     should be extended from the foot of the Rocky Mountains to the 
     <lb/>
     Pacific, and he put it to the House and the Pacific, whether a 
     <lb/>
     line could not be built to the Pacific, much cheaper, in 
     <lb/>
     proportion, than one ending at the Rocky Mountains. The one 
     <lb/>
     would be available for local traffic only, and very much larger 
     <lb/>
     subsidies, therefore, would have to be paid, whereas a line 
     <lb/>
     running from the Atlantic to the Pacific would receive a very 
     <lb/>
     large amount of through traffic, and in addition to this, it had 
     <lb/>
     always been contemplated and determined that there should be 
     <lb/>
     such a line through Canadian Territory. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     It had been stated both by the Minister of Militia and the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Finance that it was not considered that the amount 
     <lb/>
     necessary for the construction of the railway, would involve any 
     <lb/>
     increase in the taxation of the people of the Dominion, and he had 
     <lb/>
     no doubt that that statement was correct, for taking the 
     <lb/>
     calculations of the hon. member for Sherbrooke himself as a 
     <lb/>
     basis, that the annual increase of the population of the Dominion 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="281" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_281.jpg"/>
           <fw type="dateline">March 28, 1871</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">281</fw>
           

     would be three per cent, (although when the railway to the Pacific 
     <lb/>
     was completed, and the vast Territory of the North West opened 
     <lb/>
     for settlement, there was no doubt the increase would be much 
     <lb/>
     greater), he believed the additional revenue derived from that 
     <lb/>
     increased population, irrespective of the increased paying ability, 
     <lb/>
     estimated at two per cent by the member for Sherbrooke, would 
     <lb/>
     be fully equal to all demands upon it without any increased 
     <lb/>
     taxation. He entirely agreed with his hon. friend that it was 
     <lb/>
     impossible to take large Provinces into the Dominion with a small 
     <lb/>
     population, and acquire all their lands without giving them in 
     <lb/>
     return the means of carrying out the local works necessary to 
     <lb/>
     make the country attractive to emigrants, and how could it be 
     <lb/>
     expected that the people of this large Province, twice the size of 
     <lb/>
     Ontario, would be in a position to develop the resources of their 
     <lb/>
     country without assistance—and that assistance was what the 
     <lb/>
     Government proposed to render in the proposition before the 
     <lb/>
     House? The member for Sherbrooke had said that he would have 
     <lb/>
     preferred that the Government should have come down and have 
     <lb/>
     asked a direct vote for that purpose, but he would remind the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member that he had not been in favour of that mode, when it was 
     <lb/>
     proposed with reference to Newfoundland. The delegates from 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia estimated the population of their country, at 
     <lb/>
     13,000 whites, 5,000 Chinese, and 45,000 Indians. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Then what was there to be got out of this country. At the 
     <lb/>
     present time it cost from 12¢ to 14¢ a pound for all supplies sent 
     <lb/>
     into that country, and no one could live there unless he earned $5 
     <lb/>
     a day. If, however, the country were opened up, they would be 
     <lb/>
     able to get supplies there as cheap as at Ottawa, and those who 
     <lb/>
     now live on $5 a day would be able to live on $2.50 a day, and 
     <lb/>
     there would very soon be a population which would yield a 
     <lb/>
     revenue that would speedily compensate for the cost of the 
     <lb/>
     railway. According to his judgment, seeing they had the North 
     <lb/>
     West, and must develop it, there was no question but that the 
     <lb/>
     Railway must be built, and even in a financial point of view, 
     <lb/>
     although he did not assume to have anything like the knowledge 
     <lb/>
     or experience of financial matters as was possessed by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Sherbrooke, he could not see that there would be any 
     <lb/>
     difficulty. The line of railway would pass through magnificent 
     <lb/>
     lands, and the proposed grant would give 50 million acres, leaving 
     <lb/>
     every alternate lot which could be converted into a sinking fund 
     <lb/>
     or some other mode for securing the amount of money granted, 
     <lb/>
     and taking into consideration the probable increase of population, 
     <lb/>
     the speedy settlement of the North West on its being opened up, 
     <lb/>
     and the increased paying ability, he had no fear, and the 
     <lb/>
     Government had no fear, that the people would be subjected to 
     <lb/>
     any increase of taxation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO8">Hon. Mr. McDOUGALL</persName> (Lanark North): There are not forty 
     <lb/>
     millions of acres of arable land in the whole North West Territory. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said he was not sure as to the number of 
     <lb/>
     acres, but the land would secure the building of the railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     It being six o'clock the House rose. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <cb/>
</div>
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">AFTER RECESS</head>
           
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> resumed the debate. He had been pointing 
     <lb/>
     out the difference between the proposition of British Columbia, and 
     <lb/>
     that adopted ultimately, which he regarded as the more favourable 
     <lb/>
     to the Dominion. In connection with the railway scheme he would 
     <lb/>
     take issue with his hon. friend from Sherbrooke. By the 
     <lb/>
     construction of the road the population of the Pacific coast would 
     <lb/>
     soon be so increased as to pay for the cost of the road in a very 
     <lb/>
     short time. A gentleman who had worked in the mines of 
     <lb/>
     California, lecturing on this subject a few years ago, argued that 
     <lb/>
     such a result would soon be attained by building the railway. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Sherbrooke was willing to give a subsidy to 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia without admitting it as a Province for some time 
     <lb/>
     to come. In making this admission, the hon. member gave up the 
     <lb/>
     whole case, for, if he could not object to giving a subsidy under 
     <lb/>
     such circumstances and without deriving every advantage from the 
     <lb/>
     expenditure, he surely ought not to object when British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     was ready to surrender her revenues to the Dominion. The increase 
     <lb/>
     of the debt would not fall on the present population of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion alone. The evidence which the increase of the Western 
     <lb/>
     States since the construction of railways through them, was that the 
     <lb/>
     North West would soon be filled up with a population brought there 
     <lb/>
     by the new railway which would soon pay for its construction. With 
     <lb/>
     reference to the question of fortifications, he would say that he 
     <lb/>
     hoped the result of the present negotiations at Washington would be 
     <lb/>
     such as to prevent all necessity for the constructing such works. The 
     <lb/>
     expense for local works would hardly amount to as much as the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Sherbrooke estimated they would. Excluding the 
     <lb/>
     annual sum of $100,000 for the land grant and the expenses of 
     <lb/>
     Government, these charges would amount to a total of $361,300. 
     <lb/>
     The revenue amounted to $363,400, which, of course, would 
     <lb/>
     largely increase in the future. The difference, therefore, was not so 
     <lb/>
     great after all. Even supposing that the local Government should 
     <lb/>
     accept our lower tariff, the revenue would reach $308,000. The 
     <lb/>
     $100,000 was, therefore, the amount of expenditure in excess of 
     <lb/>
     receipts, and for this the Dominion received a large grant of 
     <lb/>
     valuable land. Now, the question was, was the union of the colony 
     <lb/>
     worth the cost? The Pacific Railway, already in course of 
     <lb/>
     construction through the North Western States of the United States, 
     <lb/>
     was being built without the expenditure of a single dollar. It was 
     <lb/>
     being built by the land grants which had been made to the company. 
     <lb/>
     But, the hon. member for Lambton said there were only 50,000,000 
     <lb/>
     acres of good land to be settled in the North West. Admitting it to 
     <lb/>
     be the fact, what difference did it make so long as it was settled. 
     <lb/>
     That was the main point. Persons who had travelled through the 
     <lb/>
     Fertile Belt had informed him that there was no engineering 
     <lb/>
     difficulties to be met with this side of the Rocky Mountains, and 
     <lb/>
     there could be no difficulty in getting a company to undertake the 
     <lb/>
     construction of the railway. Having said this much, the case was 
     <lb/>
     clear. The question was now, whether it was better to embrace 
     <lb/>
     the opportunity to complete the Confederation scheme, or to let 
     <lb/>
     this best chance of all pass by unimproved for consummating 
     <lb/>
     the union. He could understand why Annexationists should be 
     <lb/>
     opposed to this extension of the Union, but he could not 
     <lb/>
     understand how the Independence advocates like the hon. 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="282" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_282.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">282</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">March 28, 1871</fw>

            

     member for Sherbrooke could oppose it. He could tell hon. 
     <lb/>
     members who did not approve of this scheme that delay was 
     <lb/>
     dangerous, and if this chance to bring British Columbia was not 
     <lb/>
     improved, that Colony might yet be absorbed into the American 
     <lb/>
     Union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>: How? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said as the country was at present the 
     <lb/>
     miners were obliged to pay enormous prices for the necessaries 
     <lb/>
     of life and they were looking to their country for the means of 
     <lb/>
     communication by which they were to be supplied at reasonable 
     <lb/>
     rates. If Canada would not undertake it, they might look to the 
     <lb/>
     Republic for help. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear</hi>.) But this Union could benefit 
     <lb/>
     Canada commercially, for the opening up of the North West and 
     <lb/>
     the consequent increase of trade must bring an immense volume 
     <lb/>
     of trade to Montreal and Quebec and the Maritime cities. 
     <lb/>
     Everything conspired to make this Union a prosperous one and 
     <lb/>
     he did not doubt that the House would sustain the measure 
     <lb/>
     which was now submitted to them. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Cheers</hi>.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> regretted that the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     opposite could not discuss this question for three quarters of an 
     <lb/>
     hour without threatening the annexation of that colony to the 
     <lb/>
     United States if this House rejected the present propositions. 
     <lb/>
     Such a line of argument could only be indulged in by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen in order to create a feeling that the papers brought 
     <lb/>
     down as agreed between the Dominion Government, and that of 
     <lb/>
     Columbia is in the nature of a treaty that is not to be altered by 
     <lb/>
     any proposition to be made in this House; if such were the case 
     <lb/>
     it would be useless to discuss the question. In 1865 the 
     <lb/>
     Parliaments of Canada, Nova Scotia, and New Brunswick were 
     <lb/>
     told the same story with reference to the resolutions which 
     <lb/>
     formed the basis of Confederation, but those resolutions were 
     <lb/>
     afterwards altered by the delegation at London, and he was not 
     <lb/>
     prepared to accept these resolutions in the nature of a treaty 
     <lb/>
     which this House could not alter. He believed on the other hand 
     <lb/>
     that it was essential for the future prosperity of the Dominion, 
     <lb/>
     that this colony should be admitted into the Union and that there 
     <lb/>
     should be the best possible understanding as to the terms of 
     <lb/>
     admission to prevent future complications, and he should not be 
     <lb/>
     prepared to acquiesce quietly in the resolutions which had been 
     <lb/>
     prepared by the hon. gentlemen opposite. By these resolutions, 
     <lb/>
     the basis of our political system would be violated as was done 
     <lb/>
     in the case of Manitoba last session, and after the struggle which 
     <lb/>
     had to be gone through to secure that basis, he should certainly 
     <lb/>
     oppose any further attempt to alter it, that is representation by 
     <lb/>
     population as regards the House of Commons. Some deviation 
     <lb/>
     he acknowledged might be made in the Senate. The Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Customs tells us that the population of Whites, 
     <lb/>
     Chinese, and Indians is 60,000 in that country, but we have 
     <lb/>
     never given representation under our system to Indians. If such 
     <lb/>
     were allowed we could claim several more members for 
     <lb/>
     Ontario. He would consent to a considerable grant of money to 
     <lb/>
     carry on the Government of a new colony, and particularly of 
     <lb/>
     such a difficult country as Columbia, and he would not show 
     <lb/>
               
               <cb/>
            
   
          
     himself less liberal than any other member of this House in 
     <lb/>
     considering what ought to be done in the present case. In the 
     <lb/>
     discussion in reference to Newfoundland, he preferred allowing 
     <lb/>
     a sum to carry on the Government rather than make over the 
     <lb/>
     public hands, as while the revenue was $3,000 per annum, the 
     <lb/>
     cost of management was $6,000, and he took the same view 
     <lb/>
     with regard to the land grant for the construction of the railway 
     <lb/>
     to the Pacific. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     From all he knew of the country after descending from the 
     <lb/>
     Rocky Mountains the country was valueless for agricultural 
     <lb/>
     purposes. The gold mines have certainly proved very 
     <lb/>
     remunerative, but they are carried on by large companies, and 
     <lb/>
     the large importations of breadstuffs into the colony 
     <lb/>
     corroborated the barrenness of the land. He thought the 
     <lb/>
     Government should be prepared to give every information as to 
     <lb/>
     the mode they propose of constructing the Railway, and whether 
     <lb/>
     any propositions had been received for its construction. He 
     <lb/>
     denounced the Government for desiring to undertake the 
     <lb/>
     completion of the work in ten years, and should certainly record 
     <lb/>
     his protest against such an arrangement, and he considered that 
     <lb/>
     to give such an immense grant as was proposed to any Company 
     <lb/>
     would be to retard the settlement of the country, as was found to 
     <lb/>
     be the case in the western States. He doubted very much if the 
     <lb/>
     Province of Ontario would grant the land as anticipated by the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Customs, and if they did the greater part of it was 
     <lb/>
     valueless for cultivation, and certainly would not realize $1 per 
     <lb/>
     acre as estimated. The Northern Pacific road was largely built 
     <lb/>
     by English capital before the land and money grant of the 
     <lb/>
     United States was obtained, and the difficulties were not to be 
     <lb/>
     compared to those which would be met on the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     Railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Canadian Pacific Railway would cost from six to seven 
     <lb/>
     times as much as the Intercolonial, and he was not prepared to 
     <lb/>
     involve the country so deeply. He then moved an amendment 
     <lb/>
     that all the words after "that" be expunged, and the following 
     <lb/>
     substituted, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     "the proposed terms of union with British Columbia pledge the Dominion to 
     <lb/>
     commence within two years and complete within ten years the Pacific Railway, 
     <lb/>
     the route for which has not been surveyed nor its expense calculated. The said 
     <lb/>
     terms also pledge the Government of Canada to a yearly payment to British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia, of the sum of $100,000 in perpetuity, equal to a capital sum of 
     <lb/>
     $2,000,000 for the cession of a tract of Wasteland on the route of the Pacific 
     <lb/>
     Railway to aid in its construction, which British Columbia ought to cede without 
     <lb/>
     charge, in like manner as the lands of Canada are proposed to be ceded for the 
     <lb/>
     same purpose. This House is of opinion that Canada should not be pledged to do 
     <lb/>
     more than proceed at once with the necessary surveys and after the route is 
     <lb/>
     determined, to prosecute the work at as early a period as the state of the finances 
     <lb/>
     will justify." 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GRAN2">Mr. GRANT</persName>: I have listened with a very great degree of 
     <lb/>
     pleasure to the broad spirited and statesmanlike observations of the 
     <lb/>
     hon. Minister of Militia and Defence. Truly, this is the age of union, 
     <lb/>
     in which we, as a people enjoying the fullest extent of freedom 
     <lb/>
     under the eye and protection of the Mother Country, should come 
     <lb/>
     together and realize the privileges of union in the widest and most 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="283" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_283.jpg"/>
           <fw type="dateline">March 28, 1871</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">283</fw> 
          

     comprehensive sense. Last session the whole of the North West 
     <lb/>
     Territory was brought into this Dominion by the almost unanimous 
     <lb/>
     consent of the members of this House, owing to the very 
     <lb/>
     satisfactory terms arranged by the Hon. the Minister of Militia and 
     <lb/>
     Defence, and the hon. member for Lanark opposite. Today we are 
     <lb/>
     taking into serious consideration the desirability of adding one more 
     <lb/>
     link to the Confederation scheme by the taking in of British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia. The time then is not far distant when we shall have a 
     <lb/>
     greater degree of intercourse in trade and travel, and if possible a 
     <lb/>
     greater extension of those principles of free speech which we now 
     <lb/>
     enjoy with courteous personal consultation. These are the signs of 
     <lb/>
     the times: these are the signs by which four millions of Her 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's subjects, scattered over this widespread country, 
     <lb/>
     recognize the importance of self-govemment with a warm 
     <lb/>
     allegiance to that sovereign who, though distant, dwells in the 
     <lb/>
     homes and hearts of the people of this country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     It must be a source of great gratification to all interested in the 
     <lb/>
     prosperity of this Dominion to learn today the terms upon which 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia is to be admitted into the Union. That section of 
     <lb/>
     country though remote as to position is an all important one from a 
     <lb/>
     Dominion point of view. It possesses a most salubrious climate, 
     <lb/>
     well known agricultural capacity, and as to value is entirely beyond 
     <lb/>
     present computation both politically and commercially. In looking 
     <lb/>
     over the statistics of 1868, 1 observed that there had been no 
     <lb/>
     apparent increase in the population for that year beyond the children 
     <lb/>
     born in the country, and notwithstanding the great numbers who 
     <lb/>
     annually emigrate from Great Britain and various parts of Europe to 
     <lb/>
     the North American continent, it is surprising that with all the 
     <lb/>
     attractions of the Pacific section of British North America so few 
     <lb/>
     emigrants should have found their way there up to the present date, 
     <lb/>
     and more particularly so when we consider its climate, its soil, and 
     <lb/>
     its resources, such as coal, iron, timber and gold. The vigorous 
     <lb/>
     measures about to be adopted will doubtless be the means of 
     <lb/>
     causing a greater tide of immigration than has been observed at any 
     <lb/>
     time in the history of that country. An examination of the statistics 
     <lb/>
     of the population of British Columbia shows the somewhat 
     <lb/>
     remarkable fact that the male exceeds the female population by 
     <lb/>
     about 277 per cent. Such an anomalous condition does not, that I 
     <lb/>
     am aware of, exist in any other country at the present time—in 
     <lb/>
     England, the United States and in Canada—precisely the reverse is 
     <lb/>
     the case. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The wonder is that British Columbia should have attained its 
     <lb/>
     present prosperous condition wanting in so great a measure so 
     <lb/>
     material an element of success. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Cheers</hi>.) 1n 1863 British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     was looked upon as being then, in a flourishing condition, 
     <lb/>
     stimulated as it was to the utmost degree of intensity by the gold 
     <lb/>
     fever. After a time, things in general assumed a more normal state, 
     <lb/>
     and business on the whole gradually rested on a more substantial 
     <lb/>
     basis. Farms became cultivated, immense herds of cattle were 
     <lb/>
     raised, saw and grist mills were erected, and the lumberman's axe 
     <lb/>
     found its way into the magnificent forests of that country, in places 
     <lb/>
     where a few years before such was scarcely dreamt of Material 
     <lb/>
     prosperity and general advancement are now taking the place of the 
     <lb/>
     feverish gold excitement, which is gradually passing away. When 
     <lb/>
               
               
               <cb/>
            
   
           
     we become possessors of British Columbia, we shall have a most 
     <lb/>
     magnificent inland sea of harbours such as between Vancouver and 
     <lb/>
     the main land. It appears as if set apart by a special providence as a 
     <lb/>
     depot for the shipping of the East, and as an entrance to the great 
     <lb/>
     highway for all nations across the British American Continent, 
     <lb/>
     doubtless in course of time, the trade of China, Japan and the 
     <lb/>
     Asiatic Archipelago will centre there. This is the prize that was as 
     <lb/>
     anxiously sought after in ancient as it is in modern times. Persia, 
     <lb/>
     Assyria, Carthage and Rome prospered and held, in fact, 
     <lb/>
     commercial supremacy while they controlled the trade of the East. 
     <lb/>
     Venice, Genoa, Lisbon, Amsterdam and London each in turn held a 
     <lb/>
     proud commercial position, while it catered up the luxuries of the 
     <lb/>
     East for the Western world. This is the inheritance of the Pacific 
     <lb/>
     Coast. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     We, the people of this Dominion, have every assurance that Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain has a warm interest in our prosperity. What better or more 
     <lb/>
     substantial proof could we have than the expression of the 
     <lb/>
     sentiment which only a few days ago flashed across the Atlantic 
     <lb/>
     telegraph, that England would as soon think of having itself 
     <lb/>
     annexed to the United States as to allow any portion of this country 
     <lb/>
     be attached to the neighbouring Republic. Both England and the 
     <lb/>
     United States are equally well aware that the time has now arrived 
     <lb/>
     when that power which shall be enabled to construct the shortest 
     <lb/>
     route between Asia and Europe will hold the commercial 
     <lb/>
     supremacy of this continent in its grasp. The great trade of the East 
     <lb/>
     will not alone pass through the Suez Canal and the Red Sea. This is 
     <lb/>
     the prize which we as a people must look forward to, and certainly 
     <lb/>
     it is one which is well worth the endeavour to obtain. An able 
     <lb/>
     English writer remarks that the great benefit to be derived from the 
     <lb/>
     experience of the past is the application of its teaching to the 
     <lb/>
     present. Thus, in taking a retrospective view of Confederation, and 
     <lb/>
     the benefits arising out of it, even although the time is short since its 
     <lb/>
     inception, we must be congnizant of the fact that day by day we are 
     <lb/>
     becoming more intimately associated as a people, co-operating in 
     <lb/>
     every way that is possible to develop our resources. During the 
     <lb/>
     early discussions on the subject of Confederation, a frequent 
     <lb/>
     expression was "whither are we drifting." This was reiterated until 
     <lb/>
     at last it became irksome and unworthy of attention. The only 
     <lb/>
     sentiment which seemed in any way likely to form with it a twin 
     <lb/>
     was the theory of independence. Both of these have had their day, 
     <lb/>
     and now I feel satisfied that the impression of everyone who takes a 
     <lb/>
     warm interest in the welfare of our country is that both these ill- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     judged sentiments have gone down unhonoured and unsung. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Fortunate is it that trade has a natural and inevitable power to 
     <lb/>
     rectify itself. For a time after the repeal of the Reciprocity Treaty 
     <lb/>
     this country was put to a moderate degree of inconvenience; 
     <lb/>
     however, the master mechanical minds and the politicians of the 
     <lb/>
     country, so accommodated matters and things in general as to tide 
     <lb/>
     that difficulty over, and now a more prosperous state of affairs 
     <lb/>
     exists than we have experienced for many years. As the result of the 
     <lb/>
     vigorous policy of those in charge of the affairs of Government, we 
     <lb/>
     are happy to recognize the very important fact that our Finance 
     <lb/>
     Minister has been so exceedingly successful in his operations as to 
     <lb/>
     have been enabled to bring down in his recent budget a surplus of 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="284" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_284.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">284</fw> <fw type="num">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">March 28, 1871</fw> 
          

     no less than two and a half millions of dollars! Truly our Dominion 
     <lb/>
     under these circumstances cannot be suffering! Our merchants are 
     <lb/>
     not embarrassed; our young men are not leaving the country to seek 
     <lb/>
     employment in distant parts as formerly, and we have every 
     <lb/>
     assurance that the farmers of the country are reaping the benefits of 
     <lb/>
     their labour and industry in finding ready markets for their produce. 
     <lb/>
     Still further evidences of the prosperous state of our Dominion are 
     <lb/>
     found in the condition of our savings banks, the ordinary bank 
     <lb/>
     deposits, the prosperity of our municipal institutions, our increased 
     <lb/>
     and increasing railway traffic, our large importations and our 
     <lb/>
     rapidly increasing exports. All these beyond doubt point 
     <lb/>
     incontrovertibly to a flourishing state of affairs throughout our 
     <lb/>
     Dominion at the present day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     When we review the commercial history of the British American 
     <lb/>
     Provinces for the past thirty years, we notice that the progress of old 
     <lb/>
     Canada dates from the Union of the Eastern with the Western 
     <lb/>
     section and has followed the construction of Canals and Railways. 
     <lb/>
     The present Canal system of Canada was brought to its present 
     <lb/>
     condition, with all its imperfections the finest in the world—during 
     <lb/>
     that period. Twenty years ago, there were only some fifty miles of 
     <lb/>
     railway in operation in the Province. At present, the total number of 
     <lb/>
     miles of rail is nearly 3,000—one of the lines is the second longest 
     <lb/>
     on the Continent—the total cost of these works is nearly 
     <lb/>
     $160,000,000—the total amount of their earnings cannot be less 
     <lb/>
     than $13,000,000 annually. In 1841 when we commenced our canal 
     <lb/>
     improvements the revenue of Old Canada was $1,283,000 or $1 per 
     <lb/>
     head for every man, woman and child within its limits. In 1854, the 
     <lb/>
     commencement of railway enterprise, it was $5,694,000, or $2 per 
     <lb/>
     head', in 1866 it was above $12,000,000 or $4 per head. In 1850 the 
     <lb/>
     population of united Canada was only 1,842,265, and the exports 
     <lb/>
     some $30,000,000 or about $15.50 for every person. At present the 
     <lb/>
     total population is over 3,500,000 and exports $120,000,000 or 
     <lb/>
     nearly $35 per head. Or let us illustrate the subject by reference to 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion. In 1843 the revenue was about $2,000,000, whilst at 
     <lb/>
     the present time it is about $15,000,000, or about $3.50 per head of 
     <lb/>
     the population. In 1806 the value of exports from all British North 
     <lb/>
     America was only $9,287,940; in 1831 $16,523,579; in 1870 it was 
     <lb/>
     $73,573,490. In 1851 the tonnage entered inwards by sea in all 
     <lb/>
     British North American ports was 1,590,663. In 1870 the tonnage 
     <lb/>
     entered inwards by sea in the Dominion was 5,796,663. In 1851 the 
     <lb/>
     tonnage cleared outwards in all British North America was 
     <lb/>
     1,583,104. In 1870 the tonnage cleared outwards in Canada was 
     <lb/>
     5,619,745. In 1806, the aggregate tonnage of British America was 
     <lb/>
     71,943; in 1850, 446,935; at the present time, it is upwards of 
     <lb/>
     950,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The expenditures have kept pace with the receipts during the 
     <lb/>
     period mentioned, and were devoted to a large extent to useful 
     <lb/>
     public works indispensable to the material development of the 
     <lb/>
     country. Our wealth, however, is increasing in a greater ratio than it 
     <lb/>
     was at the time we entered into large expenditures for canals, and 
     <lb/>
     our ability to go into important enterprises necessary to the 
     <lb/>
     expansion of Trade and Commerce is correspondingly improved. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Before closing my remarks, I would wish to allude briefly to an 
     <lb/>
     important union which took place some time ago in the North West 
     <lb/>
               
               <cb/>
             

     Country, and one which bears materially upon the prosperity of that 
     <lb/>
     section as far as the fur trade is concerned. The Hudson's Bay 
     <lb/>
     Company is an association formed, as it is well known, of two 
     <lb/>
     distinct elements, the stockholders who, as a company have other 
     <lb/>
     interests apart from those of fur trading; and the chief factors and 
     <lb/>
     chief traders known as the working partners of the fur trade portion 
     <lb/>
     of the concern. The stockholders are the representatives of those to 
     <lb/>
     whom, under the name of "The Company of Adventurers of 
     <lb/>
     England trading in the Hudson's Bay" was granted the charter by 
     <lb/>
     King Charles II to trade furs, etc. in the Hudson's Bay and adjacent 
     <lb/>
     country. This company established a few posts near the shores of 
     <lb/>
     the Bay, and for years confined their operations within 
     <lb/>
     comparatively a short distance from the coast. In course of time 
     <lb/>
     they advanced into the interior, where they came in contact with 
     <lb/>
     other traders, of whom the most active were sent out by a company 
     <lb/>
     having its headquarters in Canada and known as "The North West 
     <lb/>
     Company." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     For a number of years these two rival companies competed for 
     <lb/>
     trade with such determination that not unfrequently when opposing 
     <lb/>
     parties met a conflict took place, resulting in loss of life. Under 
     <lb/>
     these circumstances it is not a matter of surprise that the business 
     <lb/>
     was found to be carried on at a considerable loss to both parties in 
     <lb/>
     consequence of which a Union took place. Since that time, business 
     <lb/>
     has been carried on to the mutual benefit and satisfaction of all 
     <lb/>
     parties concerned. The Factors, Traders and Officers in the service 
     <lb/>
     of the Company, generally may be considered Canadians as hitherto 
     <lb/>
     with but few exceptions, they have all either settled on the Red 
     <lb/>
     River or come down to Ontario and Quebec. In dealing, therefore, 
     <lb/>
     with this question of the Hudson's Bay Company, it is to be hoped 
     <lb/>
     that the interests of these people will not be overlooked. The Fur 
     <lb/>
     Trade is a subject of no ordinary importance at the present time. 
     <lb/>
     Instead of leaving the Indians at the mercy of whoever may come in 
     <lb/>
     contact with them, there are but two alternatives, either of which, 
     <lb/>
     according to the opinion of experienced men, if adopted, might be 
     <lb/>
     made a source of large revenue to the Dominion. Of course it 
     <lb/>
     cannot be expected that the company will continue the fostering 
     <lb/>
     care with which it has hitherto treated the Indians in the trade 
     <lb/>
     operations with them. The fur country may become flooded with 
     <lb/>
     unscrupulous adventurers in consequence of which the company 
     <lb/>
     will be obliged in a great measure to abandon the practice of giving 
     <lb/>
     supplies to them. Without the usual advances in the autumn a great 
     <lb/>
     number of the unfortunate people will be obliged to abandon 
     <lb/>
     systematic fur hunting in order to devote their chief attention to pot- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     hunting to support their families and prolong their own lives. It is 
     <lb/>
     only in case of competition that there is danger of the Indians 
     <lb/>
     suffering. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     When in the control of a company it will be the duty of that 
     <lb/>
     company to give proper supplies, which could not possibly be 
     <lb/>
     accomplished with rival parties scouring the country, and it is 
     <lb/>
     not unlikely that the scenes enacted half a century ago would 
     <lb/>
     under such circumstances be revived. It appears to me that 
     <lb/>
     some plan such as that adopted with regards to the salmon 
     <lb/>
     fisheries of the Lower St. Lawrence might be applicable in 
     <lb/>
     letting out the fur country of the North West. It is true that a 
     <lb/>
     few individuals might thus control the trade, but such would 
     <lb/>
            

            <pb n="285" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_285.jpg"/>
           <fw type="dateline">March 28, 1871</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">285</fw>  
           

     be vastly preferable to leaving it open to all comers from all 
     <lb/>
     parts of the world, which could not but prove exceedingly 
     <lb/>
     injurious to the trade. The existing divisions of the country 
     <lb/>
     into districts as recognized by the Hudson's Bay Company is 
     <lb/>
     of great importance, inasmuch as such districts have different 
     <lb/>
     tribes—a very important fact both for the Indians and the 
     <lb/>
     trade. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     If not disposed of as the salmon fisheries the whole trade 
     <lb/>
     might be managed by an experienced Board of Direction. This 
     <lb/>
     would be the best for the country, and likely under all 
     <lb/>
     circumstances most profitable. This trade is a subject of vast 
     <lb/>
     importance, for it involves the living of fully 75,000 of our 
     <lb/>
     fellow subjects, and nothing could be more desirable than to 
     <lb/>
     direct the affairs of the Indians in such a manner as may be 
     <lb/>
     generally acceptable to the chiefs of those great bodies. The 
     <lb/>
     principle must be <hi rendition="simple:italic">protection</hi> not <hi rendition="simple:italic">extermination</hi>. Thus, the 
     <lb/>
     Indians would become peaceable subjects, and warm adherents 
     <lb/>
     to whoever would tend most towards the welfare of the 
     <lb/>
     Northern fur trading country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     At the lowest estimate, the value of the exports, that is 
     <lb/>
     including the fur obtained from British Columbia, would 
     <lb/>
     amount to about $1,000,000 annually. This, if well managed, it 
     <lb/>
     is supposed by competent authority would yield fully half that 
     <lb/>
     amount to the revenue of this Dominion. As this whole matter 
     <lb/>
     will no doubt receive the consideration of the Government, I 
     <lb/>
     would merely say in conclusion that I trust the day is near at 
     <lb/>
     hand when British Columbia will become part and parcel of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Cheers</hi>.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MASS2">Mr. MASSON</persName> (Terrebonne) had always been opposed to 
     <lb/>
     the acquisition of the North West, and to-night he heard from 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Lambton that he had good reason for that 
     <lb/>
     opposition. It seemed that, after all, there were only some 
     <lb/>
     50,000,000 acres of habitable land in the whole territory which 
     <lb/>
     was capable of sustaining a population of about two millions 
     <lb/>
     of people, giving twenty-five acres to each person. A very 
     <lb/>
     different state of affairs to what the House had been led to 
     <lb/>
     believe existed. Now, after having acquired the unsettled four- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     fifths of the territories there, the House was asked to take 
     <lb/>
     possession of the remaining settled one-fifth. It seemed to him 
     <lb/>
     that having got the worst part of the land, having pushed our 
     <lb/>
     boundaries up to the verge of the wilderness, the House need 
     <lb/>
     hardly hesitate about extending the Dominion to the Pacific. 
     <lb/>
     Then, with respect to the railway, he believed it would be 
     <lb/>
     better to construct it with as little delay as possible, and he 
     <lb/>
     believed the Government policy to be the correct one. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART3">Mr. CARTWRIGHT</persName> doubted whether $100,000,000 was a 
     <lb/>
     sufficiently large estimate of the cost of constructing a Pacific 
     <lb/>
     Railway 2,500 miles in length. The House should consider 
     <lb/>
     well before taking upon the Dominion such a debt as they were 
     <lb/>
     now asked to bear. The present obligations of the country 
     <lb/>
     either actually incurred or to be incurred amounted to not less 
     <lb/>
     than $130,000,000. Then they were asked to increase it 
     <lb/>
               
               <cb/>
             
     $6,000,000 by this measure, and besides the minimum cost of 
     <lb/>
     the Pacific Railway, which was $100,000,000. This would give 
     <lb/>
     a total debt of $240,000,000, which would place on each 
     <lb/>
     family in the Dominion a debt of $125. The result would be to 
     <lb/>
     ruin our credit at home and abroad. Then the Government 
     <lb/>
     proposed to give to this railway a grant of land amounting to 
     <lb/>
     100,000 square miles—a tract of country equal to the whole 
     <lb/>
     New England States, or to New York, Pennsylvania and Ohio. 
     <lb/>
     He believed if the people of British Columbia who had shown 
     <lb/>
     such a liberal spirit in these negotiations were informed that it 
     <lb/>
     would be physically impossible for this Dominion to undertake 
     <lb/>
     the construction of a railway at a cost of from $100,000,000 
     <lb/>
     and complete it within ten years, they would consent to a 
     <lb/>
     modification of the terms proposed to this House. He was 
     <lb/>
     strongly in favour of the Union and was willing to go as far as 
     <lb/>
     it could safely be done to consummate Confederation by the 
     <lb/>
     admission of this colony into the Dominion. But the House 
     <lb/>
     should be careful before risking the safety of the 
     <lb/>
     Confederation by incurring a burden of debt under which they 
     <lb/>
     might sink. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:YOUN2">Mr. YOUNG</persName> said that while he was a Unionist, he felt that 
     <lb/>
     the measure before the House was objectionable. He was of 
     <lb/>
     opinion that the Dominion should not seek to incur large 
     <lb/>
     indebtedness to secure the admission of British Columbia into 
     <lb/>
     the Union until all the Eastern Provinces were added to the 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. Under any circumstances there were provisions 
     <lb/>
     in this Bill which were objectionable. Chief among these was 
     <lb/>
     the departure from the established principle of representation. 
     <lb/>
     He referred to the proposed railway, and read from a report of 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Fleming on the subject an extract to the effect that the 
     <lb/>
     engineering difficulties to be overcome were startling in their 
     <lb/>
     magnitude, while the cost of keeping the road in running order 
     <lb/>
     would alone render it a formidable undertaking, being not less 
     <lb/>
     than $10,000,000, and until the gross annual earnings of the 
     <lb/>
     line should reach $14,000,000, the railway would not pay the 
     <lb/>
     expenses connected with maintaining it. Speaking of the 
     <lb/>
     financial aspect of the measure he quoted statements as to the 
     <lb/>
     charges on the Government. And the revenue to be derived, 
     <lb/>
     showing that British Columbia would receive $225,000 more 
     <lb/>
     than she paid in, and even that calculation was contingent on 
     <lb/>
     the continuance of the tariff now in force, which was very 
     <lb/>
     uncertain. He maintained that these conditions were not fair to 
     <lb/>
     the rest of the Dominion, and the result would be that the 
     <lb/>
     finances would go back to the chronic state of deficiency that 
     <lb/>
     had existed some years ago. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName> desired to call the attention of the House to the 
     <lb/>
     single point before it. As one who was always desirous that the 
     <lb/>
     Union should be created, and that the express objects of the Union 
     <lb/>
     Act, which contemplated the admission of British Columbia, should 
     <lb/>
     be consummated as rapidly as circumstances and prudence would 
     <lb/>
     permit. He retorted on those who had uttered it, the accusation that 
     <lb/>
     he was desirous that the Union should be consummated. He had 
     <lb/>
     been at a loss how an Administration basing its claim to public 
     <lb/>
     confidence on professions of representing the Great Union Party 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="286" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710328_Page_286.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">286</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">March 28, 1871</fw>  
           

     could come down to the House with a proposition which would be 
     <lb/>
     fatal to the existence of confederation. A reference to public 
     <lb/>
     documents, however, had convinced him that the true object of the 
     <lb/>
     Administration must have been to destroy all present hope of a 
     <lb/>
     Union on reasonable and prudent terms. His reason for this 
     <lb/>
     conclusion was that the Department which was naturally charged 
     <lb/>
     with the conduct of negotiations on this subject was under the 
     <lb/>
     control of a gentleman who had, some time ago, in a letter to the 
     <lb/>
     public of Canada, used expressions, which in him (Mr. Blake) 
     <lb/>
     would have been called treason, and he could not but think that the 
     <lb/>
     preposterous proposition of the Government with respect to the 
     <lb/>
     Pacific Railway, was specially framed to defeat a Union with 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     These observations were made by Mr. Howe, when he was about 
     <lb/>
     to assume the position of Secretary of State. These being his 
     <lb/>
     expounded views, written in a deliberate letter, who could wonder 
     <lb/>
     that he was a party to bringing down a measure so iniquitous that 
     <lb/>
     the House could not help rejecting it. No wonder then that Governor 
     <lb/>
     Musgrave should have stated publicly that he was amazed at the 
     <lb/>
     concessions granted by the Canadian Government. Were not hon. 
     <lb/>
     members justified then, in asking for further information before 
     <lb/>
     taking this irrevocable step. If this measure should become law, the 
     <lb/>
     faith of the Dominion would be blighted and without the consent of 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia could never break one jot or tittle these cast-iron 
     <lb/>
     obligations. But the hon. Minister of Militia did not propose to 
     <lb/>
     increase the taxation of the country. Let him then put it in the 
     <lb/>
     bargain with British Columbia that no future misunderstandings 
     <lb/>
     might arise in the fulfillment of our pledge. Hon. members opposite 
     <lb/>
     had stated that they were willing to give 60,000,000 acres of land to 
     <lb/>
     aid the railway, and to pay off the interest on the debt incurred by 
     <lb/>
     the railway by the sale of lands in the North West. The Ontario 
     <lb/>
     Government had found it advisable to make free grants of their 
     <lb/>
               <cb/>
              
     lands to settlers, instead of making a revenue from them, and the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Government would find it no less difficult to derive a 
     <lb/>
     revenue from lands in the North West. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     He (Mr. Blake) called upon every member in this House to 
     <lb/>
     consider whether he was not betraying the interests of the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     in ratifying this bargain which the administration of the day had 
     <lb/>
     made. The fixed date of commencement and completion of the 
     <lb/>
     railway were dead weights on the enterprise under which the 
     <lb/>
     country was already staggering. They enhanced the difficulty of the 
     <lb/>
     undertaking. Could any country expect more than a promise to 
     <lb/>
     build this railway as soon as possible? Could British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     expect more from this Dominion? He was an advocate of Union, 
     <lb/>
     but under such terms as these, he considered it his duty to oppose it. 
     <lb/>
     He did not blame British Columbia for these unjust stipulations, but 
     <lb/>
     he blamed this Government for having stultified themselves by 
     <lb/>
     making such proposals. No solid argument could be brought against 
     <lb/>
     the view that the terms proposed by British Columbia and to which 
     <lb/>
     the colony was content to submit, should have been accepted by the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Government. The amendment of the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Lambton was not in opposition to the union. The Opposition did not 
     <lb/>
     oppose the scheme but the unjust terms by which it was 
     <lb/>
     accompanied, and he could not see how any lover of his country 
     <lb/>
     should hesitate as to what course to take with respect to this 
     <lb/>
     measure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     After a short discussion as to whether the debate should be 
     <lb/>
     adjourned or continued, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOLT1">Mr. BOLTON</persName> rose to explain his position with respect to this 
     <lb/>
     measure, and opposed the Ministerial scheme. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The debate was adjourned, and the House rose at midnight. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
       </div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
