<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_1871-02-17"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1871-02-17">17 February 1871</date>, Canadian Confederation with British Columbia</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Canadian Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>Norman Ward and Pamela Hardisty</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2007"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="13"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710217_Page_013.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-10-06">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710217_Page_013">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710217_Page_013.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="013" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710217_Page_013.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     February 17, 1871 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
           
            <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     Friday, February 17, 1871 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     The SPEAKER took the chair at three o’clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prayers</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Several petitions and motions were presented. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
   
            <head>
     LACHINE CANAL BRIDGE 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. HOLTON asked if the Grand Trunk Railway had 
     <lb/>
     asked permission to erect an additional bridge on or near the 
     <lb/>
     Lachine Canal, at the Wellington Bridge, Montreal, and if so, when 
     <lb/>
     the permission was applied for and when granted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. LANGEVIN said the Railway company was allowed 
     <lb/>
     to cross the canal with a swing bridge at Wellington Street, to be 
     <lb/>
     built at the place and in the stead of the existing bridge, and subject 
     <lb/>
     to the conditions he would lay before the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. HOLTON: When was the permission applied for, and 
     <lb/>
     when granted? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. LANGEVIN: Applied for on 17th January, 1871, and 
     <lb/>
     granted 28th January. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     GRAND TRUNK RETURNS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. MACKENZIE moved for returns of statements, showing 
     <lb/>
     the gross earnings of the Grand Trunk Railway during certain 
     <lb/>
     years. — Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p></div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head>
     NORTH WEST INSTRUCTIONS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. MACKENZIE moved an address for copies of all 
     <lb/>
     instructions to Lieutenant-Govemor Archibald, also copies of all 
     <lb/>
     reports and ofﬁcial correspondence between the Lieutenant- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Governor and the Dominion Government from the date of his 
     <lb/>
     appointment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD said that while no objection 
     <lb/>
     would be urged to furnishing the returns asked for, it would be as 
     <lb/>
     well to mention exactly the papers which were wanted. There was a 
     <lb/>
     very large amount of correspondence continually passing between 
     <lb/>
           
           <cb/>
             <fw type="num">13 <lb/></fw>
         
     the Local Government and the Dominion Government, only a 
     <lb/>
     portion of which could be of any service to the hon. member. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. MACKENZIE said he only wished to obtain that portion 
     <lb/>
     relative to the new system of Government, the division of the 
     <lb/>
     Province into electoral districts, and everything, in fact, connected 
     <lb/>
     with the new order of things. He did not want the formal 
     <lb/>
     correspondence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER called the attention of the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member to the fact that Lieutenant-Governor Archibald was 
     <lb/>
     the Governor of the North West Territory as well as of Manitoba, 
     <lb/>
     and correspondence relevant to both capacities should be included. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The motion was amended in accordance with the suggestion, and 
     <lb/>
     carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     * * * 
     <lb/>
     
            </p></div>

<div type="section">
            <head>PUBLIC ACCOUNTS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
            <p/>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir FRANCIS HINCKS submitted the public accounts for the year.<lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>(<hi rendition="simple:italic">Applause</hi>) 
     <lb/>Mr. MACKENZIE: It will save us a great deal of trouble. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir FRANCIS HlNCKS also laid on the table details of 
     <lb/>
     expenditure for the defence of the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. MACKENZIE: Perhaps the hon. member will give us 
     <lb/>
     details of all the expenditure from the fund for unforeseen expenses. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir FRANCIS HINCKS said they would be submitted in a 
     <lb/>
     few days. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head>
     BRITISH COLUMBIA CORRESPONDENCE 
     <lb/>
     MOTIONS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. MACKENZIE moved for an address for copies of all 
     <lb/>
     correspondence between the Government and British Columbia, its 
     <lb/>
     delegates, or the Imperial Government relative to the admission of 
     <lb/>
     such colony into the Dominion', also copies of all orders in council 
     <lb/>
     or other documents relating to such negotiation.—Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD said all correspondence 
     <lb/>
     would be brought down by message, and the motion was 
     <lb/>
     unnecessary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
