<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_1871-03-14"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1871-03-14">14 March 1871</date>, Canadian Confederation with British Columbia</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Canadian Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>Norman Ward and Pamela Hardisty</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2007"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="182"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710314_Page_182.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-10-06">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710314_Page_182">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710314_Page_182.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="182" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710314_Page_182.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">182</fw>
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. DORION said the hon. gentleman did not seem to 
     <lb/>
     propose any amendment of the Act of last session except to allow 
     <lb/>
     the Banks to come under this general law. One part of the 
     <lb/>
     resolutions had given rise to some difficulty. What was meant by 
     <lb/>
     the words “cash reserves?” In Montreal there had been a good deal 
     <lb/>
     of discussion as to the exact meaning or requirement of the “cash 
     <lb/>
     reserves” on which was to be based the amount of Dominion notes 
     <lb/>
     or funds to be kept by the bank. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir FRANCIS HlNCKS said he did not see any difﬁculty 
     <lb/>
     of the kind mentioned; nor had he heard of any, though he had had 
     <lb/>
     a great deal of conversation with bankers since the Act of last 
     <lb/>
     session was passed. The course he proposed was the reference of 
     <lb/>
     the Bill to the Standing Committee on Banking and Commerce, 
     <lb/>
     where all those matters could be fully considered. He was sure the 
     <lb/>
     Bill would come from that Committee in a satisfactory shape. He 
     <lb/>
     then moved the adoption of the first resolution, which was carried 
     <lb/>
     as were all the others. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir FRANCIS HlNCKS then introduced a Bill relating to 
     <lb/>
     Banks and banking. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<div type="section">
   
            <head>
     BRITISH COLUMBIA 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir GEORGE-E. CARTIER moved that the House go 
     <lb/>
     into committee on Friday next to consider the resolutions respecting 
     <lb/>
     the admission of British Columbia. He explained that as this was a 
     <lb/>
     most important measure it would not be discussed till Friday next. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. DORION suggested that the debate be deferred till a 
     <lb/>
     week from Friday next. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir GEORGE-E. CARTIER said it was not likely that the 
     <lb/>
     subject would be exhausted in one day. On next Tuesday, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Trutch, who was at present in Washington, would be here, and as 
     <lb/>
     that gentleman wished to go to England as soon as possible, the 
     <lb/>
     debate would commence on Tuesday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. DORION said it was a very large measure, and it 
     <lb/>
     would be well to have the Ontario Opposition and the members of 
     <lb/>
     the Ontario Cabinet who were absent, in the House while it was 
     <lb/>
     under discussion. The debate would be protracted rather than 
     <lb/>
     advanced by the course which the Government proposed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. HARRISON said it was pleasant to observe that the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen opposite were alive to the fact that several Ontario 
     <lb/>
     members were absent from the House. Yesterday, when the 
     <lb/>
     arbitration question was brought up, they seemed to be quite 
     <lb/>
     oblivious to the fact. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear</hi>.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. MILLS thought the House should be put in possession of a 
     <lb/>
     statement of the imports of British Columbia before the question 
     <lb/>
     should be brought before the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <cb/>
            <fw type="dateline">
     March 14, 1871 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
   
            <p>
     After some further discussion the motion was carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<p> *** <lb/></p>

   </div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     WEIGHTS AND MEASURES 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. MORRIS moved that the House go into Committee at 
     <lb/>
     some future day to consider certain resolutions for the establishing 
     <lb/>
     of a uniform system of weights and measures for all Canada. The 
     <lb/>
     resolutions also permitted the use of the metric system where two 
     <lb/>
     parties to a contract were agreeable. -Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <p> *** <lb/></p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     INSPECTION LAWS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir FRANCIS HlNCKS moved that the House go into 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole at a future day to consider a resolution 
     <lb/>
     declaring it expedient to amend and consolidate, and to extend to 
     <lb/>
     the whole Dominion of Canada, the laws respecting the inspection 
     <lb/>
     of certain staple articles of Canadian produceiCarried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <p> *** <lb/></p>
   </div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     FENIAN RAIDS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir FRANCIS HlNCKS moved the reception ofthe report 
     <lb/>
     of the Committee of the Whole on certain resolutions afﬁrming the 
     <lb/>
     expediency of indemnifying the Government for having authorized 
     <lb/>
     the issue of a special warrant for $200,000, to provide for the 
     <lb/>
     defence of the Dominion, in repelling the Fenian invasion in the 
     <lb/>
     month of May last. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The resolutions having been read a second time, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir FRANCIS HlNCKS introduced a Bill founded on 
     <lb/>
     them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

 <p> *** <lb/></p>
   </div>
   
<div type="section">
            <head>
     INTERIM ELECTIONS BILL 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The House went into Committee of the Whole on Bill No. 16, to 
     <lb/>
     make temporary provision for the election of members to serve in 
     <lb/>
     the House of Commons of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. IRVINE in the chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir GEORGE-E. CARTIER said he understood the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member opposite intended to make certain amendments to the Bill 
     <lb/>
     now before the Committee. He suggested that the amendments 
     <lb/>
     should be proposed aﬁer the Committee should rise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
