<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_BC_1871-02-16"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>[<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1871-02-16">16 February 1871</date>, Canadian Confederation with British Columbia]</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>Norman Ward and Pamela Hardisty</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2007"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="7"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="11"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710216_Page_007.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710216_Page_011.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-10-06">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710216_Page_007">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710216_Page_007.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710216_Page_011">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710216_Page_011.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="7" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710216_Page_007.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     February 16, 1871 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     obtainment of the opinion of this House in reference to the 
     <lb/>
     important matters to be dealt with by the approaching International 
     <lb/>
     Commission. The Hon. Premier was soon to leave for Washington. 
     <lb/>
     No discussion of the ﬁshery or other questions, to come before the 
     <lb/>
     Commission, would be of the slightest advantage if it were to 
     <lb/>
     follow the departure of the leader of the Government. He thought it 
     <lb/>
     was their bounden duty to strengthen the hands of their 
     <lb/>
     representative on that Commission by every means in their power. 
     <lb/>
     He proposed to do so by a resolution. If the Government promised 
     <lb/>
     him an early opportunity of doing so—say Monday or Tuesday, he 
     <lb/>
     would not stand in the way of the immediate passage of the address. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName> promised the early 
     <lb/>
     opportunity solicited. He quite recognised the importance of these 
     <lb/>
     subjects, and the propriety of the discussion before he left for 
     <lb/>
     Washington. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GALT1">Hon. Sir A.T. GALT</persName> said he was satisfied with that statement, 
     <lb/>
     as he believed fair play would be given him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The matter then dropped. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     * * * 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
    <head> THE DEBATE ON THE ADDRESS 
     <lb/></head>
          
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LACERTE</persName> rose to propose the address in reply to His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency’s Speech from the Throne. Taking up the various 
     <lb/>
     paragraphs, he spoke briefly on each, as usual, expressing 
     <lb/>
     concurrence in the different views therein set forth, and 
     <lb/>
     complimenting the Government on its administrative policy. He 
     <lb/>
     referred particularly to the Fenian enterprise of last spring, and the 
     <lb/>
     wise and vigorous efforts put forth for its overthrow. He hoped the 
     <lb/>
     House would fully sustain the Administration in this matter by 
     <lb/>
     voting the additional expenditure it was compelled to incur. He was 
     <lb/>
     glad at the prospect of the settlement of the fishery dispute, and 
     <lb/>
     believed everything would be done to protect Canada’s interests. 
     <lb/>
     Fortunately the Red River trouble was ended, thanks to the 
     <lb/>
     judicious and conciliatory action of the Government, and to the 
     <lb/>
     exertions and bravery of the Volunteers. The Dominion was in a 
     <lb/>
     prosperous condition, largely owing to the wisdom of Ministers, 
     <lb/>
     who deserved the confidence of Parliament and the people. He had 
     <lb/>
     much pleasure in moving the Address. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KIRK2">Mr. KIRKPATRICK</persName> rose to second the motion. The topics of 
     <lb/>
     the speech well deserved the compliments paid them. Scarcely had 
     <lb/>
     the Parliament been prorogued last summer when hordes of 
     <lb/>
     miscreants from the United States suddenly assembled on our 
     <lb/>
     frontier to pillage and ravage our land. To add to the infamy and 
     <lb/>
     offensiveness of this outrage, those marauders chose for the time of 
     <lb/>
     their unwarranted operations, the day above all, dear to loyal British 
     <lb/>
     subjects, the Queen’s birthday. The hostile movement was, thanks 
     <lb/>
     to the bravery and loyalty of our volunteers and the troops of the 
     <lb/>
     Queen, hurled back in disgrace from our border. He hoped and 
     <lb/>
     doubted not the House would cheerfully vote the extra expenses 
     <lb/>
     entailed by this attempted Fenian invasion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The next subject of the Speech was the Fisheries, and it was but 
     <lb/>
     truth to say that the action of the Canadian Government in regard to 
     <lb/>
               
               <cb/>
            <fw type="num">
            7<lb/></fw>
          

     them had met with the approbation of the whole country. The 
     <lb/>
     reference of General Grant to the action of Canada exhibited both 
     <lb/>
     ignorance and prejudice. The Dominion had but acted within its 
     <lb/>
     right, and it was certain The next subject in the speech was that of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba. No better Governor could have been chosen than him 
     <lb/>
     who is now <hi rendition="simple:italic">de facto</hi>, if not <hi rendition="simple:italic">de jure</hi> in power. The improvements 
     <lb/>
     already witnessed in Manitoba prove the judiciousness of the efforts 
     <lb/>
     made to suppress disorder and rebellion, and set up the authority of 
     <lb/>
     Canada. The brave Volunteers who had been instrumental in 
     <lb/>
     securing those happy results, deserved the thanks of the country. 
     <lb/>
     When disbanded he believed they were entitled to grants of land in 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba. No better settlers could be chosen, and in justice to them, 
     <lb/>
     and in the interests of the Province, everything should be done to 
     <lb/>
     retain them in the North West. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The proposed admission of British Columbia and Vancouver 
     <lb/>
     Island was a subject of satisfaction to us all. The great scheme of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation was being rapidly consummated. Those great 
     <lb/>
     territories, so rich in natural resources, would be a great acquisition 
     <lb/>
     to Canada, and everything possible should be done to unite them to 
     <lb/>
     her by a Pacific Railway, grants of land, and, if possible, pecuniary 
     <lb/>
     contributions, should be made in aid of such enterprises. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     There is little doubt that in this way they could be achieved. 
     <lb/>
     Immigrants were necessary to development of the great resources of 
     <lb/>
     the Pacific colonies, and good, rapid communications were 
     <lb/>
     indispensable to the attraction of immigration. The next subject of 
     <lb/>
     the Speech was the Fisheries, and it was but truth to say that the 
     <lb/>
     action of the Canadian Government in regard to them had met with 
     <lb/>
     the approbation of the whole country. The reference of General 
     <lb/>
     Grant to the action of Canada exhibited both ignorance and 
     <lb/>
     prejudice. The Dominion had but acted within its right, and it was 
     <lb/>
     certain that action was justiﬁed by the approval of the Government 
     <lb/>
     of England also. However, a Joint Commission had been appointed 
     <lb/>
     to consider the Fishery question and that relating to events 
     <lb/>
     connected with the last war, and from it he thought Canada had 
     <lb/>
     nothing to fear. He hoped, however, that the injury done to Canada 
     <lb/>
     by repeated Fenian raids would form one of the subjects discussed, 
     <lb/>
     and that indemnity for our losses thereby would be as rigorously 
     <lb/>
     required as was indemnity for the losses from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Alabama</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The improvement of our coinage system and other proposals of 
     <lb/>
     the speech would be cordially received. The interests of the country 
     <lb/>
     demanded such ameliorations. The general administration of the 
     <lb/>
     affairs of the Dominion had been beneficial, as its progress and 
     <lb/>
     prosperity amply testified. He could but concur in the closing 
     <lb/>
     aspiration of the Speech from the Throne, upon which the future 
     <lb/>
     happiness and advancement of Canada would largely depend. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said that it was important in opening the 
     <lb/>
     grant inquest of the nation, that they should review the 
     <lb/>
     administration of affairs and foreign events, while abstaining from 
     <lb/>
     unusual criticism. Tremendous events had taken place since the last 
     <lb/>
     session, including those of a gigantic and disastrous war. It was but 
     <lb/>
     right he should express his sympathy with the sacrifices and 
     <lb/>
     sufferings of that great nation, being the friend and ally of England. 
     <lb/>
     He did hope that France would not suffer much either in feeling or 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="11" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710216_Page_011.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     February 16, 1871 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
       
     fight in our own quarrels. In our present position the feeling in 
     <lb/>
     favour of independence was spreading. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HINC1">Hon. Sir FRANCIS HINCKS</persName> [excitedly]: No, no. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MASS2">Mr. MASSON (Terrebonne)</persName>: Yes, yes. The feeling was 
     <lb/>
     spreading. He appealed to the Government if they wished to 
     <lb/>
     continue the connection with England, as he did to enlighten the 
     <lb/>
     House on the intention of the Imperial Government, for Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Cardwell, a member of that Government; had recently delivered a 
     <lb/>
     speech the argument of which was that the colonies should in future 
     <lb/>
     act for the defence of England, or be feeders and not suckers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> said the Federal system made it necessary that each 
     <lb/>
     Province should have an independent governmental existence. Such 
     <lb/>
     could not be given to any Province by this Parliament. He had 
     <lb/>
     called attention to this fact last year, and was glad the Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Justice had changed his views in this respect. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear</hi>.) As to 
     <lb/>
     the murder of Scott it was still competent for the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada to authorize the trial and punishment of Riel. The Minister 
     <lb/>
     of Justice had said that this Government had no power to cause the 
     <lb/>
     arrest of the murderers of Scott. This was not so. The Hudson’s Bay 
     <lb/>
     Company were bound by the Imperial Government to transfer to 
     <lb/>
     Canada, for trial and punishment, persons guilty of higher crimes 
     <lb/>
     than rnisdemeanour. It was still competent for the Government of 
     <lb/>
     Canada to authorize the trial and punishment of Riel, and it was 
     <lb/>
               
               <cb/>
            <fw type="num">
     11 
     <lb/>
           
   </fw>
          
     also competent for the Lieutenant-Governor of Manitoba to ask for 
     <lb/>
     extradition. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The second paragraph of the address was agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DORI1">Hon. Mr. DORION</persName> on the proposal of the adoption of the 
     <lb/>
     paragraph relating to the admission of British Columbia, protested 
     <lb/>
     that he knew nothing of the merits of the terms of this admission, 
     <lb/>
     and declared his unwillingness to express blindfold any concurrence 
     <lb/>
     in the Govemment’s Paciﬁc Railway scheme. If it was to be one of 
     <lb/>
     the character of the Intercolonial Railway, he would give it his 
     <lb/>
     strenuous opposition. He could not approve of the wording of the 
     <lb/>
     paragraph. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName> consented to a verbal 
     <lb/>
     alteration to meet the objection of the last speaker. The change was 
     <lb/>
     of a non-committal character, and thus modiﬁed, the clause was 
     <lb/>
     adopted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The remaining paragraphs were read and concurred in without 
     <lb/>
     debate, and the address, being read a second time, was agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     After the usual formal resolutions in regard to the address and its 
     <lb/>
     presentation, <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName> gave notice of an 
     <lb/>
     address of congratulation to Lord Lisgar on the distinguished 
     <lb/>
     honour recently conferred upon him by Her Majesty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House adjourned at a quarter past nine. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
