<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_BC_1871-04-01"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1871-04-01">1 April 1871</date>, Canadian Confederation with British Columbia</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>Norman Ward and Pamela Hardisty</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2007"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="318"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_315.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_316.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_317.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_318.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-10-06">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710401_315">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_315.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710401_316">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_316.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710401_317">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_317.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710401_318">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_318.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="315" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_315.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     April 1, 1871 
     <lb/>
            </fw><fw type="num">315 <lb/></fw>
            
<div type="section">
            <head>HOUSE OF COMMONS</head>
            <p>
     Saturday, April 1, 1871 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     The SPEAKER took the chair at 3 o’clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prayers</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     AFTER ROUTINE 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR1">Mr. CURRIER</persName> introduced a Bill to incorporate the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     Construction Co. The Bill was read a first time and referred to the 
     <lb/>
     Committee on Miscellaneous Private Bills. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     INSURANCE ACT 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HINC1">Hon. Sir FRANCIS HINCKS</persName> moved the second reading of the 
     <lb/>
     Bill respecting Insurance companies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName> objected to the measure, as limiting the class of 
     <lb/>
     securities to be deposited with the Government. He also objected to 
     <lb/>
     establishing a system of inspection. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HINC1">Hon. Sir FRANCIS HINCKS</persName> assured the hon. member that 
     <lb/>
     there was no disposition to limit the class of securities, but, on the 
     <lb/>
     contrary, to relieve companies of the necessity of depositing cash 
     <lb/>
     with the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Bill was read a second time and referred to the Committee 
     <lb/>
     on Banking and Commerce. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     BRITISH COLUMBIA 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-E. CARTIER</persName> moved the second reading of 
     <lb/>
     the Address to Her Majesty for the union of British Columbia with 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> did not propose to reply to the speeches of 
     <lb/>
     the hon. members opposite delivered last night. They extended over 
     <lb/>
     a good space of time, but there was nothing in them. He merely 
     <lb/>
     wished to enter his protest against the extraordinary address now 
     <lb/>
     about to be read a second time. He, therefore, moved the following: 
     <lb/>
        
        <cb/>
          
           
     “Resolved that this House, while willing to give its best 
     <lb/>
     consideration to any reasonable terms of union with British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia, is of opinion that the terms embodied in the said address 
     <lb/>
     are so unreasonable, and so unjust to Canada, that this House 
     <lb/>
     should not agree thereto.” 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. Mr. TUPPER</persName> said he had not taken any part in the debates 
     <lb/>
     on this subject so far. He had listened with mingled pain and 
     <lb/>
     pleasure to the speeches of hon. members. He had heard with pain 
     <lb/>
     old friends of Confederation opposing this union movement. He 
     <lb/>
     defended the policy of the Government at considerable length, 
     <lb/>
     arguing that everything conspired to favor the construction of the 
     <lb/>
     Pacific Railway. While the United States had to contend against 
     <lb/>
     great natural difficulties in pushing their railways to the Pacific, the 
     <lb/>
     territory through which the Canadian route would lie, was of great 
     <lb/>
     natural fertility, and presented comparatively few engineering 
     <lb/>
     difficulties to the construction of a railway. It gave us a pass 
     <lb/>
     through the Rocky Mountains 2,000 feet lower than the best pass 
     <lb/>
     through that chain on American territory. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Lambton had endeavored to show that the route from Nipissing to 
     <lb/>
     Fort Garry was an almost impassable wilderness. Only last session 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member had taken a very different view of the question 
     <lb/>
     and had stated that the very best route to the west lay through 
     <lb/>
     Canadian territory North of Lakes Huron and Superior. The hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman could not say that he had heard anything to present the 
     <lb/>
     matter in a different light. There were then, all these favourable 
     <lb/>
     circumstances to aid this great enterprise, but in addition to all that, 
     <lb/>
     the route once opened would place Canton and Liverpool 1,000 
     <lb/>
     miles nearer than by any other line of communication that could be 
     <lb/>
     found. The hon. member had pleaded for delay in order to submit 
     <lb/>
     this question to the people, but the hon. gentleman had taken the 
     <lb/>
     ground on a former occasion that Parliament, representing the 
     <lb/>
     people, could act for them in a case like this. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said this was a very different matter. When 
     <lb/>
     the Confederation scheme was first mooted he (Mr. Mackenzie) 
     <lb/>
     went before his constituents and presented the matter to them in 
     <lb/>
     twenty speeches held in different parts of his constituency and told 
     <lb/>
     them that if they were not favourable to Confederation they might 
     <lb/>
     elect some one who would oppose it in Parliament, he would not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. Mr. TUPPER</persName> admitted that the honourable member for 
     <lb/>
     Lambton was an important member of the House, and honoured the 
     <lb/>
     intelligent electors who sent him to Parliament, but he did not 
     <lb/>
     represent the whole people, and the Confederation scheme was not 
     <lb/>
     submitted to the country generally. But this question had been 
     <lb/>
     submitted to the people of British Columbia and the terms had been 
     <lb/>
     accepted by them. It was not new to the people of Canada. Six 
     <lb/>
     months ago the Toronto <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> had published the terms and they 
     <lb/>
      
            <pb n="316" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_316.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">316</fw><fw type="dateline">
     April 1, 1871 
     <lb/>
            </fw>

     had appeared in other leading papers. No objections were urged 
     <lb/>
     against them that he had heard of, till now. He did not believe the 
     <lb/>
     people were so wanting in intelligence that they would silently 
     <lb/>
     submit to terms which did not meet their approval without 
     <lb/>
     protesting against them. When a small question of duties came 
     <lb/>
     before this Parliament, the people who disapproved of them 
     <lb/>
     petitioned against them, and the Press generally discussed the 
     <lb/>
     question very thoroughly. It was absurd, therefore, in the face of 
     <lb/>
     these facts to say that the people were taken by surprise on this 
     <lb/>
     question, or that the scheme met with their disapproval. But if this 
     <lb/>
     House had accepted the position which the hon. members of the 
     <lb/>
     opposition wished to force the country into, they would bring 
     <lb/>
     discredit on this country which would probably be fraught with 
     <lb/>
     consequences which might be irreparable. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The hon. member for Sherbrooke had raised a question as to how 
     <lb/>
     far this enterprise lay within our means. The hon. member had done 
     <lb/>
     better justice to the position of the Dominion in a former speech in 
     <lb/>
     which he had depicted the prosperity which Confederation had 
     <lb/>
     brought upon the country. It showed that the hon. member who first 
     <lb/>
     presented Confederation in a tangible shape, in the year 1858, had 
     <lb/>
     spoken with prophetic zeal when he referred to it as the great means 
     <lb/>
     of elevating them, not only in the political, but in the financial and 
     <lb/>
     commercial scale. The friends of Union might proudly point to the 
     <lb/>
     present position of the Dominion as irrefragable proof of the 
     <lb/>
     correctness of that statement for the prophecy had been more than 
     <lb/>
     realized. The Confederation was but a movement of yesterday, and 
     <lb/>
     the result already was a large surplus in the treasury after meeting 
     <lb/>
     all the Dominion engagements that the necessities of the Local 
     <lb/>
     Governments required, but the Government of this Dominion could 
     <lb/>
     come down, and not only point to the prosperity of every one of its 
     <lb/>
     component parts, but at the same time, show that this Dominion 
     <lb/>
     had entered on a career of ﬁnancial prosperity hitherto unknown to 
     <lb/>
     Canada. If this had been the result in the past, what might we not 
     <lb/>
     expect in the future? Two years ago the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Sherbrooke, in his criticism on the budget speech, had complained 
     <lb/>
     of what was not in it, rather than of what it did contain, and had said 
     <lb/>
     that some provision should have been made for opening up the 
     <lb/>
     North West. He (Hon. Mr. Tupper) thought the Government 
     <lb/>
     deserved credit rather than censure for having adopted the 
     <lb/>
     suggestion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     In reply to the objections of the hon. member for Lambton about 
     <lb/>
     the cost of the proposed railway, he referred to the fact that its 
     <lb/>
     construction would be undertaken by a private company. No one 
     <lb/>
     had disputed the necessity of providing means of communication 
     <lb/>
     with the North West in order to settle it, yet hon. gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     opposite complained that large grants of land should be made to any 
     <lb/>
     company undertaking the construction of a railway. Yet it was only 
     <lb/>
     by means of a railway that the country could ever be settled, and the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion could give infinitely better land for the purpose than the 
     <lb/>
     United States had offered or could now offer to American 
     <lb/>
     companies. The reservation of large blocks of lands, which would 
     <lb/>
     be greatly enhanced in value through the construction of this 
     <lb/>
     railway, would enable the Government to cover largely any outlay 
     <lb/>
     they should be called on to make. Confederation had changed the 
     <lb/>
    
    <cb/>
            
   
            
     whole story of financial deficit, and had enabled the Government 
     <lb/>
     the other day, partly without their consent, to reduce the taxation of 
     <lb/>
     the country by $1,000,000—thus, too, at a time when they were 
     <lb/>
     constructing the lntercolonial and other kindred works and 
     <lb/>
     preparing to improve the canal system of the country—without 
     <lb/>
     embarrassing the Government. He believed, also, that if this railway 
     <lb/>
     were built, the Northern Pacific road would either be abandoned or 
     <lb/>
     become a branch of the Canadian Pacific. It could never compete 
     <lb/>
     with our line, running as it did through a much less fertile country 
     <lb/>
     than our North West, and lying between our line and the Central 
     <lb/>
     Pacific route. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     This union was a question of such magnitude, when regarded in 
     <lb/>
     the light of the status it was going to give to this Dominion that it 
     <lb/>
     naturally tempted him to descant upon it. He believed God and 
     <lb/>
     nature had placed it in the power of this Parliament to take up this 
     <lb/>
     question and give us advantages in connection with becoming the 
     <lb/>
     great highway of communication, not only across this continent, but 
     <lb/>
     between Europe and Asia. The Government would be recreant to 
     <lb/>
     their trust if they failed to meet the wishes of this country as 
     <lb/>
     expressed by the majority in this Parliament and carry it forward to 
     <lb/>
     a successful issue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SCAT1">Mr. SCATCHERD</persName> was surprised to find that in the debate on 
     <lb/>
     the present question there was less enthusiasm than was shown on 
     <lb/>
     the first scheme of Confederation. He complained that only one 
     <lb/>
     party to this compact, the people of British Columbia had had an 
     <lb/>
     opportunity of pronouncing on this subject, while the greater party 
     <lb/>
     of the people of Canada had received no such opportunity. Already 
     <lb/>
     we had the lntercolonial Railway on our hands, for which we had 
     <lb/>
     had to submit to increased expenditure and taxation. Yet we were 
     <lb/>
     told that a larger and more difficult work would not add to our 
     <lb/>
     burdens. A more monstrous and unreasonable proposition was 
     <lb/>
     never urged than this vast road could be built without increasing the 
     <lb/>
     burdens of the people. He held that Confederation so far had not 
     <lb/>
     proved the success predicted. In various sections there were 
     <lb/>
     jealousy, ill-feeling and discontent in relation to this Union and 
     <lb/>
     three sections, Nova Scotia, Quebec and Manitoba might be cited in 
     <lb/>
     support of his theory that Confederation had not been very 
     <lb/>
     satisfactory. He saw no difference between the position of the 
     <lb/>
     minority in 1865, and that of the minority now. The conduct of the 
     <lb/>
     Government was as unreasonable and arbitrary now as then. He 
     <lb/>
     believed this scheme would but add to difficulties and taxation on 
     <lb/>
     the country, and that its ill effects would be felt for 50 years. 
     <lb/>
     Holding these opinions he would vote for the amendment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HUNT2">Hon. Mr. HUNTINGTON</persName> said he was prepared and desirous to 
     <lb/>
     see this scheme of Confederation carried to a magnificent success, 
     <lb/>
     and that he was prepared to go quite as far as the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Cumberland, or indeed any one, in the great scheme of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation, but while he claimed credit for earnestly and 
     <lb/>
     sincerely entertaining the desire to consummate successfully that 
     <lb/>
     great scheme, he could not shut his eyes to the fact that, 
     <lb/>
     Confederation was not a machine that would run without winding, 
     <lb/>
     but that it contained many details which from time to time required 
     <lb/>
     serious consideration. When the Dominion Parliament had first 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="317" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_317.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     April 1, 1871 
     <lb/>
            </fw><fw type="num">
     317 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
         
     assembled, the obligations of the country had been largely 
     <lb/>
     increased, and now all at once the whole debt of the country was to 
     <lb/>
     be doubled. Surely this was a serious matter, and even the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Militia had termed it a “big job” though he had 
     <lb/>
     afterwards tried to make it a very little job. It was useless to say that 
     <lb/>
     the country would not be expected to accomplish impossibilities, 
     <lb/>
     and that no burden would be added to the people, for when they had 
     <lb/>
     entered into a compact, they must carry out their promise, and when 
     <lb/>
     they went to England to raise money they would find this obligation 
     <lb/>
     considered a charge on the credit of the country. Notwithstanding 
     <lb/>
     the glowing terms in which the grandeur of Confederation had been 
     <lb/>
     depicted, the fact still remained that the debt had first been 
     <lb/>
     increased fifty per cent and now it was sought to be doubled. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     He maintained, however, that the measure of Confederation had 
     <lb/>
     been carried, not by the Government but in consequence of the 
     <lb/>
     loyal respect of the people for the policy of the Imperial 
     <lb/>
     Government which was known to favor the scheme, and now the 
     <lb/>
     Government was breaking away if not from Imperial policy at least 
     <lb/>
     from Imperial aid, in proposing to carry out the work of 
     <lb/>
     communication alone and unassisted. If it had been the duty and the 
     <lb/>
     policy of the Imperial Government to aid the construction of the 
     <lb/>
     Intercolonial Railway it was a hundred fold their duty and policy to 
     <lb/>
     aid the construction of the Pacific, and he would ask the 
     <lb/>
     Government for what reasons they had absolved the Imperial 
     <lb/>
     Government from all duties in the work of consolidating British 
     <lb/>
     power on this continent. He referred to rumours which he said had 
     <lb/>
     been greatly inﬂuenced by the presence of Capitalists and 
     <lb/>
     Contractors who were opposed to the Northern Pacific Railway, and 
     <lb/>
     who thought that if the Canadian Government would decide 
     <lb/>
     definitely to construct the Canadian line, it would operate strongly 
     <lb/>
     against the Northern Pacific, and said he could not but think that 
     <lb/>
     those rumours had gained weight by the utterance of the President 
     <lb/>
     of the Council that if the Canadian line was constructed the 
     <lb/>
     Northern Pacific would never get beyond Red River. That hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman had also urged as a reason for hurry in this matter, that if 
     <lb/>
     they did not hasten to accept the terms proposed, British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     might exact conditions still more difficult, but such an argument 
     <lb/>
     was absurd. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     British Columbia was a Crown colony, and if it were really, the 
     <lb/>
     policy of the Imperial Government, to consolidate British power on 
     <lb/>
     this continent, though every man in that colony might be in favor of 
     <lb/>
     annexation, their power to bring about such a result would be as 
     <lb/>
     light as a feather, it would be as nothing. If ever the British 
     <lb/>
     possessions on this Continent should become part of the United 
     <lb/>
     States, it could only be at the cannon’s mouth, and as the 
     <lb/>
     consequence of the total ruin and prostration of British power on 
     <lb/>
     this continent. The same reason for hurry had been urged in the 
     <lb/>
     discussion on Confederation, and he very much deprecated it as 
     <lb/>
     tending very much to unsettle the minds of the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     These great questions should be discussed solely on their merits 
     <lb/>
     without the fulmination of insincerities in regard to alternatives that 
     <lb/>
     might ensue in case of the scheme being rejected. He had no doubt 
     <lb/>
     that many, hon. gentleman, had been writing to their constituents 
     <lb/>
         
         <cb/>
            
   
         
     speaking of the wonderful benefits of Confederation as evinced in 
     <lb/>
     their being no longer a deficiency in the revenue, but a surplus of 
     <lb/>
     two millions, and he could not but cornmiserate them in having now 
     <lb/>
     to write that that surplus of two millions had disappeared to be 
     <lb/>
     replaced by a debt of one hundred millions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:RYMA1">Mr. RYMAL</persName> had hoped that the Government would have been 
     <lb/>
     forced to explain in what way the money for the railway was to be 
     <lb/>
     raised. He ventured to say that the Minister of Finance was not 
     <lb/>
     properly performing the functions of his office, in failing to explain 
     <lb/>
     fully the financial aspect of the matter. He feared nothing he could 
     <lb/>
     say would change one single vote, but he was convinced that if the 
     <lb/>
     question had been one of policy and not of party, the resolutions 
     <lb/>
     would never have been carried. Richelieu had said that many 
     <lb/>
     persons who, as private members might be saved, were in great 
     <lb/>
     danger of being damned for having wandered into public life, and if 
     <lb/>
     Richelieu had lived in these days and uttered those words, he (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Rymal) would have been quite sure that his eyes were fixed on the 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen of the Canadian Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:THOM4">Mr. THOMPSON</persName> (Ontario North) desired to explain why he 
     <lb/>
     should support the amendment, which was because no explanation 
     <lb/>
     had even been attempted as to how so large a debt as that proposed 
     <lb/>
     could be incurred without crippling most seriously the resources of 
     <lb/>
     the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. MACKENZIE’S amendment was then put with the 
     <lb/>
     following result: Yeas, 68; Nays, 86. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On the amendment being declared lost, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GALT1">Hon. Sir A.T. GALT</persName> rose and said, it might be considered that 
     <lb/>
     the address was practically carried, but he desired before the final 
     <lb/>
     passage, to place on record an explanation of the terms under which 
     <lb/>
     the address was understood to be adopted. The Government had 
     <lb/>
     stated as a reason why these terms should be accepted, that it was 
     <lb/>
     not their intention to undertake the whole cost of the railway out of 
     <lb/>
     the money reserves of the Dominion, but that they proposed to do it 
     <lb/>
     through the intervention of companies to whom they would be 
     <lb/>
     prepared to give subsidies of land and money, and further that this 
     <lb/>
     was the understanding between themselves and the delegates from 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia. He therefore moved: That the word “now” be 
     <lb/>
     left out, and the words “on Monday next, and that meantime it be 
     <lb/>
     Resolved, That in accepting the terms of Union with <hi rendition="simple:italic">British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia</hi>, this House understands that the engagement for the 
     <lb/>
     construction of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Pacific</hi> Railroad within ten years is subject to 
     <lb/>
     the understanding had between the Government of the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     and the Commissioners from <hi rendition="simple:italic">British Columbia</hi> that the said 
     <lb/>
     Railroad should be constructed through the medium of private 
     <lb/>
     Companies, receiving subsidies in money and land, and that it was 
     <lb/>
     not intended to pledge the Dominion beyond the application of its 
     <lb/>
     money and resources to the loyal and earnest prosecution of the 
     <lb/>
     work, without entailling undue and excessive burdens upon the 
     <lb/>
     people.” 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="318" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710401_Page_318.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">318</fw> <fw type="dateline">
     April 1, 1871 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> said this amendment was 
     <lb/>
     equally objectionable with the others that had been moved to 
     <lb/>
     prevent to passing of the address, and he would announce to the 
     <lb/>
     House, and to the hon. member for Sherbrooke, that the 
     <lb/>
     Government intended and determined that this great railway should 
     <lb/>
     be carried out by companies and not by the Government, and 
     <lb/>
     through the means principally of land grant and small money 
     <lb/>
     subsidies, and further that early in the ensuing week, the 
     <lb/>
     Government would place before the House a resolution by which to 
     <lb/>
     take the sense of the House with regard to the manner in which that 
     <lb/>
     Railway should be built, and he might announce beforehand that the 
     <lb/>
     determination of the Government was that, when the sense of the 
     <lb/>
     House had been so taken, they would carry it out more prudently 
     <lb/>
     with regard to the Exchequer of the country than was proposed in 
     <lb/>
     the amendment of the hon. member for Sherbrooke. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said that the terms of the amendment were 
     <lb/>
     so general that he was not prepared to vote for it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName> said he must oppose the amendment not only for 
     <lb/>
     the reason named by the hon. member for Lambton, but because he 
     <lb/>
     considered that no action could put an interpretation on the terms 
     <lb/>
     other than that they literally contained. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOWE1">Mr. BOWELL</persName> said his great objection to the amendment was 
     <lb/>
     that it did not go far enough for it would not prevent the 
     <lb/>
     Government from carrying on the Railway after its construction. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The amendment was lost, the vote being—Yeas, 7; Nays, 126. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The main motion was then carried and the address read a second 
     <lb/>
     time, and on the motion of <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> the 
     <lb/>
     address was ordered to be engrossed, and a motion for an address to 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency, praying His Excellency to transmit the address to 
     <lb/>
     Her Majesty the Queen was carried; the address to His Excellency 
     <lb/>
     was ordered to be engrossed, and to be presented by such members 
     <lb/>
     of the House as belonged to the Privy Council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     It being six o’clock the House rose. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     AFTER RECESS 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The following Private and Local Bills were read a second and 
     <lb/>
     third time and passed:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>An Act to comprise in one Act the financial affairs of the Great 
     <lb/>
     Western Railway Company, as amended by Standing Committee on 
     <lb/>
     Railways, Canals and Telegraph Lines—<persName ref="pers:CAME2">Hon. Mr. CAMERON</persName> 
     <lb/>
     (Peel). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
    
    <cb/>
           
   
            <p>
     An Act concerning the Vandreuil Railway Company, as amended 
     <lb/>
     by Standing Committee on Railways, Canals andTelegraph lines<lb break="no"/>-<persName ref="pers:SHAN1">Mr. SHANLY</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     An Act to incorporate the Metropolitain Bank, as amended by 
     <lb/>
     Standing Committee on Banking and Commerce—<persName ref="pers:WORK1">Mr. 
     <lb/>
     WORKMAN</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     An Act to incorporate the Western Bank, as amended by 
     <lb/>
     Standing Committee on Banking and Commerce—<persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. KILLAM</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     SUPPLY 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     On the motion of <persName ref="pers:HINC1">Hon. Sir FRANCIS HINCKS</persName> to go into 
     <lb/>
     Committee of Supply, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. HOLTON</persName> called the attention of the Government to 
     <lb/>
     the manner in which a certain parcel of land belonging to the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion was leased to the Montreal Warehousing Company. The 
     <lb/>
     history of the land was this: In 1865 Government purchased from 
     <lb/>
     private parties in Montreal a lot of land adjoining the canal basin, 
     <lb/>
     on the recommendation of Mr. Allan, for the purpose of increasing 
     <lb/>
     the wharfage and shed accommodation there. For this lot the 
     <lb/>
     Government paid the sum of $25,000. The Warehousing Co., 
     <lb/>
     through Mr. Brydges, made application to Government for the 
     <lb/>
     purchase of the lot subsequent to confederation of the Provinces, 
     <lb/>
     but on the advice of the officers of the Public Works Department, 
     <lb/>
     the Government refused to sell it. On the 19th July, 1870, the hon. 
     <lb/>
     the Minister of Militia, in the absence of the Minister of Public 
     <lb/>
     Works, and acting for that minister, reported to the Council in favor 
     <lb/>
     of granting the lease of this lot to the Warehousing Company for a 
     <lb/>
     term of 21 years with an annual rental of $700, that being 
     <lb/>
     considered less than simple interest on one half the cost. This report 
     <lb/>
     was made to the Privy Council without being supported by any of 
     <lb/>
     the professional gentlemen connected with the Department. One of 
     <lb/>
     the conditions, however, was that the Government might resume 
     <lb/>
     possession of the property on giving three months’ notice, on 
     <lb/>
     condition of paying for any building that might be erected thereon, 
     <lb/>
     subsequent to the lease of the property. He, therefore, moved an 
     <lb/>
     amendment to the motion to go into Committee of Supply, reciting 
     <lb/>
     the facts above stated, and resolving “that this House is of opinion 
     <lb/>
     that it is the duty of this Government to take immediate steps to 
     <lb/>
     resume possession for public uses, of the said lot of ground.” 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Hon. Mr. LANGEVIN</persName> said he would take the full responsibility 
     <lb/>
     of the transaction on himself. He had no desire to shield himself 
     <lb/>
     behind the Minister of Militia in this matter. The action in the 
     <lb/>
     matter was taken while he (Hon. Mr. Langevin) was absent, but it 
     <lb/>
     was with his entire approval. What he had to complain of was that 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Châteauguay had not gone farther back in the 
     <lb/>
     history of this affair. The hon. member knew quite well that in order 
     <lb/>
     to arrive at the true position of affairs, it was necessary to go back 
     <lb/>
     further than 1865. In 1851 the Government of the day offered for 
     <lb/>
            </p>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
