<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_BC_1871-02-15"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1871-02-15">15 February 1871</date>, Canadian Confederation with British Columbia</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>Norman Ward and Pamela Hardisty</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2007"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710215_Page_001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710215_Page_002.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-10-06">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710215_Page_001">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710215_Page_001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710215_Page_002">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710215_Page_002.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710215_Page_001.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               February 15, 1871</fw>
 <fw type="num">1</fw>
            <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               Wednesday, February 15, 1871 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
            <p>
               The SPEAKER took the chair at 3.00 pm. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prayers</hi> 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               A MESSAGE was brought by René Kimber, Esquire, Gentleman 
               <lb/>
               Usher of the Black Rod:―<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The SPEAKER, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               His Excellency, the Governor General desires the immediate 
               <lb/>
               attendance of this Honorable House in the Senate Chamber. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Accordingly, Mr. Speaker, with the House, went to the Senate 
               <lb/>
               Chamber:― And being returned: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Speaker informed the House, that during the Recess, he had 
               <lb/>
               received the following notiﬁcations of vacancies which had 
               <lb/>
               occurred in the representation of the electoral districts of 
               <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Missisquoi</hi>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Quebec</hi> (City) East, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Cumberland</hi>, (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Nova Scotia</hi>) <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bellechasse</hi>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Saint-Hyacinthe</hi>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Colehester</hi>, (N .S.), <hi rendition="simple:italic">Richelieu</hi> and 
               <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Restigouche</hi>; and that he had issued his Warrants to the Clerk of the 
               <lb/>
               Crown in Chancery to make out new Writs for the Election of 
               <lb/>
               Members to serve in this present Parliament for the said Electoral 
               <lb/>
               Districts: 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Adolphe Tourangeau, Esquire, Member for the Electoral District 
               <lb/>
               of Quebec East; Louis Delorme, Esquire, Member for the Electoral 
               <lb/>
               District of Saint-Hyacinthe', George Moﬂatt, Esquire, Member for 
               <lb/>
               the Electoral District of Restigouche (New Brunswick); Leverett de 
               <lb/>
               Veber Chipman, Esquire, Member for the Electoral District of 
               <lb/>
               Kings; Georges Isidore Barthe, Esquire, Member for the Electoral 
               <lb/>
               District of Richelieu; and the Honorable Charles Tupper, C.B., 
               <lb/>
               Member for the Electoral District of Cumberland, having 
               <lb/>
               previously taken the Oath, according to Law, and subscribed before 
               <lb/>
               the Commissioners the Roll containing the same, took their seats in 
               <lb/>
               the House. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Ordered</hi>, That the Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald have leave to 
               <lb/>
               bring in a Bill respecting the administration of Oaths of Ofﬁce. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               He accordingly presented the said Bill to the House, and the same 
               <lb/>
               was received and read the ﬁrst time. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. Speaker reported, That when the House did attend His 
               <lb/>
               Excellency the Governor General this day, in the Senate Chamber, 
               <lb/>
               His Excellency was pleased to make a Speech to both Houses of 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         <cb/>
            
            <p>
               Parliament, of which Mr. Speaker said he had, to prevent mistakes, 
               <lb/>
               obtained a copy which he read to the House, as followeth:―<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Honorable Gentlemen of the Senate, Gentlemen of the House of 
               <lb/>
               Commons</hi>,―<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               I have much satisfaction in meeting you at this, the usual and 
               <lb/>
               most convenient season of the year, and under the present 
               <lb/>
               auspicious circumstances of the Country. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The hope I was sanguine enough to express at the close of the 
               <lb/>
               last session that no further attempt would be made to disturb our 
               <lb/>
               frontier, was doomed to early disappointment. The Session had 
               <lb/>
               scarcely closed when lawless bands assembled within the <hi rendition="simple:italic">United 
               <lb/>
               States</hi> in great numbers, and renewed the menace of invasion. They 
               <lb/>
               ventured to cross the border at two points, but were promptly met 
               <lb/>
               and repelled. So complete and humiliating was the repulse, that the 
               <lb/>
               invaders lost heart and hope, threw away quantities of arms, and fell 
               <lb/>
               back to encumber the villages in their rear, with their starving and 
               <lb/>
               demoralized masses. Our Militia rallied at the ﬁrst call to arms with 
               <lb/>
               praiseworthy alacrity, and the spirit which pervades the country, 
               <lb/>
               swelled their numbers with volunteers from all quarters. The 
               <lb/>
               gallantry displayed and the success achieved, have been duly 
               <lb/>
               recognized by the highest Military authority, and honored in 
               <lb/>
               gratifying terms of appreciation, by Her Most Gracious Majesty. In 
               <lb/>
               maintaining the Militia on active duty, the Government incurred an 
               <lb/>
               outlay to a considerable amount beyond what was provided by the 
               <lb/>
               votes of last Session. The accounts of the entire expenditure for the 
               <lb/>
               defence of the frontier will be laid before you, and I feel conﬁdent 
               <lb/>
               that you will pass a bill to indemnify the Government. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               My anticipations of success in regard to the Act passed for the 
               <lb/>
               Government of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Manitoba</hi>, and the North West Territories, and in 
               <lb/>
               regard to the Military Expedition, which it was necessary to 
               <lb/>
               despatch, have been fortunately realized. The troops surmounted the 
               <lb/>
               difﬁculties of the long and toilsome route with endurance and 
               <lb/>
               intelligence. They encountered no armed opposition, and their 
               <lb/>
               arrival at the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Red River</hi> was cordially welcomed by the inhabitants. 
               <lb/>
               The people of the new Province have, under the Constitution 
               <lb/>
               accorded to them last year, assumed all the duties of self- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               government, and every appearance warrants the hope that they are 
               <lb/>
               entering steadily upon a career of peace and prosperity. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The Legislature of <hi rendition="simple:italic">British Columbia</hi> has passed an Address to 
               <lb/>
               Her Majesty, praying for admission into the union, on the terms and 
               <lb/>
               conditions therein stated. All the papers on this important subject 
               <lb/>
               will be submitted, and your earnest attention is invited to them. I 
               <lb/>
               hope you will think that the terms are so fair as to justify you in 
               <lb/>
               passing a similar Address, so that the boundaries of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Canada</hi>, may, 
               <lb/>
               
               <pb n="2" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710215_Page_002.jpg"/>
               <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
 <fw type="num"> 2</fw>
<fw type="dateline">February 15, 1871</fw>

               at an early day, be extended from the shores of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Atlantie Ocean</hi> 
               <lb/>
               on the one side, to the shores of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Pacific</hi> on the other. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para "
               at an early day, be extended from the shores of the Atlantie Oce..." merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p>
               Should such an Address be adopted, it will be necessary for you 
               <lb/>
               to take steps to secure the early exploration and survey of a route 
               <lb/>
               for an Interoceanic Railway, with a view to its construction in 
               <lb/>
               accordance with the terms of Union. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The acquisition of the North West Territories throws upon the 
               <lb/>
               Government and Parliament of the Dominion the duty of promoting 
               <lb/>
               their early settlement by the encouragement of immigration. This 
               <lb/>
               duty can be best discharged by a liberal land policy, and by opening 
               <lb/>
               up communications through our own country to <hi rendition="simple:italic">Manitoba</hi>. The 
               <lb/>
               means proposed for accomplishing these purposes will be submitted 
               <lb/>
               for your consideration. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Her Majesty’s Government has decided upon referring the 
               <lb/>
               Fishery question, along with other questions pending between the 
               <lb/>
               two countries, to a joint commission to be named by Her Majesty’s 
               <lb/>
               Government and the Government of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">United States</hi>. On this 
               <lb/>
               commission <hi rendition="simple:italic">Canada</hi> will be represented. This mode of dealing with 
               <lb/>
               the various matters in controversy will, I trust, lead to their 
               <lb/>
               satisfactory adjustment. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Canada</hi> urges no demand beyond those to 
               <lb/>
               which she is plainly entitled by Treaty and the law of Nations. She 
               <lb/>
               has pushed no claim to an extreme assertion, and only sought to 
               <lb/>
               maintain the rights of her own people fairly and ﬁrmly, but in a 
               <lb/>
               friendly and considerate spirit and with all due respect to foreign 
               <lb/>
               powers and international obligations. The thanks of the country are 
               <lb/>
               due to the Admiral on the Station and those under his command, for 
               <lb/>
               the valuable and efﬁcient aid which they rendered to our cruisers 
               <lb/>
               during the past season in maintaining order and protecting the 
               <lb/>
               inshore ﬁsheries from encroachment. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The prospect of the adoption of an international currency seems, 
               <lb/>
               in the present state of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Europe</hi>, to be so remote, that I recommend 
               <lb/>
               you to consider the propriety of assimilating the currency of the 
               <lb/>
               Dominion without further delay. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The extension to <hi rendition="simple:italic">Manitoba</hi> of the militia and other laws of the 
               <lb/>
               Dominion, and their adaptation to the present circumstances of that 
               <lb/>
               young Province, will require your attention. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The decennial Census will be taken on the third day of April 
               <lb/>
               next, and it is believed that a more thorough and accurate system 
               <lb/>
               has been adopted than any that has hitherto obtained. It may be 
               <lb/>
               necessary to amend the Act of last session in some particulars. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Among other measures, Bills will be presented to you relating to 
               <lb/>
               Parliamentary Elections, Weights and Measures, Insurance 
               <lb/>
               Companies, Savings Banks, and for the Consolidation and 
               <lb/>
               Amendment of the Inspection Laws. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gentlemen of the House of Commons</hi>,―<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               I have given directions that the Public Accounts shall be laid 
               <lb/>
               before you. You will learn with satisfaction that the Revenue for the 
               <lb/>
               past year was in excess of what was estimated, and that the 
               <lb/>
               prospects for the current year are so encouraging that, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         <cb/>
            
            <fw type="dateline">
               February 15, 1871 
               <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
         
            
            <p>
               notwithstanding the extensive public improvements which are 
               <lb/>
               contemplated, you will probably be able to diminish the taxation of 
               <lb/>
               the Country. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The Estimates for the ensuing year will be submitted to you, and 
               <lb/>
               I feel assured that you will be of opinion that the supplies which 
               <lb/>
               you will be asked to vote can be granted without inconvenience to 
               <lb/>
               the people. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Gentlemen of the Senate, Gentlemen of the House of 
               <lb/>
               Commons,-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I lay these various and weighty matters before you, in full 
               <lb/>
               conﬁdence that they will engage your mature attention, and I pray 
               <lb/>
               that the result of your deliberations may, with the Divine Blessing, 
               <lb/>
               prove conducive in all respects to the advancement and happiness 
               <lb/>
               of the country. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD moved that His 
               <lb/>
               Excellency’s speech be taken into consideration tomorrow. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The House resolved to establish the usual Standing Committees, 
               <lb/>
               and adjournment was moved, by Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald, 
               <lb/>
               seconded by Hon. Sir George-E. Cartier. 
               <lb/></p>
               
               <p> *** <lb/></p>

<div type="section">
               <head>THE FISHERIES</head>
               
<p>On the motion for adjournment, Mr. MACKENZIE asked if it 
               <lb/>
               was the intention of the Government to bring down any 
               <lb/>
               correspondence regarding the ﬁsheries before the discussion on the 
               <lb/>
               address of His Excellency tomorrow. It was desirable on so 
               <lb/>
               important a matter, if there was any correspondence relative to the 
               <lb/>
               appointment of the Joint High Commission that the House should 
               <lb/>
               have it before them, as it was quite impossible for them to avoid 
               <lb/>
               discussing it during the debate tomorrow. It was a matter of far too 
               <lb/>
               much importance to this country, looking at it simply as one 
               <lb/>
               respecting our national rights, that the House should pass durnbly 
               <lb/>
               over this portion of His Excellency’s speech without discussing, to 
               <lb/>
               some extent, at least, the questions that everyone could see were 
               <lb/>
               involved in it. The Commission, for anything they might know to 
               <lb/>
               the contrary, might adopt some course that this Parliament might 
               <lb/>
               not think consistent with the national interests in this Dominion', 
               <lb/>
               and it was desirable that, at the earliest possible moment some 
               <lb/>
               expression of the opinion of public men in the country should be 
               <lb/>
               had on it. He took it for granted that the correspondence would be 
               <lb/>
               brought down. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para "
               On the motion for adjournment, Mr. MACKENZIE asked if it 
      ..." merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD said it was not the intention 
               <lb/>
               of the government to bring down any correspondence or any papers 
               <lb/>
               of any kind before the answer to the address was carried. It was an 
               <lb/>
               unusual course and an exceedingly inconvenient one that the hon. 
               <lb/>
               member proposed. Care would be taken that the address to be 
               <lb/>
               moved should not commit any member of this House to the 
               <lb/>
               approval of the policy of the government on that or any other 
               <lb/>
               question. The government would, so soon as the House should 
               <lb/>
               address itself to business, bring down such portions of the 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
