<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_BC_1871-02-28" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1871-02-28">28 February 1871</date>, Canadian Confederation with British Columbia</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1871">
          

               <editor>Norman Ward and Pamela Hardisty</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2007"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="68"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710228_Page_067.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710228_Page_068.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-10-06">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>

<change who="fan_gloria" when="2016-12-08">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710228_Page_067">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710228_Page_067.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710228_Page_068">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710228_Page_068.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="67" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710228_Page_067.jpg"/>
           <fw type="dateline">February 28, 1871</fw> <fw type="num">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
             <fw type="num">67 <lb/></fw>
            
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS</head>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Tuesday, February 28, 1871 
     
            </head>

</div>
<div type="section">

            <p>
     <emph>The SPEAKER</emph> took the chair at 3.00 pm. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prayers</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Several petitions were presented. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CORRECTION 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName> (whose remarks were very indistinctly 
     <lb/>
     heard in the reporter's gallery) referred to a mistake which had been 
     <lb/>
     made in the report of his speech yesterday with regard to the 
     <lb/>
     settlement of accounts between New Brunswick and the Dominion. 
     <lb/>
     He had been represented as saying that "it would be necessary to 
     <lb/>
     get an alteration of the Union Act." He would not like to have it go 
     <lb/>
     abroad to his constituents that he had made such an absurd 
     <lb/>
     statement. He had no wish to have the Union Act disturbed for a 
     <lb/>
     settlement of the accounts between New Brunswick and the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. He had no doubt that a just and equitable arrangement 
     <lb/>
     would be made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     LIBRARY OFFICIALS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> moved that the Library 
     <lb/>
     Committee be instructed to inquire into the remuneration, 
     <lb/>
     classification, etc., of the officers of the library. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     NEW MEMBER 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PEAR1">Mr. PEARSON</persName> the member elected by the constituency of 
     <lb/>
     Colchester to fill the place rendered vacant by the appointment of 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Mr. Archibald to the Lieutenant-Governorship of the North 
     <lb/>
     West, was introduced by Messrs. Carmichael and Killam, and took 
     <lb/>
     his seat. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     * * * 
     <lb/></p></div>

<div type="section">
     
<head rendition="simple:centre">THE ELECTION LAW 
     <lb/></head>
            
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> introduced a bill to make 
     <lb/>
     temporary provision for the election of members for the House of 
     <lb/>
           
           <cb/>
           
           
     Commons. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear from the Opposition</hi>.) He expected that his 
     <lb/>
     hon. friends opposite would say "hear, hear" at the very mention 
     <lb/>
     of the measure. He would explain that since we were about to have 
     <lb/>
     another province comprised in this Dominion, it was obvious that 
     <lb/>
     the government could not yet enact a law to affect all the provinces 
     <lb/>
     of the Dominion, as far as the representation of this House was 
     <lb/>
     concerned. The circumstances of Manitoba having been recently 
     <lb/>
     admitted into the Union and British Columbia being on the eve of 
     <lb/>
     joining the Confederation, had led the Government to the 
     <lb/>
     conclusion that it would be better to carry on the next election for 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion under the laws as they now prevail in the several 
     <lb/>
     provinces. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear from the Opposition</hi>.) He might state that the 
     <lb/>
     bill too, contained a provision with regard to the number of days on 
     <lb/>
     which elections were to take place. This Bill provided that the 
     <lb/>
     elections should take place on one day. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear</hi>.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName> said that afier two permanent Electoral Bills had 
     <lb/>
     been passed, the House was now asked to enact a temporary one. 
     <lb/>
     Last session one had been passed, the session before the House had 
     <lb/>
     passed one, and now they were asked to deal with another one. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman had explained that the reason why he now 
     <lb/>
     submitted this temporary measure, was because of the introduction 
     <lb/>
     of the new Provinces into Confederation. At what period since the 
     <lb/>
     lst July, 1867, was not the House favoured with the news that new 
     <lb/>
     Provinces were to be added? Every day they were told they were 
     <lb/>
     coming in, though they didn't come. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HINC1">Hon. Sir FRANCIS HlNCKS</persName>: Yes! yes! 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>: And yet the Hon. Minister of Militia had asserted 
     <lb/>
     that it was in view of these additions to the Dominion that this 
     <lb/>
     temporary Act was provided. Last session the Opposition had 
     <lb/>
     pointed out the effect that the new measure then submitted would 
     <lb/>
     have in the East and in the West. They had shown that it would be 
     <lb/>
     impossible to work it in Manitoba, and that difficulties would arise 
     <lb/>
     in other Provinces too. But they were told that their arguments were 
     <lb/>
     fallacious, and that the Union would overcome all the difficulties 
     <lb/>
     which were then deprecated. He was glad to hear that, taught by 
     <lb/>
     experience, they had admitted the truth of the arguments then 
     <lb/>
     advanced by the Opposition, that it was necessary to respect the 
     <lb/>
     views of the different Provinces on the subject and by degrees as 
     <lb/>
     they became more acquainted with the franchise laws of other 
     <lb/>
     countries, the Government had made some approach towards 
     <lb/>
     providing for a common franchise for the Dominion. He was not 
     <lb/>
     surprised that it was merely a temporary Act. It would be coming 
     <lb/>
     down too far to propose as a permanent Act what they opposed so 
     <lb/>
     consistently before, but, he had no doubt that it would contain for 
     <lb/>
     some years to come the principle at the base of our Parliamentary 
     <lb/>
     representation, founded on the motion of the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710228_Page_068.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">68</fw> <fw type="num">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">February 28, 1871</fw>

            <p>
     Hochelaga, that the franchise should be for the Dominion the same 
     <lb/>
     as by law established for each of the Provinces. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear</hi>.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> said he did not intend to 
     <lb/>
     discuss the measure at this moment, but he felt it to be his duty to 
     <lb/>
     answer some of the observations made by the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     opposite. The Manitoba measure was submitted to the House as the 
     <lb/>
     result of the negotiations carried on between the Dominion of 
     <lb/>
     Canada and the gentlemen sent as delegates from Manitoba. No one 
     <lb/>
     knew at the close of last session that Manitoba would certainly be a 
     <lb/>
     member of the Confederation. There was no necessity or intention 
     <lb/>
     at the outset that Manitoba should form a province and be 
     <lb/>
     comprised in the Confederation. It was intended that it should be a 
     <lb/>
     Crown colony, and that very reason induced the Government at the 
     <lb/>
     time to withdraw the Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>: Hear, hear! 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-E. CARTIER</persName>: Then with regard to the 
     <lb/>
     remarks of the hon. member for Lambton, he would say that the Bill 
     <lb/>
     was proposed last year as there was no hope that we should have 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia so soon. Every one expected of course, that 
     <lb/>
     sooner or later that colony would be comprised as one of the sister 
     <lb/>
     colonies in the Dominion. It would be useless at the close of this 
     <lb/>
     Parliament, with one Province just admitted and another shortly to 
     <lb/>
     be admitted into the Confederation, to endeavour to assimilate the 
     <lb/>
     laws. They could not make a law now which would apply to British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia. He hoped his hon. friend would take with a better feeling 
     <lb/>
     the good intention of the Government in adopting this course. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Bill was read a first time. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>* * * 
     <lb/></p></div>

<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">PAPERS ON BRITISH COLUMBIA 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     A message from His Excellency, accompanying papers relative 
     <lb/>
     to the proposed union of British Columbia with Canada, was read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     HIS EXCELLENCY'S PEERAGE 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> read the following reply of His Excellency the 
     <lb/>
     Governor General to the recent congratulatory address of the House 
     <lb/>
     of Commons: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker and Gentlemen of the House of Commons</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I beg you to accept my sincere thanks for the address of 
     <lb/>
     congratulation with which you have honoured me on the occasion 
     <lb/>
     of my elevation to the Peerage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The expression of your acquiescence in the favourable view 
     <lb/>
     which our Sovereign has graciously deigned to take of my services 
     <lb/>
     is highly to be valued, as conveying the good opinion of the freely 
     <lb/>
               
               
     <cb/>
            
   

     chosen representatives of a people possessing the precious 
     <lb/>
     endowments of energetic industry, self-reliance, and firm and 
     <lb/>
     orderly attachment to the freedom and institutions of their country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The North West Territories already added to the Confederation 
     <lb/>
     and the willing accession of British Columbia, which, it is to be 
     <lb/>
     hoped, will shortly take effect, as they extend your bounds, so they 
     <lb/>
     proportionately augment the cares and responsibilities of those who 
     <lb/>
     are in the high places of the land', but the legislature and people of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion will, I feel persuaded, prove equal to the lofty task, 
     <lb/>
     the vast and varied interests throughout the wide domain will be 
     <lb/>
     safe in their charge and gradually cemented into one compact and 
     <lb/>
     contented whole, by the same wise legislation, and the same equal 
     <lb/>
     administration of affairs as have done so much in the past to 
     <lb/>
     establish the well being and satisfy the just expectations of the 
     <lb/>
     people. In conclusion, I return your good wishes with all sincerity, 
     <lb/>
     and assure you I shall retain and cherish to the close of my life a 
     <lb/>
     warm interest in all that regards the position and prospects of this 
     <lb/>
     great and growing country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">LISGAR<lb/>
GOVERNMENT HOUSE,<lb/>         
     FEBRUARY 27, 1871 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>* * *<lb/></p> </div>

<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">BRITISH COLUMBIA PAPERS</head>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-E. CARTIER</persName> moved that the papers just 
     <lb/>
     submitted to the House be printed without delay. He explained that 
     <lb/>
     the Hon. Mr. Trutch, the delegate from British Columbia, was now 
     <lb/>
     in Chicago, on his way to Ottawa, and would reach here, he 
     <lb/>
     expected, on Saturday. It was necessary, therefore, that the House 
     <lb/>
     should be in possession of the correspondence relative to the 
     <lb/>
     admission of the sister colony into the union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MASS2">Mr. MASSON</persName> (Terrebonne) complained of delays in printing 
     <lb/>
     public documents in the French language. He knew that it took 
     <lb/>
     some time to translate papers, but then, if there were not translators 
     <lb/>
     enough to do the work, more should be employed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     After a short discussion on the subject the motion was carried. 
     <lb/>
     * * * 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div> 
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     EXPENSE OF FENIAN INVASION 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HINC1">Hon. Sir FRANCIS HINCKS</persName> moved that the House should on 
     <lb/>
     Friday next go into Committee of the Whole to consider resolutions 
     <lb/>
     affirming the expediency of indemnifying the Government for 
     <lb/>
     having authorized the issue of a special warrant for $200,000, to 
     <lb/>
     provide for the defence of the Dominion in repelling the Fenian 
     <lb/>
     invasion in the month of May last. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>