<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_BC_1871-03-23"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1871-03-23">23 March 1871</date>, Canadian Confederation with British Columbia</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>Norman Ward and Pamela Hardisty</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2007"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="248"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710323_Page_247.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710323_Page_248.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-10-06">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710323_Page_247">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710323_Page_247.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710323_Page_248">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710323_Page_248.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="247" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710323_Page_247.jpg"/>
         <fw type="dateline">March 23, 1871</fw>   <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">247 <lb/></fw>
            
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS</head>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>Thursday, March 23, 1871</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>
<div type="section">

           
 <p>
     <emph>The SPEAKER</emph> took the chair at 3 o'clock afier routine. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prayers</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>
<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     WESTERN BANK 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KILL1">Mr. KILLAM</persName> introduced a Bill to incorporate the Western 
     <lb/>
     Bank. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     * * * 
     <lb/></p></div>

<div type="section" rendition="simple:centre">

    <head> SUN INSURANCE COMPANY 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WORK1">Mr. WORKMAN</persName> withdrew the Bill to incorporate the Sun 
     <lb/>
     Insurance Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     INSOLVENT ACT 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MAGI1">Mr. MAGILL</persName> introduced a Bill to amend the Insolvent Act of 
     <lb/>
     1869. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     * * * 
     <lb/></p></div>

<div type="section">

    <head rendition="simple:centre"> QUEBEC MARINE AND FIRE INSURANCE COMPANY 
     <lb/></head>
            
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SIMA1">Mr. SIMARD</persName> introduced a Bill to amend the Act incorporating 
     <lb/>
     the Quebec Marine and Fire Insurance Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     * * * 
     <lb/></p></div>

<div type="section">
    <head rendition="simple:centre">FEMALE CONVICTS 
     <lb/>
          </head>   
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:IRVI1">Hon. Mr. IRVINE</persName> introduced a Bill to make provision for the 
     <lb/>
     detention of Female convicts in the Reformatory Prison of the 
     <lb/>
     Province of Quebec. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     (All these bills received first reading.) 
     <lb/>
     * * * 
     <lb/></p></div>

<div type="section">
   <head rendition="simple:centre">BRITISH COLUMBIA DEBATES 
     <lb/></head>
     
     
            <p><persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-E. CARTIER</persName> announced that the 
     <lb/>Government had made no further arrangement for special reports of 
     <lb/>the debates on the British Columbia measure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <cb/>
           
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GALT1">Hon. Sir A.T. GALT</persName> said he was sorry that the Government had 
     <lb/>
     arrived at that conclusion, for the debates would be particularly 
     <lb/>
     interesting to British Columbia, and would not reach there in as full 
     <lb/>
     a form as they would otherwise have done had his suggestion been 
     <lb/>
     adopted. He trusted that the energy usually displayed by the reports 
     <lb/>
     would on this occasion supplement the necessity that would exist 
     <lb/>
     for full reports. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JONE3">Mr. JONES</persName> (Leeds North and Grenville North) believed the 
     <lb/>
     Government deserved credit for the decision to which they had 
     <lb/>
     come. He was about to proceed further, when 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> called him to order. There was no question 
     <lb/>
     before the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JONE3">Mr. JONES</persName> (Leeds North and Grenville North) thought he 
     <lb/>
     had as good a right to speak on the subject as other hon. gentlemen. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> explained that a minister of the Crown had 
     <lb/>
     simply answered a question put on a former occasion by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Sherbrooke, and there the matter should drop. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JONE3">Mr. JONES</persName> (Leeds North and Grenville North) said he was 
     <lb/>
     sorry to be obliged to resort to extreme measures, but he had a 
     <lb/>
     precedent for it only the other day. He moved the adjournment of 
     <lb/>
     the House. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Laughter</hi>) He continued at some length to explain that 
     <lb/>
     he was elected on the Independent ticket, and though he might have 
     <lb/>
     erred in judgment, he had always endeavoured to preserve economy 
     <lb/>
     in the administration of public affairs. (At this point the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman's voice became inaudible, owing to the slamming of 
     <lb/>
     desks and other noises in the House resorted to, to silence him.) He 
     <lb/>
     did not approve of going to any additional expense in the British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> suggested that it would be as well to postpone 
     <lb/>
     the discussion until the British Columbia Bill should be before the 
     <lb/>
     House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JONE3">Mr. JONES</persName> (Leeds North and Grenville North) bowed to the 
     <lb/>
     opinion of the Speaker, and withdrew his motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:RYMA1">Mr. RYMAL</persName> rose to reply to some remarks made by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Leeds and Grenville, with respect to his (Mr. Rymal's) 
     <lb/>
     course in Parliament. The hon. member had seen fit to take him 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Rymal) to task and would fain make the House believe that he 
     <lb/>
     would encourage extravagance in the administration of public 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="248" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710323_Page_248.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">248</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">March 23, 1871</fw>
            
     affairs. He (Mr. Rymal) believed that his course would show that he 
     <lb/>
     had advocated economy whenever it was in the interest of the 
     <lb/>
     public, and he had no desire that every man's utterances should be 
     <lb/>
     fully reported in the case. He had no desire that a column should be 
     <lb/>
     given to his own speech, though the hon. member for Leeds might. 
     <lb/>
     Whether that hon. gentleman was reported in the regular way or 
     <lb/>
     not, he (Mr. Rymal) could not say, but he had frequently noticed 
     <lb/>
     that if the hon. member only spoke for five minutes in the House, a 
     <lb/>
     column report of it, at least, appeared in the papers. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Laughter</hi>) No 
     <lb/>
     doubt the hon. member engaged a special reporter to record his wise 
     <lb/>
     sayings. As for the charge of inconsistency and want of 
     <lb/>
     independence, he (Mr. Rymal) left it to those who had known them 
     <lb/>
     to say whether he or the hon. member for Leeds was the more 
     <lb/>
     deserving of the charge. The hon. member's course had been what 
     <lb/>
     Wm. Lyon Mackenzie had said of such members—that those who 
     <lb/>
     boasted of independence in the House were those who never could 
     <lb/>
     be depended on. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Laughter</hi>) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p></div>
   <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     WEST INDIES MAIL 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FORB1">Mr. FORBES</persName> asked whether, in view of the business between 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion and the British and Foreign West Indies, it is the 
     <lb/>
     intention of the Government to increase the mail accommodation 
     <lb/>
     during this year between those countries so as to give greater 
     <lb/>
     advantage and larger development to this important trade. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. Mr. TUPPER</persName> said the attention of the Government had 
     <lb/>
     been drawn to the importance of establishing such a service, but 
     <lb/>
     considered it not advisable to undertake it yet. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p></div>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PROMISSORY NOTES 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KIRK2">Mr. KIRKPATRICK</persName> asked whether it is the intention of the 
     <lb/>
     Government to issue stamped paper for the purposes of the 
     <lb/>
     Promissory Notes Stamp Act? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MORR1">Hon. Mr. MORRIS</persName> replied that the subject was at this moment 
     <lb/>
     under the consideration of the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p></div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     ST. CLAIR FLATS CANAL 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     On the order for Mr. Mackenzie's resolution for the 
     <lb/>
     correspondence relative to the canal built by the United States 
     <lb/>
     Government at St. Clair Flat, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said the first Minister of the Crown had 
     <lb/>
     promised a portion of this correspondence, and he wished to know 
     <lb/>
     if that correspondence could be brought down now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-E. CARTIER</persName> said it would not be 
     <lb/>
     conducive to public interests to bring down any portion of the 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
          
  
     correspondence. The correspondence was still going on between the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian and Imperial Governments and the Government of the 
     <lb/>
     United States. He hoped the hon. gentleman would accept his 
     <lb/>
     declaration, that it would not be in the public interest to bring any of 
     <lb/>
     it down. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said he was of course bound to accept the 
     <lb/>
     assurance of the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<p>
     *** 
     <lb/>
            </p></div>
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     ADMISSION OF RUPERT'S LAND AND THE NORTH- 
     <lb/>
     WEST 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName> moved that this House do resolve itself into a 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the whole to consider the following resolutions:-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>1. That the sense of the Houses of the respective Legislatures of 
     <lb/>
     the Provinces <hi rendition="simple:italic">Canada</hi>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Nova Scotia</hi> and <hi rendition="simple:italic">New Brunswick</hi> was taken 
     <lb/>
     as to, and formed the basis of the Imperial Legislation under which 
     <lb/>
     the said Provinces were federally united into the Dominion of 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Canada</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     2. That it was by the <hi rendition="simple:italic">British North America Act</hi> (1867) enacted 
     <lb/>
     that it should be lawful for the Queen, by and with the advice of the 
     <lb/>
     Privy Council, on Addresses from the Houses of Parliament of 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Canada</hi>, to admit <hi rendition="simple:italic">Rupert 's Land</hi> and the North Western Territory, 
     <lb/>
     or either of them, into the Union by the said Act created, on such 
     <lb/>
     terms and conditions as the Queen should think fit to approve 
     <lb/>
     subject to the provisions of the said Act; and that the provisions of 
     <lb/>
     any such Order in Council should have effect as if they had been 
     <lb/>
     enacted by the Parliament of the United Kingdom. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     3. That Addresses have been passed by both Houses of 
     <lb/>
     Parliament of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Canada</hi> touching the admission of the said Territories 
     <lb/>
     into the Union, and <hi rendition="simple:italic">Canada</hi> has paid large sums, and incurred large 
     <lb/>
     liabilities in order to accomplish such admission, and an Order in 
     <lb/>
     Council has been made by the Queen for such admission. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     4. That the Parliament of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Canada</hi> has assumed to exercise 
     <lb/>
     jurisdiction over the said Territories and to make provision for the 
     <lb/>
     erection of part of the said Territories into the Province of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Manitoba</hi> 
     <lb/>
     and for the establishment of federal relations between the said 
     <lb/>
     Provinces and <hi rendition="simple:italic">Canada</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     5. That it has been made to appear to this House that the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian Government has requested the Government of the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom to submit to the Parliament of the United Kingdom a Bill 
     <lb/>
     touching the said North Western Territories or some part thereof', 
     <lb/>
     and that the Government of the United Kingdom in consequence of 
     <lb/>
     such request has proposed to the Canadian Government to submit a 
     <lb/>
     Bill, a draft of which it has forwarded to the Canadian Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     6. That in the opinion of this House the sense of both Houses of 
     <lb/>
     the Parliament of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Canada</hi> should be taken as to and should form the 
     <lb/>
     basis of such proposed Legislation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName> said that he proposed in these resolutions to 
     <lb/>
     establish the principle that legislation on matters affecting this [...]
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
