<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_BC_1871-03-31" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1871-03-31">31 March 1871</date>, Canadian Confederation with British Columbia</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>Norman Ward and Pamela Hardisty</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2007"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="310" to="313"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_310.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_311.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_312.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_313.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-10-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_310">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_310.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_311">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_311.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_312">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_312.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_313">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_313.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="310" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_310.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">310</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">March 31, 1871</fw>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">AFTER RECESS</head>


            <head rendition="simple:centre">BRITISH COLUMBIA</head>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> moved the reception of the 
     <lb/>
     report of the Committee of the Whole on certain resolutions 
     <lb/>
     respecting the admission of British Columbia into Union with 
     <lb/>
     Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said that in the speech of the Hon. Minister 
     <lb/>
     of Militia, the statement had been made that one-third of the land in 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia was fit for agriculture. But it was admitted that 
     <lb/>
     this statement embraced the Island of Vancouver. Now, in dealing 
     <lb/>
     with this question, the Island must not be taken into consideration at 
     <lb/>
     all. From all the evidence he could obtain respecting the main land, 
     <lb/>
     not one-fifth of it was available for settlement by farmers, and the 
     <lb/>
     remaining four-fifths through which the road was likely to run, had 
     <lb/>
     yet to be proved good for mining purposes. It was simply absurd to 
     <lb/>
     put the price of that land at $1 dollar per acre. The Hon. Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Customs, in his speech the other evening, had advocated entering 
     <lb/>
     into an obligation which he could not say the country would be able 
     <lb/>
     to perform. It had been said the other evening over and over again 
     <lb/>
     during the debate, that he (Mr. Mackenzie) had stated that he 
     <lb/>
     regarded the construction of the Pacific Railway as a pressing 
     <lb/>
     political necessity. He denied having made any such a statement. 
     <lb/>
     He would admit, however, that he would be willing to subject the 
     <lb/>
     country to some inconvenience in order to obtain communication 
     <lb/>
     with the Pacific through Canadian territory. He was in favour of 
     <lb/>
     opening up communication immediately through the country lying 
     <lb/>
     between the head of Lake Superior and Red River. From that point 
     <lb/>
     to the Rocky Mountains the way was comparatively easy and quite 
     <lb/>
     clear enough for the use of emigrants passing into the North West 
     <lb/>
     country. On the Pacific slope, there was no doubt that it would be 
     <lb/>
     necessary to expend large sums of money from time to time as the 
     <lb/>
     Financial condition of the Dominion permitted in opening up a 
     <lb/>
     good route to this side of the Rocky Mountains. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     But this country should not be bound to construct, within so short 
     <lb/>
     a time, such a gigantic work. The Grand Trunk had never yet paid 
     <lb/>
     one per cent on the capital expended on it, though passing through a 
     <lb/>
     well peopled country and having no scarcity of traffic, yet the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen opposite wished to lead the House to believe that this 
     <lb/>
     Pacific Railway which was to run for 2,500 miles through an 
     <lb/>
     uninhabited wilderness, would be a paying enterprise. We had 
     <lb/>
     unfortunately 200 mile lying between the head of Lake Superior 
     <lb/>
     and Winnipeg, which was an uninhabitable desert. Now, he would 
     <lb/>
     recommend a cheap narrow gauge railway with steamers on the 
     <lb/>
     smaller lakes, as the proper means of communication with the open 
     <lb/>
     prairie extending west of Fort Garry and through which it would be 
     <lb/>
     unnecessary to construct a road for years to come. He considered 
     <lb/>
     this attempt as one of the most foolish things that could be 
     <lb/>
     imagined—and what was it for? In order to get some 10,000 people 
     <lb/>
     into the Union, they were actually agreeing to pay $10,000 a head 
     <lb/>
     on their account. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <cb/>
            
       
            <p>
     Such terms argued either insane recklessness on the part of the 
     <lb/>
     Government and their supporters, or a painful want of patriotism, 
     <lb/>
     which would damage the country and the character of the hon. 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Militia. For thirty years to come it would be 
     <lb/>
     unnecessary to construct the greater portion of this line. The only 
     <lb/>
     part of the road which would need to be constructed immediately 
     <lb/>
     was in British Columbia itself. He would be prepared to consider 
     <lb/>
     that as soon as estimates of the cost, &amp;c., should be submitted to 
     <lb/>
     this House. Holding these views, he moved that all the words after 
     <lb/>
     "that" be omitted, and the following inserted: "having regard to 
     <lb/>
     the vast importance of the questions involved in the said 
     <lb/>
     Resolutions, (including the obligation to construct within ten years 
     <lb/>
     the Pacific Railway, the cost of which is estimated to exceed one 
     <lb/>
     hundred millions of dollars), time should be afforded to the people 
     <lb/>
     and their representatives for consultation before coming to a final 
     <lb/>
     decision; and that the consideration of the said Resolutions should, 
     <lb/>
     therefore, be postponed to the next Session." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> said that he had hoped after 
     <lb/>
     the discussion of the last three days all the arguments against this 
     <lb/>
     measure would have been exhausted, and that he would not be 
     <lb/>
     called upon to speak again. But after the remarks just made by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Lambton, he felt called upon to make some reply. 
     <lb/>
     He was willing to give credit to the hon. members who opposed this 
     <lb/>
     measure, for sincerity. He (Hon. Sir George-E. Cartier) was much 
     <lb/>
     surprised, at the line of argument which they had followed. He was 
     <lb/>
     surprised that the member for Larnbton should try to meet such a 
     <lb/>
     great question on the mere ground of cost. He admitted that the 
     <lb/>
     Union was a necessity and that the railway also was a necessity, but 
     <lb/>
     the honorable gentleman objected to be tied down to a specified 
     <lb/>
     time. He objected to being bound to build a line of 2,500 miles in 
     <lb/>
     ten years—but in past years even when the country was new and 
     <lb/>
     with comparatively few resources she had built 2,000 miles in eight 
     <lb/>
     years. Had Canada been ruined by those works, had her agricultural 
     <lb/>
     interests suffered on this account. And in addition to this, Canada 
     <lb/>
     had built the Victoria Bridge at Montreal, itself equal to 500 miles 
     <lb/>
     of railway, and other large bridges in different parts of the country. 
     <lb/>
     Had she suffered from building those works? No. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     It was true that the G.T.R. proprietors were not receiving so good 
     <lb/>
     a return as he would like. If the railway was practicable at all, every 
     <lb/>
     one would admit that it could well be built in ten years. If there had 
     <lb/>
     been any complaint it should have been that the time allowed was 
     <lb/>
     too long. When it had been proposed to extend the Customs Laws 
     <lb/>
     of Canada to Manitoba, it had been objected to as unfair, and that 
     <lb/>
     the people of that country were beyond the circle of Canada, and 
     <lb/>
     therefore a delay of three years had been allowed until the countries 
     <lb/>
     could be more effectively joined and connected. Let the member for 
     <lb/>
     Lambton and his friends read their speeches on the North West 
     <lb/>
     question. Then no expense was too great, no haste too much, no 
     <lb/>
     trouble too great, if only the North West could be acquired, but now 
     <lb/>
     they said don't go so fast. He wanted to get hold of the Red River 
     <lb/>
     country at any cost, and now from the very same mouth that had 
     <lb/>
     spoken of the fertility of the North West, they heard the very 
     <lb/>
     opposite. He had then been willing to send any number of men to 
     <lb/>
     obtain possession of the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="311" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_311.jpg"/>
           <fw type="dateline">March 31, 1871</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
             <fw type="num">311</fw>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> had stated his willingness to send any 
     <lb/>
     number of men not to acquire the country, but to establish the 
     <lb/>
     supremacy of law over insurrection. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> resumed the comparison of 
     <lb/>
     the expressions of the member for Lambton last year, and this, then 
     <lb/>
     he had stated distinctly that the acquisition of the North West would 
     <lb/>
     be the only way to obtain British Columbia, but now he did not 
     <lb/>
     want the Union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> denied this; he was as much in favour of 
     <lb/>
     Union as ever. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> said the member for 
     <lb/>
     Lambton had stated distinctly that in swallowing the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     scheme he had made a mistake, and now the great Reformer of 
     <lb/>
     Upper Canada, the representative of everything good, the 
     <lb/>
     representative of the great Party of Progress, said no, we must pull 
     <lb/>
     up, we must stop. The Government were really the Party of 
     <lb/>
     Progress and action, and the member for Lambton, and those who 
     <lb/>
     had followed him would at the next election be taken to task by 
     <lb/>
     their constituents for having in order to make a case against the 
     <lb/>
     Government made the humiliating confession that they had made a 
     <lb/>
     mistake in accepting the scheme of Confederation. The member for 
     <lb/>
     Lambton in his argument had said that between Thunder Bay and 
     <lb/>
     Fort Garry there was no soil and the railway could not be built but 
     <lb/>
     that question could be settled by Parliament hereafter, when the 
     <lb/>
     railway scheme should be submitted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName>: What about the obligations? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-E. CARTIER</persName> said, suppose the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman undertook an obligation, could he be obliged to fulfil it, 
     <lb/>
     if he should be prevented by unforeseen circumstances. No one 
     <lb/>
     could be compelled to perform an impossibility. The time was too 
     <lb/>
     long, and the objection could only come from an economical 
     <lb/>
     Scotchman, and he would predict that in a very few years the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman would be one of the most ardent supporters of the 
     <lb/>
     railway. He had not been sorry to lose his motion yesterday, and he 
     <lb/>
     was not sincere in his present proposal. That proposal was to entail 
     <lb/>
     a delay of seven months; what object could there be in so doing? 
     <lb/>
     The matter had already been discussed sufficiently, and the time 
     <lb/>
     was now come for settlement, and he would say that without the 
     <lb/>
     prospect of British Columbia, they would never have persuaded a 
     <lb/>
     majority of the House to consent to acquire one inch of the North 
     <lb/>
     West. For the sake of the member for Lambton himself he trusted 
     <lb/>
     his speech would not be well reported, and especially that part in 
     <lb/>
     which he had spoken of the character of the land in most 
     <lb/>
     disadvantageous terms, and yet he said he was in favour of building 
     <lb/>
     a railway as soon as possible. If the land was as described by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member, why should a railway be built at all? He reiterated 10 
     <lb/>
     years was too long, and as to the mode of building the railway that 
     <lb/>
     would all be submitted to Parliament, and within the next few days 
     <lb/>
     the Government would ask for an appropriation for the preliminary 
     <lb/>
     survey. He maintained that Canada was better able to-day to 
     <lb/>
     undertake the Pacific railway than she had been years ago to 
     <lb/>
         
         <cb/>
  
           
   
       
     advance fifteen millions to the Grand Trunk. The whole affair of the 
     <lb/>
     hundred millions was a bugbear. There was no such thing as 
     <lb/>
     incurring that debt in a few years—it was an absurdity to make such 
     <lb/>
     a statement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The policy was purposely to retain the lands of the country in 
     <lb/>
     order to build railways and open ways of communication. Canada 
     <lb/>
     would not have to bear the expenditure alone. British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     would be represented in the House, and would be equally interested 
     <lb/>
     in the work. Speaking of the cost of the railway, he maintained the 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen on the other side had played the parts of old nurses, but 
     <lb/>
     the children on his side of the House were not so easily frightened. 
     <lb/>
     He spoke of the North Pacific, quoting from a statement showing 
     <lb/>
     the whole length to be 2,000 miles, and the entire estimated cost 
     <lb/>
     seventy-six million dollars in greenbacks. lt had been objected that 
     <lb/>
     the estimate for the Canadian Pacific might not be correct. He 
     <lb/>
     admitted that, but the argument worked both ways. The cost might 
     <lb/>
     prove very much below the estimate, and an immense amount of 
     <lb/>
     land was reserved to cover it. He quoted a statement showing the 
     <lb/>
     average cost of railway communication in the United States, 
     <lb/>
     showing 2,600 miles of line in operation, the average cost being, in 
     <lb/>
     the different States, from $25,000 to $33,000 per mile. It was 
     <lb/>
     admitted that there was a large extent of prairie land to be crossed, 
     <lb/>
     and the smaller expenditure necessary there would leave means to 
     <lb/>
     overcome difficulties in other portions. The hon. members opposite 
     <lb/>
     had been sufficiently unpatriotic to represent the country as that it 
     <lb/>
     would never attract immigration, and he quoted from the 
     <lb/>
     proceedings of the House of Representatives of the State of 
     <lb/>
     Minnesota speaking of the Canadian line as practicable, and the 
     <lb/>
     territories of the North West and British Columbia, as fertile, and 
     <lb/>
     the most valuable of the Continent, and yet men in this country, the 
     <lb/>
     leaders of their party, did their utmost to decry their country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> denied that he had done anything to decry 
     <lb/>
     the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> was glad he had given the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member an opportunity to correct himself. He quoted from an 
     <lb/>
     article from an American paper, copied into the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> 
     <lb/>
     characterising the Saskatchewan country as most valuable in soil 
     <lb/>
     and minerals, and British Columbia as possessing rich mineral 
     <lb/>
     resources, magnificent climate and fine soil. It was fortunate that 
     <lb/>
     the truth could be ascertained even if it came from opponents. The 
     <lb/>
     Government had stated again and again that they themselves would 
     <lb/>
     not build the railway, but that it would be constructed by 
     <lb/>
     Companies assisted by such subsidies as would not oppress the 
     <lb/>
     people. It was absurd to speak of building a line to the Rocky 
     <lb/>
     Mountains only, a vote could not be obtained for such a purpose, 
     <lb/>
     but when it was proposed to extend the line to the ocean, the 
     <lb/>
     question assumed a very different aspect. Many great works had 
     <lb/>
     been accomplished in England, but what were any compared with 
     <lb/>
     the scheme now proposed, and he could say that already there 
     <lb/>
     was a motion in England to assist the measure, and there would 
     <lb/>
     doubtless be capitalists to take the matter in hand, and 
     <lb/>
     everything was in favor of the successful construction of the 
     <lb/>
     road. The Minister of Justice had telegraphed him to present his 
     <lb/>
     congratulations to his friends on the vote of yesterday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="312" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_312.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">312</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">March 31, 1871</fw>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName> said the member for Lambton (Mr. Mackenzie) 
     <lb/>
     in his amendment had pointed out the importance of the matter 
     <lb/>
     the grave nature of the burden proposed to be incurred, and 
     <lb/>
     therefore suggested the postponement of the consideration of 
     <lb/>
     the matter, and it was impossible to answer those statements. 
     <lb/>
     Much had been heard that the railway would not cost the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion in cash $100,000,000, but no one attempted to deny 
     <lb/>
     that the railway would cost that amount and where could the 
     <lb/>
     money come from but from the resources of the country. It 
     <lb/>
     might be in lands and it might be in money, but the result was 
     <lb/>
     the same, and the only argument the Minister of Militia had 
     <lb/>
     used was to speak of the American lines and contrast 
     <lb/>
     greenbacks with gold. He complained of the system of alternate 
     <lb/>
     sections not being followed in land grants. The argument 
     <lb/>
     seemed to be that they would not be compelled to perform 
     <lb/>
     impossibilities, but an honest man would fulfil an obligation, 
     <lb/>
     though the result might be bankruptcy. 1f rashly the national 
     <lb/>
     credit and faith were pledged to build that road in ten years, he 
     <lb/>
     said that any one who voted for that obligation with the mental 
     <lb/>
     reservation that they would not be compelled to fulfil the 
     <lb/>
     obligation unless such should be desirable was a base man. The 
     <lb/>
     spirit and the letter of the bond were alike binding, and the 
     <lb/>
     question was most serious. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Bill was not one that could be repealed but was an 
     <lb/>
     irrevocable determination to build the road in ten years 
     <lb/>
     whatever the hazard, whatever the results, and should they not 
     <lb/>
     seek to communicate with their people before arriving at this 
     <lb/>
     irrevocable determination. It had been urged in order to secure 
     <lb/>
     votes that there was a reserve power of repudiation, but if the 
     <lb/>
     obligation was undertaken, the people would hold themselves 
     <lb/>
     bound by it, and could gentlemen be prepared to meet an 
     <lb/>
     indignant people if they incurred this responsibility without 
     <lb/>
     consulting those they represented, and if the gentlemen did so 
     <lb/>
     act, though they might go back to their people, they would not 
     <lb/>
     come back to that House. The question was whether the debt of 
     <lb/>
     the country should, at a stroke, be doubled, or whether they 
     <lb/>
     should have an opportunity of consulting their people before 
     <lb/>
     taking such a step. They had been urged to haste, but he 
     <lb/>
     maintained that there had been too much haste in bringing 
     <lb/>
     about Confederation already, and he was not anxious to ruin 
     <lb/>
     entirely that portion of the scheme which had been too hastily 
     <lb/>
     consummated. He had not heard what harm could result from 
     <lb/>
     postponement and as to the argument that British Columbia was 
     <lb/>
     hanging in the balance, he would say that while England was 
     <lb/>
     true to herself, the result did not lie with British Columbia, and 
     <lb/>
     therefore time for consideration should not be refused. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said it was a great advantage to be able to 
     <lb/>
     hear both sides of a question, but he could see no very great 
     <lb/>
     difference in the proposition of the Government and the 
     <lb/>
     amendment proposed. The hon. member for Lambton after his 
     <lb/>
     defeat last night was obliged to adopt the more successful stand 
     <lb/>
     which had been taken by the hon. member for Dundas. There 
     <lb/>
     was no talk about the necessity of this delay from the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman opposite before this evening. It was all very well to 
     <lb/>
          
          <cb/>
            
   
   
     ask for this delay now, but the scheme had been before the 
     <lb/>
     people and had been discussed in the papers for months. The 
     <lb/>
     terms were published in Toronto papers three months ago, and, 
     <lb/>
     in fact, the Union had been talked of ever since the 
     <lb/>
     commencement of the Confederation. In reply to the arguments 
     <lb/>
     of the hon. members opposite, he said that a grant of $10,000 
     <lb/>
     per mile in addition to the land grant would place the 
     <lb/>
     construction of the railway beyond the possibility of a doubt. 
     <lb/>
     There could be no difficulty in disposing of the lands at a fair 
     <lb/>
     price. The fertile belt was spoken of by the American writers 
     <lb/>
     who had visited it, as being of immense extent and of great 
     <lb/>
     fertility. The Northern Pacific railway looked to it for a portion 
     <lb/>
     of their future trade. It was, therefore, in the interest of this 
     <lb/>
     Dominion to construct a road through our own territory to the 
     <lb/>
     Pacific. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO8">Hon. Mr. McDOUGALL</persName> (Lanark North) said the House 
     <lb/>
     should not be led away by claptrap speeches from the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman opposite. Let them look at the facts. Here was a 
     <lb/>
     statement of Mr. Hind, an officer appointed by this Government, 
     <lb/>
     who explored the North West, and submitted his report thereon. 
     <lb/>
     This gentleman stated that in the whole of the fertile belt there 
     <lb/>
     were not 40,000,000 acres of available land. Taking a fertile belt 
     <lb/>
     in the Rocky Mountains which was not mentioned in that report, 
     <lb/>
     to contain 10,000,000 acres more, there were but 50,000,000 
     <lb/>
     acres of any commercial or exchangeable value, in the North 
     <lb/>
     West. Where then were the Government lands to come from 
     <lb/>
     after granting large sections to the railway? The experience of 
     <lb/>
     the United States had shown that it was not in the interest of a 
     <lb/>
     country to grant its unsettled lands in large blocks to private 
     <lb/>
     companies. The proposition before the House was to give all the 
     <lb/>
     valuable lands of the North West to a company which was not 
     <lb/>
     yet formed. After the experience of English capitalists on 
     <lb/>
     Canadian railways, it was not likely that capital could be got to 
     <lb/>
     construct this railway. The money must be had in some way 
     <lb/>
     even at the risk of involving the Dominion in ruin. In reply to 
     <lb/>
     the statement of the Hon. Minister of Customs that this question 
     <lb/>
     had been before the public for some time, he would refer the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman to the files of papers in the reading room. If he 
     <lb/>
     would look at them he would see that the country was startled at 
     <lb/>
     the gigantic proportions of this scheme. On the 27th of that 
     <lb/>
     month, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">ipsissima verba</hi> of the scheme were presented to this 
     <lb/>
     House, and that was the first time the public had an opportunity 
     <lb/>
     of passing judgment on it. It was only after it was taken up and 
     <lb/>
     discussed in this House the other day, that it might be said to 
     <lb/>
     have been placed before the people. Could the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     then deny that delay should be granted before passing this 
     <lb/>
     measure. It had not been presented to the House in the 
     <lb/>
     constitutional manner and it was only right to give the people an 
     <lb/>
     opportunity to express their approval or disapproval of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The amendment was put and lost on the following division: Yeas, 
     <lb/>
     7; nays, 135. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BODW1">Mr. BODWELL</persName> moved in amendment to leave out all the words 
     <lb/>
     after "that" and insert the following: "That the proposed terms of 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="313" facs="final/images/BC_H_of_C_18710331_Page_313.jpg"/>
           <fw type="dateline">March 31, 1871</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">313</fw>

           

     Union with <hi rendition="simple:italic">British Columbia</hi> provide for its representation in the 
     <lb/>
     Senate by three Members, and in the House of Commons by six 
     <lb/>
     Members, while its population is about 10,000, and such 
     <lb/>
     representation in the House of Commons is enormously in excess of 
     <lb/>
     the proper number according to population, and is in violation of 
     <lb/>
     the fundamental principle of the fact between the Provinces, a 
     <lb/>
     principle which ought not to be disturbed without the assent of the 
     <lb/>
     Provinces, and that the said Resolutions be referred back to a 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole for the purpose of reducing the number of 
     <lb/>
     representatives of <hi rendition="simple:italic">British Columbia</hi> in the House of Commons." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JONE3">Mr. JONES</persName> (Leeds North and Grenville North) said though 
     <lb/>
     both sides deprecated the party considerations, he had never heard a 
     <lb/>
     question made so completely one of party. He did not think the 
     <lb/>
     country was in a position to undertake the expenditure proposed. He 
     <lb/>
     considered the Imperial Government ought to share in the expense 
     <lb/>
     of any scheme for opening up the North West. He maintained that 
     <lb/>
     the country was not suitable for settlement, or the present 
     <lb/>
     population would have been much larger. He objected to the 
     <lb/>
     Indians being taken into account, as they had done but little good to 
     <lb/>
     Canada. He was in favor of the consideration of the matter being 
     <lb/>
     postponed and should vote for the amendment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOLT1">Mr. BOLTON</persName> in explaining the reference made to him by the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Customs, said he had not charged him with making 
     <lb/>
     reckless statements, but that while giving him and the Government 
     <lb/>
     every credit for being in earnest in desiring to construct the road, he 
     <lb/>
     thought it very doubtful whether a company would be found to 
     <lb/>
     undertake it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. MACKENZIE'S amendment was then put, and the 
     <lb/>
     following vote taken: Yeas, 68; nays, 85. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART3">Mr. CARTWRIGHT</persName> believe that the Government had been led 
     <lb/>
     into the inconceivable blunder of naming a period for the 
     <lb/>
     construction of the road and the amendment he was about to 
     <lb/>
     propose differed from others in these respects, it did not interfere 
     <lb/>
     with the pledge to commence the railway, and only pledged that 
     <lb/>
     they would use their utmost exertions to go on with the work as fast 
     <lb/>
     as practicable, and it need involve but a very short delay. He moved 
     <lb/>
       
       <cb/>
            
   
    
     that the eleventh paragraph should be amended by inserting the 
     <lb/>
     words "use their utmost exertions" after the word "further." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KILL1">Mr. KILLAM</persName> then moved in amendment to the amendment, 
     <lb/>
     that the words "while its population is about 10,000" be struck out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. KILLAM'S amendment was rejected on the following 
     <lb/>
     division: Yeas, 43; nays 100. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. BODWELL'S amendment was then put, and the vote 
     <lb/>
     resulted as follows: Yeas, 58; nays, 87. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName> moved in amendment to leave out all the words 
     <lb/>
     after "that" and insert the following: "The proposed terms of 
     <lb/>
     Union with <hi rendition="simple:italic">British Columbia</hi> provide for the payment by the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion to <hi rendition="simple:italic">British Columbia</hi> of a yearly sum of $100,000 in 
     <lb/>
     perpetuity (equal to a capital sum of $2,000,000) for the cession of 
     <lb/>
     a tract of waste land on the route of the proposed Pacific Railway to 
     <lb/>
     aid in its construction, while any such land required for that purpose 
     <lb/>
     should be ceded without charge in like manner as the lands of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion are to be so ceded, and that the said Resolutions be re<lb break="no"/>committed for the purpose of amending the same in accordance 
     <lb/>
     with this Revolution." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The amendment was put and the vote was as follows:—Yeas, 59; 
     <lb/>
     nays, 84. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The first, second, and third resolutions were carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir GEORGE-É. CARTIER</persName> moved that an address, 
     <lb/>
     embodying the said resolutions be presented to Her Majesty and 
     <lb/>
     that a Select Committee, composed of Messrs. Tilley, Morris, 
     <lb/>
     Tupper, Chauveau, Ferguson, Savary, and the mover be appointed 
     <lb/>
     to draft such address—Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Committee presented the draft address, which was received 
     <lb/>
     and read a first time, to be read a second time, at the next Session of 
     <lb/>
     the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House adjourned at 1.45 am. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>