<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-03-10"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>


<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-03-10">10 March 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1870, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1870"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="49"/>
<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="59"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>

<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_042.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_044.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_046.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_048.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_056.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_058.hocr.html"/>
</item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-15">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_042">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_042.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_044">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_044.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_046">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_046.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_048">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_048.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_056">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_056.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_058">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_058.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="43" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_042.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">43</fw>

<head rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, March 10.</head><lb/>

<p>[...]</p>

<p>Debate on the Draft Address resumed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ARSE1">Mr. ARSENAULT</persName> said as the question <lb/>
to which the paragraph referred was an <lb/>

<pb n="44" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_044.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">44</fw> 

important one—one which might be <lb/>
regarded as the question of the day—and <lb/>
as it was expected that each member of <lb/>
the committee would declare his opinion <lb/>
on confederation, he would offer a few <lb/>
remarks. From what he had heard, he <lb/>
considered that the principle was ad<lb break="no"/>mitted by almost every hon member who <lb/>
had spoken, except the hon member for <lb/>
Tyron (Mr. Howat) who had declared <lb/>
himself a no-terms man, and the hon <lb/>
member for Belfast (Mr. Duncan) who <lb/>
had also avowed himself a no-terms <lb/>
man. He (Mr. A.) supposed they might <lb/>
be regardad as the political giants of the <lb/>
anti-confederate ranks. While he was <lb/>
not in favor of the terms offered, he was <lb/>
not opposed to the principle, for were he <lb/>
do say he was opposed to confederation <lb/>
on any terms, to his mind it would sound <lb/>
like disloyalty. (Hear from Mr. Havi<lb break="no"/>land.) It was the desire of the home <lb/>
government that the matter should be <lb/>
fairly discussed, and in the opening <lb/>
speaeh the Legislature was asked to give <lb/>
a calm and deliberate consideration to <lb/>
the subject. Some hon members had <lb/>
attended meetings and ascertained the <lb/>
opinions of the people, and formed their <lb/>
views at those meetings in accordance <lb/>
with the majority. His constituents had <lb/>
held meetings also, and those of them <lb/>
whom he heard speak upon the subject <lb/>
said they would not oppose terms that <lb/>
would be just and equitable ; but if his <lb/>
constituents were equally divided on the <lb/>
question, he would feel to be his duty <lb/>
to go against it with the hope that at <lb/>
some future time the people would view <lb/>
the question more favorably. Some hon <lb/>
members had spoken as if entering con<lb break="no"/>federation would be selling our country. <lb/>
He did not see it in that light. He <lb/>
viewed it as an alliance, and that with <lb/>
people like ourselves. Those here who <lb/>
claimed to be descendants of natives of <lb/>
Scotland, Ireland, England or France, <lb/>
going to Canada would meet with the <lb/>
same class of people, (hear) the same <lb/>
customs, institutions and laws as were <lb/>
here. He viewed it in the light of the <lb/>
alliance of a young gentleman to a lady. <lb/>
If the one was suited for the other, it <lb/>
would be an advantage to both. But <lb/>

<cb/> 

one important condition was, it must be <lb/>
mutual, otherwise it would be an injury, <lb/>
if not the ruin of them both ; and such <lb/>
were the conditions required before we <lb/>
should think of joining with the Do<lb break="no"/>minion. Were we to unite with Canada, <lb/>
we would still have the management of <lb/>
all our local affairs, but if the union was <lb/>
effected against the will of the people, <lb/>
the alliance would not be happy, con<lb break="no"/>sequently he would be sorry to give a <lb/>
vote that would mar the happiness of the <lb/>
country. He thought the terms we would <lb/>
accept should be named, and if the <lb/>
Dominion would not grant them, then <lb/>
we would have a good excuse for re<lb break="no"/>maining as we were ; but if we said we <lb/>
would accept of no terms, he thought we <lb/>
could not fairly meet the people. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWA1">Mr. HOWAT</persName>.—Name your terms. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ARSE1">Mr. ARSENAULT</persName> would not take so <lb/>
much upon him. He had voted against <lb/>
the government on the resolution in favor <lb/>
of Mr. A. McNeill as summary reporter, <lb/>
because he considered him a useful <lb/>
officer. He had heard that some voted <lb/>
against Mr. McNeill because he opposed <lb/>
the government on confederation ; if so, <lb/>
he thought it was a weak cause if it <lb/>
required this action to uphold it. It had <lb/>
been said that the synopsis of the debates <lb/>
printed in the papers was one-sided. <lb/>
The leading article in the Patriot of this <lb/>
morning was so. We heard something <lb/>
from the hon member for Georgetown <lb/>
(Mr. McAulay) about " watching", but <lb/>
he would like to know if the hon member <lb/>
(Mr. Howat) was the watchman of the <lb/>
House ? At all events he had told him <lb/>
outside that he was watching him (Mr. <lb/>
A.). He knew that the hon member for <lb/>
Tryon was coming out with a long no-<lb break="yes"/>terms pledge. Before his constituents <lb/>
he had no doubt (Mr. H.) would <lb/>
take the pledge, and with them he would <lb/>
leave the hon member. The government <lb/>
did not say it was against fair terms, nei<lb break="no"/>ther was he (Mr. A.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WIGH1">Hon. THE SPEAKER</persName> said his hon friend <lb/>
the Leader of the Opposition and himself <lb/>
did not agree respecting the imports from <lb/>
the Dominion yesterday. He had taken <lb/>
some pains to ascertain what was ex<lb break="no"/>ported to and imported from Canada. <lb/></p>

<pb n="45" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_044.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">45</fw> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.—The hon <lb/>
Speaker and he (Mr. H.) need not go <lb/>
into a dispute on this question. If he <lb/>
meant Canada, then he (Mr. H.) ad<lb break="no"/>mitted he was correct, but understood <lb/>
the hon member to say the Dominion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WIGH1">Hon. THE SPEAKER</persName> was going to show <lb/>
that the payments made to Canada, by <lb/>
our merchants were, to a great extent, <lb/>
made in bills of exchange, or in gold, <lb/>
which, as a consequence, was drawing <lb/>
from this Island the circulating medium <lb/>
required at home. In 1868 our imports <lb/>
from Canada amounted to £20,486, and <lb/>
our exports to £1,095, which was all he <lb/>
could find in the returns, and he wished <lb/>
to ascertain how the balance had been <lb/>
paid ! It must have been drawn from <lb/>
the banks, and therefore had not been <lb/>
paid for by articles which were the <lb/>
growth and production of this Island, <lb/>
hence it must have drawn away the gold <lb/>
and silver required among ourselves. <lb/>
The exports to the United States from <lb/>
this colony in 1869 amounted to £72,<lb break="no"/>808 14s. 9d., and this had been wholly <lb/>
paid for by the products of our farms <lb/>
and fisheries, and undoubtedly that was <lb/>
the country which best suited this colony <lb/>
to trade with. If we could induce the <lb/>
United States to reduce her tariff on some <lb/>
of our products which suited their mar<lb break="no"/>ket, it would be of greater advantage to <lb/>
us than an intercolonial free trade with <lb/>
the Dominion. The United States was <lb/>
a market we could not overstock, and <lb/>
were it not that since the abrogation of <lb/>
the Reciprocity Treaty we had the mar<lb break="no"/>kets of Great Britain to go to, he did not <lb/>
know what we would have done. If the <lb/>
British Government would give us the <lb/>
privilege of our own waters, and allow <lb/>
us to enter into a commercial treaty with <lb/>
the United States, we would, he had no <lb/>
doubt, find that an arrangement could be <lb/>
arrived at which would be mutually <lb/>
satisfactory, and greatly to our advan<lb break="no"/>tage. But this Great Britain would not <lb/>
allow. But he believed, on account of <lb/>
our being out of the union, the United <lb/>
States had and would retain a more <lb/>
kindly feeling for the people of this <lb/>
colony than if they formed a part of the <lb/>
Dominion of Canada. <lb/></p> 

<cb/>

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> had misunder<lb break="no"/>stood this hon the Speaker on the previous <lb/>
evening. Canada was a part of the <lb/>
Dominion, and so were Nova Scotia and <lb/>
New Brunswick, and although the balance <lb/>
of trade was against us in Canada proper, <lb/>
yet it was not so in the other Provinces. <lb/>
Our merchants who purchased goods in <lb/>
Manchester paid for them in gold, which <lb/>
they procured in Liverpool or London <lb/>
for the products which find a market in <lb/>
these parts ; and so was it in the Do<lb break="no"/>minion. Hills in Canada were probably <lb/>
paid with gold procured in Halifax. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWA1">Mr. HOWAT</persName> would ask the hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Egmont Bay if he had, at the <lb/>
time of his election, expressed views <lb/>
similar to those he had now given utter<lb break="no"/>ance to ! He felt that if he had, the <lb/>
hon member would not have had the <lb/>
trouble of stating them before this hon <lb/>
committee. The hon member classed <lb/>
the greater portion of the people with <lb/>
himself, and stated that they admtted <lb/>
the principle of confederation. This he <lb/>
(Mr. H.) did not believe. The hon <lb/>
member had said that the greater portion <lb/>
of the committee had accepted the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple, but he (Mr. H.) would leave him <lb/>
and his constituents to settle that point. <lb/>
He (mr. H.) believed there were but two <lb/>
classes—the no-terms men and the con<lb break="no"/>federates. He did not see what grounds we <lb/>
had to suppose that we could get terms <lb/>
that would justify us to accept, and con<lb break="no"/>federates admitted the Dominion govern<lb break="no"/>ment had power to change the terms <lb/>
when it pleased. Were we in the <lb/>
Dominion, the terms granted by the <lb/>
present Ottawa government might be <lb/>
considered too liberal by their accessories, <lb/>
who might therefore denounce them as a <lb/>
species of bribery by which we had been <lb/>
induced to join the Dominion. The hon <lb/>
member (Mr. A.) had not the moral <lb/>
courage to state the terms he would <lb/>
accept. No, he was watching to see <lb/>
what others would say. In regard to the <lb/>
wish of the Imperial government he <lb/>
(Mr. H.) was not yet certain that it had <lb/>
expressed any anxiety on the subject, <lb/>
and, even if it had, the Imperial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment changed also, and the next one <lb/>
might be quite indifferent about the <lb/> 

<pb n="46" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_046.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">46</fw> 

matter. Besides, our experience in the <lb/>
land question had proved to us that a <lb/>
despatch was not a law. Those who <lb/>
rebelled in Canada were not only for<lb break="no"/>given, but their leaders were promoted <lb/>
by the home government to positions of <lb/>
honor, clearly proving that those who <lb/>
resisted the Imperial will were then <lb/>
right ; and it would very likely be so <lb/>
with the people of this Island if they <lb/>
continued to resist confederation. Could <lb/>
the statesmen in England have a <lb/>
correct knowledge of the position of the <lb/>
people of this Island ? It was unreason<lb break="no"/>able to suppose they could. He would <lb/>
admit the hon. Leader of the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion was an experience statesman, <lb/>
yet he went to Quebec, signed the <lb/>
Report there agree to, which he had <lb/>
since said was unjust to this Island. He <lb/>
(Mr. H.) merely mentioned this to show <lb/>
that even the hon member was at that <lb/>
time mistaken, and he feared was mis<lb break="no"/>taken yet ; yes, and the greatest statesman <lb/>
might sometimes be mistaken. He <lb/>
understood the Hon. Mr. Haviland to say <lb/>
the Dominion would always retain her <lb/>
connexion with the old country ; then, <lb/>
if so, how could she be called great until <lb/>
she was independent ? There was <lb/>
another point. The hon member said <lb/>
that many articles upon which we had <lb/>
now to pay a duty would, under union, <lb/>
come in free, but would the hon member <lb/>
say the Dominion Government could do <lb/>
with less of a revenue than at present ? <lb/>
No ! such would not be the case ; and <lb/>
when all her contemplated public works <lb/>
were undertaken, it would be found that <lb/>
the taxes would have to be increased. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ARSE1">Mr. ARSENAULT</persName> said that at the last <lb/>
election the hon member for Tryon had <lb/>
a pledge which he desired candidates to <lb/>
subscribe to ; but he believed those who <lb/>
did not do so had been just an faithful to <lb/>
the country as those who did. When he <lb/>
was returned he was not asked to take a <lb/>
pledge, nor was confederation spoken of. <lb/>
He did not speak about it, nor did the <lb/>
people. He supposed the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Patriot</hi> might <lb/>
be regarded as the greatest anti-confed<lb break="no"/>erate paper in the Island, and yet it was <lb/>
not opposed to terms. When the new <lb/>
terms were made public, that journal <lb/> 

<cb/>

said that "they were not just and fair." <lb/>
The Patriotwould, therefore, he inferred, <lb/>
have supported them had he considered <lb/>
them to be just and fair. It was said <lb/>
the $800,000 were to be given to pur<lb break="no"/>chase out the lands from the proprietors, <lb/>
therefore he did not see that the price of <lb/>
lands would be so high if we joined the <lb/>
Dominion. Our land purchase act re<lb break="no"/>quired that each estate should be made <lb/>
self-sustaining, at least as nearly so as <lb/>
possible, but in the event of our going <lb/>
into the Dominion and receiving that <lb/>
money, he thought the lands might be <lb/>
sold at a lower rate. If he was not <lb/>
correct, he would like an explanation. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC6">Hon. P. SINCLAIR</persName> said the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber was not correct in the view he had <lb/>
taken. If the $800,000 was received, <lb/>
it would be handed over to the local <lb/>
Government, which would have the <lb/>
management of the lands, and as there <lb/>
was a law which, while it required that <lb/>
each estate should, as nearly as possible, <lb/>
be made self-sustaining, yet it also pro<lb break="no"/>hibited the Government from making <lb/>
any profits on the land. He would be <lb/>
sorry if any such opinions were enter<lb break="no"/>tained in the country, for if so they were <lb/>
not correct and might do harm. But <lb/>
he must say he did not for a moment <lb/>
suppose that any hon. member of this <lb/>
committee entertained such an opinion. <lb/>
The price of the land was now reduced <lb/>
to cost and charges, and if we were into <lb/>
confederation the people would find that <lb/>
it would not be had any lower than it <lb/>
could be had now. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—It was true the ten<lb break="no"/>antry, even if we went into confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, would have to pay as high for thir <lb/>
lands as they did at present. The only <lb/>
difference would be that we had now to <lb/>
take it out of the general revenue. If the <lb/>
Dominion gave us the $800,000, it would <lb/>
make no difference in so far as the price <lb/>
of the land was concerned. He agreed <lb/>
with the hon. member for Tryon that <lb/>
there were but two alternatives—<hi rendition="simple:italic">no <lb/>
terms, or terms</hi>. The hon. member was <lb/>
more manly than the government which <lb/>
he supported, in his views upon that <lb/>
question. <lb/></p>

<pb n="47" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_046.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">47</fw> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWA1">Mr. HOWAT</persName> said he was not a sup<lb break="no"/>porter of the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CAME5">Mr. CAMERON</persName>.—Perhaps it would be <lb/>
those who were for just and equitable <lb/>
terms that would, in naming them, be as <lb/>
much of no-terms men as the hon. <lb/>
member for Tryon. For his part, he <lb/>
did not see what terms could be offered <lb/>
which would be an equivalent for what <lb/>
we were expected to give up. For it <lb/>
would not be possible to name terms to <lb/>
which some objection might not be taken. <lb/>
He (Mr. Cameron) contended that this <lb/>
Island was not to gain so much by the <lb/>
saving of duties on importations from the <lb/>
Dominion as some imagined , for the ex<lb break="no"/>cise duties in Canada were so high that <lb/>
it would necessarily keep prices up to <lb/>
nearly their present rate, if not quite as <lb/>
high a figure as they were now bought <lb/>
at. One disadvantage would be that our <lb/>
duties would be immediately raised to 15 <lb/>
per cent., and probably very soon to 20 <lb/>
per cent. Certainly we had no guaran<lb break="no"/>tee that such would not be the case, for <lb/>
by the Imperial Act they could raise a <lb/>
revenue by any modes of taxation they <lb/>
might choose to adopt. The hon member <lb/>
for Egmont Bay said he opposed some of <lb/>
the present terms, but was willing to accept <lb/>
fair terms. He believed the hon. <lb/>
members who said so might be as hard to <lb/>
satisfy as any of the no-terms men, for <lb/>
he felt satisfied the Dominion could not <lb/>
give terms that would be satisfactory, so <lb/>
that the action of the fair-terms men <lb/>
and the no-terms men would have the <lb/>
same effect, and for that reason he would <lb/>
oppose the scheme entirely. A great deal <lb/>
bad been said about the railroads of <lb/>
Canada and the advantages this Island <lb/>
would derive from their use ; but he <lb/>
might ask, would our remaining out of <lb/>
confederation deprive us of such advan<lb break="no"/>tages. His opinion was, that by <lb/>
entering into a union with Canada we <lb/>
had much to dread from the construction <lb/>
of the railroads and other contemplated <lb/>
public works of the Dominion. Nor did <lb/>
he believe the Pacific railroad would <lb/>
ever prove, even if built, as beneficial <lb/>
as its advocates imagined. One reason <lb/>
why he thought so, was, because it would <lb/>
consist of detached parts, and to show <lb/>

<cb/> 

the difficulties that had to be encounter<lb break="no"/>ed, he thought it sufficient to state <lb/>
that the route selected was 200 miles <lb/>
north of a direct line, and this line had <lb/>
to be chosen in order to avoid passing <lb/>
through the territory of the United <lb/>
States. He regarded our isolation as our <lb/>
best protection, and thought we had <lb/>
more to hope than to dread by re<lb break="no"/>maining as were were; nor could he see <lb/>
what better position the Dominion was <lb/>
in, with its population of four millions, <lb/>
when placed beside the United States <lb/>
with her 42,000,000, than we were. As <lb/>
to the great value of the North-west ter<lb break="no"/>ritory, he much doubted the correctness <lb/>
of statements which had been made. <lb/>
The population was only about 20,000, <lb/>
and, in 1868, they were in a state of <lb/>
starvation. The numerous obstacles to <lb/>
be encountered and overcome would, <lb/>
for a long time, continue. The country <lb/>
was liable to plagues, grass-hoppers, lo<lb break="no"/>custs, drought and inundations, any one <lb/>
of which was sufficient to destroy the <lb/>
crops of the country, and frequently did <lb/>
so. The country around Winnipeg had <lb/>
frequently been inundated. Great por<lb break="no"/>tions of its crops, after droughts, <lb/>
which were frequent, had also been <lb/>
destroyed by fire. The argument used, <lb/>
that the British government desired us <lb/>
to unite with the Dominion, he regarded <lb/>
as weak. Had we acted upon the ex<lb break="no"/>pressed desire of the Home government, <lb/>
he felt convinced that this Colony would <lb/>
never have made an effort to have freed <lb/>
itself from the hands of the proprietors, <lb/>
and the tenantry to-day would still be <lb/>
under them. As to our being forced into <lb/>
confederation, he thought the opinion of <lb/>
John Bright and other distinguished <lb/>
statesmen in England, when speaking on <lb/>
the Nova Scotia difficulty, supplied the <lb/>
best answer to that objection. Mr. <lb/>
Bright said :—"Your scheme (of confe<lb break="no"/>deration) must break down if the Nova <lb/>
Scotians resolve they will not have it. <lb/>
It is not possible to coerce them. There <lb/>
is no statesman living in England who <lb/>
will venture to bring about the shedding <lb/>
of one drop of blood upon the continent." <lb/>
And no doubt the same arguments would <lb/>
be used and applied to this Island. That <lb/>
was if the argument contained in the <lb/>
logic of force was ever to be used. The <lb/>
hon. member for Egmont Bay had drawn <lb/>
a comparison between our union with <lb/>
Canada and that of a party getting mar<lb break="no"/>ried. He thought the comparison would <lb/>
not hold good, because there was too <lb/>
great a disparity between them ; nor did <lb/> 

<pb n="48" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_048.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">48</fw>

he at all think the rule would hold good <lb/>
in this case, for the party wooing was <lb/>
too extravagant and unequal to suit little <lb/>
Prince Edward Island. With respect to <lb/>
the idea that the $800,000 was to be <lb/>
given to the tenantry, from whatever <lb/>
source the opinion originated, he thought <lb/>
it was somewhat generally believed. <lb/>
But the thought it would be a long time <lb/>
before that money would be received; the <lb/>
promise was all we should ever obtain. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> observed that the terms <lb/>
offered to this Island were much more <lb/>
favorable than those offered to Nova Scotia. <lb/>
Our indebtedness was arranged on the <lb/>
same principle as that of the other Provin<lb break="no"/>ces. They, for their debt, had handed <lb/>
over to the Dominion government some <lb/>
costly and valuable railroads, the construc<lb break="no"/>tion of which had greatly increased their <lb/>
liabilities; but our indebtedness was caused <lb/>
mainly by the purchase of the lands of the <lb/>
Colony, which would not be given up to the <lb/>
Dominion government; and yet for this <lb/>
debt we were credited, while we would give <lb/>
no equivalent to the general government. <lb/>
Yet to the extent of that indebtedness were <lb/>
we offered better terms than those given to <lb/>
Nova Scotia and New Brunswick. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCAU1">Hon. Mr. McAULAY</persName> admitted that the in<lb break="no"/>debtedness of the Provinces was taken <lb/>
equally into account, but thought it was <lb/>
proper to enquire from what cause their <lb/>
indebtedness arose? The other Colonies <lb/>
got into debt by building railroads with <lb/>
borrowed money, and in their construction <lb/>
they circulated the money paid for building <lb/>
them among their people so that they had <lb/>
received a two-fold benefit from them, <lb/>
the use of the roads and then the benefit <lb/>
arising from the circulation of the money. <lb/>
But how was it with us? We had the satis<lb break="no"/>faction of doing the patriotic work of buy<lb break="no"/>ing out our own hands, which were wrongly <lb/>
given away. For the Cunard estate alone <lb/>
this Colony paid £57,000, all of which had <lb/>
walked away from the country; not one <lb/>
shilling if it was circulated among our peo<lb break="no"/>ple, and the same was true of other estates <lb/>
which were purchased by the government <lb/>
of this Island. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> thought the fact had been <lb/>
overlooked by hon. members, that while <lb/>
Nova Scotia and New Brunswick had built <lb/>
these roads they had handed them over to the <lb/>
general government, and to the use of <lb/>
these, we, if in the Dominion, would have a <lb/>
common right, while they cost us nothing. <lb/></p>

<cb/>

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> said that Nova <lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick were gainers <lb/>
by handing their roads over to the general <lb/>
government, for they were not paying <lb/>
working expenses; and he believed there <lb/>
were very few railroads that did pay the <lb/>
cost of working. He was told that one of <lb/>
the best lines in England--that between <lb/>
Liverpool and London--would not pay, if <lb/>
the traffic on it was confined to that between <lb/>
the two cities alone. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> thought the roads in New <lb/>
Brunswick were paying, and even if they <lb/>
were not, it would be no argument against <lb/>
their construction, for they opened up the <lb/>
country and aided in developing its re<lb break="no"/>sources. Public men did not look upon <lb/>
them in the light of a paying matter but in <lb/>
the broader view of the many benefits their <lb/>
construction conferred upon the country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CALL1">Hon. Mr. CALLBECK</persName>--The hon. Leader <lb/>
of the Opposition said he understood him <lb/>
(Mr. Callbeck) to state that when the better <lb/>
terms came down he had said he was pre<lb break="no"/>pared to accept them, but he had been <lb/>
misunderstood, for, under no circumstances, <lb/>
would be content to do so without sub<lb break="no"/>mitting the matter to the people. For his <lb/>
own part, he would never consent to unite <lb/>
with the Dominion while it remained uncon<lb break="no"/>solidated and discontented. Nova Scotia <lb/>
was forced in against the will of her people; <lb/>
nor could he see why it should have been kept <lb/>
in, for it was never united to Canada in <lb/>
accordance with the well-understood wishes <lb/>
of her people. If he understood the hon. <lb/>
member for Charlottetown (Mr. B.) cor<lb break="no"/>rectly, he said if the Americans were dis<lb break="no"/>posed to conquer those colonies, they could <lb/>
do so, but that they would find them too <lb/>
expensive to hold. But until Great Britain <lb/>
gave us to understand that she would not <lb/>
defend us any longer, he would feel dis<lb break="no"/>posed to consider that she intended to <lb/>
stand by us. As to terms, he considered <lb/>
that no matter what they were, it would be <lb/>
found that, like water, they would eventu<lb break="no"/>ally find their level. If we were living in <lb/>
Nova Scotia and found that this Island had <lb/>
received more than a fair share of her pro<lb break="no"/>portions of the general revenue, he was in<lb break="no"/>clined to believe we would feel disposed to <lb/>
make up the difference in some other way. <lb/>
Our Province could not expect to enjoy an <lb/>
advantage at the expense of others. The <lb/>
hon. Leader of the Opposition said yester<lb break="no"/>day he was glad that those on his (Mr. C.'s) <lb/>
side of the house had no gene into figures. <lb/></p>

<pb n="49" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_048.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">49</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> said it would be bet<lb break="no"/>ter if hon. members would reply to state<lb break="no"/>ments in which they did not concur, at the <lb/>
time they were made. He (Mr. H.) alluded <lb/>
to the tabular statement, and said he had <lb/>
no faith in the figures, but that there were <lb/>
something more grand in the question in <lb/>
which, he had faith. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CALL1">Hon. Mr. CALLBECK</persName> stated he had not <lb/>
admitted the principle. He had said that <lb/>
he considered it his duty to give proper <lb/>
consideration to any proposal coming from <lb/>
the British Government had fre<lb break="no"/>quently pledged itself to defend this <lb/>
Colony, but he was not aware that this <lb/>
pledge extended to the Dominion. The <lb/>
inter-colonial railroad, it was said, was <lb/>
being constructed more for military than <lb/>
commercial purposes, hence it would be of <lb/>
little commercial advantage, nor did he think <lb/>
the benefits to be derived from a free trade <lb/>
with the Dominion would prove as impor<lb break="no"/>tant to this Island as some supposed. He <lb/>
was aware that some thought vessels would <lb/>
be allowed to run from one Province to <lb/>
another without having to go to a custom <lb/>
house; but he found that a rule had been <lb/>
laid down by which a vessel on the pay<lb break="no"/>ment of £5 could have a permit so to run; <lb/>
but then the master had to keep a book in <lb/>
which all the shipments were to be entered, <lb/>
which he thought would be found a trouble<lb break="no"/>some arrangement. He admitted that goods <lb/>
coming in, which were the manufacture and <lb/>
production of the Dominion, would pay no <lb/>
duty, but doubted if they would be any <lb/>
cheaper, for he noticed that a spice mill <lb/>
had been put up in one of the Provinces, <lb/>
and a duty of 25 per cent, was placed upon <lb/>
ground spices, as a protection, he supposed, <lb/>
to that mill, and, of course , spices bought <lb/>
there would be that much higher than if <lb/>
this duty had not been imposed. Nor could <lb/>
manufactures be carried on successfully in <lb/>
the Colonies unless a high protective tariff <lb/>
was imposed. He was not aware that <lb/>
goods of any kind could, to any extent, be <lb/>
had on advantageous terms in the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion. A drawback on some goods could be <lb/>
had, it was true, but only when the bills <lb/>
amounted to a certain sum, and these pur<lb break="no"/>chased in one establishment. He knew if <lb/>
the free list was examined carefully, it <lb/>
would be seen that it was wholly limited to <lb/>
articles manufactured in the Dominion. <lb/>
He objected also to the representation in <lb/>
the Senate. The senators in the United <lb/>
States had every six years to return to their <lb/>
constituents. In the Dominion, the ap<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/> 

pointment was for life, and he believed they <lb/>
need not, unless they chose, remain in the <lb/>
Colony they represented. He knew that the <lb/>
Receiver General for Nova Scotia spent a <lb/>
large portion of his time in Ottawa, and <lb/>
when a man had two homes it was hard to <lb/>
say where his interest was. He was far from <lb/>
considering that the taxation to which we <lb/>
should be subjected under confederation, <lb/>
ought to be considered as a bugbear, unless <lb/>
it could be shown that such a correspond<lb break="no"/>ing value was to be received, which he <lb/>
thought could not be proved in this case. <lb/>
Reference had been made to salaries. He <lb/>
knew Mr. Kenny received £1,250 currency, <lb/>
as Receiver General, and did not, he <lb/>
thought, do as much as our Treasurer, who <lb/>
held quite as responsible a position , that was <lb/>
when all things were fairly considered. The <lb/>
Receiver General had a staff of six clerks, <lb/>
each of whom received £500 currency a <lb/>
year, and when one of these, some time ago <lb/>
was found minus the funds which should <lb/>
have been forthcoming he would ask if Mr. <lb/>
Kenny was held responsible? Mr. Kenny <lb/>
was not held accountable, hence he conclud<lb break="no"/>ed that our Treasurer occupied a more re<lb break="no"/>sponsible position than that of the Receiver <lb/>
General of the Dominion. It had been <lb/>
said that if we desired to have faithful offi<lb break="no"/>cials they should be well paid; but he was <lb/>
satisfied that large salaries did not always <lb/>
secure a faithful discharge of duty. A large <lb/>
salary not unfrequently drew men into so<lb break="no"/>ciety and expensive habits of living that <lb/>
were injurious. He believed our public <lb/>
officers had proved themselves as honest <lb/>
and efficient as if their salaries had been <lb/>
higher. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> hoped the hon. member did <lb/>
not bring that forward as an argument why <lb/>
our officials should not receive a fair salary. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CALL1">Hon. Mr. CALLBECK</persName> did not bring it for<lb break="no"/>ward as such, but for the purpose of show<lb break="no"/>ing that it should not be used as an argu<lb break="no"/>ment in favor of confederation. He knew <lb/>
that the municipal taxes in Canada were <lb/>
very high. He noticed that in one county <lb/>
(Dundas) it was as high as one per cent, <lb/>
and that a farmer whose property was <lb/>
valued as being worth £600 was assessed <lb/>
£6. It was true they lowered the tariff <lb/>
from 20 to 15 per cent., but were forced to <lb/>
resort to a tax upon newspapers and <lb/>
other articles to make up this deficiency. <lb/>
Nor could we by accepting the terms offered <lb/>
expect to maintain our schools and other <lb/>
public works without resorting to direct <lb/>
taxation in some shape or other. <lb/></p> 

<p>The third paragraph was then agreed to. <lb/></p>

<p>House adjourned for one hour. </p>
 
<pb n="57" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_056.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">57</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>.—The hon member <lb/>
for Charlottetown had boosted of his <lb/>
courage because he had expressed his <lb/>
opinions freely on confederation, and <lb/>
exposed himself to the attack of some <lb/>
writer in the newspapers. Whether he <lb/>
was pursuing a course contrary or not to <lb/>
the understanding on which he was re<lb break="no"/>turned to this House, was a matter which <lb/>
rested between him and his constituents ; <lb/>
but he (Mr. L.) held that no hon member <lb/>
was deserving of praise for courage in <lb/>
opposing the popular voice. He (Mr. L.) <lb/>
contended that when a representative of <lb/>
the people had changed his opinions <lb/>
through conscientious convictions, and <lb/>
found he could not advocate those prin<lb break="no"/>ciples on which he was elected, his duty <lb/>
was to resign his trust into the hands of <lb/>
those from whom he received it. The <lb/>
hon member's reference to other coun<lb break="no"/>tries in regard to the method of support<lb break="no"/>ing education was a very poor argument <lb/>
indeed. All other countries might be <lb/>
wrong in this matter. We had tested <lb/>
the principle in this Colony of paying <lb/>
the teachers' salaries wholly from the <lb/>
public chest, and we had found it to <lb/>
work well ; this, therefore, was a far <lb/>
better guide for us than what some great <lb/>
country did, or some distinguished man <lb/>
thought. He (Mr. L.) supposed the hon <lb/>
member for Charlottetown had changed <lb/>
his views on confederation, because some <lb/>
great man was in its favor. Great men <lb/>
were only but men, and often erred, <lb/>
consequently we should judge for our<lb break="no"/>selves, and do what we thought was <lb/>
right. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p> 

<cb/>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—The hon. member for <lb/>
Bedeque had begun his remarks by leveling <lb/>
a shot at him (Mr. B.) for opposing the <lb/>
popular voice. That gentleman did not <lb/>
appear to understand the first principles of <lb/>
politics. When a person was not prepared <lb/>
to vote on a question, which had to go be<lb break="no"/>fore the people again, he could not be <lb/>
charged with betraying their trust. When <lb/>
the documents came down from the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment relative to the negotiations with <lb/>
the Canadian delegates, he (Mr. B.) thought <lb/>
it would be found that the members of the <lb/>
Executive themselves had violated their <lb/>
pledges. The hon. member for Tryon had <lb/>
said to-day that those who admitted the <lb/>
principle of union were confederates, and <lb/>
only no-terms men were anti-confederates ; <lb/>
but when he did so, the hon. member for <lb/>
Bedeque had not the manliness to rise and <lb/>
state whether he was with his colleague or <lb/>
not. <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="58" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_058.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">58</fw>  

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. McNEILL</persName>—When this paragraph <lb/>
was read he did not think it was going to <lb/>
call forth such discussion. He pretty much <lb/>
agreed with the views expressed by the <lb/>
hon. member for Charlottetown on this <lb/>
question. His own belief was that if de<lb break="no"/>nominational schools were to be introduced <lb/>
as a part of our educational system ,we <lb/>
would have to give up free schools alto<lb break="no"/>gether. The people of this Island had de<lb break="no"/>rived great benefit from these free schools ; <lb/>
and he thought it was pretty much from <lb/>
their intelligence on this account that they <lb/>
were opposed to confederation. 'To give <lb/>
up our independence for a sum of money <lb/>
would place us in a ridiculous position. <lb/>
He was surprised to find men inclined to <lb/>
accede to the proposal to go into union on <lb/>
account of the paltry sum of $800,000. <lb/>
Some advocates of confederation asked us, <lb/>
if not satisfied with the offers made by <lb/>
Canada, to propose terms. It was not our <lb/>
place to make proposals. Great Britain <lb/>
had wronged us in regard to our lands, and <lb/>
it was from her that we ought to get re<lb break="no"/>dress. We could return this answer to <lb/>
Canada, that we had no quarrel with her, <lb/>
but we had a dispute with the mother <lb/>
country, and we wished to have that set<lb break="no"/>tled first before we could entertain the <lb/>
question of confederation. Look at the <lb/>
case of Newfoundland; some of her poli<lb break="no"/>ticians went up to Ottawa, received an offer <lb/>
for that colony, and came back thinking <lb/>
they would carry the country, but the peo<lb break="no"/>ple rejected the money with disdain. The <lb/>
people of this Island, he thought, would, <lb/>
treat the money offers of the Dominion <lb/>
pretty much in the same manner. He ob<lb break="no"/>served that the Ottawa government had <lb/>
advertised for six schooners to protect the <lb/>
fisheries. It would, however, he feared be <lb/>
poor protection. Probably the attempt <lb/>
would prove something like one set on foot <lb/>
here some years ago, and of which he had <lb/>
heard his father speak. Two boats crews <lb/>
were fitted out from Charlottetown, armed <lb/>
with soythes handled so as to suit instead of. <lb/>
cutlasses, and provided with liquor and <lb/>
other supplies. Thus equipped, they set <lb/>
sail for Souris or some place else, but he <lb/>
believed that when the rum went done, they <lb/> 

<pb n="59" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-10_Page_058.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">59</fw>  

returned home. (Laughter.) He thought <lb/>
it would be pretty much the same way with <lb/>
the Canadian fleet. In concluding his re<lb break="no"/>marks, he would express the hope that the <lb/>
people of this colony would accept of no <lb/>
sum of money to enter confederation. Like <lb/>
our fathers, who cleared away the forests, <lb/>
we should trust in Providence, remain as <lb/>
we were, and not sell our birthright. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> would ask the hon. member <lb/>
what he meant by selling our birthright ? <lb/>
If he could show him (Mr. B.) that we were <lb/>
going to sell our birthright by entering <lb/>
confederation then he would sign the pledge <lb/>
of his friend, the hon. member for Tryon. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. McNEILL</persName> would answer the hon. <lb/>
member for Charlottetownn. We had <lb/>
cleared away the forests, made our own <lb/>
roads, and paid for our lands, and if these <lb/>
things did not make this country our birth<lb break="no"/>right, he did not know what would. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>—The hon. member had <lb/>
made a very neat little speech. But would <lb/>
confederation take away our roads or lands <lb/>
from us?   Would it prevent the sun from <lb/>
shining or the rain from falling upon us, or <lb/>
would it shorten our winters?   <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. McNEILL</persName>—No. (Laughter.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>— Lengthen our winters he <lb/>
should have said. Would not everything <lb/>
connected with the Colony, which we had <lb/>
earned or purchased, be guaranteed to us, <lb/>
by fair and equitable terms? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> thought the hon. <lb/>
member for Charlottetown would find that <lb/>
the eyes of the city mechanics were upon <lb/>
their representative. That gentleman had <lb/>
referred to the educational systems of other <lb/>
countries to find arguments to condemn our <lb/>
own. He (Col. Sec.) could tell that hon.   <lb/>
member that the people of most European <lb/>
nations would be glad to have such a school <lb/>
system as was established in this Island. <lb/>
The member for the City had shown to<lb break="no"/>night the old Tory principles which were <lb/>
ingrained into him, when he had advocated <lb/>
the sustaining of high schools ; as for the <lb/>
others, which were for the good of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple, he did not appear to care whether they <lb/>
went down or not. He (Col. Secretary), <lb/>
contended that too great facilities to obtain <lb/>
a high education were no benefit in a coun<lb break="no"/>try where there was not scope for the em <lb/>
ployment of scholars; it made men more <lb/>
able to do mischief. Where there was a <lb/>
number of educated persons idle about <lb/>
the community, they were sure to be<lb break="no"/>come parasites. The hon member had <lb/>
repeatedly addressed this hon. committee <lb/>

<cb/> 

on confederation, but had never once <lb/>
attempted to show what advantage it would <lb/>
be to the Colony. He kept putting questions <lb/>
to other hon. members,but he never ad<lb break="no"/>vanced any solid arguments himself in favor <lb/>
of union. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.-The hon. Col. Secretary <lb/>
had called him a Tory. He (Mr. B.) was <lb/>
not a Tory ; but he could point out a gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen who was once returned to this House <lb/>
by the assistance of his conservative friends , <lb/>
and after being elected jumped into the Liberal <lb/>
car . The same hon. member had also left the <lb/>
Executive a year or so ago, for some reason <lb/>
which he had never publicly explained, and <lb/>
last summer we found him again returning <lb/>
to the same Executive, without his stating <lb/>
that it had changed its policy, and accept- , <lb/>
ing an office for himself and getting another <lb/>
for his son. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> had never deceived <lb/>
the people. They knew his sentiments at <lb/>
the time referred to, and he had never be<lb break="no"/>trayed them. He had always been with the <lb/>
people. He jumped into the Liberal car <lb/>
after the election which, preceded the in<lb break="no"/>troduction of responsible government, and <lb/>
he was proud of it. <lb/></p> 

<p>The debate was adjourned until to-mor<lb break="no"/>row. <lb/></p> 

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>