<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1871-02-21"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1871-02-21">21 February 1871</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1871">
               <title>The Parliamentary Reporter of Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly</title>.
          <date when="1871"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Examiner</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="35"/>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="40"/>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="43"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_034.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
   
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_038.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_039.hocr.html"/>
               </item>

               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_042.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_043.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-07-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-07-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_034">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_034.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_038">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_038.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_039">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_039.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_042">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_042.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_043">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_043.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1871-02-21_Page_034"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_034.jpg"/>


            <fw type="num">1871</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">35</fw>
            
            
            <p>[<persName ref="pers:DAVI1">Hon. D. Davies</persName>]
     It 
     <lb/>was well known that the question of Confed<lb break="no"/>eration had made a division to the ranks of<lb/>the Conservaties and that the Education<lb/>question did the same, to some extent, for the<lb/>
       
       
            <cb/>
          
          
     Liberals. He had always been in favor of<lb/>the principle of Confederation, but not of<lb/>any hasty action, or of committing the<lb/>country to it unless it was prepared for the<lb/>change. But during his absence in England,<lb/>five years ago, advantage was taken of his<lb/>views on that question, and the result had<lb/>been that he was not then returned, and a<lb/>statement which he had made to the effect<lb/>that he was neglecting his business by attend<lb break="no"/>ing to his Legislative duties, had also been<lb/>used against him. He (Hon. D. Davies)<lb/>could not go to the polls and say he was a no-<lb break="yes"/>terms man, while there were others who<lb/>would kick at terms of any kind. But at the<lb/>late election, his hon. and learned Colleague<lb/>the Attorney General and himself were re<lb break="no"/>turned. After the Election, it was well<lb/>known that one section of the Liberal party<lb/>made overtures to the Palmer wing of the<lb/>Conservatives, and hence, to save themselves<lb/>from annihilation, those with whom he acted<lb/>had to form the present coalition Government.<lb/>The step they took, had, in those ways, been<lb/>forced upon them. He knew that coalition<lb/>Governments were generally strong Govern<lb break="no"/>ments, and it was sometimes said, corrupt<lb/>ones, but he trusted that nothing of that<lb/>kind would then exist, but that due at<lb break="no"/>tention would be given, and regard had to<lb/>the best interests of the country.</p>
     
     
     
     

            <pb n="1871-02-21_Page_038"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_038.jpg"/>
 
     <fw type="dateline">1871</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">39</fw> 
  
  
            <p>[<persName ref="pers:PERR3">Hon. Mr. PERRY</persName>] The hon. member for <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> (Mr. McLean)<lb/>have very well that it was understood when<lb/>the present Government was formed, that the<lb/>question of grants in the Catholic schools was<lb/>not to be melded with the four years, in<lb/>condition that Confederation was then to be<lb/>dropped.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <pb n="1871-02-21_Page_039"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_039.jpg"/>
    
    
            <fw type="num">40</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1871</fw>
            
            
            <p>
     [...] point. He had however pledged himself 
     <lb/>against Confederation, and as for as his vote<lb/>and influence was concerned, he was proposed<lb/>to do all in his power against a scheme which<lb/>the people of this Colony are not proposed to<lb/>accept at present. He (Mr. Perry) would be<lb/>violating his pledge if he should oppose the<lb/>present Government, however they could not<lb/>give a grant to St. Duncan's College ; the<lb/>present Government is composed of gentle<lb break="no"/>men who have pledged themselves against<lb/>Confederation and Sectarian grants, and so<lb/>long as they legistlated for the good of the<lb/>country they would receive his support.<lb/>However, he (Mr. Perry) hoped that the time<lb/>would soon arrive when all denominations<lb/>would agree in enduring Sectarian schools.<lb/>And further if the opposition were sincere in<lb/>giving a grant and would pledge themselves<lb/>to that effect he (Hon. Mr. Perry) would be<lb/>very happy to join them. (Hear hear, from<lb/>several of the hon. members.)<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI1">Hon. D. DAVIES</persName> said that in justice to the<lb/>Roman Catholic members on the Government<lb/>side of the House, he would state that in<lb/>forming the Government, it was distinctl<lb/>understood that these members did not give<lb/>up their principles in reference to grants to<lb/>Catholic schools ; they merely held them in<lb/>abeyance, on condition that Confederation<lb/>would be held in the same way by its sup<lb break="no"/>porters and friends. They say, " We are in<lb/>a minority, and will wait till a change takes<lb/>place in the Protestant mind, in reference to<lb/>the Education Question, but we will not give<lb/>up our opinions in reference to it. " He<lb/>could not see anything discreditable in their<lb/>joining the Conservatives on the conditions<lb/>agreed upon. He had been asked, also, to<lb/>hold his opinion on the Question of Con<lb break="no"/>federation in abeyance, for a time, and agreed<lb/>to do so. But he still held the same views<lb/>on that great Question as he ever had, and<lb/>thought the time would yet arrive when<lb/>Confederation would be accepted by the peo<lb break="no"/>ple. His constituents were opposed to it,<lb/>and he felt bound not to press it upon their<lb/>attention, nor to forward it in any way.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <pb n="1871-02-21_Page_042"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_042.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">42</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER</fw> <fw type="dateline">1871</fw>
      
      
      
            <p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> [...]
               <lb/>
             
     His (Hon. Attorney General's) principles 
     <lb/>
     were the same as they were twelve month 
     <lb/>
     ago, they had not nndergonethe slightest 
     <lb/>
     change. He did not occupy his seat in that 
     <lb/>
     House as a confederete, for he owed his seat 
     <lb/>
     to his anti-confederate constituents , and 
     <lb/>
     would not betray them. He would never 
     <lb/>
    play the same game on confederation which 
     <lb/>the hon. member played upon the Tenant 
     <lb/>League. When the hon. member's sup<lb break="no"/>porters smote him on the one cheek, he 
     <lb/>turned to them the other also. He (Hon. 
     <lb/>Attorney General) was pledged on confeder<lb break="no"/>ation just as the hon. member for Rustice 
     <lb/>had been, and he felt bound to keep first 
     <lb/>pledge. He did not intend to discuss the 
     <lb/>subject either publicly or privately, directly 
     <lb/>or indirectly. He claimed his right to ex<lb break="no"/>press his views on the question on the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple that he would go back to the people at 
     <lb/>the polls for their decision. He would give 
     <lb/>the hon member every liberty to oppose 
     <lb/>him, if he deviated from his principles to 
     <lb/>the breadth of a hair.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. MCNEILL</persName>—I remember when the Hon. 
     <lb/>Attorney General pleaded pathetically for 
     <lb/>Confederation, although he has now changed 
     <lb/>his position with reference to that question. 
     <lb/>The Reform Bill and other great measures of 
     <lb/>British Legislation were not carried by such 
     <lb/>a course of inconsistency. When, sir, in a 
     <lb/>former session of the Legislature, I was twit<lb break="no"/>ted by the Hon. Attorney General with my 
     <lb/>connection with the Tenant League) and had 
     <lb/>complained that the Sheriff oi Queen's Coun<lb break="no"/>ty had libelled the people, the hon. Attorney 
     <lb/>
           
           
            <cb/>
        
        
     General asked why the matter had not been
<lb/>brought before the house, but, when it was
<lb/>so brought up, he dared not going to an in<lb break="no"/>vestigation, but move that it be postponed
<lb/>3 months, in other words dismissed; he had
<lb/>influential friends, when motion in reference
<lb/>to the tenant means he did not care to have
<lb/>criticized in the house, and unfortunately,
<lb/>there were gentlemen on the other side, si<lb break="no"/>milarly situated.  Sir, never in my life did
<lb/>I feel more Perot of my position than when
<lb/>I took my stand at inside the Bar of this House,
<lb/>in company with my eye hon friend the Mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Belfast (Hon. B. Davies) to vindicate
<lb/>the character of the people from the asper<lb break="no"/>sions cast upon them.  I ask, Mr. Chairman,
<lb/>which of the public man of the colony can
<lb/>the people rely on, when we see men of in<lb break="no"/>telligence, education, and high social posi<lb break="no"/>tion advocating one line of policy to-day, and
<lb/>to-morrow, when it may suit their interest
<lb/>or convenience, turn around and support a
<lb/>course directly to reverse?  The hon Att'y
<lb/>General has processed himself a confederate,
<lb/>but now he says, "only make me Att'y Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, and I will be a strong anti-confeder<lb break="no"/>ate as you'll be able to find in the coun<lb break="no"/>try." Oh! filthy here, you have slain your
<lb/>thousands, you have always been an enemy
<lb/>to the patriotism and liberty.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BREC1">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> - The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber has told the house that his constituents
<lb/>Endorsed his views and action, in connection
<lb/>with the Tenants League.  I have no doubt
<lb/>of it, nor of the fact that he owes to that or<lb break="no"/>ganization his see in this house; but my 
<lb/>reference to that body was not intended to
<lb/>supply to be hon Member individually, but
<lb/>to the governments, members of which had
<lb/>encouraged and justified their proceedings
<lb/>which are well known to us all.  With re<lb break="no"/>ference to the question of Confederation my
<lb/>opinion are before the country, and, sir, the
<lb/>pledge I gave to my constituents, I shall
<lb/>faithfully keep.  I told them to the hustings
<lb/>that my views are unchanged, and I pledg<lb break="no"/>ed myself not to vote for confederation un<lb break="no"/>til the question had been submitted to the
<lb/>people at the Polls.  That pledge was frank<lb break="no"/>ly given, and was well understood by my con<lb break="no"/>stituents; but, sir, there are some who will
<lb/>not understand another.  I must leave them
<lb/>in the enjoyment of their own views.  I have
<lb/>not retracted nor been asked to retract a
<lb/>single word of what I stated, and as long as
<lb/>my constituents are satisfied with my can con<lb break="no"/>duct, I am content.  I have exercised my
<lb/>judgment independently; but, did not be
<lb/>hon. member only last year, argued that 
<lb/>the position of members in this house was, mor<lb break="no"/>ally, that of delegates?<lb/> 
               <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <pb n="1871-02-21_Page_043"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-02-21_Page_043.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1871</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">43</fw>
        
        
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. MCNEILL</persName>.—I said that we were sent 
     <lb/>here to make laws and not to destroy the<lb/>constitution of the country. I hope the hon.<lb/>Att'y General will bear that in mind and be<lb/>content to stand or fall by it.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:SINC6">Hon. Mr. SINCLAIR</persName>- [...]<lb/>
               As<lb/>to Confederation, I inferred from what fell<lb/>from the Hon. Atty General that he would<lb/>do nothing in the way of initiating our con<lb break="no"/>nection with Canada, but, Mr. Chairman,<lb/>there are more ways than one of carrying<lb/>out a favorite point, and many a measure<lb/>has been carried indirectly which would<lb/>never have succeeded by direct action. I am<lb/>inclined to think from the Speech that we may<lb/>have Confederation, whether we like it or not<lb/>I have no desire to join Canada and the great<lb/>majority of the people of the Island, are of<lb/>the same way of thinking, but if it shall<lb/>happen that we are weighed down under a<lb/>burden of taxation greater than that of Can<lb break="no"/>ada, it might be desirable to join that Do<lb break="no"/>minion. As I read the paragraph before the<lb/>Committee, I cannot but believe there is<lb/>something more in this railway scheme than<lb/>meets the eye.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>