<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1872-03-09"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1872-03-09">9 March 1872</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1871">
               <title>The Parliamentary Reporter of Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly</title>.
          <date when="1872"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Examiner</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="46"/>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="55"/>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="69"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_046.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_054.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_068.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-07-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-07-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_046">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_046.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_054">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_054.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_068">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_068.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1872-03-09_Page_046"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_046.jpg"/>
           
           <fw type="num">46</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1872</fw>
        
        
            <p>
     They (Messrs. <persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Howlan</persName> and 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD10">McDonald</persName>) said they represented the largest 
     <lb/>
     religious body in the colony. and thought 
     <lb/>
     that some consideration should he given to 
     <lb/>
     their request. It was agreed that the ques<lb break="no"/>tion should he put on the shelf while those 
     <lb/>
     who favored Confederation would do the 
     <lb/>
     same, and no membur of the Government on 
     <lb/>
     either side, had in the smallest iota, since, 
     <lb/>
     violated that not. There was a meeting 
     <lb/>
     held immediately, or soon after, when about 
     <lb/>
     sixteen or seventeen were present and when 
     <lb/>
     they went in they were discussing what the 
     <lb/>
     policy of the Government should be. When 
     <lb/>
     the question of Confederation was sank also.   
     <lb/>He (Mr. B.) had been returned to opppose<lb/>that question for four years, or that if in the<lb/>meantime the matter should come before<lb/>them that no action should be taken until the<lb/>matter was sent to the people at the polls.<lb/>Some gentleman suggested that it should be<lb/>put in writing to which he (Atty. General)<lb/>said "certainly." when Dr. Robertson said<lb/>"put in the School Question too."</p>
     

            <pb n="1872-03-09_Page_054"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_054.jpg"/>
           
           <fw type="num">54</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1872</fw>
        
        
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BREC1">Hon. Attorney General</persName> said that if his 
     <lb/>honor the Speaker attempted to reprimand<lb/>the prisoner at the Bar, without giving him<lb/>a hearing, the consequences might be serious.<lb/>He (Mr. B.) had distinctly stated, last even<lb break="no"/>ing, that the house had no power to arrest<lb/>Mr. Carlton, and that if they attmepted to do<lb/>so, they would place themselves on danger<lb break="no"/>ous ground. Mr Carlton was not bound to<lb/>obey the summons of the House, for they had<lb/>no jurisdiction over him; if the House had<lb/>no power to issue a warrant in this case,<lb/>they had no power to issue a summons<lb/>either. He Mr. B: would ask his honor the<lb/>Speaker in the of British justice not to<lb/>reprimant that, as the House had no<lb/>jurisdiction over him. To carry out the<lb/>wishes of the Opposition in this matter, as<lb/>expressed in their resolution, was like knock<lb break="no"/>ing a man down, and then kicking him for<lb/>falling. If the motion submitted by the<lb/>Opposition be carried over we may be told<lb/>that we are not able to conduct the affairs of<lb/>the country, and the loss of our constitution<lb/>may possibly be the result. He (Mr. B.)<lb/>would be sorry to see our Island taken into<lb/>Confederation because its Legislature did<lb/>not administer justice in such a case as the<lb/>one now before the House. But we should<lb/>remember that it was a little ship-money<lb/>
          
          
         
         
          
          <fw type="dateline">1872</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">55</fw>
        
        
     which cost Charles I. his head, and that it is 
     <lb/>quite possible that this bribe-money may<lb/>cause the loss of our constitution. </p>
    
    
            <pb n="1872-03-09_Page_068"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1872-03-09_Page_068.jpg"/>
    
    
          <fw type="dateline">1872</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">69</fw>
         
         
               <p> [<persName ref="pers:BREC1">Hon. Attorney General</persName>]
     But to-night he had to part 
     <lb/>
     politicts company with his old associate 
     <lb/>
     and former political friend, and hoped his 
     <lb/>
     new found friends would not object to his 
     <lb/>
     strong views on Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. D Davies had been, and was still, 
     <lb/>
     in favor of the policy of Colonial Union, and 
     <lb/>
     saw no reason yet why Confederation was 
     <lb/>
     not desirable. He knew it was the imper<lb break="no"/>ial policy and thought we should not op— 
     <lb/>
     pose it, and thought in the Railway matter 
     <lb/>
     they had evidence of how the country 
     <lb/>
     might be legislated into the Dominion in 
     <lb/>
     the same way. The same thing could be 
     <lb/>
     done; for if the Legislature could pass the 
     <lb/>
     Railway Bill without an appeal to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple, it could do the other in the same 
     <lb/>
     way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Howlan thought the hon. mem-   
     <lb/>
     ber should recollect that there was a dis<lb break="no"/>tinct understanding that such should not 
     <lb/>
     be done. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. D. Davies though then, and was still 
     <lb/>of the same opinion, that they might be<lb/>legislated, as a colony, into the Dominion of<lb/>Canada in the same way. And the thought<lb/>if necessary that we should go into Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. The Dominion Government would<lb/>pay for the Railroad and place the Land<lb/>question of this Island in the same position<lb/>as that of the Dominion. They knew how it<lb/>was in Ireland, and the same might be their<lb/>case too. He believed generous terms would<lb/>be submitted, and that it would be the duty<lb/>and for the interest of the colony to accept<lb/>them. He fully reiprocated the friendly<lb/>of the learned Attorney General.<lb/>THey had been personal friends from their<lb/>boyhood, but it so happened that they took<lb/>different views of the matter, which caused<lb/>them to diverge politically, the one from<lb/>the other. <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>