<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1865-03-31"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1865-03-31">31 March 1865</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1864">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1865, Being the Third Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1865"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Protestant" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="71"/>
</bibl>

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_065.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_066.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_067.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_068.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_069.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_070.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_071.html"/>
</item> 
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-08">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_065">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_065.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_066">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_066.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_067">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_067.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_068">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_068.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_069">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_069.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_070">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_070.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_071">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_071.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="65" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_065.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">65</fw>

<!-- DL 2018-06-08 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--leave us, would be little better than a town council ; we <lb/>
would have this building here merely to look at. As to <lb/>
the General Legislature I consider the representation in it <lb/>
allowed to this Island unfair and unjust. I think the four <lb/>
Lower Provinces, at least, should have as many members <lb/>
in the Upper Branch as Canada. The five representatives <lb/>
allotted to us in the Lower House would not give this <lb/>
Colony much influence there ; but as our population will <lb/>
not increase so rapidly as that of Canada, there is a <lb/>
prospect, through the operation of one clause in the <lb/>
Report, that our five representatives would dwindle down <lb/>
to three. Taking all these points into consideration, <lb/>
therefore, it is clear to me that we have nothing to gain <lb/>
but much to lose by adopting the Quebec scheme. <lb/></p> 

<p>Adjourned. <lb/></p> -->

<head rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, March 31.</head><lb/> 

<p>Debate on Union of Colonies resumed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.— Mr. Speaker: As leader of the <lb/>
Liberal party of this Island, I felt in a peculiar position <lb/>
while attending the Conferences on the question of <lb/>
Colonial Union now before the House, I felt that in <lb/>
acting as a Delegate I had not my own interest merely to <lb/>
look to, but that of a party who have acknowledged me <lb/>
as their leader for nearly eighteen years. And now, Sir, <lb/>
in addressing you I desire to make such explanations as <lb/>
may satisfy my constituents and the party with whom I <lb/>
am connected, in regard to the course which I have pur<lb break="no"/>sued on this question. Explanations of this nature may <lb/>
fairly be expected from me, since I am the only Delegate <lb/>
in this House opposed to the Confederation Scheme of the <lb/>
Quebec Conference—being one against four. It has been <lb/>
stated by former speakers that we all agreed to the scheme <lb/>
while at the Conference. I object to this statement. I <lb/>
admit that we were all unanimous in passing the first <lb/>
resolution of the Report ; but it was only with the under<lb break="no"/>standing that the details of the scheme were to be just to <lb/>
the several Provinces. Those who affirm that there was <lb/>
unanimity at the Conference ground their assertion, I <lb/>
believe, on several speeches delivered at evening meetings. <lb/>
But, Sir, I contend that an occasion graced with the pre<lb break="no"/>sence of ladies—such being the case when I spoke at <lb/>
Ottawa—was not the proper place to attack any person, <lb/>
or take strong exception to any vote passed at the Confer<lb break="no"/>ence. I did not do so then ; but at the Conference a few <lb/>
days before, I said that if the grant for the purchase of <lb/>
the lands of this Colony was not conceded, they might as <lb/>
well strike Prince Edward Island out of the Report alto<lb break="no"/>gether. The public men of Canada knew my views on <lb/>
the subject : this is evidenced by a paragraph which lately <lb/>
appeared in the Toronto <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi>, a paper under the con<lb break="no"/>trol of the Hon. George Brown. The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> says :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The anti-Confederation papers at Halifax are making much <lb/>
of the fact that two of the Prince Edward Island delegates who <lb/>
were at the Quebec Conference have, since their return home, <lb/>
declared against the Confederation scheme. These gentlemen <lb/>
are the Hon. E. Palmer, Attorney General in the present <lb/>
Government, and the Hon. George Coles, a leading member of <lb/>
the Opposition. The <hi rendition="simple:italic">attitude assumed by these gentlemen is <lb/>
but what was to have been anticipated from expressions made <lb/>
by them while in Canada</hi>, so that their hostility to Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion is not any indication of the way in which the scheme has <lb/>
been received by the people of the Provinces. The gentlemen <lb/>
had their minds made up before their constituents had heard the <lb/>
details of the Quebec scheme at all. " <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Even my speech at Ottawa did not give satisfaction to <lb/>
the supporters of Confederation in Canada, for after<lb break="no"/>wards, the brother of the proprietor of the Toronto <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> <lb/>
came to me, at Toronto, and desired that I would not <lb/>
persevere in the sentiment to which I had given <lb/>
utterance, namely, that the scheme would require to be <lb/>
submitted to the people for their approval. All that I <lb/>
said on that occasion which can be construed as favorable <lb/>
to the series of resolutions passed at the Quebec Confer<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

ence, is, that it was creditable to the delegates from so <lb/>
many Provinces that they could agree to draw up such a <lb/>
Report. I still hold to that opinion ; and the British  <lb/>
Government has also acknowledged that it was a credit<lb break="no"/>able Report. If the people, I remarked, were satisfied  <lb/>
with the scheme, I had nothing more to say on the subject. <lb/>
But that I was personally dissatisfied with the new Con<lb break="no"/>stitution is clear from the fact that I refused to sign it. <lb/>
Before I left Canada, the Secretary of the Conference <lb/>
came to me, supposing probably that I was opposed to <lb/>
the Report, and asked me if I would sign the document. <lb/>
I said no. He then answered that if I should agree to <lb/>
sign it he would send it down to Prince Edward Island. <lb/>
I said, " you need not trouble yourself. " I may also <lb/>
mention that Hon. Mr. Gray of New Brunswick, in one of <lb/>
his speeches after his return from Canada, stated that all <lb/>
the delegates at the Conference had signed the Report, <lb/>
and would be bound in honor to support it. This, I <lb/>
thought, was going too far, so I wrote a letter to the <lb/>
newspapers here contradicting the statement, and showing <lb/>
that it was not correct at least as regarded myself. And, <lb/>
Sir, we have been informed during this debate that two <lb/>
others of the delegates from this Island have not signed the <lb/>
document. The absence of their signatures, however, is <lb/>
a matter of little consequence, as they have agreed to the <lb/>
Report, one of them having broadly declared that its <lb/>
principles are just and liberal to Prince Edward Island. <lb/>
It was understood that the proceedings at the Conference <lb/>
should be secret ; but they have been alluded to by <lb/>
delegates at other places, therefore there can be very little <lb/>
impropriety in referring to them in this discussion. I <lb/>
may also mention here that when the proposition in favor <lb/>
of secrecy was first made at the Charlottetown Conference, <lb/>
I objected to it, but stood alone in my opposition. I <lb/>
was then allowed to state the fact to my con<lb break="no"/>stituents. I make these explanations, for it may be <lb/>
necessary in the course of my remarks to refer to the <lb/>
proceedings at the Conference in self vindication. Only <lb/>
two of us, I believe, who were delegates to Quebec, object <lb/>
to the terms of the Report. For this opposition we have <lb/>
been charged as being almost traitors. Indeed it has <lb/>
been affirmed that Anti-unionists are guilty of combining <lb/>
with Americans against British interests. Hear what the <lb/>
Hon. D'Arcy McGee said in the Canadian Legislature on <lb/>
this subject. During the course of his speech on the <lb/>
Confederation question, in replying to some interruption <lb/>
from the opposition benches, he remarked :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The hon. member for North Hastings Mr. (T. C. Wallbridge) <lb/>
seemed to repudiate the idea that American influence had any<lb break="no"/>thing to do with the result of the New Brunswick elections. He <lb/>
had to tell that hon. gentleman that one of these successful can<lb break="no"/>didates was agent for the American line of steamers, the <lb/>
International line, which did all the carrying trade to New <lb/>
Brunswick, and here was not a pound of the stock of that <lb/>
Company held in New Brunswick. (Hear, hear.) <hi rendition="simple:italic">It was in  <lb/>
point of fact a fight—a fair stand-up fight of Yankee interests <lb/>
on the one side and British interests on the other ; and those <lb/>
who were</hi> rejoicing over Mr. Tilley's defeat were in reality <lb/>
rejoicing over the defeat of British interests. It was a contest <lb/>
between prejudice and patriotism ; between ignorance and intel<lb break="no"/>ligence ; between Yankee influence and the broad national <lb/>
principles of British North American policy. (Hear, hear.) <lb/>
Those who rejoiced over this state of things might congratulate <lb/>
themselves if they chose; but it was for the House to stand by <lb/>
the true public opinion of the country. It was for us to show an <lb/>
example of firmness and good faith in carrying out this scheme. <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">It was for us to shew the Empire that we were determined to <lb/>
adhere to our original resolution and that we were not people <lb/>
who would forget our determination in a few days or a few <lb/>
weeks</hi>. " (Cheers.)  <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>I deny these charges. I believe that the Anti-unionists <lb/>
are just as loyal as any Unionist can be. I feel that my <lb/>
loyalty is equally as sincere as that of those who so <lb/>
zealously advocate the Quebec scheme, for I have yet to <lb/>
learn that Great Britain has said we must go into <lb/>

<pb n="66" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_066.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">66</fw>
 
Confederation. All that we have yet heard is the saction <lb/>
of the Colonial Minister to the holding of a Conference in <lb/>
Canada, consisting of representatives from all the Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces to consider the larger scheme of Union, and his <lb/>
opinion that the Report of that Conference upon the <lb/>
whole was creditable to the assembled delegates. And <lb/>
this much too has been accorded evidently to please <lb/>
Canada, owing to the troubles in which her politicians <lb/>
have become involved. What foundation, then, have <lb/>
those for their statements who tell us that we shall be <lb/>
compelled to go into Union ? who say that unless we enter <lb/>
the proposed Confederation we shall not get a single ship <lb/>
or man from the Mother Country to defend us ? The <lb/>
Home Government has given not intimation of the kind. <lb/>
In fact it seems to be passive in regard to the Union <lb/>
movement. The Colonial Minister stated in eflect in one <lb/>
of his despatches that it the people of the Colonies were <lb/>
desirous to enter into a Union, Her Majesty's Government <lb/>
would throw no obstacles in the way. This language <lb/>
conveys no such threat as has been held up by some hon <lb/>
members of this House. Indeed Mr. Cardwell does no <lb/>
appear at all satisfied with some portions of the Report. <lb/>
He has taken exception to the provision with respect to <lb/>
the prerogative of pardon, and to the principle of having <lb/>
a fixed number of nominated life members in the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Council. To the latter principle I made strong <lb/>
objections at the Conference, and fortunately for me 1 <lb/>
also referred to the matter in the public prints before the <lb/>
Colonial Minister's despatch was received. My reason <lb/>
for opposing such a provision was that as the members of <lb/>
the Legislative Council were to be nominated from the <lb/>
existing Councils in the different Provinces, a number of <lb/>
them would be old men, who had been obstructives, and <lb/>
might remain so all their lives, consequently a dead-lock <lb/>
would probably soon occur between the two branches of <lb/>
the Legislature, in which case an appeal would have to <lb/>
be made to the Imperial Government to settle the dispute. <lb/>
They have had quite enough of disputes in Canada <lb/>
already. In that Province, Sir, the parliament buildings <lb/>
have been burned, and the Stars and Stripes thrown out <lb/>
to the winds. Such proceedings, Sir, have never been <lb/>
seen in the Lower Provinces. (Cheers.) And are we now <lb/>
to be told that we must enter a Union with them, and <lb/>
submit to such taxes as they may choose to impose? The <lb/>
amount to be allowed this Colony under the proposed <lb/>
scheme is some £35,000 a year, and more than this we <lb/>
are not to receive for local purposes though our revenue <lb/>
should increase to £200,000. but does Mr. Galt say <lb/>
respecting allowances to the local governments ? In <lb/>
explaining this part of the Report he remarks:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Now one objection to confederation was made on the ground <lb/>
of expense, and in order to meet this, every effort had been <lb/>
made to reduce the cost of the Local Governments, so that the <lb/>
local machinery should be as little costly as possible, for it <lb/>
would not do to aflront the intelligence of the people, and tell <lb/>
them we had devised an expensive kind of machinery to do a <lb/>
very insignificant amount of work. <hi rendition="simple:italic">The gentlemen from the <lb/>
Lower Provinces had been asked what reductions they could <lb/>
make in the Government of the several colonies, and the figures <lb/>
he was about to give would be most satisfactory as showing the <lb/>
disposition of those gentlemen, who had reduced their require<lb break="no"/>ments to the lowest sum</hi>. In her estimate of outlay for 1864 for <lb/>
objects of local character the Province of Nova Scotia had pro<lb break="no"/>vided for an expenditure of no less than $667,000, but had <lb/>
undertaken to perform the same service in future under a con<lb break="no"/>federation at $371,000, or a reduction of 40 per cent. The <lb/>
expenditure of New Brunswick in 1864 for the same objecis was <lb/>
estimated at $404,000. From causes explained at the time and <lb/>
shown to be satisfactory, she proposed to reduce the expenditure <lb/>
to $353,000, and at the same time undertook within ten years <lb/>
tn make a further reduction of $63,000; making a total reduc<lb break="no"/>tion to $290,000. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prince Edward Island would reduce her <lb/>
expenditure from</hi> $170,000 <hi rendition="simple:italic">to</hi> $124,000, <hi rendition="simple:italic">and Newfoundland <lb/>
from </hi>$479,000 <hi rendition="simple:italic">to</hi> $350,000. <hi rendition="simple:italic">In regard to Upper and Lower <lb/>
Canada he would not undertake to say what reduction would <lb/>
be made ; but he could show that under the scheme proposed they <lb/>
would have the means of limiting the present outlay which was, <lb/>

<cb/>

taking the average of the last four years, </hi>$2,021,979. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Besides <lb/>
that there would be an additional item brought against them for <lb/>
the interest on the excess of their debt over that of the other Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, making their full local charge </hi>$2,260,149, <hi rendition="simple:italic">which was <lb/>
the present outlay of Canada for works which would not <lb/>
become a charge under a confederation. The outlay of all the <lb/>
provinces being however greater than their local revenues it be<lb break="no"/>came necessary to make provision out of the general Fund for <lb/>
the purpose of enabling their Local Legislatures to carry on <lb/>
the machinery of Government. It was proposed to take away <lb/>
from them every source of revenue they possessed except minor <lb/>
local revenues, and then to give them from the public chest a <lb/>
sufficient subsidy to enable the machinery to work</hi>. The esti<lb break="no"/>mate was formed on the wants of Nova Scotia. It was at first <lb/>
proposed to form it on the wants of New Brunswick, but these <lb/>
were found greater than those of the former, which had conse<lb break="no"/>quently been taken as the basis. The estimate was that 80 <lb/>
cents a head on the population of Nova Scotia would be suffi<lb break="no"/>cient to enable her to work her local system. She would want <lb/>
$264,000. In the case of Upper Canada, 80 cents a head was <lb/>
considerably more than she wanted at the present day, and in <lb/>
the case of Lower Canada was at least adequate with the pre<lb break="no"/>sent local funds that would become available to her. But it was <lb/>
felt that in giving a subsidy from the public chest it was impossible <lb/>
to draw a distinction between one part of the country and ano<lb break="no"/>ther. But it was not intended to hold out any inducement to future <lb/>
extravagance to local Governments, but it was hoped that by <lb/>
the operation of natural causes such a check would be put upon <lb/>
expenditures as would bring them down to the lowest point, or <lb/>
at least prevent them from becoming lavish. Therefore the <lb/>
subsidy proposed to be given to local legislatures was fixed, not <lb/>
at an increasing rate according to population, but at the rate   <lb/>
which existed at the census of 1861. By this means, as the <lb/>
population increased, the subsidy would not increase with it. <lb/>
Upper and Lower Canada would thus get within a fraction of <lb/>
two million dollars, and when their population increased to five <lb/>
millions instead of two and a half, would get no more. <hi rendition="simple:italic">If they <lb/>
increased their expenses in proportion to the growth of popula<lb break="no"/>tion they would be obliged to resort to direct taxation; and he <lb/>
thought they might trust the people themselves to keep a sharp <lb/>
watch over the local Governments lest they should resort to di<lb break="no"/>rect taxation. He thought no surer check could be put upon <lb/>
them than thus fixing the grants they were respectively to <lb/>
receive</hi>." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Now, Sir, this is the opinion of the Finance Minister of <lb/>
Canada, who may be considered as good authority in <lb/>
regard to the contemplated working of the Quebec <lb/>
scheme; and he urged it in an address to his own <lb/>
constituents at Sherbrooke, as a reason why they should <lb/>
gladly accept that scheme. Here we may see the pitiable <lb/>
condition to which this Island would be reduced under <lb/>
Confederation,- our revenues taken away, scarcely <lb/>
enough allowed us to work the machinery of the local <lb/>
government, and should more money be required when <lb/>
our population increased, it would have to be raised by <lb/>
direct taxation. The people of this Colony were battling <lb/>
four years to gain responsible government, and since <lb/>
obtained, I believe it has given general satisfac<lb break="no"/>tion. But, Sir, were we to adopt this Report, it <lb/>
would deprive us of our constitution and leave us no <lb/>
corresponding benefit in return. It is urged that as a <lb/>
compensation for our less we would become part of a <lb/>
great union that in time would form a mighty nation. <lb/>
But I ask what greater nationality can we enjoy than that <lb/>
with which it is our pride and privilege at present to be <lb/>
connected? What greater flag can wave over us than the <lb/>
time-honored banner of Old England ? I do not think <lb/>
that Great Britain wishes to throw us off; on the contrary <lb/>
I believe that her statesmen see that the separation of <lb/>
the Colonies from the parent state would cause trouble. <lb/>
Sir, I look upon this talk about the Mother Country <lb/>
casting us off from her apron strings, and this shakin of <lb/>
the stars and stripes in our face, as only stories intended <lb/>
to frighten the timid. Let us remain true to the Mother <lb/>
Country and she will stand by us. Separate as we are <lb/>
from the other Colonies, our hands are just as strong and <lb/>
our hearts as willing to aid in the defence of the Empire, <lb/>
as they could be under any scheme of political union <lb/>

<pb n="67" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_067.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">67</fw>

whatever. The union which I advocated was one that <lb/>
would give is inter-colonial free trade and a uniformity <lb/>
of currency. But here is this Report we have a constitu<lb break="no"/>tion under which we may be taxed at any rate the <lb/>
Canadians think proper. At present we hold the power <lb/>
of taxation in our own hands ; under Confederation, it <lb/>
would be placed almost entirely beyond our control, as <lb/>
well as the power to say what portion of these taxes im <lb/>
posed upon the people of the Colony should be expended <lb/>
for objects in which they are immediately interested. <lb/>
To revert to the meaning of the Conference at Charlotte<lb break="no"/>town, I may say that the Government having behaved so <lb/>
handsomely to me by giving me a commission as a <lb/>
delegate without asking my compliance to any particular <lb/>
course, I was disposed not to persist in some of my views. <lb/>
if the administration of the day were inclined to enter <lb/>
the proposed Union. I yielded more of my principles <lb/>
than I would ever do on such an occasion again. When <lb/>
the Canadian delegates came down to the Conference the <lb/>
chief points which they laid down were representation by <lb/>
population for the Lower House, and a nominated Upper <lb/>
House to consist of 60 members—20 for Upper Canada, <lb/>
20 for Canada East, and 20 for the Lower Provinces. <lb/>
Representation by population, however appeared to be <lb/>
the leading principle for which they contended. I <lb/>
enquired what they would be willing to concede to us for <lb/>
giving up the privilege of taxing ourselves, and for <lb/>
handing over the revenue ; and they asked what I thought <lb/>
would be fair. I said £200,000, sterling, or £300,000, <lb/>
currency : and that this money should be placed into our <lb/>
land funds, entirely at the control of the Colony for the <lb/>
purchase of proprietors' estates. This proposition, I <lb/>
understood, was assented to. I had also private con<lb break="no"/>versations afterwards with Hon. Mr. Brown and Hon. <lb/>
Mr. Cartier, and they admitted the justice of the claim. <lb/>
With the impression that a grant to the amount, and on <lb/>
the conditions which I have stated, was to be given to <lb/>
this Colony for the purchase of lands, I did not offer that <lb/>
opposition at Quebec to some of the first clauses of the <lb/>
Report, which I otherwise would have done. I found <lb/>
that two of the leading members of our Government were <lb/>
in favor of Union, and providing that anything like fair <lb/>
terms were allowed this Island, I was disposed to throw <lb/>
no obstacle in the way. I little thought then, however, <lb/>
that such a constitution as this was to be brought down <lb/>
here. We had been in Conference only a few days when <lb/>
the question of representation in the Upper Branch came <lb/>
up for consideration. On account of the Newfoundland <lb/>
delegates taking part in the proceedings, and it being <lb/>
proposed to give that Colony 4 members in the Legislative <lb/>
Council, the Canadian ministers retired into their council <lb/>
chamber, and returned with the proposition that 24 <lb/>
members should be allowed to each of the two sections of <lb/>
that Province. Lower Canad stood out for equal <lb/>
representation in the Upper Branch as a security against <lb/>
the superior influence which the Upper Province would <lb/>
possess in the Lower House on the principle of represen<lb break="no"/>tation by population. When the question of representation <lb/>
in the House of Commons came up for discussion, this <lb/>
principle was ably and strenuously contended for by the <lb/>
Hon. George Brown ; and well it might, for he knew that <lb/>
it would enable Upper Canada to maintain the control of <lb/>
the General Legislature for ever. Representation by <lb/>
population will give the two Canadas 100 of a majority <lb/>
over all the Lower Provinces in the House of Commons, <lb/>
and by each of the Canadas having as many members in <lb/>
the Legislative Council as the whole of their eastern <lb/>
sisters, they will together always command a majority <lb/>
there of 24 over us, so that the only principle on which <lb/>
we, in the Maritime Colonies, can expect justice will be <lb/>
through the quarrels of the two western Provinces. In <lb/>
view of this, I ask what prospect is there for us if we <lb/>
give up our revenue, but to put our hands in our pockets <lb/>
and pay our own expenses. We cannot hope to contend <lb/>
with the influence which will be brought the bear against <lb/>
us in Canada. What did we see in Toronto but an <lb/>

<cb/>

establishment fitted up with every convenience, which was <lb/>
presented to the Hon. Mr. Brown in consideration of his <lb/>
advocacy of Upper Canada's interests ? And then again <lb/>
in Lower Canada, the Hon. D'Arcy McGee has been <lb/>
presented with a house, furnished complete to the silver <lb/>
plate on the table, for his advocacy of the interests of <lb/>
Montreal. These examples show what is to be gained by <lb/>
able and persevering politicians in Canada ; but here we <lb/>
have no reward save the sense of right in defending the <lb/>
interests of our country. (Cheers.) It has been said by <lb/>
some of the advocates of the Quebec scheme that we <lb/>
should bot blame the Canadians if it contains objectionable <lb/>
provisions, for, at the Conference, votes were taken by <lb/>
Provinces. They were not at fault in all cases ; in a few <lb/>
instances the delegates from the Lower Provinces were <lb/>
most to blame. Several of the Canadians were in favor of <lb/>
the elective principle for the Legislative Council ; but <lb/>
nearly all the delegates from the Lower Provinces declared <lb/>
against it. They seemed to be carried away with the idea <lb/>
of the members of the Upper House being taken from the <lb/>
existing Legislative Councils in the several Colonies, and <lb/>
voted that they should be appointed for life. On this <lb/>
question the delegates from the other Lower Provinces <lb/>
acted in a most selfish manner. They even agreed to the <lb/>
Canadian proposition that the number of Councillors should <lb/>
be fixed. This, as I have already stated, I consider a <lb/>
very objectionable feature in the new constitution. We <lb/>
know that in Nova Scotia they had to break through the <lb/>
warrant of Her Majesty and appoint additional Councillors <lb/>
to carryresponsible government. And we also know that <lb/>
in Britain it is sometimes found necessary to create new <lb/>
Peers in order to carry certain measures. But I wish to <lb/>
explain further in regard to the action taken in the Con<lb break="no"/>ference on the question as to whether the Legislative <lb/>
Council should be elective or nominative. After the <lb/>
motion in favor of making it elective was lost—as I held <lb/>
the opinion that if it were not elective, it ought to be <lb/>
constituted, as nearly as possible, on that principle—I <lb/>
submitted a resolution to test the Conference on the <lb/>
point. When I did so, I was under the impression that it <lb/>
would be placed on record. During the first few days <lb/>
after the Delegates met, all motions were put down, and also <lb/>
the names of the movers and seconders, the understanding <lb/>
being that business was to be conducted according to the <lb/>
practice of the Canadian Parliament. Subsequently, <lb/>
however, it was agreed that the votes should be taken by <lb/>
Colonies, and that no record should be kept of the <lb/>
proceedings. But to show that the clause as it stands in <lb/>
the Report did not pass without an effort on my part to <lb/>
modify it, I will read the resolution which I submitted : <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That at the first and all subsequent elections of <lb/>
members to serve in the Upper Branch of the Federal Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, they shall be chosen to a majority of both branches of <lb/>
the Local Legislatures from such properly qualified persons in <lb/>
the Colony as shall be of upwards of thirty years of age ; one-<lb break="yes"/>half of the said Council to go out every four years after the first <lb/>
election. Those who shall go out at the end of the first four <lb/>
years to be decided by lot, and the drawing to take place during <lb/>
the first Session of the Federal Legislature." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>I considered it advisable that the men who should repre<lb break="no"/>sent each Province in the Legislative Council, as they <lb/>
would be few in number, ought to be appointed by, and <lb/>
possess the confidence of, both branches of the local <lb/>
legislature. This provision I deemed especially neccessary <lb/>
as regarded the interests of this Island, for it is extremely <lb/>
doubtful, should the Union take place, whether we shall <lb/>
ever have a singly representative in the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment ; and if otherwise, we at least cannot expect more <lb/>
than one. My motion, however, was lost. I will not <lb/>
accuse my brother delegates from this Island, who voted <lb/>
against it, of being actuated by the same motives as the <lb/>
majority from the other Provinces evidently were. These <lb/>
saw the difficulty of the Confederation scheme receiving <lb/>
the sanction of the present Legislative Councils of the <lb/>
several Provinces unless their leading members felt secure <lb/>

<pb n="68" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_068.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">68</fw>

of a seat in the Upper House of the General Legislature, <lb/>
therefore they provided that the Legislative Councillors <lb/>
of the Federal Parliament should be nominated from the <lb/>
existing Councils. To ensure as much unanimity, also, <lb/>
as possible at the Conference, a clause was thrown in to <lb/>
the effect that due regard should be had to the claims of <lb/>
the members of the Legislative Council of the Opposition <lb/>
in each Province. But this provision will be of little <lb/>
account, for after the divisions which the discussion of <lb/>
the Confederation question has caused, I think it will be <lb/>
difficult to tell how individuals stand with respect to <lb/>
parties. When I saw the drift of the whole section in <lb/>
regard to the constitution of the Legislative Council as it <lb/>
now stands in the Report, I strongly expressed the hope <lb/>
that the delegates would except this Island from such a <lb/>
piece of corruption. Again with respect to our Local <lb/>
Legislature under the Confederation scheme, what would <lb/>
it amount to ! We would be a laughing stock to the <lb/>
world. The City Council would be a king to such a <lb/>
Legislature. In this House scarcely anything would be <lb/>
left us to do, but to legislate about dog taxes and the <lb/>
running at large of swine. Some hon members have <lb/>
referred to the great advantage of this Colony being <lb/>
allowed to retain its local legislature. Probably they <lb/>
intend to remove to Canada themselves, and care little <lb/>
about what they leave behind them. I will now turn to <lb/>
the financial part of the Report. When the Committee on <lb/>
finance was appointed at the Conference, I was so satisfied <lb/>
that the proposition for a grant of £200,000, sterling, to <lb/>
this Colony would be carried out, that I scarcely gave <lb/>
the appointment any consideration. But, Sir, when the <lb/>
committee reported at the Conference Board, I was <lb/>
struck with amazement, and expressed myself very freely <lb/>
to that effect. At my suggestion it was resolved that the <lb/>
committee should reconsider their scheme. But, Sir, I <lb/>
believe that my objections to the committee's report <lb/>
aroused the delegates from Newfoundland and New <lb/>
Brunswick, for when it was brought in again next <lb/>
morning a subsidy was provided for each of these Colonies, <lb/>
but it did not include any allowance for this Island. <lb/>
Newfoundland received a liberal consideration at the <lb/>
hands of the committee, the sum guaranteed to her being <lb/>
$150,000 annually. The Report says that this allowance is <lb/>
for the surrender of her mines and minerals and public lands <lb/>
to the General Government ; but in reality it was given to <lb/>
that Colony on account of the plea put forth by the New<lb break="no"/>foundland delegates that their people were, to a great <lb/>
extent, paupers. The Colonial Secretary informed us at <lb/>
the Town meeting that the grant to Newfoundland was <lb/>
made in consideration of her revenue being nearly wholly <lb/>
derived from customs' duties, the relinquishment of which <lb/>
would leave her without any local income. But I ask <lb/>
what are the local revenues of this Island ? Would we <lb/>
not be nearly in the same position as Newfoundland if <lb/>
our revenue from duties were given up to the General <lb/>
Government ! Then New Brunswick, too, received a <lb/>
consideration to induce her to enter the Uuion, namely. <lb/>
the respectable sum of $63,000 a year for ten years. This <lb/>
grant, no doubt, was obtained through the able advocacy of <lb/>
Hon. Mr. Tilley, who was on the committee as finance <lb/>
minister for that Province. And, Sir, I am not much <lb/>
surprised that the £200,000, sterling, was not secured <lb/>
for this Island, since I heard the Colonial Secretary, who <lb/>
acted on the financial committee for this Colony, declare <lb/>
that he considered the terms of the Report just and liberal <lb/>
to Prince Edward Island. When I objected to the report <lb/>
of the financial committee on the ground that no grant <lb/>
was to be given to this Colony, the Hon. George Brown said <lb/>
that more money was already allowed us than we would know <lb/>
what to do with. And no wonder that he said so, when the <lb/>
delegate from this Island, who assisted to draw up the financial <lb/>
arrangement, affirms that it is liberal. I shall next refer to the <lb/>
subject of expenses, and show that our taxation must be greatly <lb/>
increased. Besides having to tax ourselves for local improve<lb break="no"/>ments, we will have to bear a share of the expenses of Canada, <lb/>
as she is unable to meet them now, and will be less able to do <lb/>
so under Confederation, for they will be much heavier than at <lb/>

<cb/>

present. In the matter of defences alone the outlay will be <lb/>
enormous. What says Colonel Jervois' report ? I will read <lb/>
an extract from the Quebec <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chronicle</hi> of March 17, 1865, <lb/>
which, after giving some remarks of the London <hi rendition="simple:italic">Times</hi> on that <lb/>
report, freely admits that Canada is unable to undertake the <lb/>
share of these defences assigned her. The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chronicle</hi> remarks ; <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Turn we now for a brief space to the consideration of that <lb/>
portion of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Times'</hi> article having reference to the preparation <lb/>
for defence. There is something in it so naive, and at the <lb/>
same time so thoroughly selfish, that we hardly know whether <lb/>
to be most amused or most contemptous. Speaking of the <lb/>
fortifications which Colonel Jervois's report says are necessary <lb/>
for effectual defence, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Times</hi> says-- </p> 

<p>"'They are no trifles, indeed. Canada, though with but a <lb/>
small population, has a long frontier ; in fact, it may be des<lb break="no"/>cribed as being all frontier, and as being vulnerable all over. <lb/>
There is hardly a village of a farm in the country that is more <lb/>
than a few days' march from some spot which may be reached <lb/>
at once by a party of Federal soldiers. Hence the magnitude <lb/>
of the works, which if executed by the Provinces will be a rea <lb/>
financial burden to them, and if takes in hand by as will add <lb/>
considerably to our estimates for years to come. Colonel Jer<lb break="no"/>vois says that he regards the works for the defence of Montreal <lb/>
and Quebec as being of the most pressing importance. The <lb/>
cost of these at Quebec is to be £200,000, of those at Mon<lb break="no"/>treal of £443,000, and the armaments at those places will cost <lb/>
about £100,000. The works of fortification recommended at <lb/>
Kingston, Toronto and Hamilton will cost about £500,000, and <lb/>
the armaments for those places about £100,000. Thus on, for<lb break="no"/>tifications for Canada alone it is proposed to expend £1,343,000, <lb/>
which any one acquainted with the history of such matters is <lb/>
well aware will expand to at least a couple of millions. Now, <lb/>
of this sum Her Majesty's Government propose to supply £200,<lb break="no"/>000--the amount necessary for fortifying Quebec. This is "an <lb/>
Imperial fortress ;" it was the scene of one of the most cele<lb break="no"/>brated of English victories, and has so wide a reputation as one <lb/>
of the strong places of the world that the national honor is com<lb break="no"/>mitted to maintaining it. We have no desire to quarrel with <lb/>
the decision of the Goverument. Whether the Canadian Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment will really spend half a million on fortifying Montreal, <lb/>
as Lord de Grey expects, we very much doubt, for there is a <lb/>
great difference between calling out Volunteers and Militia at a <lb/>
time of excitement, and taxing the community to raise masses of <lb/>
earthworks and put guns in position. If the fortification of <lb/>
Quebec by England be looked upon as part of an arrangement <lb/>
between the Mother Country and the Colony, then we suppose <lb/>
we must submit and pay the £200,000, or whatever more the <lb/>
works may cost. But we cannot affect to say that it will be <lb/>
done with any enthusiasm.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"Any one acquainted with such matters, we are told, well <lb/>
knows that these fortifications will cost two millions sterling. <lb/>
Of this sum the Times considers two hundred thousand, or one-<lb break="yes"/>fifth, all, and more, than Great Britain's share of the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture. And this view of the relative responsibilities forces us to <lb/>
return to the cause which necessitates the outlay. Again then, <lb/>
we say, Canada has no quarrel with her powerful neighbor, nor <lb/>
would have but as a dependency, an outlaying portion of the <lb/>
British Empire, a weak point, vulnerable and easily assailable. <lb/>
That we are all this is no fault of ours ; but says the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Times</hi>, <lb/>
" you must take the consequences, you must fortify the weakest <lb/>
points, and England will undertake that which requires the <lb/>
least expenditure." But wherefore must we ? Suppose we are <lb/>
not able ? How then ? And most assuredly we are not. Two <lb/>
millions less one-fifth--£1,800,000 sterling ! Something more <lb/>
for armament and militia, and we shall reach perhaps some<lb break="no"/>what over the original two millions--a sum as nearly as may <lb/>
be equal to a pound sterling per head of the whole population, <lb/>
or five dollars for every man, woman and child in the Province <lb/>
Gentlemen of Tooley Street, it can't be done. If Canada <lb/>
wants defending England must defend her." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Now there is the opinion of ones of the Canadian newspapers, <lb/>
and that of the London <hi rendition="simple:italic">Times</hi>. About two million pounds, <lb/>
sterling, will be required for fortifications, and of this sum <lb/>
Great Britain will only provide £200,000, leaving an amount to <lb/>
be raised by Canada, together with the armaments she will have <lb/>
to provide, equal to five dollars per head of her population. <lb/>
This sum would be more than enough ; yet it is not all that <lb/>
would be required. In connections this subject I will read <lb/>

<pb n="69" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_069.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">69</fw>

the following extract from the Hamilton <hi rendition="simple:italic">Weekly Times</hi>, another <lb/>
Canadian Journal : <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Equally necessary as the construction of the fortifications <lb/>
will be the creation of an outlet to the sea-board. In case of <lb/>
war with the United States, we would have no means of com<lb break="no"/>municating with the outside world save by the St. Lawrence. <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">At the best this would</hi> be unsatisfactory, for it would be liable to <lb/>
be only open to us during the summer months. In winter we <lb/>
could make no use of it, and would be compelled to obtain a <lb/>
new route to the sea independent of that which in time of peace <lb/>
we enjoy through United States territory. The intercolonial <lb/>
railway would be an absolute necessity. Saying nothing as to <lb/>
the infinite difficulty, if not impossibility, that would be <lb/>
experienced in keeping such a line open in the face of a vigilant <lb/>
and powerful foe, we would refer at present only to its cost. <lb/>
The estimate furnished is that it can be built for $15,000,000, <lb/>
and the amount that Canada would be called on to pay would be <lb/>
$6.000,000,—<hi rendition="simple:italic">the balance to be provided by the Maritime <lb/>
Provinces</hi>. This, together with the construction of fortifications, <lb/>
would have to be proceeded with at once." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>These works, it is said, must be undertaken at once, but it will <lb/>
take some years to complete them ; and does any person sup<lb break="no"/>pose that if the Americans are going to attack the Colonies they <lb/>
will wait until we are prepared ? Sir, this whole talk about <lb/>
invasion from the United States I believe to be a will-o'-the <lb/>
wisp got up to frighten us into Confederation. But let us <lb/>
proceed with the calculation of expenses. The Confederated <lb/>
Provinces would set out with a debt of $25 per head : fortifica<lb break="no"/>tions will add at least $5 per head more, and gunboats and <lb/>
other naval armaments probably an equal sum. Then there is the <lb/>
Intercolonial railway, which will cost at least $15,000,000, and <lb/>
add a further debt of $5 per head of the population. The <lb/>
enlargement of the Canals is another project, requiring a draft on <lb/>
the finances, which is to be proceeded with as soon as practicable. <lb/>
This work will add not less than other $5 per head to the <lb/>
general debt, and what with the opening up of the North West <lb/>
Territory, and other expenses which I have not enumerated, <lb/>
will run up the debt to $60 per head of the entire population of <lb/>
the Confederate Provinces. We have been informed during this <lb/>
debate that the debt of the United States now amounts to $125 <lb/>
per head of her people. But this debt was caused by a pro<lb break="no"/>tracted war. Our debt of $60 per head would be incurred <lb/>
during peace ; and should war break out with the States, even <lb/>
for a short time, our debt would soon be equal to theirs. I <lb/>
believe that a few hundred pounds spent on a friendly delegation <lb/>
to Washington would save millions of dollars, and do much <lb/>
more to preserve peace between the two countries than all the <lb/>
fortifications which could be built. All these expenses to which <lb/>
I have referred, a large portion of which will have to be borne <lb/>
by the General Government should Union take place, shew <lb/>
clearly that our taxation under Confederation must be very <lb/>
heavy indeed. But some say that the people of this Island are <lb/>
too lightly taxed. I admit that were the money spent among <lb/>
themselves in local improvements, perhaps they would not <lb/>
suffer by a little higher taxation ; but when the money is to be <lb/>
taken away and spent in other Provinces, it quite alters the <lb/>
case. This House has just voted £50,000 to aid tenants in <lb/>
purchasing their farms ; Sir, we would be acting more wisely to <lb/>
vote £150,000 for this purpose than to enter the Union. The <lb/>
£50,000 which we have voted this year would be nearly the <lb/>
amount we would lose every year under Confederation. In <lb/>
Canada they have stamp duties and other taxes which we in <lb/>
this Island know nothing about ; and once united with that <lb/>
country they would send down their collectors to gather up the <lb/>
money and carry it off. Talk of our young men rising to <lb/>
judgeships, and to be premiers in Canada ; why, Sir, they have <lb/>
far too many hangers on of their own, for our youth ever to <lb/>
expect any favors at their hands. The politicians in that <lb/>
Province are sometimes put to their wits and how to provide <lb/>
snug berths for persons they wish to shelve out of their way. A <lb/>
little transaction of this kind occurred when the delegates were <lb/>
there. A member of the Legislature was appointed to a judge<lb break="no"/>ship under the Stamp Act, in order to make room for the <lb/>
Provincial Secretary, who had lost his election in the district <lb/>
which he formerly represented. Under Confederation such <lb/>
work would, no doubt, be carried on to a much greater extent, <lb/>
and amid the intriguing of Canadian office seekers on the spot, <lb/>
the young aspirants in Lower Provinces would stand very <lb/>

<cb/>

little chance of success. I wish now to refer to exaggerated <lb/>
statements which have been made by union advocates respecting <lb/>
the prosperity of Canada. This attempt has been so ably <lb/>
exposed by Hon. Mr. Currie, a member of the Canadian <lb/>
Legislative Council, in his speech before that body on the <lb/>
Confederation question, that I think I will be excused for <lb/>
reading his remarks. Mr. Currie said :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"But speaking of the Lower Provinces, he was really <lb/>
afraid that some public men down there were disposed to <lb/>
exaggerate the advantages of a Union with Canada, just as <lb/>
some of ours seemed prone to magnify the riches of the <lb/>
Lower Provinces. If we were going into a partnership, <lb/>
which he hoped would last if entered into—(hear, hear,) — <lb/>
we should not attempt to deceive each other, for if the people <lb/>
found they had been deceived, the compact would be short-<lb break="yes"/>lived. To give honorable members some idea of the manner <lb/>
in which the subject was presented by leading men in the <lb/>
provinces, he would read them an extract from the speech of <lb/>
a Mr. Lynch, at a large meeting in Halifax, as reproduced <lb/>
by one of the organs of the Government there." <lb/></p> 

<p>"Hon. Mr CAMPBELL—What organ?" <lb/></p> 

<p>"Hon. Mr. CURRIE—They had so many organs they did not <lb/>
seem to know them all. (Laughter) He would now read <lb/>
from the speech in question:— <lb/></p> 

<p>"'But we are told by others that we had better have <lb/>
nothing to do with Canada, because she is bankrupt. Canada <lb/>
bankrupt! I wish we were all such bankrupts. She is <lb/>
overflowing with wealth. This is now rapidly developing <lb/>
itself, and must eventually place her among the first nations <lb/>
of the earth. I have travelled over and examined that great <lb/>
country, and it would take more than all the time allotted to <lb/>
me to tell you of her wealth and resources. Her rivers are <lb/>
among the largest in the world, and her lakes are mighty <lb/>
inland oceans. I never had any idea of their extent until 1 <lb/>
stood on the shore of Lake Erie, saw before me a large square <lb/>
rigged ship, and was told that such was the class of vessels <lb/>
that navigated those waters. Why, sir, 7,000,000 tons of <lb/>
shipping trade upon those mighty lakes. Again, look at the <lb/>
growth of the population. Sixty years ago it was 60,000, <lb/>
new it is 3,000.000. Upper Canada doubled her population <lb/>
in ten years, and Toronto, in the beginning of this century <lb/>
the abode of the red man of the forest, is now one of the <lb/>
finest cities of British America, with a population of 40,000. <lb/>
The soil is of the richest description, indeed it is only too <lb/>
much so. In some places rich alluvial deposit is found to <lb/>
the depth of 50 feet, and in many instances lands have <lb/>
yielded their crops for years without the aid of a spadeful <lb/>
of manure. Canada has not only the greatest yield but the <lb/>
best wheat in America. It is a. well-known fact that the <lb/>
people of the United States in exporting their best flour mix <lb/>
it to a large extent with Canadian wheat, and in order to <lb/>
give you an idea of the increased growth of it I would inform <lb/>
you that while in ten years the wheat crop increased in the <lb/>
States 50 per cent. (an immense increase), it in the same <lb/>
time in Canada increased 400 per cent. The average crop <lb/>
is equal to that of the best wheat growing countries in <lb/>
Europe, while some places have yielded the almost incredible <lb/>
quantity of 100 bushels to the acre. The yield of last year <lb/>
was 27,000.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"He only wished that this honorable gentleman alone had <lb/>
been mistaken, but even the Hon. Mr. Tilley, one of the <lb/>
most. distinguished statesmen of New Brunswick, had made <lb/>
the statement that our tariff was in fact only an eleven per <lb/>
cent. tariff. But all the errors were not on that side, for <lb/>
they need but to turn to a celebrated speech of one of our <lb/>
own leading men—a speech regarded almost as an important <lb/>
state paper—and there it. was stated that the United Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces would become the third maritime power in the world. <lb/>
(Hear, Hear) England, it said, was first, then the United <lb/>
States, and the speaker doubted if France could take the <lb/>
third rank before us. Our sea-going tonnage would be five <lb/>
millions, and our lake tonnage seven millions. These were <lb/>
vast figures, and it almost bewildered the mind to conceive <lb/>
their-magnificent proportions. (Laughter) Now supposing <lb/>
all these vessels were 500 tons each, it would require 14,000 <lb/>
to make up the sum, but unfortunately the census showed <lb/>
that we had but 808 sailors to navigate them—rather I. <lb/>
small number it must be admitted for 14,000 ships. (Great <lb/>

<pb n="70" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_070.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">70</fw>

laughter. ) The way the mistake—to use the mildest ex<lb break="no"/>pression—was made, was simple enough. The vessels were <lb/>
entered at the Custom Houses every time they came in and <lb/>
left port, and as some of them came into port 200 times in <lb/>
the year, as at Toronto for instance, their tonnage was <lb/>
counted 200 times. It was easy in this way to run up our <lb/>
inland marine to seven millions of tons." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Now, Sir, this is the way the advocates of Union endeavor to <lb/>
deceive the people of the Lower Provinces. Even the Hon. <lb/>
Mr. Tilley is not altogether innocent on this point. And in this <lb/>
Island, too, deception has been attempted. The famous speech <lb/>
of the late leader of the Government at the dinner of the Cale<lb break="no"/>donian Club, was an illustration of this, for he spoke of the <lb/>
taxation by the municipal boards in Upper Canada as of no <lb/>
account, whereas wee know it is in a great measure levied for <lb/>
local requirements such as are here defrayed out of the public <lb/>
chest. Then again the Colonial Secretary came out with a new <lb/>
table of figures every few days, showing that the gain to the <lb/>
Colony by Confederation was to be so and so. But, Sir, their <lb/>
efforts to delude the people did not meet with much success <lb/>
here. Some of the young men of the Anti-union press are as <lb/>
well posted up in figures as their opponents, and have done <lb/>
good service to the country by showing up the fallacies of the <lb/>
Union advocates. In spite of all that those in favor of Confed<lb break="no"/>eration can say, it is clear that our taxes will be increased. <lb/>
Before all the expenses which Union will inevitably bring with <lb/>
it can be met, probably even the present high tariff of Canada <lb/>
will require to be raised. Then what will the party in Britain <lb/>
say who advocate a separation of the Colonies from the Mother <lb/>
Country on the ground of their expense ? They would indig<lb break="no"/>nantly enquire Are our people to continue paying taxes to pro<lb break="no"/>tect these Colonies who are doing all in their power to injure <lb/>
out trade by levying still heavier duties upon our manufactures. <lb/>
Sir, I would prefer free trade with England, the land of my <lb/>
fathers, to free trade with Canada. If we are to give any priv<lb break="no"/>ileges let them be accorded to those who have protected us in <lb/>
times past, and not to those who never did anything of the <lb/>
kind. If we are to pay any sum for defences let it be given to <lb/>
the Mother Country, which can protect us, and not to Canada <lb/>
that is quite unable to protect herself. I am much mistaken if <lb/>
Great Britain would allow the Provinces to impose high duties <lb/>
on British goods ; and if this were the case they would then <lb/>
have to resort to direct taxation. But I now come to a point <lb/>
respecting which a good deal has been said, namely, the altera<lb break="no"/>tion of the Report by the Canadians. I have here before me <lb/>
three copies of the Report, and they are all different. In the <lb/>
first copy sent down here, which was signed by Sir E. P. Tache, <lb/>
the President of the Conference, the 24th section reads thus :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"24 The local Legislature of each Province may from time <lb/>
to time alter the Electoral Districts for the purpose of Representa<lb break="no"/>tion in the House of Commons, and distribute the Representatives <lb/>
to which the Province is entitled in any manner such Legislature <lb/>
may think fit." <lb/></p> 

<p>In another copy which I received since, and which is the same <lb/>
as that lade before the Canadian Legislature, the section has <lb/>
been altered to read as follows :— <lb/></p> 

<p>"24. The local Legislature of each Province may from time <lb/>
to time alter the Electoral Disticts for the purpose of Repre<lb break="no"/>sentation <hi rendition="simple:italic">in such Legislature</hi>, and distribute the Representatives <lb/>
to which the Province is entitled <hi rendition="simple:italic">in such local Legislature</hi> in <lb/>
any manner such Legislature may seem fit." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Now, Sir, this is a very material alteration, in a very important <lb/>
clause, and does not say much for our safety should we place <lb/>
ourselves in the power of the Canadians by entering Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. It has been said in justification of the alteration that the <lb/>
section referred entirely to the Local Legislatures, and therefore <lb/>
the rendering in the clause as it first stood was evidently an <lb/>
oversight. This apology, however, is unsatisfactory, as the 24th <lb/>
section is not in that part of the Report which relates to the <lb/>
Local Legislatures, but in that which lays down the constitution <lb/>
of the House of Commons. I may say that a dispute arose as to <lb/>
whether the General Legislature should be allowed to arrange <lb/>
the constituencies, and it was understood that this power should <lb/>
be left to the Local Legislatures. When the delegates for this <lb/>
Island contended for 6 members in the House of Commons <lb/>
instead of 5, our chief argument was that if we were allowed 6 <lb/>
representatives, it would render it an easy matter to divide the <lb/>
electoral districts between the three Counties. The Hon. <lb/>
Attorney General brought forward this proposition, and when it <lb/>

<cb/>

was decided against us, and the principle of representation by <lb/>
population strictly adhered to, l was particular in noticing that <lb/>
rhe right of distributing the representatives to which each <lb/>
Colony would be entitled, should be left with the Local <lb/>
Legislatures, because I considered such a provision would afford <lb/>
us some protection, by placing it beyond the power of the <lb/>
Canadians to divide the constituencies in order to carry their <lb/>
own objects. Judge of my surprise, therefore. at receiving, <lb/>
three or four weeks after my return home, a letter from Mr. <lb/>
Bernard, Secretary to the Conference, and who is also Clerk of <lb/>
the Executive Council of Canada, a letter, enclosing a copy <lb/>
with the 24th section altered as I have stated, and explaining <lb/>
that the alteration had been made because the wording of the <lb/>
section in the first copy, was an accidental departure from the <lb/>
views of the Conference. But I have lately received another <lb/>
copy in which there is an alteration in favor of Nova Scotia and <lb/>
New Brunswick . providing that the former shall be allowed to im<lb break="no"/>pose an export duty on coal and the latter on timber and logs,which <lb/>
special reservation was not in the copy laid before this House. <lb/>
This alteration, I consider. is equally as culpable as the other. <lb/>
What right, I ask, had the Canadian Government to alter one <lb/>
word of the document after it was signed? They might almost <lb/>
as well change the whole Report to suit their own particular <lb/>
views. I wish also to show that this Report, as a whole, does <lb/>
not place Nova Scotia and New Brunswick in such an unfavor<lb break="no"/>able position as this lsland. 'l'hese Provinces have large local <lb/>
revenues, that of Nova Scotia in 1863. being, as shown by Mr. <lb/>
Galt in his speech at Sherbrooke, $107,000, and that of New <lb/>
Brunswick in the same year $ 9,000. He sets down the local <lb/>
revenues of this Colony at $32,000 ; but I am at a loss to <lb/>
know how he made up that sum unless he included in the <lb/>
amount the instalments paid in during the year from the sales <lb/>
under the Land Purchase Act. This money, however, forms <lb/>
no part of our local revenues ; it is all required to make up the <lb/>
price paid by the Government for the proprietors' estates which <lb/>
have been purchased. In the neighboring Provinces the case <lb/>
is different ; their public lands are Crown lands, the sale of <lb/>
which brings in a large revenue, that will be wholly available <lb/>
for sectional purposes, Taking into consideration also that these <lb/>
Provinces are to receive 80 cents per head for their local wants <lb/>
as well as this Island, and that New Brunswick is guaranteed a <lb/>
subsidy besides, they are tolerably well provided for. But <lb/>
Canada will fare still better. Her local revenues in 1863. as <lb/>
given by Hon. Mr. Galt, were $l.297,043 ; and the allowance <lb/>
of 80 cents per head of her population would yield her about $2,<lb break="no"/>000,000, which will just be $2,000,000 more than she now <lb/>
expends out of the public funds for local purposes. This Island <lb/>
hitherto has almost solely relied on her customs revenue, and <lb/>
therefore it is that with the small per capita allowance of 80 <lb/>
cents, we would be unable to carry on the local government <lb/>
without restoring to direct taxation. We are even prevented from <lb/>
levying an export duty on our produce, while this privilege is <lb/>
allowed Nova Scotia and New Brunswick on certain articles. <lb/>
Taking all these points into consideration, I think it is clear that <lb/>
the Report before us is not such as should be adopted by this <lb/>
House. To enter such a Confederation as is here proposed <lb/>
would evidently prove ruinous to the Colony. If a change is <lb/>
thought desirable, I consider it would be more for our advantage <lb/>
to have a representation in the British Parliament, and to <lb/>
pay a per centage to the Imperial Government out of our <lb/>
revenue for any purpose they may think proper. I believe <lb/>
that one representative there would secure for us a greater share <lb/>
of justice than we are ever likely to receive from a federal <lb/>
legislature in Canada. Should Confederation take place, I be<lb break="no"/>lieve that in a very few years the people under it will be as <lb/>
heavily taxed as the people of the United States are now at the <lb/>
termination of a civil war. 1 shall vote for the resolutions <lb/>
submitted by the hon. leader of the Government, and trust they <lb/>
will receive the support of a large majority of this House; also <lb/>
that an Address to Her Majesty will be passed, showing the true <lb/>
position of this Colony in regard to the Confederation scheme. <lb/></p> 

<p>(Prolonged cheers.) <lb/></p> 

<p>After a few remarks by Hon members who had already <lb/>
spoken, the motion was put on the amendment submitted by <lb/>
Hon J.. C. Pope in lieu of the resolutions approving of the <lb/>
Quebec Report, proposed by the Hon. Colonial Secretary, <lb/>
which amendment was carried on the following Division: <lb/></p> 

<p>For the Amendment—Hon. Messrs. J. C. Pope, Longworth, <lb/>
Laird; Davies, Kaye, Coles, Kelly, Hensley, Thornton, War— <lb/>
burton, Benton, Messrs. Ramsay, Montgomery, Yeo, Duncan, <lb/>

<pb n="71" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-31_Page_071.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">71</fw>

Brecken, Howat, Conroy, Howlan, Sinclair, Walker, Suther<lb break="no"/>land—23. <lb/></p> 

<p>Against it—Hons. Colonial Secretary, Solicitor General, <lb/>
Gray, Whelan, and Mr. Green—5. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Sinclair then proposed a Resolution, to the effect that, <lb/>
Whereas the Government had exceeded the authority of last <lb/>
Session by the appointment of Delegates to Canada ; and <lb/>
whereas this House, by resolutions, declared that Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, if effected, would prove disastrous to the rights and <lb/>
liberties of the people of this Colony, therefore, that the <lb/>
Government should appoint no further Delegations, or take <lb/>
any action to alter the Constitution without the express <lb/>
authority of the Legislature. <lb/></p> 

<p>A discussion then ensued on the subject of this Resolution, <lb/>
when it was argued that the adoption of such course was <lb/>
unusual and would place extraordinary restrictions on the <lb/>
prerogative of the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p>The question was then put on the said Resolution which <lb/>
was negatived on the following division: <lb/></p> 

<p>Against it—Hon. Messrs. J. C. Pope, Gray, Longworth, <lb/>
Laird, Davies, Kaye, Col. Secretary, Solicitor General, <lb/>
Whelan, Thornton ; Messrs. Ramsay, Montgomery, Haslam, <lb/>
Yeo, Duncan, Brecken, Howat, Green, McLennan—19. <lb/></p> 

<p>For the Resolution—Hons. Messrs. Coles, Hensley, War-<lb break="yes"/>burton, Beaton, Kelly ; Messrs. Sinclair, Conroy, Howlan, <lb/>
Walker, Sutherland—10. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Resolution was accordingly lost. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. J. C. Pope then submitted a Resolution for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of appointing a Committee to prepare a joint address to <lb/>
Her Majesty the Queen, founded upon the Resolutions of <lb/>
that House, upon the subject of the proposed Confederation <lb/>
of the British North American Colonies, expressive of the <lb/>
determination of the Legislature, on the part of the people <lb/>
of the Colony, not to assent to such Confederation. <lb/></p> 

<p>Ordered, that the Hon. Messrs. J. C. Pope, Longworth, <lb/>
Hensley, Coles, and Mr. Sinclair, be a Committee, on the <lb/>
part of that House, to prepare such address. <lb/></p> 

<p>After which, at a very late hour, the House adjourned. <lb/></p> 

<!-- DL 2018-06-08 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>SATURDAY, March 25.* <lb/></p> 

<p>*The dates are repeated, because the Reporters, with the <lb/>
permission of the House, published the Debate on the Union <lb/>
of the Colonies, in a connected form, though it was resumed <lb/>
only on the evening of each day. <lb/></p> 

<p>End of Column <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Solicitor General presented a petition from diverse <lb/>
inhabitants of Georgetown, asking permission to erect a <lb/>
Pound on the public square of that Town. <lb/></p> 

<p>Said petition was referred to the following special <lb/>
Committee to report thereon, viz : Hons. Solicitor General, <lb/>
Longworth, Kaye. <lb/></p> 

<p>Debate on the Union of the Colonies resumed and <lb/>
adjourned. <lb/></p>-->
</div> </body> </text> </TEI>