<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1869-04-01"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1869-04-01">1 April 1869</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1869">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1869, Being the Third Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1869"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edward Reilly, Queen's Printer</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="160"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_157.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_158.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_160.hocr.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-12">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_157">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_156.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_158">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_158.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_160">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_160.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">


<pb n="157" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_157.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">157</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, April 1.</p><lb/>

<p>[...]</p>

<cb/>

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Afternoon Session.</hi></p>

<p>[...]</p>

<p>Mr. Cameron in the Chair. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERNMENT</persName>.-- <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="158" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_158.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">158</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p>I <lb/>
do not, therefore, purpose asking this hon. Com<lb break="no"/>mittee to make any further provision than what <lb/>
will meet the Salary, and beg therefore, to submit-<lb break="yes"/>the following Resolution:— <lb/></p> 

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That a Salary, annually to be paid, to <lb/>
the Lieut. Governor or other Administrator of the <lb/>
Government of this Island, after the present Lieut. <lb/>
Governor shall relinquish his office, be provided <lb/>
and fixed at £1,400 sterling, equal to £2,100 of <lb/>
current money of Prince Edward Island. I may <lb/>
say that my opinion was quite conclusive as to <lb/>
the uselessness of appealing to the Home Govern<lb break="no"/>ment again, and that it was prudent and wise not <lb/>
to go Home again with another memorial on the <lb/>
subject. The despatch to-day read, shows con<lb break="no"/>clusively that the decision of the Home authori<lb break="no"/>ties is fixed, and that they have assumed that we <lb/>
will soon be placed into Confederation. I think <lb/>
that no man of influence could be got in the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Parliament to undertake the successful <lb/>
prosecution of our demand. I am not so terribly <lb/>
afraid of Confederation, as to suppose but that we <lb/>
could get along even if we were placed in the <lb/>
union; but this is not the wish of the people of <lb/>
this Colony, and our duty is to prevent it if we <lb/>
can, and give no cause for having it forced upon <lb/>
us contrary to our wishes. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. LEADER OF THE OPPOSITION</persName>.— <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p>I cannot, therefore, give the <lb/>
Government my applause for what they have done <lb/>
in this matter. It appears as if they wished to <lb/>
frighten hon. members into voting for the Reso<lb break="no"/>lution, by pursuading them that if it was not agreed <lb/>
to, we would be immediately pitchforked into the <lb/>
Dominion. Whereas my learned friend the hon. <lb/>
member for Charlottetown and myself argued, <lb/>
that we could only be placed in by both Branches <lb/>
of the Legislature passing a Bill for that purpose <lb/>
and sending it home for the sanction of the Home <lb/>
Government ; and now, we have that Despatch <lb/>
and it fortifies the arguments that we used. In <lb/>

<cb/>

the reply which the Government received, the <lb/>
Home Government refuses to guarantee a loan to <lb/>
enable them to purchase out the Estates of the <lb/>
remaining proprietors, and the Imperial Minis<lb break="no"/>ter says: "Having regard to the evident uncer<lb break="no"/>tainty, whether the Colony of Prince Edward <lb/>
Island will or will not soon unite itself to the <lb/>
Dominion of Canada," obviously showing that it <lb/>
is not the intention of the Imperial authorities, <lb/>
to do anything in the movement in any other way <lb/>
than that indicated by the hon. member for Char<lb break="no"/>lottetown and myself. The Despatch is plain; <lb/>
go into Confederation, and you will have your re<lb break="no"/>ward. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>.—It appears to me, that the <lb/>
learned Leader of the Opposition sees more in the <lb/>
Despatch than any one else; at all events, it ap<lb break="no"/>pears to me, that if the hon. member would read <lb/>
it over carefully, that he will find that the views <lb/>
which have been expressed on this side of the <lb/>
House, are substantially such as those which <lb/>
have so far been used by those hon. members who <lb/>
supported the resolution. A general election <lb/>
may show that a change, with respect to Confede<lb break="no"/>ration, has taken place in the views of the people <lb/>
on that question, but I have no reason to suppose <lb/>
that it has, and I believe that who ever our suc<lb break="no"/>cessors may be, they will be, like ourselves, <lb/>
charged to vote against anything, and everything, <lb/>
which might lead us into a Union with Canada. <lb/>
It is clear though, that in the opinion of the au<lb break="no"/>thorities at Home, they look upon Confederation <lb/>
as a settled fact, that it is to take place at no dis<lb break="no"/>tant day, and if the Salary of the Lieutenant Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor had not been provided, what better argu<lb break="no"/>ment would they require to place us into the Do<lb break="no"/>minion, than our refusal to comply with the <lb/>
demand ; and I have little doubt but they will <lb/>
yet endeavor to find some means for driving us <lb/>
into a union with the New Dominion. <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.— <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p> 

<pb n="159" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_158.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">159</fw> 

<p>[...]</p> 

<p>I think it fully <lb/>
bears out the arguments used by the Opposition ; <lb/>
for instead of using any threats towards us, it is <lb/>
quite clear from the whole of the Despatch, that <lb/>
it will be left to the decision of the people of this <lb/>
Island whether they " will or will not" unite with <lb/>
the Dominion of Canada. I must say that I think <lb/>
the hon. Leader of the Government did not act <lb/>
fairly in withholding this Despatch so long. <lb/>
Why allow us to come to a conclusion in the <lb/>
matter when there was information in his posses<lb break="no"/>sion which should have been laid upon the table <lb/>
of this House ? In the Despatch which the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment sent Home, the Imperial guarantee is <lb/>
asked for raising a loan on our Debentures and if <lb/>
this is conceded, the Government say they will <lb/>
make provision for the payment of the Governor's <lb/>
Salary. No Imperial guarantee has been given ; <lb/>
and even before they knew it would not, they <lb/>
ask this hon. Committee to provide for it. Al<lb break="no"/>though we do stand here as a small minority, I <lb/>
tell them that this despatch does not breathe a <lb/>
single threat or contain any statements to justify <lb/>
the Government in the arguments which they <lb/>
have used here on this question. This Despatch <lb/>
does not fortify the position they have taken. <lb/>
The whole tenor of it is, that they will not inter<lb break="no"/>fere with any of our affairs,—in plain English, <lb/>
will do nothing for us, while we remain out of the <lb/>
Union. The last House passed some strongly <lb/>
worded no-terms resolutions ; this House have <lb/>
also virtually acted upon them. Now, the Home <lb/>
Government obviously hold out a bait. They <lb/>
do not say if you not do so and so, we will take <lb/>
up this question you have submitted for our con<lb break="no"/>sideration; but tell us if we do not, we must settle <lb/>
our Land Question and all others as we can best <lb/>
do so ourselves ; and if we now refuse, it is not <lb/>
beyond the range of possibility for them to use <lb/>
means to put us into the Union. The whole <lb/>
tenor of the Despatch fortifies the views of the <lb/>
Leader of the Opposition and myself on this ques<lb break="no"/>tion. <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

<cb/>

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName>.—I look upon this minute of Coun<lb break="no"/>cil as another very strong remonstrance on the <lb/>
part of the Government, against the gross injus<lb break="no"/>tice of the demand for the payment of the Lieut. <lb/>
Governor's salary by this Colony ; and I am de<lb break="no"/>cidedly of the opinion that the Government did <lb/>
right in asking some consideration from the Home <lb/>
Government, on account of the great injustice <lb/>
done to us in the disposal of our lands. The <lb/>
answer shows that they look to our connec<lb break="no"/>tion with Canada as an event which is soon to <lb/>
take place. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. McNEILL</persName>.—I think I said, yesterday or the <lb/>
day before, that, if we want to go into confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, we have but to accept the $200,000 bribe <lb/>
which had been offered to us ; and in this Des<lb break="no"/>patch we are clearly and plainly told that if we <lb/>
want our land question settled, we have to go <lb/>
into confederation. This Island would never <lb/>
have objected to the payment of the salary of the <lb/>
Lieut. Governor, if we had been placed in the <lb/>
same position as the other Colonies were. This <lb/>
Despatch plainly proves that when the demand <lb/>
was made, in 1865, when confederation was the <lb/>
order of the day, that it was with a view to our <lb/>
being placed in the Dominion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>.—The memorial which was <lb/>
read here to-day, to which this despatch is a re<lb break="no"/>ply, shows very plainly the sincere and ardent <lb/>
desire of the Government to do all they can to <lb/>
settle the land question, and that they have left <lb/>
no stone unturned in their endeavor to induce the <lb/>
Home Government to consent to what is but just <lb/>
and reasonable in the matter. But, sir, I really <lb/>
now do not see that there is any way in which to <lb/>
carry out the great wish of the people for the <lb/>
settlement of the land question, as the proprietors <lb/>
will not accept what we can offer them. With <lb/>
reference to the whole tenor of Lord Granville's <lb/>
reply, it at least shows quite plainly that the <lb/>
British Government do not care much for us ; <lb/>
that they have cast off all protection ; and, in <lb/>
effect, have said, that we can go and find protec<lb break="no"/>tion where we can. I only wish the Despatch <lb/>
was more explicit and out-spoken on this point ; <lb/>
then we would know the extent of our freedom. <lb/>
As to the offer, seemingly, or plainly, implied, <lb/>
to go into confederation, it is similar to the one <lb/>
made to Newfoundland, which was, in effect, that if <lb/>
they went into the Union, Her Majesty's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment believed that Reciprocity would soon fol<lb break="no"/>low. Such a statement is in the speech of the <lb/>
Lieut. Governor of that Colony, at the opening of <lb/>
the Legislature ; and, sir, you know that there <lb/>
was never a poorer prospect of obtaining Reci<lb break="no"/>procity than there is at present. We know that <lb/>
the feeling between the United States and Great <lb/>
Britain just now is not such as warrants us to <lb/>
expect that a renewal of reciprocal trade rela<lb break="no"/>tions with these Colonies is likely to be soon <lb/>
realized. I see it stated in press that the feeling <lb/>
in the United States is, that no pecuniary recom<lb break="no"/>pense which Great Britain could offer to the <lb/>

<pb n="160" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_160.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">160</fw> 

United States Government, on account of the <lb/>
Alabama claims, would compensate them for the <lb/>
evil they received from them during the last war. <lb/>
That, but for Great Britain, the war would have <lb/>
been closed two years earlier than it was ; and <lb/>
they say further, that, while this was going on, <lb/>
the Government of England was expressing great <lb/>
sympathy for them, and yet, at the same time, <lb/>
was allowing their ships to go and destroy her <lb/>
commerce ; and, therefore, I think that the en<lb break="no"/>couragement held out to Newfoundland had no <lb/>
foundation in fact. We all know where the <lb/>
treaty making power lies, and the prospect of its <lb/>
being soon renewed with Canada is now apparently <lb/>
out of the question, so that the union of New<lb break="no"/>foundland with the Dominion will only have the <lb/>
effect of making that country poorer, as their <lb/>
taxes will immediately increase, without affording <lb/>
any means for improving their trade ; and such <lb/>
would also be the effect upon this Colony. The <lb/>
obvious policy of the Dominion is to impose a tax <lb/>
upon our products and exact large duties. The <lb/>
duty on oat-meal, last year, was fifteen per cent. <lb/>
As to Confederation, I am not for going into it <lb/>
on any terms which they may or can offer ; for <lb/>
it is not in their power to offer terms to us that it <lb/>
would be any advantage for us to accept. I only <lb/>
regret that the Home Government did not tell us <lb/>
more plainly what we might do ; but I think they <lb/>
have very nearly told us to go where we please, <lb/>
and had they but said so in plainer terms the <lb/>
answer would be more satisfactory. <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName>.—It does appear from the <lb/>
whole tenor of this Despatch as if there is an in<lb break="no"/>clination to put the screws on this Colony, unless <lb/>
we conform to the present policy of the British <lb/>
Government. I said a few days ago that I be<lb break="no"/>lieved the British nation, at heart, was right, and <lb/>
that the great bulk of her people meant that jus<lb break="no"/>tice, and that only, should be extended to the <lb/>
Colonies ; but, between red-tape-ism, on the one <lb/>
hand, and the leviathian crust, on the other, in <lb/>
the present Government, with the so-called <lb/>
wholesale reform now pressing upon the Govern<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

ment, upon which the party in power will, in <lb/>
their dealing with it, have to stand or fall, so <lb/>
that the view I took of it a few days ago agrees <lb/>
with what we have since learned. If any claims <lb/>
in way of saving the Imperial finances is made <lb/>
upon us, it must be responded to by us in the <lb/>
manner in which we are directed to do so ; but if <lb/>
we present our grievance and ask to be allowed <lb/>
to pass such measures as we know would assist <lb/>
us in redressing them, we are told to go into <lb/>
Confederation. We have always called Great <lb/>
Britain the Mother Country, but I think we may <lb/>
now call her the step-mother, and a very harsh <lb/>
one at that. I am a British subject, and I be<lb break="no"/>lieve a loyal one, and think British justice should <lb/>
consist in extending equal justice to all her sub<lb break="no"/>jects ; and justice to myself and those who sent <lb/>
me here demand that I say this much. There is <lb/>
also an additional matter to be considered, and <lb/>
one which ought not to be overlooked. This <lb/>
Colony asked for Reciprocity ; this is an Imperial <lb/>
measure, and one that can only be entered into <lb/>
by independent powers ; but the idea that we <lb/>
should use a privilege which belongs to every <lb/>
British subject as his inalienable right—the right <lb/>
of petition for what we knew would be to our <lb/>
advantage—gave offence, and for so doing we <lb/>
were snubbed at once. We have, sir, held our <lb/>
shoulder against pressure for the last five years <lb/>
from those who wished us to go into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, and now I consider it no more than justice <lb/>
to our own people, since the Imperial authorities <lb/>
are bearing so harshly upon us, that we should <lb/>
see to our own interests ; and if the Imperial <lb/>
Government send a gentleman here to represent <lb/>
Her Majesty, I consider that the allowance <lb/>
should be according to our circumstances, and, <lb/>
therefore, consider that £1,000 is as much as we <lb/>
can afford to give, and if his Imperial masters <lb/>
think the amount too small, they can add to it as <lb/>
much as they please. <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>
 
<pb n="161" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_160.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">161</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Mr. G. SINCLAIR</persName>.—The Despatch only the more <lb/>
firmly fortifies the views expressed, that if we <lb/>
wish to keep out of the Dominion of Canada, we <lb/>
have promptly to comply with this demand ; for <lb/>
we are clearly given to understand that it is <lb/>
owning to the uncertainty of our remaining out of <lb/>
the Union, that the authorities in Great Britain <lb/>
decline to discuss our grievances, or enter into <lb/>
their consideration, yet there is no doubt but that <lb/>
the British Government would be loath to force <lb/>
us into the Union, unless we give them some <lb/>
reason ; and my opinion is that if we do not com<lb break="no"/>ply with this request, they may compel us by the <lb/>
force of circumstances to do so. I do not think <lb/>
we should offer a lower salary than that pro<lb break="no"/>posed in the Resolution. This Island is differ<lb break="no"/>ently situated from the other Provinces, as they <lb/>
have their Lieut. Governors appointed by the <lb/>
Dominion Government, whereas ours will receive <lb/>
his appointment, like that of the Governor of the <lb/>
Dominion, directly from the Imperial Government. <lb/>
We are aware that the Dominion Government <lb/>
endeavored to have the salary of their Governor <lb/>
lowered, but they could not, and in the attempt <lb/>
were met with a stern refusal. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>