<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-04-06"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>


<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-04-06">6 April 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1870, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1870"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="187"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>

<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_174.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_176.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_178.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_180.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_182.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_184.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_186.hocr.html"/>
</item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-16">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-16">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_174">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_174.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_176">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_176.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_178">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_178.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_180">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_180.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_182">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_182.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_184">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_184.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_186">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_186.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>
<div type="debate">


<pb n="175" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_174.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">175</fw>  

<p>[...]</p> 

<p rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, April 6.<lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">Confederation.<lb/></p> 

<p>Debate on Despatches resumed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WIGH1">Hon. the Speaker</persName> said the question <lb/>
under discussion was an important one, <lb/>
and therefore required to be dispassion<lb break="no"/>ately considered by each hon. gentleman <lb/>
on that committee. But when he (the <lb/>
Speaker) looked around that chamber, <lb/>
and saw that empty chair, once so ably, <lb/>
—yes, so nobly, occupied by a gentleman <lb/>
whose exertions on behalf of the inhabi<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="176" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_176.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">176</fw>

tants of this Island, in maturing measures <lb/>
for their welfare, had so hardened his <lb/>
over-taxed mind, that he had been forced <lb/>
to seek rest and repose by withdrawing <lb/>
to another colony. When he (Mr. S.) <lb/>
thought of the labors of that man for <lb/>
his country, and of the effects they had <lb/>
had upon his once active and powerful <lb/>
mind, he could not but feel how saw was <lb/>
the <hi rendition="simple:italic">fate of mankind</hi>. How often had <lb/>
hon. gentlemen seen him uniting with <lb/>
them in sending home faithful accounts <lb/>
of the grievance of the colony to the <lb/>
Colonial office, and in return receiving <lb/>
nothing but the cold and chilling winds <lb/>
of Downing Street. And now what did <lb/>
they see? Just this, that grievances <lb/>
so justly complained of, were by these in <lb/>
authority there, transferred to a neigh<lb break="no"/>boring colony to be redressed by its <lb/>
government. No doubt the people <lb/>
wished to know the opinion of their <lb/>
representatives upon the question as it <lb/>
was now presented. He cordially ap<lb break="no"/>proved of the proceedings taken by the <lb/>
constituencies in calling meetings in the <lb/>
different districts, and inviting their <lb/>
representatives to attend and discuss the <lb/>
question of confederation before assem<lb break="no"/>bling in the legislature, and warning <lb/>
them not to surrender to a separate <lb/>
country and a separate legislature, the <lb/>
liberties and properties of eighty or <lb/>
ninety thousand inhabitants of Prince <lb/>
Edward Island, who delegated them <lb/>
here to defend, but not to destroy the <lb/>
constitution. The hon. leader of the <lb/>
government, in his speech, drew atten<lb break="no"/>tion of the union of Ireland and Scotland <lb/>
with England, and he (Mr. S.) knew that <lb/>
some of Ireland's ablest statesmen, and <lb/>
other able men also, had in their speeches <lb/>
shown, that under the adminstration of <lb/>
Castlereagh, Ireland had received unjust <lb/>
treatment; and that undue influences <lb/>
were brought to bea rupon her public <lb/>
men when they gave up their parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. And no reform that had yet been <lb/>
introduced, or that could be carried, <lb/>
would fully satisfy that people, until <lb/>
their parliament was again established <lb/>
on College Green, as that was the grand <lb/>
aspiration which moved the hearts of <lb/>
the people on that "sea girt Isle." In <lb/>
reading a speech of the great Irish Liber<lb break="no"/>ator—the great O'Connel—he could not <lb/>
fall ot notice the force contained in the <lb/>
words used and the statements made by <lb/>
that great man, when he said, that Great <lb/>
Britain had nineteen colonies, each one <lb/>
of which had a distinct and separate <lb/>
legislature, while Ireland with a popula<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

tion greater than them all had none! <lb/>
The hon. and learned member, the leader <lb/>
of the opposition, in his speech, entered <lb/>
into the history of the union of Scotland <lb/>
with England, and gave a lucid and <lb/>
flattering account of its results; but he <lb/>
(Mr. S.) could assure his hon. friend <lb/>
that many a day had passed over the <lb/>
heads of the Scottish people before they <lb/>
became reconciled ot that union. Trade <lb/>
and commerce, however, gradually al<lb break="no"/>layed a feeling which was very keenly <lb/>
felt by all classes in that country. <lb/>
Through her representatives, Scotland <lb/>
had been able to make her influences felt <lb/>
in the Imperial Parliament; but the <lb/>
benefits resulting therefrom, she owed, <lb/>
not to the union, but to the wisdom and <lb/>
energy so characteristic of her sons. He <lb/>
saw no occasion now, to go so far away <lb/>
to look for information bearing upon the <lb/>
question, or for dwelling upon scenes <lb/>
which were removed such a distance <lb/>
from us in the past, upon which to place <lb/>
our attention for the purpose of consider<lb break="no"/>ing the results which confederation with <lb/>
the Dominion of Canada would probably <lb/>
produce in this Colony. We had but to <lb/>
go to Nova Scotia, observe the change <lb/>
which had taken place in the feelings of <lb/>
that province, and notice the discontent <lb/>
pervading the minds of the people. <lb/>
New Brunswick also, which, of its own <lb/>
free will and accord, nailed with Canada, <lb/>
complained now that their wants were <lb/>
neglected, and their interests overlooked <lb/>
by the authorities at Ottawa; and with <lb/>
the discontent pervading Nova Scotia <lb/>
and New Brunswick, he had to connect <lb/>
the difficulties existing at Red River, <lb/>
and he thought when all these were fair<lb break="no"/>ly considered, no difficulty would be <lb/>
found in arriving at the conclusion that <lb/>
the duty of this Island was to remain as <lb/>
it was and that hon. committee, he was <lb/>
sure, would endorse that opinion also. <lb/>
Th ehon. member for Murray Harbor, <lb/>
(Mr. Henderson) showed very clearly last <lb/>
night, how Nova Scotia had been treated <lb/>
and betrayed by her public man, and he <lb/>
had no doubt but that our people were <lb/>
determined that their public men should <lb/>
not have an opportunity to betray them. <lb/>
He hoped the public men of this ISland <lb/>
would never do an act which should cast <lb/>
that dark stain upon their public character, <lb/>
which must ever be associated with that of <lb/>
some of those members of Parliament, in <lb/>
Nova Scotia, who betrayed so shamefully <lb/>
the confidence of the people, in voting <lb/>
away the constitution of their country <lb/>
without the knowledge or concurrence of <lb/>

<pb n="177" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_176.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">177</fw> 

their constituents, and yet some of them <lb/>
had the audacity to say in London, that <lb/>
the question had been submitted ot the <lb/>
people at the polls! At the present mo<lb break="no"/>ment, those of them in the neighboring <lb/>
Province of New Brunswick, who voted <lb/>
themselves into union. were now as anxious <lb/>
to sever the connection, as those on this <lb/>
ISland were to keep free from a political <lb/>
Union with the Dominion; and he (Mr. S.) <lb/>
hoped the day was far distant when this <lb/>
colony would enter into such a connection. <lb/>
This colony was now in a happy and inde<lb break="no"/>pendent position. Her people were free <lb/>
from any trouble or turmoil. It was not <lb/>
so with the Dominion. We had an in<lb break="no"/>telligent population. Our government <lb/>
was faithfully and satisfactorily attending <lb/>
to the interests of the country and our <lb/>
people were thankful that they had repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives so able and faithful, and so long <lb/>
as such would continue, he wa satisfied <lb/>
there would never be any desire to go into <lb/>
confederation. The people acted wisely in <lb/>
holding meetings before the Legislature <lb/>
met, to notice th action of the Ottawa <lb/>
government, and warn the public men of <lb/>
the displeasure and results which would <lb/>
follow if they presumed to betray their <lb/>
trust. The people had been warned by <lb/>
what took place in Nova Scotia. But he <lb/>
thought the Legislature of Prince Edward <lb/>
Island would never be guided by so degrad<lb break="no"/>ing a sentiment as to do such an act as was <lb/>
perpetrated in Nova Scotia. With respect <lb/>
to the despatches which had been sent to <lb/>
the government of this ISland from Can<lb break="no"/>ada, and the offer therein made, he thought <lb/>
our government had acted wisely in stating <lb/>
that Great Britain should first set the ex<lb break="no"/>ample of rectifying the wrong done to this <lb/>
colony herself. Well did he recollect how <lb/>
a man who had been sent there on a mis<lb break="no"/>sion, bad at one time romised more good <lb/>
measures, and beneficial results theiefrom, <lb/>
than any other seven did, yet when with <lb/>
our representations he a peared at the <lb/>
home office at. Downing treet, how sum<lb break="no"/>marily were they disposed of Great Brit<lb break="no"/>ain, instead of looking fairly at the duty <lb/>
which. it owed to this Island, transferred <lb/>
our claim, to be disposed of by another <lb/>
colony, and had asks it to pay us what. <lb/>
should be paid by herself! According to <lb/>
the last despatch, we must not say any <lb/>
more about our claim. Well! all he would <lb/>
say was, the people of this colony were as <lb/>
loyal as any under the British flag. No <lb/>
eople could be found who were more so. <lb/>
But if Britain began to use force, he was <lb/>
afraid their loyalty would soon cool. He <lb/> 

<cb/>

trusted, therefore, that the argument of <lb/>
force would never be resorted to. He <lb/>
observed some time ago, that an editor of <lb/>
one of the papers of 'the city, stated that <lb/>
be (Mr. S.) had on a previous occasion, <lb/>
made an erroneous statement. He did no<lb break="no"/>thing of the kind. For he had distinctly <lb/>
stated that his references applied to our <lb/>
trade with Canada. proper, and took his <lb/>
information from the Custom House re<lb break="no"/>turns, and had stated that in 1868, our <lb/>
imports from Canada proper were £29,486, <lb/>
and our exports to the same place were <lb/>
but £1,093, and wodld again ask where the <lb/>
balance came from which met that debt? <lb/>
They took none of our produce, nor did <lb/>
our shipbuilders find a market in ports of <lb/>
Canada proper, for any of the vessels they <lb/>
built. Of course it was not. so with New <lb/>
Brunswick, which purchased largel from <lb/>
the shippers of this colony; but in Halifax, <lb/>
our trade thirty years ago, was better than <lb/>
it was now, He recollected also when we <lb/>
had to sell our vessels and produce in New<lb break="no"/>foundland, to obtain money to ay bills <lb/>
contracted in Nova Scotia. Therefore <lb/>
when he spoke on the occasion referred to, <lb/>
he referred to Canada proper. His state<lb break="no"/>ments had been misrepresented. He <lb/>
knew the people of this Island had no <lb/>
desire to unite with Canada in apolitical <lb/>
alliance. lt had been said that Canada <lb/>
was, this year, going to buy our pork. <lb/>
Admitting such to be the case, twenty <lb/>
years might pass away before such would <lb/>
happen again. Our position, politically, <lb/>
was far better now than it could ever be <lb/>
were we in the Dominion. We were willing <lb/>
to trade with them, but anything further <lb/>
was not desired, and he hoped we had <lb/>
heard the last about a union with the great <lb/>
Dominion of Canada. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. MCNEILL</persName>.—This subject had been <lb/>
pretty well ventilated by hon. gentlemen <lb/>
who prrcedcd him, and as he did not expect <lb/>
to advance anything new, he would not <lb/>
then address that committee were it not <lb/>
that since the question had been debated <lb/>
in reply to the speech of his honor the <lb/>
Administrator at the opening of the session, <lb/>
another despatch had been laid on the <lb/>
table. He would therefore offer a few <lb/>
remarks, but would not trouble the chair<lb break="no"/>man to read the despatch, as he supposed <lb/>
hon. gentlemen recollected its contents; <lb/>
and as they were pretty well accustomed <lb/>
to such despatches, he did not think its <lb/>
tone and tenor surprised any one; but he <lb/>
might inform Earl Granville—if the voice <lb/>
of one of the representatives of little P. E. <lb/>

<pb n="178" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_178.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">178</fw>

Island, could reach his illustrious ear—that <lb/>
the wrong complained of in the minute of <lb/>
Council, had been already acknowledged <lb/>
by one of his Lordship's predecessors in the <lb/>
colonial office—Lord Stanley, a statesman <lb/>
quite as talented, and of greater colonial <lb/>
experience. Lord Stanley did not hesitate <lb/>
to state in his place in the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons, that the Imperial Government had <lb/>
done a wrong to this colony ; and although <lb/>
it had been said that the demand for its <lb/>
redress by Great Britain need not be re<lb break="no"/>peated, yet he (Mr. McNeill) knew, should <lb/>
unreasonable claims be again made upon <lb/>
this Island, that the Home government <lb/>
would be reminded of the injury it had <lb/>
inflicted upon this country. No doubt the <lb/>
people, as the hon. Speaker had observed, <lb/>
were anxious about the question before the <lb/>
committee. Nor was it a matter of surprise <lb/>
that as intelligent people should take such <lb/>
a deep interest in it, when they considered <lb/>
that thte action taken upon the matter, if <lb/>
in favor of confederation, was so important <lb/>
as to embrace the giving up of our free <lb/>
constitution, which, once surrendered, could <lb/>
never be recovered again. It had been said <lb/>
that isolation was played out, but no proof <lb/>
had been adduced to show that such was <lb/>
the case. It was certain, isolation had not <lb/>
so far injured the Island, for had it entered <lb/>
into confederation on the basis of the <lb/>
Quebec Scheme, the people would be in a <lb/>
far worse position to-day than they were. <lb/>
He would not go into figures. But from <lb/>
such statistics as he had seen, he thought <lb/>
there was room to believe the statements <lb/>
made might be a few thousand pounds <lb/>
astray on either side. But he did not view <lb/>
the question from a financial stand-point, <lb/>
but thought, that after this colony had <lb/>
overcome so many difficulties, managed its <lb/>
affairs not only as well, but better than the <lb/>
other Provinces, and held its own so suc<lb break="no"/>cessfully, it would be very unwise to give <lb/>
up on our constitution, which was not obtained <lb/>
without a struggle. This Island was sep<lb break="no"/>arated from the Province of Nova Scotia at <lb/>
the instance of the proprietors, for their <lb/>
own selfish purposes, and now the remnant <lb/>
of those of them who were left, as if pur<lb break="no"/>suing the people with an undying hatred, <lb/>
now wished to hand-cuff the colony on to <lb/>
the Dominion again ! The advocates of <lb/>
confederation said Canada would not im<lb break="no"/>pose upon this Island in any way, or legis<lb break="no"/>late in a manner adverse to its interests ; <lb/>
and in support of their arguments pointed <lb/>
to Rhode Island, which received as much <lb/>
justice from the Federal government of the <lb/>
United States as any other state in the <lb/>
Union ; but judging from what was now <lb/>

<cb/> 

occurring in the other provinces, he con<lb break="no"/>cluded such would not long be the exper<lb break="no"/>ience of this Island if it went into the <lb/>
union. The people of New Brunswick now <lb/>
complained that their rights and privileges <lb/>
were completely overlooked, as might he <lb/>
seen from the following extract from the <lb/>
St. John <hi rendition="simple:italic">Telegraph</hi>, a stormy confederate <lb/>
journal, which, after enumerating several <lb/>
grievances, to which it referred, and point<lb break="no"/>ing out reforms that were expected, added : <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"But the fact is far otherwise. The number <lb/>
of departments in the Government is unneces<lb break="no"/>sarily large, as "the noble army" of employees <lb/>
at Ottawa is decidedly formidable. It is safe to <lb/>
say that many of them are not very fully em<lb break="no"/>ployed." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>On this Island we had two tests of public <lb/>
opinion—the press and public meetings. <lb/>
And so long as the press was free and un<lb break="no"/>corrupted, there would be no danger. It <lb/>
had not been so, however, in Nova Scotia, <lb/>
where it was well known that the press <lb/>
had been subsidized, and instead of speak<lb break="no"/>ing out the sentiments of Nova Scotia, <lb/>
it gave utterance to those of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment at Ottawa. And now, when he saw <lb/>
so many well-informed people here, as in <lb/>
that province, still protesting against the <lb/>
union, he could not but believe that they <lb/>
were right. One of the public men of <lb/>
Nova Scotia had undoubtedly deceived <lb/>
Mr. Bright by inducing him to believe the <lb/>
question had been submitted to the people <lb/>
at the polls, otherwise that gentleman <lb/>
would not afterwards have gone with eitghty <lb/>
other members of the House of Commons, <lb/>
into the lobby, for a rehearing of the case <lb/>
of Nova Scotia. There was not much doubt <lb/>
that the delegate from that province acted <lb/>
the part of a deceiver ; nor would this sur<lb break="no"/>prise any one who recollected the ante<lb break="no"/>cedents of an individual who had once de<lb break="no"/>ceived an unprotected female, who confided <lb/>
in his honor ! A man who could thus act, <lb/>
would not scruple to betray his country. <lb/>
That statement he saw in print, and men<lb break="no"/>tioned it merely to show that vice was pro<lb break="no"/>gressive. That circumstances might be <lb/>
regarded as a small matter by some hon. <lb/>
gentlemen, but it had great weight with <lb/>
him, (Mr. McNeill) as it showed the char<lb break="no"/>acter of one who played so prominent a <lb/>
part in betraying his country, and deceiv<lb break="no"/>ing British statesmen. There were few <lb/>
public men for whom he entertained more <lb/>
respected than the hon. the leader of the <lb/>
Opposition, who, he felt satisfied, would <lb/>
never consent to place this Island in con<lb break="no"/>federation, unless the terms had been sub<lb break="no"/>mitted and approved of by the people at <lb/>
the polls ; but he noticed that on a former <lb/> 

<pb n="179" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_178.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">179</fw>

occasion, the leader of the Opposition, in <lb/>
referring to what the Legislature of Scot<lb break="no"/>land, Ireland and Jamaica had done, and to <lb/>
the passing of the Septennial Act, undertook <lb/>
to justify and show the legality of the <lb/>
manner in which union had been carried in <lb/>
Nova Scotia. The Septennial Act, however <lb/>
arbitrary, did not take away from the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of England their constitution ; it only <lb/>
checked for three years the expression of <lb/>
public opinion ; nor did the statesmen of <lb/>
that day ever claim the right of handing <lb/>
over that kingdom to France, or any foreign <lb/>
country, or taking away from Parliament a <lb/>
power which a succeeding Parliament could <lb/>
not reassert? Was Nova Scotia in that <lb/>
position to-day? or would this Island be <lb/>
in that position if it was legislated into the <lb/>
Dominion without consulting the people? <lb/>
Jamaica was a crown colony. They had a <lb/>
good deal of trouble there in 1864. Some <lb/>
of the members of its Legislature were <lb/>
emancipated slaves, or their descenddents, <lb/>
against whom a strong prejudice existed <lb/>
among the white planters. Taking advan<lb break="no"/>tage, therefore, of the disturbance in the <lb/>
colony, the Legislature abandoned its func<lb break="no"/>tions to get rid of the negro element. As to <lb/>
Ireland, the men who represented her when <lb/>
the union was effected, had not been elected <lb/>
to vote away the constitution of their coun<lb break="no"/>try, and though he (Mr. McNeill) was not <lb/>
in favor of length quotations, yet he would <lb/>
read a short extract to prove that the mea<lb break="no"/>sure was carried by the basest of means. <lb/>
Sir Jonah Barrington, who knew what took <lb/>
place at that time. says :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The grand and fundamental point, which <lb/>
was then urged, reasoned upon, and which never <lb/>
has, and never can be refuted, was the incom<lb break="no"/>petence of Parliament to betray its trust." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>and it was that grievance—that unconsti<lb break="no"/>tutional act, which had caused most of the <lb/>
trouble which had since arise in Ireland. <lb/>
The same writer adds further :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Whilst the first elements of the British con<lb break="no"/>stitution exist, that principle is its surest pro<lb break="no"/>tection ; the entire incompetence of representa<lb break="no"/>tives elected by the people, as their delegate <lb/>
trustees, to represent them in the great national <lb/>
inquest, and as such trustees and guardians, to <lb/>
preserve the rights and constitution so entrusted <lb/>
to them, inviolate ; and at the expiration of the <lb/>
term of that trust, deliver back their trust to <lb/>
their constituents as they received is, to be re<lb break="no"/>placed in their own hands, or of any other trustees, <lb/>
for another term. But they had, and could have <lb/>
no power to betray their trust corrupt it to their <lb/>
own corrupt purposes, or transfer the most valu<lb break="no"/>able of all funds, an independent constitution, <lb/>
the integrity of which they become trustees <lb/>
solely for the purpose of protecting." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>That, he (Mr. McN.) thought, carried rea<lb break="no"/>

<cb/> 

son with it, as it went to prove that all the <lb/>
power parliament had was that derived from <lb/>
the people, who elected its members under a <lb/>
constitution clearly defined; and before any <lb/>
parliament undertook to alter the constitu<lb break="no"/>tion under which its members were, or had <lb/>
been, elected it should dissolve, and sub<lb break="no"/>mit so important a matter to the people. <lb/>
He contended that parliament had no more <lb/>
a legal, or constitutional, right to destroy <lb/>
itself, than an individual had to commit <lb/>
suicide ; and in support of his position he <lb/>
would read the following from Lord Chan<lb break="no"/>cellor Plunkett, who, addressing the Speaker <lb/>
of the Irish House of Commons, said :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Sir, I, in the most express terms, deny the <lb/>
competency of Parliament to do this act. I <lb/>
warn you, do not dare to lay your hand on the <lb/>
constitution. I tell you that if, circumstanced <lb/>
as you are, you pass this act, it will be a mere <lb/>
nullity, and no man in Ireland will be bound to <lb/>
obey it. I make the assertion deliberately. I <lb/>
respect it. I call any man who hears me, to <lb/>
take down my words. You have not been elected <lb/>
for this purpose. You are appointed to make <lb/>
laws, and not Legislatures ; you are appointed to <lb/>
exercise the functions of legislators, and not to <lb/>
transfer them ; you are appointed to act under <lb/>
the constitution, and not to alter it ; and if you <lb/>
do so, your act is a dissolution of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment ; you resolve society into its original ele<lb break="no"/>ments. and no man in the land is bound to obey <lb/>
you." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Whatever sympathy he (Mr. McN.) might <lb/>
have for the unfortunate individual, who, <lb/>
bereft of reason, destroyed himself, and <lb/>
was buried, as in olden times, at a cross <lb/>
road, with a stake through his grave, he <lb/>
was utterly at a loss for language to de<lb break="no"/>scribe the abhorrence in which men should <lb/>
be held who would unite to vote away the <lb/>
Parliament of their country. Such men <lb/>
should be held in execration for all time to <lb/>
come. He saw no reason why this Island <lb/>
should unite with Canada. Our system of <lb/>
government was so good as theirs ; they had <lb/>
no privilege we did not enjoy, and certainly <lb/>
in common school education we were in <lb/>
advance of the Dominion. Why then should <lb/>
we think of giving up our constitution? <lb/>
So long as we could manage our own affairs <lb/>
so satisfactorily, and there was so much dis<lb break="no"/>content int he neighboring Provinces, we <lb/>
should never harbor so suicidal an idea. <lb/>
The hon. member for Charlottetown endea<lb break="no"/>vored to prove that the progress of Scot<lb break="no"/>land was owing to her union with England. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—I had said that Scotland <lb/>
had prospered notwithstanding the union. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. McNEILL</persName>.—Perhaps the remark fell <lb/>
from the hon. leader of the Opposition. <lb/></p>

<pb n="180" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_180.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">180</fw> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> said that Scotland <lb/>
had prospered since the union. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. McNEILL</persName> would not deny that; <lb/>
but it was well known that Scotland <lb/>
owed much of her success to those in<lb break="no"/>herent qualities with which God had <lb/>
endowed her sons, and it would be ut<lb break="no"/>terly unfair to assume, as had been done, <lb/>
that Scotland, without her union with <lb/>
England, would nor. have prospered. All <lb/>
knew that the trouble between the two <lb/>
countrieshad been caused by the fre<lb break="no"/>quent wars which took place between <lb/>
them, and when " Prince Charlie" went <lb/>
to Scotland the people thought hewould <lb/>
be placed upon the throne of England. <lb/>
It was about the succession, and not <lb/>
about the repeal of the union that Scot<lb break="no"/>land then contended. But that the Scotch <lb/>
were dissatisfied with the union, a <lb/>
quotation from a letter by their Poet <lb/>
written as late as 1790, to his friend Mrs. <lb/>
Dunlap, would prove. The patriotic <lb/>
poet exclaimed:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Alas! have I often said to myself, what <lb/>
are all the boasted advantages which my <lb/>
country reaps from the union. that can counter<lb break="no"/>balance the annihilation of her independence, <lb/>
and even of her name." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>And in an article from "Tait's Magazine," <lb/>
in 1838, referring to Scottish legislation <lb/>
before and since the union, he read <lb/>
that:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"In 1696 when the Kingdom was in a state <lb/>
of quiet, we find that the Scotch Parliament <lb/>
met at Edinhurgh on the 8th September, and <lb/>
adjourned on thee 12th October, during which <lb/>
46 acts were passed. What is not the least <lb/>
remarkable part of the matter is, that the <lb/>
whole 46 acts are contained in 48 small octo<lb break="no"/>decimo pages. Nearly the whole of those re<lb break="no"/>lating to the law, are to this day in force. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The experience of a century and a half <lb/>
having been able to add little or nothing to the <lb/>
provisions. *** And all of them have not <lb/>
given as much trouble in their interpretation <lb/>
to our courts of law, short as they are, as the <lb/>
Judicature Act, the Cessio Act, or any Act <lb/>
relative to the law which has been passed <lb/>
within the last quarter of a century." <lb/></p> 

<p>"No one, we imagine, will be so absurd as <lb/>
to pretend that the affairs of Scotland can be so <lb/>
efficiently managed by a legislative body sittln <lb/>
hundreds of miles from her territory, an <lb/>
having the interests of an empire dispersed <lb/>
over the whole face of the earth. and containin <lb/>
more than 100,000,000 of human beings to attend <lb/>
to, as by a Parliament meeting in Edinburgh. <lb/>
The Imperial Parliament is, in truth, unfitted <lb/>
for that department of legislation called local <lb/>
and personal. Such legislation is best con<lb break="no"/>ducted on the spot, or as near as possible to <lb/>
the spot, which is to be effected. Witnesses <lb/>
are then at hand; information can be got with <lb/>
expedition and with little expense; the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of a local parliament can be dismissed and <lb/>
called together with little inconvenience. The <lb/>
expense at present necessarily incurred for a <lb/>

<cb/> 

road, a barber, or a railway bill for Scotland is <lb/>
intolerable. One thousand pounds a mile. even <lb/>
in long lines. is not an exaggerated estimate <lb/>
for the mere Parliamentary expense of obtain<lb break="no"/>ing the bill. * * * <lb/></p> 

<p>"Then all matters relative to Scotland are <lb/>
slurred over in the reports or the debates—first, <lb/>
because the reporters think a Scotch Bill, <lb/>
though vitally a acting Scotland, is of no public <lb/>
importance; secondly, because they cannot <lb/>
intelligibly report what they in general do not; <lb/>
understand; and third, because Scotch business <lb/>
is generally put off till past midnight, an hour <lb/>
at which, except on extraordinary occasions, <lb/>
the reporters, by a well organized combination <lb/>
—Whig, Tory, and Radical reporters agreeing <lb/>
on this point—retire from their labor.". <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>This showed how Scottish affairs were <lb/>
managed in England since the union. <lb/>
Nor did he doubt but that the hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Georgetown (Mr. McA.) recol<lb break="no"/>lected what Burns said about Edinburgh. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCAU1">Hon. Mr. McAULAY</persName>.—Repeat it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. McNEILL</persName>.—I will.   <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Edina, Scotia's darling seat, <lb/>
All hail thy palaces and towers; <lb/>
Where once neath a monarch's feet, <lb/>
Sat legislation's sovereign powers." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>That Burns expressed the general senti<lb break="no"/>ment of the people, no one. he thought, <lb/>
would deny. The loss oftheir Parliament <lb/>
drew influential members of society out <lb/>
of the country; they spent their incomes <lb/>
away from home, and there could be no <lb/>
doubt that this proved prejudicial to both <lb/>
Ireland and Scotland. The nobility of <lb/>
both countries removed to London, and <lb/>
even the small proprietors followed their <lb/>
example, and those on their estates were <lb/>
therefore excluded from the consump<lb break="no"/>tion, in their own districts and among <lb/>
themselves. of those fruits which their <lb/>
own industry had created. These and <lb/>
numerous other evils. which those coun<lb break="no"/>tries complained of, he had no doubt <lb/>
they might attribute to the absenteesim <lb/>
attendant upon both unions. The people <lb/>
of this island, aware of what occurred <lb/>
in Nova Scotia, were looking forward <lb/>
with some anxiety to the result of their <lb/>
deliberations. and to the individual opin<lb break="no"/>ions of their representatives. The hon. <lb/>
member for Charlottetown had been, with <lb/>
respect to confederation, on the lence, but <lb/>
had got clean over to the Confederate side <lb/>
at last. He (Mr. McN.) had, in debate, <lb/>
mentioned the name of Benedict Arnold, <lb/>
but not in reference to the hon member <lb/>
for Charlottetown (Mr. B.) He was <lb/>
referring to any persons who would sell <lb/>
their country for Canadian gold. If the <lb/>
union was to prove cordial, It should not <lb/>
be carried by bribery and corruption. <lb/>
Great Britain, upon which we had a <lb/> 

<pb n="181" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_180.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">181</fw> 

claim, should have first settled that <lb/>
claim, for if we accept the $800,000, <lb/>
the colony might, in the union, find that <lb/>
it would be a debt which it would never <lb/>
be able to repay to the Dominion. The <lb/>
hon member for Charlottetown, the other <lb/>
evening, indulged in a tirade of invective <lb/>
against some of his constituents, and <lb/>
although he (Mr. McN.) did not come <lb/>
there to defend the respectable mechanics <lb/>
and merchants of Charlottetown, yet he <lb/>
thought it was out of place for the hon <lb/>
member to use the language he did, for <lb/>
the large majority of his constituents <lb/>
were opposed to confederation, and <lb/>
having returned the hon. member as a <lb/>
no-terms man, was it any wonder that <lb/>
they should say in the language of Wash<lb break="no"/>ington, when Arnold endeavored to betray <lb/>
the West Point, "Who can we trust <lb/>
next?" In listening to the hon. gentleman, <lb/>
he thought his remarks were out of place, <lb/>
when from the sublime to the ridiculous, <lb/>
he soared to the upper story of that build<lb break="no"/>ing where the stuffed owls were kept. He <lb/>
(Mr. McN.) was not going to answer that <lb/>
part of his speech, but in the words of the <lb/>
Dunciade, would say, "Answer him ye <lb/>
owls," and answer him, he had no doubt <lb/>
they would. As a justification for his <lb/>
change of views, he (Mr. B.) mentioned <lb/>
Burke, but the hon. gentleman seemed to <lb/>
forget that when Edmund Burke changed <lb/>
his political opinions, he gave very good <lb/>
reasons for so doing. He had great respect <lb/>
for Mr. Fox, who, for about eighteen years, <lb/>
led that talented opposition in the House <lb/>
of Commons, and who, when the revolu<lb break="no"/>tion arose, thought it was going to give <lb/>
more freedom to the French people; but <lb/>
when he saw that their best men were ex<lb break="no"/>ecuted, and that a reign of terror ensued, <lb/>
he exclaimed, "Oh! bloody, ferocious, <lb/>
cruel democracy;" and in referring to his <lb/>
friend, Mr. Fox, did not indulge in abuse <lb/>
of those from whom he parted but said: <lb/>
"I have indeed made a great sacrifice. I <lb/>
have save dmy conscience, but I have lost <lb/>
my friend." The hon. member (Mr. McN.) <lb/>
also quoted what Sir Robert Peel said to his <lb/>
constituents at Teignmouth, in reference to <lb/>
the principles of free trade, which he <lb/>
characterized as the principles of common <lb/>
sense. Free Trade was then demanded by <lb/>
the nation. The arguments of the anti <lb/>
corn law advocates convinced Peel that he <lb/>
was wrong, and that they were right. <lb/>
Convinced in his own mind, he reversed his <lb/>
policy, and gave the people cheap bread. <lb/>
Did the hon. member for Charlottetown <lb/>
stand in a similar position? The protec<lb break="no"/>tionists agreed that if free trade was car<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

ried, England would go to ruin; or, to use <lb/>
the words of Disraeli on that occasion:— <lb/>
"England, without her agriculture, would <lb/>
fall like the Tyrian die and crumble into <lb/>
pieces like the Venetian Palaces. The <lb/>
free traders admitted that the landed in<lb break="no"/>terests might suffer, but argued that it was <lb/>
the duty of Parliament to legislate for the <lb/>
man, and not for the few. But the re<lb break="no"/>sult had shown that if England never had a <lb/>
corn law, her people would never have <lb/>
thought one was required. It had been <lb/>
said, by some hon. gentlemen, as he al<lb break="no"/>ready observed, that isolation was played <lb/>
out, and that this Island must cast in its <lb/>
lot with the other provinces. The treat<lb break="no"/>ment of this Island had always been ex<lb break="no"/>ceptional; its lands were given away; it <lb/>
was separated from Nova Scotia to please <lb/>
the landed proprietors, and now there was <lb/>
hardly one of the proprietary party who <lb/>
did not wish to tack us on the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion again. That Great Britain would force <lb/>
the people of this colony against their wills <lb/>
to unite with Canada, he did not believe <lb/>
and, therefore, our position wholly depend<lb break="no"/>ed upon ourselves. The hon. leader of the <lb/>
Opoosition was an anti, previous to his go<lb break="no"/>ing to Quebec in 1864, but since then he <lb/>
was in favor of a union, and he (Mr. McN.) <lb/>
believed he was conscientious in the course <lb/>
he was pursuing. But he was utterly at a <lb/>
loss ot understand what had come over the <lb/>
hon. member for Charlottetown. He <lb/>
thought the hon. member must have had a <lb/>
pleasant dream, and fancied himself in the <lb/>
legislative halls of the Dominion, with that <lb/>
musical voice of his pleading the cause of <lb/>
little Prince Edward Island; or imagined <lb/>
that he had arrived at the summit of the <lb/>
ambition of a gentleman of the long robe, <lb/>
clothed in the ermine of a judge, on the <lb/>
bench at Ottawa. But he (Mr. McN.) did <lb/>
not think the hon. leader of the Oppos<lb break="no"/>ition was dreaming; he believed that hon. <lb/>
gentleman was in earnest, but hoped he <lb/>
would yet alter his opinion. No doubt the <lb/>
hon. gentleman thought the anti-confeder<lb break="no"/>ates were slow coaches, and that confedera<lb break="no"/>tion was progress, but such was not the <lb/>
case; confederation was a retrograde move<lb break="no"/>ment. The people of this Island fought a <lb/>
hard battle before they obtained self-gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, and it would not be progress to <lb/>
go into union with Canada, and thus de<lb break="no"/>prive themselves of that constitution. Still, <lb/>
he was inclined to think, neither of the hon. <lb/>
members would act as the representatives <lb/>
of Nova Scotia had done, when they voted <lb/>
away their independence without the know<lb break="no"/>ledge of their constituents. He was sure <lb/>
the hon. the leader of the Opposition would <lb/>

<pb n="182" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_182.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">182</fw>  

not, nor did he think the hon. member for <lb/>
Charlottetown would either. He would be <lb/>
sorry to see the country deprived of the <lb/>
services of the hon. leader of the Opposition, <lb/>
for since he (Mr. McN.) had the honor of <lb/>
a seat in that House, he observed that the <lb/>
hon. gentleman did what he could to for<lb break="no"/>ward the business of the country; and al<lb break="no"/>though they might not meet again in that <lb/>
legislative hall, yet he felt it was due to <lb/>
the hon. gentleman to say, there was some<lb break="no"/>thing very fair about him in debate. But <lb/>
when he saw him pursuing a line of policy, <lb/>
which he regarded as ruinous to the coun<lb break="no"/>try-yes, for if confederation was carried <lb/>
out, it would make a wreck of this Island-<lb break="yes"/>he (Mr. McN.) would be derelict in the <lb/>
duty he owed to his constituents, if he did <lb/>
not raise his voice against anything, and <lb/>
everything, which would produce so dis<lb break="no"/>astrous a result. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>. - The hon. member (Mr. <lb/>
McN.) had made allusion to him; he had <lb/>
first rubbed him (Mr. B.) down and then <lb/>
flattered him up. He had always compli<lb break="no"/>ments for the leader of the Opposition, <lb/>
but none for the member for Charlotte<lb break="no"/>town. Why, he would ask, did the hon. <lb/>
member for Cavendish direct all his <lb/>
remarks to him, and compare him to a <lb/>
Benedict Arnold? There were others to <lb/>
whom he might as properly have applied <lb/>
the comparison as to him, (Mr. B.). <lb/>
The hon. member was a supporter of the <lb/>
present government. Why did he not <lb/>
also include in his remarks his own lead<lb break="no"/>er, the premier of the colony, Hon. Mr. <lb/>
Haythorne, who was a confederate, and <lb/>
not by any means a no-terms man? That <lb/>
hon. gentleman believe that terms might <lb/>
be offered which could be accepted. <lb/>
Why not take him up on this point? He <lb/>
(Mr. B.) would never consent to the <lb/>
Island going into confederation until the <lb/>
people agreed to it, but what did Hon. <lb/>
Mr. Haythorne say:- <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That he had opposed the Quebec scheme, <lb/>
which he considered unfair to the people of the <lb/>
Island, but that he was not, nevertheless, a no-<lb break="yes"/>terms man; that he anticipated a time when <lb/>
proposals of a union of this Island with Canada <lb/>
might be entertained." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Would the hon. member for Cavendish <lb/>
say, that for uttering these remarks, he <lb/>
would take his leader and drive a politi<lb break="no"/>cal stake through his body? (Laughter.) <lb/>
Like the hon. member for Murray Har<lb break="no"/>bor, the last speaker had taken up a line <lb/>
of argument to show that the legislature <lb/>
of Nova Scotia had not the power to <lb/>
legislate the country into union without <lb/>

<cb/> 

the consent of the people. He (Mr. B.) <lb/>
would say that such legislation was a <lb/>
high-handed act, yet it had been done. <lb/>
But what had that to do with the ques<lb break="no"/>tion here? The few extracts which the <lb/>
hon. member (Mr. McNeill) had read were <lb/>
just about as much out of place in this <lb/>
discussion, as would be quotations <lb/>
from Jack the Giant Killer. He said <lb/>
he (Mr. B.) had compared himself to <lb/>
Burke; but he, (Mr. B.) had done <lb/>
nothing of the kind. He had read <lb/>
from that author, but as well might the <lb/>
young lawyer who read an extract from <lb/>
Mansfield be said to be comparing him<lb break="no"/>self to the eminent jurist, as he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
be charged with putting himself in the <lb/>
same category with Burke. The hon. <lb/>
member had also accused him of speak<lb break="no"/>ing savagely against his own constituents. <lb/>
This was another fabrication. He (Mr. <lb/>
B.) had uttered nothing against them; <lb/>
he had only condemned the action of <lb/>
some anonymous scribbler who had said <lb/>
that he should be silent. But he would <lb/>
now turn his attention to the Queen's <lb/>
Printer. (Hear, hear, form Mr. Howlan). <lb/>
Yes, the hon. member might say "hear," <lb/>
but he as leader of the Government was <lb/>
responsible for the setniments of the <lb/>
Queen's Printer. Now, that hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber (Mr. Reilly) had said in his speech <lb/>
last night that accepting union with <lb/>
Canada, on what was known as the <lb/>
"Better Terms," would be practically <lb/>
taxation without representation. That <lb/>
was all very well now, but he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
knew that the Queen's Printer had ad<lb break="no"/>vocated confederation. On the hustings <lb/>
last summer, when the hon. Colonial <lb/>
Secretary was re-elected, the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for St. Peter's uttered something very <lb/>
like confederate sentiments. Besides, he <lb/>
published a newspaper, the Herald, and <lb/>
he (Mr. B.) would read an extract or two <lb/>
therefrom to show what were the hon. <lb/>
member's real sentiments: <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"At all events, we think the time has now <lb/>
arrived when this Colony must state the terms <lb/>
upon which it will consent to enter the pro<lb break="no"/>posed Confederacy. The British Government <lb/>
is apparently determined upon the scheme, for <lb/>
reasons that Mr. Howe's able pamphlet has <lb/>
rendered too obvious, and it may be better for <lb/>
us to make the best terms we can now, whilst <lb/>
a gentleman is in the Colonial Office who is <lb/>
friendly to the Provinces, and who is desirous <lb/>
of securing to this Island the very best terms <lb/>
that can possibly be obtained." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Now place that extract alongside of the <lb/>
hon. member's expressions last night, <lb/>
and see what could be thought of his <lb/>
consistency. <lb/></p>

<pb n="183" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_182.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">183</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName>.- Let the hon. member <lb/>
read the whole article. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> would read what suited, <lb/>
and he would give further extracts from <lb/>
other numbers of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi>:-<lb break="yes"/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"While we speak thus against deception, we <lb/>
have no doubt that the guarantee of the British <lb/>
Government, and a clause in the articles of <lb/>
Confederation, to the effect that the money <lb/>
would be immediately handed over to this <lb/>
Government when the Colony expressed its <lb/>
willingness to join the Confederacy, would find <lb/>
many advocates and friends who had previously <lb/>
opposed the Quebec basis." <lb/></p> 

<p>"We have no hesitation in expressing our <lb/>
belief that if the offer were assented to by <lb/>
Canada, and the money tendered to this Island <lb/>
as the price of its adhesion to Confederation, a <lb/>
majority might be found to accept it." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName>.- Let the hon. member <lb/>
read from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi>; what he held in <lb/>
his hand was not the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi>. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.- Let the hon. member <lb/>
keep cool, and he would read from the <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> of 12th January last:-<lb break="yes"/> </p> 

<quote><p>"We believe that once more an opportunity <lb/>
of settling the land question is at hand. To ob<lb break="no"/>tain that object, all parties, Confederates and <lb/>
Antis, Tories and Liberals- nay, even proprie<lb break="no"/>tors themselves should join hands. Possibly <lb/>
this may be the last opportunity we shall ever <lb/>
see; one was lost at Quebec, which, if judicious<lb break="no"/>ly used, might have led to the happiest results." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>This was strong language, and after <lb/>
what the hon. member had said last <lb/>
night, he (Mr. B.) was almost afraid that <lb/>
something must be wrong with his (Mr. <lb/>
B.'s) spectacles. (Applause.) He would <lb/>
read it again, in case he had been mis<lb break="no"/>taken. [Hon. member re-read extract.] <lb/>
No, there it was, and to what after this <lb/>
should be (Mr. B.) compare the Queen's <lb/>
Printer? Last night union on the better <lb/>
terms would be tyranny-virtually tax<lb break="no"/>ation without representation, and a few <lb/>
weeks ago he said an opportunity was <lb/>
lost at Quebec which, if judiciously used, <lb/>
might have led to the happiest results. The <lb/>
hon. member for St. Peter's could not evi<lb break="no"/>dently be named alongside of his talented <lb/>
fellow countrymen, Grattan and Flood, <lb/>
who contended manfully for the legisla<lb break="no"/>ture of their country; he could only be <lb/>
compared to a political hen, sitting on its <lb/>
nest, and hatching its little political nest <lb/>
egg. (Laughter.) He took up any phase <lb/>
of the question, that would probably keep <lb/>
him undisturbed in his comfortable emol<lb break="no"/>uments. That he was a confederate in <lb/>
sentiment could bee seen by the several <lb/>
extracts which he (Mr. B.) had read from <lb/>
the paper under his control, and if the <lb/>
hon. member for Cavendish wished to <lb/>

<cb/> 

bury all such traitors at his political <lb/>
cross-roads, he had better begin with Her <lb/>
Majesty's Printer. The hon. member <lb/>
from Wilmot Creek also-who was so <lb/>
afraid of the swells and pedlers from <lb/>
Canada,- had better look after [illegible] prin<lb break="no"/>ter of his own government, who support<lb break="no"/>ed it for the sake of office, and not <lb/>
devote so much of his time to the hon. <lb/>
member for Charlottetown, who was no <lb/>
more a confederate than the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for St. Peter's <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> claimed the right to reply to <lb/>
the hon. member for the City, (Mr. Brecken) <lb/>
as that hon. member had made a direct at<lb break="no"/>tack upon him, (Mr. R.). It was not the <lb/>
first time the hon. member for the City had <lb/>
made a political as well as a personal attack <lb/>
upon him. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> denied that he ever made a <lb/>
personal attack upon any hon. member. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> said that when he hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber made personal attacks he always quali<lb break="no"/>fied them with the word, political. He <lb/>
(Mr. B.) was put forward as a sort of <lb/>
political threshing machine, to thresh every <lb/>
hon. member who gave an honest expression <lb/>
of opinion. Some years ago that hon. <lb/>
member had spoken in favor of no-terms, <lb/>
but now he (Mr. R.) believed he was will<lb break="no"/>ing to take almost any terms, and many <lb/>
of his constituents believed the same thing. <lb/>
He (Mr. R.) was willing to abide by what <lb/>
he did say, but it was dishonest for any <lb/>
hon. member to cut out certain parts and <lb/>
paragraphs of an article which might be <lb/>
made to convey a very different meaning <lb/>
from the whole article. The hon. member <lb/>
(Mr. Brecken) had no right to bring up <lb/>
matters connected with a newspaper, in <lb/>
this House; if he would address himself to <lb/>
the editor of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> in the columns of <lb/>
that paper, he would get a reply. He <lb/>
(Mr. R.) was not responsible to the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment for what appeared in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi>, <lb/>
but only for the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Royal Gazette</hi>. The hon. <lb/>
member (Mr. Brecken) had referred to the <lb/>
Queen's Printer as sitting on his nest egg; <lb/>
but when that hon. member (Mr. B.) sat <lb/>
on the nest egg of the Attorney General<lb break="no"/>ship, without the consent of the people, <lb/>
he, (Mr. R.) much as he despised him, had <lb/>
never referred to the fact before. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> said in reference to the <lb/>
Attorney Generalship, he had never asked <lb/>
for the office, but he had been appointed to <lb/>
the office; and he held it at the time of his <lb/>
election by the people of Charlottetown. <lb/>
But where was the Attorney General <lb/>

<pb n="184" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_184.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">184</fw>

of the present government? The Con<lb break="no"/>servatives had been told that they <lb/>
mutilated responsible government by having <lb/>
officials who were not members of the <lb/>
legislature, but now the Liberals had no <lb/>
Attorney General, and scarcely any other <lb/>
officials, on the floor of the House. The <lb/>
reason he (Mr. B.) had brought up the <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> was because the editor of that <lb/>
paper was conducted with a certain <lb/>
amount of ability, and had some influence <lb/>
in the country. The Ottawa <hi rendition="simple:italic">Citizen</hi>, in a <lb/>
leading article on P. E. Island, had congra<lb break="no"/>tulated the confederates on having the <lb/>
Queen's Printer in favor of confederation. <lb/>
The Queen's Printer had accused him (Mr. <lb/>
B.) of taking extracts from articles in his <lb/>
paper, and leaving out what would materi<lb break="no"/>ally alter the sense, but he would ask, <lb/>
could anything qualify such statements as, <lb/>
"The time has arrived when the Island <lb/>
must state the terms on which they will <lb/>
enter the Confederacy," and "It may be <lb/>
better for us to make the best terms we <lb/>
can now." <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> said it was a lawyer's trick <lb/>
to bring forward extracts, without bringing <lb/>
the whole article which would convey a very <lb/>
different impression. The hon. member had <lb/>
not the courage to produce the whole arti<lb break="no"/>cles. He (Mr. R.) would defy any gentlemen <lb/>
to prove that he had ever given his adhesion <lb/>
to confederation on any terms. He (Mr. <lb/>
R.) had never heard of a union being <lb/>
brought about without bribery, and he <lb/>
would tell the people of this Island to <lb/>
beware. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CAME5">Mr. CAMERON</persName> thought the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers who had spoken in favour of confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, had still failed to produce either <lb/>
facts or arguments sufficiently strong to <lb/>
prove that that scheme, if carried into ef<lb break="no"/>fect, would be an advantage to this Island. <lb/>
They had told the hon. committee that <lb/>
Great Britain's desire expressed in Lord <lb/>
Granville's despatch, was that we should <lb/>
unite with Canada, which he admitted <lb/>
to be correct; but he would ask, would <lb/>
we be justified in sacrificing our own <lb/>
real interests as a colony of the empire, <lb/>
for the solo purpose of gratifying the <lb/>
Imperial Government, or the Dominion <lb/>
of Canada, in this matter, and more <lb/>
especially as we had no evidence that <lb/>
coercive means would or could ever be <lb/>
resorted to to unite us? We were told <lb/>
that in the event of a union, Canada <lb/>
would become a market for our exports, <lb/>
and great advantages would accrue from <lb/>
having free trade with the Dominion; as <lb/>

<cb/> 

we would have no duties to pay, the ne<lb break="no"/>cessity for Custom Houses would cease. <lb/>
To this he would say, that even now we <lb/>
had the privilege of regulating our tariff <lb/>
so as to admit Canadian or other goods <lb/>
duty free. And some articles of Domin<lb break="no"/>ion production, which were most in de<lb break="no"/>mand in P. E. Island, were even now on <lb/>
our free list. But as a revenue had to <lb/>
be raised from whatever source it was <lb/>
derived, he believed no special benefit <lb/>
would arise from discriminating, as re<lb break="no"/>garded tariff generally, in favor of the <lb/>
Dominion. Whatever imports we re<lb break="no"/>ceived from the Dominion, would have <lb/>
to be paid in money, instead of taking <lb/>
our surplus produce in exchange. Her <lb/>
climate and soil were similar to those of <lb/>
our own Island. She could therefore <lb/>
never afford a profitable market for our <lb/>
exports, for her own supply would al<lb break="no"/>ways meet her demands. The best mar<lb break="no"/>kets for our agricultural products and <lb/>
fisheries, were found in the United <lb/>
States, the West Indies and Great Brit<lb break="no"/>ain, and from these countries we re<lb break="no"/>ceived in exchange many articles which <lb/>
it was quite certain Canada, from her <lb/>
high latitude and limited manufactures, <lb/>
could never produce. The import duties <lb/>
of Canada - which were 15 per cent ad <lb/>
valorem, and he had reason to believe <lb/>
would soon be raised to 20 per cent, <lb/>
would be extended to this Island if we <lb/>
entered confederation. The effect of <lb/>
such a change would seriously cripple <lb/>
our commercial intercourse with other <lb/>
countries, and injure our propserity <lb/>
agriculturally, commercially and finan<lb break="no"/>cially. The union of Scotland with <lb/>
England in the reign of Queen Anne, <lb/>
had been frequently referred to in the <lb/>
debate, and the prosperity of the former <lb/>
country was held up as being exclusively <lb/>
the result of that union. While he ad<lb break="no"/>mitted that some advantages to both <lb/>
countries had arisen from it, inasmuch <lb/>
as it brought to an end the rivalries and <lb/>
hostilities formerly existing, he believed <lb/>
the commercial propserity and literacy <lb/>
genius of Scotland, might, in a great <lb/>
measure be attributed to the progress of <lb/>
the age in civilization, and the enterprise <lb/>
and the intelligence of the inhabitants, which <lb/>
manifested itself abroad as well as at <lb/>
home. He (Mr. C.) might, with equal <lb/>
force, assert that the national greatness <lb/>
of the United States was due to the <lb/>
separation of the thirteen original colon<lb break="no"/>ies from Great Britain. The arguments <lb/>
in favor of the Scottish union, would <lb/>
not, however, apply to P. E. Island, for <lb/>

<pb n="185" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_184.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">185</fw>

we were too far from Ottawa, the seat of <lb/>
government, with which we could hold <lb/>
no communication during half the year. <lb/>
The isolated position in which the Is<lb break="no"/>land, by nature, existed, would prevent <lb/>
us from deriving any benefit from the <lb/>
railways, canals, and other public works <lb/>
of Canada, while their construction <lb/>
would necessarily involve an enormous <lb/>
amount of taxation, a fortieth part of <lb/>
which would have to be borne by us. <lb/>
The federal government, in levying <lb/>
those taxes, could resort to excise as well <lb/>
as impost duties, as would be seen by <lb/>
an extract from Mr. Galt's remarks, while <lb/>
addressing his constituents in Canada <lb/>
before the union of the other colonies. <lb/>
He then said-<lb break="yes"/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The general government would also have the <lb/>
power of regulating excise duties. The imposi<lb break="no"/>tion of these duties was as necessary as the im<lb break="no"/>position of the duties of customs, and the power <lb/>
to impose the one must be given to the same <lb/>
authority that exercised the power to impose the <lb/>
other. That while the Lower Provinces had no <lb/>
excise duties to any extent, they would have to <lb/>
be subjected to the same regulations that were <lb/>
established in Canada. In general terms, he <lb/>
would state that the general government would <lb/>
have the power of raising money by all thhe other <lb/>
modes and systems of taxation, and there was <lb/>
only one method left to the local governments, <lb/>
which was direct taxation, if their own resources <lb/>
became exhausted." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>He (Mr. C.) felt quite sure that all this <lb/>
would be in store for P. E. Island if she <lb/>
threw in her destiny with that of the <lb/>
Dominion, for our expenditure was <lb/>
yearly increasing. The amount required <lb/>
for our education and public highways <lb/>
alone, would soon exceed our receipts <lb/>
from the central government. Direct <lb/>
taxation would then be inevitable. Sheer <lb/>
necessity would oblige us to resort to <lb/>
local assessments for the support of our <lb/>
present <hi rendition="simple:italic">Free Education</hi>, a policy of which <lb/>
the hon. member for Charlottetown (Mr. <lb/>
Brecken) always appeared to be an ardent <lb/>
admirer, but which he (Mr. C.) thought, <lb/>
would press heavily on our population, <lb/>
while it would create the necessity of an <lb/>
additional staff of officials as collectors. <lb/>
Our system of education was perhaps <lb/>
second to none in the British Provinces, <lb/>
and our mode of providing for it the <lb/>
least cumbersome that could be adopted. <lb/>
That Canada was financially in a worse <lb/>
position than ourselves was quite evi<lb break="no"/>dent from the sentiments of her own <lb/>
statesmen. The gentlemen from whome <lb/>
he had already quoted had stated in his <lb/>
place in the Canadian Legislature --<lb/> </p>

<cb/> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That Canada standing alone had seen her <lb/>
credit seriously impaired, but Confederation <lb/>
would give us a much larger fund to pledge for <lb/>
the security of the public creditor, as the Lower <lb/>
Provinces were in a much better position." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>It might suit the purposes of [illegible] con<lb break="no"/>federate friends very well to say that <lb/>
Canada was not anxious to get P. E. <lb/>
Island, but he (Mr. C.) was of opinion <lb/>
that the above extracts showed very <lb/>
clearly the sentiments which promoted <lb/>
her politicians. Such was their position <lb/>
before the union of the Maritime Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, and now, like Pharaoh's lean kine, <lb/>
they had eaten up those provinces and <lb/>
were still craving for more. We were <lb/>
told that the policy of representation <lb/>
according to population, such as the <lb/>
Dominion adopted, was the soundest in <lb/>
the world, and that it was based on all <lb/>
that was desirable in the constitutions of <lb/>
Great Britain and of the United States. <lb/>
But he would observe that on that prin<lb break="no"/>ciple, Scotland and the city of London <lb/>
would be equally represented in the <lb/>
British House of Commons, as their <lb/>
populations were nearly the same. In<lb break="no"/>stead of this being the case, however, <lb/>
Scotland had 53 members, while London <lb/>
had less than a third of that number. <lb/>
And while the American system in the <lb/>
house of representatives was adopted <lb/>
by the Dominion of Canada in the <lb/>
lower house, the constitution of the <lb/>
senate was entirely different, for each <lb/>
state in the American Republic was <lb/>
represented by two senators, whose <lb/>
tenure of office was confined to six years <lb/>
without any respect to population or <lb/>
extent of territory. The small state of <lb/>
Rhode Island was thus on the same foot<lb break="no"/>ing with New York, whose population <lb/>
was twenty times as great. But in the <lb/>
Dominion of Canada, while each of the <lb/>
Uppoer Provinces had 24 members in <lb/>
the senate, P. E. Island was only to be <lb/>
allowed 4, who were to be appointed for <lb/>
life by the Governor General in Council. <lb/>
Each of the Canadas had thus as many <lb/>
in the Uppoer House as all the Lower <lb/>
Provinces put together. Besides, from <lb/>
the manner of their appointment, they <lb/>
were not responsible to the people whom <lb/>
they represented. It would thus be clearly <lb/>
seen that the constitution of the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion was not the best adapted, at least to <lb/>
suit the circumstances of P. E. Island. <lb/>
We were frequently told that isolation <lb/>
was "played out" and that it was im<lb break="no"/>possible for the Island to remain "out <lb/>
in the cold" much longer. That if not <lb/>
embodied in the Dominion it was sure <lb/>

<pb n="186" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_186.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">186</fw>

to fall in with some foreign power. But <lb/>
he would remark that it had already <lb/>
stood many years while its population <lb/>
were fewer in number and its resources <lb/>
much less developed than at present. <lb/>
Besides, we had many instances of other <lb/>
colonies existing in the same way, and <lb/>
while Britain continued to protect us as <lb/>
one of her dependencies, we had nothing <lb/>
to fear in future, if left alone. But the <lb/>
persistent desire on the part of Canada <lb/>
to confederate British America against <lb/>
the choice of the colonies, was calculated <lb/>
to engender bitterness and disloyalty. <lb/>
Nova Scotia was far from sastisfied. And <lb/>
British Columbia had sent a memorial to <lb/>
the President of the United States, from <lb/>
which he would read some extracts, to <lb/>
show that that colony, while professing <lb/>
loyalty to Her Majesty's government, <lb/>
was forced to seek annexation rather <lb/>
than to be confederated with Canada. <lb/>
The memorialists stated:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That those who are British subjects are <lb/>
penetrated with the most profound feelings of <lb/>
loyalty and devotion to her Majesty and her <lb/>
government, and that all entertain for her feel<lb break="no"/>ings of the greatest attachment and to the <lb/>
country" <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Such were the sentiments and most <lb/>
probably would continue to be, if al<lb break="no"/>lowed to retain their position as a <lb/>
colony. But the next paragraph showed <lb/>
how they regarded the scheme of con<lb break="no"/>solidation:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That we view with feelings of alarm the <lb/>
avowed intention of Her Majesty's government <lb/>
to confederate the colony with the Dominion of <lb/>
Canada, as we believe such a measure can only <lb/>
tend to further depression and ultimate injury, <lb/>
for the following reasons, viz: Trust the confed<lb break="no"/>eration cannot give us protection against internal <lb/>
enemies or foreign fees, owing to the distance of <lb/>
this colony from Ottawa; that it cannot open to <lb/>
us a market for the produce of our lands, our <lb/>
forcats, our mines or our waters." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>He (Mr. C.) felt convinced that the <lb/>
arguments set forth in the above ex<lb break="no"/>tracts would equally apply to P. E. <lb/>
Island. And if any thing approaching a <lb/>
coercive policy was attempted the result <lb/>
might be as serious. He would now <lb/>
call attention to what the people of <lb/>
British Columbia further added:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That our connection with the Dominion can <lb/>
satisfy no sentiment of loyalty or devotion; that <lb/>
her commercial and industrial interests are op<lb break="no"/>posed to ours; that the tariff of the Dominion <lb/>
will be the ruin of our farmers and the com<lb break="no"/>merce of our chief cities; that we are instigated <lb/>
by every sentiment of loyalty to Her Majesty by <lb/>
an attachment to the laws and institutions of <lb/>

<cb/>
 
Great Britain, and our deep interest in the pros<lb break="no"/>perity of our adopted country, to express our <lb/>
opposition to a severance from England and a <lb/>
confederation with Canada. We admit that the <lb/>
Dominion may be organized by confederation <lb/>
but we can see no benefit, either present or <lb/>
future, which can accrue therefrom; that we <lb/>
desire a market for our coal and lumber and our <lb/>
fish, and this the Dominion seeks for the same <lb/>
produce of her own sell. She can take nothing <lb/>
from us and supply us nothing in return; that <lb/>
confederating this colony with Canada may re<lb break="no"/>lieve the mother country from the trouble and <lb/>
expense of fostering and protecting this isolated <lb/>
distance colony, but it cannot free us from our <lb/>
long enduring depression owing to the lack of <lb/>
population as aforesaid, and the continued want <lb/>
of a home market for our produce." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>The folly of attempting to force a peo<lb break="no"/>ple into a political alliance which they <lb/>
were not prepared to acknowledge, was <lb/>
strongly expressed in a declaration of <lb/>
independence reccently issued by the <lb/>
people of the North West Territory <lb/>
which read as follows:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"It is admitted by all men, as a fundamental <lb/>
principle, that the public authority demands the <lb/>
obedience and respect of all its subjects, it is <lb/>
also admitted that the people to be governed <lb/>
have the right to adopt or reject the form of <lb/>
government. In accordance with these funda<lb break="no"/>mental principles, the people of this country <lb/>
have obeyed and respected that authority to <lb/>
which the circumstances surrounding its in<lb break="no"/>fancy compelled it to be subjected. A company <lb/>
of adventurers known as the Hudson Bay Com<lb break="no"/>pany, and invvested with certain powers granted <lb/>
by his Majesty Charles the Second, established <lb/>
itself in Rupert's Land and in the Northwest <lb/>
Territory, for trading purposes only." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>In that declaration they refuse to re<lb break="no"/>cognize th authority of Canada, which <lb/>
they say harmed to have a right to <lb/>
coerce them, and impose upon them a <lb/>
form of government contrary to their <lb/>
rights as British subjects. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.—Will the hon. <lb/>
member state from what paper he is <lb/>
reading? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CAME5">Mr. CAMERON</persName>.—The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Progress</hi>. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.—Oh! That will <lb/>
do! <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CAME5">Mr. CAMERON</persName>.—But he would tell the <lb/>
hon. member that the documents from <lb/>
which he quoted had originated else<lb break="no"/>where, as he (Mr. C.) stated, before find<lb break="no"/>ing their way to the columbs of that <lb/>
paper, which he believed did not by any <lb/>
means misrepresent them, and they must <lb/>
therefore be quite reliable. Those peo<lb break="no"/>ple had no communication iwth Canada, <lb/>
and could not expect therefore to re<lb break="no"/> 

<pb n="187" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-06_Page_186.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">187</fw>

ceive any benefit from a union. Much <lb/>
had been said about the minute of <lb/>
council adopted by the government in <lb/>
reply to the proposals contained in the <lb/>
report of the committee of the Privy <lb/>
Council of Canada. But he thought that <lb/>
document was cautiously worded, and <lb/>
not open to the objections urged against <lb/>
it, because it demanded a "settlement <lb/>
of the land tenure, an indemnity from <lb/>
the Imperial Government for loss of <lb/>
territorial revenue," before the proposals <lb/>
could be recommended to the people for <lb/>
their <hi rendition="simple:italic">consideration</hi>, not their acceptance. <lb/>
The Canadian proposals known as the <lb/>
"better terms" stated:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That in the event of the Island becoming <lb/>
part of the union, the government of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion will endeavor to secure for the Island, <lb/>
from the Imperial Government, fair compensa<lb break="no"/>tion for the loss of crown lands." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Now, what was more reasonable than to <lb/>
test the assumption of the Dominion <lb/>
government, as to what influence they <lb/>
really could exercise at Downing Street <lb/>
respecting our land question? But it <lb/>
did not at all follow that we should <lb/>
accept the terms of union, even if the <lb/>
land grievance or any of the other ob<lb break="no"/>jections stated in the minute of council <lb/>
were redressed. The land question <lb/>
stood on its own merits, and as such <lb/>
demanded a settlement first, independent <lb/>
of union. But we were told in Lord <lb/>
Granville's last despatch never be acknow<lb break="no"/>ledged by the British government, not<lb break="no"/>withstanding the boasted influence of <lb/>
the Canadians. <lb/></p> 

<p>The debated was then adjourned. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>