<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1866-05-05"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1866-05-05">5 May 1866</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1866">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1866, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1866"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Examiner" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="52"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-05_Page_051.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-05_Page_052.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-08">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-05_Page_051">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-05_Page_051.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-05_Page_052">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-05_Page_052.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="51" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-05_Page_051.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">51</fw>

<p rendition="simple:right">Saturday, May 5.<lb/></p>
 
<pb n="52" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-05_Page_052.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">52</fw>

<p>Hon. Leader of the Government then remarked that as many un<lb break="no"/>founded rumors were circulated, and groundless fears entertained<lb/>
by many, touching the course intended to be pursued in regard to<lb/>
the all absorbing topic, Confederation, he considered it would be as<lb/>
well to submit the Resolutions on that subject, which had been pre<lb break="no"/>pared in answer to the Despatches from the Secretary of State to<lb/>
His Excellency the Lieutenant Governor relative to that subject.<lb/>

</p>
<p>Said Resolutions were then laid on the table, and are as follow:—<lb/>

</p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"This House having had under consideration the message<lb/>
of His Excellency the Lieut. Governor communicating a Des<lb break="no"/>patch from the Right Hon. Edward Cardwell, Her Majesty's<lb/>
Principal Secretary of State for the Colonial Department, up<lb break="no"/>on the subject of a Federation of the British North American<lb/>
Provinces, and having most carefully and earnestly considered<lb/>
the project in all its bearings—<lb/>

</p>
<p>"Resolved, As the deliberate opinion of this House, that<lb/>
any Union of the British North American Colonies which<lb/>
would embrace Prince Edward Island, upon the terms and<lb/>
principles set forth in the Resolutions of the Conference of<lb/>
Quebec, held on the 10th October, 1864, would not only be<lb/>
unjust to the inhabitants of this Colony, but prove disastrous<lb/>
to their dearest and most cherished rights and interests as a<lb/>
free people, enjoying the blessings of a priceless constitution<lb/>
guaranteed to them by the Imperial Government of Great<lb/>
Britain.<lb/>

</p>
<p>"That, considering the isolated, peculiar and exceptional<lb/>
position of Prince Edward Island, as contrasted with the other<lb/>
British North American Provinces and Colonies, this House<lb/>
deems it to be its duty , as the Constitutional Representative<lb/>
of the people of Prince Edward Island, to re-affirm the decision<lb/>
so clearly and unequivocally declared by this House in the<lb/>
Resolutions passed by it, in its last Session, upon the subject<lb/>
of a Union of the British North American Colonies, and after<lb break="no"/>wards communicated by the joint Address of the Legislative<lb/>
Council and House of Assembly of this Colony to Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's Imperial Government.<lb/>

</p>
<p>"RESOLVED FURTHER, That even if a Union of the Conti<lb break="no"/>ental Provinces of British North America should have the<lb/>
effect of strengthening and binding more closely together those<lb/>
Provinces, or advancing their material and commercial inter<lb break="no"/>ests, this House cannot admit that a Federal Union of the<lb/>
North American Provinces and Colonies, which would include<lb/>
Prince Edward Island, could ever be accomplished upon terms<lb/>
that would prove advantageous to the interests and well-be<lb break="no"/>ing of the people of this Island, cut off and separated as it is,<lb/>
and must ever remain, from the neighboring Provinces, by an<lb/>
immovable barrier of ice for many months in the year ; and<lb/>
this House deems it to be its sacred and imperative duty to de<lb break="no"/>clare and record its conviction, as it now does, that any Fede<lb break="no"/>ral Union of the North American Colonies, that would embrace<lb/>
this Island, would be as hostile to the feelings and wishes, as<lb/>
it would be opposed to the best and most vital interests, of its<lb/>
people.<lb/>

</p>
<p>"RESOLVED FURTHER, That while this House cannot assent<lb/>
to a Federal Union of this Island with the other Colonies, they<lb/>
recognize it to be the duty of this Colony to contribute, from<lb/>
its local revenues, towards its defence, in fair and just propor<lb break="no"/>tion to its means."</p></quote>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>