<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1873-04-30"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1873-04-30">30 April 1873</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1873">
               <title>The Parliamentary Reporter of Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly</title>.
          <date when="1873"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Examiner</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="104" to="129"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_104.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_106.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_108.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_110.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_112.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_114.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_116.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_118.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_120.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_122.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_124.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_126.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_128.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-08-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-08-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_104">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_104.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_106">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_106.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_108">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_108.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_110">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_110.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_112">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_112.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_114">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_114.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_116">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_116.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_118">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_118.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_120">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_120.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_122">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_122.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_124">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_124.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_126">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_126.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_128">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_128.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_104"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_104.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">104</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            
            <!-- IC, 2018-08-14, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day -->
<!--            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">MR. D. LAIRD</persName> wished to explain 
     <lb/>the statement made by the hon. Leader<lb/>of the Government, in reference to the<lb/>money spent on the Intercolonial Rail<lb break="no"/>way by the Dominion Government.<lb/>We know that that Railway is about<lb/>being finished this coming year, and<lb/>this construction account does not refer<lb/>to the past year at all. The whole<lb/>amount was included in the sum by<lb/>which the $45 per head was obtained.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Debate was then adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>House adjourned till ten o'clock to<lb break="no"/>morrow.<lb/>
            </p>-->
            <head rendition="simple:centre">WEDNESDAY, April 30.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">MR. McNEILL</persName>.- Mr. Speaker, the<lb/>hon. member, the Leader of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment said the Terms offered for our<lb/>acceptance now, are not as good as we<lb/>are entitled to. This may be so. For<lb/>my part I was alwaays one of those<lb/>who thought Prince Edward Island,<lb/>under proper management, could raise<lb/>means sufficient to supply all her<lb/>wants. But now I am sorry to ob<lb break="no"/>serve that both sides of this House<lb/>seem to be of the opinion that Con<lb break="no"/>federation is inevitable, either on the<lb/>Terms now offered or better if they<lb/>can be obtained. But let us see what<lb/>has brought about this state of affairs.<lb/>In answering this question I feel<lb/>bound to say that the Government<lb/>which introduced and carried the Rail<lb break="no"/>way Bill through the Legislature, was<lb/>the part at whose door the cause<lb/>producing that which we now deplore,<lb/>must be laid. If the Railway and<lb/>Confederation are to benefit this<lb/>Island, then no man will deserve more<lb/>credit for the measure than the hon.<lb/>member the Leader of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Ever since the time of the<lb/>Quebec Conference the people have<lb/>closely watched their public men, and<lb/>any of them who expressed a desire<lb/>in favor of the Confederation, had no<lb/>chance of being returned. At all their<lb/>public meetings the question had been<lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           discussed, and their representatives<lb/>understood very well what the feeling<lb/>of their constituents was on the ques<lb break="no"/>tion. In a word, the people were pre<lb break="no"/>pared for everything but that which<lb/>happened. The people of this Island<lb/>never supposed any body of men<lb/>would come into power who would<lb/>pass a measure of such magnitude<lb/>without their consent. But such a<lb/>party did arise. Well do I recollect<lb/>how at that time the prosperity of the<lb/>country was set forth. Not only when<lb/>the road would be building, but ever<lb/>afterwards, was this Colony to be in a<lb/>flourishing condition. How different<lb/>the experience of the reality, with<lb/>what was then so glowingly pictured<lb/>in the speeches of hon. members. It<lb/>was not the paltry outlay upon bridges<lb/>which produced the pressure now felt<lb/>upon the public funds of the Colony.<lb/>I am surprised that the hon. member<lb/>should refer to such matters in the<lb/>manner he did. After listening to his<lb/>speech on Nomination day, I did ex<lb break="no"/>pect to see him coming down with<lb/>better arguments than those which he<lb/>has used in this discussion. On Nomi<lb break="no"/>nation day the hon. member thought a<lb/>branch line of the Railroad was re<lb break="no"/>quired for Rustico, and I did expect<lb/>to hear that he was going to ask this<lb/>of the Dominion Government, instead<lb/>of the small and trifling matters to<lb/>which he referred; such as our Drill<lb/>Sheds, &amp;c. I am inclined to believe<lb/>now, that the speech of the hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber on that occasion was delivered<lb/>more for the purpose of defeating my<lb/>election, than anything he intended to<lb/>do for Rustico. Matters, however,<lb/>have come to such a pass that the peo<lb break="no"/>ple saw no alternative but to enter into<lb/>a union with the Dominion. If better<lb/>Terms can be had, so much the better.<lb/>But this I do not expect. I told my<lb/>constituents that I would not consent<lb/>to lay one dollar more of taxation upon<lb/>them unless the Terms brought down<lb/>were accepted. There are many lease<lb/>holders in my district, and they find<lb/>
            
            <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">105</fw><lb/>
            
           the rent tax enough. One great error<lb/>on the part of the former Government<lb/>was the haste with which the Railway<lb/>Bill was pushed through the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture. And if there is any value at all<lb/>in the Engineer's Report, it is in the<lb/>information it contains on this point.<lb/>With respect to the rest of their Re<lb break="no"/>port it is not worth the paper it is<lb/>written on. There was no person in<lb/>the Legislature, when the Bill was<lb/>passed, who knew anything about<lb/>Railroads, therefore, the time allowed<lb/>for its consideration was too short.<lb/>With respect to the branch lines, it<lb/>was well understood by my constitu<lb break="no"/>ents that the main Trunk was under<lb break="no"/>taken without the consent of the most<lb/>of the people, and they knew also<lb/>when the main line was undertaken,<lb/>the branches were to follow. It may<lb/>be asked how I know this? I answer<lb/>by saying that when the Railway Bill<lb/>was before the House, petitions, numer<lb break="no"/>ously signed, came in against the<lb/>measure. But when the branch line<lb/>Bill was before us, no petition came in<lb/>against it. This shows that the peo<lb break="no"/>ple knew and understood we would<lb/>have to build the branch lines. It<lb/>was neither the building of the<lb/>branches, nor the effect produced by<lb/>the Engineer's Report, which led to<lb/>the unpopularity of the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. In my district these considera<lb break="no"/>tions did not influence half a dozen of<lb/>votes. It was the School Question<lb/>which caused my majority to be but<lb/>fifty at the last election. I am not<lb/>going to say whether the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment did right or wrong, but this I<lb/>will say: They appealed to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple, and in so far as their policy on<lb/>Confederation went, have carried the<lb/>country with them. Nor do I doubt<lb/>but that if the hon. member had ap<lb break="no"/>pealed to the country in the same waay<lb/>with his Railwaay measure, though he<lb/>would not have been sustained, at all<lb/>events he would have incurred less<lb/>blame. Considering the smallness of<lb/>the Island, and the limited revenue of<lb/>
            
         <cb/>
            the Colony, the measure, to say the<lb/>least of it, amounted to a reckless<lb/>piece of legislation. If we have to<lb/>give up our Statute as a separate<lb/>Colony, and go into Confederation, we<lb/>will require the ability of all our ablest<lb/>men to secure the best Terms we can<lb/>obtain, (hear.) But in attempting to<lb/>re-open negotiations with the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government on this question,<lb/>we had better take care we do not lose<lb/>more thant we will gain. The Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government have to contend<lb/>with an able and vigilant opposition,<lb/>and unless the Government are certain<lb/>that better Terms are to be had, this<lb/>House should not consent to open up<lb/>negotiations again. Under the Terms<lb/>brought down we can get along much<lb/>better in Confederation than out of it.<lb/>But under and circumstances we will<lb/>have to resort to local taxation to meet<lb/>the internal requirements of the coun<lb break="no"/>try. You cannot show me any coun<lb break="no"/>try which can get along without taxa<lb break="no"/>tion. We see at this moment that the<lb/>United States Government have now<lb/>to incur expense in putting down a<lb/>war with the Indians; nor do we know<lb/>but the same may occur in Canaada.<lb/>They are encroaching upon the lands<lb/>long held by the original owners of the<lb/>soil, and when they come to be driven<lb/>out of their possessions and hunting<lb/>grounds, it is hard to say what may<lb/>not take place. I have no special<lb/>benefit to receive or expect from any<lb/>Government, but hope every hon.<lb/>member will use his best efforts to see<lb/>that justice is done to the country at<lb/>large. While I hope and trust there<lb/>will be no ill feeling manifested on<lb/>either side in dealing with this very<lb/>important question, (hear.)<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ARSE1">MR. ARSENAULT</persName>.- Mr. Speaker, in<lb/>rising to offer a few remarks upon this<lb/>question, I do not know that I can<lb/>throw any new light upon the subject.<lb/>In listening to the speeches of hon.<lb/>members on both sides, it was notice<lb break="no"/>able that each party threw blame upon<lb/>the other, for the state of affairs exist<lb break="no"/>
           
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_106"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_106.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">106</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            ing in this Colony at present. Per<lb break="no"/>haps the sins are as heavy on the one<lb/>side as the other. For my part, ever<lb/>since Confederation was first men<lb break="no"/>tioned, I thought sooner or later we<lb/>would have to unite our destinies with<lb/>those of the Dominion. When the<lb/>Railway Bill was passed, it was said<lb/>that it was with a view of forcing this<lb/>Island into Confederation. I never<lb/>heard such a matter mooted, nor for<lb/>one did I for a moment believe any<lb break="no"/>thing of the kind. And moreover, I<lb/>believe if the men, who introduced and<lb/>carried the measure, had been allowed<lb/>to complete what they began, it would<lb/>have been better for the country.<lb/>When the late Government was formed,<lb/>it is well known the country at large did<lb/>not force the building of the extension<lb/>lines upon them. It is well known<lb/>that the men who wished to build<lb/>these, left the Government of Mr.<lb/>Pope, and for that support, the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment met the views of the Eastern<lb/>members on that question. But little<lb/>did I suppose that the Opposition<lb/>would adopt a principle they found so<lb/>much fault with. Certainly their act<lb/>in that matter was much more incon<lb break="no"/>sistent than anything which can be<lb/>alleged against Mr. Pope's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment for consenting to go into Confed<lb break="no"/>eration. The late Government have<lb/>been in the habit of arguing that four-<lb break="yes"/>fifths of the people were opposed to<lb/>building the Railway. This I deny.<lb/>Eighteen members voted for the Bill,<lb/>and of these the members of the first<lb/>third, and fifth Districts of Prince<lb/>County, had the instructions of their<lb/>constituents to do so. So had the<lb/>representatives of Charlottetown and<lb/>Georgetown, and the other eight had,<lb/>I suppose, partly the consent of their<lb/>supporters for what they did, so that I<lb/>contend a majority of the people were<lb/>in favor of the measure. But if, as<lb/>they say, four-fifths of the people were<lb/>opposed to building the Railroad, how<lb/>was it that the late party went in for<lb/>the immediate construction of fifty<lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     miles more without the consent of their 
     <lb/>constituents ? It was said the allow<lb break="no"/>ance for land damages was too high,<lb/>and that such is the case I know my<lb break="no"/>self. I believe in some instances the<lb/>allowance has been five hundred per<lb/>cent too high. In one place $500 has<lb/>been paid for the right of way for a<lb/>distance of five chains through a mud<lb/>hole, when the whole piece through<lb/>which the road passes is not worth<lb/>$100. $40,000 was paid to the con<lb break="no"/>tractors for consenting to allow the<lb/>station to be altered at Summerside.<lb/>I mention these as a few out of many<lb/>instances of extravagance which I<lb/>might name, to show how uselessly<lb/>they have been spending the public<lb/>money. I am not pledged on Con<lb break="no"/>federation or any other question. My<lb/>constituents have left me free to vote<lb/>as I may consider best for the interests<lb/>of the country. The hon. member for<lb/>Belfast came down upon this side of<lb/>the House for the extra allowance last<lb/>year to hon. members. I see no rea<lb break="no"/>son why he should do so. The late<lb/>Government were in the majority, and<lb/>might have prevented it. Each of<lb/>them took the money, and having done<lb/>so, I do not see why they should make<lb/>a hobby horse of it to ride themselves<lb/>into an argument. I will support the<lb/>motion for going into committee, and<lb/>shall vote in favor of a delegation<lb/>being sent to Ottawa, to arrange for<lb/>better Terms. Each hon. member<lb/>should do his best to further the in<lb break="no"/>terests of the Colony, and when that<lb/>is done, no blame can attach to any<lb/>one.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROWE1">MR. ROWE</persName>.—Sir, in rising to offer<lb/>a few remarks upon the question be<lb break="no"/>fore us—a question which involves<lb/>giving up our constitution—I will be<lb/>as brief as possible ; and in the offset<lb/>may say, that I was elected to a seat<lb/>in this House by the constituencey of<lb/>Murray Harbor, to go for accepting<lb/>the present Terms. This is the en<lb break="no"/>gagement entered into between them<lb/>
            
           
            <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">107</fw>
            
            and myself, and from which I will<lb/>neither release them nor myself, unless<lb/>very good reasons are shown why I<lb/>should do so. Certainly if better<lb/>Terms can be had I shall offer no<lb/>objections to them. But that they<lb/>will be obtained appears to be very<lb/>doubtful. I have been one of the<lb/>most determined of the anti-Confeder<lb break="no"/>ate, anti-Railway, and anti-Grant<lb/>men in the country. These are my<lb/>principles, and to them I will hold.<lb/>They are also the principles of my<lb/>constituents. But they, like reason<lb break="no"/>able men, seeing the position in which<lb/>the country has been placed, believe<lb/>it is better to receive the present offer,<lb/>and go into Confederation. Were it<lb/>not for the villainous and vicious<lb/>policy of a former Government, we<lb/>would not now be in a position which<lb/>called for surrendering our position as<lb/>a separate and independent Colony.<lb/>I was last autumn elected as an anti-<lb break="yes"/>Confederate. When the House was<lb/>dissolved this spring I did not go to<lb/>the people to get their support for re<lb break="no"/>election. A number of gentlemen<lb/>waited on me to know what my opinion<lb/>was upon the situation of the country.<lb/>I told them I had not thought over<lb/>the matter sufficiently to say what my<lb/>opinion was. They said they had<lb/>changed their mind one one question,<lb/>and believed that under existing cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances we would have to accept<lb/>of Confederation, and asked me if I<lb/>would consent to become their repre<lb break="no"/>sentative. In reply I said, if you,<lb/>knowing my principles, have confi<lb break="no"/>dence enough in me to send me there,<lb/>and will allow me to keep my opinions<lb/>in abeyance, and take my own way<lb/>when there, I will. Well, after the<lb/>Terms came down I went among the<lb/>people and laid them before them, tell<lb break="no"/>ing them they would have to choose<lb/>these, or increased taxation. I did not<lb/>try to persuade them as to what they<lb/>should do, but placed Confederation or<lb/>taxation before them, asking them to<lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            say which they would choose. They<lb/>choose the former. And now Sir, it<lb/>becomes us to see what the basis of<lb/>the union of the different Provinces<lb/>is. The basis seems to have been<lb/>laid down at the Quebec Conference,<lb/>and was the indebtedness of each Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. Now is this, or is it not a<lb/>proper basis ? If so, then in so far as<lb/>I can see, the delegates have made an<lb/>arrangement for the admission of this<lb/>Island into a union with the Dominion,<lb/>in consistency therewith. If, on the<lb/>other hand, they are going to send<lb/>another delegation to Ottawa, it be<lb break="no"/>comes them to shew that this basis is<lb/>an improper one. It appears that the<lb/>present and prospective debt of the<lb/>Dominion, for fifteen years to come,<lb/>were made up, which brought up their<lb/>indebtedness to $45 a head, and start<lb break="no"/>ing with that as basis agreed to, the<lb/>Terms have been brought down in<lb/>accordance therewith. This was, I<lb/>think a wise arrangement on the part<lb/>of our delegates. They looked for<lb break="no"/>ward to the probable increased in<lb break="no"/>debtedness of the Dominion for ten or<lb/>fifteen years, and thereby secured a<lb/>large margin in our favor. This<lb/>shows the Dominion Government are<lb/>willing to deal fairly with us. It<lb/>shows too, that if our resources had<lb/>not been wasted on the Railroad, what<lb/>an excellent position we would be in<lb/>to-day, and how much more we would<lb/>receive from the Dominion for local<lb/>purposes. If the Government, or the<lb/>majority of this House are going to<lb/>send up another delegation, they should<lb/>show, before asking for a vote in support<lb/>of such a motion, that there was some<lb/>omission on the part of the late dele<lb break="no"/>gates. On submitting their resolution<lb/>there should be no concealment as to<lb/>what they intend to ask for. If the<lb/>late delegates failed to ascertain the<lb/>full amount of the indebtedness of the<lb/>Dominion, or omitted any important<lb/>point which should have been taken<lb/>into account ; then the hon. member,<lb/>
         
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_108"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_108.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">108</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873.</fw>    
    
           
     the Leader of the Government, is<lb/> perfectly justified in asking for a dele<lb break="no"/>gation to go to seek for better Terms<lb/>than those they brought down.  But<lb/>as they have not shown that such is<lb/>the case, and as I fail to see that they<lb/>have any just reason for the course<lb/>they are pursuing, I do not feel that it<lb/>is my duty to support the motion. <lb/>Had we not entered into the wild <lb/>speculation of building the Railroad,<lb/>our public debt would be $4,000.000<lb/>less than it is, which at 5 per cent<lb/>would yield an annual revenue of<lb/>$200,000.  Who, therefore, having<lb/>the good of the country at heart, is<lb/>there but what must regret that that<lb/>road was ever built. Had it not been<lb/>for that costly undertaking, we would<lb/>have had that amount of money placed<lb/>to our credit, the interest of which<lb/>might have been drawn for the in<lb break="no"/>ternal improvements of the country.<lb/>Why it would have made our little<lb/>Island almost a paradise. The road,<lb/>I am confident, will never pay its <lb/>working expenses.  The financial<lb/>affairs of the Colony have been gone<lb/>into so fully by the hon. member, the<lb/>Leader of the Oppposition, the hon.<lb/>member for New London. and my<lb/>learned and hon. colleague, that I<lb/>deem it unnecessary to go into that<lb/>matter.  Indeed, they have so lucidly<lb/>set that matter before this hon. House,<lb/>that the Government have entirely 
     <lb/>
    failed to show that they are justified 
     <lb/>in going to Beck for better Terms, or 
     <lb/>able to disprove the statements set 
     <lb/>forth by my hon. friends on this side 
     <lb/>of the House.
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD11">MR. ARCH. J. MCDONALD</persName>.—I 
     <lb/>
     must say, Mr. Speaker, that I am not. 
     <lb/>
     like a great many—or like the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member who spoke last—a Confederate 
     <lb/>from necessity On the contrary, I<lb/>have always been in favor of a union<lb/>of the Colonies, but not having been<lb/>in public life my opinions were not<lb/>known. I believed all along that<lb/>Confederation would  materially ad<lb break="no"/>
               
         <cb/>
               
            vance the general interests  of this<lb/>Island.   The public mind, for a num<lb break="no"/>ber of years has heen so excited by the 
     <lb/>
     agitation kept up on this question, that 
     <lb/>
     it was very difficult to get the people 
     <lb/>
     to give this subject a calm and im<lb break="no"/>partial consideration.  I can distinctly 
     <lb/>
     refer back to a public meeting, where 
     <lb/>
     the suhject was discussed, which I 
     <lb/>
     atttended shortly after the first dele<lb break="no"/>gation was sent to Canada. On that 
     <lb/>
     occasion the junior member   for Bel<lb break="no"/>fast was present, enlightening the 
     <lb/>
     people with his advice and eloquence. 
     <lb/>
     And to this day I have not forgotten 
     <lb/>
     the manner in which  he pictured the 
     <lb/>
     evils which would fall upon.us should 
     <lb/>
     we join the Dominion of Canada. He 
     <lb/>
     pictured Canada as a poor, barren, 
     <lb/>
     narrow strip of country.  I do not 
     <lb/>
     remember whether the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     had a map or not, (laughter). but if 
     <lb/>
     so, it was something of the kind by 
     <lb/>
     means of which he or his party went 
     <lb/>
     through the country with; showing the 
     <lb/>
     curves of the Railroad, by the use of 
     <lb/>
     which I suppose he undertook to con<lb break="no"/>vince the people how foolish they 
     <lb/>
     would be to unite with such a miser<lb break="no"/>able country. Most heartily do I 
     <lb/>
     congratulate the hon. member on his 
     <lb/>
     change of views. But change they 
     <lb/>
     yet will, I have no doubt, on another 
     <lb/>
     question too.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">MR. LAIRD</persName>.—I suppose the hon 
     <lb/>
     member thinks so.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD11">MR. ARCH. J. MCDONALD</persName>—The 
     <lb/>
     Terms brought down, are, I consider, 
     <lb/>
     very fair indeed. I have not the 
     <lb/>
     slightest doubt but if the people had 
     <lb/>
     been in earnest in the matter, that as 
     <lb/>
     good, if not better Terms, could have 
     <lb/>
     been obtained before.   But the hos<lb break="no"/>tility of the country to a movement in 
     <lb/>
    that direction, kept alive and fostered<lb/>by political agitators, was such, that<lb/>those of our public men who were <lb/>Confederate dared not approach the<lb/>question at all. Well, the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment went to the country with these<lb/>
           
         
           <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">109</fw>
           
          
     
     Terms, and I contend that the people<lb/>voted against them.  But while doing<lb/>so they also voted in favor of the<lb/>
     
     principle of Confederation; a majority<lb/>declaring that we were justly entitled<lb/>
     to better Terms still.  Such being the <lb/>case I contend that it is the duty of<lb/>this side of the House to see what<lb/>
     better Terms can yet be obtained, and<lb/>I am sanguine we will soon form a <lb/>
     
     part of the Dominion of Canada on <lb/>Terms which will be just and liberal,<lb/>and which will be much better than <lb/>
     those recently brought down.  Those<lb/>already offered may satisfy me, the<lb/>
     hon. member for Belfast and others,<lb/>but we have to recollect that there are<lb/>
     many men in the Colony who are not<lb/>
     
     satisfied with them.  In entering into<lb/>union with the Dominion, it is a mat<lb break="no"/>ter of great importance to have as<lb/>
    many of the people of this Colony as<lb/>possible satisfied with the conditions <lb/>upon which we enter.  Under such<lb/>circumstances the advantages of Con<lb break="no"/>federation would sooner become ap<lb break="no"/>parent. It would be very wrong to<lb/>force a large proportion of the people<lb/>into union against their will, and I<lb/>think when the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will see that we are in earnest,<lb/>as an arrangement can be made that will<lb/>satisfy the great body of the people.<lb/>The figures have been gone over pretty<lb/>fully.  I would, perhaps, differ with<lb/>hon. members on both sides in some<lb/>of their calculations, but the difference<lb/>is not very material.  I think it is<lb/>much more desirable that the question<lb/>should be fairly laid before the people,<lb/>and to guard against their being mis<lb break="no"/>lead by statements not strictly correct.<lb/>One hon. member said 9 1/2  per cent is<lb/>the average duty paid on articles in<lb/>the Dominion.  I do not think the<lb/>hon. member is quite correct.  It may<lb/>be the average on most of the articles,<lb/>but there may be an excess on others..<lb/>which will make a very material dif<lb break="no"/>ference.  These are matters we can<lb break="no"/>not look too carefully into, nor can we<lb/>
            <cb/>
            speak very positively regarding the<lb/>future on such questions.  Changes<lb/>will take place,and the probability is,<lb/>that in, or out of the Dominion, our<lb/>duty in ten years will be higher, than<lb/>it is now.  The Opposition have en<lb break="no"/>deavoured to make a point about the<lb/>building of the Railroad, and to talk<lb/>loudly about the burden it has im<lb break="no"/>posed upon the country.  Unless they<lb/>show more skill in debating that sub<lb break="no"/>ject than they have yet used, they<lb/>might as well give that argument up.<lb/>They take credit to themselves for<lb/>getting the people to consent to Con<lb break="no"/>federation, and for the ability they<lb/> displayed in securing the Terms .<lb/>brought down.  Yet according to their<lb/>own showing and admission, they could<lb/>not have done so but for the Railroad.<lb/>I contend Sir, that the building of the<lb/>Railway will be of permanent advan<lb break="no"/>tage to the Colony.  The advance in <lb/>the price of labor must amount to<lb/>more than the interest of the cost of<lb/>its construction.  Four cents a day<lb/>for the male working population gives<lb/>about $216,000 per year, and sixteen<lb/>cents makes $900,000 a year of an<lb/>increase in favor of the labor popula<lb break="no"/>ion of the Colony.  Then again,<lb/>equally puerile are their arguments<lb/>when they assert that the exchange <lb/>required to pay the interest of the<lb/>Railway debt, will embarrass the trade<lb/>of the Colony.  They might as well<lb/>say that the building of the Prince<lb/>Edward Steam Boat ship, which cost<lb/>£30,000 sterling, had injured the trade<lb/>of the city, because paying for the ves<lb break="no"/>sel drew that amount of exchange<lb/>from the country.  They may make  <lb/>people who do not understand business<lb/>believe it, but it is unworthy the posi<lb break="no"/>tion of any hon. member to use such<lb/>arguments on the floor of this hon.<lb/>House, (hear.)   Had the present <lb/>Government been in power last year, <lb/>the difficulties, of which so much is<lb/>now said, would not have been heard<lb/>of.  I think, Mr. Speaker, that the<lb/>
          
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_110"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_110.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">110</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            
     present and prospective standing of 
     <lb/>the Dominion of Canada, is such as is<lb/>in every way encouraging. I believe<lb/>it is our duty and interest to try and<lb/>get in under the best Terms we can,<lb/>and make their interests ours, and ours<lb/>to be theirs also, as we shall march<lb/>onward to participate in the bright<lb/>future before the Dominion of Canada.<lb/>(Applause.)<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACE1">Hon. Mr. McEACHEN</persName>.— Mr.<lb/>Speaker, I do not understand why the hon<lb/>members on the opposite side of this<lb/>hon. House should deem it their duty<lb/>to be so frequently taunting the Catho<lb break="no"/>lic members on the School question.<lb/>I am a grant man, nor am I ashamed<lb/>of my views ; on the contrary, I hope<lb/>the time will come when justice will<lb/>be done to them. If Catholics are op<lb break="no"/>posed to having their children in<lb break="no"/>structed in the mysteries of heathen<lb/>mythology, in the public schools, and<lb/>choose to educate them at their own<lb/>expense, they have no right to be<lb/>taunted because they use their own<lb/>money in doing this. Although the<lb/>supreme head of our church is now a<lb/>prisoner, yet nevertheless, I wish hon.<lb/>members opposite to know, that we<lb/>do not intend to let our claims drop.<lb/>We shall press them when we shall be<lb/>in a position honorably to do so. With<lb/>respect to Confederation, I am forced<lb/>to consent to it on the principle of ex<lb break="no"/>pediency, but not of choice. For this<lb/>I blame the late Government. By<lb/>assertions the most reckless, and slan<lb break="no"/>ders as vile as could be conceived and<lb/>uttered, they succeeded in defeat<lb break="no"/>ing a popular Government. Thet<lb/>led the people to believe that wrong<lb/>to an alarming extent was going on ;<lb/>that the Engineers, including Mr.<lb/>Boys, were aiding the Government in<lb/>defrauding the people. Few men<lb/>were more abused than Mr. Boyd,<lb/>simply because he was on our side.<lb/>The love they had for the loaves and<lb/>fishes was so strong, that when <choice><sic>th</sic><corr>they</corr></choice><lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     attained to power they eat their pro<lb break="no"/>mises, and greedily swallowed their<lb/>convictions. They had to do so, or<lb/>yield up the reins of power. I laid a<lb/>trap for them and into it they all fell.<lb/>(Laughter). Yes, after all these slan<lb break="no"/>ders, and strong assertions for the con<lb break="no"/>trary, they went in for constructing<lb/>the branch lines. For any of those<lb/>abominable lines and slanders I do not<lb/>blame the hon. member for New Lon<lb break="no"/>don, but this I do say, he took advan<lb break="no"/>tage of them and used them to aid him<lb/>in carrying out his "Dashaway Policy,"<lb/>The hon. member charged the Pope<lb break="no"/>Howlan Government with making the<lb/>road longer than it was expected it<lb/>would be. Well, on that question at<lb/>least, they have the answer of the in<lb break="no"/>specting Engineers. They brought the<lb/>New York Engineers here and sent<lb/>them on the road to curse both it and<lb/>the men who undertook its construc<lb break="no"/>tion. Respecting the length the En<lb break="no"/>gineers say : "The tables above<lb/>presented, in our opinions, shew that<lb/>while it was possible to have so run the<lb/>Railway, that its total length between<lb/>the termini would have been, say in the<lb/>neighborhood of five miles less than it is,<lb/>yet that this could not have been done<lb/>without increasing the cost per mile to<lb/>a sum greater than the limit fixed by<lb/>the Railway Act" Further on in the<lb/>Report they add : "Our attention has<lb/>been called to the fact that in the de<lb break="no"/>bates on the Railway Act, and also in<lb/>the contract,- which was drawn up we<lb/>believe before any surveys had been<lb/>made,- the total length of the road be<lb break="no"/>tween the termini Alberton and George<lb break="no"/>town, is spoken of as 'about 120 miles.'<lb/>We do not know upon what data this<lb/>distance was estimated ; it seems clear<lb/>however, on the inspection of the map,<lb/>that a line but 120 miles in length<lb/>cannot be run between these places,<lb/>intersecting the points the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment directed it should intersect, even<lb/>if it were quite straight, without a<lb/>curve, other than such as would be<lb/>
     

     <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>  <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">111</fw>  
    
            
   
            
     needed for changes of direction. An 
     <lb/>
     estimate of the cost of road is append<lb break="no"/>ed. This estimate should be kept in 
     <lb/>
     view in connection with what has been 
     <lb/>
     said on the subject of location." Yet, 
     <lb/>
     notwithstanding this clear and reason<lb break="no"/>able answer to their pointed enquiries, 
     <lb/>
     the Government of which the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Haythorne was President, and his 
     <lb/>
     friend, Hon. Mr. Sinclair, the Leader 
     <lb/>
     in this House, wrote for further expla<lb break="no"/>nations on a question answered so 
     <lb/>
     plainly. Do curse the road they 
     <lb/>
     seemed to say. (Laughter.) Well, 
     <lb/>
     here is the answer to their next en<lb break="no"/>quiry: "Now the question is asked 
     <lb/>
     why is the total length of the Railway 
     <lb/>
     more than 'about 120 miles?' To this 
     <lb/>
     interrogatory we beg leave toanswer 
     <lb/>
     that it is because it cannot be materially 
     <lb/>less, and intersect the points named in 
     <lb/>the orders of the Government of 
     <lb/>Prince Edward Island to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment Engineer, who had charge of 
     <lb/>locating the line; neither do our ob<lb break="no"/>servations point out to us that the 
     <lb/>main line could, under any circum<lb break="no"/>stances, be mnch less in length than it 
     <lb/>is; certainly not, unless at a greater 
     <lb/>expenditure than that fixed by the 
     <lb/>Railway Act." After having received 
     <lb/>this answer, I wonder they are not 
     <lb/>ashamed to rise up on the floor of this 
     <lb/>hon. House, and say that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of hon. Mr. Pope made the main 
     <lb/>line longer than it should have been. 
     <lb/> But Sir, they are as destitute of shame 
     <lb/>as their party is of consistency. What 
     <lb/>have they done? They have allowed 
     <lb/>a higher grade on the branches than 
     <lb/>was permitted on the main line, while 
     <lb/>they have given nigh $1,000 a mile 
     <lb/>more for its construction. With re<lb break="no"/>spect to curves, from a point within 
     <lb/>three miles of Souris they have five 
     <lb/>miles of road. I do not blame them 
     <lb/>for this. But why had they not the 
     <lb/>manliness to extend the same justice 
     <lb/>to others? My constituents are 
     <lb/>strongly opposed to Confederation, 
     <lb/>but knowing they do that the reck<lb break="no"/><cb/>less extravagance and gross mis<lb break="no"/>management of the late Government 
     <lb/>
     have brought about the present state 
     <lb/>
     of affairs, they allow me to exercise 
     <lb/>
     my unbiassed judgment in dealing 
     <lb/>
     with Confederation. I am free, there 
     <lb/>
     fore, to give to the Resolution my cor<lb break="no"/>dial support.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Debate adjourned for one hour. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CALL1">MR. CALLBECK</persName> — Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>
     while it is expected that each member 
     <lb/>
     will express his views on this question, 
     <lb/>
     it is noticeable that a good deal of 
     <lb/>
     repetition has been uttered in what 
     <lb/>
     has already been said. Some hon. 
     <lb/>
     members say they have, against their 
     <lb/>
     will, been convinced that Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion is inevitable. I question if in 
     <lb/>
     this respect it is as much against their 
     <lb/>
     will as they would wish many to 
     <lb/>
     suppose. Hitherto I have been op<lb break="no"/>posed to Confederation, but am now 
     <lb/>fully convinced that our duty is to 
     <lb/>Unite with the Dominion of Canada. 
     <lb/>If we do not, then we will have to 
     <lb/>resort to increased taxation immedi<lb break="no"/>ately ; and to this I believe the coun<lb break="no"/>try at large is opposed. The hon. 
     <lb/>member from Egmout Bay gave utter<lb break="no"/>ance to what was no doubt the candid 
     <lb/>truth, when he said both sides were 
     <lb/>chargeable with the causes which pro<lb break="no"/>duced this state of affairs ; although 
     <lb/>other hon. members seem to think it 
     <lb/>is wholly due to the action of the late 
     <lb/>Government in building the branch 
     <lb/>lines and other matters in which they  
     <lb/>took a part during their administration. 
     <lb/>The hon. member for Souris, with 
     <lb/>respect to building the branch lines, 
     <lb/>said he laid a trap for the Government. 
     <lb/>How this was done is best known to 
     <lb/>the hon. member himself. I do know, 
     <lb/>however, that the branch lines formed 
     <lb/>a part of the Railway Act, and by it 
     <lb/>they had to be carried into effect, as 
     <lb/>much as the building of the main line, 
     <lb/>the only difference being as to time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACE1">Hon. Mr. MCEACHEN</persName>.—Did I un<lb break="no"/>derstand the hon. member as referring 
     <lb/>to me? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_112"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_112.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">112</fw><fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw><fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            
            
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CALL1">MR. CALLBECK</persName>.—I understood the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member to say, when he was 
     <lb/>
     speaking on this question, that the 
     <lb/>
     immediate construction of the branch 
     <lb/>
     lines had been forced upon the late 
     <lb/>
     Government by a trap which the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member laid for them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACE1">Hon. Mr. McEACHEN</persName>,—I am proud 
     <lb/>
     to admit that such is the case.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CALL1">MR. CALLBECK</persName>.—I take it then 
     <lb/>
     that the Coalition Government was 
     <lb/>
     pledged to the immediate construction 
     <lb/>
     of the branch lines, moreover I have 
     <lb/>
     it on good authority that his honor, 
     <lb/>
     the leader of the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment promised, before the dissolution 
     <lb/>
     last year, to go for their immediate 
     <lb/>
     construction, and that this arrange<lb break="no"/>ment was agreed to and signed on 
     <lb/>
     behalf of Mr. Pope's Government, by 
     <lb/>
     him as President of the Executive 
     <lb/>
     Council. Such being the case, the 
     <lb/>
     late  Government was, according 
     <lb/>
     to constitutional usage, morally bound 
     <lb/>
     to accept and carry out the conditions 
     <lb/>
     thus bequeathed to them by their 
     <lb/>
     predecessors. In carrying out that 
     <lb/>
     stipulation, however, the lines were 
     <lb/>
     ran, and surveys made, before the con<lb break="no"/>tract was let, and every precaution 
     <lb/>
     taken to guard against injustice being 
     <lb/>
     done to the country. The Leader of 
     <lb/>
     the Government said the 21/2 per cent 
     <lb/>
     imposed would raise sufficient of 
     <lb/>
     revenue to meet the necessary expen<lb break="no"/>ture. Besides, it was well known, 
     <lb/>
     that no further outlay would be re<lb break="no"/>quired until the present session. I 
     <lb/>
     contend, therefore, that in building the 
     <lb/>
     branches the late Government did not 
     <lb/>
            
          <!-- IC, 2018-08-15, untaggedTable commented out table to be marked-up at later date.-->
          <!--  <p>
     $45 per head amounts to 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Interest on the above at 5 per  cent, gives 
     <lb/>
      Amount  brought  forward,    
     <lb/>
     Ditto on  $900,000  
     <lb/>
     Ditto on $69,000 for our Law Courts, 
     <lb/>
      Legislative  Grant,  
     <lb/>
    Head Money,  
     <lb/>One per cent on Railway debt being 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            <cb/>
           
     act inconsistently. With respect to 
     <lb/>
     the financial question, I would simply 
     <lb/>
     remark, that if an individual was do<lb break="no"/>ing a legitimate business and that all 
     <lb/>
     of a sudden he rushed into a specula<lb break="no"/>tion which increased his indebtedness 
     <lb/>
     eighteen fold, would it be any wonder 
     <lb/>if he found his credit injured in con<lb break="no"/>sequence ? It is precisely so with a 
     <lb/>Government. In 1869, our public 
     <lb/>indebtedness amounted to but $5 a 
     <lb/>head, while that of the Dominion was 
     <lb/>$25 a head. Ours is now up to $40, 
     <lb/>while by the Terms the delegates have 
     <lb/>brought down, the Dominion debt, has 
     <lb/>—or soon will be—up to $45. Now 
     <lb/>when the short space of four years 
     <lb/>our debt per head of the population 
     <lb/>has increased from $5 to$40 a head, 
     <lb/>is it any wonder that the public debt 
     <lb/>of the Colony has suffered in conse<lb break="no"/>quence? Unquestionably it  is the 
     <lb/>duty of  every public man to use his 
     <lb/>best efforts to maintain the credit of 
     <lb/>the Colony. But I have not met with 
     <lb/>one man who can point out how our 
     <lb/>public credit can be restored outside 
     <lb/>of Confederation. I am not opposed to 
     <lb/>seeking better Terms providing it can 
     <lb/>be shown that these  now offered are 
     <lb/>unjust or unfair towards this Colony. 
     <lb/>I have carefully looked into the mat<lb break="no"/>ter, and believe that  the Dominion 
     <lb/>Government, in the Terms agreed to 
     <lb/>with the delegates, have allowed us as 
     <lb/>much as they could ; and that they 
     <lb/>could not have consented to more 
     <lb/>favorable Terms, without doing in<lb break="no"/>justice to the other Provinces. Our 
     <lb/>cash receipts from the Dominion, un<lb break="no"/>der the Terms brought down, would 
     <lb/>be as follows:— ' 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <!-- IC, 2018-08-15, untaggedTable commented out table to be marked-up at later date.-->
            <!--<p>
     $4,230,945 
     <lb/>
     $211,547 
     <lb/>
        $211,547 
     <lb/>
      45,000 
     <lb/>
     3,450 
     <lb/>
     30,000 
     <lb/>
     75,000 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            <p>
     the interest we pay,       32,500 
     <lb/>
    Interest on $22,000 for Steam Dredge,    1,100   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Thus our annual cash receipts from the 
     <lb/>Dominion would be        $398,597 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I will now invite your attention Mr. Speaker, and that of this hon House, to 
     <lb/>
    what our receipts would be under the Dominion Tariff ; supposing we were to 
     <lb/>adopt it and remain as we are. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Customs and Excise, $308,850 
     <lb/>
     Stamp Tax,  5,000 
     <lb/>
     Bank Impost, 250 
     <lb/>
     Distilling Licenses 600 
     <lb/>
     Light and Anchorage Duties,    2,000 
     <lb/>
     Post Office Revenue, 10,000 
     <lb/>
     Savings Bank, 3,700 
     <lb/>
     Malt and Tobacco Taxes, 10,000 
     <lb/>
     Fees from Customs, 1,000 $341,400 
     <lb/> <lb/>
     Thus leaving in our favor a balance of $57,197 
     <lb/>
     by the terms of Messrs. Laird and   
     <lb/>
     
     Heythorne.   
     <lb/>
     To which we may add for salaries and 
     <lb/>
     other expenses borne by the Do<lb break="no"/>minion, the further sum of 94,000 
     <lb/>
      <lb/>Thus showing a total of $151,197 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <p>
     
     Which shows clearly that we have in    
     <lb/>
     the arrangements entered into the best 
     <lb/>
     of the bargain. In dealing with this        
     <lb/>
     question of union, the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment have laid down a principle        
     <lb/>
     based upon the indebtedness of each     
     <lb/>
     Colony, and it is unreasonable to sup<lb break="no"/>pose that Canada will now step aside     
     <lb/>
     from it. To do so would virtually         
     <lb/>
     alter the foundation upon which  the        
     <lb/>
     whole superstructure of the Dominion     
     <lb/>
     is built. We have no right to ask for 
     <lb/>
     more than what is right and reason<lb break="no"/>able. And even were we to obtain     
     <lb/>
     more, we would find in the end that it  
     <lb/>
     would only open the door for similar 
     <lb/>
     demands from the other Provinces.      
     <lb/>
     When the Terms came down, I ex<lb break="no"/>amined them carefully, and the more 
     <lb/>closely I look into them, the more 
     <lb/>reasonable they appear to me to be.<lb/>I have also heard several say it would<lb/>be a risk to trifle with them. Because<lb/>it the Dominion have offered and<lb/>
           
            <cb/>
            
     agreed to Terms that are just to us,   
     <lb/>
     it we open up negotiations again, we     
     <lb/>
    will leave it in their power to with<lb break="no"/>draw them. And this the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada might be induced to 
     <lb/>do if they apprehended an opposition            
     <lb/>in Parliament to them, which they  
     <lb/>might not be able to overcome, there<lb break="no"/>fore, I think it is far better to hold on<lb/>to what we have. Were it not for<lb/>our isolated position I believe they<lb/>would not have dealt so liberally with<lb/>us. Of all the public works likely in<lb/>the future to be undertaken in the<lb/>Dominion, there will be none from<lb/>which this Island will receive more<lb/>direct and immediate benefits, that the<lb/>Bay de Verte Canal. By it a short<lb/>route will be opened up to St. John<lb/>and the seaport cities of the neighbor<lb break="no"/>ing Republic. Indeed, I question if it<lb/>will be of any more advantage to<lb/>those on the main land than it will<lb/>be to ourselves. So great will the<lb/>advantage be, which will accrue to us<lb/>
            
    
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_114"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_114.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">114</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
           
     from that work, that I think the one-<lb break="yes"/>fortieth part of the estimated cost ought<lb/>not to be deducted from the amount<lb/>charged against us. Then, with re<lb break="no"/>spect to what Mr. Tilley has said, if<lb/>
    his statementsn are not correct, he will<lb/>be corrected.  But I take it that his<lb/>statements are correct. The Leader          
     <lb/>of the Government in his calculations . 
     <lb/>has not, I think, shown any more<lb/>ability in dealing with the financial      
     <lb/>aspects of the question, than the Leader<lb/>of the Opposition. For my part I         
     <lb/>question if he has shown as much. I             
     <lb/>cannot for one agree with him that<lb/>one third should be struck off from<lb/>what the sale of public lands is set            
     <lb/>down for. I admit, if it were to fall off       
     <lb/>as Lot 19 did, there might be some 
     <lb/>reason for making such a calculation, 
     <lb/>but this is not what we may expect.   
     <lb/>Our delegates have done well for the       
     <lb/>Colony in securing $800,000 for the           
     <lb/>purchase of our public lands. When   
     <lb/>land can be bought, and the proprie-         .   
     <lb/>tors disposed to sell, the money can be           
     <lb/>drawn for, as may be required. So         
     <lb/>that I think we have in this arrange-       
     <lb/>ment the prospect of being able to           
     <lb/>buy out the last of the proprietors.       
     <lb/>No doubt to effect this we shall have           
     <lb/>the assistance of the Dominion Gov-       
     <lb/>ernment. The home Government         
     <lb/>never could understand why a farm         
     <lb/>of 100 acres, though wholly covered           
     <lb/>with wood, was not cheap to a poor<lb/>man at the rate of £5 a year But       
     <lb/>the Dominion Cabinet is composed of<lb/>men who fully understand the ques-     
     <lb/>tion. Under all the circumstances, I     
     <lb/>think we can get along for a consider-         
     <lb/>able time under the Terms proposed,           
     <lb/>without having to resort to an increase                 
     <lb/>of local taxation. The remarks of the             
     <lb/>hon. member for Georgetown, respect<lb break="no"/>ing the increased value of labor.<lb/>might have some weight if we had a<lb/>surplus of laborers, but as we have<lb/>not, I cannot see any force in the              
     <lb/>argument.  It has also been said that<lb/>the country as a whole oppose the <lb/>present Terms. But in this hon.   
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     House there are but two members who 
     <lb/>are really anti-Confederate, and I re<lb break="no"/>spect them for their consistency, while<lb/>I cannot but admire the outspoken<lb/>honesty of the junior member for<lb/>Bedeque, who, I think, admitted that<lb/>he saw no means by which we might<lb/>keep out.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOLL1">MR. HOLLAND</persName>.-I said that.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CALL1">MR. CALLBECK</persName>.---As regards the               
     <lb/>recklessness charged against the late<lb/>Government, I think if the matter is ex<lb break="no"/>amined into, it will be found that the<lb/>recklessness was not all on one side.<lb/>It was stated that the road would not<lb/>be more than 120 miles long from<lb/>Alberton to Georgetown, and that the<lb/>cost would not exceed £5,000 per<lb/>mile, while I think the Leader of<lb/>the Government said ££6,000 per mile<lb/>would cover the whole cost of the<lb/>road.  Now these calculations were <lb/>made on the supposition that the dis<lb break="no"/>tance would not exceed 120 miles.  I<lb/>said then I believed the road would<lb/>cost £800,000, but my statement was <lb/>laughed at.  It is now admitted that<lb/>the road will cost three and one quarter<lb/>millions of dollars, which shows that<lb/>when I based my calculations on the<lb/>number of miles then given, that I<lb/>was nearer the mark than than the hon.<lb/>member, was in his estimate.  Cer<lb break="no"/>tainly I was much nearer to it than<lb/>the hon. member the Leader of the <lb/>Government was in his calculations for<lb/>land damages.  Now, if these able<lb/>financiers made such mistakes when<lb/>there was no inducemtoent for them to<lb/>do so, in order to get their supporters <lb/>to vote for the measure, I can only<lb/>come to the conclusion that in these<lb/>respects they were just as ignorant as <lb/>men whose opinions they seemed to<lb/>despise.  If, however, the Leader of<lb/>the Government is going to endeavor<lb/>to get a branch line of the Railway to<lb/>Rustico, he shall have my support in<lb/>that matter.  But when I find his<lb/>disposition is now to find fault with<lb/>
               
            <fw type="dateline">1873</fw><fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw><fw type="num">115</fw>
               
            the late Government for contracting<lb/>for the New London, Victoria, and<lb/>other bridges, so much required in<lb/>those parts of the country, I have little<lb/>hope that he intends to exert himself<lb/>much for the benefit of the people of<lb/>Rustico. The subscription for some<lb/>of the bridges and local works referred<lb/>to are considerable, the payment of<lb/>some of them over a period of of<lb/>two  or three years, while some have<lb/>paid up the first instalment already.<lb/>But it is not specially my duty to refer<lb/>to these matters.  There are hon. <lb/>members on this side of the House<lb/>who are quite capable of doing so.<lb/>At all events in the Terms brought<lb/>down, from the statistics I have read,<lb/>it will be seen, that there is a balance<lb/>in our favor sufficient to cover the cost<lb/>of some of these works.  The Terms<lb/>now offered are in excess of those of<lb/>1869, and not as the hon. member at<lb break="no"/>tempted to show, $89,000 less.  The<lb/>hon. member does not attempt to<lb/>show now that the Railway will pay<lb/>working expenses, or that it is worth<lb/>the cost of its construction.  We have<lb/>Terms offered that are just to Prince<lb/>Edward Island.  By accepting them<lb/>we do justice to those we represent,<lb/>while acceding also to the expressed <lb/>desire of her Majesty's Government,<lb/>by going with the Dominion to share<lb/>in her honors, and participate in her <lb/>reverses. No doubt we will yet if we<lb/>go in, have to contribute our propor<lb break="no"/>tion towards the defences of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion of Canada, and in case of war<lb/>or invasion, be called upon to bear our<lb/>fair share of the burden.. As the pop<lb break="no"/>ulation increases so will the taxes.<lb/>It is found to be so in all new coun<lb break="no"/>tries.  Hence in so far as we are con<lb break="no"/>cerned it will be the same, in that<lb/>respect whether we go into or remain<lb/>out of Confederation.  If in the Union<lb/>we will have our advantages, we shall<lb/>also have to put up with disadvan<lb break="no"/>tages.  I believe that according <lb/>to our population we can bear as much<lb/>taxation as they can in the Dominion.<lb/>
               <cb/>
               <lb/>Our soil is as good, and our people as<lb/>industrious and economical as theirs<lb/>are, and, therefore, in that respect we<lb/>can bear our lot just as well as they can.<lb/>While the people of Canada have as<lb/>great an aversion to high taxes as a<lb/>people can have, I do not see what we<lb/>have to dread from a union with the<lb/>Dominion on the score of increased<lb/>taxation.  Unquestionably if we re<lb break="no"/>main out of Confederation, our taxes<lb/>will have to be raised fifty per cent<lb/>higher than they are at present.<lb/></p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:BEER2">Mr. BEER</persName>.---Sir, I did not expect<lb/>the discussion on the motion to go into<lb/>committee on the dispatches would<lb/>have continued so long.  But as the hon.<lb/>members on both sides have gone into<lb/>the matter so fully, I feel called upon<lb/>to offer a few remarks. I already<lb/>stated that I ran my election on the<lb/>Terms brought down by hons, Mr.<lb/>Haythorne and Laird, and was re<lb break="no"/>turned to this House to vote for ac<lb break="no"/>cepting them.  In any of the argu<lb break="no"/>ments advanced in favor of sending up<lb/>another delegation to seek for better<lb/>Terms still, I have failed to see that<lb/>they have any grounds to hope that<lb/>they will succeed in obtaining better<lb/>than those already offered.  State<lb break="no"/>ments have been made here which<lb/>are not correct, and have obviously<lb/>been brought forward to mystify the<lb/>House.  Still. if better Terms can be<lb/>had, I am sure no one will be more<lb/>pleased than I will be. I have be<lb break="no"/>come a Confederate from necessity,<lb/>not from choice, while I hold the<lb/>opinion now which I did three years<lb/>ago, that, were it not for the Railroad<lb/>and the heavy burden it has imposed<lb/>upon the country, this Island would<lb/>be under no necessity to appear at the<lb/>Bar of the Privy Council if Canada,<lb/>seeking for admission.  No doubt the<lb/>Bill was passed with that intent, and<lb/>the gentleman who told me he felt<lb/>easy respecting the matter after it was <lb/>carried, did no more than express the<lb/> <lb/>
            
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_116"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_116.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">116</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            
     the..hon. members wanted. the   support 
     <lb/>
    of. the Eastern members, failing to 
     <lb/>secure that he lost all interest in the   
     <lb/>extension of the branch lines. Again, 
     <lb/>objection has been taken to the amount 
     <lb/>paid for the Boat which runs to South<lb break="no"/>port.  Well., I do not think the hon. 
     <lb/>member will gain much credit to him<lb break="no"/>self on that score. Are those who live 
     <lb/>on the south side of the Hillsborough 
     <lb/>going to see all the revenue expended 
     <lb/>in building Railways in which they 
     <lb/>have no direct interest, and when they 
     <lb/>ask for the convenience of a suitable 
     <lb/>Ferry Boat to enable them to reach 
     <lb/>the capital are they to be denied? 
     <lb/>Are we to be told we have no right 
     <lb/>to such accommodation ? Such argu<lb break="no"/>ments won't do. Again, if the Branches 
     <lb/>did cost nigh $1,000 a mile more than 
     <lb/>the Main Line, the material is to 
     <lb/>be so much better, that the contractors 
     <lb/>will not make so much money out of 
     <lb/> it as they will on the Main Line. The 
     <lb/>Light Houses, Drill Sheds, &amp;c, will 
     <lb/>form the basis of a poor ground of 
     <lb/>argument, on our behalf, for better 
     <lb/>terms, as the hon. member will find 
     <lb/>when he gets to Ottawa. The report 
     <lb/>of the inspecting Engineers was not 
     <lb/>received until September, while the 
     <lb/>maps, &amp;c., did not come to hand until 
     <lb/>some considerable time afterwards. 
     <lb/>The correspondence did not close until 
     <lb/>the 6th of November, so that the late 
     <lb/>government were wrongly accused   in 
     <lb/>the matter.  I would like to know Mr. 
     <lb/>Speaker, if the Report exonerates the 
     <lb/>former Government from blame, in 
     <lb/>the matter of the wire fence? The 
     <lb/>Engineers were asked to report upon 
     <lb/>the sufficiency of the wire fence. Just 
     <lb/>allow me to read their reply:—" Re<lb break="no"/>specting the sufficiency of the wire 
     <lb/>fence, of which you have doubt, we 
     <lb/>  suggested in our. report, certain modes 
     <lb/>of increasing its strength, which we 
     <lb/>think will make it adequate to protect 
     <lb/>the line." This is in the last reply. 
     <lb/>In the former report   they say :—" If 
     <lb/>the .government are satisfied   that the: 
     <lb/>doubts respecting the sufficiency of this 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     fence are well founded; measures 
     <lb/>
     should .be taken to make it of adequate 
     <lb/>
     strength."   I question if there is a 
     <lb/>
     little school boy in the country who 
     <lb/>
     would not have given a more direct 
     <lb/>
     and satisfactory answer to the question 
     <lb/>
     than this.  To that, if we are to judge 
     <lb/>
     of the report by the answer given to 
     <lb/>
     the enquiry respecting the wire fence, 
     <lb/>
     it is simply not worth  the paper it is 
     <lb/>
     written on.  With regard to McNeill's 
     <lb/>
     Tender for the construction of the 
     <lb/>
     Branch lines the government did a 
     <lb/>
     good thing for the country by not 
     <lb/>
     accepting it.   He actually, by his Ten<lb break="no"/>der, wished to obtain for grading the 
     <lb/>
     Road $150,000 or $50,000 more than 
     <lb/>
     it would cost, while he only offered us 
     <lb/>
     securityfor $100,000: He either did 
     <lb/>
     not know his business, or he was 
     <lb/>
     trying to take an advantage of the 
     <lb/>
     Government. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Summerside referred to the alteration 
     <lb/>
     of the Station at Summerside, and said 
     <lb/>
     he thought a supporter of the . govern<lb break="no"/>ment was aware of tbat, before it was 
     <lb/>
     generally known, and used that know<lb break="no"/>ledge to his advantage in disposing 
     <lb/>
     of some lots of land, before the know<lb break="no"/>ledge he possessed respecting the al<lb break="no"/>teration was generally known.  All I 
     <lb/>
     can say in reply to that matter is, that 
     <lb/>
     the removal of the station was pretty 
     <lb/>
     generally spoken of   for a considerable 
     <lb/>
     time before it took place. The hon. 
     <lb/>
     member said   further that the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Haythorne promised that he would 
     <lb/>
     not do anything in the matter of con<lb break="no"/>federation without consulting his con<lb break="no"/>stituents. But Mr. Haythorne's action 
     <lb/>
     in that matter has been endorsed by 
     <lb/>
     the constituents he represents. He is 
     <lb/>
     therefore free of all blame in the mat<lb break="no"/>ter. It was next asked why the 
     <lb/>
     contract was kept back so long be<lb break="no"/>fore it was completed respecting the 
     <lb/>
     Branch Lines?  My answer to that is, 
     <lb/>
     that an unlooked for spell   of stormy 
     <lb/>
     weather prevented the members of the: 
     <lb/>
     Government to get in from the coun<lb break="no"/>try earlier. That I believe was the 
     <lb/>
     chief reason why the matter was de<lb break="no"/><fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">117</fw><lb/>layed so long. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Alberton said that were it not for the 
     <lb/>
     money circulated in building the Rail<lb break="no"/>way last year he did not know what 
     <lb/>
     the country    would have done for ex<lb break="no"/>change. Well if there is any force in 
     <lb/>
     that argument, if two years hence, or at 
     <lb/>
     .any future time a financial pressure is 
     <lb/>
     likely to happen, we will only have to 
     <lb/>
     enter into another Railway speculation, 
     <lb/>
     when we would obtain what exchange 
     <lb/>
     we might require.  No doubt the ob<lb break="no"/>ject the hon. member had in view was 
     <lb/>
     to shew that messrs. Haythorne and 
     <lb/>
     Laird were not the men whom the 
     <lb/>
     late Government should have sent to 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa. They, of course were not 
     <lb/>
     the men the hon. member would 
     <lb/>
     have selected. Last year we heard a 
     <lb/>
     good deal about the Tracadie estates, 
     <lb/>
     and of the hardships tenants had to 
     <lb/>
     contend with. For my part I believe 
     <lb/>
     it is worth going into Confederation, 
     <lb/>
     if it is for no other reason than the 
     <lb/>
     certainty that exists by so doing of 
     <lb/>
     relieving these people out of their 
     <lb/>
     present, almost, state of bondage. As  
     <lb/>
     to the delegation now going up to 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa, I have no faith that they 
     <lb/>
     will receive any better Terms than 
     <lb/>
     those already offered. I am strongly 
     <lb/>
     of the opinion that in going up   again 
     <lb/>
     they will place themselves and the 
     <lb/>
     Island in a false position. Still, it is 
     <lb/>
     not impossible but that something 
     <lb/>
     better may be obtained, and if so, I 
     <lb/>
     will hold myself free to support them. 
     <lb/>
     I hope soon to hear my hon. colleague 
     <lb/>
     come out against Confederation.  Cer<lb break="no"/>tainly during the election I thought 
     <lb/>
     he ran as an anti-Confederate, and 
     <lb/>
     will only be disappointed if he does 
     <lb/>
     not join in supporting the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Bedéqiie in his anti-Confed<lb break="no"/>erate Resolution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KELL2">Hon. F. KELLY</persName>.--My hon. col<lb break="no"/>league referred to what I said during<lb/>the canvass of the last election. I did<lb/>not say I thought we could keep out<lb/>of a union with Canada.  What I did<lb/>say was, that I would use my exertions<lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     to get better Terms, and make a better 
     <lb/>
     bargain than the one agreed to by the 
     <lb/>
     late delegates . With respect to the 
     <lb/>
     Tracadie estate, I was the first who, in 
     <lb/>
     this House brought in a Bill for the 
     <lb/>
     relief of these people, and if I had 
     <lb/>
     been here last year I would not have   
     <lb/>
     allowed the measure to have been dis<lb break="no"/>posed of so easily. I contend the late 
     <lb/>
     Government did not dea1 justly with 
     <lb/>
     the tenants on that estate.   If the Bill   
     <lb/>
     I brought forward, and which was dis<lb break="no"/>posed of by the late Government, last 
     <lb/>
     Session, had been sustained, it would 
     <lb/>
     have relieved them from their present 
     <lb/>
     embarrassing condition. With respect 
     <lb/>
     to the motion before the hon. House, I 
     <lb/>
     am free to vote on it as I please, and 
     <lb/>
     when the proper time comes I will do 
     <lb/>
     so. I do not wish to find too much 
     <lb/>
     fault with the Opposition, or their 
     <lb/>
     actions when they were in power, 
     <lb/>
     but still I do believe if the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment; which brought in the Railway 
     <lb/>
     Bill has been left in power, the coun<lb break="no"/>try wonld not to day be in its present 
     <lb/>
     position. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEW2">MR. STEWART</persName>.—Mr. Speaker, I 
     <lb/>have listened with considerable atten<lb break="no"/>tion to the speeches of hon. members 
     <lb/>on the Government side of the House, 
     <lb/>and am sorry to say I have heard no 
     <lb/>tangible arguments advanced why we 
     <lb/>should support the motion. I listened 
     <lb/>last evening to the speech of the hon. 
     <lb/>member from Alberton, but am bound 
     <lb/>to say it was remarkable for nothing 
     <lb/>but its length. He told us he had 
     <lb/>been Chancellor of the Exchequer 
     <lb/>for four years, and I sat patiently 
     <lb/>for the Oracle to open his lips and 
     <lb/>shew some good reason why this hon. 
     <lb/>House should consent to send another 
     <lb/>delegation to Ottawa. I expected a 
     <lb/>rare treat, but was most thoroughly 
     <lb/>disappointed. The hon. member, the 
     <lb/>Leader of the Government in the way 
     <lb/>in which he placed the matter before 
     <lb/>the country, did so in a very illusory 
     <lb/>manner. Yet the hon. member thinks 
     <lb/>his mere assertions ought to convince 
     <lb/>this side of the House that we should 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_118"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_118.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">118</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTERR.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
           
     support a second delegation to Ottawa 
     <lb/>
     We might do so if we saw any just 
     <lb/>
     grounds for doing so, for I can assure 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member we have no disposi<lb break="no"/>tion to other than plume our wings 
     <lb/>
     and raise ourselves above party and 
     <lb/>
     party strife, for the common weal. 
     <lb/>
     We are disposed to deal with the 
     <lb/>
     question wholly and entirely upon its 
     <lb/>
     merits. Such being the disposition of 
     <lb/>
     this side of the House, we have waited 
     <lb/>
     to hear reasons advanced which might 
     <lb/>
     induce us to support the motion, but 
     <lb/>
     as yet no arguments have been brought 
     <lb/>
     forward that are of any value. They 
     <lb/>
     have utterly failed to open up a single 
     <lb/>
     one that is sufficient to induce one 
     <lb/>
     member on this side to vote for the 
     <lb/>
     motion. The hon. member said he 
     <lb/>
     wished a delegation to go up sup<lb break="no"/>ported by a strong resolution of this 
     <lb/>
     House. Well I suppose he would like 
     <lb/>
     to have all the credit of bringing about 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. Unless he has grounds 
     <lb/>
     upon which to found an argument, and 
     <lb/>
     reason to suppose he will succeed in 
     <lb/>
     arranging better Terms of union, I 
     <lb/>
     hold it unworthy of the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     to think of having this House ad<lb break="no"/>journed for any such a purpose. To 
     <lb/>
     ask this House to adjourn in order that 
     <lb/>
     the Leader of the Government may, 
     <lb/>
     in this matter, be placed in a higher 
     <lb/>
     position than he now occupies, when no 
     <lb/>
     advantage is to accrue to the country 
     <lb/>
     by the act is simply wrong. In 
     <lb/>
     looking at this question, we have to 
     <lb/>
     consider the cause which has forced 
     <lb/>
     us into our present position. Was it 
     <lb/>
     brought about by the Railway or 
     <lb/>
     otherwise? Whatever answer may 
     <lb/>
     be given to the question, it is agreed by 
     <lb/>
     all that Confederation must be carried, 
     <lb/>
     or the business of the country cannot 
     <lb/>
     be carried on. Hence Confederation 
     <lb/>
     appeals now, not to our party feelings, 
     <lb/>
     but to our patriotism. Although they 
     <lb/>
     claim to have on their side the whole 
     <lb/>
     of the political, mercantile, and finan<lb break="no"/>cial ability of the Colony, yet I can 
     <lb/>
     tell the hon. member from Alberton, 
     <lb/>
     and the Leader of the Government as 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     well, that there are men on this side 
     <lb/>
     of the House quite capable of com<lb break="no"/>peting with them. The delegates, 
     <lb/>
     whom the late Government sent up to 
     <lb/>
     negotiate for terms of union, are men 
     <lb/>
     which they cannot give instructions to. 
     <lb/>
     Nor do I feel that they are the men 
     <lb/>
     either, to give instructions to the men 
     <lb/>
     who sent me here. And I maintain 
     <lb/>
     further, that the late Government 
     <lb/>
     managed the public affairs of the 
     <lb/>
     Colony as well, and better too, than 
     <lb/>
     those whom they superseded. While 
     <lb/>
     my hon. colleague, in his speech, has 
     <lb/>
     refuted the arguments of those of the 
     <lb/>
     Government side to whom he so ably 
     <lb/>
    replied. There is, I believe, as much 
     <lb/>money in the Treasury now, including 
     <lb/>what is funded abroad, as there was 
     <lb/>when they came into power. And, 
     <lb/>notwithstanding what has been said 
     <lb/>respecting the Dashaway policy, I 
     <lb/>contend the money appropriated by the 
     <lb/>late Government was expended for 
     <lb/>legitimate purposes. If there ever 
     <lb/>was a Dashaway policy inaugurated 
     <lb/>by any Government, it was when the 
     <lb/>Railway Bill was introduced. Not 
     <lb/>the Branch Bill of the late party, but 
     <lb/>the Dashaway Bill of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment now in power. Were it not to 
     <lb/>me as clear as noonday that our duty 
     <lb/>is to accept of Confederation, and that 
     <lb/>there is no prospect of obtaining better 
     <lb/>Terms, I would not for a moment op<lb break="no"/>pose the motion of the hon. member. 
     <lb/>But believing as I do, that full justice 
     <lb/>has been done by the Privy Council 
     <lb/>of the Dominion of Canada in the 
     <lb/>Terms agreed to, I will not, by my 
     <lb/>vote, attempt to take any advantage of 
     <lb/>the Canadian Ministry. If the Terms 
     <lb/>are fair and honest in every particular, 
     <lb/>then our duty is to accept them. I 
     <lb/>am surprised that hon. members on 
     <lb/>the Government side of this hon- 
     <lb break="yes"/>House should have made any refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the manner in which the dele<lb break="no"/>gates left this Island when they went 
     <lb/>up to Ottawa. Neither the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment nor the delegates have any cause 
     <lb/>for shame for any change which might 
     <lb/>
            
    
           
     <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">119</fw> 
     <lb/>
           
   
           
     have taken lace in their minds re<lb break="no"/>signing Confederation. As the annual 
     <lb/>
     accounts came in, the Government 
     <lb/>
     became more fully convmced that one 
     <lb/>
     of two courses would have at once to 
     <lb/>
    be taken—either go into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion on reasonable Terms if they could 
     <lb/>be had, or to increase the taxes greatly 
     <lb/>in advance of what they now are, dur<lb break="no"/>ing this Session of the Legislature. 
     <lb/>No other course lay before them, and 
     <lb/>for the satisfactory manner in which 
     <lb/>they have paved the way for an ad<lb break="no"/>mission into the Dominion, they de<lb break="no"/>serve much credit. I am not one of 
     <lb/>those who am a Confederate from 
     <lb/>necessity. I can look forward with 
     <lb/>pleasure to the time when we shall 
     <lb/>form a part of the great Dominion, 
     <lb/>which extends from the Atlantic to 
     <lb/>the Pacific. I see before me a great 
     <lb/>territory, rich in agriculture, mineral, 
     <lb/>and resources for mechanical improve<lb break="no"/>ment, not excelled in any part of the 
     <lb/>world. Why Sir, we are about unit<lb break="no"/>ing with a country of which we may 
     <lb/>justly feel proud; with a people who 
     <lb/>have sprung from the same race, speak 
     <lb/>the same language; who are governed 
     <lb/>by the same laws, and who are ani<lb break="no"/>mated with the same hopes and de<lb break="no"/>sires as we chen'sh among ourselves. 
     <lb/>Why then should we have any horrors 
     <lb/>about Confederation? I am, therefore, 
     <lb/>sorry that the hon. Leader of the 
     <lb/>Government should think of pursurng 
     <lb/>a course which will only add delay 
     <lb/>and expense, without producing any 
     <lb/>beneficial results to the Colony. But 
     <lb/>I suppose the hon. member from Alber<lb break="no"/>ton wishes to play his last act in the 
     <lb/>comedy. I can well imagine with 
     <lb/>what solicitude the hon. member wrll 
     <lb/>set out on his mission. Even now I 
     <lb/>can fancy I see him before the Privy 
     <lb/>Council, pleading, with sorrow depicted 
     <lb/>in his countenance, and tears tlowrng 
     <lb/>from his eyes, for his country, and an 
     <lb/>additional allowance to pay for the 
     <lb/>Breakwater at Tignish Run. (Laugh<lb break="no"/>ter.) Yes, pleading that the Drill- 
     <lb break="yes"/>sheds, Lighthouses, and other similar 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     works may be taken into account and 
     <lb/>
     paid for; assurring them that when 
     <lb/>
     this is done our people will fold their 
     <lb/>
     hands and peacefully sit down under 
     <lb/>
     the shade of the maple tree of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion of Canada. But Sir, I cannot 
     <lb/>
    see why we should wish to force un<lb break="no"/>fair claims from Canada, as if we had 
     <lb/>any right to live upon the generosrty 
     <lb/>of other people. We all know that 
     <lb/>for internat improvements, the people 
     <lb/>of Canada have to tax themselves. 
     <lb/>Education and many local wants are 
     <lb/>all provided for by their municipalities. 
     <lb/>And to this we will also have to come 
     <lb/>too. I have carefully examined into 
     <lb/>the matter, and having done so, do not 
     <lb/>feel that I can vote for sending up 
     <lb/>another delegation. As Col. Gray 
     <lb/>said, the Terms are exceedingly good, 
     <lb/>and I have heard no argument ad<lb break="no"/>vanced to convince me that it is our 
     <lb/>duty to reject them. It is said that 
     <lb/>the Bay de Verte Canal will be of ad<lb break="no"/>vantage to this Island, and one hon. 
     <lb/>member thinks we should pay a pro<lb break="no"/>portion of its cost. I admit. that if it 
     <lb/>was open it would be an indirect bene<lb break="no"/>fit to this Island. It would open up a 
     <lb/>direct road to the Bay of Fundy, 
     <lb/>which would be a great matter to us, 
     <lb/>and doubtless we would reap some 
     <lb/>advantages from its construction. It 
     <lb/>is thought by some that its cost will 
     <lb/>not exceed $500,000, while others are 
     <lb/>of opinion it will cost much more. 
     <lb/>But it is not yet built, and may not for 
     <lb/>many a day. It may not be built at 
     <lb/>all. The fact is, Mr. Speaker, they 
     <lb/>have brought forward no arguments. 
     <lb/>We have been contending with sha<lb break="no"/>dows, and have taken the ground from 
     <lb/>under their feet. It is not wisdom to 
     <lb/>keep up this discussion much longer. 
     <lb/>If this delegation goes up, m all pro<lb break="no"/>bability the matter will be staved off 
     <lb/>for another year. This is not desir<lb break="no"/>able. The business of the country is 
     <lb/>now embarrassed. Trade is encum<lb break="no"/>bered with many difficulties. All this 
     <lb/>would be relieved if Confederation was 
     <lb/>effected. That is one reason why I 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_120"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_120.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">120</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
           
     am so anxious that no unnecessary 
     <lb/>
     delay should take place. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. the SPEAKER then put the                                                                                                                                                                                                                               
     <lb/>
     motion, which being carried in the 
     <lb/>
     affirmative, the House resolved itself 
     <lb/>
     into a Committee of the whole House 
     <lb/>
     on the further consideration of the 
     <lb/>
     despatches. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD10">MR. A. C. McDONALD</persName> in the chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon Mr. Pope</persName>—Mr. Chairman, I 
     <lb/>
     beg leave to move the following Re<lb break="no"/>solution : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Whereas</hi>, the question of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion of this Island with the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     of Canada, having formed the subject 
     <lb/>
     of negotiations between the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     of Canada and the late Executive 
     <lb/>
     Council of this Colony, the correspond<lb break="no"/>ence interchanged between His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency the Governor General and His 
     <lb/>
     Honor the Lieut. Governor of this 
     <lb/>
     Island, and the members of the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council of Canada and this Island, 
     <lb/>
     embodying certain terms and condi<lb break="no"/>tions relating to the proposed union, 
     <lb/>
     having been officially laid before the 
     <lb/>
     House and duly considered. The 
     <lb/>
     House is of opinion that said terms 
     <lb/>
     and conditions do not secure to this 
     <lb/>
     Colony a sum sufficient to defray the 
     <lb/>
     ordinary and indispensable require<lb break="no"/>ments of its local government, and are 
     <lb/>
     by no means an equivalent for the 
     <lb/>
     Revenue, present and prospective, 
     <lb/>
     which it would be called upon to sur<lb break="no"/>render to the Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">And, Whereas</hi>. The strong objec<lb break="no"/>tions hitherto entertained by the peo. 
     <lb/>
     ple of this Island to Confederation, 
     <lb/>
     having been much modified, and the 
     <lb/>
     present House of Assembly feeling 
     <lb/>
     anxious to meet the desire of Her 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's lmperial Government to unite  
     <lb/>
     under one Government, all the .British 
     <lb/>
     possessions in America, is willing in 
     <lb/>
     good faith and loyaly to merge the 
     <lb/>
     interests of the inhabitants of Prince 
     <lb/>
     Edward Island with those of their 
     <lb/>
     fellow subjects in the Dominion, on 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     terms which are just and reasonable, 
     <lb/>
     and such as will not involve the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of this Island in direct local taxa<lb break="no"/>tion for objects for which the ordinary 
     <lb/>
     Revenue has hither to enabled them to 
     <lb/>
     provide. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
                 <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved Therefore</hi>, That this House 
     <lb/>
     being most desirous to secure, to the 
     <lb/>
     people of Prince Edward Island on 
     <lb/>
     entering the union, just and reasonable 
     <lb/>
     terms, does hereby authorize His 
     <lb/>
     Honor. the Lieutenant Governor to 
     <lb/>
     appoint delegates to proceed at once 
     <lb/>
     to Ottawa to confer with the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the Dominion of Canada, on 
     <lb/>
     this great and important subject with 
     <lb/>
     a full confidence that the terms to 
     <lb/>
     which they will agree, will be such as 
     <lb/>
     will insure their immediate and
     <lb/>
     unqualified ratification by the Legis<lb break="no"/>ture of the Colony. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As the night is somewhat advanced I 
     <lb/>
     am willing the matter should lay over 
     <lb/>
     for consideration until another day, I, 
     <lb/>
     therefore, move that the Speaker take 
     <lb/>
     the chair, the Chairman report prog<lb break="no"/>ress, and ask leave to sit again. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On motion of the Hon. LEADER OF 
     <lb/>
     THE GOVERMENT, the House resolved 
     <lb/>
     itself into a committee of the whole to 
     <lb/>
     resume the consideration for the de<lb break="no"/>spatches relating to Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD10">MR. A C. <choice><sic>DCDoNALD</sic><corr>McDonald</corr></choice></persName> in the chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERN<lb break="no"/>MENT</persName>.—This opportunity of securing 
     <lb/>
     union with the. Dominion of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     on just and favorable terms should not 
     <lb/>
     be lost. I am prepared to table a 
     <lb/>
     resolution to appoint a delegation for 
     <lb/>
     the purpose of seeking better Terms, 
     <lb/>
     and expect support from both sides of 
     <lb/>
     this House.  There can be nothing 
     <lb/>
     lost by endeavoring to secure the best 
     <lb/>
     Terms, as we fully believe and feel that 
     <lb/>
     under the present offer we have not 
     <lb/>
     sufficient for the maintenance of   our 
     <lb/>
     local. Government. By the Imperial 
     <lb/>
     or, North American Act, we shall be 
     <lb/>
     prevented from making any demand 
     <lb/>
      
            <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">121</fw><lb/>
            
           
     upon the Dominion Government after 
     <lb/>
     entering the Union, and we are there<lb break="no"/>fore, anxious to secure such Terms 
     <lb/>
     before accepting Confederation,  as 
     <lb/>
     will enable us to get along without 
     <lb/>
     being compelled to resort to immediate, 
     <lb/>
     direct taxation. If the delegation 
     <lb/>
     should fail, we shall be in no worse 
     <lb/>
     position than at present; but I have 
     <lb/>
     not the slightest doubt that more 
     <lb/>
     liberal Terms will be conceded to us. 
     <lb/>
     It is a matter that will affect our peo<lb break="no"/>ple for all time, and if reasonable 
     <lb/>
     Terms are obtained, they will be re 
     <lb/>
     lieved from a certain amount of taxa<lb break="no"/>tion. If, on the other hand, no better 
     <lb/>
     Terms can be procured, it will be for 
     <lb/>
     the Legislature to determine what it is 
     <lb/>
     prepared to do. If reasonable Terms 
     <lb/>
     are offered us, I am satisfied that both 
     <lb/>
     sides will be prepared to accept them, 
     <lb/>
     and to consummate the union as soon 
     <lb/>
     as possible. I know the Opposition 
     <lb/>
     regret that a split has not taken place 
     <lb/>
     on this side of the House, as they de<lb break="no"/>sired, but we should all unite for the 
     <lb/>
     common interest of our country, and 
     <lb/>
     consummate the union as soon as pos<lb break="no"/>sible, by procuring and accepting 
     <lb/>
     reasonable Terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">Mr. D. LAIRD</persName>.—As the resolution 
     <lb/>
     submitted by his honor the Leader of 
     <lb/>
     the Government relates to an impor<lb break="no"/>tant matter, due notice should have 
     <lb/>
     been given of its introductlon. It con<lb break="no"/>tains statements, which, I think, are 
     <lb/>
     not borne out by the facts of the case. 
     <lb/>
     The statement that the Terms now 
     <lb/>
     offered us do not meet the wants of 
     <lb/>
     this Colony, is, in my opinion, an alto<lb break="no"/>gether erroneous one, and hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers on the Government side of the 
     <lb/>
     House have not produced arguments 
     <lb/>
     to substantiate it. The argument that 
     <lb/>
     because our wants are great, we are 
     <lb/>
     entitled to better Terms, seems to me 
     <lb/>
     a very poor one.   Why are the Terms 
     <lb/>before us insufficient?  We have been<lb/>allowed $20 per head more than any<lb/>
     
    of the other Provinces of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion, on account of our isolated 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     position, which is certainly a great 
     <lb/>
     favor. The claim we preferred was 
     <lb/>
     much larger than the sum we received, 
     <lb/>
     but we were told plainly by the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government that they would 
     <lb/>
     grant no more, and that they consider<lb break="no"/>ed they had dealt fairly with us. 
     <lb/>
     When we (the delegates) met the 
     <lb/>
     committee of the Privy Council, and 
     <lb/>
     stated our demands, we were told that 
     <lb/>
     we were to have a conference 
     <lb/>
     with the Finance Minister on the 
     <lb/>
     following day, and were directed 
     <lb/>
     to present our claims to him, in order 
     <lb/>
     to show how we could base them. 
     <lb/>
     Our arguments were not taken on our 
     <lb/>
     mere word, as we had to show the 
     <lb/>
     why and the wherefore for every de<lb break="no"/>mand we made. We met the Finance 
     <lb/>
     Minister, presented our claims and 
     <lb/>
     showed that on account of our isolation, 
     <lb/>
     during nearly six months in the year, 
     <lb/>
     we could not receive the benefits of 
     <lb/>
     their public works, and were entitled 
     <lb/>
     to a full equivalent for all the Do<lb break="no"/>minion debt, present and prospective. 
     <lb/>
     The Finance Minister acknowledged 
     <lb/>
     our statements to be ingenious, and 
     <lb/>
     next day we presented our case before 
     <lb/>
     the Privy Council. The latter said 
     <lb/>
     that some of the positions we took 
     <lb/>
     were inadmissible, and could not be 
     <lb/>
     entertained, that our arguments on 
     <lb/>
     these matters were not such as they 
     <lb/>
     could place before their Parliament for 
     <lb/>
     approval, and that unless they could 
     <lb/>
     uphold our claims in the face of the 
     <lb/>
     whole Dominion, they could not grant 
     <lb/>
     them. They told us they were willing 
     <lb/>
     to go as far as lay in their power, just 
     <lb/>
     so far as—in the words of the Finance 
     <lb/>
     Minister—not to upset their own apple 
     <lb/>
     cart. They conceive that they have 
     <lb/>
     conceded to us the most liberal Terms 
     <lb/>
     they can carry through Parliament, 
     <lb/>
     and that is also the expression of 
     <lb/>
     numerous journals, and of outside 
     <lb/>
     opinion generally, throughout the Do<lb break="no"/>minion. If arguments are to be based 
     <lb/>
     upon our wants, and not upon our 
     <lb/>
     rights, they will amount to nothing at 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_122"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_122.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">122</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            
     all, and I fear will meet with but poor 
     <lb/>
     success. If our Island Legislature had 
     <lb/>
     from the first husbanded its Revenues, 
     <lb/>
     there would have been plenty for cen<lb break="no"/>turies to come, but they went into ex<lb break="no"/>travagant expenditures in building a 
     <lb/>
     Railway, and thus placed as in the 
     <lb/>
     present positibn of embarassment. 
     <lb/>
     They expended just like a lady who 
     <lb/>
     spent so much money upon her dress 
     <lb/>
     that her husband could not buy a 
     <lb/>
     plough. If we have become embarass<lb break="no"/>ed by entering into a great enterprise, 
     <lb/>
     what is that to the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment? Is our extravagance any argu<lb break="no"/>ment for better Terms? The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment have not, so far, shown that 
     <lb/>
     $45 per head of our population is not 
     <lb/>
     a liberal allowance, and cannot do so. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. Leader of the Government 
     <lb/>
     tried to make out that something had 
     <lb/>
     been overlooked in reckoning the pre<lb break="no"/>sent and prospective debt of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion, that ten millions of dollars had 
     <lb/>
     been expended on the Intercolonial 
     <lb/>
     Railway last'year, which had not been 
     <lb/>
     taken into account. Here is the state<lb break="no"/>ment of the Finance Minister in his 
     <lb/>
     Budget Speech :—"I would now, for a 
     <lb/>
     few moments, call your attention to the 
     <lb/>
     financial position of the Dominion. I 
     <lb/>
     have no doubt that every hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber who has examined the public ac<lb break="no"/>counts, will have read the statements, 
     <lb/>
     showing the Debt of the Dominion, 
     <lb/>
     and the expenditures on capital ac<lb break="no"/>count, with the greatest satisfaction, 
     <lb/>
     for they show that during the last five 
     <lb/>
     years there has been paid out of sur<lb break="no"/>plus revenue, over and above ordinary 
     <lb/>
     charges on the consolidated revenue 
     <lb/>
     fund, and contributed towards the con<lb break="no"/>struction of public works that were 
     <lb/>
     chargeable to the capital, a sum of 
     <lb/>
     $9,522,000." "It will be seen by the 
     <lb/>
     estimates that it is proposed to ask the 
     <lb/>
     House for a total expenditure of $31, 
     <lb/>
     008,433. This includes the expendi<lb break="no"/>tures authorized by statute for con<lb break="no"/>struction of public works and all other 
     <lb/>
     charges. Of this sum $9, 974,240 
     <lb/>
     will be chargeable to capital ; railroads 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     (Intercolonial) $4,335,240; canals $5,<lb break="no"/>277,000; public buildings, including the 
     <lb/>
     Library and grounds, $362,000; mak<lb break="no"/>ing a total of $9,974,240; also deduct 
     <lb/>
     from the expenditure $93,000 in pay<lb break="no"/>ment of debts; this leaves to be pro<lb break="no"/>vided for during the coming year, out 
     <lb/>
     of income $29,941,183." The hon. 
     <lb/>
     Leader of the Government would en<lb break="no"/>deavor to make out that something had 
     <lb/>
     been overlooked in calculating the 
     <lb/>
     debt of the Dominion, but he cannot 
     <lb/>
     prove his statement, as he has nothing 
     <lb/>
     upon which to base an argument. Ten 
     <lb/>
     millions more expended on the Inter<lb break="no"/>colonial up to the first of January last, 
     <lb/>
     and every dollar of that sum was in<lb break="no"/>cluded in our calculation. For every 
     <lb/>
     dollar expended on the Intercolonial 
     <lb/>
     Railway we are to receive a share, 
     <lb/>
     when we receive $45 per head. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. Leader of the Government says 
     <lb/>
     that some of our Lighthouses and all 
     <lb/>
     our Drill Sheds have. been erected 
     <lb/>
     since the Quebec Scheme was agreed 
     <lb/>
     upon, and that we are entitled to re<lb break="no"/>ceive their value from the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     Government. He should remember 
     <lb/>
     that the debt of the Dominion to day 
     <lb/>
     is not more than $25 per head, and, 
     <lb/>
     judging from their increase of popula<lb break="no"/>tion, is not likely to exceed that 
     <lb/>
    amount, while we receive $20 over 
     <lb/>and above that sum. The little appeal 
     <lb/>for the cost of Lighthouses and Break<lb break="no"/>waters will not succeed in the face of 
     <lb/>these facts. I never heard a more 
     <lb/>flimsy argument from a Leader of a 
     <lb/>Government asking the House for  
     <lb/>another delegation. Why, he has not 
     <lb/>shown a shadow ofa shade of a reason 
     <lb/>for his present course of action. In 
     <lb/>their Minute of Council they do not 
     <lb/>even state that they agree to pay us 
     <lb/>for our Post Office, because there was 
     <lb/>not a Post Office in the other Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces which had been used as such, 
     <lb/>which was paid for by the Dominion 
     <lb/>Government. Our building is men<lb break="no"/>tioned in the Terms as the Law Courts 
     <lb/>and Registry Office, so careful were 
     <lb/>they in wording their document. If 
     <lb/>
            
        
            
     <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">123</fw> 
     <lb/>
            
   
           
     we had advocated remuneration for a 
     <lb/>
     long catalogue of Lighthouses, Drill 
     <lb/>
     Sheds, &amp;c., built since the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     Scheme was agreed upon, how could 
     <lb/>
     they present such matters before their 
     <lb/>
     Parliament for payment, when the 
     <lb/>
     other Provinces were not paid for 
     <lb/>
     similar works? They have a vigorous 
     <lb/>
     Opposition, Sir, and while on account 
     <lb/>
     of our isolated position we have a 
     <lb/>
     right to some special claims to make 
     <lb/>
     our position equal to theirs, we have 
     <lb/>
     no right to press any unreasonable 
     <lb/>
     demands. We had no claim on the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion for the loss of our lands; 
     <lb/>
     but we presented our casein this way: 
     <lb/>
     We stated that as our Island had been 
     <lb/>
     granted away by the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, we had no Crown lands from 
     <lb/>
     which to derive a Revenue; Ontario 
     <lb/>
     had her Crown lands and forests, and 
     <lb/>
     had received an income of a million of 
     <lb/>
     dollars from them, while we had no 
     <lb/>
     such means at our command. Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia has mines, and New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick mines and forests, and we 
     <lb/>
     contended that we could not run an 
     <lb/>
     equal race with them, and were, there<lb break="no"/>fore, entitled to something to compen<lb break="no"/>sate us for the loss of our lands. If 
     <lb/>
     we never expend the principal granted 
     <lb/>
     us by the Dominion, we can draw the 
     <lb/>
     interest at five per cent, and the sum 
     <lb/>
     thus received will be equal to the 
     <lb/>
     amount per head received by the other 
     <lb/>
     Provinces from their lands. They 
     <lb/>
     said that this was a matter which they 
     <lb/>
     could lay before their Parliament, for 
     <lb/>
     which they could show some reason, 
     <lb/>
     for they could not expect us to pay 
     <lb/>
     dollar for dollar in taxes with them, 
     <lb/>
     unless placed on the same footing. I 
     <lb/>
     cannot see how we can press our 
     <lb/>
     claims merely on account of our neces<lb break="no"/>sity or poverty. We, on this Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion side of the House, wish to know 
     <lb/>
     whereon the Government can base 
     <lb/>
    their claims for additional concessions 
     <lb/>from Candaa, when we have already 
     <lb/>received such a liberal allowance. We 
     <lb/>have some honor and dignity to main<lb break="no"/>tain in this matter, and have no right<lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     to send off a begging delegation to<lb/>Ottawa for new Terms. The Colony<lb/>has already obtained Terms which the<lb/>Governor General has declared can<lb break="no"/>not be increased, and I, for one, cannot<lb/>stultify myself in supporting the reso<lb break="no"/>lution in favor of another delegation at<lb/>present, as the Government have<lb/>shown no good reason for it. The<lb/>only argument adduced by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and their supporters is that<lb/>the amount we should receive from<lb/>the Dominion under the present Terms<lb/>would not meet our wants. If new<lb/>delegates are sent to up to Ottawa, they<lb/>will find that the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will analyse our Revenue under 
     <lb/>
     those Terms, and will find their state<lb break="no"/>ments incorrect. The School system 
     <lb/>
     of Canada is chiefly supported by local 
     <lb/>
     taxation, while our system is wholly 
     <lb/>
     supported from public funds; they 
     <lb/>
     would, therefore, never concede to us 
     <lb/>
     sufficient to meet our educational 
     <lb/>
     wants from the Treasury, while they 
     <lb/>
     pay local taxes for a similar purpose. 
     <lb/>
     Three-fourths of the expenditure of 
     <lb/>
     the Board of Works in the Dominion, 
     <lb/>
     for building litte bridges and meeting 
     <lb/>
     other small local wants, is not borne 
     <lb/>
     by the local Government, but by the 
     <lb/>
     muncipalities. For the reasons I have 
     <lb/>
     already given, I cannot support the 
     <lb/>
     resolution introduced by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     Leader of the Government. I see no 
     <lb/>
     reason for delay or for sending another. 
     <lb/>
     delegation to Canada; it will require, 
     <lb/>
    probably, at least three weeks, as they 
     <lb/>cannot rush everything through at 
     <lb/>Ottawa, and the whole Privy Council 
     <lb/>is not prepared to dance attendance 
     <lb/>upon them. The Dominion Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment is now in session, and, therefore, 
     <lb/>the Government will have precious 
     <lb/>little time to devote to the delegation 
     <lb/>Every hour's delay is injuring the 
     <lb/>trade of this Colony, and merchants 
     <lb/>scarcely know whether to import 
     <lb/>goods or not, as they are not sure of 
     <lb/>being able to obtain exchange to pay 
     <lb/>for them. Under our present system 
     <lb/>our duties come in to meet our present 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_124"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_124.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">124</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            
     wants, but when we form a part of the  
     <lb/>
    Dominion, we shall receive our allow<lb break="no"/>ance in advance. This will cause 
     <lb/>plenty of exchange for the first few 
     <lb/>years, at least, and will help trade to 
     <lb/>go on smoothly. The local Government 
     <lb/>will have no local debt, and we shall 
     <lb/>be' able to begin with clean books. I 
     <lb/>had some doubt at first that Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation would work well under the 
     <lb/>British Constitution, unless the Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces became more prosperous than 
     <lb/>they had been ; but I am now happy 
     <lb/>to acknowledge that the Dominion, as 
     <lb/>a Government, has been a greater 
     <lb/>success than I ever anticipated, or its 
     <lb/>promoters expected. This can be 
     <lb/>proved most clearly. I will read a 
     <lb/>statement from Mr. Tilley's speech, 
     <lb/>which will show their position and 
     <lb/>prospects : "Now, having dealt with 
     <lb/>this point, I trust the House will par<lb break="no"/>don me for a few moments if I refer 
     <lb/>to the future with reference to our 
     <lb/>liabilities and engagements and our 
     <lb/> prospects of meeting those liabilities. 
     <lb/>In doing so, I must again refer to the 
     <lb/>past, and I will do it in a very few 
     <lb/>words. We have an annual surplus, 
     <lb/>after meeting all engagements and 
     <lb/>providing the necessary sinking fund, 
     <lb/>sufficient to pay the interest on a debt 
     <lb/>of $30,000,000 more than the debt 
     <lb/>now is. We have in the present year 
     <lb/>a Surplus, without taking into account 
     <lb/>the sinking fund, amounting to some<lb break="no"/>thing like three quarters of a million. 
     <lb/>We are, however, entering upon new 
     <lb/>and increased engagements, involving 
     <lb/>a very large sum of money. We are 
     <lb/>entering upon works—we have already 
     <lb/>done so—which will require a large 
     <lb/>increase of our debt. We have $10,<lb break="no"/>000,000 to expend on the Intercolonial 
     <lb/>Railway. We have $30,000,000 for 
     <lb/>the Canadian Pacific, and the Canal 
     <lb/>system, that has been accepted by the 
     <lb/>Government, will involve an expendi<lb break="no"/>ture of at least $20,000,000. These 
     <lb/>are serious matters, inasmuch as they 
     <lb/>add $60,000,000 to our existing debt.  
     <lb/>Let us now see what is the annual<lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     charge involved in this matter. In 
     <lb/>
     the first place we have available the 
     <lb/>
     Imperial guarantee  for  £2,500,000 
     <lb/>
     sterling, given to us in lieu of the 
     <lb/>
     Fenian claims. Then we have a 
     <lb/>
     guarantee of £1,500,000 for the con<lb break="no"/>struction of the Intercolonial Railway. 
     <lb/>
     We have also a guarantee of £300,000 
     <lb/>
     for the North West territories, and I 
     <lb/>
     may state to the House that the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Government has assented to the 
     <lb/>
     transfer of the fortifications guarantee 
     <lb/>
     of £1,100,000 to be expended in the 
     <lb/>
     enlargement and construction of our 
     <lb/>
     canals, and in the construction of the 
     <lb/>
     Pacific Railway.  (Cheers.) Thus 
     <lb/>
     we have a total amount guaranteed of 
     <lb/>
     £5,400,000 or $26,000,000 which we 
     <lb/>
     can obtain at an interest off our percent. 
     <lb/>
     On that item alone, we have, there<lb break="no"/>fore, an annual charge of $1,040,000, 
     <lb/>
     and on the $34,000,000 remaining, the 
     <lb/>
     annual charge, at five per cent, will 
     <lb/>
     be $1,700,000. For the sinking fund 
     <lb/>
     of one per cent, we require $600,000, 
     <lb/>
     and for commission on interest $27,<lb break="no"/>400, making a total annual charge, 
     <lb/>
     when these works are completed, of 
     <lb/>
     $3,367,400." They are paying less 
     <lb/>
     per contage of interest to-day than 
     <lb/>
     they ever paid, and it is lessening year 
     <lb/>
     after year. I must acknowledge that 
     <lb/>
     Confederation, as a political scheme, 
     <lb/>
     has been successful far beyond my ex<lb break="no"/>pectations. Things looked dark at the 
     <lb/>
     the time of the Quebec Scheme, and it 
     <lb/>
     actually appeared at that time that 
     <lb/>
     several prominent men in their Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment came down here for assist<lb break="no"/>ance because they could not carry out 
     <lb/>
     their Government at home. The 
     <lb/>
    seven per cents and six per cents of 
     <lb/>old Canada have all vanished, and the  
     <lb/>highest interest now paid is only five 
     <lb/>per cent. One of the arguments of 
     <lb/>the hon. Leader of the Government is 
     <lb/>that we are not, under the present 
     <lb/>Terms, going to receive an equivalent 
     <lb/>for what we are to give up. Instead 
     <lb/>of their taking away anything, we shall 
     <lb/>receive more than the Revenue  col<lb break="no"/>lected by them on this Island. As<lb/>
            
           
     <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">125</fw> 
     <lb/>
            
   
          
     time rolls on the manufactures of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion will increase, and we shall 
     <lb/>
     import more and more of their goods, 
     <lb/>
     which will greatly reduce the amount 
     <lb/>
     of duties collected here. Many of the 
     <lb/>
     American manufacturers have moved 
     <lb/>across the border into Canada, and 
     <lb/>have established manufactures of 
     <lb/>mowing machines and agricultural 
     <lb/>implements. All these and a great 
     <lb/>variety of other manufactures will 
     <lb/>likely increase, and intercolonial trade 
     <lb/>will so increase, that instead of Canada 
     <lb/>taking away money for duties collected 
     <lb/>here, it will be far otherwise. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve they will get no more revenue 
     <lb/>from this Colony ten years hence than 
     <lb/>they will this year, if we enter the 
     <lb/>Dominion. The taxation of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion at present amounts to only 
     <lb/>$3.54 per head, while ours will 
     <lb/>amount to $6 per head when the 
     <lb/>whole Railway debt  falls upon us, if 
     <lb/>we remain out of Confederation. The 
     <lb/>Opposition have a right to know 
     <lb/>whether it is the intention of the hon. 
     <lb/>Leader of the Government to ask the 
     <lb/>Dominion to give us back the Rail<lb break="no"/>way, and to make it a local work for 
     <lb/>this Island or not. If it is going to 
     <lb/>pay $50,000 per year over working 
     <lb/>expenses, as stated by the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Alberton, it would pay us to 
     <lb/>work it ourselves. I am sure the 
     <lb/>Government can get it back by tele<lb break="no"/>graphing to Ottawa, without taking 
     <lb/>the trouble to send up a delega<lb break="no"/>tion. But the hon. Leader of the 
     <lb/>Government has never breathed a 
     <lb/>syllable in reference to taking back 
     <lb/>the Railway, and working it ourselves. 
     <lb/>It was all very well to cry out at 
     <lb/>Election times that the Railway is 
     <lb/>worth what it costs but he has not a 
     <lb/>word to say now about asking the Do<lb break="no"/>minion to give it back to us, although 
     <lb/>he knows they would be willing to do 
     <lb/>so. I believe he will be only too glad 
     <lb/>to allow the Dominion to  keep it, as 
     <lb/>he knows it will not pay its working 
     <lb/>expenses for four or five years at least.<lb/>At the end of that time the spruce<lb/>
            
            <cb/>
          
     sleepers will require to be removed, 
     <lb/>
     and where will the money come   from 
     <lb/>
    to do this? Even the working ex<lb break="no"/>penses will not be paid by the earn<lb break="no"/>ings of the road ! I see that the Nova 
     <lb/>Scotia Railway, to this day, has not 
     <lb/>nearly paid its working expenses, and 
     <lb/>the New Brunswick Railway has only 
     <lb/>paid a small per centage on its cost. 
     <lb/>The people do not want the Railway 
     <lb/>back, but look upon it as a happy thing 
     <lb/>that the Dominion have agreed to take 
     <lb/>it and pay for it, and that they will 
     <lb/>be able to get along in their usual way 
     <lb/>without that burden. Many hon. 
     <lb/>members will soon require to go home 
     <lb/>to their farms and sow their seeds ; 
     <lb/>but instead of proceeding with the 
     <lb/>business of the country as is required, 
     <lb/>we shall have a recess for two or 
     <lb/>three weeks, and will require to meet 
     <lb/>again at the very busiest portion of 
     <lb/>the spring season. Unless  the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment can show some ground for 
     <lb/>their claims, they will most egregi<lb break="no"/>ously tail before the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment—mere mendicant claims will 
     <lb/>not be recognized by them. A great 
     <lb/>many of the Canadians are of the 
     <lb/>opinion that we are better off than 
     <lb/>they are, and that we are just as able 
     <lb/>to pay our debts. Perhaps the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government will give the new 
     <lb/>delegation a little more for pity's sake, 
     <lb/>to get them out of their way, but it 
     <lb/>will be only a more trifle, if anything 
     <lb/>at all. The more manly and straight<lb break="no"/>forward counts would be to carry the 
     <lb/>question through the House in good 
     <lb/>faith with Canada, without delay; there 
     <lb/>is no time to lose. As I went to the 
     <lb/>people on these terms, I am now pre<lb break="no"/>pared to do my duty to my constitu<lb break="no"/>ents and the country by giving them 
     <lb/>my support. I therefore move the 
     <lb/>following amendment :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Whereas</hi>, This House has had un<lb break="no"/>der consideration certan papers relat<lb break="no"/>ing to the Confederation of this island 
     <lb/>with the Dominion of Canada, and 
     <lb/>more particularly a despatch of His<lb/>Excellency the Governor General,<lb/>
            

            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_126"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_126.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">126</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
           
     dated the 14th of March last, trans<lb break="no"/>mitting to His Honor Lieut. Governor 
     <lb/>
     Robinson, the copy of a report of a 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Honorable the Privy 
     <lb/> Council of Canada, approved of by His 
     <lb/>Excellency in Council, on the 10th of 
     <lb/>the said month, which report contains 
     <lb/>minutes of Conference between the 
     <lb/>said Committee of the Privy Council, 
     <lb/> and delegates from the Government of 
     <lb/> Prince Edward Island, on the subject 
     <lb/> of the Union of this Colony with the 
     <lb/> Dominion of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">And Whereas</hi>, By a Telegraphic 
     <lb/>
     Despatch from the Governor General, 
     <lb/>dated the 12th of March last, His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency, with respect to the terms of 
     <lb/>Confederation contained in said min<lb break="no"/>utes of Conference, signifies his Minis<lb break="no"/>ters' opinion—an opinion in which he 
     <lb/>fully coincides—that "no additional 
     <lb/>concessions would have any chance of 
     <lb/>being accepted by the Parliament of 
     <lb/>Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">And Whereas</hi>, It is highly desirable 
     <lb/>
     that this question of Union should be 
     <lb/>
     carried by the Legislature of this 
     <lb/>
     Island with as little delay as possible, 
     <lb/>
     in view of the financial and commer<lb break="no"/>cial necessities of the Colony. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Therefore, Resolved</hi>, That this 
     <lb/>
     House do appoint a Committee of 
     <lb/>
     seven to prepare an address to the 
     <lb/>
     Queen, praying Her Majesty in Coun<lb break="no"/>cil to pass an order in conformity with 
     <lb/>
               the 14th section of "<hi rendition="simple:italic">British North 
     <lb/>
     American Act, 1867</hi>," uniting Prince 
     <lb/>
     Edward Island with the Dominion of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, on the terms and conditions 
     <lb/>
     approved of in the minute of the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council of Canada, on the 10th of 
     <lb/>
     March, 1872., 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERN<lb break="no"/>MENT</persName>.—The hon. member for Belfast 
     <lb/>
     stands up here and asks why the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment do not state whether they in<lb break="no"/>tend to ask the Dominion to give us 
     <lb/>
     back our Railway? Well, I ask why 
     <lb/>
     he did not let the country know what 
     <lb/>
     Terms he intended to ask from Canada, 
     <lb/>
     before starting on that delegation ? He 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     stole away, because he knew the late 
     <lb/>
     Government were defeated before he 
     <lb/>
     went ; and yet he stands up here and 
     <lb/>
     declares it is our duty to let him know 
     <lb/>
     what we intend to ask in addition to 
     <lb/>
     the Terms he obtained ! He admits 
     <lb/>
     that he wanted to entrap and ensnare 
     <lb/>
     the people into Confederation, and is 
     <lb/>
     most anxious that the Terms brought 
     <lb/>
     down by himself he accepted at once. 
     <lb/>
     When he states that I will go to Can<lb break="no"/>ada begging some small concession, he 
     <lb/>
     forgets the sneaking, contemptible 
     <lb/>
     manner, in which he left his country, to 
     <lb/>
     hand it over to the Dominion, without 
     <lb/>
     the knowledge or consent of any per<lb break="no"/>son outside the late Government. He 
     <lb/>
     gained his position in the last House 
     <lb/>
     by lying and slander ; and by printing 
     <lb/>
     and circulating a speech, made at St. 
     <lb/>
     Dunstan's College, by his political 
     <lb/>
     opponent, and by lying and misrepre<lb break="no"/>sentation in reference to the School  
     <lb/>Question, he obtained a seat in the 
     <lb/>present House. There would not 
     <lb/>have been three men of the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment party returned to this House 
     <lb/>on the Terms before us, or the policy 
     <lb/>of the late Government, if the School 
     <lb/>Question had not be dragged into their 
     <lb/>assistance, and made to do them ser<lb break="no"/>vice. The complimentary speech, 
     <lb/>made by the hon. Col. Gray, was cir<lb break="no"/>culated in Raasa, Rona and Belle 
     <lb/>Creek, and the people were duped ; 
     <lb/>but if the copies of that speech had 
     <lb/>been circulated among more intelligent 
     <lb/>people, and his election had depended 
     <lb/>upon the result, he would never have 
     <lb/>obtained a seat in this House. Dur<lb break="no"/>ing the last year, while he was in 
     <lb/>power, he spent some $13,000 for 
     <lb/>which the Accounts do not show that 
     <lb/>the country received anything in re<lb break="no"/>turn. I hope I have too much regard 
     <lb/>for my character and for my country, 
     <lb/>to undertake a mission of this kind, 
     <lb/>unless I felt and believed that far 
     <lb/>better Terms, than those now offered 
     <lb/>us, can be obtained. I shall endeavor 
     <lb/>to do all loan, and I have not the 
     <lb/>slightest doubt of our getting better 
     <lb/>
            
            
      <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">127</fw> 
     <lb/>
            
   
           
     Terms. I believe it will be sour 
     <lb/>
     grapes for the hon. junior member for 
     <lb/>
     Belfast, if we do get anything in addi<lb break="no"/>tion to the Terms brought down by 
     <lb/>
     He will find that notwith<lb break="no"/>standing his extraordinary exertions, 
     <lb/>
     this question will be carried, and the 
     <lb/>
     delegates appointed. I did not take 
     <lb/>
     the School Question to the people and 
     <lb/>
     make political capital out of it ; but I 
     <lb/>
     do not hesitate to say that the hon. 
     <lb/>
     jun. member for Belfast and his friends 
     <lb/>
     owe their seats in this House to the 
     <lb/>
     prejudices which they aroused in their 
     <lb/>
     several districts, on that question. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. member says that the present 
     <lb/>
     Terms are sufficient, and that no argu<lb break="no"/>ment can be brought to show that we 
     <lb/>
     should have better Terms. We have 
     <lb/>
     no wilderness lands unsettled, to de<lb break="no"/>pend upon as a source of Revenue ; no 
     <lb/>
     mines, no minerals, no forests ; and, 
     <lb/>
    therefore, the allowance we shall re<lb break="no"/>ceive from the Dominion wlll be al<lb break="no"/>most a fixed one for all time to come. 
     <lb/>When we give up our right to levy 
     <lb/>duties on goods imported, we surrender 
     <lb/>an increasing Revenue for a fixed one, 
     <lb/>which will be certain, in the course of 
     <lb/>a very few years, to fall far short of 
     <lb/>our requirements. Is the Revenue 
     <lb/>offered us in the present Terms an 
     <lb/>equivalent to the increasing one we 
     <lb/>surrender ? I maintain that it is not. 
     <lb/>The hon. member credits the Dominion 
     <lb/>with our miscellaneous items ; but he 
     <lb/>will find that under our Government 
     <lb/>we shall always have a list of items not 
     <lb/>enumerated in the Terms, which must 
     <lb/>be paid for out of our local Revenue. 
     <lb/>I now repeat what I stated on a former 
     <lb/>occasion, viz: that if the $800,000 be 
     <lb/>invested in the purchases of the pro<lb break="no"/>prietary lands, not more than two- 
     <lb break="yes"/>thirds of that amount will ever be re<lb break="no"/>turned to the Treasury. Some hon. 
     <lb/>members of the Opposition put down 
     <lb/>the expenditure of the Board of 
     <lb/>Works at $56,000 per year. To show 
     <lb/>how far below the mark that statement 
     <lb/>is, I may state that during the present 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     year alone, there has been $61,000 
     <lb/>
     spent by that Board. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">MR. D. LAIRD</persName>—That amount may 
     <lb/>
     be marked upon the books, but a large 
     <lb/>
     portion of it is not yet expanded, as 
     <lb/>
    there are some large bridges which 
     <lb/>will not be finished for two years to 
     <lb/>come. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERN<lb break="no"/>MENT</persName>.—The money is to all intents 
     <lb/>
     and purposes expended. The hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for New London referred to 
     <lb/>
     his " dashaway policy," and endeavour<lb break="no"/>ed to show that that statement con<lb break="no"/>tained in his letter did not refer to the 
     <lb/>
     late Government, and that the portion 
     <lb/>
     of that letter which was published in 
     <lb/>
     the newspapers was not a true copy. 
     <lb/>
     Now, I have a copy of that letter in 
     <lb/>
     my possession, and will guarantee its 
     <lb/>
     correctness, and that it is genuine, and 
     <lb/>
     I know that the published portion was 
     <lb/>
     also a correct copy. When we see a 
     <lb/>
     member of a Government reveal his 
     <lb/>
     intentions to Mr. Lawson, that he in<lb break="no"/>tended to "dash away, levy taxation, 
     <lb/>
     and run the Government while it will," 
     <lb/>
     we must come to the conclusion that 
     <lb/>
     he has committed one of the most dis<lb break="no"/>honorable acts of which a man can be 
     <lb/>
     guilty. The very men who charged 
     <lb/>
     the members of the Coalition Govern<lb break="no"/>ment with being dishonest and corrupt, 
     <lb/>
     adopted the dishonest dash away policy. 
     <lb/>
     If ever there were dishonest and un<lb break="no"/>principled men entrusted with the 
     <lb/>
     reins of power, it was during the last 
     <lb/>
     twelve months. Their policy was to 
     <lb/>
     "dash away, levy taxation, and to 
     <lb/>
     blame their political opponents for the 
     <lb/>
     results of their actions." Such con<lb break="no"/>duct was surely beneath any right 
     <lb/>
     minded, honorable man, and could not 
     <lb/>
     be justified in any manner whatever. 
     <lb/>
     Many serious charges have been made 
     <lb/>
     by several hon. members of the present 
     <lb/>
     Opposition ; but they have never con<lb break="no"/>victed me of lying and slandering ; and 
     <lb/>
     the Journals of the House do not make 
     <lb/>
     me out a malicious defamer, as they 
     <lb/>
     do the hon. <choice><sic>Leaderof</sic><corr>Leader of</corr></choice> the Opposition 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="1873-04-30_Page_128"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-04-30_Page_128.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">128</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw><lb/>
            
           
           I was never kicked out of a Temper<lb break="no"/>ance Society, as he was, for violating<lb/>an honorable and sacred pledge. No<lb/>truthful charge can be made against<lb/>me of being guilty of falsehood and<lb/>slander, of which he has been convict<lb break="no"/>ed again and again. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for New London thought he made<lb/>a telling speech, and asked how the<lb/>country was going to stand the drain<lb/>from it to pay the interest on the Rail<lb break="no"/>way debt. I answer that £100,000<lb/>sterling have been expended in this<lb/>country in the construction of the<lb/>Railway, of which the merchants have<lb/>received the benefit ; and of that<lb/>amount only some £800 have been<lb/>transmitted to London to pay the in<lb break="no"/>terest on the Debentures. The con<lb break="no"/>struction of the Steamer <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward</hi> drained more than three times<lb/>the amount of the whole Railway tax<lb/>from the Island, in sterling exchange.<lb/>Had it not been for the construction<lb/>of the Railway, every Bank on the<lb/>Island would, at one time, have ceased<lb/>to do business, as was the case with<lb/>many in the other Provinces, and<lb/>there would have been a commercial<lb/>panic. After the Railway is com<lb break="no"/>pleted, if the trade and exports of the<lb/>Colony do not increase considerably,<lb/>there might be some difficulty in pro<lb break="no"/>curing exchange, but while the con<lb break="no"/>struction of the Railway is in progress,<lb/>there can be no difficulty in that re<lb break="no"/>spect, so that the remarks of the hon.<lb/>member do not apply. There would<lb/>be no difficulty in raising money suffi<lb break="no"/>cient to pay the interest on the Rail<lb break="no"/>way debt as well as all other demands,<lb/>but it is not so easy to restore the<lb/>credit of the country after it has been<lb/>injured by the hawking of the Deben<lb break="no"/>tures by the late Colonial Secretary.<lb/>I showed clearly, last night, in my<lb/>remarks, that even admitting that the<lb/>miscellaneous items will be borne by<lb/>the Dominion, the present Terms<lb/>would still be some $70,000 short of<lb/>meeting the requirements of the coun<lb break="no"/>try. Now, I believe that the states<lb break="no"/>
            
            <cb/>
               
           men of Canada are liberal enough not 
     <lb/>to ask us to place ourselves in a ruin<lb break="no"/>ous position, in which we would be<lb/>compelled to resort to local taxation,<lb/>immediately after accepting Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, and becoming a portion of the<lb/>Dominion. It would be far better,<lb/>and more conducive to their interests,<lb/>as well as our own, to give us suffici<lb break="no"/>ent to make our people contented,<lb/>prosperous, and happy. I do not in<lb break="no"/>tend to go over the whole ground<lb/>again ; but I believe we shall have no<lb/>difficulty in obtaining better Terms,<lb/>and that this is a sore spot to the hon.<lb/>members of the Opposition. I am not<lb/>the man who would undertake to go<lb/>on a begging expedition ; when I go<lb/>to ask better Terms I shall go fortified<lb/>by a resolution from this House,—I<lb/>have no intention of sneaking off to<lb/>Ottawa without the knowledge of the<lb/>people, as some before me have done.<lb/>After the last delegation started, a<lb/>prominent member of the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment declared at a public meeting, in<lb/>this city, that they were gone "to fend<lb/>off" Confederation, while in reality<lb/>they were gone to seek terms of union.<lb/>The only man outside the Government<lb/>to be trusted with the secrets of their<lb/>scheme was "dear Mr. Lawson." I<lb/>give the hon. member credit for a good<lb/>deal of shrewdness and clear-headed<lb break="no"/>ness, but I wish I could give him credit<lb/>for more fair dealing and less conspir<lb break="no"/>acy. Before those delegates left for<lb/>Ottawa, it was circulated in St. John,<lb/>N B., paper that there was to be a<lb/>race between Laird for Confederation,<lb/>and Pope for the grants for this Island.<lb/>This precious bit of news was sent<lb/>there in the same way as the despatch<lb/>of the Governor General was suggest<lb break="no"/>ed from this Island. When I make<lb/>this statement, I wish no reflection to<lb/>be cast on the Governor General as<lb/>he was not to blame in any way.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SINC6">MR. SINCLAIR</persName>.—I only wish the<lb/>hon. Leader of the Government would<lb/>produce the original letter written by<lb/>
           
            <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">129</fw><lb/>
            
           me to Mr. Lawson, in order that I<lb/>might publish it. The manner in<lb/>which that letter was obtained, and<lb/>used, was the most contemptible I<lb/>ever heard of. Instead of stating in<lb/>that letter that the late Government<lb/>had determined to dash away, levy<lb/>taxation, &amp;c., as represented by his<lb/>honor, I said that there were men in<lb/>the country who entertained different<lb/>views from my own, and would dash<lb/>away, levy taxation, &amp;c. I also stated<lb/>that the trade that would result from<lb/>a union with Canada, would be greatly<lb/>in favor of this Colony, and that a large<lb/>quantity of goods from the Dominion<lb/>would come in here duty free. The<lb/>hon. Leader of the Government has<lb/>produced a mere garbled extract from<lb/>that letter. I deny that $61,000 have<lb/>been expended this year by the Board<lb/>of Works. Nothing injured the credit<lb/>of this Colony more than the action of<lb/>the Coalition Government in using the<lb/>money, raised by the Railway tariff,<lb/>for general purposes. Their action<lb/>was contrary to law, and detrimental<lb/>to the best interests of the country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Progress was then reported, and<lb/>leave obtained to sit again.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>House adjourned till ten o'clock this<lb/>morning.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, May 1st.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>