<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1873-06-03"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1873-06-03">03 June 1873</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1873">
               <title>The Parliamentary Reporter of Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly</title>.
          <date when="1873"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Examiner</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="260" to="263"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-03_Page_260.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-03_Page_262.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-08-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-08-17">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-03_Page_260">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-03_Page_260.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-03_Page_262">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-03_Page_262.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1873-06-03_Page_260"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-03_Page_260.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">260</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            <p>
       <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. L. H. DAVIES</persName> did not think it 
     <lb/>
    would be conducive to the ends of 
     <lb/>justice that the appointmetnt of the 
     <lb/>Judges of the new Courts should be 
     <lb/>made by the Local Government. The 
     <lb/>appointments of this kind, in the Do<lb break="no"/>minion, are made by the Governor 
     <lb/>General, and as the new Courts will 
     <lb/>not come into operation till the first of 
     <lb/>July next, there was no occasion for 
     <lb/>any haste in making the appointments. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BREC1">HON. ATTY. GENERAL</persName> said that it 
     <lb/>
     was the duty of our Local Government 
     <lb/>
     to constitute the Courts and appoint 
     <lb/>
    the Judges. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POPE2">HON. LEADER OF THE GOVERN<lb break="no"/>MENT</persName> said he would prefer to have the 
     <lb/>
     appointments made by the Governor 
     <lb/>
     General of the Dominion, but it was 
     <lb/>
     the duty of the Lieutenant Governor 
     <lb/>
     in Council to make them. He did 
     <lb/>
     not think the Governor General would 
     <lb/>
     act upon a local statute in a case of 
     <lb/>this kind.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. L. H. DAVIES</persName> said it would be 
     <lb/>
    much more preferable to have the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment of the Judges vested in a 
     <lb/>party having no party bias, or local 
     <lb/>interests to serve ; but at the same 
     <lb/>time, he did not not mean to say that 
     <lb/>the Judges appointed by the local 
     <lb/>Government would not be men of 
     <lb/>ability, honesty, and integrity. He 
     <lb/>was afraid party politics would have 
     <lb/>something to do with those appoint<lb break="no"/>ments, and for that reason thought it 
     <lb/>highly improper that they should be 
     <lb/>made by our local Government. If 
     <lb/>the Governor General is to have the 
     <lb/>power of making such appointments 
     <lb/>after Confederation takes place, why 
     <lb/>not vest in him the power to do so 
     <lb/>under our present circumstances ? 
     <lb/>Why should not the Governor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral have the appointment from the 
     <lb/>beginning, as well as the filling of 
     <lb/>vacancies afterwards ?  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SULL1">HON. Mr. SULLIVAN</persName> thought it per<lb break="no"/>fectly right that our Lieut. Goveror<lb/>in Council should have the appoint<lb break="no"/>
           
            
           <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">261</fw> 
    
            
   
           
     ment of the Judges of those Courts as 
     <lb/>
     long as we remain a separate Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. The present Act comes into 
     <lb/>
     force before this Island forms part of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion, and there is no reason 
     <lb/>
     why we should not transact our own 
     <lb/>
     business till we enter the Union. 
     <lb/>
     After we become a part of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     her Government will pay the salaries 
     <lb/>
     of the Judges, and make all new ap<lb break="no"/>pointments that may be necessary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BREC1">HON. ATTY. GENERAL</persName> said that the 
     <lb/>
     Courts could not be established till the 
     <lb/>
     Judges  were appointed. When the 
     <lb/>
     present Act does pass, the Courts are 
     <lb/>
     not established till they are constituted 
     <lb/>
     by the appointment of the Judges. 
     <lb/>
     If we wish to reap the advantages of 
     <lb/>
     the terms now offered this Island by 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion, we must establish the 
     <lb/>
     Courts by the appointment of the 
     <lb/>
     Judges. Future appointments will 
     <lb/>
     rest with the Dominion Government. 
     <lb/>
     as, when Confederation takes place, it 
     <lb/>
     will be a matter legally belonging to it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. L. H. DAVIES</persName> said that the 
     <lb/>
     question for that hon. Committee to 
     <lb/>
     consider, was, whether our local Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment was more liable to be biased 
     <lb/>
     by party motives in the appointment of 
     <lb/>
     the Judges than the Governor General 
     <lb/>
     in Council, in Canada, was. He was 
     <lb/>
     of opinion that it would be a difficult 
     <lb/>
     matter to get good, well-qualified men, 
     <lb/>
     to accept those appointments. The 
     <lb/>
     consequence of this would be that 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen would be appointed who 
     <lb/>
     are not as eligible as might he wished 
     <lb/>
     for. He would, for the reasons he 
     <lb/>
     had given, move that the words " Lieut. 
     <lb/>
     Governor "  be struck out, and the 
     <lb/>
     words "Governor General of Canada" 
     <lb/>
     be inserted in lieu thereof. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CALL1">Mr. CALLBECK</persName> felt inclined to sup<lb break="no"/>port the amendment. The Dominion 
     <lb/>
     Government has rendered itself liable 
     <lb/>
     for the payment of the Judges' salaries, 
     <lb/>
     and, therefore, there was some reason 
     <lb/>
    why they should have the appoint<lb break="no"/>ments in their hands. Beside this, he 
     <lb/>
          
   
      
            <cb/>
               
            was of opinion that an appointment by<lb/>the Governor General would be more<lb/>acceptable to people, because more<lb/>free from party bias. Gentlemen<lb/>connected with the Bar in this Island,<lb/>are not likely to be neutral in politics,<lb/>and it is probable it will always be so.<lb/>The new Judges will have no paltry<lb/>duty to fulfil, and should, therefore, be<lb/>well qualified for their work. Large<lb/>sums of money will be adjudicated<lb/>upon by them. Gentlemen of high<lb/>standing, good natural talent and<lb/>ability, and quite free from party bias,<lb/>should be appointed to fill such respon<lb break="no"/>sible positions. There was no neces<lb break="no"/>sity to appoint these Judges until we<lb/>enter the Dominion ; the appointment<lb/>could, therefore, be easily vested in<lb/>the Governor General, as it should be.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWL2">HON. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> said that the 
     <lb/>
     Governor General had no control over 
     <lb/>
     the Bill now before the Committee, 
     <lb/>
     and no legal right to appoint the 
     <lb/>
     Judges of the new Court, till we enter 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">Mr. LAIRD</persName> thought the Governor 
     <lb/>
     General should have the appointment 
     <lb/>
     of the Judges of the new Courts, 
     <lb/>
    as the Dominion would have to pay 
     <lb/>their salaries. The Judges should be 
     <lb/>men above local politics, to a certain 
     <lb/>extent, and not mere partizans, chosen 
     <lb/>by the local Government for the time 
     <lb/>being. It is just as well to begin 
     <lb/>right as to end right. He noticed, the 
     <lb/>other day, that the Bill provided for 
     <lb/>their appointment by the Lieutenant 
     <lb/>Governor in Council, but thought it, 
     <lb/>at the time, a mistake on the part of 
     <lb/>the framer of the Bill. It now appears 
     <lb/>that this matter is to be snatched out 
     <lb/>of the hands of the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment before the first of July comes 
     <lb/>round. This is most unfair, just on 
     <lb/>the eve of union with Canada. It is 
     <lb/>not probable that the local Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would have thought of establish<lb break="no"/>ing these Courts if we were not about 
     <lb/>to enter the Dominion. It is now 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="1873-06-03_Page_262"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-03_Page_262.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">262</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
           
     only a matter of form to complete the 
     <lb/>
     union with Canada.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERN<lb break="no"/>MENT</persName>.—The hon. Leader of the 0p<lb break="no"/>position thinks the Governor General 
     <lb/>
     should have the appointment of the 
     <lb/>
     Judges, because the latter should be 
     <lb/>
     free from all party bias, and almost 
     <lb/>
     angels, no doubt. What difference 
     <lb/>
     would the fact that they were appoint<lb break="no"/>ed by the Governor General of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion, make in the individual so 
     <lb/>
     appointed ? The Government of New 
     <lb/>
     Brunsmck appointed their Judges 
     <lb/>
     just before entering Confederation, and 
     <lb/>
     when the union took place, the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government paid the salaries. 
     <lb/>
     The Governor General may decline to 
     <lb/>
     act upon our Local Statute if he 
     <lb/>
     chooses to do so. As far as his (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     P's.) own feelings were concerned, he 
     <lb/>
     would sooner see the Governor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral make the appointments, but it 
     <lb/>
     was the legal duty of the Local Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to do so. The latter had 
     <lb/>
     supporters among legal gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     just as competent and able to fill 
     <lb/>
     places on the Bench as any one who 
     <lb/>
     supported the Opposition. The law<lb break="no"/>yers who support the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment are not greater partizans than 
     <lb/>
     those who support the Opposition. 
     <lb/>
     One would suppose from the remarks 
     <lb/>
     made by the hon. member for West 
     <lb/>
     River, just now, that any lawyer who 
     <lb/>
     did not support the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was an angel, without question. 
     <lb/>
     The Government conceded every<lb break="no"/>thing they could reasonably concede to 
     <lb/>
     the Opposition in the division of the 
     <lb/>
     districts and location of the Courts, 
     <lb/>
     and supposed that in return they 
     <lb/>
     would receive their fair and honest 
     <lb/>
     support in reference to the other 
     <lb/>
     matters contained in the Bill, instead 
     <lb/>
     of a factious opposition, such as they 
     <lb/>
     had given. If the Opposition chose to 
     <lb/>
     prolong the discussion, he was pre<lb break="no"/>pared to sit there till the Bill was 
     <lb/>
     passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. L. H. DAVIES</persName> said that the 
     <lb/>
    Bill could not be carried as brought 
     <lb/>down by the Government, as there 
     <lb/>was just as much opposition given to 
     <lb/>it by hon. members on the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment side of the House, as by the 
     <lb/>Opposition. There was no intention 
     <lb/>on the part of the Opposition to offer 
     <lb/>a factious opposition to the Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">Mr. LAIRD</persName> said there was no need 
     <lb/>
     that the Bill should go into operation 
     <lb/>
     immediately, as had been intimated by 
     <lb/>
     some hon. members on the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment side of the House ; because the 
     <lb/>
     country should have some warning of 
     <lb/>
     the change about to be made. There 
     <lb/>
     was no need for haste in reference to 
     <lb/>
     this matter on the part of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, except to suit some particular 
     <lb/>
     party purpose they may have in view. 
     <lb/>
    As we were so near Dominion Day, 
     <lb/>the appointments should be vested in 
     <lb/>the Governor General, in order that 
     <lb/>they might be made independent of 
     <lb/>local politics altogether. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CALL1">Mr. CALLBECK</persName> thought it would 
     <lb/>
     be quite time enough to set the new 
     <lb/>
     machinery in motion when proper 
     <lb/>
     Court Houses were erected in the 
     <lb/>
     several districts, The Act was not 
     <lb/>
     likely to give satisfaction till some 
     <lb/>
    preparation was made for working the 
     <lb/>new system. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI2">HON. COL. SECRETARY</persName> was 
     <lb/>
     of opinion that it would be unconstitu<lb break="no"/>tional to invest the power of making 
     <lb/>
     the appointments of the new Judges in 
     <lb/>
     a Government that has no control over 
     <lb/>
     the Island. The Governor General 
     <lb/>
     would not be bound by any Act this 
     <lb/>
     House might pass before going into 
     <lb/>
     Confederation, in reference to this 
     <lb/>
     matter. It would be all very well for 
     <lb/>
     the Governor General to make the 
     <lb/>
     appointments if we were in the Do<lb break="no"/>minion ; but nothing the House could 
     <lb/>
     now do, would bind His Excellency in 
     <lb/>
     Council to make them before we be<lb break="no"/>come a part of the Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
           
            <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">263</fw>
            
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">Mr. LAIRD</persName> considered that unless 
     <lb/>
     the Island went into Confederation, it 
     <lb/>
     would not be desirable to put the new 
     <lb/>
     Courts into operation at all. If any<lb break="no"/>thing occurred to prevent our forming 
     <lb/>
     a part of the Dominion, he would not 
     <lb/>
     like to see the Bill become law. Im<lb break="no"/>mediately alter we enter the Union,  
     <lb/>
     the Governor General would have the 
     <lb/>
     power of making the appointments if 
     <lb/>
     they were not previously filled. There 
     <lb/>
     was no need to appoint the new 
     <lb/>
     Judges before the first of July. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWL2">HON. MR. HOWLAN</persName> asked whether 
     <lb/>
     it was to be supposed that the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor General knew more about our 
     <lb/>
     Barristers, or was in a better position 
     <lb/>
     to make a good selection from their 
     <lb/>
     ranks for the new Judgeships than 
     <lb/>
     the members of our local Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. If the power to make the ap<lb break="no"/>pointments were vested in His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency the Governor General, he would 
     <lb/>
     require information from some source 
     <lb/>
     before he could make them. To find 
     <lb/>
     a Barrister of five years' standing who 
     <lb/>
     has not taken a part in party politics 
     <lb/>
     would not be an easy matter. Where 
     <lb/>
     is the lawyer of five years' standing 
     <lb/>
     who has never made a stump speech ? 
     <lb/>
     It was only fair to presume that the 
     <lb/>
     local Government are, at least, in as 
     <lb/>
     good a position to select a good Judge 
     <lb/>
     as the Governor General and Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government. The former are 
     <lb/>
     better acquainted with gentlemen of 
     <lb/>
     the legal profession in this Colony. 
     <lb/>
     The whole action of the Opposition, 
     <lb/>
    with reference to this matter, is a com<lb break="no"/>plete farce from beginning to end. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SULL1">HON. Mr. SULLIVAN</persName> thought the 
     <lb/>
     amendment proposed by the hon. jun. 
     <lb/>
     member for Murray Harbor was as 
     <lb/>
     absurd as anything that could be im<lb break="no"/>agined. The hon. member thinks the 
     <lb/>
     Governor General in Council should 
     <lb/>
     have the appointment of the new 
     <lb/>
     Judges before they have any power 
     <lb/>
     over our Colonial affairs ! It would 
     <lb/>
    be altogether illegal for them to  make  
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
       them, and the result of vesting the 
     <lb/>
       appointment in them would probably 
     <lb/>
    be that they would treat it as a nullity. 
     <lb/>The Courts must be established before 
     <lb/>we enter the Dominion, in order that 
     <lb/>we may reap the advantages to which 
     <lb/>we, as a Colony, are entitled; and to do 
     <lb/>this, the Judges must be appointed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The question was then put, and 
     <lb/>
     the amendment lost. The original 
     <lb/>
     clause was agreed to. The next clause 
     <lb/>
     was then read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. L. H. DAVIES</persName> said that in all 
     <lb/>
     similar Bills in the other Provinces 
     <lb/>
     and Great Britain, Barristers of seven 
     <lb/>
     years' standing were required to fill 
     <lb/>
     the positions of Judges. In fact, this 
     <lb/>
     was the lowest standard. The 
     <lb/>
     principle was a good one, and would 
     <lb/>
     commend itself to every hon. member 
     <lb/>
     of the House. He would, therefore, 
     <lb/>
     move that the word "five"  be struck 
     <lb/>
     out of the clause, and the word "seven" 
     <lb/>
     inserted instead. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">Mr. LAIRD</persName> seconded the motion, 
     <lb/>
     and said that he could not understand 
     <lb/>
     why the standard of qualification for 
     <lb/>
     the office of Judge should be made 
     <lb/>
     lower here than anywhere else. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The question was then put and the 
     <lb/>
     amendment lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After some further consideration, 
     <lb/>
     other clauses in the Bill were adopted 
     <lb/>
     without debate.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Speaker then took the chair, 
     <lb/>
     and the Chairman reported progress, 
     <lb/>
     and obtained leave to sit again. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     House adjourned till ten o'clock to<lb break="no"/>day.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <p rendition="simple:right">I.O.</p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>