<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1866-05-07"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1866-05-07">7 May 1866</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1866">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1866, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1866"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Examiner" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="110"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_100.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_101.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_102.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_103.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_104.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_105.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_106.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_107.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_108.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_109.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_110.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-08">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_100">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_100.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_101">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_101.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_102">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_102.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_103">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_103.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_104">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_104.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_105">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_105.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_106">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_106.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_107">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_107.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_108">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_108.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_109">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_109.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_110">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_110.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="100" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_100.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">100</fw>

<head rendition="simple:right">MONDAY, 7th May, 1866.</head><lb/>

<p>House in Committee on various Despatches and Papers <lb/>
Mr. John Yeo in the Chair <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">CONFEDERATION QUESTION</p> 

<p>Hon. the Leader of the Government (J.C POPE). <lb/>
With respect to the important questions of Confederation I <lb/>
do not at present intend to say much more than that I <lb/>
hold in my hand certain Resolutions in which are embodied <lb/>
my views concerning that question, and which are most de<lb break="no"/>cidedly adverse to the scheme of Union as propounded and <lb/>
agreed to at the Quebec Conference. To hon. members <lb/>
holding the same opinion as myself concerning that scheme, <lb/>
these Resolutions will I apprehend be accepted as a suffi<lb break="no"/>ciently full and satisfactory declaration of our sentiments <lb/>
concerning it. To some, however, whose repugnance to the <lb/>
proposed union may be little less than my own, they may <lb/>
probably be considered too strong; and perhaps, by others, <lb/>
not strong enough. I shall, however, submit them to this <lb/>
Committee in their present form and it will be for them <lb/>
to modify, abridge, enlarge, or accept them in their present <lb/>
form just as the maority in thier wisdom may determine. <lb/>
The great reason why we protest against anything in the <lb/>
shape of Union is our dream of being swamped by the Ca<lb break="no"/>nadas. When the scheme was before this House in the <lb/>
session of 186 , it was condemned by a majority on each <lb/>
side. As respects the Executive, one or two members of it <lb/>
are, I regret to say, inveurable to it, but the majority are <lb/>
strenuously opposed to it. That, however, as respects the <lb/>
discussion of the question, is but of little consequence, for <lb/>
opposition to the scheme is not now to be offered as any <lb/>
part of the policy of the Cabinet, and all parties are quite <lb/>
free to discuss the question wholly upon its own merits, and <lb/>
quite untrammeled by political ties or connexions. Two <lb/>
members of the Cabinet were Delegates to the Quebec Con<lb break="no"/>vention and in the Conference held by that Convention, <lb/>
none expressed themselves more strongly in favor of the <lb/>
Scheme of Union projected by it than they did and, for <lb/>
their consistent adherence to the vonventions concerning it <lb/>
which they then avowed surely even such amongst us who are <lb/>
the most opposed to the Union, can have no right whatever <lb/>
to censure or condemn them; and neither do I believe any <lb/>
one of us arrogates to himself or assumes such a right. <lb/>
These gentlemen have, ever since the question arose, noted <lb/>
with respect to it, most honestly and consistently, and in <lb/>
perfect good faith. I speak more particularly of the Hon. <lb/>
he Solicitor General (Mr. Haviland) whose conduct with <lb/>

<pb n="101" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_101.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">101</fw>

reference to the projected Union, has, throughout, been so <lb/>
open, candid, and honorable, that honestly to impugn it, in <lb/>
any particular. I hold to be morally impossible on the part <lb/>
even of the most bitter opponent of the project. I have <lb/>
said that some hon. members, although in the main approv<lb break="no"/>ing of the Resolutions, may think them too strong ; it, <lb/>
therefore appears to me to be only right that, before we enter <lb/>
upon a discussion of them. I should explain the reason why <lb/>
they are so strongly worded. It is this : Great fears are <lb/>
entertained by the public mind that the Government, in pur<lb break="no"/>suance of the same course which it seems, is about to be <lb/>
adopted by Canada and Nova Scotia, and, perhaps, by New <lb/>
Brunswick, may be induced to send delegates to London for <lb/>
the purpose of conferring with the Imperial Government on <lb/>
the Conference Scheme ; and that, although such delegates, <lb/>
if sent by our Government, might be instructed to oppose our <lb/>
being included in the Scheme, and they themselves should be <lb/>
sincere in their intention to do so, yet, when associated in <lb/>
conference on the question with the British Cabinet, who <lb/>
are desirous that the Confederation should be accomplished, <lb/>
and with delegates from the other Provinces, whose mission <lb/>
will be to endeavour to induce the Imperial Government to <lb/>
frame, and carry through the British Parliament, a Bill to <lb/>
decree and establish the Confederation, they might be in<lb break="no"/>duced to change their views and assent to the scheme, as, <lb/>
perhaps, materially modified in compliance with the sug<lb break="no"/>gestions of the Imperial Government ; and so eventually <lb/>
Prince Edward Island, even against the will of our people, <lb/>
might be made a member of the Confederate States, or Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces of British America. It is to prevent this that, warn<lb break="no"/>ed by experience, the Resolutions are so strongly worded. <lb/>
What has taken place once may, under similar in<lb break="no"/>fluences, take place again. The hon. gentleman <lb/>
then stated by what pressure the Legislature of Prince <lb/>
Edward Island had, in the Session of 1866, been <lb/>
induced to appoint His Excellency the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor to appoint delegates to confer with delegates from <lb/>
Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, touching the expediency <lb/>
of a Union of the three Provinces of Nova Scotia, New <lb/>
Brunswick, and Prince Edward Island, under one Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and Legislature, the Report of the said Delegates to <lb/>
be laid before our own Legislature. He then went on to <lb/>
state that its having been arranged that the Delegates so to <lb/>
be appointed by the Governments of these three Provinces <lb/>
should hold their Conference in Charlottetown, Canada— <lb/>
at that time engaged in considering the necessity of a <lb/>
change in its constitution—solicited permission to be pre<lb break="no"/>sent by Delegation at the Conference, and their request <lb/>
having been courteously complied with, the issue of the Con<lb break="no"/>ference—of which, however, no report has yet been given <lb/>
to the public—was, through the influence which the Cana<lb break="no"/>dian Delegation brought to bear upon the Conference, a re<lb break="no"/>solution to hold a further Conference at Quebec, with the <lb/>
content of the Governments of the Lower Provinces, for con<lb break="no"/>sidering the feasibility of a Union upon a larger basis than <lb/>
that originally contemplated by the Maritime Provinces. <lb/>
That Conference was held accordingly ; our Delegates, if <lb/>
not wholly yet in part, were induced to give their assent <lb/>
to the scheme of Confederation ; and it is not only, with the <lb/>
intention of convincing the Imperial Government that the <lb/>
people of Prince Edward Island are most decidedly opposed <lb/>
to a Union with Canada upon any terms, but also to pre<lb break="no"/>vent the possibility of the Governments sending deleagates <lb/>
to the London Conference without acting in the matter in <lb/>
direct opposition to the will of the people as delcated <lb/>
through their parliamentary representatives, that the word<lb break="no"/>ing of the Resolutions are so strong and conclusive. I <lb/>

<cb/> 

shall, said the hom. gentleman, say no more upon the mat<lb break="no"/>ter at present, although, perhaps, when it has progressed <lb/>
a little, I may have some observations to make touching the <lb/>
merits and nature, as I apprehend them, of the Quebec <lb/>
Scheme of Confederation itself. I will now submit the Re<lb break="no"/>solutions to the Committee—to be as I have before said, mo<lb break="no"/>dified, softened, or strengthened according to the will and <lb/>
pleasure of the majority ; and, to that end, I beg leave to <lb/>
suggest, Mr. Charman, that, in the first place, it will be <lb/>
proper for you to read the whole of them at once to the <lb/>
Committee. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Chairman then read the Resolutions as here below <lb/>
given :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"This House having had under consideration the message of <lb/>
His Excellency the Lieut. Governor communicating a Despatch <lb/>
from the Right Hon. Edward Cardwell, Her Majesty's Principal <lb/>
Secretary of State for the Colonial Department, upon the sub<lb break="no"/>ject of a Federation of the British North American Provinces, <lb/>
and having most carefully and earnestly considered the project <lb/>
in all its bearings— <lb/></p> 

<p>"RESOLVED, As the deliberate opinion of this House, that any <lb/>
Union of the British North America Colonies which would em<lb break="no"/>brace Prince Edward Island, upon the terms and principles set forth <lb/>
in the Resolutions of the Conference of Quebec, held on the 10th <lb/>
October, 1864, would not only be unjust to the inhabitants of <lb/>
this Colony, but prove disastrous to their dearest and most <lb/>
cherished rights and interests as a free people, enjoying the bles<lb break="no"/>sings of a priceless constitution guaranteed to them by the Imperial <lb/>
Government of Great Britain. <lb/></p> 

<p>"That, considering the isolated, peculiar and exceptional posi<lb break="no"/>tion of Prince Edward Island, as contrasted with the other British <lb/>
North American Provinces and Colonies, this House deems it to <lb/>
be its duty, as the Constitutional Representative of the people <lb/>
of Prince Edward Island, to re-affirm the decision so clearly and <lb/>
unequivocally declared by this House in the Resolutions passed <lb/>
by it, in its last Session, upon the subject of a Union of the <lb/>
British North American Colonies, andafterwards communicated <lb/>
by the joint Address of the Legislative Council and House of <lb/>
Assembly of this Colony to Her Majesty's Imperial Government. <lb/></p> 

<p>"RESOLVED FURTHER, That even if a Union of the Continental <lb/>
Provinces of British North America should have the effect of <lb/>
strengthening and binding more closely together those Provinces, <lb/>
or advancing their material and commercial interests, this House <lb/>
cannot admit that a Federal Union of the North American Provin<lb break="no"/>ces and Colonies, which would include Prince Edward Island, could <lb/>
ever be accomplished upon terms that would prove advantageous <lb/>
to the interests and well-being of the people of this Island. cut off <lb/>
and separated as it is, and must ever remain, from the neighboring <lb/>
Provinces, by an immovable barrier of ice for many months in <lb/>
the year; and this Heuse deems it to be its sacred and imperative <lb/>
duty to declare and record its conviction, as it now does, that <lb/>
any Federal Union of' the North American Colonies, that would <lb/>
embrace this Island, would be as hostile to the feelings and <lb/>
wishes, as it would be opposed to the best and most vital in<lb break="no"/>terests, of its people. <lb/></p> 

<p>"RESOLVED FURTHER, That while this House cannot assent to a <lb/>
Federal Union of this Island with the other Colonies, they recog<lb break="no"/>nize it to bathe duty of this Colony to contribute, from its local <lb/>
revenues, towards its defence, in fair and just proportionto its <lb/>
means," <lb/></p> </quote>

<p><persName ref="pers:KELL1">Hon. Mr. KELLY</persName>. I approve of every word of these <lb/>
Resolutions ; and I believe,the majority of the Committee <lb/>
will heartily agree to them. My determination is to ad<lb break="no"/>here to every word of them ; although, if they could be <lb/>
made stronger, I would wish that they were. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Mr. SINCLAIR</persName>. He was pleased to see Resolutions of <lb/>
this nature tabled by the Hon. Leader of the Government <lb/>
He believed that fears were entertained throughout the <lb/>
country as to the action of the Government on this question. <lb/>
The Governments of the other Provinces have acted so un<lb break="no"/>constitutionally, and seem so determined to force Confeder<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="102" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_102.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">102</fw>

ation upon the people, that it is no wonder the people of this <lb/>
Colony wait with anxiety the action of this Legislature. He <lb/>
was glad however, to find, by the Resolutions submitted, that <lb/>
no fears need be entertained that they will commit us in any <lb/>
way to the principle of Confederation. Indeed, if he had any ob<lb break="no"/>jection to the Resolutions, it would be that the language in <lb/>
the last Resolution was rather too strong. It might imply <lb/>
that we were so obstinate that no terms could be given us <lb/>
which would induce this Colony to comply with the desire <lb/>
of the British Government. He believed terms could be given, <lb/>
but be firmly believed no terms would be given which would <lb/>
compensate us for the sacrifice we would make in going into <lb/>
Confederation. We have this to consider in tabling our <lb/>
Resolutions to see that they are not such as to prevent some <lb/>
hon. members from supporting them, although much hon. <lb/>
members may be opposed to Confederation ; the Resolutions <lb/>
against Confederation last Session were carried by a majority <lb/>
of twenty, and if our Resolutions this Session are carried by <lb/>
a much smaller majority, it might injure the cause by allow<lb break="no"/>ing the pro-Confederation to misrepresent the feelings both of <lb/>
the House and of the country, by arguing that it indicated a <lb/>
change of sentiment in favor of Confederation. He hoped <lb/>
this House would be united in supporting a Resolution which, <lb/>
whilst drawn up in courteous language, will yet firmly ex<lb break="no"/>press our refusal to acknowledge the principle of Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Mr. DUNCAN</persName>. I protest against a Union of Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island with the Canadas upon any terms. We could not <lb/>
possibly gain anything by it, but it would certainly be preju<lb break="no"/>dical to us in every particular. We could not be benefited even <lb/>
by free and unrestricted commercial intercourse with them, <lb/>
Everything which could be exported from this Island, Canada <lb/>
produces ; and therefore no trade of any importance can spring <lb/>
up between that Province and this Colony. If we were to <lb/>
send up oats to Canada, they would have to send them down <lb/>
again to Halifax for a market. As for fish, they can export <lb/>
enough to supply all North America. Our oysters are, perhaps, <lb/>
all that we could supply them with ; and I would say if they <lb/>
want them, let them pay for them. Their railroads and <lb/>
canals would not benefit us. As for our sending delegates <lb/>
to London, with a view to the procuring of better terms, the <lb/>
idea was absurd in the extreme. What concessions for our <lb/>
benefit could our two delegates- - were we to send them—ob<lb break="no"/>tain against the opposition and eloquence of the delegates of <lb/>
Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, and the Canadas—two for <lb/>
each of this Provinces, eight in all opposed to our two? <lb/>
Besides Canada has declared that she will not admit of any <lb/>
alteration in the Quebec Scheme, and even threatened that <lb/>
if the Imperial Government should insist upon making any <lb/>
she would withdraw her allegiance to the British Crown, <lb/>
and declare herself independent. Nothing could be more <lb/>
unjust to Prince Edward Island than representation on the <lb/>
basis of population, as laid down by that scheme, according <lb/>
to which the Canadas would have 100 representatives in the <lb/>
House of Commons, more than the aggregate of all the <lb/>
Colonies, the number assigned to us being only 5. Repre<lb break="no"/>sentation on this basis might do very well for Canada ; but as <lb/>
respects Prince Edward Island, it would be nothing but <lb/>
mere mockery. Again, by that scheme, in exchange for <lb/>
our revenue, now £67.000, we should receive only some <lb/>
£48,000 per annum. Even had Canada, in view of such a  <lb/>
commutation on our part, agreed to give us £200,000 sterl<lb break="no"/>ing to enable us to buy up the proprietary claims, we should <lb/>
still, in this point of view, be material sufferers. In fact <lb/>
the whole scheme has been devised for the benefit of Canada, <lb/>
and were we to go into it, we would, as I have said before, <lb/>
be losers in every particular. We would have to yield up <lb/>
our position of independence—the power to make our own <lb/>
laws and to direct the application of our moneys—our <lb/>
local legislature would be little better than a town council ; <lb/>
and should our local revenue become inadequate, we would <lb/>
have to sub,it to the burthen of direct taxation ; and, in <lb/>
fact all our interests would be sacrificed for the benefit of <lb/>
Canada. The Resolutions are by not means too strong. If <lb/>
it were possible I would wish to have them made still <lb/>
stronger. <lb/></p>

<cb/> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WARB1">Hon. Mr. WARBURTON</persName>. If the determination of the <lb/>
great majority of the House was—as he believed it was— <lb/>
to declare against a Union of Prince Edward Island with <lb/>
Canada, upon any terms, that determination could not be <lb/>
expressed in language too strong. It was necessary to give <lb/>
the Home Government to understand that our resolution <lb/>
on that head was conclusive. Our representation by 5 <lb/>
members in the House of Commons would be of no service <lb/>
to us. The allowance to us of 80 cents per head of our <lb/>
population, as determined by the Census of 1861, in ex<lb break="no"/>change for our revenue, and in full settlement of all <lb/>
future demands upon the General Government, would <lb/>
be a palpable injustice— £48,000 for a revenue already <lb/>
nearly double that amount ! Besides, according to the <lb/>
system of taxation which obtained in Canada, our taxation <lb/>
would be doubled. To give us any chance of justice at all, <lb/>
the Union, should we be forced to accept, it should be a Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Union. In a Federal Union we should have no power <lb/>
at all : our Local Legislature would avail us nothing ; and, <lb/>
in that case, it would be as well that our Legislative Halls <lb/>
should be blown up in the air. If we were to be compelled <lb/>
to enter into a Union at all, he would prefer a Legislative <lb/>
one ; but he believed scarcely one man in the Island, cer<lb break="no"/>tainly not many, would consent to a Union of any kind. If <lb/>
we looked to history, we should find a warning against the <lb/>
Quebec scheme in the unequal and ill-assented Union of <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LONG2">Hon. Mr. LONGWORTH</persName>. Last Session, I supported <lb/>
the Resolutions submitted by the Hon. the Leader of the <lb/>
Government (Hon. J.C. Pope) ; and I did so because I <lb/>
believed that a Union of Prince Edward Island with Cana<lb break="no"/>da and the other British American Provinces upon the <lb/>
terms laid down in the Quebec Scheme, would be disastrous <lb/>
to her best interests. I conceive our position to be an ex<lb break="no"/>ceptional one, and that, from its peculiarity, although we <lb/>
should be taxed equally with the peoples of the other Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces for Railways, Canals and other Public Works in <lb/>
Canada, it was not in the nature of things that we could <lb/>
derive any direct benefit from them. During five months <lb/>
of the year, cut off as we are by an icy barrier from the <lb/>
continent, I considered that we could hold no commercial <lb/>
intercourse whatever with the other Federated Provinces ; <lb/>
and that, therefore our Union with them, except upon terms <lb/>
very different from those contained in the Report of the <lb/>
Quebec Convention, would have been one of extreme hard<lb break="no"/>ship and injustice. Another objection which I had to the <lb/>
Union was that according to the Scheme laid down in the <lb/>
Report, representation in the House of Commons is to be <lb/>
based upon population. Representation on that basis is as <lb/>
objectionable, as it respects New Brunswick and Nova <lb/>
Scotia, as it is with respect to Prince Edward Island. <lb/>
Upper Canada is a growing country and her population will <lb/>
rapidly increase ; and as that increases, so, according to the <lb/>
Quebec scheme of representation, her representation in the <lb/>
Federal House of Commons would increase, whilst that of <lb/>
Prince Edward Island would decrease. And, in fact, if the <lb/>
increase in the population of Nova Scotia and New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick does not, in the future, grow more rapidly than it has <lb/>
in the past, they will also, if the plan be strictly carried <lb/>
out, be losers, instead of gainers, as respects legislative re<lb break="no"/>presenation. Thus, as respects representation on the basis <lb/>
of population, the scheme appeared to me to be unjust to <lb/>
us, and I was therefore prepared to go against it ; and the <lb/>
result of our deliberations upon it in this House was its re<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="103" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_103.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">103</fw>

jection by a large majority. I. for one, am not changed. <lb/>
I entertain the same objections to the Scheme which I en<lb break="no"/>tertained then, and I am therefore glad to presume that <lb/>
the Resolutions just submitted by the Hon. the Leader of <lb/>
the Government harmonize with the views on that question <lb/>
of a majority on both sides. In respect to Prince Edward <lb/>
Island, the allowance of 80 cents per head of our population <lb/>
in exchange for our revenue, is quite insufficient. What! <lb/>
only £48,000 a year for the relinquishment of our revenue <lb/>
of £70,000 a year. and that too to be in full settlement of all <lb/>
future demands upon the General Government. A most <lb/>
princely offer indeed! Why in the course of a few years, <lb/>
it will in all probability amount to £150,000 a year, and <lb/>
all that, together with our independent constitution, we <lb/>
would, according to the Quebec Scheme of Union, if we <lb/>
accede to it, have to surrender for an annual allowance of <lb/>
£48,000 for our local expenses, all of which, with the ex<lb break="no"/>ception of the salaries of the Lieutenant Governor and the <lb/>
Judges we should have to defray ourselves out of that <lb/>
magnificentallowance ; and, should it not be found sufficient, <lb/>
we would have to make up the deficiency by direct tax<lb break="no"/>ation. This is quite sufficient to convince us, I think, that <lb/>
if we were to enter into Confederation on the basis of the <lb/>
Quebec \report, justice could never be done to us. This is <lb/>
the decided opinion of the people as a body, generally <lb/>
speaking, and through a majority of their parliamentary re<lb break="no"/>presentatives they have already declared, and will now again <lb/>
declare, that the Quebec Scheme of Confederation will never <lb/>
be acceded to by them. That they are most decidedly op<lb break="no"/>posed to a Union with Canada upon any terms, we know with <lb/>
certainty, and their decided objection to it, or rather rejec<lb break="no"/>tion of it, is affirmed by a majority of their representatives <lb/>
in this House, last Session. It is now our duty to re-affirm. <lb/>
We must all admit that Nova Scotia and New Brunswick <lb/>
must be the best judges of their own affairs, and have a <lb/>
constitutional right to decide concerning them for them<lb break="no"/>selves. But, when we see it asserted in their papers that if <lb/>
a Union, on the basis of the Quebec Scheme, take place at <lb/>
all, it must include Prince Edward Island ; and, further, <lb/>
whilst admitting that possibly, if we exerted ourselves to <lb/>
procure them, better terms might be conceded to us, main<lb break="no"/>taining but we shall not be allowed to stand aloof ; it be<lb break="no"/>hoves us most distinctly and peremptorily to declare that we <lb/>
were to admit that such terms could be conceded us as <lb/>
would make our union with the other Provinces beneficial <lb/>
to us, that would go a long way towards warranting an as<lb break="no"/>sumption on the part of the other Provinces, and even on <lb/>
that of the House Government, that, by a little skillful <lb/>
management on their part, and the promise of one or two <lb/>
flattering concessions, we might be induced to give a favor<lb break="no"/>able ear to the Scheme ; and, as respects proceedings on our <lb/>
part, the next step might be the appointment of delegates <lb/>
to the London Conference. And, that step once taken, our <lb/>
delegates would decide ; we could neither insist upon better <lb/>
terms, nor could we fall back upon our original resolution <lb/>
to reject the scheme. We would be completely trapped, <lb/>
and our heads drawn into the noose. Our best course. <lb/>
therefore, will be not to admit the possibility of such terms <lb/>
being accorded to us as would be acceptable and conducive <lb/>
to our interests. The first Resolution repudiates the idea <lb/>
that we can be embraced in any Union of the Provinces, <lb/>
upon the terms of the Quebec Scheme, in any way which <lb/>
would be beneficial or advantageous to us. The second is <lb/>
stronger ; and one hon. member (Mr. Sinclair,) has said <lb/>
that it is too strong. But it only says that this House can <lb/>  

<cb/>

not admit that a <hi rendition="simple:italic">Federal</hi> Union of the North American <lb/>
Provinces and Colonies, which would include Prince Edward <lb/>
Island, could never be accomplished on terms that would <lb/>
prove advantageous to the interests and well-being of her <lb/>
people ; and assigns a reason for that affirmation ; but it <lb/>
does not say that, if Great Britain and the other Provinces <lb/>
would agree to it, a <hi rendition="simple:italic">Legislative</hi> Union, which would allow <lb/>
us to retain our Revenue might not be made acceptable to us. <lb/>
It has been said that if Prince Edward Island remain <lb/>
out of the Union, she will either be left in a most undesir<lb break="no"/>able isolated position, or be annexed to the United States. <lb/>
As to the perils of isolation, the people, I feel certain, will <lb/>
be very willing to encounter them provided they are left in <lb/>
the enjoyment of all their present rights and privileges, <lb/>
And as to annexation to the United States, I believe that <lb/>
will never take place against their will ; and, moreover, I <lb/>
believe that such annexation will never be sought by them, <lb/>
so long as Great Britain shall be willing to regard them as <lb/>
her children, and to watch over and protect them, with that <lb/>
truly parental care and solicitude for their well-being, which <lb/>
she has hitherto manifested towards them. The people of <lb/>
this Island will never consent to be annexed to a foreign <lb/>
power, unless great Britain shall herself cast them adrift. <lb/>
That, however, I believe she will never do ; and our pre<lb break="no"/>sent happy connexion with her will, I trust, endure for <lb/>
so, ages to come. As long as Britain is willing that it shall be <lb/>
we will remain true in our allegiance to the British Crown. <lb/>
But the duties of Great Britain to us, and to her other <lb/>
subjects in these Provinces are great. It is her duty to <lb/>
protect us, by her fleets and armies, against any foreign foe. <lb/>
But, whilst we assert this, we freely admit that it is also <lb/>
equally our duty, in each of the Provinces, to contribute <lb/>
freely from our local revenues towards our defence ; and <lb/>
cheerfully will we of Prince Edward Island fulfill that duty <lb/>
in fair and just proportion to our means. I shall steadily <lb/>
resist anything like an acknowledgment of the principle of <lb/>
a Federal Union of these Provinces as asserted in the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Report ; for I believe that were we once to admit that <lb/>
principle, we would, inevitably, be driven into it. Our ac<lb break="no"/>knowledgement of the principle would be tantamount to our <lb/>
signing and sealing of the bond ; and we, our children, and <lb/>
our children's children would be bound by, it for all time to <lb/>
come. I know hon. gentlemen in this house will say that <lb/>
it is our duty to acquiesce in the Quebec Scheme of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, because that scheme is not only approved of by Her <lb/>
Majesty the Queen and her Government, but also because it is <lb/>
their earning desire that it should forthwith be carried into <lb/>
effect. Now, with great deference to the opinion of those <lb/>
hon. gentlemen, I beg leave to say that, although in senti<lb break="no"/>ments of loyalty and attachment to the British Crown, I in <lb/>
no way yield to them ; yet, representing, in this House, <lb/>
a large independent and intelligent constituency, whose <lb/>
opinions concerning the projected Union of these Provinces <lb/>
fully coincide with my own, to these opinions it is my <lb/>
bounden duty firmly to adhere. Now is the time for us to <lb/>
be cautious. These are my sentiments, and, in pursuance <lb/>
of them, I am ready to support the Resolutions now before <lb/>
us ; but if they can be amended without an acknowledg<lb break="no"/>ment of the principle of Union, in such an amendment of <lb/>
them, I shall, most likely, be found quite willing to ac<lb break="no"/>quiesce. I will not trespass upon the attention of the <lb/>
House any longer, at present, further than by again saying <lb/>
that I am prepared not only to vote for the first Resolution, <lb/>
which says that it is "the deliberate opinion of this House, <lb/>
that any Union of the British North American Colonies <lb/>
which would embrace Prince Edward Island, upon the <lb/>
terms and principles set forth in the Resolutions of the Con<lb break="no"/> 

<pb n="104" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_104.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">104</fw>

ference of Quebec, would not only be unjust to the inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants of this Colony, but prove disastrous to their dearest <lb/>
and most cherished rights and interests as a free people, en<lb break="no"/>joying the blessings of a priceless Constitution, guaranteed <lb/>
to them by the Imperial Government of Great Britain " ; <lb/>
and, as respects the second Resolution, which declares that <lb/>
" we cannot admit that a Federal Union of the North Ame<lb break="no"/>rican Provinces and Colonies, which would include Prince <lb/>
Edward Island could ever be accomplished upon terms that <lb/>
would prove advantageous to the interests and well-being of <lb/>
the people of this Island,"— I am also prepared to vote for it <lb/>
in its full integrity ; although, should it be found possible <lb/>
so to modify it—without any acknowledgement of the princi<lb break="no"/>ples of Confederation set forth in the Report of the Quebec <lb/>
Conference—as to render it more acceptable to such hon. <lb/>
members as may think it rather too strong in its present <lb/>
form,—to such a modification of it I shall certainly offer no <lb/>
opposition. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>. Having, at length, in the House, last <lb/>
Session, and subsequently, at public meetings, expressed <lb/> 
his views concerning the projected Confederation of the <lb/>
British North American Provinces, he did not think it <lb/>
necessary that he should then enter into any thing like a <lb/>
full recapitulation of them. The Resolutions submitted to <lb/>
the Committee were certainly very strong : the last, in his <lb/>
opinion was too strong. However, it was to be remembered <lb/>
that in debating the question of Confederation, they were <lb/>
not debating a party question, nor one of only passing in<lb break="no"/>terest ; but one, their determination of which might affect, <lb/>
advantageously or otherwise, the destinies of Prince Edward <lb/>
Island for generations to come. John Bull had always <lb/>
claimed, as one of his greatest privileges, the right to <lb/>
grumble, and to stand out, to the last moment, for whatever <lb/>
he thought himself fairly entitled to ; and that privilege the <lb/>
people of this Colony had never been backward to claim and <lb/>
assert. The Quebec Confederation Scheme was, it was well <lb/>
known, favourably viewed by the Imperial Government, and <lb/>
equally so, it was said, by Her Majesty the Queen ; yet <lb/>
admitting all that—and he was not disposed to dispute it ; <lb/>
for he could see no impropriety in its being so regarded at <lb/>
Home—he did not think, as some did, that we could fairly <lb/>
be subjected to the imputation of disloyalty because, so far <lb/>
as that Scheme was meant to apply to Prince Edward Island, <lb/>
we were adverse to it, and should express our aversion to it <lb/>
in the strongest language. He certainly did not, for one <lb/>
moment, imagine that the Imperial Government would ever <lb/>
consent to sanction any Scheme of Confederation, by which <lb/>
it was obvious to them that the interests of even the smallest <lb/>
and most feeble of the Colonies would be sacrificed for the pro<lb break="no"/>motion of those of the largest and most powerful. The Impe<lb break="no"/>rial Government were, doubtless, bent upon carrying out the <lb/>
Confederation Scheme ; but, in their determination to give <lb/>
it effect, they contemplated nothing but the general good of <lb/>
all the Provinces which it was intended to embrace. They <lb/>
could conceive nothing but the retardation of the individual <lb/>
interests and progress of these Provinces, and general feeble<lb break="no"/>ness, as the natural consequences of our governments, inde<lb break="no"/>pendent of each other, our diverse laws, our different cur<lb break="no"/>rencies and hostile tariffs. This justly appeared to them <lb/>
a most anomalous state of things. A group of Provinces, <lb/>
lying closely together, and all paying allegiance to the same <lb/>
Sovereign, could not, or at least ought not, it seemed to <lb/>
them, to have separate and conflicting interests ; and, there<lb break="no"/>fore, it was, seeing that all of them were rapidly approaching <lb/>
to a state, the further expansion of which would require that, <lb/>
as respected all the relations of trade, commerce, laws, and <lb/>
government, they should, as it were, intertwine with and lean <lb/>

<cb/>

upon each other—that the Imperial Government thought <lb/>
the very best thing which could be divised for them, was such <lb/>
a Union as would consolidate their growing strength, and <lb/>
give to all an interest in, and a share of the individual or <lb/>
peculiar resources and privrleges of each. And, to that end, <lb/>
it had doubtless appeared to them that no Scheme could be <lb/>
more happily framed than that of the Quebec Conference. <lb/>
In that opinion, however, at least so far as it respected <lb/>
Prince Edward Island, they were certainly in error ; and <lb/>
what had especially led to their mistake, with respect to us, <lb/>
was their ignorance—for it could not be forgetfulness—of <lb/>
our peculiar position, resources, and trade. They did not <lb/>
comprehend our exceptional position. That they should be <lb/>
ignorant on that head did not surprise him , for, at the De<lb break="no"/>troit Trade Convention, he found several of the Delegates <lb/>
to that Convention, although comparatively speaking our <lb/>
near neighbours almost as ignorant respecting our resources <lb/>
and trade, as must of necessity be the peoples of China and <lb/>
Japan. The Imperial Government thought that, if we went <lb/>
into the Confederation, our material interests would all re<lb break="no"/>ceive an immediate and most sensible progressive impulse ; <lb/>
and that, in fact, our prosperity would increase in every <lb/>
direction. As respected our representation in the Confe<lb break="no"/>derate House of Commons, small as the number was at <lb/>
which it was set down in the Report, on the basis of popula<lb break="no"/>tion, and decennial readjustments on that basis, at the <lb/>
expiration of the first ten years of the Union, our repre<lb break="no"/>sentation would be still further diminished. The allowance <lb/>
of £51,850, to be made to this Island, in consideration of <lb/>
the transfer of our revenue and of' the powers of taxation to <lb/>
the General Parliament, was manifestly a very inadequate <lb/>
compensation for our relinquishment of our Revenue, <lb/>
now amounting to £70,000, and which, in a few years <lb/>
would, in all probability, amount to £100,000 per annum. <lb/>
That allowance would not suffice to defray our annual local <lb/>
expenditure ; and, whenever it should be found necessary for <lb/>
us to undertake any large public work for our own local <lb/>
benefit, we would have to provide for the expense by extra <lb/>
direct local taxation. As respected the direct benefits which, <lb/>
it was said by the advocates of Confederation, we would derive <lb/>
from the Canals and Railroads of the other Provinces, and <lb/>
towards the past and future cost of which we were to con<lb break="no"/>tribute, considering that we should be shut out from the use and <lb/>
advantage of them for five months of the year, it would be <lb/>
about just as reasonable to say that on account of the bene<lb break="no"/>fits which we might derive from the construction of public <lb/>
works in Kamtschatka, we should contribute towards the ex<lb break="no"/>pense incurred by it.—His greatest objection to the Con<lb break="no"/>federation Scheme was based on his dread of the enormous <lb/>
taxation to which we would, in all probability, be subjected <lb/>
under it. The construction of fortifications, the creation of a <lb/>
Confederate army and navy to afford protection against the <lb/>
annexation proclivities of Brother Jonathan, the deepening <lb/>
and widening of the Canals of Upper Canada, and the cons<lb break="no"/>truction of other public works, which would be required as <lb/>
the country became more and more opened up and improved, <lb/>
would necessitate such an outlay of public money as could <lb/>
not be raised independently of extraordinary taxation ; and <lb/>
to prevent either that, or to check any extravagance on the <lb/>
part of the General Government, the small share which we <lb/>
should have in parliamentary representation, would render <lb/>
us powerless. The hon. and learned member said he did <lb/>
not go quite so far as some anti-confederates ; for he be<lb break="no"/>lieved that, if the other Provinces went into the Union we <lb/>
should not be able to keep out. We were told that the <lb/>
British Government would not deprive us of a Constitution <lb/>
which they themselves had guaranteed to us. But we <lb/>

<pb n="105" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_105.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">105</fw>

ought to remember our great indebtedness to the Mother <lb/>
Country, and to take care that our refractoriness should not <lb/>
be the cause of some estrangement of feeling towards us on <lb/>
her part, and incline her to resent what she may deem our <lb/>
undutifulness towards her at the present juncture. Some <lb/>
again said that, if we refused to go into the Union, no <lb/>
course would be open to us but that of annexation to the <lb/>
United States ; but annexation to the United States would <lb/>
not be our fate, even if we desired it. The Imperial Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, ignorant as they might be concerning our trade <lb/>
and resources, knew too well the importance of the geogra<lb break="no"/>phical position of Prince Edward Islandthe key to the <lb/>
St. Lawrence—to allow us to annex ourselves to the United <lb/>
States. Some said it would be better for us, at first to go <lb/>
into Union as grumblers, than to be obliged to go in after<lb break="no"/>wards as beggars ; there was nothing disreputable, they said, <lb/>
in grumbling—it was a British privilege ; but begging was <lb/>
position degradation. That might all be very fine ; <lb/>
but, he maintained, there would be nothing mean in going <lb/>
in by begging, even at the eleventh hour, if, by re<lb break="no"/>maining our until then, we could obtain better terms <lb/>
than were offered to us by the Quebec Scheme. He <lb/>
said, with the hon. member for the Third District of <lb/>
Prince County, (Mr. Sinclair,) that to give us better <lb/>
terms was not impossible ; but he believed that Canada <lb/>
would never, of herself, consent to give us better terms <lb/>
His (Mr. Brecken's) opinion then was that our best policy <lb/>
would be to keep out until Canada, in her eagerness to in<lb break="no"/>clude us in the Union, should offer to treat with us on fair<lb break="no"/>er terms ; and then, should we find that we were suffering <lb/>
by keeping out, self-interest might induce us to accept the <lb/>
best terms we could get. The second Resolution, he said <lb/>
again, was too strong. To say that no terms of Union that <lb/>
would prove advantageous to our interests and well-being <lb/>
as a people, could be offered, was certainly saying too much <lb/>
and going too far ; but, when he took into consideration the <lb/>
object to be attained by so wording the Resolution, which <lb/>
was the rendering it impossible for the Government to con<lb break="no"/>sent to the appointment of delegates to the projected Lon<lb break="no"/>don Convention—a course which, if adopted, would in all <lb/>
probability result in a repetition of the Quebec agreement— <lb/>
he was quite prepared to vote for it, too strong as, in its <lb/>
prima faciesense, he thought it. If Deletgates were ap<lb break="no"/>pointed, by our Government, to to attend the London Con<lb break="no"/>vention, even for the purpose of opposing the Quebec <lb/>
Scheme, and endeavouring to procure a modification of it <lb/>
for our benefit, he feared they might, as at Quebec, be won <lb/>
over to the opinions of the Canadian and Nova Scotia Dele<lb break="no"/>gates in favor of it. Still he would like that Resolution <lb/>
to be remodelled, if that could be done without an acknow<lb break="no"/>ledgment of the principle of a Union on the Quebec basis ; <lb/>
for, as it stood, a position was assumed in it, from which <lb/>
possibly we might hereafter have to recede. It was the <lb/>
duty of the House, however, to speak out clearly, plainly <lb/>
and without ambiguity. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. Mr. McEACHEN</persName>. He was happy to be able to en<lb break="no"/>dorse the Resolutions exactly they had been submitted <lb/>
by the Hon. the Leader of the Government. They were <lb/>
strong ; but not too strong. he agreed with the hon mem<lb break="no"/>bers (Mr. Sinclair and Mr. Brecken) that were we to admit <lb/>
the principle as set forth in the Quebec Report, that was <lb/>
the possibility of its being made just to Prince Edward Is<lb break="no"/>land, we would have been drawn to it. If we allowed the small <lb/>
end of the wedge to be insinuated, it would soon be driven <lb/>
through. He was glad to hear the hon. and learned mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Charlottetown (Mr. Brecken) allude to the right <lb/>
claimed by John Bull to grumble and to be stubborn when <lb/> 

<cb/> 

called upon to resign any thing which he believed himself <lb/>
entitled to hold ; and to hear the hon. member then base <lb/>
thereon an argument for the people of this Island being like <lb/>
John Bull, stubborn in the retention of their free constitu<lb break="no"/>tion. Such stubborness was certainly becoming in a free <lb/>
people ; but although he would not deny that the sons of <lb/>
John Bull had an hereditary right to assert that privilege, <lb/>
yet yet would say it became them not—the descendants of the <lb/>
men who were conquered by the Normans and lost their liberty <lb/>
at the battle of Hastings—as well as it did the descendants of <lb/>
those men whose ancestors—the Caledonians of old—beat <lb/>
back from their mountain fastnesses of liberty the conquering <lb/>
eagles of Imperial Rome. He (Hon. Mr. McEachen) was a <lb/>
descendant of those unconquered heroes of the North ; and he <lb/>
would never consent that, in asserting our right to preserve <lb/>
our free constitution, with all its rights, privileges, and im<lb break="no"/>munities, we should adoph the cowardly, cringing tone in <lb/>
which it suited venality and corruption to plead for the at<lb break="no"/>tainment of the objects of their selfish designs. There was <lb/>
no reason to fear that we should be driven into the project<lb break="no"/>ed Confederation. The people of Prince Edward Island had <lb/>
a Constitution as well as Canada ; and, if they did their <lb/>
duty, they would never lose it. Mr. Cardwell would, no <lb/>
doubt, be glad if he found us willing to agree to go into the <lb/>
Union on the terms of the Quebec Scheme ; but, if he found <lb/>
we were not willing, he would not dare to force us into it. <lb/>
If once, like the Hungarians and the Polels, we should be <lb/>
deprived of our Constitution, we would never be able to re<lb break="no"/>gain it. He would, therefore, support the Resolutions, <lb/>
both in the spirit and the letter. They were certainly <lb/>
strong ; but they were not too strong for him. We know, <lb/>
said the hon. gentleman in conclusion, what we enjoy under <lb/>
our present free Constitution ; but we know not what we <lb/>
should have to endure, were we, by a Union with Canada, <lb/>
on the terms of the Quebec Scheme of Confederation, to be <lb/>
deprived of it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HENS1">Hon. Mr. HENSLEY</persName>. As to the first Resolution, which <lb/>
went to reaffirm the decision of the House, in its last session, <lb/>
upon the question of a Union of the British North American <lb/>
Colonies, to the effect "that any Union of those Colonies <lb/>
which should embrace Prince Edward Island, upon the terms <lb/>
and principles set forth in the Resolutions of the Quebec <lb/>
Conference, would not only be unjust to the inhabitants of <lb/>
this Colony, but prove disastrous to their dearest and most <lb/>
cherished rights and interests as a free people, enjoying most <lb/>
blessings of a priceless Constitution guaranteed to them by <lb/>
the Imperial Government of Great Britain,"—having hearti<lb break="no"/>ly concurred in that Resolution when it was first affirmed, it <lb/>
was not necessary, perhaps, for him to say more than that <lb/>
he still firmly adhered to the opinion then expressed by him <lb/>
of its propriety. And neither did it appear to him to be <lb/>
necessary that he should, in his opposition to the Quebec <lb/>
Scheme, restate the arguments which, whilst speaking upon <lb/>
the first Resolution, had been so ably brought to bear <lb/>
against that Scheme by the hon and learned member for <lb/>
Charlottetown (Mr. Brecken) with every word of which he <lb/>
agreed. He would, therefore, proceed to give his views <lb/>
touching the propriety of the second Resolution, which de<lb break="no"/>clared <hi rendition="simple:italic">that the House could not admit that a Federal <lb/>
Union of the North American Provinces and Colonies, <lb/>
which would include Prince Edward Island, could ever <lb/>
be accomplished upon terms that would prove advan<lb break="no"/>tageous to the interests and well-being of the people of the <lb/>
Island.</hi> He looked upon the declaration in that Resolution <lb/>
in much the same light in which it had been viewed by <lb/>
the hon. member for the Third District of Prince County <lb/>
(Mr. Sinclair) and the hon. and learned member for the Se<lb break="no"/> 

<pb n="106" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_106.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">106</fw>

cond District of Queen's County) Hon. Mr. Longworth). <lb/>
He was not exactly of opinion that it was quite impossible— <lb/>
as was affirmed by that Resolution—that any terms of Fe<lb break="no"/>deral Union could be offered to the people of Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island which would prove advantageous to their inter<lb break="no"/>ests and well-being ; but he believed that no such terms <lb/>
would be agreed to by the other Provinces ; and he thought <lb/>
that, lest it should, in any way, be made to appear that we <lb/>
acknowledge the principle of the Quebec Scheme of Union, <lb/>
and should, in consequence of such assumed acknowleg<lb break="no"/>ment, be dragged into it, it was necessary to express our<lb break="no"/>selves in the strong, unequivocal, and decisive language used <lb/>
in the framing of that Resolution. It had been said to the <lb/>
anti-Confederates, " If you object to the terms of the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Scheme of Union, why do you not lay down such as <lb/>
you think it would be advantageous for the Island to ac<lb break="no"/>cept." He would reply, that we have no desire whatever <lb/>
to become a party in the projected Union of the Provinces ; <lb/>
and it would be the height of absurdity in us to lay down <lb/>
terms for a compact which we are not only unwilling to enter <lb/>
into ; but from which we are determined to stand aloof so long <lb/>
as we shall have the power to do so. These were the rea <lb/>
sons why he was in favor of the second and third resolu<lb break="no"/>tions. Were we ones to admit the principle of the project<lb break="no"/>ed Federation, it would be impossible for us to keep out of <lb/>
it. He would go back to the inception of the scheme about <lb/>
three years ago. When in the Session of 1863, the ques<lb break="no"/>tion was first brought before the Assembly, whether it would <lb/>
be better for Prince Edward Island to enter into the proposed <lb/>
Confederation of the Lower Provinces, or to remain as she <lb/>
was in her separate and independent position, there was not <lb/>
found one hon. member of the House to advocate her entering <lb/>
into such Confederation ; on the contrary the whole House <lb/>
were of opinion that if Prince Edward Island entered into the <lb/>
Confederation, she would inevitably be swamped by the <lb/>
weight of the debts of the other Provinces—that she would <lb/>
forfeit the right of self-government, and would, besides, be <lb/>
crushed by the weight of excessive taxation. The hon. and <lb/>
learned gentleman then went pretty fully into the history of <lb/>
the Question of Confederation, from its inception up to the <lb/>
present time, for the purpose of shewing that neither had the <lb/>
Scheme ever been favourably entertained by the Legislature, <lb/>
nor bad Legislative Authority ever been given to our Island <lb/>
Delegates to enter into any consideration of it, either in <lb/>
Charlottetown, at Halifax, or at Quebec, with a view to our <lb/>
becoming a party to it. Upon what grounds, then, he asked, <lb/>
would our Confederates say that the Report of the Quebec <lb/>
Conference was binding upon us, when even the appointment <lb/>
of Island Delegates by the Government had been made inde<lb break="no"/>pendently of Legislative sanction. We were, indeed, only a <lb/>
small Colony, but we were possessed of a free representative <lb/>
constitution ; and we had quite as much right to retain it as <lb/>
had the English to retain theirs. He had, however, yet to <lb/>
learn that Great Britain would, so long as we continued true <lb/>
to ourselves and firm in our allegiance to the British Crown, <lb/>
ever seek to deprive us of it. Nova Scotia and New Brunswick <lb/>
might derive great advantages from their Union with Canada ; <lb/>
but not so Prince Edward Island, separated as she is from <lb/>
those Provinces, by an immoveable barrier of ice for five <lb/>
months in the year. Mr. Brown in Canada, in his advocacy <lb/>
of the Confederation Scheme, had said they wanted an outlet <lb/>
to the sea ; and that, independently of Confederation, <lb/>
they could not obtaiu without going through another country. <lb/>
That was trne enough. But what had Prince Edward Island <lb/>
to do with it ? Canada's obtaining that outlet, by means of <lb/>
Confederation, would confer no benefit upon us. It was all <lb/>
very fine to say we would, under Confederation, belong to a <lb/>
great country, and would consequently grow in wealth and <lb/>
importance ; instead of being as we were, a little isolated in<lb break="no"/>significant Colony. We already, said the hon. and learned <lb/>
member, belong to a great country—the greatest in the <lb/>
world—and we have no desire to belong to any other. Great Bri<lb break="no"/>tain will never cast us off so long as it shall be our wish to <lb/>

<cb/>

remain under the protection of her flag ; and we are willing, <lb/>
as the third Resolution expresses it, to contribute, from our <lb/>
local revenues, towards our own defence, in fair and just pro<lb break="no"/>portion to our means. I do not see that our present isolated <lb/>
and independant position, even although the other Provinces <lb/>
should confederate, would, in any way, prove disadvan<lb break="no"/>tageous to us, unless Nova Scotia and New Brunswick should <lb/>
enact hostile tariffs against us ; but that, I believe, Great <lb/>
Britain would not allow them to do. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WHEL1">Hon. Mr. WHELAN</persName> then rose and moved that all <lb/>
after the word " Resolved" be struck out of the Resolu<lb break="no"/>tions submitted by the Hon. the Leader of the Government, <lb/>
and that the following be substituted : — <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"As the opinion of this House, that the Confederation <lb/>
of Her Majesty's American Colonial Possessions would be,—while <lb/>
in conformity with Her Majesty's frequently expressed desire— <lb/>
conducive to their welfare, separately and collectively. And this <lb/>
House believes that a plan of Confederation might be so framed <lb/>
as not to involve the sacrifice of any material interests on the <lb/>
part of any Province ; but inasmuch as the people of Prince <lb/>
Edward Island do not appear to be prepared to regard with <lb/>
any favor the project of Confederation, it is unwise to press it <lb/>
upon public attention, as its discussion is only calculated to pro<lb break="no"/>duce excitement and apprehension, without reasonable cause. <lb/></p> 

<p>"AND FURTHER RESOLVED, as the opinion of this House, than <lb/>
there should be no vote passed by the Legislature of this coun<lb break="no"/>try in favor of a Confederation of the Provinces until the people <lb/>
shall first be afforded an opportunity of pronouncing their judg<lb break="no"/>ment on the question at a general Election." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>The hon. gentleman then proceeded to say that he thought <lb/>
the question should not be pressed upon the people before <lb/>
they were educated up to it, and their judgment matured <lb/>
respecting it. As he had said to his own constituents, he <lb/>
did not think it was the duty of the province of the Assembly <lb/>
either to pronounce in favor of Confederation, or to reject it, <lb/>
until the decision of the people should be fairly given, either <lb/>
for or against it, at the polls. With all due deference to <lb/>
the House, he begged leave to say, however, that he did not <lb/>
believe any decision, either for or against Confederation, on <lb/>
the part of Prince Edward Island, would materially affect <lb/>
the action or determination of the other Provinces concern<lb break="no"/>ing it ; and that, if they were favorable to it, Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island would be placing herself in a very absurd and <lb/>
ridiculous position by refusing to accede to it. But whilst <lb/>
the question appeared to be settled in Nova Scotia and New<lb break="no"/>foundland, and to be in a transition state in New Brunswick, <lb/>
he thought our wisest course would be to leave it as it now <lb/>
stood, for the calm and deliberate consideration of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple, until time and events should throw new light upon it, <lb/>
and, perhaps, bring new influences to bear upon their minds <lb/>
concerning it. He could not, however, for one moment, sup<lb break="no"/>pose, that provided the other Provinces were confederated, <lb/>
Great Britain would allow Prince Edward Island to remain <lb/>
out of the Union, to be a source of weakness and annoyance <lb/>
to the Federation, which, if she stood alone and aloof from <lb/>
it, she, most undoubtedly, would be. He would then merely <lb/>
ask the Chairman to submit the Resolution which he had <lb/>
proposed as an amendment to the Resolutions submitted by <lb/>
the Hon. the Leader of the Government, although it had <lb/>
been his intention to speak to some other points of the ques<lb break="no"/>tion. That intention he would then, however, forego ' as <lb/>
another opportunity might, perhaps, be afforded him of car<lb break="no"/>rying it into effect, and of repelling, at the same time, the <lb/>
unjust, the unmanly, the cowardly insinuations of bribery, <lb/>
corruption, and treachery, which had, by certain parties <lb/>
in the community, been thrown out, not only against him, <lb/>
but against other gentlemen, members of the Assembly, <lb/>
who had, in common with himself, and in pursuance of their <lb/>
honest convictions concerning the question, been the open <lb/>

<pb n="107" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_107.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">107</fw>

and candid advocates of such a Confederation of the North <lb/>
American Provinces as would include Prince Edward Is<lb break="no"/>land. Will any of those who stigmatize us produce proof <lb/>
for their assertions ? I challenge them before the conntry <lb/>
to show proof. " Bribed traitors " forsooth ! Are Her <lb/>
Majesty's Ministers "bribed traitors ? " Surely it cannot <lb/>
be thought that the Colonial Minister and Her Majesty's <lb/>
Government, who have given a decided opinion in favor of <lb/>
Confederation, are " bribed traitors ! " And let me <lb/>
ask these calumniators this question : Are the Catholic <lb/>
Hierarchy of Nova Scotia the Archbishop of Halifax, and <lb/>
the Bishop of Arichat, who have pronounced in favor of <lb/>
Confederation—are they " traitors ? " Are they influenced <lb/>
by improper and corrupt motives in bringing this question <lb/>
favorably before their fellow Colonists ? I bring this ques<lb break="no"/>tion before you and ask it in it is your firm conviction that I, <lb/>
and others in a much higher position than myself, should be <lb/>
designated as traitors. It is false and dishonest in the <lb/>
highest degree to bring such an accusation against us in the <lb/>
face of the country. I do not ask you, Sir. I will not ask <lb/>
you, to believe that I am perfectly sincere in this matter ; <lb/>
but I will ask you to allow me to use my own opinion, and <lb/>
because I do advocate this measure in accordance with my <lb/>
honest convictions—because I think this House should not <lb/>
place itself in a position hostile to the British Government, <lb/>
or antagonistic to the course pursued by the other Colonies <lb/>
—am I to be singled out for contumely ? I never, in the <lb/>
course of my parliamentary experience of 20 years, was <lb/>
made the subject of so much calumny—so many false ac<lb break="no"/>cusations, as n reference to this question. I do not, as the <lb/>
Resolution which I have submitted shows, force my opinion <lb/>
on the country. I have not done so since I returned from <lb/>
the Quebec Conference. I may say that at that Conference <lb/>
we did not get as much as I, as one of the delegates, think <lb/>
we should have got ; but we got what I think should be ac<lb break="no"/>cepted as a compromise, and I say now, in the presence of <lb/>
this House, and of the country, that ALL the Delegates did <lb/>
agree to the terms there proposed, notwithstanding their dis<lb break="no"/>agreement afterwards as to matters of detail. When I re<lb break="no"/>turned from Quebec I was assailed because I stated this palp<lb break="no"/>able truth, and many times since, in such language as it is im<lb break="no"/>possible for me to characterize. But I will allow that to pass. <lb/>
I do not seek to press the question upon the people. I do <lb/>
not wish that without the most mature reflection, they <lb/>
should accede to Confederation ; but I do wish that, before <lb/>
they decide either for or against it, they may be fully en<lb break="no"/>lightened concerning it ; and I will ask this House not to <lb/>
pledge itself to any course concerning it until the peo<lb break="no"/>ple shall have pronounced concerning it at the polls. <lb/>
It is my right—a right which God has given me—to form <lb/>
my own opinion on all public questions, and I will endea<lb break="no"/>vour to exercise that right. But surely I and they who <lb/>
hold the same opinions as myself on the subject of Confede<lb break="no"/>ration ought not, on account of those opinions, to be sub<lb break="no"/>jected to insult and persecution, most vile and most unjust, <lb/>
on the part of any who hold different opinions on that sub<lb break="no"/>ject. I ask you, Mr. Chairman, most respectfully—I ask <lb/>
this honorable Committee—whether this system of perse<lb break="no"/>cution shall continue to be practised ? I appeal to the good <lb/>
sense and love of fair play which characterizes the members <lb/>
of this community, whether a man shall be allowed to have <lb/>
an opinion of his own or not ? I do not object to this <lb/>
House expressing its disapproval of Confederation, without <lb/>
reference to the Quebec Scheme, because that is thrown <lb/>
aside ; but in regard to the general plan of Confederation, <lb/>
any opinion is that these Colonies would assume great impor<lb break="no"/>tance—they would obtain stability and security against foreign <lb/>

<cb/> 

aggression, and they would also obtain more efficient pro<lb break="no"/>tection from Britain, were they confederated, than she could <lb/>
extend to them should they remain in their present isolated <lb/>
condition. I do not wish to trespass upon the attention of <lb/>
the House, but I rose to submit the Resolution which is now <lb/>
before you, and it is of that mild character that I do not <lb/>
think hon. members should vote against it. But, however, <lb/>
if they do, I shall be enabled to place my opinion upon re<lb break="no"/>cord, which is, that I am favourable to Confederation, pro<lb break="no"/>vided it be based upon a plan just to the several Provinces, <lb/>
without sacrificing the interests of any, and also providing <lb/>
that the people be perfectly prepared to accept it. Any<lb break="no"/>thing more fair, I do not think, could be presented to the <lb/>
House. If you pass the other Resolutions, which are very <lb/>
strong, it will not affect the question one way or the other. <lb/>
Let me tell you that the decision of a Colony of only 80,<lb break="no"/>000 inhabitants will have but very little effect in deciding <lb/>
the fate of three and a half millions of people, however <lb/>
much some gentlemen may be under the impression that <lb/>
the other Provinces may be confederated and Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island remain " out in the cold." The Confederacy <lb/>
of the United States took place under very peculiar cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, and Rhode Island, an isolated Province, as <lb/>
small nearly as we are, although at first refusing to enter it, <lb/>
was yet, before long, very glad to seek admission into it. <lb/>
So, if a Federation of the British North American Provinces <lb/>
take place, and Prince Edward Island be left out, will she, <lb/>
in like manner, sue to be admitted into it. Would any one <lb/>
tell me—and I put the question plainly—would the United <lb/>
States, if no Confederacy had taken place, have been so <lb/>
powerful a nation as they are to-day ? We are not seeking <lb/>
a separation from Great Britain, but to combine our <lb/>
strength, by which we may be able to resist aggression, <lb/>
whether from Fenianism or from any other quarter. Last <lb/>
year, we were told that the advocacy of this question was <lb/>
premature, because there was not the slightest probability <lb/>
of an interruption of the friendly relations existing between <lb/>
Great Britain and the United States on account of the Fe<lb break="no"/>nian organization ; but now we know that the Fenian or<lb break="no"/>ganization, contemptible as it is, has been such as to render <lb/>
it necessary, on the part of Her Majesty's Government, to <lb/>
take extraordinary precautions against its aggressions. In <lb/>
England a law has been passed suspending the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Habeas <lb/>
Corpus</hi> Act in Ireland, because the Fenian organization was <lb/>
supposed to have taken effect there. In the Colonies, ex<lb break="no"/>traordinary preparations have been made for resistence to <lb/>
any possible attacks on the part of that lawless association. <lb/>
The resources of the several Colonies have been pledged for <lb/>
their individual defence. We were told, last year, that <lb/>
there was no necessity to prepare for defence ; but what do <lb/>
we see here this year ? A unanimous vote placing all the <lb/>
resources of the Colony at the disposal of the Government <lb/>
for the purpose of putting the Island in a position of de<lb break="no"/>fence. What does that indicate ? Is it not that our li<lb break="no"/>berties are threatened ? Does it not indicate a feeling of <lb/>
insecurity—a feeling that Prince Edward Island is not safe <lb/>
while those marauders threaten the invasion of the other <lb/>
Provinces ? A gentleman in the other branch of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature said, on a former occasion, that in the event of Confe<lb break="no"/>deration, if Canada was to be threatened by hostile invasion, <lb/>
the young men of Prince Edward Island would have to go <lb/>
and fight for that Province. I ask you was there ever such <lb/>
intolerable nonsense uttered by any man in his senses ! <lb/>
Does any man suppose that the young men of this Island <lb/>
would have to be sent to the borders of Canada ? No, Sir ; <lb/>
it was nonsense sought to be imposed upon the people. The <lb/>
fact is that, for twelve months past Canada has been exer<lb break="no"/> 

<pb n="108" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_108.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">108</fw>

cising its great influence—spending its enormous resources <lb/>
—to ward off the doe, and has been a protection, not only <lb/>
to Prince Edward Island, but to the whole of the Lower <lb/>
Provinces. There have been no raids into these Provin<lb break="no"/>ces ; and, if they were to be invaded, Canada surely would <lb/>
be, and that Province once lost to the British Crown, these <lb/>
Maritime Colonies would fall an easy prey, either to Fe<lb break="no"/>nians, or to some other foe. But I think, Mr. Chairman, <lb/>
that, in view of the hostile spirit manifested by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the United States towards these Colonies, in a <lb/>
variety of ways, it is right that we should take counsel and <lb/>
set in accordance with the views of the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. It is scarcely necessary to observe that the United <lb/>
States have no love for Great Britain—no desire to see <lb/>
these Colonies remain a part of the British dominions. <lb/>
And they would rather that they should remain separated <lb/>
and isolated, than be consolidated in power by Confedera<lb break="no"/>tions, so that, one by one, they might fall an easy prey <lb/>
whenever they should choose to set about their absorption. <lb/>
Isolated, they could be—united, they could not, be absorbed, <lb/>
United, Great Britain would employ her whole power to <lb/>
defend them ; isolated she would not. All I wish to say is <lb/>
that the subject having been so well debated last year, I <lb/>
am not disposed to trespass upon your patience, Sir, and <lb/>
that of the House, at present ; but I ask that forbearance <lb/>
which is due to any person holding an opinion of his own <lb/>
on a great public question. The Resolution I have submit<lb break="no"/>ted is not offensive to those holding views opposed to mine. <lb/>
It is that I believe Confederation would be conducive to <lb/>
the best interests of these Colonies ; but I will not press it, <lb/>
but leave it to the people to decide ; and I may express the <lb/>
hope and belief that, while hon. members have their own <lb/>
opinions, they will not use offensive expressions, or insinuate <lb/>
that any member is influenced by improper motives in ad<lb break="no"/>vocating his own views of the great question now under our <lb/>
consideration. I am influenced by no such motives ; and, <lb/>
if I be assailed on any such grounds I will take the earliest <lb/>
opportunity to retaliate. I do not bring any charge against <lb/>
those whose views upon the subject are adverse to my own, <lb/>
nor offer any offence to their sensibilities. They have a <lb/>
perfect right to believe that Confederation will not be con<lb break="no"/>ducive to the interests of the Colony. I believe it will ; <lb/>
but I beg that we may be permitted to agree to differ. I <lb/>
leave the subject for the present ; perhaps before the debate <lb/>
closes I may take an opportunity of offering a few more ob<lb break="no"/>servations concerning it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName>. I must say this is a very moderate Resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, Mr. Chairman, but there are two or three points in <lb/>
it in which I cannot concur. The hon. member, (Hon. <lb/>
Mr. Whelan) proposes to admit the principle of Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation ; and the Resolution would teach us that, while the <lb/>
hon. member himself would not force us into a union with <lb/>
the other Colonies, yet some other power would do so. Now <lb/>
the hon. member has not clearly explained what power that <lb/>
is by which we are to be forced, but I admit that some <lb/>
grounds for the argument may be drawn from the despatch <lb/>
of the Colonial Minister, who says it is the strong desire of <lb/>
the British Government that we should go into Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. But whether he thinks that despatch is to force us <lb/>
into the Union, or whether it is some power in the Colonies, <lb/>
I do not understand. Whatever power it is I do not know <lb/>
how we could respect a Government of which we stand in <lb/>
dread. Up to the present time we have been proud to look <lb/>
to the British flag, not in dread, or as a coercive, but as a <lb/>
protective power ; and I do not think, therefore, that we <lb/>
have anything to fear in that direction. When the Go<lb break="no"/>vernors of the different Colonies were at Downing Street, <lb/>

<cb/> 

we have reason to believe that they were instructed to use <lb/>
their influence to carry Confederation ; but I am at a loss <lb/>
to know why any force should be brought to bear upon us. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WHEL1">Hon. Mr. WHELAN</persName>. Will the hon. member allow <lb/>
me to put him right ? I did not suggest, either in my re<lb break="no"/>marks, or by the Resolution which I have submitted, that <lb/>
any force was to be used. Then why should the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber dwell so long upon that word ? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName>. Well, I may have mistaken the tenor <lb/>
of the hon. member's remarks, but that was the impression <lb/>
they left upon my mind ; and I cannot believe that the <lb/>
British Government, which has always protected the Colo<lb break="no"/>nies, would now force us into Confederation. The amend<lb break="no"/>ment proposed by the hon. member (Mr. Whelan) is cer<lb break="no"/>tainly very moderately worded ; but it admits the principle <lb/>
of Confederation, and, therefore, I will oppose it. I do <lb/>
not think the Resolutions of the hon. the Leader of the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment are too strong ; but I have a small objection to <lb/>
them, which was, that while they do not admit the princi<lb break="no"/>ple of Confederation as applicable to this Island, yet I was <lb/>
afraid that they were admitting it in regard to the other <lb/>
Colonies. However, as some hon. members think it will <lb/>
not bear that construction, I am willing to waive that ob<lb break="no"/>jection, though I consider that there is a pressure brought <lb/>
to bear upon the other Colonies, which, in my opinion, is <lb/>
hardly constitutional. And I would regret, to the latest <lb/>
day of my life were I in any way to assist in strengthen<lb break="no"/>ing that pressure, which might result in carrying Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. I believe the day has come when we must make a <lb/>
stand for the preservation of our independence ; for, when <lb/>
we see a pressure brought to bear upon the other Colonies, <lb/>
we may be sure that our turn is coming. If the other <lb/>
Colonies go into Confederation, no doubt a pressure will <lb/>
be brought to bear upon us also ; and then does it not re<lb break="no"/>main for us to make a united effort to resist any attempt <lb/>
to take away our constitution, our revenue, and, I might <lb/>
almost say, everything else belonging to us ? I was op<lb break="no"/>posed to Confederation last year, for I saw there was <lb/>
danger even in admitting the principle of it, and I am just <lb/>
as much, or more, opposed to it now. Suppose, for argu<lb break="no"/>ment sake, we should even go into Confederation with terms <lb/>
with which we would be satisfied, would we be safe then ? <lb/>
I should say no. Does not the British Government re<lb break="no"/>cognize the right to change the constitution ? Now, if this <lb/>
is the case, though I do not profess to have any great <lb/>
knowledge in constitutional matters, I believe that, even if <lb/>
we should go into it with the most favourable terms, the <lb/>
Federal Government would have power to change the con<lb break="no"/>stitution, and therefore we would not be secure. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. Sol. GENERAL</persName> : I would like to know what authority <lb/>
has laid down a constitutional law of that kind ? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName> : Well, it appears to me that the constitution <lb/>
of the United States is undergoing a change ; and if we go <lb/>
to former times we will see that even the British Constitution <lb/>
has undergone a change. Surely then, if those constitutions <lb/>
have been changed, it is reasonable to suppose that an agree<lb break="no"/>ment of this kind might be changed also. And considering <lb/>
that we would be such a small portion of the Confederacy, our <lb/>
voice would not be heard in it. We would be the next thing <lb/>
to nothing. Indeed I would almost as soon be without any <lb/>
voice in it at all. We would be as small a minority as the <lb/>
hon. member on my right (Hon. Mr. Laird) and myself are <lb/>
in this House. Are we then going to surrender our rights <lb/>
and liberties ? It is just a question of "self or no self." <lb/>
Talk about a local Legislature ! It would be a mere farce. <lb/>
We would not even have the control of our local affairs, for <lb/>
every trifling or petty bill would have to be sent to Ottawa for <lb/>

<pb n="109" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_109.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">109</fw>

the approval of the Federal Government. This House would <lb/>
be dwindled down to a level with the small municipal bodies <lb/>
throughout Canada for the management of local affairs. <lb/>
Again I say that, for the good of the country, I will waive <lb/>
any objections I have to the Resolutions of his Honor the <lb/>
Leader of the Government, and will give them amy hearty <lb/>
support ; believing, as I do, that we require a united effort <lb/>
to resist any invasion of our rights and liberties. Taking <lb/>
away the constitution of a country is a serious affair. We <lb/>
have now the management of our own matters; and if one <lb/>
party does not please us, we can have another ; but the mo<lb break="no"/>ment we would go into Confederation we would cease to have <lb/>
any control even of matters which concern ourselves. The <lb/>
other colonies speak of us now with the greatest contempt, <lb/>
and then what chance would we have? All we would get <lb/>
would be by begging. Therefore, I will resist, to the utmost <lb/>
of my power, any attempt, either to drive or lead us into <lb/>
Confederation. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI1">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName> : When this question came before us <lb/>
last year, there was a Resolution submitted by which the <lb/>
members who supported it would be pledged to support the <lb/>
Quebec Scheme ; and as I was not in favour of that scheme, <lb/>
I opposed that Resolution, but still I am in favour of Con<lb break="no"/>federation on fair terms. It has been argued by the hon. <lb/>
member for the East Point (Mr. Hensley) that, as attempts <lb/>
have been made to force it upon the people of New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, that, therefore, we should not admit even the principle. <lb/>
He believes we have a Constitution which cannot be taken <lb/>
away from us without the consent of the people. Well, <lb/>
then, if we have, how can an affirmation of the principle draw <lb/>
us into Confederation ? I shall support the Resolution of <lb/>
the hon member for St. Peter's, (Mr. Whelan,) which states <lb/>
that no action is to be taken till after a general election ; and <lb/>
I am glad to be able to now to express my opinion, so that, at <lb/>
the election the constituency I represent may return a mem<lb break="no"/>ber who is opposed to it if they desire to do so. I think it is <lb/>
better fairly and openly to state one's opinion so that there <lb/>
may be no mistake or misconception about it. Attempts have <lb/>
been made to draw a parallel between the Union of the Colo<lb break="no"/>nies, and the Union of Ireland with Great Britain ; but I can<lb break="no"/>not see any similarity between them. An agitation has been <lb/>
kept up in Ireland for many years, chiefly on account of reli<lb break="no"/>gious disabilities, but which I believe will soon be done away <lb/>
with my objections to the Quebec Scheme were on a financial <lb/>
basis. Eighty cents a head, with the light duty adjusted on <lb/>
a fair basis, and, in view of the comparative smallness of our <lb/>
debt, would be entitled to the interest of something like a <lb/>
half a million of money. When we consider that for five or <lb/>
six months of the year we are bound up by ice, and the great <lb/>
tide of prosperity by the railroad would be rolling past us, <lb/>
I admit that, taking that peculiarity of our position into view, <lb/>
we should get a greater sum than 80 cents per head, which <lb/>
would only be about one third of our revenue. All they <lb/>
would pay for us would not amount to a great deal. I think <lb/>
the grant should be doubled ; then there would not be so much <lb/>
objection to that scheme. As to being swamped in the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, I have no fear of being treated with injustice. We <lb/>
see what influence a few men bees of Ireland going into the <lb/>
British Parliament have, and it would be the same here. <lb/>
Even if they were disposed to treat us with injustice, they <lb/>
could not accomplish it. My colleague has said that our <lb/>
small population would become less in proportion to the other <lb/>
colonies ; but I do not look upon it in that light. We have <lb/>
plenty of unoccupied land yet, which, together with the fish<lb break="no"/>eries would absorb a large population. I am quite satisfied <lb/>
to remain as we are ; but I do not think, with the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber from St. Peter's, that whether we agree to have it <lb/>
or not will have little influence on this question. I think <lb/>
it is a proof that there is a pressure brought to bear upon <lb/>
the other Colonies that, while last year their was only a small <lb/>
minority in favour of Confederation, this year they passed <lb/>
Resolutions in favour of it, and yet it is pretty well known <lb/>
that a large majority of the people are opposed to it. There<lb break="no"/>fore, the inference is that if there is such a pressure on the <lb/>
large Colonies, we, of course, will have to follow. From the <lb/>
time these Colonies were wrested from French, till the intro<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

duction of Responsible Government, they were governed by <lb/>
the "old family compact" as it were called ; but not Great <lb/>
Britain says "you are 3 1/2 millions of people, and it is time <lb/>
for you to unite und look forward to the period when you <lb/>
will become a great Monarchy, and one of the first Powers in <lb/>
the World." These Provinces have almost every element of <lb/>
greatness, and they are peopled by a superior race of man<lb break="no"/>kind. Great Britain also knows that we have a great and <lb/>
powerful neighbour on our borders, and we would be much <lb/>
more easily absorbed, it is stated, than if united. Many per<lb break="no"/>sons say they would rather be absorbed into the American <lb/>
Union than be Confederated with Canada ; but they surely do <lb/>
not consider the enormous taxation to which annexation to <lb/>
the United States would subject us. I think the Resolutions <lb/>
of the Hon. the Leader of the Government are very strong ; <lb/>
and I do not believe with the hon. member from the East <lb/>
Point (Mr. Hensley) that our Constitution would not be <lb/>
taken away from us—that Great Britain would still protect <lb/>
us, if we rejected Confederation. It is too much to expect <lb/>
that she would do so. It is the policy of the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to unite the Colonies ; and I think our duty is not to go <lb/>
flat in the face of the Despatch before us, and say we will not <lb/>
go into the Union on any terms. Great Britain will say we <lb/>
are sorry we cannot fall into your views ; but your geogra<lb break="no"/>phical position, is such that you must go into Confederation. <lb/>
But if our Constitution cannot be taken away without the <lb/>
consent of the people, I do not see how it can prejudice us to <lb/>
admit the principle. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LONG2">Hon. Mr. LONGWORTH</persName>: I would be glad if the hon. <lb/>
member would define his intention as to how far he would <lb/>
admit the principle. If we do not admit the principle we <lb/>
may have the right of submitting terms upon which we <lb/>
would enter the Union, and to which Her Majesty's Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment might accede ; but the moment we admit the <lb/>
principle we must submit to the Imperial Government or a <lb/>
Board of Delegates, and I would ask what would be our <lb/>
fate if the question were submitted to either ? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI1">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>: I do not see how, merely ad<lb break="no"/>mitting the principle, would prejudice our interests. I <lb/>
do not wish to send Delegates to England on the question ; <lb/>
but suppose we did do so, it does not follow that we are to <lb/>
go into Confederation on any terms that may be dictated <lb/>
to us, if our constitution cannot be taken away. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LONG2">Hon. Mr. LONGWORTH</persName>: If you do not admit the <lb/>
principle. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI1">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>: That does not follow. I believe <lb/>
that if we refuse to adopt the views of Great Britain on this <lb/>
question, she both can and will take away our Constitution. <lb/>
I think she has been preparing us for it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>: I do not see that there is anything <lb/>
before us that would lead us to think that we will be de<lb break="no"/>prived of our Constitution if we do not go into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion ; neither do I think we have any reason to fear such <lb/>
a result ; and why then should we be asked to surrender it <lb/>
voluntarily ? For my part, I see nothing to induce us to <lb/>
go into a Union with Canada. If the Canadians take it <lb/>
into their heads to agitate a Union of the Colonies, that is <lb/>
no reason that we should do so too. It is for ourselves to <lb/>
say whether we will go into the Union or not. I have no <lb/>
inclination to go into the Union ; for I do not see what we <lb/>
would gain by it. Our expenses and taxes would be in<lb break="no"/>creased, and our liberties would be curtailed. As our time <lb/>
to represent the people has nearly expired, we shoud leave <lb/>
the Constitution of the country as we found it, and if the <lb/>
people desire a change it will be for them to say so at the <lb/>
next election. There was nothing about this question <lb/>
when we were elected ; and I do not think there is any <lb/>
necessity to discuss it at such great length now, for it is <lb/>
pretty well understood in the country. The Resolutions <lb/>

<pb n="110" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-07_Page_110.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">110</fw>

are strong; but, perhaps, it is necessary that they should <lb/>
be so. If the people wish for loufederntion at the next <lb/>
election, well and good; but I would have nothing to do <lb/>
with it at present. We are not offered anything to induce <lb/>
us to go into the Union. We would get eighty cents per <lb/>
head, and never to increase. All the Colonies are progress<lb break="no"/>ing. and why should not this Island do so too. We need <lb/>
not, so far as I can see, expect fair play if we go into the <lb/>
Union, and I will, therefore, support the Resolutions in<lb break="no"/>troduced by the Hon. the Leader of the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Mr. HOWLAN</persName>: It is very amusing to listen to the <lb/>
Confederationists. They are not in favour of Confederation <lb/>
on the terms of the Quebec report at all—not they. We <lb/>
are to propose our own terms—to say what we will do and <lb/>
what we will not do—but hear the Resolution which they <lb/>
introduced last year :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"RESOLVED, That the Report of the Conference of Delegates from <lb/>
the British North American Provinces and Colonies held at Quebec, <lb/>
in October last, taken as a whole, contains a declaration of principles <lb/>
—as the basis of a Federal Union—which this House considers just to <lb/>
the several Provinces and Colonies." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p><persName ref="pers:WHEL1">Hon. Mr. WHELAN</persName>: That is not fair. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Mr. HOWLAN</persName>: It is quite fair; I have listened to <lb/>
the speech of the hon. member (Hon. Mr. Whelan) atten<lb break="no"/>tively, and I perceive that his views have undergone a <lb/>
change since last year. It is very gratifying to know that <lb/>
he has seen the error of his ways. The advocates of Union <lb/>
desire something more this year than we would get by the <lb/>
Quebec Scheme. Now, suppose that a change has taken <lb/>
place. and no basis is laid down with regard to the financial <lb/>
part of the Scheme, what would our position, or what would <lb/>
our influence be? I might refer to Rhode Island, but that. <lb/>
is an old story now. It would be said, " Who are you <lb/>
that attempt to raise your head? A little isolated place <lb/>
like Prince Edward Island attempting to raise your voice !" <lb/>
Some say now, " What! do you suppose that little Prince <lb/>
Edward Island will be allowed to stand in the way of this <lb/>
magnificent Union?" Then, why ask us to say yes or no? <lb/>
Why sit here discussing the question when members are so <lb/>
anxious to get home. It is said that we are only 80,000 <lb/>
people—that we are not able to protect ourselves—and, <lb/>
therefore, We must go into the Union. And, say some <lb/>
hon. members, " If you do not go into the Union the Army <lb/>
and Navy of Great Britain will not protect you ;" but I <lb/>
have higher authority for stating that the Army and Navy <lb/>
of Great Britain will protect us. Mr. Gladstone saysthat <lb/>
the Imperial Government pledges itself to protect. tothe <lb/>
utmost of its power, every British subject in British North <lb/>
America. [Cries of—No! No!] I say Mr. Gladstone <lb/>
does say so; and he is a member of the House of Commons, <lb/>
and quite as good a statesman as any of the hon. members <lb/>
who say "No." Is not this then sufficient authority for <lb/>
us to say that the British Government will protect us? Is <lb/>
any class in this Island tired of our Constitution ? There <lb/>
is nothing respecting which we have not the right to pe<lb break="no"/>tition, or which we have not the right to ask for why then <lb/>
should we be forced to give up our Constitution? I see <lb/>
gentlemen here who are older than my father, and who say <lb/>
we must go into Confederation. If the ruling statesmen of <lb/>
Canada and Nova Scotia, say that we must units, is that <lb/>
any reason why we should do so? If that is the right <lb/>
and privilege of British subjects. I am sorry I am one; but <lb/>
I believe that though I live on this little Island, I have as <lb/>
much liberty as if I lived in London; and I feel proud <lb/>
that the BritishGovcrnment is composed of men who pledge <lb/>
themselves to protect us with the whole resources of the <lb/>
Empire. We are now told that we must unite—that the <lb/>

<cb/>

British flag will be swept from the seas unless we con<lb break="no"/>federate;— I remember that an hon. member (Hon. <lb/>
Mr. Whelan) enunciated very different views a few years <lb/>
ago. I do not wish to misconstrue the hon. member's <lb/>
sentiments—far front it—but there appears to be a sort of <lb/>
hallucination in about the subject; for, otherwise, his mind <lb/>
and those of some other hon. members, it is difficult to ac<lb break="no"/>count for the change which their views have undergone <lb/>
concerning it. We are told that, whether we adopt the <lb/>
Quebec Report or not, we must contederate upon some <lb/>
terms; but I consider that we have just as much right to <lb/>
call upon the other Colonies to confederate as they have to <lb/>
call upon us. It is said that, if Nova Scotia and New <lb/>
Brunswick, go into the Union. we also must, for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of mutual defence; but we have already placed the <lb/>
whole Revenue of the Colony at the disposal of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment for putting the Island in a state of defence. and we <lb/>
are willing to pay our proportion for the general defence of <lb/>
the Colonies; but why should we be forced into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion against our will? If, after a general election, there <lb/>
should he a majority in favour of Confederation, the case <lb/>
would be different; but to say that we must unite with <lb/>
Canada is absurd. If we were considered fit to govern <lb/>
ourselves, and if we have conducted the business of the Colony, <lb/>
properly for fifteen years, it does not appear reasonable to <lb/>
suppose that the British Government will now deprive us of <lb/>
our Constitution. I do not think the people of this Island <lb/>
are so much afraid of Confederation; but they object to <lb/>
being forced into it. We have, at present, as much right <lb/>
to tax ourselves as Canada has; but, in the event of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, will we stand in the same relative position to <lb/>
the other Colonies as Rhode island does to the rest of the <lb/>
American Union? That island has the same representa<lb break="no"/>tion in the United States Senate as New York. Rhode <lb/>
Island is the smallest part of the American Union, and i <lb/>
suppose we would remain for a long time the smallest part <lb/>
of British America; still, we have shown a disposition to <lb/>
do what we can to defend ourselves, and have thereby <lb/>
shown that we are not disloyal, but we wish to let it be <lb/>
seen that Confederation is not as applicable to us as to <lb/>
other portions of British America, and that. therefore, <lb/>
we are not disposed to go into a Union on the basis of <lb/>
the Quebec Report. <lb/></p> 

<p>Pgogress reported and House adjourned at 10 minutes <lb/>
to 12. <lb/></p> 

<!-- DL 2018-06-09 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>TUESDAY, 8th May, 1866. <lb/></p> 

<p>House in Committee of the whole on Despatches.   Mr. <lb/>
JOHN YEO in the Chair. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. CONROY. Sir, I have very little to say in addi<lb break="no"/>tion to what I said upon the question last Session. I am <lb/>
decidedly opposed to Confederation. I am quite satisfied <lb/>
to remain as we are, and to retain the management of our <lb/>
own affairs. I have considered the question with all the <lb/>
ability and attention I could bring to bear upon it, and l <lb/>
have failed to discover any advantage which would acrue to <lb/>
us through a Federal Union with Canada. But whilst I <lb/>
am persuaded that We should reap no advantaues from it, I <lb/>
am convinced that, in almost every particular, it would be <lb/>
highly injurious, if not absolutely ruinous to us. Accord<lb break="no"/>ing to the Quebec Scheme, we would have to give up our <lb/>
revenue, however great its amount, in exchange for £30,000 <lb/>
or £40,000 per annum; and we would have to surrender to <lb/>
strangers the power to raise our duties of impact and ex<lb break="no"/>cise to any amount they chose. We would be allowed to <lb/>
retain our local Legislature; but of what service would the <lb/></p>--> 

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>