<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1865-03-25"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1865-03-25">25 March 1865</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1864">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1865, Being the Third Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1865"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Protestant" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="50"/>
</bibl>
 
<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_045.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_046.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_047.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_048.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_049.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_050.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>
<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-06">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_045">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_045.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_046">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_046.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_047">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_047.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_048">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_048.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_049">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_049.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_050">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_050.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">
<pb n="45" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_045.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">45</fw>

<!-- DL 2018-06-06 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--in other respects, are, in the opinion of this House, so unair <lb/>
to the people of Prince Edward Island ; thus sacrificing our <lb/>
commercial and financial interests for the sake of securing <lb/>
the co-operation of Canada in a military point of view, feel<lb break="no"/>ing assured that so long as we remain a loyal and attached <lb/>
Colony of Great Britain. the powerful aid of that great <lb/>
country will continue, as heretofore, to be extended to us, in <lb/>
common with the other North American Dependencies of the<lb/>
British Crown.<lb/></p> 

<p>"Lastly, Resolved, That this House disagrees to the re<lb break="no"/>commendations of the Quebec Convention, and, on the part of<lb/>
Prince Edward Island, emphatically declines a Union which,<lb/>
after a serious and careful consideration, it believes would<lb/>
prove politically, commercially and financially disastrous to<lb/>
the rights and interests of its people."<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon Col SECRETARY—I submit to you, Mr Speaker, for <lb/>
your judgment, the question whether the leader of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment having given notice of his intention to move the House on <lb/>
this matter, it was not competent for me or any other member to <lb/>
propose other resolutions for the approval of the House. The <lb/>
subject comes before us as an avowedly open question, and <lb/>
therefore I assert that my action evinces no want of courtesy to<lb/>
the leader, or any member, of the Government.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon Mr POPE —The question, Mr Speaker, which forms the <lb/>
subject of both sets of resolutions, is the most important which <lb/>
has ever occupied the attention of the Legislature of this Colony ; <lb/>
and approving of the abstract principle of the proposed Union, <lb/>
regret that I must oppose the measure, for the reason that the <lb/>
details, as adopted by the Quebec Conference, do not offer, in <lb/>
my opinion, fair terms to the people of the Island. It must be <lb/>
remembered, in the discussion of this question, that our insular <lb/>
position, the absence from our soil of minerals, and the difficulty, <lb/>
I might almost say, impossibility, of communication with our sister <lb/>
Colonies during half the year, place us, in dealing with this <lb/>
question, in a position totally different from that of Nova Scotia <lb/>
or New Brunswick. These Provinces are geographically con<lb break="no"/>nected with Canada, and have, within themselves, the materials <lb/>
requisite to constitute them manufacturing countries. As to the <lb/>
argument that our trade would be increased by the Union with <lb/>
Canada, I cannot recognize its force, for we produce the same <lb/>
description of articles as that country can or could supply us <lb/>
with. Our trade must naturally be with Great Britain, the <lb/>
United States, and the West Indies, the products and manufac<lb break="no"/>tures of which we require. The high tariff of Canada would <lb/>
raise the cost to the consumer of goods from those countries much <lb/>
higher than it is at present on the Island, and firmly believing <lb/>
that the true principle of trade is to buy in the cheapest, and sell <lb/>
in the dearest, market, I should be doing violence to my own <lb/>
convictions, if I affirmed by my vote any other rule. I have <lb/>
said, Sir, that I entertained objections to the details of the <lb/>
scheme. Among these objections I may mention the principle <lb/>
of representation by population. A very simple calculation will <lb/>
show that the adoption of this as a standard would entitle the <lb/>
city of London to send to the British House of Commons no less <lb/>
than seventy representatives, and the city of Montreal in the <lb/>
Confederate Parliament would have a representation greater than <lb/>
that of this whole Island. Its statistics warrant the belief that in <lb/>
a few years the population will be so increased by the influx of <lb/>
the tide of immigration that the Island would lose in the halls of <lb/>
legislation even the small voice which she might raise at her <lb/>
entrance into the Union. It is not to be supposed that the <lb/>
increased taxation which, it is not denied, the Canadian tariff <lb/>
imposes, will have any other effect than that of driving from our <lb/>
shores those who would naturally seek in enlarged fields of action <lb/>
more ample returns for their labor, and greater means of meeting<lb/>
the liabilities imposed upon them. The military phase of the <lb/>
question is not worthy of much consideration, for if an invasion <lb/>
of Canada by the people of the United States should take place,<lb/>
it would involve, as a matter of course, the necessity of retaining<lb/>
all available strength in each of the other Provinces for the<lb/>
defence of their respective territories. While I admit, as<lb/>
cordially as any, that it is the duty of every man to contribute,<lb/>
as far as in him lies, to the defence of the country in which he<lb/>
lives, and that it is not fair to the taxpayers of Britain that they<lb/>
should be at the exclusive cost of our protection, I am willing to<lb/>
trust a reasonable portion of that duty to the Mother Country,<lb/>
the army and navy of which must be kept somewhere; and her<lb/>
experience shows that nowhere can they be maintained as<lb/>
cheaply as in the Colonies. In conclusion, I may state that<lb/></p> 

<p>12 <lb/>

<cb/>

while I give the delegates credit for sincerity in their proceedings, <lb/>
my opinion is that they went further than they were authorised<lb/>
or justified to go.<lb/></p> 

<p>In accordance with a suggestion of Hon Mr WHELAN, the <lb/>
discussion was postponed until the papers connected with the<lb/>
subject should be printed.<lb/></p> -->

<head rendition="simple:right">SATURDAY, March 25.</head><lb/> 

<p>Debate on the Union of the Colonies resumed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon Col GRAY</persName>.—Mr Speaker, It might reasonably be <lb/>
expected, and honorable members may consider that it would be<lb/>
more in accordance with the elevated character of a project,<lb/>
which, having engrossed the minds of the statesmen of British<lb/>
America for many years, has at length culminated in the phase<lb/>
in which it now attracts the attention of the people of not only<lb/>
these Provinces and Great Britain, but also of our neighbors in the<lb/>
Great Republic who are anxiously watching our proceedings,<lb/>
that I should elaborate the argument in support of my own views.<lb/>
But, Sir, I do not at present intend to enlarge upon the grander<lb/>
features of this great question—a Confederation of the varied<lb/>
and gigantic interests involved, the benefits which must inevitably<lb/>
accrue to all British America were we confederated in one strong<lb/>
and indissoluble bond of brotherhood from Newfoundland to<lb/>
Vancouver. However desirous I might be, under a state of<lb/>
public opinion other than that which at present exists, to ap<lb break="no"/>proach in a far more extended sense than one of mere local<lb/>
interest, the consideration of a measure which has for its object<lb/>
the consolidation of any hitherto isolated and disjointed<lb/>
fragments into a Confederation which will form a state as large<lb/>
as the entire Continent of Europe, yet it is not my present<lb/>
intention to do so ; neither do I intend to offer any comments<lb/>
upon the resolutions which my hon friend, the leader of the<lb/>
Government, in accordance, doubtless, with the desires of a large<lb/>
majority of members of this House, has now submitted for our<lb/>
consideration, but I shall confine myself solely to a few obser<lb break="no"/>vations on those points which apply more particularly to the<lb/>
immediate condition of the people of this Island separately, as<lb/>
evidencing the motives and reasons which actuated me in ear<lb break="no"/>nestly desiring that we may have the good fortune to be admitted<lb/>
within, and to become an integral part of, the proposed Confed<lb break="no"/>eration. Mr Speaker, we all know that our free trade with the<lb/>
United States is about to cease. Already had notice for the<lb/>
abrogation of the Reciprocity Treaty been given by the American<lb/>
authorities, and, when this shall have been finally acted upon, we<lb/>
must look elsewhere for markets for our produce, or submit to a<lb/>
taxation on it in the ports of the United States which will be<lb/>
almost prohibitory ; therefore, as we are peculiarly an agricul<lb break="no"/>tural people, the great object of our solicitude should be to look<lb/>
around and enquire where we may best secure ready markets,<lb/>
and as near to our own doors as possible ; for it is obvious that if<lb/>
we can have easy access to markets in rich and populous cities<lb/>
in our midst, we will receive far better returns than if driven to<lb/>
have recourse to places remote, and only to be reached after<lb/>
long and tedious voyaging. Sir, I believe that we may safely<lb/>
assume that in a very few years, when confederated, that<lb/>
Halifax and St. John alone will be ready to absorb all we can<lb/>
raise unless every acre in this Island be cultivated like a kitchen<lb/>
garden. Let us consider the future of these two cities, for, great<lb/>
as their natural advantages now are, all pales before the con<lb break="no"/>templation of what they are destined ultimately to become. Let<lb/>
me instance the rise and progress of two places somewhat<lb/>
similarly situated, in the past—Singapore and Chicago. When<lb/>
that eminent man, Sir Stamford Raffles, first suggested the<lb/>
idea of founding that famous emporium for the China trade,<lb/>
how the enemies of progress lifted up their eyes in amaze<lb break="no"/>ment ! how they ridiculed the idea! how great the ruin<lb/>
which must ensue from the adoption of the policy<lb/>
proposed! But what was the result? Soon he was enabled<lb/>
to write, (I quote from memory his own words), "From an<lb/>
insignificant fishing village, our town, in three years, has a<lb/>
population of ten thousand; our lands are rapidly rising in<lb/>
value, and we have every reason to expect, that, in a very<lb/>
few years, we shall have ten times our numbers." How<lb/>
truly the prognostics of this great man have been fulfilled,<lb/>
this wonderful mart of commerce, with its hundred thousands<lb/>
of population, bears, at this day, ample witness. Look again<lb/>
at Chicago. In the year 1833, it was a town of fifty inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants ; twenty years after it had a population of eighty<lb/>
thousand. The tide of emigration must flow to British<lb/>

<pb n="46" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_046.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">46</fw>

America. Already Australia is overdone. Taxation in the<lb/>
United States has become so terribly oppressive that many<lb/>
thousands have, during the past year, left them to settle in<lb/>
Canada ; and we may fairly assume, as certain, that the good<lb/>
time for these Provinces has at length come. The Intercolonial<lb/>
Railway will bring the whole trade of the West into Halifax<lb/>
and St. John. It is easy to foretell the rapidity with which<lb/>
they will increase in wealth and population ; and how readily<lb/>
they will supply us with a market for our cattle, our pork,<lb/>
our oats and potatoes, at paying prices ; and although I wish<lb/>
to confine my observations to what appears more particularly<lb/>
the desire of our people—immediate benefits—yet, I cannot<lb/>
pass this subject without asking hon members to take a<lb/>
prospective glance of what will be the future of these two<lb/>
cities. When the Intercolonial Railroad is finished, a third<lb/>
of the distance to Vancouver is completed. Does any hon<lb/>
member imagine that the capitalists of Great Britain will rest<lb/>
satisfied until the remaining portion of this great highway of<lb/>
the nations is pushed on to the Pacific ? Why, the opening<lb/>
up of the valley of the Saskatchewan will cause a rush of<lb/>
immigrants from Europe to occupy its millions of acres ; its<lb/>
waters teeming with varieties of fish ; its plains covered with<lb/>
myriads of buffalo ; the beds of its streams abounding in<lb/>
gold ; its land the finest arable, in fact, so vast, so inexhaus<lb break="no"/>tible are the resources of this favored region that it excites<lb/>
but little wonder to hear a distinguished British statesman,<lb/>
on his return from that locality, declaring it to be his firm<lb/>
conviction that the child is now born who will see us with a<lb/>
population of fifty millions. From Vancouver to Yeddo is<lb/>
thirteen days' sail ; to Shanghai three days more, and if, in<lb/>
addition, we allow seven days for the land transit, we will<lb/>
have the costly products from the banks of the Yangtsekiang,<lb/>
the mighty St. Lawrence of the East, deposited in the ware<lb break="no"/>houses of Halifax and St. John in little over three weeks,<lb/>
instead of occupying, as they now do, from four to five<lb/>
months in the transmission, thereby causing considerable<lb/>
loss to the mercantile world, as well from the perishable<lb/>
nature of the articles themselves as from the slow returns of<lb/>
profits. Halifax and St. John having become the storehouses<lb/>
of Europe for the China and Japan trade, can any one have<lb/>
the temerity to take upon himself to prescribe the bounds of<lb/>
their prosperity ? A few days ago, my eye was attracted by<lb/>
the heading of an article in a newspaper which I shall read<lb/>
to the House :<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>" A PROSPEROUS CITY.—The City of Portland had, in 1844,<lb/>
a valuation of $4,365,788, which was increased to $26,963,939<lb/>
in 1864. Her exports to foreign countries increased from<lb/>
$251,097 in 1845, to $4,396,142 in 1864 ; her imports from<lb/>
$339,791 in 1845, to $13,039,749 in 1864, showing not only <lb/>
growth of business, but an increase of wealth unexampled<lb/>
in any other city of New England during the same period.<lb/>
This great increase of wealth is wholly due to the trade with<lb/>
Canada by the Grand Trunk Railway. "<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Such would be the increase of trade and prosperity in Halifax<lb/>
and St. John with a Union of the Provinces and the con<lb break="no"/>struction of the Intercolonial Railway. But the object of all<lb/>
others to be desired by every freeman should be the having<lb/>
a strong Government at his back to maintain his rights and<lb/>
secure him justice whenever demanded, and certainly, if<lb/>
ever there were a people needing this, it is ourselves. What<lb/>
a pitiful position we have ever occupied, when knocking at<lb/>
the doors of Downing Street ! It is needless for me to<lb/>
particularize instances, too well is the fact known to us all ;<lb/>
and I can now truly say, after a considerable experience as<lb/>
a member of this Government for six years, that I sincerely<lb/>
believe that the Acts of this Legislature weigh no more than<lb/>
a feather in the scale, compared with the influence possessed<lb/>
by a few private individuals of whose second-hand intermed<lb break="no"/>dling we have lately had a pretty fair specimen. I believe,<lb/>
also, that so long as we occupy our present isolated position,<lb/>
we must bear patiently and submit with resignation to what<lb break="no"/>ever befalls us ; but I would ask, does any hon member in<lb/>
this House suppose that the legislative enactments of the<lb/>
representatives of four millions of people would ever be<lb/>
imperiled or set at naught any more than those of the<lb/>
Imperial Parliament of Great Britain ? Let us now consider<lb/>
the benefits which will accrue to such places as East Point,<lb/>
St. Peter's, Cavendish and others when we come in for our<lb/>
share of Public Grants for harbors on the north side ; for we<lb/>
may rest assured that our fisheries will be developed on a<lb/>

<cb/>

scale of considerable magnitude, and harbors will be a<lb/>
necessity for those interests. I was glad to notice that the<lb/>
Prime Minister of Canada, in his opening address in Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment on the proposed Confederation, in reply to remarks<lb/>
which had fallen from another hon member, to the effect that<lb/>
these Provinces being very poor and unproductive, only<lb/>
sought Confederation for the purpose of being allied to a rich<lb/>
and powerful neighbor, particularly dwelt upon the immense<lb/>
value of our Gulf fisheries ; and capital is all we require to<lb/>
enable us to turn them to account. Last month I received a<lb/>
letter from a gentleman in Boston, in which he writes : " I<lb/>
believe that, could the people of Charlottetown see something<lb/>
of the extent and value of the mackerel fisheries, as now<lb/>
prosecuted from this, they would very soon engage in them<lb/>
themselves. Massachusetts took, last season, three hundred<lb/>
thousand barrels, valued at not less than four millions of<lb/>
dollars. " I also notice that the Commissioner of Public<lb/>
Works in Canada, referring to the establishment of harbors in<lb/>
various places where they were demanded, stated that the<lb/>
Government fully recognized this necessity, and would do all<lb/>
in their power to meet this want. We would have the<lb/>
General Government also securing to us unobstructed inter<lb break="no"/>course and communication with the Mainland by properly<lb/>
fitted Steam-propellers, making the passage from Georgetown<lb/>
and the Wood Islands in the winter season. A Canal has<lb/>
long been considered a necessity between Bay Verte and<lb/>
Cumberland Basin, and I have every reason for saying that<lb/>
it would be almost immediately undertaken by a Company<lb/>
ready to comence the work. This will bring St. John<lb/>
within a few hours' sail of Summerside, and shorten the<lb/>
voyages for the Southern trade, and also, in all likelihood,<lb/>
would exercise a very important thermal influence upon the<lb/>
waters of Northumberland Straits. I now refer to a subject<lb/>
which has, for long, proved a fertile source of discontent to<lb/>
our people, and I must regret to see the present dissatisfac<lb break="no"/>tion manifesting itself in the formation of Tenant Leagues,<lb/>
which the experience of all countries but proves eventually<lb/>
to be the means of bringing trouble and distress upon all<lb/>
parties. By the sixty-third resolution of the Report, we are<lb/>
secured a subsidy of nearly two millions of dollars, and I<lb/>
cannot help saying that, when, towards the close of the<lb/>
Conference, I found this would be the case, I hailed it as the<lb/>
harbinger of a bright era for this Island ; because the<lb/>
Government will have it in its power to enter into such<lb/>
arrangements with the proprietors as must be satisfactory to<lb/>
all parties ; for while we respect the rights of property, yet<lb/>
the best interests of this Island demand that Tenant Leagues<lb/>
and discontent be put an end to. We have often been told<lb/>
that a loan of one hundred thousand pounds would be all<lb/>
that would be necessary. Such loan would have to be re<lb break="no"/>paid, and any losses incurred must have fallen on one and all<lb/>
of us. Now, after putting aside an ample provision for our<lb/>
annual requirements, the Government will have a surplus of<lb/>
three hundred and eighty thousand pounds. Let this be<lb/>
applied to purchasing the lands, and if there be any loss it<lb/>
will harm none of us ; and the proceeds arising from the re<lb break="no"/>sales to the tenantry can be applied to local wants, such as<lb/>
provision for old and infirm teachers of youth, hospitals,<lb/>
market houses or otherwise. But to shew the influences at<lb/>
work to keep the people in the dark, several of them, to<lb/>
whom I mentioned this matter, answered me, " But we are<lb/>
told it is of no use getting our lands free in this way, because<lb/>
if we go into the Union we will be taxed some five or six<lb/>
pounds a year—as much as our present rents—like the<lb/>
farmers of Upper Canada, some of whom have come away<lb/>
from thence, complaining of the excessive taxation there."<lb/>
I believe this has been told the people with the express design<lb/>
of intimidating them. Those who tell them that the taxation<lb/>
in Upper Canada can affect us to the amount of one farthing,<lb/>
either knowingly or ignorantly state what has not a shadow<lb/>
of foundation in truth. I have been told that, at different<lb/>
meetings in the country, the taxation in Upper Canada was<lb/>
brought forward as a reason against Union. It is one of the<lb/>
very strongest points which the advocates of Union can bring<lb/>
to bear in favor of it. Hon members are, doubtless, aware<lb/>
that this taxation is not laid on by the Government, but<lb/>
solely by the people themselves. Upper Canada is divided<lb/>
into forty-two Counties ; these Counties are sub-divided into<lb/>
Townships, each ten miles square. The inhabitants of each<lb/>
Township elect annually five Councillors. These five elect<lb/>

<pb n="47" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_047.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">47</fw>

annually one of their number as presiding officer, who is <lb/>
designated by the title of Reeve. The Reeves and Deputy <lb/>
Reeves of the Townships form the County Councils. Each <lb/>
County Council levies its own taxes, pounds or pence, as the <lb/>
people may choose. The County Councils construct Roads <lb/>
and Bridges, Court Houses and Jails, Grammar Schools and <lb/>
Houses of Correction. They loan also sums of monev for the <lb/>
improvement of the country ; and, as I said before, they, and <lb/>
they alone tax the people. Now, I would ask, what has this <lb/>
taxation to do with us ? It can never affect us to the extent <lb/>
of one fartthing; and, surely, if the farmers of Upper Canada <lb/>
are willing to be taxed by their local boards, we, in this <lb/>
Island, are not going to begrudge their right to do so. It <lb/>
will be a long time, I dare say, before we will follow their <lb/>
example, and tax ourselves for local works as they do ; but <lb/>
I would observe, it must be very obvious to those who choose <lb/>
to understand, that if the people of Upper Canada have al<lb break="no"/>ready heavily taxed themselves by their local boards, they are <lb/>
sure to send representatives into Parliament, pledged to <lb/>
economy, who will unite with the other Provinces to keep <lb/>
down any profuse expenditure of the public funds. The <lb/>
next point I would remark upon is our share in the Repre<lb break="no"/>sentation in the General Parliament, and the complaints <lb/>
of the objectors that we have too few members. When <lb/>
the revolted Provinces ordained and established their <lb/>
Constitution, it was provided that Representatives from <lb/>
any State might be sent to Parliament in the proportion <lb/>
of one member to every thirty thousand of the population. <lb/>
The State of Delaware, large and influential, as well as <lb/>
that of Rhode Island, somewhat similar in extent to this <lb/>
Colony, did not think it against the interests of their <lb/>
people to enter their Union with <hi rendition="simple:italic">one</hi> member each; this <lb/>
Island is invited to enter the proposed Confederation with <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">five</hi>. We are also told that our four members in the <lb/>
Council will be no protection to our interests ; and that the <lb/>
custom obtaining in the United States is far better. Now <lb/>
let us take this view of the question, and follow the <lb/>
United States' system. Vancouver, Columbia, Red River, <lb/>
Upper Canada, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, Newfound<lb break="no"/>land and Prince Edward Island, each sends two members <lb/>
to the Upper Chamber. If a question arose affecting our <lb/>
sectional rights, interests and privileges, do we imagine <lb/>
that our two members could carry the point against the <lb/>
other sixteen ? But, I would ask, has a case ever occurred <lb/>
in which such injustice was attempted or even hinted at, <lb/>
as the opponents of Confederation are so grievously afraid <lb/>
of ? At the time of the Revolution, the white population <lb/>
of the whole thirteen States was less than that of Canada <lb/>
at this time. The population of Canada is now consider<lb break="no"/>ably more than thirty times that of this Island, and if we <lb/>
are to follow the plan of the United States to mete out <lb/>
even-handed justice, we must first portion out Canada <lb/>
into thirteen sections, approximating to what the United <lb/>
States <hi rendition="simple:italic">were</hi> at the time of their Union, not what they now <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">are</hi>. But, I would ask, is it necessary that we should go <lb/>
into this Confederation with our hearts and minds filled with <lb/>
suspicions ? Is it a foregone conclusion with us that all <lb/>
the other Provinces will unite to do injustice to one <lb/>
particular section of their common country ? Yet we <lb/>
have all these dark surmisings, and much more freely <lb/>
enunciated by all parties who oppose the Confederation <lb/>
" Where will the interests of Upper Canada be, " cries <lb/>
Mr. Cameron, " when the other Provinces hold a majority <lb/>
of thirty against her in the Lower, and fifty-two in the <lb/>
Upper Chamber ? " Then M. Dorion cries out for poor <lb/>
Lower Canada. Then comes New Brunswick, Nova <lb/>
Scotia and Prince. Edward Island. Let us say, " away <lb/>
with such unworthy suspicions, they should not be held <lb/>
by liberal and enlightened men. " As I said before, such <lb/>
a case has never occurred in the history of nations, and is <lb/>
it not monstrous doctrine to pretend that it could ever <lb/>
occur with us in this age of reason ? But the weapon <lb/>
which has been wielded, with greatest success in setting <lb/>
our people against Confederation has been the cry of <lb/>
taxation.  " Oh, " say the opponents, " if we come under <lb/>
the Canada Tariff we shall be ruined." It was but the <lb/>
other day my attention was called to speeches delivered at <lb/>

<cb/>

public meetings in this city, and published in the news<lb break="no"/>papers, where certain gentlemen broadly gave utterance <lb/>
to the assertion, " the advocates of Union admit a loss of <lb/>
£27,000 under Confederation . " What is the foundation <lb/>
for this statement ? The Hon. Col. Secretary published <lb/>
some tables of Tariffs, showing their bearing upon us <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">while out of Confederation</hi>. The hon. gentleman stated that <lb/>
if, while we are out of a Union, the Canada Tariff was <lb/>
applied to our imports, the excess would be £27,000 ; <lb/>
but so far from this being the case, should we become <lb/>
united under the proposed Confederation, so far from there <lb/>
being excess of taxation, the taxation under the Canada <lb/>
Tariff would he even less than we now pay under our <lb/>
Island Tariff. I know that, in some things set forth by <lb/>
the Hon. Col. Secretary, although correctly stated, yet he <lb/>
somewhat fails in giving as clear an exposition of their <lb/>
bearing as would enable every one clearly to comprehend ; <lb/>
but in this case, I would ask, can any excuse be offered, <lb/>
could any mistake exist in the minds of those, who, if <lb/>
they had read the Hon. Col. Secretary's statement would <lb/>
have seen that the exact words he used were : " I shall <lb/>
now give you my reasons for believing that should we <lb/>
become a portion of the Confederation, the taxes we <lb/>
should pay, assuming the Canada Tariff to remain at its <lb/>
present rate, <hi rendition="simple:italic">would be less in amount than those now paid <lb/>
by the people of this Island</hi>. The foregoing table exhibits <lb/>
the amount of duties which the articles imported into this <lb/>
Island in 1863, would have paid, according to our Tariff <lb/>
for 1864, contrasted with the amount which the like <lb/>
articles, <hi rendition="simple:italic">in the absence of Confederation</hi>, would have paid <lb/>
under the Canada Tariff of the same year. By this table <lb/>
it appears that while under the Island Tariff of 1864, the <lb/>
importations of 1863 would have paid a duty of £41,963 ; <lb/>
they, under the Canada Tariff, <hi rendition="simple:italic">had they been imported from <lb/>
places beyond the limits of Confederation</hi>, would have been <lb/>
chargeable with £69,792. The opponents of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion will, doubtless, exclaim, ' Here is conclusive evidence <lb/>
that were we to enter the Confederation we should <lb/>
annually lose thereby to the extent of £27,829. I submit, <lb/>
with deference to these gentlemen, that it is evidence of <lb/>
no such thing. ' " Here we have language so plain that it <lb/>
is sad to see with what a reckless disregard of truth we <lb/>
have had it paraded in the columns of some of our Island <lb/>
newspapers " the advocates of Union admit a loss of <lb/>
£27,000. " That this misstatement was made for a pur<lb break="no"/>pose can scarcely be doubted ; for it has been the great <lb/>
capital upon which the opponents have traded to frighten <lb/>
and intimidate our people. I ask, what confidence can <lb/>
the people place in statements so unblushingly made by <lb/>
those from whom they ought to expect truthful informa<lb break="no"/>tion on such an important point ? but I acquit those <lb/>
gentlemen who, at the public meetings, repeated this <lb/>
misstatement. I have no doubt they were led into the <lb/>
error from reading it in those of our Island newspapers, <lb/>
which have not hesitated to misquote the Hon. Col. Secre<lb break="no"/>tary. That the hon. gentleman's statement was perfectly <lb/>
correct I will show as I proceed. I believe that many of <lb/>
our people do not rightly comprehend the meaning or bear<lb break="no"/>ing of the term Tariff. Some of them fancy that a Tariff is <lb/>
a direct tax, somewhat like our land tax, and quite as <lb/>
objectionable. Others again proclaim that if we go into <lb/>
the Union and the Tariff be increased five per cent., we <lb/>
must necessarily pay one-twentieth more for the articles <lb/>
of ordinary consumption than we now do. I will show <lb/>
the fallacy of this. We are not a rich people, but those <lb/>
among us who can afford to purchase expensive articles of <lb/>
foreign manufacture, such as English carriages, harness, <lb/>
saddlery, silks, velvets, jewelry, broadcloths, and expensive <lb/>
wines, surely they should not object to pay one shilling <lb/>
in the pound more for these articles than they now do. <lb/>
But it is the bulk of the people with whose interests I <lb/>
would deal, and I maintain that, under the Canadian <lb/>
Tariff, we can have the articles of ordinary consumption <lb/>
at as low a rate as they are now sold for in Charlottetown ; <lb/>
but before proving this I will quote, as germane to the <lb/>
subject, a statement made in Halifax before a very large <lb/>

<pb n="48" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_048.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">48</fw>

meeting, at which numbers of the wealthiest merchants <lb/>
were present, and we know how strongly many of them<lb/>
are opposed to Union. One of them alone, it is currently<lb/>
reported, has subscribed one thousand pounds to start a<lb/>
newspaper to help to write Confederation down ! I am told<lb/>
that the mercantile establishment with which the gentleman<lb/>
referred to is connected, supplies many of the small<lb/>
dealers in this Island, and clears some sixteen or twenty<lb/>
thousand pounds a year by their transactions. No wonder<lb/>
such influences are brought to bear to deceive our people.<lb/>
I need not refer to the two great influences which we<lb/>
ourselves have had against us from the first— long before<lb/>
the result of the Quebec Conference was known—they<lb/>
were in the field to prejudice the people against any Union<lb/>
whatever, on any terms. But, as I was saying, not one<lb/>
one of these gentlemen could refute the statement made<lb/>
in reply to what we have so often read in some portions<lb/>
of our Island press, that "whereas the Tariff of Nova<lb/>
Scotia was ten per cent., and that of Canada twenty, of<lb/>
course the people would, if confederated, be taxed double."<lb/>
Mr Adams Archibald, and I believe, Mr Speaker, you and<lb/>
every honorable member in this House, know him to be<lb/>
one of the most reliable of the men of Nova Scotia, proved<lb/>
from the public returns that, in the prevrous year, the <lb/>
duties collected in Nova Scotia on the six articles of <lb/>
ordinary consumption, viz., Tea and Coffee, Sugar and <lb/>
Molasses, Tobacco and Liquors, including all ardent <lb/>
Spirits and Wines, amounted to the sum of four hundred <lb/>
and twenty-three thousand dollars, while, if the Canada <lb/>
Tariff and system had been in force in Nova Scotia, this <lb/>
sum would have been only three hundred and ninety <lb/>
thousand dollars, not, so much by thirty-three thousand <lb/>
dollars as the people of Nova Scotia paid under their <lb/>
present Tariff. To make this apparent, I need only <lb/>
mention that in the year 1863, the people of Canada con<lb break="no"/>sumed three millions seven hundred and sixty-seven <lb/>
thousand nine hundred and seventy-nine gallons of <lb/>
liquors, upon which they paid a duty of only three pence <lb/>
three farthings of our currency per gallon ; that they also <lb/>
consumed eight millions sixty thousand one hundred and <lb/>
forty-nine pounds of manufactured tobacco, on which <lb/>
they did not pay one single farthing of duty. Yet, if we <lb/>
look at the newspapers in this Island, we will see how it <lb/>
has been paraded that the Canada Tariff on manufactured <lb/>
tobacco is thirty per cent. Yes, but our people had it <lb/>
not explained to them that this duty is only levied on <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">foreign</hi> manufactured tobacco ; the eight millions were <lb/>
manufactured in Canada, and we could have imported it, <lb/>
if in Confederation, duty free. Let us see how far we <lb/>
would have been affected by this article. Our share <lb/>
would have been in round number's two hundred and fifty <lb/>
thousand pound ; the duty we would have paid, under <lb/>
the Canada Tariff, would have been not one farthing ! <lb/>
Under our Island Tariff, of four pence per pound, it would <lb/>
have been four thousand one hundred and sixty-six <lb/>
pounds, thirteen shillings and four pence. Here we see <lb/>
a direct saving to the pockets of our people under the <lb/>
Canada Tariff, of four thousand pounds on one article<lb/>
alone. I may remark that, this year, an excise of some<lb/>
cents has been put upon it in Canada, the returns of<lb/>
which I have not seen, tobacco is sold to-day at a lower<lb/>
price with them than with us. In 1863 (I have not<lb/>
got returns for 1864) the people of Canada consumed<lb/>
thirty six millions pounds of sugar, besides which<lb/>
they manufactured sixteen millions pounds. One<lb/>
business firm in Toronto manufactures upwards of<lb/>
sixty thousand pairs of boots and shoes yearly. The<lb/>
manufactures of cotton and woollen goods are largely<lb/>
established, and so great has been the improvement in the<lb/>
manufacture of agricultural implements and machinery,<lb/>
that they are now next to independent of the United<lb/>
States. Under their tariff they import eighty articles<lb/>

<cb/>

duty free. I said that, under the Canada Tariff, we can <lb/>
purchase the articles mostly consumed by our people, at<lb/>
as low a rate as under our present Island Tariff. I now<lb/>
give the proof. I hold in my hand the printed list of the<lb/>
Trade Prices in the months of December and February,<lb/>
for which these articles are sold in Canada. I give them<lb/>
all in Prince Edward Island currency : Hyson Twankay<lb/>
Tea, one shilling and ninepence per pound. Choice<lb/>
breakfast Congou, two shillings per pound. Souchong, <lb/>
choice family, two shillings and four pence per pound. <lb/>
West India Sugars, six pence per pound. Loaf and <lb/>
Crushed Sugars, ten pence per pound. Rice, two pence <lb/>
half penny per pound. Molasses, two shillings per gal<lb break="no"/>lon. Coffee, one shilling and four pence per pound. <lb/>
Tallow Candles, seven pence half penny per pound. Man<lb break="no"/>ufactured Tobacco, one shilling and five pence per pound. <lb/>
Whiskey, two shillings and six pence per gallon. Super<lb break="no"/>fine, No. 1, Flour, four dollars per barrel. Superfine, No. <lb/>
2, three dollars and a quarter per barrel. If we compare <lb/>
these prices with those which we now pay in Charlotte<lb break="no"/>town, and if our country friends say that these prices will <lb/>
ruin them, then I will admit that their ideas of union and <lb/>
those which I entertain are widely dissimilar. It was <lb/>
only a short time since that I was under the impression <lb/>
that, under the tariff of Canada, Tea and Sugar would be <lb/>
a trifle dearer than we now have them in Charlottetown, <lb/>
because these are some thousand miles further for the place <lb/>
of transit of these articles, butI find I was mistaken, and <lb/>
that they can be sold as low under the tariff of Canada <lb/>
as under our own ; hence I maintain, if the people were <lb/>
truthfully informed, that they would see that it is clear <lb/>
as the sun at noonday, that if we become the consumers, <lb/>
duty free, of the various manufactures of four millions of <lb/>
people, possessing abundance of water-power, raw mater<lb break="no"/>ial and steadily increasing markets, the great bulk of the <lb/>
population of this Island could dispense with the con<lb break="no"/>sumption of dutiable articles, with the exception of tea, <lb/>
sugar, and molasses, the prices of which, I have shown, <lb/>
are not higher under the Canadian than our own tariff. <lb/>
We should find also that, instead of the Revenue annually <lb/>
required to be raised being doubled, under Confederation, <lb/>
as the opponents of the measure scruple not to assert, it <lb/>
would not be one half of its present amount, and each <lb/>
year would witness its diminution proportionately to the <lb/>
increase of our population. The existing tariffs of all the <lb/>
Provinces would, this year, give a surplus of nearly one <lb/>
million over their aggregate expenditure, and it has been <lb/>
clearly shown that the elevation of the lowest to the level <lb/>
of the highest would produce more money than the requi<lb break="no"/>rements of the public service demand ; and, therefore, <lb/>
it has been clearly understood that, should we go into <lb/>
Confederation, it will be proposed to reduce the present <lb/>
Tariff of Canada to a medium standard with those of the <lb/>
other Provinces. A country starting, as it were, into life, <lb/>
with a surplus of a million, commences with happy <lb/>
auguries for the future. This sum would pay the interest <lb/>
of a loan of twenty-five millions, and we know that the <lb/>
Home Government would guarantee this at four per cent. <lb/>
It would pay for the Intercolonial Railroad, Canals where<lb break="no"/>ever needed, and provide amply for the public defences ; <lb/>
and, while mentioning the defences, I may remark that, <lb/>
not only would the people of this Island save several pounds <lb/>
per head, yearly, by the importation of so many articles, <lb/>
duty free, but they would save the expense of arms and <lb/>
material, and of annual maintenance of the militia. <lb/>
Mr Speaker, we may rest assured that, in Confederation, <lb/>
or out of Confederation, the people of Great Britain will <lb/>
take care that they will not, in future, pay more towards<lb/>
the defence of these Colonies than what recollection of their<lb/>
past, and anticipation of their future, may satisfy them<lb/>
is right and just ; and, Sir, if we prefer to remain outside<lb/>
the proposed Confederation, we will be under the necessity<lb/>
which must, sooner or later arrive, of taxing ourselves<lb/>
pretty heavily for this object of defence. The arms alone<lb/>
which we would require for the equipment of our sixteen<lb/>

<pb n="49" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_049.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">49</fw>

thousand men would cost some eighty thousand pounds <lb/>
sterling, and material many thousands additional. The<lb/>
annual five days' drill of the Militia would be a heavy<lb/>
charge on the Treasury and individuals. Now, if we<lb/>
were in Confederation the General Government would<lb/>
furnish arms and material, and grant us an annual<lb/>
allowance for maintenance, &amp;c. Again, all who are at all<lb/>
conversant with military matters know that there can be<lb/>
but one arm, one executive, as it were, to work where<lb/>
military matters are concerned ; but, if our people prefer<lb/>
it, they will find out that it is no small matter. Yet it<lb/>
must be done in some shape. A few years ago we were<lb/>
in the presence of a neighbour with a standing army of<lb/>
eight thousand, now they have seven hundred thousand.<lb/>
There are many other points to which I could advert,<lb/>
showing what would be the gain to this Island which<lb/>
would result from Confederation. I might dilate upon<lb/>
the good fortune of our young men, were so extended a<lb/>
field opened to their ambition ; but I shall defer the con<lb break="no"/>sideration of that branch of the subject to another time ;<lb/>
and I now gladly borrow from one of the most distinguished<lb/>
and venerable of the statesmen of British America, when<lb/>
he tells us that the choice offered to the Legislatures of<lb/>
these Provinces is, " on the one hand, Union under one<lb/>
government, giving to the British subjects in their confeder<lb break="no"/>ate and growing strength, a nationality worthy of their<lb/>
origin, where, putting forth the energies of free men,<lb/>
they and their descendants may, under a Gracious Provi<lb break="no"/>dence, have the opportunity of rising to degrees of politi<lb break="no"/>cal influence, material prosperity, intellectual and liter<lb break="no"/>ary attainments, religious, educational and moral progress<lb/>
and refinement of taste and manners, which cannot be<lb/>
reached in small and contracted communities ; or, on the<lb/>
other hand, the perpetuation of the present isolated con<lb break="no"/>dition of the Provinces, few in numbers, unequal to the<lb/>
development of our own resources, unable to furnish to<lb/>
our sons professional education, or to retain at home our<lb/>
enterprising youth. We have little prospect for the<lb/>
future beyond a dwarfed existence and ultimate absorp<lb break="no"/>tion into the neighboring Republic. One of these must<lb/>
be chosen, the other rejected—there is no other alternat<lb break="no"/>tive." Yes Mr. Speaker, federation or annexation is<lb/>
what we must regard as our future. And I would ask,<lb/>
have we considered the alternative ! Do we imagine that<lb/>
it is remote, something to be thought upon at a future<lb/>
day ! Already the warning notes have been sounded, and<lb/>
what steps have these Provinces taken to meet the reality !<lb/>
We know that the feeling in England has been, untile very<lb/>
lately, most strongly excited against us, but since this<lb/>
question of Confederation has been agitated a more kindly<lb/>
spirit has been evoked, because, in Confederation, the<lb/>
Mother Country sees at length aroused a disposition here<lb break="no"/>tofore dormant, an awakening to a sense of the duty we<lb/>
owe to ourselves and our posterity, and a determina<lb break="no"/>tion on our part to unite as one people against the<lb/>
coming storm : and in this case they have promised to<lb/>
stand by us, but I know very little of the people of Eng<lb break="no"/>land, if we do not, before many weeks, hear that the late<lb/>
action of the people of New Brunswick has revived all the<lb/>
old distrust. If we are not, now true to ourselves, in<lb/>
this great crisis, we may rest assured that England will<lb/>
not send a man to help us in our hour of need. We will<lb/>
find, to our cost that, on the very first outbreak, the Stars<lb/>
and Stripes will wave over us ; what then will be the<lb/>
position in which our folly will have placed us ? Truly, in that<lb/>
hour it will not be a question of a few cents more or less<lb/>
in a tariff. Fancy every man among us, with five in family<lb/>
being under a yearly tax of forty-five dollars, and for<lb/>
what ? The improvement of the country, the construction<lb/>
of railroads, or the erection of cities of palaces ? No !<lb/>
but taxation incurred by another people, in sweeping<lb/>
with the besom of destruction, hundreds of thousands, (I<lb/>

<cb/>

believe the number exceeds two millions) of their fellow <lb/>
men intro eternity, and turning into a howling wilder<lb break="no"/>ness the fairest country the sun has ever shone upon ; and<lb/>
this is the alternative the opponents of Confederation<lb/>
offer us. I am told that it is unpopular with us—that<lb/>
those who oppose Confederation have gained a vast<lb/>
amount of popularity by decrying it. For myself, I may<lb/>
say, so far as rewards in this world weigh with me, I know<lb/>
none greater than the approval of my fellow men, but, to<lb/>
obtain even this, I cannot condemn what I truly believe to<lb/>
be for the best interests of us all ; nor can I, for any<lb/>
amount of popular applause, give utterance with my lips,<lb/>
to what, in my heart, I disapprove. Probably, as times<lb/>
go, I, too, might have acquired some <hi rendition="simple:italic">quasi</hi> popularity, if,<lb/>
on my return from Canada, I had denied and repubiated<lb/>
all I had ever said in favor of Union and joined the cry<lb/>
against it ; but then I would have lost what I value far<lb/>
more highly than popular applause— self respect. The<lb/>
various details embodied in the Report of the Delegates<lb/>
speak for themselves. Hon members need not to be<lb/>
told that delegates from six Provinces, each repre<lb break="no"/>senting a diversity of interests, could only be mutual<lb/>
concessions obtain such a united whole as we could all<lb/>
agree in supporting and submitting to the people. That<lb/>
we had arrived at such a result I never for one moment<lb/>
doubted until my return here from Canada. Taken as a<lb/>
whole, I cannot come to any other conclusion than this,<lb/>
that the principles here set forth are well calculated to<lb/>
establish and consolidate a great nationality, and to be<lb/>
the means of elevating British America to a height of<lb/>
wealth, grandeur and prosperity, such as we can never<lb/>
in any other way attain to. And as far as this Island is<lb/>
concerned, as Confederation will bring prosperity to<lb/>
Halifax and St John, whose rise will be ours, as it will<lb/>
bring us an influx of capital to develop the mines of<lb/>
wealth we possess in our fisheries ; as it will build up<lb/>
harbours where needed for the interest of that trade ; as it<lb/>
will give us manufactories in our own midst with constant<lb/>
employ to our youth of both sexes, summer and winter;<lb/>
the means of banishing the discontent of the tenantry ;<lb/>
a Government elected by four millions of people, which<lb/>
will be as formidable in its strength as ours ever has<lb/>
been impotent in its weakness ; a Revenue amply suf<lb break="no"/>ficient for our local wants as heretofore ; and instead of a<lb/>
Legislative Union, such as deprived Ireland of her separate<lb/>
Parliament, we are secured all the advantage of having<lb/>
our own Island Parliament for the management of our<lb/>
local affairs. Also the further representation of nine<lb/>
members in a General Parliament, and nine gentlemen<lb/>
should be able to represent this Island as efficiently as four<lb/>
times that number. Also the hearty support of England<lb/>
with her fleet and army. And as all this can be obtained<lb/>
without any increase of taxation, but, on the contrary,<lb/>
with a great decrease in the amount now paid by the bulk<lb/>
of our people. Although the subject of Confederation has<lb/>
been made unpopular, because neither explained nor<lb/>
understood, yet I am glad to place on record my earnest<lb/>
and hearty advocacy of it, leaving my action to be judged<lb/>
by reflecting minds at a future day ; being assured that<lb/>
neither you, Mr Speaker, nor any other hon member will do<lb/>
me the injustice to suppose that the few observations I have<lb/>
deemed it my duty to make on this momentous question,<lb/>
will be construed into anything approaching a desire to<lb/>
influence any hon member in the vote he may now record ;<lb/>
because Mr Speaker, both yourself and hon members are<lb/>
aware what an overwhelming majority have made up their<lb/>
minds to oppose it. I can, then, but be fully conscious<lb/>
how futile would be such a desire on my part or on that<lb/>
of any of the advocates of Confederation, at this juncture.<lb/>
I will not, therefore, say more, but conclude by burrowing<lb/>
again from my venerable friend, when I repeat that this is<lb/>
no small affair, the influence of which will die away with<lb/>
the excitement of its discussion ; nothing of petty politics<lb/>
reaching no further than personal interests ; no matter of<lb/>
party strife; our country and its destinies, our descendants<lb/>

<pb n="50" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-25_Page_050.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">50</fw>

and their future are the subjects, and the consideration <lb/>
should be approached with an earnestness, and the decision<lb/>
made under a sense of responsibility not to be exceeded in<lb/>
the discharge of the most solemn religious duty.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WARB1">Hon Mr WARBURTON</persName>.—Mr Speaker, I did not think that<lb/>
this question would be take up this evening. As, however, it has<lb/>
come up for discussion, and as it is expected that every member<lb/>
will give expression to his views on the question, I shall briefly<lb/>
state my opinions. I have always been opposed to this scheme.<lb/>
If we are to have a Union I would prefer a Legislative to a<lb/>
Federal one, under which this House would become a useless<lb/>
bauble, with no power save that of taxing the people. Last<lb/>
Session we sanctioned a delegation for a specified purpose—to<lb/>
confer on the subject of a Union of the Maritime Provinces.<lb/>
The Hon Col Secretary has stated that Union is strength<lb/>
It may be so ; but a connection of the character recom<lb break="no"/>mended by the Report before us, would only be a Union of<lb/>
the Lion with the Lamb ; we would be devoured by the<lb/>
Canadians. The hon member for Belfast told us that under the<lb/>
Union we would pay less taxes. I cannot see how they can be<lb/>
the result if we have to defray our proportion of the expenses of<lb/>
an army and navy, and of the fortifications necessary for the<lb/>
protection of Canada. The operation of the tenant system in<lb/>
this Island proves that our people cannot pay the rates imposed<lb/>
in that country. The Act which passed this House last Session<lb/>
precludes the idea of any relief being afforded to the tenantry<lb/>
under Confederation, for a law once passed must be obeyed. I,<lb/>
for one, opposed its passage, and we have no reason to suppose<lb/>
that the United Government would abolish it ; for, if they should<lb/>
do so there would be no security for any man's property. I<lb/>
agree that we have no influences at the Colonial Office. While<lb/>
I believe that the tenantry would have a better chance of freeing<lb/>
themselves from the Rent Roll system under the stars and stripes.<lb/>
I myself will never consent to live under any other than the old<lb/>
flag of Britain, under which there are no people on this continent<lb/>
who enjoy as much freedom from taxation as ourselves. In<lb/>
Canada it is well known that the taxation is heavy ; we increased<lb/>
our Tariff, but the people do not feel the operation of it as they<lb/>
would that of a system of direct taxation, such as obtains in<lb/>
Canada. This system properly adjusted would, I admit, be<lb/>
found to be the cheapest ; but the people cannot be persuaded to<lb/>
adopt that view. There is a great and insuperable dread of<lb/>
direct taxation. The principle of representation by population,<lb/>
as embodied in the resolutions of the Conference, I cannot agree<lb/>
to ; for, under it in the Confederate Parliament we should have<lb/>
no influence. Sir, I believe that nine tenths of the people of the<lb/>
island are opposed to a Union either Federal or Legislative. I<lb/>
myself shall use all my endeavors against it inside these walls<lb/>
and throughout the country, and if my constituents disapprove of<lb/>
my conduct, they can readily get some one else to represent<lb/>
them. We have heard hon members enlarge upon the glory<lb/>
argument. It might be that I, by supporting the proposed Con<lb break="no"/>federate Government, but considerations of that nature do not<lb/>
weigh with me. In conclusion, I repeat that I am opposed to a<lb/>
Union of any kind, but if we are to have any, I prefer a Legis<lb break="no"/>lative one to the mongrel scheme adopted at Quebec.<lb/></p> 

<p>The Debate was then adjourned<lb/></p> 

<!-- DL 2018-06-06 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>MONDAY, March 27 <lb/></p> 

<p>House resumed consideration of the papers relating to the Union<lb/>
of the Colonies.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. MR HENSLEY, Mr Speaker, I have heard it stated that <lb/>
all the talent in this House was enlisted on the side of the Union ;<lb/>
assuming such to be the case, as I am not in the habit of making<lb/>
long speeches, which, under such a state of fact, must, of neces<lb/>
sity, be productive of no benefit, I am happy to console myself<lb/>
by the reflection, that we have, at least, a numerical superiority,<lb/>
as there are some 25 or 26 members who are opposed to "all the<lb/>
talent" on this question. A question of this magnitude should be<lb/>
approached free from political or party bias. When the matter<lb/>
of Confederation was under discussion last Session the idea was<lb/>
expressed, and very generally acquiesced in, that united with<lb/>
only the Maritime Provinces, we would be absorbed, and<lb/>
quotations from speeches of the Provincial Secretary of Nova<lb/>
Scotia, and others, as to the absorption of that Province in case of<lb/>
Union with Canada were adduced to warrant the opinion.<lb/>
Well, Sir, if such would probably be the effect of our connection<lb/>

<cb/>

with Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, I can only come to the <lb/>
conclusion that we would be entirely swamped if we cast in our<lb/>
lot with Canada. No doubt the idea of forming part of a great<lb/>
country is very captivating, if we really were a separate and<lb/>
solitary people ; but, I cannot recognise its force in our case when<lb/>
I call to mind that we are part and parcel of the great British<lb/>
Empire. The important question for our consideration is<lb/>
whether we are bound by the action of the Quebec Convention.<lb/>
It is quite clear that we are not. That Convention was held<lb/>
without any authority from this House, and the Delegates had<lb/>
no power to agree to any conclusions on the subject, but at the<lb/>
utmost, merely to report to this House. I regret that they agreed<lb/>
to so formal a document as the one before us, as it seems to con<lb break="no"/>vey the idea to the world that they possessed powers to treat and<lb/>
make a binding arrangement. It has been said and written that<lb/>
we shall be driven into this Confederacy. I would ask what<lb/>
foundation exists for such an assertion ? Whence does it arise ?<lb/>
We have no despatches before us indicating such an eventuality ;<lb/>
in fact the documents submitted to us lead to the belief in my<lb/>
mind that we shall be allowed to deal with this matter as we<lb/>
please. I believe that the fact is that the Canadians finding a<lb/>
general Union of the Colonies would be of service to themselves,<lb/>
sent Delegates here with the view of commending their project<lb/>
to the favorable consideration of the Legislatures of the Lower<lb/>
Provinces, and I do not blame them for doing so. The terms of<lb/>
the Report before us are, in my opinion, very unfavorable to<lb/>
this Island. On the scale of representation proposed, we would<lb/>
be without the slightest influence in the United Parliament. It<lb/>
is true that, if we went into the proposed Union, we would have<lb/>
no right to expect as large a number of representatives as either of<lb/>
the Lower Provinces, but then, if, or why should we throw away<lb/>
our independence which we now enjoy ? There would, of neces<lb break="no"/>sity, be an increased tariff under the Union, and before I can<lb/>
admit the force of the argument that Canada and New Brunswick<lb/>
will supply us with boots, shoes, spirits and other articles of<lb/>
manufacture and at a lower rate than we can get them at present,<lb/>
I should like to be satisfied, as to their present ability, to supply<lb/>
themselves with those articles. Such returns of importations<lb/>
into these two Provinces, for the year 1863, as we have before<lb/>
us, seem to me rather to indicate an entirely different state of<lb/>
things in that respect. Now, Mr. Speaker, if the people of those<lb/>
two Colonies cannot, with a high protective tariff, furnish the<lb/>
articles I have specified in quantities sufficient for their own re<lb break="no"/>quirements, it is not to be supposed that they can supply them to<lb/>
us. Our chief, because most advantageous, trade is with the<lb/>
United States and Great Britain, and as long as we shall find it to<lb/>
our advantage that it should be so, it will naturally seek these<lb/>
channels ; and if we come under the influence of a highest Tariff<lb/>
we shall be taxing our best customers and crippling our most<lb/>
profitable channels for commercial interchange. I cannot think<lb/>
that Great Britain will look favorably on a scheme which, so far<lb/>
as these Lower Colonies are concerned, will have the effect of<lb/>
placing heavier duties on the importation of her manufactured<lb/>
goods.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon Mr DAVIES.—This question, Mr Speaker, is, in my <lb/>
opinion, forced upon us. If the States were now in the same<lb/>
position as they were before the outbreak of the Civil War, I<lb/>
would oppose any measure of the sort, but they have now become<lb/>
a great military country, whose boast it has long been to carry<lb/>
out the Monroe doctrine, and to spread the principles of Repub<lb break="no"/>licanism over the whole Continent. The Imperial Government<lb/>
has expressed its willingness to aid us. It has said, "Do all<lb/>
that you can towards your own defence, and we will supplement<lb/>
your efforts." We are too small a people for separate and<lb/>
independent action, and that the termination of the present Civil<lb/>
War is at hand may be inferred from the fact that the captain of<lb/>
a blockade-runner told me during the last winter that the game<lb/>
was up ; and we are all aware of the state of feeling which exists<lb/>
in the Northern States and Great Britain, which will most likely<lb/>
find expression in an attempt to realize their oft-repeated vaunt—<lb/></p> 

<p>No boundless Utica confines our powers, <lb/>
But the whole boundless continent is ours<lb/></p> 

<p>Frequent allusion has been made to the debt of Canada, but that <lb/>
debt has been principally incurred in the construction of public<lb/>
works of great value and utility. If we should be absorbed into<lb/>
the United States we would be compelled to assume far greater<lb/>
burdens than those to which we would be liable if united to Canada.<lb/>
I agree that Confederation would exercise a certain moral<lb/>
 <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>