<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1873-06-04"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1873-06-04">04 June 1873</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1873">
               <title>The Parliamentary Reporter of Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly</title>.
          <date when="1873"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Examiner</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="267"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-04_Page_266.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-08-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-08-17">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-04_Page_266">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-04_Page_266.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1873-06-04_Page_266"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-06-04_Page_266.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">266</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            
            
            <p>[...]
     gation and the conveyance of mails 
     <lb/>
     between Prince Edward Island and 
     <lb/>
     the Provinces of Nova Scotia and New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. L. H. DAVIES</persName> thought it a 
     <lb/>
     monstrous proposition that Charlotte<lb break="no"/>town is only to have one or two trips 
     <lb/>
     per week, by Steamboat, allowed it 
     <lb/>
     instead of the present arrangement, or 
     <lb/>
     a more progressive one still. But 
     <lb/>
     be supposed that this question would 
     <lb/>
     be more fully discussed when the Bill 
     <lb/>
     was brought down. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SINC6">Mr. SINCLAIR</persName> asked whether it was 
     <lb/>
     not going too far to enter into a new 
     <lb/>
     engagement for ten years with the 
     <lb/>
    present contractor, when the Dominion 
     <lb/>had engaged to provide for the con<lb break="no"/>veyance of our mails to the other 
     <lb/>Provinces. He thought that to do so 
     <lb/>would be taking too much upon our<lb break="no"/>selves under present circumstances. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> said that in 
     <lb/>
     passing the resolution before them, 
     <lb/>
     the Committee did not pledge itself in 
     <lb/>
     any way, or make any engagement 
     <lb/>
     that would be binding. No Bill im<lb break="no"/>posing a tax upon the subject could 
     <lb/>
     be introduced unless it originates with 
     <lb/>
     a Committee of the whole House. 
     <lb/>
     The proper time to take objection to 
     <lb/>
     the principles and provisions of the 
     <lb/>
     Bill, will be when the Bill itself comes 
     <lb/>
     down. The question for present con<lb break="no"/>sideration is whether the House is in 
     <lb/>
     favor of increased steam communica<lb break="no"/>tion with the other Provinces, and 
     <lb/>
     whether a new contract should be 
     <lb/>
     entered into for that purpose. As re<lb break="no"/>gards the necessity for increased steam 
     <lb/>
     communication between this Island 
     <lb/>
     and the other Provinces when the 
     <lb/>
     Railway is opened up throughout the 
     <lb/>
     whole length. there can be little doubt. 
     <lb/>
     It is, on the other hand, far better to 
     <lb/>
     enter into acontract with capitalists 
     <lb/>
     amongst ourselves, who own substan<lb break="no"/>tial and commodious Boats, which 
     <lb/>
     have given every satisfaction, and thus 
     <lb/>
     have the money expended amongst us, 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     than to trust to outsiders, who would 
     <lb/>
     spend the money elsewhere. The ad<lb break="no"/>vantage of having a Steam Naviga<lb break="no"/>tion Company located amongst our<lb break="no"/>selves, owning such Boats as the 
     <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Princess of Wales</hi>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Heather Belle</hi> and 
     <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">St. Lawrence</hi>, when free trade opens 
     <lb/>
     with the Dominion, will be apparent 
     <lb/>
     to the commonest observer. Free 
     <lb/>
     trade with Canada will be a great ad<lb break="no"/>vantage to the Company, and will 
     <lb/>
     enable them to afford greater facilities 
     <lb/>
     to the travelling public, and for the 
     <lb/>
     conveyance of freight, than they have 
     <lb/>
     ever yet been able to supply. The 
     <lb/>
     question in reference to the number of 
     <lb/>
     trips to be made between the several 
     <lb/>
     ports is a matterto be settled when 
     <lb/>
     the House goes into Committee on the 
     <lb/>
     Bill itself. It will be more satisfac<lb break="no"/>tory to enter into a contract with a 
     <lb/>
     local Company, owning local Boats, 
     <lb/>
     and thus have the profits of the enter 
     <lb/>
     prise spent among ourselves, and the 
     <lb/>
     Boats officered, from the Captain down 
     <lb/>
     to the firemen. from our own people, 
     <lb/>
     than to have Boats employed belong<lb break="no"/>ing to any of the other Provinces. All 
     <lb/>
     those matters would, he hoped, receive 
     <lb/>
     the due consideration of that hon. 
     <lb/>
     Committee. As to whether ten years 
     <lb/>
     was too long a time tor which to enter 
     <lb/>
     into a contract with a Company, or 
     <lb/>
     not, it would be time enough to con<lb break="no"/>sider when the Bill came before the 
     <lb/>
     House in Committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The resolution was then put and 
     <lb/>
     carried. The Speaker then took the 
     <lb/>
     chair and the Chairman then reported 
     <lb/>
     the resolution agreed to. A Commit<lb break="no"/>tee, consisting ofhons. Pope, Haviland, 
     <lb/>
     and Mr. John Yeo, was appointed to 
     <lb/>
     bring in a Bill in accordance with the 
     <lb/>
     resolution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERN<lb break="no"/>MENT</persName>, Chairman of said Committee, 
     <lb/>
     accordingly submitted a Bill, intituled 
     <lb/>
     " An Act relating to Steam Communi<lb break="no"/>cation and the conveyance of Mails 
     <lb/>
     between Prince Edward Island and 
     <lb/>
          
            
     <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">267</fw>
     
          the Provinces of Nova Scotia and 
     <lb/>New Brunswick." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Received and read a first time and 
     <lb/>
     ordered to be read a second time to-<lb break="yes"/>morrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     House in Committee of the whole in 
     <lb/>
     further consideration of the County 
     <lb/>
     Courts Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KELL2">Mr. T. KELLY</persName> in the chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     After some time spent in Commit<lb break="no"/>tee, without debate, the Speaker re<lb break="no"/>sumed the chair, progress was reported 
     <lb/>
     and leave obtained to sit again. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="simple:right">
     I. O. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     House went into Committee on the 
     <lb/>
     Bill for preventing, at improper sea<lb break="no"/>sons, the shooting of wild duck, snipe 
     <lb/>
     and woodcock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     House resumed, when resolution 
     <lb/>
     was reported agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BREC1">Hon. Mr. BRECKEN</persName>, from Commit<lb break="no"/>tee, submitted a Bill in accordance 
     <lb/>
     with said resolution, which Was read a 
     <lb/>
     first time and ordered to be read a 
     <lb/>
     second time to-morrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On motion of hon. Mr. Brecken, a 
     <lb/>
     Bill was introduced, and referred to a 
     <lb/>
     Committee on Private Bills, to en<lb break="no"/>able the Society for the propogation 
     <lb/>
     of the Gospel in foreign parts, to dis<lb break="no"/>pose of some Parsonage lands in this 
     <lb/>
     Island. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SULL1">Hon. Mr. SULLIVAN</persName> moved that the 
     <lb/>
     House go into Committee on the Bill 
     <lb/>
     relating to the Master of the Rolls and 
     <lb/>
     Assistant Judges. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BREC1">Hon. Mr. BRECKEN</persName> seconded the 
     <lb/>
     motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">Mr. LAIRD</persName> said he had some ob<lb break="no"/>jection to the Bill. Judges have good 
     <lb/>
     salaries, and should not be allowed to 
     <lb/>
     do business as agents or otherwise in 
     <lb/>
     matters which can be done by others. 
     <lb/>
     If they have friends who wish to have 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     them set in the capacity of Attorneys 
     <lb/>
     for them, they cannot suppose this 
     <lb/>
     House will sanction any measure of 
     <lb/>
     this nature. Judges should, as far as 
     <lb/>
     possible, keep clear from acting as 
     <lb/>
     agents for any parties. Nor could he 
     <lb/>
     think any injustice would be done to 
     <lb/>
     them by refusing to pass this Bill. In 
     <lb/>
     so far as be (Mr. L.) understood the 
     <lb/>
     Bill, he was opposed to the principle 
     <lb/>
     it contained. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. Mr. POPE</persName> did also feel op<lb break="no"/>posed to the Bill. Their salaries 
     <lb/>
     should be sufiicient to maintain them 
     <lb/>
     in the high position they occupy, 
     <lb/>
     without having to come down from 
     <lb/>
     that height to act as agents or Attor<lb break="no"/>neys for any one. When we enter 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion, the probability is, their 
     <lb/>
     salaries will be increased, when they 
     <lb/>
     will be enabled to live as becomes 
     <lb/>
     their high station in society, without 
     <lb/>
     having to resort to an occupation which 
     <lb/>
     Judges should not engage in. He 
     <lb/>
     considered it the duty of the House to 
     <lb/>
     set their faces against all such mea<lb break="no"/>sures. It was all very well for them 
     <lb/>
     to say they only intended to act for 
     <lb/>
     relatives; but in passing such a Bill 
     <lb/>
     we would be endorsing a principle 
     <lb/>
     which would be susceptible of great 
     <lb/>
     abuse, and calculated to dishonor the 
     <lb/>
     Bench. This House will take the 
     <lb/>
     wisest course, if it sets its face against 
     <lb/>
     this and all like measures. To keep 
     <lb/>
     our Judges clear of all such transac<lb break="no"/>tion, in so far as legislation can do so, 
     <lb/>
     was the clear duty of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BREC1">Hon. Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—The prin<lb break="no"/>ciple advocated by his honor the Lea<lb break="no"/>der of the Government, is undoubtedly 
     <lb/>
     a sound one; yet it is fair to state, 
     <lb/>
     that by all the principles known to 
     <lb/>
     jurisprudence, Judges are prohibited 
     <lb/>
     in acting in any case where they 
     <lb/>
     are individually or collectively in<lb break="no"/>terested, and this Bill is not intended 
     <lb/>
     to allow any Judge to act in any case 
     <lb/>
     in opposition to this acknowledged 
     <lb/>
     principle. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>