<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-03-30"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>


<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-03-30">30 March 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1870, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1870"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="144"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>

<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_134.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_136.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_138.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_140.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_142.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_144.hocr.html"/>
</item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-16">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-16">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_134">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_134.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_136">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_136.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_138">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_138.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_140">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_140.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_142">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_142.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_144">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_144.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>
<div type="debate">

<pb n="135" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_134.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">135</fw> 

<head rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, March 30.</head><lb/>

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="136" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_136.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">136</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre">AFTERNOON SESSION.<lb/></p>

<p>Hon. Mr. Howlan presented to the <lb/>
House supplementary estimates, which <lb/>
were laid on the table. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">Confederation.<lb/></p>

<p>House again in committee on the <lb/>
despatches. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> said the matter <lb/>
referred to in the resolution submitted <lb/>
by the hon. Leader of the Government, <lb/>
last night, was of vast importance to the <lb/>
Colony, and it was expected that each <lb/>
hon. gentleman on this committee would <lb/>
express an opinion thereon. He (Mr. <lb/>
Davies) expected that the hon. Leader <lb/>
of the Opposition would have risen and <lb/>
given his opinion whether the resolution <lb/>
under consideration met his views or <lb/>
not; but, perhaps the hon. member was <lb/>
waiting, under the impression that fuller <lb/>

<pb n="137" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_136.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">137</fw> 

information would be laid before the <lb/>
committee. But the Government had <lb/>
nothing more to lay before the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture on the question. From the corres<lb break="no"/>pondence on the table, it was to be seen <lb/>
that we were asked to unite as a colony <lb/>
with the Dominion of Canada. To this <lb/>
he objected, because he believed our <lb/>
present constitution was sufficient to <lb/>
meet all the governmental requirements <lb/>
of the Colony ; and he knew our people <lb/>
considered that to hand over the collec<lb break="no"/>tion and expenditure of our revenue, <lb/>
with all the other splendid privileges we <lb/>
enjoyed, to Canada, would be to relin<lb break="no"/>quish our birthright. Should this <lb/>
Colony do so, it would then be nothing <lb/>
more than a municipality, and he thought <lb/>
the people of this Island should seriously <lb/>
consider the consequences of such an <lb/>
important and irretrievable step before <lb/>
it was taken. The first effect this Island <lb/>
would experience under confederation <lb/>
would result from having our usual re<lb break="no"/>venue expended upon the public works <lb/>
in the Dominion, the whole of which <lb/>
would be under the control of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of Canada ; while our own ne<lb break="no"/>cessities would compel us to resort to <lb/>
direct taxation for local purposes. Our <lb/>
roads, wharfs and public schools would, <lb/>
in common with other public require<lb break="no"/>ments, have to be maintained from the <lb/>
same source. Looking at confederation <lb/>
from that point of view, he had great <lb/>
objections to it. This Island never ask<lb break="no"/>ed or sought confederation ; but the <lb/>
public men of the Dominion came first <lb/>
down here and sought our co-operation. <lb/>
Of course they were received as became <lb/>
gentlemen occupying their high positions, <lb/>
and before they left, succeeded in induc<lb break="no"/>ing some of our public men to follow <lb/>
them up to Canada, where the most of <lb/>
them signed the terms agreed upon at <lb/>
Quebec. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.—They all agreed <lb/>
to them. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName>.—The people <lb/>
were in utter ignorance with respect in <lb/>
those terms, and were indebted to Hon. <lb/>
Edward Palmer for placing them in their <lb/>
true light. And so strong was public <lb/>
opinion, from the information given at <lb/>
that time, that the House of Assembly <lb/>
felt it to be its duty to pass a strong no-<lb break="yes"/>terms resolution. In adopting that <lb/>
course, he was of opinion that the House <lb/>
acted prematurely, for he believed it <lb/>
would have been sufficient to have said <lb/>
that the overtures made were not accept<lb break="no"/>able. Such would have been a wiser and <lb/> 

<cb/>

less offensive line of policy. No doubt <lb/>
the British Government had a strong <lb/>
desire to see those colonies united, and <lb/>
in giving expression to these opinions <lb/>
her public men were guided by the im<lb break="no"/>pression that British interests in those <lb/>
Colonies would thereby be more likely <lb/>
to be continued. That opinion had re<lb break="no"/>cently been again expressed by Earl <lb/>
Granville, in his despatch to Sir John <lb/>
Young, who brought it to the notice of <lb/>
the Government of this Island in the <lb/>
despatch on the table; and we had a <lb/>
right now to express our opinions also. <lb/>
Yet he thought it would be wrong to go <lb/>
directly and positively against what was <lb/>
known to be the earnest desire of the <lb/>
Imperial Government, and he might <lb/>
add, the people of England, whose wishes <lb/>
were made known to us in the despatches <lb/>
which were then under consideration. <lb/>
While he would not deny but that Great <lb/>
Britain might exercise a control over us <lb/>
which would all but compel us to unite <lb/>
with Canada, yet he did not suppose <lb/>
she intended to do so; and this, he <lb/>
thought, might reasonably be inferred <lb/>
from an extract which he would read <lb/>
from the despatch of Earl Granville to <lb/>
Governor Musgrave, dated August 14th, <lb/>
1869:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"I have now to inform you that the terms on <lb/>
which Rupert's Land and the North West Ter<lb break="no"/>ritory are to be united to Canada, have been <lb/>
agreed to by the parties concerned, and the <lb/>
Queen will probably be advised before long, to <lb/>
issue an order in Council which will incorpor<lb break="no"/>ate, in the Dominion of Canada, the whole of <lb/>
the British Possessions on the North Ameri<lb break="no"/>can Continent, except the then conterminous <lb/>
Colony of British Columbia." <lb/></p> 
</quote>

<p>From this he inferred that Great Britain <lb/>
would, in so far as she constitutionally <lb/>
could do so, place all her colonies on <lb/>
this continent into confederation. But <lb/>
to this Island she had granted a consti<lb break="no"/>tution which could not be taken away <lb/>
but by the consent of our own people. <lb/>
Rupert's Land was in the position of this <lb/>
Island, previous to 1850, and, therefore, <lb/>
Her Majesty's Government could place <lb/>
that country into confederation when she <lb/>
pleased ; but he regarded our situation <lb/>
as entirely different. The fact was, we <lb/>
were an independent people, having had <lb/>
self-government granted to us, which <lb/>
was confirmed and sanctioned by the <lb/>
statute law of the Colony. He men<lb break="no"/>tioned these facts to show that Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty had not power now, constitutional<lb break="no"/>ly, to annexions to Canada, and hence <lb/>
our destiny was in our own hands; but <lb/>
it nevertheless was our duty to pay due <lb/>
respect to the Imperial wishes, and not <lb/>

<pb n="138" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_138.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">138</fw> 

to treat disrespectfully any offer coming to <lb/>
us either from England or the Dominion. <lb/>
Taking these matters into consideration <lb/>
it would not be prudent to pass a no-<lb break="yes"/>terms resolution. If we did no, Earl <lb/>
Granville, speaking for the British Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, might say, we had placed our<lb break="no"/>selves in opposition to the policy of the <lb/>
empire ; and that as we were but a <lb/>
colony of 100,000 people, it could not be <lb/>
permitted that we should thus obstruct <lb/>
the Imperial wish. Canada might be in<lb break="no"/>structed to offer terms which, on refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the Home Government would be <lb/>
regarded as fair and just ; then if that <lb/>
was the case and we declined to accept <lb/>
them, the question would arise whether <lb/>
it would be right to allow each a small <lb/>
colony to set at defiance the policy of the <lb/>
mother country and the probability was <lb/>
that the Imperial ministry would say <lb/>
they could not ; and those ideas, he (Mr. <lb/>
D.) thought were worthy the serious <lb/>
consideration of that hon. committee, <lb/>
for he believed if a resolution similar to <lb/>
the one passed by the late Government <lb/>
should be carried this session, it would <lb/>
but defeat the end which the country had <lb/>
so much at heart, namely, the retaining <lb/>
of our constitution intact, as it was now <lb/>
happily enjoyed. The Canadian Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, in compliance with instructions <lb/>
received from Great Britain, had offered <lb/>
us better terms, by $800,000, thank those <lb/>
contained in the Quebec Report, and <lb/>
said;-- <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That in the event of the Island becoming <lb/>
part of the Union, the Government of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion will endeavor to secure for the Island, <lb/>
from the Imperial Government, fair compensa<lb break="no"/>tion for the loss of Crown Lands. Should the <lb/>
Dominion Government fail in their efforts to <lb/>
secure such compensation, they will undertake <lb/>
to raise by Loan; guaranteed by the Imperial <lb/>
Government; or upon their own securities, <lb/>
should such guarantee be refused, either hun<lb break="no"/>dred thousand dollars ($800,000), and pay the <lb/>
same to the Island Government, as a compen<lb break="no"/>sation for the loss of such Crown Lands–this <lb/>
sum to be in addition to the other sums men<lb break="no"/>tioned in the preceding proposals. That the <lb/>
Dominion Government will also use their in<lb break="no"/>fluence to secure such legislation as will enable <lb/>
the Government of the Island to purchase the <lb/>
Land, now held in large blocks, upon terms <lb/>
just and equitable to all parties concerned." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>This paragraph merely promised that <lb/>
if we entered the union, the Dominion <lb/>
Government would use its effort to pro<lb break="no"/>cure this addition to the propositions of <lb/>
the Quebec terms. He felt that the <lb/>
Government should do its duty but no <lb/>
more ; and in the reply given to those <lb/>
proposals it did that, and we were to<lb break="no"/>day as free as we were before the offer <lb/>

<cb/>
 
was received. No overtures were made <lb/>
by the Government of this Island, or <lb/>
promises held forth that this Island <lb/>
would accept of any terms. He (Mr. <lb/>
D.) admitted the right of the learned <lb/>
Leader of the Opposition, on any other <lb/>
gentleman on that hon. committee, to ask <lb/>
for all papers which had passed between <lb/>
the Government and the delegates from <lb/>
Ottawa, but these were all given. No <lb/>
meeting was held with them but the in<lb break="no"/>formal one mentioned, nor was any re<lb break="no"/>cord kept, and he could assure that hon. <lb/>
committee that no overtures made <lb/>
to the delegation. Nor did the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment endeavor to throw unreasonable <lb/>
obstacles in the way or hold out delusive <lb/>
hopes. He had himself stated that the <lb/>
people of the Island would never listen <lb/>
to any proposals of union until the land <lb/>
question was just finally settled ; and <lb/>
that even if it was they should then be <lb/>
still as free as ever, either to receive or <lb/>
reject any proposals which might be <lb/>
made. But there were other meetings <lb/>
held by the delegates from Canada, and <lb/>
these were the gentlemen in Charlotte<lb break="no"/>town outside of the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.–who were they ? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> did not know. <lb/>
But, in their report the delegates said <lb/>
that they–<lb break="yes"/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Visited the Island of Prince Edward, in <lb/>
August last, and having, while there, had the <lb/>
opportunity of discussing, informally, with <lb/>
members of the Government, and <hi rendition="simple:italic">other leading <lb/>
public men</hi>, the question of the political union <lb/>
of the Island with the Dominion." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>This showed that they discussed the ques<lb break="no"/>tion with " other leading public men, " and <lb/>
as the government of the Island gave them <lb/>
no encouragement, it appeared to him (Mr. <lb/>
D.) that overtures were made to them by <lb/>
some parties, or the Canadian government <lb/>
would not have sent any proposals down. <lb/>
He knew there were a few in Charlottetown <lb/>
and vicinity who arrogated to themselves <lb/>
all the respectability and influence in the <lb/>
country, and from the heights of their own <lb/>
creating looked down with contempt upon <lb/>
the present government, and regarded the <lb/>
party new in power as being composed of <lb/>
men who obtained their position by misre<lb break="no"/>presentation ; and they very likely led the <lb/>
gentlemen from Canada to believe that pub<lb break="no"/>lic opinion would not long support the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment ; therefore it was that he (Mr. D.) <lb/>
believed that the Delegation formed their <lb/>
opinions, not from the government, but from <lb/>
what they heard from gentlemen outside. <lb/>
This to him was also more apparent from the <lb/> 

<pb n="139" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_138.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">139</fw> 

fact that in the House of Commons as Otta<lb break="no"/>wa they were upbraided for the unsuccessful <lb/>
and unsatisfactory result of their recent <lb/>
mission to this Island, and were unable to <lb/>
defend themselves for having led the au<lb break="no"/>thorities at Ottawa to believe the overtures <lb/>
would be accepted. The hon. member (Mr. <lb/>
Davies) then reviewed the despatch of <lb/>
Earl Granville, and drew the inference <lb/>
therefrom that no coercive measures were <lb/>
to be used towards this Island, but he would <lb/>
pass that by and dwell for a moment upon <lb/>
the $800,00 item. When he first read <lb/>
that part of the despatch, he thought the <lb/>
money, under confederation, could be at <lb/>
once obtained ; but, on examining the <lb/>
matter more closely, he saw that it would <lb/>
be then as far from us as it was twenty <lb/>
years ago. There was, however, an ac<lb break="no"/>knowledgment in that offer which he re<lb break="no"/>garded as important, and worthy the earnest <lb/>
attention of that Committee. The admission <lb/>
was therein made that this Island had been <lb/>
unjustly dealt with. The crown lands, <lb/>
which belonged to the colony, had been <lb/>
given away ; and the quit rents, which <lb/>
should have become the property of this <lb/>
colony also, were never paid. It was in <lb/>
fact an admission from the Home and <lb/>
Canadian Government that this colony had <lb/>
been unfairly treated. He regarded the <lb/>
offer as no equivalent for what we were ex<lb break="no"/>pected to give up in return, yet hoped the <lb/>
Committee would not forget that the pro<lb break="no"/>bability of our ever receiving the money, <lb/>
even if the terms were accepted, was <lb/>
doubtful. If Britain would not pay it at <lb/>
once, Canada might fairly ask to be allowed a <lb/>
reasonable time to use its influence with <lb/>
the Home Government, and that reasonable <lb/>
time might extend over a period of thirty <lb/>
or forty years, and then the question be as <lb/>
far from being settled as ever. But as dis<lb break="no"/>cussing all such details was premature, he <lb/>
would pass on to consider the real value of <lb/>
our lands, and here he found the answer sup<lb break="no"/>plied by Great Britain herself. Our lands, as <lb/>
a whole, were worth four times acre for <lb/>
acre, that of the average value of those of <lb/>
the Dominion, and had been valued by the <lb/>
Imperial Government in the rent which had <lb/>
been exacted, and its payment enforced by <lb/>
Imperial Troops under the influence of the <lb/>
late government ; and that annual rent <lb/>
ranged from £2 10s. to £7 10s. per hundred <lb/>
acres. The average might be set down at <lb/>
£5 sterling as the annual rent of each one <lb/>
hundred acres. This value, he held, the <lb/>
Home Government established, for, quite <lb/>
recently, when a few of the Tenant Union <lb/>
men refused to pay their rent, British <lb/>
soldiers were brought to this Island and <lb/>

<cb/> 

employed to enforce its payment at the <lb/>
point of the bayonet—an act which con<lb break="no"/>clusively proved the value set upon our <lb/>
lands by Great Britain. Therefore, if we <lb/>
were asked to set a price upon them, we <lb/>
would have but to say, " You have set a <lb/>
price upon them yourselves ; and when <lb/>
that was figured up it would amount, not as <lb/>
had been stated, to $1,240,000, but probably <lb/>
to that many pounds sterling, a sum which <lb/>
would surprise the Home Government itself, <lb/>
but to which, by its own decision, it could <lb/>
not object. His (Mr. D.'s) opinion was, <lb/>
that the Canadian delegates had, by some <lb/>
means or other, been deceived. We knew <lb/>
as the hon. leader of the Government had <lb/>
said last night, that Scotland and Ireland <lb/>
had had promises made to them before <lb/>
union, which had not for a long time been <lb/>
fulfilled ; and, with respect to the latter <lb/>
country, the promises made were only being <lb/>
earnestly and fairly considered now. He <lb/>
thought, therefore, that this question re<lb break="no"/>quired careful and cautious attention, and <lb/>
that it was the duty of all to treat any <lb/>
proposals which might be made firmly, but <lb/>
at the same time, to avoid giving the least <lb/>
offence. This the government had done, <lb/>
and it was no light duty successfully to dis<lb break="no"/>charge. He knew that there were some <lb/>
who maintained that acceptance of the <lb/>
terms proposed would confer immediate <lb/>
advantages upon this Island ; but, admitting <lb/>
they were correct in the opinions which  <lb/>
they had formed, he thought it must be <lb/>
evident to every man who would carefully <lb/>
look into the matter that eventually, or in <lb/>
four or five years, we could not possibly be <lb/>
in any better position than our fellow <lb/>
colonists in Canada ; and we knew that for <lb/>
roads, education, and other objects which <lb/>
must be attended to, they had now to resort <lb/>
to direct taxation. It was unreasonable to <lb/>
suppose but that we would, under confed<lb break="no"/>eration, have to do the same. He saw <lb/>
lately in a letter from a friend who removed <lb/>
from this Island to Canada a few years ago, <lb/>
that the local tax on his farm of one hundred <lb/>
acres was $26, and, unquestionably, in a <lb/>
short time, every man whose farm would be <lb/>
worth £500 or £600 on this Island would, <lb/>
for local taxes, have to pay a like annual <lb/>
amount if we should become a part of the <lb/>
Dominion of Canada. Representing, there<lb break="no"/>fore, as he did, an agricultural constituency, <lb/>
he would oppose any measure which would <lb/>
have a tendency to bring us into confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. He knew that his constituents sought <lb/>
no bounty at the hands of Canada to in<lb break="no"/>duce them to consent to any such proposals. <lb/>
He would be ashamed of his country if, for <lb/>
any amount of money, his countrymen  <lb/>

<pb n="140" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_140.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">140</fw> 

would sell their glorious birthright. We <lb/>
had bought out the rights of most of the <lb/>
landed proprietors, and our excellent mea<lb break="no"/>sure for affecting that object was working <lb/>
so admirably well, he hoped the time was <lb/>
not far distant when a landed proprietor <lb/>
would be numbered among the things of <lb/>
the past on Prince Edward Island. Our <lb/>
position as a colony was good. Our public <lb/>
lands, including the bonds held for what <lb/>
was sold, would meet the greater portion on <lb/>
our public debt. In arriving at this con<lb break="no"/>clusion he was guided by the Report of the <lb/>
Lands Commissioner, who, he noticed, had <lb/>
very properly placed the lands at the lowest <lb/>
figure ; and, independent of this, there <lb/>
were 60,000 acres to which no value had <lb/>
been affixed ; therefore, as his hon friend, <lb/>
the leader of the Government, observed, if <lb/>
we were to follow the rule adopted in <lb/>
Canada of making out our public accounts, <lb/>
we would not merely have no public debt <lb/>
against this colony, but a surplus in its <lb/>
favor. Turning to figure he found a balance <lb/>
against the colony of £145,885, against <lb/>
which was to be placed the value of lands <lb/>
and bonds in hand for lands sold, which <lb/>
amounted to £105,945, which left a balance <lb/>
of £39,940 against the colony ; but when <lb/>
the land not valued, public works, buildings, <lb/>
&amp;c., were taken into account, it would be <lb/>
seen that our position was far in advance of <lb/>
that of any of the provinces in the Do<lb break="no"/>minion. He had thus made matters as plain <lb/>
as he thought necessary, and went into <lb/>
details as far as was then required, believing, <lb/>
as he did, that a bright future was before <lb/>
the Island. Canada proper would not <lb/>
purchase our exports, and offered us no <lb/>
market ; but new and better ones would be <lb/>
gradually opening up, which would confer <lb/>
increased advantages upon the colony. We <lb/>
had successfully encountered difficulties <lb/>
which none of the other colonies had to <lb/>
contend with ; and he thought there was no <lb/>
fear as to the future if a prudent course was <lb/>
persevered in for the time to come. He <lb/>
had thus expressed himself as clearly as he <lb/>
deemed it his duty, and thought when that <lb/>
hon. committee would calmly review the <lb/>
action of the government during the recess, <lb/>
it would admit it did its best to discharge <lb/>
that duty which it owed to the Legislature <lb/>
and the country as faithfully as it was <lb/>
possible for men placed in their position to <lb/>
do. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> felt that he must <lb/>
congratulate the House on the changed tone <lb/>
that had taken place on this question since <lb/>
a few years ago. Then it was almost dan<lb break="no"/>gerous to rise on this floor and admit the <lb/>

<cb/>

principle. of confederation. The present <lb/>
government, however, had admitted the <lb/>
principle. Their leader in this House had <lb/>
last night given a lengthy speech, in which <lb/>
there was not one word against the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple; and the hon Colonial Secretary, in his <lb/>
opening remarks to-day, had declared that <lb/>
it would be dangerous to pass a no-terms <lb/>
resolution ; - and no wonder, because if <lb/>
they did, it would conflict with the part <lb/>
played by the Executive during the recess. <lb/>
Neither in the minute of Council of the 7th <lb/>
January, nor in that of the 4th February, <lb/>
was there anything set forth as standing in <lb/>
the way of union but the land question. In <lb/>
these minutes the members of the Executive <lb/>
in effect say, " if the Canadian govenrment <lb/>
will use their influence and obtain a settle<lb break="no"/>ment of the land question, they will estab<lb break="no"/>lish their prestige, and we will go into <lb/>
confederation. Then Newfoundland and <lb/>
the other colonies outside of the confederacy <lb/>
will enter the union, and the Dominion <lb/>
shall become a great and powerful nation." <lb/>
Again, the hon member from Wilmot Creek <lb/>
had said that because of the position he <lb/>
(Mr. Laird) had taken on this question, <lb/>
perhaps he might lose his seat. That mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the Executive, who had been the <lb/>
only one of its numbers who had discussed <lb/>
the policy of the government, and he (Mr. <lb/>
H.) would then be fighting shoulder to <lb/>
shoulder. Then the hon leader of the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had expressed the opinion last night <lb/>
that it would not be right to change our <lb/>
constitution until every acre of land in the <lb/>
colony was our own. What other inference <lb/>
could be drawn from this remark than that <lb/>
when the land question was settled we would <lb/>
go into confederation ? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> would explain that by-<lb break="yes"/>and-bye. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> had no doubt the <lb/>
hon member would attempt to wriggle out <lb/>
of it in some way. That gentleman had <lb/>
quoted authorities last night to show that <lb/>
the union of Scotland and England had <lb/>
produced injurious results. When he (Mr. <lb/>
H.) asked him at the time for the name of <lb/>
the author from whose works he had read, <lb/>
he was told this morning that it was Smollett. <lb/>
That writer might be a very good novelist, <lb/>
but of all the authorities on history that he <lb/>
(Mr. H.) ever heard of, a more disgraceful <lb/>
one could not be cited. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> had also quoted <lb/>
MeCulloch. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>. - Yes, and like Dr. <lb/>
Tupper, who, in his controversy with Mr. <lb/>

<pb n="141" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_140.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">141</fw> 

Howe, had quoted that gentleman against <lb/>
himself, he (Mr. H.) would quote McCulloch <lb/>
against McCulloch. Here was what that <lb/>
writer had also said : <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"No old settled country, of which there is <lb/>
any authentic account, ever made half the <lb/>
progress in civilization and the accumulation <lb/>
of wealth that Scotland had done since the year <lb/>
1768, and especially since 1787." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> - That was sixty years <lb/>
after the union. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.-No matter, the <lb/>
principle was the same. And since the hon <lb/>
member had gone into history, together <lb/>
with the press in the pay of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, as he say by a later number of the <lb/>
paper issued from the office of the Queen's <lb/>
Printer, he (Mr. H.) would quote authori<lb break="no"/>ties also. He would first read from Jeffery, <lb/>
the father of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Edinburgh Review</hi>: <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"If any one doubts of the wretchedness of an <lb/>
unequal and unincorporatingalliance of the de<lb break="no"/>gradation of being subject to a provincial par<lb break="no"/>liament and a distant king, and of the efficacy <lb/>
of a substantial union in curing all these evils, <lb/>
he is invited to look to the obvious example of <lb/>
Scotland. While the crowns only were united, <lb/>
and the governments continued separate, the <lb/>
weaker country was the scene of the most atro<lb break="no"/>cious cruelties, the most violent injustice, the <lb/>
most degrading oppressions. The prevailing <lb/>
religion of the people was proscribed and per<lb break="no"/>secuted with a ferocity greater than has ever <lb/>
been systematically exercised, even in Ireland; <lb/>
her industry was crippled and depressed by un<lb break="no"/>just and intolerable restrictions; her parlia<lb break="no"/>ments corrupted and overawed into the degraded <lb/>
instruments ofa distant court, and her nobility <lb/>
and gentry, cut off from all hope of distinction <lb/>
by vindicating their rights or promoting the in<lb break="no"/>terests of the country at home, were led to <lb/>
look up to the favour of her oppressors as the <lb/>
only remaining avenue to power, and degener<lb break="no"/>ated, for the most part, into a band or mercen<lb break="no"/>ary adventures ; - the more considerable as<lb break="no"/>piring to the wretched honor of executing the <lb/>
tryannicalorders which were dictated from the <lb/>
South, and the rest acquiring gradually those <lb/>
habits of subserviency and selfish submission, <lb/>
the traces oi which are by some supposed to be <lb/>
yet discernible in their descendants. The Re<lb break="no"/>volution, which rested almost entirely on the <lb/>
prevailing antipathy to Popery, required of <lb/>
course, the co-operation of all classes of Protes<lb break="no"/>tants ; and, by its success, the Scottish Presby<lb break="no"/>terians were relived, for a time, from their <lb/>
Episcopalian persecutions. But it was not till <lb/>
after the Union that the nation was truly <lb/>
emancipated ; or lifted up from the abject con<lb break="no"/>dition of a dependant at once suspected and <lb/>
despised. The effects of that happy consolid<lb break="no"/>ation were not indeed <hi rendition="simple:italic">immediately</hi> apparent ; <lb/>
for the vices which had been generated by a <lb/>
centure of provincial mis-government, the <lb/>
meannesses that had become habitual, the ani<lb break="no"/>mosities that had so long been fostered, could <lb/>
not be cured at once, but the mere removal of <lb/>
their cause. The generation they had de<lb break="no"/>graded, must first be allowed to die out - and <lb/>
more, perhaps, than one generation : But the <lb/>
poison tree was cut down - the fountain of <lb/>

<cb/>

bitter waters scaled up, and symptoms of <lb/>
returning vigour and happiness were perceived. <lb/>
Vestiges may still be traced, perhaps, of our <lb/>
long degradation ; but for, at least, forty years <lb/>
back, the provinces of Scotland have been on <lb/>
the whole, but the Northern provinces of Great <lb/>
Britain. There are no local oppressions, no <lb/>
national animosities. Life, and liberties, and <lb/>
property, are as secure in Caithness as they are <lb/>
in Middlesex - industry as much encouraged, <lb/>
and wealth still more rapidly progressive while <lb/>
not only different religious opinions, but differ<lb break="no"/>ent religious establishments subsist in the two <lb/>
ends of the same island in unbroken harmony <lb/>
and only excite each other, but a friendly emu<lb break="no"/>lation, to greater purity of life and greater zeal <lb/>
for Christianity." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Then hear what Jeffry said in reference to <lb/>
Ireland, which had had a most corrupt and <lb/>
venal parliament: <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"So far from tracing any substantive part of <lb/>
her miscries to the Union of 1800, we think they <lb/>
are to be ascribed mainly to its long delay, and <lb/>
its ultimate incompleteness. It is not by a dis<lb break="no"/>solution of the Union with England then, that <lb/>
any good can be done, but by its improvement <lb/>
and consolidation. Some injury it may have <lb/>
produced to the shopkeepers of Dublin, and <lb/>
some inconsiderable increase in the number of <lb/>
the absentees. But it has shut up the main <lb/>
fountain of corruption and dishonor ; and palsied <lb/>
the arm and broken the heart of local insolence <lb/>
and oppression. It has substituted, at least po<lb break="no"/>tentially and in prospect, the wisdom and honor <lb/>
of the British Government and the British peo<lb break="no"/>ple, to the passions and sordid interests of a <lb/>
junto of Irish boroughmongers, -and not only <lb/>
enabled, but compelled, all parties to appeal <lb/>
directly to the great tribunal of the British <lb/>
public." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>These were the opinions of Jeffery, and he <lb/>
(Mr. H.) would place them in the scale <lb/>
against those of Smollett. And if one <lb/>
authority was not enough he would quote <lb/>
another. He would read an extract from <lb/>
the works of one of the brightest men of <lb/>
modern times - one whose 1ight went out <lb/>
before he came to years of ripeness. He <lb/>
alluded to Henry Thomas Buckle, who, 1n <lb/>
his History, of Civilization, said: — <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The Union with England, which was com<lb break="no"/>pleted in 1707, produced immediate and strik<lb break="no"/>ing effects on trade. Its first effect was, to <lb/>
throw open to the Scotch a new and extensive <lb/>
commerce with the English colonies in America. <lb/>
Before the Union, no goods of any kind could <lb/>
be landed in Scotland from the American plan<lb break="no"/>tations, unless they had first been landed in <lb/>
England, and paid duty there; nor even, in <lb/>
that case, might they be conveyed by any Scotch <lb/>
vessel. This was one of many foolish regula<lb break="no"/>tions by which our legislators, interfered with <lb/>
the natural course of affairs, and injured the <lb/>
interests of their own country, as well as those <lb/>
of their neighbors. Formerly, however, such <lb/>
laws were considered to be extremely sagaci<lb break="no"/>ous, and politicians were constantly contriving <lb/>
protective schemes of this sort, which, with <lb/>
the best intentions, inflicted incalculable harm. <lb/>
But, if as seems probable, one of their objects, <lb/>
in this instance, was to retard the improvement <lb/>
of Scotland, they were more than usually suc<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="142" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_142.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">142</fw>

cessful in effecting the purpose at which they <lb/>
aimed. For, the whole of the western coast, <lb/>
being cut off from direct intercourse wit the <lb/>
American colonies, was debarred from the <lb/>
only foreign trade it could advantageously fol<lb break="no"/>low ; since the European ports lay to the east, <lb/>
and could not be reached by the inhabitants of <lb/>
Western Scotland without a long circumnavi<lb break="no"/>gation, which prevented them from competing, <lb/>
on equal terms, with their countrymen, who, <lb/>
[illegible] from the other side, were already near <lb/>
the thief seats of commerce. The consequence <lb/>
was, that Glasgow and the other western ports <lb/>
remained almost stationary ; having compara<lb break="no"/>tively few means of gratifying that enterprising <lb/>
spirit, which rose among them late in the <lb/>
seventeenth century, and not daring to trade <lb/>
with those prosperous colonies which were <lb/>
just before them across the Atlantic, but from <lb/>
which they were entirely excluded by the jeal<lb break="no"/>ous precautions of the English parliament. <lb/></p> 

<p>"When, however, by the Act of the Union, the <lb/>
two countries became one, these precautions <lb/>
were discontinued, and Scotland was allowed <lb/>
to hold direct intercourse with America and <lb/>
the West India Islands. The result which this <lb/>
produced on the national industry, was almost <lb/>
instantaneous, because it gave vent to a spirit <lb/>
which had begun to appear among the people <lb/>
late in the seventeenth century, and because it <lb/>
was sided by those still more general causes, <lb/>
which, in most parts of Europe, predisposed <lb/>
that age to increase industry. The west of <lb/>
Scotland, being nearest to America, was the <lb/>
first to feel the movement. In 1707, the inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants of Greenock, without the interference of <lb/>
government, imposed on themselves a volun<lb break="no"/>tary assessment, with the object of constructing <lb/>
a harbor. In this undertaking, they displayed <lb/>
so much zeal, that, by the year 1710, the whole <lb/>
of the works were completed ; a pier and capa<lb break="no"/>cious harbor were erected, and Greenock was <lb/>
suddenly raised from insignificance to take an <lb/>
important part int he trade of the Atlantic. <lb/>
For a while, the merchants were content to <lb/>
carry on their traffic with ships hired from the <lb/>
English. Soon, however, they became bolder ; <lb/>
they began to build on their own account; and, <lb/>
in 1719, the first vessel belonging to Greenock <lb/>
sailed for America. From that moment, their <lb/>
commerce increased so rapidly that, by the <lb/>
year 1740, the tax which the citizens had laid <lb/>
on themselves sufficed, not only to wipe off the <lb/>
debt which had been incurred, but also to leave <lb/>
a considerable surplus available for municipal <lb/>
purposes. At the same time, and by the action <lb/>
of the same causes, Glasgow emerged from <lb/>
obscurity. In 1718, its enterprising inhabitants <lb/>
launched in the Clyde the first Scotch vessel <lb/>
which ever crossed the Atlantic ; thus, antici<lb break="no"/>pating the people of Greenock by one year, <lb/>
Glasgow and Greenock became the two great <lb/>
commercial outlets of Scotland, and the chief <lb/>
centres of activity. Comforts, and, indeed, <lb/>
luxuries, hitherto only attainable at enormous <lb/>
cost, began to be diffused through the country. <lb/>
The productions of the tropics could now be <lb/>
procured direct from the New World, which, in <lb/>
return, offered a rich and abundant market for <lb/>
manufactured good. This was a further sti<lb break="no"/>mulus to Scotch industry, and its effects were <lb/>
immediately apparent. The inhabitants of <lb/>
Glasgow, finding a great demand among the <lb/>
Americans for them, introduced its manufac<lb break="no"/>ture into their city in 1720, whence it extended <lb/>

<cb/> 

to other places, and, in a short time, gave em<lb break="no"/>ployment to thousands of workmen." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>There was one statement here which was <lb/>
rather curious, namely, that it was not un<lb break="no"/>til the year 1718 that the first Scotch <lb/>
vessel sailed from Glasgow for America. <lb/>
After noting the progress of events a few <lb/>
years later, Duckle further said:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Such as the state of Scotland towards the <lb/>
middle of the eighteenth century ; and surely <lb/>
a fairer prospect was never opened to any <lb/>
country. The land was at peace. It had noth<lb break="no"/>ing to fear, either from foreign invasion, or <lb/>
from domestic tyranny. The arts, which in<lb break="no"/>crease the comfort of man, and minister to his <lb/>
happiness, were sedulously cultivated; wealth <lb/>
was being crested with unexampled speed, and <lb/>
the blessings which follow in the train of wealth <lb/>
were being widely diffused ; while the [illegible] <lb/>
of the nobility was so effectually curbed, that <lb/>
industrious citizens could, for the first time, <lb/>
feel their own independence, could know that <lb/>
what they earned that likewise they should <lb/>
enjoy, and could hold themselves erect, and <lb/>
with a manly brow, in the presence of a class <lb/>
before whom they had long crouched in abject <lb/>
submission. <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>And he (Mr. H.) could cite other author<lb break="no"/>ities to the same effect. We all knew that <lb/>
previous to the reign of Queen Anne, Scot<lb break="no"/>land could not trade with the colonies. Nor <lb/>
could she receive manufactured goods from <lb/>
England on account of the high duties, and <lb/>
her own linen, the only Scotch manufacture <lb/>
of that time of any importance, was almost <lb/>
excluded from England owing to the same <lb/>
cause. Before the union a great rivalry <lb/>
existed between the two nations. About <lb/>
the close of the 17th century the Scotch <lb/>
organized a great company called the Darien <lb/>
Company, which was to plant a colony on <lb/>
the Atlantic side of the isthmus by that <lb/>
name, and so form a commercial entrepôt <lb/>
between the eastern and western hemis<lb break="no"/>pheres; and so high did the feeling run <lb/>
between them and the English, that, though <lb/>
under the one sovereign, a vessel was seized <lb/>
and the captain hung. All this was because <lb/>
instead of having the generous rivalry, <lb/>
occasioned by being placed on the same <lb/>
footing, the Scotch were under a disadvan<lb break="no"/>tage in not being allowed to trade with the <lb/>
colonies. Scotland had succeeded wonder<lb break="no"/>fully since her union with England, not only <lb/>
in agriculture and manufactures, but in the <lb/>
progress which her sons had made in engi<lb break="no"/>neering skill, in the sciences generally, and <lb/>
in literature ; they were the first people in <lb/>
the world, and he, (Mr. H.) if he had the <lb/>
choice of his country, would sooner be a <lb/>
Scotchman than anything else, except, of <lb/>
course, a British American. The hon. <lb/>
member (Mr. Howlan) thought he had <lb/>
made a great point when he quoted from <lb/>

<pb n="143" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_142.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">143</fw>

the celebrated Tobias Smollett about the <lb/>
dissatisfaction in Scotland relative to the <lb/>
imposition of a malt tax. It was to be <lb/>
expected that troubles would sometimes <lb/>
arise, for no state could make laws to please <lb/>
all parties. But those cases cited by the <lb/>
hon. Leader of the Government were <lb/>
chiefly those which took place about the <lb/>
time of the rebellions of 1715 and 1745. <lb/>
They were disputes which had nothing to <lb/>
do with the Act of Union—they more <lb/>
properly related to the glory argument, <lb/>
and arose from the loyalty of the Scotch to <lb/>
the house of Stuart. He would now say a <lb/>
word with respect to Ireland—that country <lb/>
which was held up to be miserably down<lb break="no"/>trodden. Her union with England was a <lb/>
blessing, for it did away with the Irish <lb/>
parliament, than which there had never been <lb/>
a more useless, corrupt, venal, and miser<lb break="no"/>able body of the kind anywhere. We know <lb/>
that up to the year of 1783, by the action of <lb/>
what was called Poyning's law, a bill could <lb/>
not be introduced into that parliament until <lb/>
it was first submitted to the parliament of <lb/>
Britain. Grattan, Flood, Plunket and <lb/>
Purke by their eloquence obtained a repeal <lb/>
of this law. He wondered at Roman <lb/>
Catholics regretting the loss of the Irish <lb/>
parliament, for no man could vote for a <lb/>
member, or sit as a member in that parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, unless he were a Protestant. There <lb/>
was no independence about that body ; it <lb/>
had not a few of what was called " borough <lb/>
members." About 200, out of the whole <lb/>
300 of which it was composed, could be <lb/>
returned by about 100 gentlemen outside. <lb/>
Such was the great Irish parliament. And <lb/>
when it obtained the power to introduce <lb/>
a bill without submitting it to the English <lb/>
parliament, it did not remove the disabil<lb break="no"/>ities from Roman Catholics. The measure <lb/>
for their relief did not originate in Ireland, <lb/>
but in England under the great Pitt. Had <lb/>
the Irish parliament remained as it was in <lb/>
1783, we would never have seen Roman <lb/>
Catholic emancipation in that country, nor <lb/>
Gladstone's great bill of last year for the <lb/>
disestablishment of the Irish church. The <lb/>
measure which had brought about this was <lb/>
the one introduced by Pitt, which united <lb/>
Ireland with Britain, and placed her in an <lb/>
equal position under the same parliament. <lb/>
By that union she became part of the <lb/>
greatest empire in the world ; and by it she <lb/>
obtained in time the franchise for her Ro<lb break="no"/>man Catholic population. There was no <lb/>
guarantee when the union took place that <lb/>
this emancipation would follow. Pitt <lb/>
pledged his word that it should be carried ; <lb/>
but King George would not agree to it, as <lb/>
he thought it would be a violation of his <lb/>

<cb/>

coronation oath. Then, again, with respect <lb/>
to the Irish land question, which had been <lb/>
a grievance from time immemorial, and was <lb/>
bandied about from one political party to <lb/>
the other, it was now about to be remedied <lb/>
by Gladstone. For all these measures, <lb/>
then, the Irish Roman Catholics had to <lb/>
thank the union of their country with <lb/>
Protestant Britain. After referring to <lb/>
history, the hon. member (Mr. Howlan) <lb/>
had taken up the glory argument. The <lb/>
Imperial Government, he said, were going <lb/>
to leave us to our own resources. To show <lb/>
that, if this took place, we should be in a <lb/>
bad position, he had read an extract from a <lb/>
speech of Lord Carnarvon's. He quoted <lb/>
Bright and Lowe in support of his position, <lb/>
that the colonies would have to look out <lb/>
for themselves. But he (Mr. H.) was not <lb/>
a little astonished, after the hon. member <lb/>
had quoted these statesmen, as if he was <lb/>
giving views expressed by them during the <lb/>
present session of the Imperial parliament, <lb/>
to find that he had been reading from <lb/>
speeches delivered by them six or seven <lb/>
years ago. He had given their opinions <lb/>
when they were on the opposition benches, <lb/>
but he could not show that they had made <lb/>
such remarks since they became Her <lb/>
Majesty's Ministers. they must have ap<lb break="no"/>proved of the despatches recently sent to <lb/>
the Dominion, otherwise they would have <lb/>
resigned. He had also cited Earl Granville's <lb/>
announcement that the troops were to be <lb/>
withdrawn from Canada, to show that the <lb/>
policy of the British government was to <lb/>
leave us to our own resources. But the <lb/>
hon. member had omitted the best part of <lb/>
the noble Earl's speech, wherein he referred <lb/>
to the duty of self-defence. He (Mr. <lb/>
Haviland) entirely agreed with the Colonial <lb/>
Minister ; the Provinces should prepare for <lb/>
their own protection, and not be always <lb/>
dependant upon the British red coats. We <lb/>
should defend ourselves on the land, and <lb/>
Great Britain would do it for us on the sea. <lb/>
The sentiment of British statesmen <lb/>
appeared to be that if the Colonies pre<lb break="no"/>ferred to join the United States—to come <lb/>
under a government that was a despot<lb break="no"/>ism for four years, we should be allowed <lb/>
to go free, but if we chose to retain Bri<lb break="no"/>tish connection, they would defend us <lb/>
with the last man that could stand under <lb/>
the old flag. But this subject had been <lb/>
so much discussed by public men and <lb/>
through the press that he would not <lb/>
dwell on it here. The great argument in <lb/>
favor of confederation was the breaking <lb/>
down of hostile tariffs ; and union would <lb/>
not prevent, but rather assist us in ob<lb break="no"/>taining free trade with the United States. <lb/>

<pb n="144" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-30_Page_144.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">144</fw>  

It would, in short, give us a chance to <lb/>
become great and prosperous. No doubt <lb/>
the people had been frightened to a great <lb/>
extent by persons going round the coun0 <lb/>
try, and telling them that under union <lb/>
the taxes would be increased — that <lb/>
almost every time they opened the door <lb/>
they would meet a tax-gatherer. But <lb/>
he (Mr. H.) thought that the manufac<lb break="no"/>tures of the Dominion itself were so ex<lb break="no"/>tensive, that if we were included therein, <lb/>
we would not require to import much <lb/>
from the outside world. There were <lb/>
certain articles, of course, which could <lb/>
not be produced in the country, such as <lb/>
tea, sugar and tobacco, and on these the <lb/>
duties would be raised. With respect to <lb/>
the last mentioned, he did not look upon <lb/>
it as a requisite—the less, he thought, <lb/>
people used of it the better; therefore, <lb/>
he did not look upon it as all loss to have <lb/>
a high tariff on some articles. Then we <lb/>
had the prospect of a cloth factory going <lb/>
on at Spring Park, which he hoped would <lb/>
turn out tweeds and other cloth of a des<lb break="no"/>cription that would enable us to do with<lb break="no"/>out the imported article to a great ex<lb break="no"/>tent. It was his wish to see all the <lb/>
colonies united as he thought it would <lb/>
tend to establish British insitutions on <lb/>
the American continent. He entirely <lb/>
agreed with the hon. Colonial Secretary, <lb/>
that it would be dangerous for us to pass <lb/>
no-terms resolutions; Great Britain <lb/>
would not all this Colony to be a <lb/>
stumbling-block in the way of consum<lb break="no"/>mating the confederation scheme. He <lb/>
believed that there were several hon. <lb/>
members among the Government sup<lb break="no"/>porters who were more of his opinion on <lb/>
this question than some of his own side <lb/>
of the House; still he would not go with <lb/>
the Government in supporting the reso<lb break="no"/>lution which had been proposed. He <lb/>
could not approve of that part of the re<lb break="no"/>solution which endorsed the general <lb/>
tenor of the minutes of Council. He <lb/>
would, therefore, move a resolution of <lb/>
his own, which he did not suppose he <lb/>
would get many to support, but he be<lb break="no"/>lieved it would be awkward for some to <lb/>
oppose it. He would cast it upon the <lb/>
waters, feeling assured that it would <lb/>
bear fruit hereafter:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>Resolved, That the best interests and future <lb/>
prosperity of this Island will be promoted by a <lb/>
Federal union with the Dominion of Canada, <lb/>
provided the said union can be effected upon <lb/>
such just and equitable terms as may be approved <lb/>
of by the people at the polls. <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Progress was reported and the House <lb/>
adjourned. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>