<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-04-14"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-04-14">14 April 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
               <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1870, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
          <date when="1870"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="251"/>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="259"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_248.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_250.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_252.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_254.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_256.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_258.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-07-03">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-07-03">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_248">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_248.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_250">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_250.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_252">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_252.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_254">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_254.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_256">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_256.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_258">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_258.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="248" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_248.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">248</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1870</fw>
            
            
            <head rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, April 14.</head>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Confederation 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Debate on the despatches resumed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName> was aware that 
     <lb/>speech-making was not now regarded as<lb/>agreeable, and hon. members knew he<lb/>made lengthy ones. But any hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman on that committee who could<lb/>make a speech to successfully contradict<lb/>the statements he had previously made,<lb/>would find it somewhat difficult. He<lb/>had noticed that members of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment said nothing about the last despatch,<lb/>which he (Mr. H.) regarded as an im<lb break="no"/>portant one, in consequence of the plain<lb/>statements which it contained respecting<lb/>the state of the land question, and<lb/>thought it was well they should know<lb/>how they stood in relation to that ques<lb break="no"/>tion with the British Government. In<lb break="no"/>deed, from the nature of the demand<lb/>made for the payments of the Lieutenant<lb/>Governor's salary, it might be inferred<lb/>that the Home Government would not<lb/>consent to the proposals in the minute of<lb/>council. Hence the curt reply in the<lb/>despatch. In that document they were<lb/>told that it was their interest to form a<lb/>part of the Dominion, but he (Mr. H.)<lb/>thought there was no analogy between<lb/>the position of this Island and that of<lb/>the other provinces. Looking at the<lb/>question, in connection with their public<lb/>works, there certainly was none. They<lb/>need not go to Ireland to enquire into<lb/>the nature of their land question, for no<lb/>reason could be shown to justify the<lb/>manner in which the people of this<lb/>colony had been deprived of their public<lb/>lands, and the idea that this colony was<lb/>to be forced into Dominion, against<lb/>the will of the people, was what he<lb/>thought the Home Government would<lb/>not do. the hon. the leader of the<lb/>Opposition said Earl Granville's despatch<lb/>was not the end of the question, and in<lb/>his reply referred to the speech he made<lb/>before he (Mr. H.) voted for the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor's salary. He (Mr. H.) in doing so<lb/>protested against the injustice of the<lb/>
          
          
            <cb/>
    

     <fw type="dateline">1870</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">249</fw>       
 
 
     demand, and gave satisfactory reasons 
     <lb/>for the vote he gave. He did not wish<lb/>the British Government to have the<lb/>shadow of a reason which could be laid<lb/>hold of as an argument for forcing this<lb/>Island into a union with the Dominion,<lb/>and felt his reasons for voting as he did<lb/>would bear examination. Yielding on<lb/>that point took away the only plea which<lb/>could be urged. We were but a small<lb/>body of people, nor did he mean to say<lb/>we had much influence ; but we had<lb/>rights, and when we coupled those with<lb/>the benefits which were conferred upon<lb/>the other provinces, he thought the<lb/>Home Government would not coerce us.<lb/>Troops were left among them, where<lb/>they spent a great deal of money, but<lb/>when they came here, in one sense, we<lb/>were treated like strangers, and were<lb/>called upon to pay the last [illegible]<lb/>which the presence of the soldiers here<lb/>cost. The Home Government had small<lb/>claim on the gratitude of the people of<lb/>the Island, nor had it a claim to one<lb/>inch of the soil, and where was the man<lb/>who, knowing his rights would not de<lb break="no"/>fend them? Should a coercive policy be<lb/>resorted to, our moral obligations to the<lb/>Home Government, he feared would<lb/>now be regarded as small. Reference<lb/>had been made to the union of Scotland<lb/>and Ireland in the minutes of Council,<lb/>He thought such reference unnecessary.<lb/>The union of Scotland, with England<lb/>was more natural. Was it the Tweed<lb/>which separated them? The Scotch were<lb/>simply Saxons, growing corn upon a<lb/>poorer soil than those who lived in Eng<lb break="no"/>land. That they should unite was there<lb break="no"/>fore more natural than that they should<lb/>be separated . but when it was said that<lb/>Scotland's prosperity was owing to her<lb/>union with England, he must demur<lb/>against such an assertion, because it<lb/>was not strictly true. He admitted that<lb/>the result had practically benefitted the<lb/>people on both sides of the border, be<lb break="no"/>cause it put a stop to their feuds. Scotch<lb break="no"/>men, as such, at that time, had, in self-<lb break="yes"/>defence, on account of the frequent<lb/>inroads of the English, to be constantly<lb/>armed, and that was a tax upon their<lb/>time, and a drawback to their prosperity<lb/>but in so for as England was concerned,<lb/>she had but to turn the swords she used<lb/>so unjustly against Scotchmen, into<lb/>ploughshares. When due allowance was<lb/>made for those considerations, Scotland's<lb/>inherit native energy of her sons.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> agreed with the hon. 
     <lb/>gentleman on that point.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName>.—The things to 
               <lb/>which he referred, with the introduction of<lb/>a better and purer system of governing the<lb/>country, and administering the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> all in<lb/>the course of time, contributed to make Scot<lb break="no"/>land what this was. But this Island had<lb/>never been at war with Nova Scotia or<lb/>New Brunswick, and there were no feuds<lb/>to put down. What surprised him (Mr.<lb/>H.) most was to hear the hon. member for<lb/>Charlottetown say that Parliament, while<lb/>it existed, could do that which was really<lb/>morally right or wrong, just <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>and yes. all it might thus do, would be law<lb break="no"/>ful ! That was that Parliament had power<lb/>to turn the constitution upside down!<lb/>and the hon. the leader of the Opposition<lb/>repeated what the hon. member (Mr.B.)<lb/>said. If that was the case, then the respon<lb break="no"/>sibilities of this hon. committee, were little<lb/>more than that of a debating club, But<lb/>he contended that Parliament had not such<lb/>powers. He also argued that even if what<lb/>the Parliament of Nova Scotia did was con<lb break="no"/>stitutional, still there was a difference be<lb break="no"/>tween her and us ; for her representation<lb/>were not pledged as we had hoped, at the<lb/>polls. But as soon as the people in Nova<lb/>Scotia could, when they heard what was<lb/>doing, they sent 183 petitions in against<lb/>the measure. And when the general elec<lb break="no"/>tion took place, the result showed how<lb/>opposed the people were to it. The act of<lb/>Nova Scotia's representatives was a political<lb/>wrong, and what was a political wrong<lb/>could never be made out to be righ. In<lb/>reference to the general question, he<lb/>thought if the they took into consideration the<lb/>acknowledged state of the Dominion ex<lb break="no"/>chequer and they acknowledged policy of<lb/>the Canadian government, with the fact 
     <lb/>that the estimates for the year, if they 
     <lb/>were not misrepresented— setting aside 
     <lb/>the construction of the Intercolonial Rail<lb break="no"/>road, and other public works—it would be 
     <lb/>a suicidal bet for us to give up on our present 
     <lb/>position to unite with the Dominion   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.— With respect to Nova 
     <lb/>Scotia, the people were dissatisfied because<lb/>they had not bee treated as they were in<lb/>New Brunswick. He had no doubt but the<lb/>result in each Province would have been<lb/>the same had the same course been adopted.<lb/>Some of the ablest and best minds in Nova<lb/>Scotia were in favor of confederation.<lb/>Mr. Johnston, one of the ablest men in<lb/>those colonies, when in the Legislature,<lb/>favored the principle ; and all knew that<lb/>
       
       
            <pb n="250" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_250.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">250</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1870</fw>
          
          
     Chief Justice Young was a unionist. The 
     <lb/>main reason why the question had not been<lb/>submitted to the people at the polls was,<lb/>because of the feeling which then existed<lb/>against Mr. Tupper, on account of their<lb/>education act. And in so far as his re<lb break="no"/>election was concerned, that, and not con<lb break="no"/>federation, it was that turned the people<lb/>against him. Again, there was Mr. Howe ;<lb/>he had accepted the situation, and was<lb/>returned by the people to represent them<lb/>in the Dominion parliament, Mr. Archi<lb break="no"/>bald had also been lately returned, although<lb/>at first they were so opposed to him. He<lb/>(Mr. B.) thought, when all these facts were<lb/>duly considered, it would be admitted that<lb/>it was not opposition to a union with Can<lb break="no"/>ada, but the manner in which they were<lb/>treated, that led to the feeling which had<lb/>been evoked in Nova Scotia.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACA1">Hon. Mr. MACAULAY</persName> did not think the 
     <lb/>conclusion drawn from Nova Scotia's his<lb break="no"/>tory, in her connection with confederation,<lb/>was legitimate. She struggled to free her<lb break="no"/>self from the yoke imposed upon her, and<lb/>being unable to succeed, had to make up<lb/>her mind either to accept, and make the<lb/>best of her position, or choose sedition and<lb/>look to Washington. Her people and gov<lb break="no"/>ernment chose the former, and acted<lb/>wisely in choosing and sending their best<lb/>men to represent them in the Dominion<lb/>parliament. With Nova Scotia it was<lb/>choosing the least of two evils.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:JENK1">Dr. JENKINS</persName>, ever since he had a seat in 
     <lb/>this House, had been careful not to make<lb/>any statement which he could not substanti<lb break="no"/>ate. He had been charged by a member of the<lb/>Government, with saying what was not true,<lb/>
     when he (Dr. J.) stated that the government 
     <lb/>here had taken the land question out of the<lb/>hands of the Dominion government. The<lb/>hon. Colonial Secretary, however, had ad<lb break="no"/>mitted that his (Dr. J's) view of the case<lb/>was correct, when he (Col. Secy.) said that<lb/>the Home government had rejected the<lb/>method of settling the question set forth in<lb/>the Minute of Council. How could the<lb/>hon. member from Wilmot Creek, then,<lb/>make the charge which he did, when his<lb/>colleague in the government not only cor<lb break="no"/>roborated what he (Dr. J.) stated, but said<lb/>he was proud that the Colonial Minister had<lb/>written about the land question as he had<lb/>done! But he would give an illustration to<lb/>convince the hon. member from Wilmot<lb/>Creek that he was in error. Supposing<lb/>that he had a claim against a man, and was<lb/>to write to him that unless it was settled at<lb/>a certain time, he would take some other<lb/>course to collect it, would not that take<lb/>
          
          
            <cb/>
         
         
     the case out of the hands of the Solicitor? 
     <lb/>In the same way the Island government<lb/>had taken the land question out of the<lb/>hands of the Canadian government. We<lb/>could not expect them now to exert their<lb/>influence with the Home Government in the<lb/>matter. He (Dr. J.) might also state that<lb/>he did not look upon the offer of $800,000,<lb/>by the Dominion Cabinet, as in any way<lb/>compromising us if it were accepted. It<lb/>was offered as a free gift. We had never<lb/>asked them for it; they simply said that if<lb/>the British government would not grant any<lb/>compensation to the colony for the loss of<lb/>territorial revenues, they would give us<lb/>$800,000. The hon. member for New<lb/>London, (P. Sinclair) had said, that were<lb/>we in the union we would pay double the<lb/>taxes we did at present. He (Dr. J.) could<lb/>not allow such a statement to pass un<lb break="no"/>noticed. The tariff of the Dominion would<lb/>not raise anything like the revenue for<lb/>them out of the Island, which was raised<lb/>now by our present tariff, at least for the<lb/>first five years. With the facilities for<lb/>smuggling which existed around our coast,<lb/>he did not believe the Canadians would<lb/>collect half the revenue here with their<lb/>tariff, which was done now with out 11 per<lb/>cent.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName> thought this Island<lb/>could not calculate to gain much by her<lb/>facilities for smuggling; Nova Scotia had<lb/>the same facilities, and what advantage<lb/>were they to her.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCMI3">Mr. McMILLAN</persName> could not see any<lb/>benefit this Island would derive from<lb/>confederation. If he thought it would<lb/>be any advantage to the country he<lb/>would support it. Nova Scotia and<lb/>New Brunswick, he knew a little about,<lb/>and he thought we were better off than<lb/>the people of those Provinces. Our<lb/>roads and bridges were better than theirs,<lb/>and indeed almost everything we had.<lb/>He had travelled from Gaspe all the way<lb/>to Halifax, and saw nothing in that ex<lb break="no"/>tent of country to compare to this Island.<lb/>Upper Canada, he knew little about;<lb/>but he had lived in both New Brunswick<lb/>and Lower Canada for a number of<lb/>years, and he was somewhat able to<lb/>judge of them. We raised more crops<lb/>than the Dominion, taking it through;<lb/>nearly as much as Upper Canada did,<lb/>and more than the other Provinces.<lb/>With respect to the $800,000 offer, he<lb/>valued it as nothing, for the politicians<lb/>of the Dominion might very soon take<lb/>it out of us again. He had asked a<lb/>little money for Summerside to procure<lb/>
           
           
   
   
          
          
     <fw type="dateline">1870</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">251</fw> 
   
   
       safes required in some of the public<lb/>offices, and some other person had added<lb/>handcuffs. (Laughter); but the hon.<lb/>member for Charlottetown immediately<lb/>inquired if we had not received a sum of<lb/>money to purchase a square. That<lb/>would be pretty much the fate of this<lb/>Colony at Ottawa; if our members were<lb/>to ask for some grant, the Canadians<lb/>would rise and say that the Island had<lb/>for $800,000, and what more did she<lb/>want? Reference had been made to<lb/>Scotland; and he (Mr. McM.) did not<lb/>deny that she had received benefit from<lb/>her union with England. But the rea<lb break="no"/>son was that John Ball happened to be<lb/>a warring sort of person, and would be<lb/>crossing the border, and so the Scotch<lb break="no"/>men had to fight to prevent him.<lb/>Scotland, however, in many respects,<lb/>was not so well off as this Island. He<lb/>(Mr. McM.) had lived in that country<lb/>until he was fourteen years of age, and<lb/>he had travelled a great part of it since.<lb/>In many places there were neither roads<lb/>nor bridges; and towards the West of<lb/>Scotland you might go twenty miles or<lb/>so at a time, and see nothing but sheep,<lb/>sheep, and dogs. (Laughter.) You<lb/>would find it difficult to raise an army<lb/>of soldiers in many parts of that country<lb/>now. He had been across to Ireland,<lb/>likewise, and in a very rough season,<lb/>the year 1842. They had pretty hard<lb/>times there, too, and especially in sup<lb break="no"/>porting a church which they did not<lb/>attend, and the houses of worship be<lb break="no"/>longing to which would be seen on<lb/>Sunday with two or three people in<lb/>them. If Ireland had had no grievance,<lb/>in the way the church was supported,<lb/>would Gladstone have taken up the<lb/>question? The land grievance was also<lb/>pretty severely felt in Ireland; many of<lb/>the proprietors lived in England, and<lb/>the rent was consequently taken out of<lb/>the country, and the people had to<lb/>follow to dig canals, and do other work.<lb/>He (Mr. McM.) had made a calculation<lb/>about our lands, as to the loss we had<lb/>sustained by having them taken from us,<lb/>and he thought we should receive about<lb/>three million dollars instead of $800,000,<lb/>to compensate for that loss. If our<lb/>lands had been left to us, we might, by<lb/>this time, have had a railway from East<lb/>Point to West Cape. If the present<lb/>government were only left in power for<lb/>a few years longer, he believed the<lb/>Island would become like Jerusalem in<lb/>the days of Solomon—gold would be<lb/>as plenty as stones in the streets.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>(Laughter.) We had heard a great deal<lb/>about the Tenant League; but he be<lb break="no"/>lieved that nothing made tenant, or any<lb/>other leagues, except bad government.<lb/>Hon. Joseph Howe had been frequently<lb/>referred to in this debate; well he (Mr.<lb/>McM.) did not think much of him; if he<lb/>had not been bought himself he had sold<lb/>us about the land commission. (Laugh<lb break="no"/>ter.) With respect to the confederate<lb/>members of the House, he (Mr. McM.)<lb/>did not wish to say as much. He had al<lb break="no"/>ways been a Liberal himself. There<lb/>was the hon. leader of the Opposition—a<lb/>red-hot confederate; but for all that he<lb/>(Mr. McM.) did not believe he would<lb/>sell his country. However, supposing<lb/>he were to turn round, we would be<lb/>glad to have him on our side. With<lb/>respect to the hon. member for Char<lb break="no"/>lottetown (Mr. Brecken), it was said that<lb/>he had changed his opinions from what<lb/>they were at the time he stood on the<lb/>hustings. He (Mr. McM.) did not know<lb/>whether it was so or not. It had been<lb/>said that on account of this change in<lb/>his opinions, the hon. member should<lb/>resign; that would be too much to ex<lb break="no"/>pect him to do; but if a majority of his<lb/>constituents were to ask him to give up<lb/>his seat, he (Mr. McM.) believed the<lb/>hon. member had too much noble spirit<lb/>about him not to comply with their re<lb break="no"/>quest. He (Mr. McM.) had not changed<lb/>his opinions on confederation yet, but<lb/>he might do so some day. It would be<lb/>natural to expect that some Antis would<lb/>turn after the long speeches they had<lb/>heard from the other side of the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName>.— The hon. member<lb/>had referred to the Tenant League; as<lb/>their friends were in power now, would<lb/>the hon. member state what they had<lb/>done for the league?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCMI3">Mr. MCMILLAN</persName> was prepared to sup<lb break="no"/>port any measure that was calculated to<lb/>do them good. He believed they were<lb/>respectable people. He met both parties<lb/>one night, the leaguers and the force<lb/>that was pursuing them, and the leaguers<lb/>were the better behaved of the two.<lb/>The constables almost dragged him out<lb/>of his wagon; and had it not been for<lb/>the respectable person they had for<lb/>High Sheriff, he supposed they would<lb/>have shot him, for he would have been<lb/>shot before he would have given up.<lb/>They took into custody some of the most<lb/>honest men in the country, and many of<lb/>their deeds were most discreditable than<lb/>those of the leaguers.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <pb n="252" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_252.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="num">252</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER. 1807</fw>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>-->
            <fw type="num">1870</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER. 253</fw>
          <div type="section"> 
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Confederation.</head>
             
            <p>House in committee on the further<lb/>consideration of despatches.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GREE5">Mr. GREEN</persName> rose to speak a few words 
     <lb/>on the all-important question of confed<lb break="no"/>eration, but felt himself unable to do 
     <lb/>that justice to the subject which its im<lb break="no"/>portance demanded.  It had been so 
     <lb/>long before the committee, and so many 
     <lb/>speeches had been made on it, that it 
     <lb/>was almost impossible to find any new 
     <lb/>matter; but as it was a question in 
     <lb/>which great interests were involved, and 
     <lb/>a very large extent of country concerned, 
     <lb/>there migh be some points of interest 
     <lb/>which had not yet been referred to. He 
     <lb/>(Mr. G.) would first refer to the minutes  
     <lb/>of Council, as in them reference was 
     <lb/>made to the discontent prevailing in 
     <lb/>New Brunswick and Nova Scotia, which  
     <lb/>now formed part of the Dominion. It  
     <lb/>had been said that  as Nova Scotia did 
     <lb/>not join the union, by the consent of the 
     <lb/>people, it should now be freed from that 
     <lb/>union, but according to the same argu<lb break="no"/>ment, those counties of New Brunswick 
     <lb/>that did not vote in favor of confedera<lb break="no"/>tion should  be freed. Those provinces 
     <lb/>had been estranged so long, separ<lb break="no"/>ated by hostile tariffs, having little or no 
     <lb/>communication, no intercoloninl free 
     <lb/>trade, that it could hardly be expected 
     <lb/>that in so short a time, they would settle 
     <lb/>down to the new order of things, and be 
     <lb/>altogether contented. A great deal had  
     <lb/>been said about the people of Canada—  
     <lb/>their statesmen in particular had come 
     <lb/>in for a large share of abuse during this 
     <lb/>discussion, they had been represented as 
     <lb/>almost unfit to govern the country. But 
     <lb/>what were the facts of the case? Can<lb break="no"/>ada, before the union, was the most 
     <lb/>enterprising and progressive of the Brit<lb break="no"/>
         
         
            <pb n="254" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_254.jpg"/>
          
          
          <fw type="num">254</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1870</fw>
         
         
     ish American provinces. They had a 
     <lb/>great deal to contend with; they had to<lb/>expend large sums of money in opening<lb/>up the resources of the country, they<lb/>had built most magnificent canals- the<lb/>most magnificent in the world.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACA1">Hon. Mr. MACAULAY</persName>.- No, they had<lb/>not.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GREE5">Mr. GREEN</persName>.- The canals of Europe<lb/>were mere ditches compared with those<lb/>of Canada. They had opened up those<lb/>canals, which, with their great inland<lb/>seas, would monopolize the greatest part<lb/>of the carrying trade of Canada, and<lb/>also a very large portion of the trade of<lb/>the United States. It was stated by<lb/>scientific men, that the Missouri and<lb/>Mississippi rivers were fast filling up,<lb/>and when whole trade would have to<lb/>flow through the canals of Canada. It<lb/>had been said that the maritime pro<lb break="no"/>vinces would not participate in the ad<lb break="no"/>vantages resulting from this trade, but<lb/>this was a mistake, for if this trade was<lb/>opened up to our ships, we must reap<lb/>some benefit. Then, again, the North<lb break="no"/>west Territory was capable of maintain<lb break="no"/>ing a population of twenty millions, and<lb/>when it became settled, there would be<lb/>a large increase in the trade through the<lb/>Canadian canals. The disturbance in<lb/>the North-west had been mentioned in<lb/>the minute of Council as an obstacle to<lb/>union, but he (Mr. Green) looked upon<lb/>that disturbance as a mere "tempest in<lb/>a teapot." A great deal had been said<lb/>about the way in which Nova Scotia had<lb/>been pitchforked into confederation; but<lb/>it appeared that Nova Scotia was now<lb/>perfectly willing to lend a helping hand<lb/>in opening up the resources of the coun<lb break="no"/>try. British North Americans had a<lb/>country which was capable of becoming<lb/>a great nationality. Its resources were<lb/>almost unlimited. It had the finest coal<lb/>fields in the world, and they were so<lb/>near the seaboard, that the coal might<lb/>almost be shovelled into vessels. Coal,<lb/>for manufacturing purposes, could be<lb/>procured in Nova Scotia for one dollar<lb/>per ton, which was cheaper than it could<lb/>be obtained in any other country. There<lb/>was also an abundance of iron in the<lb/>
         
         
            <cb/>
         
         
         Dominion, and the iron of Nova Scotia<lb/>was superior to the far-famed Swedish<lb/>iron, which cost as much for transporta<lb break="no"/>tion to the sea coast, as the Nova Scotia<lb/>iron could be procured for. In Canada,<lb/>there were mountains of iron that would<lb/>supply the market of the world for the<lb/>next century. British America had all<lb/>the minerals that were useful to man;<lb/>it contained immense forests, its fisher<lb break="no"/>ies were the best in the world, and it<lb/>was inhabited by as fine a race of man<lb/>as could be found in any part of the<lb/>globe. He (Mr. G.) believed that Brit<lb break="no"/>ish America was destined to run the<lb/>race of the Empire, and if the people were<lb/>determined to settle down as separate<lb/>communities, they would be like a man<lb/>sitting down in a crowded street to try to<lb/>stop the throng of people. By uniting<lb/>all the provinces, a country would be<lb/>built up which would be the means of<lb/>preserving British institutions on this<lb/>continent, and handing them down to<lb/>posterity. It was an acknowledged<lb/>principle that union was strength, and<lb/>since the first union was consummated in<lb/>the Garden of Eden, that principle had<lb/>a powerful influence on the human<lb/>family. Much fault had been found by<lb/>hon members with the constitution of<lb/>the Dominion, but that constitution,<lb/>drawn up by the statesmen of the differ<lb break="no"/>ent Provinces, P. E. Island included,<lb/>had been shown to some of the greatest<lb/>statesmen of the world, and was pro<lb break="no"/>nounced a masterpiece of statesmanship.<lb/>The people of Canada were an educated<lb/>people; they enjoyed the advantages of<lb/>Responsible Government; and if the<lb/>present parliament was corrupt, they<lb/>would never return them again to power.<lb/>(Hear, hear.) Fault had been found<lb/>with the representation we would have<lb/>in the Dominion Parliament, but the<lb/>principle of representation was one<lb/>adopted by the United States - that<lb/>country to which some hon members<lb/>took great pleasure in referring- and<lb/>was found to work well, and he (Mr. G.)<lb/>believed it to be a sound principle. He<lb/>(Mr. G.) attributed the great prosperity<lb/>of the United States to union, for if each<lb/>state had remained separated from the<lb/>
          
          
          
          
          
          
          <fw type="dateline">1870</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">255</fw>
         
         
         rest, and a duty would have to be paid<lb/>on manufactured articles as soon as taken<lb/>over the lines, manufactures would never<lb/>have flourished. The hon member for<lb/>Georgetown (Mr. McAulay) had stated<lb/>that the late rebellion in the United<lb/>States was chargeable to union, but he<lb/>(Mr. G.) was of quite a different opinion.<lb/>One great cause of that rebellion was<lb/>slavery; and another was the diversity<lb/>of interests on account of the great extent<lb/>of their country. The South were as<lb/>different from the North as any two<lb/>nations. The southern people were not<lb/>much engaged in manufactures, and they<lb/>argued that they had a right to sell in<lb/>the dearest markets and buy in the<lb/>cheapest. If British North America<lb/>stood in the same position as the United<lb/>States, he (Mr. G.) would never advocate<lb/>union, for they could never be bound<lb/>together. They had one rebellion, and<lb/>he feared it was not the last. Anti-con<lb break="no"/>federates were in the habit of belittling<lb/>Canada; they called it a narrow belt,<lb/>and spoke of the extensive frontier that<lb/>would have to be defended in case of<lb/>invasion; but on this frontier there were<lb/>forests where an army might wander as<lb/>long as the children of Israel did in the<lb/>wilderness; and, besides, the United<lb/>States had enough to settle among them<lb break="no"/>selves without taking British America.<lb/>A line of communication from the West<lb break="no"/>ern shore to the Red River country would<lb/>open up a vast territory, which was<lb/>capable of sustaining ten millions of in<lb break="no"/>habitants. The valley of the Saskat<lb break="no"/>chewan was eight hundred miles long,<lb/>and one hundred and eighty miles wide.<lb/>The land there would grow forty bushels<lb/>of wheat per acre; and there were also<lb/>grown flax and hemp and tobacco. As<lb/>this great country became settle,d there<lb/>would be great demand for manufactures,<lb/>which would be supplied by the maritime<lb/>provinces. The interests of all the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces were so mixed up that he (Mr.<lb/>G.) did not see how they could remain<lb/>separated. If we remained in our isolated<lb/>position, the Dominion could shut their<lb/>gates against our products, and thus<lb/>cripple our trade. The hon member<lb/>from Belfast (Mr. Duncan) said that<lb/>
         
         
            <cb/>
    

    Nova Scotia and New Brunswick were<lb/>going to grow all they required for<lb/>themselves, as they were agricultural<lb/>countries; but the present government<lb/>had sent a delegation to Washington to<lb/>try and open up a trade with the United<lb/>States, and it was one of the greatest<lb/>agricultural countries in the world. He<lb/>(Mr. G.) well remembered the time when<lb/>all the ports between here and New<lb/>York were filled with every description<lb/>of eatables produced by the United<lb/>States, not excepting wooden hams and<lb/>nutmegs. But now we were anxiously<lb/>seeking a market for our products in the<lb/>United States. What had caused the<lb/>change? The vast increase in the popu<lb break="no"/>lation of the seaport downs of Massachu<lb break="no"/>setts, Rhode Island, and New York.<lb/>Those States were like a beehive, and<lb/>foreigners were flocking in from all parts<lb/>of the world, and now they were import<lb break="no"/>ing Chinese workmen. In Great Britain,<lb/>which was over-peopled, we heard of<lb/>riots, but the law was strong enough to<lb/>suppress them; but in the United States,<lb/>as soon as it became densley populated,<lb/>they would have riots also; but as they<lb/>had a free franchise, and so many for<lb break="no"/>eigners in their country, the case would<lb/>be very different. Before that time<lb/>came, it behoved British Americans to<lb/>look to their safety. A great deal had<lb/>been said about the union of England and<lb/>Scotland, and Ireland and England; but<lb/>although they united under very un<lb break="no"/>favourable circumstances, they had fought<lb/>together, and become almost masters of<lb/>the world. They had maintained their<lb/>institutions, the freest and best institu<lb break="no"/>tions in the world; and would any person<lb/>say they would have risen to such great<lb break="no"/>ness had they not been united? They<lb/>counted their ships by thousands; their<lb/>sails whitened every sea, and their flag<lb/>was unfurled on every ocean. He (Mr.<lb/>G.) was prepared to make sacrifices to<lb/>maintain British institutions. His was<lb/>no lip-loyalty; neither did he carry his<lb/>loyalty in his pocket. Britain had given<lb/>us a constitution in common with the<lb/>other provinces. She now wished us to<lb/>unite under one government, and it was<lb/>only reasonable for us to pay respect to<lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="256" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_256.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">256</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1870</fw>
         
         
     the wishes of the Imperial authorities. 
     <lb/>
      Something had been said about the out<lb break="no"/>lying portions of a country not partici<lb break="no"/>pating in the benefits of the general<lb/>government; but in the United States 
     <lb/>those territories two thousand miles from 
     <lb/>the seat of government were just as well 
     <lb/>satisfied with the doings of Congress as<lb/>any other portion of the country. Mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the House of Commons of the 
     <lb/>Dominion were now returned from Nova 
     <lb/>Scotia, New Brunswick, and Canada ; 
     <lb/>but soon the dividing lines would be 
     <lb/>obliterated, and members of parliament 
     <lb/>would feel that they represented, not one 
     <lb/>particular section, but the whole of 
     <lb/>British America. As regarded Prince 
     <lb/>Edward Island, an offer had been made 
     <lb/>before the last election, and the present 
     <lb/>party in power had raised a great cry 
     <lb/>against the Canadians. They represented 
     <lb/>the Canadians as being the most <choice><sic>intol<lb break="no"/>lerable</sic><corr>intolerable</corr></choice> people in the world. Had he 
     <lb/>(Mr. G) been a member of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment that raised such a cry against the 
     <lb/>Canadians, he would have told those who 
     <lb/>came as a delegation last summer that he 
     <lb/>would have nothing to do with them ; 
     <lb/>that would have been antlng consistently. 
     <lb/>But the present government had enter<lb break="no"/>tained the question, the had debated 
     <lb/>it with closed doors, and a member of 
     <lb/>the government in the other end of the 
     <lb/>Building, had stated at the opening of 
     <lb/>the session, that what took place in that 
     <lb/>secret Council should be laid before the  
     <lb/>House, but it had not been done. It 
     <lb/>was said that some of the members of 
     <lb/>the government went to the country 
     <lb/>bursting with confederation, and he (Mr 
     <lb/>G.) heard same of them utter senti<lb break="no"/>ments which they denied in this House. 
     <lb/>Unfortunately for them, however, they 
     <lb/>had penned the minutes of Council 
     <lb/>which had been referred to so often, and 
     <lb/>if it were those minutes of Council that 
     <lb/>were before the House, he (Mr. G.) 
     <lb/>would vote for them, for they breathed 
     <lb/> as strong confederate views as pen could 
     <lb/>on paper. Settle the land question and 
     <lb/> there would be a " spontaneous reaction" 
     <lb/>from one end of the Island to the other, 
     <lb/>was the assertion made in the minute of 
     <lb/>Council, but now they said that meant 
     <lb/>nothing. It would be better for the 
     <lb/>government to make a clean breast or 
     <lb/>affair, endlet the pen is know the 
     <lb/>conclusions they came to in that secret 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <cb/>
           
           
     Council. The government thought to 
     <lb/>
     move around quietly, and feel the public 
     <lb/>pulse before giving an expression of<lb/>opinion, and if the people were in favor<lb/>of confederation, they would have <choice><sic>car<lb break="no"/>red</sic><corr>carried</corr></choice> it. But the people were not in favor<lb/>of it. The press took their views from<lb/>an unscrupulous opposition in Canada,<lb/>and everything that would tell against<lb/>confederation was brought to the notice<lb/>of the public, so that a strong prejudice<lb/>against union was created in the minds<lb/>of the people. Irrespective of creed or<lb/>party, all should view this great question<lb/>impartially, and if it could be shown<lb/>that confederation would increase our<lb/>trade, and develop our resources, we<lb/>should not throw cold water on the<lb/>scheme, but wish it God speed. He<lb/>(Mr. G.) did not wish, however, to press<lb/>his views on the people of the Island,<lb/>he entertained his own opinions, and<lb/>let every person do the same. He be<lb break="no"/>lieved in the consolidation of British<lb/>America; union would knock down the<lb/>barriers to commerce, and open up a<lb/>trade with four millions of people, and<lb/>if proper arrangements could be made, a<lb/>fair proportion of the revenue obtained<lb/>for public works, and a railroad built on<lb/>the Island, if the people could make up<lb/>their minds to accept confederation, it<lb/>would be for their benefit. We could<lb/>send our produce to the markets of the<lb/>Dominion in a few days, while it would<lb/>take months to send to England; and he<lb/>(Mr. G.) believed the day was not far<lb/>distant when it would tax our capabi<lb break="no"/>lities to the utmost to supply their<lb/>markets.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName> would leave the 
     <lb/>members of the government to reply to<lb/>the remarks of the last speaker, which<lb/>referred to them, but he thought he<lb/>could satisfy the committee that some<lb/>of the hon. member's arguments, in<lb/>favor of confederation, rested on a very<lb/>sandy foundation. He (Mr. Green)<lb/>stated that under confederation our ships<lb/>would share in the trade of the canals of<lb/>Canada, but he (Mr. D.) contended that<lb/>our ships would not be shut out of those<lb/>canals whether we joined Canada or not.<lb/>He (Mr. Green) also wished all those<lb/>provinces to be united, because they<lb/>were in the same latitude, but that was<lb/>an argument against union, for they<lb/>would produce the same kind of crops,<lb/>and there would not be the same inter<lb break="no"/>change of productions as if they were in<lb/>different climates. He (Mr. D.) did not<lb/>know what we were to send to Red<lb/>
          
          
         
         
     <fw type="dateline">1870</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">257</fw> 
  
  
     River; the hon. member (Mr. Green) 
     <lb/>
     should have informed the House. The 
     <lb/>hon. member (Mr. Green) had made a<lb/>great glory argument; the idea of be<lb break="no"/>longing to a large country seemed to<lb/>have great weight with him, and paying<lb/>for the privilege was nothing at all. He<lb/>(Mr. Green) stated that every country<lb/>that confederated, prospered, but Bel<lb break="no"/>gium and Holland united, and they<lb/>could not agree at all.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>—Religions was 
     <lb/>the cause of their disagreement, the<lb/>northern portion was a strong Protes<lb break="no"/>tant country, and Belgium was an ultra<lb break="no"/>montane Catholic country.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName>—We were also 
     <lb/>told that Canada had the largest canals<lb/>in the world. He (Mr. D.) thought that<lb/>the Suez canal, which would take a ship<lb/>drawing eighteen feet of water, and was<lb/>wide enough to allow two vessels to<lb/>pass, was the largest in the world. He<lb/>(Mr. Green) also referred to the United<lb/>States, and said that Rhode Island had<lb/>only one representative in Congress, but<lb/>he forgot to tell that she had two in the<lb/>Senate, so that in the Senate, little Rhode<lb/>Island had the same representation as<lb/>New York. The Senators in the United<lb/>States were not nominated by Congress,<lb/>but chosen by the Representatives of the<lb/>State, so that they were a check on the<lb/>Lower House, but in Canada the Sena<lb break="no"/>tors were chosen by the government,<lb/>and the representation was by popula<lb break="no"/>tion both in the upper and lower branch<lb/>of the Legislature. The last speaker<lb/>also referred to the manufactures that<lb/>Canada would require, but had it never<lb/>occurred to him that Canada West was<lb/>as good a manufacturing country as<lb/>Nova Scotia or New Brunswick. If the<lb/>Mississippi river was to be closed up,<lb/>would they bring cotton down to Nova<lb/>Scotia to be manufactured. And poor<lb/>Prince Edward Island could never be a<lb/>manufacturing country, because it was<lb/>shut out the rest of the world for<lb/>five months in the year. If the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion put a tax on our produce, as it was<lb/>expected, we had nothing to fear, for<lb/>our pork would bring two cents a pound<lb/>more than theirs, and it was probable<lb/>we should find a market for our potatoes<lb/>in the United States. Oats were, at the<lb/>present time, worth only sixteen pence<lb/>half penny in New Brunswick, and let<lb break="no"/>ters had been received from there, send<lb break="no"/>ing for vessels to take them away.<lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GREE5">Mr. GREEN</persName>.—As regarded the canals      
     <lb/>of Canada, he would assert it broadly<lb/>that they were the best in the world.<lb/>The Americans wanted the right to get<lb/>through them, and if the trade of the<lb/>Great West came down that way, those<lb/>canals on the route would pay 15 or 20<lb/>per cent. A person whose mind was so narrow<lb/>that he could not judge of these<lb/>things was not fit to argue about them.<lb/>A great part of the grain which came<lb/>down the canals in the canal boats to New<lb/>York was not fit to ship, a waste that could<lb/>be prevented by sending it down through<lb/>this canals of Canada in vessels, without<lb/>breaking bulk. He contended that the<lb/>capital expended on the Dominion canals<lb/>would yet become productive capital.<lb/>The hon. member for Belfast, (Mr.<lb/>Duncan) had asked what trade we could<lb/>have with the Great West? Let him ask<lb/>the sea-board States, what their trade was<lb/>with that great country. The Western<lb/>States, in his (Mr. G's.) opinion, could<lb/>not begin to manufacture in comparison<lb/>with Nova Scotia, and one reason of this<lb/>was because of the expense of taking up<lb/>coal.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName> said the Confederates 
     <lb/>did not pay any attention to taxes or the<lb/>price of pork or oats. All they wanted<lb/>was the glory of belonging to a big<lb/>country, but he was content to live on<lb/>our own little Island, and had no wish<lb/>to go up to Ottawa.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName> rose merely to reply 
     <lb/>to the charge made by the hon member,<lb/>Mr. Green, against the government, as<lb/>the arguments in favor of confederation<lb/>advanced by that hon member had<lb/>already been answered by the hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber from Belfast (Mr. Duncan.) The<lb/>cry was that the government sat with<lb/>close doors with the delegates from the<lb/>Dominion, but the statement of the dele<lb break="no"/>gates themselves was sufficient to refute<lb/>that—they "had an opportunity of dis<lb break="no"/>cussing informally with members of the<lb/>Government and other public men" this<lb/>great question. The fact was, the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment never sat as a government with<lb/>the delegates. The hon member (Mr.<lb/>Green) said the Dominion was sparsely<lb/>populated, and they had to be heavily<lb/>taxed to purchase the Red River territory,<lb/>and he thought it a legitimate question<lb/>to ask what benefit Red River would be<lb/>to us. If it was the country it was re<lb break="no"/>presented to be, we should not be able to<lb/>export anything to it. We were asked<lb/>
        
        
            <pb n="258" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-14_Page_258.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">258</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1870</fw>
      
      
     to join a country and submit to taxation 
     <lb/>
     to conquer a province that was united to 
     <lb/>
     them without their consent, and to be 
     <lb/>governed by men who were unfit to rule<lb/>any country. The hon member had<lb/>predicted that the members of the present<lb/>government would never be returned to<lb/>the House, because they appended their<lb/>names to the Minute of Council, and that<lb/>this Minute of Council committed the<lb/>Island to confederation. But the very<lb/>first words of the Minute of Council<lb/>were: - <lb/>
            </p>
             
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" Inasmuch as the said terms do not comprise<lb/>a full and immediate settlement of the land<lb/>tenures, and indemnity from the Imperial<lb/>government fro loss of territorial revenues, the<lb/>committee cannot recommend said terms to the<lb/>consideration of their constituents."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
             
             
            <p>Was it an expression of approval to say<lb/>they could not recommend the terms<lb/>even to the people's consideration ?<lb/>Another paragraph read as follows:-<lb/>
            </p>
             
             <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" The opinion of the people of this Island on 
     <lb/>the question of union has been expressed by<lb/>them, in the most decisive language, as opposed<lb/>to any union with the Dominion. This opinion<lb/>the Council has no reason to believe has been<lb/>changed, and therefore conceives it is unne<lb break="no"/>cessary for them to enter into any other details<lb/>to which they believe many valid and serious<lb/>objections are entertained."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     There were the sentiments expressed by 
     <lb/>the members of the government, and it<lb/>was said they would never be returned<lb/>to the House. By whom was such a<lb/>statement made? Surely he must be a<lb/>paragon of perfection. The immaculate<lb/>member censuring the government for<lb/>favoring confederation appeared to him<lb/>like Satan rebuking sin. He (Mr. L.)<lb/>would now look at another part of the<lb/>Minute of Council which confederates<lb/>were very fond of quoting :-<lb/>
            </p>
             
             <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"The Council can only further express a<lb/>hope that the government and parliament will<lb/>adopt this question (that is the Land Question)<lb/>as their own, and make such persistent and<lb/>powerful representations thereon to the Im<lb break="no"/>perial authorities as may result in obtaining<lb/>redress for this injured colony. Success would<lb/>be productive of the best results. It would<lb/>establish the prestige of the Dominion ; cause<lb/>a spontaneous, not an artificial reaction of<lb/>public opinion in Prince Edward Island."<lb/>(Hear, hear, from several hon members.)<lb/>
            </p></quote>
             
             
            <p>He would ask was it any harm to request<lb/>the Dominion Parliament to make the<lb/>Land Question of this Island their own?<lb/>And if they succeeded in settling it there<lb/>would be a great reaction in the feelings<lb/>of the people of this Island towards them.<lb/>They said they would settle the question,<lb/>and the government told them to do so.<lb/>It was used as an argument in favor of<lb/>confederation that the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>
         
         
            <cb/>
      
      ernment had so much more power with 
     <lb/>the British Parliament than we had, and<lb/>it was deemed advisable to test their<lb/>power. The result proved that they had<lb/>no more power than ourselves to settle<lb/>this long existing grievance. He (Mr.<lb/>L.) would challenge his hon member to<lb/>put his finger on any passage in the<lb/>Minute of Council to prove that the<lb/>government pledged themselves to accept<lb/>confederation, even had the Dominion<lb/>Government settled the Land Question.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> said the government<lb/>could not pledge themselves to that, but<lb/>they threw in their weight, and did all<lb/>they could.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>. - He (Mr. Brecken)<lb/>presumed so; and he (Mr. L.) presumed<lb/>he (Mr. B.) was a very bad judge. There<lb/>was not even a wish expressed ; it was<lb/>only giving them a chance to prove that<lb/>their pretended power was real, and had<lb/>they been honest statesmen, they would<lb/>have performed what they were asked<lb/>to do. It was states, in a speech delivered<lb/>in the Ottawa Parliament, but Sir John<lb/>A. McDonald, that the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment saw eye to eye with the Dominion<lb/>Government on the question of coercing<lb/>the people of Red River into submission<lb/>to the Canadian authorities. The British<lb/>Government had stained their escutcheon<lb/>when they forced their trade upon the<lb/>unwilling Chinese; and he (Mr. L.)<lb/>hoped we might never see their banner<lb/>unfurled to crush the free-born people of<lb/>Red River unless justice was first meted<lb/>out to them. He (Mr. L.) was sorry to<lb/>see the hon member for Charlottetown<lb/>(Mr. Brecken) desire that we should<lb/>join a country and pay taxes to a gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to help carry on a war against<lb/>another colony. The hon member (Mr.<lb/>Brecken) was willing to take the " Better<lb/>Terms, " with the addition of a railroad<lb/>from Summerside to Georgetown.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>. - So were you.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName> would deny the<lb/>change, and the hon member would have<lb/>to prove his accusation or stand convicted<lb/>of falsehood. We should be in a very<lb/>different position under confederation<lb/>from what we were now. Now the<lb/>members of the upper branch of our<lb/>parliament were chosen by the people,<lb/>but then they would be chosen by the<lb/>politicians of Canada.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> remarked that if<lb/>he had the same feelings against the<lb/>British Government as the hon member<lb/>who just sat down, he would not hold a<lb/>
    
    
    
     <fw type="dateline">1870</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">259</fw>
            </p>
            <p>seat in the Executive Government. The<lb/>hon member had also spoken very hard<lb/>against the Canadians ; but the truth<lb/>was, Canada had made rapid strides in<lb/>civilization, in agricultural progress, and<lb/>commercial prosperity. In 1841, when<lb/>the two Canadas were united, they had<lb/>not half the population they had at<lb/>present. With the difficulties of an un<lb break="no"/>happy situation to contend with, they<lb/>had made rapid progress - they had built<lb/>railways.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>.-Whose money built<lb/>them?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr, HAVILAND</persName>. —Whose money   
     <lb/>built all the railroads in the United<lb/>States ?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>. - They paid interest 
     <lb/>for it in the United States.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.-In 1867 the debt<lb/>of Canada was sixty-seven millions of<lb/>dollars, which was very small in pro<lb break="no"/>portion to the great benefits derived from<lb/>the expenditure of the money. Canada<lb/>had two-thousand miles of railroad, and<lb/>the finest canals in the world, and their<lb/>public buildings had cost millions of<lb/>dollars. The hon member seemed to<lb/>have a great horror of confederation<lb/>now than when he made his speech at<lb/>Summerside, or when he signed the<lb/>Minute of Council. The United States<lb/>were opposed to the confederation of<lb/>those provinces, because they considered<lb/>that if they remained separate there<lb/>would be a greater probability of them<lb/>being united to their great country. The<lb/>government had a great horror of re<lb break="no"/>ceiving money from Canada, but they<lb/>wished them to settle the Land Question.<lb/>A Machiavellian policy again. The hon<lb/>member (Mr. Laird) said they had not<lb/>pledged themselves to accept confedera<lb break="no"/>tion in case the Canadians succeeded in<lb/>settling the Land Question ; but Lord<lb/>Granville thought differently. He (Mr.<lb/>H.) believed the Dominion Government<lb/>would never have taken the trouble to<lb/>send down those proposals unless they<lb/>had been encouraged to do so by the<lb/>Island Government. The hon member<lb/>talked of shedding blood at Red River ;<lb/>but the only blood shed there was<lb/>that of a man named Scott, who was<lb/>shot by Riel, and this was the man the<lb/>hon member had such sympathy for.<lb/>That territory was given to a company in<lb/>the reign of Charles II, and all the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government had done was to buy<lb/>out the rights of that company ; but the<lb/>hon member (Mr. Laird) would not wish<lb/>
           
           
            <cb/>
    

    

     Canada to get possession of it, because it<lb/>was the keystone of the Dominion, and<lb/>if not taken possession of by Canada, the<lb/>Stars and Stripes would soon be floating<lb/>over it.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>The Committee then divided on the<lb/>amendment proposed by Hon. Mr. Havi<lb break="no"/>land.<lb/>
            </p>
             <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Yeas</hi>- Hon. Mr. Haviland; Messrs.<lb/>Brecken, Green, Jenkins, Prowse - 5.<lb/>
            </p>
             <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Nays</hi> - Hons. Howlan, Col. Secretary,<lb/>Laird, Callbeck, P. Sinclair, Henderson,<lb/>Duncan, McAulay, the Speaker, Messrs.<lb/>McNeill, Bell, McCormack, McMillan,<lb/>Owen, Howat, Kickham, Cameron,<lb/>Reilly, McLean - 19.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     The Hon. Mr. McAulay then proposed 
     <lb/>his resolution as an amendment to the<lb/>resolution proposed by Hon. Mr. Howlan,<lb/>when the House divided.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Yeas</hi> - Hons. McAulay, Henderson, 
     <lb/>Duncan ; Messrs Owen, and Howat - 5.<lb/>
            </p>
             <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Nays</hi> - Hons. Howlan, Col Secretary,<lb/>Laird, Callbeck, P. Sinclair, the Speaker,<lb/>Haviland ; Messrs. Brecken, McNeill,<lb/>Bell, McCormack, McMillan, Kickham,<lb/>Reilly, McLean, Cameron, Jenkins,<lb/>Green, Prowse - 19.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The question was then put on the<lb/>original resolution proposed by Hon. Mr.<lb/>Howlan :-<lb/>
            </p>
             <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Yeas</hi> - Hons. Howlan, Lard, Callbeck,<lb/>P. Sinclair, the Speaker, Col. Secretary ;<lb/>Messrs. McNeill, Bell, McMillan, Mc<lb break="no"/>Cormack, Kickham, Cameron, Reilly,<lb/>McLean - 14.<lb/>
            </p>
             <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Nays</hi> - Hons. Haviland, Henderson,<lb/>McAulay, Duncan ; Messrs. Brecken,<lb/>Owen, Green, Prowse, Jenkins, Howat.<lb/>- 10.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> then proposed<lb/>another Resolution (No. 2 of those re<lb break="no"/>ported on Saturday), but it was decided<lb/>that said resolution would have to lie 24<lb/>hours on the table before a division could<lb/>be taken thereon. Progress was re<lb break="no"/>ported, and the House adjourned till<lb/>Saturday.<lb/>
            </p>
             
             
          
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>