<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1869-04-12"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1869-04-12">12 April 1869</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1869">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1869, Being the Third Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1869"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edward Reilly, Queen's Printer</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="196"/>
</bibl>

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1869-04-12_Page_195.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1869-04-12_Page_196.hocr.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-13">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1869-04-12_Page_195"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-12_Page_195.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1869-04-12_Page_196"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-12_Page_196.jpg"/></surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="195" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-12_Page_195.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">195</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCMI3">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>. --There should be a line of tele<lb break="no"/>graph extended from Cascumpec to Georgetown, <lb/>
for communication of that kind is required be<lb break="no"/>tween those two ports, particularly late in the fall <lb/>
of the year. I am also of the opinion that we <lb/>
should also have a railroad between Summerside <lb/>
and the latter port. If a railroad was established, <lb/>
as many more vessels as are now engaged in trad<lb break="no"/>ing to Summerside, Charlottetown and George<lb break="no"/>town, would be required in ten years from the <lb/>
present time to carry on that trade. I believe the <lb/>
time is not far distant when we shall have a rail<lb break="no"/>road between Cascumpec and Georgetown. Since <lb/>
we are called upon to pay our Governor's Salary, <lb/>
many persons are of the opinion that we shall be <lb/>
forced into Confederation; if this is the case, we <lb/>
should at once enter into a contract to have a rail<lb break="no"/>road buiult between the two ports I have mention<lb break="no"/>ed, that the Dominion Government may have the <lb/>
expenses to pay. At any rate, the Government <lb/>
should cause a survey of the route to be made as <lb/>

<cb/>

prayed for in a petition unanimously signed and <lb/>
laid before them. I would support the extension <lb/>
of a telegraph line to Georgetown, because of the <lb/>
advantages of its harbor in the fall and spring. When <lb/>
the Steamer runs from that port in winter, while <lb/>
all other ports are closed by the ice, telegraph <lb/>
communication with it will be very much required. <lb/>
Indeed I am of the opinion that Georgetown re<lb break="no"/>quires those advantages as much as any place on <lb/>
this Island. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. Mr. CALBECK</persName>.--I quite agree that George<lb break="no"/>town should have the advantages of telegraphic <lb/>
communication, for it is a central port for fisher<lb break="no"/>men as well as an important one when all our other <lb/>
ports are ice-bound. I think those advantages should <choice><sic>should</sic><corr></corr></choice> also be extended to Souris, for it <lb/>
is a great place of resort for fishermen, and we <lb/>
know they often wish to send a message to distant <lb/>
parts. Indeed vessels of all kinds seek refuge <lb/>
in that port during stormy weather, and it is nat<lb break="no"/>ural to conclude that if a vessel wished to send a <lb/>
message anywhere she would run into the nearest <lb/>
port for that purpose. The hon. member for <lb/>
Summerside referred to Confederation; but I hope <lb/>
the day is far distant when the telegraph lines <lb/>
will convey the intelligence that this, or any other <lb/>
House of Assembly that may sit here, passed a <lb/>
vote in favor of joining the Confederation. I trust <lb/>
that we shall always remain separate from Cana<lb break="no"/>da, while things go on as they now do in that <lb/>
country. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.--I am of the opinion that the Com<lb break="no"/>pany would not be willing to open offices where <lb/>
the amount of business transacted does not re<lb break="no"/>quire them; but there is no doubt the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would make great exertions to supply every <lb/>
place of any consequence with the means for tele<lb break="no"/>graphic communication. There is a good deal in <lb/>
what the hon. member for Summerside stated, <lb/>
concerning railroads; if Confederation is coming <lb/>
up in the distance it would not be a bad policy for <lb/>
this Colony to enter into a contract with some <lb/>
company to build a railroad from Cascumpec to <lb/>
Georgetown at once. If we go into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion without a railroad, the chances are that we <lb/>
will not get it afterwards; therefore we should <lb/>
begin in time to get it finished before going in. <lb/>
It would be rather too late for the Government to <lb/>
enter into large contracts when they see that our <lb/>
entering Confederation is unavoidable. If we ful<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="196" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-04-12_Page_196.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">196</fw> 

ly believe that this Colony must, some day not far <lb/>
distant, enter Confederation, the Government <lb/>
should begin the construction of railroads and <lb/>
other costly public works at once, for there is no <lb/>
doubt the Dominion Government would take the <lb/>
burden of our debt as it did that of the other Pro<lb break="no"/>inces, upon itself. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>