<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1868-04-21"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1868-04-21">21 April 1868</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1868">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1868, Being the Second Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1868"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Patriot" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="216" to="218"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_216.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_217.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_218.html"/>
</item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-11">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_216">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_216.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_217">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_217.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_218">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_218.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>
<div type="debate">

<pb n="216" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_216.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">216</fw> 

<head rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, April 21.</head><lb/>

<p>[...]</p>


<p rendition="simple:centre"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Afternoon Session.</hi><lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre">DESPATCHES.<lb/></p>

<p>On motion of Hon. Leader of the Government, the <lb/>
House resolved itself into a committee of the whole <lb/>
on the consideration of certain despatches. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Reilly in the chair. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Despatch was read relating to the Confederating <lb/>
of the Provinces of Canada, New Brunswick and Nova <lb/>
Scotia. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">HON. LEADER OF THE GOVERNMENT</persName>.-This Despatch, <lb/>
Mr. Chairman, merely informs us of the fact that the <lb/>
provinces mentioned in it have been confederated. We <lb/>
might remark, however, that if we take notice of the <lb/>
working of the Dominion, which has lately been formed, <lb/>
we will find that not only has it lost one of its most <lb/>
talented statesmen as we have heard within the last few <lb/>
days, but that there is a great deal of dissatisfaction ex<lb break="no"/>isting among its people In fact a delegation has been <lb/>
sent to England from one of the confederated provinces, <lb/>
(Nova Scotia) for the purpose of trying to get a repeal <lb/>
of the Act which unites that province with Canada. In <lb/>
the province of New Brunswick also, if we are to be<lb break="no"/>lieve what appears in the newspapers, there is a great <lb/>
deal of dissatisfaction. Although we did not join the <lb/>
Union, we may be sorry that those who have done so <lb/>
should begin to complain before they have given the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment of the New Dominion a fair trial. As to <lb/>
whether Nova Scotia will succeed in her attempt, to <lb/>
withdraw from the Dominion or not, is a subject upon <lb/>
which I will not venture an opinion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>.-Mr. Chairman, when in <lb/>
London last year I saw a great placard posted up con<lb break="no"/>taining the proclamation which is in that despatch, and <lb/>
I was not sorry to find that our little Island was not in<lb break="no"/>cluded in it. With the doubts we had on the subject, I <lb/>
think it was well to wait and ascertain how the system <lb/>
would work. And now we see that the people of one of <lb/>
the most important parts of the Dominon are very dis<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="217" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_217.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">217</fw> 

satisfied, and I think with very good reason, for they <lb/>
were forced into the Union against their will ; and if <lb/>
justice is done to that colony I think that before many <lb/>
months we shall see a great change in the constitution <lb/>
of the Dominion. If Nova Scotia records in getting <lb/>
out of Confederation, New Brunswick will very likely <lb/>
follow, for she connected to enter the Union with the <lb/>
understanding that Nova Scotia was also to be a part of <lb/>
the Dominion. It has not worked as well as it promo<lb break="no"/>ters thought it would, and I think we may be satisfied <lb/>
that we are free from it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCAU1">Hon. Mr. MCAULAY</persName>.—There is scarcely an incident, <lb/>
Mr. Chairman, which passes before the eyes of a wine <lb/>
man which does not teach him a lesson, and I think we <lb/>
have learned a lesson from what has transpired in the <lb/>
neighboring provinces. I think we acted the wine part <lb/>
in refraining from joining the Union until we found out <lb/>
what effect Confederation would have on the other pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. It is a satisfaction also to know that the most <lb/>
ardent unionist in this Island would not comment to join <lb/>
the Union without appealing to the people and obtaining <lb/>
their comment. So soon as it appears that a Union will <lb/>
be advantageous to us, it will be soon enough for us to <lb/>
think seriously of joining it. We have taken the safe <lb/>
course, and we are not affected with that disaffection <lb/>
which prevails in the other colonies. They acted the <lb/>
part of a child springing to grasp something which ap<lb break="no"/>peared bright, but the nature of which it did not under<lb break="no"/>stand. I hope, however, that the results will not be so <lb/>
disastrous to them as some persons anticipated. I can<lb break="no"/>not agree with my hon. friend the Attorney General that <lb/>
New Brunswick can free herself from the Union—for <lb/>
she entered it in of her own accord, and she must lie on the <lb/>
bad which she made for herself, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName>.—I think, Mr. Chairman, that <lb/>
no hon. member can think with indifference of the sub<lb break="no"/>ject before the committee. It is true that the New <lb/>
Brunswickers entered the union with too great haste, <lb/>
and the fact that they are now dissatisfied with their <lb/>
position goes to confirm what you, Sir, and others have <lb/>
so often expressed as your convictions, that nothing <lb/>
would justify us in entertaining the question while we <lb/>
could avoid it. But while the people of New Brunswick <lb/>
entered the union those of Nova Scotia were dragged <lb/>
into it by a conspiracy, a conspiracy against the best <lb/>
interests of the whole colony, and a gross abuse to the <lb/>
constitutional power put into the hands of the people's <lb/>
representatives for a very different purpose. Now, Sir, <lb/>
I feel no pleasure at any confusions or disturbance in any <lb/>
portion of the North American Provinces, for whatever <lb/>
tends to distrub any portion, more or less tends to dis<lb break="no"/>turb the whole, and we being so closely connecting with <lb/>
the rest must sensibly feel the effects of any jarring ele<lb break="no"/>ments at work within them. But, Sir, it is easy to con<lb break="no"/>trast the first movements of the Dominion machinery <lb/>
with the glorious state of things which the admirers of <lb/>
union would fain have made us believe would be the re<lb break="no"/>sult. I think that whatever may be said of the future <lb/>
prospects of the Dominion, every person who takes a fair <lb/>
survey of the question will come to the conclusion that <lb/>
for the present, at least, it will be better for Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island to retain her isolated position, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERNMENT</persName>.—About the time <lb/>
the Dominion Government was being formed, an offer <lb/>
of $800,000 was made to this Island, and it was thought <lb/> 

<cb/>

by a great many that this would be sufficient to induce <lb/>
the people to go into Confederation, that it would be enough <lb/>
to buy out the proprietors claims. But it should be re<lb break="no"/>membered that that was an offer of the Nova Scotia and <lb/>
New Brunswick Delegates, and was not confirmed by <lb/>
the Canadians, and if the people of this Island had joined <lb/>
the Union it is very doubtful if these promises would <lb/>
have been fulfilled. I believe the people of this Island <lb/>
are satisfied that they are better off in their present posi<lb break="no"/>tion than they would be if connected with Canada even had <lb/>
they obtained the $800,000. There was no guarantee <lb/>
that the Dominion Government would pass a compulsory <lb/>
measure to settle the land question, and from the Des<lb break="no"/>patch from the Colonial Minister now before us, we may <lb/>
infer that such a measure would not be sanctioned by the <lb/>
British Government. If the proprietors were unwilling <lb/>
to sell, the Dominion Government although they had <lb/>
offered the $800,000, would not be called upon to pay it. <lb/>
If ever this Island does enter Confederation it will be <lb/>
when matters are going on more smoothly than at pre<lb break="no"/>sent. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>.—I wish, Mr. Chairman, to my a <lb/>
few words on this subject, chiefly to express my sympa<lb break="no"/>thy with the people of Nova Scotia who have been dragged <lb/>
into the Union against their wishes. A far as my <lb/>
knowledge goes, I believe the people of this Island are <lb/>
unwilling to join the Union on any terms. The $800,<lb break="no"/>000 would nothing like compensate us for the disadvan<lb break="no"/>tages to which we would be subjected by enter con<lb break="no"/>federation. I believe that if the grievances connected <lb/>
with the land tenure were far worse than they are, the <lb/>
people would submit to them rather than join themselves <lb/>
to Canada. We may, however, express our regret that <lb/>
the people of Nova Scotia have been forced into a union <lb/>
which they did not desire. There is a strong link con<lb break="no"/>necting us with the people of Nova Scotia, and it is <lb/>
lamentable to contemplate the position they are in at <lb/>
present ; but I have no doubt but that they will yet be <lb/>
allowed to secede from the Dominion, and again assume <lb/>
the proud position they formerly occupied. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. MCNEILL</persName>.—It is true, Mr. Chairman, that the <lb/>
people of the lower provinces entered the union without <lb/>
sufficiently considering the subject, and numbers of the <lb/>
people of this Island thought it would be a bene<lb break="no"/>fit. It was a new thing which the people did not under<lb break="no"/>stand; we had suffered a good deal from this rent system, <lb/>
and some were under the impression that confederation <lb/>
might be a panacea for that evil. About the time it <lb/>
was first brought to our notice, however, a great many <lb/>
public meetings were held through the country, (for what <lb/>
purpose it is not necessary now to state,) but this mat<lb break="no"/>ter, among others, was thoroughly discussed. The people <lb/>
of this Island when they take a matter into considera<lb break="no"/>tion are quite capable of judging for themselves, and <lb/>
they declared against confederation for this reason, that <lb/>
if they joined it instead of having the management of <lb/>
their own affairs, they would have no control, and these taxes <lb/>
would be appropriated without their consent. There <lb/>
was another reason also, they watched the proceedings <lb/>
of the delegates who met at Quebec, and they found <lb/>
there was very little sympathy or respect for Prince <lb/>
Edward Island. Even the talented T. D'Arcy McGee, <lb/>
whose untimely death we have been lately deploring, <lb/>
could not refrain from indulging in a little burlesque on <lb/>
our Island by saying that they would send one of their <lb/>

<pb n="218" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-21_Page_218.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">218</fw>

steamers and tow it up into one of their lakes. But <lb/>
while we rejoice that we have escaped the evils of con<lb break="no"/>federation, we deplore the fact that our sister province <lb/>
Nova Scotia was not so fortunate. She was sold into <lb/>
confederation by her unprincipled representatives, but <lb/>
her brave and intelligent people unwilling tamely to sub<lb break="no"/>mit to such treatment, are at present engaged in a great <lb/>
contest for the recovery of their former rights and privi<lb break="no"/>leges. They have just reason to rebel; and it is my <lb/>
opinion that they will eventually regain their constitu<lb break="no"/>tion and forsake their undesirable alliance with Canada. <lb/>
The Americans were many years trying to gain their in<lb break="no"/>dependence; and Nova Scotia may also be a considerable <lb/>
time before she gets free, and it is not improbable that <lb/>
another American war may be brought on before the <lb/>
question is settled. Nova Scotia is an injured pro<lb break="no"/>vince, she has been forced into union against the wishes of <lb/>
five-sixths of her inhabitants. The British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment may not however be blameable in this matter, for <lb/>
after the Quebec Conference the delegates went home <lb/>
and stated that all the people were in favor of Confe<lb break="no"/>deration. The Lieutenant Governor's of the different <lb/>
provinces received their instructions to carry out this <lb/>
matter, (I was going to say by fair means or foul,) and <lb/>
a pressure was brought to bear which should not have <lb/>
been in a free colony. I think it would be no more <lb/>
than right for this Legislature to pass a resolution <lb/>
sympathising with Nova Scotia in the struggle in which <lb/>
she is now engaged, and expressing a hope that she will <lb/>
succeed to her efforts, er if she can be forced into con<lb break="no"/>federation against her will, we may be also. It appears <lb/>
that the New Brunswickers are also beginning to be <lb/>
dissatisfied with their condition, but as they voluntarily <lb/>
entered it they must put up with the consequence. <lb/></p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>