<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1865-02-28"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

 
<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1865-02-28">28 February 1865</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1864">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1865, Being the Third Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1865"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Protestant" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="3"/>
</bibl>
 
 

<list>
<item><ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-02-28_Page_003.html"/></item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-05">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-02-28_Page_003">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-02-28_Page_003.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">
<pb n="3" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-02-28_Page_003.jpg"/>

<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">THE</hi></fw>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER,</hi></fw>
<p><hi rendition="simple:bold"><hi rendition="simple:centre">SESSION, 1865.</hi></hi></p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:bold"><hi rendition="simple:centre">Meeting of the Legislature.</hi></hi><lb/></p>
 
<p>
 On Tuesday, February 28th, His Excellency 
<lb/>
 Lieutenant Governor Dundas, came down to the 
<lb/>
 Council Chamber at 3 o'clock, when he was pleased 
<lb/>
 to open the Third Session of the Twenty-second 
<lb/>
 General Assembly with the following 
<lb/>
</p>
 
<p><hi rendition="simple:centre">SPEECH:</hi><lb/></p>
 
<p>
 In compliance with the Resolution, which you passed last 
<lb/>
 Session, I appointed Delegates to confer with Delegates ap<lb break="no"/>pointed by the Governments of Nova Scotia and New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, for the purpose of discussing the expediency of a 
<lb/>Legislative Union of the Maritime Provinces. 
<lb/>
</p>
 
<p>
 Correspondence on this subject, together with the Report 
<lb/>
 of the Conference of the Delegates will be laid before you. 
<lb/>
</p>

<p>
 From these papers you will learn the origin of a second 
<lb/>
 Conference, to consider the wider question of a general 
<lb/>
 Union of the British North American Provinces. 
<lb/>
</p>

<p>
 On the invitation of the Governor General I nominated 
<lb/>
 Delegates to proceed to Quebec to attend this second 
<lb/>
 Conference. 
<lb/>
</p>

<p>
 In appointing Delegates, I deemed it expedient, on both 
<lb/>
 occasions, to select them from each of the political parties in 
<lb/>
 the Legislature. 
<lb/>
</p>
 
<p>
 Copies of the Resolutions adopted at the Quebec Conference 
<lb/>
 will be submitted to you. 
<lb/>
</p>

<p>
 Despatches from Her Majesty's Principal Secretary of State 
<lb/>
 for the Colonial Department, on this important subject will 
<lb/>
 also be laid before you. 
<lb/>
</p>

<p>
 From this correspondence you will perceive that Her 
<lb/>
 Majesty's Government have given to these Resolutions their 
<lb/>
 most deliberate consideration, and have expressed their 
<lb/>
 general approval of the proceedings of the Conference. 
<lb/>For this, the most momentous question ever submitted to 
<lb/>you, I ask your earnest consideration. 
<lb/>
</p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>