<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1865-03-29"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1865-03-29">29 March 1865</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1864">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1865, Being the Third Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1865"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Protestant" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="62"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_060.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_061.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_062.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-08">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_060">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_060.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_061">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_061.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_062">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_062.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">
<pb n="60" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_060.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">60</fw>

<!-- DL 2018-06-08 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>Which is set off by 100 vessels, <lb/>
24,991 tons, the value of <lb/>
which is about £125,000 <lb/>
Which leaves a balance in the <lb/>
favor of the Colony of £40,000 <lb/></p> 

<p>It is well enough for those to go into Confederation who <lb/>
have not been able to manage their own affairs ; but for <lb/>
us to do so in the prosperous state of our Revenue, would <lb/>
be but committing political suicide. Some of the delegates, <lb/>
however, inform as that we may obtain £250,000 to buy <lb/>
proprietary lands. There is nothing in the Report to this <lb/>
affect ; all that I see promised is interest for a certain <lb/>
sum. If the hon. member for St. Peters were in the <lb/>
General Legislature, and to rise and ask for a grant of <lb/>
£200,000 to purchase proprietors' lands, could he have <lb/>
the face to paint to a certain paragraph of the Report, and <lb/>
may I claim this sum as a constitutional right ? (Laughter.) <lb/>
But it might be said, he would have other four members <lb/>
to aid him in orging our rights. Our delegates, did they <lb/>
wish to secure our rights, had a much better opportunity <lb/>
tog ain their point at a conference of a few individuals <lb/>
than in a Hopse of 194 membes. Their first object ought <lb/>
to have been to get the settlement of our Land Question-<lb break="yes"/>the only question which is a grievance in the Colony, and <lb/>
then they might have come with some show of reason and <lb/>
asked as to go into Confederation. But they ask us to give <lb/>
up our constitution - for what ! simply the glory of <lb/>
belonging to a country with four millions of people ! <lb/>
(Hear, hear.) I believe our people would prefer repre<lb break="no"/>sentation in the Imperial Parliament to Union with <lb/>
Canada, for though they might scarcely have one member <lb/>
in the British House of Commons, they would at least <lb/>
feel that their liberties were in the lands of people that <lb/>
could be trusted. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Debate was then adjourned. <lb/></p>--> 

<head rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, March 29.</head><lb/> 

<p>Debate on Union of Colonies resumed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LONG2">Hon. Mr. LONGWORTH</persName> - Mr. Speaker. This question <lb/>
comes before us with a different aspect from that which it <lb/>
presented last Session. Last year the question of a Union <lb/>
of the Maritime Provinces was discussed on the sug<lb break="no"/>gestions of the Lieut. Governors of Nova Scotia and New <lb/>
Brunswick. An argument has been drawn from this, that <lb/>
it was wrong in the Island Government to send delegates <lb/>
to Canada without the previous consent of the Legislature. <lb/>
We thought it but right to follow the example of our <lb/>
sister Colonies in complying with the request of Lord <lb/>
Monok. The number of delegates who were appointed to <lb/>
the Conference which sat at Charlottetown was increased <lb/>
by the addition of the Hon Mr. Whelsh and the Hon <lb/>
Solicitor General. The Government had every confidence <lb/>
in the judgment and ability of the gentlemen whom they <lb/>
had appointed on the Canadian mission. Whatever <lb/>
might be the result of the Conference, the Government <lb/>
had expressed no opinion ; they left it an open question, <lb/>
andtherefore every member has a right to express his own <lb/>
opinion on it. It is not my intention to discuss the <lb/>
great principles involved, nor the various details set forth <lb/>
in the Report of the delegates as the result of their <lb/>
deliberations. In view of the thorough manner in which <lb/>
the subject has been handled in the press and at public <lb/>
meetings, it is unnecessary to encumber this debate with <lb/>
figures and calculations. The first consideration that <lb/>
occurs to my mind on the subject is the peculiar situation <lb/>
of the Island. We are an agricultural country, our <lb/>
fishers are but partially developed. Our insular position <lb/>
necessitates our entrance into the Union under circumstance less <lb/>
favorable than either Nova Scotia or New Brunswick. Canada <lb/>
has great resources, and her agricultural capabilities are un<lb break="no"/>bounded. Nature has united Canada and New Brunswick. It <lb/>
is impossible that we can participate in the advantages anticipated <lb/>
from the Union in proportion to the other Colonies ; therefore, in <lb/>
my opinion, the Conference at Quebec should have treated us as <lb/>

<cb/>

entitled to an exceptional <hi rendition="simple:italic">status</hi> in the Confederacy. I do not <lb/>
mean to say that under no circumstances would a Union be <lb/>
advisable, but we should have been placed upon a different <lb/>
and more favorable footing than the other Colonies. I agree that <lb/>
the Report is an able one, but many of its details will not bear <lb/>
scrutiny. As to the principle of representation by population ; <lb/>
although not objectionable under some circumstances, yet I do <lb/>
not approve its application in the present matter. The repre<lb break="no"/>sentation in the Lower House should have been on the British <lb/>
principle, while the example afforded by the United States <lb/>
Senate could have been advantageously followed in the con<lb break="no"/>stitution of the Upper Branch of the Legislature. When my hon. <lb/>
ad learned friend, the Hon. Solicitor General, says that the <lb/>
delegates from the Maritime Colonies exercised a controlling <lb/>
influence in the framing and adoption of the Report, it appears <lb/>
to be an admission that they were novel principles, principles not <lb/>
hither tested by the experience of any previous Confederation <lb/>
of which history makes mention. It shows me that it was a <lb/>
plan devised to meet some complications or the particular views <lb/>
of some parties. The Island representative to the Upper Branch <lb/>
would ahve some check which might avail to compensate for the <lb/>
wretched minority which we would be entitle to for the <lb/>
Lower House, where a presentation of 5 our of 194 might <lb/>
render it impolitic for our members of oppose a measure they <lb/>
disapproved of, lest they should not be permitted to carry any <lb/>
vote which they might wish. I cannot use any prospect of might <lb/>
for this Colony in a Legislature composed in such proportions. <lb/>
Canada could, at any moment, on vote as ; now is there any <lb/>
reason to suppose that Nova Scotia and New Brunswick would <lb/>
unite to save us. But Sir, looking at this question in £ pounds ; <lb/>
billings and pence, point of view, the scheme fails to commend <lb/>
itself to my judgment. What are the terms proposed ? We are <lb/>
to receive some £48,000 per annum in commutation of a revenue <lb/>
which has been increasing for the last fourteen years, until last <lb/>
ear it approximated to £86,000, and which it is but reasonable <lb/>
to suppose would continue to increase in the same way as it <lb/>
has manifested for th period to which I have referred. When <lb/>
it is asked of us that we should surrender our separate rights and <lb/>
submit to the terms which the proposed Confeders may impose <lb/>
upon us, do hon members realize the full extent of the concession <lb/>
involved ? We are requested to give up not merely the difference <lb/>
in amount of revenue to which I have referred, but matters of <lb/>
higher moment. We are required to yield up our position of <lb/>
comparative dependance as a separate Colony, and to reduce <lb/>
the scope of our legislative functions to the privileges of a local <lb/>
vestry in the Mother Country - the right of levying pariah taxes <lb/>
for local purposes. In reference to what hs been said on the <lb/>
subject of free trade with Canada and the benefits we would <lb/>
receive from it, I will take the liberty of confirming my views <lb/>
by extracting from the official statistics the returns of our com<lb break="no"/>merical Intercourse with that country for a few years. From <lb/>
our Public Accounts it appears that the duty paid on Imports into <lb/>
P. E. Island from Canada in 1868, was, on <lb/></p> 

<table>
<row>
<cell>Ale and Porter</cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">£9</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">8</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">9</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Soap</cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">2</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">3</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right"></hi>3</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Leather</cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">1</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">13</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right"></hi>7½</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Miscellaneous</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right"></hi>15</cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right"></hi>9</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Tobacco*</cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">43</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">13</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">6</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Wines*</cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">12</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">17</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">7</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Tea*</cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">8</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">14</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">7½</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Salt*</cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">7</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">17</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">3</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Molasses*</cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">2</hi></hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">3</hi></hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">6</hi></hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">Total</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">£89</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">7</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">10</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Those marked thus * (evidently not</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>the productions of Canada) paid</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>in duty</cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">75</hi></hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">6</hi></hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">6</hi></hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Leaving for Ale and Porter, Soap,</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>&amp; c. the supposed produce of</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Canada</cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">£14</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right">1</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rendition="simple:right"></hi>4</cell>
</row>
</table>

<p>In 1860, 1861, and 1862 the duty on Imports into P.E. Island <lb/>
from Canada, amounting to the aggregate value of £15 15s, 9d <lb/>
was only £4 5s 6d for the three years, or £1 8e 6d a year ! ! ! <lb/>
yAnother and most important consideration is the position in <lb/>
which we, under Confederation, will be placed with reference to <lb/>
our obligations to contribute to the defence of Canada. We have <lb/>
been told that an army and navy must be organised for the pro<lb break="no"/>tection of that country, for the local defence of which, in the <lb/> 

<pb n="61" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_061.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">61</fw>

shape of permanent works of military defence, competent <lb/>
authority had declared that no less a sum than 1, 143, 000 sterling <lb/>
will be required. In view of those considerations, and looking at <lb/>
the vast sums of money which, under the terms of the Report it <lb/>
is calculated to expend in the building of Railways and Canals <lb/>
and other Public Works, I am of opinion that if we should cast <lb/>
in our lot with Canada, instead of witnessing a reduction of her <lb/>
present tariff from 20 to 15 per cent, as intimated by the <lb/>
advocates of Union, we should see it largely increased. In fact <lb/>
the only argument on which the probability of the supposed <lb/>
reduction can be based is that the Lower Provinces would con<lb break="no"/>sume a much larger amount of dutiable articles than they do <lb/>
present. I maintain that it is a reasonable inference that the <lb/>
tariff of Canada would, under Confederation, rise instead of <lb/>
falling 5 per cent. Our exports being a similar character to <lb/>
those which Western Canada furnishes in abundance, the idea <lb/>
of a mutual interchange of commodities is chimerical, and the <lb/>
only result to our people from Confederation would be direct <lb/>
taxaction, which would be necessary to raise the revenue, our <lb/>
proportion of which we would have to assume. This question, <lb/>
Mr. Speaker, should be viewed from the single stand point of the <lb/>
individual Colony to be affected by it, and therefore I do not, as <lb/>
one of the representatives of Prince Edward Island, regard the <lb/>
expression of public opinion which has been elicited on it in the <lb/>
neighboring Province of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick. It <lb/>
is our duty to deal with it as if affects ourselves. The Colonies <lb/>
to which I have alluded are territorially situate with reference to <lb/>
Canada in a manner very different from this Island, and therefore <lb/>
arguments which, on that account might be used in those <lb/>
Colonies in favor of the project, cannot hold or apply here. As <lb/>
a representative of Prince Edward Island I feel it my duty con<lb break="no"/>scientiously to record my solemn protest against the principles <lb/>
and terms of a Union which, in my judgment, would prove most <lb/>
injurious to the best interests of this my native country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Mr. SINCLAIR</persName>.-The advocates of Union can easily <lb/>
occupy time in speaking on this question. Extensive <lb/>
railways, large canals, and cities springing rapidly into <lb/>
existence is such a beautiful and glowing picture that it <lb/>
forms a theme on which they can expatiate at pleasure. <lb/>
But, Mr. Speaker, when we seek to examine the picture <lb/>
it is found to be nothing but dreams and vanishes away <lb/>
I think it would be most detrimental to the interests of <lb/>
Prince Edward Island to enter the proposed Union. But <lb/>
still I am open to conviction. I have, however, listened <lb/>
to the able speeches of the advocates of Confederation <lb/>
without my opinion being changed-without being able to <lb/>
think otherwise than that Union with Canada would ruin <lb/>
the Island politically and financially. One great argument <lb/>
of the friends of Union is the "glory argument." It <lb/>
would, say they, open a wide field for our young men. <lb/>
This Colony, however, small as it is, might send forth <lb/>
talented individuals from among her sons. It is true <lb/>
greatness to product great men. We might belong to <lb/>
Russia with her vast territories, but would that make us <lb/>
great ? What is it that leads Englishmen, Scotchmen and <lb/>
Irishmen to be proud of their respective countries ? <lb/>
It is because they have been distinguished by many great <lb/>
men. And this Island might be the same. I am proud <lb/>
of being descended from British ancestors, but I am proud <lb/>
also of being an Islander. (Hear, hear.) I believe that <lb/>
the people of Prince Edward Island can take their position <lb/>
beside the people of any country in the globe. There is <lb/>
nothing in her present situation to prevent her sons from <lb/>
rising in the world. It is argued further that by doing <lb/>
away with hostile tariffs this Colony will make great <lb/>
strides in improvement. I do not admit that we have <lb/>
hostile tariffs. The view I take of such tariffs is that they <lb/>
are to prevent competition, namely to foster manufac<lb break="no"/>tures by preventing people from buying in the cheapest <lb/>
market. This would be the nature of the tariffs under <lb/>
Confederation, for it is well known that Canada, Nova <lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick cannot manufacture for many <lb/>
years the articles which we require. It is well known, <lb/>
also that it is impossible to carry on manufactures <lb/>
extensively with a sparse population, the arguments of <lb/>
the Hon Solicitor General to the contrary not withstanding. <lb/>
Labor cannot be so cheap in a new country. That a large <lb/>
part of the population of Britain is dependent on manu<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

factures, was evidenced by the fact that many of those <lb/>
working for low wages in factories were nearly starved <lb/>
when cotton became high. This could not be the case in <lb/>
an extensive country like America. Prince Edward <lb/>
Island, on account of her position, can never become a <lb/>
great manufacturing country. Our exports will not be to <lb/>
Canada, because she does not want our agricultural <lb/>
produce, still we will be compelled to purchase many <lb/>
manufactured articles there, for if we shut out the <lb/>
Americans by hostile tariffs they will not trade with us ; <lb/>
and British goods will be excluded in the same way. We <lb/>
have, therefore, seen that the "glory argument" promises <lb/>
no benefit, and that the tariff argument is worse. What <lb/>
then are we to receive to induce us to enter Confederation? <lb/>
The hon and gallant member for Belfast says we are to <lb/>
get a large sum of money from Canada to buy up the <lb/>
proprietors' lands. I maintain that by the terms of this <lb/>
Report we will not receive a single farthing from Canada. <lb/>
The 28, 000 interest, or thereabouts, which it is said we <lb/>
are to draw for the proportion of debt in our favor, <lb/>
would not be drawn at all-it would only be placed to <lb/>
our credit. We would have our share of the aggregate <lb/>
debt of the Colonies to pay, and amount placed to our <lb/>
credit annually would be just equal to the interest which <lb/>
this Colony, according to her population, would require <lb/>
to pay on the debt of Canada, Nova Scotia and New <lb/>
Brunswick. So that by this arrangement not one penny <lb/>
would really come to the Island-it would only save us <lb/>
from being taxed for the debt of other people. Besides <lb/>
this, however, we are told that this Island is to receive a <lb/>
capitation grant of 80 cents which will yield a little over <lb/>
20, 000 ; and that the salaries of her judges, and some <lb/>
other expenses will be paid, amounting to about 10,000 <lb/>
more. But as our Revenue is now 66,000, by this <lb/>
arrangement we would lose over 30,000 annually, with <lb/>
the tariff as ours is at present ; if the Canadian tariff, <lb/>
however, were adopted, the sum lost would be nearer <lb/>
90,000. But some maintain that the expenses under <lb/>
Confederation would be less. This is more than <lb/>
questionable, for there would be a general government to <lb/>
support, public works to be undertaken, and the cost of <lb/>
defences to provide for. It has been estimated that the <lb/>
whole expenses under Confederation would amount to <lb/>
$13,000,000, but I believe it would be nearer $20,000,000. <lb/>
It is impossible to say what the future shall be, but I <lb/>
may be allowed to make a calculation, basing my figures <lb/>
on the past. The expenditure of the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment for six years, from 1857 to 1862, was 21,432,584, <lb/>
or an average yearly expenditure of 3,572,110. Now <lb/>
taking the population of Canada at 2 1/2 millions, it is a <lb/>
simple question, in simple proportion, if 2 1/2 millions of a <lb/>
population expends 3,572,110 a year, what wuld <lb/>
P. E. Island, with a population of 80,000 expend at the <lb/>
same rate, and I find we would expend 114,307 <lb/>
a year. Now we will see what P. E. Island did expend <lb/>
during the same period. In the same 6 years the <lb/>
Government of this Island expended 299,168, or an <lb/>
average yearly expenditure of 49,861 ; so that if we had <lb/>
been in connection with Canada the last 6 years, we <lb/>
would have had to pay for the Canadian Government the <lb/>
sum of 386,672. This is the sum which we have gained <lb/>
by being out of our without Confederation for the last six <lb/>
years. Canada cannot decrease her expenditure, so it is <lb/>
well for us in looking forward to the future in financial <lb/>
matters to judge by the past. But then, again, by this <lb/>
scheme we will be required to give up our political <lb/>
independence. What is dearer to a man than this country <lb/>
and its institutions ? By accepting Confederation we <lb/>
would be surrendering everything which we can politically <lb/>
hold dear. While we have a system of self-govern<lb break="no"/>ment, we may sometimes get into difficulties, yet affairs <lb/>
will soon rectify themselves ; but if we cast in our lot <lb/>
with other much more numerous than ourselves we will <lb/>

<pb n="62" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-29_Page_062.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">62</fw>

my remarks without protesting against the manner in <lb/>
which this question has come before us. A subject of <lb/>
such importance as this should have been before us for <lb/>
years, and canvassed fully by the press and the people ere <lb/>
it was submitted to the House in the form which it <lb/>
assumes in the Report under discussion. It has not <lb/>
originated with the people, and almost the first clause <lb/>
which it contains deprives them of a right, as it provides <lb/>
places for at least 77 Councillors in a general parliament <lb/>
of the Colonies, where they will be independent of the <lb/>
people, and independent of the Crown. What authority <lb/>
had the delegates to go to Canada and thus sign away our <lb/>
rights ! They may say that they were invited by the <lb/>
Governor General. I say the Governor General has no <lb/>
power to interfere with the constitutional liberties of the <lb/>
people of the Colony. The people or their representatives <lb/>
alone should take up this question, and I look upon the <lb/>
action taken in this matter as a conspiracy against their <lb/>
privileges. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Col. SECRETARY moved an adjournment, and Hon. <lb/>
Mr. POPE opposed the motion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWA1">Mr. HOWAT</persName>.—Mr. Speaker ; I would prefer that we <lb/>
should finish the discussion this evening, as the advanced <lb/>
season renders it desirable that we should get through <lb/>
the business of the Session as soon as possible. As to the <lb/>
question of Union I may say that I am opposed to it on <lb/>
any conditions. The proportion assigned to us in the <lb/>
United House of Commons would deprive us of all <lb/>
influence in that branch of the Legislature, and our <lb/>
situation in the Upper Branch would render us more <lb/>
helpless still ; and the fact that some of the most able and <lb/>
intelligent men in the Island failed to obtain better terms <lb/>
at the Conference is as strong an argument as I require <lb/>
show me what our position would be under Confederation. <lb/>
The advocates of Union who have addressed you on the <lb/>
subject have endeavored to show that our taxes will not <lb/>
be increased when united ; but how, I would ask, could <lb/>
the expenses to be incurred for an army, a navy, and <lb/>
fortifications be met except by increase of taxation ? <lb/>
Increase of manufactures to any considerable amount would <lb/>
require a protective tariff, and our Legislature can adopt <lb/>
the principles of protection or free trade, as it suits them, <lb/>
just as well at present as they could under Confederation. <lb/>
The Hon. Solicitor General has remarked upon the benefit <lb/>
we should receive from Union by having an independent <lb/>
Legislature, but by the Report of the delegates I perceive <lb/>
that our legislation would require approval in Canada, <lb/>
and might afterwards be disallowed at Downing Street. <lb/>
As to the defences in Canada they would be no safeguard <lb/>
to us. The loyalty of some of the Canadians is not beyond <lb/>
doubt in my mind, and notwithstanding the allusion made <lb/>
by the Hon. Solicitor General to such men as Cromwell <lb/>
and Washington, I am disposed to judge of the future of <lb/>
some people by their conduct in the past. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. HOWLAN seconded the motion for an adjournment. <lb/>
It was unfair to press a division to night when some <lb/>
members had not spoken. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. POPE, though anxious to close the debate, was <lb/>
not disposed to treat the Minority unjustly, and would <lb/>
consent to the division being taken to-morrow evening. <lb/></p> 

<!-- DL 2018-06-08 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>THURSDAY, March 30. <lb/>
Hon. Mr. KELLY.—Mr. Speaker ; In rising to address you <lb/>
on this all important subject of Confederation with Canada and <lb/>
the Lower Provinces, I find few arguments adduced in favor of <lb/>
it which have not been ably confuted by hon members already. <lb/>
Sorry I am to see as its advocates hon members in this House of <lb/>
whose talents and position in any other cause our Island might <lb/>
justly feel proud. I wish, Sir, to record my determined <lb/>
opposition to Confederation with Canada or with the Lower <lb/>
Provinces in any shape or on any terms. I feel convinced that <lb/>
any change in our constitution of the nature contemplated, would <lb/>
not operate beneficially to us. We are told that unless we <lb/>
surrender our separate constitution and place ourselves under the <lb/>

<cb/>

protection of the Canadian Legislature and the general <lb/>
Confederacy of Canada, we shall be overrun by, or absorbed <lb/>
into, the United States. I have no fear, Sir, that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the Stars and Stripes will interfere with us if we do not <lb/>
interfere with them, of which there is little prospect. I am glad <lb/>
to hear that New Brunswick has condemned the scheme—that <lb/>
Nova Scotia does not wish it, and if report speaks truly, New<lb break="no"/>foundland is not likely to adopt it—and it has been said that a <lb/>
majority of the people of Canada are themselves opposed to it. <lb/>
But I regret to hear some hon members of this House, while <lb/>
declaring their opposition to the measure, their willingness to <lb/>
adopt it, if more favorable terms could be obtained for the Island. <lb/>
I have no doubt, Sir, that the Canadian diplomatists having set <lb/>
their minds upon effecting their object, would, rather than fail in <lb/>
their pet scheme, yield whatever concessions might be required <lb/>
of them, knowing that their preponderance in the United <lb/>
Legislature would enable them to make whatever alterations in <lb/>
the terms they pleased, and that the mockery of a parliament <lb/>
then left us would render us powerless to prevent them, or even <lb/>
to complain. The hon and gallant Colonel, the member for <lb/>
Belfast, told us a few evenings ago, that in agitating for a repeal <lb/>
of the Union between England and Ireland, O'Connell would have <lb/>
gladly accepted a restoration to College Green of an Irish Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment similar in its constitution to that proposed for us at the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Conference. The hon member labors under a sad mistake. <lb/>
Sorry would a great man have been to have accepted for his <lb/>
country a Legislature less independent than that which she <lb/>
possessed before it was traitorously sold from her by a pack of <lb/>
wretches elected to the last Parliament of that ill fated nation <lb/>
through the influence of Pitt, Cornwallis and Castlereagh. A <lb/>
few of the names of those men I will read to you from a list <lb/>
which I hold in my hand, and although the descendants of some <lb/>
of them may retain the titles so villainously obtained, their <lb/>
names and races will be held in execration by Irishmen over the <lb/>
world to the end of time. The present question forcibly reminds <lb/>
me of the lament of your gifted countryman, Mr Speaker, when <lb/>
he refers to the sad time <lb/></p> 

<p>"When once beneath a monarch's feet <lb/>
Sat Legislation's sovereign powers." <lb/></p> 

<p>We have, Sir, sovereign legislative powers, whereby we can <lb/>
make our own laws and direct the application of our own monies <lb/>
among our own people at our own pleasure, and I hope the day <lb/>
is far distant when this, our Parliament, shall be converted into <lb/>
a Barrack or a Bank, or ourselves deprived of the constitutional <lb/>
privileges which we have so long enjoyed under the guarantee of <lb/>
the Imperial Government. The following list contains the <lb/>
names of some of the parties who sold Ireland, and the prices at <lb/>
which they consented to barter away the constitution of their <lb/>
country :—Lord Shannon, £45,000. Lord Loftus, £45,000. John <lb/>
Bingham, a Peerage, (Lord Wallcourt.) James G. Blackwood, <lb/>
a Peerage, (Lord Dufferin.) Joesph Cuffe, a Peerage, (Lord <lb/>
Tyrawley.) Richard Hare, a Peerage, (Lord Ennismore.) <lb/>
John Hutchinson, a Peerage, and a Regt., (Lord Hutchinson.) <lb/>
Wm. Handcock, a Peerage, (Lord Athlone.) Charles Coote, a <lb/>
Peerage, (Lord Castlecoote, since extinct.) Lodge Morris, a <lb/>
Peerage. William Newcomen, a Peerage for his wife. John <lb/>
Blaquiere, a Peerage, (Lord DeBlaquiere.) G. Cradock, a <lb/>
Peerage, (Lord Howden) John Longfield, a Peerage, (Lord <lb/>
Longueville.) Wm. Sandford, a Peerage, (Lord Mt Sandford.) <lb/>
Richard French, a Peerage, (Lord Ashtown.) John Stewart, <lb/>
a Lawyer, a Peerage, and a Judgeship, (Lord Clonmel.) <lb/>
Arthur Galbraith, an Attorney, a Baronetcy. Herculus <lb/>
Langrishe, a Baronetcy and £15,000. George Jocelyn, his <lb/>
brother made a Bishop, (Clogher.) Henry Alexander, his <lb/>
brother made a Bishop. John Bagwell, his son made a Dean, <lb/>
John Fitzgibbon, son of an obscure Roman Catholic Lawyer, <lb/>
made Lord Chancellor and Earl of Clare, an arrogant, cruel and <lb/>
overbearing tyrant. Isaac Corry, Chancellor of the Exchequer. <lb/>
John Toler, made L.C. Justice and a Peer, (the brutal Norbury.) <lb/>
Luke Fox, a Judge of the Common Pleas. Charles Osborne, <lb/>
Judge of the King's Bench. St. John Daly, Judge of the <lb/>
Common Pleas. Robert Johnston, Judge of the K. B. Wm. <lb/>
Johnston, a Baron of the Exchequer. James McClelland, Baron <lb/>
of the Exchequer. Wm. Smith of the Exchequer. <lb/>
R. Torrens, a Judge of the King's Bench. W. Vandeleur, a <lb/>
Judge of the Common Pleas. The lowest of the foregoing at a <lb/>
salary of £3,300 a year with over 20 country Judges at £600 a <lb/>
year. In addition to the foregoing I might give the names of <lb/>
over twenty-five of the Renegades who were made Colonels <lb/></p>-->
</div> </body> </text> </TEI>