<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1864-03-22"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1864-03-22">18 March 1864</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1864">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1864, Being the Second Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1864"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Protestant" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="37"/>
</bibl>


<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_032.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_033.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_034.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_035.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_036.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_037.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-05-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-05-23">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_032">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_032.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_033">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_033.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_034">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_034.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_035">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_035.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_036">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_036.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_037">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_037.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>
<div type="debate">

<pb n="32" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_032.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">32</fw>

<p><hi rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY AFTERNOON, March 22<lb/></hi></p> 

<p>At 4 o'clock the House waited on His Excellency with<lb/>
the address, and, on their return, the Speaker reported the<lb/>
reply.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon Col. Gray, Messrs Coles, Longworth, Hensley,<lb/>
and Messrs Sinclair and McLennan were appointed a<lb/>
Committee to join a Committee of the Legislative Council<lb/>
to prepare an address of congratulation to Her Majesty, on<lb/>
the occasion of the birth of the Son of the Prince of Wales.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon Col. Gray, in moving the 2d reading of the Bill,<lb/>
for vesting the Command of the volunteers in the Com<lb break="no"/>mander-in-Chief of the Island, explained that doubts had<lb/>
arisen as to the command of the colunteer force; the latter<lb/>
were in a different position from the regular army and<lb/>
militia. In Britain the volunteers were under the com<lb break="no"/>mand of the Lords Lieutenants of their respective Coun<lb/>
ties, and the Commander-in-chief exercised no control<lb/>
over them, save when on active service. Here we had no<lb/>
officers analogous to Lords Lieutenants of Counties, and<lb/>

<cb/> 

the Bill would vest the command of the volunteers in the <lb/>
Lieutenant Governor of the Island, during the absence<lb/>
from it of the Governor General. The Bill and the des<lb break="no"/>patch relation to it having been referred to Committee of<lb/>
the whole, the former was agreed to.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon Mr. Longworth submitted the report of the Medi<lb break="no"/>cal Attendant of the Lunatio Asylum. Hon Col. Secre<lb break="no"/>tary, the Blue Book for 1862, and the returns of the Bank<lb/>
of P.E. Island, for 1863<lb/></p> 

<p><hi rendition="simple:centre">UNION OF THE COLONIES</hi><lb/></p> 

<p>On motion, the House resolved itself into a Committee of that<lb/>
whole to take into further consideration the various Despatches<lb/>
and papers, transmitted by Message to the House this Session.<lb/>
The Correspondence relative to a Union of the three Lower Pro<lb break="no"/>pose, Mr. Chairman, on the correspondence before you, which is<lb/>
to the following effect:-<lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>Resolved, That His Excellency the Lieutenant Governor be<lb/>
authorized to appoint Delegates (not to exceed five) to confer<lb/>
with Delegates who may be appointed by the governmentss of<lb/>
Nova Scotia and New Brunswick for the purpose of discussing the<lb/>
expediency of a Union of the three provinces of Nova Scotia,<lb/>
New Brinswick and P.E. Island, under one government and<lb/>
Legislature - the report of said Delegates to be laid before the<lb/>
Legislature of this Colony, before any further action shall be taken<lb/>
in regard to the proposed question.<lb/></p></quote> 

<p>The question of a Union of the Colonies, is one, Sir, of very<lb/>
great importance; and I might occupy a large share of the time<lb/>
of this hon Committee in advancing the views which I have long<lb/>
entertained on the subject; but, Sir, the present aspect of the<lb/>
question does not call for much remark. Being ignorant as to<lb/>
he terms of Union which may be proposed be the sister Provin<lb break="no"/>ces, we are scarcely in the position to discuss whether or not such<lb/>
a Union would be advantageous to this Colony. If the Provinces<lb/>
of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick were to be annexed to<lb/>
Prince Edward Island, great benefits might result to our people;<lb/>
but if this Colony were to be annexed to these Provinces, the<lb/>
opposite might be the effect. From the documents before you,<lb/>
Sir, it appears that the Governments of Nova Scotia and New<lb/>
Brunswick intend to bring before their respective Legislature a<lb/>
resolution authorizing the appointment of Delegates to confer<lb/>
with other Delegates who may be appointed, for "the purpose<lb/>
of arranging a preliminary plan," respecting a Union of the<lb/>
three Maritime Provinces; and we are called upon to take simi<lb break="no"/>lar action. Now, Sir, I cannot avoid expressing my opinion<lb/>
that our neighbors are proceeding too hastily in this matter. I<lb/>
think the first point to consider is, Shall there be "a preliminary<lb/>
plan?" Is it advisable to have a Union at all? On the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion which I have submitted it is proposed to appoint Delegates,<lb/>
simply for the purpose of discussing the expediency of a union of<lb/>
the three Provinces of Nova Scotia, New Brunswick and P.E.<lb/>
Island, under one Government and Legislature. This is as far<lb/>
as I deem to be prudent for us to proceed at present. It beloves<lb/>
this House to view the question in all its bearings before it<lb/>
should take any action which might be considered as a willing<lb break="no"/>ness on our part to have the constitution of the Colony taken<lb/>
away. Owing to our insular position, and the difficulty of<lb/>
crossing the Straits at certain seasons of the year, a legistative<lb/>
union might in many respects operate to our disadvantage. I,<lb/>
however, am free to admit that weighly reasons can be adduced<lb/>
to show why the three Provinces in question should be united<lb/>
under one Government. It is an old maxim that "union is<lb/>
strength," and in the case under consideration, I believe union<lb/>
would be strength. What would have become of the thirteen<lb/>
Colonies had there not been union among them at the time of<lb/>
the revolutionary war? What would have become of Massa<lb break="no"/>chusetts if good old Virginia had not stepped forward to assist<lb/>
her, and given her gallant troops, and more than all a George<lb/>
Washington - conduct which, I am sorry to say, has met with<lb/>
base ingratitude from the dollar-worshipping aristocracy of that<lb/>
northern State? And the strength which union affords may ere<lb/>
long be required in these British Provinces. it is understood<lb/>
that Maximilian has accepted the Crown of Mexico, and he<lb/>
may even now be almost landed in America. Once seated upon<lb/>
the throne of this new Empire, his government will, in all pro<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="33" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_033.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">33</fw>


bability acknowledge the independence of the Confederate<lb/>
States. This [illegible] would be followed by France, and the recog<lb break="no"/>nition of France, no doubt, by a peace between the Federal and<lb/>
Confederate States. What then would become of Illinois,<lb/>
Wisconsin, Iowa, Minnesota, Kansas, and others of the Western<lb/>
States and out from the Mississippi. Sir, they would find it<lb/>
expedient to join the [illegible] Confederacy. Thus stripped of<lb/>
their territory south and west, the Northern States would seek<lb/>
to extend their boundaries in other directions. What then<lb/>
would be the position of these Colonies? The British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment maintaining, or pretending to maintain a neutrality<lb/>
as witness the case of the steam rams at Liverpool- has given<lb/>
satisfaction to neither contending party. When the [illegible] of<lb/>
two nations of government are trembling in the balance, they<lb/>
are each disposed to imagine that every offence not exerted<lb/>
directly in their favor, operates against them. Owing to recent<lb/>
occurances the South does not now look with favor on our govern<lb break="no"/>ment, this I regret, for the [illegible] population of the Confeder<lb break="no"/>ate States are the natural sons of Britain. On the other hand,<lb/>
the North has never seemed satisfied with the course [illegible]<lb/>
by the British Government during the present war, and [illegible] one<lb/>
view of the [illegible] this need not be wondered [illegible], for her people<lb/>
are a mixed population gathered from all the nations of the<lb/>
earth. In the event of its peace, the South would [illegible] re<lb break="no"/>spects be in a better position than the North. The Confederate<lb/>
States unquestionably have a large debt, but [illegible] is chiefly in<lb/>
the hands of her own people, and might for some [illegible] be<lb/>
[illegible]. With the North, however, it is different; [illegible]<lb/>
[illegible] are held all over the world- in England, France,<lb/>
Russia, and other countries, and her debt, now [illegible]<lb/>
of Great Britain, will have to be paid. The army of the North<lb/>
now numbers above 600,000 men, nearly all mercenaries;<lb/>
men whose services can be bought and sold. These troops<lb/>
will have to be provided for, and should hostilities come against<lb/>
the South, the government which employed them would have<lb/>
to seek for them another [illegible] of those men are<lb/>
the soldiers of New York, and other large cities, and to satisfiy<lb/>
their thirst for plunder, they within all probabily demand to be<lb/>
[illegible] Canada. The village and town of the fine Prov<lb break="no"/>ince will afford them [illegible] in which to [illegible] and gratify their<lb/>
[illegible]. Taking [illegible] of the case I think that something will<lb/>
[illegible] long [illegible] to be [illegible] these Colonies for self- defence.<lb/>
A Union must be effected [illegible] legislators [illegible] federal. I am not<lb/>
prepared to say, however, how it is to be carried out or what<lb/>
are to be the [illegible]. If there is to be a Legislative<lb/>
Union of these Maritime Provinces, are new government and<lb/>
parliament buildings to be erected, and where are theyt to be<lb/>
built? Is Charlottetown or Summerside to be the capital of<lb/>
Canada or Acadia, or whatever the country may be called?<lb/>
Are we to be the Ottawa of the United Provinces, and are build<lb break="no"/>ings to be erected here, [illegible] as in Canada, millions of dollars?<lb/>
Then again when are the Sessions of Parliament to be held -<lb/>
in December, January, February, or in June, July or Septem<lb break="no"/>ber? Are we to be required to keep our Representatives [illegible]<lb/>
some capital in one of the sister Provinces, from autumn to<lb/>
spring, or are they to be expected to take pole in hand and lean<lb/>
from ice-berg to ice-berg across the Straits in the dead of winter.<lb/>
All these questions which would require to be answered,<lb/>
before I would be prepared to say whether it would be expedient<lb/>
or not for this Colony to enter into the proposed union. I have<lb/>
heard it objected by some that, this Island could have no repre<lb break="no"/>sentation in the executive government of the United colonies, as<lb/>
on a count of the distance, and the inconvenience of travelling,<lb/>
members of government from here would be unable to attend<lb/>
the cabinet meetings of council .I, however, can see no force<lb/>
in this objection, as any gentlemen who might obtain a seat in <lb/>
the executive of the United Provinces would no doubt have a <lb/>
salaried office of £1000 a year. It is also objected by some that this<lb/>
Colony would be swamped in a Union with the other Provinces.<lb/>
I, Sir, have an apprehensions on their ground, - I would not al<lb break="no"/>low myself or my country to be swamped by any body of men<lb/>
on earth. We, Sir, are here to maintain our rights, and we<lb/>
shall never enter a Union which will deprive us of this birthright<lb/>
in a united Legislature we might possess the balance of parties,<lb/>
and if refused our [illegible], might force the government to do us<lb/>
justice. We would be in a position similar to the Irish member<lb/>
in the British Parliament who frequently compel the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, yield to their requests. But as I have already stated<lb/>
the only coarse which is [illegible] for us at present to adopt, is<lb/>
that pointed out in the resolution which I have submitted, namely<lb/>

<cb/> 

to authorize the appointment of Delegates in the first place<lb/>
simply to consider the expediency of a Union.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE3">Hon. COLONIAL SECRETARY</persName>- hon Chairman, [illegible]<lb/>
with much pleasure, the resolution just submitted by my<lb/>
honorable friend, the Leader of the Government. It pro<lb break="no"/>poses that this House shall authorize His Excellency the<lb/>
Lieutenant Governor to appoint delegates to confer with dele<lb break="no"/>gates who may be appointed by the neighboring Provinces<lb/>
of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, for the purpose of dis<lb break="no"/>cussing the expediency of a union of the lower Provinces-<lb break="yes"/>or rather a reunion of three dependencies. Chief among<lb/>
the [illegible], from which have sprung the evils under which<lb/>
this Island suffers, in my opinion, may be ranked the grant<lb break="no"/>ing the Township lands in the year 1767 and the constituting<lb/>
the Island a separate government three years afterwards.<lb/>
The one evil produced the other. In [illegible], in answer to the<lb/>
prayer of a large number of the grantees, this Island was<lb/>
separated from the Province of Novia Scotia, of which New<lb/>
Brunswick was then a part and constituted a distinct govern<lb break="no"/>ment, on condition that the grantees should provide funds<lb/>
for the payment of its civil establishment. The grantees,<lb/>
although they failed to perform their contract in this respect<lb/>
[illegible], nevertheless, been [illegible] to control the destinies of<lb/>
the colony, from the first day of its existence as a separate<lb/>
government, to the present hour. They also, without an<lb/>
exception, neglected to fulfill the conditions upon which they<lb/>
received their Townships, yet such was the influence which<lb/>
they were enabled to command, that they did so with<lb/>
impunity. Their lands became liable to [illegible], and should<lb/>
have been [illegible] by the Crown, but the grantees induced<lb/>
the Ministers of George III, from [illegible] , to waive the<lb/>
forfeitures; and the evil created by the original grantes has,<lb/>
in consequence, been perpetuated to this day. I have stated<lb/>
that this Island was, prior to 1769, a portion of the Province<lb/>
of Novia Scotia, although this was the case, the inhabitants<lb/>
were not represented in the parliament of Nova Scotia,<lb/>
nor were the laws of that Province made to extend to<lb/>
Prince Edward Island. In 1768 the Government of<lb/>
Nova Scotia sent to the Island a Mr. Morris- Survey or<lb/>
of the Prince of Nova Scotia- who [illegible] off Charlottetown<lb/>
[illegible] a Mr. Deschamps, who was appointed by Governor Frank<lb/>
[illegible] the first Magistrate of the Island of Saint John. This<lb/>
gentleman in that year opened the Court of Common [illegible]<lb/>
in Charlottetown, and from his reports, I learn that the popu<lb break="no"/>lation of the Island then consisted of 271 souls- of whom<lb/>
2016 were French Acadians. There is something very ludi<lb break="no"/>crious in the idea of a colony so limited in extent as this<lb/>
Island, and containing only a few hundred of inhabitants,<lb/>
having a "Captain General" and "Governor-in-Chief" and<lb/>
two Legislative Chambers- playing at Kings, Lords and Com<lb break="no"/>moners. In 1774, the fifth year of the existence of the Island<lb/>
as a separate government - a census was taken- and it was<lb/>
found that the population of the Island had increased to<lb/>
[illegible] souls. In 1784 our Island was re-annexed to Nova<lb/>
Scotia. It nevertheless [illegible] its separate government <lb/>
and legislature, although Walter Patterson, therefore<lb/>
"Captain-General and Governor-in-Chief," received Dutch<lb/>
promotion, and was afterwards known as "Lieutenant Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor." Mr. Chairman, the inhabitants of this Island have<lb/>
never been able to remedy the first of the two evils of which<lb/>
I have spoken, that caused by the original grants and to re<lb break="no"/>invest in the Crown the lands so injudiciously granted in<lb/>
1767; but Sir, they may now remedy the second, they may<lb/>
now again become one with the neighboring Provinces. I pur<lb break="no"/>pose to enquire. How would such re-union effect this Island.<lb/>
It must be plain to every gentleman of this Committee, that the<lb/>
legislation of this Island cannot be of a nature calculated to<lb/>
develop its resources and to promote its prosperity, so long<lb/>
as the inhabitants are divided into two parties, the one vio<lb break="no"/>lently antagonistic to the other- so long as the chief object<lb/>
of one party is to hold office, and of the other to obtain office.<lb/>
I readily admit, Mr. Chairman, that, in my opinion, we have<lb/>
party legislation in the worst form, and that neither of the<lb/>
parties into which we are divided, is free from the influence<lb/>
of party spirit. Partly [illegible] are violent in all com<lb break="no"/>munities, in proportion to their size. Our ocmmunity is a<lb/>
very limited one, and the difference which divide us par<lb break="no"/>take of a religious character. 85,000 of our inhabitants are <lb/>
arrayed in bitter antagonism to the remaining 45,000. We<lb/>

<pb n="34" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_034.jpg"/> <fw type="num">34</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER 1864</fw> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">34</fw>

have 35,000 Roman Catholic, the majority of them Irish, of <lb/>
the extreme, ultramontans stamp, and we have 45,000 Pro<lb break="no"/>testants, the majority of whom are Scotch Presbyterian,<lb/>
many the sons of covenanters, who will never submit to be<lb/>
made by Roman Catholics. If this Island were united with<lb/>
the neighboring Provinces, our protestant populations would<lb/>
have less ??? to speed Popish supremacy than they have at<lb/>
present, religious animosities would be weakened, and great<lb/>
good would be the consequence. Another result of such<lb/>
union would be the establishment of an uniform currency,<lb/>
an uniform Tarrif, a common Legislature, and a common<lb/>
Judiciary. The deliberation of the Legislature of the United<lb/>
Provinces, upon our Island matters, would be more distinter<lb break="no"/>ested, more liberal, and enlightened, than we can ever<lb/>
expect from our little Legislature constituted as at present.<lb/>
Judges who now preside in our Courts, have practised<lb/>
for many years at our Bar, and are acquainted with almost<lb/>
every suitor who comes into Court.It occasionally happens<lb/>
that they are disqualified or try actions brought, and conse<lb break="no"/>quences of their having then employed as Attorney or Counsel<lb/>
in such actions, and, Sir, although in their impartiality and<lb/>
integrity have never been questioned, in my opinion, they<lb/>
cannot but I take in the prejudices of the little community<lb/>
in which they have so long lived. I would ask, Sir, what<lb/>
has been the chief subjects of legislation in this House<lb/>
during the past half century ? The Land Question, - the Land<lb/>
Tenures - conflicts between Landlords and Tenants, and, Sir,<lb/>
when proprietors of land in this Island, have, at the Colonial<lb/>
office, objected to bills passed in this house, and urged that<lb/>
such bills were passed by tenants to the prejudice of their<lb/>
landlords, is it not reasonable to suppose that their objec<lb break="no"/>tions have carried with them as influence, attributable<lb/>
chiefly to the character of the legislators. I can readily<lb/>
understand that Bills passed by our Legislature, as at pre<lb break="no"/>sent constituted, would, if opposed by the Proprietors, be<lb/>
disallowed, which, should they be enacted by a Legislature<lb/>
such as we shall have, in the event of a union, would be<lb/>
confirmed by the Sovereign in the face of greater opposition.<lb/>
The people of this Island should ask themselves these ques<lb break="no"/>tions. In the even of a union will they be called upon to<lb/>
pay more in the shape of taxes than they pay at present ? If<lb/>
so will they derive more than corresponding benefits ? It<lb/>
must be evident to every member of this Committee, that if<lb/>
the farmers of this Island shall have better Roads, Bridges<lb/>
and Wharves, better accomodation for shipping their products<lb/>
better communication by means of steamers over our rivers,<lb/>
and with the other Provinces, and better markets than they<lb/>
possess at present, they will be able to pay a moderately in<lb break="no"/>creases taxation with greater ease than they pay the taxes<lb/>
now extracted from them. The farmers may rest assured that<lb/>
a ???? with the adjoining Provinces would not cause their<lb/>
lands to yield less than they yield at present. Would the<lb/>
circumstances of our being united cause capital to be<lb/>
invested in this Island ? If so, it is for our interest that we should<lb/>
be united. The chief exports of this Island are Ships and<lb/>
Agricultural Produce - Oats. I, Mr. Chairman, cannot re<lb break="no"/>gard the future of this Island as being as bright, or as<lb/>
promising as many consider it. The past year, it is true,<lb/>
has been one of unexampled prosperity. But do we not owe<lb/>
this to the fact that shipbuilding is a most precarious<lb/>
business, and that whether it shall continue profitable or<lb/>
otherwise, it must soon cease with us, simply because the day<lb/>
is very near, when materials for the construction of ships<lb/>
will not be found on the island? Already our shipbuilders<lb/>
import materials from New Brunswick and Nova Scotia.<lb/>
The report from Mr. Wightman has showns us that forty per<lb/>
cent of the tenantcy of this Island do not produce from their<lb/>
farms a sufficiency of food. How do these people procure the<lb/>
necessities of life ? I answer by the employment which<lb/>
shipbuilding demands. What will become of such persons<lb/>
when shipbuilding can no longer be carried on in this Island -<lb/>
when our forests shall have entirely disappeared ? They must<lb/>
emigrate - or depend upon the sailor upon the fisheries. We<lb/>
have during the year just passed exported from the Island<lb/>
about 1,490,000 bushels of oats, for which our farmers re<lb break="no"/>ceived remunerative prices. The demand in the United<lb/>
States, consequent upon the war, had greatly increased the<lb/>
value of oats. But this unhappy war must come to an end.<lb/>

<cb/> 

The termination of the American Reciprocity Treaty we may <lb/>
look for, and should this event occur during the present year,<lb/>
and, a duty, as formerly, be imposed upon our agricultural<lb/>
produce on its importation into the United States, we shall<lb/>
have to depend chiefly upon England as a market for our<lb/>
oats, and the English market is an uncertain one. At present<lb/>
it is very low. Mr. Chairman :-Many persons consider the<lb/>
enormous export of oats during the past year as a proof of<lb/>
agricultural prosperity. I view this exportation in a very<lb/>
different light. I consider it proof of bad farming - an<lb/>
evidence that, tempted by the high prices which oats have<lb/>
commanded during the past three of four years - our farmers<lb/>
have grown them, to the great injury of their lands. It is<lb/>
well known, that land which will not yield wheat, or barley,<lb/>
will give good oats, and that oats are a very exhausting crop.<lb/>
Where oats have been grown upon the same land several<lb/>
years in anccession, without manure, as they generally have <lb/>
been in this Island, the result must necessarily be the con<lb break="no"/>plete exhaustion of the soil. Mr. Chairman : - Those who <lb/>
pride themselves upon the agricultural prosperity of this Is<lb break="no"/>land at the present time, should not forget that of this 1,400,000 <lb/>
bushels of oats exported, at least 800,000 would be required<lb/>
to pay for the bread stuffs imported, - for the more than 40,<lb break="no"/>000 barrels of flour brought into the Colony in 1863. Not <lb/>
only are the lands of the great majority of our farmers, be<lb break="no"/>coming exhausted by injudicious cropping ; they are also fast <lb/>
being denuded of materials necessarily required for fuel and<lb/>
fencing. Many farms are not destitute of both. Such ??? <lb/>
for fence poles may be found in hedges and dykes ; and these <lb/>
the farmers can themselves construct ; but when firewood <lb/>
shall have disappeared, coal will have to be purchases and <lb/>
when the agriculturists of this Island shall be necessitated to <lb/>
pay for coal, and to haul it from the harbors on the coast to <lb/>
their farms in the interior - ??? then shall have no more <lb/>
new land - rich in the mould formed by the decayed leaves or <lb/>
fertilized by the ashes obtained from wood burns in the <lb/>
process of clearing to fall back upon, when manure will <lb/>
have to be obtained in order to render productive the lands <lb/>
which over-cropping have exhausted yield when hedges <lb/>
will have to be planted, and dykes constructed, ??? will <lb/>
large portions of Prince Edward Island be far less prosperous <lb/>
than they are at present. Add to this, the evils something<lb/>
from the inhabitants being divided into two parties, each<lb/>
regarding the other with animosity. Under such circum<lb break="no"/>stances, Mr. Chairman, I fear that if left to ourselves, we <lb/>
shall share the fate of the Killkenny Cats. We have no <lb/>
mines, no minerals, no quarries of limestone, no extensive <lb/>
forests. Our dependence, ultimately must be solely upon <lb/>
our Agriculture and our Fisheries. To develop these, we <lb/>
require capital. Would a Union with the sister Provinces, <lb/>
cause capital to be invested in this Island ? I think Mr. Chair<lb break="no"/>man, it would. This, I repeat, is a very important consideration. <lb/>
If it can be shown that one result of a union would be that <lb/>
persons in Nova Scotia and New Brunswick would employ<lb/>
capital in this Island, in farming and fishing, it is clearly<lb/>
for our interest that we should assent to the proposed Union.<lb/>
The Railroads of Nova Scotia, and New Brunswick, will soon<lb/>
connect our island, very closely with the commercial capitals<lb/>
of those Provinces. Our lands are more easily cultivated<lb/>
than are those of either Provinces, and are quite produc<lb break="no"/>tive as the land of Nova Scotia or New Brunswick, - the<lb/>
alluvial lands of those Provinces excpeted. Our Fisheries<lb/>
are the best in the British Provinces. Soon being the case,<lb/>
I think it may fairly be assumed that if this island, were a<lb/>
portion of the Union, under a common Legislature, in which<lb/>
the people of the adjoining Provinces had confidence, and<lb/>
which would afford a guarantee for enlightened legislation,<lb/>
and the protection of the rights of property, we should find<lb/>
many disposed to invest their capital in this Island, who<lb/>
will never do so, so long as it remains what it now is, a very<lb/>
little community torn by the contentions of rival political<lb/>
and religious parties. I have said, Mr. Chairman, that I<lb/>
cannot regard the future of this Island as bright, I view<lb/>
that of Nova Scotia, and New Brunswick very differently.<lb/>
It has been stated that the debt of those Provinces is enor<lb break="no"/>mous and their taxation excessive. As to taxation it is very<lb/>
little in advance of our own. The amount of their debt is<lb/>
not such as should occasion any alarm. They have con<lb break="no"/>structed Railroads, and in doing so, have created a debt it is<lb/>
true ; but in this ago, in every country, Railroads are a<lb/>

<pb n="35" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_035.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">35</fw> 

necessary. Mr Chairman, hope are long to see Rairoads <lb/>
___ those Provinces Halifax to Canada and<lb/>
accessible to immigrants. The resources of the neighbor<lb break="no"/>ing Provinces are boundless. In Nova Scotia, especially,<lb/>
__, Coal, and ___ are to be found in inexhaustible<lb/>
quality. In New Brunswick, in addition to minerals, these<lb/>
____ forests had extensive districts of land suitable<lb/>
for cultivation. In those Provinces are noble Harbors open<lb/>
all the year round, and, Sir, I cannot believe that the day is<lb/>
far distant, when by means of the railroads, of which I have<lb/>
spoken, the trade of Canada will find its outlet during a<lb/>
great portion of the year, in the Harbors of St John, and<lb/>
Halifax. I should have been better pleased, Sir, had the<lb/>
resolution before you, proposed a Union of all the British<lb/>
Provinces on the Atlantic Board. Such a Union, I consider,<lb/>
made some day take place, and I trust the Union of the mari<lb break="no"/>time Provinces will prove the first step towards it. Who can<lb/>
ever ___ the commercial greatness which these depend<lb break="no"/>encies of Great Britain are destined to attain ? Less than a<lb/>
century ago, the entire exports of Great Britain did not ex<lb break="no"/>ceed $50,000,000. The exports of Canada alone, for 1868,<lb/>
reached more than half this amount. At the time of the<lb/>
accession of Queen Ann, the exports of Great Britain were less<lb/>
by one fourth than the exports of Canada, for 1868. Burke,<lb/>
the friend and advocate of the British Colonies, employed his<lb/>
eloquence to portray, the commercial growth, which during<lb/>
a life time, those of the North American Colonies of his day, —<lb/>
now included in the neighboring Republic,—had attained.<lb/>
He pictured them in 1704, men in a commercial sense, utterly<lb/>
insignificant—of Countries which served for title more than<lb/>
to amuse with stories of savage life and unsouth manners.<lb/>
In 1776, he saw them possessed of a Commerce equal to this,<lb/>
which, seventy years previously, had made England the envy<lb/>
of the world. The progress of the Colonies, after they at<lb break="no"/>tained their independence, was far greater than that which<lb/>
had excited the wonder of Burke. Mr Chairman, at this day,<lb/>
British North America comprises a larger territory than was<lb/>
possessed by the Revolted Colonies in 1776, larger than the<lb/>
limited States now possess, and although much of this<lb/>
territory must necessarily remain sterile, so far as agriculture<lb/>
is concerned, it is nevertheless valuable. The population of<lb/>
Canada, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, and Prince Edward<lb/>
Island, is greater than was that of the Revolted Colonies of<lb/>
the date of their independence. Our mines and minerals<lb/>
and forests are as valuable as were theirs. We have magni<lb break="no"/>ficent, rivers and lakes connecting the Atlantic with the far<lb/>
West. Our people are a hardy race characterizes by deter<lb break="no"/>mination of character, and fitted to overcome those ___<lb/>
which are caused by the nature of our climate, which how<lb break="no"/>ever, is not more savage than in portions of Germany, of<lb/>
Sweden, of Norway or of Russia. We possess all the ele<lb break="no"/>ments, essential to the formatio of a great and powerful<lb/>
people. Why should we not advance towards greatness in<lb/>
something like the same ___ as did the Revolted Colonies ?<lb/>
The manufactures of England, are the chief source of her<lb/>
wealth. Those who have travelled through that Country<lb/>
are aware, that it is little other than a vast workshop, from<lb/>
which a great portion of the world is supplied. Why should<lb/>
not the people of British America have their manufactures ?<lb/>
They have iron, and coal, and ___, why should they<lb/>
not turn them to ___ ? Why should they depend upon<lb/>
England for articles manufactured from iron ? I can see no<lb/>
reason why. Food is __ easily obtained int he Colonies<lb/>
then in England and after all, Mr Chairman, the question of<lb/>
labor ___ itself into bread and butter. It is well known<lb/>
to this Committee, that the people of New England, before<lb/>
the Reciprocity Treaty was ___ carried coal, and<lb/>
__ and ___ from Nova Scotia to the Unitefd States, <lb/>
manufactured them, and brought them back to us,—that we<lb/>
___ them and notwithstanding the manufactures had<lb/>
paid the duties, and a double ___, they became __<lb/>
Mr Chairman, I was satisfied that Canada, New Brunswick,<lb/>
and Nova Scotia, will be united, and that, after the example<lb/>
of the Revolted Colonies, they will become a great and<lb/>
wealthy people. I desire that this my native Island may<lb/>
___ their greatness, she not remain, ___ present, the<lb/>
___ of assembly contests, which prevent all ___ legis<lb break="no"/>

<cb/> 

lation. In conclusion, Mr Chairman, the question under <lb/>
discussion that they should be fully consulted, that the matter<lb/>
should be fully discussed, and notwithstanding my individual<lb/>
opinions. I shall not be prepared to vote for a Union. Until<lb/>
after they shall have been consulted, and the question dis<lb break="no"/>cussed among them ; but, Sir, this House is not called upon<lb/>
to come to any such vote. The question before the Comit<lb break="no"/>tee is, shall we send delegates to confer with the delegates<lb/>
from the other Provinces, on the expediency of a Union, and,<lb/>
whatever may be the opinions of hon. members—however<lb/>
much they may be opposed to the proposed Union—common<lb/>
courtesy requires us to send delegates as proposed by they<lb/>
resolution before you.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.—Mr Chairman, this is a subject, which, <lb/>
as the hon. Col. Secretary has justly remarked, is not a<lb/>
party question ; but I presume it will be like other questions,<lb/>
there will be a party in its favor, and a party opposed to it.<lb/>
The hon. member who last spoke, hinted that there is no<lb/>
security of property in this Colony. Now, Sir, I believe<lb/>
there never was a measure introduced into this Legislature<lb/>
so calculated to interfere with the rights of property as the<lb/>
Bill on the Land Question, submitted this morning by the<lb/>
hon. leader of the Government. It is only a piece of politi<lb break="no"/>cal clap-trap. The subject of the war in the neighboring<lb/>
States has been introduced into this debate, and we have<lb/>
been told that when it terminates, a host of mercenaries will<lb/>
be ready to rush in upon these Colonies. I entertain no fears<lb/>
on this ground, for I have every confidence in the power of<lb/>
Great Britain to defend her possessions against the combined<lb/>
force of either the Northern or Southern States. The hon.<lb/>
leader of the Government said that he could not support a<lb/>
resolution similar to those passed in the adjoining Province,<lb/>
_ that delegates should be appointed to arrange a preliminary<lb/>
plan in regard to Union. I concur with the hon. member in<lb/>
this view of the subject; we ought first to consider whether<lb/>
a union at all is desirable. I hold my own opinions respect<lb break="no"/>ing a union of the Colonies. I have long thought that these<lb/>
Provinces ought to have more influence at the Colonial Office.<lb/>
This Island as also the other Colonies have labored under<lb/>
great disadvantage in this respect—a disadvantage which a<lb/>
union of the whole would probably have removed. Still it<lb/>
does not appear to me that great benefit would result from a<lb/>
union of the three maritime Provinces. We have been<lb/>
making progress, small as our Colonies. I hold in my hand<lb/>
an order of the date of 1790, for is, which is a fair specimen<lb/>
of our currency at that time. Now we have two or three<lb/>
Banks, and an extensive trade ; so I think we better work<lb/>
along with our separate government, until it is thought that<lb/>
"the time has arrived" to consummate a federal union of the<lb/>
whole of British America, allowing each Colony to retain its<lb/>
own Legislature. If this could be effected with the good will<lb/>
of the Home Government—Britain acting towards us in a<lb/>
friendly and paternal manner, just as a father does with a<lb/>
son setting up for himself—it might be well. The new gov<lb break="no"/>ernment might be either a monarchy or a republic, but I, for<lb/>
my part, would prefer a monarchy. All the Colonies united<lb/>
from Newfoundland to Columbia, would be one of the most<lb/>
powerful governments on the face of the earth ; but with<lb/>
only Nova Scotia, New Brunswick and this Island united,<lb/>
we would still be looked down upon by our neighbors. I do<lb/>
not think the people of this Island would agree to such a<lb/>
union as is proposed ; if they would consent to a change at<lb/>
all, I believe they would desire a union that would place the<lb/>
Colonies in a position that would give them some weight<lb/>
among the powers that be. As to religious strife here being<lb/>
an argument in favor of our union which the other Colonies,<lb/>
a differ from the hon. Colonial Secretary. If people are dis<lb break="no"/>posed, to be contentious in regard to creeds, union with<lb/>
another body of men will not prevent it. In fact, I believe<lb/>
that the religious strife which exists in this Island was an<lb/>
infection from the other Provinces. It occurs to me that this<lb/>
union delegation will be like the one on the land question ;<lb/>
it will cost several hundred pounds and produce nothing, I<lb/>
do not __ that I shall oppose the motion for the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of delegates but I would prefer taking higher ground<lb/>
than a legislative union of the three maritime Provinces.<lb/>
We might again _ some points by such a union, yet the other<lb/>
Colonies have a __ debt, and I am inclined to believe that<lb/>

<pb n="36" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_036.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">36</fw> 

we would get along just as well without being connected <lb/>
with them. This question should be considered solely on its<lb/>
own merits, altogether irrespective of what it is taking place<lb/>
in the neighboring states, or any other country, and I hope<lb/>
hon. members will take no hasty view of the matter. We<lb/>
might to some extent the committing ourselves to union, by<lb/>
if very appointment of a delegation.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCAU1">Hon. Mr. McAULAY</persName> - It is true that by passing the reso<lb break="no"/>lution before the Committee we are acknowledging that a<lb/>
union may possibly be desirable; would while doing so, it<lb/>
carefully goes against committing us to any course which<lb/>
Might result in our destruction. A union of these three Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, has much to recommend it. The suggestion has come<lb/>
from the other Provinces, and it would be uncourteous in us<lb/>
Not to send delegates to me the delegates whom they may ap<lb break="no"/>point. We might wait until we hear the report of those<lb/>
delegates before we pronounce an opinion as to whether<lb/>
It would be desirable for this colony to enter the pro<lb break="no"/>posed union or not. For my own part, I would rather hear<lb/>
arguments against than for the union, because it is better to en<lb break="no"/>dure the ills we know man to endure those with which we are<lb/>
entirely unacquainted. United with the other Provinces, we<lb/>
would raise money here for revenues that would be divided by<lb/>
other hands. Supposing even that there was a territorial division<lb/>
of the money, we would scarcely be allowed to obtain our share,<lb/>
as if they would maintain that their railways were in part for our<lb/>
advantage as well as theirs. Another consideration is that our<lb/>
roads in this Island are not so durable as in Nova Scotia, and<lb/>
consequently it would require more to keep them in repair-a<lb/>
necessity which the united Legislature might not be willing to<lb/>
meet. Religions agitation has been referred to as an argument<lb/>
in favor of the union, but it is very doubtful if strife would cease<lb/>
where the same elements continue to insist, merely because the<lb/>
community was enlarged. I have never taken any active part<lb/>
iIn this agitation, but I have felt it's effects ever since I first<lb/>
offered for the seat in this House. It is an evil which a union of<lb/>
the Provinces would not quash ; we must wait until it dies out<lb/>
of sheer shame. Now, Mr. Chairman, one point ought to be<lb/>
considered before we enter into the details of the union. Would<lb/>
this colony be allowed to retain a representation of 60 members<lb/>
in the lower House of the United Legislature, in would Nova<lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick be allowed to retain the same<lb/>
representation as at present? If our representation were<lb/>
decreased, and theirs permitted to continue as now, I conceive<lb/>
it would be doing our Island an injustice. This is a matter for<lb/>
the delegates to consider. I shall support the resolution, be<lb break="no"/>cause the delegates, on't it authorizes His Excellency to<lb/>
appoint, are not to be empowered to decide why [illegible] but<lb/>
merely to hear suggestions, and report to this Legislature.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CONR1">Mr. CONROY</persName> - Mr. Chairman, this subject was partially dis<lb break="no"/>cussed here last session, and on that occasion there was a general<lb/>
expression of opinion against a union of the Colonies. I believe<lb/>
that I was the only member who spoke in its favor ; and my<lb/>
reason for so doing was one assigned by the hon. Colonial<lb/>
Secretary, namely that it might be the means of allaying the <lb/>
religious feeling in the Island. I have weighed the matter since<lb/>
then, and must state that I have arrived at a different conclu<lb break="no"/>sion, and now think that this agitation would not be any argu<lb break="no"/>ment in favor of a union, but rather the reverse. What have<lb/>
the other Colonies to give us in return, if our Legislature is taken<lb/>
away? Nothing, unless they aid us in settling our Land Ques<lb break="no"/>tion, If they could give our people free land as an equivalent<lb/>
for depriving us of our constitution, it might be something. But<lb/>
as the Bill which was introduced this morning respecting the<lb/>
land question will probably be passed, I cannot see what we<lb/>
are to gain by a union. At the meeting which my colleague<lb/>
and I had with out constituents, before we came to the opening<lb/>
of the session, the subject of a union of the Colonies was dis<lb break="no"/>cussed, and they desired us to vote against it should it come up<lb/>
in this House for consideration, as it might place the Colony in<lb/>
a worse position than at present.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LONG2">Hon. Mr. LONGWORTH</persName> - Mr. Chairman, the subject and in <lb/>
consideration is one of vast importance. It appears that the<lb/>
Legislature of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick have adopted<lb/>
a resolution to appoint delegates to arrange a preliminary plan<lb/>
for a union of the three maritime Provinces, and therefore it<lb/>
seems that they have come to the conclusion that such a union<lb/>
is expedient. The question is one which has been discussed for<lb/>
a length of time. The present leader of the Government in<lb/>
Nova Scotia advocated the scheme years ago, as also did the<lb/>

<cb/>
 
leader of the late Government in that Province. The [illegible] <lb/>
description which [illegible] politicians have [illegible]<lb/>
future of these Colonies [illegible] while in [illegible]<lb/>
[illegible] away the [illegible] of [illegible] lower Provinces <lb/>
[illegible] of the proposal. The union of Canada with these <lb/>
Colonies [illegible] immediately [illegible] . Objectives have<lb/>
[illegible] the part of Canada, and this [illegible]<lb/>
difference of population [illegible]<lb/>
[illegible]<lb/>
[illegible]<lb/>
have changed, and Upper Canada has become the most [illegible].<lb/>
[illegible] quite an agitation between backwit parts<lb/>
of that Province with respect [illegible] by population,<lb/>
and [illegible] of the results is that Upper Canada objects to a reign<lb/>
with the lower Colonies, on the ground that as they adjoin Lower<lb/>
Canada, they would probably take part with her. On the other<lb/>
hand, Lower Canada [illegible] objects to the union fearing that [illegible] <lb/>
the population of these Lower Colonies as regards nationality<lb/>
and religion, resemble the people of Upper Canada, she would<lb/>
be such a union be placed in a worse position than at present.<lb/>
Hence a new scheme of union has arisen and it is proposed<lb/>
that these three maritime Provinces alone should unite. It is<lb/>
argued that from their proximity and similarity of interest, they<lb/>
should be united under one Legislature, and that this is necessary<lb/>
to give us of these Colonies standing and respectability in the<lb/>
scale of governments. It is not contemplated to alter our con<lb break="no"/>nection with the Mother country, but merely to make us a larger<lb/>
dependency of the British Crown. As we are peculiarly situated<lb/>
in this Island, I think it would be imprudent in us to raise such<lb/>
resolution as has been agreed to in the other Provinces. They<lb/>
no doubt feel that the advantage would be on their side, and there<lb break="no"/>fore they had no hesitation in adopting such a resolution as has<lb/>
been referred to. They anticipate no danger to their interests in<lb/>
resolving to take little Prince Edward Island under their wing.<lb/>
We are not burdened with the same proportionate amount of<lb/>
debt as the adjooining Colonies, consequently though we might<lb/>
hesitate in deciding as to the expediency of a union, they at once<lb/>
commit themselves in the course. They have nothing to lose<lb/>
for as they have more railways to construct, their debt must go on<lb/>
increasing. At the present moment, we hear of several Railways<lb/>
being projected in New Brunswick, as well as a very expensive<lb/>
one in Nova Scotia to connect Truro with Pictou, and Bills, it is<lb/>
reported are now actually before the Legislature of these Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces for giving effect to those projects. In addition to all this,<lb/>
it would appear that a change in the policy of the Canadian<lb/>
Government in regard to the Intercolonial Railroad had recently<lb/>
taken place, and that that vast scheme for the purpose of opening<lb/>
a great railway through Canada and New Brunswick to Halifax<lb/>
is likely to be realized. These undertakings must involve a<lb/>
large amount of expenditure, and entail upon the Provinces of<lb/>
Canada, New Brunswick and Nova Scotia a large sacrifice to<lb/>
their public debts, and, as a necessary consequence, an increased<lb/>
[illegible] upon the people of those Respective Provinces. The<lb/>
local Railways must be both at the cost of the Provinces to<lb/>
with htey belong, and the Intercolonial at the joint ecpense of<lb/>
the [illegible] . The question now arises, as these works are to be<lb/>
constructed for the [illegible] of these Provinces, and [illegible] <lb/>
of is, what advantage [illegible] from a union with Nova<lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick that we do not enjoy in our present<lb/>
position ? As an agricultural country, we [illegible] benefit by the<lb/>
[illegible] of these works to supply [illegible] <lb/>
[illegible]<lb/>
our Island ; but what [illegible] which we will enjoy [illegible] <lb/>
we enter the union or [illegible] our independent condition. The<lb/>
hand of nature to be giving us our fruitful a soil and so [illegible] a<lb/>
climate, has secured [illegible] advantage to be independent of all<lb/>
political or national consideration similar [illegible] present position<lb/>
we enjoy comparative [illegible] from taxation. There [illegible] facts <lb/>
which bargained we lose sight of [illegible] we are prepared to<lb/>
yield up our local Legislature and the right of taxation [illegible]<lb/>
for our local purposes and improvements and [illegible] besides<lb/>
all the other advantages which our independent position as a<lb/>
[illegible] Colonial Government confer upon us, we must [illegible] that <lb/>
we are to receive larger and more permanent advantages - in<lb/>
fact, as [illegible] for what we are called upon to surrender. <lb/>
The question, then, as has been already remarked is, what are<lb/>
we going to gain by such a union ? Should it [illegible]<lb/>
of religious feeling it might be something in the scale ; but there<lb/>
is very little prospect of this being a result, seeing it is a matter<lb/>
entirely among ourselves. It is [illegible] been which the other Colonies<lb/>
can offer, it is only an effect which might arise out of union. It<lb/>
appears to me that they can scarcely offer us an equivalent for<lb/>

<pb n="37" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-03-22_Page_037.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">37</fw>
 
our independent position, and hence I consider that the resolution<lb/>
proposed by the hon. leader of the Government, is the only one<lb/>
we can safely adopt. We must not commit ourselves to the<lb/>
union as the other Colonies, by their Resolutions, appear to have<lb/>
done. We should first consider the expedience of a union ; but<lb/>
before we can be in a position to do so, we must hear the argu<lb break="no"/>ments and reasons which may be offered in support of it, and<lb/>
therefore, it is our duty to appoint delegates ; to refuse this much,<lb/>
would be uncourteous to our sister Colonies. Besides, we can<lb break="no"/>not lose by obtaining information; upon all colonial questions<lb/>
which may have a tendency to affect us as a government or a<lb/>
people. If the time should arrive when we might be necessitated<lb/>
to enter into a union, by refusing to confer on the subject now,<lb/>
we might be placed in a disadvantageous position hereafter.<lb/>
But while we appoint delegates, we must not tie up our hands,<lb/>
and commit ourselves to a union, without knowing what equiva<lb break="no"/>lent we are to receive. I admit that it might add to our im<lb break="no"/>portance to be a part of a larger Province which might be called<lb/>
Acadia or Cabotis, or any thing else, still this would not satisfy<lb/>
our people unless there was some material and great permanent<lb/>
advantage to be gained by the change. Though united with<lb/>
Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, we could do little in giving<lb/>
battle to a government like the United States, if it should ever<lb/>
be the policy of that country to go to war with England or her <lb/>
North American Colonies ; consequently, I can see no force in<lb/>
the argument drawn from probable occurrences in that country.<lb/>
We must look to ourselves, and our own interests, and act ac<lb break="no"/>cordingly. The practical difficulty that would be experienced<lb/>
by us in sending Representatives across our ice-bound Strait in<lb/>
the winter season to attend the United Legislature in Halifax, or<lb/>
some other favored city on the other side of the water, seems to<lb/>
me at present almost sufficient to overbalance every argument in<lb/>
favor of the project, unless indeed, Charlottetown were made<lb/>
the capital of the United Provinces, which we could not expect<lb/>
it would be. The question is, then, should we give up our <lb/>
independent position—our separate Government—and become a<lb/>
part of a greater Province ? My own opinion is decidedly in the<lb/>
negative, but the question can only be satisfactorily answered<lb/>
when we ascertain the terms of union, which it would be the<lb/>
duty of delegates, if appointed, to learn ; therefore, I will support<lb/>
the resolution before the Committee authorizing such appointment,<lb/>
reserving to ourselves, as a Legislature, our own action hereafter<lb/>
upon the results of that Delegation.<lb/></p> 

<p>Adjourned for one hour.<lb/></p> 

<!-- DL 2018-05-23 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>MONDAY AFTERNOON, April 18.<lb/></p> 

<p>Committee on despatches resumed.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. SPEAKER.—Mr. Chairman, since I have had<lb/>
a seat in this House, many questions of moment have<lb/>
been introduced and discussed, but although I was a<lb/>
member of the Legislature at the times when the princi<lb break="no"/>ples of Responsible Government, Free Trade, and an Elec<lb break="no"/>tive Legislative Council were debated, yet the subject on<lb/>
which we are now engaged, is, in my opinion, of import<lb break="no"/>ance paramount to any which has ever engaged the at<lb break="no"/>tention of our local legislature. The question at issue is<lb/>
briefly, whether we are to have a Legislature of our own,<lb/>
or whether we shall be absorbed by union with Nova<lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick. This is a subject which can<lb/>
be discussed without party bias, and it is the duty of<lb/>
every hon. member to give his individual opinion on a <lb/>
matter of such importance, irrespectively of the obliga<lb break="no"/>tions which the interests of political combination in many<lb/>
cases impose. This question of a union of the Maritime<lb/>
Colonies is not a new one. In 1814, the father of Her<lb/>
Majesty, the late Duke of Kent, while Commander-in-<lb break="maybe"/>Chief of the Province of Nova Scotia, corresponded on<lb/>
the subject with Judge Sewell in Canada. The Duke was<lb/>
of opinion that these Colonies, without a political union,<lb/>
would never occupy the influential position to which they<lb/>
were entitled by the elements of material prosperity<lb/>
which they possessed. It was urged this morning as an<lb/>
argument in favor of the union, that, in the event of a<lb/>
cessation of the present civil war in the States, we would<lb/>
be powerless against a northern army or against the<lb/>
united forces of the restored union. If that be the only<lb/>
argument which can be advanced by the advocates of the<lb/></p> 

<p>10<lb/></p> <milestone type="unknown"/> 

<p>suggested, association, their position is weak indeed ; for<lb/>
I ask, what could the united colonies effect against the<lb/>
forces which could be brought against them ? Assuming<lb/>
the population of the Canadas to be two and one-half<lb/>
millions, and that of the Lower Provinces half a million,<lb/>
can it be expected that we could, in case of invasion, offer<lb/>
successful resistance to the disciplined armies which a<lb/>
population exceeding twenty millions could send forth ?<lb/>
The minds of hon. members may be seduced from a sober<lb/>
consideration of this question, by the idea that we would<lb/>
be laying the foundations of a great country, and I admit<lb/>
the influence of that feeling on my own mind last Session.<lb/>
But, Sir, I confess that a change has come o'er the spirit<lb/>
of my dream. What benefits are we to reap from the <lb/>
proposed reunion, for we were united up to 1769 ? New<lb/>
Brunswick has a large funded debt, in comparison to<lb/>
which our public liabilities, the fruitful subject of so<lb/>
much grumbling, are mere matter of moonshine. The<lb/>
public debt of the Island amounts to not more than<lb/>
£60,000 or £ 70,000, and we have the public domain to<lb/>
the credit of the country. Although the resolution sub<lb break="no"/>mitted does not commit this House to the expression of<lb/>
any opinion on the subject of the union of the colonies, it<lb/>
is but right that the delegates, who may be appointed as<lb/>
the representatives of the Island at the proposed conference,<lb/>
should have their position fortified by the avowed senti<lb break="no"/>ments of members of the Legislature—that they should<lb/>
be able to tell the representatives of the sister colonies<lb/>
what are the feelings of those whom they represent. I<lb/>
am decidedly of opinion that we should, as an act of com<lb break="no"/>mon courtesy, assent to the appointment of delegates, if<lb/>
for no other purpose than that of hearing what proposi<lb break="no"/>tions may be offered by the representatives of the other<lb/>
provinces. With this view, I shall support the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, but I entertain very decided objections to the pro<lb break="no"/>posed union. In New Brunswick, the Railway barely<lb/>
supports itself, and earns nothing towards repayment of<lb/>
the money borrowed for its construction. In looking<lb/>
over the Journals of the House of Assembly of that Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, I find that its Railway Debentures require no less<lb/>
than £58,000 annual interest, to be paid at Baring's in<lb/>
London. In his speech on the Union of the Lower Colo<lb break="no"/>nies, the Hon. Mr. Tupper, Provincial Secretary of Nova<lb/>
Scotia, said that the time had not yet arrived for an<lb/>
union with Canada because of the large debt of that<lb/>
Colony. " I thank thee, Jew, for teaching me that word, "<lb/>
for the argument deduced from it, is applicable against<lb/>
our union with the other colonies. Canada is burdened<lb/>
with a debt of more than sixty millions of dollars, and<lb/>
there is an annual deficit in the revenue of a million. As<lb/>
to the idea attributed to the Imperial Government that<lb/>
these Colonies are able to bear the burden of defending<lb/>
themselves against the invasion of a foreign foe, the<lb/>
sooner Great Britain awakes from that delusion the<lb/>
better. Our small annual appropriation of £400 for the<lb/>
volunteer organization is not passed without strong ex<lb break="no"/>pressions of disapprobation, while Nova Scotia grants<lb/>
$20,000 for that service. If we are to have a union, I<lb/>
should hope that it would be of a Federative, not Legis<lb break="no"/>lative, character, so that we might retain our Local<lb/>
Legislature, and our people have the management of our<lb/>
affairs. Our status, if united, would, I am bound<lb/>
to assume, be adjusted on the basis, either of territorial area<lb/>
or numerical ratio of population. If the first criterion be<lb/>
adopted, we would occupy a very inconsiderable position<lb/>
in the United Legislature. If our representation is to be<lb/>
regulated by population, the official statistics on that<lb/>
point afford but little prospect of Prince Edward Island<lb/>
exercising much influence in the halls of the United<lb/>
Colonies. The House of Assembly in Nova Scotis is com<lb break="no"/>posed of some 55 members, New Brunswick has 42 or 43,<lb/>
and in any political combination of the kind foreshadowed,<lb/>
we might expect to receive the treatment that Scotland<lb/>
and Ireland were subjected to when their separate Legis<lb break="no"/>latures were abolished. I own, Mr. Chairman, to a feel<lb break="no"/>ing of surprise when I read the allusion made by the Hon.<lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>