<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-03-29"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>


<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-03-29">29 March 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1870, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1870"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="134"/>
</bibl>

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_126.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_128.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_130.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_132.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_134.hocr.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-15">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_126">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_126.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_128">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_128.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_130">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_130.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_132">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_132.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_134">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_134.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="126" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_126.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">126</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:bold"><hi rendition="simple:centre">Confederation.</hi><lb/></p> 

<p>The order of the day was then taken <lb/>
up and gone into, for the House in <lb/>
Committee on the message of His Honor <lb/>
the Administration of the 14th [illegible] <lb/>
transmitting various Despatches and <lb/>
papers. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Kelly in the chair. <lb/></p> 

<p>The chairman having read the Des<lb break="no"/>patches- <lb/> </p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">HON. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> rose to move a <lb/>
resolution, [illegible] before doing so would <lb/>
briefly express his sentiments upon the <lb/>
question of a [illegible] of this Colony with <lb/>
the Dominion of Canada, and as the des<lb break="no"/>patches just read, had brought this mat<lb break="no"/>ter so fully to the notice of [illegible] <lb/>
committee he would not re-read them. <lb/>
It [illegible] admitted that the [illegible] of  <lb/>
the [illegible] <lb/> 

<pb n="127" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_126.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">127</fw>

gentlemen came to ascertain if there were <lb/>
valid reasons why this Island should re<lb break="no"/>fuse to confederaate with Canada, and to <lb/>
see if there was what they might regard <lb/>
as "method in our madness," when we <lb/>
refused to do so. Nor did he suppose <lb/>
exception would be taken to the recep<lb break="no"/>tion which the Government, on behalf of <lb/>
the Colony, extended to those gentlemen. <lb/>
They had been told that if terms better <lb/>
than those contained in the Quebec re<lb break="no"/>port were given, our objections would <lb/>
be removed. Well, they came and sought <lb/>
information not merely from the com<lb break="no"/>mittee of Connell, but from other public <lb/>
men also and he (Mr. H.) thought that <lb/>
was quite proper. It was an important <lb/>
question, and public men, whether in the <lb/>
legislature or not, had a perfect right to <lb/>
express their views respecting it; and he <lb/>
(Mr. H.) thought it their duty specially <lb/>
to do so on such an important matter as <lb/>
that upon which the gentlemen from the <lb/>
Dominion Government came to seek <lb/>
information. He would look at the ques<lb break="no"/>tion in its political aspect. Those who <lb/>
held the reins of power in the Island <lb/>
were known as the Liberal party, which <lb/>
nigh thirty years ago unfurled its flag, <lb/>
upon which was inscribed "Free Soil, <lb/>
Free Education, and a Free Press." This <lb/>
party had of late years been augmented <lb/>
by an element known as the Tenant <lb/>
Union element, and the men of this party <lb/>
were not a whit behind their liberal <lb/>
friends, if they did not go much further <lb/>
in advocating their principles. It was <lb/>
true the great Liberal Chief, who so <lb/>
nobly led his party to victory was now in <lb/>
the neighboring Province seeking repose <lb/>
for his tired brain, which had, for nigh <lb/>
half a life time been so overtasked on <lb/>
behalf of the interests of his country. <lb/>
The second in command had, with the <lb/>
full consent and concurrence of his party, <lb/>
been elevated to the Bench to aid in the <lb/>
better and more satisfactory administra<lb break="no"/>tion of justice; but around those desks <lb/>
he saw enough of the spirit of those who <lb/>
unfurled the old flag, and whose determina<lb break="no"/>tion was not to [illegible] up the consti<lb break="no"/>tution of the country into other hands <lb/>
until the portrait of the last landlord was <lb/>
hung up in the Legislative Library of <lb/>
the Island as a memento of the past. <lb/>
Then, and not till then, would the dif<lb break="no"/>ferent sections of the country be brought <lb/>
into closer communion with each other <lb/>
by the introduction of the iron horse, <lb/>
which could then run through one free <lb/>
farm, as it were- extending from the <lb/>
North Cape to the East Point, carrying <lb/>

<cb/> 

the products of our thrifty and enter<lb break="no"/>prising farmers to the best market. He <lb/>
would now ask the committee to look at <lb/>
the $800,000 proposed to be given as <lb/>
compensation for the loss of our crown <lb/>
lands. This he (Mr. H.) contended waas <lb/>
not a sufficient equivalent [illegible] ; <lb/>
for having figured the matter [illegible] him<lb break="no"/>self and duly compared our losses with <lb/>
the corresponding advantages derived by <lb/>
the other colonies from their public lands, <lb/>
the very lowest amoutn we should re<lb break="no"/>receive was $1,240,00, which sum would <lb/>
enable the Government of the Colony to <lb/>
settle up the land and education [illegible]<lb break="no"/>tions satisfactorily. and in other respects <lb/>
place us in about the same position as <lb/>
the other Provinces now were. It was <lb/>
true we were but a Colony of 100,000 <lb/>
people yet we prized our constitutional <lb/>
rights and privileges which were as dear <lb/>
to the inhabitants of this Colony as they <lb/>
were to those living in any of the other <lb/>
Provinces. We might be told that with <lb/>
all our constitutional privleges we <lb/>
should be able to settle the vexed ques<lb break="no"/>tion ourselves, but that as we [illegible] not <lb/>
done this, we should join the Dominion <lb/>
as its influence would soon obtain this <lb/>
settlement for us, and hence the offer re<lb break="no"/>lative to the $800,000 on condition of <lb/>
our entering into partnership with <lb/>
Canada; but were we to do so we should <lb/>
be allowed as much for our land as they <lb/>
vained their own at, which was $1 an <lb/>
acre; and as the area of our Island was <lb/>
about 1,240,000 acres, that would give <lb/>
us, as he had before stated, $1,240,000, <lb/>
the interest of which would, at 6 per <lb/>
cent., amount to about £22,230 per year. <lb/>
Such a sum would go far to enable us to <lb/>
strike the sum required for schools and <lb/>
lands out of the annual vote required for <lb/>
the public service of the country. But, <lb/>
he saw no reason why we should ever <lb/>
think of receiving that money from the <lb/>
Dominion. Canada did us no wrong, <lb/>
and owed us no money. In coming <lb/>
down here to make enquires, and in <lb/>
following them up with proposals, she, <lb/>
no doubt, was situated by a desire to do <lb/>
justice to her weakest and youngest sis<lb break="no"/>ter. But, supposed we did enter into <lb/>
Confederation, and efforts to induce the <lb/>
Home Government to pay the $800,000 <lb/>
were to fail, and Canada should ever be <lb/>
called upon to pay the money, the <lb/>
Dominion Government might say they <lb/>
bought us. And is the [illegible] of such <lb/>
statesmen [illegible] <lb/>
of this Colony would [illegible] themselves <lb/>
placed in an [illegible] position. Again, <lb/>

<pb n="128" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_128.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">128</fw>

what reason had we to suppose that <lb/>
a succeeding Government might not <lb/>
disannul the arrangement. We found that <lb/>
even now Ontario was loudly complaining, <lb/>
and quite recently Mr. Blake brought <lb/>
forward a resolution having reference to <lb/>
the alteration made in favor of Nova <lb/>
Scotia, and said: <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"In some way or other the compact must be <lb/>
re-affirmed and safeguards against its violations <lb/>
imposed. It must not be regarded as a mere <lb/>
statute to be altered by a majority. If the sub<lb break="no"/>sidy can be changed, what is to hinder a ma<lb break="no"/>jority, under the dictation of the ministry of the <lb/>
day, reversing that portion of the compact <lb/>
which provides that representation shall be <lb/>
based on population ; there can be no such [illegible] <lb/>
ground for the Dominion amidst the storms <lb/>
which will beset her if the original compact is <lb/>
not adhered to in its integrity, or changed with <lb/>
due care and formality by the power which <lb/>
created it - the Imperial Parliament." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>While he (Mr. H.) would be very sorry to <lb/>
[illegible] the slightest disrespect to the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the Dominion, yet if he might <lb/>
be allowed to judge the present and the <lb/>
future from the history of the past, and <lb/>
compare small things with great, he <lb/>
thought Ireland's history for the past hun<lb break="no"/>dred years would in several particulars, <lb/>
be a close analogy to the history of this <lb/>
Island. She also had two troublesome <lb/>
questions which were promised to be <lb/>
settled - her land and church questions. <lb/>
"Come into the House of Commons," <lb/>
said the wily Castlereagh, "and your <lb/>
grievances will receive due considera<lb break="no"/>tion." They went and according to Sir <lb/>
Jonah Barrington, in his "Rise and Gall <lb/>
of the Irish Nation," cajolery, deceit, <lb/>
bribery, corruption, and intimidation <lb/>
were resorted to, to bring about the <lb/>
union, to such a shameful extent, that <lb/>
the then Speaker of the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons earned the sonbriquet of the <lb/>
"undertaker." Henry Grattan, too, <lb/>
one of the purest patriots the world ever <lb/>
saw, lived long enough to see all the fair <lb/>
promises which had been made, broken, <lb/>
his own influence withered, and cause <lb/>
sufficient given him to curse the day <lb/>
the union was consummated. But, lest <lb/>
Barrington might be regarded as a par<lb break="no"/>tial witness, he would read an extract <lb/>
from the London <hi rendition="simple:italic">Times</hi>, which corro<lb break="no"/>borated his statement. The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Times</hi> <lb/>
said: <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"In 1798, at the very crisis of way with <lb/>
France, an insurrection broke out in Ireland, <lb/>
and was only suppressed with great bloodshed! <lb/>
Pitt made this the occasion of promoting a union <lb/>
between Great Britain and Ireland, as neces<lb break="no"/>sary to the safety of the state, and he wished to <lb/>
accompany the great reform by two measures <lb/>
which he believed likely of vital interest to <lb/>

<cb/>

Ireland, A state provision for the Catholic <lb/>
priesthood of Ireland and the emancipation of <lb/>
the Irish Catholics. A majority of the cabinet <lb/>
opposed this policy. The King was aware of <lb/>
it, and the support of the Irish Catholics to the <lb/>
Union was obtained on an understandin ; at <lb/>
least that its supplement, so important to <lb/>
them, was to be an integral part of it ; but <lb/>
when, <hi rendition="simple:italic">after the Union had passed, Pitt had <lb/>
tried to accomplish the rest of his plan, the <lb/>
King absolutely refused this union on a scru<lb break="no"/>ple about his coronation oath.</hi>" <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>The result was, the Catholics of Ireland <lb/>
were betrayed and Pitt was driven from <lb/>
office. Harrington said: The Catholics, <lb/>
in 1798, were ranged ; in 1799, carressed ; <lb/>
in 1800, cajoled, and in 1801, discarded <lb/>
altogether! È He (Mr. H.) would now <lb/>
invited attention to the result of the union <lb/>
of Scotland with England. On looking <lb/>
over a speech in the Parliamentary Re<lb break="no"/>porter, delivered by the hon. Leader of <lb/>
the Opposition, in 1866, he saw that he <lb/>
then stated that-- <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The great benefit of that national treaty <lb/>
had been generally felt and acknowledged for <lb/>
the last hundred years." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>. - That is all sound <lb/>
is it not? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName>. - No, It is not. <lb/>
The hon. member at that time went on to <lb/>
say: <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">From the period of its (the Union's) ac<lb break="no"/>complishment, there was awakened in Scotland <lb/>
a spirit of industry and enterprise formerly <lb/>
unknown in that country</hi>, and ever since the <lb/>
two kingdoms of England and Scotland, in<lb break="no"/>calculably to their mutual benefit, have been <lb/>
gradually forgetting their former subjects of <lb/>
discord, and uniting cordially, we the people, in <lb/>
the improvement and defence of their union <lb/>
country." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>He (Mr. H.) would now see how that <lb/>
agreed with what Smollet's History, <lb/>
vol. 1, page 242, said: <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"In 1725 the malt tax was found so grievous <lb/>
to the people of Scotland that they refused to <lb/>
pay it, and writs ensured at Glasgow. The <lb/>
populace rifled the house of Donald Campbell, <lb/>
their representative in Parliament, who had <lb/>
voted fro the tax. They maltreated some ex<lb break="no"/>cisement, and were fired upon by the military. <lb/>
Twenty were killed and wounded. Evenutally <lb/>
General Wade took military possession of <lb/>
Glasgow. A bill was passed to indemnify <lb/>
Donald Campbell from the proceeds of taxes on <lb/>
all the beer and ale brewed in Glasgow. Against <lb/>
the malt tax petitions were presented by the <lb/>
convention of the Royal Burghess, and from <lb/>
different times treating it as a burden their <lb/>
country could not bear." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>In 1784, as we find at page 333, three <lb/>
Scotch Dukes, Hamilton, Queensbury, <lb/>
and Montrose and three Earls, Dundonald, <lb/>
Marchmont and Stair, presented a petition <lb/>
complaining "that undue influence had <lb/> 

<pb n="129" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_128.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">129</fw>

been used for carrying the election of <lb/>
representative Peers." The Duke of <lb/>
Bedford presented their petition. It was <lb/>
stated that a list of names had been <lb/>
handed in called the 'King's List,' and <lb/>
that endeavors were used to induce Peers <lb/>
to vote for the list, by promises of pen<lb break="no"/>sions and offices civil and military, to <lb/>
themselves and relations ; that pensions, <lb/>
offices, and release from debts owing to <lb/>
the Crown, were actually granted to <lb/>
Peers who voted for the 'list.' The <lb/>
petition was rejected, but not without a <lb/>
motion for renewed enquiry, which <lb/>
plainly demonstrated the truth of the <lb/>
allegation contained in the petitions. <lb/>
McCulloch, page 312, said: <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"In 1787, a bill was sent down from the Lords <lb/>
for punishing the magistrates and city of Edin<lb break="no"/>burgh on account of the murder of John Bor<lb break="no"/>tens. This brought up the question as to <lb/>
whether the charter of the city was forfeited by <lb/>
the assumed misconduct of the magistrates and <lb/>
parts of the citizens. Lord Corteret took the <lb/>
affirmative Earl of Hay the negative. Amongst <lb/>
the witnesses brought from Scotland were three <lb/>
Judges. A debate arose as to the manner of <lb/>
their examination, whether at the bar, the <lb/>
table, or the woolsack. Some Scotch Lords <lb/>
affirmed their right to be seated next the Eng<lb break="no"/>lish Judges. Eventually they appeared at the <lb/>
bar in their robes. A bill was brought in to <lb/>
disable Alexander Wilson, Esquire, from hold<lb break="no"/>ing office in the magistracy in Edinburgh or <lb/>
elsewhere ; for imprisoning the said A. W. for <lb/>
abolishing the guard and taking away the gate <lb/>
of the western bow-port. The bill was sent <lb/>
down to the Commons, a warm debate ensued, <lb/>
Lord Polwarth said, among other things, [and <lb/>
he (Mr. H.) thought it was suggestive,] 'If the <lb/>
Government would lay their hands on their <lb/>
hearts and ask themselves whether they would <lb/>
vote in the manner they were about to do, had <lb/>
the case of Edinburgh been that of Bristol, <lb/>
York or Norwich ? He was persuaded they <lb/>
would have required every title of their evi<lb break="no"/>dence to be proved.' The bill with some <lb/>
amendments was sent back to the Lords and <lb/>
passed. <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>In 1745, occurred the second rebellion, <lb/>
headed by Prince Charles Edward. Its <lb/>
short-lived success proved that Scotland <lb/>
was anything but a quiet, happy, contented <lb/>
country. If the union in those 38 years <lb/>
which had expired since it became law, had <lb/>
really accomplished any of the fine things <lb/>
its advocates claimed for it, it was certainly <lb/>
strange its value should have been so little <lb/>
appreciated. Certainly peace, security and <lb/>
contentment were not among the benefits it <lb/>
had at that date conferred. McCulloch <lb/>
further said : <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Sir John Cope defeated at Present Pans 6000 <lb/>
Dutch auxiliries commanded by Prince Charles <lb/>
Edward, at Derby, 40 miles from London. <lb/>
December, 1746, commenced with a retreat into <lb/>
Scotland, and General Harding defeated at <lb/> 

<cb/> 

Falkeith. In 1746, the rebels were defeated at <lb/>
Culloden, [after which he (Mr. H.) read that] 'all <lb/>
the jails of Great Britain, from the capital north<lb break="no"/>ward, were filled with unfortunate captives.' <lb/>
In May, the Duke of Cumberland advanced into <lb/>
the Highlands, encamped near Fort Augustus, <lb/>
and sent off detachments on all hands to hunt <lb/>
down the fugitives and lay waste the country <lb/>
with fire and sword. The castles of Glengarry <lb/>
and Lochliel were plundered an burned ; every <lb/>
house, hut or habitation met the same fate. All <lb/>
the cattle and provisions were carried off. The <lb/>
men were either shot upon the mountains like <lb/>
wild beasts or put to death in cold blood, with<lb break="no"/>out form of trial. The women, after having <lb/>
seen their husbands and fathers murdered, <lb/>
were subjected to brutal violations and then <lb/>
turned out naked, with their children, to starve <lb/>
on the barren heaths. One whole family was <lb/>
inclosed in a barn and burned." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>"In a few days," says Smollet, "neither <lb/>
house, cottage, man, nor beast could be <lb/>
found in a compass of fifty miles." The <lb/>
union was consummated in 1710, and Smol<lb break="no"/>let, page 90, vol. 2d, states that in 1713, <lb/>
three years after: <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"During the adjournment of the  Parliament, <lb/>
on account of the Whitsun-holidays, the Scots <lb/>
of both Houses, laying aside all party dis<lb break="no"/>tinctions, met and deliberated on this subject. <lb/>
They deputed the Duke of Argyle, the Early of <lb/>
Mar, Mr. Lockhart, and Mr. Cockburn, to lay <lb/>
their grievances before the Queen. They repre<lb break="no"/>sented that their countrymen bore with im<lb break="no"/>patience the violation of some articles of the <lb/>
Union ; and that the imposition of such an <lb/>
insupportable burthen as the malt tax would, <lb/>
in all probability, prompt them to declare the <lb/>
Union dissolved. The Queen, alarmed at this <lb/>
remonstrance, answered that she wished they <lb/>
might not have cause to repent of such a pre<lb break="no"/>cipitate resolution, but she would endeavor to <lb/>
make all things easy. On the first day of June, <lb/>
the Earl of Finolater in the House of Peers <lb/>
represented that the Scottish nation was ag<lb break="no"/>grieved in many instances ; they were deprived <lb/>
of a privy council, and subjected to the English <lb/>
laws in case of treason ; that their nobles were <lb/>
rendered incapable of being created British <lb/>
Peers ; and that now they were oppressed with <lb/>
the insupportable burden of a malt tax, when <lb/>
they had reason to expect they should reap the <lb/>
benefits of peace. He therefore moved that leave <lb/>
might be given to bring in a Bill for dissolving <lb/>
the Union. <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>He (Mr. H.) would, however, pass over <lb/>
the events of 1715, which might very <lb/>
properly be termed the first rebellion, <lb/>
and therefore, an unfavorable moment <lb/>
to look at Scotland, and turn to what the <lb/>
Rev. Dr. Playfair said was the condition <lb/>
of the country thirty-eight years after <lb/>
the union: <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Since the year 1745, a fortunate epoch for <lb/>
Scotland, in general, improvements have been <lb/>
carried on with great ardor and success. At that <lb/>
time the state of the country was rude beyne <lb/>
description. The most fertile tracts were wastes, <lb/>
or indifferently cultivated. The education, man<lb break="no"/>ners, dress, furniture and tables of the gentry <lb/> 

<pb n="130" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_130.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">130</fw>

were not so liberal, decent and sumptuous as <lb/>
those of ordinary farmers are at present. The <lb/>
common people, clothed in the coarsest garb and <lb/>
starving on the meanest fare, live in despicable <lb/>
huts with their cattle. Their half-ploughed <lb/>
fields yielded but scanty crops. Manufacturers <lb/>
scarcely existed amongst them, and improvements <lb/>
culture were of a more recent date. Peas, <lb/>
grass, turnips or potatoes were not then raised ; <lb/>
no cattle were fattened ; and very little grain <lb/>
was exported. Oats and barley were alternately <lb/>
sown, and during seven months in the year, the <lb/>
best soil was ranged by flocks of sheep, a certain <lb/>
number of which were annually sold and carried <lb/>
off to be fed on richer pastures." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>McCulloch states : — <lb/></p> 

<p>"At the period referred to no manufactures, <lb/>
with the exception of that of linen, had been in<lb break="no"/>troduced into Scotland. Its agriculture was in <lb/>
the most wretched state imaginable, and the in<lb break="no"/>habitants were miserably supplied. even in the <lb/>
best years, with food, and were every now and <lb/>
then exposed to all the horrors of famine. The <lb/>
details already laid before the reader have shown <lb/>
the extreme prevalence of outrage and disorder <lb/>
in England in the sixteenth century; <hi rendition="simple:italic">but Scotland <lb/>
was a prey to the same sort of disorders so late as <lb/>
the end of the seventeenth and the beginning of the <lb/>
eighteenth centuries.</hi>" <lb/></p> 

<p>He (Mr. Howlan) thought, after the <lb/>
proofs he had given respecting the state <lb/>
of Scotland from 1710 to 1745 , that the <lb/>
statement made by the hon. Leader of <lb/>
the Opposition, in 1866, when speaking <lb/>
of the union of Scotland will England, <lb/>
vanished into thin air. That hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber than said: -— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">That, from the period of its accomplishment, <lb/>
there was awakened in Scotland a spirit of industry <lb/>
and enterprise</hi> formerly unknown in that industry <lb/>
and <hi rendition="simple:italic">ever since</hi> the two kingdoms of England and <lb/>
Scotland, incalculably to their mutual benefit," &amp;c. <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>He (Mr. H .) could not regard such <lb/>
statements in any other light than that of <lb/>
taking an unwarrantable liberty with <lb/>
history for the purpose of hood-winking <lb/>
the people of this Island. He (Mr. H.) <lb/>
had taken more pains to show the effect <lb/>
which the union had upon Scotland than <lb/>
with Ireland, because some people sup<lb break="no"/>posed that nothing would satisfy the <lb/>
people. of the latter country. But the <lb/>
impartial reader of history would admit <lb/>
that promises were made to Ireland, be<lb break="no"/>fore it went into union with England, <lb/>
and that her people have had many grie<lb break="no"/>vous wrongs to complain of and yet un<lb break="no"/>til Mr. Gladstone arose to take hold of <lb/>
those causes of discontent, it could not <lb/>
be said that an honest effort had ever <lb/>
been put forth to rectify those wrongs, <lb/>
and if Mr. Gladstone succeeded in settling <lb/>
those long-vexed questions, he would <lb/>

<cb/> 

deserve the approbation of every honest <lb/>
mind; and he thought the lessons of <lb/>
history were those from which that hon. <lb/>
committee were warranted to draw de<lb break="no"/>ductions for their guidance ; and believed <lb/>
the lessons there taught showed that be<lb break="no"/>fore we spoke of union our land question <lb/>
should be first settled, when the question <lb/>
of confederation could be approached <lb/>
with more freedom. He thought the ex<lb break="no"/>perience of New Brunswick should teach <lb/>
this Colony a lesson, and the following <lb/>
from the St. John <hi rendition="simple:italic">Telegraph</hi> he would <lb/>
read: <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"It would be interesting to learn why it is <lb/>
that New Brunswick influence counts for nothing <lb/>
at Ottawa. Why is it that we have no proper- <lb break="yes"/>weight or influence in the Government ? How <lb/>
is it that the PREMIER dares to propound mea<lb break="no"/>sures to his Cabinet which he knows our repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives can only accept with humiliation ? Is <lb/>
it because they do not take a proper stand or <lb/>
are divided in sentiment, or why is it ? We have <lb/>
cordially and heartily supported the Government, <lb/>
and encouraged the New Brunswick members to <lb/>
do the same, in cases not a few, but we would a <lb/>
thousand times rather see our representatives in <lb/>
and out of the Government opposing it, with all <lb/>
their might, than to have our just demands <lb/>
treated with contempt, and our cherished privi<lb break="no"/>leges wrested from us without the slightest re<lb break="no"/>gard to our feelings or wishes, and without any <lb/>
necessity for so doing . <lb/></p> 

<p>"Our correspondent tells us that the New <lb/>
Brunswick members, with one or two exceptions, <lb/>
will stand by the ballot, as we know they will by <lb/>
the currency resolutions, but that it will be all <lb/>
in vain. Why is this ? We can explain. New <lb/>
Brunswick has gone in loyally for Confederation. <lb/>
Her public men have not spouted treason, nor <lb/>
heeded explosive and disloyal political combina<lb break="no"/>tions. They have not threatened an appeal to a <lb/>
foreign nation. ' What and next ? ' They <lb/>
have not taken advantage of the fears or necessi<lb break="no"/>ties of the Dominion to drive a hard bargain. <lb/>
These are the reasons why they are to be humi<lb break="no"/>liated and injured ! 0r, perhaps, it is to teach a <lb/>
lesson to Prince Edward Island. That Island is <lb/>
keenly alive to what is passing' in New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick. . [illegible] The Government professes to be <lb/>
very hearty' in promoting a union between that <lb/>
Island and Canada. And how does it proceed ? <lb/>
It says by its actions, which speak louder than <lb/>
words that any concessions, reasonable or un<lb break="no"/>reasonable, may be made and offered to a pro<lb break="no"/>vince so long as it remains out of the Union, or <lb/>
even all but in arms against it, if within its <lb/>
bounds. But let a Province be loyal and true to <lb/>
the Union, let its influence be cast in that <lb/>
direction, at whatever sacrifice, and the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will treat it and its representatives as so <lb/>
many ciphers. Its most reasonable demands <lb/>
will be refused and its most cherished privileges <lb/>
will be swept away without the slightest com<lb break="no"/>punction ! A fine Union lesson this for Prince <lb/> 

<pb n="131" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_130.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">131</fw>

Edward Island ! Yet it is the lesson which the <lb/>
Government are now busily teaching and the <lb/>
one which the Island will not be slow to learn. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'The currency resolutions will not be <lb/>
pressed.' Of course not ! That might offend <lb/>
the anti-confederate bankers and brokers. The <lb/>
taking away of the ballot "<hi rendition="simple:italic">will</hi> be pressed," but <lb/>
who cares that New Brunswick is offended and <lb/>
indignant ? And then a tax is to be placed on <lb/>
three or four articles which New Brunswick can<lb break="no"/>not produced. She is to pay tribute on the right <lb/>
hand and on the left, and to bring her into a <lb/>
pleasant humor to do so, she is not to have the <lb/>
currency assimilated, and she is to lose the <lb/>
ballot ! <lb/></p> 

<p>"There is one consolation. We know well <lb/>
why we are thus treated. So much injury and <lb/>
contumely would never be heaped upon us if we <lb/>
had been less loyal and less subservient. A more <lb/>
cowardly policy it would be difficult to conceive. <lb/>
It is that of men who imagine that they know <lb/>
when to bully and when to bribe, and know little <lb/>
more. Perhaps they do not know even quite so <lb/>
much, and may yet live to discover that by their <lb/>
ungrateful, unjust and humiliating treatment of <lb/>
New Brunswick, they have committed a crime <lb/>
and a blunder. We hope yet to see that lesson <lb/>
brought home to them in a manner which they <lb/>
will never forget. " <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Patriot</hi> of March 28th, comment<lb break="no"/>ing upon New Brunswick affairs, says: — <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"In 1868, the total revenue of the local gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of New Brunswick, was $826,587, and <lb/>
the expenditure $618,514. In 1869, the whole <lb/>
income (including a balance from the year before ) <lb/>
was $747,572, and the expenditure $634,582. " <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>The St. John <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> says :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The available income for 1870 is set down at <lb/>
$433,938, and the expenditure $432,391, leaving <lb/>
a balance of $1,547, in favor the Government, <lb/>
but as the current expenditure of 1869 was <lb/>
$474,325, we do not believe that that of 1870 <lb/>
will fall short of this amount, particularly as <lb/>
there is to be a general election, which will cost <lb/>
largely in itself, and will require heavy subsidies <lb/>
to aid Government supporters <lb/></p> 

<p>"The balance which the Government pretends <lb/>
to have on hand is, we believe, fictitious, and <lb/>
the Province, ln a year at least,will be reduced <lb/>
to its last dollar. In 1871 a new census will be <lb/>
taken, and if there will be found to be any addi<lb break="no"/>tion to the population eighty cents per head will <lb/>
be allowed for each additional head," <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Now, if this was the experience of a <lb/>
Province which had a railway and was <lb/>
in receipt of the advantages flowing from <lb/>
the prosperous trade which was carried <lb/>
on by that means of conveyance last <lb/>
year - which, upon the whole, was a <lb/>
prosperous one - and yet if after a fair <lb/>
trial of confederation, her people were <lb/>
forced to conclusion that they would <lb/>
have to resort to local taxation to meet <lb/>
their public wants, he would leave that <lb/> 

hon. committee to say what our position <lb/>
would be had we become a part of the <lb/>
Dominion when that Province did. With <lb/>
respect to their currency, there had long <lb/>
been a rivalry existing between Nova <lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick on that ques<lb break="no"/>tion. There difference between the cur<lb break="no"/>rency of the two Provinces was about <lb/>
2.5 per cent, and Nova Scotia was likely <lb/>
to have her policy carried rather than <lb/>
New Brunswick ; hence the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Telegraph</hi> <lb/>
enquired why that Province had no <lb/>
weight, why the remonstrances of her <lb/>
public men were unheeded at Ottawa. <lb/>
Having reviewed the matter from a politi<lb break="no"/>cal stand-point, he would now look at its <lb/>
statistical aspect, and here he would <lb/>
merely say that he thought the statement <lb/>
of the statistical report of the Union <lb/>
committee, recently published in Char<lb break="no"/>lottetown, would show that the terms <lb/>
proposed were unjust to this Colony. He <lb/>
would therefore read the following ex<lb break="no"/>tract: <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That the proposed grant of $800,000 as an <lb/>
alleged equivalent for the lands taken from us <lb/>
for Imperial purposes, and for the purchase of <lb/>
the remaining Proprietary Estates, is but a very <lb/>
small compensation as compared with the value <lb/>
of the Lands and Royalties <hi rendition="simple:italic">reserved</hi> by the other <lb/>
Provinces for local purposes, and yielding a large <lb/>
annual income. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The grants and allowances to us—save and <lb/>
except by the small amount which would be de<lb break="no"/>rived from the increase in our population, until <lb/>
it reaches 400,000, of 80 cents a head - would be <lb/>
a <hi rendition="simple:italic">fixed</hi> sum, quite insufficient to provide for the <lb/>
construction of such public improvements as are <lb/>
indispensable to our advancement. <lb/></p> 

<p>"It must also be borne in mind that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment in the application of the grant for the <lb/>
purchase of the remaining Proprietary Lands, <lb/>
would find that the fund from the sale of those <lb/>
Lands would not be self-sustaining, as much <lb/>
higher prices would have to be paid for them <lb/>
than heretofore. A large potions of the unset<lb break="no"/>tled or wild land, would not realize one-half the <lb/>
price at which it could be acquired ; this loss, <lb/>
and the expense of managing the land depart— <lb/>
ment we absorb more than one-half of the <lb/>
sum to be granted. The working of the Wor<lb break="no"/>rell and some of the other Estates bought by the <lb/>
Government fully warrants this conclusion. <lb/></p> 

<p>"That to surrender our Revenue, which under <lb/>
our present Tariff has doubled itself within the <lb/>
last fourteen years, and may reasonably be ex<lb break="no"/>pected to increase in a still greater ratio for <lb/>
many years to come, would leave us at no dis<lb break="no"/>tant period with an income so small as to be <lb/>
much below the actual requirements of the <lb/>
Colony, and in a financial position inferior to <lb/>
that of other Provinces of the Dominion. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The Committee would further observe that <lb/>
by the 92d Sect. of the Union Act, this Island <lb/>
would not be entitled to any grants from the <lb/>

<pb n="132" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_132.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">132</fw>

Dominion Parliament for any local Public Works, <lb/>
such as Canals and Railways ; inasmuch as from <lb/>
its isolated position it would be excluded as not <lb/>
coming within this stipulations of the Act, which <lb/>
declares "<hi rendition="simple:italic">that such works if local, must be declared <lb/>
by the Parliament of Canada to be for the general <lb/>
advantage of Canada or for the advantage of two <lb/>
or more of the Provinces</hi>." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>He (Mr. H.) might here say that this <lb/>
portion of the report met all his views <lb/>
on the matter. He would now turn to <lb/>
what was looked upon by some as the <lb/>
"glory argument," and if in this view <lb/>
of the subject we were to be guided by <lb/>
enlightened and experienced statesmen, <lb/>
we should pay attention to what they <lb/>
said. Earl Carnarvon, who was in office <lb/>
when confederation was being carried, <lb/>
said:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"England ought to be proud of her colonies, <lb/>
and should do all that in her lay to strengthen <lb/>
the feeling which happily existed between Great <lb/>
Britain and her colonies in all parts of the world ; <lb/>
but that if the connection was severed the poli<lb break="no"/>tical effect would be that the North American <lb/>
Colonies would be left to the memory of any set of <lb/>
privateers, in the case of a war breaking out with <lb/>
the United States." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Such were the sentiments uttered by the <lb/>
noble Earl, and he (Mr. H.) thought <lb/>
those views did not just now place con<lb break="no"/>federation in a flattering position ; and <lb/>
if we entered into a federal union with <lb/>
Canada we would immediately be called <lb/>
upon to take up the policy of defending <lb/>
ourselves. On this Mr. Lowe said:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"We ought, in my opinion, to tell Canada that <lb/>
we will defend her with all our strength, that we <lb/>
consider her interests bound up with ours, that <lb/>
we will fight for her to the last, as long as she <lb/>
belongs to us, but that we see no chance of de<lb break="no"/>fending her on her own ground. IF she chooses <lb/>
British connexion she must take it subject to this <lb/>
condition ; we should also represent to her that <lb/>
it is perfectly open to her to establish herself as <lb/>
an independent republic ; it is our duty, too, to <lb/>
represent to her that if after well-weighed con<lb break="no"/>sideration she thinks it more to her interest to <lb/>
join the great American Republic itself, it is the <lb/>
duty of Canada to deliberate for her own interests <lb/>
and happiness." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>This clearly showed that we would be <lb/>
called upon to defend ourselves if we <lb/>
were confederated with Canada; and, <lb/>
moreover, it was worthy of note that <lb/>
since confederation had taken place the <lb/>
Imperial Government had been carrying <lb/>
out that policy. At the time the union <lb/>
was consummated, there were in the <lb/>
Dominion about 12,000 troops, which <lb/>
had been gradually withdrawn, until the <lb/>
number was now reduced to about 8000, <lb/>
and that they were to be entirely with<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

drawn he inferred from the following <lb/>
statement of Earl Granville:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Last year we made further reduction, giving <lb/>
the Government of the Dominion fair notice that <lb/>
a very short time would elapse before we should <lb/>
carry out that policy to the fullest extent. It <lb/>
would be out of place for me now to anticipate <lb/>
what may be said in a few days bu the Secretary <lb/>
of War in moving the army estimates ; but I <lb/>
quite admit that the general tendency of our <lb/>
policy is to leave a country like Canada contain<lb break="no"/>ing 4,000,000 of brave people the duty of self-<lb break="yes"/>defence." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Therefore, it was that he did not see <lb/>
what inducement there was for the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of this Island to change their positon. <lb/>
He believed there was no situation in <lb/>
which this Colony could be placed that <lb/>
her people would be more centented and <lb/>
happy than they were at present. In <lb/>
every respect we occupied a more <lb/>
enviable position than our neighbours. <lb/>
Last year, it was said that a man could <lb/>
hardly have a warrant in his possession <lb/>
until it was called in, and why? Just <lb/>
because the Government was prepared <lb/>
to redeem its paper at the Treasury. Our <lb/>
debt was, to speak in round numbers, <lb/>
£150,000, and when our public lands <lb/>
were allowed for, we had at least £100, <lb/>
000 to place against that amount, which <lb/>
would reduce our real debt to about ten <lb/>
shillings a head for the population of the <lb/>
Island ; but if we placed to our credit, as <lb/>
they did in the Dominion, all our public <lb/>
works and public buildings, our debt <lb/>
would be more than fully met. In the <lb/>
matter of trade, our position was en<lb break="no"/>couraging. Our exports, in round num<lb break="no"/>bers, for the past year were £865,191, <lb/>
and our imports, £864,282, so that the <lb/>
balance of trade was now turning in our <lb/>
favor ; and he held when a country com<lb break="no"/>menced thus to turn the scale, that her <lb/>
prosperity would advance from that pe<lb break="no"/>riod more rapidly than it did before. <lb/>
Under a tariff of eleven per cent, we paid <lb/>
£22,000 for education, and had £23,000 <lb/>
in the Treasury and in the two Banks. <lb/>
After paying all the expense and expen<lb break="no"/>diture of the past year, notwithstanding <lb/>
that the markets for oats and other pro<lb break="no"/>duce were so low, still our revenue ex<lb break="no"/>ceeded the expenditure by nearly £9000. <lb/>
We had our two Houses of Legislature, <lb/>
and all the benefits, privileges and ad<lb break="no"/>vantages of a free people. Hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men would also bear in mind that there <lb/>
was no way for us to go but by the voice <lb/>
of our people as expressed by themselves <lb/>
at the polls, and through their represen<lb break="no"/>tatives in the Legislature. The question <lb/> 

<pb n="133" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_132.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">133</fw>

was one of the most important any peo<lb break="no"/>ple could be called upon the consider— <lb/>
even the changing, to a great extent, of <lb/>
their position as it now was, and in a <lb/>
measure transferring to others a power <lb/>
which we now enjoyed ourselves. He <lb/>
would move the following resolution:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Whereas</hi> the people of this Island value <lb/>
highly the powers and privileges which, as a <lb/>
Colony of the British empire, they now exercise <lb/>
and enjoy: <lb/></p> 

<p>And <hi rendition="simple:italic">whereas</hi> this Island having prospered <lb/>
under the constitution granted it by the parent <lb/>
country, its inhabitants are exceedingly averse <lb/>
to any change in their political condition which <lb/>
would take the management of the affairs of <lb/>
the Colony out of their hands, and place them <lb/>
under the control of a distant government: <lb/></p> 

<p>And <hi rendition="simple:italic">whereas</hi> this House believes that a union <lb/>
of this Island with the Dominion of Canada, as <lb/>
proposed in a minute of the Privy Council of <lb/>
Canada, dated 14th Dec., 1869, would be in<lb break="no"/>imical to the best interests of the Colony: <lb/></p> 

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Therefore, Resolved</hi>, That this House cannot <lb/>
entertain the said proposals of the Dominion <lb/>
Government, and consequently approves of the <lb/>
general tenor of the Reply of the Executive <lb/>
Government of this Island, as expressed in <lb/>
their minutes of Council, dated respectively the <lb/>
7th day of Jan. and the 4th day of Feb., 1870. <lb/></p> </quote>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> did not rise to respond to <lb/>
the extraordinary historical statements of <lb/>
the hon. Leader of the Government ; but <lb/>
he might remark that he could not ascer<lb break="no"/>tain from that hon. member's lengthy <lb/>
speech, nor from the resolution which he <lb/>
had proposed what position he intended to <lb/>
occupy—whether he was a no-terms man <lb/>
or the reverse. He (Mr. B.) might also say <lb/>
in a general way with respect to the corres<lb break="no"/>pondence before this hon. committee, that <lb/>
it was not what he expected. He thought <lb/>
this House would have been furnished <lb/>
with memoranda and the Canadian delegates <lb/>
while on their visit here last summer. It <lb/>
was true there was on the table a minute of <lb/>
council, dated 7th of January, and a more <lb/>
lengthy one dated the 4th of February ; <lb/>
but it was well known that the delegates <lb/>
were here in the month of August. The <lb/>
House had heard nothing of the arguments <lb/>
with which the members of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment sought to enlighten the delegates on <lb/>
the claims of this Colony ; all that was be<lb break="no"/>fore the committee were those minutes of <lb/>
council, which he supposed had been pre<lb break="no"/>pared after the Government had ascer<lb break="no"/>tained the opinions of the country. But he <lb/>
did not rise to reply to the speech with <lb/>
which this debate had been, opened or to <lb/>
anticipate the hon. Leader of the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion, Certain changes had been made <lb/>
against him (Mr. B. which he felt called <lb/> 

<cb/>

upon to rebut. A member of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had said he (Mr. B.) ought to resign his <lb/>
seat, if his prevent views on this question <lb/>
were different from those which he had held <lb/>
when elected, and the taunt had afterwards <lb/>
been taken up by the hon. member for Tryon, <lb/>
Another hon. member had accused him of <lb/>
being willing to sell his birthright for a <lb/>
mess of pottage. If he (Mr. B.) were to <lb/>
be guilty of such an act, he feared that he <lb/>
would fare worse than even Esau, for Esau <lb/>
received his pottage, but where he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
was to get his, God only knew. He had <lb/>
been sold in this House, and through the <lb/>
columns of the press, that he had violated <lb/>
his public pledges on the hustings and <lb/>
elsewhere. Who the writer was that <lb/>
attacked him in the newspapers, he knew <lb/>
not, for he was unacquainted with his style. <lb/>
Anonymous writing was sometimes justi<lb break="no"/>fiable, but when a constituent attacked his <lb/>
representative, he should put his name to <lb/>
his correspondence. He (Mr. B.) in reply<lb break="no"/>ing to his opponents would use as few <lb/>
names as possible of those not on the floor <lb/>
of this House. At the <hi rendition="simple:italic">dejeuner</hi> given to  <lb/>
the Governor General when the delegates <lb/>
were her, he was called upon to reply to <lb/>
some toast, and he then stated that the <lb/>
people of this colony had no prejudices to <lb/>
overcome, but that this was a young country, <lb/>
and the opposition to union chiefly arose <lb/>
from the belief that we would lose the <lb/>
control of our own affairs. After the <lb/>
delegates were at Quebec, and the scheme <lb/>
then agreed upon came down to the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, we were told that it was of the <lb/>
nature of a treaty—that it could not be <lb/>
altered, no not so much as to dot and or <lb/>
cross a t. Believing this to be the aspect <lb/>
of the question as it was then under con<lb break="no"/>sideration, when the no-terms resolutions <lb/>
were submitted by the Hon. J.C. Pope, he <lb/>
gave them his support, though he stated at <lb/>
the time that he did not approve of their <lb/>
wording. About that time Nova Scotia <lb/>
had been unfairly dealt with by her repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives, and he was unwilling that any one <lb/>
should have the opportunity of putting this <lb/>
Colony into confederation on the terms of <lb/>
the Quebec scheme, though he expressed <lb/>
the belief that terms could be offered which <lb/>
we might accept. In supporting the no-<lb break="yes"/>terms resolutions, he might be accused of <lb/>
insincerity, but he thought it right to stand <lb/>
by the country, and he would support <lb/>
them again were he placed in a similar <lb/>
position. As reference had chosen made in <lb/>
this public papers to the reflection of the <lb/>
Hon. Daniel Davies at the late election, he <lb/>
might be excused for alluding to the sub<lb break="no"/>ject here. Mr. Davies did not approve of <lb/> 

<pb n="134" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_134.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">134</fw> 

the Quebec scheme, but he was in favor of <lb/>
the principle of union, and therefore voted <lb/>
against the no-terms resolutions. It was <lb/>
asserted that he had not been put in <lb/>
nomination because he was a confederate. <lb/>
The assertion was not true. Mr. Davies, <lb/>
than whom there had never been a more <lb/>
honest and faithful representative, had <lb/>
been very unfairly treated, and that by a <lb/>
clique who opposed him on the ground of <lb/>
his being too much under the influence of <lb/>
Mr. W. H. Pope. This was the reason <lb/>
of their action, and the hon. leader of the <lb/>
Opposition knew what he was stating to be <lb/>
a fact. To prove that those persons could <lb/>
not be opposed to Mr. Davies on account <lb/>
of his confederate principles, he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
need only refer to the circumstance that <lb/>
spins of the same individuals who were in<lb break="no"/>strumental in bringing forward another <lb/>
candidate in his place, recorded their votes <lb/>
for the hon. member for Georgetown (Mr. <lb/>
Haviland) who was known to be a "red-hot <lb/>
unionist." These men supported one who <lb/>
was always ready to fight for union, even <lb/>
for the Quebec scheme, yet the would not <lb/>
trust Mr. Davies, who only admitted the <lb/>
principle, and advocated our entering con<lb break="no"/>federation when we received fair terms. <lb/>
Having proved his point in regard to his <lb/>
position at the last election, he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
would now turn to some of the other <lb/>
charges made against him and here he <lb/>
would remark that the malignity of his <lb/>
accusers was only exceeded by their stu<lb break="no"/>pidity. Did they not know that a general <lb/>
election was coming on, and that then he <lb/>
would have to appear before the people ? <lb/>
Yet, in view of all this, they had the effron<lb break="no"/>tery to tell him that if he did not choose to <lb/>
hold his tongue, he should leave the House. <lb/>
Was a member of parliament a mere dele<lb break="no"/>gate or a representative ? This was the <lb/>
point to be considered, and he would quote <lb/>
high authority to show that members <lb/>
should act out their convictions as to what <lb/>
was right and not to be swayed by the <lb/>
passing considerations of the hour. He <lb/>
would give an extract from the speech of <lb/>
Edmund Burke to the electors of Bristol, <lb/>
in 1780, which was one of the most cele<lb break="no"/>brated ever uttered by a public man. Burke <lb/>
said :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"If we degrade and deprave their minds by <lb/>
servility, it will be absurd to expect that they <lb/>
who are creeping and abject towards us will <lb/>
ever be bold and incorruptible asserters of our <lb/>
freedom against the most seducing and the <lb/>
most formidable of all powers. No! Human <lb/>
nature is not so formed nor shall we improve the <lb/>
faculties or better the morals of public men, by <lb/>
our possession of the most infallible receipt in <lb/>
the world for making cheats and hypocrites. <lb/> 

<cb/>

Let me say, with plainness, I, who am no <lb/>
longer in a public character, that if, by a fair, <lb/>
by an indulgent, by a gentlemanly behavior to <lb/>
our representatives, we do not give confidence <lb/>
to their minds, and a liberal scope to their un<lb break="no"/>derstandings, if we do not permit our members <lb/>
to act upon a very enlarged view of things, we <lb/>
shall, at length, infallibly degrade our national <lb/>
representation into a confused and shuffling <lb/>
bustle of local agency. When the popular <lb/>
member is narrowed in his views, and rendered <lb/>
timid in his proceedings, the service of the <lb/>
crown will be the sole nursery of the states<lb break="no"/>man. Among the frolics of the court it may <lb/>
take that of attending to its business. Then <lb/>
the monopoly of mental power will be added to <lb/>
the power of all other kinds it possesses. <hi rendition="simple:italic">On <lb/>
the side of the people there will be nothing but <lb/>
impotence, for ignorance is impotence</hi>; nar<lb break="no"/>rowness of mind is impotence, and makes all <lb/>
other qualities that go along with it impotent <lb/>
and useless." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Upon these sentiments a distinguished man <lb/>
had remarked :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The voice of posterity has decided in Mr. <lb/>
Burke's favor upon the principle here discuss<lb break="no"/>ed, and the wonder is that these masterly reas<lb break="no"/>onings should ever have been necessary in <lb/>
defence of such political principles." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Now, the position of Burke was this, he <lb/>
went into parliament opposed to certain <lb/>
measures, and while there voted to carry <lb/>
them. But he (Mr. B.) was differently <lb/>
situated ; he would not vote itself in this <lb/>
House to carry confederation. No, his <lb/>
conscience would not allow him to do it. <lb/>
He would give no man an opportunity to <lb/>
point to his son and say your father was a <lb/>
traitor. Those political purists who had <lb/>
been attempting to assail his consistency, <lb/>
he thought would now have good reason to <lb/>
feel ashamed of themselves. His views on <lb/>
this question were scarcely different from <lb/>
those of some members of the Government, <lb/>
but because he had the manliness to come <lb/>
forward and avow his sentiments, he was <lb/>
made the object of petty, contemptible <lb/>
newspaper attacks. Some of the ablest <lb/>
statesman of Britain had changed their <lb/>
opinions on most important questions, and <lb/>
a verdict of public opinion in their own <lb/>
time as well as of posterity had justified <lb/>
them in the course they had pursued. Sir <lb/>
Robert Peel who had upheld the protection<lb break="no"/>ist policy, violated his pledge when he found <lb/>
it opposed to the true interests of his <lb/>
country, adopted free trade principles, made <lb/>
his bow to the landed gentry, and took for <lb/>
his companions Cobden and Bright. Hear <lb/>
what he said in his famous speech on the <lb/>
Corn Laws, delivered on the 4th of May, <lb/>
1846 :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"I admit, Sir, that those who have intuitive <lb/>
perception to tell them that which is right in <lb/>
respect to matters relating to commercial policy ; <lb/>
I admit, Sir, that those who, after patient and <lb/> 

<pb n="135" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-29_Page_134.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">135</fw>

deliberate consideration, adopt at once the right <lb/>
course, are much more entitled to the credit <lb/>
attending such a course of policy than others <lb/>
who, at a later period of life, adopt their senti<lb break="no"/>ments. But it is the duty of those who have <lb/>
reason to change their opinions to have the <lb/>
manliness to come forward and own their con<lb break="no"/>victions. Sir, I think it is dishonest for a man, <lb/>
after being convinced upon a particular subject, <lb/>
to endeavor to gain credit for consistency, by <lb/>
being unwilling or afraid to admit the change. <lb/>
I admit that this alteration in my opinions may <lb/>
disentitle me to the noble Lord's confidence ; <lb/>
but I must recollect that the question for the <lb/>
country is not a personal one. It is not a <lb/>
question as to what period a man has changed, <lb/>
or ought to change his political opinions. The <lb/>
real question is: Are these measures consistent <lb/>
with justice and sound policy? That, Sir, is the <lb/>
only question we have now to consider. If you <lb/>
blame me for not having discovered sooner the <lb/>
necessity of such a measure as the present, you <lb/>
may say that this circumstance disentitles me <lb/>
to your confidence; but that will not enable you <lb/>
to escape the necessity of arguing this question <lb/>
on account of personal imputations. Are these <lb/>
restrictions politic and just? I have no hesi<lb break="no"/>tation in saying I do not think they are con<lb break="no"/>sistent with justice." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>He (Mr. B.) would also read an extract from <lb/>
Sir James Graham's speech, at Carlisle, in <lb/>
1859, in reply to the taunt of being a <lb/>
weather-cock :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Now something is said about change of <lb/>
opinion. The last half century has been the <lb/>
period of my active life. Within that period all <lb/>
has changed around me. I have seen the face <lb/>
of nature changed. I have seen morasses con<lb break="no"/>verted into dry ground. I have seen desert <lb/>
wastes in this country now teeming with golden <lb/>
harvests. I have seen grass supplanting <lb/>
heather, and running up to the tops of our <lb/>
highest hills. I have seen night turned into <lb/>
day in our cities and dwellings by the aid of <lb/>
gas. I have seen time and distance all but <lb/>
annihilated by the locomotive power of steam <lb/>
by sea and land. I have seen the electric <lb/>
telegraph conveying from pole to pole the in<lb break="no"/>tercourse of man by a spark stolen, as it were, <lb/>
from Heaven. I have seen mighty monarchies <lb/>
fall. I have seen republics founded on their <lb/>
ruins crumbling to dust. I have seen despotic <lb/>
tyrannies arise and fall. And shall man, frail <lb/>
man, amid all those changes of nature and of <lb/>
policy, alone stand immoveable, unaltered in <lb/>
his opinions, and say he is unchanged? Is he <lb/>
to refuse to yield to the pressure of the times <lb/>
and of the circumstances in which his lot is <lb/>
cast, if he is not open to conviction? I, frail in <lb/>
my judgment, but honest in my purpose, have <lb/>
changed many opinions; but to say that a man <lb/>
dealing with state affairs is not to change his <lb/>
opinions under any circumstances—that may be <lb/>
a recommendation for any deliberative <lb/>
assembly in the world." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Those were noble utterances, and they fell <lb/>
from one whose change of opinions was one <lb/>
of the most remarkable instances of the <lb/>
kind on record, for by it he forfeited the <lb/>
confidence of Dukes and Earls. But he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) would tell the political purist he <lb/>

<cb/>

had another example, that of no less a per<lb break="no"/>sonage than the late Lord Palmerston, a <lb/>
statesman who swayed the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons almost at his will. Hear what he <lb/>
said when taunted with changing his opin<lb break="no"/>ions :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Public men may change their opinions upon <lb/>
questions of great public importance without <lb/>
any other motive than an honorable one. I <lb/>
will say a noble regard for their country's <lb/>
good." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Having given these examples to show that <lb/>
politicians were often justified in changing <lb/>
their opinions, he (Mr. B.) would trouble <lb/>
this hon. committee no longer. On some <lb/>
future occasion he would have an oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity to refer to the documents on the <lb/>
table. He had risen to defend himself from <lb/>
the aspersions of his opponents; but he felt <lb/>
restrained by the rules of the house from <lb/>
properly characterizing one who, under a <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">nom de plume</hi>, had vented upon him his <lb/>
malignity. What, he would ask, should be <lb/>
done with such a purist ? He would say, <lb/>
pass him over to some political bird-stuffer; <lb/>
in one hand place his own vile productions, <lb/>
and in the other these extracts on this in<lb break="no"/>dependence of representatives which he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) had just read. And when this was <lb/>
done, where should he be put? In this <lb/>
building we were to have an apartment for <lb/>
specimens of Island ornithology. Let him <lb/>
be given a position there ; but where in the <lb/>
collection should he be placed? Beside the <lb/>
hawk? No, he would not disgrace the <lb/>
noble, courageous bird with such company. <lb/>
Beside the humming bird? No, he would <lb/>
not soil his fair plumage with the unseemly <lb/>
contact. Where then in all the group <lb/>
should the character be perched? Where, <lb/>
he would again ask? Put him side by side <lb/>
with the unsightly owl, that was his only <lb/>
fitting place ! (Prolonged Applause.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> said the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Charlottetown had treated the <lb/>
committee to a most extraordinary speech. <lb/>
He had not advanced one argument in favor <lb/>
of confederation. His remarks were wholly <lb/>
of a personal character and had nothing to <lb/>
do with the subject under consideration. <lb/></p> 

<p>After a few explanations from Mr Breck<lb break="no"/>en and others, the debate was adjourned. <lb/></p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>