<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-04-04"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>


<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-03-09">9 March 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1870, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1870"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="152" to="161"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>

<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_152.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_154.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_156.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_158.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_160.hocr.html"/>
</item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-16">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-16">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_152">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_152.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_154">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_154.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_156">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_156.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_158">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_158.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_160">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_160.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="152" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_152.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">152</fw>  

<head rendition="simple:right">MONDAY, April 4.</head><lb/>

<p>House met at 5 o'clock. <lb/></p>
<p>Hon. Mr HOWLAN introduced a Bill for <lb/>
taking the Census of Prince Edward Island. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><hi rendition="simple:bold">Confederation.</hi><lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> delivered to Mr. <lb/>
Speaker a message from his Honor the <lb/>
Administrator of the Government, trans<lb break="no"/>mitting various Circulars and Despatches <lb/>
to the House, among which was Despatch <lb/>
No. 8, of the 7th of March, 1870, on the <lb/>
subject of the terms offered by Canada for <lb/>
the incorporation of the Island into the <lb/>
Dominion. <lb/></p> 

<pb n="153" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_152.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">153</fw>  

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>The message was referred to the Commit<lb break="no"/>tee of the whole House on the despatches, <lb/>
and on motion the House again resolved <lb/>
itself into said committee. <lb/></p></quote> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>—.When the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee rose on Wednesday night last, he <lb/>
was obliged to cease speaking before he had <lb/>
concluded his remarks, owing to the oppres<lb break="no"/>give state of the atmosphere in the room. <lb/>
He purposed now to notice a little further <lb/>
the advantages which had arisen to Scotland <lb/>
and Ireland from union with England. It <lb/>
might seem strange that he should advert <lb/>
to this subject again but he considered it <lb/>
important, on account of the position taken <lb/>
up by prominent anti-confederates at <lb/>
several public meetings, and by the Execu<lb break="no"/>tive in their minute of council. He would <lb/>
not give his own views but those of men <lb/>
who lived at or near the time in which the <lb/>
events happened. The last time he spoke <lb/>
on this question, he quoted so great an <lb/>
authority as Jeffery ; he would now give <lb/>
another, who was no less a one than the <lb/>
celebrated author of the History of Europe, <lb/>
Sir Archibald Alison. In his Essay on <lb/>
Bruce, after describing the efforts made by <lb/>
that brave men for preserving the inde<lb break="no"/>pendence of his country, he says:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"In these observations we have no intention, <lb/>
as truly as we have no desire, to depreciate <lb/>
the incalculable blessings which this country <lb/>
has derived from her union with England. We <lb/>
feel as strongly as we can do the immense <lb/>
advantage which this measure has brought to <lb/>
the wealth, the industry, and the spirit of Scot<lb break="no"/>land. We are proud to acknowledge that it is <lb/>
to the efforts of English patriotism, that we <lb/>
owe the establishment of liberty in our civil <lb/>
code; and to the influence of English example, <lb/>
the diffusion of a free spirit among our people." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>These were Sir Archibald Alison's views. <lb/>
But to show that Scotland had greatly in<lb break="no"/>creased in wealth since her union with <lb/>
England, he need only had the following <lb/>
short extract from the 5th vol. of Macaulay's <lb/>
History :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"A great part of Scotland was then (1699) <lb/>
as poor and rude as Iceland now is. There <lb/>
were five or six Shires which did not altogether <lb/>
contain so many guineas and crowns as were <lb/>
tossed about every day by the shovels of a <lb/>
single goldsmith in Lombard Street. Even the <lb/>
nobles had very little ready money ; they gen<lb break="no"/>erally took a large part of their rents in kind, <lb/>
and were thus able, on their own domains, to <lb/>
live plentifully and hospitably. But there were <lb/>
many esquires in Kent and Somersetshire, who <lb/>
received from their tenants a greater quantity <lb/>
of gold and silver, than a Duke of Gordon,or a <lb/>
Marquis of Athol, drew from extensive pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. The pecuniary renumeration of the <lb/>
clergy was such as would have moved the pity <lb/>
of the most needy curate, who thought it a <lb/>
privilege to drink his ale and smoke his pipe in <lb/>
the kitchen of an English manor-house. Even <lb/> 

<cb/>

in the fertile Meuse, there wore parishes of <lb/>
which the minister received only from four to <lb/>
eight points sterling in cash. The official in<lb break="no"/>come of the Lord President of the Court of <lb/>
Session, was only five hundred a year. The <lb/>
land tax of the whole Kingdom was fixed some <lb/>
years later by the Treaty of Union at little <lb/>
more than half the land tax of the single County <lb/>
of Norfolk. Four hundred thousand pounds <lb/>
probably bore as great a ratio to the wealth of <lb/>
Scotland then,as forty millions would bear now." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Then with respect to Ireland, He (Mr. H.) <lb/>
thought he was justified in saying that had <lb/>
it not been for her union with Britain, she <lb/>
would not now have her church question <lb/>
settled, and her land question in a fair way <lb/>
for adjustment, These reforma would never <lb/>
have been granted to Ireland by her own <lb/>
parliament, which consisted wholly of Pro<lb break="no"/>testants, a large proportion of whom were. <lb/>
landlords. He would again quote from <lb/>
Thomas Babington Macaulay, who was <lb/>
one of the greatest historians who had figured <lb/>
in modern times. In a speech which he <lb/>
made in Parliament in 1833, in answer to <lb/>
Daniel O'Connell, who had been setting <lb/>
forth the grievances of Ireland, Macaulay <lb/>
said :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Ireland has undoubtedly just causes of <lb/>
complaint. We heard those causes recapitu<lb break="no"/>lated last night but he honorable and elarned <lb/>
Member, who tolls us that he represents not <lb/>
Dublin alone, but Ireland, and that he stands <lb/>
between his country and civil war. i do not <lb/>
deny that most of the grievances which he re<lb break="no"/>counted exist, that they are serious, and that <lb/>
they ought to be remedied as far as it is in the <lb/>
power of legislation to remedy them. What I <lb/>
do deny is that they were caused by the Union, <lb/>
and that the Repeal of the Union would re<lb break="no"/>move them, I listened attentively while the <lb/>
honorable and learned gentleman went through <lb/>
that long and melancholy list; and I am con<lb break="no"/>fident that the did not mention a single evil <lb/>
which was not a subject of bitter complaint <lb/>
while Ireland had a domestic parliament. Is <lb/>
it fair, is it reasonable in the honorable gentle<lb break="no"/>man to impute to the Union evils which, as he <lb/>
knows, better than any other man in this house, <lb/>
existed long before the Union? <hi rendition="simple:italic">Post hoc: ergo, <lb/>
propter hoc</hi> is not always sound reasoning. <lb/>
But <hi rendition="simple:italic">ante hoc: ergo non propter hoc</hi> is unan<lb break="no"/>swerable. The old rustic who told Sir Thomas <lb/>
More that Tenterden steeple was the cause of <lb/>
Godwin sands, reasoned much better than the <lb/>
honorable and learned gentleman. For it was <lb/>
not until after the Tenterden steeple was built, <lb/>
that the frightful wrecks on the Godwin sands <lb/>
were heard of. But the honorable and learned <lb/>
gentleman would make Godwin sands the cause <lb/>
of Tenterden steel. Some of the Irish griev<lb break="no"/>ances which he ascribes to the Union, are not <lb/>
only older than the Union, but are not peculiar<lb break="no"/>ly Irish. They are common to England, Scot<lb break="no"/>land and Ireland ; and it was in order to get <lb/>
rid of them that we, for the common benefit of <lb/>
England, Scotland and Ireland, passed the <lb/>
Reform Bill last year. Other grievances which <lb/>
the honorable and learned gentleman mentioned <lb/>
are doubtless local : but is there to be a local <lb/>
legislature where ever there is a local grievance? <lb/>

<pb n="154" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_154.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">154</fw>  

We all remember the complaints which were <lb/>
made a few years ago about the Welsh judicial <lb/>
system ; but did any body therefore propose <lb/>
that Wales should have a distinct parliament ? <lb/>
Cornwall has some local grievances ; but does <lb/>
any one propose that Cornwall shall have its <lb/>
own House of Lords and its own House of <lb/>
Commons ? Leeds has local grievances. The <lb/>
majority of my constituents distrust and dislike <lb/>
the municipal government to which they are <lb/>
subject ; they therefore call loudly on us for <lb/>
corporation reform : but they do not ask us for <lb/>
a separate legislature. Of this I am quite sure, <lb/>
that every argument which has been urged for <lb/>
the purpose of showing that the north of Ire<lb break="no"/>land and the south of Ireland ought to have <lb/>
two distinct parliaments. The House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons of the United Kingdom, it has been said, <lb/>
is chiefly elected by Protestants, and therefore <lb/>
cannot be trusted to legislate for Catholic Ire<lb break="no"/>land. If this be so, how can an Irish House of <lb/>
Commons, chiefly elected by Catholics, be <lb/>
trusted to legislate for Protestant Ulster ? It <lb/>
is perfectly notorious that theological anti<lb break="no"/>pathies are stronger in Ireland than here. I <lb/>
appeal to the honorable and learned gentleman <lb/>
himself. He has often declared that it is im<lb break="no"/>possible for a Roman Catholic, whether prose<lb break="no"/>cutor or culprit, to obtain justice from a jury <lb/>
of Orangemen. It is indeed certain that, in <lb/>
blood, religion, language, habits, character, the <lb/>
population of some of the northern counties of <lb/>
Ireland has much more in common with the <lb/>
population of England and Scotland than with <lb/>
the population Munster and Connaught. I <lb/>
defy the honorable and learned member, there<lb break="no"/>fore, to find a reason for having a parliament <lb/>
at Dublin, which will not be just as good a <lb/>
reason for having another parliament in Lon<lb break="no"/>donderry." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>He (Mr. H.) could adduce much more evi<lb break="no"/>dence of the same kind in support of his <lb/>
position, but he had quoted sufficient to <lb/>
meet the arguments of the hon. member <lb/>
on the opposite side of the House (Mr. <lb/>
Howlan). That hon. gentleman had also <lb/>
read from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Patriot</hi> of last week, an <lb/>
article from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Daily Telegraph</hi> published <lb/>
in St. John in the Province of New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, complaining of some acts of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion parliament, which appeared to afford <lb/>
him great satisfaction. He (Mr. Haviland), <lb/>
however, would say that the advocates of <lb/>
union did not contend that there would <lb/>
always be unanimity of sentiment in the <lb/>
Dominion. There would be difference of <lb/>
opinion as in other countries, but this need <lb/>
not cause any alarm. One of the questions <lb/>
in dispute to which the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Telegraph</hi> re<lb break="no"/>ferred was vote by ballot, and the other <lb/>
the currency question. Upon the ballot, <lb/>
that journal had taken up views of its own, <lb/>
and on the currency question Nova Scotia <lb/>
and New Brunswick were at issue. The <lb/>
people of Nova Scotia were in favor of re<lb break="no"/>taining the sovereign as the standard of <lb/>
value, and those of New Brunswich con<lb break="no"/>tended for the dollar. With respect to the <lb/>
ballot, New Brunswick itself was not agreed <lb/>

<cb/> 

upon it. The Dominion had been in exist<lb break="no"/>ence only about three years, and though a <lb/>
few questions still remained unsettled yet <lb/>
that afforded no sufficient reason to say <lb/>
that it would not succeed. Even after the <lb/>
flight of James II. from England, there were <lb/>
certain parties who wished for his return. <lb/>
When any public movement took place <lb/>
there was always a reaction to a certain <lb/>
extent ; therefore he looked upon those <lb/>
grievances which a portion of the Dominion <lb/>
press made such a noise about, as very <lb/>
trivial. Then again there was a paragraph <lb/>
in the minute of council—this wonderful <lb/>
minute which the government organ called <lb/>
a statesman-like document—which, refer<lb break="no"/>ring to Nova Scotia, said that she had sent <lb/>
a deputation to Washington. He (Mr. <lb/>
Haviland) might affirm that this Colony <lb/>
was in the same position, for the hon. leader <lb/>
of the government in this House had been <lb/>
at Washington to negotiate a free trade <lb/>
treaty. In the next place we had been told <lb/>
by the hon. Colonial Secretary and his <lb/>
leader that we had no trade with the Do<lb break="no"/>minion ; and that if we came under her <lb/>
tariff we should be nothing better than <lb/>
slaves. He (Mr. H.) could tell those hon. <lb/>
members in reply, that if we had the Do<lb break="no"/>minion 15 per cent tariff, together with its <lb/>
free list, we would not be much more <lb/>
heavily taxed than at present. In Canada <lb/>
everything connected with the building of <lb/>
ships, and the various articles of raw materi<lb break="no"/>al used in the manufactures, were all ad<lb break="no"/>mitted duty free ; whereas here under our <lb/>
miserable tariff there was nothing worth <lb/>
speaking of on the free list. Only the <lb/>
other day there was a petition brought <lb/>
before this House praying that the duty <lb/>
might be taken off articles used in the <lb/>
manufacture of soap. This circumstance <lb/>
showed the nature of our tariff. But in the <lb/>
Dominion last year out of some $66,000,000 <lb/>
worth of imports, $22,000,000 were on the <lb/>
free list. Then with respect to the state<lb break="no"/>ment that we had no trade with the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion, he would read a few figures, which he <lb/>
had compiled from the Journals of the <lb/>
House, to prove that it was not correct. <lb/>
In 1869 the Dominion took us in oats <lb/>
alone to the value of £30,285 18s. 4d. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName>.—That was to <lb/>
Nova Scotia. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.—Well, Nova <lb/>
Scotia was a part of the Dominion. The <lb/>
value of pork which went from here to <lb/>
the Dominion in 1869 was £33,116 ; of po<lb break="no"/>tatoes, £18,387 ; of upper leather, £1,112 ; <lb/>
of oysters, £1,697 ; of butter, £3,112 ; of <lb/>
sheep—principally to the St. John mar<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="155" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_154.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">155</fw>  

ket—£2,227. Who could say now that <lb/>
we had no trade with the Dominion ? <lb/>
And more that this, he could show that <lb/>
it was a growing trade. He would first <lb/>
give our imports and exports from and <lb/>
to the Provinces in 1863, and then com<lb break="no"/>pare them with that of last year. In <lb/>
taking 1863, he was choosing a year that <lb/>
was one of the most prosperous in the <lb/>
history of these colonies—a year in which <lb/>
the tonnage of shipping built in this <lb/>
Island was nearly double of what it was <lb/>
in 1869. In 1863, our exports to the <lb/>
Provinces were: Nova Scotia, £31,511 <lb/>
12s 3d ; New Brunswick, £23,340 5s 4d ; <lb/>
Canada proper, £1,255 12s 11d ; total to <lb/>
the Provinces that now form the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion, £63,107 10s 6d. Our imports for <lb/>
the same year were: from Nova Scotia, <lb/>
£66,890 11s 5d ; New Brunswick, £19,<lb break="no"/>975 3s 11d ; Canada, £6152 8s 3d ; total <lb/>
from the Dominion Provinces, £83,018 <lb/>
3s 7d. He would now give the returns <lb/>
for 1869. In that year our exports to <lb/>
Nova Scotia were: £82,013 10s 3d ; to <lb/>
New Brunswick, £30,100 13s 5d ; to <lb/>
Canada proper, £1,681 11s 4d ; total to <lb/>
the Dominion, £113,795 15s. Our im<lb break="no"/>ports for the same year were, from Nova <lb/>
Scotia, £68,215 18s 5d. New Brunswick, <lb/>
£35,124 12s 8d ; Canada proper, £32,946 <lb/>
3s 9d ; total from the Dominion, £136,<lb break="no"/>286 14s 10. These figures, he ought to <lb/>
say, were all in British sterling. Last <lb/>
year our exports to the United Kingdom, <lb/>
exclusive of shops, were, £108,860 16s <lb/>
8d ; and to the United States, £48,205 <lb/>
11s 6d. Our imports for the same year <lb/>
from the United Kingdom were, £165,<lb break="no"/>095 7s 10 ; and from the United States, <lb/>
£55,826 7s 6d. It would thus be seen <lb/>
that our exports to the Dominion were <lb/>
greater than to any other country ; and <lb/>
our imports from her nearly equal to <lb/>
those from the United Kingdom. Having <lb/>
met his opponents on the trade argument, <lb/>
he (Mr. H.) would next refer to their bug<lb break="no"/>bear of local taxation. Articles had been <lb/>
repeatedly published in the newspapers, <lb/>
setting forth the amount of direct taxes <lb/>
the people in Canada had to pay. But <lb/>
in this colony we would not require to <lb/>
resort to such a method of taxation as <lb/>
long as we could carry on the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and pay our way with the sums <lb/>
allowed by the general government. He <lb/>
believed that with proper management <lb/>
those subsidies would be enough for the <lb/>
next generation to come. The expensves <lb/>
of the local government might be cur<lb break="no"/>tailed. We would not need so many <lb/>
public officers. With all deference to <lb/>

<cb/> 

the honorable body in the other end of <lb/>
the building, he believed we might dis<lb break="no"/>pense with its services altogether. If <lb/>
Ontario—the largest province of Ontario <lb/>
—could do without an upper chamber, <lb/>
surely this little Island might get along <lb/>
in the same way. He (Mr. H.) was also <lb/>
of opinion that the number of members <lb/>
in this House might be reduced. When <lb/>
he first came to it, there were only <lb/>
twenty-four members ; after a time, how<lb break="no"/>ever, so many office holders obtained <lb/>
seats in the House, that the authorities <lb/>
at home called attention to the in<lb break="no"/>sufficient proportion of independent <lb/>
members which it contained, and a <lb/>
measure was introduced to increase the <lb/>
representation. But as only a few <lb/>
office-holders were now admitted into <lb/>
this House, we might very well go back <lb/>
to the former number of members, or <lb/>
lower still, to the old number, eighteen. <lb/>
By thus cutting down our expenditure, we <lb/>
would find that the grants from the <lb/>
Dominion government would be quite <lb/>
ample to meet our wants for a genera<lb break="no"/>tion, and after that our people would <lb/>
have become so wealthy, that they would <lb/>
be able and willing to submit to a little <lb/>
more taxation. Though this colony re<lb break="no"/>mained in her isolated position, her taxes <lb/>
would have to be increased. It might <lb/>
be all very well to stave off taxation on <lb/>
the eve of a general election ; but not <lb/>
longer ago than last session, the leader <lb/>
of the government talked of increasing <lb/>
the land tax. Though it was put off for <lb/>
the time, yet it must come. Lately we <lb/>
had a <hi rendition="simple:italic">coleur de rose</hi> statement of the <lb/>
financial condition of the colony, but on <lb/>
examining into the matter, he found that <lb/>
it was not all gold that glittered. In <lb/>
1854, the Worrell estate was purchased <lb/>
for £20,500, and after working it for <lb/>
some fifteen years, there was only £2,600 <lb/>
to the credit of the estate, to meet the <lb/>
purchase money. And in the working <lb/>
of all the estates in the hands of the <lb/>
government, during the last financial <lb/>
year, after paylng interest and all, there <lb/>
was the amount of £154 11s 11d on the <lb/>
wrong side of the book. Only one es<lb break="no"/>tate among the whole, had been self- <lb break="yes"/> sustaining, and that was the one repre<lb break="no"/>sented by the hon. member for Belfast. <lb/>
He (Mr. H.) did not think, from the <lb/>
calculations he had made, that the others <lb/>
would ever pay. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName>.—"Figures are <lb/>
dangerous things." <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.—"Yes they are <lb/>

<pb n="156" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_156.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">156</fw> 

dangerous things." And he (Mr. Havi<lb break="no"/>land) thought the hon. member would <lb/>
find the $800,000 offer a dangerous thing, <lb/>
after the buncombé speeches which he <lb/>
and the Colonial Secretary had made, <lb/>
the one setting down the compensation <lb/>
which we should receive from the Do<lb break="no"/>minion for the loss of crown lands at <lb/>
$1,240,000, and the other fixing it at as <lb/>
many pounds sterling. It would not do <lb/>
for us to be indulging the vain hope, that <lb/>
the British government would pay for <lb/>
the loss of these lands. If we were to <lb/>
judge from the short, pithy despatch laid <lb/>
on the table this evening, the govern<lb break="no"/>ment might make up their minds that <lb/>
they would receive no help from that <lb/>
quarter. They must get up some other <lb/>
political cry before the elections came <lb/>
off. But he supposed he ought not to <lb/>
speak againsthon. members on the other <lb/>
side of the House; they were so much <lb/>
confederate that it seemed wrong to be <lb/>
twitting them. They appeared to be <lb/>
more his friends than some on this side <lb/>
of the House, who were no-terms men. <lb/>
There, for example, was the hon. the <lb/>
Leader of the Government in the other <lb/>
end of the building, who was reported <lb/>
by a writer in Saturday's <hi rendition="simple:italic">Patriot</hi>, to <lb/>
have said at a late meeting held at the <lb/>
Ten Mile House, Lot 35:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That he had opposed the Quebec scheme, <lb/>
which he considered unfair to the people of the <lb/>
Island, but that he was not, nevertheless, a no- <lb break="yes"/> terms man: that be anticipated a time when <lb/>
proposals of a union of this Island With Canada <lb/>
might be entertained." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>After this it seemed cruel to attack hon. <lb/>
members opposite, seeing that they had <lb/>
such a red-hot unionist as leader. And <lb/>
when we turned to the minute of <lb/>
council what did it say :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The long delayed settlement of the Land <lb/>
Question is thus made contingent upon the on- <lb break="yes"/> trance of Prince Edward Island into the North <lb/>
American Confederation; and the Dominion, <lb/>
from whom the Island has received no injury, <lb/>
and to whom no purchase monies or rents of <lb/>
lands have been paid, is required to assume a <lb/>
duty which clearly is not hers; but which, if <lb/>
just and liberal treatment is a debt due the Is<lb break="no"/>land, as Earl Granville seems to imply, un<lb break="no"/>doubtedly belongs to Imperial Britain. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The Council can only further express a <lb/>
hope that the Government and Parliament of <lb/>
the Dominion will adopt this question as their <lb/>
own, and make such persistent and powerful <lb/>
representations thereon, to the Imperia authori<lb break="no"/>ties as may result in obtaining redress for this <lb/>
injured Colony. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Success would be productive of the best re<lb break="no"/>sults. It would establish the prestige of the <lb/>
Dominion—cause a spontaneous, not an artifi<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

cial reaction of public opinion in Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Here there was nothing said to be in the <lb/>
way, but this land question. True, it <lb/>
might be objected that what this states<lb break="no"/>man-like document stated in one para<lb break="no"/>graph it toppled over in the next. And <lb/>
the best of the joke was that the sup<lb break="no"/>porters of the government in the House <lb/>
would have to eat the leek, as the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion proposed by their leader, required <lb/>
them to approve of the "general tenor" <lb/>
of the in notes of council. With respect <lb/>
to the $800,000 offered by the Dominion <lb/>
for a settlement of the land question, he <lb/>
was surprised to see it so strongly ob<lb break="no"/>jected to by the government. The Hon. <lb/>
Mr. Coles, who was as great a Liberal as <lb/>
any in this House, moved at the Quebec <lb/>
convention that this Island should re<lb break="no"/>ceive £200,000 in consideration for the <lb/>
loss of her lands, and there was a rivalry <lb/>
between Hon. E. Palmer and Hon. A. A. <lb/>
McDonald as to which of them should <lb/>
second the resolution. But now he ob<lb break="no"/>served that Hon. Mr. McDonald said he <lb/>
could not accept the $800,000 unless it <lb/>
came from Britain; and Hon. Mr. Palmer <lb/>
had said something of the same kind. <lb/>
He (Mr. H.) contended that the <lb/>
government instead of pursuing the tor<lb break="no"/>tuous policy which they had done, since <lb/>
they admitted the principle, ought <lb/>
to have set to work and drawn up a <lb/>
statement of such terms as they thought <lb/>
would be fair to the Colony, and sent it <lb/>
to Ottawa in place of those contradictory <lb/>
minutes of council. But he would not <lb/>
despair of them; their leader was with <lb/>
us, and he believed Confederation, was <lb/>
only a question of time. Those who were <lb/>
now opposed to it, in his (Mr. H.'s) <lb/>
opinion, would soon the heater cham<lb break="no"/>pions for it than himself. Even the hon. <lb/>
member for Belfast (Mr. Duncan) he ex<lb break="no"/>pected to see among its advocates, per<lb break="no"/>haps their very leader in chief. (Ap<lb break="no"/>plause.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName> asked the last speaker <lb/>
(Mr. Haviland) if it was not possible for <lb/>
this Legislature to put the land into <lb/>
Confederation, as he (Mr. D.) understood <lb/>
him to say that the cuss could not do it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.—If the members of <lb/>
this House were political vagabonds, they <lb/>
could put the Island into Confederation. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName> was satisfied; he did <lb/>
not wish the idea to go abroad that the <lb/>
Legislature had not the power to unite the <lb/>
Island with the Dominion. <lb/></p>

<pb n="157" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_156.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">157</fw> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>.—The two leaders in <lb/>
this end of the building in discussing Con<lb break="no"/>federation had edified the House by going <lb/>
into the misty records of the history of <lb/>
Ireland and Scotland, and the effects of <lb/>
union upon them; but he (Mr. L.) thought <lb/>
the chairman of this committee (Mr. Kelly) <lb/>
must have been very much amused with it, <lb/>
for he believed that he (Mr. Kelly) had <lb/>
forgotten more of the history of those <lb/>
countries than these two hon. members <lb/>
ever knew. The hon. Leader of the Op<lb break="no"/>position had stated that the tariff of the <lb/>
Dominion was preferable to ours because it <lb/>
protected home manufactures, and he (Mr. <lb/>
L.) thought the hon. member must be a <lb/>
new convert to the protective system, because <lb/>
judging from his speeches for many years <lb/>
he always appeared to be an advocate of <lb/>
free trade. Of all the causes which the <lb/>
Leader of the Opposition had adovcated, <lb/>
free trade was the one he (Mr. L.) thought <lb/>
most of, and he was very sorry the hon. <lb/>
member had fallen from the high position <lb/>
he occupied as an advocate of free trade, <lb/>
by joining the protectionists. How did it <lb/>
happen that proposals for the union of this <lb/>
Island were made? In 1864 a proposal for <lb/>
the union of the Maritime Provinces was <lb/>
sent to our Legislature, and although op<lb break="no"/>posed to it they agreed to meet the dele<lb break="no"/>gates from the other provinces to discuss <lb/>
the question. At the time this was taking <lb/>
place, some of the statesmen of Canada <lb/>
came down as suitors soliciting these <lb/>
provinces to unite with Canada, and ever <lb/>
since, the question of Confederation had <lb/>
been agitating the minds of the people of <lb/>
this Island. In considering the proposals <lb/>
made to us, we should endeavor to acquire <lb/>
as much information as possible of the <lb/>
country with which we were asked to unite, <lb/>
and also the history of the government which <lb/>
ruled that that country.   A book had been <lb/>
published called, "Eighty, Years' Progress <lb/>
in British America" from, which he (Mr. <lb/>
L.) would read a few extracts showing that <lb/>
the government of Canada had been almost <lb/>
supported by the Imperial Parliament— <lb/>
immense loans were guaranteed, and British <lb/>
gold was freely spent in the country. The <lb/> 
Rideau Canal was built by the Imperial <lb/>
government at a cost of £900,000 sterling. <lb/>
When had the British Govemment spent <lb/>
money here? They had spent a few <lb/>
sovereigns in building a battery near Char<lb break="no"/>lottetown, which was about all the money <lb/>
we received from them. Further on in the <lb/>
same book was an account of the building <lb/>
of Railways, and also of the effect which the <lb/>
spending of so much money in the country <lb/>
had on the politicians—training them up <lb/> 

<cb/>

to extravagance. The influence of contrac<lb break="no"/>tors in the country was felt, as the follow<lb break="no"/>ing would show:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Before the invasion of the province at the <lb/>
east, by a deputation from the most experienced <lb/>
railway men of England, bringing with them all <lb/>
the knowledge and appliances of that conserva<lb break="no"/>tive country, it had been penetrated on the west <lb/>
by some contractors from the United States, bred <lb/>
in that school of politics and public works which <lb/>
brought New York to a dead stand and Pennsyl<lb break="no"/>vania to the goal of reputation. These practical <lb/>
men had built state canals with senators and <lb/>
even governors as silent partners, and were <lb/>
versed in all the resources peculiar to a democra<lb break="no"/>tic community. The convergence of these two <lb/>
systems on the poor but virgin soil of Canada, <lb/>
brought about an education of the people and <lb/>
their representatives more rapid than the most <lb/>
sanguine among them could have hoped for. <lb/>
One bold operator organized a system which <lb/>
virtually made him ruler of the province for <lb/>
several years. In person or by agents he kept <lb/>
'open house,' where the choicest brands of <lb/>
champagne and cigars were free to all the <lb/>
peoples' representatives, from the town councillor <lb/>
to the cabinet minister; and it was the boast of <lb/>
one of these agents that when the Speaker's bell <lb/>
rang for a division, more M. P. P.'s were to be <lb/>
found in his apartments than in the library or <lb/>
any other single resort." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>This was the school in which the statesmen <lb/>
of Canada were trained. Another extract <lb/>
would show how this gigantic contractor <lb/>
had to be brought off before another could <lb/>
take a contract. <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"An English contractor was, without competi<lb break="no"/>tion, about to pounce quietly upon the contract <lb/>
for the Toronto and Hamilton Railway, when his <lb/>
American 'brother' demanded and received a <lb/>
royalty of £10,000 sterling, before he would <lb/>
allow a corporation to be imposed upon." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>These things were winked at by the gov<lb break="no"/>ernmen, and we should be cautious in <lb/>
uniting with a country whose rulers would <lb/>
act in such a manner, and also as was <lb/>
stated a little farther on. <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"A member of the government paid away <lb/>
nearly £10,000 of the first mortgage bonds of the <lb/>
Toronto Northern Road company in the purchase <lb/>
of real estate." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Again when the Great Western Railway <lb/>
Company applied to the government for <lb/>
power to lay a double track -- <lb/></p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"They were gravely assured that the govern<lb break="no"/>ment was powerless to give them their bill, in <lb/>
consequence of the influence of the enterprising <lb/>
Pennsylvanian, in the house. The contractor's <lb/>
price for permitting the bill to pass was - the <lb/>
contract for the work to be done."</p></quote> 

<p>Thus in Canada twelve years ago contractors <lb/>
rules the country, while in this Island the <lb/>
government was carried on as faithfully and <lb/>
honestly as it was now. <lb/></p>

<pb n="158" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_158.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">158</fw> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Canadians, indeed have had cause to blush at <lb/>
the spectacle of men filling the highest offices in <lb/>
their province, with a seat at the council board <lb/>
of their sovereign, accepting fees and favors from <lb/>
contractors and officials of a railway company <lb/>
(between whom and them there should have been <lb/>
a gulf as wide as that which seperates the judges <lb/>
of [illegible] from the suitors before them), and lay<lb break="no"/>ing the honor of their country in the dust, often <lb/>
at the feet of boorish and uneducated men whose <lb/>
only recommendations were - the material one of <lb/>
ill-gotten wealth, and the immoral one of un<lb break="no"/>scrupulousness in the use of it." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>With this history of Canada before them, <lb/>
any colony that wished to unite with the <lb/>
Dominion, he (Mr. L.) thought, had no <lb/>
interest at stake. It might be said that the <lb/>
statesmen of the Dominion had reformed; <lb/>
but in looking at the politicians in Ottawa <lb/>
at the present time, it would be difficult to <lb/>
see where the improvement was. Judging <lb/>
from the amount of British gold expended <lb/>
there, and the number of railroads and <lb/>
other public works, we should expect to <lb/>
find a country in a flourishing condition, <lb/>
carrying on a large trade, and having plenty <lb/>
of money. But what were the facts? A <lb/>
statement made by Sir Francis Hincks, <lb/>
Finance Minister in the House of Commons, <lb/>
would show the way in which the accounts <lb/>
of the country were kept. <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"It must be perfectly obvious to gentlemen <lb/>
that years might elapse before anything con<lb break="no"/>nected with the debt could be brought down. <lb/>
Items were constantly springing up from time to <lb/>
time, and had to be considered as they came up." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>If the government of this Island kept <lb/>
accounts in such a way, the representatives <lb/>
of the people would soon send them about <lb/>
their business. It could easily be seen, <lb/>
from the account of Sir F. Hincks' banking <lb/>
scheme, how the Dominion Government were <lb/>
pressed for money. <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"It is imperatively necessary also to a right <lb/>
understanding of the question now before parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, that the confession of Sir Francis Hincks <lb/>
on Tuesday night should be kept steadily in <lb/>
view-namely:- that the scheme of the 1866 was <lb/>
gone into by government before of 'their <lb/>
financial difficulties,' and 'they were obliged to <lb/>
accept whatever terms the banks thought proper <lb/>
to put upon them." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>He (Mr. L.) was proud of our banking <lb/>
institutions, but he would be very sorry to <lb/>
see the government in such a position that <lb/>
they would be obliged to take whatever <lb/>
terms the banks chose to put upon them. <lb/>
Yet such was the humiliating position of <lb/>
the government of the Dominion-at the <lb/>
mercy of the banks of the country. Sir F. <lb/>
Hincks proposed a banking scheme, not <lb/>
because any fault was found with the banks, <lb/>
but on account of the imperative necessity <lb/>

<cb/> 

of the government to raise money. A <lb/>
country that was already indebted to the <lb/>
amount of twenty-five dollars per head of <lb/>
their population in such want of money! <lb/>
A country that took money, guaranteed for <lb/>
the building of a railroad, for other pur<lb break="no"/>poses, lauded to the skies in our day! The <lb/>
following comments were made by a mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the Dominion Parliament: <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"There was one phase of the proposed mea<lb break="no"/>sure to which be desired to call the attention of <lb/>
the House, and that was that the Finance Minis<lb break="no"/>ter had signed that the measure was brought in <lb/>
not because the country stood in need of a re<lb break="no"/>vised banking system, but because the govern<lb break="no"/>ment necessities imposed on him the duty of <lb/>
providing a certain amount of money. The <lb/>
system of raising money was brought to the <lb/>
greatest perfection by the present government. <lb/>
The government had obtained from the Insur<lb break="no"/>ance Companies $4,000,000, a million and a half <lb/>
from the Savings Banks- they had also sold one <lb/>
million of silver, exchanging Dominion notes for <lb/>
it, and paying a large commission, and they had <lb/>
also five and a half million of Dominion notes in <lb/>
circulation. Now there was a scheme proposed <lb/>
by which the government wished to increase this <lb/>
indirect load of debt to the extent of $12,000,<lb break="no"/>000, making an aggregate increase of $20,000,<lb break="no"/>000- an increase of the greater portion of which <lb/>
the country was altogether in ignorance." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>The scheme proposed an aggregate increase <lb/>
in the debt of $20,000,000 which increase <lb/>
was to be made without the knowledge of <lb/>
the people, so that it required a scheming, <lb/>
talented man as Finance Minister of the <lb/>
Dominion. Was ever a country in such a <lb/>
state before as to be obliged to substitute <lb/>
government bonds for gold in the banks? <lb/>
The following was the scheme proposed to <lb/>
the Dominion parliament by the Finance <lb/>
Minister:- <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Sir. Francis Hincks proposes that the banks <lb/>
shall be prohibited from issuing notes of a less <lb/>
value than $4 and that all the one, two, and <lb/>
three dollar notes in circulation throughout the <lb/>
Dominion shall be government greenbacks. He <lb/>
alleges that this will only yield the government <lb/>
£2,500,000, but as he intends to force out of the <lb/>
country the American silver now in such vast <lb/>
circulation, it may safely be stated at double that <lb/>
amount. But Sir Francis is not content with <lb/>
this, he proposes that all the banks shall hold <lb/>
AT LEAST one-half of their cash reserves in <lb/>
government greenbacks. On the 31st of Jan<lb break="no"/>uary of this year, the said cash reserves of the <lb/>
banks of the Dominion exceeded fourteen millions <lb/>
of dollars. This demand of Sir Francis, there<lb break="no"/>fore, covers no less a sum than seven millions of <lb/>
dollars. And not to conceal his determination <lb/>
to get hold of as much more of these reserves as <lb/>
possible, Sir Francis plumply proposes to free <lb/>
the banks from all obligation to hold any specie <lb/>
for the protection of their liabilities! They may <lb/>
have all their reserves in greenbacks if they so <lb/> 

<pb n="159" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_158.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">159</fw>  

choose. Sir Francis gravely assured the House <lb/>
of Commons on Tuesday night that it was <lb/>
'rather dangerous than otherwise' to require <lb/>
banks 'to hold a certain amount of specie, and <lb/>
that for the very curious reason that they might <lb/>
imagine the prescribed amount to be quite suf<lb break="no"/>ficient and confine themselves to it." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Such was the state of the Dominion that <lb/>
expedients of such a nature had to be re<lb break="no"/>sorted to for the purpose of raising money. <lb/>
A talented correspondent of the St. John, <lb/>
N. B., "Globe" summed up the whole <lb/>
matter as follows:-<lb break="yes"/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The time may come when the Finance <lb/>
Minister may have scattered all over the country <lb/>
$10,174,000 in Dominion notes, and yet, without <lb/>
violating the law, hold only $1,174,000 in gold <lb/>
as security! Whether this is sufficient security, <lb/>
is, of course, another question." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>It was indeed a very important question <lb/>
whether that was sufficent specie for the <lb/>
government to keep. He (Mr. L.) would <lb/>
now direct attention to the power the re<lb break="no"/>presentatives of the maritime provinces had <lb/>
in the Dominion, from which we might <lb/>
judge of our influence were we to go into <lb/>
confederation. Hon. Joseph Howe, in speak<lb break="no"/>ing on the election law, said:- <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"He had yet to learn that Nova Scotia could <lb/>
control this great Dominion. (Hear, hear.) <lb/>
There must be an accommodation of the various <lb/>
systems of the provinces; Nova Scotia must give <lb/>
up something, New Brunswick must give up <lb/>
something, Canada might perhaps learn some<lb break="no"/>thing, but if Canada did not choose to learn, <lb/>
Canada had votes and could control the measure." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>This was what we should probably be told <lb/>
"if Canada did not choose to learn", we <lb/>
must humbly submit to them. It had been <lb/>
said that if we joined the Dominion we <lb/>
should become a part of it, and our interests <lb/>
would be identified with theirs, but it ap<lb break="no"/>peared that the party lines had been kept <lb/>
up, and that Canada could rule. It had <lb/>
been stated that the population of Ontario <lb/>
was increasing very fast, and that she would <lb/>
soon be able to control the vote in the <lb/>
Dominion Parliament. The representa<lb break="no"/>tives of Ontario had been asking for a tariff <lb/>
of twenty per cent, so that if we joined the <lb/>
union we might expect to pay that tariff <lb/>
before long. He (Mr. L.) was proud he <lb/>
belonged to a colony that bought in the <lb/>
cheapest market and sold in the dearest, <lb/>
and did not go in for the Japanese policy of <lb/>
putting a very heavy duty on some articles <lb/>
and letting others come into the country free. <lb/>
One of the reasons why the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment wished to cast off the Dominion was <lb/>
because they had exhausted their liberality, <lb/>
and instead of opening a market for British <lb/>
goods had virtually closed their market <lb/> 

<cb/>

against British manufactures. One of the <lb/>
objects of Britain in founding colonies was <lb/>
to get a market for their manufactures, but <lb/>
her ungrateful child, Canada, had put <lb/>
heavy duties on all her manufactures. We <lb/>
were asked to unite ourselves with that <lb/>
spendthrift colony. There was no com<lb break="no"/>parison between our Island and Canada, <lb/>
for while money had been lavishly spent on <lb/>
Canada, we were refused even a loan to <lb/>
buy out our lands, of which we were un<lb break="no"/>justly deprived. One of the reasons which <lb/>
induced Canada to seek confederation with <lb/>
the other provinces, was because they had <lb/>
a political deadlock- they could not carry <lb/>
on the business of the country. Was that <lb/>
symptom of intelligence? If they had <lb/>
the interests of the country at heart, they <lb/>
would have sunk their differences for the <lb/>
country's welfare. They did not form a coali<lb break="no"/>tion for the purpose of carrying out the <lb/>
pet scheme of confederation, and some of <lb/>
the means made use of to carry out their <lb/>
purpose were not very commendable. In <lb/>
New Brunswick, a Fenian scare was got up <lb/>
to intimidate the people, and three routes <lb/>
were proposed for a railroad, so that the <lb/>
people near the whole of them might be <lb/>
induced to vote for Confederation, which <lb/>
was going to bring a railroad to their <lb/>
doors. By such means the election was <lb/>
carried in New Brunswick. Nova Scotia <lb/>
was used still worse- language would <lb/>
fail to picture the duplicity of the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of that unhappy, much-abused <lb/>
country. And Canada was to be exe<lb break="no"/>crated for receiving Nova Scotia in such <lb/>
a way. It did not say much for either <lb/>
the parliament of the Dominion or the <lb/>
Imperial Government, that they sanc<lb break="no"/>tioned such an act as to confederate <lb/>
Nova Scotia without her people having <lb/>
a voice in the matter. He (Mr. L.) <lb/>
hoped the day was far distant when the <lb/>
government of this Island would take <lb/>
any terms that might be offered without <lb/>
submitting the matter to the people. <lb/>
The terms lately sent from Canada might <lb/>
be subjected to a closer scrutiny than <lb/>
they had yet been. Canada agreed to <lb/>
pay a number of our officials, and well <lb/>
she might, when she took our revenue <lb/>
to do it with. They offered to pay us <lb/>
five per cent on the difference between <lb/>
our debt and that of the Dominion, but <lb/>
we would have to help to pay the interest <lb/>
on the whole debt of the country at <lb/>
seven or eight per cent, if we became <lb/>
part of the Dominion, and our share of <lb/>
that interest according to our population <lb/>
would be $2,250 a year; and if they paid <lb/>
us in Canadian bonds, which were selling <lb/>

<pb n="160" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_160.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">160</fw>  

at latest quotations at 95 percent, we <lb/>
should lose $4,500 more every year. We <lb/>
never asked the British Government to <lb/>
indemnify us for the loss of territorial <lb/>
revenues; we only asked to be allowed to <lb/>
test the proprietors' titles. But the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government said we were en<lb break="no"/>titled to compensation for the loss of our <lb/>
public lands, which was one of the rea<lb break="no"/>sons which induced the Government to <lb/>
frame their reply in the way they did. <lb/>
When the Dominion government, with <lb/>
Sir John Young at their head, made that <lb/>
statement, the government thought it <lb/>
time to demand their rights, even should <lb/>
they never join the Dominion. The <lb/>
reply of the government to the proposals <lb/>
from Canada had been misrepresented, <lb/>
and the Leader of the Opposition had <lb/>
stated that the government were bound <lb/>
to go into confederation if compensation <lb/>
was received for the loss of terrirorial <lb/>
revenues, but he (Mr. L.) would challenge <lb/>
any hon. member to prove that they <lb/>
were so bound. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.— Lord Granville <lb/>
said so. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>.—Were we to be <lb/>
bound by Lord Granville or any under<lb break="no"/>strapper in the Colonial Office? The <lb/>
government said we could not go into <lb/>
confederation until the land question was <lb/>
first settled — this means that if <lb/>
such a settlement was accomplished <lb/>
the government would feel it their <lb/>
duty to submit the matter to the <lb/>
people. When it was considered that on <lb/>
the formation of a government in this <lb/>
Island in 1770, this land question was <lb/>
discussed, and ever since had been a <lb/>
vexed question, it would be only fair to <lb/>
submit the question of confederation to <lb/>
the people, if indemnity was obtained for <lb/>
our lands. Even had the government <lb/>
said they would accept those terms, the <lb/>
people would not be bound to do so; <lb/>
but the only course the government were <lb/>
committed to in the event of our obtain<lb break="no"/>ing indemnity for our lands, was to <lb/>
submit the matter to the people. If we <lb/>
did obtain the $800,000 we should still be <lb/>
far from receiving as much from Britain <lb/>
as Canada had. Some had said it was <lb/>
no difference whether this money was <lb/>
received from Britain or Canada, but he <lb/>
(Mr. L.) considered it of vital importance <lb/>
where it should come from, and the <lb/>
reasons were very fully given in the <lb/>
minute of Council. This $800,000 would <lb/>
not be sufficient to buy up the remainder <lb/>
of our township lands, even had it come <lb/> 

<cb/>

from the proper source. The Council <lb/>
stated that the inion would not prove <lb/>
successful unless it was accomplished <lb/>
"with the free and unbiased consent of <lb/>
the contracting parties." That was <lb/>
surely a self-evident fact. Then again, it <lb/>
was stated "that the interests of the <lb/>
Island with reference to public works <lb/>
had been overlooked." As the public <lb/>
works of Canada were not self-sustaining <lb/>
we should have to help to pay their ex<lb break="no"/>penses, as well as contribute our share <lb/>
towards building others, while we should <lb/>
have none built on the Island out of the <lb/>
general revenue. He (Mr. L.) supposed <lb/>
some would think the most difficult part <lb/>
of the minute of Council for him to "success" <lb/>
in settling the land question would <lb/>
"cause a spontaneous reaction in the <lb/>
minds of the people of Prince Edward <lb/>
Island." When the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had, unsolicited, been making offers <lb/>
to us, there was nothing wrong in trying <lb/>
to get their assistance in settling this <lb/>
long vexed question. When agents, <lb/>
swells, or pedlers travelling through a <lb/>
country became too troublesome, the best <lb/>
way to get rid of them was to give them <lb/>
a difficult job to perform without any <lb/>
compensation. The members of the <lb/>
Dominion Government came here and <lb/>
said we were wronged by the British <lb/>
government, and the government told <lb/>
them to redress this grievance, and it <lb/>
would cause a spontaneous reaction in <lb/>
the minds of the people of this Island. <lb/>
If the Dominion government settled this <lb/>
great question, the people of the Island <lb/>
would regard them with very different <lb/>
feelings from what they did at present, <lb/>
but at the same time they would not be <lb/>
bound to unite with them. The Domin<lb break="no"/>ion government would deserve to be <lb/>
well thought of by the people of this <lb/>
Island if they should settle this question <lb/>
of a century's standing. The minute of <lb/>
council declared that before the people <lb/>
of this Island should be called upon to <lb/>
discuss the question of confederation, <lb/>
they should be placed in the same position <lb/>
as the other colonies. It had been stated <lb/>
that, in our present isolated position, we <lb/>
should never have any influence, but that <lb/>
united ot Canada, we should be a part of <lb/>
a great nation. He (Mr. L.) would ask <lb/>
what constituted greatness? A large <lb/>
population did not constitute greatness, <lb/>
or China would be the greatest empire in <lb/>
the world. Neither did large extend of <lb/>
country, or Russia would be great; <lb/>
neither did wealth make a country great <lb/> 

<pb n="161" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-04_Page_160.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">161</fw>  

unless there was also freedom. The <lb/>
greatness that was to be desired was to <lb/>
have freedom of conscience, and to have <lb/>
every man educated. We should not be <lb/>
improved in these respects by joining <lb/>
the Dominion, and as far as wealth was <lb/>
concerned we could also compare favor<lb break="no"/>ably with them. Some had said we <lb/>
would be safer from invasion in the <lb/>
union; but he would ask where would <lb/>
the great Dominion be if the Republic of <lb/>
America made a raid on them, as Canada <lb/>
was without an army, without a navy, <lb/>
without an able statesman to manage af<lb break="no"/>fairs. We would gain nothing commerci<lb break="no"/>ally by uniting with the Canadians, as they <lb/>
grew everything we did, and we would aid <lb/>
them in building railroads, which would <lb/>
be a means of conveyance for their pro<lb break="no"/>duce, and enable them to supply the <lb/>
different markets more readily than we <lb/>
could. If we paid one-fortieth part of the <lb/>
civil service of the Dominion, it would <lb/>
be more than the whole expense of our <lb/>
government at present, ad we would be <lb/>
obliged to keep up our local government <lb/>
besides. We had now a cheap govern<lb break="no"/>ment and a contented people, and could <lb/>
manage our affairs very well. It was all <lb/>
very well to talk of the duties being <lb/>
taken off certain articles in the event of <lb/>
union, but if so, higher duties would <lb/>
have to be imposed on other things, for <lb/>
government must be sustained, and it <lb/>
made no difference to a man whether he <lb/>
paid his duties on what he ate or what <lb/>
he were. We had nothing to fear if we <lb/>
remained in our present isolated con<lb break="no"/>dition. We had a soil capable of yielding <lb/>
a great deal more than it did at present, <lb/>
and he (Mr. L.) believed the time would <lb/>
come when our Island would be a market <lb/>
garden, and the whole world a market <lb/>
for its production. Our loyalty had <lb/>
been called in question, but when a raid <lb/>
was threatened the whole revenue of the <lb/>
colony was placed at the disposal of the <lb/>
government for defence; and he would <lb/>
ask was the like ever done in any other <lb/>
colony? Our loyalty was beyond dispute, <lb/>
and he (Mr. L.) believed that in case of <lb/>
war with any foreign power, no colony <lb/>
would send more men to assist Great <lb/>
Britain than Prince Edward Island, in <lb/>
proportion to population. <lb/></p> 

<p>[Mr. Brecken followed, reading several <lb/>
length extracts, which have not been <lb/>
furnished the Reporter; consequently he <lb/>
is compelled to omit the speech.] <lb/></p> 

<p>House adjourned. <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>
</div> </body> </text> </TEI>