<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-03-08"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-03-08">8 March 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1870, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1870"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="29"/>
</bibl>

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_016.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_018.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_020.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_022.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_024.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_026.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_028.hocr.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-13">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_017">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_017.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_018">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_018.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_020">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_020.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_022">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_022.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_024">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_024.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_026">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_026.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_028">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_028.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>
<div type="debate">


<pb n="17" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_017.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">17</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, March 8.<lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. McLEAN</persName> said that no people could <lb/>
be called free and independent unless they <lb/>
had power to make their own laws, and on <lb/>
looking at the position we would occupy <lb/>
in the Dominion, were we to join it, he con<lb break="no"/>cluded we would be virtually deprived of <lb/>
that privilege. In the Senate we would <lb/>
certainly have no representation, because <lb/>
whoever might represent us there would be <lb/>
appointed by the Governor General, and <lb/>
not by us. This, he considered, would be <lb/>
bordering on despotism. It might be argued <lb/>
by hon. members of the Opposition that Her <lb/>
Majesty the Queen had the power of appoint<lb break="no"/>ing the British Peers. This he admitted to <lb/>
be true, but she might be said to hold her <lb/>
position by divine right, or inheritance from <lb/>
King Wm. III., who was placed on the <lb/>
throne by the unanimous voice of the <lb/>
people. But no such right existed in, or <lb/>
should be conferred upon the Governor <lb/>
General of, the Dominion. He was nothing <lb/>
more than a loyal British subject, who receiv<lb break="no"/>ed his appointment from the Crown and not <lb/>
from the people. It appeared to him that <lb/>

<cb/> 

the great desire evinced for confederation <lb/>
by certain hon. members of this Legis<lb break="no"/>lature arose from the attraction which <lb/>
$4,000 per annum looming up in the <lb/>
distance had for them, but not from the <lb/>
conviction that such a union would benefit <lb/>
this Island. He thought it should have <lb/>
the opposite effect, and induce us more <lb/>
earnestly to set our faces against such <lb/>
proposals. Last evening he heard an hon. <lb/>
member refer to loyalty, who said that in <lb/>
this day it was in the pocket, and not in <lb/>
the heat, and that loyalty now necessarily <lb/>
led to confederation, and that confedera<lb break="no"/>tion was a stepping stone to annexation. <lb/>
He could not see that such was a correct <lb/>
conclusion, and hoped the question, when <lb/>
it came up, would be fairly considered. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="18" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_018.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">18</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BELL3">Mr. BELL</persName> did not understand why any <lb/>
fault should be found with the expression <lb/>
in the Address. The members of the <lb/>
Legislature represented the people, and all <lb/>
the interests of the country were, for the <lb/>
time being, committed to the keeping of <lb/>
the Government. He could not see how <lb/>
the Government could show their interest <lb/>
for the welfare of the country better than <lb/>
by carefully watching the movements of <lb/>
any party who were suspected of aiming at <lb/>
depriving us of our privileges, nor could he <lb/>
perceive any word more appropriate or <lb/>
suitable than the one used. It was well <lb/>
known that the visit of His Excellency had <lb/>
something to do with confederation, and <lb/>
hence they were watching to see that no <lb/>
occasion should be given to confirm those <lb/>
alarms which appeared in the public press <lb/>
of the country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:KICK1">Mr. KICKHAM</persName> - The Hon. Mr. Haviland <lb/>
said last night that each hon. member <lb/>
should express an opinion on this subject. <lb/>
At present we had power to levy our own <lb/>
taxes, regulate all our own affairs as we <lb/>
thought proper, and place whom we pleased <lb/>
in authority to manage our public affairs. <lb/>
For the last half century we had done so <lb/>
without receiving any assistance from <lb/>
Canada or elsewhere. We had lived with<lb break="no"/>out their aid so far, and he felt convinced <lb/>
were able to do so yet. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PROW2">MR. PROWSE</persName>. - Perhaps it was well that <lb/>
the sentiments of all the members of this <lb/>
hon. committee should now be known on <lb/>
the important question of confederation. <lb/>
When he came to the House this session, <lb/>
he expected that he would have to oppose <lb/>
the majority on this question, but, to his <lb/>
surprise, he found the Government com<lb break="no"/>mitted to the principle of confederation, as <lb/>
this committee was asked to give its calm <lb/>
consideration to the question. He thought <lb/>
it would have been more consistent for the <lb/>
Government to have expressed their decided <lb/>

<cb/> 

opinion on the subject than to be waiting <lb/>
to feel the public pulse. The Government <lb/>
had not expressed any decisive opinion, and <lb/>
believing that public men should do so, he <lb/>
must condemn such conduct. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Newfoundland did not express an <lb/>
opinion so undecisive, but distinctly said <lb/>
that no terms would be accepted. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> could not understand <lb/>
why the hon. member should condemn the <lb/>
government for submitting the question to the <lb/>
consideration of the House, when the hon. <lb/>
member himself said the subject should be <lb/>
well considered by each hon. member. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PROW2">Mr. PROWSE</persName> was not in favor of <lb/>
confederation on the terms proposed, but <lb/>
was in favor of the principle, and believed it <lb/>
would be difficult for this Colony to remain <lb/>
in isolation much longer. He knew that <lb/>
loyal men who had a sympathy with our <lb/>
institutions were making strenuous efforts <lb/>
to connect the whole of British America <lb/>
under one government. Last year we were <lb/>
called upon to provide for the payment of <lb/>
the Governor's salary, and when he reflect<lb break="no"/>ed that the sum annually required to meet <lb/>
this demand represented a capital of £42,<lb break="no"/>000, at 5 per cent., he felt that the demand <lb/>
was a large one, and thought it was but the <lb/>
commencement of a pressure which might <lb/>
be continued, if we refused to accept rea<lb break="no"/>sonable terms and enter the Dominion. It <lb/>
was commonly said that straws showed how <lb/>
the wind blew, and this circumstance de<lb break="no"/>clared to us the determination of the British <lb/>
Government, and he believed their wishes <lb/>
should have weight with us. He was not <lb/>
afraid of the terms that had already been <lb/>
proposed, and believed the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment was disposed to do full justice to <lb/>
this Colony. He felt that if the Dominion <lb/>
would bear a fair proportion of the expenses <lb/>
of our public works, in addition to the con<lb break="no"/>struction of railroad throughout this Island, <lb/>
then the question should be formally <lb/>
considered. If a railroad was proposed to <lb/>
be built in any other way than in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with the Dominion he would oppose its <lb/>
construction. He considered it the duty of <lb/>
the Government to state the terms we <lb/>
should acacept, and give the Dominion <lb/>
Government to know that if they were <lb/>
granted we would unite with them. As to <lb/>
increased taxation, he thought we could <lb/>
bear it as well as the other Colonies, and <lb/>
ours would be no higher than theirs would <lb/>
be. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CAME5">Mr. CAMERON</persName> said the hon. member was <lb/>
last year opposed to confederation, and he <lb/>
was surprised to see what a change had <lb/>

<pb n="19" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_018.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">19</fw>

come over the spirit of his dream. He <lb/>
thought if the hon. member was justified in <lb/>
changing his mind on this important ques<lb break="no"/>tion, he certainly gave no reason to show it. <lb/>
Some hom. members appeared to think that <lb/>
if we resisted confederation it would lead <lb/>
to annexation. The tendency of the remarks <lb/>
of the hon. member for Charlottetown led <lb/>
to this conclusion. The hon. member for <lb/>
Murray Harbor said, if the Dominion would <lb/>
agree to build a railroad for us he would be <lb/>
willing to enter confederation, but that he <lb/>
would oppose the building of one out of our <lb/>
own resources. His (Mr. Cameron's) <lb/>
opinion was that our chances for a railroad <lb/>
outside of confederation were greater than <lb/>
if we were joined to the Dominion. Judg<lb break="no"/>ing from what had already taken place, he <lb/>
saw no reason to suppose that even if we were <lb/>
to enter the Dominion, that the conditions <lb/>
upon which we might enter would be always <lb/>
held inviolable. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCAU1">Hon. Mr. McAULAY</persName> regarded the discus<lb break="no"/>sion of the question now as altogether out <lb/>
of place. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName> was of a different opinion, <lb/>
and thought hon. members should now <lb/>
give their views at once; others might <lb/>
have changed their opinions on this subject, <lb/>
but he saw no reason why he should change <lb/>
his. Although we should get terms that <lb/>
we might regard as favorable, the power of <lb/>
changing these would always rest with the <lb/>
Dominion. When the delegates went to <lb/>
Quebec, they said the terms were favorable, <lb/>
and he believed one of those who signed <lb/>
them sat in the House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> asked if he meant <lb/>
him. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName>.-Yes. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> was glad that he <lb/>
signed his name to that document. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName>.- Those who signed the <lb/>
Quebec Report said the terms were good, <lb/>
yet other and better were now offered. <lb/>
This he regarded as showing that no <lb/>
confidence should be placed in the <lb/>
offer. The Imperial Government had already <lb/>
said that the Dominion Government had <lb/>
power to alter or change the constitution, <lb/>
which he regarded as a clear proof that <lb/>
any terms which might be agreed upon <lb/>
could be altered. The Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was now making strenuous efforts to <lb/>
get us to unite with Canada. Strenuous <lb/>
efforts were also now being made in some <lb/>
parts of the Dominion to upset the present <lb/>
Government, and what guarantee had we if <lb/>
a new Government was formed that it would <lb/>
not overturn, and set aside any arrangements <lb/>

<cb/>

their predecessors might have entered into. <lb/>
It was said that our produce would be shut <lb/>
out of the Dominion markets, but this <lb/>
should not alarm us. All the Provinces <lb/>
had fine capabilities for agriculture, and <lb/>
would soon have to turn their attention to <lb/>
it. They then would supply [illegible] own <lb/>
markets. He saw no reason why we should <lb/>
place ourselves in a position to be taxed by <lb/>
the Dominion. The hon. member for Mur<lb break="no"/>ray Harbor said he was not afraid of high <lb/>
taxes; that if the Dominion could stand them <lb/>
so could we, but he thought that was a race <lb/>
our people would not wish to run. There <lb/>
were islands in the British Channel that <lb/>
had retained their own government, and why <lb/>
might not we do the same? He would not <lb/>
consent to surrender our privileges. We <lb/>
could be as loyal out of the Dominion, as in <lb/>
it, and our duty was to oppose confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. McNEILL</persName> said it was well known that <lb/>
the terms of the Quebec report were con<lb break="no"/>demned by the people of this Colony, and <lb/>
yet, without any offer from this Island, the <lb/>
Canadians came down here and proposed <lb/>
ether terms. When the first terms were <lb/>
offered, they were considered fair by some, <lb/>
these last were regarded as better, but, as <lb/>
the hon. member for Tryon said, what <lb/>
guarantee would we have that they might <lb/>
not be altered? Why, our agreement with <lb/>
them would probably prove no stronger <lb/>
than a rope of sand! The other Provinces <lb/>
might complain, even as Ontario was doing <lb/>
respecting Nova Scotia. They might say <lb/>
that the concessions made to us were unfair <lb/>
to the other Provinces. Money seemed to <lb/>
be the object, and the only one now in the <lb/>
way, in the opinion of many; but he would <lb/>
not look at it from that point of view. He <lb/>
would like to have the opinion of an expe<lb break="no"/>rienced man like the hon. member for <lb/>
Georgetown (Mr. McAulay) and hoped he <lb/>
would favor the committee with it; he was <lb/>
sorry that the hon. Leader of the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion was in favor of confederation, for if he <lb/>
was opposed to it he felt sure that no undue <lb/>
influence would ever induce him to betray <lb/>
the country. He would, therefore, be glad <lb/>
to see him in the anti-confederate ranks, <lb/>
and regarded it as unfortunate that he was <lb/>
pursuing a course which, if carried, would <lb/>
prove so detrimental to the interests of the <lb/>
country. He viewed the matter also from <lb/>
another point. One hundred years ago, his <lb/>
grand-father came to this country, and, in <lb/>
common with others, had to encounter <lb/>
many hardships, such as clearing their <lb/>
farms, opening up new roads, and contend<lb break="no"/>ing with wild beasts and land agents. The <lb/>

<pb n="20" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_020.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">20</fw>

country had since prospered, and that en<lb break="no"/>tirely by the industry of the people. We <lb/>
had no resources for the construction of <lb/>
our public works. The other Provinces de<lb break="no"/>rived a revenue from their public lands, and <lb/>
it appeared to him hard that a resort to <lb/>
any unfair means should be thought of to <lb/>
force us into a connection we disliked. It <lb/>
was now but one hundred years since we <lb/>
were separated from Nova Scotia. Since <lb/>
then we had managed our own affairs as <lb/>
well, if not better, than our neighbors, and <lb/>
if Canada had studied her own interests she <lb/>
would have seen that it was no use to be <lb/>
proposing new terms. To accept of any <lb/>
terms would be to give up our independence. <lb/>
We elected our men for four years, and could <lb/>
replace them with others, if tehy did not do <lb/>
right, but, once into confederation, what <lb/>
power would we then have to alter the <lb/>
government? He read the lecture which <lb/>
was delivered in the city, last fall, on con<lb break="no"/>federation, and noticed that an argument <lb/>
was drawn from the union of the thirteen <lb/>
colonies in favor of confederation. He con<lb break="no"/>tended there was no analogy between them. <lb/>
Their union was cordial ; they were united <lb/>
by a common interest, being drawn together <lb/>
to fight for their liberty ; and by the <lb/>
arrangement made between them they had <lb/>
prospered commercially, as they exchanged <lb/>
their products with each other. In New <lb/>
Foundland, wealthy men engaged in fishing, <lb/>
but the superior privileges conferred upon <lb/>
the French fishermen by the government of <lb/>
France, rendered their fishing, to a great <lb/>
extent, a failure. With regard to the union <lb/>
of the colonies, he felt that we were not <lb/>
prepared for it, and did not believe we <lb/>
would ever be forced to go into union with <lb/>
Canada. It had been laid down that parlia<lb break="no"/>ment could not destroy itself and this was <lb/>
admitted by good authority and laid down <lb/>
by some of the best minds in England. He <lb/>
did not think Nova Scotia was fairly dealt <lb/>
with, and with her example before us, he <lb/>
believed this Island would never return men <lb/>
to the Legislature who would destroy our <lb/>
parliament. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> said the hon. member <lb/>
was not correct in saying a parliament coukd <lb/>
not destroy itself, for facts in this case were <lb/>
stronger than theory. In the reign of <lb/>
Queen Anne, the parliament of Scotland <lb/>
destroyed itself. The parliament of Irelan <lb/>
did the same, and so did that of Jamaica. <lb/>
Hence the theory of the hon. member did <lb/>
not hold good. <lb/></p> 

<p>House Adjourned for one hour. <lb/></p>

<cb/> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">AFTERNOON SESSION.<lb/></p>
 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> said he did not <lb/>
intent to make many remarks on the <lb/>
question of confederation until the de<lb break="no"/>spatches and papers relating to that <lb/>
subject were laid before the House, but <lb/>
he purposed replying to some hon. <lb/>
members who had spoken on the subject. <lb/>
He agreed with the remark of the hon <lb/>
member from East Point (Mr. McLean) <lb/>
that no people were independent unless <lb/>
they had a right to make their own laws, <lb/>
but he took exception to the application <lb/>
of that principle to the union of this <lb/>
Island with Canada, for, in case such <lb/>
union should take place, our local gov<lb break="no"/>ernment would still make our local laws, <lb/>
and we should have representatives in <lb/>
the Parliament at Ottawa who would <lb/>
assist in making the general laws of the <lb/>
Dominion. It had been said that we <lb/>
would only have five members in the <lb/>
Dominion Parliament, but if we joined <lb/>
the United States we would have no <lb/>
representatives in Congress at all, for, <lb/>
according to the American law, no place <lb/>
could have a representative unless it <lb/>
had a population of one hundred and <lb/>
twenty-seven thousand. There was ter<lb break="no"/>ritorial representation in the Senate. <lb/>
The Dominion was divided into three <lb/>
sections, and each section sent twenty-<lb break="yes"/>four members to the Senate. The hon <lb/>
member (Mr. McLean) had been very <lb/>
indignant that the Senators should be <lb/>
appointed by the Governor General, and <lb/>
not elected by the people ; but the former <lb/>
great leaders of the Liberal party in this <lb/>
Island, Messrs. Coles and Whelan, had <lb/>
always argued in favor of having the <lb/>
Legislative Council nominative, and not <lb/>
elective. The hon member (Mr. Howat) <lb/>
had informed the House that he (Leader <lb/>
of the Opposition) had been guilty of <lb/>
signing the Quebec Report, but he would <lb/>
say that he was in very good company in <lb/>
doing so, as all the leading statesmen of <lb/>
the colonies had done the same. The <lb/>
only delegates from this Island who had <lb/>
not signed that Report were the Hon. <lb/>
Colonel Gray and the Hon. George <lb/>
Coles, who were in the United States at <lb/>
the time it was signed. The hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber (Mr. Howat) had stated that our <lb/>

<pb n="21" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_020.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">21</fw> 

trade with Canada was nothing, and that <lb/>
we had better therefore hug our isolation ; <lb/>
but if he would look at the statistics he <lb/>
would find that our trade with the Do<lb break="no"/>minion was equal to that with Great <lb/>
Britain, if we excepted the new ships <lb/>
sent to England. Large quantities of <lb/>
butter, lard, and pork, which was be<lb break="no"/>coming a large article of export, were <lb/>
sent to the Dominion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName> said that the Hon. Leader <lb/>
of the Opposition had misunderstood <lb/>
him. He referred to the future, and <lb/>
stated that they had plenty of land in the <lb/>
Dominion capable of producing all they <lb/>
could consume. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> was glad that the <lb/>
hon member (Mr. Howat) only referred <lb/>
to teh future, and that he acknowledged <lb/>
that the inhabitants of Nova Scotia and <lb/>
New Brunswick did require our produce <lb/>
at the present time. The agricultural <lb/>
capabilities of Nova Scotia had been <lb/>
over estimated. A great part of it was <lb/>
utterly sterile. The soil of this Island <lb/>
was much more easily cultivated than that <lb/>
of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick. It <lb/>
would not be so easy as some hon mem<lb break="no"/>bers thought for us to find a market for <lb/>
our produce, if the Dominion treated us <lb/>
as a foreign state, and taxed all our <lb/>
exports, especially at the present time, <lb/>
when all our products were prohibited <lb/>
from the American market. The first <lb/>
thing that should be done was to ascer<lb break="no"/>tain whether a union with the rest of <lb/>
British America would benefit us or not, <lb/>
and when that question was decided, it <lb/>
would be time enough to talk about the <lb/>
terms. He (Mr. Haviland) had given it <lb/>
as his opinion four years ago, that con<lb break="no"/>federation was only a work of time. <lb/>
Then there were only three or four <lb/>
confederates on the Island, but now there <lb/>
were more than the hon member for <lb/>
Belfast (Mr. Duncan) would like to see. <lb/>
The youngest men of the country, who were <lb/>
being literally educated, would under<lb break="no"/>stand this subject, and would be strong <lb/>
advocates of confederation. In the middle <lb/>
of the nineteenth century to say that <lb/>
isolation was preferable to confederation, <lb/>
was contrary to the spirit of the age. If <lb/>
states were better apart than joined, why <lb/>

<cb/>

had the United States not permitted the <lb/>
Southerners to have their independence <lb/>
instead of expending so much to force <lb/>
them back to their allegiance? The petty <lb/>
German States were being absorbed by <lb/>
the larger countries around theirs. Scot<lb break="no"/>land had prospered since her union with <lb/>
England, and weas not ahead of almost <lb/>
any other country in proportion to her <lb/>
size. If we joined the Dominion we <lb/>
would be of some importance, and not <lb/>
the miserable, wretched sand bank in the <lb/>
Gulf of St. Lawrence that we now were. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName> said that this <lb/>
isolated sand bank in the Gulf of St. <lb/>
Lawrence was more prosperous than the <lb/>
lower provinces, and he believed also <lb/>
was better off than Cnada ; and if, as <lb/>
had been argued, the union of two pro<lb break="no"/>vinces was for the benefit of the poorer <lb/>
one, this was an argument against our <lb/>
joining the Dominion. If the Dominion <lb/>
should put a duty on our exports, we <lb/>
could turn our potatoes and barley into <lb/>
pork, and find a market for that in <lb/>
England. He (Mr. Duncan) had received <lb/>
a statement from an intelligent farmer <lb/>
that he could raise pork of the value of <lb/>
£ 82 10s. at a cost of £76, reckoning <lb/>
potatoes at 1s., and barely at 3s. per <lb/>
bushel. Thus a farmer could get a re<lb break="no"/>numerative price for his potatoes without <lb/>
the trouble of hauling thers. Some time <lb/>
ago New Brunswick required a large <lb/>
quantity of our oats, but of late years <lb/>
they had shipped oats to England them<lb break="no"/>selves, and in a few years New Brunswick <lb/>
and Nova Scotia would grow all the <lb/>
produce they required. If we required <lb/>
£80,000 to supply our local wants now, <lb/>
when we had a population of about one <lb/>
hundred thousand, what would be the <lb/>
consequence when our population should <lb/>
increase to two hundred thousand, were <lb/>
we joined to the Dominion? for the only <lb/>
additional amount we would then receive <lb/>
would be £24,000 (eighty cents per head <lb/>
for one hundred thousand) which would <lb/>
be utterly inadequate to meet our re<lb break="no"/>quirements, and a resort to direct taxation <lb/>
would be inevitable. Canada could not <lb/>
give us terms which would be fair to us <lb/>
and themselves. If we should be obliged <lb/>
to go into Confederation, as some hon <lb/>

<pb n="22" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_022.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">22</fw>

members had stated, that was no argument <lb/>
why we should voluntarily go into it— <lb/>
we should not commit suicide because we <lb/>
had to die. He (Mr. Duncan) believed <lb/>
that confederates were increasing in <lb/>
number, for he had heard the present <lb/>
Leader of the Government party (Mr. <lb/>
Davies) state, at a public meeting of his <lb/>
constituents, that if they had changed <lb/>
their views on confederation, it would <lb/>
make a great difference with him, in<lb break="no"/>timating that he would be ready to <lb/>
change his opinions to suit the times. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName>, in reply to Hon. <lb/>
Mr. Duncan, stated that he had never <lb/>
made use of the language attributed to <lb/>
him by that hon. member, but had merely <lb/>
asked his constituents, at the meeting <lb/>
referred to, if they had changed their <lb/>
opinion on the subject of confederation. <lb/>
The people at that meeting had almost <lb/>
unanimously declared against confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, but he (Col. Sec'y) had told them <lb/>
that they should give the subject their <lb/>
calm consideration, and not look upon <lb/>
all the advocates of confederation as in<lb break="no"/>sincere. At first he (Col. Se'cy) had <lb/>
thought the terms somewhat liberal, but <lb/>
on closer investigation, he had seen the <lb/>
injustice of them. The Canadian gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had performed one act of justice <lb/>
towards us, in stating that our lands had <lb/>
been taken from us unjustly. The offer <lb/>
made by the Canadian government was <lb/>
not sufficiently positive. They were <lb/>
first to endeavor to induce the British <lb/>
Government to give us compensation for <lb/>
our lands, and he (Col. Sec'y) did not <lb/>
think the British government would pay <lb/>
any more attention to their requests than <lb/>
they had to ours. The Dominion gov<lb break="no"/>ernment not only asked us to give up <lb/>
our revenue, but to give them power to <lb/>
tax us at whatever rate they might think <lb/>
proper, and we would have no privileges <lb/>
under confederation that we did not now <lb/>
enjoy. It would be better for us not to <lb/>
have any representatives in the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Parliament, because if we sent <lb/>
five members there, we would be re<lb break="no"/>sponsible for all the laws passed by that <lb/>
Parliament, and could not protest against <lb/>
them. The Governor General would <lb/>
have the appointing of the senators, and <lb/>
as it would be done by the advice of his <lb/>
ministers, they would be all chosen from <lb/>
one political party—the party which had <lb/>
carried confederation. It was the policy <lb/>
of the present government to keep on <lb/>
friendly terms with both the Canadian <lb/>

<cb/> 

and Imperial governments, so that we <lb/>
might be allowed to remain in our pre<lb break="no"/>sent position. If we treated the <lb/>
despatches from the British government <lb/>
on the subject of confederation with con<lb break="no"/>tempt, the Colonial Minister might make <lb/>
it a pretext for recommending that <lb/>
this Island should be forced into <lb/>
union. The British government should <lb/>
put us in the same position with respect <lb/>
to public lands as Nova Scotia and New <lb/>
Brunswick were, before they asked us to <lb/>
join the Dominion. Instead of receiving <lb/>
a revenue from public lands we had been <lb/>
paying a heavy rent, and if we received <lb/>
fair play we should get the interest of <lb/>
about one million pounds sterling paid <lb/>
to us annually by the British Government. <lb/>
Had Scotland not united with England <lb/>
she would probably have been just as <lb/>
wealthy as she now is, her prosperity <lb/>
was owing to the energy and industry <lb/>
of her inhabitants. Our union with the <lb/>
Dominion would be no advantage to us, <lb/>
as the Canadians did not want our oats <lb/>
or pork, which were our principal articles <lb/>
of export. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> said that Mr. Owen <lb/>
Connolly had a contract to deliver four <lb/>
hundred barrels of pork in Quebec on <lb/>
the opening of the navigation. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> quoted the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing from the speech of Mr. McKenzie, <lb/>
one of the leaders of the opposition in the <lb/>
Commons of the Dominion Parliament, <lb/>
published in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> newspaper of 25th <lb/>
February, 1870: <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"We find at one end of the Dominion chronic <lb/>
discontent, at the other end open rebellion; we <lb/>
find all the Provinces that were then out of the <lb/>
Dominion still out of the Dominion. We find <lb/>
that, although this government has enjoyed the <lb/>
most powerful support that any government <lb/>
has received in this country since 1849, they <lb/>
have utterly failed to accomplish what they <lb/>
promised, and what they charged the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion with wishing to obstruct them in doing. <lb/>
* * * * The financial department is in such <lb/>
a state of utter disorder that it is quite impos<lb break="no"/>sible to give the slightest attention to any docu<lb break="no"/>ment coming from it. Last session a report <lb/>
was taken three times for correction, and came <lb/>
back incorrect after all. The balances are <lb/>
false. The late Finance Minister brought down <lb/>
a statement, made in 1868, showing the amount <lb/>
of interest on the public debt. At the beginning <lb/>
of the next session we were informed that there <lb/>
was an error of $200,000 or $300,000. We find <lb/>
that most extraordinary irregularities have <lb/>
taken place in the Receiver General's depart<lb break="no"/>ment; that there has been no proper system of <lb/>
book keeping; that the leader had not been <lb/>
posted for years; that it is very nearly impos<lb break="no"/>sible for any one to get a proper statement of <lb/>
our debenture debt. I make these statements <lb/>
simply because they are known to every one, <lb/>

<pb n="23" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_022.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">23</fw> 

and the extraordinary revelations made in con<lb break="no"/>nection with one of the officers of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment some time ago, show a state of things <lb/>
which no merchant in the country could endure, <lb/>
and which would bring ordinary commercial <lb/>
affairs into ruin a couple of months." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>In view of such a state of affairs, he <lb/>
(Col. Sec'y) thought the charge of bribery <lb/>
and corruption brought against the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government was not without <lb/>
foundation, and we would act the part <lb/>
of wisdom in refraining from linking <lb/>
our destinies with a country under such <lb/>
a government. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> thought it would have <lb/>
been better to have left the discussion of <lb/>
confederation until all the documents re<lb break="no"/>lating to it had been laid on the table. <lb/>
As the "better terms" were sent by the <lb/>
Dominion Government shortly after the <lb/>
visit of Sir John Young and some of the <lb/>
members of his cabinet to the Island, <lb/>
the inference was that our government <lb/>
had given them to understand that some <lb/>
such terms would be acceptable to the <lb/>
people; and if so, the conduct of the pre<lb break="no"/>sent Leader of the Government party <lb/>
(Mr. Davies) was unaccountable. The <lb/>
hon. member had certainly been very <lb/>
inconsistent; one moment lauding the <lb/>
Canadian Government to the skies be<lb break="no"/>cause they coincided with his views <lb/>
on the land question, and the next mo<lb break="no"/>ment declaring them so corrupt that <lb/>
he did not wish to have any connection <lb/>
with them. The bug-bear of taxation <lb/>
had been brought up to frighten the <lb/>
people, but the Canadians could impose <lb/>
no taxes on us that they did not put upon <lb/>
themselves, and if we were wealthy, as <lb/>
had been stated by some hon. members, <lb/>
we would be able to bear taxation. It <lb/>
was a deplorable piece of ignorance on <lb/>
the part of the Colonial Secretary to say <lb/>
that strangers might be appointed to rep<lb break="no"/>resent us in the Dominion Senate, for a <lb/>
section of the Act expressly provided <lb/>
that they should be taken from the <lb/>
Province which they were to represent. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> said he had not <lb/>
made such a statement, but that the <lb/>
senators would all be chosen from one <lb/>
political party. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. McLEAN</persName> did not believe there was <lb/>
any such clause in the Act, and wished <lb/>
the hon. member (Mr. Brecken) to point <lb/>
it out if there was. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> said it was also provided <lb/>
in the Act that, if a senator, after <lb/>
being appointed, left the Province <lb/>
which he represented and went to live <lb/>

<cb/>

in another country, his seat would be<lb break="no"/>come vacant, and a permanent resident <lb/>
of the Province would be appointed. He <lb/>
(Mr. Brecken) believed the present gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of Canada were an extravagant <lb/>
set, and probably they had some dishonest <lb/>
officials, so that the accounts might not <lb/>
always be correct, but that was no more <lb/>
an argument against confederation than <lb/>
the want of proper attention to roads <lb/>
and bridges by a member of this House <lb/>
would tell against responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment. He (Mr. Brecken) had been <lb/>
charged with saying that anti-confeder<lb break="no"/>ation meant annexation; what he meant <lb/>
was, that unless we united with the other <lb/>
colonies, we should be absorbed by the <lb/>
Republic. The statesmen of Great <lb/>
Britain were in favor of consolidation, <lb/>
as was evidenced by their not interfering <lb/>
when Prussia swallowed up the little king<lb break="no"/>dom of Hanover, the birth place of some of <lb/>
England's sovereigns. When king George, <lb/>
the poor blind ruler of Hanover, was <lb/>
driven from his throne, the statesmen of <lb/>
England had not raised a voice against it, <lb/>
because they believed in the great prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of confederation—the happiness of <lb/>
the many must prevail over the comfort <lb/>
of the few. The United States could not <lb/>
make a treaty with us, and every offer <lb/>
they made now was only for the purpose <lb/>
of tampering with our loyalty. <lb/></p> 

<p>[The hon. member here read a letter which <lb/>
had appeared in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Cape Ann Advertiser</hi>, <lb/>
but the Reporter was unable to obtain a copy.] <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. members were in the habit of dis<lb break="no"/>paraging the people of Canada, but if <lb/>
they would travel through that country <lb/>
they would find as fine a set of men as <lb/>
were to be seen in any country. The <lb/>
following article appeared in the London <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Times</hi>, which would show the feelings <lb/>
of the people of England respecting these <lb/>
colonies. Respecting Mr. Beaumont's <lb/>
resolutions it said: <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The first three relate to the short comings <lb/>
of the mother country, the remainder to the <lb/>
means of remedying them. The first resolution <lb/>
declared the duty of England to afford "pro<lb break="no"/>tection" to every colonist. 'As British subjects <lb/>
in the colonies no less than in the mother <lb/>
country are bound to render, and do render, <lb/>
allegiance to the Crown of England, they are <lb/>
no less entitled to the constitutional rights of <lb/>
British subjects; and to withhold from them <lb/>
any such rights which are applicable to their <lb/>
situation would be a grave offence on the part <lb/>
of any responsible officer of the Crown.' The <lb/>
sonorous language about protection from the <lb/>
Crown of England being the constitutional <lb/>
right of every British subject, does not imply <lb/>
any dereliction of duty on the part of the mother <lb/>
country as against a European enemy. The <lb/>
colonists know well that if France or the <lb/>
United States threatened them, the mother <lb/>

<pb n="24" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_024.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">24</fw>

country would strain every nerve in their de<lb break="no"/>fence. A few years since we sent the Guards <lb/>
to Canada in the depth of winter, and hurried <lb/>
to sea the squadrons which should guard the <lb/>
British American coast and the West India Is<lb break="no"/>lands. Was there here any failure in duty, any <lb/>
shrinking from the responsibilities with Eng<lb break="no"/>land had incurred by the planting of colonies, <lb/>
any disregard of the colonists as fellow subjects <lb/>
or as men? To persist in ignoring the plain <lb/>
and just, and equitable distinction which has <lb/>
been laid down by the home government is to <lb/>
trifle with public opinion. It has been declared <lb/>
that England is ever ready to defend the col<lb break="no"/>onies from external and civilized enemies, but <lb/>
that it belongs to themselves to deal with local <lb/>
tumult or with the barbarous races who may <lb/>
exist within their borders. The pretence that <lb/>
such an apportionment of duties is an abandon<lb break="no"/>ment of our own, or a withdrawal of a due <lb/>
protection, tends to make us suspect the spirit <lb/>
in which the colonists call for a closer union. <lb/>
As to the severance of the colonies from the <lb/>
Empire, we retain the opinion we always ex<lb break="no"/>pressed that politically, socially and commer<lb break="no"/>cially, the colonies are in the highest degree <lb/>
valuable to England, and ought to be retained. <lb/>
When their abandonment was urged some <lb/>
years ago by Mr. Goldwin, Smith, with the <lb/>
dogmatic intolerance of his school, we combated <lb/>
the proposal, and should it be renewed, we <lb/>
would combat it again. But there is a great <lb/>
difference between maintaining an honorable <lb/>
connection with free fellow-subjects, and mak<lb break="no"/>ing them helpless by keeping them in leading <lb/>
strings like children. God forbid that the col<lb break="no"/>onies should be abandoned! But if ever this <lb/>
comes to pass, it will be the result of a convic<lb break="no"/>tion on the part of England that their inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants look only to the loaves and fishes of the <lb/>
Imperial system, and that the dependencies are <lb/>
suckers and not feeders of the body politic." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p><persName ref="pers:BELL3">Mr. BELL</persName> did not see the first thing we <lb/>
would gain by confederation. The <lb/>
Dominion could provide no market for <lb/>
our produce or our fish; and whatever <lb/>
inducement they might offer to us in <lb/>
money, as we had seen to-day, might be <lb/>
taken from us again. The British Amer<lb break="no"/>ican Act had been violated by the late <lb/>
arrangement with Nova Scotia, and what <lb/>
was given us one year by the Ottawa <lb/>
parliament might be taken away another. <lb/>
It ought to be our great aim to open up <lb/>
trade with the country that would fur<lb break="no"/>nish us a market, and Canada could do <lb/>
nothing for us in this respect. The con<lb break="no"/>federation scheme was highly objection<lb break="no"/>able in that it offered almost a fixed <lb/>
income for a rapidly increasing revenue. <lb/>
Though the tabular statement issued in <lb/>
Charlottetown showed that a considerable <lb/>
quantity of goods were imported from <lb/>
the Dominion, and claimed that under <lb/>
confederation they would come in here <lb/>
free, yet on examination it was found <lb/>
that a large proportion of these articles <lb/>
were of English manufacture, or were the <lb/>

<cb/>

produce of the West Indies, and would <lb/>
be subject to duty under the Canadian <lb/>
tariff. With respect to the exports to <lb/>
the Dominion set down in that state<lb break="no"/>ment, a great portion of them were only <lb/>
articles forwarded through New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick to the United States. For example, <lb/>
those statistics showed that a quantity of <lb/>
fish had been exported to the Dominion, <lb/>
and he knew that the part of the country <lb/>
from which he came sent almost all that <lb/>
quantity over the New Brunswick rail<lb break="no"/>way to St. John, for the American mar<lb break="no"/>ket. Our isolation here prevented us <lb/>
from having any trade with the outside <lb/>
world for about five months in the year, <lb/>
consequently it would be hard for us to <lb/>
pay equally with the other Provinces in <lb/>
supporting the public works of the <lb/>
Dominion. Once into confederation, <lb/>
the general parliament could tax us as <lb/>
much as they pleased, and only grant us <lb/>
what they thought proper; they might <lb/>
even refuse to give us what they pro<lb break="no"/>mised. This $800,000 which they offered <lb/>
to settle the land question, they had no <lb/>
right to pay, as the grievance was not of <lb/>
Canadian but Imperial origin; therefore, <lb/>
we might expect, it we entered the <lb/>
Dominion, that the first time our repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives asked for money, they would <lb/>
be told that Prince Edward Island had <lb/>
already for her share and would have to <lb/>
be content. In answer to the hon. Leader <lb/>
of the Opposition's remarks with respect <lb/>
to his (Mr. Bell's) annexation tendencies, <lb/>
he might say that his great desire was to <lb/>
see this Island obtain a free market for <lb/>
her fish and produce. He thought, too, <lb/>
that any observer of events must come <lb/>
to the conclusion that this continent <lb/>
would some day be under one govern<lb break="no"/>ment ; and though he was a Scotchman, <lb/>
and would yield to no person in loyalty <lb/>
to his sovereign, he did not think that <lb/>
our interests should be overlooked. In <lb/>
his opinion, there would be nothing im<lb break="no"/>proper in petitioning the home govern<lb break="no"/>ment to allow us to change our alle<lb break="no"/>giance; he would never give his consent <lb/>
to strike one blow or shed one drop of <lb/>
blood against the Queen's authority, but <lb/>
he could not see that it would be dis<lb break="no"/>loyalty to ask in a peaceable way for <lb/>
separation from her government. John <lb/>
Bright, now one of Her Majesty's cabinet <lb/>
ministers, had expressed the opinion that <lb/>
America would be one from Baffin's <lb/>
Bay to the Gulf of Mexico, and he (Mr. <lb/>
B.) contended that we should not be <lb/>
called disloyal for holding the same <lb/>
views. <lb/></p> 

<pb n="25" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_025.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">25</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—The British American <lb/>
Act, it was said, had been violated, and <lb/>
the questions asked what guarantee had we <lb/>
that the proposals of the Dominion, if <lb/>
accepted by this Colony, would not be <lb/>
receded from again by the general par<lb break="no"/>liament? True there was a party in <lb/>
Upper Canada that did gramble at the <lb/>
increased allowances made to Nova <lb/>
Scotia, as being a violation of that Act, <lb/>
but he thought if it were an error, it was <lb/>
one on the right side, as Nova Scotia had <lb/>
had nothing taken from her. We had as yet <lb/>
been no party to any arrangement with <lb/>
the Dominion, and to say that any com<lb break="no"/>pact entered into between her and this <lb/>
Colony, would afterwards be altered by <lb/>
the general parliament, was simply ab<lb break="no"/>surd. The hon. member from Alberton <lb/>
had stated that Canada could not effect a <lb/>
removal of the restrictions on our trade. <lb/>
But what prospects, he (Mr. B.) would <lb/>
ask, had this Colony of obtaining free <lb/>
trade with the United States on her own <lb/>
account? A reciprocity committee from <lb/>
Congress had been here, and their visit <lb/>
had only resulted in showing that there <lb/>
was not the ghost of a chance of the <lb/>
Island alone getting the restrictions on <lb/>
her trade with that country removed. <lb/>
Any person who had listened to the ex<lb break="no"/>tract read from an American paper by <lb/>
the hon. Leader of the Opposition must <lb/>
be convinced that any concessions in that <lb/>
direction must be obtained at the expense <lb/>
of our loyalty. It was said by some that <lb/>
were we to enter confederation we <lb/>
would lose the glorious privilege of self-<lb break="yes"/>government. Well, that was a very <lb/>
taking argument. Self-government was <lb/>
a great blessing, and we were undoubt<lb break="no"/>edly about as free as any part of the <lb/>
world. Greater freedom existed here <lb/>
than even in the United States, as was <lb/>
evidenced by the difficulty there a short <lb/>
time ago between President Johnson and <lb/>
Congress. Here there could be no dead <lb/>
lock of that kind, for as soon as this <lb/>
House passed a vote of want of confi<lb break="no"/>dence in the government the adminis<lb break="no"/>tration was overthrown. Here also we <lb/>
could worship God as we pleased ; but <lb/>
if we became a part of the Dominion, <lb/>
would our freedom in this respect be <lb/>
tampered with? The liberty of the <lb/>
press was another of those glorious pri<lb break="no"/>vileges of which we boasted in this <lb/>
Colony, but was the press less free in <lb/>
Canada? Would the right of trial by <lb/>
jury be taken from us were we in the <lb/>
Dominion? Had the people there not <lb/>
the same sun to shine upon them, the <lb/>

<cb/>

same dews to moisten them, and the <lb/>
same showers to water their fields as we <lb/>
had in this Island? Then why all this <lb/>
ontery about losing our self-government, <lb/>
when the whole question between us <lb/>
and Canada resolved itself in one of <lb/>
money? In considering the subject of <lb/>
confederation, there was no occasion to <lb/>
soar to the regions of political fancy ; <lb/>
just look at our various public officers, <lb/>
what a miserable pittance they received. <lb/>
Yes, it was money we needed, so let the <lb/>
government go to work and make up <lb/>
their bill, and tell Canada what they want<lb break="no"/>ed. At a recent public meeting in this <lb/>
city, he had heard gentlemen in high-<lb break="yes"/>sounding strains ask their auditors whe<lb break="no"/>ther they would sell their rights for <lb/>
money. Such language could only be <lb/>
addressed to the passions of the people, <lb/>
for it must be evident to every unpreju<lb break="no"/>diced mind that not one feather would be <lb/>
plucked from the eagle of our liberty by <lb/>
uniting with the Dominion. It was use<lb break="no"/>less, as he said before, for us, a separate <lb/>
colony, to think of getting free trade <lb/>
with the United States. When the dele<lb break="no"/>gates, General Butler, Judge Poland and <lb/>
that other talented gentleman, Mr. Beck, <lb/>
were here the other summer, he (Mr. <lb/>
Brecken) put the question to Mr. Beck <lb/>
whether he expected their visit would <lb/>
accomplish anything towards establish<lb break="no"/>ing reciprocity between their country <lb/>
and this Island. He answered, no. In <lb/>
fact, he remarked, he was only put on <lb/>
the committee by Speaker Colfax, to <lb/>
hold one end of the political rope whilst <lb/>
General Butler held the other, and he <lb/>
was very glad of it, for they had had an <lb/>
exceedingly pleasant time; but, said he, <lb/>
you will have no reciprocity treaty until <lb/>
you have it with the whole of British <lb/>
America included. He (Mr. Brecken) <lb/>
knew that our fisheries were valuable, <lb/>
but an agricultural people, such as ours, <lb/>
did not care to engage in them; our <lb/>
neighbors, however, who had not so fer<lb break="no"/>tile a country as this Island, would pro<lb break="no"/>secute them. Nova Scotia would also <lb/>
become a manufacturing province, as she <lb/>
possessed the coal and the iron, and all <lb/>
these industries would tend to make a <lb/>
market for our produce. These were <lb/>
some of the results which we might ex<lb break="no"/>pect from confederation, but whether we <lb/>
entered it or not, we could not stop the <lb/>
progress of events in the Dominion. <lb/>
Many in the country thought this agita<lb break="no"/>tion was started by a set of young poli<lb break="no"/>ticians in Charlottetown, who saw that <lb/>
there was no scope for them in this <lb/>

<pb n="26" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_026.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">26</fw>

Colony, and wished to have the wider <lb/>
field of Canada for their ambition. <lb/>
Charges of bribery and corruption had <lb/>
been freely made against the advocates <lb/>
of confederation, but the expression of a <lb/>
little independent sentiment in this <lb/>
House had had a wholesome effect for <lb/>
within the last day or two nothing had <lb/>
been heard about Canadian gold. No <lb/>
person had a right to hold up past poli<lb break="no"/>tical actions to any one, and say, you <lb/>
ought not to pursue this or that course. <lb/>
Every hon. member should have the <lb/>
manliness to express his own conviction. <lb/>
When this great anti-confederate party <lb/>
would be returned at the next election, <lb/>
he hoped they would not play a fast and <lb/>
loose policy on the question, like what <lb/>
the hon. Colonial Secretary had done <lb/>
when he went down to the Uigg meeting, <lb/>
and asked the people there whether they <lb/>
had changed their opinions and were <lb/>
now in favor of confederation. A voice <lb/>
in the crowd answered, "no;" and he <lb/>
replied, "then I am with you !" <lb/>
(Laughter.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MCLEAN</persName> maintained that he was <lb/>
right with respect to what he said in the <lb/>
morning about the senators of the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion; they were to be appointed by the <lb/>
Governor General, and it made very little <lb/>
differenee where they lived, as it would be <lb/>
their interest to please him. We, at least, <lb/>
would have no control over them. The <lb/>
fewness of their number was also an objec<lb break="no"/>tion. In the United States, the smallest <lb/>
state had as many senators as the largest ; <lb/>
but, in the Dominion, it was not so. Upper <lb/>
Canada had 24 senators, Lower Canada 24, <lb/>
and the Lower Provinces 24, once New<lb break="no"/>foundland shonld come in, when the num<lb break="no"/>ber would be 28. He contended that this <lb/>
arrangement was against the Lower Provin<lb break="no"/>ces; in his opinion, they ought to have a <lb/>
majority in the Senate, so that if any en<lb break="no"/>croachment upon them should be attempt<lb break="no"/>ed, it might be counteracted by that body. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>. —The last speaker was a new <lb/>
member, and he would not employ the same <lb/>
language towards him which he did to the <lb/>
Colonial Secretary, who ought to know <lb/>
better. The senators, no doubt, would be <lb/>
nominally appointed by the Governor Gene<lb break="no"/>ral, but he must act according to the advice <lb/>
of his council, who were responsible to <lb/>
parliament. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>. -Hon. members of the <lb/>
Opposition had twitted the Govemmant for <lb/>
holding any conference with the delegates <lb/>
from Ottawa, if they did not intend to en<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

tertain their proposals. He did not see <lb/>
what harm could result from asking these <lb/>
gentlemen what they were able to do for <lb/>
us. He (Mr. L.) was not present at these <lb/>
negotiations, a circumstances for which he <lb/>
was sorry. But had he been with his col<lb break="no"/>leagues on the occasion, he would not have <lb/>
objected to head their proposals, so that any <lb/>
terms they might offer could be placed be<lb break="no"/>fore the people at the next general election. <lb/>
He considered it was the duty of members <lb/>
of the Executive to ask the so-called <lb/>
all-powerful government of the Dominion <lb/>
what it could do to aid us in obtaining a <lb/>
redress of our grievances. It was admitted <lb/>
on all sides that we had been wronged by <lb/>
Britain with respect to our lands, and were <lb/>
this government, this noble government of <lb/>
Canada, to give us some tangible proof that <lb/>
they had an irresistible influence with the <lb/>
Imperial authorities, it would go a great <lb/>
way to remove his objections to confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. He was surprised that the hon. <lb/>
Leader of the Opposition, who was such an <lb/>
admirer of free trade, did not look to <lb/>
his own favorite, model country, Canada, <lb/>
and vent his righteous indignation against <lb/>
her Japanese trade policy, instead of wast<lb break="no"/>ing all his eloquence in condemning the re<lb break="no"/>strictive tariffs between this Island and the <lb/>
Dominion. Here we imposed a duty on such <lb/>
articles as wine, tobacco, &amp;c., for a revenue <lb/>
must be raised from something, as govern<lb break="no"/>ments did not live on air; but surely it <lb/>
was better to replenish the treasury in this <lb/>
way than to impose a tax on newspapers, <lb/>
printing paper, books, and notes-of-hand. <lb/>
In the Dominion, even knowledge was taxed, <lb/>
but here we were free from all such restric<lb break="no"/>tions. The hon. member for Charlottetown <lb/>
must also receive a little notice; but he <lb/>
(Mr. L.) had to confess he remembered <lb/>
very little of what that gentleman had said; <lb/>
his words, indeed, were pleasing to the ear; <lb/>
but they left little behind them but an <lb/>
echo-an echo, too, of the sentiments some <lb/>
person else had uttered before. Well, he <lb/>
(Mr. Brecken) seemed to be very much ex<lb break="no"/>ercised about the views expressed by the <lb/>
members of the government to the dele<lb break="no"/>gates from Ottawa. He (Mr. L.) thought <lb/>
it made very little difference what had <lb/>
passed at the informal meeting with these <lb/>
gentlemen, for it was quite probable that <lb/>
they had formed their conclusions chiefly <lb/>
from outside information. About the time <lb/>
of their visit, it was stated in the Toronto <lb/>
Globe that the government here was in a <lb/>
tottering condition, and that, no doubt, a <lb/>
change int he sentiments of the people <lb/>
would be seen when the general election <lb/>
came off next spring. If this was the <lb/>

<pb n="27" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_026.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">27</fw>

opinion entertained by the Canadian dele<lb break="no"/>gates, it was altogether unlikely that such <lb/>
far-seeing statesmen would base their pro<lb break="no"/>posals on the views of a shaky administra<lb break="no"/>tion. It had been said that Canada had at <lb/>
present an economical government. He was <lb/>
glad to head it, for evidently such a charac<lb break="no"/>ter could not be given its predecessors. <lb/>
The customs revenue of the Dominion for <lb/>
the year ending June 20, 1868, was in <lb/>
round numbers $8,000,00, and the interest <lb/>
paid in the same time on the public debt <lb/>
over $4,000,000. This was a debt, too, <lb/>
incurred without any expensive war. What <lb/>
would her case be when she had to provide <lb/>
a standing army to defend her frontier from <lb/>
ocean to ocean, and a navy to protect <lb/>
her commerce on every sea ? The hon. <lb/>
member for Charlottetown (Mr. Brecken) <lb/>
said isolation was played out. If it was <lb/>
played out, how came it that we were so <lb/>
wall off on this Island, with a trifling pub<lb break="no"/>lic debt, and free newspapers, books and <lb/>
no stamp duties ; with a people, too, as <lb/>
happy and contented as those of any other <lb/>
country in the world. Nor need we refer <lb/>
to this Island alone, for where was the <lb/>
British colony that had not prospered <lb/>
without confederation, unless there was <lb/>
some natural cause to prevent it ? It <lb/>
might be answered, however, that it was <lb/>
time for these colonies to cast off the lead<lb break="no"/>ing strings of the mother country. He <lb/>
(Mr. L.) was of opinion that they would be <lb/>
allowed to choose their own destiny, either <lb/>
to remain as they were or to set up for <lb/>
themselves. The British people, he believed, <lb/>
as he said yesterday, were opposed to the <lb/>
dismemberment of the empire. As to <lb/>
the good looks of the Canadians, so much <lb/>
commented on by the same speaker, (Mr. <lb/>
Brecken) he (Mr. L.) was sure they could <lb/>
not produce a finer looking gentleman than <lb/>
that hon. member himself. (Laughter.) <lb/>
The peace of the Dominion, he (Mr. L.) <lb/>
feared was nearly at an end. This very <lb/>
day a paper had been put into his hand, <lb/>
containing a series of resolutions proposed <lb/>
in the Ontario legislature by no less a per<lb break="no"/>son than Mr. Blake, complaining that the <lb/>
Provinces had been broken, and the British <lb/>
American Act violated by the Dominion par<lb break="no"/>liament giving to Nova Scoita nearly <lb/>
$2,000,000 more than was specified in that <lb/>
Act. Then, again, the North-West terri<lb break="no"/>tory had been purchased, at a cost of <lb/>
£300,000 sterling. What right, he asked, <lb/>
had the people of the several Provinces to <lb/>
pay this money for lands which should be <lb/>
the property of the settlers in that country? <lb/>
It was no wonder that the half-breeds of <lb/>

<cb/>
 

Red River had rebelled against being liter<lb break="no"/>ally sold - no wonder that the Hon. Joseph <lb/>
Howe should caution them to look after <lb/>
their own rights as inhabitants of the terri<lb break="no"/>tory. Now was the time for them to see <lb/>
to their lands, and not be like this <lb/>
colony, oppressed by a system which noth<lb break="no"/>ing short of a miracle could relieve from. <lb/>
It had been argued that this new nation<lb break="no"/>ality, the Dominion, would state on its <lb/>
career as strong as the United States were <lb/>
at first. But the relative positions of the <lb/>
two countries he (Mr. L.) contended were <lb/>
very different. The United States had <lb/>
variety of climate, and, consequently, a <lb/>
market to a great extent within themselves. <lb/>
Then, again, the young republic had no <lb/>
powerful rival state on its borders that ne<lb break="no"/>cessitated it to keep up an expensive mili<lb break="no"/>tary establishment. As to the liberal terms <lb/>
which we might receive from Canada, on <lb/>
condition of our entering the union, he con<lb break="no"/>sidered them of very little account. He <lb/>
believed that before ten years the whole <lb/>
financial arrangement between the Provinces <lb/>
of the Dominion would be re-adjusted, and <lb/>
very properly so, for a government could not <lb/>
be expected to prosper if based upon wrong <lb/>
principles. Hence he was opposed to this <lb/>
us for the loss of our lands. It would be <lb/>
unjust to tax her people to remove wrongs <lb/>
which her government did not cause. <lb/>
Any sum that Canada might give us now <lb/>
for the settlement of our land question, <lb/>
would undoubtedly be counted against us <lb/>
when the re-arrangement which he antici<lb break="no"/>pated in the affairs of the Dominion took <lb/>
place. Let the home government redress <lb/>
our land grievances, and then we would be <lb/>
able to enter confederation on something <lb/>
like equal terms with the other Provinces. <lb/>
But even then, he would like to see our <lb/>
rights as a local government places on a <lb/>
more substantial basis than the will of a <lb/>
parliamentary majority at Ottawa. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> - The hon. member for <lb/>
Bedeque had referred to the resolution <lb/>
brought up in the Ontario legislature <lb/>
against the additional allowances to <lb/>
Nova Scotia. It was well known that <lb/>
when confederation was proposed, it was <lb/>
cordially entered into by Hon. George <lb/>
Brown and other Upper Canadian poli<lb break="no"/>ticians, as a scheme whereby they might <lb/>
free themselves from the difficulties of <lb/>
their position, Wen the delegates went <lb/>
to the Quebec conference they were fully <lb/>
aware of this, and compromises were <lb/>

<pb n="28" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_028.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">28</fw>

made, but he (Mr. B.) did not think <lb/>
Ontario had much reason to complain of <lb/>
what had been done for Nova Scotia, <lb/>
considering the improved position which <lb/>
she herself occupied in the confederacy <lb/>
to what she held under the union of the <lb/>
two Canadas. The hon. member (Mr. <lb/>
Laird) appeared to justify the course <lb/>
pursued by the rebels at Red River. <lb/>
The people there were chiefly half-<lb break="yes"/>breeds and indians, and because they <lb/>
preferred living in a semi-lawless state to <lb/>
coming under an organized government <lb/>
that would foster civilization and the arts <lb/>
of peace, they forsooth were to be held <lb/>
up as patterns to all true patriots. The <lb/>
terms proposed by the Canadian dele<lb break="no"/>gates, said the hon. member, were of no <lb/>
account. He (Mr. B.) wondered when <lb/>
the memoranda came down to this House <lb/>
whether anything like this sentiment <lb/>
would be found recorded there ; and <lb/>
whether the overshadowing power of the <lb/>
Great Republic would therein be set <lb/>
forth. He would ask, looking at the re<lb break="no"/>spective positions of Great Britain and <lb/>
the United States, whether a war be<lb break="no"/>tween them was to be apprehended ? <lb/>
Did the hon member not know that there <lb/>
were millions of British gold invested in <lb/>
the United States ? And further, would <lb/>
not one week's war cost the United <lb/>
States more than all British America <lb/>
was worth? He (Mr. B.) was sorry to <lb/>
hear a member of the government argue <lb/>
that we should not take the $800,000 <lb/>
from the Dominion for the settlement of <lb/>
our land question. The British govern<lb break="no"/>ment would never pay us that money <lb/>
after all she had expended in supporting <lb/>
military establishments in these Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces ; and Canada, in consideration of <lb/>
this, might well give us the amount <lb/>
offered. The Dominion held property <lb/>
belonging to the mother country of much <lb/>
greater value than $800,000, and he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) could see no impropriety in our <lb/>
taking that money form the Ottawa gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. The Hon. Mr. Coles, at the <lb/>
time of the Quebec conference, saw no <lb/>
impropriety in it either, when he <lb/>
asked for £200,000 to settle our land <lb/>
question. Reference had been made to <lb/>
the newspaper postage and stamp duties <lb/>

<cb/>

of the Dominion. He (Mr. B.) admitted <lb/>
those taxes were obnoxious, particularly <lb/>
in a new country ; but were we to con<lb break="no"/>demn everything about Canada because <lb/>
some of her duties were objectionable ? <lb/>
In the United States even photographs <lb/>
were taxed, and go where we would, <lb/>
something of the sort would meet us. <lb/>
The present government of the Dominion <lb/>
would not always remain in power ; the <lb/>
reformers of Upper Canada, who were <lb/>
mostly Scotchmen and economists, would <lb/>
yet get control of the finances, and then <lb/>
we might look for the abolition of all <lb/>
obnoxious taxes. But taxation was be<lb break="no"/>ing increased in this colony ; last year <lb/>
our duties were raised one per cent., and <lb/>
if the public works were carried out <lb/>
which we required, he believed that in a <lb/>
few years our tariff would be up to 15 <lb/>
per cent., or as high as it now was in <lb/>
the Dominion. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Hon. P. SINCLAIR</persName> scarcely knew what <lb/>
side of this questions the hon member for <lb/>
Charlottetown was on till to-night ; but <lb/>
he had now come out squarely in favor <lb/>
of confederation. The Scotchmen of <lb/>
Canada had come in for a share of his <lb/>
admiration ; he thought they were so <lb/>
economical they would keep down tax<lb break="no"/>ation. He (Mr. S.) could tell that gen<lb break="no"/>tleman that these Scotchmen, or their <lb/>
forefathers, came from a country much <lb/>
more heavily taxed than even Canada, <lb/>
and perhaps would not be able to keep <lb/>
down these burdens in their adopted, any <lb/>
more than in their native, country. <lb/>
That hon member had a great deal to say <lb/>
about confederation, but he had never <lb/>
shown what benefit it would be to this <lb/>
Colony. He had soared away to the <lb/>
glory argument, and asked if we would <lb/>
not have the same sun to shine upon us, <lb/>
and the same dew to fall upon us in the <lb/>
Dominion as we had now. He (Mr. S.) <lb/>
wondered if we were to become subjects <lb/>
of the Sultan of Turkey whether we <lb/>
would have a different sun to shine upon <lb/>
us! All this was beside the question. <lb/>
We had our rain and sunshine independ<lb break="no"/>ently of any earthly government, and <lb/>
our duty was to consider those things <lb/>
which a change of our constitution might <lb/>

<pb n="29" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_028.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">29</fw>

bring upon the Colony. We knew we <lb/>
were lightly taxed at present, and that <lb/>
in a general way our revenue, from the <lb/>
improvement of the country, would keep <lb/>
pace with out expenditure. With re<lb break="no"/>spect to the proposals from Canada, he <lb/>
did not look upon them as any better <lb/>
than the Quebec Scheme, as revised at <lb/>
the London Conference, with the excep<lb break="no"/>tion of the increased number of our <lb/>
population on which the 80 cents a head <lb/>
would be paid ; and the $800,000 for <lb/>
our lands, which was only an offer of <lb/>
the amount asked by Hon. Mr. Coles at <lb/>
the first conference, namely, £200,000 <lb/>
Canadian currency. It had been stated <lb/>
on the floor of this House that we had a <lb/>
very large trade with the Dominion. He <lb/>
(Mr. S.) had looked into the matter, and <lb/>
found that our exports to Canada during <lb/>
the last three years had decreased from <lb/>
£2,188 9s. 6d. to £1,093 19s.; while our <lb/>
export trade with the United States dur<lb break="no"/>ing the same period, in the face of a <lb/>
hostile tariff, had increased from £21,<lb break="no"/>688 4s. to £48,031 19s. 7d. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> merely rose to <lb/>
ask the hon. member from Wilmot Creek <lb/>
(Mr. Laird), who had such a horror of <lb/>
taxes on newspapers, and the like, why <lb/>
it was that we had to pay time pence <lb/>
postage here on a letter to the neighbor<lb break="no"/>ing Provinces, while throughout the Do<lb break="no"/>minion it was only three cents ? and <lb/>
why postage from Britain to Canada  <lb/>
had been reduced to three pence sterling, <lb/>
and to this Island it was still six pence; <lb/>
and to those who had to pay the fine by <lb/>
late mails, thirteen pence half-penny <lb/>
currency ? <lb/></p>
 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>—The postage refer<lb break="no"/>red to was only a temporary inconve<lb break="no"/>nience, which, he believed, would be re<lb break="no"/>medied with as little delay as possible; <lb/>
but the taxes in the Dominion were a <lb/>
deliberate charge imposed by parliament. <lb/></p>
 
<p>Debate adjourned till to-morrow. <lb/></p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>