<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1865-03-02"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>


<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1865-03-02">3 March 1865</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1864">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1865, Being the Third Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1865"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Protestant" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="11"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_004.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_005.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_006.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_007.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_008.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_009.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_010.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_011.html"/>
</item>



</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-05">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_004">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_004.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_005">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_005.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_006">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_006.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_007">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_007.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_008">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_008.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_009">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_009.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_010">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_010.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_011">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_011.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">
<pb n="4" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_004.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">4</fw>

<head rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, March 2.</head><lb/>

<head rendition="simple:right">DEBATE ON THE ADDRESS IN ANSWER TO HIS <lb/>
EXCELLENCY'S SPEECH.</head><lb/> 

<p>On motion of Mr. Brecken the House went into the order <lb/>
of the day, vir; Committee of the whole on the Draft Address<lb/>
in answer to His Excellency's speech. Mr Yeo in the chair,<lb/></p> 

<p>The Chairman first read the whole Draft Address, which is <lb/>
as follows:<lb/></p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">To His Excellency George Dundas, Esquire, Lieutenant<lb/>
Governor and Commander in - Chief in and over Her<lb/>
Majesty's Island Prince Edward and the Territories <lb/>
thereunto belonging, Chancellor, Vice Admiral, and <lb/>
Ordinary of the same, etc, etc,</hi><lb/></p> 

<p>3. We thank your Excellency for having, in compliance <lb/>
with the Resolution passed last Session, appointed Delegates<lb/>
to confer with Delegates appointed by the Governments of<lb/>
Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, respectively, for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of discussing the expediency of a Legislative Union of<lb/>
the Maritime Provinces, and we shall be happy to receive the<lb/>
Correspondence on this subject, together with the Report of<lb/>
the Delegates.<lb/></p>

<p>4. We shall be pleased to learn the origin of the second<lb/>

<cb/>

Conference held at Quebec to consider the wider question of <lb/>
general Union of the British North American Provinces, to<lb/>
attend which, your Excellency, on the invitation of the<lb/>
Governor General, appointed Delegates selected, as were the<lb/>
Delegates to the former Conference, from each of the political<lb/>
parties in the legislature.<lb/></p> 

<p>5. We beg to assure Your Excellency that we shall not <lb/>
fail to give your earnest consideration to the Resolutions<lb/>
adopted at the Quebec Conference, upon the mementous sup<lb break="no"/>port of a General Union of the Provinces, and also to the<lb/>
Despatches from Her Majesty's Principal Secretary of State<lb/>
or the Colonial Department, relative thereto.<lb/></p> 

<p>The first four paragraphs of the Address having been again <lb/>
read, were agreed to without discussion. When the adoption of<lb/>
the 5th paragraph was moved, <persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon Mr Coles</persName> addressed the<lb/>
Committee to the following effect:<lb/> </p> 

<p>There is no doubt. Mr Chairman, that this House will give due <lb/>
attention to the subject of the paragraph which has just been <lb/>
readand 1 wish that the Government had done likewise. They <lb/>
have received the Report of the Conference held at Quebec, and, <lb/>
that being the case, they should have met the Legislature with a <lb/>
decided declaration of opinion on the   subject of the Union of the <lb/>
Colonies. On a question of such importance—the most moment<lb break="no"/>ous that ever was submitted to the consideration of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature of the Island—a question involving the interests of all the <lb/>
North American Colonies—l assert that the Government should <lb/>
have given   a decided expression of opinion, and l am sorry that <lb/>
they have not taken the responsibility of declaring their policy ; <lb/>
instead of doing so, they  have brought, the subject before us as <lb/>
bring non political. While I admire the man who maintains an <lb/>
opinion of his own, and admit that in political parties, the <lb/>
several members must often yield their individual views, yet, <lb/>
when a great general  principle is involved, as in the present <lb/>
question, the people have the right to know what are the opinions <lb/>
of the Government which they placed in power. When that <lb/>
supporter of the Conservative party in England, Sir Robert <lb/>
Peel differed from his colleagues on a great public question, he <lb/>
took his own ground, and was respected by men of all parties for <lb/>
his independent spirit. It may be said that under this scheme of <lb/>
Confederation, the principles of Responsible Government are <lb/>
maintained, but the people will view it with caution if not satis<lb break="no"/>fied with the terms One gentleman has published the statement <lb/>
that a majority) of the Government is opposed to the Union; but <lb/>
if that be a faithful expression of opinion, their acts are incon— <lb/>
sistent with it ; no Government taken its opponents into its <lb/>
confidence. In New Brunswick a member of the Executive <lb/>
resigned his seat and office,    rather than remain to listen to the <lb/>
plans of a policy he did not agree with. We have a similar case <lb/>
nearer home and no man of honor will consent to act as a spy. <lb/>
Here we have the Government putting into the situation fo their<lb/>
only legal adviser a red hot opponent. I mean to convey no<lb/>
imputation on that gentleman; but I blame the Government for<lb/>
professing one set of opinions and appointing to so important an<lb/>

<pb n="5" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_005.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">5</fw>

office a gentleman who entertains views entirely opposite. The <lb/>
Government are playing fast and and loose, and are not agreed <lb/>
among themselves on this great question. The other day the <lb/>
leader had several teams employed in removmg a building which <lb/>
they did by pulling together ; but had he set them to <lb/>
work in opposite directions he would have failed in his object. <lb/>
This is like the position of the Government, and this is what I <lb/>
disapprove of. If the members of Government are not a party <lb/>
entertaining the same political views, in what position are we <lb/>
placed ? If the majority of the Council are opposed to this <lb/>
measure, they have to trust to their opponents in the House, the <lb/>
Col. Secretary and the Solicitor General, if the latter be re<lb break="no"/>elected, to carry out their views. I, for one, have no confidence <lb/>
in the non-departmental system, and these gentlemen are the <lb/>
only officials here. Last year the Government treated this sub<lb break="no"/>ject very cautiously, the then Leader asserting that the duty of <lb/>
the delegates was but to report the proceedings of the Convention. <lb/>
I myself said that the Union would be no benefit to the people of <lb/>
the Island, and voted against the delegation. But the question <lb/>
now comes up in a new shape. We have a new constitution <lb/>
signed and approved of by members of the Government, and our <lb/>
position would have been very different if we had for consideration <lb/>
merely the report of what had been done. The present position <lb/>
of the Government is such that it is our duty as representatives <lb/>
of the people, to express our opinion on their conduct. The fact <lb/>
that they have an Attorney General who is not a member of the <lb/>
Executive, and the recent appointment to that body of two <lb/>
gentlemen of opposite sentiments require that the expression of our <lb/>
opinions should accompany the paragraph before the Committee, <lb/>
before it goes forth to the public. We have had so many changes <lb/>
in the Government of late, that it is hard to say whether it is now <lb/>
a new Government, or merely the old one with a new head. <lb/>
Were it based on constitutional principles, it would have been <lb/>
reconstructed, every member going back to his constituents. It <lb/>
would have been better if the Government had waited for the <lb/>
opinion of the Legislature, before filling up the vacancies as they<lb/>
have done. So much has appeared through the press on the<lb/>
subject of Confederation, that I shall not occupy the time of the<lb/>
Committee by harping on it. I will put my opinions on record<lb/>
by moving a resolution which embodies my views on the policy<lb/>
of forming a Government, some members of which sanction one<lb/>
line of policy, and others the reverse. Whoever may be in<lb/>
power, it is but right that they should shew their colors. I now<lb/>
move the following amendment :—<lb/></p> 

<p>"But we regret that your Excellency should have appointed, <lb/>
as one of your legal advisers, a gentleman, who, as a Delegate,<lb/>
has declared himself " a red-hot Unionist," upon the terms<lb/>
agreed on at the Quebec Conference."<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. Mr. POPE</persName>.—The hon. leader of the Opposition, Mr. <lb/>
Chairman, must be very eager to show his hostility to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment when he would propose such an amendment to the Address<lb/>
as that which he has just submitted. It has nothing to do with the<lb/>
real subject before the committee ; the paragraph under consid<lb break="no"/>eration does not express any opinion either in favor of or against<lb/>
a union of the Colonies. He seems to be in great haste to declare<lb/>
his opposition to the proposed Confederation, but if he would go and<lb/>
read his own speech delivered at Ottawa on the question it ought<lb/>
to bring the blush of shame to his face. He has moved a vote of<lb/>
want of confidence in the Government, and assigns as his reason<lb/>
for this procedure that he has heard certain members of the Ex<lb break="no"/>ecutive state that they were in favor of Union. When the Des<lb break="no"/>patches and other papers on the subject are laid before the House,<lb/>
and the question comes up in due form, it will be fully dealt with.<lb/>
If the hon. member, however, wishes an assurance as to the<lb/>
course the Government will pursue, I can tell him that we have<lb/>
no intention to force this matter upon the House or people—that<lb/>
the Government is not in favor of the scheme, and therefore it<lb/>
was not submitted as a Government measure. When it comes<lb/>
up properly they will not hesitate to give an expression of opin<lb break="no"/>ion on the subject. The hon. leader of the Opposition may sup<lb break="no"/>pose that some of the supporters of the Government will not<lb/>
approve of the appointment of one who advocates Union to a seat<lb/>
in the Executive ; but I can assure hon. members that there is<lb/>
no disposition on the part of the Government to take advantage<lb/>
of the country on the question. No decisive action in favor of<lb/>
Union will be taken until the opinion of the people is ob<lb break="no"/>tained at the polls.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HENS1">Hon. Mr. HENSLEY</persName>.—This subject of a Union of the Colonies<lb/>
being one of the most momentous which has ever come up for<lb/> 

<cb/>

consideration before this House, it does strike me as very <lb/>
irregular that it has not been made a Government question. <lb/>
They should, in view of the great interests which it involves, <lb/>
have come down with a decided policy, instead of a negative one <lb/>
as they have done. It is impossible to ascertain from the views <lb/>
of members of the Government expressed outside of this House, <lb/>
or from the Address before us, what course they intend to pursue. <lb/>
I have some objection to the resolution proposed by my friend the <lb/>
hon. leader of the Opposition ; I consider it too personal. I have <lb/>
nothing against the gentleman alluded to in that resolution on <lb/>
personal grounds ; on the contrary I have a very high respect for <lb/>
him. If persons are going to be particularly objected to for their <lb/>
views, I hold that the hon. member has almost as good a reason <lb/>
for opposing the Government because the Hon. Colonial Secretary, <lb/>
who is also an advocate of Union, is allowed to retain his seat at <lb/>
the Executive board. Before the discussion is over I may sub<lb break="no"/>mit a resolution, with no personal allusions, to test the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment on the general question of the proposed Union of the Colonies. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.—I have no personal objections to the gentle<lb break="no"/>man who was the hon. member for Georgetown. I merely <lb/>
referred to him, because having declared himself so decidedly in <lb/>
favor of Union, his appointment might seem to indicate that the <lb/>
Government were disposed to support the scheme. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI1">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>.—It would have been rather a strange <lb/>
proceeding to have inserted in the address anything decided on <lb/>
the subject of Union. There is a great difference of opinion on <lb/>
the question, and it would certainly be premature to pronounce <lb/>
upon it until all the papers containing information on the subject <lb/>
are laid before the House. I, for one, am rather in favor of a <lb/>
Union of the Colonies ; but I am opposed to the terms contained <lb/>
in the Report of the Quebec Conference. We ought to contribute <lb/>
towards our defence, and therefore I would not object to the <lb/>
expense of the proposed Union on this ground ; but it would be <lb/>
unfair to burden us with the cost of constructing railways and <lb/>
making canals in Canada, from which we would derive little or no<lb/>
benefit. When the Despatches on the subject, however, come<lb/>
down will be the proper time to discuss the merits of the question.<lb/>
I cannot agree with the hon. leader of the Opposition that we<lb/>
should have appealed to the people if we could not construct a<lb/>
Government unanimously opposed to the United Scheme.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LONG2">Hon. Mr. LONGWORTH</persName>.—Before we come to a decision<lb/>
on the Union question, we should possess full information on the<lb/>
subject, and from whom can we obtain this information more<lb/>
saisfactorily than from the Delegates themselves who attended<lb/>
the Conference ? These hon. gentlemen, however, at this stage<lb/>
of our proceedings, are not in a position to consistently enter into<lb/>
explanations on the subject of their deliberations. We therefore<lb/>
should wait and not come to a vote on this question until the<lb/>
Report of the Delegation and the correspondence relative thereto<lb/>
are laid before us. The hon. leader of the Opposition seems to<lb/>
be desirous of amusing himself, or perhaps feeling the pulse of<lb/>
his own party by his experimental and rather singular motion ; for<lb/>
it is evident that he has not consulted his party. One of his<lb/>
supporters, the hon. and learned member for East Point, is dis<lb break="no"/>satisfied with the resolution which he has proposed, and intends,<lb/>
it appears, to submit one himself, expressive of his own views.<lb/>
The hon. leader of the Opposition censures the Government<lb/>
because they have not defined their policy and assumed the<lb/>
responsibility of dictating to the people on this grave and momen<lb break="no"/>tous subject, which affects alike the interests and well being of all<lb/>
classes, races, and political parties in this Colony. It would, in<lb/>
my judgement, be premature for the Government of this Island<lb/>
at this early stage of our proceedings, and before the other Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces had given their voice on the subject, to anticipate the<lb/>
action and decision of those Provinces and to declare their opinion<lb/>
on the proposed scheme of Confederation. In Nova Scotia, where<lb/>
every member of the Government is in favor of the measure, they<lb/>
have not made it a Government question. If this was deemed a<lb/>
prudent course in Nova Scotia, certainly it would have been<lb/>
impolitic for the Government of a small Colony like this to have<lb/>
taken a more decided step. Our proper course is to make the<lb/>
matter an open question, and thereby allow all parties the op<lb break="no"/>portunity of discussing the subject freely, and of recording their<lb/>
opinions upon it according to their unbiased judgement. I, for<lb/>
one, am determined to do no act to prejudice the constitutional<lb/>
right of the people to decide on this great question, as I conceive<lb/>
it to be our duty to return to the people intact the rights and the<lb/>
constitution with which we were entrusted, and which we were<lb/>
bound to uphold when we were elected to this House. This is<lb/>

<pb n="6" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_006.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">6</fw>

my view of the subject, and it has also been ably and well laid <lb/>
down by the hon leader of the Government, that the people ought<lb/>
to be consulted before a decision should be givin in favor of the<lb/>
Union scheme. We have now, however, as a House, no<lb/>
data to work upon, and therefore I repeat that it would be<lb/>
premature at present to enter upon a discussion of the subject, or<lb/>
come to any resolution bearing upon it.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon Mr COLES</persName>.--This is the very point at which I am<lb/>
aiming, namely, to draw out an expression of opinion from the<lb/>
Government. Should a dissolution of the House take place, how<lb/>
are the people to know what is submitted to them unless the<lb/>
Government says yea or nay. If I only knew their policy per<lb break="yes"/>haps I would give them my support. It is evading the question <lb/>
to say that we are not informed on the subject, for almost every <lb/>
child between Ottawa and Charlottetown knows all about it -- <lb/>
even to nice calculations on the cost of the Intercolonial Rail<lb break="no"/>way. The hon member who last spoke, has, I understand,<lb/>
declared his views on the Union scheme at a public meeting ;<lb/>
and after expressing himself as decidedly opposed to it, I am<lb/>
astonished that he, as a member of the Government, should give<lb/>
his sanction to the appointment of a gentlemen to be one of his<lb/>
colleagues, who has announced himself to be a "red-hot<lb/>
Unionist." I contend that it was the duty of the Government<lb/>
to declare their principles, and then appeal to the people at once,<lb/>
and not to wait until the House was in Session some time before<lb/>
they agreed upon their policy--then perhaps only to put off the<lb/>
question. In Canada they deemed the matter of such importantance<lb/>
as to grapple with it at the very opening of the Session. If we<lb/>
should delay giving a decision upon the question here until the<lb/>
House dies out, it will not be treating the Canadians fairly, who<lb/>
are desirous to have the measure carried immediately into effect.<lb/>
It was the duty of the Government, instead of acting as they have<lb/>
done, to have aimed at leading public opinion, and then taken<lb/>
the case to the polls. It is a very easy course for a Government<lb/>
to pursue, merely to slip along without advancing their views on<lb/>
questions of the greatest importance to the country. There is<lb/>
another subject occupying a share of public attention-- a Union<lb/>
of a different description to that under consideration, which has<lb/>
been passed over in silence in His Excellency's speech. I<lb/>
allude to the Tenant Union, and I am partly disposed to censure<lb/>
the Government for not declaring their sentiments in reference to<lb/>
this organization, as its principles may have to be tested at the<lb/>
next general election. But I will not enter into that<lb/>
subject now. The Government of New Brunswick have<lb/>
taken decided action on the question of Union ; Hon Mr Tilley<lb/>
has declared himself in its favor and appealed to the people. If<lb/>
Confederation be rejected in that Province at the polls, will he<lb/>
retain office ? No, Mr Chairman, I believe he has too much<lb/>
principle to attempt anything so unconstitutional. Allusion has<lb/>
also been made to Nova Scotia ; but from what I know of the<lb/>
gentlemen who is leader of the Government there, I think it is<lb/>
not at all probable that he will shirk the question. It will come<lb/>
up in the Legislature, and if he is unable to carry it I believe he<lb/>
 <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. GRAY</persName>.--Mr. Chairman, I am of opinion that the<lb/>
conclusion of the hon member's remarks might have been<lb/>
spared. I would have preferred to have taken no part in this<lb/>
discussion, but when referred to and misrepresented, I cannot<lb/>
be silent. Perhaps the hon. member may not be acquainted<lb/>
with the merits of the case to which he has alluded. Let me,<lb/>
then, state that the difference between an hon gentleman, not a<lb/>
member of this House, and myself, was unconnected with the<lb/>
question of a Union of the Colonies. It was quite a different mat<lb break="no"/>ter altogether. If the hon member who has introduced this un<lb break="no"/>pleasant subject would refer to the files of some of the public jour<lb break="no"/>nals, he would find the reasons which I assigned for resigning my<lb/>
position as president of the Executive Council and as a member<lb/>
thereof. The case had nothing to do with a Union of the<lb/>
Colonies. It might have occured in any other circumstances.<lb/>
It affected myself personally, and also the interests and honor<lb/>

<cb/>

of the country apart from the question of Union. The hon <lb/>
leader of the Opposition has referred to two points which though<lb/>
at first dissevered he has since connected--the subject of a<lb/>
Union of the Colonies and a Government question respecting an<lb/>
appointment to office. I am at a loss to understand how the<lb/>
hon member for the East Point intends to propound his views on the<lb/>
subject ; perhaps he will present his objections to the Address<lb/>
in a more connected form. Surely hon members cannot have so<lb/>
soon forgotten that the Government appointed delegates, according<lb/>
to the resolution of this House last session, to confer with other<lb/>
delgates, on the subject of a Union of the Maritime Provinces;<lb/>
and also at a later date on the invitation of His Lordship the<lb/>
Governor General, that delegates were appointed to consider<lb/>
the broader question of a Union of the whole of the Provinces.<lb/>
This is a matter calculated to effect the interests and welfare<lb/>
of every subject in British America irrespective of party, race or<lb/>
faith ; and consequently to divest it as much as possible from a<lb/>
party question, three members of the Government, three mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Opposition, and one independent member of this<lb/>
House, were appointed to proceed to Quebec as delegates.<lb/>
This delegation was nominated on precisely the same grounds<lb/>
as the first was appointed. When the request came from<lb/>
Canada for this Colony to send delegates to confer on the<lb/>
question of a Union of the whole of the Provinces, surely it<lb/>
was not necessary to call the Legislature together to<lb/>
consider the propriety of acceding to the request. If<lb/>
this were the case of what use would the Executive be ?<lb/>
It would, indeed, be a do-nothing Government. There was no<lb/>
occasion to seek new powers from the Legislature ; the two<lb/>
delegations were for precisely the same purpose, only the latter<lb/>
was to consider the subject on a grander scale. The one scheme<lb/>
was for uniting Provinces comparatively unimportant ; the other<lb/>
was for consolidating the same Provinces into a confederation<lb/>
which would form a state as large as the entire Continent of<lb/>
Europe. If I had thought that this subject was to have been<lb/>
speaking, for the hon leader of the Opposition, or for the hon<lb/>
gentleman on his right, the member for St Peter's--as well as<lb/>
another hon gentleman from the other end of the building who<lb/>
has generally been opposed to my views--that I should have ap<lb break="no"/>pointed them on this delegation ? My friendship for them on<lb/>
political grounds was not so great that I would have urged their<lb/>
appointment had I thought that the subject which the delegation<lb/>
met to consider was to be a question on which an effort would<lb/>
be made to defeat the Government. I encountered no little<lb/>
opposition in procuring the appointment of my political opponents ;<lb/>
but if there be any blame attaching to it, I assume it all. I<lb/>
believe, however, that there is not a member of this House who<lb/>
does not appreciate and approve of the motives which influenced<lb/>
the choice. But Sir, I have recently learned that there are<lb/>
three great commandments for politicians--of which I was<lb/>
entirely ignorant when I entered political life. This first of these<lb/>
is for the politician to take good care of himself and his pocket ;<lb/>
the second is to crush his enemy ; and the third is to attend to<lb/>
the good of the country. And, Sir, I fear that the third is some<lb break="no"/>times wholly forgotten in the zeal to carry out the other two.<lb/>
(Applause.) Acting on these rules, therefore, it is fair game for<lb/>
the hon leader of the Opposition to endeavor to trip up the<lb/>
Government on any pretence whatever. I think, however, it<lb/>
would have been more prudent in him to have deferred bringing<lb/>
up this question until it came before the House in due form.<lb/>
The delegates appointed were required to report to the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, which I as their chairman am prepared to do ; but at this<lb/>
stage of the proceedings, until this Report can be laid before the<lb/>
House, it is premature to discuss the subject. At Quebec I<lb/>
decide ; when I returned here, however, I found the statement<lb/>
had gone forth--like many more which were untrue--that this<lb/>
question was to be carried without an appeal to the people. I<lb/>
immediately wrote a letter to the different newspapers in the<lb/>
Colony stating some of my views on the subject, and assuring the<lb/>
people that the measure could not be sanctioned without an<lb/>
appeal to them. The hon member has referred to the course<lb/>
pursued by the Government of Nova Scotia on the question.<lb/>
They have adopted there the plan which I thought we ought to<lb/>
follow out in this Colony. I understand it is the intention of the<lb/>
Government of Nova Scotia to submit the Report of the delegates<lb/>
to the House of Assembly, and if but a majority of that body<lb/>
were in favour of the scheme, that then there would be an appeal<lb/>
to the people. I have not consulted with the members of our<lb/>

<pb n="7" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_007.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">7</fw>

course they purpose to adopt ; but I consider that it is their duty <lb/>
to submit the Reports to the House, and then will be the time<lb/>
for this honorable body to deal with them on their merits. The<lb/>
question has assumed such grave features of late on account of<lb/>
the action of the Home Government, that it may be necessary to<lb/>
deal with it in a practical manner. It is difficult to say what<lb/>
despatches from the Secretary of State for the Colonies may be<lb/>
laid before us in the course of a month. There are some hon.<lb/>
members here, doubtless, of far greater political sagacity than I<lb/>
can pretend to, who will probably enlighten this House on the<lb/>
best course to pursue in the case. There may be facts connected<lb/>
with it submitted to our notice of which we are at present unin<lb break="no"/>formed ; so it is impossible to determine what steps it may be im<lb break="no"/>perative on us to take. If I mistake not His Excellency stated in his<lb/>
speech that the papers on the subject will be laid before the House.<lb/>
It will be time enough then to judge of the matter. As chair<lb break="no"/>man of the delegation I had my own share of the work to perform,<lb/>
and I do not desire to be called upon to enter into explanations<lb/>
until the question is brought up in proper shape. With<lb/>
reference to the appointment to which the hon leader of the<lb/>
Opposition objects, I will refrain from making any observations<lb/>
at present, for it would perhaps necessitate a reference to another<lb/>
gentleman to whom I do not now wish to allude. I dare say the<lb/>
Government were actuated by the best possible motives in making<lb/>
the selection which they did. It is no easy matter, as I can<lb/>
testify from my experience during the last two years, to procure<lb/>
able assistants. I suppose the Government would scarcely have<lb/>
ventured to offer the appointment to the hon member for East<lb/>
Point, with any hopes of receiving a favorable reply. (Laughter.)<lb/>
I regard the hon gentleman who has been appointed as every way<lb/>
well qualified for the situation he has been called upon to fill. I<lb/>
look upon him, Sir, as the father of this House—but in making<lb/>
this remark I am not certain that I am doing justice to the hon<lb/>
member for Cardigan.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon Mr COLES</persName>.—Nor to one or two others on this side of the <lb/>
House.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon Col GRAY</persName>.—Well, I am right in saying that he has been <lb/>
longer a member than any on the Governmentside of the House.<lb/>
We are all here, I believe comparatively young members<lb/>
(laughter.) I am safe in saying, however, that the gentleman<lb/>
appointed is one well entitled to the confidence of the country<lb/>
I am not aware, at least, that the Government could have done<lb/>
better in the selection.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon Mr COLES</persName>.—I did not censure the Government for ap<lb break="no"/>pointing delegates, but for saying that they are opposed to<lb/>
Confederation, and at the same time appointing a Unionist to a<lb/>
seat in the Executive.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI1">Hon Mr DAVIES</persName>.— It is difficult to tell who is, and who is <lb/>
not a Unionist in this House. The hon member who last spoke<lb/>
has, I understand, expressed himself in favor of a Union of the<lb/>
Colonies. At Ottawa he certainly made a speech approving of<lb/>
the terms of the Quebec Conference. As this is a question on<lb/>
which the people have not made up their minds I do not see how<lb/>
the Government could be expected to lay down any definite<lb/>
policy in the matter. The hon member for Belfast has set the<lb/>
case very fairly before the Committee, by stating that the time<lb/>
to discuss the question is when the Report of the delegates and<lb/>
the papers connected therewith have been presented to the<lb/>
House.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. MR COLES</persName>.—I cannot allow the statement of the hon<lb/>
member for Charlottetown to pass uncontradicted, I defy him<lb/>
or any other person to show that I, in the Conference or any<lb/>
where else, said that I was in favor of the terms contained in<lb/>
the Report of the delegates. All I said at Ottawa in favor of<lb/>
the Report was, that it was creditable to so many men that they<lb/>
had agreed so well in drawing it up. Hon members may say<lb/>
that this is not a Government question ; but I am determined to<lb/>
make it one, so that if it be taken the polls the people may have<lb/>
the matter fairly before them. Some may be disposed to say<lb/>
that the terms are not very favorable to this Colony ; but they<lb/>
have confidence that the gentlemen at Ottawa will do what is<lb/>
fair. Now, I am of opinion that the people of this Island would<lb/>
not be satisfied to leave the matter in this way. To have hon<lb/>
members acting like loose fish on such a question is dangerous.<lb/>
Had I been desirous to carry my resolution I would have put it<lb/>
in a different shape altogether. I do not wish them to vote<lb/>
against their declared principles. I believe the hon member on<lb/>
my right (hon Mr Whelan) and the late leader of the Govern<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

ment would vote to have the Report of the delegates confirmed <lb/>
by the Imperial Government. There are fewer old party ties<lb/>
to bind us now than formerly. The Land Question appears to<lb/>
be settled, as it is not referred to in His Excellency's speech<lb/>
this Session—the first time which it has been omitted for years.<lb/>
I would perhaps have assisted the Government had they de<lb break="no"/>clared their principles. As it is at present, I do not understand<lb/>
their policy.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr BRECKEN</persName>.—I had hoped, Mr Chairman, that this ques<lb break="no"/>tion would have been met in the spirit of the third of the motives<lb/>
of politicians mentioned by the hon member for Belfast—that of<lb/>
the general interests of the country—but, Sir, I now despair of<lb/>
that, seeing that the hon the leader of the Opposition has ex<lb break="no"/>pressed his determination to degrade this high theme to the<lb/>
level of a mere party question. Never since this Island had a<lb/>
Legislature, never since the sun of civilization shone upon it,<lb/>
has a matter of such momentous interest, wherein such great<lb/>
principles are involved, occupied the attention of its parliament.<lb/>
The hon leader of the Opposition has talked much about trim<lb break="no"/>ming sails to catch the varying breeze of popular favor, but I<lb/>
can tell him that the example is better than precept. No one should<lb/>
regard a question of such magnitude in the light of his own per<lb break="no"/>sonal interests or those of his party. Generations yet unborn<lb/>
are to be affected by the decision of this matter, and it is truly to<lb/>
be regretted that the hon member has not thought fit to follow<lb/>
the example adopted by the Legislatures of the other Colonies,<lb/>
where party spirit has been merged in the treatment of this sub<lb break="no"/>ject. In Canada we find gentlemen who had long been bitter<lb/>
opponents now agreeing as we are told the lion and the lamb<lb/>
shall do. In Nova Scotia, the leader of the Government and of<lb/>
the Opposition in the Legislative Council, and in the Assembly<lb/>
the ex-Attorney General, view this subject only as it regards the<lb/>
general interests of their country, Such example would not be<lb/>
without its effect on the hon member. My own opinion is op<lb break="no"/>posed to the contemplated Union, as I believe that we should<lb/>
not be as advantageously situated under it as we are at present.<lb/>
But, Sir, this is not the time to discuss the question, for how can<lb/>
hon members from opinions on the matter until the information<lb/>
embodied in the correspondence shall be placed before them ?<lb/>
I have not sought to know the course the Government may adopt<lb/>
on this question; but it is no imputation on their courage that<lb/>
they have not indicated their action in the address.—I think it<lb/>
would be more prudent to await the action of the other Colonies.<lb/>
I see by the debates in the Canadian Legislature that this Re<lb break="no"/>port of the Conference is regarded as a treaty. Perhaps that<lb/>
report may have been assented to by the hon member himself.<lb/>
There may be possible be another Conference ; if such should be the<lb/>
case and the hon member should assist at it, I hope he will oc<lb break="no"/>cupy a more comfortable position than I fear he does at present.<lb/>
As one of the seven representatives of this Island, he occupied<lb/>
at the Quebec Conference a high position, and he had a high and<lb/>
solemn duty to perform, and he should have discharged it<lb/>
untrammelled by considerations of mere party. If he was op<lb break="no"/>posed to the Scheme, then was the time for him to have mani<lb break="no"/>fested his independence, and if he considered that the project<lb/>
would operate prejudicially to the interests of his country, he<lb/>
should have stated so. Sir, he should have recollected that it<lb/>
devolved upon him as a prominent public man of the Island,<lb/>
delegated to the mission on which he went, on account of his<lb/>
position, to have asserted and illustrated the reputation of his<lb/>
country for straightforward honest conduct. If our Island home<lb/>
be limited in area, if its population be sparse and its people poor<lb/>
in comparison to our neighbors, these circumstances rendered<lb/>
more incumbent on those who represented us to show that we<lb/>
were disposed to act without deception, and not to subject the<lb/>
Colony of the imputation of a breach of faith with our neighbors.<lb/>
As to what has been said by the hon member with reference to<lb/>
the appointment of the Solicitor General it becomes not me,<lb/>
situated as I am, with reference to that gentleman, to discuss<lb/>
the subject as fully and freely as I might under other circum<lb break="no"/>stances ; but I do that the constituency of Georgetown which<lb/>
he has for years represented, and from whom he seeks a renewed<lb/>
expression of confidence, is, although comparatively small, as<lb/>
intelligent as any in the Island. They have had ample oppor<lb break="no"/>tunities of estimating his character for veracity, and when he<lb/>
openly avows his opinions in seeking their suffrages, they are<lb/>
best qualified to know what amount of credence is to be accord<lb break="no"/>ed to him. The hon leader of the Opposition finds that, the<lb/>
Land Question having been finally disposed of, no locus standi<lb/>
is left for him, and consequently he must lower the question of<lb/>

<pb n="8" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_008.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">8</fw>

the proposed Union to the lowest platform of party. There is<lb/>
no fear that the Imperial Government will constrain us to the<lb/>
positive adoption of the Union, and if I supposed that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the Island would force this measure without the<lb/>
opinion of the people having been taken upon it, I would vote<lb/>
for their impeachment. This question involves our political ex<lb break="no"/>istence, and the principles for which the oppressed nationalities<lb/>
of the world have been and are struggling. There is no neces<lb break="no"/>sity for haste, if the other Colonies, Nova Scotia and New<lb/>
Brunswick, decline to enter into the compact there is an end of<lb/>
it ; if they shall consent to it , and we be forced to cast in our lot<lb/>
with them, we shall at least have the satisfaction of knowing<lb/>
that we have done our duty to our country.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.—If we are to wait for the action of the<lb/>
other Colonies, and to follow in their footsteps, we may as tell<lb/>
them to send to the Island copies of their proceedings and that<lb/>
we will adopt them. I repeat that this is a question on which<lb/>
the Government should declare their policy. In Canada and<lb/>
the other Colonies it is true that parties formerly opposed to each<lb/>
other have united on this matter, but it should be remembered,<lb/>
on the other hand that there has been a combination of men<lb/>
who formerly took different sides in politics, in oppoisiton to the<lb/>
scheme. In Canada M. Dorion is not found lying down beside<lb/>
his former colleague, Mr. Brown. When I say that this is a po<lb break="no"/>litical question, I do not mean to assert that the same party ties<lb/>
which formerly existed must necessarily remain. I object to the<lb/>
Government expressing themselves as opposed to a question of<lb/>
such importance as this, and taking into their councils a gentle<lb break="no"/>man who has expressed himself most warmly in favor of it.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—I did not say that I would consent to any<lb/>
course which Nova Scotia or New Brunswick might adopt. I<lb/>
stated that it would be advisable to wait until we had ascertained<lb/>
their views ; and surely the hon. member must admit that if those<lb/>
Provinces decline to unite their destinies with those of Canada,<lb/>
there is not much probability that the latter will force Prince<lb/>
Edward Island into a union with her. I agree with the hon.<lb/>
member that new political associations have arisen in the other<lb/>
Colonies on this question. In Canada, Mr. Brown sits beside his<lb/>
old opponents, Messrs. Cartier and McGee, and a similar fusion of<lb/>
parties may take place here. Public men have and do change<lb/>
their views on particular questions, and it may be that the hon.<lb/>
member himself shall, at some future day, find himself the leader<lb/>
of a Union party ; and, Sir, such a position would imply no dis<lb break="no"/>credit to him, if additional information should dawn upon his mind.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.—With reference to the appointment of the<lb/>
Solicitor General, my objection is, that if that gentleman be re<lb break="no"/>turned to this House, and the question of Confederation be<lb/>
brought up during the present Session, he must either vote on it,<lb/>
against his own convictions, or against the Government of which<lb/>
he is a member and paid official.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—I repeat that if elected on his public<lb/>
assertion to his constituents that however strong may be the<lb/>
opinions he entertains on the subject of the contemplated Union,<lb/>
it is not the intention of the Government which he has joined to<lb/>
force it upon the people before they shall have had the opportu<lb break="no"/>nity of signifying their wishes on the subject, he can, without the<lb/>
slightest imputation of inconsistency, sit in the Executive<lb/>
Council and this House as Solicitor General of his party ; and it<lb/>
is somewhat inconsistent with the character of a great liberal that<lb/>
he should advocate the principle of a representative of the people<lb/>
forcing his opinions upon those who differed from them.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE3">Hon. Col. SECRETARY</persName>.—Mr. Chairman, in the absence of<lb/>
all official information, this discussion is premature and irrele<lb break="no"/>vant. When the proper time shall have arrived I will be pre<lb break="no"/>pared to discuss fully the appointment to which reference has<lb/>
been made, and the subject of the Conference at Quebec. The<lb/>
paragraph before us merely states that we will give due con<lb break="no"/>sideration to the correspondence when it shall have been submit<lb break="no"/>ted to us. When that shall have been done, we can, with<lb/>
propriety, discuss the matter, and not sooner.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Mr. SINCLAIR</persName>.—Mr. Chairman, I am of the opinion of those<lb/>
who believe that the interests of the people are not so safe in the<lb/>
keeping of a Government in favor of Union as of one opposed to it.<lb/>
When the hon. member for Charlottetown, Mr. Brecken, says that<lb/>
this question involves our very political existence, he necessarily<lb/>
implies that it is pre-eminently a question of a political nature—of<lb/>
such nature that the Government should express their opinion on<lb/>

<cb/>

it, and not adopt the hide-and-seek policy which they are<lb/>
pursuing. The people can form no estimate of the Government,<lb/>
the acts of which are in opposition to their expressed opinions.<lb/>
On a question of such mementous importance the people have<lb/>
the right to the fullest information ; and, Sir, we, the representa<lb break="no"/>tives of that people, find ourselves in a position very different<lb/>
from that which we occupied last Session when this question<lb/>
of Union was before us. We now find that instead of the cautious<lb/>
manner in which this matter was treated by the Government last<lb/>
year, that they consider themselves justified in acting without<lb/>
reference to the wishes or opinions of the House. The hon.<lb/>
leader of the Government ridicules the idea of consulting the<lb/>
popular branch of the legislature on the propriety or expediency<lb/>
of the second conference, while we all know that the opinion of<lb/>
the House last year was almost unanimous in opposition to the<lb/>
Union of even the Maritime Provinces. It is in the recollection<lb/>
of hon. members that the House dealt with the subject very<lb/>
cautiously ; they were particular in limiting the authority of the<lb/>
delegates who might be appointed by the Government to the<lb/>
mere preparation and report of the preliminary details of such<lb/>
scheme as might meet the approval of the assembled representa<lb break="no"/>tives of the Lower Provinces. The following is the resolution<lb/>
submitted last year by the then leader of the Government :—<lb/></p> 

<p>" <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That His Excellency the Lieutenant Governor<lb/>
be authorized to appoint Delegates (not to exceed five) to<lb/>
confer with Delegates who may be appointed by the govern<lb break="no"/>ments of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick for the purpose of<lb/>
discussing the expediency of a Union of the three provin<lb break="no"/>ces of Nova Scotia, New Brunswick and P. E. Island under<lb/>
one government and Legislature—the Report of said Dele<lb break="no"/>gates to be laid before the Legislature of this Colony, before<lb/>
any further action shall be taken in regard to the proposed<lb/>
question."<lb/></p> 

<p>And in the speech which that hon. member made on that<lb/>
occasion he said :—<lb/></p> 

<p>" Now, Sir, I cannot avoid expressing my opinion that our<lb/>
neighbors are proceeding too hastily in this matter. I think<lb/>
the first point to consider is, Shall there be " a prelimi<lb break="no"/>nary plan ?" Is it advisable to have a Union at all ? In the <lb/>
resolution which I have submitted it is proposed to appoint<lb/>
Delegates, simply for the purpose of discussing the expedi<lb break="no"/>ency of a union of the three Provinces of Nova Scotia, New<lb/>
Brunswick and P. E. Island, under one Government and<lb/>
Legislature. This is as far as I deem to be prudent for us<lb/>
to proceed at present."<lb/></p> 

<p>Now, Sir, I assert that in the action they have taken the<lb/>
Government have exceeded their authority. They ap<lb break="no"/>pointed another delegation having a very different object,<lb/>
and that delegation instead of merely agreeing to and re<lb break="no"/>porting upon a preliminary plan, have subscribed and<lb/>
adopted the details of a constitution so definite as to have<lb/>
been viewed in the light of a treaty entered into by parties<lb/>
invested with full powers to bind the countries they<lb/>
represented; and we may be sure that we shall be re<lb break="no"/>proached as having been guilty of a breach of faith, if we<lb/>
do not ratify their proceedings. Our legislative constitu<lb break="no"/>tion will be a mere farce if the Government are allowed<lb/>
to do as they please irrespectively of the formally expressed<lb/>
opinions of this House. If it is the privilege and the duty<lb/>
of this House to criticise and pass judgment upon the acts<lb/>
of the Government, what is the use of calling us together<lb/>
after our rights have been taken from us by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment ? The hon. member for Belfast (Hon. Col. Gray) took<lb/>
credit to himself for the composition of the Island delega<lb break="no"/>tion—that it embraced men of opposite opinions, gentlemen<lb/>
selected from each of the political parties in the leislature.<lb/>
That affords to my mind a very strong argument in favor<lb/>
of cautious deliberation, for there is always cause to fear<lb/>
that the prospect of honors and emoluments may be held<lb/>
out to induce unanimity of sentiment between parties who<lb/>
were previously opposed to each other.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LONG2">Hon. Mr. LONGWORTH</persName>.—Mr. Chairman, if the hon.<lb/>
member is of opinion that all the leading men of British<lb/>
North America have united to sell the rights of the<lb/>
people, he should shew that the arguments they have made<lb/>
use of are unsound.<lb/></p>

<pb n="9" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_009.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">9</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Mr. SINCLAIR</persName>.—I said that the people should view the<lb/>
proceedings with caution.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LONG2">Hon. Mr. LONGWORTH</persName>.—The inference to be drawn<lb/>
from the hon. member's remarks is as I have stated, and<lb/>
the very argument he uses shows the propriety of putting<lb/>
the question before the people. If it were introduced<lb/>
here as a Government measure, that very fact would have<lb/>
a tendency to influence the opinions of some on a matter<lb/>
which should be divested of all party views and spirit. I<lb/>
have heard no arguments to change my opinion that this<lb/>
should not be made a Government question. If, recognizing<lb/>
its importance, all approach it resolved to view it calmly<lb/>
in all its bearings, we shall be doing justice to ourselves<lb/>
and the people to whom it is due that it should not be<lb/>
made the subject of party discussion. Full opportunity<lb/>
will be afforded for discussion when the correspondence<lb/>
shall be submitted, and the interests of the people will be<lb/>
better conserved by treating the subject irrespectively of<lb/>
party.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. Mr. POPE</persName>.—As to the objection urged by the hon.<lb/>
member from Princetown that the Government were not<lb/>
justified in despatching delegates to Canada without the<lb/>
previous sanction of this House, I may inform him that<lb/>
His Excellency did so at the request of His Lordship the<lb/>
Governor General, who, as such, is Governor of this<lb/>
Island. With this request, of course, His Excellency the<lb/>
Lieut. Governor felt it to be his duty to comply. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, I consider, is the Executive Committee of this House<lb/>
when it is not in Session, and must carry on the public<lb/>
business of the country. The desire of the hon. leader of<lb/>
the Opposition to embarrass the Government by this<lb/>
irregular discussion is easily seen, and his motives are<lb/>
duly appreciated ; but he may as well wait till the papers<lb/>
are laid before us.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>. It is hard to say when the proper<lb/>
time will be to consider this question As it has now<lb/>
come up in the Address, though there are no other papers<lb/>
before the House on the subject, I hold that this is a<lb/>
proper time to give a right vote upon it. I believe the<lb/>
pretty general opinion throughout the country is, that the<lb/>
Government were a little rash in appointing one to a seat<lb/>
in the Executive who had expressed himself so strongly in<lb/>
favor of Union. The Government are bound to act ac<lb break="no"/>cording to the well understood wishes of the people, and<lb/>
in this case they have failed, consequently I cannot give<lb/>
them my support. Supposing the Government be called<lb/>
upon to send delegates to England to assist in preparing<lb/>
a measure relating to the question for the Imperial<lb/>
Parliament, if the Executive be composed of men in favor<lb/>
of Confederation, they will probably send Home " red<lb/>
hot Unionists. " The Government have not consulted<lb/>
their own friends in regard to the appointment in question,<lb/>
and they have acted contrary to the wishes of the people,<lb/>
therefore I will oppose them.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:KELL1">Hon. Mr. KELLY</persName>.—Mr. Chairman, in the Session of<lb/>
1863, when the subject of this contemplated Union was<lb/>
for the first time mooted here; and last year when the<lb/>
question of the appointment of delegates was before<lb/>
us, I expressed my decided opposition to the whole<lb/>
scheme, and I have seen nothing yet to induce a<lb/>
change of opinion. It may suit some gentlemen in the<lb/>
Island who can afford to remove to Canada to advocate<lb/>
the merging of our political institutions into those of<lb/>
that country. It has been said by some hon. members<lb/>
that the present is not the proper time to discuss the<lb/>
matter, as the paragraph in the address contains no<lb/>
expression of opinion upon it. Such may be the case,<lb/>
but I well recollect that when it was sought to effect the<lb/>
Union of my native country with Great Britain, the wily<lb/>
Lord Castlereagh used precisely the same arguments;<lb/> 

<cb/>

and although at that time he was defeated by an over<lb break="no"/>whelming majority, the next Session of the Irish<lb/>
House of Commons found him with his plans matured.<lb/>
Bribery and corruption had time to do their work, and<lb/>
did it but too effectually. I trust that hon. members of<lb/>
this House will not follow his example, or meet the fate<lb/>
which overtook the betrayer of the rights of his country.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWA1">Mr. HOWAT</persName>.—I suppose this discussion has been<lb/>
brought pretty near to a close, but I wish to offer a<lb/>
few remarks. I have opposed this Union of the Colonies<lb/>
from the first. When the question of Union with the<lb/>
other Maritime Provinces came up last Session, I ob<lb break="no"/>jected to the appointment of delegates, but was told<lb/>
that it was only a matter of courtesy, and that those<lb/>
appointed were not to agree to any scheme, but only to<lb/>
report. Now, however, the case has assumed a very<lb/>
different form. It has been said that this should be an<lb/>
open question ; if so, I suppose I may be allowed to<lb/>
differ with those whom I generally support. If Con<lb break="no"/>federation takes place it will effectually do away with<lb/>
parties, for our powers as a local Legislature will amount<lb/>
to little or nothing. I wish to oppose Union in every<lb/>
phase and shape in which it can present itself ; without<lb/>
considering the interests of my party, I must stand by<lb/>
the country. I believe the appointment which has<lb/>
been so often referred to was an injudicious one ;<lb/>
however much I may respect the gentleman in question,<lb/>
I think it was imprudent to appoint him, considering<lb/>
that he has declared himself decidedly in favor of Union.<lb/>
If, however, I can be assured that he will not hereafter<lb/>
advocate Union I shall be satisfied ; but not other<lb break="no"/>wise, for I wish the Government which I support to be<lb/>
entirely composed of anti-Union men. I am in favor<lb/>
of the amendment ; though I regret that a case has<lb/>
arisen in which I should oppose my party, yet I feel<lb/>
that this time I must do it.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Mr. DUNCAN</persName>.—I wonder where we are to go to find<lb/>
an anti-Union party ; it is not to the Opposition, for<lb/>
some on that side are strongly in favor of Union. I<lb/>
think it is quite out of place to discuss this question<lb/>
now, and for my part I will oppose the amendment. I<lb/>
shall not fail, however, at the proper time, to state my<lb/>
strong objections to the proposed scheme of Con<lb break="no"/>federation.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.—I did not expect that the hon.<lb/>
member for Murray Harbor would support my resolution<lb/>
—he could not be supposed to agree with any person<lb/>
of liberal principles. Perhaps we cannot get an Anti-<lb break="yes"/>Union party in this House ; but let us take the matter<lb/>
to the country, and probably then the hon. member for<lb/>
New Glasgow, or the hon. member for Tryon may be<lb/>
called upon to form a Government. I am sorry that I<lb/>
had to differ with the late leader of the Government,<lb/>
since he exerted himself to procure my appointment on<lb/>
the delegation.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. GRAY</persName>.—When did the hon. member differ<lb/>
with me, for I never heard him express any difference<lb/>
of opinion at the Conference ?<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.—I stated at the Conference when<lb/>
they refused my proposition with respect to the Land<lb/>
Question of this Colony, that they might as well strike<lb/>
Prince Edward Island out of the constitution altogether.<lb/></p>

<pb n="10" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_010.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">10</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. GRAY</persName>.—I never heard any such declara<lb break="no"/>tion from the hon. member in the Conference.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.—The hon. member, then might<lb/>
have heard it, for not being very well pleased, I made<lb/>
the statement loud enough. I can tell him, also, of<lb/>
another point on which we differed, namely the con<lb break="no"/>stitution of the Upper branch of the proposed Federal<lb/>
Legislature.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. GRAY</persName>.—I am unable to tell on what point<lb/>
we were not unanimous, for if there was one delegate<lb/>
at the Conference more ardently in favor of Union<lb/>
than myself, it was the hon. member. I was not aware<lb/>
that there was any difference of opinion which was not<lb/>
mutual to the Island delegates.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.—I can positively state that the hon.<lb/>
member said in the Conference that in Prince Edward<lb/>
Island they were opposed to the principle contained in<lb/>
the resolution which I moved, viz., that the members<lb/>
of the Legislative Council should be appointed by the<lb/>
Local Legislatures.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. GRAY</persName>.—But I positively state that this was<lb/>
not the case. How could I say that the people of<lb/>
Prince Edward Island were opposed to such a principle,<lb/>
when their opinion was not taken on the subject ?<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.—By the majority of their delegates<lb/>
who were present.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. GRAY</persName>.—The hon. member well knows that<lb/>
each Province had one vote at the Conference ; and as<lb/>
the leader of the Government, it was my duty to vote<lb/>
for this Colony. When four of our delegates were<lb/>
opposed to any resolution, I was required to say that<lb/>
Prince Edward Island was against it, and the contrary,<lb/>
if the majority were in favor of the proposition. This<lb/>
was the way in which the question was put ; and a<lb/>
majority being opposed to the hon. member's resolution,<lb/>
I had to say Prince Edward Island was against it.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.—It is admitted then that there was<lb/>
a difference of opinion on this point. On the financial<lb/>
vote Prince Edward Island was unanimous ; but this<lb/>
is not the question now before the Committee. With<lb/>
reference to the remark of the hon. member for Murray<lb/>
Harbor that no Government could be formed on anti-<lb break="yes"/>Union principles.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Mr. DUNCAN</persName>.—What I stated was to the effect<lb/>
that no Government could be formed on that principle<lb/>
from the present parties, without dismissing some of<lb/>
their supporters. The Government is not a Union<lb/>
Government ; if it were I would not support it.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>.—The hon. member apparently does<lb/>
not wish to censure the Government for what is has<lb/>
done in appointing a Unionist ; but I think the case<lb/>
has been very well stated by the hon. member from New<lb/>
Glasgow, that it is dangerous to have so many Unionists<lb/>
in the Executive, for if delegates have to be sent<lb/>
Home, they may appoint those who are strongly dis<lb break="no"/>posed to favor the proposed Confederation, and therefore<lb/>
commit the country to the scheme. There are several<lb/>
acts of the Government during the past year to which<lb/>
I object ; but the appointment under consideration is<lb/>
one of which I entirely disapprove. When the question<lb/>
of Union comes up again perhaps my hon. friend on the<lb/>
right, (Mr. Whelan) will place the Government in an<lb/>

<cb/>

awkward position by moving a resolution in favor of<lb/>
the scheme.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WHEL1">Hon. Mr. WHELAN</persName>.—My hon. friend on the left (Hon.<lb/>
Mr. Coles) seems very anxious to draw me out on the pres<lb break="no"/>ent occasion. I, however, shall say only a very few words.<lb/>
This discussion I consider as altogether irrelevant, be<lb break="no"/>cause the question of Confederation must come up again<lb/>
when the papers on the subject are laid before the House.<lb/>
I will not, therefore, enter into the merits of the scheme<lb/>
at present, though I am not at all disposed to evade any<lb/>
responsibility which attaches to me in the matter. I have<lb/>
no desire to act one part in Canada and another in Prince<lb/>
Edward Island. (Hear, from Hon. Col. Gray.) Though <lb/>
the delegates from this Colony did not gain all they could<lb/>
wish, yet I was not disposed to throw aside a great ques<lb break="no"/>tion, and one which I shall be prepared by and by to<lb/>
show will be for the advantage of this Island. The<lb/>
amendment of my hon. friend on the left, was brought<lb/>
forward, I imagine, to show his opposition to the Union<lb/>
scheme at the earliest possible period ; and perhaps to<lb/>
show that he is still in opposition to the Government.<lb/>
With respect to the latter, I will ever stand true to my<lb/>
party, when the local policy of the Government is opposed<lb/>
to my well-understood principles ; but on the question of<lb/>
Confederation I cannot shut my eyes to the fact, which<lb/>
has presented itself to some of the greatest minds on the<lb/>
continent, that it is one of such momentous importance<lb/>
as to call upon us to act upon it without reference to old<lb/>
party predilections. Should the Government, then, be<lb/>
prepared to introduce a measure to give effect to the Re<lb break="no"/>port of the Quebec Conference, they shall have my hearty<lb/>
support. One of the reasons assigned by my hon. friend<lb/>
for submitting the amendment before the Committee, was<lb/>
that he wished to show the people of the other Provinces<lb/>
that this House was not in favor of a Union of the Colo<lb break="no"/>nies. But I believe the course which he has taken will<lb/>
have the contrary effect to what he intended. He ought<lb/>
to have chosen another time to show his opposition to<lb/>
Union, for hon. members on the other side of the House<lb/>
cannot be expected to support his motion, although they<lb/>
may agree with him in his opposition to Confederation,<lb/>
consequently the division on his resolution will be such as<lb/>
to lead the people of the other Provinces to suppose that<lb/>
the Confederation scheme is not very unfavorably received<lb/>
by this House. It is not my place or my intention to de<lb break="no"/>fend the Government, but it appears to me to be a most<lb/>
injudicious proceeding on the part of my hon. friend to<lb/>
single out a particular appointment on which to censure<lb/>
the Administration. If we are to object to the policy of<lb/>
the Government, let us do it on general grounds. For my <lb/>
part, I may state that I approve of the appointment of the<lb/>
Solicitor General—not that I say it ought to have been<lb/>
made at this particular time, for I hold that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should have had firmness enough to tell their princi<lb break="no"/>pal Crown Officer to resign, and thus save them the<lb/>
necessity of resuscitating an office which has become obso<lb break="no"/>lete and unnecessary. This is the course which I think<lb/>
they ought to have pursued. But to object to the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of the Hon. Solicitor General, because he has ex<lb break="no"/>pressed himself in favor of Confederation, is a proceeding<lb/>
of which I cannot approve. I rather hold it as one<lb/>
reason why he should be appointed. This view is strengthened<lb/>
by the fact that the other gentleman appointed at the<lb/>
same time as the Solicitor General, is opposed to Union.<lb/>
With regard to the second appointment, I think the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment might have selected a person having stronger<lb/>
political claims on their party ; but I will not censure<lb/>
them for the appointment on the ground of his opposition<lb/>
to Union. This question of Confederation is one which<lb/>
should be viewed in all its future bearings ; and the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment will doubtless make known their policy respecting<lb/>
it, when the papers on the subject come up for considera<lb break="no"/>tion. Since Her Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colo<lb break="no"/>nies has recommended them to give the scheme effect, they<lb/>

<pb n="11" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-02_Page_011.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">11</fw>

cannot well treat it with indifference, much less opposition. <lb/>
When the proper time arrives I will be prepared to enter <lb/>
into the merits of the whole question. I have had no <lb/>
opportunity, through indisposition, to express my opinions <lb/>
on the subject at any public meetings, except some held <lb/>
in my own district; and when it comes up here I shall <lb/>
regard it as my duty to assume all the responsibility <lb/>
which attaches to my conduct in the matter, as well as to <lb/>
deal with every feature of the question. I would be glad <lb/>
were my hon friend to withdraw his amendment, as I <lb/>
consider it to be too trifling a matter on which to divide <lb/>
this hon Committee. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CONR1">Mr CONROY</persName>.—Mr Chairman, if party feeling has not been <lb/>
sunk on this question in this House, it has been pretty well laid <lb/>
aside in the country. At Tignish, a part of the district which <lb/>
I have the honor to represent, where the people are very much <lb/>
divided in their political opinions, my colleague and I lately at<lb break="no"/>tended a meeting, at which every one appeared to be opposed to <lb/>
the proposed Union. I never saw a time when newspapers <lb/>
were so much sought after, and the speeches delivered at public <lb/>
meetings so generally read. The speech of the hon Solicitor <lb/>
General was read in our part of the Island with great dis<lb break="no"/>satisfaction; and his appointment to a seat in the Executive <lb/>
is considered, in consequence of his decided Union sentiments, <lb/>
to have been very injudicious on the part of the Government. <lb/>
I know that the country is dissatisfied with the appointment, <lb/>
therefore I have no hesitation in supporting the amendment <lb/>
proposed by the hon leader of the Opposition. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HENS1">Hon Mr HENSLEY</persName>.—When I came into the house this <lb/>
afternoon, Mr Chairman, the resolution proposed by the hon <lb/>
leader of the Opposition was on the table. I would rather it <lb/>
had not been brought forward, or at least, that it had been <lb/>
put in another form; but as he appears desirous to press it, <lb/>
every member must say yea or nay. The question on which <lb/>
we are required to vote, is, Should the hon Solicitor General <lb/>
have been appointed to a seat in the Executive? Notwith<lb break="no"/>standing all the respect which I entertain for the hon gentle<lb break="no"/>man alluded to, yet considering his extreme views in favor <lb/>
of Union, and the excited state of the country on the question, <lb/>
I consider the Government would have stood better with the <lb/>
people had his appointment not been made. When I <lb/>
previously addressed you, Mr Chairman, I stated my intention <lb/>
to submit a resolution expressing regret that the Government <lb/>
had not declared its policy on the question of Confederation. <lb/>
Though I have abandoned the idea of proposing a motion to <lb/>
that effect, yet I must state, that as this subject is one of the <lb/>
most momentous which has ever come before the consideration <lb/>
of the Legislature, I think the Government ought, to have <lb/>
given some decided expression of opinion upon it. I believe <lb/>
there is sufficient information before the public to have <lb/>
warranted such an expression of opinion. It is all very well <lb/>
to say that a majority of the members of the Government <lb/>
have made speeches against Union ; but they ought to have <lb/>
come out as a Government with some decided declaration <lb/>
in regard to the question. What information can be gathered <lb/>
from such speeches when we find them here contradicting <lb/>
each other as to the tendency of their remarks. Even some <lb/>
of the speeches given in Canada, we are told, are not to be <lb/>
understood in that sense which we would take to be their <lb/>
natural meaning. I will vote for the amendment ; but in so <lb/>
doing I disclaim any personal objections to the hon gentleman <lb/>
to whom it refers. I have, on the contrary, a very high <lb/>
respect for him. The hon member for Murray Harbor has <lb/>
stated that he will support the paragraph, and not the <lb/>
amendment. I have heard him express strong sentiments on <lb/>
the question of Union—stating that the man who supported <lb/>
the scheme must be almost a lunatic. If he is not sorry that<lb/>
a person of this description should be appointed to a seat in<lb/>
the Government, then I have nothing more to say. (Laughter.)<lb/></p> 

<p>The question was then put to the Committee by the<lb/>
chairman:<lb/></p> 

<p>For Mr Coles' amendment—Honorables Coles, Kelly, <lb/>
Thornton, Warburton, Hensley, Laird; Messrs Sinclair,<lb/>
Conroy, Walker—9.<lb/></p> 

<p>Against it— Hons J. C. Pope, Longworth, Col. Gray, Col. <lb/>
Secretary, Davies, Kay, Speaker, Whelan ; Messrs Ramsay,<lb/>

<cb/>

Brecken, Montgomery, Haslam, Green, McLennan, Duncan <lb/>
—15. <lb/></p> 

<p>Progress was then reported, and the House adjourned till <lb/>
10 o'clock to-morrow. <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>