<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1873-05-30"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1873-05-30">30 May 1873</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1873">
               <title>The Parliamentary Reporter of Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly</title>.
          <date when="1873"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Examiner</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="238"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_234.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_236.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_238.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-08-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-08-17">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_234">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_234.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_236">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_236.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_238">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_238.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1873-05-30_Page_234"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_234.jpg"/>
            
           
            <fw type="num">232</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            
            <head rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, May 30th.<lb/>
            </head>
         
            <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">235</fw>
            
            
           <head rendition="simple:centre">AFTERNOON SESSION</head>
            
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERN<lb break="no"/>MENT</persName> moved that the House do now 
     <lb/>
     resolve itself into a Committee of the 
     <lb/>
     Whole on Ways and Means, and said 
     <lb/>
     that it was the intention of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to submit a measure to in<lb break="no"/>crease the duty on several articles im<lb break="no"/>ported into the Island, for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     assimilating our tariff to that of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion. An undue advantage had been 
     <lb/>
     taken of our low tariff by certain parties 
     <lb/>
     in shipping large quantities of liquors to 
     <lb/>
     this Island for the purpose of re-ship<lb break="no"/>ping them to the Dominion, duty free, 
     <lb/>
     after the first of July next. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">MR. LAIRD</persName> said that the proposed 
     <lb/>
     increase would not be very burden<lb break="no"/>some upon this Colony, and the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government had a right to 
     <lb/>
     expect us to deal justly and fairly with 
     <lb/>
     them in reference to this matter. As 
     <lb/>
     Canada has dealt very liberally with 
     <lb/>
     us, it was only fair that Rum, &amp;c., 
     <lb/>
     should pay as heavy duty here as 
     <lb/>
     there, during the month we remain out 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="1873-05-30_Page_236"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_236.jpg"/>
               
            <fw type="num">236</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            
           of the Dominion. It had been stated<lb/>in some of the Halifax newspapers,<lb/>that if any Rum were re-shipped to<lb/>the other Provinces, from this Island,<lb/>after the union, it would have to pay<lb/>the difference between their duty and<lb/>ours. But the proposed arrangement<lb/>would, in his opinion, be more satis<lb break="no"/>factory to both parties.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERN<lb break="no"/>MENT</persName> said that if, in addition to the<lb/>$25,000, we received the difference or<lb/>increase of duty, the whole would<lb/>amount to over $100,000, which would<lb/>make a vast difference for all time to<lb/>come, as the amount is a large one.<lb/>All this had been gained by not adopt<lb break="no"/>ing the course recommended by the<lb/>Opposition while passing the Revenue<lb/>Bill, &amp;c. The Government had not<lb/>made up their minds to go into Con<lb break="no"/>federation, if better Terms had not<lb/>been secured. After passing the Ad<lb break="no"/>dress to Her Majesty to unite this<lb/>Colony to the Dominion, the tariff of<lb/>this Island should not be allowed to<lb/>remain in such a way as to lessen the<lb/>revenue of Canada for the remaining<lb/>month. It was, he believed, the in<lb break="no"/>tention of the Dominion Government<lb/>to protect themselves by compelling all<lb/>who re-shipped liquors from this Island<lb/>after the union, to pay the difference<lb/>between our present duty and theirs.<lb/>It was a rather difficult matter to make<lb/>an arrangement that would not injure<lb/>some individuals, but the equalizing of<lb/>the duty on certain articles to that of<lb/>the Dominion, would prevent loss to<lb/>the Dominion Revenue.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SINC6">MR. SINCLAIR</persName> thought the hon.<lb/>Leader of the Government had shown<lb/>good reason why this change in the<lb/>duties upon certain articles should be<lb/>made. Merchants were re-shipping<lb/>boots and shoes to the Dominion, and<lb/>intended, after the union, to bring them<lb/>back here duty free. We should,<lb/>therefore, look after our own interests,<lb/>while the Dominion looked after its<lb/>
           
            <cb/>
            
            own. In order to do this, it would be<lb/>necessary to pass a resolution to pro<lb break="no"/>tect our interests, as they had done in<lb/>reference to theirs. The Dominion<lb/>Government was losing its Revenue<lb/>by the way in which ours at present<lb/>stood, and it was only fair and just<lb/>that matters should be put right in<lb/>order that both parties should be pro<lb break="no"/>tected. He saw that about forty<lb/>mowing machines had been re-shipped<lb/>to the Dominion in order that they<lb/>might be brought back, after the union,<lb/>duty free. This should be prevented<lb/>by some means or other. If the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Parliament were so sensitive<lb/>to their interests, we should act in a<lb/>similar manner, and prevent the re<lb break="no"/>shipment of goods, upon which no duty<lb/>had been paid.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI3">MR. L. H. DAVIES</persName> said that when<lb/>the Revenue Bill was submitted, the<lb/>same amendment as that now proposed<lb/>by the hon. Leader of the Government<lb/>was submitted by the Opposition, but<lb/>it was voted down by the Government,<lb/>who informed the House that the Bill<lb/>would remain as then passed, till the<lb/>Island entered the Dominion. Mer<lb break="no"/>chants, generally, had acted under that<lb/>impression, and were now importing a<lb/>large quantity of goods, on the under<lb break="no"/>standing that no amendment would be<lb/>made in the Revenue Bill till the<lb/>first of July next. The amendment<lb/>would have been perfectly fair if made<lb/>when the Bill was passed ; but under<lb/>present circumstances, it was unfair to<lb/>those now importing goods. The gain<lb/>to the Revenue of this Island, by our<lb/>not raising the duties equal to those of<lb/>the Dominion till now, cannot be re<lb break="no"/>cognized as a legitimate one.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion, the House resolved itself<lb/>into a Committee of Ways and Means.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD10">MR. A. C. McDONALD</persName> in the chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERN<lb break="no"/>MENT</persName> said that the remaks made by<lb/>the hon. member for New London in<lb/>
            
            
            <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">237</fw>
            
           
     reference to the necessity of protecting 
     <lb/>our own interests, were correct, and to<lb/>the point. The matter was well<lb/>worthy of the consideration of the<lb/>House, but it was not easy to provide<lb/>the necessary remedy, without injuring<lb/>somebody's interests. It was to the<lb/>interests of the Dominion to protect<lb/>her own manufactures, and she had<lb/>done so. The article of Sugar, for<lb/>instance, was one of them. He be<lb break="no"/>lieved that large quantities of goods<lb/>had been imported into this Island by<lb/>speculators, who did not belong to this<lb/>Island, and if they had to pay the dif<lb break="no"/>ference of duty when they re-ship to<lb/>the other Provinces, there will be no<lb/>money lost by our people. Our Trea<lb break="no"/>sury would receive forty cents per<lb/>gallon of the duties on liquors, and the<lb/>Dominion would receive the other<lb/>forty. He would move the following<lb/>resolution :—<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, that the Act 36th, Vic.<lb/>Cap. I. entitled " An Act for rais<lb break="no"/>ing a Revenue, " be amended by in<lb break="no"/>creasing the duties impost on Rum,<lb/>Spirits, Sugar, brown and muscovado,<lb/>Tobacco, manufactured, and Cigars,<lb/>as follows :—<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The duty on Rum to be 80 cents<lb/>per gallon. Spirits and strong waters<lb/>imported into this Island, mixed with<lb/>any ingredient or ingredients, are, al<lb break="no"/>though thereby coming under the deno<lb break="no"/>mination of Proprietory Medicines,<lb/>Tinctures, Essences, Extracts, or any<lb/>other denominations, shall be neverthe<lb break="no"/>less deemed Spirits, or strong waters,<lb/>and are subject to duty as such, $1.20<lb/>per gallon. Spirits and strong waters,<lb/>imported into this Island, $1.20 per<lb/>gallon. Sugar equal to or about No. 9<lb/>Dutch, 1 cent per lb., and 25 per cent<lb/>ad valorem. Sugar below No. 9 Dutch<lb/>standard 3/4 of a cent per lb., and 25<lb/>per cent ad valorem. Tobacco manu<lb break="no"/>factured, 20 cents per lb., and 12 1/2 per<lb/>cent. ad valorem. Cigars 45 cents per<lb/>lb.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAIR2">MR. LAIRD</persName> said that the more he<lb/>considered the course followed by the<lb/>
            
   
       
            <cb/>
               
           Opposition when the Revenue Bill<lb/>was passed, the clearer he saw it to be<lb/>the correct one. They understood<lb/>that if we entered Confederation the<lb/>course they proposed would be fair<lb/>to the Dominion, and would prevent<lb/>jobbery in reference to the duties, and<lb/>at the same time, would be just and<lb/>fair to our own merchants. If we had<lb/>remained out of Confederation, we<lb/>should have required the extra duties<lb/>for our own purposes. If the last dele<lb break="no"/>gation had failed, and Confederation,<lb/>had not been accepted, the amendment<lb/>proposed by the Opposition would<lb/>have been the means of increasing our<lb/>Revenue during the interval. The<lb/>Opposition were on the right track,<lb/>and in the end it would prove to be so.<lb/>It was now proposed to increase the<lb/>duties on a few of the principal articles<lb/>imported. The chief difference in the<lb/>duty would be on Rum. It seemed<lb/>that the politicians of Canada were too<lb/>shrewd to allow their own interests to<lb/>be endangered by the loss of a portion<lb/>of their Revenue, and had arranged to<lb/>demand the extra duty on goods re<lb break="no"/>shipped to the other Provinces after<lb/>the first of July. He understood there<lb/>was sufficient liquor in store on this<lb/>Island for three years' consumption !<lb/>Every puncheon not required for<lb/>present use, would be re-shipped, and<lb/>drawbacks would be taken out by<lb/>those speculators in rum. All the<lb/>duties they would have to pay would<lb/>be the difference between our present<lb/>tariff and that of the Dominion. The<lb/>hon. Leader of the Government had<lb/>referred to the difficulty of preventing<lb/>the re-shipment of goods to the Do<lb break="no"/>minion, and the evasion of the pay<lb break="no"/>ment of the duties upon them. There<lb/>was but one course to be taken, and<lb/>that was to repeal the clause in the<lb/>Revenue Bill permitting drawbacks<lb/>upon goods. If no drawbacks were<lb/>allowed till after the union, we should<lb/>be able to have our Revenue ; but un<lb break="no"/>less this were done, everything im<lb break="no"/>
           
            <pb n="1873-05-30_Page_238"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-30_Page_238.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">238</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
          
     ported from the Dominion would dis<lb break="no"/>appear before the first of July.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>