<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1867-04-23"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1867-04-23">23 April 1867</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1867">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1867, Being the First Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1867"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Patriot" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="28"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-04-23_Page_027.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-04-23_Page_028.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-11">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-04-23_Page_027">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-23_Page_027.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-04-23_Page_028">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-23_Page_028.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>
<div type="debate">

<pb n="27" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-23_Page_027.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">27</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI1">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>.—I did not say that the Judges <lb/>
had done wrong ; I merely repeated what I had heard<lb/>
and read in the public newspapers ; and will, Mr.<lb/>
Chairman, hon. members on the other side of this<lb/>
undertook to purchase the Cunard estate, it was their<lb/>
duty to have made some provision for the payment.<lb/>
I think I saw in some paper a statement to the effect<lb/>
that the Banks represented that they could meet all these<lb/>
payments as they became due, without inconvenience.<lb/>
I believe such a statement was made, and that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment would not have effected the purchase unless<lb/>
they had such expectations. But we know the situa<lb break="no"/>

<cb/> 

ation of the Banks, that, under their constitution, they <lb/>
can not afford the accommodation required, because<lb/>
it has been and is as much as the Banks can do to<lb/>
afford merchants the ordinary requirements for remit<lb break="no"/>tances to Britain ; and it is evident to every man<lb/>
acquainted with the trade of the Colony, that the Banks<lb/>
cannot now meet the payment on exchange in Eng<lb break="no"/>land without draining the specie from their vaults. In<lb/>
doing so, the community would suffer, because the<lb/>
exchange they require will be absorbed by Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and the distress which we already feel will be<lb/>
fearfully augmented when the second and third pay<lb break="no"/>ments are made. I therefore blame the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment for entering into a purchase before providing<lb/>
means to pay it—without distracting the trade of<lb/>
the Colony. Sir, they have left us this difficulty to<lb/>
contend with, without allowing time to make the<lb/>
neccessary arrangement for overcoming this want of<lb/>
statesmanship, by obtaining money in the British<lb/>
market to meet it. While trade is flourishing, it is all<lb/>
very well, but when a reverse comes around, and the<lb/>
Banks cannot give the facilities required, it is different ;<lb/>
and where is the gentleman in business, who is not<lb/>
aware of this? I am apprehensive that, when the time<lb/>
for the next payment to be made on the estate comes<lb/>
on, a great difficulty will be experienced, unless some<lb/>
remedy is the provided. When the late Government<lb/>
made the first payment, where did they go for money?<lb/>
They went to the Banks. The Banks do not create<lb/>
exchange or bring gold into the market ; that is the<lb/>
merchants' avocation, who employ our labor in various<lb/>
ways, in constructing ships, in fishing, &amp;c., &amp;c.; and<lb/>
by exporting these effects abroad, they (the merchants)<lb/>
then give the Banks exchange on their brokers for the<lb/>
proceeds of their shipments. It is true the merchant<lb/>
cannot go on without aid from the Banks,—one assists<lb/>
the other; it therefore follows if the Government<lb/>
drain the Banks of gold, that they cannot afford the<lb/>
accommodation trade requires, then it becomes<lb/>
paralyzed. This is what we are rapidly approaching<lb/>
tom and if the Government cannot effect credit in Lon<lb break="no"/>don, to draw on in payment for the sums falling due<lb/>
on the Cunard estate, I think the Banks will either<lb/>
have to stop specie payment or shut up for a time,<lb/>
which will not only entail ruin on the trader,<lb/>
but eventually fall as heavily on the agricultural<lb/>
classes I cannot account for gentlemen, possessing<lb/>
the ability the late Government were acknowledged to<lb/>
possess, entering at all into this arrangement,<lb/>
unless it was that they expected the payment of this<lb/>
debt would be an inducement for us to go into Confed<lb break="no"/>eration, as we might be enabled to meet this<lb/>
difficulty out of the sum they expected the Canadians<lb/>
would give us for yielding up our liberty. A deeper<lb/>
laid scheme could not have been devised. (Hear,<lb/>
hear.) You may say hear, hear ; but many who hear<lb/>
me know it was so. My hon. colleague has said that<lb/>
this state of affairs has been brought on by overtrading.<lb/>
I cannot agree with him The stock now in this Island<lb/>
is not one-sixth more than it was last year; nor does<lb/>
the fall in the price of shipping apply to this Island<lb/>
with any force. It applies with more force to those<lb/>
ships sent from St. Jogn and Quebec. The people of<lb/>
England ought to-be proud of these Colonies, when<lb/>
they look at such splendid ships as are sent from New<lb/>
Brunswick and Quebec. They are classed for seven<lb/>
years, when they should be classed for twelve. They<lb/>
are equal to ships built of English oak, being built of<lb/>
material that will not take the dry rot. Now, I wish<lb/>
to show that the cause of the low price of these splen<lb break="no"/>did ships sent home from the sister Provinces, is<lb/>
that there are more of them in the market than are<lb/>
required ; this is the reason why their price is so<lb/>
much depressed. The ships we build range from 100<lb/>
to 300 tons, and was but few so small are sent to market<lb/>
from other parts.—the requirements being greater, our<lb/>
vessels have not fallen equally low in price with those<lb/>

<pb n="28" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-23_Page_028.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">28</fw> 

of St. John and Quebec. These vessels range from 300 <lb/>
to 2,000 tons register. There are but thirty or forty<lb/>
Island vessels unsold in the English market. It is the<lb/>
withdrawal of the money from this Colony that makes<lb/>
the pressure. I do not mean to throw any blame on<lb/>
the Banks ; I know better. They must respect the<lb/>
rights of their shareholders. If the Banks have not got<lb/>
bills of exchange, they must pay ont the gold ; and, if<lb/>
means are not obtained before the first of July, the<lb/>
Banks will have to close. Their object was to drive us<lb/>
into Confederation. They thought it would release us<lb/>
from these difficulties, and that they money we would<lb/>
get out of Confederation would pay for the Cunard<lb/>
estate. They were willing to sell our rights for the<lb/>
self-interests of a few. But before closing, Mr. Chair<lb break="no"/>man, I would observe there is a very interesting tale<lb/>
being published at London. It comes out in the peri<lb break="no"/>odicals, and is called "Birds of Prey." If the author<lb/>
were as well acquainted with the transactions of some<lb/>
of the proprietary party as I am, and would introduce<lb/>
one of them into his work, it would render his name<lb/>
immortal.<lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>