<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1867-04-22"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1867-04-22">22 April 1867</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1867">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1867, Being the First Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1867"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Patriot" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="005" to="013"/>
</bibl>

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_005.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_006.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_007.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_008.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_009.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_010.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_011.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_012.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_013.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-10">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-10">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_005">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_005.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_006">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_006.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_007">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_007.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_008">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_008.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_009">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_009.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_010">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_010.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_011">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_011.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_012">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_012.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_013">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_013.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="5" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_005.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">5</fw>

<head rendition="simple:right">MONDAY, April 22.</head><lb/>

<p>Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL moved that the <lb/>
House do adopt the usual Resolution touching the <lb/>
distribution of a certain number of copies of the <lb/>
Journals. In submitting which, he observed that it <lb/>
would be necessary to forward copies to the Govern<lb break="no"/>mental departments of the Provinces recently Confed<lb break="no"/>erated. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. HAVILAND asked the Hon. Attorney <lb/>
General if he admitted that Confederation was a fixed <lb/>
fact. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. DUNCAN remarked that the people of <lb/>
Nova Scotia were driven into Confederation without <lb/>
their consent—they were denied the privilege of an <lb/>
appeal to the Polls. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. HOWAT did not see the necessity of recognizing <lb/>
the Confederated Government, as it was termed, for it <lb/>
could scarcely be said that it had, as yet, an existence <lb/>
—certainly it was not yet in working order, and, <lb/>
therefore, it was unnecessary on the part of that House <lb/>
to give it any hasty recognition. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. DAVIES said the fact that the Bill for <lb/>
Confederating Canada and the two Maritime Provinces <lb/>
had passed the Imperial Parliament, and received Her <lb/>
Majesty's Roya1 assent, rendering it necessary that the <lb/>
House should recognize it. He thought the views of <lb/>
some hon. members of the Opposition must have been <lb/>
considerably modified on the question of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, for it appeared that they had nominated the Hon. <lb/>
Mr. Haviland, who was a strong Confederate, as their <lb/>
Leader. <lb/></p> 

<p>After some further remarks from hon. members, the <lb/>
resolution was put and agreed to. <lb/></p>

<pb n="6" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_006.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">6</fw>

<p rendition="simple:centre">AFTERNOON SESSION.<lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><hi rendition="simple:bold">Debate on the Draft Address in Answer to <lb/>
His Excellency's Speech.</hi><lb/></p> 

<p>On motion of Hon. Mr. KELLY, the House resolved <lb/>
itself into a Committee of the whole to take into consid<lb break="no"/>eration the Draft Address in answer to His Excellency's <lb/>
Speech at the opening of the Session,—Mr. BELL in <lb/>
the Chair. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">The 1st paragraph was agreed to without remark.<lb/></p> 

<p>On the 2d paragraph being read— <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HENS1">Hon. Mr. HENSLEY</persName> rose to move its adoption, and <lb/>
said:—Mr Chairman: This clause may not meet with <lb/>
the approval of all lion. members, though I am unable <lb/>
to see that any one can raise against it a valid objection. <lb/>
It does not censure any party; it simply states a fact. <lb/> 
While it says that "the late time at which it was deemed <lb/>
advisable to dissolve the last Assembly, and the Minis<lb break="no"/>terial arrangements resulting from the General Elec<lb break="no"/>tion," prevented His Excellency from summoning the <lb/>
House at an earlier period, it does not cast the least <lb/>
reflection upon the late Government. We charitably <lb/>
suppose that they had good reason for delaying the <lb/>
Election. But, as some eight or ten months of the <lb/>
most suitable season of the year for holding it, elapsed <lb/>
before the House was dissolved, a satisfactory explan<lb break="no"/>ation of the matter, from some of His Excellency's <lb/>
late advisers, would, no doubt, be gratifying to hon. <lb/>
members, as well as to the people generally. As you <lb/>
are aware, Sir, the "ministerial arrangements" <lb/>
referred to in the clause, are those rendered necessary <lb/>
by the resignation of the late Government and its <lb/>
principal officers, whose places had to be filled up to <lb/>
carry on the public business of the Colony. Those <lb/>
hon. members who accepted offices of emolument, of <lb/>
course, had to vacate their seats; and, though the <lb/>
writs for the Elections, in such cases, were made <lb/>
returnable as soon as possible, delay in calling the <lb/>
Legislature together was impossible. We do not wish <lb/>
to attach blame ot the late party in power; we <lb/>
merely express our willingness, notwithstanding the <lb/>
lateness of the Session, to devote a sufficient time to <lb/>
mature such measures as the exigencies of the Colony <lb/>
and the public service may require. It, however, <lb/>
would afford me pleasure to hear from two hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers present (Messrs. Duncan and Henderson), who <lb/>
held seats at the late Executive Board, an explanation <lb/>
of the reason why the General Election was so long <lb/>
delayed. It is surmised that the late Government <lb/>
deferred the dissolution of the Assembly until Con<lb break="no"/>federation might be matured; but as those two hon <lb/>
members are understood to be decidedly opposed to <lb/>
that measure, they could not have consented to the <lb/>
delay on any such ground. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCAU1">Hon. Mr McAULAY</persName>.—Mr. Chairman, 1 cannot <lb/>
but admire the moderation of the hon. gentleman <lb/>
who has just resumed his seat! At first he was not <lb/>
going to cast any reflection upon the late Government, <lb/>
but he concluded his speech by calling upon them to <lb/>
give an account of their actions. Conduct like <lb/>
this is unparliamentary. Never before, I believe, has <lb/>
such a thing occurred in any country, as an incoming <lb/>
Government attempting to call their predecessors to <lb/>
account on the floors of the Legislature. A new light <lb/>
has dawned upon the world since the advent of the <lb/>
present Government party to power, and I hope it <lb/>
will benefit from the.faint illumination which that <lb/>
light affords. It is contrary to parliamentary rule for <lb/>
one House to refer to the proceedings of another. <lb/>
But the hon. member's allusion to the acts of the late <lb/>
Government seems merely intended to cover tho mis<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

deeds of his own party. He complains of the lateness <lb/>
of the Session, and throws all the blame upon His <lb/>
Excellency's former advisers. His excuse will not <lb/>
stand the test of investigation. The General Election <lb/>
was held on the 26th of February, and the House was <lb/>
not summoned to meet until the 18th of April. Why <lb/>
the delay? The pleading about ministerial arrange<lb break="no"/>ments will not satisfy the public. Were the Officers <lb/>
of the late Government asked to retain their places for <lb/>
a few months, until the business of the Session could <lb/>
be got over? The real fact of the case appears to be <lb/>
that the leaders of the party now in power were so <lb/>
anxious to obtain office, that, rather than forego the <lb/>
sweets of emolument for a few weeks, they were pre<lb break="no"/>pared to put the people to expense, and the country <lb/>
members to great inconvenience. I will not move any <lb/>
amendment to the paragraph under consideration; but <lb/>
I hope that the Hon. Attorney General will adhere to <lb/>
parliamentary rule more strictly in the future. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—I regret that the hon. Leader of <lb/>
the Opposition is not in his place: if he were, I have <lb/>
no doubt he would satisfy the Hon. Attorney General <lb/>
respecting the delay in holding the General Election, <lb/>
which seems to cause that hon. member so much un<lb break="no"/>easiness. I believe, however, that his surmise was <lb/>
pretty nearly correct; that the late Government deem<lb break="no"/>ed it advisable to delay the Election until the inten<lb break="no"/>tions of the Imperial Government, with respect to the <lb/>
position this Island would occupy in regard to Con<lb break="no"/>federation should be made known. Though I am <lb/>
opposed to Confederation, I believe the policy of the <lb/>
late Administration, in waiting to ascertain the decision <lb/>
of the Home Government on that question, was a <lb/>
sound one. It was but right that the people of this <lb/>
Island should be made aware of what the Imperial <lb/>
Government purposed to do with them, before they <lb/>
were required to go to the polls. This is a small <lb/>
Colony; and, though we objected to enter the proposed <lb/>
Confederation, it was possible that the authorities at <lb/>
Home might resolve to include us in the Bill then about <lb/>
to be brought before parliament The people, I think, <lb/>
will not blame the late Government for delaying the <lb/>
Election until the public mind was relieved upon that <lb/>
point. It would have been unwise to put the country <lb/>
to the expense of a General Election, without knowing <lb/>
what would be our future fate. But, Mr. Chairman, <lb/>
if I recollect rightly, the late Government placed their <lb/>
resignations in His Excellency's hands some ten or <lb/>
twelve days before their successors were appointed, <lb/>
therefore the very late period at which the Session was <lb/>
called, could not be altogether attributable to the time <lb/>
at which the Election was held. And, after the <lb/>
Government was formed, and they had placed their <lb/>
friends in office, there was apparently no occasion for <lb/>
delaying the opening of the Session until last week. <lb/>
They were strong—at least numerically so, whether <lb/>
really strong or not. They had nineteen to eleven of <lb/>
the Opposition—or eighteen to twelve—a question <lb/>
which I suppose the hon. member for Tryon alone <lb/>
can solve; consequently the absence of two or three <lb/>
members from their seats should not have delayed the <lb/>
public business. But, I suppose we must accept the <lb/>
explanation in the paragraph under consideration, that <lb/>
"ministerial arrangements," or perhaps more properly, <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">ministerial difficulties</hi>—prevented an earlier call of the <lb/>
House. We know, Sir, from the declaration of the hon. <lb/>
Leader of the Government himself, at the late nomina<lb break="no"/>tion, that his present supporters in the Legislature are <lb/>
composed of all political parties; therefore it is easy to <lb/>
understand how difficulties may arise. The paragraph <lb/>
before the Committee is moderate; and, indeed, the <lb/>
whole Address is moderate, and, had it not been for <lb/>
the allusion made by the Hon. Attorney General to the <lb/>
course pursued by the late Government in reference to <lb/>
the General Election, I would not have troubled this <lb/>
hon. Committee so early in the debate. <lb/></p>

<pb n="7" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_007.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">7</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>.—The hon. member for Char<lb break="no"/>lottetown has stated that the reason the late Admin<lb break="no"/>istrators delayed the Election, was in order to ascert<lb break="no"/>tain what action the Home Government intended to <lb/>
take on Confederation. This is a very extraordinary <lb/>
excuse to offer. Did they suppose or desire that the <lb/>
Imperial Government would force us into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion? The British Parliament would not be so unjust <lb/>
as to sanction such an act. We are in as independent <lb/>
a position as any of the States in the neighboring <lb/>
Republic; and our independent rights cannot <lb/>
properly be taken from us. But the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment never wished to coerce us into Confederation. <lb/>
Those who held up this idea, were the men who <lb/>
wished that this Island might be legislated into the <lb/>
Union without the people's consent. The Home <lb/>
Government could not rightfully deprive us of our <lb/>
separate Government, unless we had violated the <lb/>
constitution of the Colony. And I believe this is <lb/>
what the late Government attempted to impress upon <lb/>
the Home authorities, when they sent for troops to <lb/>
quell, what they represented to be a disturbance <lb/>
among the tenantry, thereby bringing the Island <lb/>
into discredit. To state that the late Administration <lb/>
delayed the election until it was known whether this <lb/>
Colony would be included in it or not, is as much as <lb/>
to say, that they believed the Legislature of this <lb/>
Island to be a farce, and our constituents not a free <lb/>
people. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—Mr. Chairman, I agree with the <lb/>
hon. member for Belfast, that it was not at all pro<lb break="no"/>bable that the Home Government would take away <lb/>
the Constitution of the Colony without our consent. <lb/>
But the Government did not know what instructions <lb/>
His Excellency might, almost at any moment, receive. <lb/>
He might have been instructed by the Secretary of <lb/>
State for the Colonies to dissolve the House, and <lb/>
test the opinion of the country on the question of <lb/>
Confederation. Suppose that he had received such <lb/>
instructions a week or two after the Election was <lb/>
over, would not the country have thought that the <lb/>
Government of the day had been too hasty in making <lb/>
an appeal to the people? I am just as prepared as the <lb/>
hon. member to stand up for the rights of the Colony; <lb/>
but considering our insignificance, I cannot admit <lb/>
that we are so independent of the Mother Country, <lb/>
as he has asserted. The object of the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, he also stated, seemed to be to bring discredit, <lb/>
or a stigma upon the Colony. This was caused, he <lb/>
says, by their sending for the troops. The Tenant <lb/>
Union disturbances, are no doubt looked upon by <lb/>
him, as a very trifling affair. He did not condescend <lb/>
to inform us whether he was a member of that organ<lb break="no"/>ization or not; but I know, Sir, that when a proces<lb break="no"/>sion of that body paraded the streets of Charlottetown, <lb/>
they halted opposite the hon. gentleman's business <lb/>
establishment, and gave him an ovation. He appeared <lb/>
at the door before them, and received the honor with <lb/>
a countenance radiant with the smiles of patriotism. <lb/>
I am not going to detain this hon. committee at present <lb/>
to discuss the point whether the nature of the dis<lb break="no"/>turbances which arose, out of the great Tenant League <lb/>
agitation, were such as to justify the late Government <lb/>
in sending for troops. I will merely say that if the <lb/>
hon. member for Belfast sincerely believes that their <lb/>
action in the matter was intended, or calculated to <lb/>
bring the Colony into disgrace, he ought, now, <lb/>
since he is a member of the Government, to have intro<lb break="no"/>duced a paragraph into His Excellency's speech to <lb/>
carry out the objects of this Tenant Association which <lb/>
he countenanced and supported. A little pepper in <lb/>
the Speech would have been an improvement. I was <lb/>
not at the hon. member's elbow through his election <lb/>
campaign, but I have been informed that the League <lb/>
had not a little to do with his presence here. If, then, <lb/>
Sir, he owes his seat in this House to the influence <lb/>

<cb/>

of that organization, why has he not something in <lb/>
this Address on the subject, even supposing he could <lb/>
not procure a place for it in the speech from the <lb/>
Throne? I fear, Sir, that having ridden into this <lb/>
House on that political horse, he has turned him <lb/>
away, never more to be heard of, until the next <lb/>
Election day comes round. I can only compare <lb/>
his conduct to a man who has undertaken a long <lb/>
journey on foot, and finding himself fatigued, and <lb/>
almost despairing of reaching his destination, he meets <lb/>
with a horse which he coaxes with a little provender, <lb/>
leaps on his back, rides to the end of his journey, and <lb/>
turns him adrift. So is the hon. member with the <lb/>
Tenant organization; he gave it a few political oats, <lb/>
and encouraged it to help him along, but having <lb/>
served his purpose, he has now quietly forgotten its <lb/>
claims. He may declaim about the troops and the acts <lb/>
of the late Government, but now, after having become <lb/>
one of His Excellency's sworn advisers, he will dis<lb break="no"/>cover that he must pursue the same policy in maintain<lb break="no"/>ing law and order, as was adopted by the Conservative <lb/>
party. It is rumored that the British troops are to be <lb/>
withdrawn from the other Provinces after they are <lb/>
confederated. If so, those which are here will also <lb/>
be called away. Should the hon. member for Belfast, <lb/>
then ascertain that law and order can not be main<lb break="no"/>tained in this Colony, except at the point of the <lb/>
bayonet, he, I think, will conclude that we are not <lb/>
so independent as he at present imagines. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName>.—The subject of the Tenant <lb/>
League having been brought forward by the hon. <lb/>
member for Belfast (Mr. Davies) one of the members <lb/>
of the Government, it is, Mr. Chairman, no harm for <lb/>
the Opposition to mention it. The conduct of my hon. <lb/>
colleague in regard to the Tenant association has been, <lb/>
I think, somewhat strange. In fact he has merely <lb/>
used that body as a means of getting into power, and <lb/>
even in his canvass before the late Election, he regu<lb break="no"/>lated his speeches in regard to the Land Question and <lb/>
the rights of the Tenantry very much by the character <lb/>
of the people whom he happened to be addressing. <lb/>
He should not, I think, have alluded to this question <lb/>
at all, and I wonder that he has done so. But, Sir, <lb/>
returning to the paragraph under discussion, why did <lb/>
not the present Government, if they desired to call <lb/>
the Legislature at an earlier period, wait a few weeks <lb/>
before appointing their principal officers from the <lb/>
members on floor of the House? Could not some <lb/>
of these appointments have been postponed until the <lb/>
House had risen, and thereby no delay be occasioned? <lb/>
But the Address throughout follows the policy of the <lb/>
late Government—that policy which the present Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment at the late Election found so much fault with, <lb/>
but which now they appear ready to carry out. I, for <lb/>
my part, Mr. Chairman, see nothing objectionable in <lb/>
this paragraph, but am surprised at my hon. colleague's <lb/>
allusions to the Tenant League. It is plain that he <lb/>
has merely used that organization as a means of get<lb break="no"/>ting into the Government, and that he will now have <lb/>
no further use for the tenantry until he again calls <lb/>
upon them at another Election. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>.—I wish, Mr. Chairman, to <lb/>
make a few remarks regarding the defence of the hon. <lb/>
member for Charlottetown, with respect to the <lb/>
action of the late Government in delaying the <lb/>
General Elections. The observations which have <lb/>
fallen from that gentleman would lead us to believe <lb/>
that had certain news come from England regarding <lb/>
Confederation, the House would never have been <lb/>
called. This is but a poor defence of the action <lb/>
of the Government, and is equal to saying that <lb/>
its members were willing to sell their country <lb/>
and prove traitors to the trust reposed in them. And <lb/>
is not the party carrying out the same policy still? <lb/>
Have not the Opposition chosen the hon. and learned <lb/>

<pb n="8" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_008.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">8</fw>

member for Georgetown, a red hot Unionist, as their <lb/>
leader, thus showing their leanings to the Confederation <lb/>
Scheme? With regard to what my hon. colleague <lb/>
(Mr. Duncan) has said of my connection with the <lb/>
Tenant League, I may tell him that I am not now in <lb/>
this House through the influence of that body, though <lb/>
many of its members voted for me. It is true that I <lb/>
at first supported the Tenants in their demands, but I <lb/>
had afterwards cause to disapprove of many of their <lb/>
acts. The hon. member's rambling allusions to my <lb/>
canvass and election in Belfast have not very much <lb/>
weight. He clearly expected to carry all Belfast <lb/>
'before him,but failed in the attempt. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>—In the explanation which I gave <lb/>
of the probable cause of the delay in issuing the Writs <lb/>
for the General Election, I merely stated that, in my <lb/>
opinion, that delay was occasioned by a desire on the <lb/>
part of the late Government to postpone the Elections <lb/>
until something more definite was known on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject of Confederation; but I did not wish to convey <lb/>
the impression that they were waiting in order to sell <lb/>
their country. Even if disposed to take such action <lb/>
on Confederation, they wouid have had to submit <lb/>
it to the Legislature; and I therefore do not see that <lb/>
they were in a position to act as traitors, even were <lb/>
they so inclined. Much, Mr. Chairman, has been said <lb/>
about the Opposition's having chosen the hon. member <lb/>
for Georgetown, (Mr. Haviland) who is a Confeder<lb break="no"/>ate, as their leader, but I cannot think it consistent in <lb/>
,the hon. member for Belfast to condemn them for <lb/>
doing so when the party of which he is a member <lb/>
offered the highest honor in this House which they <lb/>
could confer upon the same Confederate gentleman, <lb/>
namely. the Speaker's Chair. And has not the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of which he is a member appointed a gentleman <lb/>
who is a strong Confederate to the most lucrative <lb/>
office in their gift? That gentleman has since lost his <lb/>
Election, and I am sorry that such is the case. The <lb/>
Queen's Printer has always been a credit to the House <lb/>
and i would not have the slightest objection to seeing <lb/>
him now on the floor, for I have always respected him, <lb/>
strongly though he has denounced the policy of the <lb/>
Conservative party. I consider that the Liberal party <lb/>
—if such a party. exists—acted rightly in appointing <lb/>
Mr. Whelan; l merely object to the inconsistency of <lb/>
hon. members who made that appointment, now <lb/>
finding fault with the Opposition for selecting their <lb/>
ablest and most experienced member as Leader, even <lb/>
though he be a Confederate. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>—The. hon. member who has <lb/>
just spoken considers that I cannot, with any degree <lb/>
of consistency, approve of Mr. Whelan's appointment <lb/>
as Queen's Printer, and yet condemn the Opposition <lb/>
for choosing the hon. member for Georgetown (Mr. <lb/>
Haviland) as their Leader. It is well-known that Mr. <lb/>
Whelan had strong claims upon the Liberal party. <lb/>
He ran his election, was returned, and then applied <lb/>
for the Printership; but, before that office was given <lb/>
him, he renounced his former opinions in favor of <lb/>
Confederation, and promised to oppose the measure in <lb/>
the House, if again elected. It appears, however, <lb/>
that, on his returning to his constituents, they were <lb/>
not satisfied with his promise, and rejected him; and. <lb/>
I am proud, as a politician, they did so, though I my<lb break="no"/>self believe that, had Mr.Whelan been again returned, <lb/>
he would have opposed Confederation. But the case is <lb/>
different in regard to Mr. Haviland. The Opposition <lb/>
have chosen him unpledged, and he will still support <lb/>
Confederation. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—I am sorry, Mr. Chairman, that <lb/>
Mr. Whelan is not present. I have always had too <lb/>
high an opinion of that gentleman to think that he <lb/>
would sell himself and' his opinions for an office, and, <lb/>
if he were now in the House, he would not, I think, <lb/>

<cb/>

thank the hon. member who has just sat down, for <lb/>
the character which he has given him, that of a poli<lb break="no"/>tical hireling. I have never seen his abandonment of <lb/>
his opinions, and I do not htink such was ever made. <lb/>
The hon. member thinks there is a vast difference <lb/>
between the appointment of Mr. Whelan and that of Mr. <lb/>
Haviland. If he objects to the Opposition being led <lb/>
by the latter gentleman, why was he so anxious to <lb/>
place him in the Speaker's Chair? If he is bent upon <lb/>
betraying the interests of his native country, was that <lb/>
the reward to give him,— make him first Commoner of <lb/>
the land? I believe Mr. Whelan is as much a Con<lb break="no"/>federate as ever, and he was placed in office by the <lb/>
present <hi rendition="simple:italic">composite</hi> Government, for, that is its character. <lb/>
There are in it fragments of the old Liberal party, <lb/>
some of the Tenant League element, I believe, and <lb/>
some Conservatives. The position of the present hon. <lb/>
Leader of the Opposition is before the country. He <lb/>
is, we know, a staunch Confederate; and, since his <lb/>
avowal of his opinions on this matter, he has been <lb/>
returned by his constituents. Regarding the delay in <lb/>
the Elections, Mr. Chairman, as I said before, I do not <lb/>
think that the Conservative party delayed them, in <lb/>
order to sell the people, or that they had the power or <lb/>
inclination to do so. Surely the House of Assembly <lb/>
that passed the "No terms Resolution" would not be <lb/>
willing to sell the country. There was, I think, as <lb/>
much integrity in the late House, as in the present one; <lb/>
and I consider it right that the Elections were <lb/>
delayed, in order that the people might be better <lb/>
informed upon the subject of Confederation, and the <lb/>
wishes of the Imperial Government. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HENS1">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>.—I did not, Mr. <lb/>
Chairman, think that the Tenant League and Confed<lb break="no"/>eration would be brought up for discussion, when I <lb/>
moved the clause now under consideration. Nothing <lb/>
of the sort was mentioned in the clause; and, in <lb/>
moving it, I merely stated that no blame was cast <lb/>
upon the late Government, as they were probably able <lb/>
to give good reasons for their acts. It was reported <lb/>
that the late Government desired to sacrifice the Island <lb/>
on the altar of Confederation, and therefore delayed the <lb/>
dissolution of the Assembly; but, as a proof that this <lb/>
could notbe the case, I alluded to the fact that the hon. <lb/>
members opposite, for Belfast and Murray Harbor, <lb/>
both strong anti-Confederates, were in the Executive <lb/>
up to and after the time at which the dissolution would <lb/>
ordinarily have taken place. But, if the dissolution <lb/>
was delayed to enable the people to obtain more <lb/>
information on Confederation, that they might thereby <lb/>
form a more correct opinion on the subject, I am <lb/>
willing to concede the wisdom of the delay. Regard<lb break="no"/>ing the case of the hon. Leader of the Opposition, and <lb/>
that of the present Queen's Printer, I consider that, if <lb/>
any person thinks proper to cover his views on a <lb/>
subject, and to say that he will not press them upon <lb/>
the attention of the House, I am perfectly at liberty <lb/>
to accept him as an officer, either of the Government <lb/>
or of this House. I look upon the hon. member for <lb/>
Georgetown as pledged not to support Confederation, <lb/>
until he shall again appeal to his constituents on the <lb/>
subject. It was not at all unparliamentary for the <lb/>
Government to offer him the Speaker's chair. In the <lb/>
British Parliament, the Speaker is chosen simply with <lb/>
regard to his merits, leaving his political opinions out <lb/>
of the question; and why could not we do the same? <lb/>
The hon.member for Charlottetown also stated that he <lb/>
believed that the dissolution of the late House was <lb/>
probably delayed, in order to afford time to receive <lb/>
despatches from the Home Government on the subject of <lb/>
Confederation. It was probably of advantage to the <lb/>
people, that, at the time the Elections took place, the ques<lb break="no"/>tion, in all its bearings, and all its fulness, should be be<lb break="no"/>fore them, giving them an opportunity of forming their <lb/>
own opinions on the matter, and taking these opinions <lb/>
as a guide for their actions; and I consider that no <lb/>

<pb n="9" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_009.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">9</fw> 

compulsion that could be brought to bear, would <lb/>
prevent them doing so. The hon. member for George<lb break="no"/>town (Mr. McAulay) has accused me of acting in an <lb/>
unparliamentary manner. That gentleman occupied <lb/>
the Speaker's Chair for some time, in the late House, <lb/>
and, of course, his statements will carry great weight. <lb/>
It sounded very well for him to say that I had <lb/>
departed from Parliamentary practice; but I am unable <lb/>
to see in what respect I did so. If asking for an explan<lb break="no"/>ation, to enlighten this hon. Committee, is unparlia<lb break="no"/>mentary. I must, I confess, plead guilty. Much has <lb/>
been said about Departmental and Responsible Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. I lately read. in a Halifax newspaper, an arti<lb break="no"/>cle on this subject, which defined Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to be a government according to the well-under<lb break="no"/>stood wishes of the people, as expressed through a major<lb break="no"/>ity of their Representatives. We, then, have Responsible <lb/>
Government in its pure form, so long as we have a ma<lb break="no"/>jority of the Representatives carrying out their wishes. <lb/>
The hon. member for the City also stated that there <lb/>
was nothing in His Excellency's Speech,- that, in the <lb/>
Speech the Government merely followed the policy of <lb/>
the late Administration. What an example the Tories <lb/>
have set, certainly? They laid aside the Land Purchase <lb/>
Bill, which was a Liberal measure, and tried other <lb/>
measures for the purchase of the Lands; but, these <lb/>
failing, they finally returned to the original Bill. Does <lb/>
the hon. member think that, because the Conservatives <lb/>
adopted the policy of the Liberals, that the party, in <lb/>
its return to power, is to throw aside that policy, and <lb/>
adopt a new one? We do not, Sir, follow the Conser<lb break="no"/>vative party, but merely support a measure brought <lb/>
forward by ourselves,-a measure the best adapted to <lb/>
settle the Land Question, and which as done so to a very <lb/>
great extent. But, Sir, the present Government have <lb/>
been blamed, by some hon. members of the Opposition, <lb/>
for not having waited until the House had risen, before <lb/>
appointing its officers from that body. It was impos<lb break="no"/>sible for the Government to work until its principal <lb/>
officers, such as the Colonial Secretary, were appointed; <lb/>
and I think that my hon. friend, the Leader of the Op<lb break="no"/>position, would have been rather surprised, had the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment asked him to remain in office after the defeat <lb/>
of his party. I trust that the hon. member for George<lb break="no"/>town (Mr. McAulay) will see fit to withdraw the <lb/>
charge of being unparliamentary, which he has brought <lb/>
against me. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCAU1">Hon. Mr. McAULAY</persName>.- If the hon. member expects <lb/>
me to retract his hopes, Mr. Chairman, will end in <lb/>
disappointment. When I charged him with being <lb/>
unparliamentary, I did not speak unadvisedly; and <lb/>
there are now, or were lately, before him, authorities <lb/>
to prove the correctness of what I said. If he is not <lb/>
too indolent to peruse these authorities, he will find <lb/>
that references in consure are not allowed in the <lb/>
Imperial Parliament. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.- If I had been in my place <lb/>
at the commencement of this debate much discussion <lb/>
might have been saved. The debate, Mr. Chairman, <lb/>
should have been confined to the paragraph now be<lb break="no"/>fore you, instead of which, we have subjects brought <lb/>
up and discussed which do not even appear in the <lb/>
Address. The hon. member for Charlottetown was <lb/>
right in saying that Confederation was the cause of <lb/>
the delay in holding the late General Election. Her <lb/>
Majesty's Representatives, together with his advisers, <lb/>
considered that it was for the interest of the Island to <lb/>
defer the Election as late as possible, that all the in<lb break="no"/>formation which could be received might have laid before <lb/>
the people at the polls, that they might know the re<lb break="no"/>sult of the Conference in London, and the principles <lb/>
of the Confederation Bill before the Imperial Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. We expected some despatch in answer to the <lb/>
Address sent from this House last year which would <lb/>
contain more than the usual announcement that Her <lb/>
Majesty had received it graciously. On the day of <lb/>

<cb/>

nominations such as despatch was received and immedi<lb break="no"/>ately published the people might read it; and <lb/>
had the Election taken place in the autumn the coun<lb break="no"/>try would have been in ignorance of many of the facts <lb/>
concerning Confederation. Very probably the reason <lb/>
why some hon. members object to the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment's having delayed the Election, is that they were <lb/>
then anxiously waiting to get into the House, and <lb/>
were therefore impatient of any delay. Some insinu<lb break="no"/>ation has been thrown out that the late Government <lb/>
were waiting to sell the country. I can tell hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers,-and my word will, I think, have some weight, <lb/>
for I am pretty well known,-that I was returned by <lb/>
my constituents pledged not to commit the Island to <lb/>
any scheme of Confederation, without first appealing <lb/>
to the people, anjd I would as soon cut off my hand as <lb/>
allow it to be done. I only hope that hon. members <lb/>
opposite will be as well able to clear their skirts when <lb/>
they go out of power as I am. I never, Mr. Chairman, <lb/>
heard on the floor of this House such an extraordinary <lb/>
admission as that made by the hon. member for Belfast <lb/>
(Mr. Davies) regarding the Queen's Printer's appoint<lb break="no"/>ment. He actually seemed to me to sing a pean of joy <lb/>
over that gentleman's defeat. If the hon. member <lb/>
was unwilling to see him in office, he should, I think <lb/>
have resigned his position as a member of the Execu<lb break="no"/>tive. By the principles of Responsible Government <lb/>
every member of that body is individually responsible <lb/>
for every appointment, and it is the duty of each <lb/>
of them to defend that appointment when made. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>.- I think I may be allowed to <lb/>
explain my statement in regard to Mr. Whelan's ap<lb break="no"/>pointment as Queen's Printer. I would have been <lb/>
oppposed to his appointment, had I not been aware <lb/>
that, before his first Election, he publicly renounced his <lb/>
opinions on Confederation. When I said that I was <lb/>
glad that the people had now rejected him, I merely <lb/>
meant that I was glad they had done so, if they did <lb/>
not consider him sincere in the pledges which he had <lb/>
given. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName>.- I omitted, Mr. Chairman, to <lb/>
remind my hon. colleague, who so strongly condemned <lb/>
the action of the late Government in sending for the <lb/>
troops, that the Opposition of last Session, with the <lb/>
exception of two hon. members, approved of the step <lb/>
taken by the Conservative Administration in that <lb/>
matter. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName>.- During the Debate, <lb/>
reference has been made to me personally, as a member <lb/>
of the late Government, and an insinuation has been <lb/>
made against the Government, for which I consider it <lb/>
my duty to demand something more than assertion. <lb/>
The hon. member for Belfast (Mr. Davies) has stated <lb/>
that the late Government had called the soldiers into the <lb/>
Island, with the intention of forcing the Island into <lb/>
Confederation. Can he produce any proof-anything <lb/>
like proof-for that statement? Does he mean to say <lb/>
that his Honor the Chief Justice, who was at that time <lb/>
Administrator of the Government, would consent to <lb/>
anything like that? I repudiate the statement, and hand <lb/>
it back to the gentleman for proof. I admit that, per<lb break="no"/>haps preliminary steps, on the part of the civil power, <lb/>
were not used in time, and I will give you no opinion <lb/>
now, contrary to the opinions which I held when in <lb/>
the Government. I do not wish to occupy the time of <lb/>
this hon. Committee: but when the integrity of the <lb/>
late Government is called in question, I consider it my <lb/>
duty to defend them. I say, then, that the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Belfast (Mr. Davies) has given no proof-<lb break="yes"/>except his bare assertion--that such was the motive of <lb/>
the late Government, in calling the Troops. I regret <lb/>
that this subject has been brought forward. I would <lb/>
be one of the last to mention it. Some gentlemen <lb/>
have referred to the fact that my hon. and learned <lb/>

<pb n="10" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_010.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">10</fw>

friend, the member for Georgetown, has been chosen <lb/>
as Leader by the Opposition. We were in this act, <lb/>
Sir, as consistent as were the Government in offering <lb/>
him the Speaker's chair. The fact of their having <lb/>
done this only proves that we have made a wise choice. <lb/>
I myself heard that gentleman, when addressing his <lb/>
constituents in Georgetown, say, if ever that crisis <lb/>
came, when his vote could put this Island into Con<lb break="no"/>federation without the consent of the people, God <lb/>
forbid that he should give it. Take this fact in con<lb break="no"/>nection with the well-known character of the hon. <lb/>
member for Georgetown, and we have, I think, as <lb/>
good a guarantee for his conduct as can be required. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName>.-I did not, Mr. Chairman, <lb/>
intend to speak at this stage of the proceedings; but, <lb/>
certainly, I did not expect that any hon. gentleman <lb/>
would have made such statements as the hon. member <lb/>
for Belfast (Mr. Duncan) has done. He said that all <lb/>
the Opposition of last year were in favor of bringing <lb/>
the troops here, except two-the hon. member for <lb/>
New Glasgow, and the hon. member for Tryon. All <lb/>
the members of the minority of last year, with the ex<lb break="no"/>ception of two, were not in favor of the action of the <lb/>
late Government in that matter; and, therefore, Sir, <lb/>
his statement is incorrect. There was a Resolution <lb/>
brought in by the Government, to which the hon. <lb/>
member for Tryon moved an amendment, and eight <lb/>
members voted for it—which amendment I will now <lb/>
read:<lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That the House of Assembly regret the disturbances <lb/>
and troubles which occurred in this Colony in the past year, <lb/>
but the House, at the same time, are of opinion that the <lb/>
alleged open and systematic defiance of the law might <lb/>
have been set aside by a further recourse to the aid of the <lb/>
civil power at the disposal of the local anthorities, before <lb/>
calling in the aid of Her Majesty's troops." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Now, Sir, I find that eight voted for this amendment, <lb/>
and this is an important fact. I did not intend to go <lb/>
into this question. I am sorry, and I think every <lb/>
hon. member in this House is sorry, that the Hon. Mr. <lb/>
Whelan has not been returned,-sory that he was so <lb/>
unfortunate . There have been other matters brought <lb/>
up, which, I think, we had better now pass by, as we <lb/>
shall have amply opportunity, hereafter, to speak to <lb/>
them. I will only say that I was surprised at the ex<lb break="no"/>planation given by the hon. memeber, with respect to <lb/>
the delay in holding the Election, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.—Does the hon. member <lb/>
refer to me? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName>.—I referred to the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Belfast (Mr. Duncan). <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName>.—Mr. Chairman, I was the one who <lb/>
moved the resolution in the House last year which <lb/>
has just been read by the hon. member. I believe <lb/>
that law and order should be maintained; and I be<lb break="no"/>lieve that all classes are liable to become excited at <lb/>
times; but I do think that the Government should <lb/>
have used the means at their disposal before they <lb/>
brought the troops here. Had theydone so, they <lb/>
would have had no occasion for the troops to put <lb/>
down any disturbance. But now that they are here, <lb/>
I am glad to see them. it is admitted by all that this <lb/>
Session was called too late, and both sides of the <lb/>
House seem to try to get clear of the blame. Now, is <lb/>
there cause for complaint? I, for one, believe that there <lb/>
is blame, and I wish that blame to rest upon those on <lb/>
whom it should. If the present Government, as ex<lb break="no"/>plained by the Hon. the Atty. Gen., had no more time <lb/>
than was required by law for calling the Legislature, <lb/>
then the blame must rest with the late Government. <lb/>
I am at a loss to understand the hon. member for <lb/>
Charlottetown (Mr. Brecken) when he gave as a rea<lb break="no"/>son that they were waiting for fuller information on <lb/>

<cb/>

Confederation. Now, Sir, if he was sincere last year <lb/>
in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">no terms resolution</hi>, there was no necessity to <lb/>
wait for any further information on the subject of <lb/>
Confederation; and the Election should have been <lb/>
held at the proper time, and the country not put to <lb/>
the inconvenience of calling the Legislature so late. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—In the absence of the Leader of <lb/>
the Opposition, I suggested what I thought probably <lb/>
was the reason why the late Election did not take <lb/>
place at an earlier date, that the Government were <lb/>
waiting the result of the deliberations of the delegates <lb/>
of the other Provinces, in London, on the subject of <lb/>
Confederation. If such was their reason, it appears to <lb/>
me a sufficient one; for who could tell to what extent <lb/>
our position might have been effected by the policy of <lb/>
the Imperial Government? Some persons predicted <lb/>
that we would be coerced into union; others, that cer<lb break="no"/>tain terms would be offered for the acceptance or re<lb break="no"/>jection of the people of this Colony, and with that <lb/>
object a dissolution would have to take place. The <lb/>
hon. member for Belfast (Mr. Davies) will surely <lb/>
admit that it was of consequence that all doubts in this <lb/>
important matter should be removed before the Electors <lb/>
were called upon to choose their representatives. The <lb/>
hon. member charges me, as one of the supporters of <lb/>
the celebrated no terms resolution, with inconsistency <lb/>
in excusing this delay; but Sir, the hon. member <lb/>
knows very well that, although I voted for these reso<lb break="no"/>lutions, I did not agree with the wording of them; and <lb/>
if he refers to the report of my speech on that occa<lb break="no"/>sion, he will find that I stated that they went too far, <lb/>
that to say that no terms of union that would prove <lb/>
advantageous to our interests and the well-being of <lb/>
the people could be offered was going too far. My rea<lb break="no"/>sons for voting for these resolutions were, that I be<lb break="no"/>lieved that no other terms were in store for us other <lb/>
than those offered by the Quebec Scheme--terms <lb/>
which I believe then, and still do, were neither just <lb/>
nor liberal to the Island; and that in a union on such <lb/>
terms, our material interests would be most seriously <lb/>
depressed. That looking at what was then taking <lb/>
place in the neighboring Province of Nova Scotia, the <lb/>
very great dissatisfaction that appeared to exist there, <lb/>
and the protests that were being made against the <lb/>
policy of the Government going into Confederation <lb/>
without first appealing to the people, I considered it <lb/>
would have been dangerous for us to admit the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple in the abstract, until there was a prospect of <lb/>
getting fair terms, such as the people of this Colony <lb/>
would be prepared to accept. If the hon. member <lb/>
(Mr. Davies) will take the trouble to refer to <lb/>
my speech, when these resolutions were under discus<lb break="no"/>sion last Session, he will find that I have not changed <lb/>
my opinions. That I then said that terms might be <lb/>
offered which it would be to our interest to accept. <lb/>
Not that I think it any discredit to a man to change <lb/>
his opinions, on political as well as other subjects. <lb/>
The man who never changes his opinion, never corrects <lb/>
his errors. Since last Session Confederation has <lb/>
undergone a material change. The union of Canada, <lb/>
Nova Scotia, and New Brunswick has been accom<lb break="no"/>plished; besides the terms of the compact have also <lb/>
been materially changed. With us, Sir, I think it is <lb/>
only a question of time. I have never thought that <lb/>
we can stand alone and keep out of the union. If i <lb/>
thought we could without imperilling our various in<lb break="no"/>terests, I would say in the words of Shakspeare, "better <lb/>

<pb n="11" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_011.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">11</fw>

bear those ills we have than fly to others we know not <lb/>
of." Our position now is such that it becomes the <lb/>
duty of every public man to look the question fairly <lb/>
in the face, not in a party spirit with the object of <lb/>
making political stock out of it. It is time we made <lb/>
up our minds on this great question, as to the most <lb/>
beneficial course to be pursued, and having done so to <lb/>
stand or fall by those opinions. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>.--I look at members who have <lb/>
pledged themselves. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.--The hon. member need not <lb/>
alarm himself about my inconsistency. I am not going <lb/>
to play with the question. I have pledged myself in <lb/>
common, I believe, with every hon. member of this <lb/>
House, not to commit the country to Confederation <lb/>
until the question is first submitted to the people at <lb/>
the polls. This pledge was most distinctly given, and <lb/>
I intend to keep it strictly. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>.--I understood the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Charlottetown. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.--I consider myself bound by a <lb/>
pledge to hand back to my constituents the power <lb/>
they entrusted me with undiminished. I do not feel <lb/>
myself precluded from discussion the question. For, <lb/>
if the present Government were to open negociations <lb/>
with the Confederate Colonies, for the purpose of <lb/>
joining the Union--a course that would not very much <lb/>
surprise me--and obtain an offer on favorable terms, I <lb/>
should consider myself bound to vote against closing <lb/>
with that offer, and vote for referring the question to <lb/>
the people I am surprised at the coolness of the hon. <lb/>
member, twitting me with inconsistency on the subject <lb/>
of Confederation. I ask him, what candidate did he <lb/>
support at the recent Election for Charlottetown,-my <lb/>
hon. colleague, a prominent supporter of Confederation, <lb/>
one of the celebrated " ninety-four. " If, Sir, the hon. <lb/>
member and his party, well-knowing my colleague's <lb/>
views on that question, supported, and, with the assist<lb break="no"/>ance of some Confederates in the city, returned him to <lb/>
this House; but--strange and inconsistent--having <lb/>
placed him in that responsible position, they are afraid, <lb/>
I understand, to trust him as a member of the Execu<lb break="no"/>tive Council, and resolutely refuse to appoint him to <lb/>
that position, although he has as resolutely insisted on <lb/>
his right to be there. Looking at the fact that he is <lb/>
one of the representatives of the capital of the Colony, <lb/>
and the only one who is in harmony with the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, if there is anything of that element amongst <lb/>
them, which I much doubt, and considering that his con<lb break="no"/>stituents are the most wealthy, and certainly as intelli<lb break="no"/>gent as any in the Island, and that the greater portion of <lb/>
the mercantile, mechanical, and many other of our <lb/>
important interests are centred in the Town and Royal<lb break="no"/>ty, I do think my colleague, and those who sent him <lb/>
here, have a right to see him at the Executive Council <lb/>
Board. I understand the Government distrusts him <lb/>
on account of his qualifications and position, in other respects, <lb/>
do not justify the appointment. Strange inconsistency, <lb/>
voting for a gentleman, returning him to this House, <lb/>
and still afraid to trust him as a member of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. But, Sir, for another piece of inconsistency on <lb/>
the part of the hon member (Mr. Davies) and his <lb/>
party. How does he defend the appointment to the <lb/>

<cb/>

office of Queen;s Printer of a gentleman, one of the <lb/>
most ardent and talented (and on that account the <lb/>
most dangerous) advocates of Confederation. The <lb/>
hon. member designates Confederates as traitors. Is <lb/>
this his mode of punishing treachery by appointing <lb/>
the offender to the most lucrative office in the gift of <lb/>
the Government? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:KELL1">Hon. Mr. KELLY</persName>.--Mr. Davies was not appointed <lb/>
to the Executive until after Mr. Whelan was appoint<lb break="no"/>ed Queen's Printer. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.--So much the worse for him, if <lb/>
such was the fact, for, by accepting a seat in the <lb/>
Government, he endorsed and approved of the Act; <lb/>
but the fact is Mr. Davies was a member of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment at the time the appointment was made. The <lb/>
hon. member (Mr. Davies) jeers us for having a red-hot <lb/>
Unionist as Leader of the Opposition. It is within the <lb/>
knowledge of this hon. House, that that hon. member <lb/>
and the Government proposed to punish the Leader of <lb/>
the Opposition for his red-hot Confederate ideas, by <lb/>
making him first Commoner of the land, placing him <lb/>
in the Speaker's Chair. Strange method this, of <lb/>
marking the people's and the hon. member's disappro<lb break="no"/>bation of the Leader of the Opposition's unsound and <lb/>
traitorous opinions on a question so vitally affecting <lb/>
our interests. The fact is, the Government is a mass <lb/>
of inconsistency; there are scarcely two of them who <lb/>
profess the same principles. Their Leader, who has <lb/>
not at present a seat in this House, always contented, <lb/>
(and no later than a few days ago, on the hustings in <lb/>
Charlottetown.) that the departmental system of Re<lb break="no"/>sponsible Government was the only true system. How <lb/>
often have we, on this side of the House, been denun<lb break="no"/>ciated as traitors for departing from it, by excluding <lb/>
office-holders from the Legislature. Now, we find this <lb/>
composite Government following the course laid down <lb/>
by the Conservatives, without having the honesty or <lb/>
candor to confess that they have seen the error of their <lb/>
way, or to assign reasons for changing their minds. No, <lb/>
Sir; rather than admit that it was honorable for their <lb/>
opponents to do anything right, they prefer pursuing a <lb/>
course which they have denounced as deceptive. They <lb/>
tell us that all political parties must make compromises. <lb/>
To a certain extent this is true,--but in matters of <lb/>
detail, there is a point at which compromises must <lb/>
stop. There are certain vital principles, which admit <lb/>
of no compromise, unless they wish to be, as this Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment are, compromised from head to foot, without <lb/>
any distinctive principle, composed of a remnant of the <lb/>
old Liberal party, an infusion of Tenant Leaguers, and <lb/>
a few calling themselves moderate Conservatives. Look <lb/>
at some of their recent and most important appoint<lb break="no"/>ments. What principle of Responsible Government <lb/>
was respected in the appointment of the Colonia! <lb/>
Treasurer--a gentleman who, a few weeks ago, was <lb/>
rejected, at the Legislative Council Election, by an <lb/>
overwhelming majority; and, as to the appointment to <lb/>
the head of the Customs' Department, I cannot say <lb/>
what known rule of the Constitution has been invaded, <lb/>
as the framers of that system of government, wide and <lb/>
comprehensive as they made it, never contemplated <lb/>
such a case of unblushing political jobbery occurring; <lb/>
this was reserved for the ingenuity of Prince Edward <lb/>
Island Liberals. And bear in mind, Mr. Chairman, that <lb/>
the Government, by making this appointment, endorses <lb/>
its propriety collectively and individually, otherwise <lb/>

<pb n="12" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_012.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">12</fw>

they would insist on the Controller of Customs <lb/>
obtaining the approval of his constituents. I can <lb/>
picture to myself that gentleman, when on the hustings, <lb/>
diluting on the grievances and wrongs perpetuated by <lb/>
those ruthless and grinding Tories, and assuring the <lb/>
people that, if they would only return him to Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, he would put his shoulder to the wheel, and case <lb/>
them of all their burdens and wrongs. They do so. <lb/>
He, on his part, accepts a lucrative office, makes his <lb/>
bow to his oppressed constituency, and takes final leave <lb/>
of them and their grievances. I have always looked <lb/>
upon Responsible Government as a very elastic thing; <lb/>
it may be compared to an Indian rubber bag, capable <lb/>
of being squeezed into a variety of shapes and forms; <lb/>
and, provided you keep it inflated with the breath of <lb/>
the well-understood wishes of the people for the time, <lb/>
all well; but the present composite Government seem <lb/>
disposed to squeeze that very breath out of it, and hold <lb/>
it up to the people as an empty and meaningless thing. <lb/>
So much, Sir, for the consistency of the hon. member <lb/>
for Belfast and his new-found friends. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>.--Mr. Chairman; being a young <lb/>
member, I did not wish to be too hasty in rising to <lb/>
address this hon. Committee. But I cannot any longer <lb/>
retain my seat, when I hear such a reason given for <lb/>
delaying the General Election. In fact, it is no rea<lb break="no"/>son at all. Sir, in my boyish days I was led to believe <lb/>
that law and lawyers were nearly synomous terms for <lb/>
roguery and deception; but I have lived that opinion <lb/>
down. Still, when I hear the hon. and learned mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Charlottetown advancing such reasons as he <lb/>
has done to-night, I am almost forced to the conclusion <lb/>
that my early impressions were correct. Now, if <lb/>
he was honest in voting for the " no terms " <lb/>
resolutions, it ought to be a matter of indifference to <lb/>
him how early in the summer the elections were held. <lb/>
If consistency had characterized the actions of the late <lb/>
Government, delay in the case was unnecessary. The <lb/>
attempt to justify putting off the Elections, on account <lb/>
of the general tenor of the resolutions on Confederation <lb/>
passed last Session, is, I think, without force, when we <lb/>
consider that the " no terms " portion of themis their <lb/>
most prominent feature,--so much so, that they receive <lb/>
their designation from it, and will continue to do so, <lb/>
while the Journals of this House remain in existence. <lb/>
The hon. member for Charlottetown has also twitted <lb/>
the members of the Government about the "composite" <lb/>
material of which it is formed. Be that as it may, I <lb/>
think their opinions are more in harmony with each <lb/>
other, and their actions characterized by greater <lb/>
unanimity, than were those of the late Government. <lb/>
One member of that " happy family "--the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Murray Harbor (Mr. Henderson)--was kicked <lb/>
(pardon the expression) out of that honorable body. <lb/>
And the operation appears to have had a beneficial <lb/>
effect upon him, judging from his present conduct, <lb/>
following, as he does, closely to, and firmly supporting, <lb/>
the present hon. Leader of the Opposition, who <lb/>
remained a member of the late Government after his <lb/>
(Mr. Henderson's) gentle dismissal. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.--To say that no terms could be <lb/>
offered that would induce us to enter into Confederation, <lb/>
was certainly going too far. The hon. member from <lb/>
Bedeque insinuates that I was prepared to enter into <lb/>
Confederation, if better terms were offered. This is an <lb/>
error. I did not say so, or deviate from my pledge to <lb/>
return the matter to the hustings. <lb/></p>

<cb/>

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName>.--Mr. Chairman; the hon. <lb/>
member, who has just sat down (Mr. Laird), in his <lb/>
reply to the hon. and learned member on my right <lb/>
(Mr. Brecken) had alluded to me; but, I would remind <lb/>
him that it is quite unnecessary to attack me over the <lb/>
shoulders of another, for, I believe, I can stand upon <lb/>
my own legs. He affirms that I was kicked out of the <lb/>
late Government; but I can assure him that I was <lb/>
neither kicked nor pushed out of the Government, as <lb/>
the correspondence on the subject, published several <lb/>
months ago, has sufficiently proved; and, if the ques<lb break="no"/>tion were put to the vote of the intelligent people of <lb/>
the Island, I venture to say that they would pronounce <lb/>
my conduct as honorable as that of any member in this <lb/>
House. The illustration made use of by the hon. <lb/>
member, I did not distinctly hear, but its drift I can <lb/>
easily understand; and believe that, if it may be taken <lb/>
as a true index to his forthcoming speeches, he may <lb/>
expect laurels, not a few, before the end of the Session. <lb/>
He has only bound on the state harness; let him not <lb/>
think too hastily that he would work his way through <lb/>
a difficulty like the one alluded to, with more credit <lb/>
than I have done. The hon. member (Mr. Davies) is <lb/>
muttering on his seat, while I am speaking; but, I <lb/>
must tell that hon. member that it would be much <lb/>
more gentlemanly for him to stand up and reply to me <lb/>
himself, if able to do so, than to sit prompting another <lb/>
for that purpose. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE7">Mr. McLENNAN</persName>.--This discursive debate, Mr. <lb/>
Chairman, is a perfect waste of time. I am one of <lb/>
those who approve of the action of the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in reference to the General Election. Hon. <lb/>
members have brought into this discussion matters not <lb/>
before this hon. Committee. In the paragraph under <lb/>
consideration, there is not one word that has any <lb/>
reference to Confederation. It is a waste of time to be <lb/>
referring now to many of the subjects which have been <lb/>
dragged into this debate. There will be ample oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity to do so when these questions come up, in <lb/>
proper form, before the House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PROW2">Mr. PROWSE</persName>.--Mr. Chairman: I feel it to be my <lb/>
duty to tell the hon. member for Belfast (Mr. Davies) <lb/>
that, when he undertakes to charge this side of the <lb/>
House as being the Confederate side, he is stating <lb/>
what is incorrect. There are, Sir, on this side of the <lb/>
House, men as strongly anti-Confederate as can be <lb/>
be found anywhere. Why, Sir, the conduct of the <lb/>
majority, with respect to the elections for the City of <lb/>
Charlottetown, cannot be defended. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man charges us with changing our opinions on Con<lb break="no"/>federation, because we have a Confederate for our <lb/>
Leader; and yet he and his party were willing and <lb/>
anxious to put that same gentleman into the Speaker's <lb/>
Chair. I am sure, if a Confederate was placed in that <lb/>
honorable position by this House, it would be regarded <lb/>
by the public as a tendency towards Confederation, <lb/>
much more than the act of the Opposition, in choosing <lb/>
him to be their Leader. I need not say one word with <lb/>
respect to the hon. member giving his own vote for a <lb/>
strong Confederate, after what has been said by others <lb/>
on that act of his. The Government side of this House <lb/>
is made up of old Liberals, Tenant-Leaguers, Confed<lb break="no"/>erates, and Conservatives; and on this side, there are <lb/>
men who are strongly opposed to Confederation. <lb/>
With respect to the question, why the late Government <lb/>
did not cause the Elections to take place earlier, I may <lb/>
say that, if they felt that any danger was to come out <lb/>
of hasty steps, they were doing a good serivce in <lb/>
acting as they did. And, Sir, I believe, there was a <lb/>
time when a Legislature, only nine months old, was <lb/>
dissolved, and a late Assembly taken place at the usual <lb/>
time, there was reason to apprehend that the same <lb/>
would have again occurred. If that was the reason, <lb/>
I consider it a perfectly satisfactory one, for it <lb/>
probably saved the country the expense of a second <lb/>

<pb n="13" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-04-22_Page_013.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">13</fw>

Election. We know that the Home Authorities were <lb/>
more anxious that this Colony should go into Confed<lb break="no"/>eration, than they were, spme time ago, that we should <lb/>
have six additional members in this House; therefore, <lb/>
it was quite probable that they might have instructed <lb/>
His Excellency to dissolve the Assembly, and test the <lb/>
question of Confederation at the polls. <lb/></p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>