<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1871-03-28"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1871-03-28">28 March 1871</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1871">
               <title>The Parliamentary Reporter of Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly</title>.
          <date from="1871" to="1872"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Examiner</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="270" to="270"/>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="272" to="273"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_270.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_271.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_273.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-07-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-07-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_270">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_270.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_271">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_271.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_273">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_271.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1871-03-28_Page_270"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_270.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">270</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1871</fw>
   
   
            <p>[Hon. B. DAVIES] The<lb/>Opposition press believed the Government,<lb/>in bringing forward the measure, did so<lb/>
    
    
            <cb/>
       
       
     with a view to free the country into Con<lb break="no"/>federation, which he, (Hon. B. D.) felt as<lb break="no"/>sured would follow as a result of the debt<lb/>the undertaking would entail upon the Colo<lb break="no"/>ny. In engaging in an undertaking so far<lb/>beyond the resources of the country, the<lb/>consequences would be they would as a Colo<lb break="no"/>ny become debtors to the party which would<lb/>back their paper, and occupy the position<lb/>which a debtor does to a creditor, which<lb/>was not a desirable one. The creditor con<lb break="no"/>trolled the debtor, and such he feared would<lb/>be their position with regard to Canada, if<lb/>that costly work were proceeded with, for<lb/>they would have to ask the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to endorse their paper. Such be<lb break="no"/>ing the case, the Opposition deserved well of<lb/>the country.<lb/>
            </p>


            <pb n="1871-03-28_Page_271"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_271.jpg"/>
       
       
            <fw type="num">272</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1871</fw>
            
            
            <p>[<persName ref="pers:BREC1">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>] The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber's imagination has enabled him to see the<lb/>grim skeleton of Confederation behind the<lb/>thin screen of the Railway scheme, and<lb/>gravely tell us that we will have to go to<lb/>Canada to get our paper endorsed. I ask<lb/>him does he really believe what he asserted?<lb/>Canada has quite as many responsibillities<lb/>already as she can bear. The improvement<lb/>of the canals, the construction of the Pacific<lb/>Railroad, the purchase and settlement of the<lb/>North west Territory, and other great de<lb break="no"/>mands upon her resources, will absorb all<lb/>her available resources for some years to<lb/>come. Although in favor of Confederation,<lb/>I would scorn to ask her to pledge her credit<lb/>for our proposed Railway. 
            </p>
        
      
            <p>[<persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName>] I tell<lb/>that hon. member and the hon. Leader of<lb/>the Government that there is not money<lb/>enough in the Treasury to purchase my<lb/>support as a journalist to Confederation.<lb/>The railroad will be a benefit to the country,<lb/>and so far from believing that it will con<lb break="no"/>duce to confederation it will be the best<lb/>means of keeping us out of it. [...]
               
          </p>
            <p>[...] But this Pictou
               
            <pb n="1871-03-28_Page_271"
               facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-28_Page_273.jpg"/>
               
               <fw type="dateline">1871</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">273</fw>
               
               Union with the Dominion, the price to be <lb/>paid us will be
               enhanced. Under any cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances no pressure can be brought
               to<lb/>bear on us from our Railway indebtedness<lb/>for thirty years, as the
               debentures will not<lb/>be redeemable until the expiration of that<lb/>time.<lb/> </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>