<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1873-05-02"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1873-05-02">02 May 1873</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1873">
               <title>The Parliamentary Reporter of Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly</title>.
          <date when="1873"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Examiner</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="152" to="154"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-02_Page_152.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-02_Page_154.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
      
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-08-16">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-08-16">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-02_Page_152">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-02_Page_152.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-02_Page_154">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-02_Page_154.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1873-05-02_Page_152"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-02_Page_152.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">152</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            
            <!-- IC, 2018-08-16, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day -->
            <!--<p>they who look best after their general<lb/>interests are best entitled to have their<lb/>support. He would, some time ago<lb/>have been unwilling to support the<lb/>resolution before them, but seeing<lb/>what the state of the Colony is, would<lb/>now feel it his duty to vote for it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOWA1">MR. HOWATT</persName>'S amendment was<lb/>then put and lost ; 2 for it and 24<lb/>against.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The main resolution was then car<lb break="no"/>ried—yeas 16, nays 10.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House then resumed, when the<lb/>Chairman reported from the Commit<lb break="no"/>tee one resolution agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD10">MR. A. C. McDONALD</persName> then said,<lb/>Mr. Speaker, during my election I ran<lb/>as an anti-Confederate. At that time<lb/>I did not believe the situation of the<lb/>country was such as it is. I was then of<lb/>the opinion that we would be able for<lb/>this year, and for some time to come<lb/>to carry on the business of the coun<lb break="no"/>try, and to meet the usual expendi<lb break="no"/>ture. Now we have to look at mat<lb break="no"/>ters as they are, and not as we sup<lb break="no"/>posed they were, and having done so<lb/>I feel it to be my duty to support the<lb/>resolution. As a public man I believe<lb/>my first duty is to consider what is best<lb/>for the country at large, and then act ac<lb break="no"/>cordingly. I have, as one, to consider<lb/>our embarrassed position, and act as I<lb/>believe will best promote the common<lb/>good. Reference has been made to<lb/>the Railroad ; all I have to say is that<lb/>the vote I gave then, I gave heartily,<lb/>and from the firm conviction that it<lb/>would be promotive of the best in<lb break="no"/>terests of the country. It is not worth<lb/>our while now to enquire what led to<lb/>the present difficulty, but I am per<lb break="no"/>suaded the uppermost idea in the mind<lb/>of those who originated and voted for<lb/>the Railway Bill, was the general good<lb/>of the country, and in voting for this<lb/>resolution I am sure it will prove to<lb/>be for the best interests, not only of my<lb/>constituents, but of the country at<lb/>large.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>The amendment of Mr. Laird was<lb/>put and lost. Yeas 16, nays 10.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOWA1">MR. HOWATT</persName> then moved his<lb/>amendment, which was lost. Yeas 2,<lb/>nays 24.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The main resolution was then car<lb break="no"/>ried on the following division :—<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Yeas —Messrs. J. C. Pope, Howlan,<lb/>Owen, T. Kelly, Lefurgy, A. J. Mc<lb/>Donald, Howatt, Holland, John Yeo,<lb/>F. Kelly, McLean, A. C. McDonald,<lb/>McEachen, J. A. McDonald, McIsaac,<lb/>Arsenault—16.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Nays—Messrs. Laird, B. Davies,<lb/>Callbeck, McNeill, Beer, Stewart,<lb/>James Yeo, L. H. Davies, Sinclair,<lb/>Rowe—10.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Adjourned until 10 o'clock to-mor<lb break="no"/>row.<lb/>
            </p>-->
            <head rendition="simple:centre">FORENOON SESSION.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, May 2nd.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hons. Pope, F. Kelly, Owen ;<lb/>Messrs. John Yeo and Arsenault were<lb/>appointed a Committee to prepare the<lb/>draft of an Address to the Lieutenant<lb/>Governor, praying His Honor that the<lb/>resolution contained in the Report of<lb/>the Committee of the whole House on<lb/>several despatches and other docu<lb break="no"/>ments, transmitted by message to the<lb/>House, on the 25th of April last, con<lb break="no"/>nected with the Confederation of this<lb/>Colony with the Dominion of Canada,<lb/>may be carried into effect.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. Mr. POPE</persName>, Chairman of the<lb/>Committee, reported the draft of an<lb/>Address to His Honor the Lieutenant<lb/>Governor, praying that His Honor<lb/>will be pleased to give effect to the<lb/>resolution adopted by the House.<lb/>Said Address is as follows :—<lb/>
            </p>
       
            <fw type="dateline">1873</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">153</fw>
           
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">To His honor W. C. F. Robinson,<lb/>Esq., Lieut. Governor and Com<lb break="no"/>mander in Chief in and over Her<lb/>Majesty's Island Prince Edward,<lb/>and the dependencies thereunto<lb/>belonging, Chancellor, Vice Ad<lb break="no"/>miral and Ordinary of the same,<lb/>&amp;c,m &amp;c.</hi><lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MAY IT PLEASE YOUR HONOR—<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House of Assembly having had<lb/>under their consideration several de<lb break="no"/>spatches and other documents trans<lb break="no"/>mitted by message to the House of<lb/>Assembly on the 25th day of April<lb/>last, connected with the Confederation<lb/>of this Colony with the Dominion of<lb/>Canada, came to a resolution on the<lb/>same, a copy of which is herewith sub<lb break="no"/>mitted.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House respectfully requests<lb/>that your Honor will be pleased to<lb/>give effect to the said resolution.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Address was then ordered to<lb/>be engrossed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Ordered that the same Committee<lb/>who prepared the Address be a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee to wait on His Honor with the<lb/>same.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>House in committee to take into<lb/>further consideration all matters relat<lb break="no"/>ing to roads and bridges.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD11">MR. A. J. McDONALD</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>After some time spent in Commit<lb break="no"/>tee, the Speaker resumed the Chair,<lb/>progress was reported, and leave ob<lb break="no"/>tained to sit again.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>House adjourned for one hour.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. Mr. POPE</persName>, as a member of the<lb/>Executive Government, presented a<lb/>message from His Honor the Lieut.<lb/>Governor, asking that the House, at<lb/>its rising to-day, do adjourn until the<lb/>12th inst.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. Mr. POPE</persName> presented return of<lb/>Sheriff of Queen's County for a mem<lb break="no"/>ber to represent the City of Charlotte<lb break="no"/>town.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
           
            <p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. Mr. POPE</persName> and Mr. John Yeo<lb/>conducted Hon. Mr. Brecken into the<lb/>House as the member so returned, who<lb/>being sworn in at the Clerk's table,<lb/>was introduced to the hon. the Speaker,<lb/>and took his seat.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Hon. Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—Mr. Speaker,<lb/>having been a few days outside of the<lb/>bar of this hon. House, and thereby<lb/>having had an opportunity of listening<lb/>to the debate, I now feel constrained<lb/>to express the hope that henceforth<lb/>our discussions may be more than ever<lb/>distinguished by calmness and forbear<lb break="no"/>ance. We have reached that period<lb/>in our history when we may well<lb/>pause, and review the past. We have<lb/>passed through an ordeal. We have<lb/>had our angry discussions, and in these,<lb/>I too, have taken my part. But we<lb/>are now on the eve of becoming a<lb/>part of the Dominion, our former sub<lb break="no"/>jects of contention —many of them at<lb/>least—were of small moment, they<lb/>may be compared to smelt fishing<lb/>when contrasted with the importance<lb/>of fishing in the deep blue sea. It<lb/>does not become us now at so impor<lb break="no"/>tant a crisis in our history, to belittle<lb/>one another, and thereby overlook the<lb/>true interests of the country. De<lb break="no"/>pend upon it, the Dominion will re<lb break="no"/>spect us in proportion as we respect<lb/>each other. In discussing such an<lb/>important question, I think it a great<lb/>pity that any allusion was made to<lb/>side issues. The School Question, for<lb/>instance, was dragged into the discus<lb break="no"/>sion. For my part I could not see<lb/>why it should have been referred to at<lb/>all. I am willing to forget and for<lb break="no"/>give, and to put my feet upon the<lb/>many calumnies and unjust reproaches<lb/>which were cast upon us ; and I be<lb break="no"/>lieve, now that Mr. Pope's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment has been allowed by Providence,<lb/>again to attain to power to show to the<lb/>people of this Island and the neighbour<lb break="no"/>ing Provinces, that the charges made<lb/>against that Government were untrue.<lb/>To show that notwithstanding all the<lb/>
            
            <pb n="1873-05-02_Page_154"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-02_Page_154.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">154</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
          
     late Government said about Mr. Pope 
     <lb/>
     and his friends not sending the Railway 
     <lb/>
     Bill to the people, yet they rushed the 
     <lb/>
     Branch Bill through the Legislature. 
     <lb/>
     and have let the contract, while not 
     <lb/>
     one, save Mr. John Yeo, opposed such 
     <lb/>
     a course. An evening or two ago, a 
     <lb/>
    few of us received invitations from  
     <lb/>His Lordship Bishop McIntyre to 
     <lb/>attend an examination at one of his: 
     <lb/>schools. We went, and I have under 
     <lb/>stood that the matter was brought up 
     <lb/>in this House. Has it come to this 
     <lb/>that a public man cannot be present 
     <lb/>at the examination of a school, where 
     <lb/>the pupils, mere youths, or lads, ex<lb break="no"/>hibited a knowledge that was exceed<lb break="no"/>ing creditable to their years, and an 
     <lb/>acquaintance with Euclid in the pro<lb break="no"/>blems they worked out which showed 
     <lb/>they possessed a knowledge of various 
     <lb/>branches that would do credit to a full 
     <lb/>grown man. It is time public men 
     <lb/>should rise above such narrow-minded<lb break="no"/>ness. As to the School Question, no 
     <lb/>Catholic ever spoke to me on that 
     <lb/>subject. I hope the time will soon 
     <lb/>arrive. when in our Legislative Halls, 
     <lb/>all political questions will be discussed 
     <lb/>without referring to Catholics and 
     <lb/>Protestants. Let us drop the hatchet, 
     <lb/>and henceforth, if any of us attend 
     <lb/>seminaries of learning, let us not do 
     <lb/>as the hon. member did with the 
     <lb/>speech of Col. Gray, which he circu<lb break="no"/>lated by the thousand, and won his 
     <lb/>election in consequence. Nor in the 
     <lb/>future, if public men attend examina<lb break="no"/>tions of schools, let not such a circum<lb break="no"/>stance be dragged into debate in the 
     <lb/>House of Assembly. I do hope the 
     <lb/>time for all such exhibitions has for<lb break="no"/>ever passed away. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">MR. LAIRD</persName>.—Mr. Speaker, when I 
     <lb/>
     came from Ottawa last spring, I made 
     <lb/>
     the same request in the Market Hall, 
     <lb/>
     which the learned Attorney General 
     <lb/>
     has made now. But how was my re<lb break="no"/>quest received? Was it taken in 
     <lb/>
     good faith ? No, I regret to say it was 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     not. On the contrary the hon. mem. 
     <lb/>
     her and his friends took it up as a 
     <lb/>
     party question, They discussed it as 
     <lb/>
     such, and dealt with it wholly as a 
     <lb/>
     party matter. For my part it was my 
     <lb/>
     most sincere and earnest desire that 
     <lb/>
     Confederation should have been dis<lb break="no"/>cussed and carried wholly upon its 
     <lb/>
     own merits. When I was away they 
     <lb/>
     had so much to say about me, that the 
     <lb/>
     grander and sublimer aspects of the 
     <lb/>
     question were entirely lost sight of. 
     <lb/>
     No doubt, Sir, it is a matter for regret 
     <lb/>
     that Confederation, pure and simple, 
     <lb/>
     was not considered wholly upon its 
     <lb/>
     merits. With respect to the learned 
     <lb/>
     Attorney General, during my canvass, 
     <lb/>
     Col. Gray brought him into my Dis<lb break="no"/>trict to curse me, even as Balax 
     <lb/>
     brought Baalam to curse a certain 
     <lb/>
     people, but be blessed me all the while, 
     <lb/>
     I really feel that the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     rendered me much service in my can<lb break="no"/>vass. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <!-- IC, 2018-08-16, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day -->
            <!--<fw type="num">1873</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">155</fw>-->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>