<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1868-03-09"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1868-03-09">9 March 1868</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1868">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1868, Being the Second Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1868"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Patriot" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="11"/>
<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="17"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-03-09_Page_010.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-03-09_Page_011.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-03-09_Page_017.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-11">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-03-09_Page_010">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-03-09_Page_010.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-03-09_Page_011">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-03-09_Page_011.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">
<pb n="10" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-03-09_Page_010.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">10</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">HON. Mr. HOWLAN</persName>.- </p>

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="11" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-03-09_Page_011.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">11</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p>
 But, Sir, had the late Government succeeded in 
<lb/>
 their plans, where would we be to-day? Why into Con<lb break="no"/>federation, and not in the proud position which we now 
<lb/>
 occupy. We might have been in the position that Nova 
<lb/>
 Scotia is now placed in. This is one of the reasons 
<lb/>
 why this Government stands so high in the estimation of 
<lb/>
 the people. They know that on this important question 
<lb/>
 they can trust us. The hon. member has said that there 
<lb/>
 was no political manliness in this Government. But, Sir, 
<lb/>
 where was the political manliness of the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. In 1865 Confederation was a question then 
<lb/>
 brought to their notice by the highest authority. Did 
<lb/>
 they come down with a measure upon the subject, or a 
<lb/>
 decisive expression of opinion? No! nothing of the 
<lb/>
 kind. They had men in that party who were determined 
<lb/>
 to carry it if they could. They knew also that the 
<lb/>
 Hon. Mr. Whelan was a Confederate, and doubtless 
<lb/>
 thought that his influence would secure a few votes in 
<lb/>
 favour of the measure from this side of the House, and 
<lb/>
 thus by obtaining a vote here and another there, they 
<lb/>
 hoped to succeed in forcing the measure upon this 
<lb/>
 country. But this question, I may state, will not be 
<lb/>entertained by any hon. member from the one end of our<lb/>party to the other.-The hon. the Leader of the Oppo<lb break="no"/>sition, in referring to Education, made quite a<lb/>circuit ; but, lawyer like, took care to express no opinion<lb/>of his own. I am surprised though that he never<lb/>before made the discovery that he so strongly sympathised<lb/>with the Catholics.<lb/>
</p>

<p>[...]</p>
 
<p>R. Gordon, Reporter. <lb/></p>

<pb n="17" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-03-09_Page_017.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">17</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BELL3">Mr. BELL</persName>—I do not wish, Mr. Chairman, to say much <lb/>
on this question; but it appears to me that parties in this <lb/>
House take great pleasure in raking up everything they <lb/>
can against each other. I have taken an active part <lb/>
in politics for some time, in connection with the Liberal <lb/>
party, and I think that they have always been the friends <lb/>
of the tenantry. There is one act of the Conservative <lb/>
party which I would like to notice—that is the bringing <lb/>
of the troops here. I feel pretty sensitive on this subject; <lb/>
it is not a very pleasant thing for a whole country to be <lb/>
branded as rebels. The Government of the day should <lb/>
have advised the people of the dangerous course they were <lb/>
pursuing. I do believe, and always have believed, that <lb/>
some of the members of the Government, then in power, <lb/>
had no other end in view than to bring the Island into <lb/>
Confederation. One prominent member of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment laid his schemes for that purpose, and he thought <lb/>
that by stigmatising us as rebels, the Home Government <lb/>
would be induced to force us into Confederation. The <lb/>
present party must, however, have the credit of getting the <lb/>
charges for the pay of the troops remitted. There is, also, <lb/>
a great deal of talk about the Land Purchase Act. The <lb/>
fact of the matter is, that this Act is not what it is said <lb/>
to be. If, when this Act first came into operation, the loan <lb/>
Bill had been passed, it might have been different ; but the <lb/>
Land Purchase Act, as it is to-day, is a failure. It is <lb/>
worse than paying rent. No active farmer will purchase <lb/>
his farm when he can invest his money to more advantage. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. LEADER OF THE OPPOSITION</persName>.—I have certainly <lb/>
been rather amused with the speaker who has just sat <lb/>
down. He got up to lecture us on political morality, and <lb/>
said that we should not impute motives ; but he soon got <lb/>
the fever on him, and he also imputed motives, for he <lb/>
said he believed the late Government got the Tenant <lb/>
League into existence for the purpose of forcing the Island <lb/>
into Confederation. It is not often that the hon. member <lb/>
troubles us, but when he gets up to lecture us on politi<lb break="no"/>cal morality he should be careful not to fall into the error <lb/>
which he condemns. The charge he attempts to sustain <lb/>
is altogether false. He also attempted to lecture the <lb/>
Conservatives because they did not warn the Tenant Lea<lb break="no"/>guers of the dangerous course they were pursuing. The <lb/>
same doctrine felt from the lips of the hon. member for <lb/>
Belfast, who was himself a Tenant Leaguer. All I can <lb/>
say to him is, that the Tenant League, from its first in<lb break="no"/>ception, was unconstitutional, if the doctrines which em<lb break="no"/>anated from that League are to be believed. The hon. <lb/>
member said that they were organized merely to form an <lb/>
Association. We know, Sir, that one of the conditions of <lb/>
membership in that Association was, that each member <lb/>
should subscribe for <hi rendition="simple:italic">Ross's Weekly</hi>—a paper that did a <lb/>
vast amount of injury to this Colony. The Tenant Lea- [...]</p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>