<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1873-05-19"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1873-05-19">19 May 1873</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1873">
               <title>The Parliamentary Reporter of Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly</title>.
          <date when="1873"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Examiner</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="162" to="163"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-19_Page_162.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
    
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-08-16">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-08-16">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-19_Page_162">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-19_Page_162.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1873-05-19_Page_162"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1873-05-19_Page_162.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">162</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1873</fw>
            
            <p rendition="simple:right">Monday, May 19th</p>
            
            
            <fw type="num">1873</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">163</fw>
            
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BREC1">Hon. ATTY. GENERAL</persName> said it was  
     <lb/>proposed to increase the toll upon ves<lb break="no"/>sels, for keeping up the Cape Race<lb/>Lighthouse, from one-sixteenth to one-<lb break="yes"/>twelfth of a penny per ton, and that<lb/>this toll would be collected from all<lb/>new vessels before they leave the har<lb break="no"/>bor. There is already a law upon<lb/>our Statute Book providing for the<lb/>collection of this toll, and this de<lb break="no"/>spatch merely asks for a small increase.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD11">MR. A. J. McDONALD</persName> said that the      
     <lb/>toll was regularly paid by all vessels<lb/>trading between the Dominion, and<lb/>Great Britain, as well as vessels sail<lb break="no"/>ing between this Island and Great<lb/>Britain, and was transmitted to the<lb/>English Board of Trade. If a vessel<lb/>leaves this Island for Great Britan<lb/>without paying the toll, she pays it on<lb/>her arrival there.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAIR2">Mr. D. LAIRD</persName> thought the Do<lb break="no"/>minion authorities would attend to this<lb/>matter on our entering Confederation,<lb/>and that there was no necessity for the<lb/>House to Legislate on the matter, un<lb break="no"/>der present circumstances.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Hon. ATTY. GENERAL</persName> said that the<lb/>Cape Race Lighthouse has not been<lb/>erected at the cost of the Dominion,<lb/>and that the toll would not go into<lb/>their treasury. At the same time, if<lb/>the Colony were in the Dominion, we<lb/>would not be asked to pass such a law<lb/>as this. If we go into Confederation,<lb/>it will be all right in reference to this<lb/>toll, and if we remain out, the pro<lb break="no"/>posed alteration in our present law<lb/>will take effect when the Bill is passed.<lb/>He would move the following resolu<lb break="no"/>tion:—<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That it is expedient to     
     <lb/>introduce a Bill to increase the toll<lb/>collected for the Cape Race Light<lb/>Duties, and to provide for the collec<lb break="no"/>tion in this Island of the said toll.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. B. DAVIES</persName> thought it prema<lb break="no"/>ture to attempt to legislate on a<lb/>matter of this kind on the eve of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, as it is a matter with which<lb/>the Dominion Government will have<lb/>to deal. It would be advisable to let<lb/>the question stand over till the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment have decided what they in<lb break="no"/>tent to do with reference to Confed<lb break="no"/>eration.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The resolution was then put and       
     <lb/>agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Speaker took the chair, and<lb/>the Chairman reported the resolution<lb/>agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Brecken, Messrs. A.J.       
     <lb/>McDonald and J. A. McDonald,<lb/>were, on motion, appointed a Commit<lb break="no"/>tee to bring in a Bill in accordance<lb/>with the said resolution.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Hon. ATTY. GENERAL</persName>, Chairman of<lb/>said Committee, presented said Bill,<lb/>and on motion, it was read a first time,<lb/>and ordered to be read a second time<lb/>to-morrow.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>House adjourned till ten o'clock to-<lb break="yes"/>morrow.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <!-- IC, 2018-08-14, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 
            <!--<p rendition="simple:right">Wednesday, May 21st.</p>-->
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>