<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1868-04-07"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1868-04-07">07 April 1868</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1868">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1868, Being the Second Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1868"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Patriot" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="146" to="148"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_146.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_147.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_148.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-11">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_146">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_146.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_147">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_147.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_148">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_148.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>
<div type="debate">

<pb n="146" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_146.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">146</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. LEADER OF THE OPPOSITION</persName>—I shall press my <lb/>
motion. It does seem to me unfortunate that extraneous <lb/>
matter is dragged into every subject which comes be<lb break="no"/>fore us, whatever the matter under discussion may be, <lb/>
whether it is the Land Question, the Barracks or the <lb/>
Fisheries, other questions are mixed up with it. The <lb/>
subject under consideration might be crowded into a <lb/>
nut shell, and therefore there was no necessity for the <lb/>
Attorney General to drag in the building of the Bar<lb break="no"/>racks or any other matter. I am prepared to justify <lb/>
the expenditure of the £12,000 laid out by the late <lb/>
Government in the erection of theses buildings. We <lb/>
are to look upon that sum as so much money expended <lb/>
to maintain British law and order, and to put down an <lb/>
association which, if it had not been checked in time, <lb/>
would have ended in open rebellion. The result of this <lb/>
state of things would be, that we would be placed <lb/>
where the people of this Colony do not wish to be—in <lb/>
the great Confederation. I move that the resolution <lb/>
be amended by striking out the words "and contingent <lb/>
expenses," because there is no necessity to pay a person <lb/>
one hundred pounds per year to take care of these Bar<lb break="no"/>racks. When the hon. member for Belfast (Mr. <lb/>
Davies) said the troops were brought here for the <lb/>
purpose of injuring the character of the people of this <lb/>
country, and thereby be the means of getting the Colony <lb/>
forced into Confederation, he stated what was politically <lb/>
untrue. He knows very well that there were gentle<lb break="no"/>men in the late Executive Council who were as much <lb/>
opposed to Confederation as he himself was, and who <lb/>
had a great deal more firmness than he has. Among <lb/>
those hon. members of that Council there was Mr. <lb/>
Henderson—there is not much of the Confederate in <lb/>
him, There was also another strong anti-Confederate, <lb/>
who is now in his grave, and who had more of the blood <lb/>
of a true patriot in his little finger than the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Belfast has in his whole body—I refer to the late <lb/>
James McLaren. This hon. gentleman who looked upon <lb/>
with confidence from one end of Queen's County to the <lb/>
other. He was respected by both Liberals and Con<lb break="no"/>servatives, by Catholics and Protestants ; in fact he <lb/>
was like Caesar's wife, above suspicion. He was no <lb/>
Confederate, Mr. Speaker. Will the hon. member <lb/>
say that John Longworth is a Confederate? No. <lb/>
Sir. He was the father of those strong resolutions <lb/>
which were brought into this House against Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, and much as I differ with him on that question, I <lb/>
believe him to be perfectly honest in his intentions. If <lb/>

<cb/> 

either of these gentlemen had had a shadow of a doubt <lb/>
as to the intentions of their party in bringing the troops <lb/>
to this Colony they would have vacated their seats in the <lb/>
late Executive Council. It is know that if that Coun<lb break="no"/>cil had opposed the calling in of those troops the Adminis<lb break="no"/>trator of the Government, for the time being, would <lb/>
have undertaken to do so, to maintain order and <lb/>
to uphold British law in the Colony. I too, have <lb/>
always said that I would ever by any means, by any <lb/>
back-stair work put Prince Edward Island into <lb/>
Confederation unless the majority if the people were in <lb/>
its favor. I would rather cut off my right hand than be <lb/>
guilty of such under-hand work as to legislate against the <lb/>
wishes of the people ; but, I presume, the hon. member for <lb/>
Belfast measures my corn by his own bushel. We, the <lb/>
members of the late Government wished to maintain law <lb/>
and order, and there was no other alternative, but to <lb/>
call in the troops. If the hon. member was opposed to <lb/>
Confederation, he has proved recreant to his principles, <lb/>
he has proved to be a traitor to his country. The late <lb/>
Government lost grounds at the late elections, not on the <lb/>
Confederation question, but because they opposed the <lb/>
Tenant League. What did the present Government do <lb/>
whenever they obtained the reins of power? They appoint<lb break="no"/>ed the late Editor of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Examiner</hi> to the highest office <lb/>
in the gift of the Colony, although that gentleman had <lb/>
denounced the Tenant League and was strongly in favor <lb/>
of Confederation. We know, Sir, that the Liberal <lb/>
Party promised the people to appoint no Confederate to <lb/>
office, and that they were also pledged against Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation; but a change came over the spirit of their dreams, <lb/>
and they gave the Queen's Printership to a strong Con<lb break="no"/>federate. The hon. Attorney General, who is the real <lb/>
Leader of the Government, pleads guilty to the soft im<lb break="no"/>peachment that the retaining of this Mr. Hayden in <lb/>
office as Keeper of the Barracks, is a political job. I <lb/>
give the hon member credit for being a moral man and <lb/>
well read in sacred scriptures, but because his brother <lb/>
is wrong should be go wrong also? WHat has the <lb/>
building of the Barracks to do with paying a man one <lb/>
hundred pounds per year to take care of these buildings? <lb/>
If the Barracks were left in a dirty state the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment could have remedied the matter by reporting to <lb/>
General Doyle who would very soon have caused the <lb/>
detachment to pay expenses because there is noting the <lb/>
military are so particular about as cleanliness. The <lb/>
officers in command will not allow a nail to be driven <lb/>
without cause, and they cause all damages to be repaired. <lb/>
But as these Barracks were a necessity, they should not <lb/>
go to destruction for want of proper care, they should be <lb/>
given in charge of the Drill Sergeants, who are best <lb/>
qualified for the offices of keepers. Have the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment got a bond from Mr. Hayden for the value of these <lb/>
buildings? If they are burned down when he is out <lb/>
fishing or when he is about his private business, is he <lb/>
bound to pay the Government £12,000? I very much <lb/>
doubt that any man would be fool enough to join him in <lb/>
giving that bond. The Government would be just as <lb/>
well secured in giving the property in case of one of the <lb/>
Drill Sergeants who would take just as much or more <lb/>
care of it than Mr. Hayden, but now comes in the ex<lb break="no"/>traordinary statement of the hon. member for Belfast, <lb/>
that if the Government had appointed a military man <lb/>
they would have to pay a Corporal's guard to relieve <lb/>
him. Well, that is paying a poor compliment to those <lb/>
who have been soldiers. If his theory is sound we will <lb/>
not want any more sergeants to red-coats anywhere, but <lb/>

<pb n="147" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_147.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">147</fw> 

I have no faith in his doctrine, we can get the Barracks <lb/>
looked after at a less cost than a hundred a year. I am <lb/>
not ashamed to own that the buildings cost a large sum <lb/>
because they were a necessity, but I do not wish them to <lb/>
be destroyed now. Although the Tenant League is dead <lb/>
outside of this House, it has a little leaven inside. But <lb/>
we hope that the sword will be turned into a reaping <lb/>
hook, and that these Barracks may yet serve some peace<lb break="no"/>ful and useful purpose. Possibly the building may be <lb/>
turned into a Normal School, goodness knows what is in <lb/>
store for us. If the Government can afford to give a <lb/>
hundred pounds a year for taking care of these Barracks, <lb/>
then can get them insured for a larger sum for the same <lb/>
money as they now pay the keeper. They can get as <lb/>
much insurance as they like, and, therefore, the build<lb break="no"/>ings might be converted into an elegant edifice for In<lb break="no"/>dustrial Exhibitions for the whole Island. For these <lb/>
reasons we should keep it insured, and therefore I will <lb/>
press my motion. <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. MCNEILL</persName>.—I do not care about voting money <lb/>
for these Barracks, but they contain a good deal of <lb/>
valuable property which might be destroyed or carried <lb/>
away by evil disposed persons if it is not placed under <lb/>
the care of a Keeper. I will support the resolution. As <lb/>
the Hon. Leaders of the Opposition has tried to justify <lb/>
the building of the Barracks, I will make a few remarks <lb/> 

<cb/>

on the subject, and show why certain individuals offered <lb/>
so much opposition to the Tenant League. I am sorry <lb/>
to mention the name of a gentleman who is no more, for <lb/>
I do not like to bring in the name of a person who can<lb break="no"/>not reply. The hon member (Mr. H.) has tried to prove <lb/>
that the troops were brought to this Colony on account <lb/>
of the doings of the League, but I can prove that they <lb/>
were brought here to serve the selfish ends of the Con<lb break="no"/>federate party in the ranks of the late Government. I <lb/>
took the late Mr. Whelan's paper for a number of years <lb/>
before there were any signs of a disturbance, and I can <lb/>
show that, by his writings, he encouraged the formation <lb/>
of an association of this kind. And not only did Mr. <lb/>
Whelan do so, but a Colonial Secretary, appointed by <lb/>
the late Government, did the same. Mr. Whelan said <lb/>
that if a few poor devils resisted the law they would be <lb/>
put down, but if the whole body of the tenantry resisted <lb/>
in a mass, something would be done, and the Land Ques<lb break="no"/>tion would be settled. The editors of both the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Islander</hi> <lb/>
and <hi rendition="simple:italic">Examiner</hi> were then strong Confederates, and ad<lb break="no"/>vocated these measures before the people thought of <lb/>
uniting for the purpose of obtaining free land at a reason<lb break="no"/>able cost. But whenever these two editors saw that the <lb/>
Tenant League declared against Confederation, they <lb/>
opened fire upon the association at once, and said that <lb/>
the troops must be brought here for the purpose of sup<lb break="no"/>pressing it. The late editor of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Examiner</hi> prophe<lb break="no"/>sied that an association would be formed, but when he <lb/>
found that it opposed Confederation, he declared that <lb/>
the late Government were quite justified in bringing the <lb/>
troops here for its suppression. But I do not intend to <lb/>
occupy the time of this hon House about this matter. I <lb/>
do not think these were the only causes for the opposi<lb break="no"/>tion manifested towards the Tenant League for I believe <lb/>
there were other causes. There was a long spell of <lb/>
tyranny and oppression, owing to the evils of the lease<lb break="no"/>hold system, and the people were deluded by political <lb/>
demagogues, till at last they were out of patience, <lb/>
and determined to arise in their strength and act for <lb/>
themselves. I think the best thing the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment could have done when their term of office had ex<lb break="no"/>pired, was to send the troops away, and either to destroy <lb/>
the buildings or take them down and use the materials <lb/>
for some other purpose. As matters are at present, <lb/>
something else must be done with these Barracks ; perhaps <lb/>
the best plan would be to turn them into a workhouse. <lb/>
But the building of them at all, under the circumstances, <lb/>
was a scandalous waste of the public money. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>.—I do not intend to take much <lb/>
time in making a reply to some statements made by hon. <lb/>
members on the other side of the House. The hon. <lb/>
Leader of the Opposition has attempted to justify the <lb/>
bridging of the troops to this Colony, and gave as a rea<lb break="no"/>son for so doing, that Mr. Henderson and other gentle<lb break="no"/>men were in the Government at the time, and that the <lb/>
troops were not brought here for the purpose of disgrac<lb break="no"/>ing the Colony, to get us forced into Confederation. <lb/>
But, I believe a party in the late; Government had those <lb/>
objects in view. There was a deep laid scheme among <lb/>
their supporters, which that Government were not fully <lb/>
aware of ; this was to stir up the people as they did, and <lb/>
get them to believe that an extraordinary settlement of <lb/>
the Land Question was about to take place, then to <lb/>
completely disappoint the tenantry, and thus drive them <lb/>
to resist the laws, if possible. They would then have a <lb/>
pretext for sending for the troops, and would try to <lb/>
make the world believe that the Colony was not ca<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="148" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-07_Page_148.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">148</fw> 

pable of governing itself. When all this was done they <lb/>
thought to have us forced into Confederation, but they <lb/>
were miserably disappointed. The people were satisfied <lb/>
with the provisions of the Land purchase Bill, and the <lb/>
members of the late Government knew this ; but they <lb/>
declared that the people were imposed upon by that Bill, <lb/>
and they made the whole country believe that by the <lb/>
great settlement of the Land Question, which they <lb/>
would bring about, the lands of the Colony would be <lb/>
bought at a price under which the poorest person would be <lb/>
enabled to become a freeholder. The supporters of the <lb/>
Conservative party especially believed that the Land <lb/>
Question was at last about to be settled, but what was <lb/>
the result ? The people saw that the Award was a <lb/>
mere sham, and they were exasperated. This was just <lb/>
what a certain party in the late Government wanted. <lb/>
They wished to stir up the people to revolt, to show the <lb/>
Mother Country that the people were not worthy of a <lb/>
Free Government, and that the Colony should be attach<lb break="no"/>ed to another country—in short that we should be forci<lb break="no"/>bly joined to the Confederation. They wished to prove <lb/>
that the Tenant League was a mean, disorderly society, <lb/>
but they knew that it was not. I supported measures <lb/>
which were calculated to relieve the people from the <lb/>
burden which has been imposed upon them. I do not <lb/>
act from selfish motives as they did, when they opposed <lb/>
the League. The Conservative party supported the <lb/>
proprietory faction, and they deceived the people, not <lb/>
only about free lands, but about the main object they <lb/>
had in view. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR2">Hon Mr. LAIRD</persName>.—The Government will expend no <lb/>
more on the Barracks than is absolutely necessary, for <lb/>
the current year. <lb/></p> 

<p>The question then being put on the amendment, the <lb/>
House divided as follows :—In favor of the amendment : <lb/>
Hons. Haviland, McAulay, Henderson, Kelly ; Messrs. <lb/>
Brecken, Owen, MacLennan, Ramsay, Howatt, Green, <lb/>
Prowse, Yeo—12 <lb/></p> 

<p>Against it—Hons. Coles, Hensley, Laird, Davie <lb/>
Callbeck, Howlan ; Messrs. G. Sinclair, P. Sinclair, <lb/>
Arsenault, MacCormack, MacNeill, Kickbam, Camer<lb break="no"/>on, Reilly, Bell—15 <lb/></p> 

<p>So the Resolution passed in the negative ; and the <lb/>
question being again put, it was resolved in the affirma<lb break="no"/>tive. <lb/></p> 

<p>House adjourned for one hour. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:right">I. OXENHAM, Reporter.<lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>