<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1871-03-17"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1871-03-17">17 March 1871</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1871">
               <title>The Parliamentary Reporter of Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly</title>.
          <date when="1871"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Examiner</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="193"/>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="201"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-17_Page_192.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-17_Page_200.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-07-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-07-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-17_Page_192">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-17_Page_192.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-17_Page_200">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-17_Page_200.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1871-03-17_Page_192"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-17_Page_192.jpg"/>
    
   
            <fw type="num">1871</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">193</fw>
            
            
            <p>[<persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. B. DAVIES</persName>]
     I consider it to be one of the most        
     <lb/>wild, reckless, and uncalled for undertakings<lb/>
      
      
            <cb/>
          
          
     ever thought of in a country situated as we are,          
     <lb/>and altogether beyond our means, and which<lb/>if ever carried out, will be an everlasting<lb/>charge on the community, especially on the<lb/>farmers. It is so far beyond our means that<lb/>I am convicned that the Government are fully<lb/>aware that they cannot accomplish one-third<lb/>of the undertaking without aid, and that aid<lb/>I have no doubt, they expect to obtain from<lb/>their friends in the Dominion, in exchange for<lb/>delivering the Island into their hands. Con<lb break="no"/>federation is, in my opinion, the object sought,<lb/>and not the prosperity of the Island. It is<lb/>Confederation, Mr. Chairman; it is the miser<lb break="no"/>able, grovelling, pecuniary interest of the<lb/>Government and its supporters, that is sought<lb/>to be advanced under the resolution now before<lb/>us, and not that of the people and this<lb/>country by a railroad. Mr. Chairman, neither<lb/>the Members of the Government nor their<lb/>supporters in this House were returned to<lb/>carry out this scheme. It was not monied<lb/>before the last election, and it was by mere<lb/>chance that the Government came into pow<lb break="no"/>er, and they do not possess the confidence of<lb/>their constituencies; and, under there cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, nothing but the confidence of<lb/>their being retained in power by the men who<lb/>had desired their party bring forward this undertak<lb break="no"/>ing. If they were conscious that the people<lb/>approved their conduct, they would not scorn<lb/>to consult them before committing the coun<lb break="no"/>try. Sir, I consider it discreditable to any<lb/>party, claiming a right to be respected, to at<lb break="no"/>tempt, as the Government are now doing<lb/>without the consent of the people, to mort<lb break="no"/>gage every man's farm, house and stock, to<lb/>pay the interest on this railroad.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <pb n="1871-03-17_Page_200"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-17_Page_200.jpg"/>
            
            
            <fw type="dateline">1871</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">201</fw>
            
            
            <p>[<persName ref="pers:SINC6">Hon. P. SINCLAIR</persName>]
     The hon. Atty. Gener<lb break="no"/>al speaks very loudly in his praise of the<lb/>country, and in showing its superiority over<lb/>the other colonies; but it is only a short time<lb/>since we heard him speak of our insignificance<lb/>of the greatness of the Dominion, of its stal<lb break="no"/>wart sons, &amp;c. Times have changes, and<lb/>it is we who are now great and prosperous<lb/>when compared with any part of Canada.<lb/>When we find men occupying high positions<lb/>changing with the wind, we cannot but feel<lb/>that they do not carry as much weight as<lb/>they otherwise would. It is no wander<lb/>that the hon. Leader of the Government<lb/>complains of the want of confidence in the<lb/>government when they wish to undertake<lb/>a work of such magnitude as the construc<lb break="no"/>tion of a railway, and attempt to force it<lb/>upon the people without consulting them on<lb/>the matter, and without giving them time to<lb/>consider their position and what they would<lb/>have to bear in consequence of it. If the<lb/>railway is to be built, it will involve us in<lb/>a taxation heavier than that of Canada, and<lb/>there will be nothing left us but to enter<lb/>the Dominion on any terms on which they<lb/>will accept us. England is taxed four dol<lb break="no"/>lars per head for her debt, Canada one dol<lb break="no"/>lar; and this Colony, if the railway is pro<lb break="no"/>ceded with, will be taxed over two dollars [...]
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>