<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1865-03-30"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1865-03-30">30 March 1865</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1864">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1865, Being the Third Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1865"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Protestant" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="65"/>
</bibl>

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_062.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_063.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_064.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_065.html"/>
</item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-08">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_062">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_062.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_063">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_063.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_064">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_064.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_065">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_065.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="62" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_062.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">62</fw>

<!-- DL 2018-06-08 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--my remarks without protesting against the manner in <lb/>
which this question has come before us. A subject of <lb/>
such importance as this should have been before us for <lb/>
years, and canvassed fully by the press and the people ere <lb/>
it was submitted to the House in the form which it <lb/>
assumes in the Report under discussion. It has not <lb/>
originated with the people, and almost the first clause <lb/>
which it contains deprives them of a right, as it provides <lb/>
places for at least 77 Councillors in a general parliament <lb/>
of the Colonies, where they will be independent of the <lb/>
people, and independent of the Crown. What authority <lb/>
had the delegates to go to Canada and thus sign away our <lb/>
rights ! They may say that they were invited by the <lb/>
Governor General. I say the Governor General has no <lb/>
power to interfere with the constitutional liberties of the <lb/>
people of the Colony. The people or their representatives <lb/>
alone should take up this question, and I look upon the <lb/>
action taken in this matter as a conspiracy against their <lb/>
privileges. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Col. SECRETARY moved an adjournment, and Hon. <lb/>
Mr. POPE opposed the motion. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. HOWAT.—Mr. Speaker ; I would prefer that we <lb/>
should finish the discussion this evening, as the advanced <lb/>
season renders it desirable that we should get through <lb/>
the business of the Session as soon as possible. As to the <lb/>
question of Union I may say that I am opposed to it on <lb/>
any conditions. The proportion assigned to us in the <lb/>
United House of Commons would deprive us of all <lb/>
influence in that branch of the Legislature, and our <lb/>
situation in the Upper Branch would render us more <lb/>
helpless still ; and the fact that some of the most able and <lb/>
intelligent men in the Island failed to obtain better terms <lb/>
at the Conference is as strong an argument as I require <lb/>
show me what our position would be under Confederation. <lb/>
The advocates of Union who have addressed you on the <lb/>
subject have endeavored to show that our taxes will not <lb/>
be increased when united ; but how, I would ask, could <lb/>
the expenses to be incurred for an army, a navy, and <lb/>
fortifications be met except by increase of taxation ? <lb/>
Increase of manufactures to any considerable amount would <lb/>
require a protective tariff, and our Legislature can adopt <lb/>
the principles of protection or free trade, as it suits them, <lb/>
just as well at present as they could under Confederation. <lb/>
The Hon. Solicitor General has remarked upon the benefit <lb/>
we should receive from Union by having an independent <lb/>
Legislature, but by the Report of the delegates I perceive <lb/>
that our legislation would require approval in Canada, <lb/>
and might afterwards be disallowed at Downing Street. <lb/>
As to the defences in Canada they would be no safeguard <lb/>
to us. The loyalty of some of the Canadians is not beyond <lb/>
doubt in my mind, and notwithstanding the allusion made <lb/>
by the Hon. Solicitor General to such men as Cromwell <lb/>
and Washington, I am disposed to judge of the future of <lb/>
some people by their conduct in the past. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. HOWLAN seconded the motion for an adjournment. <lb/>
It was unfair to press a division to night when some <lb/>
members had not spoken. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. POPE, though anxious to close the debate, was <lb/>
not disposed to treat the Minority unjustly, and would <lb/>
consent to the division being taken to-morrow evening. <lb/></p> -->

<p><hi rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, March 30.</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KELL1">Hon. Mr. KELLY</persName>.—Mr. Speaker ; In rising to address you <lb/>
on this all important subject of Confederation with Canada and <lb/>
the Lower Provinces, I find few arguments adduced in favor of <lb/>
it which have not been ably confuted by hon members already. <lb/>
Sorry I am to see as its advocates hon members in this House of <lb/>
whose talents and position in any other cause our Island might <lb/>
justly feel proud. I wish, Sir, to record my determined <lb/>
opposition to Confederation with Canada or with the Lower <lb/>
Provinces in any shape or on any terms. I feel convinced that <lb/>
any change in our constitution of the nature contemplated, would <lb/>
not operate beneficially to us. We are told that unless we <lb/>
surrender our separate constitution and place ourselves under the <lb/>

<cb/>

protection of the Canadian Legislature and the general <lb/>
Confederacy of Canada, we shall be overrun by, or absorbed <lb/>
into, the United States. I have no fear, Sir, that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the Stars and Stripes will interfere with us if we do not <lb/>
interfere with them, of which there is little prospect. I am glad <lb/>
to hear that New Brunswick has condemned the scheme—that <lb/>
Nova Scotia does not wish it, and if report speaks truly, New<lb break="no"/>foundland is not likely to adopt it—and it has been said that a <lb/>
majority of the people of Canada are themselves opposed to it. <lb/>
But I regret to hear some hon members of this House, while <lb/>
declaring their opposition to the measure, their willingness to <lb/>
adopt it, if more favorable terms could be obtained for the Island. <lb/>
I have no doubt, Sir, that the Canadian diplomatists having set <lb/>
their minds upon effecting their object, would, rather than fail in <lb/>
their pet scheme, yield whatever concessions might be required <lb/>
of them, knowing that their preponderance in the United <lb/>
Legislature would enable them to make whatever alterations in <lb/>
the terms they pleased, and that the mockery of a parliament <lb/>
then left us would render us powerless to prevent them, or even <lb/>
to complain. The hon and gallant Colonel, the member for <lb/>
Belfast, told us a few evenings ago, that in agitating for a repeal <lb/>
of the Union between England and Ireland, O'Connell would have <lb/>
gladly accepted a restoration to College Green of an Irish Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment similar in its constitution to that proposed for us at the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Conference. The hon member labors under a sad mistake. <lb/>
Sorry would a great man have been to have accepted for his <lb/>
country a Legislature less independent than that which she <lb/>
possessed before it was traitorously sold from her by a pack of <lb/>
wretches elected to the last Parliament of that ill fated nation <lb/>
through the influence of Pitt, Cornwallis and Castlereagh. A <lb/>
few of the names of those men I will read to you from a list <lb/>
which I hold in my hand, and although the descendants of some <lb/>
of them may retain the titles so villainously obtained, their <lb/>
names and races will be held in execration by Irishmen over the <lb/>
world to the end of time. The present question forcibly reminds <lb/>
me of the lament of your gifted countryman, Mr Speaker, when <lb/>
he refers to the sad time <lb/></p> 

<p><hi rendition="simple:centre">"When once beneath a monarch's feet <lb/>
Sat Legislation's sovereign powers." <lb/></hi></p>

<p>We have, Sir, sovereign legislative powers, whereby we can <lb/>
make our own laws and direct the application of our own monies <lb/>
among our own people at our own pleasure, and I hope the day <lb/>
is far distant when this, our Parliament, shall be converted into <lb/>
a Barrack or a Bank, or ourselves deprived of the constitutional <lb/>
privileges which we have so long enjoyed under the guarantee of <lb/>
the Imperial Government. The following list contains the <lb/>
names of some of the parties who sold Ireland, and the prices at <lb/>
which they consented to barter away the constitution of their <lb/>
country :—Lord Shannon, £45,000. Lord Loftus, £45,000. John <lb/>
Bingham, a Peerage, (Lord Wallcourt.) James G. Blackwood, <lb/>
a Peerage, (Lord Dufferin.) Joesph Cuffe, a Peerage, (Lord <lb/>
Tyrawley.) Richard Hare, a Peerage, (Lord Ennismore.) <lb/>
John Hutchinson, a Peerage, and a Regt., (Lord Hutchinson.) <lb/>
Wm. Handcock, a Peerage, (Lord Athlone.) Charles Coote, a <lb/>
Peerage, (Lord Castlecoote, since extinct.) Lodge Morris, a <lb/>
Peerage. William Newcomen, a Peerage for his wife. John <lb/>
Blaquiere, a Peerage, (Lord DeBlaquiere.) G. Cradock, a <lb/>
Peerage, (Lord Howden) John Longfield, a Peerage, (Lord <lb/>
Longueville.) Wm. Sandford, a Peerage, (Lord Mt Sandford.) <lb/>
Richard French, a Peerage, (Lord Ashtown.) John Stewart, <lb/>
a Lawyer, a Peerage, and a Judgeship, (Lord Clonmel.) <lb/>
Arthur Galbraith, an Attorney, a Baronetcy. Herculus <lb/>
Langrishe, a Baronetcy and £15,000. George Jocelyn, his <lb/>
brother made a Bishop, (Clogher.) Henry Alexander, his <lb/>
brother made a Bishop. John Bagwell, his son made a Dean, <lb/>
John Fitzgibbon, son of an obscure Roman Catholic Lawyer, <lb/>
made Lord Chancellor and Earl of Clare, an arrogant, cruel and <lb/>
overbearing tyrant. Isaac Corry, Chancellor of the Exchequer. <lb/>
John Toler, made L.C. Justice and a Peer, (the brutal Norbury.) <lb/>
Luke Fox, a Judge of the Common Pleas. Charles Osborne, <lb/>
Judge of the King's Bench. St. John Daly, Judge of the <lb/>
Common Pleas. Robert Johnston, Judge of the K. B. Wm. <lb/>
Johnston, a Baron of the Exchequer. James McClelland, Baron <lb/>
of the Exchequer. Wm. Smith of the Exchequer. <lb/>
R. Torrens, a Judge of the King's Bench. W. Vandeleur, a <lb/>
Judge of the Common Pleas. The lowest of the foregoing at a <lb/>
salary of £3,300 a year with over 20 country Judges at £600 a <lb/>
year. In addition to the foregoing I might give the names of <lb/>
over twenty-five of the Renegades who were made Colonels <lb/>

<pb n="63" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_063.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">63</fw>

in his Majesty's service, among whom is the name of the <lb/>
aforesaid Charles Coote to a Regiment taken from <hi rendition="simple:italic">Colonel <lb/>
Warburton</hi>,the grandfather, I believe, of our own hon member <lb/>
of that name from Lot 1 1, and who, to his lasting honor be it <lb/>
remembered, <hi rendition="simple:italic">"Castlereagh" could not purchase</hi>. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CONR1">Mr. CONROY</persName>.—Sir, I have considerable diffidence in <lb/>
addressing you on the subject before the House, on consequence <lb/>
of the very long and eloquent speeches we have listened to for <lb/>
the last three nights ; but I believe every gentleman in the <lb/>
House is expected to state his opinions on the matter before us. <lb/>
I do not hesitate to say that I am decidedly opposed to the con<lb break="no"/>templated Union. Two questions have occupied the most <lb/>
prominent part in the debate—Finance and Glory. I do not <lb/>
think that any person can be found so simple as to believe that <lb/>
the terms offered can be financially beneficial to us. We give <lb/>
up our present revenue for little more than half its amount. <lb/>
The sum we are to receive is not to increase with our increasing <lb/>
population. While we give to strangers the power to raise our <lb/>
duties of impost and excise to any amount they choose, we have <lb/>
no guarantee but that in a few years, if we entered this famous <lb/>
Confederation, they would be raised to three times the amount <lb/>
they are at present. As the wants of the Confederacy would <lb/>
require, taxation would be increased. And what control or <lb/>
management are we to have in our affairs? Having but five <lb/>
representatives in a Parliament composed of one hundred and <lb/>
ninety-four members, we might as well have none at all. But <lb/>
it is said that we need not fear, that taxation will be uniform, <lb/>
and when they tax us they also tax themselves in like manner. <lb/>
But, Sir, when I observe how unwilling we have been to increase <lb/>
our tariff in a trifling way, for the purpose of raising an amount <lb/>
which we absolutely required, I cannot see how we can agree <lb/>
to place such a power in the hands of persons who are so <lb/>
reckless in matters of taxation affecting themselves ; and as to <lb/>
the glory part of the scheme, as it is called, I have no sympathy <lb/>
with soldering unless it is required, nor would I agree to have <lb/>
our Militia sent to Canada; they had better stay at home and <lb/>
protect their own country ; and if, as it is said, the battle must <lb/>
be fought in Canada, all the better for us. With the protection <lb/>
and support of England we need not fear ; but if England is to <lb/>
abandon us, as some say she will, and the United States should <lb/>
make war on us, the more quietly we submit the better. That <lb/>
we could, by entering into the proposed Confederation, success<lb break="no"/>fully resist such a power is simply absurd. Sir, I have no fear <lb/>
that the Americans would come here to cut our throats or do us <lb/>
any serious injury. We have never done them wrong, they <lb/>
have no revenge to gratify ; and when I say this I must be <lb/>
understood as not expressing disloyal sentiments, for have I not <lb/>
read of English statesmen, even in Parliament, stating that their <lb/>
protecting these Colonies cost more than they were worth, and <lb/>
the sooner we were left to ourselves the better, showing their <lb/>
loyalty to us to be a matter of pounds, shillings and pence? So <lb/>
that if we are to be abandoned by the Mother Country, we should <lb/>
be permitted to look for protection in the place most beneficial to <lb/>
ourselves. A,d Sir, I have heard it discussed within the last <lb/>
few days by men of standing in this city, whether it would not <lb/>
now be more beneficial to this Island to enter into the great <lb/>
American Union than remain as she now is. And throughout <lb/>
the country—more particularly among the tenantry—the fear of <lb/>
American invasion is not as great as might be fancied. they <lb/>
say that whoever comes they cannot be worse off than they are <lb/>
at present, and, at all events, it will completely settle the Land <lb/>
Question. They say they have nothing to fight for, that they <lb/>
have little interest in the soil, that they have to procure a <lb/>
miserable livelihood by daily toil, that wherever they go they <lb/>
can earn a subsistence as easily as they do on this Island. And <lb/>
this being so, can you expect people so situated to risk their <lb/>
lives in defending the country? I will now quote from a <lb/>
respectable newspaper published in Montreal, wherein, reviewing <lb/>
a speech of the Hon. T.D. McGee, made in fence of the Irish <lb/>
residing in Canada from the charge of Fenianism, the Editor <lb/>
goes on to say that he fully coincides with Mr McGee that Irish<lb break="no"/>men in Canada have no sympathy with Fenianism, that they, <lb/>
beyond any other people, left their country on consequence of <lb/>
the land tenure, but in Canada they possessed all the advantages <lb/>
they sighed for in Ireland. The land they tilled was their own <lb/>
in freehold, and they would fight for its possession against all <lb/>
comers. This is what I want for our people ; give them their <lb/>
land in freehold, give them an interest in the country, without <lb/>
which no man can be truly loyal, and you will not want for <lb/>
Volunteers or Militia here to resist invasion. I have read that <lb/>

<cb/>

the Canadian Delegates, in excusing themselves for agreeing to <lb/>
such on outlay as would be caused by building the intercolonial <lb/>
railroad, said that they had to do so, as the Delegates from <lb/>
Nova Scotia and New Brunswick would have nothing to do with <lb/>
them before they agreed to build that road. And had our <lb/>
Delegates no public work, the performance of which they might <lb/>
urge should be agreed on before we entered into any terms? <lb/>
Why did they not press the extinction of the rental system as a <lb/>
work of necessity, and insist on receiving the means necessary <lb/>
for abolishing it? We have heard with what small courtesy the <lb/>
Leader of the Opposition was treated by the Delegates when he <lb/>
proposed a resolution asking for a sum to purchase the claims of <lb/>
the Proprietors. Some of the Canadian Delegates stated, I <lb/>
believe, when in Charlottetown, that the amount asked for by <lb/>
the Leader of the Opposition would be given, but the proposal <lb/>
was afterwards ridiculed. Sir, I want to say that the money <lb/>
could not have been better laid out ; it would have relieved this <lb/>
Island from a difficulty, social and political, which has been the <lb/>
great grievance of this country for the last fifty years, and has <lb/>
kept the country periodically in a state bordering on rebellion up <lb/>
to the present time. The amount asked would be scarcely <lb/>
distinguishable in the gross total, for the debt of Canada is <lb/>
counted by millions, and this, if we enter into the proposed <lb/>
Confederation, we must assist in paying. But we will have <lb/>
nothing to do with this Union. We can, by increasing our <lb/>
taxation for a few years, make every man in the Island a <lb/>
freeholder. Nor do I think the country would be displeased at <lb/>
our doing so, as it would be for the general advantage. I have <lb/>
spoken much longer than I intended, and will conclude by <lb/>
stating that I will vote for the amendment. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI1">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>— Mr. Speaker; the hon member from <lb/>
Tignish (Mr Conroy) has stated that unless we continue to <lb/>
enjoy British protection we shall be absorbed into the United <lb/>
States. I would be sorry that we should become a part of a <lb/>
country, the public debt of which, created without about four <lb/>
years, is already no less than three billions, or, in other words, <lb/>
three thousand millions of dollars. I am not apprehensive of <lb/>
such an event, for the British Government, under the pressure <lb/>
of public opinion in Great Britain, has declared we are willing to <lb/>
do our share in assisting your reasonable efforts to defend your<lb break="no"/>selves. I agree with those hon members who have argued <lb/>
Confederation involves increased taxation. But, Sir, we cannot <lb/>
remain long in our present isolated condition. Confederation <lb/>
or absorption into the States are the two alternatives presented <lb/>
to us. I should prefer to see this Island made, if possible, a <lb/>
free port, and thus, become a vast centre of commerce. As to <lb/>
the financial terms offered to us by the delegates at the Quebec <lb/>
Conference, I do not think that justice has been dealt out to us. <lb/>
We should receive half a million of dollars, for it must be borne <lb/>
i mind that for various reasons which have been referred to in <lb/>
this debate we will not receive benefits proportionate to those <lb/>
conferred on the other Colonies. In the present aspect of the <lb/>
matter, I would give a preference to a Federal Union with <lb/>
Great Britain to absorption or confederation. It has been <lb/>
objected by the hon members, Messrs. Sinclair and Howlan, that <lb/>
the delegation to Canada was unauthorized by the Legislature. <lb/>
Why, Sir, the Governments of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick <lb/>
did not convene their respective legislatures to sanction their <lb/>
delegations. As to the argument that the delegates exceeded <lb/>
their powers when they framed a constitution, they would be <lb/>
laughed at if they had not done so. We are not bound to <lb/>
accept it, and it is unfair to find fault with them on that account. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Mr HOWLAN</persName>.—The first delegation was authorized to discuss <lb/>
the subject of a Union of the Maritime Provinces. The Canadian <lb/>
delegation had an entirely different object. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon Solicitor GENERAL</persName>.—I cannot agree that under the <lb/>
system of Responsible Government the Executive had no power <lb/>
to send a delegation to confer with those sent from the other <lb/>
Provinces. The case would be different if the country were <lb/>
pledged to their proceedings. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Mr SINCLAIR</persName>.—I maintain that in adopting a constitution <lb/>
they exceeded their powers. This having been signed by three <lb/>
members of the Government, that body is, to a certain extent, <lb/>
pledged to it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MONT1">Mr MONTGOMERY</persName>.—Mr Speaker ; I have been informed <lb/>
and believe that the Report of the delegates is not approved by <lb/>
the people, and, in my own opinion, it would prove injurious to <lb/>

<pb n="64" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_064.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">64</fw>

the best interests of the Island. It calls upon us to increase our <lb/>
tariff and surrender our revenues. We are required to surrender <lb/>
revenues for 80 cents per head of the population according to <lb/>
the census of 1861. We do not receive fair terms. We have <lb/>
no minerals or territorial revenues as the other Colonies. We <lb/>
have benn told that we shall have free trade with all parts of the <lb/>
Confederacy. If so, we must raise whatever revenue we may <lb/>
require beyond the allowance accorded to us from the general <lb/>
Government, to which we ourselves contribute from our own <lb/>
resources. For myself and my constituents I shall oppose the <lb/>
scheme. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE7">Mr. McLENNAN</persName> –I shall not detain you long, Mr. Speaker. <lb/>
It is but dull debating when all are on the same side. I shall <lb/>
not enter into the question of defence,–that I shall leave for the <lb/>
hon and gallant Colonel. the member for Belfast ; that of finance <lb/>
to his colleague, the Hon Col Secretary. I am conscious that <lb/>
anything which I may say can have no effect in promoting or <lb/>
retarding the adoption of the measure. If that were not the <lb/>
case I would be inclined to enter more fully into the merits of <lb/>
this great question. Our action one way or the other can make <lb/>
little difference in the view of the opinion expressed by the people <lb/>
of New Brunswick at the hastings, and in Nova Scotia through <lb/>
the press. The protraction of this debate is, in my opinion, but <lb/>
a waste of public time and money. I would prefer that the vote <lb/>
were taken on the resolutions of the Hon Col Secretary seriatim. <lb/>
That would show the country how far their representatives would <lb/>
go in this matter. I am not prepared to go the extreme length <lb/>
of those who declare they are opposed to Confederation on any <lb/>
terms. I am of the same opinion as the hon member for the <lb/>
city, Mr. Davies, who believes that we are drifting into some <lb/>
kind of Union, that we should manfully grapple with the question, <lb/>
and, before any Union takes place, obtain the best terms possible. <lb/>
I believe that majority of the people of New Brunswick had not <lb/>
the subject fairly submitted to them in all its bearings when they <lb/>
voted against it ; nor was it the bulk of the intelligence of that <lb/>
Province that decided it. For myself I would not assume the <lb/>
responsibility of voting in favour of Confederation without first <lb/>
submitting it to the people. I believe my constituents are <lb/>
satisfied that I am acting an independent part in the matter. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WHEL1">Hon. Mr. WHELAN</persName> then addressed the House at con<lb break="no"/>siderable length, but he having mislaid the extract which <lb/>
he read, the Reporter is unable to give a connected report <lb/>
of his speech. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Mr. DUNCAN</persName> –I have a few words to say on this great <lb/>
scheme which is to make this a wonderful country, give us <lb/>
a market of three millions of people, and cheap teal all <lb/>
the way from China. All those who have been in <lb/>
this Colony heretofore, it appears, are but children in <lb/>
trade ; let them, however, only go up to Canada a few <lb/>
weeks and they will come down perfectly prepared to argue <lb/>
out any question on trade and finance. We are told that <lb/>
Confederation would promote manufactures in this <lb/>
Colony. Now, in my opinion, this Island can never <lb/>
become a manufacturing country, and I will give my <lb/>
reasons for so thinking. Supposing a person were to start <lb/>
a manufactory here, and another a similar establishment <lb/>
at Pictou, the former would have every market closed <lb/>
against him during the winter except this Island, and the <lb/>
latter would have all the country open to him the whole <lb/>
year round except this Colony in the winter season. The <lb/>
Pictou manufacturer could always send off his stock to <lb/>
market immediately while his Island rival would require <lb/>
to store his up for five or six months until the opening of <lb/>
navigation in the spring. The Islander, besides requiring <lb/>
an immense capital, the interest of which would diminish <lb/>
his profits, would frequently suffer from a fall of prices, <lb/>
causing a loss which might have been obviated by an open <lb/>
market. I do not think that any place which is closed in <lb/>
as we are for a part of the year has ever become a great <lb/>
manufacturing country. Then, again, the neighboring <lb/>
Province have other advantage over this Island for <lb/>
manufacturing. Canada has abundance of water power ; <lb/>
so have Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, and those latter <lb/>
Provinces possess coal likewise. But this Colony has no <lb/>
coal, nor has it iron, another advantage which its <lb/>
neighbor possess. This being the case, I think few <lb/>
manufactures can be carried on successfully here. The <lb/>

<cb/>

tanners may have a little export for a few years ; but <lb/>
the bank will soon be done, and then probably it will be <lb/>
better to export the hides and import leather. Our <lb/>
interest therefore, as we cannot manufacture, is to obtain <lb/>
our goods in the cheapest market. The other Provinces <lb/>
cannot compete with Britain in manufactures for many <lb/>
years ; but if we enter Confederation we may be forced to <lb/>
purchase within its bounds, on account of the high tariff <lb/>
on European merchandize. This would prove a loss to <lb/>
the Island in the following way : Suppose an article <lb/>
which could be purchased in Britain for £100 were to <lb/>
cost in Canada £118 ; but on account of the duty on the <lb/>
British article, it might be found more advantageous to <lb/>
purchase that of Canadian manufacture, the consequence <lb/>
being the loss of just £18 to the Island. This would <lb/>
be one of the benefits arising out of the boasted inter<lb break="no"/>colonial free trade ! By remaining as we are, the people <lb/>
of this Colony, generally speaking, will obtain their <lb/>
goods, even after paying a moderate duty to be expended <lb/>
among themselves, at a cheaper rate than they would <lb/>
under Confederation. But there are certain articles, such <lb/>
as tea, which can never be produced in these Provinces ; <lb/>
and which, under the Canadian tariff, would cost the <lb/>
people here much more than at present. Again, we are <lb/>
told that if we enter Confederation our fisheries will be <lb/>
developed. People, it is said, will come here from Canada <lb/>
to fish. This is a strange argument, when it is known <lb/>
that the Canadians already export enough fish to supply <lb/>
all British America.Herrings wehave not to spare ; <lb/>
these will have to be procured at the Magdalen Islands, a <lb/>
place which, though it has been basking for a long time <lb/>
under the sunshine of the Canadian Government, does not <lb/>
show many signs of progress. Everything which can be <lb/>
exported from this Island Canada produces, therefore no <lb/>
trade of any importance can spring up between this <lb/>
Colony and that Province. Notwithstanding this, I <lb/>
suppose we must contribute to build the Intercolonial <lb/>
Railway. The only article I see that we have got to send <lb/>
to Canada is oysters. Evidently, the Colonial Secretary <lb/>
has been very considerate in bringing in a Bill to encourage <lb/>
the planting of oysters, as it seems to me that we will <lb/>
have nothing else to send up to Canada on theIntercolonial <lb/>
Railway. Then, again, there is the matter of defence. <lb/>
It is stated that the police force which Canada has on the <lb/>
frontier this winter to prevent border raiding will cost a <lb/>
million of dollars. We are now in the Union, our <lb/>
proportion of that sum, according to the population, would <lb/>
be £768. But the general defences of Canada, according <lb/>
to Colonel Jervois, are to cost$ 6,500,000. In Confed<lb break="no"/>eration this Island would have to bear its share of this <lb/>
expense, one which, in the present circumstances of our <lb/>
people, they are altogether unable to afford. Another <lb/>
objection which I have to the Quebec scheme is, that it <lb/>
would allow us only about £35,000 for local requirements, <lb/>
and this too a <hi rendition="simple:italic">fixed</hi> sum, while our wants would yearly <lb/>
increase ; perhaps the Canadians thought that under such <lb/>
a scheme they would <hi rendition="simple:italic">decrease</hi>.(Laughter) Our <lb/>
Revenue for last year was about £65,000, and deducting <lb/>
the sum to be received from this amount, shows that our <lb/>
loss under our own tariff would be £30,000. But besides <lb/>
this we would have to bear our proportion of building the <lb/>
Intercolonial railway, enlarging the canals, and furthering <lb/>
other public works, which would increase our taxation, <lb/>
and do us no good, but rather an injury by drawing away <lb/>
our people to labor upon them. Again, the "glory <lb/>
argument" is one which the advocates of Confederation <lb/>
never fail to bring forward. We are to become agreat <lb/>
nation, but how this is to be affected the promoters of the <lb/>
scheme scarcely understand themselves. One of the <lb/>
advantages of it is, that our members of Parliament will <lb/>
go to live at Ottawa, and we will be left here to pay <lb/>
them ! We are told also that ouryoung men will rise to <lb/>
be chief justices in Canada. They need not deceive them<lb break="no"/>selves, for none but those belonging to Canada will stand <lb/>
much chance of attaining to such distinction. The Local <lb/>
Legislature, which the QuebecReport contemplates to <lb/>

<pb n="65" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-30_Page_065.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">65</fw>

leave us, would be little better than a town council ; we <lb/>
would have this building here merely to look at. As to <lb/>
the General Legislature I consider the representation in it <lb/>
allowed to this Island unfair and unjust. I think the four <lb/>
Lower Provinces, at least, should have as many members <lb/>
in the Upper Branch as Canada. The five representatives <lb/>
allotted to us in the Lower House would not give this <lb/>
Colony much influence there ; but as our population will <lb/>
not increase so rapidly as that of Canada, there is a <lb/>
prospect, through the operation of one clause in the <lb/>
Report, that our five representatives would dwindle down <lb/>
to three. Taking all these points into consideration, <lb/>
therefore, it is clear to me that we have nothing to gain <lb/>
but much to lose by adopting the Quebec scheme. <lb/></p> 

<p>Adjourned. <lb/></p> 

<!-- DL 2018-06-08 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>FRIDAY, March 31. <lb/></p> 

<p>Debate on Union of Colonies resumed. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. COLES.— Mr. Speaker: As leader of the <lb/>
Liberal party of this Island, I felt in a peculiar position <lb/>
while attending the Conferences on the question of <lb/>
Colonial Union now before the House, I felt that in <lb/>
acting as a Delegate I had not my own interest merely to <lb/>
look to, but that of a party who have acknowledged me <lb/>
as their leader for nearly eighteen years. And now, Sir, <lb/>
in addressing you I desire to make such explanations as <lb/>
may satisfy my constituents and the party with whom I <lb/>
am connected, in regard to the course which I have pur<lb break="no"/>sued on this question. Explanations of this nature may <lb/>
fairly be expected from me, since I am the only Delegate <lb/>
in this House opposed to the Confederation Scheme of the <lb/>
Quebec Conference—being one against four. It has been <lb/>
stated by former speakers that we all agreed to the scheme <lb/>
while at the Conference. I object to this statement. I <lb/>
admit that we were all unanimous in passing the first <lb/>
resolution of the Report ; but it was only with the under<lb break="no"/>standing that the details of the scheme were to be just to <lb/>
the several Provinces. Those who affirm that there was <lb/>
unanimity at the Conference ground their assertion, I <lb/>
believe, on several speeches delivered at evening meetings. <lb/>
But, Sir, I contend that an occasion graced with the pre<lb break="no"/>sence of ladies—such being the case when I spoke at <lb/>
Ottawa—was not the proper place to attack any person, <lb/>
or take strong exception to any vote passed at the Confer<lb break="no"/>ence. I did not do so then ; but at the Conference a few <lb/>
days before, I said that if the grant for the purchase of <lb/>
the lands of this Colony was not conceded, they might as <lb/>
well strike Prince Edward Island out of the Report alto<lb break="no"/>gether. The public men of Canada knew my views on <lb/>
the subject : this is evidenced by a paragraph which lately <lb/>
appeared in the Toronto Globe, a paper under the con<lb break="no"/>trol of the Hon. George Brown. The Globe says :— <lb/></p> 

<p>" The anti-Confederation papers at Halifax are making much <lb/>
of the fact that two of the Prince Edward Island delegates who <lb/>
were at the Quebec Conference have, since their return home, <lb/>
declared against the Confederation scheme. These gentlemen <lb/>
are the Hon. E. Palmer, Attorney General in the present <lb/>
Government, and the Hon. George Coles, a leading member of <lb/>
the Opposition. The attitude assumed by these gentlemen is <lb/>
but what was to have been anticipated from expressions made <lb/>
by them while in Canada, so that their hostility to Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion is not any indication of the way in which the scheme has <lb/>
been received by the people of the Provinces. The gentlemen <lb/>
had their minds made up before their constituents had heard the <lb/>
details of the Quebec scheme at all. " <lb/></p> 

<p>Even my speech at Ottawa did not give satisfaction to <lb/>
the supporters of Confederation in Canada, for after<lb break="no"/>wards, the brother of the proprietor of the Toronto Globe <lb/>
came to me, at Toronto, and desired that I would not <lb/>
persevere in the sentiment to which I had given <lb/>
utterance, namely, that the scheme would require to be <lb/>
submitted to the people for their approval. All that I <lb/>
said on that occasion which can be construed as favorable <lb/>
to the series of resolutions passed at the Quebec Confer-<lb break="maybe"/> </p> 

<p>17 <lb/>

<cb/>

ence, is, that it was creditable to the delegates from so <lb/>
many Provinces that they could agree to draw up such a <lb/>
Report. I still hold to that opinion ; and the British  <lb/>
Government has also acknowledged that it was a credit<lb break="no"/>able Report. If the people, I remarked, were satisfied  <lb/>
with the scheme, I had nothing more to say on the subject. <lb/>
But that I was personally dissatisfied with the new Con<lb break="no"/>stitution is clear from the fact that I refused to sign it. <lb/>
Before I left Canada, the Secretary of the Conference <lb/>
came to me, supposing probably that I was opposed to <lb/>
the Report, and asked me if I would sign the document. <lb/>
I said no. He then answered that if I should agree to <lb/>
sign it he would send it down to Prince Edward Island. <lb/>
I said, " you need not trouble yourself. " I may also <lb/>
mention that Hon. Mr. Gray of New Brunswick, in one of <lb/>
his speeches after his return from Canada, stated that all <lb/>
the delegates at the Conference had signed the Report, <lb/>
and would be bound in honor to support it. This, I <lb/>
thought, was going too far, so I wrote a letter to the <lb/>
newspapers here contradicting the statement, and showing <lb/>
that it was not correct at least as regarded myself. And, <lb/>
Sir, we have been informed during this debate that two <lb/>
others of the delegates from this Island have not signed the <lb/>
document. The absence of their signatures, however, is <lb/>
a matter of little consequence, as they have agreed to the <lb/>
Report, one of them having broadly declared that its <lb/>
principles are just and liberal to Prince Edward Island. <lb/>
It was understood that the proceedings at the Conference <lb/>
should be secret ; but they have been alluded to by <lb/>
delegates at other places, therefore there can be very little <lb/>
impropriety in referring to them in this discussion. I <lb/>
may also mention here that when the proposition in favor <lb/>
of secrecy was first made at the Charlottetown Conference, <lb/>
I objected to it, but stood alone in my opposition. I <lb/>
was then allowed to state the fact to my con<lb break="no"/>stituents. I make these explanations, for it may be <lb/>
necessary in the course of my remarks to refer to the <lb/>
proceedings at the Conference in self vindication. Only <lb/>
two of us, I believe, who were delegates to Quebec, object <lb/>
to the terms of the Report. For this opposition we have <lb/>
been charged as being almost traitors. Indeed it has <lb/>
been affirmed that Anti-unionists are guilty of combining <lb/>
with Americans against British interests. Hear what the <lb/>
Hon. D'Arcy McGee said in the Canadian Legislature on <lb/>
this subject. During the course of his speech on the <lb/>
Confederation question, in replying to some interruption <lb/>
from the opposition benches, he remarked :— <lb/></p> 

<p>" The hon. member for North Hastings Mr. (T. C. Wallbridge) <lb/>
seemed to repudiate the idea that American influence had any<lb break="no"/>thing to do with the result of the New Brunswick elections. He <lb/>
had to tell that hon. gentleman that one of these successful can<lb break="no"/>didates was agent for the American line of steamers, the <lb/>
International line, which did all the carrying trade to New <lb/>
Brunswick, and here was not a pound of the stock of that <lb/>
Company held in New Brunswick. (Hear, hear.) It was in  <lb/>
point of fact a fight—a fair stand-up fight of Yankee interests <lb/>
on the one side and British interests on the other ; and those <lb/>
who were rejoicing over Mr. Tilley's defeat were in reality <lb/>
rejoicing over the defeat of British interests. It was a contest <lb/>
between prejudice and patriotism ; between ignorance and intel<lb break="no"/>ligence ; between Yankee influence and the broad national <lb/>
principles of British North American policy. (Hear, hear.) <lb/>
Those who rejoiced over this state of things might congratulate <lb/>
themselves if they chose; but it was for the House to stand by <lb/>
the true public opinion of the country. It was for us to show an <lb/>
example of firmness and good faith in carrying out this scheme. <lb/>
It was for us to shew the Empire that we were determined o <lb/>
adhere to our original resolution and that we were not people <lb/>
who would forget our determination in a few days or a few <lb/>
weeks. " (Cheers.)  <lb/></p> 

<p>I deny these charges. I believe that the Anti-unionists <lb/>
are just as loyal as any Unionist can be. I feel that my <lb/>
loyalty is equally as sincere as that of those who so <lb/>
zealously advocate the Quebec scheme, for I have yet to <lb/>
learn that Great Britain has said we must go into <lb/></p>-->
</div> </body> </text> </TEI>