<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1866-05-08"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1866-05-08">8 May 1866</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1866">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1866, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1866"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Examiner" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="54"/>
<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="121"/>
<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="156"/>
</bibl>
 
<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_054.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_110.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_111.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_112.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_113.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_114.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_115.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_116.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_117.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_118.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_119.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_120.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_121.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_151.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_152.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_153.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-09">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>

<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_054"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_054.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_110"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_110.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_111"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_111.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_112"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_112.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_113"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_113.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_114"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_114.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_115"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_115.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_116"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_116.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_117"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_117.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_118"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_118.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_119"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_119.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_120"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_120.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_121"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_121.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_151"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_151.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_152"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_152.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_153"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_153.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_154"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_154.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_155"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_155.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_156"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_156.jpg"/></surface>

</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="54" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_054.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">54</fw>

<!-- DL 2018-06-10 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>54 PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER. 1866 <lb/></p> 

<p>The following Committee was then appointed to select such <lb/>
accounts as should be published in the Appendix to the Jour<lb break="no"/>nals, viz.: Hons. Messrs. Pope, Hensley, Longworth. <lb/></p> 

<p>On motion of the Hon. Leader of the Government, the House <lb/>
resolved itself into a Committee of the whole on the Des-<lb break="maybe"/>patches. <lb/></p> 

<p>A debate then ensued, and was kept up till a very late <lb/>
hour, on the subject of the Resolutions submitted by the Hon. <lb/>
Leader of the Government; in amendment to which, the Hon. <lb/>
Mr. Whelan submitted the following, viz:— <lb/></p> 

<p>Resolved, as the opinion of this House, that the Confederation of <lb/>
Her Majesty's American Colonial Possessions would be—while in <lb/>
conformity with Her Majesty's frequently expressed desire—con- <lb break="maybe"/> ducive to their welfare, individually and generally. And this House <lb/>
believes that a plan of Confederation might be so framed as not to <lb/>
involve the sacrifice of any material interesto n the part of any Pro<lb break="no"/>vince; but inasmuch as the people of Prince Edward Island do not <lb/>
appear to be prepared to regard with any favor the project of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, it is unwise to press it upon public attention, as its dis<lb break="no"/>cussion is only calculated to produce excitement and apprehension, <lb/>
without reasonablc cause. <lb/></p> 

<p>And further Resolved, as the opinion of this House, that there <lb/>
should be no vote passed by the Legislature of this Colony in favor <lb/>
of a Confederation of the Provinces until the people shall first be <lb/>
afforded an opportunity of pronouncing their judgment on the ques<lb break="no"/>tion at a general Election. <lb/></p> 

<p>Progress was reported. <lb/>
House adjourned. <lb/></p> -->

<head rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, May 8.</head><lb/>

<p>[...]</p>

<p>The adjourned debate on the subject of Confederation was re<lb break="no"/>sumed at the hour of 5 o'clock in the afternoon, and kept up with <lb/>
much interest till after midnight. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Sol. General opened the debate by resuming his speech <lb/>
which he had commenced in the forenoon, and spoke for nearly two <lb/>
hours. <lb/></p> 

<p>He was followed by the Hon. Mr. Coles, who also spoke at great <lb/>
length. <lb/></p> 

<p>During the debate on that great and momentous question, a <lb/>
most every hon. member of the House expressed his views on the <lb/>
subject, all of whom were present excepting the Hon. Colonial <lb/>
Secretary, absent from the Island on the Delegation to Brazil, the <lb/>
West Indian Islands, and Mexico. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. Cole, in the course of debate, remarked that had he <lb/>
been consulted in framing the Resolutions, he would have suggested <lb/>
an alteration in that which stated, that any Federal Union of the <lb/>
British Provinces which would include Prince Edward Island could <lb/>

<cb/> 

ever be accomplished upon terms that would prove advantageous to <lb/>
the best interests of the latter; but although that Resolution was <lb/>
not worded exactly as he would like to see it, yet, from the state<lb break="no"/>ments of one of the leaders of the Government in Canada, Mr. <lb/>
Cartier, to the effect, that the Resolutions at the Quebec Confer<lb break="no"/>ence in 1864 should not be altered; and also statements published <lb/>
in Quebec reflecting the views of the Government of that country <lb/>
on the question of Union, to the effect, that should England favor <lb/>
the Resolutions of the House of Assembly of Nova Scotia, to the <lb/>
prejudice of the Quebec Scheme, she could not hold Canada against <lb/>
her will. With such statements as these before him, he felt bound <lb/>
to support the Resolutions, as submitted by the Hon. Leader of the <lb/>
Government, as there appeared to be no hope of getting any modifi<lb break="no"/>cation of the Quebec Report. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Sinclair, while expressing himself pleased with the Resolu<lb break="no"/>tions submitted against Confederation, thought the language in the <lb/>
second Resolution almost too strong. He believed terms could be <lb/>
given which would justify P. E. Island in going into a Federal <lb/>
Union, but, at the same time, he firmly believed such terms never <lb/>
would be given to this Colony. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Brecken also said, in his speech, that he would not go so far <lb/>
as to say that a Union of the Colonies, on terms advantageous to P. <lb/>
E. Island, was a matter of impossibility; but from the present con<lb break="no"/>struction of the question, as advocated by the supporters of the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Report, he felt it his duty to give the resolutions in question his <lb/>
hearty support. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Leader of the Government admitted that the paragraph in <lb/>
question was worded in very strong terms, and had he consulted his <lb/>
own individual views on that point, he would have modified it. <lb/>
Last year he admitted the principles of a Union in the abstract; <lb/>
and he still thought that terms might be proposed which would be <lb/>
advantageous to this Island; but such terms could not be had, and <lb/>
in consequence of the very extraordinary course pursued with re<lb break="no"/>gard to this question in Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, it behoved <lb/>
us to resist everything in the shape of a Union, lest we might be <lb/>
committcd to the Quebec scheme. He believed nineteen out of <lb/>
every twenty of the people of this Island were opposed to Union at <lb/>
any kind with Canada. He, therefore, conceived it to be his duty <lb/>
in deference to their wishes, and to secure a strong vote in this <lb/>
House; to pursue the course he had done. At the same time, he <lb/>
must say, expressing his own opinion, he wished the second Resolu<lb break="no"/>tion were struck out. <lb/></p> 

<p>The question was then put on the Hon. Mr. Whelan's Resolutions <lb/>
in amendment to the Resolutions submitted by the Hon. Leader of <lb/>
the Government, and negatived on the following division:— <lb/></p> 

<p>For Hon. Mr. Whelan's amendment—Hons. E. Whelan Col. <lb/>
Gray, Sol. General, Davies, Kaye Messrs. McLennan, and Green—7. <lb/></p> 

<p>Against it—Hons. J. C. Pope, the Speaker, Longworth, Coles, <lb/>
Warburton, Thornrton. Hensley, Kelly, Laird, McEachen; Messrs. <lb/>
Howat, Brecken, Duncan, Haslain, Ramsay, Montgomery, Howlan, <lb/>
Conroy, Sutherland, Walker, Sinclair—21. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Resolutions of the Hon. Leader of the Government were ac<lb break="no"/>cordingly reported to the House agreed to. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Sinclair then submitted the following Resolution:— <lb/></p> 

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That inasmuch as the will be a generrl election this <lb/>
summer, it is, therefore, inexpedient for the Government to appoint <lb/>
any farther delegations on the subject of Colonial Union or Confede<lb break="no"/>ration, or to take any action calculated to commit the people of this <lb/>
Colony to any scheme of Union until authorized by the people and <lb/>
sanctioned by their Representatives, returned at said general Elec<lb break="no"/>tion." <lb/></p> 

<p>The supporters of the Government on that question contended that <lb/>
the above Resolution was uncalled for, inasmuch as hon. members <lb/>
of the Executive, in their places on the floor of that House, had <lb/>
during the debate just ended, declared that the Government would <lb/>
take no action whatever on the subject, and that therefore it would <lb/>
be unfair to throw a doubt on their expressed declaration. <lb/></p> 

<p>The supporters of the resolution contended that their object was <lb/>
to arm the Government against making any concessions that might <lb/>
lead to the appointment of any delegation tending to commit the <lb/>
people of the Colony to any measure not sanctioned by their Repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives. <lb/></p> 

<p>After considerable debate on the subject, the question was put <lb/>
and the Resolution negatived on the following division, viz:— <lb/></p> 

<p>For Mr. Sinclair's Resolution—Hons. Messrs. Coles, Laird War-<lb break="yes"/>burton, Hensley, Thornton, Kelly, Messrs. Sinclair, Howlan, Howat, <lb/>
Walker, Sutherland, Conroy, —12. <lb/></p> 

<p>Against it— Hons. J. C. Pobe. Col. Gray, Sol. General, Whelan, <lb/>
Kaye, Longworth, Davies, McEachen, Messrs. Duncan, Yeo, Has-<lb break="yes"/>lam, Montgomery, Ramsay, McLennan, Green, Brecken—16. <lb/></p> 

<p>House adjourned. <lb/></p>

<pb n="110" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_110.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">110</fw>

<!-- DL 2018-06-10 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--are strong; but, perhaps, it is necessary that they should <lb/>
be so. If the people wish for loufederntion at the next <lb/>
election, well and good; but I would have nothing to do <lb/>
with it at present. We are not offered anything to induce <lb/>
us to go into the Union. We would get eighty cents per <lb/>
head, and never to increase. All the Colonies are progress<lb break="no"/>ing. and why should not this Island do so too. We need <lb/>
not, so far as I can see, expect fair play if we go into the <lb/>
Union, and I will, therefore, support the Resolutions in<lb break="no"/>troduced by the Hon. the Leader of the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. HOWLAN: It is very amusing to listen to the <lb/>
Confederationists. They are not in favour of Confederation <lb/>
on the terms of the Quebec report at all—not they. We <lb/>
are to propose our own terms—to say what we will do and <lb/>
what we will not do—but hear the Resolution which they <lb/>
introduced last year:— <lb/></p> 

<p>"RESOLVED, That the Report of the Conference of Delegates from <lb/>
the British North American Provinces and Colonies held at Quebec, <lb/>
in October last, taken as a whole, contains a declaration of principles <lb/>
—as the basis of a Federal Union—which this House considers just to <lb/>
the several Provinces and Colonies." <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. WHELAN: That is not fair. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. HOWLAN: It is quite fair; I have listened to <lb/>
the speech of the hon. member (Hon. Mr. Whelan) atten<lb break="no"/>tively, and I perceive that his views have undergone a <lb/>
change since last year. It is very gratifying to know that <lb/>
he has seen the error of his ways. The advocates of Union <lb/>
desire something more this year than we would get by the <lb/>
Quebec Scheme. Now, suppose that a change has taken <lb/>
place. and no basis is laid down with regard to the financial <lb/>
part of the Scheme, what would our position, or what would <lb/>
our influence be? I might refer to Rhode Island, but that. <lb/>
is an old story now. It would be said, " Who are you <lb/>
that attempt to raise your head? A little isolated place <lb/>
like Prince Edward Island attempting to raise your voice!" <lb/>
Some say now, " What! do you suppose that little Prince <lb/>
Edward Island will be allowed to stand in the way of this <lb/>
magnificent Union?" Then, why ask us to say yes or no? <lb/>
Why sit here discussing the question when members are so <lb/>
anxious to get home. It is said that we are only 80,000 <lb/>
people—that we are not able to protect ourselves—and, <lb/>
therefore, We must go into the Union. And, say some <lb/>
hon. members, " If you do not go into the Union the Army <lb/>
and Navy of Great Britain will not protect you;" but I <lb/>
have higher authority for stating that the Army and Navy <lb/>
of Great Britain will protect us. Mr. Gladstone saysthat <lb/>
the Imperial Government pledges itself to protect. tothe <lb/>
utmost of its power, every British subject in British North <lb/>
America. [Cries of—No! No!] I say Mr. Gladstone <lb/>
does say so; and he is a member of the House of Commons, <lb/>
and quite as good a statesman as any of the hon. members <lb/>
who say "No." Is not this then sufficient authority for <lb/>
us to say that the British Government will protect us? Is <lb/>
any class in this Island tired of our Constitution? There <lb/>
is nothing respecting which we have not the right to pe<lb break="no"/>tition, or which we have not the right to ask for why then <lb/>
should we be forced to give up our Constitution? I see <lb/>
gentlemen here who are older than my father, and who say <lb/>
we must go into Confederation. If the ruling statesmen of <lb/>
Canada and Nova Scotia, say that we must units, is that <lb/>
any reason why we should do so? If that is the right <lb/>
and privilege of British subjects. I am sorry I am one; but <lb/>
I believe that though I live on this little Island, I have as <lb/>
much liberty as if I lived in London; and I feel proud <lb/>
that the BritishGovcrnment is composed of men who pledge <lb/>
themselves to protect us with the whole resources of the <lb/>
Empire. We are now told that we must unite—that the <lb/></p> <milestone type="unknown"/> 

<p>British flag will be swept from the seas unless we con<lb break="no"/>federate;— I remember that an hon. member (Hon. <lb/>
Mr. Whelan) enunciated very different views a few years <lb/>
ago. I do not wish to misconstrue the hon. member's <lb/>
sentiments—far front it—but there appears to be a sort of <lb/>
hallucination in about the subject; for, otherwise, his mind <lb/>
and those of some other hon. members, it is difficult to ac<lb break="no"/>count for the change which their views have undergone <lb/>
concerning it. We are told that, whether we adopt the <lb/>
Quebec Report or not, we must contederate upon some <lb/>
terms; but I consider that we have just as much right to <lb/>
call upon the other Colonies to confederate as they have to <lb/>
call upon us. It is said that, if Nova Scotia and New <lb/>
Brunswick, go into the Union. we also must, for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of mutual defence; but we have already placed the <lb/>
whole Revenue of the Colony at the disposal of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment for putting the Island in a state of defence. and we <lb/>
are willing to pay our proportion for the general defence of <lb/>
the Colonies; but why should we be forced into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion against our will? If, after a general election, there <lb/>
should he a majority in favour of Confederation, the case <lb/>
would be different; but to say that we must unite with <lb/>
Canada is absurd. If we were considered fit to govern <lb/>
ourselves, and if we have conducted the business of the Colony, <lb/>
properly for fifteen years, it does not appear reasonable to <lb/>
suppose that the British Government will now deprive us of <lb/>
our Constitution. I do not think the people of this Island <lb/>
are so much afraid of Confederation; but they object to <lb/>
being forced into it. We have, at present, as much right <lb/>
to tax ourselves as Canada has; but, in the event of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, will we stand in the same relative position to <lb/>
the other Colonies as Rhode island does to the rest of the <lb/>
American Union? That island has the same representa<lb break="no"/>tion in the United States Senate as New York. Rhode <lb/>
Island is the smallest part of the American Union, and i <lb/>
suppose we would remain for a long time the smallest part <lb/>
of British America; still, we have shown a disposition to <lb/>
do what we can to defend ourselves, and have thereby <lb/>
shown that we are not disloyal, but we wish to let it be <lb/>
seen that Confederation is not as applicable to us as to <lb/>
other portions of British America, and that. therefore, <lb/>
we are not disposed to go into a Union on the basis of <lb/>
the Quebec Report. <lb/></p> 

<p>Pgogress reported and House adjourned at 10 minutes <lb/>
to 12. <lb/></p> -->

<p rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, 8th May, 1866.</p><lb/>

<p>House in Committee of the whole on Despatches.   Mr. <lb/>
JOHN YEO in the Chair. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CONR1">Mr. CONROY</persName>. Sir, I have very little to say in addi<lb break="no"/>tion to what I said upon the question last Session. I am <lb/>
decidedly opposed to Confederation. I am quite satisfied <lb/>
to remain as we are, and to retain the management of our <lb/>
own affairs. I have considered the question with all the <lb/>
ability and attention I could bring to bear upon it, and l <lb/>
have failed to discover any advantage which would acrue to <lb/>
us through a Federal Union with Canada. But whilst I <lb/>
am persuaded that We should reap no advantaues from it, I <lb/>
am convinced that, in almost every particular, it would be <lb/>
highly injurious, if not absolutely ruinous to us. Accord<lb break="no"/>ing to the Quebec Scheme, we would have to give up our <lb/>
revenue, however great its amount, in exchange for £30,000 <lb/>
or £40,000 per annum; and we would have to surrender to <lb/>
strangers the power to raise our duties of impact and ex<lb break="no"/>cise to any amount they chose. We would be allowed to <lb/>
retain our local Legislature; but of what service would the <lb/>

<pb n="111" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_111.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">111</fw>

machinery of legislature be to us, without the power to ap<lb break="no"/>propriate our revenue for our own immediate benefit? A <lb/>
great part of the allowance of £30,000 or £40,000 a year <lb/>
would be required to keep up the useless parapharnalia of <lb/>
a local Government and local Legislature. All that was <lb/>
said last night upon the subject, was merely a repetition of <lb/>
what was urged for and against the Union last Session. I <lb/>
have myself noting to advance against it; and I will, <lb/>
therefore, say no more but that I heartily support the Reso<lb break="no"/>lutions submitted by the Hon. the Leader of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, although I must admit I see nothing objectionable in <lb/>
the Resolution submitted, in amendment, but my hon. friend <lb/>
the member for St. Peter's (Mr. Whelan). <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. COL. GRAY apologized for his absence from the <lb/>
House for the last two or three days; which, he explained, <lb/>
had been occasioned by indisposition. The Resolutions which <lb/>
had been submitted by the Hon. the Leader of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, he presumed he had before him in the Legislative <lb/>
Summary; but he was not exactly aware of the purport of <lb/>
the amendment which, it seemed, had been subitted there<lb break="no"/>to. He would, therefore, feel obliged by the Chairman's <lb/>
reading it for his information. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Chairman having, in compliance with the request of <lb/>
the hon and gallant Colonel, read the amendment submitted <lb/>
by the Hon. Mr. Whelan, he—the Hon Col. Gray spoke as <lb/>
follows: I will say I am glad that I have now, in my place, <lb/>
an opportunity to give my opinion upon the Resolutions <lb/>
submitted by the Hon. the Leader of the Government. It <lb/>
appears to me that he House in saying,-as, by the words <lb/>
of the second of those Resolutions, they are made to do,— <lb/>
"That they cannot admit that a Federal Union of the North <lb/>
American Provinces and Colonies, which would include <lb/>
Prince Edward Island, could <hi rendition="simple:italic">ever</hi> be accomplished upon <lb/>
terms that would prove advantageous to the interests and <lb/>
well-being of the people of this Island." are in a mose arro<lb break="no"/>gant, and almost impious manner, assuming to themselves <lb/>
two of the grand attributes of the Deity—prescience and <lb/>
omniscience. I must say I would be very sorry to have my <lb/>
name, as a supporter of such a Resolution, recorded for <lb/>
transmission to posterity. I do not look for posthumous <lb/>
fame; and I regard popular applause as little, perhaps, as <lb/>
most public men; but I regard my own conscience, and <lb/>
nothing, I trust, will ever induce me to give my sanction or <lb/>
concurrence to any act, project, or declaration, which, <lb/>
through a cool and dispassionate exercise of my judgement, I <lb/>
cannot conscientiously approve. I regard my own conscience <lb/>
much more than any thought of future fame or prospect of <lb/>
immediate popular applause. As a parliamentary repre<lb break="no"/>sentative of the people, I endeavour to act in accordance <lb/>
with its dictates. On every public question which comes <lb/>
before the Assembly, I claim the right to exercise my con<lb break="no"/>scientious judgement, independently of all party connexion or <lb/>
considerations; and that right I not only, most willingly <lb/>
concede to every other member of the House, but I most <lb/>
sincerely desire that, on every occasion, whatever the nature <lb/>
of the question at issue may be, he may freely exercise it. <lb/>
The hon. member from Cascumpeque (Mr. Conroy) has very <lb/>
properly said, if I understood him aright, that nothing more <lb/>
than was enunciated upon the question of Federal Union, in <lb/>
the last Session, could now be advanced concerning it. In <lb/>
the last of the Resolutions against the Union, agreed to by <lb/>
the majority of this hon. House, last session, it is said, <lb/>
"That this House disagrees to the recommendations of the <lb/>
Quebec Convention; and, on the part of Prince Edward <lb/>
Island, emphatically declines a Union, which, after a serious <lb/>
and careful consideration, it believes would prove politically, <lb/>
commercially, and financially disastrous to the rights and <lb/>
interests of its people." This, surely, was language strong <lb/>
enough; and its simple re-affirmance now, without the most <lb/>
absurd and censurable assumption of the Divine attributes <lb/>
of prescience and omniscience, ought to have fully satisfied <lb/>
the opponents of Confederation in this House. On my <lb/>
return from Canada in 1864, I publicly declared that, in <lb/>
my opinion, simple justice to the people demanded that no <lb/>

<cb/>

further action, either executive or legislative, should be <lb/>
taken, either for or against the projected Union, until after <lb/>
they should have had an opportunity to pronounce con<lb break="no"/>cerning it at the hustings. That was my opinion then; and <lb/>
it is still my opinion; and, I, therefore, hold that this House <lb/>
is not in a position to pronounce constitutionally concerning <lb/>
the matter. Whether the people as yet rightly comprehend <lb/>
the question in all its features, it is not for me to determine. <lb/>
By my individual opinion is that they have not yet, through <lb/>
the labours of any competent and impartial instructers, been <lb/>
enabled to arrive at that full understanding of it, to which, <lb/>
before they can wisely conclude concerning it, it is necessary <lb/>
they should attain. So vast a subject has never before been <lb/>
submitted to their consideration; no question so likely to <lb/>
arouse their prejudices, and, with reference to which, there <lb/>
has been so great a probability to misconceptions on their <lb/>
part, has ever before been propounded to them for solution. <lb/>
They are called upon to deal with a matter of such gravity <lb/>
and importance, as may, according to their decision concern<lb break="no"/>ing it, either settle or unsettle the whole balance of our <lb/>
Constitution; and, therefore, it seems to me to be absolutely <lb/>
necessary that, before they form a final judgement upon it, <lb/>
they should be enabled to understand the measure in all its <lb/>
bearings, and have ability to look upon it with an enlarged <lb/>
and comprehensive view. I do not see, however, that any <lb/>
remarks made in this House, at this time, can in any way <lb/>
alter the state of the question; nor can I perceive that— <lb/>
uninstructed, as we are, by our constituents with re<lb break="no"/>gard to it—we can with any regard to constitutional pro<lb break="no"/>priety, take action upon it. Such being my view of <lb/>
the present state of the question, it is only in conse<lb break="no"/>quence of the unexampled features of the Resolutions <lb/>
which have been submitted by the Hon. the Leader of the <lb/>
Government, and which I apprehend will be sustained and <lb/>
carried by a majority of the House, that i have risen to offer <lb/>
any remarks upon the subject. The Resolution which asserts <lb/>
that "this House cannot admit that a Federal Union of the <lb/>
North American Provinces and Colonies, which would in<lb break="no"/>clude Prince Edward Island, could <hi rendition="simple:italic">ever</hi> be accomplished <lb/>
upon terms that would prove advantageous to the interests <lb/>
and well-being of the people of this Island;" shuts out every <lb/>
member who shall agree to it from every again entertaining <lb/>
the question, how changed soever, and how much more <lb/>
favourable soever may be the terms upon which acceptance <lb/>
of Confederation may be required of the Colony. Nothing <lb/>
can be more preposterous than such a Resolution. We know <lb/>
not what changes even a single day may bring forth. And <lb/>
yet, as if all the events of futurity were laid open to our <lb/>
view, we are called upon to decide against the projected <lb/>
Union of these Provinces upon anyterms. We talk of this <lb/>
Island being cut off and separated, by an immovable barrier <lb/>
of ice from the neighbouring Provinces. Science and art <lb/>
may yet overcome the obstruction of that barrier. An un<lb break="no"/>obstructed intercourse and communication with the Mainland, <lb/>
by properly fitted Steam-propellers may yet be secured to us in <lb/>
the winter season. What is the barrier which Britons can<lb break="no"/>not overleap? But, if the Island is to be bound by the Re<lb break="no"/>solutions in question, it will indeed by more effectually cut <lb/>
off and separated from neighbouring Provinces, and-denied <lb/>
for ever all participation in the growing strength, wealth, and <lb/>
and prosperity of the Confederated Provinces- it will have <lb/>
little prospect for the future beyond a dwarfed existence, or <lb/>
ultimate absorption into the neighbouring Republic. The <lb/>
great burthen of all the speeches which have been delivered <lb/>
in the Island, both in this House and out of it, against <lb/>
Confederation has been that the terms offered to us <lb/>
are not commensurate with our wants or such as our <lb/>
exceptional position demands that they should be <lb/>
that they are not sufficiently favorable. But now, by <lb/>
these Resolutions, you shut yourselves out from the <lb/>
acceptance of anyterms which may be offered, however <lb/>
favourable they may be. In declaring that a Union of these <lb/>
Provinces can neverbe ffected on terms favourable to <lb/>
Prince Edward Island, you arrogate to yourselves the power <lb/>
of Omniscience. The hon. and gallant Colonel, then ridi<lb break="no"/>culed the idea which had been put forth by some anti-con<lb break="no"/> 

<pb n="112" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_112.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">112</fw>

federates, that, in the event of the Federation's taking <lb/>
place, and Canada's being imided by Fenian marauders or <lb/>
any other enemy, we would be called upon to send tip our <lb/>
Militia or Volunteers to assist. the Canadians to defend <lb/>
themselves. What probability, he asked, was there that a <lb/>
Province which, in obedience to a call to arms, could, with<lb break="no"/>in 24 hours, have an army of 150,000 well disciplined men, <lb/>
fully equipped, and ready to encounter whatever foe might <lb/>
menace or ass-ail them, and which, besides, had at its dis<lb break="no"/>posal a surplus revenue of one million dollars, should stand <lb/>
in need of any direct aid, either of men or money from <lb/>
Prince Edward Island? Bankrupt Canada! The idea was <lb/>
most preposterous. The hon. member then significantly <lb/>
hinted to the Committee the very great probability that <lb/>
their determination to remain out of the Union. in oppo<lb break="no"/>sition to the wishes of the Home Government, might prove <lb/>
a cause of such irritation as they might, when too late, have <lb/>
reason to repent their having provoked. As a proof that <lb/>
he had never centemplated the forcing of the Quebec Scheme <lb/>
upon the people against their will, he stated that after his <lb/>
return from Canada, in 1864, he had, at a public meeting of <lb/>
his constituents, at Belfast, told them that the question of <lb/>
Confederation. so far as it was intended to apply to Prince <lb/>
Edward Island, was one for the people—and for the people <lb/>
alone—to decide. The Delegates had drawn up a Report, <lb/>
embracing a scheme of Union; but the people were at per<lb break="no"/>fect liberty to accept or reject it as they themselves should <lb/>
think best. Because I, as one of the island Delegates, as<lb break="no"/>sented to that Scheme I have been accused of having sold <lb/>
my country. and been stigmatized by the name of traitor, <lb/>
Even a clergyman—I will not say of what denomination— <lb/>
has declared that he had been told that I had been bribed <lb/>
to give my assent to that Scheme. When that rather amus<lb break="no"/>ing charge was brought against me, it was brought equally <lb/>
against the other Delegates from Prince Edward Island. <lb/>
for we all assented to the Quebec Report, and the Hon. <lb/>
the Leader of the Opposition (Hon. Mr, Coles), who was one <lb/>
of us, when—after the Conference had terminated—publicly <lb/>
speaking of the Report, at the Dejeuner, at Ottawa, said: <lb/>
" He thought they (the Delegates) had reason to congratu<lb break="no"/>late themselves upon the labours of the Conference. That <lb/>
thirty-three men, representing the various political Opinions <lb/>
of six different Provinces, could have assembled so and amalga<lb break="no"/>mated their opinions as to agree upon a Constitution Suited <lb/>
for that great Confederation, was something, he believed, <lb/>
the Delegates were worthy of the position they held. He <lb/>
said this, although there was no man more disappointed than <lb/>
himself with respect to some parts of that constitution; <hi rendition="simple:italic">but, <lb/>
by mutual concessions, they had arrived at a result which they <lb/>
could all agree in supporting and submitting to the people; for <lb/>
he held that it must be submitted to the people. They could <lb/>
not force it on the people; they must endeavour to shew them <lb/>
that it was for their benefit, and thus induce them to accept <lb/>
it.</hi>" The foul charge of his having been bribed to agree to <lb/>
the Report—a Report which was agreed to by all the Dele<lb break="no"/>gates—must apply equally to all the other Island Delegates; <lb/>
but a charge so scandalous was one which they with him, <lb/>
would trample under foot, By a part of the Island press, it <lb/>
had been said that he and his brother Delegates who were <lb/>
advocates of the complete Federation of these Provinces were <lb/>
prepared to thrust it down the threats of the people. He, <lb/>
on the contrary,—and he wished it to go forth to the public— <lb/>
took the very earliest opportunity which presented itself, to <lb/>
publish in the papers that, in his opinion, it would be most un<lb break="no"/>just to the people to take any action with respect to the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Scheme, until it should have been fairly put to them at <lb/>
the Hustings. The people have not had it before them, and <lb/>
therefore what we may say now can be but of little avail. <lb/>
This is the last Session of the House; and, at the ensuing <lb/>
General Election, every candidate for the suffrages of the peo<lb break="no"/>

<cb/> 

ple will have an opportunity of declaring his sentiments con<lb break="no"/>cerning the Confederation Scheme; and such as shall be <lb/>
elected will take their seats in the Assembly duly instructed <lb/>
how they are to vote concerning it. If I be again returned <lb/>
to this House—I shall, according to the instructions of my <lb/>
constituents, know how to comport myself with respect to <lb/>
that momentous question. As to the appointment of Dele<lb break="no"/>gates to a London Convention, I do not see how His Excel <lb/>
lency the Lieutenant Governor, as the question now stands <lb/>
would dare to make such an appointment. Before any step <lb/>
of that kind can be constitutionally taken, there must be an <lb/>
appeal to the people; and that appeal must be first responded  <lb/>
to by no approval of Confederation views. I believe there are <lb/>
members on the flor of the House who, although adverse to <lb/>
the terms of the Quebec Scheme, would yet willingly vote <lb/>
for a reconsideration of it. I believve the Hon. the <lb/>
Leader of the Opposition is not opposed to a Federal <lb/>
Union of all the Provinces; but he wants better terms <lb/>
than those offered to us by the Quebec Scheme. He wants <lb/>
the very best terms which it may be possible for us to <lb/>
obtain; and so do I. His opposition to the Quebec Scheme <lb/>
is based upon his conviction that the terms which it accords <lb/>
us are not sufficiently favorable to our interests—I am not <lb/>
much in the habit of looking to members in opposition for <lb/>
amendments to Resolutions submitted from this side of the <lb/>
House. I was returned to support the Conservative party; <lb/>
and, in good faith, I have fought with them, and done my <lb/>
duty in every conflict which they have had with the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion. In the support of any particular policy or measure to <lb/>
which the Conservatives have been pledged, I have never <lb/>
flinched. This, however, is the lost Session of this House <lb/>
and with it my immediate connexion with the Conservative; <lb/>
will cease. At the ensuing General Election, if I offer my<lb break="no"/>self again as a Candidate for a seat in the Assembly; I will <lb/>
not do so either as a Conservative or as a Liberal and, if elected <lb/>
I will not pledge myself to support either party. I will reserve <lb/>
to myself the privilege of judging for myself, independently <lb/>
of all party consideration . The present question is not a <lb/>
Government question; but a free and open one; and, there<lb break="no"/>fore, in voting, as I shall do, for the amendment submitted <lb/>
by a member of the Opposition—the hon. member for St. <lb/>
Peter's (Hon. Mr. Whelan)—l shall not be forsaking my <lb/>
party. The good sense and moderation of that amendment, <lb/>
especially when contrasted with the assumption, at once <lb/>
arrogant and fatuous of the Resolutions to which it is op<lb break="no"/>posed, so recommend it to my judgment and sense of propriety, <lb/>
that I can have no hesitation in voting for it. In sneaking <lb/>
against the Resolution submitted by the Hon. Premier, I have <lb/>
done soon account of their binding character. As to the <lb/>
Resolutions of amendment, I do not see how any member, on <lb/>
either side of the House, whatever his opinions concerning <lb/>
the Quebec Scheme may be, can object to it. But, by the <lb/>
other, we are called upon to exclude ourselves for over from a <lb/>
Confederation which, in all probability, is destined to be<lb break="no"/>come one of the greatest nations on the earth. What! are <lb/>
we going to ostracise ourselves from the community of our <lb/>
Sister Provinces? Are we going to stand alone to become the <lb/>
resort of strugglers, and a nest of hornets in the sides of the <lb/>
Confederation? Do we suppose that Her Majesty's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will allow such a political solecism? Will not our de<lb break="no"/>clared hostility to any scheme of Union which will include <lb/>
Prince Edward Island, in opposition to the well considered <lb/>
and truly parental desire of the Government of Great Britain, <lb/>
be very likely so far to exasperate them, as to cause them to <lb/>
legislate us into the Confederation even against our will? As to <lb/>
the Hon. the Leader of the Government, I have the highest res<lb break="no"/>pect for him, both politically and socially; and although voting against <lb/>
the Resolutions submitted by him, I am not voting against the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment of which he is the Leader. The Confederation question is <lb/>
not a Government one [Hon. Mr. Coles. It should be, though.] I <lb/>
will not say whether the questions might or might not have been made <lb/>
a Government question. A Government question, however, it could <lb/>
not have been made constitutionally without an appeal to the people. <lb/>
But I will ask how can the hon. the Leader of the Government now <lb/>
tell that his own or other constituencies are at present opposed to <lb/>
Confederation, even although he may have had reason to believe they <lb/>
were so at the time of the last general election. Events of a most <lb/>

<pb n="113" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_113.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">113</fw>

in some districts they who were formerly opposed to Confederation, <lb/>
may now be in favor of it. The great objection has been to the terms <lb/>
offered us by the Quebec Scheme; but not, I believe, generally to <lb/>
Federation on any terms. Thinking men who, at first, were opposed <lb/>
to it may now take another view of it; and recognise the possibility <lb/>
of our obtaining better terms, if, through a constitutional channel, <lb/>
we should be wise enough to seek them. In accepting the Premier's <lb/>
Resolutions, the Committee will be blindly committing themselves to <lb/>
a rejection of they know not what. Not a member of the Committee <lb/>
knows how the Quebec Scheme of Confederation may yet be modified; <lb/>
and, therefore, I say every member who may now vote in favor of those <lb/>
Resolutions, may afterwards find that, by having done so, he has <lb/>
bound himself to reject terms of Union, which, in his own judgment, <lb/>
be is forced to admit could not, if accepted, fail to be for the lasting <lb/>
benefit and welfare of the country! Can anything be more absurd <lb/>
than such a course as this? To bind ourselves down to reject terms <lb/>
of Federation which, perhaps, may be of so favorable a character, and <lb/>
so advantageous to us, that, if accepted, they would, in a manner, <lb/>
pour down showers of gold upon us! I cannot see the soundness of <lb/>
the spirit in which these Resolutions have been conceived; and I fear <lb/>
the acceptance of them, by the Committee, may be so far exasperate the <lb/>
Home Government, that we may have much reason to regret the de<lb break="no"/>termination which they express. The hon. and gallant Colonel, then, <lb/>
—referring to the time when, not long since, he had the honor to fill <lb/>
the post of President of the Executive Council, and to the part, <lb/>
which, with the concurrence of his hon. colleagues therein, he then <lb/>
took with a view to the accomplishment of a Federation of the whole <lb/>
of the British North American Provinces and Colonies, —said, he <lb/>
hoped that, not only such of those hon. gentlemen as still agreed with <lb/>
him in opinion as to the desirability of such Federation, but also <lb/>
such of them as now differed with him, on that subject, would kindly <lb/>
bear with his free and independent expression of his sentiments con<lb break="no"/>cerning it and the Hon. Premier's Resolutions then before the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee; and that although, as respected those Resolutions, be stood <lb/>
forward <hi rendition="simple:italic">politically</hi> opposed to some hon. gentlemen, of whom, not <lb/>
long since, he was a colleague in the Government, he should not, on <lb/>
that account, bare any reason to believe that he could not still <lb/>
<choice><sic><hi rendition="simple:italic">soically</hi></sic><corr><hi rendition="simple:italic">socially</hi></corr></choice> look upon them as his friends. The Government of Great <lb/>
Britain, continued the hon. gentleman, had ever been truly parental <lb/>
to this Island as well as to our sister Provinces, and our opposition <lb/>
to what the Imperial Government were thoroughly convinced would <lb/>
be our lasting benefit, could not be viewed, by them, in any other <lb/>
light than that of a most ungrateful return for benefits and privi<lb break="no"/>leges, which Great Britain had most abundantly and generously <lb/>
showered upon us; and we could not, therefore, reasonably expect <lb/>
that she would submit to be thwarted, by that ungrateful opposition, <lb/>
with respect to so grand a scheme as the Confederation of the British <lb/>
North American Provinces—the inauguration of another great power <lb/>
in the world. The Hon. and gallant Colonel—after again express<lb break="no"/>ing a gear that the determined rejection of the Confederation upon any <lb/>
terms, by the House, would be so exasperate the Imperial Government as <lb/>
to cause them to determine concerning us, as respected Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, according to the practice of resolute parents when necessitated <lb/>
to enforce submission on the part of refractory and disobedient chil<lb break="no"/>dren—concluded by saying he gave his hearty support to the Resolu<lb break="no"/>tion of amendment submitted by the hon. member for St. Peter's <lb/>
(Hon. Mr. Whelan.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. Mr. McEACHEN</persName>. It appeared from the great <lb/>
sensitiveness of some hon. members on the subject of bribe<lb break="no"/>ry, that only to hint the possibility of their being accessible <lb/>
to the influence of bribes, was a crime almost as gross as <lb/>
blasphemy. But we knew that no man was infallible; and <lb/>
that traitors had been found in higher circles than any in <lb/>
which those hon. but sensitive gentlemen had ever moved <lb/>
in, or were likely ever to move in. The hon. member who <lb/>
had spoken last had ridiculed the idea of Canada, with her <lb/>
army of 150,000 disciplined men being saved through the <lb/>
aid of little Prince Edward Island; but we had read of a <lb/>
lion's having been saved by a mouse. It was crouching <lb/>
and cowardly to accept the idea that Great Britain would <lb/>
ever force us into Confederation against our will. What <lb/>
reasons could Mr. Cardwell have to assign for so arbitrary <lb/>
a step? We were not disloyal, we were not traitors. They <lb/>
terms of the Quebec Scheme were unjust to us in every <lb/>
point of view—most glaringly so in a financial one—but the <lb/>
wrong done to us in that respect, would be light indeed <lb/>
when compared with the loss of our liberty—the loss of the <lb/>
power to regulate our own affairs. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName> denied that he had ever agreed to the <lb/>
Quebec Scheme, and declared that when he found that, <lb/>

<cb/> 

financially, it was impossible to obtain justice for Prince <lb/>
Edward Island, he told the Conference that they had better <lb/>
leave us out of the Scheme altogether. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man then argued that they only means by which we could <lb/>
escape being dragged into the Union, was positively to de<lb break="no"/>clare that we would not enter into it upon any terms. <lb/>
Unless we declared ourselves altogether hostile to the <lb/>
Scheme, we would be dragged in. It was true that the <lb/>
Home Government had not endeavoured to compel our ac<lb break="no"/>ceptance of the Scheme by threats of compulsion. Al<lb break="no"/>though we are the smallest o the Provinces, Mr. Cardwell <lb/>
knows better than to do that. Let us, then, decidedly take <lb/>
our stand against our being included in the projected Union, <lb/>
resolved not to be comprehended in it, until we find that we <lb/>
can no longer keep out. Some Confederates argued that if <lb/>
we agreed to go into the Union, even upon the proposed <lb/>
terms, there would be no insuperable difficult, after its <lb/>
consummation, in any way of our obtaining better terms, <lb/>
should our claims be fully urged by our representatives in <lb/>
the Federal Parliament. Such an idea was absurd in the <lb/>
extreme. Of obtaining better terms, or even a revision of <lb/>
our claims, through the exertions on our behalf of our 5 <lb/>
members, in the Federal House of Commons, opposed to 147 <lb/>
Canadian members, we should just have as little chance as <lb/>
a cat without claws in Hell. It was folly, indeed, to think <lb/>
that we might go into the Federation, and then obtain bet<lb break="no"/>ter terms than were offered to us by the Quebec Scheme. <lb/>
The Canadian statesmen thought we were too well of in be<lb break="no"/>ing free from direct taxation; but happily free from bur<lb break="no"/>thens of that kind as we were, we had quite enough to do <lb/>
with all our money. The hon. gentlemen then commented <lb/>
with some severity on what he called the anomalous position <lb/>
of the Government with respect to the Confederation Ques<lb break="no"/>tion,—four members of it, in the Legislature, arguing in <lb/>
favor of Union, against fine opposed to it. For a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment when so divided in opinion concerning the most im<lb break="no"/>portant, the most vital question that the Government and Par<lb break="no"/>liament of any country could be called upon to entertain— <lb/>
the remodelling of its Constitution and Government,—was <lb/>
a thing unheard of. In the British Parliament, it was <lb/>
never found that, upon important questions, one member of <lb/>
the Administration voted in one way, and another, in an<lb break="no"/>other. It was said by those who argued in favour of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, that if we valued British institutions, if we <lb/>
valued our rights and privileges as British subjects, we <lb/>
would accede to Confederation. He, however, maintained <lb/>
that were we to become a member of the projected Union, <lb/>
we would actually be deprived of all these, and retrograde <lb/>
a century. Confederation, instead of being a means of bind<lb break="no"/>ing us more closely and indissolubly to the British Crown, <lb/>
would, eventually, be the cause of our separation from it. <lb/>
The moment the Upper House should come into collision <lb/>
with the Lower House, some extreme measure would be had <lb/>
recourse to. Should we, however, remain as we were, we <lb/>
would be safe. If we entered into Confederation, we would <lb/>
be much more in danger of quarreling with the United <lb/>
States than we are now. As we were, should we be as<lb break="no"/>sailed by the United States, what would Great Britain do <lb/>
with us, but protect us? The glory argument was, that, <lb/>
by confederating with Canada and the other Provinces, we <lb/>
should become part and parcel of a great nation; byt the <lb/>
people of Prince Edward Island knew themselves to be al<lb break="no"/>ready part and parcel of a great nation, and they had no <lb/>
desire to belong to any other. As to defence, we were quite <lb/>
willing to contribute our full quota for that purpose accord<lb break="no"/>ing to our ability. We were told that, as it was the posi<lb break="no"/>tive desire of the Home Government that we should agree <lb/>

<pb n="114" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_114.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">114</fw>

to confederate, we would be looked upon as rebels if we did <lb/>
not. No fear of that. So long, said the hon. gentleman, <lb/>
as Great Britain shall allow us to remain in our present in<lb break="no"/>dependent position, there will be no fear of our assuming, <lb/>
towards her, any thing like a disloyal or rebellious attitude; <lb/>
and a manifestation of our sacred regard for the priceless <lb/>
boon of Self-Government, which she has conferred upon us, <lb/>
and our determination to retain it unimpaired, as long as <lb/>
we shall be able to do so, will never be looked upon by her <lb/>
as a proof of disaffection, but rather as an undeniable evid<lb break="no"/>ence of our most just and grateful appreciation of that in<lb break="no"/>estimable blessing. What drove Canada into rebellion was <lb/>
the Home Government's refusal to grant her Responsible <lb/>
or Self Government; and what had brought her back to <lb/>
loyalty and affection was the conferring upon her, and under a <lb/>
free representative Constitution, the full control and manage<lb break="no"/>ment of her own revenue and affairs. Great Britain well <lb/>
knew that the boon of Responsible or Self-Government was <lb/>
the greatest which she could confer upon any of her De<lb break="no"/>pendencies or Colonies, and that which bound them most <lb/>
strongly in loyalty and affection to her; and, as respected <lb/>
any Colony or Dependency, upon which she had conferred <lb/>
that privilege, as long as it continued true in its allegiance <lb/>
to her, and obedient to the laws, and desired to retain that <lb/>
form of Government in all its independent integrity, so long, <lb/>
he firmly believed, would she consider it to be beyond the <lb/>
constitutional stretch, even of her Imperial power, either to <lb/>
suspend or withdraw that form of Government from such <lb/>
Colony or Dependency, or even to impair it. We had not <lb/>
obtained that form of Government by rebellion, but by an <lb/>
exercise of constitutional means; and, both as account of <lb/>
the mode by which we had obtained it, and the happy man <lb/>
ner in which—although even to the establishment of universal <lb/>
manhood suffage—we had carried its privileges into practice, <lb/>
we were entitled to the especial consideration of the Home <lb/>
Government; and, he doubted not, we would receive it. <lb/>
Hon. members who advocated our being embraced by the <lb/>
Confederation Scheme had very plainly hinted their belief <lb/>
that if we did not, of our own accord, agree to enter it, the <lb/>
Home Government would compel us to do so; but he did <lb/>
not believe that the British Parliament would allow us to <lb/>
be coerced. Hon. members may refer to speeches made by <lb/>
me in Canada, and endeavour, by attaching undue weight <lb/>
to the import of some isolated expressions which I then, per<lb break="no"/>haps rather unguardedly made us of, to shew that I then ap<lb break="no"/>proved of the Quebec Scheme; but, at the same time, these <lb/>
hon. members well know, in their hearts, that I was not <lb/>
so; and you, yourself, Mr. Chairman, might, I think, testify <lb/>
so much in my behalf, for you will, doubtless, recollect that <lb/>
when I met you, in New Brunswick, on my way home from <lb/>
the Quebec Conference, I told you it would be impos<lb break="no"/>sible for Prince Edward Island to go into Confederation <lb/>
upon the terms of the Quebec Scheme, without a sacrifice <lb/>
of her independence, and of her best and dearest interests; <lb/>
and that, therefore, I was decidedly opposed to the Island's <lb/>
being included in it. But even granting that, as has been <lb/>
said, I changed my views concerning Confederation after my <lb/>
return from Canada to Prince Edward Island, what will <lb/>
that matter? If we are never to change our views concern<lb break="no"/>ing any measure which may be projected, f what use is our <lb/>
debating upon it. In a Legislature, if members were never <lb/>
to be allowed to change their opinions, there would be no <lb/>
chance whatever of return, and abuses would for ever re<lb break="no"/>main unredressed. In Great Britain, every reform, every <lb/>
rectification of wrong, every redress of grievances, which <lb/>
has been effected by parliamentary action has been brought <lb/>
about by a change of opinion, not infrequently both with<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

out, as well as within, the walls of Parliament. It has been <lb/>
said, by some hon. members, that with our tariff lower than <lb/>
that of the Federation we would not be left out, because in <lb/>
that case we would become the resort of smugglers; but I <lb/>
believe, if the people would submit to be governed by the <lb/>
opinion of mercantile men, and consent to the obolition of <lb/>
customs and impost duties, and fully establish free-trade <lb/>
privileges, and have recourse to direct taxation in lien of <lb/>
those duties, they would find the change a most beneficial <lb/>
one. It was also said by hon. members who advocated <lb/>
Confederation, that no action should be taken with respect <lb/>
to it, by the Assembly, until it should have been fairly put <lb/>
before the people at the coming General Election. Well, <lb/>
we would all be glad, no doubt, to have an opportunity of <lb/>
again appealing to the people. When we do so, they will <lb/>
certainly wish to know who of the candidates for their suf<lb break="no"/>frages, are in favour of Confederation, and who are opposed <lb/>
to it; and I am quite willing that " Confederation or No <lb/>
Confederation" shall be the issue to be submitted to the <lb/>
people for their determination, and the test of the fitness <lb/>
of candidates for election. As respects the amendment, said <lb/>
the hon. gentleman, if we vote for it, we shall vote for Con<lb break="no"/>federation; and yet, most inconsistently, it concludes by <lb/>
saying that, in the opinion of this House no vote should be <lb/>
passed by the Legislature of this country in favor of Confe<lb break="no"/>deration until the people shall first have been afforded an <lb/>
opportunity of pronouncing their judgment on the question <lb/>
at a General Election." Now, as I do not wish to go into <lb/>
what I said last Session, I will be brief in any further re<lb break="no"/>marks which I have to make touching the subject. As res<lb break="no"/>pects the Resolutions which have been submitted by the Hon. <lb/>
the Leader of the Government. I will now merely observe <lb/>
that, had I been consulted concerning them, I would have <lb/>
advised the striking out of the middle one, and the reten<lb break="no"/>tion of only the first and last. I know not what pressure <lb/>
has been brought to bear upon the Government, but I be<lb break="no"/>lieve some has, and the effect has been the bringing down <lb/>
of the Resolutions in their present form. As they stand, <lb/>
however, I will vote for them. I certainly was once, I <lb/>
must confess, in favor of a Federal Union of these Provinces, <lb/>
because I was of opinion that it would give us greater weight <lb/>
at the Colonial Office, where the influence of the large pro<lb break="no"/>prietors had always prevailed against us to the hinderanos <lb/>
of any fair and equitable settlement of the Land Question. <lb/>
But now I am fully convinced that any advantage we might, <lb/>
on that score, derive from our confederating with the other <lb/>
Provinces, would be far overbalanced by the losses which it <lb/>
would, politically, commercially, and financially, directly <lb/>
bring upon us; and, therefore, with the qualifications which <lb/>
I have already made with respect to them, I am prepared <lb/>
unhesitatingly to vote for the Resolutions of the Hon. the <lb/>
Leader of the Government. I do not wish to say any thing <lb/>
harsh against those hon. members who differ with me on <lb/>
this question. If we went into the proposed Union, we <lb/>
would be at the mercy of those who do not think as we do <lb/>
on the subject of parliamentary representation. We have <lb/>
universal manhood suffrage and an elective Legislative <lb/>
Council; but they have neither. I think that, if we, in little <lb/>
Prince Edward Island, be left as we are, we shall be able to <lb/>
manage our own affairs quite as well as the people of Canada <lb/>
have managed theirs, and, indeed, I believe a great deal better. <lb/>
We are told that Her Majesty the Queen is earnest in her <lb/>
desire thatsuch a scheme of Confederation as will, without ex<lb break="no"/>ception, embrace all these Provinces, shall speedily be carried <lb/>
into effect; and that, if we oppose ourselves to that earnest <lb/>
desire of Her most gracious Majesty—a desire entertained <lb/>
by her solely in consequence of her belief that such Confede<lb break="no"/> 

<pb n="115" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_115.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">115</fw>

ration would afford the best security for the preservation of <lb/>
our free British institutions and for the promotion of the <lb/>
present and future well-being of the whole - we shall justly <lb/>
lay ourselves open to the imputation of disloyalty. From <lb/>
this view of the question, I, however, wholly dissent. I sin<lb break="no"/>cerly believe, indeed, that our good and gracious Queen is, <lb/>
at all times, animated by a truly parental solicitude and re<lb break="no"/>gard for the well-being of her faithful subjects, in every <lb/>
quarter of her immense empire; but 1 do not believe that <lb/>
she will ever determine to manifest that solicitude and re<lb break="no"/>gard towards any portion of them, constituting a people, by <lb/>
urging them to do that which they believe wlll be either fatal <lb/>
to their best and dearest interests, or at least be greatly in<lb break="no"/>imical to them. I do not, therefore, believe that Her gra<lb break="no"/>cious Majesty, if duly informed of our unwillingness—and <lb/>
of the grounds of that unwillingness—to be included in the <lb/>
projected Confederation of these Provinces. will ever consent <lb/>
to our being coerced into it; or that, because—after the ex<lb break="no"/>perience of a long and, upon the whole, successful manage<lb break="no"/>ment of our own affairs—we presume to know better, than <lb/>
we believe she can possibly do. what is best for our own in<lb break="no"/>terests, she will ever be brought to think of us as a disobedient <lb/>
or disloyal people. But besides, Sir, 1 do not believe that <lb/>
the question of the Confederation of these Provinces has <lb/>
ever been submitted to Her Majesty for the purpose of as<lb break="no"/>certaining her views concerning it, or that she has really, <lb/>
of herself, expressed any opinion either for or against it— <lb/>
any wish either that it should or should not take place. <lb/>
Her present ministers are indeed, in favor of it; and, in <lb/>
the usual ministerial style, when recommending it, they <lb/>
give to their own views the semblance of the Royal will. <lb/>
But all this we fully understand; and we know that neither <lb/>
in Parliament nor out of Parliament, are parties or indivi<lb break="no"/>duals opposing an administration ever, on account of such <lb/>
opposition, accused of disloyalty to the Sovereign. There<lb break="no"/>fore to say that we shall deservedly subject ourselves to the <lb/>
imputation of disloyalty, if, on the question of Confederation, we op<lb break="no"/>pose the views of Her Majesty's Ministers—men who, although in, <lb/>
power to-day, may, tomorrow, have to give place to others of a dif<lb break="no"/>ferent way of thinking—is truly absurd. As respected the hints <lb/>
which had been thrown out concerning the probability of our ob<lb break="no"/>taining, by means of Delegates to the proposed London Convention, <lb/>
the concession of better terms than those which are offered to us by <lb/>
the Quebec Scheme of Confederation, he was fully persuaded that, <lb/>
should any attempt of that kind be made, it would be altogether fu<lb break="no"/>tile. The leading Canadian statesmen and the Home Government <lb/>
were pledged to the integrity of the Quebec Scheme; and, even al<lb break="no"/>though the Heme Government might be found willing to have it mo<lb break="no"/>dified, either for the benefit of Prince Edward Island, or that of any <lb/>
of the Lower Provinces, leading Canadians had declared that no <lb/>
modification whatever of that scheme should be made, and that, ra<lb break="no"/>ther than it should, Canada would declare herself independent of <lb/>
the Mother Country and defy the power of Great Britain to control <lb/>
her. To show how really small are the chances of our obtaining, by <lb/>
any means, better terms than those which are offered us by the Que<lb break="no"/>bec scheme, I will read from an article on this point from the Que<lb break="no"/>bec "Weekly Citizen," of 5th May, 1866. The hon, gentleman then <lb/>
read as follows: <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p rendition="simple:italic"><hi rendition="simple:centre">(From the Weekly Citizen, 5th May, 1866.)</hi><lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Cartier,in the Canadian Parliament, in 1865, in reply to a <lb/>
speech of the Hon. Mr. Dorion, intimating that the British Go<lb break="no"/>vernment might introduce into the Act to be passed by the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Parliament features not contemplated by the original <lb/>
Resolutions, said: <lb/> </p> 

<p>"In reply to what the hon. member for Hochelaga has just <lb/>
said, I shall merely tell the honorable member of this House that <lb/>
they need not take alarm at the apprehensions and predictions of <lb/>
that hon. gentleman. I have already declared in my own name, <lb/>
and on behalf of the Goverment, that the delegates who go to <lb/>
England <hi rendition="simple:italic">will accept from the Imperial Government no act but one <lb/>
based on the Resolutions adopted by this House, and they will not <lb/>
bring back any other. I have pledged my word of honor and that of <lb/>
the Government to that effect.</hi>" <lb/></p> 

<p>Will this satisfy the opponents of the Quebec Scheme in the <lb/>
country, how unsubstantial and insincere are the representations <lb/>

<cb/> 

that have been made as to the possiblitiy of the terms of Union <lb/>
being changed? If not, if anything more is wanted to convince <lb/>
them, let them read the following from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Journal de Quebec</hi>, <lb/>
the organ of Mr. Coucheon, an able and influential supporter of <lb/>
the McDonald Cartier Ministry and of their Confederation <lb/>
policy:— <lb/></p> 

<p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">The Canadian Parliament has adopted a scheme of constitution <lb/>
which has been approved of by England, and that of Nova Scotia has <lb/>
adopted a simple resolution which permits the Government of the <lb/>
Empire to determine its future lot. The first Province numbers <lb/>
more than three millions of inhabitants; the second has but three <lb/>
hundred thousand. Which of these two Provinces will make its <lb/>
opinions prevail in the Council of the Sovereign?</hi> Moreover, if it is <lb/>
the Parliament of Nova Scotia which has adopted the resolution of <lb/>
which we havejust spoken, it is the Parliament of Canada. which <lb/>
has adopted the plan of the Quebec Convention, and our Ministers <lb/>
cannot renounce it without the consent of the some authority. <lb/>
Hence we may, and do say that if the Delegates should go to Eng<lb break="no"/>land, on the invitation of the Imperial Government, before the <lb/>
opening of our Legislature, they must go there to maintain abso<lb break="no"/>lutely the plan of the Quebec Convention; and England, even if <lb/>
she desires it, could not go beyond that, because she NEITHER <lb/>
WOULD NOR COULD RETAIN CANADA AGAINST HER WILL." <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon Gentleman then argued that, such being the opinions of the <lb/>
fathers of the Confederation Scheme—and as, in all probability, the <lb/>
Delegates who should be apoointed to the London Convention, as <lb/>
well on the part of the Lower Provinces as on the part of the Cana<lb break="no"/>das. would be such as had already pledged themselves to support <lb/>
the Quebec Scheme in its entirety—any Delegates from Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>Ward Island who might be appointed to that Convention for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of obtaining a modification in the Quebec Scheme favourable to our <lb/>
interests, would—however talented, and however zealous they might be <lb/>
in their endeavours to obtain such a modification of it—be overborne <lb/>
and outweighed by the Canadian Delegates. In further evidence of <lb/>
the soundness and tenability of my opinion, said the hon. gentleman, <lb/>
I will read another short passage with reference to the same point <lb/>
from a late number of <hi rendition="simple:italic">La Minerve</hi>, the Hon. Mr. Cartier's own or<lb break="no"/>gan. He then read as follows: <lb/></p> 

<p>"The position taken in Nova Scotia requires the formation of a <lb/>
new Convention at London, for the elaboration of a scheme to be <lb/>
presented to the Imperial Government. This Convention, as we <lb/>
have already said, <hi rendition="simple:italic">will have little to do</hi> since THE QUEBEC SCHEME <lb/>
CANNOT BE AMENDED." <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon. gentleman then concluded by saying, that these opinions <lb/>
concerning the Quebec Scheme, expressed in no abiguous language, <lb/>
fully warranted, he thought, his belief that neither by any appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of Delegates to the London Convention, nor by any other means to <lb/>
which it was possible for us to have recourse, could we either procure <lb/>
the framing and adoption of such a new scheme as we could approve of, <lb/>
or such a modification of the terms of the Quebec one as would ren<lb break="no"/>der it. worthy of our acceptance. Prince Edward Island, would, <lb/>
therefore, in his opinion, not wisely in remaining as she is—leaving <lb/>
to others the hazardous experiment of'abandonirg their present seve<lb break="no"/>ral independent and assured positions to engage in an untried con<lb break="no"/>nexion. and to assume burthens and responsibilities, the weight of <lb/>
which is unknown. <lb/></p></quote>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. SOL GENERAL</persName>: I would like to give some <lb/>
explanation respecting a clause in the Quebec Report re<lb break="no"/>ferring to the manner in which the Legislative Councillors <lb/>
for this island were to be selected. The hon. member has <lb/>
laid down the theory that, by that Report, the Councillors <lb/>
were not to be selected from the Council as it stands, and <lb/>
no doubt, he said, the Canadians would not select them for <lb/>
particular reasons; but I say to you, Mr. Chairman, and <lb/>
to this House, and to the public. that the clause referred to, <lb/>
Was placed in the Report at the unanimous request of the <lb/>
Delegates of Prince Edward Island. because we considered <lb/>
it unfair that, as the other Colonies had nominative Coun<lb break="no"/>cils. and we had our elective one, the choice should be nar<lb break="no"/>rowed down to twelve or thirteen hon. members who were <lb/>
elected by constituencies, and make them Councillors for <lb/>
life. We considered that they should have the length and <lb/>
the breadth of the Island to choose from. That, I con<lb break="no"/>sidered a sound principle. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Mr. DUNCAN</persName>: If they were chosen from the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil there would be some probability at least that they would <lb/>
be the choice of the people; but very little respect was <lb/>
paid to the wishes of the people. The members of the <lb/>

<pb n="116" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_116.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">116</fw>

Council were elected by men of property, and therefore, <lb/>
are more likely to be lit to be members of the Federal <lb/>
Council than men chosen by the Government of Canada, <lb/>
which knew nothing bout the Island, and cared less. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. Sol. GENERAL</persName>: The hon. member himself has <lb/>
laid down the principle that the members of Council should <lb/>
possess a property qualification, and real and personal <lb/>
estate' was placed in the Constitution at the suggestion of <lb/>
the hon. the Leader of the Opposition. He showed that, <lb/>
if it was confined to freehold, it would not be fair because <lb/>
many tenants on the Island were as well qualified as free<lb break="no"/>holders. When he threw out that suggestion the other <lb/>
Island Delegates were in favor of it; and it should be re<lb break="no"/>membered that they were to be chosen by the Federal Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, not by the Canadian Government. If members <lb/>
of the House and the people would look upon it independ<lb break="no"/>ently of party views. and if they were asked whether they <lb/>
would have them chosen from the Council or have the <lb/>
whole Island to choose from. I believe nine-tenths would <lb/>
pronounce in favor of the mode adopted in the Report. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Mr. DUNCAN</persName>: I was not opposed to a property <lb/>
qualification. either real or personal; but I said, and I <lb/>
think it is very strange, that they should be taken from <lb/>
the Councils in the other Provinces, and this Island be <lb/>
made an exception. The views of both parties were to be <lb/>
respected; but it is very possible that they had little pros<lb break="no"/>pect of finding persons favorable to their views in the <lb/>
Council of this Island. Whatever it was, I hope it will <lb/>
never be put to the test, for I hope we will never have <lb/>
more to do with them in that way than we have at present. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. J. C. POPE</persName>: It is not my intention to occupy <lb/>
the attention of the Committee for any length of time; but, <lb/>
regarding the remarks made by the Hon. the Leader of the <lb/>
Opposition. I must object to the principle that some mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Government disagreeing with others should re<lb break="no"/>sign. On the contrary, I think they should state their <lb/>
views on this great question freely, and independently. We <lb/>
know that the hon. member agreed to the Report of the <lb/>
Delegates at Quebec, as well as members of' the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Therefore, having been assented to by both, sides, <lb/>
it could scarcely be expected that it would be brought <lb/>
down as a Government measure; and suppose it had, there <lb/>
is a majority in the Government opposed to the Quebec <lb/>
Scheme, who do not think that Prince Edward Island <lb/>
should go into Confederation with Canada. And how is a <lb/>
Government to be carried on in the country? Suppose <lb/>
some members favorable to Confederation should resign- <lb break="yes"/> the Leader of the Opposition was favorable to it himself, <lb/>
and how would a Government be formed? Under all the <lb/>
circumstances, I do not think a resignation was called for, <lb/>
and it was so understood when Resolutions were introduced <lb/>
by myself last year. It was plainly stated that it was a <lb/>
free and open question, and that members could act as they <lb/>
thought proper. Allusion has been made to some pressure, <lb/>
brought to bear upon the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>: I only repeated what the hon. the <lb/>
Solicitor General said. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. J. C. POPE</persName>: I do not acknowledge a pressure <lb/>
from any quarter so long as I represent the views of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple and the majority of the Legislature. If a pressure were <lb/>
brought to bear upon me I would not hold the position <lb/>
which I occupy to-day. If the question were put to me I <lb/>
would, perhaps, say the Resolutions are stronger than I <lb/>
desire; but at the same time, there is a necessity at present <lb/>
to make them strong, so that there can be no possibility of <lb/>

<cb/>

mistaking what the views of the Legislature are. It has been <lb/>
said that Confederation could not be carried without an appeal <lb/>
to the people. In Nova Scotia it was not submitted to the <lb/>
people. In two or three places where elections were held <lb/>
the friends of the Scheme were rejected; but now there is a <lb/>
Delegation to be sent to England to arrange a Scheme of <lb/>
Confederation, and that Scheme is the Quebec Scheme of <lb/>
would be useless for us to send Delegates. This Island in <lb/>
so small in comparison with Canada and the other Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, that they would have no influence beyond the pro<lb break="no"/>portionate extent of country they would represent. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve the Governor of New Brunswick has taken an impro<lb break="no"/>per course. The Quebec Scheme was rejected at the polls; <lb/>
and how could the Governor carry on the business of the <lb/>
country with a Government opposed to the wishes of the <lb/>
people? Therefore, it beboves this House to pass stronger <lb/>
Resolutions than it would, perhaps, otherwise do, because I <lb/>
do think that if Nova Scotia and New Brunswick go into <lb/>
the Union, this Island must, sooner or later, go in also— <lb/>
At the same time we will not be told by the British Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment that we must go in, but a pressure will be brought <lb/>
to bear upon us, and we will be made to feel that it will be <lb/>
for our own interest to go in. The reason the Resolutions <lb/>
were made so strong was that a large majority might sup<lb break="no"/>port them, for if they were not strong, while there is such <lb/>
a strong feeling in the House and in the country, stronger <lb/>
Resolutions would be introduced, and parties would be <lb/>
split up. One or two more, perhaps, may declare in favor <lb/>
of Confederation than voted for itlast year; but the course <lb/>
pursued by the Colonial Secretary last year was such that <lb/>
members were debarred from voting on the abstract ques<lb break="no"/>tion of a Union of the Colonies. I dare say some will be <lb/>
prepared to vote against the Resolutions; but, as I believe <lb/>
that ninety-nine out of every hundred of the people are <lb/>
against Confederation, I think we, as their representatives, <lb/>
are bound to represent or express their views, even though <lb/>
the matter has not been submitted to them at an election, <lb/>
And as to the Government not being composed of members <lb/>
who are all favorable to the Quebec Scheme, if so, the Lead<lb break="no"/>er of the Opposition would support the Government, and <lb/>
we would have no Opposition at all. Now, there are two <lb/>
or three points in that Scheme which I particularly object <lb/>
to, though I do not intend to go into the details. Repre<lb break="no"/>sentation by population is not fair as regards this country. <lb/>
Where there are large towns there are not so many dif<lb break="no"/>ferent interests as there are in a country like this— <lb/>
Therefore, I do not believe in it as a principle. It is not <lb/>
favorably looked upon by reformers of the present day.— <lb/>
Even Earl Russell does not believe in representation by <lb/>
population. As was said here last year, by that rule <lb/>
London would have more representatives than Scotland- <lb break="yes"/>If I had acted as a delegate when the delegates from Ca<lb break="no"/>nada were here, and when they laid it. down that they <lb/>
would not entertain the question at all, unless representa<lb break="no"/>tion by Population were acceded to. I would stopped there <lb/>
and said no. I will not agree to it and [blame the Leader <lb/>
of the Opposition and those other delegates who agreed to <lb/>
it. They should not have done so; for it is one of the <lb/>
strongest objections to that scheme. The Solicitor General <lb/>
says he was opposed to Legislative Union; but, in my opin<lb break="no"/>ion, that is the proper Union for us to have if we have any. <lb/>
If we have a Parliament in Canada, what do we want with <lb/>
a Governor and Legislative Council and House of Assembly <lb/>
here? It is considered the next thing to a farce now. We <lb/>
are looked upon as too small to have a Government and <lb/>
Legislature. The thign would be absurd. If the Colonies <lb/>
were confederated, and we had our Local Legislature, you <lb/>

<pb n="117" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_117.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">117</fw>

here and go through the farce of legislating. The Island <lb/>
would dwindle down to the position of a small rotten borough. <lb/>
These are two of the strongest objections I have to the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Scheme. I do not find fault with gentlemen for adhering <lb/>
to what they agreed to in Canada; but I do not think it <lb/>
was fair for the Canadians to come here and say "We will <lb/>
not entertain the question unless you acknowledge this prim<lb break="no"/>ciple." The Leader of the Opposition said he would rather <lb/>
see the middle paragraph struck out of the Resolutions. So <lb/>
would I; but I said they were here for the House to deal <lb/>
with them as it thought proper. The Resolution says:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"This House cannot admit that a Federal Union of the North <lb/>
American Colonies, that would include Prince Edward Island, could <lb/>
ever be accomplished upon terms that would prove advantageous to <lb/>
the interests and well-being of the people of this Island, cut off and <lb/>
separated as it is, and must ever remain, from the neighbouring Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, by an immovable barrier of ice for many months in the year; <lb/>
and this House deems it to be its sacred and imperative duty to de<lb break="no"/>clare and record its conviction, as it now does, that any Federal Union <lb/>
of the North American Colonies, that would include Prince Edward <lb/>
Island, would be as hostile to the feelings and wishes, as it would be <lb/>
opposed to the best and most vital interests of its people." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Now, that is the strong part of the Resolutions; but what is <lb/>
meant is that we presume that no terms could be got from <lb/>
the Canadians, that would be just and acceptable to the <lb/>
people of this Island. But once make an admission that we <lb/>
are favorable to a Union and there is a probability of our be<lb break="no"/>ing dragged into it in such a way that we could not well <lb/>
extricate ourselves from it. As I believe these Resolutions <lb/>
represent the views of the majority of the people, I have, so <lb/>
far, very little objection to them. I am prepared to vote <lb/>
for them as they are; and, if the House should choose to <lb/>
strike out the middle paragraph, I would care very little <lb/>
about it. The Resolutions of last year were strong, and the <lb/>
first Resolution here conveys all that is required to confirm <lb/>
them; which, for me, would have been strong enough. I <lb/>
said, Sir, on rising, that I did not intend to prolong the de<lb break="no"/>bate, and it may be considered presumption in me to <lb/>
criticise the amendment of the hon. member for St. <lb/>
Peter's (Mr. Whelan); but I do not think I can give him <lb/>
credit for its being a very able and straightforward Resolu<lb break="no"/>tion. It says: <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"RESOLVED, as the opinion of this House, that the Confederation <lb/>
of Her Majesty's American Colonial possessions would be—while in <lb/>
conformity with Her Majesty's frequently expressed desire—condu<lb break="no"/>cive to their welfare, separately and collectively. * * * * But <lb/>
inasmuch as the people of Prince Edward Island do not appear to be <lb/>
prepared to regard with any favor the project of Confederation, it is <lb/>
unwise to press it upon public attention, as its discussion is only cal<lb break="no"/>culated to produce excitement and apprehension, without a reasonable <lb/>
cause. <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Now, I consider it to be the duty of a representative of the <lb/>
people, if he considers that any measure would be for their <lb/>
benefit to bring it before, and urge it upon them; but to say <lb/>
that although, in his opinion, it would be conducive to the wel<lb break="no"/>fare of the people, yet, because they do not think so, it should <lb/>
be pressed, is not a good argument. If I considered any <lb/>
matter to be for the good of the country, I think it would be <lb/>
my duty to advocate it, whether the people were satisfied <lb/>
with it or not; and if he believes his constituency would be <lb/>
benefited by Confederation, he should use every means in his <lb/>
power to bring the people up to it, instead of saying because <lb/>
the people do not think so it is fully to press it. Then, if he <lb/>
admits that the people are not in favour of it, the proper way <lb/>
would be to go against Confederation in any shape. I take <lb/>
it, that a gentleman standing here should represent the views <lb/>
of his constituency. If he is satisfied that any measure is for <lb/>
the good of the country, it is his duty to go to the country <lb/>
and stand or fall by it; and if he cannot make the people be<lb break="no"/>lieve that it is for their interests, he should either keep his <lb/>
opinion in abeyance, or retire, and let the people choose an<lb break="no"/>other who would represent their views. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr. COLES</persName>: The Hon. the Leader of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment said that the Delegates should not have consented to <lb/>
the principle of representation by population. They did not <lb/>
consent to it; for, after the Canadian Delegates came here <lb/>
and stated their case, the first Delegation ceased, and another <lb/>

<cb/>

was appointed. Therefore, it was for the Government to con<lb break="no"/>sider the matter. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. GRAY</persName>: The Hon. the Leader of the Opposition <lb/>
was not present when the Canadian Delegates declared that <lb/>
they would not entertain the question unless the principle of <lb/>
representation according to population were acceded to. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE7">Mr. McLENNAN</persName>: It was my intention to have addressed <lb/>
the Committee at an earlier stage of the debate; but as the <lb/>
big guns wished to fire off first, I was prepared to listen to <lb/>
their report, if not to feel their shot; and as the remarks I <lb/>
intended to make have been already expressed, I shall not <lb/>
now detain the House by repeating them.—When the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of the Quebec Scheme was before us last year, I said <lb/>
that anything I might say would not hasten or retard the <lb/>
Union. I am of the same opinion still. Whatever change may <lb/>
have taken place outside, it is evident that there is some <lb/>
change in the members of this House since last year. It is <lb/>
certainly a very important question, and the hon. member <lb/>
for New Glasgow (Mr. Longworth) said, yesterday, that we <lb/>
should be very guarded for it would be legislating for our <lb/>
children's children. That I admit; but at the same time I <lb/>
would not say that there never could be a scheme of Union pro<lb break="no"/>pounded which would be a benefit to the Island. I have no <lb/>
desire to misrepresent any member of this House; but I be<lb break="no"/>lieve there are some who are extremely strong anti-confe<lb break="no"/>derates; and without doing any injustice to the hon. member <lb/>
for Murray Harbour (Mr. Duncan) I believe he would bind <lb/>
his children and children's children never to take any action <lb/>
in Confederation; but I have no desire to do that. I stand <lb/>
here as the representative of as independent, progressive and <lb/>
intelligent a constituency as there is on the Island; but I have <lb/>
no desire to bind them, or their children, not to go for Confe<lb break="no"/>deration. The hon. and learned member for Charlottetown, <lb/>
(Hon. Mr. Brecken) said, yesterday, that the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was determined to carry Confederation. If so, any<lb break="no"/>thing I can say will not prevent it. He, at the same time, <lb/>
admitted that we would be a great deal stronger if we were <lb/>
united. I was glad to hear him say so, for I am of the same <lb/>
opinion. I would be satisfied to remain as we are, if the <lb/>
other Colonies would do so. I believe we have progressed, <lb/>
according to our means and resources, as much as the other <lb/>
Colonies for the last few years; but, if they will unite, the <lb/>
great question for us to consider will be, whether we will go <lb/>
with them or remain as we are? I want to leave it an open <lb/>
question; and, for that reason, I willsupport the amendment <lb/>
introduced by the hon. member from St. Peter's (Mr. Whe<lb break="no"/>lan). Many things have been said about bribery—that those <lb/>
in favor of Confederation are bribed: as well might we say <lb/>
that those against it are bribed. I believe that those in the <lb/>
other Provinces who have the most means are against Con<lb break="no"/>federation, and why would not they be as likely to use bri<lb break="no"/>bery as those who are in favor of it. I consider the conduct <lb/>
of the hon. member, the Leader of the Opposition, to be as <lb/>
inconsistent as that of any member of this House; and, in <lb/>
fact, I believe it is getting like the land question. I did <lb/>
not think, when the Conference was held at Quebec that <lb/>
this question would be settled in such a short time. We <lb/>
hear some members express some very extraordinary ideas. <lb/>
The hon. member from the East Point (Mr. McEachen) <lb/>
would defy the British Government to take away our Con<lb break="no"/>stitution. And then it is said we will show our loyalty by <lb/>
placing the whole Revenue at the disposal of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. What would our whole Revenue do towards defend<lb break="no"/>ing us, if the British Government should cast us off? We <lb/>
acknowledge Great Britain as our parent, and we know that <lb/>
parents, when their children disobey, will cast them off; so <lb/>
will she do with us. If I were to support the Resolutions of <lb/>
the Hon. the Leader of the Government, I believe I would be <lb/>
advancing or advocating Confederation more strongly than <lb/>
in supporting the amendment. We are not gomg to say to <lb/>
the Mother Country " We will not listen to your sugges<lb break="no"/>tions ": We are not going to say " They may withdraw all <lb/>
their troops; but then see how loyal we are!" What <lb/>
would our whole revenue do? It would not equip and com<lb break="no"/>mand one good gun boat. We talk about our Militia and <lb/>
Volunteers. I spent some time in connection with the vol<lb break="no"/> 

<pb n="118" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_118.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">118</fw>

unteer movement myself; but I got tired of it, and tendered <lb/>
my resignation last year. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. GRAY</persName>. It was not received through the <lb/>
proper authority. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE7">Mr. McLENNAN</persName>. Well, I never was notifiedthat <lb/>
such was the case. I shall not detain the Committee any <lb/>
longer. I have listened to long speeches here, but I often <lb/>
think they are intended for electioneering dodges, but it is <lb/>
not so with me. I believe my constituency understand my <lb/>
views, and I will abide by the consequences. I do not see <lb/>
why any hon. member should object to the amendment; <lb/>
nor do I see why we should say that no Scheme of Union <lb/>
that could be propounded would be a benefit to the Island. <lb/>
Circumstances alter cases and circumstances have changed <lb/>
since last year. Then we had a flourishing trade with the <lb/>
United States, but now it is cut off. I would not bind <lb/>
myself or my children to pursue any particular line of con<lb break="no"/>duct. With these few remarks I will support the amend<lb break="no"/>ment. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>. I did say that union would strength<lb break="no"/>en British America, and I am of the same opinion still; <lb/>
but at the Quebec Conference, due regard was not paid to <lb/>
the interests of this Island. I have no respect for the man <lb/>
who would advocate or condemn this Scheme for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of popularity. Perhaps the advocates of Union occupy <lb/>
a more honorable position in this House than those who op<lb break="no"/>pose it; but I would not advocate it for that reason. I <lb/>
do not altogether agree with the wording of the Resolution; <lb/>
but I would not entertain the question at all unless there <lb/>
was a prospect of getting the terms changed. I give the <lb/>
hon. member (Mr. Whelan) credit for the ingenious way in <lb/>
which he has worded the amendment. It admits the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of Confederations, and the terms were said, by the <lb/>
Colonial Secretary, to be just and liberal to Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island. I presume the hon. member did not refer to <lb/>
the Quebec Scheme, though I think the amendment has <lb/>
some connection with it. And is there any prospect of a <lb/>
change being made so that the interests of this Colony will <lb/>
be protected? I do not want to see a Union at the ex<lb break="no"/>pense of the people of this Island; and I believe the men <lb/>
who propounded that scheme did not know anything <lb/>
about the local circumstances of this Island. I have not <lb/>
thrown out any improper insinuations. I would accord to <lb/>
every man the same respect as I would claim for myself. <lb/>
But I believe it is mere delusion to talk about the Quebec <lb/>
Scheme. Let the Canadians show the people of Prince <lb/>
Edward Island that, while they pay due regard to the <lb/>
broad principle of Union, they will give us a chance to live <lb/>
—that our peculiar wants and circumstances will be pro<lb break="no"/>perly looked after—and not say to us " you must take <lb/>
any particular scheme of Union, " when they do not know <lb/>
anything about our circumstances. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Mr. SINCLAIR</persName> the hon. member from Summerside <lb/>
(Mr. McLennan) will not vote for the Resolutions of the <lb/>
hon. the Leader of the Government, because they would <lb/>
bind us for all time to come; but that is only a matter of <lb/>
opinion. The next House may pass very different Resolu<lb break="no"/>tions. I do not see how any hon. member can vote for the <lb/>
amendment; for it is certainly a strange Resolution. It <lb/>
admits that Confederation would be for the benefit of the <lb/>
Island, and yet says it is unwise to press it upon the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the people, because it would create unnecessary <lb/>
apprehension in their winds. The meaning I take out of <lb/>
it is, that it is better to let the thing slide on—to let Dele<lb break="no"/>gates be appointed and sent to England—to let a Scheme <lb/>
be concocted and carried into effort, and the people allowed <lb/>

<cb/>

to pass an opinion on it at a general election afterwards. <lb/>
The Resolution says:— "And this House believes that a <lb/>
plan of Confederation might be so framed as not to involve <lb/>
the sacrifice of any material interests on the part of any <lb/>
Province; but, inasmuch as the people of Prince Edward <lb/>
Island do not appear to be prepared to regard with any <lb/>
favor the project of Confederation, it is unwise to press it <lb/>
upon public attention, as its discussion is only calculated <lb/>
to produce excitement and apprehension without reasonable <lb/>
cause." What is the meaning of this, if it is not that the <lb/>
people of Prince Edward Island are not capable of forming <lb/>
an opinion, and, therefore, it is better to pass a Resolution <lb/>
to allow the British Government to take action, and then <lb/>
it will be time enough to press it upon public attention. I <lb/>
agree with the hon. member from Murray Harbor (Mr. <lb/>
Duncan) inasmuch as I do not see how we could vote for <lb/>
that Resolution, and refuse to appoint a Delegation. The <lb/>
hon. member from Summerside (Mr. McLennan) said that <lb/>
if the British Government was determined to unite the Co<lb break="no"/>lonies, it was little matter whether he supported the Resolu<lb break="no"/>tion or not—that it would be as well to drop the subject <lb/>
and leave it alone. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE7">Mr. McLENNAN</persName> I did not say that it would be as <lb/>
well to drop the subject and leave it alone. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Mr. SINCLAIR</persName> I understood the hon. member to say <lb/>
that it would be as well to take no action on it. The Bri<lb break="no"/>tish Government has certainly expressed a desire that the <lb/>
Colonies would unite; but we are not told that we are to <lb/>
be forced into a Union. The Colonial Minister, in his Des<lb break="no"/>patch, expressed an earnest desire for the consolidation of <lb/>
the British Provinces in one Government. In regard to <lb/>
Colonial defences, I would be willing that the views of the <lb/>
British Government should be urged upon the Colonies <lb/>
with all just authority. While I believe we are willing to <lb/>
allow that—for I consider it to be our duty to give all due <lb/>
consideration to the opinion of the British Government in <lb/>
things of that kind—yet, sir, I am of opinion that we owe a <lb/>
higher duty to our country and to our children—the duty <lb/>
to preserve the inalienable right of self-government. "Self-<lb break="yes"/>preservation is the first law of nature." and it will hold good <lb/>
with regard to nations and colonies, as well as individuals. <lb/>
We are willing to contribute of our means, but not to give <lb/>
up our liberties, which our fathers have obtained for us. <lb/>
Though we are a small Colony and unable to offer any for<lb break="no"/>midable resistance, that is no reason that we should volun<lb break="no"/>tarily surrender a Constitution with which we are satisfied. <lb/>
We are prepared to do everything in our power, within the <lb/>
bonds of reason, to maintain our connection with the Bri<lb break="no"/>tish Empire. We have liberty to tax ourselves, and we are <lb/>
prepared to do our part; therefore, I do not think the <lb/>
British Government will ever attempt to coerce us into a <lb/>
Union against the wishes of the people, and which we <lb/>
believe would be prejudicial to our interests. It <lb/>
is useless for us to go into the details of the Scheme or <lb/>
to point out all the disadvantages to the Island of a Union <lb/>
with Canada. It is admitted by nearly all, even those in <lb/>
favor of a Union, that it would not be an advantage to the <lb/>
Island to enter the Union on the basis of the Quebec Scheme; <lb/>
and, for my part, I do not expect to get better terms, <lb/>
though, even if we could we are an exception to the other <lb/>
Colonies. and a basis of Union which would be suitable and <lb/>
advantageous to them would not be so to us. I might <lb/>
point out objections which I have to the form of the Consti<lb break="no"/>tution, but I do not intend to go minutely into the merits <lb/>
or demerits of the Quebec Schemes. It is a conglomerate <lb/>
Constitution which I do not think would be, or should be, <lb/>
sanctioned by the people of British North America. <lb/></p>

<pb n="119" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_119.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">119</fw>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. McEACHEN</persName>. I think it would be better <lb/>
if the hon. member from Georgetown (Mr. Haviland) would <lb/>
propound some feasible scheme of Union than to work <lb/>
himself into such a flaring passion. It is a very bad sign <lb/>
of a cause when its advocates lose their temper. Indeed <lb/>
the advocates of Confederation appear to be very thin-<lb break="yes"/>skinned. I never accused them of being bribed, but I have <lb/>
no doubt but they may have seen something looming in the <lb/>
distance which dazzled their eyes. I do not say it was <lb/>
gold; perhaps it was something else. I suppose those gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen who sold Ireland for £600 000 were as sensi<lb break="no"/>tive touching their personal honor as the gentlemen who held <lb/>
the Conference at Quebec. The Hon. Sol. General made <lb/>
allusion to the stand the Catholic Bishops have taken, but I <lb/>
do not believe they understood the situation of the question; <lb/>
and, if they think to get us bound to Canada, they are mis<lb break="no"/>taken. The people who hunted the Prince of Wales from <lb/>
town to town as if he was a wild beast escaped from a mena<lb break="no"/>gerie, are not the people with whom they would be willing <lb/>
to be united. I wish the advocates of Union had pro<lb break="no"/>pounded some Scheme instead of scolding us; and, as they <lb/>
have not done so, I still adhere to the opinion I expressed <lb/>
yesterday. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName>. In reply to the Hon. Sol. General, <lb/>
I would say that when I was young there were very few pub<lb break="no"/>lic schools, and when he was going to school, I was probably <lb/>
holding the plough or working in a ship-yard. I do not pre<lb break="no"/>tend to be able to use very classical language, but if I can <lb/>
make people understand me, that is all I want. Though I <lb/>
have not had a liberal education, yet I have some natural <lb/>
ability. Nature has not been so niggardly to me that I <lb/>
have not been able to provide for myself; and I did not need <lb/>
the help of a father to set me agoing. I feel the want of <lb/>
education—I do not deny it; but I would call the attention <lb/>
of the House to the amendment which says; " This House <lb/>
believes that a plan of Confederation might be so planned as <lb/>
not to involve the sacrifice of any material interests on the <lb/>
part of any Province." Now, if that is the case, who is the <lb/>
party to frame it? I know the gentleman who drew up that <lb/>
Resolution has had a good education, and he has drawn it up <lb/>
in a very nice way. Perhaps he will not deny that there is <lb/>
some prize in the distance. The Resolution implies that it is <lb/>
possible to frame some plan of Union which would be accept<lb break="no"/>able to the people, and if we make that admission, just when <lb/>
the House is rising, it will be an excuse for appointing a Dele<lb break="no"/>gation I believe the man who votes for that resolution <lb/>
votes for a Union of some sort, and he must do so either igno<lb break="no"/>rantly or intentionally. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. SOL. GENERAL</persName>. I must reply to the hon. member <lb/>
from Murray Harbour again. He says that if we agree to <lb/>
this amendment we will be selling the rights of the people— <lb/>
that the Governor will be bound to appoint a Delegation to <lb/>
Downing Street. Do we not kwnow that Governors who come <lb/>
out here have previously served an apprenticeship in the <lb/>
House of Commons? And if one should come here who is <lb/>
a stranger, would he not enquire if a majority in the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature would support a Delegation? If not, he would say <lb/>
he could not appoint one. The hon. member has made <lb/>
a great blow off respecting his position, which he has <lb/>
obtained altogether in consequence of his own merits. He <lb/>
has thrown out an insinuation—and I take his challenge— <lb/>
that I hold my position in consequence of the assistance of <lb/>
my father. I say, before this House and the country, that I <lb/>
owe nothing to my father as regards my political or pecuniary <lb/>
position. Though I have a father who is well off, he has <lb/>
kept his money to himself, and left me to fight my own <lb/>
battles. The hon. member boasts that his talent has placed <lb/>
him where he is; but what I produce is my own, and free <lb/>
from outside influence. What I protect against is, that <lb/>
members of the House do not enunciate their own views, but <lb/>
use what is placed in their hands by back-street influence <lb/>
outside of the Legislature. This I say deliberately, and hon. <lb/>
members are at liberty to take the constitutional course re<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

lative to the statement I now make. But I am not going to <lb/>
stultify myself with regard to this question. It is my interest <lb/>
to advocate what I consider to be for the interest of the Co<lb break="no"/>lony. I have three sons and three daughters who were born <lb/>
here, and that shows that it is not a mere matter of moon<lb break="no"/>shine with me. Hon. members may say what they like <lb/>
about gold, but let them prove their base insinuationss. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Mr. HOWLAN</persName>. No member used the word "<hi rendition="simple:italic">gold</hi>." <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. SOL. GENERAL</persName>. I say it was used. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Mr. HOWLAN</persName>. If any person used it, it was the hon. <lb/>
member from St. Peter's. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. SOL. GENERAL</persName>. I have heard a member of this <lb/>
House use it outside of these walls. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Mr. HOWLAN</persName>. We should not say anything here about <lb/>
assertions made outside. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. SOL. GENERAL</persName>. It is my firm belief that it has <lb/>
been used, but if the majority say it was not, I will bow to <lb/>
their decision, yet I will not bow to the individual opinion <lb/>
of the hon. member from Cascumpec. The hon. member <lb/>
from the East Point may say that I speak in an excited man<lb break="no"/>ner on this subject, but when I hear the Hon. member from <lb/>
Murray Harbor (Mr. Duncan) attempt to put a construction <lb/>
upon this Resolution which I will not bear, I must speak as I <lb/>
have done. And when it says that no action should be <lb/>
taken till an appeal is made to the people, and he says that <lb/>
it will authorize the appointment of a Delegation—that the <lb/>
country may be sold—and such like assertions; I say he <lb/>
does not understand the Resolution, and he must believe that <lb/>
every man in the Government is as corrupt as he can be. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HASL1">Mr. HASLEM</persName>. I think such insinuations are quite un<lb break="no"/>called for, and are highly improper. I have heard the term <lb/>
" Canadian gold " used, but I cannot believe that any hon. <lb/>
member of this House would be so corrupt as to accept a bribe <lb/>
to sell his country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Mr. DUNCAN</persName>. I said that if the Government would not <lb/>
do so, others would. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. GRAY</persName>. The hon. member from Murray Har<lb break="no"/>bour (Mr. Duncan) insinuated a great deal, such as a mem<lb break="no"/>ber by his vote being guilty of treason to his constituency. <lb/>
What does he mean by treason? If a gentleman goes down <lb/>
to a constituency at the request of another, and that gentle<lb break="no"/>man turns round and throws out a groundless insinuation <lb/>
against the gentleman who supported him, what connection <lb/>
would that have with treason? Or will he say how far my <lb/>
supporting the amendment will be treason to my consti<lb break="no"/>tuency? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Mr. DUNCAN</persName>. I do not know what the hon. and gallant <lb/>
Col. means unless it is that he returned me to the House of <lb/>
Assembly. If so, I was not aware of it, and if it is the case, I <lb/>
must thank him, not my constituency; but they did not give <lb/>
me to understand that they were voting for Col. Gray. I <lb/>
thought they were voting for James Duncan. I am still of <lb/>
opinion, that if we pass this amendment, the Governor will <lb/>
have it in his power to send a Delegation to Downing Street. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. J. C. POPE</persName>. He can do that at any time. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Mr. SINCLAIR</persName>. Should we vote for the amendment <lb/>
would it not be voting in favour of Confederation? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. SOL. GENERAL</persName>. We want no action taken till it is <lb/>
decided at the polls; and no action to bind the Colony would <lb/>
be proper without an appeal to the people. If the hon. <lb/>
member would read the Resolution carefully, I think he would <lb/>
form the same opinion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Mr. SINCLAIR</persName>. I have read the Resolution carefully, <lb/>
and the opinion I have formed is that if it is adopted this <lb/>
House will be voting in favour of Confederation. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. SOL. GENERAL</persName>. It merely admits that practicable <lb/>
terms of Union could be devised, and it is impossible to lay <lb/>
down the principle, that no terms could be devised, which <lb/>
would be beneficial to this Colony. We admit that such <lb/>
terms could be devised, but in consequence of the extraor<lb break="no"/>dinary feeling in the country against Confederation, it would <lb/>
be injudicious to press the matter till after a general election. <lb/>

<pb n="120" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_120.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">120</fw>

Were the Governor to appoint a Delegation without an appeal <lb/>
to the people, he would be guilty of an unconstitutional act, <lb/>
unless he had a majority in the Government to support him <lb/>
in doing so. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WHEL1">Hon. Mr. WHELAN</persName>. I mean to say a word about the <lb/>
amendment. You know, Mr. Chairman, that I have not <lb/>
trespassed on the patience of the Committee, and you, Sir, <lb/>
have exercised a degree of forbearance highly commendable <lb/>
during this long debate; but it would be unwise to trespass <lb/>
upon your time at this late hour with any lengthy remarks; <lb/>
yet I think I should say a word or two in reference to some <lb/>
remarks which have been made in this debate. Before doing <lb/>
so, let me express my satisfaction at the calmness and mo<lb break="no"/>deration with which this debate has been conducted. It is <lb/>
certainly an improvement on the debates of last year, and <lb/>
leads us to suppose that, though we are not improving very <lb/>
extensively in regard to Confederation, yet we are in good <lb/>
temper; but I believe we are also improving in our views of <lb/>
Confederation — improving inasmuch as we admit that if the <lb/>
other Provinces unite we cannot stand out. I will not tres<lb break="no"/>pass upon your time, but I have a right to ask the indulgence <lb/>
of this hon. Committee for five minutes to refute some obser<lb break="no"/>vations made in opposition to my views yesterday evening <lb/>
and to-day. Yesterday evening in particular, I was assailed <lb/>
by my hon. friend from Cascumpee (Mr. Howlan) on the <lb/>
ground of my inconsistency in making a speech in this House, <lb/>
in 1864, on this question of Confederation. But it was not <lb/>
on the broad question of Confederation I then spoke, and <lb/>
the hon. member knows that he did not fairly represent me. <lb/>
It was in reference to a Legislative Union of the Colonies, and <lb/>
he knows that I have always been opposed to a Legislative <lb/>
Union. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Mr HOWLAN</persName>. I did not state anything in disparage<lb break="no"/>ment of the hon. member; but I showed that the views held <lb/>
by him now, were not the same as those held by him then. I <lb/>
quoted this passion:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"I care not for the nature of the Union, whether it be Federal of <lb/>
Legislative, either will be absurd while we remain tied to the apron-<lb break="yes"/>strings of our venerable mother—Great Britain. The time will come <lb/>
when, as foreshadowed by the statesmen and politicians of Britain, <lb/>
the Colonies will be cast off; and when that time shall arrive, they <lb/>
may, with far more propriety than at present, discuss the principle <lb/>
and details of a Union, either Federal or Legislative." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WHEL1">Hon. Mr. WHELAN</persName>. I ask you, Mr. Chairman, to pro<lb break="no"/>tect me in my position on the floor. I do not wish to hinder <lb/>
independent members from speaking, especially young mem<lb break="no"/>bers; and I am always willing to give to my friend, the <lb/>
junior member from prince County, a latitude which I would <lb/>
not be disposed to give to others. The extract from the <lb/>
speech he has read ought to be thoroughly impressed upon <lb/>
my mind, inasmuch as it has been called to it so frequently. <lb/>
It does not establish the proof of my inconsistency. I protest <lb/>
against it. That speech will show that I was not favorably <lb/>
disposed towards a Legislative Union at the time. A Fe<lb break="no"/>deral Union is another question. In what light did I view <lb/>
it, or how was it viewed by other members of this house?-<lb break="yes"/>that we would still be subservient to the Colonial Office as <lb/>
we are now?—It is not that the experience I have gained-<lb break="yes"/>not that the intelligence communicated to me from other <lb/>
quarters—not that I am inspired by undue motives that cause <lb/>
an apparent change of sentiment on my part —but that I <lb/>
have a perfect right to exercise my judgment in reference to <lb/>
this and other matters. But even if I admit that there was <lb/>
a slight shade of inconsistency on my part, why should this <lb/>
be brought up as an argument against Confederation? We <lb/>
know that a great change of opinion has taken place in all the <lb/>
other Colonies. Has it not been the case in Canada? And <lb/>
in New Brunswick, where the Government came in with a <lb/>
large majority, a little more than twelve months ago, has not <lb/>
a chance taken place there? In all the other Colonies pub<lb break="no"/>lic opinion has been undergoing a change in reference to this <lb/>
question. it has changed in the Nova Scotia Legislature, in<lb break="no"/>asmuch as last winter Dr. Tupper could not venture to ask <lb/>
the House to pass a Resolution in favour of Confederation, <lb/>
and this year it has been carried by a majority of 31 to 19. <lb/>
Does not this show that there is a change in public senti<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

ment?—That it is progressing with the progress of intelli<lb break="no"/>gence all over the Continent? Does it not show that public <lb/>
men have a right to exercise the privilege at times of cor<lb break="no"/>recting their ideas? I scorn the man—I say it without dis<lb break="no"/>respect to any gentleman in this House or community—I <lb/>
scorn the man who says he is incapable of changing his mind <lb/>
on important public questions. I change mine from time to <lb/>
time, if it is in conformity with the progress of the age in <lb/>
which I live. And I do not think I bring any discredit upon <lb/>
myself by doing so. This has been the character by which <lb/>
public men have been distinguished in Great Britain and all <lb/>
over the world. I would allude to one who has changed his <lb/>
opinion on this question. I mean the Hon. Mr. Howe of <lb/>
Nova Scotia. He was at one time decidedly in favor of a <lb/>
Confederation of all the British North American Colonies. <lb/>
Now he is not. The reason why. I shall not explain to you <lb/>
at present; but I believe that if he had been at the Quebec <lb/>
Conference he would have acted a very different part from <lb/>
what he has done. <lb/></p> 

<p>Now, the hon. member from Cascumpee has referred to <lb/>
the speech of Mr. Gladstone wherein he says— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"We are told that Canada and New Brunswick are threatened <lb/>
with fire and slaughter from the revenge of the Fenians for the <lb/>
wrongs inflicted by England upon Ireland; and this I must say, that <lb/>
if the men of Canada and New Brunswick, who are wholly guiltless <lb/>
of these wrongs—be they what they may—who are not entangled in <lb/>
the controversy, who have no more to do with it than the people of <lb/>
the Sandwich Islands—if the Fenians, as they call themselves in <lb/>
America, are capable of the abominable wickedness of passing their <lb/>
frontier and of making their impotent miserable attempts, which <lb/>
they will be (cheers) to carry desolation over these peaceful districts <lb/>
and among those harmless colonists, then, I say, that so far from <lb/>
your treating the conduct of these men—let them be Americans or <lb/>
whom they like—with allowance or indulgence, no more execrable <lb/>
manifestations of folly or guilt have ever been made in the annals of <lb/>
the human race from the time that it commenced its existence upon <lb/>
the earth. (Cheers.) Men who are capable of such proceedings <lb/>
would at once by their insanity and their guilt place themselves <lb/>
entirely beyond the sympathy of the whole civilized world (Loud <lb/>
cheers".) <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>What interpretation can the hon. member put upon these <lb/>
words? Is it that of Great Britain finds the Colonies in a <lb/>
position to help themselves, then the power of the British <lb/>
Government will be employed to supplement their resources <lb/>
for defence. Can any hon. member place any other inter<lb break="no"/>pretation on these words? Again, Mr. Gladstone says in <lb/>
the same speech:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">I feel the fullest confidence that these men who inhabit the provinces of <lb/>
British North America, who have proceeded from our loins, and who are <lb/>
governed by principles in the mun our own, knom well how to defend their <lb/>
homes, their wives, and children</hi>; and if, unhappily, the need arose, <lb/>
there is no resource possessed by this country that she would not fairly <lb/>
spend to assist them in their holy work. (Cheers".) <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>What does that indicate? A feeling on the part of the British <lb/>
Government that the people of these Colonies will have to defend <lb/>
their own homes, and in the event of their failing to d so then <lb/>
Great Britain will withdraw her support. I will not address <lb/>
myself to the questions at present as to whether we should be in<lb break="no"/>fluenced by the opinions of Statesmen in England or not. The hon. <lb/>
member from Cascumpee gave the opinion of the British Minister; <lb/>
but he did not give his words. I have given the words of Mr. <lb/>
Gladstone's speech t show the connection in which they were used, <lb/>
and they plainly indicate that when the Colonies use their proper <lb/>
amount of influence to protect themselves, then the power of Great <lb/>
Britain would be used in their behalf. That was the opinion I set <lb/>
forth last year. It is borne out by the opinion of Mr. Gladstone, <lb/>
and also by Her Majesty's Colonial Minister. I will read an extract <lb/>
from the Colonial Minister's despatch, not only for the information <lb/>
of the hon. member from Cascumpee, but other members who may <lb/>
have forgotten it:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"But there is one consideration which Her Majesty's Government <lb/>
feel it more especially their duty to press upon the Legislature of <lb/>
Nova Scotia. Looking to the determination which this country has <lb/>
ever exhibited to regard the defence of the colonies as a matter of <lb/>
Imperial concern, the colonies must recognize a right and even <lb/>
acknowledge an obligation incumbent on the House Government to <lb/>
urge with earnestness and just authority the measure which they <lb/>
consider most expedient on the part of the colonists, with a view to <lb/>
their own defence. <lb/>

<pb n="121" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_121.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">121</fw>

"Nor can it be doubtful that the Provinces of British North Ame<lb break="no"/>rica are incapable, when separate and divided from each other, of <lb/>
making those just and efficient preparations for national defence <lb/>
which would be easily undertaken by a Province uniting in itself all <lb/>
the population and the resources of the whole." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Now, what lesson are we to take from these words? Is it not <lb/>
that the Colonies must accept the Imperial policy? Is it not that <lb/>
one Colony will not be allowed to stand int he way of the Imperial <lb/>
policy which will be found acceptable to the majority? Is it not <lb/>
clear that the whole question of Confederation, no matter what <lb/>
view we may take, depends on the action of the continental Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. I am sure that I am quite willing to stand up for our <lb/>
rights and privileges; but is it to be supposed that we will be al<lb break="no"/>lowed to be regarded by the British Government as obstructive to <lb/>
the Continental Provinces, if they choose to adopt a Scheme of <lb/>
Confederation? I think not. Others may think differently, and <lb/>
we may agree to differ. My opinion is that if Nova Scotia, New <lb/>
Brunswick, Canada and Newfoundland, unite, Prince Edward <lb/>
Island may hold out for a short time, and seek for better terms; <lb/>
but it cannot hold out long. The Quebec Scheme is not before <lb/>
the Committee, and it is unfair to argue upon that Scheme. If it <lb/>
were before us then I might express my opinion upon it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. J. C. POPE</persName>: There is no other Scheme proposed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WHEL1">Hon. Mr. WHELAN</persName>: No, there is not plan at all; and the bare <lb/>
question is whether it is desirable that the Colonies should be con<lb break="no"/>federated or not. I do not press it upon the people's attention <lb/>
now, and when I was at Quebec I thought some of the details <lb/>
were such as the people would be dissatisfied with. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOR1">Hon. Mr. THORNTON</persName>: What is your scheme? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WHEL1">Hon. Mr. WHELAN</persName>: I propounded none. It was not my <lb/>
place to do so. I was there as a delegate, and though I objected <lb/>
to some of the details, yet I felt myself in that position that I could <lb/>
not refuse to accept it as a compromise. The delegates from all <lb/>
the Provinces had complaints to make about it; and who, pray, <lb/>
in his sense would suppose that a written Constitution could be <lb/>
framed that would be acceptable to all the people concerned in <lb/>
it? Could it be possible that a Constitution, affecting the rights <lb/>
of nearly four million sof people would be so framed that no fault <lb/>
could be found with it? When it came up that the Constitution <lb/>
was to be framed on the principles of representation by population, <lb/>
I had to yield to the majority. Now, though perhaps I am tres<lb break="no"/>passing in making these observations at this late hour. I would, <lb/>
before sitting down, ask the question of the hon. member from <lb/>
Murray Harbour (Mr. Duncan) whether he really believed what <lb/>
he said when he declared that this Resolution would give the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment authority to send a Delegation to England without the <lb/>
people being first consulted? But I believe he is not in his place/ <lb/>
There is no mistaking the language of the Resolution; and no <lb/>
language could be more moderate. I believe it will be considered <lb/>
by a succeeding House that Confederation will be for the benefit <lb/>
of all the Colonies, and that it would be possible to frame a Con<lb break="no"/>stitution that would not involve the sacrifice of any material in<lb break="no"/>terests on the part of any Province. Can any body doubt for a <lb/>
moment that a plan might be devised which would not involve the <lb/>
sacrifice of the interests of Prince Edward Island? Are we to be <lb/>
for ever excluded from what the Continental Provinces consider a <lb/>
benefit? Well, I cannot congratulate these members who think <lb/>
we should remain forever in our present feeble, isolated position/ It <lb/>
would render us contemptible to pass a Resolution to that effect. The <lb/>
amendment says:—" This House believes that a plan for Confede<lb break="no"/>ration might be so framed as to not involve the sacrifice of any <lb/>
material interests on the part of any Province." Who is to deny <lb/>
that? The Hon. the Leader of the Government, in the course of <lb/>
his speech, made some reference to this paragraph, and said those <lb/>
who believed that Confederation would be a benefit to this Colony <lb/>
should use their influence in every way to press it upon the people. <lb/>
I do not think so. I think it would be unwise to force public <lb/>
attention to anything in which the minds of the people have not <lb/>
been properly schooled. I think it would be better to leave it to <lb/>
take its course, and let the hand of time use its ameliorating in<lb break="no"/>fluence in reference to this as well as every other question. I bow to <lb/>
the public opinion of this country in reference to all public questions. <lb/>
When I returned from Canada, in 1864, I called meetings and told <lb/>
my constituents the opinion I entertained, and which I will pro<lb break="no"/>bably entertain as long as I love; but I told them that I would not <lb/>
seek to force it upon them. This is the proper course for a <lb/>
representative of the people to take I conceive that a spirited <lb/>
man, like the Hon. The Leader of the Government, may sometimes <lb/>
seek to control public opinion; but let him take this advice: <lb/>
the better way is to follow public opinion while he seeks to <lb/>
control it. The hon. member from Murray Harbor (Mr. Duncan ) <lb/>

<cb/>

alludes to the great sacrifice of having our rights and privileges <lb/>
destroyed, and it sounds strange from gentlemen who, up to <lb/>
1851, were opposed to what they now term a "priceless Con<lb break="no"/>stitution." It sounds strange, I say, that gentlemen should now <lb/>
value that Constitution so highly, whip, up that that time, had no <lb/>
faith in it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. J. C. POPE</persName>: That was before the commencement of my <lb/>
political career. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WHEL1">Hon. Mr. WHELAN</persName>: I am speaking in reference to the party, <lb/>
and particularly in reference to the Hon. member from Murray <lb/>
Harbour; for I remember that no gentleman was more disposed <lb/>
than he to use his influence to oppose the introduction of Responsi<lb break="no"/>ble Government. Does it not sound strange that a gentleman <lb/>
should have worked himself up to the consciousness of the "price<lb break="no"/>less blessing of our Constitution," just at this particular hour, when <lb/>
a few years ago he was fighting against it most indignantly? But, <lb/>
as he is not in his place, I will not press my observations against <lb/>
him. In reference to the original Resolutions, if we put them <lb/>
upon record we place ourselves in the most extraordinary position <lb/>
that ever a Colony occupied. They say that Prince Edward <lb/>
Island will not have anything to do with Confederation—that we <lb/>
will not accept it on any terms—no matter how advantageous <lb/>
they might be to the people. The words of the Resolution cannot <lb/>
bear any other interpretation. I am not wedded to any particular <lb/>
scheme of Confederation, but to the principle. I will not occupy <lb/>
further the time of the Committee at this late hour, now close <lb/>
upon mid-night. I did not hear all the arguments used before this <lb/>
Committee to-day. but I can hear testimony to the good spirit and <lb/>
feeling which has characterized this debate; and if anything has <lb/>
been gained it has been by the moderation of those who have not <lb/>
pressed unduly upon the attention of this House. <lb/></p> 

<p>The question was then put on the amendment, and the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee divided:— <lb/></p> 

<p>Y E A S: Honorables E. Whelan, Sol. General, Col. Gray, D. <lb/>
Davies, Dr. Kaye, Messrs. Green and Maclennan—7 <lb/></p> 

<p>N A Y S: Honorables J.C. Pope, J. Warburton, J Hensley, E. <lb/>
Maceachen, E. Thornton, F. Kelly, J Longworth, A. Laird, G. <lb/>
Coles, Messrs. Conroy, Howlan, Sinclair, Sutherland, Duncan, <lb/>
Howat, J. Yeo, D. Ramsay, F. St. C. Brecken, D. Montgomery, <lb/>
W. Haslam, and R. Walker—21 <lb/></p> 

<p>The question was then put on the original Resolutions, which <lb/>
were agreed to on a division the same as that above given—the <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Yeas</hi> for the amendment being taken as the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Nays</hi> against the Reso<lb break="no"/>lutions, and the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Nays</hi> against the amendment, as the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Yeas</hi> for the <lb/>
Resolution. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Sinclair then rose in his place, and move the following <lb/>
Resolution, for the purpose, he said, of fortifying the Government <lb/>
with an opinion of the House against any attempts which might <lb/>
be made to induce them to appoint a Delegation to the projected <lb/>
London Convention for the final consideration of the Report of the <lb/>
Quebec Conference of 1864. <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"RESOLVED, that inasmuch as there will be a General Election <lb/>
this summer, it is therefore inexpedient to appoint any further Dele<lb break="no"/>gation on the subject of Colonial Union or Confederation, or to take <lb/>
any action calculated to commit the people of this Colony to any <lb/>
Scheme of Union until authorized by the people and sanctioned by <lb/>
their Representatives returned at the said General Election." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>The Resolution was seconded by the Hon. Mr. Kelly, and then <lb/>
a short discussion ensued, in which it was argued on the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment side of the House, that the adoption of such a restrictive <lb/>
course would be tantamount to a direct expression of a want of <lb/>
confidence in the Government, and would, in fact, be an imposition <lb/>
of an unconstitutional restriction upon the Administration. <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon. members who spoke in favor of it, were Mr. Sinclair, <lb/>
and the Hon. Mr. Coles; they who spoke against it, were the Hon. <lb/>
J. C. Pope, Hon. J. Longworth, and Hon. E. Whelan. The <lb/>
question having bee put thereon, it was negatived on the follow<lb break="no"/>ing division: <lb/></p> 

<p>Y E A S: Messrs. Sinclair, Conroy, Howlan,Walker, Sutherland, <lb/>
Howat; Hons. F. Kelly, J. Hensly, G. Coles, J. Warburton, E. <lb/>
Thornton, A. Laird,—12. <lb/></p> 

<p>N A Y S: Hons. E. WHelan, Sol. General, D. Kaye, E. Maceachen, <lb/>
D. Davies, J. Longworth, J.C. Pope, J. H. Gray; Messrs. Green, <lb/>
D. Duncan, Maclennan, J. Yeo, Brecken, Montgomery, Haslain, <lb/>
Ramsay,—16. <lb/></p> 

<p>Adjourned.</p>

<!-- DL 2018-06-10 commented out below as it will form part of the errata -->

<!--<pb n="151" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_151.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">151</fw>

<p>SPEECH <lb/>
OF THE <lb/>
HON. T. HEATH HAVILAND, <lb/>
ON CONFEDERATION. <lb/>
1866. <lb/></p> 

<p>The following speech of the Hon. T. HEATH HAVI- <lb break="maybe"/>LAND, was, owing to some oversight of the Reporter <lb/>
for the Session of 1866, omitted from the Parliament<lb break="no"/>ary Reporterof that Session:— <lb/></p> 

<p>TUESDAY, 8th May, 1866. <lb/></p> 

<p>Confederation Question. <lb/></p> 

<p>House in Committee of the whole on Despatches, <lb/>
&amp;c. Mr. John Yeo in the Chair. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. T. HEATH HAVILAND (Solicitor General) <lb/>
thought the hon. member from East Point (Hon. E. <lb/>
McEachen) in his attempt to draw an argument <lb/>
against the proposed or contemplated Cofederation of <lb/>
the British American Provinces, from the history and <lb/>
results of the Union between England and Scotland, <lb/>
had been peculiarly unfortunate. That hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man seemed to have inherited all the ancient animosity <lb/>
of his blood and race to the power and domination of <lb/>
the Saxon; and, altogether ignoring the happy change <lb/>
for his country, which, in the course of time, had been <lb/>
brought about by that Union—a change from discord <lb/>
to friendship, from war to peace, and from poverty and <lb/>
distress to national prosperity,— in attempting to <lb/>
strengthen his anti-confederate position by reference <lb/>
to it, he seemed to be animated solely by the recollec<lb break="no"/>tion of what, in truth, was considered by the great <lb/>
majority of the people of Scotland, at that crisis of <lb/>
her fate, to be an annihilation of her independence <lb/>
a loss and a disgrace, and a surrendering of her rank <lb/>
among nations, for no advantages which could be <lb/>
anticipated, except such as might be obtained by <lb/>
private individuals, whose hopes of self-aggrandize-<lb break="maybe"/>ment and pecuniary gains completely stiffled in their <lb/>
breast every consideration of national honor. Such <lb/>
views as these, with reference to the contemplated <lb/>
Confederation under consideration, appeared to be <lb/>
entertained, not only by the hon. member from East <lb/>
Point (hon. E. McEachen) but, indeed, by almost <lb/>
every other anti-confederate in the Island. The cry <lb/>
raised by our anti-confederates in general was, that <lb/>
by Confederation, we would be deprived at once of all <lb/>
the consideration and advantages of a resident and <lb/>
independent government; and for the prospect and <lb/></p> <milestone type="unknown"/> 

<p>benefits of free trade and extended commerce, which <lb/>
were held out to lure us into the connection, all we <lb/>
would realize would be increase of taxation burdens, <lb/>
and duties, wholly ruinous to our prosperity, and that <lb/>
altogether for the relief and benefit of Canada. The <lb/>
only advantages, it was, most injustly and ungener<lb break="no"/>ously, said by anti-confederates, which would result <lb/>
to Prince Edward Island, from her being included in <lb/>
the contemplated Confederation, would be experienced <lb/>
by a few of her politicians who, for the rewards of <lb/>
venality, had agreed to barter away their own honor <lb/>
and the rights and liberties of their country. By those <lb/>
who thus, perversely, and he might say dishonestly, <lb/>
argued, it was most carefully kept out of sight that, <lb/>
according to the proposed scheme of Confederation, <lb/>
there would be no degradation of any of the Provincial <lb/>
Legislatures and Governments. These, on the con<lb break="no"/>trary, would be preserved intact; and each Province <lb/>
would retain the entire control and management of its <lb/>
own local and internal affairs. It was true, indeed, <lb/>
that the general Government would, undoubtedly, and <lb/>
of necessity, exercise supervision of the individual <lb/>
States; but the power of the Federal government to <lb/>
interfere with the exclusively internal affairs of any <lb/>
of the Confederated Provinces, would be of the most <lb/>
limited and inconsiderate character. In all the argu<lb break="no"/>ments brought to bear against Confederation, it was <lb/>
also very carefully kept out of view that its accomplish<lb break="no"/>ment, upon terms fair and just to every section of it — <lb/>
and upon no other terms did he wish, or had he ever <lb/>
desired, to see it established— would not only be the <lb/>
means of happily extinguishing those little waspish <lb/>
political feuds and jealousies which had so long acted <lb/>
as a drag upon our progress, and been a disgrace to <lb/>
us as a people; but would also, by putting the impost <lb/>
duties and other sources of public revenue, upon a <lb/>
uniform basis, under the control of the Federal Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, put an end to the anomaly of seperate <lb/>
customs establishments, and the conflicting and perplex<lb break="no"/>ing commercial regulations which existed, and which <lb/>
had almost of necessity arisen out of the disunited state <lb/>
of these Provinces. Again, the recognition of another <lb/>
benefit which would result from a Union of these Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, had been carefully eschewed by our Island <lb/>
anti-confederates: he meant identity of laws, and <lb/>
  <lb/>

<pb n="152" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_152.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">152</fw>

<fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER</fw>

existence within territories of the same nation—terri- <lb break="maybe"/>tories lying near to one another, aike in climate, <lb/>
natural productions, and the social condition of their <lb/>
inhabitants—the existence, he said, within such terri<lb break="no"/>tories of a multiplicity of laws, each having a distinct, <lb/>
local application upon almost every question of human <lb/>
rights; and of a plurality of courts —each peculiarly <lb/>
constituted, and having its peculiar rules of practice— <lb/>
administering those laws, hampered the ordinary <lb/>
administration of justice, tended to the promotion of <lb/>
crime, and seriously inconvenienced commercial inter<lb break="no"/>course between the various parts of these territories; <lb/>
and the desirability of the contemplated Confederation <lb/>
was, in his opinion, greatly heightened by the certain <lb/>
prospect which it afforded of the removal of these <lb/>
grievous anomalies by means of judicious and remedial <lb/>
action on that score by the Federal Legislature. In<lb break="no"/>dependent local legislation in each of a group of Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces or Territories so circumstanced was, in some, <lb/>
and those too very important, respects, a positive evil; <lb/>
for it could not but result in difference of laws pro<lb break="no"/>ductive of such evil results as those to which he had just <lb/>
adverted; and such legislation had the additional evil <lb/>
effect of cherishing those local prejudices and feelings <lb/>
of separate interests, which tend so decidedly to the <lb/>
estrangement of each member of a Confederation from <lb/>
its fellows. The Island anti-confederates had—most <lb/>
unjustly and ungenerously he was again constrained to <lb/>
say—declared, again and again, that such of our public <lb/>
men as advocated Confederation had been won over to <lb/>
that advocacy by the corrupting influence of Canadian <lb/>
gold, and had basely with a view to their own indivi<lb break="no"/>dual aggrandizement and enrichment, agreed to barter <lb/>
away our priceless Constitution. The charge of bribery, <lb/>
which had thus been boldly preferred against such of <lb/>
the Island Deputies to Canada as had openly avowed <lb/>
and advocated their convictions in favor of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, were beneath contempt or notice, although it <lb/>
would be easy to reply that perhaps American silver <lb/>
or greenbacks, had not been without their corrupting <lb/>
and denationalizing effect amongst the anti-confede-<lb break="maybe"/>rates. And he might ask these most unscrupulous <lb/>
calumniators, if they would dare to say that the vener<lb break="no"/>able Archbishop Connolly and Bishop McKinnon, the <lb/>
gallant General Williams, the veteran General Doyle, <lb/>
or Sir James Hope, who perilled his life at the storm<lb break="no"/>ing of the Peiho Forts, in China had been bribed into <lb/>
an advocacy of the projected Confederation of these <lb/>
Provinces?—for one end all of those eminently good <lb/>
and great men were, he was proud and happy to say, <lb/>
numbered amongst the most strenuous advocates of <lb/>
that great project. He thought not. But as to the <lb/>
ridiculous assertion that the advocates of Confederation <lb/>
were prepared to sacrifice our priceless Constitution <lb/>
for the establishment of a Federal Union, it was suffi<lb break="no"/>cient to refer to the terms of the Quebec Scheme of <lb/>
that Union, which showed most clearly that nothing <lb/>
was farther from the minds of the Delegates who sat <lb/>
in the Quebec Conference than the sacrifice of their <lb/>
respective Provincial Constitutions. The powers <lb/>
which; by that Scheme, if carried into effect, would be <lb/>
given to the Federal Legislature were such as would <lb/>
neither require, nor necessitate, a nulification of the <lb/>
several separate Provincial Constitutions, although <lb/>
separate legislation under those several Constitutions <lb/>
would certainly be restricted to certain classes of sub<lb break="no"/>jects, and confined without narrower limits than those <lb/>

<cb/>

which originally circumscribed their operation; and <lb/>
so happily controlled would it be by the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment or Federal Parliament, that no rivalry of in<lb break="no"/>terests could spring up between different Provinces. <lb/>
A reference to the Union of Scotland with England, <lb/>
as made by the hon. member from East Point, so far <lb/>
from yielding arguments against the Confederation of <lb/>
the British American Provinces, afforded the strongest <lb/>
in favor of it. The great benefits of that national treaty <lb/>
has been generally felt and acknowledged for the last <lb/>
hundred years. From the period of its accomplishment, <lb/>
there was awakened, in Scotland, a spirit of industry <lb/>
and enterprise formerly unknown in that country; and, <lb/>
ever since, the two kingdoms of England and Scotland, <lb/>
incalculably to their mutual benefits, have been grad<lb break="no"/>ually forgetting their former subjects of discord, and <lb/>
uniting cordially, as one people, in the improvement <lb/>
and defence of their common country—the island <lb/>
which they inhabit. Scotland's greatest grievance, <lb/>
arising out of the Union, was that which she felt in <lb/>
the deprivation of her native and independent legisla<lb break="no"/>ture, and her metropolis' ceasing to be the abode of <lb/>
royalty; and, indeed, the restoration of their national <lb/>
parliaments was yet eagerly desired by large sections <lb/>
of the populations of both Scotland and Ireland. Un<lb break="no"/>der Confederation, however, each of the Provinces <lb/>
would retain its own Legislature and Government, for <lb/>
the management of its own local affairs, limited in <lb/>
power only to such an extent as would prevent its <lb/>
operating in favor of its own prosperity at the expense <lb/>
of any of the others. Of the advantages of Union, the <lb/>
United States, since their attainment of independence <lb/>
—notwithstanding their late disastrous dislocation <lb/>
and narrow escape from complete dismemberment-<lb break="yes"/>afforded the most conclusive evidence, by their increase <lb/>
in area, wealth, and physical strength, having pro<lb break="no"/>gressed, in each of these particulars, to such an extent <lb/>
as has excited the wonder and admiration of the world. <lb/>
—Some of our Island anti-confederates had exercised <lb/>
their wit and talents in disparagement and ridicule of <lb/>
"the glory argument," as it was called; but, for his <lb/>
own part, he did not think that any man either could <lb/>
truly be said to have a country, or to deserve to have <lb/>
one, who could not rejoice and glory in the patriotic <lb/>
and ennobling recollections of ancestral virtues and <lb/>
renown. They who laughed at the glory argument <lb/>
knew little of what had enable Great Britain to boast <lb/>
that the sun never sets upon her dominions, and thaat <lb/>
the sound of her drums has always been, either the <lb/>
prelude to victory, or the announcement of its glorious <lb/>
accomplishment. Under the glorious rule of Britain <lb/>
he was born, and under it he would die. To Anglo Saxon <lb/>
genius no secrets of science were inscrutable; and to <lb/>
Anglo-Saxon perseverance, enterprise, skill, and bra<lb break="no"/>very, nothing within the bounds of human power was <lb/>
unattainable. The practicability of a Confederation <lb/>
of the Provinces and Territories of British North <lb/>
American, to their utmost extent and limits, into a <lb/>
great national power, is, with respect to geographical <lb/>
difficulties, fast ceasing to be regarded as a mere vision<lb break="no"/>ary idea. The empire of which it would form <lb/>
the foundation, would in extent, be inferior only <lb/>
to those of Russia, China, and Brazil, and, in com<lb break="no"/>manding position, its advantages would be equal <lb/>
to those of all the three combined. The people of the <lb/>
United States had not been slow to perceive all that; <lb/>
and twice, with a view to a forcible annexation of these <lb/>

<pb n="153" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1866-05-08_Page_153.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">153</fw>

Provinces to the territories of their Republic, had <lb/>
they invaded Canada. Their desire for that annexation <lb/>
is as strong as ever; they are only waiting for a favor<lb break="no"/>able opportunity to again attempt its accomplishment; <lb/>
and the cheapest and most effectual means of prevent<lb break="no"/>ing it would be to place the Provinces in a position <lb/>
to defend themselves—to give them that self-reliance, <lb/>
that compactness of physical strength, that unity of <lb/>
action, and increased dissemination and intensity of <lb/>
national feeling, which can be given to them by <lb/>
Confederation—and by Confederation only. The Im<lb break="no"/>perial Government desired to see it accomplished; <lb/>
and willing as the Mother Country was to spend her <lb/>
blood and treasure in defence of these Provinces, so long <lb/>
as they continued faithful in their allegiance to her, <lb/>
and true to the glorious Constitution and glorious old <lb/>
Flag of England, her ministers certainly had a right <lb/>
to state their views upon the question. It had been <lb/>
said that the Despatches of the Hon. Mr. Cardwell, on <lb/>
the subject of defence, were meant to be a putting of <lb/>
the screw upon us. He however, did not look upon <lb/>
them in that light. If these Provinces were not true <lb/>
to their allegiance, and willing to defend themselves, <lb/>
according to their ability, there was an end of the com<lb break="no"/>pact, on the part of Great Britain, to defend them. <lb/>
That compact would cease the moment we refused to <lb/>
exert ourselves for the preservation of British institu<lb break="no"/>tions and British connexion. Should the Confederation, <lb/>
however, take place and its accomplishment afford <lb/>
Great Britain a satisfactory evidence of the willingness <lb/>
of the united peoples of those Provinces to listen to her <lb/>
counsels, and, if possible, to anticipate her wishes for <lb/>
their own benefit, she would probably be found ready <lb/>
to yield to them a largely increased share of national <lb/>
privileges, attended, however, with proportional na<lb break="no"/>tional responsibilities. Her expressed wish that these <lb/>
Provinces should take upon themselves, the charge of <lb/>
providing and sustaining the naval and military forces <lb/>
and foreign aggression, was proof positive of that. <lb/>
The bestowal that charge would alone, it could not be <lb/>
doubted, give to the Federal Government an important <lb/>
rank as a nationalGovernment, and would ensure to <lb/>
it a degree of moral weight, not only in every section <lb/>
of the Confederation, but also with foreign powers. It <lb/>
was not to be persumed, however, that the Federal <lb/>
Government, although, in some sense, it would be in<lb break="no"/>dependent, could, without some very material modifi<lb break="no"/>cation of the relation of the Provinces to the Mother <lb/>
Country, be permitted the power of making war, and of <lb/>
concluding treaties of peace and commerce, on its own <lb/>
account, as the Government of an entirely independent <lb/>
country. The power of regulating the intercourse and <lb/>
relations of the Confederated Provinces would, on the <lb/>
contrary, be confined to such adjustment of trade and <lb/>
commercial intercourse and relations with foreign states, <lb/>
as could not be prejudicial, in any very material or ag<lb break="no"/>gressive degree, to the interests of Great Britain, and as <lb/>
would not involve her actual divesture of all authority <lb/>
over them. One of the greatest bugbears, however, which <lb/>
had been conjured up by our anti-confederates, "to <lb/>
fright our isle from its propriety," in its consideration <lb/>
of the great question, was the enormous amount of <lb/>
taxation which Confederation, if effected, would entail <lb/>
upon it. Baseless and ridiculous, as on that score <lb/>
he held the predictions and calculations of our anti-con-<lb break="maybe"/>federate prophets and financiers to be, he would not, <lb/>

<cb/>

then make any attempt to disprove or refute them; but <lb/>
would rest satisfied with merely observing that, should <lb/>
they become the chosen or accepted guides and coun<lb break="no"/>sellors of the people, the too probable effect would be <lb/>
that, whilst steering our vessel of state so as to avoid <lb/>
the rock, the Scyllaof Confederation taxation, they <lb/>
would unavoidably, if not designedly, direct her course, <lb/>
so as to be engulfed by the Charybdisof American debt, <lb/>
That debt amounted to the most amazing and enormous <lb/>
sum of two thousand six hundred and thirty three mil<lb break="no"/>lions of dollars. The prospect of being allowed to <lb/>
participate in that prodigious burthen could not, he <lb/>
thought, he openly and successfully held out as any <lb/>
very strong inducement to our people to prefer Annexa<lb break="no"/>tion to Confederation, or to incline them voluntarily to <lb/>
withdraw themselves from the assured protection of <lb/>
the old and glorious Flag of Britain, in order to seek <lb/>
precarious and doubtful refuge beneath the Stars and <lb/>
Stripes. He would like some of those exactfinanciers, <lb/>
to whose calculations he had just referred, to show <lb/>
how much pe head of our population, in the event of <lb/>
our annexation to the United States, the burthen of <lb/>
our proportionate share of that debt would amount. <lb/>
The prospect of its insignificance, as compared with <lb/>
that to which they would have to submit under Confe<lb break="no"/>deration, would surely be very inviting!—The Hon. <lb/>
Colonel Gray, in his eloquent and argumentative speech <lb/>
upon the question, which had, most deservedly been <lb/>
listened so with every evidence of respectful attention <lb/>
by both sides of the House, had, in one of his sentences, <lb/>
spoken as if he thought that the question of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion should have been made a Government question; <lb/>
and the Hon. the Leader of the Opposition (Mr Coles) <lb/>
had eagerly seized upon and echoed it, in the hope he <lb/>
(Hon. Mr. Haviland) imagined that it might prove an <lb/>
apple of discord. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Colonel GRAY explained that his own acts, <lb/>
he was glad to find the opinion of Hon. and gallant <lb/>
Colonel, on that point, exactly coincided with his own; <lb/>
and such, indeed, he said, it was evident it must have <lb/>
been from the very inception of measures by the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment of the Colony for its due consideration; for <lb/>
the gentlemen who were chosen by it to represent the <lb/>
Island at the Quebec Conference, were selected so as <lb/>
fairly to represent the two great political parties of our <lb/>
little state. That Delegation was composed of the <lb/>
Hon. Colonel Gray, President of the Executive Council, <lb/>
the Hon. W. H. Pope, Colonial Secretary, and of the <lb/>
Hon. E. Palmer, Attorney General, as representatives <lb/>
of the Government or Conservative party; and of the <lb/>
Hon. G. Coles, Leader of the Opposition, the Hon. E. <lb/>
Whelan, who was not suspected of entertaining any <lb/>
great love for the Government, the Hon. Andrew Mc<lb break="no"/>Donald, who had never been a conservative, and him<lb break="no"/>self, (Hon. M. Haviland) who, at that time, was not <lb/>
a supporter of the Government, having, some time <lb/>
before, for reasons to which it was not then necessary <lb/></p>--> 

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>