<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1865-03-28"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1865-03-28">28 March 1865</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1864">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1865, Being the Third Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1865"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Protestant" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="60"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_051.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_052.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_053.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_054.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_055.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_056.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_057.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_058.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_059.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_060.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-06">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_051">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_051.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_052">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_052.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_053">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_053.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_054">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_054.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_055">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_055.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_056">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_056.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_057">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_057.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_058">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_058.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_059">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_059.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_060">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_060.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">
<pb n="51" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_051.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">51</fw>

<!-- DL 2018-06-06 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--can in our present state of freedom from taxation. Reference <lb/>
has been made to the unsuccessful attempt made at the Quebec<lb/>
Conference to get an additional member for the Island in the<lb/>
Lower House. I cannot perceive that the additional representa<lb break="no"/>tion would have, in any appreciable degree, increased our<lb/>
influence in that body. I am not, however, equally satisfied<lb/>
with the proposed Constitution of the Union House. The prices<lb/>
in Canada of tea, sugar, &amp;c., quoted by the hon member for<lb/>
Belfast, do not prove that Confederation would enable the people<lb/>
of this Island to purchase them at the same rates ; for in Canada<lb/>
a merchant can afford to sell at low rates, in consequence of<lb/>
disposing of large quantities at a time. The excise duty must be<lb/>
added to the cost of tobacco. The truth is, Sir, that Halifax<lb/>
must regulate the prices of West India produce in this Colonies.<lb/>
I would be glad to have the continued protection of Great<lb/>
Britain ; but it is well known that these Colonies were to be<lb/>
educated up to a sense of the duties of a nationality. It is but<lb/>
natural that John Bull should at length say, " If they will not<lb/>
defend themselves, let them go?" As I said before, this question<lb/>
is forced on us and face it we must. We cannot doubt that the<lb/>
Americans look with greedy eyes upon the coal fields of Nova<lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick, the acquisition of which would be<lb/>
of incalculable advantage to them not only in times of peace, but<lb/>
also in case of a war with Britain or France, or any of the<lb/>
other European powers.<lb/></p> -->

<head rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, March 28.</head><lb/> 

<p>Debate on the Union of the Colonies resumed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HENS1">Hon. Mr. HENSLEY</persName>.— Mr Speaker, I shall conclude the<lb/>
few remarks which I was making last evening when inter<lb break="no"/>rupted. I was referring to the returns of the importations<lb/>
into Canada and New Brunswick for 1863, showing that<lb/>
these Provinces did not manufacture nearly enough of<lb/>
boots and shoes, and other articles of the kind for them<lb break="no"/>selves, and that consequently they could not supply this<lb/>
Colony. As regards tea and molasses which are said to<lb/>
be cheaper in Canada than in this Island, if this be the<lb/>
case it cannot arise from the fact that higher duties are<lb/>
paid on them there than in this Colony. But one of the<lb/>
principal points to which I did not refer last night was<lb/>
military defences. The argument advanced on this feature<lb/>
of the subject by those favorable to Union is that, in order<lb/>
to prepare for efficient military defence we require a<lb/>
central power. I, however, do not see the question in<lb/>
that light. As long as we contribute our quota of men<lb/>
and means, and the other Provinces do the same. I con<lb break="no"/>sider it would be quite as efficient a method of providing<lb/>
for defence as any organization into which we could enter.<lb/>
We are told that the General Government would take<lb/>
control of the general revenue and provide naval and<lb/>
military forces. In the event of a war with the United<lb/>
States, however, we know full well that there would be<lb/>
no chance of success without the aid of Great Britain, and<lb/>
it is difficult to understand how Confederation would<lb/>
increase our ability of resistance. By late papers I<lb/>
observe that the Colonial Minister, Mr Cardwell, has<lb/>
introduced a bill into the Imperial Parliament providing<lb/>
for a Colonial naval force, to be supported by Colonial<lb/>
funds, but to be at the command of the Imperial authori<lb break="no"/>ties. It was laid down in regard to the measure that<lb/>
commissions could not be granted by Colonial authorities ;<lb/>
they must be issued by the Imperial Government to be<lb/>
valid. If this plan can be pursued in naval affairs,<lb/>
may not a similar scheme be adopted in military matters?<lb/>
All preparations for defence must be arranged under the<lb/>
superintendence of the Imperial Government, and under<lb/>
British commissioned officers ; and since this is the case<lb/>
it is doubtful whether a central Colonial Government<lb/>
would be any advantage. We do not wish to shrink from<lb/>
our duty in regard to defence as subjects of the British<lb/>
Empire. Disagreeable as it might be to be taken away to<lb/>
fight in the neighboring Provinces, still if the order should<lb/>
come it is not at all probable that we would refuse.<lb/>
Whence the necessity of merging all these Legislatures<lb/>
together to have a central power when we are already<lb/>
all organized under the Imperial Government of Great<lb/>

<cb/>

Britain? Another portion of the Report to which I obect <lb/>
is that which provides that the expense of railways and<lb/>
canals connecting two Provinces shall be equally borne by<lb/>
all the Colonies. It was said by Mr Galt the other day in<lb/>
Canada that it was necessary all their railways should have<lb/>
an outlet to the sea. This is what he terms a geographical<lb/>
necessity ; but I do not think that this Island would<lb/>
benefit by these works. We have the same geographical<lb/>
necessity in the winter season that Canada has ; our case<lb/>
is even worse, for we are surrounded by ice, and there is<lb/>
little prospect that anything can be done to improve our<lb/>
position, unless indeed we obtain steam communication<lb/>
over the Straits during the winter, as suggested by one of<lb/>
the delegates the other night. The intercolonial railway<lb/>
will confer very few commercial advantages on this<lb/>
Island. It will no doubt afford facilities for travelling ;<lb/>
but its benefits to us will not at all compensate for the<lb/>
amount which we would have to contribute towards it by<lb/>
the terms of the Report. In view, then, of the nature of<lb/>
that Report, I am prepared to support the resolution<lb/>
submitted by the hon Leader of the Government. I do<lb/>
not say that I would be opposed to Union on any terms ;<lb/>
but I think that such terms as are contained in the Report<lb/>
are very unfair to this Colony. If agreed to I consider<lb/>
that the interests of the Island would be altogether<lb/>
sacrificed. Our taxation would be greatly increased<lb/>
without corresponding advantages. Some maintain that<lb/>
we should not be alarmed at taxes ; they would be no<lb/>
burden providing we had additional scope for trade. Byt<lb/>
what more scope do we require, as we have already<lb/>
facilities for commerce as extended as the bounds of the<lb/>
British Empire ?<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—I would gladly avoid speaking on this<lb/>
question, feeling, as I do, my inability to deal with it, as<lb/>
its importance and the interests involved in it require.<lb/>
Never in the history of this Island, since it became a<lb/>
British Colony, has a subject of such consequence been<lb/>
submitted for the consideration of its Legislature. If we<lb/>
are to view the proposition for a Union of the British North<lb/>
American Colonies as an optional one, which we may<lb/>
reject without imperilling our position as a dependency<lb/>
of the British Crown, I confess I cannot see in the terms<lb/>
offered to us in the Report of the Quebec Conference<lb/>
anything to induce us to close with the offer. If, on the<lb/>
other hand, the choice is between a Union with the sister<lb/>
Provinces and a severance of our allegiance to the Mother<lb/>
Country, I would say, let us be united, even at a sacrifice<lb/>
of our local interests. But I do not think that the latter<lb/>
is our position, although the advocates of the scheme<lb/>
profess to believe that it is. Why should we be in such<lb/>
a hurry to assume that it is? Previous to the Quebec<lb/>
Conference this question had not been pressed upon our<lb/>
attention by the Home Government, although we are now<lb/>
aware, from Mr. Cardwell's despatch, written after the<lb/>
receipt of the Quebec Report, that the measure is very<lb/>
favourably received by the Imperial Government. Nor is<lb/>
it at all to be wondered at that they should wish to see<lb/>
our present political position changed Separate Provinces<lb/>
grouped close together with governments independent of<lb/>
each other ; separate laws, different currencies and<lb/>
hostile tariffs ; and, yet, all paying allegiance to the same<lb/>
Sovereign, is a state of things that will not, in all<lb/>
probability, continue very much longer. I am not opposed<lb/>
to a Union, provided just and equitable terms are secured<lb/>
to us ; but it does appear to me that the urgent manner<lb/>
in which this question at this time is pressed upon us, is<lb/>
entirely owing to the action of politicians on this side the<lb/>
Atlantic. It only requires a very slight acquaintance with<lb/>
the politics of Canada to be aware that the political<lb/>
difficulties and complications of that Province had arrived<lb/>
at such a pitch, and had become so perplexing, that party<lb/>
government was almost an impossibility ; indeed, it would<lb/>
appear, that impending anarchy threatened them. The<lb/>
Hon. John A. McDonald, Attorney General of Canada<lb/>
West, In Parliament, when moving the Address to Her<lb/>

<pb n="52" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_052.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">51</fw>>

Majesty for an Imperial Act to carry into effect the Report <lb/>
of the Quebec Conference, after stating the origin and<lb/>
history of the Union question in Canada up tot he time he<lb/>
was speaking, says : </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Then men of all parties and all shades of politics became<lb/>
alarmed at the aspect of affairs. They found that such was<lb/>
the opposition between the two sections of the Province,<lb/>
such was the danger of impending anarchy in consequence<lb/>
of the irreconcilable differences of opinion with respect to<lb/>
representation by population between Upper and Lower<lb/>
Canada, that unless some solution of the difficulty was arrived<lb/>
at we would suffer under a succession of weak governments,<lb/>
weak in numerical support, weak in force, and weak in power<lb/>
of doing good. All were alarmed at this state of affairs. We<lb/>
had election after election ; we had Ministry after Ministry,<lb/>
with the same result. Parties were so equally balanced that<lb/>
the vote of one member might decide the fate of the<lb/>
administration and the course of legislation for a year, or a<lb/>
series of years. This condition of things was well calculated<lb/>
to arouse the earnest consideration of every lover of his<lb/>
country, and I am happy to say it had that effect. Leading<lb/>
statesmen on both sides came to the conclusion that some<lb/>
steps must be taken to relieve the country from the dead lock<lb/>
and impending anarchy that hung over it."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Such are the words of the join Premiers of Canada.<lb/>
Mr McDonald then goes on to state that to remedy this<lb/>
state of affairs-- </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The Hon. Geo. Brown's Committee was appointed, whose<lb/>
Report resulted in the formation of the present Canadian<lb/>
Government, composed as it is of men of all shades of politics,<lb/>
brought together for the purpose of bringing about a Union<lb/>
of the Provinces."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>In the face of such statements, coming from such high<lb/>
authority, it is in vain for the advocates of Union to tell<lb/>
us that it is either pressure from the Home Government,<lb/>
or the threatening aspect of affairs in the neighboring<lb/>
Republic, that has given rise to the Confederation question<lb/>
at this particular time. I believe, Mr Speaker, that if the<lb/>
Statesmen of Canada could have found within their coun<lb break="no"/>try a solution of their political difficulties, we would not<lb/>
have heard much about Confederation. After the decision<lb/>
pronounced by New Brunswick at their late General<lb/>
Election to reject the scheme, I do not think there is any<lb/>
necessity for our spending much time in debating the<lb/>
subject, as it is quite clear that we shall not be called upon<lb/>
to enter Confederation until Nova Scotia and New<lb/>
Brunswick are ready to go into it. I shall not, therefore,<lb/>
stany length, go into the objectionable parts of the Report<lb/>
as they affect us ; they have been over and over again<lb/>
brought to the notice of the public. While I admit that<lb/>
we could hardly expect that the delegates assembled at<lb/>
Quebec to block out a constitution for all British America,<lb/>
would so frame their work as to make it suit the peculiar<lb/>
circumstances and wants of the smallest and most<lb/>
insignificant of the Provinces, they, at the same time,<lb/>
appear to have entirely overlooked our claims. From our<lb/>
insular position, and the nature and character of our limited<lb/>
resources, the offer, as contained in the Report, presents<lb/>
fewer inducements to us than to any of the other<lb/>
Provinces ; but it is our duty to see that the interests of<lb/>
those we represent are not sacrificed. With regard to the<lb/>
financial arrangement justice has not been done us. We<lb/>
are asked to give up nearly the whole of our revenue, now<lb/>
(£60,000.) and which will no doubt go on increasing,<lb/>
to the General Government, and in lien thereof receiving<lb/>
a capitation allowance of 80 cents per head on our present<lb/>
the difference between our debt and the debt of the Con<lb break="no"/>federate Government, amounting to £31,600. The latter<lb/>
amount cannot be looked upon as a gift, as we are called<lb/>
of a debt which we had no hand in contracting, and from<lb/>
the results of which we have derived no benefit. These two<lb/>
amounts will be insufficient to defray our ordinary local<lb/>
expenditure, and if any large public work is required we<lb/>
will, in all probability, have to pay for it ourselves,<lb/>

<cb/>

unless its advantages extend for the general benefit of the <lb/>
Provinces, which, from our situation, is not likely to be<lb/>
the case. But who is to tell what increase of taxation<lb/>
the General Government will not be obliged to impose ?<lb/>
Mr Galt, Finance Minister of Canada, says : </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"A revenue of $13,000,000 would, at the outset, be<lb/>
required for the General Government. This estimate allows<lb/>
but $1,000,000 for fortifications, military and naval purposes,<lb/>
and, as we are told by our Union friends, that there is to be<lb/>
a Confederate army and navy to protect us against Brother<lb/>
Jonathan, this estimate will no doubt have to be increased,<lb/>
not to say anything about deepening and widening the<lb/>
canals of Upper Canada, and the construction of other great<lb/>
public works, which must go on as the country becomes more<lb/>
developed, and we, Sir, will be powerless to check any<lb/>
extravagance on the part of the General Government. But<lb/>
we are told that the commercial advantages which will flow<lb/>
to us from the Union will so increase our prosperity that we<lb/>
will be able to bear extra taxation. Intercolonial free trade<lb/>
is to be established, and we will be able to import our manu<lb break="no"/>factures from Canada and the other Provinces duty free."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>This is, in other words, telling us that our trade in<lb/>
manufactures will be confined to the Provinces, which I<lb/>
believe would be the case, as high and prohibitory duties<lb/>
would have to be imposed on imports from Britain and<lb/>
other countries, in order to provide a revenue for the<lb/>
General Government, as we can hardly expect that any<lb/>
Finance Minister would have the courage to attempt to<lb/>
raise such a revenue by direct taxation, a line of policy<lb/>
that even a Gladstone shrinks from. To have our trade<lb/>
confined to these Colonies would be a great disadvantage to<lb/>
us, as I do not believe that a new country like Canada<lb/>
could furnish us with manufactures on as favorable terms<lb/>
as the Mother Country. Among the many requirements<lb/>
necessary to make a country a manufacturing one, a<lb/>
surplus population is one of them. Now, all other things<lb/>
being equal, can it be reasonably expected that a large<lb/>
country like Canada, with a sparse population, the same<lb/>
to the square mile as that of England to every two or three<lb/>
acres, not to say anything of the inducements which the<lb/>
fertile and cheap lands of Canada hold out to men to<lb/>
become farmers, can supply us with manufactures of the<lb/>
same quality and at as cheap a rate as England ! How would<lb/>
such a policy affect our relations with the Mother Country !<lb/>
Certainly not improve them. As it is, the Manchester<lb/>
School of Politicians are for casting us adrift as uselesss<lb/>
and expensive appendages. They say we are always<lb/>
lightening John Bull's pocket, on some pretence or other,<lb/>
and buttoning up our own against them, by placing high<lb/>
duties on their exports. They say, and with much truth,<lb/>
that we, their children, ought to buy from them more<lb/>
largely than we do. Intercolonial free trade would, no<lb/>
doubt, increase this cause of complaint, and strengthen<lb/>
the ranks of men holding the views of Bright and Goldwin<lb/>
Smith. Then, again, Mr Speaker, why was not the<lb/>
principle of compensation extended to us as well as to<lb/>
Newfoundland and New Brunswick ! It is true we have<lb/>
no mines or minerals to surrender; but we are, for five<lb/>
months in the year, shut out from the use and advantage<lb/>
of the great public works of the other Provinces, for the<lb/>
past and future cost of which we are to contribute, while<lb/>
these works, during the winter, are as useless to us as the<lb/>
Car of Juggernaut. If Newfoundland, by giving up her<lb/>
mines and minerals. will have them opened and worked,<lb/>
which I presume will be the case, otherwise $150,000 a<lb/>
year in perpetuity would not have been offered for them.<lb/>
That, alone, in the increase of trade which would follow<lb/>
would be a sufficient compensation ; but I presume the<lb/>
grant was made with another object. I am afraid we were<lb/>
considered too insignificant to be worth bargaining for.<lb/>
It was easily seen that if the other Provinces went into the<lb/>
Union we would have to follow. And why pay for any<lb break="no"/>thing when you can get it for nothing! Then, again, New<lb/>
Brunswick was granted £60,000 for 10 years for a local<lb/>
work.</p>

<pb n="53" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_053.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">53</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE3">The Col SECRETARY</persName> — What about Nova Scotia ! <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> — Nova Scotia is in a different postion, <lb/>
She has a great deal to gain by Confederation. Halifax<lb/>
will likely be the terminus of the Intercolonial Railway,<lb/>
and that city become the empire city of British America.<lb/>
That Province has no claim for compensation. The reasons<lb/>
which weigh with Unionists in New Brunswick and Nova<lb/>
Scotia have little application to his Island. For instance,<lb/>
the Intercolonial Railway makes the other Province spart<lb/>
and parcel of Canadian; the iron horse annihilates time and<lb/>
distance. With respect to the political part of the Report,<lb/>
I think we have reason to complain. The principle of<lb/>
representation by population is sought to be enforced on<lb/>
too sweeping a scale ; but as this principle is a sine qua<lb/>
nonwith the people of Upper Canada, and is, I believe,<lb/>
at the bottom and root of the Confederation scheme, we<lb/>
might expect to see it applied to the Lower House ; but I<lb/>
see no reason why the constitution of the Upper House<lb/>
should not have been assimilated to that of the Senate of<lb/>
the United States ; but I do not attach much importance<lb/>
to this, as I believe the more representation we have the<lb/>
more our difficulties would increase. We have no men of<lb/>
fortune amongst us; at any rate, none foolish enough to<lb/>
engage in politics. Hon members from distant parts of<lb/>
the Island, from the North Cape and East Point, can spare<lb/>
a few weeks during the winter months to attend to their<lb/>
legislative duties ; but it would be found a very different<lb/>
matter to be obliged to leave home and business, and<lb/>
that, too, very likely in the winter season, for three or<lb/>
four months in the year to attend the General Legislature<lb/>
at Ottawa. The public men of this Island cannot afford<lb/>
to do so, even if willing. The sacrifice of interest which<lb/>
a seat in the Confederate Assembly would entail, would<lb/>
be greater than our public men could afford ; and if to remedy<lb/>
this they were adequately paid, then their constituents would<lb/>
begin to suspect that their personal interests might outweigh<lb/>
their regard for the interests of the Colony. I doubt much<lb/>
whether men of stake, and really interested in the welfare of<lb/>
the country, would be found willing to offer themselves.<lb/>
Indeed, so far as our representation is concerned, it might as<lb/>
well be wiped out of the Report altogether. There is another<lb/>
objection to the new constitution, as it applies to this Island.<lb/>
What, I would ask, looking at the wide range of subjects<lb/>
reserved for the General Government, will there be left to<lb/>
engage the attention of our Local Legislature? As it is, with<lb/>
the management of all our affairs, the subjects that most<lb/>
frequently engage our attention are not of a very broad or<lb/>
elevating character. If, from the subjects to be assigned to<lb/>
our Local Legislature we withdraw Education and the<lb/>
management of our highways, matters which, when once<lb/>
properly provided for, do not admit of being tinkered at every<lb/>
Session, what will be left for us to do? We might have a<lb/>
party for bringing in a measure that all pigs should wear<lb/>
rings in their noses, but on such a question it would be<lb/>
difficult to keep altogether either a Government or an Opposition,<lb/>
unless they were to differ as to the description of metal and<lb/>
rings should be made of; but to be serious, I believe if we<lb/>
went into Confederation we would find our Local Government<lb/>
a nuisance too cumbersome and expensive for the work<lb/>
assigned it, and before long would be petitioning to have it<lb/>
done away with, and to have municipal institutions instead.<lb/>
This very Building with its empty walls and untenanted<lb/>
offices would stand a frowning remonstrance against the<lb/>
policy of the Hon Col Secretary and his Union friends ; he<lb/>
would take fright at the sight of its decaying walls. Some<lb break="no"/>body may yet say to him what the great Irish Orator, Curran,<lb/>
once said to a Peer who had been instrumental in bringing<lb/>
about the Irish Union. Curran, who was one day setting his<lb/>
watch at the Post Office, which was then opposite to the late<lb/>
Parliament Buildings, when the noblemen, who well knew<lb/>
that the Union was a sure subject with Curran, said as he<lb/>
passed him, "Curran what do they mean to do with that<lb/>
useless building ? For my part I am sure I hate the sight of<lb/>
it." "I am not at all astonished to hear you say so, my<lb/>
Lord," replied Curran, "I never yet heard of a murderer who<lb/>
was not afraid of a ghost." We are told that by going into<lb/>
the Union we will rise form being a small and obscure<lb/>
Colony to be a part of a great country. This may, in some<lb/>

<cb/>

degree, be true; but practically we are called upon to yield <lb/>
up to a very great extent the control and management of our<lb/>
public affairs, a great privilege, which none parted with is<lb/>
not easily regained. But the argument which Unionists<lb/>
dwell most strongly upon, as proving the necessity for<lb/>
Confederation, is the question of defence. They argue that<lb/>
unless we unite we must soon become absorbed in the<lb/>
American Union. If there is really danger just now of our<lb/>
|Republican neighbours adopting an aggressive policy ; if<lb/>
they should take it into their heads to cross the Canadian<lb/>
frontier for the purpose of carrying out the Monroe Doctrine,<lb/>
or to indemnify themselves for losses recently sustained, and<lb/>
for which they may choose to hold Britain responsible, would<lb/>
a Political Union work such a change in our present position<lb/>
as to convert us once from helpless Colonies into a powerful<lb/>
Confederacy? It must be many years hence before these<lb/>
Colonies will be able, unaided by the British arm, to defend<lb/>
themselves against an invading foe, extending as they do,<lb/>
over such area, with an extensive and exposed frontier, and<lb/>
vulnerable in so many points. No doubt is it high time that<lb/>
these Colonies did more for their own protection than they<lb/>
have hitherto done. They have drawn largely from the<lb/>
pockets of the tax payers of the Mother Country for the<lb/>
purposes of fortifications and the maintenance of naval and<lb/>
military forces among them. (This Island is not open to this<lb/>
charge ; for very many years she has cost Britain nothing in<lb/>
this respect.) Colonists ought to remember that many of the<lb/>
tax payers at home who contribute to our protection are less<lb/>
able to bear their public burthens than we are. There is<lb/>
one argument urged by anti-Unionists which I do not agree<lb/>
with, viz., that when united, in case trouble arises, our young<lb/>
men will be liable to be drafted off to Canada and the other<lb/>
Provinces, there to assist in fighting their battles. This is<lb/>
not likely to be the case, as our small Militia and Volunteer<lb/>
force would be required for our own defence, which the<lb/>
safety of the other Colonies would require to be efficiently<lb/>
maintained, the chances are in such a state of things that<lb/>
not one man would be withdrawn from the Island, but men<lb/>
would have to be sent here. But even if it should so happen<lb/>
that they were taken off to assist in the defence of the other<lb/>
Colonies, ought we to complain ? Our British interests are<lb/>
intimately bound up with those of the other Colonies, in a<lb/>
national point, at any rate, and when Canada and the other<lb/>
Provinces have to succumb to a foreign power we will have<lb/>
to follow suit. In helping them we are fighting for ourselves,<lb/>
and that, too, under more favourable circumstances than the<lb/>
sister Provinces; for we would not have to meet the foe at<lb/>
our firesides. The further the scene of conflict is removed<lb/>
from one's door the better; for the most terrible of all the<lb/>
horrors and devastation that follow in the track of war is having<lb/>
women, children and country exposed to the cruelty and fury<lb/>
of a merciless soldiery. This consideration ought to make<lb/>
ready at all times when the necessity arises (and God grant<lb/>
that it may never occur) to assist our fellow Colonists, and<lb/>
that with a good will too. Our position as British Colonies<lb/>
must, for many years, depend upon the protection afforded<lb/>
us by the Mother Country. Separate or united without that<lb/>
aid we shall be powerless to defend ourselves. England's<lb/>
European interests, her position as first among the nations,<lb/>
more perhaps than her wide spread possessions, oblige her<lb/>
to maintain her present powerful military and naval force.<lb/>
Those forces require stations. England is not prepared to<lb/>
throw off her wealthy West India possessions, not to say any<lb break="no"/>thing of those Colonies. She has to maintain a naval force<lb/>
out here, which costs no more than at home, and to maintain<lb/>
that force the coal mines of Cape Breton and Nova Scotia are<lb/>
necessary. The threat that Unionists hold out to us that we<lb/>
will be cast adrift if we do not unite, is for the purpose of<lb/>
frightening us into Confederation. They must, at any rate,<lb/>
produce stronger arguments than they have done, before they<lb/>
can expect us to be convinced that it is so. I believe that<lb/>
Britain is willing to untie the apron strings and send us off to<lb/>
do for ourselves when we are strong enough to stand alone ;<lb/>
but I do not believe she will cast us off until we are able to<lb/>
protect ourselves. Hon members in favor of the scheme had<lb/>
better direct their attention to the other points of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, and endeavor to show us that our material interests<lb/>
will become improved by the proposed Union. That, I take<lb/>
it, is the great point for us to consider just now. Our<lb/>
national relations rest with the Mother Country.<lb/></p>

<!-- DL 2018-06-06 commented out below - to be included when "erratum" are addressed -->
<!--<p>ERRATUM. - On last column of preceding page, only the first sentence of the paragraph given as a quotation from Mr. Galt's <lb/>
Speech, should be read as his. The citation marks and the break out to have been placed after the worlds General Govern<lb break="no">ment, on the second line.</p>-->

<pb n="54" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_054.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">54</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Solicitor GENERAL</persName>.—Mr Speaker, I shall not shrink<lb/>
from the free expression of my opinion on this great question,<lb/>
because I happen unfortunately to be one of a minority of four.<lb/>
This is the most momentous subject ever submitted to the<lb/>
consideration of any of the Colonial Legislatures of British<lb/>
North America, and its importance is evinced by the fact that<lb/>
it has afforded the first example in the annals of this, or I believe<lb/>
any other House of Assembly, of the discussion being carried on<lb/>
with the Speaker in the Chair, thus retraining members from<lb/>
the freedom that a debate in Committee would allow them. I am<lb/>
aware that many hon members, on both sides of the House, are<lb/>
of the opinion that this should be made a Government question.<lb/>
I differ from them. Leaders of the Governments and Oppositions<lb/>
in the other Colonies united in the adoption of the Report. Nova<lb/>
Scotia treated it as an open question, and it is in that position<lb/>
here. When the project of the Legislative Union was proposed, I<lb/>
was strongly opposed to it, and I am of the same opinion still.<lb/>
There is a vital difference between a Legislative Union of the<lb/>
Maritime Provinces and a Federal Union of all the North<lb/>
American Colonies. We would be bound in all our local affairs<lb/>
by the action of a Parliament constituted under a Legislative<lb/>
Union, while a Federal connection leaves to us the unfettered<lb/>
control of all subjects of legislation peculiar to our circumstances.<lb/>
At the Conference help at Quebec, at which were represented<lb/>
Upper and Lower Canada, Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, Prince<lb/>
Edward Island and Newfoundland, the vote was taken on the<lb/>
details of the proposed Union, not by the suffrages of individual<lb/>
members of the Conference, but by each of the Colonies repre<lb break="no"/>sented. Therefore the assertion that the Report was the work<lb/>
of the Canadians is untrue ; it was adopted by all the Colonies<lb/>
who had sent their delegates to take part in the deliberations,<lb/>
and, consequently, the Maritime Provinces had a majority as<lb/>
against Upper and Lower Canada of four to two. It is unjust<lb/>
then to object to the Report as having been got up by the<lb/>
Canadians for their own purposes. Whether the Report meets<lb/>
popular favor or not, the delegates from the Lower Provinces had<lb/>
the power to defeat it, had they been opposed to it. Why, Sir,<lb/>
the very first paragraph in the Report passed unanimously, and<lb/>
its passage was greeted with three cheers. That paragraph<lb/>
reads as follows :—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The best interests and present and future prosperity of British <lb/>
North America will be promoted by a Federal Union under the<lb/>
Crown of Great Britain, provided such Union can be effected on<lb/>
principles just to the several Provinces."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>I am truly surprised that any gentleman, who being present as a<lb/>
delegate, voted for that paragraph, which affirms the principle of<lb/>
Union, can be found now to oppose it. It has been said, Mr<lb/>
Speaker, that a dead lock in the relations of political parties in<lb/>
Canada induced the proposal for a Confederation of these<lb/>
Provinces ; but, Sir, the principle of a political Union of British<lb/>
North America did not see the light for the first time in the year<lb/>
1864. The correspondence between the late Duke of Kent and<lb/>
the late Judge Sewell shows that the idea occupied the minds of<lb/>
men in high station many years ago. In that mine of political<lb/>
information, the Report of the late Lord Durham, the opinion is<lb/>
expressed that Union among themselves can alone preserve these<lb/>
Colonies from absorption into the neighboring republic These<lb/>
facts show that the idea is not peculiar to the Provinces. In<lb/>
Nova Scotia and New Brunswick several of their leading public<lb/>
mens have advanced similar opinions. At the time of the Union<lb/>
between Upper and Lower Canada, the former Province<lb/>
obtained as equal share of representation int he United Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. With Lower Canada, although the population of Upper<lb/>
Canada was less than that of Lower Canada, they each sent an<lb/>
equal number of representatives—65. But the influx of immi<lb break="no"/>gration into Upper Canada has so far changed her position to the<lb/>
Lower Province, that the former provides two-thirds of the reve<lb break="no"/>nue, the share of which appropriated to her is in the inverse ratio to<lb/>
the amount which she contributes. When the Hon George Brown's<lb/>
party came into power, the idea was broached of dissolving the<lb/>
Union with Lower Canada, and having a general Confederation.<lb/>
When the opportunity offered by the Conference of the dele<lb break="no"/>gates of the Maritime Provinces, Canada thought it a favorable<lb/>
occasion to send delegates to listen to the views of the leading<lb/>
men of the Lower Colonies, and I may say that in this instance<lb/>
Canada's difficulty is our opportunity. But, Mr Speaker, in<lb/>
whatever motives the idea of this Confederation may have had<lb/>
its origin, the result of the defeat of the project will be, I have no<lb/>
hesitation in saying, our absorption into the United States.<lb/>
Already the handwriting is on the wall, and it needs no prophet<lb/>

<cb/>

to expound its meaning that Union or Republicanism awaits us.<lb/>
A great outcry has been raised on the subject of the increased<lb/>
taxation to which we would be subjected if we became united to<lb/>
our sister Colonies ; but no hon member has yet shwon how<lb/>
much our situation in that respect would be improved by having<lb/>
to pay the far higher taxes if we should form part of the United<lb/>
States. I leave the financial part of the subject to be dealt with<lb/>
by others, and shall adopt the so-termed "glory argument." I<lb/>
maintain, Mr Speaker, that the pages of history may be ransacked<lb/>
in vain for the record of any people who ever rose to a position<lb/>
among the nations of the earth whose minds were not imbued<lb/>
with that sentiment, and the decline of those who have receded<lb/>
from their once high position dates from the time when it began<lb/>
to lose its influence. Without that element in her national<lb/>
character where would Great Britain have been in her gigantic<lb/>
struggle with Napoleon the first ? The hon member for East<lb/>
Point (Mr Hensley) says that we would be taxed for the con<lb break="no"/>struction of the Intercolonial Railroad, and that we would receive<lb/>
no benefits in return for our expenditure. Under any circum<lb break="no"/>stances we would receive indirect benefit, but I contend that the<lb/>
preservation of monarchical principles to us would be a direct<lb/>
boon, and the promised military aid of the Mother Country by<lb/>
her troops which that railway could transport in the winter season<lb/>
from Halifax to the frontier of Upper Canada, would insure our<lb/>
protection, for, as it has been truly said, if Canada falls we must<lb/>
all share her fate. In addition we would have the protection of<lb/>
her navy on our coasts as long as the navigation continued open.<lb/>
In the convention at Quebec, it was urged by myself and others<lb/>
that the principle of the constitution of the United States Senate,<lb/>
as regards the number of members from each State, should be<lb/>
applied to the Upper House of the Confederate Legislature. The<lb/>
proposal was overruled, and since that time I have begun to<lb/>
think the decision was right. The Conference adopted a medium<lb/>
course between the two extremes, and if Newfoundland shall<lb/>
come into the scheme the Maritime Provinces will receive four<lb/>
additional members. The principle of representation by popula<lb break="no"/>tion in the lower branch is not a novelty. It was recommended<lb/>
by the Late Durham as far back as 1837. The duty of<lb/>
arranging the electoral districts for the first election is to be left<lb/>
to the respective local Governments. The Conference merely<lb/>
apportions the number of representatives to the different Colonies.<lb/>
The hon member for the city (Mr Brecken) said that it<lb/>
would be time to consider our situation when our position as a<lb/>
British Colony shall be involved. He labors under a mistake;<lb/>
the present is the proper time. The crisis will soon arrive, and<lb/>
the time is at hand when we must assume our full share of our<lb/>
burdens. Let the old adage be remembered that those who aid<lb/>
themselves the gods will aid. I am aware of the great satisfaction<lb/>
experienced by the opponents of Confederation at the result of<lb/>
the general election in New Brunswick ; but the issue, Union or<lb/>
no Union was not fairly submitted to the people. Personal<lb/>
antipathies had much to do in bringing about the results. Parties<lb/>
took sides on the principle of the old distich—<lb/></p> 

<p><hi rendition="simple:centre">I do not like thee, Doctor Tell,<lb/>
The reason why, I cannot tell.<lb/></hi></p>

<p>As to Nova Scotia, any action on her part would have been<lb/>
premature before the result of the New Brunswick elections had<lb/>
been ascertained. Sir, I believe that the sun will yet rise upon<lb/>
a Confederation of those Colonies, notwithstanding the jubilant<lb/>
feelings of the opponents of this great measure at its temporary<lb/>
failure. Thirty-three representatives of the six North American<lb/>
Colonies were united on the question last year, and now several<lb/>
of them, strange to say, oppose it. The Report, in my opinion,<lb/>
embraces the best features of the constitutions of Great Britain<lb/>
and of the United States, applicable to our circumstances ; and it<lb/>
is no small satisfaction to those who support the measure of a<lb/>
Union, that though it may meet opposition in the Colonies, it has<lb/>
received approval from the statesmen and press of Great Britain.<lb/>
One great benefit which would accrue from Union would be the<lb/>
diversion of the tide of immigration from the United States to<lb/>
these Colonies, where his civil and religious liberties would be<lb/>
secured to the stranger the moment he landed on our shores. Mr<lb/>
Speaker, I may say that the Report of the delegates embodies<lb/>
principles greater in some respects than those on which the<lb/>
Constitution of the United States is based. The chief ruler of<lb/>
that country is, himself, during his term of office, irresponsible to<lb/>
the people, and is surrounded by a ministry equally unfettered.<lb/>
The Constitution of the proposed Union acknowledges only our<lb/>
gracious Queen and her successors as the chief authority, and the<lb/>
administration of the Confederate Colonies will be conducted by<lb/>

<pb n="55" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_055.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">55</fw>

her representative to be appointed by herself ; but he will be<lb/>
advised by ministers responsible for the acts of the Government,<lb/>
and whom an adverse vote in the Lower Branch of the Legislature<lb/>
would at once dismiss from power. In the States, one result of<lb/>
their institutions is the extinction, or, perhaps, more properly the<lb/>
total ignoring the rights of the minority. Where, however,<lb/>
British principles obtain, the rights and privileges of a minotiry<lb/>
are maintained to them inviolate. One reson for the fact<lb/>
alleged by the hon member for the city (Mr. Brecken) that the<lb/>
manufactures of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick are of but<lb/>
limited extent, is to be found in the limited market open for their<lb/>
consumption. Once remove the barriers of hostile tariffs, and<lb/>
free trade with four millions of people will at once be the result.<lb/>
Union will have the effect of benefitting all parties, and removing<lb/>
the feelings of estrangement arising from different tariffs. Not<lb/>
many years since the Englishman was estranged from the<lb/>
Frenchman. No international sympathy had existed between<lb/>
the two countries for many centuries ; but now a treaty of<lb/>
commerce mutually beneficial has united them, so that one<lb/>
country will not move without the other. Their Union has made<lb/>
these hereditary antagonists the harbingers of peace and civiliza<lb break="no"/>tion. So would it be with us. If hon members had the<lb/>
opportunity of associating with the statesmen of Canada, and if<lb/>
they saw the great resources and made themselves acquinted<lb/>
with her institutions, I am confident that some, at least, would<lb/>
feel that their previously formed opinions were of a very con<lb break="no"/>tracted nature, and were based on a defective knowledge of<lb/>
facts. We have been told that Canada is bankrupt—that her<lb/>
debentures are at a discount—that she is sunk in corruption—<lb/>
that it would be madness to unite our fortunes to a country in<lb/>
that condition. Sir, all this is delusive. The debt is seventy- <lb/>
five millions of dollars ; of that twenty-five millions are repre<lb break="no"/>sented by Canals ; an amount about equal in Railways, of which<lb/>
she has two thousand miles. The purchase of the Seignorial<lb/>
Tenures and the cost of the great Victoria Bridge will represent a<lb/>
large proportion of that debt. True it is that Canadian Debentures<lb/>
had fallen in the English market, but that was in consequence of<lb/>
the Trent affair. British capitalists fearing that war might arise<lb/>
out of that occurrence between England and the States, Canada<lb/>
being a portion of the Empire, her securities were naturally<lb/>
depreciated ; but I can tell hon members that on receipt of the<lb/>
Report of the Conference in England, they advanced 15 per<lb/>
cent. I have now, Sir, given you my individual views on this<lb/>
vital question, which I am convinced will resolve itself either<lb/>
into a Confederation, or an application to us of the Monroe<lb/>
Doctrine by absorption into the United States. I, for one, am<lb/>
not prepared to sacrifice the constitutional privileges we at present<lb/>
enjoy, and I trust that the inhabitants of those now separate<lb/>
Colonies will soon sing in chorus from Newfoundland to the<lb/>
extreme boundary of Upper Canada<lb/></p> 

<p><hi rendition="simple:centre">"Let us be firm and united,<lb/>
One country, one flag for us all ;<lb/>
United our strength will be freedom,<lb/>
Divided we each of us fall. "<lb/></hi></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Mr. HOWLAN</persName>.—Mr. Speaker ; the hon and learned<lb/>
member for Georgetown will probably think it vain for<lb/>
me to place my views on this great question side by side<lb/>
with his opinions. We have been told that sine the<lb/>
result of the elections in New Brunswick, discussing the<lb/>
subject in this House is only like a disputation in a mere<lb/>
debating club, as our decision can lead to no practical<lb/>
result. But, Sir, the principles involved in the scheme <lb/>
concocted by the delegates at Quebec are still the same,<lb/>
and I look upon it as our duty to give our sentiments<lb/>
freely on this question. We know not how soon another<lb/>
delegation may be originated, and advantage taken of our<lb/>
indifference should we evince such on this occasion.<lb/>
Before this debate is concluded, Sir, I hope the Hon<lb/>
Solicitor General will find that his glowing description of<lb/>
the benefits of Confederation has vanished into thin air.<lb/>
With respect to the subject before the House, there is one<lb/>
thing very apparent to those who were here last Session,<lb/>
namely, that the resolution then passed has not been<lb/>
adhered to. On that occasion the argument of the Leader<lb/>
of the Government was that it would be very uncourteous<lb/>
not to appoint delegates to confer on the subject of Union<lb/>
with others to be appointed by the two neighboring<lb/>
Provinces ; but so careful were hon members in regard to<lb/>

<cb/>

the matter that they placed it on the records of this<lb/>
House that no action should be taken on the question<lb/>
until the delegates appointed should report to the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature of the Colony. Now, Sir, we have among the<lb/>
papers laid before this House, a document, which purports<lb/>
to be a report from the delegates authorized to confer on a<lb/>
Legislative Union of the Lower Provinces, but which I<lb/>
take to be no report. It merely states that the delegates<lb/>
met at Charlottetown, then adjourned to Halifax, then to<lb/>
St. John, and then to Canada, where it was decided to<lb/>
postpone the consideration of the question of a Legislative<lb/>
Union of the Maritime Provinces. But the subject which<lb/>
the people of this Island are now called upon to consider<lb/>
is the Report of a delegation not authorized by this House,<lb/>
and one by which the constitution of this Colony is to be<lb/>
wrested from us. In considering the question of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, we ought to view it not as it would affect us<lb/>
at present, but as it would probably operate upon the<lb/>
interests of this Colony in all time to come. The<lb/>
principle of representation by population in the Lower<lb/>
House is borrowed from the American system ; yet the<lb/>
Quebec Conference did not follow out the same model<lb/>
with repect to the constitution of the Upper Branch. In<lb/>
the neighboring Republic each State has the privilege of<lb/>
sending two representatives to the Senate, no matter how<lb/>
small its population. New York with its population of<lb/>
3,097,394, has only the same number of Senators in<lb/>
Congress as the State of Rhode Island with its population<lb/>
of 147,545. The difference between the population of these<lb/>
two States is as 20 to 1, greater fully than it is between<lb/>
that of Upper Canada and this Island ; yet while this<lb/>
Report allows Upper Canada 24 members in the Legislative<lb/>
Council of the Confederation, this Colony is only allotted<lb/>
5. Instead of all the Provinces being allowed the same<lb/>
number of members each in the Upper House, according<lb/>
to the principle of the United States' constitution, each of<lb/>
the Canadas is to have as many Councillors as all the<lb/>
Lower Provinces put together. Then, again, the members<lb/>
of this body are to be appointed for life, a system which<lb/>
would undoubtedly bring about a dead lock, the very state<lb/>
of affairs in Canada which Confederation is intended to<lb/>
remedy. In the 17th paragraph of the Report we are<lb/>
told " the basis of representation in the House of Commons<lb/>
shall be population, as determined by the official census<lb/>
every ten years ; and the number of members at first shall<lb/>
be 194. " Of this number Upper Canada is to have 82,<lb/>
and Lower Canada 65 — in all for Canada 147. The <lb/>
remainder of the 194 is distributed as follows : Nova<lb/>
Scotia 19, New Brunswick 15, Newfoundland 8, P. E.<lb/>
Island 5 — in all for the Lower Provinces 47. By this<lb/>
arrangement it will be seen that Canada will have 100<lb/>
representatives in the House of Commons more than the<lb/>
aggregate of all the other Colonies. Representation by<lb/>
population might be very well for Canada herself, but in<lb/>
a general union of the Colonies it would operate injuriously<lb/>
for the Maritime Provinces, as they could not expect to<lb/>
protect their interests when they would have to contend<lb/>
with 100 of a clear majority over their own representation.<lb/>
This principle would give the city of Montreal with its<lb/>
101,000 inhabitants one representative more than this<lb/>
Island. Quite different is the representation of Great<lb/>
Britain, for while London has about the same population<lb/>
as Scotland, that city has only 16 members in the House<lb/>
of Commons, while Scotland has 53. But it may be argued<lb/>
that as our population increases our representation will<lb/>
increase. This is very doubtful. Indeed, under the<lb/>
operation of the 20th and 21st clauses of the Report it<lb/>
seems probable that we might lose our representation<lb/>
altogether. Lower Canada is always to have 65 members,<lb/>
and the representation of the other Colonies is to be<lb/>
arranged every ten years so as to give each the same ratio<lb/>
to population as she will then possess. Now, should the<lb/>
population of Lower Canada increase more rapidly than<lb/>
that of this Island, which is almost certain to be the case,<lb/>
our representation would decrease, and we would be left<lb/>
perhaps without a member at all. To show at least that<lb/>

<pb n="56" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_056.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">56</fw>
 
it is much more likely that our representation will decrease<lb/>
than increase, I will read the Hon. George Brown's<lb/>
opinions on the subject, as given in the Toronto "Globe."<lb/>
In treating of the probably effort of these two clauses of<lb/>
the Report, to which I have been alluding, on the repre<lb break="no"/>sentation of the Maritime Provinces, that journal says:—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The fact is best shown by illustration. Prince Edward<lb/>
Island, with a population, say $5,009, is, it is said, to have five<lb/>
representatives at starting. Suppose she increases at the rate of<lb/>
20 per cent. each ten years, at the end of twenty years her<lb/>
population will be 126,000. But at the same rate of progress<lb/>
the population of Lower Canada would be 1,596,000. Divided<lb/>
by 65, this would give one representative to every 24,550 of her<lb/>
people : so that the Island would not be able to claim an increase<lb/>
of membership. If similar calculations be made with respect to<lb/>
the other Provinces, it will be proved that the additions they will<lb/>
be able to make their representation will be very small. In<lb/>
fact, if the increase in the population of some of them be not<lb/>
greater in the future than it has been in the past, they will, if<lb/>
the plan be strictly carried out, lose instead of gain."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>But there is another point which I desire to notice with<lb/>
respect to representation in the House of Commons. An<lb/>
important alteration has been made by the Canadians in<lb/>
the 24th clause of the Report. In the copy before this<lb/>
House which is signed by Sir E. P Pache as a "true<lb/>
copy," the clause reads thus:—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"24. The local Legislature of each Province may from time<lb/>
to time alter the Electoral Districts for the purpose of Represen<lb break="no"/>tation in the House of Commons, and distribute the Representa<lb break="no"/>tives to which the Province is entitled in any manner such<lb/>
Legislature they think fit."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>But, Sir, I have another copy on my table in which this<lb/>
clause is quite differently worded, and which is the same<lb/>
as the one presented to the Canadian Legislature. It<lb/>
reads as follows:—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"24. The local Legislature of each Province may from time<lb/>
to time alter the Electoral Districts for the purpose of Repre<lb break="no"/>sentation <hi rendition="simple:italic">in such Legislature</hi>, and distribute the Representatives <lb/>
to which the Province is entitled <hi rendition="simple:italic">in such local Legislature</hi> in<lb/>
any manner such Legislature may see fit."<lb/></p></quote> 

<p>This is a very different matter. The clause as it first<lb/>
stood was an important one, because it gave the Local<lb/>
Legislature the power to arrange the districts for the<lb/>
representation in the popular branch of the General<lb/>
Legislature ; but as altered it would enable the gentlemen<lb/>
who might hold the destinies of this Island in their hands<lb/>
to cut and carve the constituencies as they pleased. The<lb/>
privilege of being taxed is a very great privilege indeed.<lb/>
And if the resources of our local government should be<lb/>
insufficient for the wants of the Colony we have the<lb/>
additional privilege of taxing ourselves. To show how<lb/>
the arrangement for taxing ourselves. To show how<lb/>
this arrangement for taxation contained in the Report<lb/>
will operate upon the Lower Provinces, I will read an<lb/>
extract from Mr. Galt's speech this his constituents at<lb/>
Sherbrooke, wherein he treats of excise duties. He says :<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The General Government would also have the power<lb/>
of regulating excise duties. The imposition of these duties<lb/>
was a necessary corollary to the imposition of the duties<lb/>
of Customs ; and the power to impose the one must be given to<lb/>
the same authority that exercised the power to impose the other.<lb/>
Excise duties were placed upon spirits made in the country in<lb/>
order to place the consumer thereof on the same footing he<lb/>
would be on if he consumed spirits imported from abroad. He<lb/>
might remark that in the Lower Provinces they had no excise<lb/>
duties; he believed they did not manufacture whiskey to any<lb/>
extent, but in introducing a system of excise duties they would<lb/>
have to be subjected to the same regulations that were followed<lb/>
in Canada. In general terms he would add that the Central<lb/>
Government would have the power of raising money by all the<lb/>
other modes and systems of taxation—the power of taxation<lb/>
had been confided to the General Legislature—and there was<lb/>

<cb/>

only one method let to the local Governments, if their own <lb/>
resources became exhausted, and this was direct taxation."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Again, in a speech delivered in the Canadian Legislautre<lb/>
on the 7th February, Mr Galt said:—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Let the house be frankly and kindly look at it, as a great<lb/>
measure brought down for the purpose of relieving Canada,<lb/>
from <hi rendition="simple:italic">distress and depression</hi>. At this moment Canada stand<lb break="no"/>ing alone, had seen her <hi rendition="simple:italic">credit seriously impaired, but Con<lb break="no"/>federation would give us a much larger fund to pledge for the<lb/>
security of the public creditor.</hi> The Lower Provinces are in<lb/>
a much better position, and if the local revenues became<lb/>
inadequate the local Governments <hi rendition="simple:italic">would have to resort to<lb/>
direct taxation.</hi>"<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>This talk about direct taxation is no empty theory. The<lb/>
Canadians hint that their impost duties might be lowered<lb/>
under Confederation ; but if this were done taxation in<lb/>
another form would have to be resorted to. This idea,<lb/>
however, is not new, for in a debate in the British House<lb/>
of Commons on the 28th of April, 1863, the Under<lb/>
Secretary of State for the Colonies said:—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Her Majesty's Government had freely expressed their<lb/>
opinion,, (to the Governor General) " that nothing would<lb/>
tend so much to raise the credit of Canada as a measure for<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">direct taxation</hi>, which would enable her to <hi rendition="simple:italic">lower her duties<lb/>
upon imports</hi>."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Further, we have the testimony of the Hon. George Brown,<lb/>
as to the manner in which the Maritime Provinces are to<lb/>
be taxed to bear the burdens of Canada. I will read from<lb/>
his speech on the Confederation in the Assembly of Canada,<lb/>
an extract wherein he touched on this subject:—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"It was said New Brunswick was getting more than her<lb/>
share ; but it was absurd to oppose the adoption of a scheme<lb/>
such as this for such a paltry sum. It could not be weighed<lb/>
in the balance against it, and the subsidy was granted for<lb/>
only ten years. <hi rendition="simple:italic">We would get a large additional population<lb/>
to assist us in bearing our burdens</hi>—a most economical popu<lb break="no"/>lation, too. Why the Chief Justice of Nova Scotia only gets<lb/>
£600 a year. He ws in favor of the scheme if it was for<lb/>
Canada alone. <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Conference had pledged to open up the<lb/>
great North West and deepen the canals</hi>.—He believed there<lb/>
was no such instance in history ; <hi rendition="simple:italic">other nations paid large<lb/>
sums for territory</hi>. Louisiana was bought for twenty mil<lb break="no"/>lions of dollars. <hi rendition="simple:italic">What would we not give for Maine or<lb/>
Michigan, or Minnesota, which it was possible to pay?</hi> Yet<lb/>
we have peddling objections to give us nearly a million of<lb/>
people and vast and rich territories: <hi rendition="simple:italic">a few dollars for a few<lb/>
years ought not to stand in the way</hi>."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>So we see, then, that our "<hi rendition="simple:italic">economical</hi> population" is to<lb/>
assist in bearing the burdens of Canada ; that there is<lb/>
danger ahead to the best interests of this Colony. It is<lb/>
evident that the whole scheme has been concocted to relieve<lb/>
Canada of her difficulties ; but while her politicians are<lb/>
prepared to purchase New Brunswick with a "paltry.<lb/>
sum," they have thought this Island too insignificant to<lb/>
offer us any subsidy. The next paragraph to which I will<lb/>
refer is the 55th, relating, among other things, to Canals<lb/>
and Railways. The extension of the Canals, we are told<lb/>
by some of the framers of this Report, is not to be pro<lb break="no"/>ceeded with until the state of the finances permit ; and<lb/>
we are also informed that they will be a general benefit<lb/>
to the Colonies. I am inclined to differ with these gentle<lb break="no"/>men upon this point. This subject has occupied the<lb/>
attention of the people of Canada for several years. Munro<lb/>
in his work on British America says:<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"What is the estimated cost of Canal extensions? A Canal<lb/>
between Georgian Bay and Lake Ontario is estimated at<lb/>
$22,170,750, and the improvements which will be required<lb/>
in the St. Lawrence Canals, &amp;c,. are estimated at nearly as<lb/>
much more, so as to admit vessels of 1000 tons to pass from<lb/>
Chicago to the ocean. In the Canada Board of works report<lb/>
for 1856, it is stated that the Georgian Canal from compari<lb break="no"/>son with other Works, would cost $25,000,000."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>So it appears that this work has been under the considera<lb break="no"/>tion of the Canadian Government for at least ten years,<lb/>

<pb n="57" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_057.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">57</fw>

and now we are told it is to be undertaken especially for<lb/>
the benefit of the united Colonies. But the question is,<lb/>
when will the state of the finances admit of this Canal <lb/>
extension. The Hon George Brown in his speech at<lb/>
Toronto, said : </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"I will, however, take care, gentlemen, that while I have <lb/>
the honor to be one of the advisers of the Crown, the closest<lb/>
economy shall be practised in all matters of the kind.<lb/>
(Cheers.) But in agreeing to the construction of the Inter<lb break="no"/>colonial Railway, we were not without a slight regard for <lb/>
the interests of the West, and I am happy to say that with<lb/>
UNANIMOUS CONSENT OF THE DELEGATES, WE HAVE AGREED TO<lb/>
THE EXTENSION OF THE CANAL SYSTEM OF THE WEST." (Loud<lb/>
Cheers.)<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>His constituents would have discarded him for consenting<lb/>
to the construction of the Intercolonial Railway had he<lb/>
not obtained this concession. Upper Canada will insist <lb/>
on Canal extension if the Railway is proceeded with, and <lb/>
without any regard to the state of the finances. The <lb/>
finances would be considered sufficient as soon as Confed<lb break="no"/>eration was consummated. We may look upon this as <lb/>
almost certain, and the great point for us to consider is, <lb/>
what benefit would those expensive Canals be to the tax<lb break="no"/>payers of Prince Edward Island? This is a question which <lb/>
hon members, and the people of the country can very <lb/>
easily answer for themselves. Reference has been made to <lb/>
corruption in Canada, and to the stories in newspapers ; <lb/>
but in alluding to the manner in which money has been <lb/>
squandered by Canadian politicians, I do not intend to <lb/>
quote common newspaper authority, but the remarks of <lb/>
the Hon George Brown himself, the present Premier of <lb/>
Canada, based upon an authentic document. In the <lb/>
Toronto <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> of March 8, 1861, the Hon George Brown <lb/>
wrote :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The publication of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Auditor's Report</hi> upon the finan<lb break="no"/>cial condition of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Grand Trunk Railway</hi>, may be regarded <lb/>
as the final bursting of the great bubble. What was known<lb/>
to a few, suspected by many, and feared by all, who had<lb/>
money in the concern, has now been confirmed by official<lb/>
examination, and published to the world."<lb/></p> 

<p>"The Company's accounts have been <hi rendition="simple:italic">systematically cooked <lb/>
and deliberately falsified</hi> by John Ross &amp; Co., to deceive the <lb/>
English proprietors and capitalists. While these gentlemen <lb/>
were claiming a <hi rendition="simple:italic">profit</hi> in the shape of revenue of $1,472,113, <lb/>
the Company actually suffered a loss of $1,009,491! No <lb/>
wonder the Montreal <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi>, the faithful organ of the coa<lb break="no"/>lition for years, and the <hi rendition="simple:italic">ready apologist</hi> of every railway <lb/>
iniquity hitherto brought to light, stands aghast now. The <lb/>
figures, revelations, and arguments of the Auditors, have <lb/>
proved too much even for the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi>, and he talks boldly <lb/>
of <hi rendition="simple:italic">criminal prosecutions</hi>, of the personal responsibility of the<lb/>
directors to <hi rendition="simple:italic">deluded</hi> purchasers of stock, and <hi rendition="simple:italic">quotes the statute<lb/>
book</hi> in support of his views. He declares that the Report<lb/>
'will be read with painful interest, that its statements are of<lb/>
the very gravest nature, affecting not only the character, of<lb/>
the management of the Grand Trunk Railway, but the cha<lb break="no"/>racters, and perhaps the fortunes of individuals." Of the<lb/>
fitness of the Auditors for their task the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi> says:<lb/>
'There are perhaps no men in this country better fitted than<lb/>
Messrs. Allan and Workman to pass a judgment upon it,<lb/>
none who better understand the value of figures, or who are<lb/>
more capable in such matters to winnow the chaff from the<lb/>
wheat. We simply mention this for the benefit of our <hi rendition="simple:italic">dis<lb break="no"/>tant</hi> readers. These gentlemen say distinctly, after a careful<lb/>
investigation of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">books</hi> of the company, that the balance<lb/>
sheet which has been <hi rendition="simple:italic">prepared for the eyes of the public is not<lb/>
correct</hi>."<lb/></p></quote>

<p>Hon George Brown adds,— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"But perhaps the most interesting part of the Report is <lb/>
under the head of 'General remarks." It is there stated as<lb/>
the deliberate opinion of the Auditors, that 'the present<lb/>
embarassments of the company have arisen, chiefly from its<lb/>
connection with the successive Governments of the Province,<lb/>
and the necessity therefrom of <hi rendition="simple:italic">conciliating political support</hi>.<lb/>
Under this head they appropriately place Mr GALT'S HUGE<lb/>
SWINDLE in the purchase of the St. Lawrence and Atlantic<lb/>

<cb/>

Railway at 37 1/2 per cent. premium WHEN IT MIGHT HAVE BEEN <lb/>
PURCHASED AT 60 per cent. discount. The leasing of the<lb/>
Portland end at 6 per cent. annual interest on its entire<lb/>
capital, when its stock was selling at a very large discount,<lb/>
ANOTHER SWINDLE OF MR GALT, by which he realized a<lb/>
FORTUNE, is added to the list. The loss to the company<lb/>
through the SPECULATIONS of Mr Galt and his friends is set<lb/>
down by the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Auditors</hi> at $6,000,000. The murder is out at<lb/>
last, upon the authority of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Company's own Auditors</hi>,<lb/>
that ALEXANDER T. GALT, our worthy Minister of Agriculture,<lb/>
have made ENORMOUS FORTUNES, but at an expense to the<lb/>
Grand Trunk stockholders of (6,000,000) SIX MILLIONS OF<lb/>
DOLLARS."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>I may be simply allowed to ask if it is safe to entrust the<lb/>
financial affairs of the United Colonies to such men.<lb/>
The clauses of the Report numbered 60, 61 and 62, call<lb/>
for a passing notice. The 60th says that "the General<lb/>
Government shall assume all the debts and liabilities of<lb/>
each Province." And the next two state the amount of<lb/>
debt to be assumed for Canada, Nova Scotia and New<lb/>
Brunswick. The arrangement does not give satisfaction<lb/>
to the people of Nova Scotia, for they say the debt of<lb/>
Canada is large, her railroad does not pay, and her<lb/>
debentures rate very low in the money market. New<lb/>
Brunswick has not so much reason to complain, for she<lb/>
presented her claim for compensation, and obtained <lb/>
$63,000 for ten years. But when poor Prince Edward <lb/>
Island asked for a few thousand pounds to buy up her <lb/>
proprietary lands, it would not be granted. A proposition <lb/>
to this effect was made by one of our delegates, and I <lb/>
believe none of them can tell who seconded the motion. <lb/>
There was certainly something wrong here. I am of <lb/>
opinion that had our delegates advocated the interests of <lb/>
the Island as well as Mr Tilley did those of New <lb/>
Brunswick, we would have received a grant for the <lb/>
purchase of our lands. They would have some show of <lb/>
argument in favor of this Colony entering the Union, <lb/>
could they come down to this House and tell us that the <lb/>
long vexed Land Question was to be at last set at rest. <lb/>
Instead of procuring a sum for this purpose they have not <lb/>
obtained a single farthing. Is the settlement of our land <lb/>
question not as important to us as the railway to Pictou <lb/>
for Nova Scotia, Western extension for New Brunswick, or <lb/>
$ 150,000 a year to Newfoundland? We have the best of <lb/>
authority for supposing that had the application for a <lb/>
grant to buy up the proprietors' lands of this Island been <lb/>
unanimously supported by our delegates, it would have <lb/>
been acceded to. That authority is the Hon George <lb/>
Brown, who, in an extract which I have already quoted, <lb/>
said respecting the allowance to New Brunswick, "It<lb/>
was absurd to oppose the adoption of a scheme such as<lb/>
this for such a paltry sum." I now come to what we are <lb/>
to receive under Confederation, as laid down in the 63d and <lb/>
64th clauses of the Report. I, however, can scarcely call <lb/>
it receiving, for in this case we are to pay the difference to <lb/>
boot. The Hon Colonial Secretary says this Report is just <lb/>
and liberal to Prince Edward Island. Is it justice to <lb/>
require us to pay some £20,000 more than we receive? <lb/>
If this be justice, it is such as I will never accede to. We <lb/>
are to give up a large and increasing revenue to the <lb/>
politicians of Canada, who have never been able to govern <lb/>
their own country, and what are we to receive in return? <lb/>
We are to get 80 cents per head of our present population, <lb/>
and the interest of £632,812, being the proportion of debt <lb/>
in our favor, in all amounting to about £50,000. We <lb/>
have been told that a part of this £632,812 may be taken <lb/>
to buy up proprietary lands ; but the Report says nothing <lb/>
of the kind ; it only states that we shall be entitled to <lb/>
receive the interest at 5 per cent. Besides, if the principal <lb/>
was taken to purchase lands, the amount of interest which <lb/>
would then be received would be less, and our local <lb/>
revenue diminished to that extent, consequently than <lb/>
would be no gain. With respect to the allowance of 80 <lb/>
cents per head for the benefit of the local governments, it <lb/>
would be insufficient for the Lower Provinces, but it would <lb/>

<pb n="58" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_058.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">58</fw>

be a gain to Canada, as will be seen by the following <lb/>
statement : —</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:centre">CANADA.</hi></p>
<table>
<row><cell>Subsidy,</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">$2,006,121</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Local revenues retained,</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">1,297,043</hi></hi></cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">$3,303,154</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Deduct local appropriations given up,</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">2,260,129</hi></hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Gain by Canada,</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">$1,403,035</hi></cell></row>
</table>

<p>This gain to Canada would amount to about 41 cents per <lb/>
head of the population, while the Maritime Provinces by<lb/>
giving up their customs' revenues and only receiving 80<lb/>
cents per head in return, besides having the Judges' salaries<lb/>
and a few others paid, would be under the necesrity, in<lb/>
in order to carry on their local governments, to resort to<lb/>
direct taxation, together with having to submit to an<lb/>
increased Tariff. But it is said that after the Union their<lb/>
Tariff will be reduced from 20 to 15 per cent. Why should<lb/>
theirs come down and ours go up? If, under Confederation,<lb/>
the tariff could be made 15 per cent, it must be on account<lb/>
of the flourishing state of the Maritime Provinces. But<lb/>
why should our tariff be raised to even 15 per cent? i<lb/>
must say again this is a <hi rendition="simple:italic">justice</hi> and <hi rendition="simple:italic">liberality</hi> which I can<lb/>
not understand. As a set off, however, to an increased<lb/>
tariff we are told that would an interest in thte<lb/>
vast public works of Canada, costing over 20 millions of<lb/>
dollars, and that we would be united to a country<lb/>
possessing great wealth. It is a strange thing that Canada<lb/>
with all these advantages is running so rapidly into debt.<lb/>
The following statement of her financial affairs for several<lb/>
years, copied from authentic sources, does not show thate<lb/>
she is a prosperous country : —<lb/></p> 

<table>
<row><cell></cell><cell>Receipts.</cell><cell>Payments.</cell></row>
<row><cell>1857</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">$6,981,062</hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">$11,846,690</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>1858</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">8,072,536</hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">11,163,039</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>1859</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">8,157,346</hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">9,630,592</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>1860</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">9,014,831</hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">12,585,652</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>1861</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">9,738,258</hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">11,962,652</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>1862</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">10,629,204</hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">11,395,923</hi></cell></row>
</table>

<p>In 1868 an attempt was made to reduce the expenditure, <lb/>
which was accomplished to the extent of $228,837 and still<lb/>
the result, as officially stated, was</p>

<table>
<row><cell>Expenditure, less redemption of debt</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">$10,742,807</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Receipts, less sale of Debenture and Sinking</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Fund</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">9,760,816</hi></hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Deficiency</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">$972,491</hi></cell></row>
</table>

<p>These annual deficiencies, amounting in the aggregate to <lb/>
$16,964,000 have passed into the funded debt of Canada, and<lb/>
now form part of the debt of $62,500,000 which that Province<lb/>
asks the Confederation to assume.<lb/></p> 

<p>Here in a few short years we see that her debt has <lb/>
increased over 16 millions, and for the great privilege<lb/>
of contributing towards paying the interest of this debt, we<lb/>
are to receive 80 cents per head ! But Galt says that<lb/>
last year Canada would have a balance of revenue in her<lb/>
favor, and talk of reducing the debt under Confederation.<lb/>
Now, Sir, when the statesmen of a country propose to<lb/>
lower their tariff and reduce their debt, they must intend<lb/>
to do it by taxing some person. But even though 80 cents<lb/>
a head should be sufficient for our present wants, it would<lb/>
not be sufficient in a few years. Our Prince of Wales<lb/>
College costs us a large sum, and our common Schools<lb/>
require no small portion of our revenue ; but if in a few<lb/>
years our population were to increase to 300,00, and we<lb/>
should want larger Colleges, and almost twice as many<lb/>
schools, we would not receive a single farthing more from<lb/>
the General Government. Is this justice or liberality ?<lb/>
Our revenue in 1850 was £18,000, and last year £66,000<lb/>
or nearly £70,000, making a difference of nearly £52,000.<lb/>
Supposing, then, that this Delegation had taken place in<lb/>
1850, £18,000 would have been taken as the basis to work<lb/>
upon, and the increase in 14 years, namely £52,000,<lb/>
shows to some extent the increasing amount which we<lb/>

<cb/>

would annually pay into the general treasury under Con<lb break="no"/>federation. But to begin with, the difference between the<lb/>
Tariffs of Canada and this Island, would give us at once<lb/>
nearly £27,000 additional to pay. Some, however, may<lb/>
say that the Tariff under Confederation would not yield so<lb/>
great a revenue as would appear by adding the difference<lb/>
between the Canadian Tariff and our own. The amount<lb/>
could be very little less, for the principal items which go<lb/>
to make up our revenue are the duties on articles not<lb/>
produced within the bounds of this great Confederation.<lb/>
In 1863 the revenue which we derived from the following<lb/>
articles was: —</p>

<table>
<row><cell>Molasses</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">£4834</hi></cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell>Sugar</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">1562</hi></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell>Tea</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">7045</hi></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell>Tobacco</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">1206</hi></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell>Rum</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">3506</hi></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell>Brandy</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">661</hi></hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:underline">0</hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:underline">0</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">£18,814</hi></cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
</table>
   
<p>On these six articles alone — which are only some of the <lb/>
number that must be imported— you see we had a revenue<lb/>
in 1863 of £18,814, while the whole revenue for the year<lb/>
was merely £38,550. But we are told to look at the<lb/>
advantages of intercolonial free trade. This is only a very<lb/>
weak argument, for free trade could be obtained<lb/>
independently of a Union of the Colonies. The following<lb/>
memorandum under date 18th September, 1862, signed by<lb/>
the Premiers of the three Provinces, is conclusive on this<lb/>
point :—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The delegates from Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, <lb/>
and the Government of Canada, having under consideration<lb/>
the report of the Hon. the Finance Minister of Canada, of<lb/>
the 8th September, instant on the subject of Intercolonial<lb/>
Reciprocity, agree—<lb/></p> 

<p>1. That the free interchange of goods, the growth, produce <lb/>
and manufacture of the Provinces, and uniformity of tariff,<lb/>
are considered to be an indispensable consequence of the<lb/>
construction of the Intercolonial Railway.<lb/></p> 

<p>2. But in consequence of the recent diminution of the <lb/>
revenues of the respective Provinces arising out of the war<lb/>
in the neighbouring republic, and the increased liabilities<lb/>
incurred by the additional obligations necessary to the con<lb break="no"/>struction of the proposed road, the delegates from New<lb/>
Brunswick and Nova Scotia regret that they are not at this<lb/>
moment in a position to adopt measures to carry this im<lb break="no"/>portant principle into practical effect.<lb/></p> 

<p>(Signed) J,S. MCDONALD (For Canada.) <lb/>
(Signed) JOSEPH HOWE,<lb/>
(Signed) S.L. TILLEY."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Then, again, it is said Canada will furnish a market for<lb/>
our produce. We are to have nearly 4,000,000 of people<lb/>
to deal with. It, however, will be a strange thing if<lb/>
Canada, which exports large quantities of the same kinds<lb/>
of agricultural produce we have to spare, will afford<lb/>
us any advantages in this respect. The Board of Trade<lb/>
returns for that Province show : </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"In the 1863, Canada exported 8,905,578 lbs. of<lb/>
butter ; 556,305 dozen eggs ; 3,844,272 lbs of pork ; 1,182,576<lb/>
lbs of ham; 1,201,819 barrels of flour; 1,905,980 bushels of<lb/>
oats; 5,741,479 bushels of wheat; 2,147,977 bushels of barley<lb/>
and rye; 17,650 barrels of oatmeal; 29,168 barrels of fish, and<lb/>
187,599 ewt. of dried fish."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>So that in almost every way we can view this Report, it<lb/>
presents nothing to us but increased taxation on the<lb/>
industry of this Island. And I now come to notice some of<lb/>
the more prominent items of expenditure of which we<lb/>
would have to bear a share under Confederation. The<lb/>
67th clause say: "All engagements, that may, before<lb/>
the Union, be entered into with the Imperial Government<lb/>
for the defence of the Country, shall be assumed by the<lb/>
General Government." This question of defence seems to<lb/>
have been the burden of nearly every speech of the<lb/>
delegates. At one of the dinners given to them the Hon<lb/>
George Brown said;-- <lb/></p>

<pb n="59" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_059.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">59</fw>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"I cannot conclude without referring to some other things <lb/>
which have received the grave attention of the Conference.<lb/>
And the first point to which I desire to call attention is,<lb/>
the fact that the delegates have unanimously resolved that<lb/>
the United Provinces shall be placed at the earliest moment<lb/>
in a thorough state of defence. The attacks which have<lb/>
been made upon us have created the impression that these<lb/>
Provinces are in a weak and feeble state ; if, then, we would<lb/>
do away with this false impression, and place ourselves on a<lb/>
firm and secure footing in the eyes of the world, our course<lb/>
must be to put our country in such a position of defence that<lb/>
we may fearlessly look our enemies in the face. It is a plea<lb break="no"/>sure to me to state, and I am sure it must be a pleasure to<lb/>
all present to be informed, that the Conference at Quebec<lb/>
did not separate before entering into A PLEDGE TO PUT THE<lb/>
MILITARY AND NAVAL DEFENCES OF THE UNITED PROVINCES IN<lb/>
A MOST COMPLETE AND SATISFACTORY POSITION."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Not being a military man, I approach this question of<lb/>
defence with considerable diffidence. I believe, however,<lb/>
it is all a matter of moonshine. I have the fullest con<lb break="no"/>fidence in Great Britain's ability to defend her Colonies,<lb/>
and very little faith in their being able to protect them<lb break="no"/>selves. For stating that the latter is a ridiculous idea, I<lb/>
have the authority of a military man—no less than Lieut.<lb/>
Colonel Haviland—who, in addressing this House on this<lb/>
subject last Session, said :—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"As to the idea attributed to the Imperial Government that<lb/>
these Colonies are able to bear the burden of defending them<lb break="no"/>selves against the invasion of a foreign foe, the sooner Great<lb/>
Britain awakes from that delusion the better. Our small annual<lb/>
appropriation of £400 for the volunteer organization is not<lb/>
passed without strong expressions of disapprobation, while Nova<lb/>
Scotia grants $20,000 for that service."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>I think since last year, another change has come over the <lb/>
spirit of his dream. (Laughter.) But at the utmost what <lb/>
does Great Britain expect us to do for our defence? I <lb/>
will read the resolution of the House of Commons on the <lb/>
subject, together with the war Minister's explanation <lb/>
thereof:--</p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That this House (while fully recognizing the claims of all<lb/>
portions of the British empire to imperial aid in their protection<lb/>
against perils arising from the consequences of imperial policy), is<lb/>
of opinion, that colonies exercising the rights of self-government,<lb/>
ought to undertake the main responsibility of providing for their<lb/>
own internal order and security, and ought to assist in their own<lb/>
external defence."<lb/></p></quote> 

<p>A few days after the passage of this resolution, a debate<lb/>
occurred in the Commons relative to an appropriation for<lb/>
military purposes in the Mauritius and Nova Scotia, when<lb/>
Mr Adderly spoke as follows :—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"According to the resolution assented to by the House, the<lb/>
distant possessions of the Crown were to be responsible for their<lb/>
own internal defence, and to take their share in the repulse of a<lb/>
foreign enemy, the further proposition that distant fortifications<lb/>
should be discontinued was not pressed because accepted of<lb/>
course." Mr A. continued "as regards Nova Scotia, bearing<lb/>
in mind the resolution agreed to the other night, he would like<lb/>
to ask what share of the burthen of the defence, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment expected that Colony to take ?"<lb/></p>

<p>Sir Geo. Lewis replied, "its share would be the maintenance <lb/>
of a Militia."</p></quote> 

<p>If that is what Nova Scotia is expected to do, I do not <lb/>
think it probable that this Colony will be required to<lb/>
undertake more. Then, again, what are we to understand<lb/>
by "the communication with the North Western Terri<lb break="no"/>tory," as set forth in the 69th clause. That it is no new<lb/>
subject, and an undertaking which will involve great<lb/>
expense, will be seen from an extract from the preface of<lb/>
a work by Professor Hinds, called "A Narrative of the<lb/>
Canada Exploring Expedition." He says :—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The chief difficulty in the way of rapid transit across the <lb/>
continent lies between Lake Superior and Rainay Lake. The<lb/>
liberality which has already been manifested by the Parliament<lb/>
of Canada, in voting supplies to explore and open this com<lb break="no"/>munication, will doubtless be persevered in until the route is<lb/>

<cb/>

well established." In 1857 an expedition was sent out by the <lb/>
Canadian Government with the following instructions; "The<lb/>
primary object is to make a thorough examination of the tract<lb/>
of country between Lake Superior and Red River; to determine<lb/>
the best route for a communication through British Territory<lb/>
from that Lake to the Red River Settlement, and ultimately to<lb/>
the great tracts of cultivable land beyond them." In vol. 2,<lb/>
page 212, it is stated "That the shortest line of road from the<lb/>
limits of the settlement on Western Canada via the shores of<lb/>
Lakes Huron and Superior form the basis of speculative enter<lb break="no"/>prise on an enlarged scale, a winter communication with these<lb/>
regions will become a necessity, and may ultimately extend<lb/>
Westward to Red River. It is not improbable that circum<lb break="no"/>stances now <hi rendition="simple:italic">dimly forseen</hi> may expedite the opening of this<lb/>
communication, and make it a matter not only of Colonial but<lb/>
Imperial interest."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>It would appear from these statements that the communi<lb break="no"/>cation referred to is principally for a military road.<lb/>
However that may be, if we enter the Union we must pay<lb/>
for it, whatever its cost, which will probably be nearly as<lb/>
much as that of the Intercolonial Railway. And in the<lb/>
face of all this we are told that taxation will not be<lb/>
increased. I will sum up a few of the items of increased<lb/>
expenditure to show that such an idea must be absurd; and<lb/>
in doing so I will only mention those expenses which<lb/>
must be borne immediately should the Confederation<lb/>
scheme be consummated :—<lb/></p> 

<table>
<row><cell>Intercolonial Railway, as estimated</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">$15,000,000</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Canal Extension</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">30,000,000</hi></hi></cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">$45,000,000</hi></hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Interest on the above amount for Railway and</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Canals at 6 per cent</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">$2,700,000</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Estimated expense of new Parliament</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">600,000</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Militia beyond present expense</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">500,000</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Army and Navy, estimated to cost</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">2,500,000</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">$5,300,000</hi></cell></row>
</table>

<p>Of this sum not a farthing is paid at present. How, then,<lb/>
I ask could the Government under Confederation be car<lb break="no"/>ried on without increased taxation ! Again, we are told,<lb/>
that Union would tend to develope our fisheries. But I<lb/>
would ask is there anything now to prevent people from<lb/>
Canada or any other place coming here and engaging in<lb/>
the fisheries ! I heard a gentleman who was extensively<lb/>
engaged in fisheries at Gaspe state that though he received<lb/>
a bounty of 25 per cent he would not come to prosecute<lb/>
them in this Colony. We are further told that if we do<lb/>
not enter the proposed Union we will be like dormice.<lb/>
But, Sir, would we then have any greater scope for our<lb/>
youth more than now ! Have not Davies, Hyndman, and<lb/>
others of our young men, as great a field open for them in<lb/>
the British service as they would have in a Confederation<lb/>
with a paltry population of 4 millions of people? Have <lb/>
the people of this Colony petitioned to do away with its <lb/>
constitution? Do they wish to enter Confederation? I <lb/>
believe they complain of their land tenures; but have <lb/>
they set forth any other grievance? And further, is there <lb/>
anything in the financial condition of the Colony to warrant <lb/>
us in going into Confederation? Take our Blue Book for <lb/>
1863-4 and see what unceptionable state of our Revenue <lb/>
it presents. It shows:--</p> 

<table>
<row><cell>Imports</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">£293,431</hi></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>An increase of</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">£82,191</hi></cell><cell>over</cell></row>
<row><cell>those of the previous year.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Exports</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">£200,472</hi></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>An increase of</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">£58,923</hi></cell><cell>over</cell></row>
<row><cell>those of the previous year.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Value of Imports over Exports</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">$83,959</hi></cell><cell></cell></row>
</table>

<pb n="60" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-28_Page_060.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">60</fw>

<table>
<row><cell>Which is set off by 100 vessels,</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>24,991 tons, the value of</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>which is about</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">£125,000</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Which leaves a balance in the</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>favor of the Colony of</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:right">£40,000</hi></cell></row>
</table>

<p>It is well enough for those to go into Confederation who<lb/>
have not been able to manage their own affairs ; but for<lb/>
us to do so in the prosperous state of our Revenue, would<lb/>
be but committing political suicide. Some of the delegates,<lb/>
however, inform as that we may obtain £250,000 to buy<lb/>
proprietary lands. There is nothing in the Report to this<lb/>
affect ; all that I see promised is interest for a certain<lb/>
sum. If the hon. member for St. Peters were in the <lb/>
General Legislature, and to rise and ask for a grant of <lb/>
£200,000 to purchase proprietors' lands, could he have<lb/>
the face to paint to a certain paragraph of the Report, and<lb/>
may I claim this sum as a constitutional right ? (Laughter.)<lb/>
But it might be said, he would have other four members<lb/>
to aid him in orging our rights. Our delegates, did they<lb/>
wish to secure our rights, had a much better opportunity<lb/>
tog ain their point at a conference of a few individuals<lb/>
than in a Hopse of 194 membes. Their first object ought<lb/>
to have been to get the settlement of our Land Question-<lb break="yes"/>the only question which is a grievance in the Colony, and<lb/>
then they might have come with some show of reason and<lb/>
asked as to go into Confederation. But they ask us to give<lb/>
up our constitution - for what ! simply the glory of<lb/>
belonging to a country with four millions of people !<lb/>
(Hear, hear.) I believe our people would prefer repre<lb break="no"/>sentation in the Imperial Parliament to Union with<lb/>
Canada, for though they might scarcely have one member<lb/>
in the British House of Commons, they would at least<lb/>
feel that their liberties were in the lands of people that<lb/>
could be trusted.<lb/></p> 

<p>The Debate was then adjourned.<lb/></p> 

<!-- DL 2018-06-06 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>WEDNESDAY, March 29.<lb/></p> 

<p>Debate on Union of Colonies resumed.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. LONGWORTH - Mr. Speaker. This question<lb/>
comes before us with a different aspect from that which it<lb/>
presented last Session. Last year the question of a Union<lb/>
of the Maritime Provinces was discussed on the sug<lb break="no"/>gestions of the Lieut. Governors of Nova Scotia and New<lb/>
Brunswick. An argument has been drawn from this, that<lb/>
it was wrong in the Island Government to send delegates<lb/>
to Canada without the previous consent of the Legislature.<lb/>
We thought it but right to follow the example of our<lb/>
sister Colonies in complying with the request of Lord<lb/>
Monok. The number of delegates who were appointed to<lb/>
the Conference which sat at Charlottetown was increased<lb/>
by the addition of the Hon Mr. Whelsh and the Hon<lb/>
Solicitor General. The Government had every confidence<lb/>
in the judgment and ability of the gentlemen whom they<lb/>
had appointed on the Canadian mission. Whatever<lb/>
might be the result of the Conference, the Government<lb/>
had expressed no opinion ; they left it an open question,<lb/>
andtherefore every member has a right to express his own<lb/>
opinion on it. It is not my intention to discuss the <lb/>
great principles involved, nor the various details set forth<lb/>
in the Report of the delegates as the result of their<lb/>
deliberations. In view of the thorough manner in which<lb/>
the subject has been handled in the press and at public<lb/>
meetings, it is unnecessary to encumber this debate with<lb/>
figures and calculations. The first consideration that<lb/>
occurs to my mind on the subject is the peculiar situation<lb/>
of the Island. We are an agricultural country, our<lb/>
fishers are but partially developed. Our insular position<lb/>
necessitates our entrance into the Union under circumstance less<lb/>
favorable than either Nova Scotia or New Brunswick. Canada<lb/>
has great resources, and her agricultural capabilities are un<lb break="no"/>bounded. Nature has united Canada and New Brunswick. It<lb/>
is impossible that we can participate in the advantages anticipated<lb/>
from the Union in proportion to the other Colonies ; therefore, in<lb/>
my opinion, the Conference at Quebec should have treated us as<lb/>

<cb/>

entitled to an exceptional statue in the Confederacy. I do not <lb/>
mean to say that under no circumstances would a Union be<lb/>
advisable, but we should have been placed upon a different<lb/>
and more favorable footing than the other Colonies. I agree that<lb/>
the Report is an able one, but many of its details will not bear<lb/>
scrutiny. As to the principle of representation by population ;<lb/>
although not objectionable under some circumstances, yet I do<lb/>
not approve its application in the present matter. The repre<lb break="no"/>sentation in the Lower House should have been on the British<lb/>
principle, while the example afforded by the United States<lb/>
Senate could have been advantageously followed in the con<lb break="no"/>stitution of the Upper Branch of the Legislature. When my hon.<lb/>
ad learned friend, the Hon. Solicitor General, says that the<lb/>
delegates from the Maritime Colonies exercised a controlling<lb/>
influence in the framing and adoption of the Report, it appears<lb/>
to be an admission that they were novel principles, principles not<lb/>
hither tested by the experience of any previous Confederation<lb/>
of which history makes mention. It shows me that it was a <lb/>
plan devised to meet some complications or the particular views<lb/>
of some parties. The Island representative to the Upper Branch<lb/>
would ahve some check which might avail to compensate for the<lb/>
wretched minority which we would be entitle to for the<lb/>
Lower House, where a presentation of 5 our of 194 might<lb/>
render it impolitic for our members of oppose a measure they<lb/>
disapproved of, lest they should not be permitted to carry any<lb/>
vote which they might wish. I cannot use any prospect of might<lb/>
for this Colony in a Legislature composed in such proportions.<lb/>
Canada could, at any moment, on vote as ; now is there any<lb/>
reason to suppose that Nova Scotia and New Brunswick would<lb/>
unite to save us. But Sir, looking at this question in £ pounds ;<lb/>
billings and pence, point of view, the scheme fails to commend<lb/>
itself to my judgment. What are the terms proposed ? We are<lb/>
to receive some £48,000 per annum in commutation of a revenue<lb/>
which has been increasing for the last fourteen years, until last<lb/>
ear it approximated to £86,000, and which it is but reasonable<lb/>
to suppose would continue to increase in the same way as it<lb/>
has manifested for th period to which I have referred. When<lb/>
it is asked of us that we should surrender our separate rights and <lb/>
submit to the terms which the proposed Confeders may impose<lb/>
upon us, do hon members realize the full extent of the concession<lb/>
involved ? We are requested to give up not merely the difference <lb/>
in amount of revenue to which I have referred, but matters of<lb/>
higher moment. We are required to yield up our position of<lb/>
comparative dependance as a separate Colony, and to reduce<lb/>
the scope of our legislative functions to the privileges of a local<lb/>
vestry in the Mother Country - the right of levying pariah taxes<lb/>
for local purposes. In reference to what hs been said on the <lb/>
subject of free trade with Canada and the benefits we would<lb/>
receive from it, I will take the liberty of confirming my views<lb/>
by extracting from the official statistics the returns of our com-<lb break="maybe"/>merical Intercourse with that country for a few years. From<lb/>
our Public Accounts it appears that the duty paid on Imports into<lb/>
P. E. Island from Canada in 1868, was, on<lb/></p> 

<p>Ale and Porter - £9 8 9 <lb/>
Soap - 2 3 2<lb/>
Leather - 1 13 7 1/2<lb/>
Miscellaneous - 15 9 <lb/>
Toabacco* - 43 13 6<lb/>
Wines* - 12 17 7<lb/>
Tea* - 8 14 7 1/2<lb/>
Salt* - 7 17 8<lb/>
Molasses* - 2 3 6 <lb/>
Total £89 7 10<lb/></p> 

<p>Those marked thus * (evidently not <lb/>
the productions of Canada; paid<lb/>
in duty - 75 6 6<lb/></p> 

<p>Leaving for Ale and Porter, Soap, <lb/>
&amp; e. the supposed produce of <lb/>
Canada - £ 14 1 4<lb/></p> 

<p>In 1860, 1861, and 1862 theh duty on Imports into P.E. Island<lb/>
from Canada, amounting to the aggregate value of £15 15s, 9d<lb/>
was only £4 5s 6d for the three years, or £1 8e 6d a year ! ! !<lb/>
yAnother and most important consideration is the position in<lb/>
which we, under Confederation, will be placed with reference to<lb/>
our obligations to contribute to the defence of Canada. We have<lb/>
been told that an army and navy must be organised for the pro<lb break="no"/>action of that country, for the local defence of which, in the<lb break="no"/> </p> -->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>