<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-04-07"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>


<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-04-07">7 April 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1870, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1870"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="187"/>
<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="203"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>

<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_186.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_190.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_192.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_194.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_196.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_198.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_200.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_202.hocr.html"/>
</item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-17">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_186">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_186.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_190">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_190.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_192">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_192.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_194">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_194.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_196">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_196.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_198">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_198.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_200">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_200.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_202">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_202.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>
<div type="debate">

<pb n="187" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_186.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">187</fw>   

<p>[..]</p>
 
<p rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, April 7.</p>

<p>[..]</p>

<cb/>

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="191" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_190.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">191</fw>

<p>[..]</p>
 
<p rendition="simple:centre"><hi rendition="simple:bold">Confederation.</hi><lb/></p> 

<p>House resumed further consideration <lb/>
of Despatches. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:KICK1">Mr. KICKHAM</persName>, hoped hon. gentlemen <lb/>
would recollect that they came here to do <lb/>
the business of the country, and he was <lb/>
of opinion it would be better to do so, <lb/>
without indulging in arguments which <lb/>
had a tendency to hinder, rather than <lb/>
promoted, that end. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> endorsed the sound ad<lb break="no"/>vice of the hon. member for Souris, but <lb/>
must remind his hon. friend, that it <lb/>
was well also for the country to know <lb/>
the true position of its public men. The <lb/>

<cb/> 

hon. member for Wilmot Creek, made <lb/>
an attack upon him the other night, and <lb/>
he (Mr. B.) was surprised and sorry the <lb/>
hon. member did so; but as he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
had been assaulted, it was his duty to <lb/>
reply. In doing so, however, he would <lb/>
endeavor to profit by the warning given <lb/>
by the hon. member (Mr. B.). Yet it <lb/>
would be necessary that he should reply <lb/>
to some extent in the spirit in which he <lb/>
had been addressed. He (Mr. B.) was <lb/>
replying to what the hon. member for <lb/>
Wilmot Creek had said on a former <lb/>
occasion, and, in doing so, referred to <lb/>
what the Premier of the Island had <lb/>
recently said at a public meeting, and <lb/>
did so to show that the Hon. Mr. <lb/>
Haythorne and he (mr. B.) had said he believed <lb/>
there were terms which he could accept, <lb/>
and that was precisely what he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
had also said; and for that simply and <lb/>
plain assertion he had been charged with <lb/>
presumption by the hon. member (Mr. <lb/>
Laird.) For the Hon. Mr. Haythorne he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) had as much regard as the hon <lb/>
member for Wilmot Creek; nor was he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) aware that in anything he had <lb/>
said he had treated that gentleman with <lb/>
the slightest disrespect. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber (Mr. L.) had charged him (Mr. B.) <lb/>
with acting discourteously towards the <lb/>
Premier, and had also called him (Mr. <lb/>
B.) a political threshing machine, and he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) had called him (Mr. L.) the <lb/>
silver-tongued ponderous, political phi<lb break="no"/>losopher of Wilmot Creek; yet, in both <lb/>
of these instances, neither had gone <lb/>
further than was politically proper and <lb/>
quite parliamentary, and if the hon. <lb/>
member would but consult the words <lb/>
and history of the Imperial Parliament, <lb/>
he would find that Mr. Disraeili and <lb/>
others had need even stronger expres<lb break="no"/>sions, and not unfrequently referred to <lb/>
members in the House of Londs, but no <lb/>
hon member in the House of Commons <lb/>
would ever think of charging an hon <lb/>
member with presumptions or discourtesy <lb/>
for doing so. If the Hon. Mr. Haythorne <lb/>
was not here, the fault was not his (Mr. <lb/>
B's;) and to say that because he was not in <lb/>
this House no reference was to be made <lb/>
to his public utterances, was too absurdly <lb/>
ridiculous to be for one moment enter<lb break="no"/>tained by an intelligent mind. If the <lb/>
hon member (Mr. L.) would recall to his <lb/>
recollection how Lord Derby was treated <lb/>
in the House of Commons, and what the <lb/>
true parliamentary practice was, he <lb/>

<pb n="192" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_192.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">192</fw> 

right in the course he pursued ; and be<lb break="no"/>fore the hon member made the attack <lb/>
upon him (Mr. B.) which he did, he <lb/>
should have remembered that no man <lb/>
should bear false witness against his <lb/>
neighbor. He (Mr. B.) had said Mr. <lb/>
Haythorne was a no-terms man, but that <lb/>
he had faith in him that he would not <lb/>
vote the colony into confederation with<lb break="no"/>out the consent of the people ; and in that <lb/>
respect he aw eye to eye with him (Mr. <lb/>
B.) and would appeal to the chairman, <lb/>
who knew that Parliamentary practice <lb/>
was, to say whether he, in what he said, <lb/>
had uttered anything that was disre<lb break="no"/>spectful to Hon. Mr. Haythorne. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:KELL1">Hon. Mr. KELLY</persName> said the hon member <lb/>
(Mr. B.) simply referred to Mr. Hay<lb break="no"/>thorne's speech, which he delivered at <lb/>
the Ten Mile House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.— With this explanation <lb/>
he would leave the hon member from <lb/>
Wilmot Creek to reconcile his assertion <lb/>
with that which was correct. He (Mr. <lb/>
B.) had read extracts from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> <lb/>
newspaper, and knew the hon member <lb/>
(Mr. Reilly) could not find that he (Mr. <lb/>
B.) had misquoted a single word. The <lb/>
Queen's Priter said the other night <lb/>
that he had never directly or indirectly <lb/>
advocated confederation, and had been <lb/>
forward enough to challenge proof to the <lb/>
contrary ; but he (Mr. B.) held a paper in <lb/>
his hand, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Ottawa Citizen</hi>, which in a <lb/>
leading article, reviewed several of the <lb/>
papers published in this Island—yes, the <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Citizen</hi> was published a the capital of <lb/>
the Dominion—at the place from whence <lb/>
the political swells and pedlers came who <lb/>
visited them last year. That paper—and <lb/>
no doubt those political swells and <lb/>
pedlers also—believed the ability of the <lb/>
Queen's Printer was doing its work in <lb/>
favor of confederation on this Island, <lb/>
and looked upon him as a co-worker. <lb/>
In the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Citizen</hi> of the 22d Jan. last, the <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> was thus referred to:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"We alluded briefly yesterday to the opinions <lb/>
of the Prince Edward Island papers on the <lb/>
terms proposed by the Dominion Government. <lb/>
To this it may be replied that it will make very <lb/>
little difference to the people who pays the <lb/>
money, so long as they get rid of the incubus of <lb/>
absentee proprietors." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>He (Mr. B.) did not know who the editor <lb/>
of that paper was ; but whoever he might <lb/>
be, the hon member for St. Peter's would <lb/>
have to demolish that writer before he <lb/>
could demolish him (Mr. B. Now, if <lb/>
confederation was to ruin this Island, the <lb/>
Queen's Printer was doing much towards <lb/>
it ; and when he compared what appeared. <lb/>

<cb/>
 

in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> with the speech of the hon <lb/>
member (Mr. Reilly) made the other <lb/>
night, when he said he was a Grattan— <lb/>
that no money could purchase him. That <lb/>
an impartial observer would draw such <lb/>
an inference, was what he doubted. The <lb/>
hon member from Wilmot Creek said <lb/>
Mr. Haythorne asked for a railroad, as if <lb/>
such a paltry consideration was all that <lb/>
should be considered—as if there was <lb/>
not a principle involved of more import<lb break="no"/>ance. Before the hon member made that <lb/>
statement, he should have refreshed his <lb/>
memory by recalling to his recollection <lb/>
what he said at the public meeting which <lb/>
was held at Summerside early in January <lb/>
last, when he agreed with all the Hon. <lb/>
James Pope said at the meeting, except <lb/>
in that gentleman's opposition to the <lb/>
government. In all Mr. Pope said on <lb/>
confederation he coincided ; at least he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) was so informed, and he be<lb break="no"/>lieved correctly. Then nothing was said <lb/>
about the better terms. When public <lb/>
men thus acted, it was proper the country <lb/>
should know their real position, and he <lb/>
would say to the hon member (Mr. <lb/>
Kickham) that it was doing the business <lb/>
of the country thus to make known the <lb/>
principles of a member of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Did the hon member (Mr. Laird) <lb/>
not know he was playing the part of a <lb/>
political hypocrite? He (Mr. B.) had <lb/>
been told that he was sorry when his <lb/>
hon colleague, Dr. Jenkins, was returned <lb/>
to this House ; but it should be recol<lb break="no"/>lected that when Dr. Jenkins was re<lb break="no"/>turned, it was not because he had come <lb/>
out as a liberal, and as such had been <lb/>
returned ; but he (Mr. B.) represented <lb/>
the most important constituency in <lb/>
Prince Edward Island ; nor had he done <lb/>
anything for which, as their representa<lb break="no"/>tive, he could not assign to them a satis<lb break="no"/>factory reason. He was not a member <lb/>
or supporter of the government, and <lb/>
therefore was not responsible for any of <lb/>
its acts. But the hon member (Mr. <lb/>
Laird) had been returned as a moderate <lb/>
conservative, and it was understood that <lb/>
he was to work in concert with a gentle<lb break="no"/>man in the other end of the building ; <lb/>
instead, however, of his doing so, he had <lb/>
co-operate and acted in concert with <lb/>
the Queen's Printer ; but last night, in<lb break="no"/>stead of defending the hon member for <lb/>
St. Peter's (Mr. Reilly), he took the hon <lb/>
Mr. Haythorne under his protection. <lb/>
When the hon member returned to his <lb/>

<pb n="193" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_192.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">193</fw> 

constituents at Bedeque, he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
thought he would find that they would <lb/>
not thank him for the course he had <lb/>
adopted. He (Mr. B.) had called some <lb/>
persons political, or literary owls. When <lb/>
he spoke he had no one particular gen<lb break="no"/>tleman in his mind ; be he found that <lb/>
there were three or four who were so <lb/>
tickled with the name that they would <lb/>
hardly speak to him since, when they met <lb/>
him on the street ; and it appeared they <lb/>
were contending among themselves as to <lb/>
which of them should have the honor of <lb/>
being first put into the cage along with <lb/>
those stuffed birds! But whether the <lb/>
one best entitled to be placed in the lobby <lb/>
among the stuffed owls was yet in the <lb/>
cage he did not know, but supposed the <lb/>
right man would aspire to the honor, <lb/>
although he (Mr. B.) was up to this time <lb/>
ignorant of who the aspirant was. <lb/>
(Laughter.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName> said the hon and <lb/>
learned member for Charlottetown (Mr. <lb/>
B.) considered that he (Mr. L.) had done <lb/>
him an injustice when he thought he <lb/>
should not have compared himself with <lb/>
the hon Mr. Haythorne; but what he <lb/>
(Mr. L) complained mostly of was that <lb/>
the hon member did not quote Mr. <lb/>
Haythorne's speech correctly. Had he <lb/>
done so he would have found that the <lb/>
hon gentleman's speech would not have <lb/>
borne the construction he had put upon <lb/>
it. Int hat speech there was not one <lb/>
word about a railroad, and if the hon <lb/>
member had taken a fair view of it, he <lb/>
could not have construed it as he did, <lb/>
and he (Mr. L.) felt that he acted per<lb break="no"/>fectly right in defending a gentleman <lb/>
who was not present, and who, if he were, <lb/>
could not defend himself ; but in what <lb/>
he said he meant nothing personal, nor <lb/>
did he intend that his remarks should be <lb/>
other than politically understood. But <lb/>
the hon member (Mr. B.) charged him <lb/>
(Mr. L.) with acting an inconsistent part <lb/>
at a public meeting at Summerside, but <lb/>
did so on the authority of hearsay. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—It was published in <lb/>
one of the papers. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>.—The hon member <lb/>
had charged him (Mr. L.) with acting <lb/>
the part of a political hypocrite, by say<lb break="no"/>ing that he (Mr. L.) had been returned <lb/>
as a moderate conservative, and supposed <lb/>
he got his information from the powder <lb/>
monkeys which supplied the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber with ammunition. He, Mr. Laird, <lb/>
believed that all his public acts would <lb/>
be found to be in accordance with the <lb/>

<cb/> 

promises which he had made to his con<lb break="no"/>stituents before he was returned to that <lb/>
House. He hoped the hon member (Mr. <lb/>
B.) would be able to show as clean a <lb/>
record, as he (Mr. L) could. With re<lb break="no"/>spect to the meeting at Summerside, <lb/>
what he (Mr. L) said was, that the <lb/>
views of the government would be made <lb/>
known at the proper time. And, having <lb/>
said so, shortly after returning from a <lb/>
meeting of Council, and knowing the <lb/>
views of the government, it was not <lb/>
likely he would have made a statement <lb/>
which would have been at variance <lb/>
therewith. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName>.—The hon. member for <lb/>
Charlottetown, (Mr. BRECKEN) had mis<lb break="no"/>represented him last night, by reading <lb/>
short extracts from articles in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi>, <lb/>
which, without the context, were made <lb/>
to appear as if favoring confederation. <lb/>
The committee would be surprised to <lb/>
learn that some of the extracts were <lb/>
taken from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi>, as far back as <lb/>
the year 1866. The first article from <lb/>
which he quoted was from the No. of <lb/>
October 17, 1866. He (Mr. R.) would <lb/>
reaed the whole article, as it was not <lb/>
very lengthy, to show that when ot <lb/>
garbled, it did not afford much comfort <lb/>
to the hon, member for the city. [The <lb/>
parts in the following quotations, marked <lb/>
in italics, are those read by Mr. Brecken.] <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"We have hear it rumored about that <lb/>
the Legislature is to be called forthwith, <lb/>
to submit a proposition from Her Majesty's <lb/>
Colonial Minister concerning Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. It is hinted that a sum of £250,000 <lb/>
cy., will be placed at the disposal of the <lb/>
Colony by the Confederate Government as <lb/>
the price of surrendering its independence. <lb/>
We do not know what truth there may be <lb/>
in this rumor, but should there be any <lb/>
foundation for it, and the proposition be <lb/>
submitted to the people for their considera<lb break="no"/>tion, it will, no doubt, be thoroughly can<lb break="no"/>vassed before being accepted." <lb/></p></quote> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Since writing the foregoing, we learn <lb/>
from reliable sources that the rumor con<lb break="no"/>tained therein is substantially correct, and <lb/>
that the Legislature will be convened im<lb break="no"/>mediately to consider this important pro<lb break="no"/>position. Before, however, any decisive <lb/>
action is taken by the Legislature, we trust <lb/>
the matter will be submitted to the people <lb/>
at the polls for their decision. As they <lb/>
are most immediately interested, and will <lb/>

<pb n="194" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_194.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">194</fw>  

have the power to decide it. A dissolution <lb/>
of the Legislature upon the Despatch em<lb break="no"/>bodying the proposition which was received <lb/>
by the last English mail, should be the <lb/>
first step taken by His Excellency the <lb/>
Lieutenant Governor and his advisers, as <lb/>
the people's rights and liberties are too <lb/>
sacred and important to be 1egislated away <lb/>
by a few men whose tenure of office is on <lb/>
the eve of expiring, We have sufficient <lb/>
confidence, however, in a majority of the <lb/>
Legislature that they will do nothing rash<lb break="no"/>ly, and, above all, that they will abstain <lb/>
from following in the footsteps of the Le<lb break="no"/>gislature of Nova Scotia, by appointing <lb/>
Delegates with unlimited powers to change <lb/>
the constitution of the country without the <lb/>
consent of the people. When the proposi<lb break="no"/>tion comes to be placed officially before the <lb/>
public, as we presume it will be in this <lb/>
week's <hi rendition="simple:italic">Royal Gazette</hi>, we shall be better <lb/>
prepared to offer an opinion upon it. In <lb/>
the meantime, we think the anti-Confeder<lb break="no"/>ates have reason to congratulate themselves <lb/>
upon their opposition to the Quebec <lb/>
Scheme, for had they adopted the advice of <lb/>
Messrs. Gray, Pope, Whelan Haviland and <lb/>
Green, this offer never would have been <lb/>
made to the Colony. These gentlemen <lb/>
having, by their votes, declared the Quebec <lb/>
Scheme to be just and equitable, and even <lb/>
liberal, to Prince Edward Island, ought— <lb/>
to be consistent—to oppose this new basis <lb/>
of Confederation ; but whatever consistency <lb/>
may require of them, we have no doubt <lb/>
they will be the noisiest in their exultations <lb/>
over the Colonial Minister's despatch. <hi rendition="simple:italic">At <lb/>
all events, we think the time has now <lb/>
arrived when this Colony must state the <lb/>
terms upon which it will consent to enter <lb/>
the proposed Confederacy. The British <lb/>
Government is apparently determined <lb/>
upon the scheme, for reasons that Mr. <lb/>
Howe's able pamphlet has rendered too <lb/>
obvious, and it may be better for us to <lb/>
make the best terms we can now, whilst a <lb/>
gentleman is in the Colonial Office who is <lb/>
friendly to the Provinces, and who is <lb/>
desirous of seeming to this Island the <lb/>
very best terms that can possibly be ob<lb break="no"/>tained</hi>. We know not how soon a change <lb/>
of Ministry may take place in England ; <lb/>
and of this fact we may rest assured, that <lb/>
with the return of Mr. Cardwell to the <lb/>
Colonial office, the danger of being forced <lb/>
into Confederation—terms or no terms— <lb/>
—is increased a hundred fold. In offering <lb/>
these remarks, however we by no means <lb/>
think that £250,000 would sufficiently gild <lb/>
the Quebec pill to make it palatable to this <lb/>
Colony—and, indeed, to confess the honest <lb/>
truth, we have our own suspicions that the <lb/>

<cb/> 

whole circumstances connected with the <lb/>
bribe now held out, and which is equivalent <lb/>
to about £3 per head of the population—a, <lb/>
sum infinitely less than woul be a nigger <lb/>
—is a cunningly devised plan of the Con<lb break="no"/>federates to rear a platform for themselves <lb/>
in view of the coming elections— in fact, a <lb/>
mere electioneering dodge to delude and <lb/>
betray the people ; but before proceeding <lb/>
to state what we think would prove fair <lb/>
and equitable terms—that is, if Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion is inevitable—we shall await the <lb/>
publication of Lord Carnarvon's recent <lb/>
despatch upon the subject." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>That was one of the articles from which <lb/>
the hon. member quoted ; he (MR. R.) <lb/>
would now read another, and let the <lb/>
country judge whether or not he had <lb/>
changed his opinions on confederation. <lb/>
The No. of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> in which the <lb/>
following appeared, was October 31, of <lb/>
the same year :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Although the Legislature has neither <lb/>
been called together nor dissolved, nor yet <lb/>
the despatch of the Colonial Secretary con<lb break="no"/>taining the offer of the Nova Scotia and <lb/>
New Brunswick delegates published, it is <lb/>
understood that both an early call and dis<lb break="no"/>solution of the Legislature upon: that <lb/>
despatch, will take place. We must con<lb break="no"/>fess that we do not like the secrecy which <lb/>
the Government maintains about the matter. <lb/>
We know it is said that the want of Can<lb break="no"/>ada's cause to the proposed arrangement <lb/>
is the cause of the non-publication of the <lb/>
Colonial Secretary's despatch ; but the <lb/>
want of that consent should also have pre<lb break="no"/>vented this Government from taking any <lb/>
action in reference thereto. The reason <lb/>
assigned is no reason at all why the de<lb break="no"/>spatch should not be published for the <lb/>
information of the people ; and if the <lb/>
friends of the recent proposition of the <lb/>
Colonial delegates do not wish to be over<lb break="no"/>whelmed with defeat, as the Quebec dele<lb break="no"/>gates were in 1864, they will immediately <lb/>
abandon that secrecy and shuffling which <lb/>
characterized the birth of the Quebec <lb/>
Scheme. Whether right or wrong, people <lb/>
naturally look with suspicion upon a benefit <lb/>
which is shrouded in mystery ; and it is <lb/>
folly to .suppose that a majority of any <lb/>
community is unable to decide what is for <lb/>
its own benefit. If the $800,000 free grant <lb/>
be what its friends represent it—a bona <lb/>
fide "gift"—they need have no hesitation <lb/>
in placing it before the public ; but if it be <lb/>
a mere gilded and delusive bait, captivating <lb/>
to the sight, but fatal to the touch, an <lb/>
intended, upon the eve of an election, to <lb/> 

<pb n="195" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_194.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">195</fw>

entrap the tenants and the colony at large <lb/>
into Confederation, its authors may live to <lb/>
repent their conduct. Should individual <lb/>
members of the Legislature be tampered <lb/>
with, we sincerely trust they will have <lb/>
sufficient independence, as they value <lb/>
honesty and a good name and detest treach<lb break="no"/>ery, to refuse their assent to the sending of <lb/>
a delegation to England until after an elec<lb break="no"/>tion, when the people can have an oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of pronouncing an opinion upon this <lb/>
question of $800,000. <hi rendition="simple:italic">While we speak <lb/>
thus against deception, we have no doubt <lb/>
that the guarantee of the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and a clause in the articles of <lb/>
Confederation, to the effect that the <lb/>
money would be immediately handed <lb/>
over to this Government when the Colony <lb/>
expressed its willingness to join the Con<lb break="no"/>federacy, would find many advocates <lb/>
and friends who had previously opposed <lb/>
the Quebec basis</hi>. Our own candid opinion, <lb/>
however, is, that under present circum<lb break="no"/>stances, even if this Colony were to accept <lb/>
the "free gift" or " bribe," it is extremely <lb/>
doubtful whether the Imperial Government <lb/>
or Legislature will sanction the Scheme of <lb/>
Confederation at all. The Hon. Mr. Howe <lb/>
has succeeded most effectually in arousing <lb/>
the British public to a sense of the import <lb/>
ance of the subject of Confederation, both <lb/>
in its relations to the Empire and to the <lb/>
Colonies themselves. The Hons. Mssrs. <lb/>
Tupper and McCully have attempted in <lb/>
vain to counteract Mr. Howe's influence, <lb/>
and since both parties have repaired to the <lb/>
press to fight the question out, we have <lb/>
sufficient confidence in Mr. Howe's ability <lb/>
to predict a sound thrashing for Dr. Tupper <lb/>
and his co-laborers. Many of the leading <lb/>
English journals which had previously pro<lb break="no"/>nounced in favor of the Quebec Scheme, <lb/>
now take the opposite view, and candidly <lb/>
admit, after a perusal of Mr. Howe's <lb/>
pamphlet, that they had been in error. <lb/>
Even the Colonial Secretary, whom the <lb/>
Confederate delegates sought to commit to <lb/>
Confederation, ominously abstained from <lb/>
saying one word in favor of the measure. <lb/>
From all these circumstances, we come to <lb/>
the conclusion that the whole Scheme of <lb/>
Confederation is in a fair way of ending in <lb/>
smoke ; and, therefore, even if the free <lb/>
gift is a <hi rendition="simple:italic">bona fide</hi> affair, and not a <hi rendition="simple:italic">substi<lb break="no"/>tute</hi> for the financial arrangement of the <lb/>
Quebec Scheme, as Dr. Tupper's organ <lb/>
asserts it is, its acceptance by this colony <lb/>
might turn out to be a very useless pro<lb break="no"/>ceeding,—as foolish as it was premature. <lb/>
We hope before our next issue to have <lb/>
something official before us upon which to <lb/>
comment, as at present both the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Examiner</hi> <lb/>

<cb/> 

and <hi rendition="simple:italic">Islander</hi>, as well as the anti-Confed<lb break="no"/>erate papers, are groping in the dark,—a <lb/>
state of things which the Government, <lb/>
being now committed to Confederation, <lb/>
seems to court, and for which it alone is <lb/>
responsible. <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>If there was anything in that article, <lb/>
favoring confederation, he (Mr R.) was <lb/>
prepared to stand by it. The next article <lb/>
from which the hon. member for the <lb/>
city quoted, was in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> of Nov. <lb/>
14, 1866 :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Islander</hi> and the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Royal Gazette</hi>, of <lb/>
last week at length contain the bogus pro<lb break="no"/>position of the delegates, together with the <lb/>
despatches and correspondence thereon, <lb/>
and the upshot of the matter is, that the <lb/>
Canadians repudiate the preposition. The <lb/>
Colonial Secretary, in transmitting the <lb/>
offer to Viscount Monck, concludes his <lb/>
despatch in the following cautious, non<lb break="no"/>commital style ;— <lb/></p> 

<p>"'I have taken this course in order give <lb/>
effect to the wishes of the Delegates now in <lb/>
England ; but it must be understood that I do <lb/>
so without expressing any opinion of my own <lb/>
on the subjec, as this would be premature at <lb/>
the present stage of the question.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"The Colonial Secretary cannot fail to <lb/>
meet the warm approbation of the people <lb/>
of the Maritime Provinces by his judicious <lb/>
and statesmanlike dealing with the question <lb/>
of Confederation. The contrast between <lb/>
him and his bungling predecessor is as <lb/>
great as is the estimate in which both are <lb/>
held in the Provinces. As much curiosity <lb/>
doubtlessly exists to know the real nature <lb/>
of the offer of the Maritime Province Dele<lb break="no"/>gates, we give it in full :— <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">(COPY.)<lb/></p> 

<p>At a meeting of the Delegates from Nova <lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick, held at the Alex<lb break="no"/>andra Hotel, London, on the 22nd day of <lb/>
September, 1866, all being present except the <lb/>
Hon. Mr. Wilmot, it was unanimously resolved <lb/>
that, inasmuch as the co-operation of Prince <lb/>
Edward Island, though not indispensable to a <lb/>
union of the other British North American <lb/>
Provinces, is on many accounts, very desir<lb break="no"/>able ; and as the settlement of the land question, <lb/>
which has so long and so injuriously agitated <lb/>
that colony, would be attended with great <lb/>
benefit, and at the same time place the local <lb/>
Government of the Island, by the possession of <lb/>
the proprietary lands, now on a footing with <lb/>
the other Provinces, which have crown lands <lb/>
and minerals as a source of local revenue. <lb/>
Therefore Resolved— <lb/></p> 

<p>That, in case the Legislature of the Island <lb/>
should authorize the appointment of Delegates <lb/>
to act in conjunction with those from the other <lb/>
Provinces, in arranging a plan of co-operation, <lb/>
prior to the meeting of the Imperial Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, the delegates from Nova Scotia and New <lb/>

<pb n="196" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_196.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">196</fw> 

Brunswick are hereby pledged to support the <lb/>
policy of providing such an amount as may be <lb/>
necessary for the purchase of the proprietary <lb/>
rights, but not to exceed $800,000. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:right">(Signed) CHARLES TUPPER<lb/></p>
<p rendition="simple:right">S.L. TILLEY.<lb/></p> 

<p>"The Canadian Government, after dis<lb break="no"/>cussing the proposition, state that they 'do <lb/>
not consider that they have any power or <lb/>
right to consent to the payment of that, or <lb/>
any sum, without the previous consent of <lb/>
the Canadian Parliament; and they, there<lb break="no"/>fore, cannot confer upon their delegates <lb/>
powers which they do not themselves <lb/>
possess.' Individually, however, they are <lb/>
prepared to make 'a strong representation <lb/>
to the first Government and Parliament of <lb/>
the United Provinces, in favor of their <lb/>
granting the compensation agreed upon' by <lb/>
the Delegates. This conclusion proves <lb/>
what we asserted all along, that the Quebec <lb/>
scheme is unalterable. We are glad that <lb/>
the Canadians have squarely met the pro<lb break="no"/>position by a direct refusal, for Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's Government will now plainly see <lb/>
that Prince Edward Island has good reason <lb/>
for declining to enter the Confederacy. <lb/>
When her reasonable demands are met <lb/>
with denial previous to union, her chances <lb/>
of obtaining justice afterwards are slim <lb/>
indeed. The Canadian Government, more, <lb/>
we fancy, for the purpose of humbugging <lb/>
than for remedying the evil, admit that a <lb/>
grant of $800,000 over and above what is <lb/>
allowed by the Quebec scheme, is nothing <lb/>
but just and fair to this Colony, from its <lb/>
insular position and land difficulty. <hi rendition="simple:italic">We <lb/>
have no hesitation in expressing our be<lb break="no"/>lief that if the offer were assented to by <lb/>
Canada and the money tendered to this <lb/>
Island as the price of its adhesion to <lb/>
Confederation, a majority might be <lb/>
found to accept it</hi>; and should Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's Government be anxious for all these <lb/>
Provinces to form themselves into a Con<lb break="no"/>federacy, we have no doubt the $800,00, <lb/>
and even a larger sum, will yet be offered <lb/>
to smooth the difficulties in the way of an <lb/>
harmonious union. We have no fear that <lb/>
the expectation of the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, as shadowed forth by one of its <lb/>
organs-the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Leader</hi>-from which we quoted <lb/>
last week, when it says that, without the <lb/>
$800,000, Prince Edward Island will soon <lb/>
be drawn into the Union 'in spite of her<lb break="no"/>self,' will ever be realized. The political <lb/>
axiom which the Leader seeks to establish <lb/>
from physical science is rather a dangerous <lb/>
experiment; for if it be true that the at<lb break="no"/>traction of the greater body is more than a <lb/>
match for the power of resistance of the <lb/>
smaller body, then we must admit that <lb/>

<cb/> 

annexation is inevitable. 'It is a queer <lb/>
rule that won't work both ways.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"It is amusing to observe the effect which <lb/>
the dissent of Canada has upon the editor <lb/>
of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Islander</hi>. His lower jaw hangs <lb/>
down at once, and in the most savage <lb/>
mood he snaps and bites in all directions. <lb/>
No wonder; for he has worked himself out <lb/>
of office,- he has played his last trump and <lb/>
lost; but if he imagines he is going to im<lb break="no"/>prove his condition by slanderous and ill-<lb break="yes"/>natured remarks, he is very much mistaken. <lb/>
He asserts that the recent offer could not <lb/>
bribe this Island. Let him be consoled; <lb/>
for we again repeat our belief that if Her <lb/>
Majesty's Government desires this Colony <lb/>
to unite with her sister PRovinces, and as <lb/>
a compensation for her exceptional position, <lb/>
guarantees good terms, the proposition <lb/>
will be received be a majority of its inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants. After indulging in some gloomy <lb/>
apprehensions that no delegation will be <lb/>
sent from this Colony to the London Con<lb break="no"/>ference, and treating us to a homily upon <lb/>
loyalty, the editor of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Islander</hi>, some<lb break="no"/>what after the fashion of 'Lord Lovell,' <lb/>
gives three kicks, a groan, then blows his <lb/>
nose, and gives up the ghost in the follow<lb break="no"/>ing manner: <lb/></p> 

<p>"'We feel that we have discharged our duty <lb/>
to the people- that we have fairly placed the <lb/>
subject before them, and we shall henceforth <lb/>
refrain from the advocacy of a measure which, <lb/>
notwithstanding its importance, is regarded by <lb/>
the mass of the people as one which would <lb/>
render them and their children slaves to <lb/>
Canada.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"This confession and resolution of <lb/>
amendment is like that of a culprit detected <lb/>
in the act of perpetrating some crime, and, <lb/>
if allowed to escape, immediately pursues <lb/>
his former evil courses. All the Confeder<lb break="no"/>ates, now that their schemes are detected, <lb/>
and that a general election is at hand, are <lb/>
prepared to pledge themselves to abandon <lb/>
their pet measure; but how long does the <lb/>
simple reader imagine are they going to <lb/>
adhere to such pledges? Just until after <lb/>
they secure their election; and it therefore <lb/>
behooves the people to select wisely those <lb/>
whom they shall return to Parliament as <lb/>
their representatives. The necessity is <lb/>
greater now than at any time formerly to <lb/>
elect men who are honestly opposed to <lb/>
Confederation, for we believe that if <lb/>
Canada, Nova Scotia and New Brunswick <lb/>
consent to unite, the Confederate Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will be so mean as to attempt, by <lb/>
annoying and hostile legislation, to coerce <lb/>
this Colony into Confederation; and, there<lb break="no"/>fore, those who will be at the head of <lb/>
affairs require to be men who will thwart <lb/> 

<pb n="197" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_196.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">197</fw> 

such legislation, instead of coinciding in it <lb/>
as was done by the existing Government in <lb/>
the case of surrendering the Fisheries, and <lb/>
taxing American flour. Whatever turn the <lb/>
political wheel may take, we trust Messrs, <lb/>
Palmer, Coles, and those other tried men <lb/>
who have stood by their country in time of <lb/>
trial and danger, will not be overlooked or <lb/>
forgotten. They deserve well of their <lb/>
country, and their country should not be <lb/>
slow to recognize their services." <lb/></p> 

<p>He (M. R.) had one comment to make on <lb/>
this article. It was written before the last <lb/>
election, and if his constituents thought <lb/>
it contained confederate sentiments, why <lb/>
did they return him as an anti-confed<lb break="no"/>erate? No, he had been consistent all <lb/>
through the piece, and that was the <lb/>
reason the hon member for Charlottetown <lb/>
was so much annoyed. He (Mr. R.) <lb/>
was pleased to think he had written so <lb/>
good articles, for those which he had <lb/>
read were all written by himself; and it <lb/>
was no little gratification to tind that the <lb/>
Ottawa <hi rendition="simple:italic">Citizen</hi> had spoken so compli<lb break="no"/>mentary of him. He would not read <lb/>
an article from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> of the 12th of <lb/>
January last. This one he did not write <lb/>
himself, but he would endorse its senti<lb break="no"/>ments:- <lb/> </p> 

<p>"Lord Granville, we observe, advises <lb/>
the Government of the Dominion 'to <lb/>
deal liberally as well as justly with the <lb/>
Island.' This advice seems to us un<lb break="no"/>necessary and uncalled for. We believe <lb/>
it has been very generally understood <lb/>
for some time past, that the Dominion <lb/>
Government was prepared to renew the <lb/>
offer made, without authority, by the <lb/>
Maritime Delegates in 1867, and we <lb/>
think, for a country just starting into <lb/>
national life, that offer was remarkable <lb/>
for its liberality. His Lordship seems <lb/>
to have forgotten the retort which has <lb/>
become proverbial, and is applied to <lb/>
those who advise generosity at the ex<lb break="no"/>pense of others when they ought to <lb/>
practice it themselves. Prince Edward <lb/>
Island has no cause of complaint against <lb/>
Canada. 'Why then should the latter <lb/>
embarrass herself by adopting a system <lb/>
opposed to the principle of the North <lb/>
American Act, wherein the fiscal rela<lb break="no"/>tions of the Confederated Provinces <lb/>
twoards each other are defined; why <lb/>
compromise the future independence of <lb/>
Prince Edward Island, if she should <lb/>
ever enter the union? Why adopt the <lb/>

<cb/>

ready and easy expedient of reconciling <lb/>
difficulties by payment of money, rather <lb/>
than the bolder and more manly course <lb/>
of identifying the Island's grievances as <lb/>
her own, and demanding that Great <lb/>
Britain, which has maintained [illegible] <lb/>
of wrong in this Colony, should now <lb/>
place it in a position to [illegible] a <lb/>
union with the Dominion on equal <lb/>
terms? There are Irishmen amongst <lb/>
us,- a few perhaps, who remember the <lb/>
early years of the union of their country <lb/>
with England- there are Englishment <lb/>
and Scotchmen, as well as Irishmen, <lb/>
who have read and noted the history of <lb/>
passing events in that unhappy country. <lb/>
We ask them to remember that Ireland <lb/>
waited for Catholic Emancipation till 28 <lb/>
years had elapsed after the union; that <lb/>
the richly endowed State Church of a <lb/>
small minority was maintained during <lb/>
70 years, and that to this day her land <lb/>
tenures remain unsettled, and we advice <lb/>
them, and our fellow colonist of all <lb/>
races, to adopt this as their leading <lb/>
principle on the confederation question. <lb/>
An absolute and immediate settlement <lb/>
of the land tenure <hi rendition="simple:italic">first</hi>, with adequate <lb/>
compensation from Britain for the loss <lb/>
of territorial revenues. Compensation <lb/>
means indemnity for the past as well as <lb/>
the present, and would enable the Local <lb/>
Government to invest the proceeds of <lb/>
the land sales, as other Colonies have <lb/>
done, in carrying out local improve<lb break="no"/>ments, and rendering the country, at <lb/>
this late period of its history, what it <lb/>
might have been years ago, if the pro<lb break="no"/>prietary [illegible] tree had not been planted <lb/>
in its soil. Full and just indemnity <lb/>
would place the local Legislature in a <lb/>
position to review the cases of those <lb/>
tenants who have been charged extreme <lb/>
rates for their farms-rates rendered <lb/>
necessary in order to reproduce the <lb/>
purchase money payable to the propie<lb break="no"/>tor, who receives the same price for <lb/>
worthless and indifferent as for the best <lb/>
lands. <lb/></p> 

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">"We believe that once more an oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of settling the land question is at <lb/>
hand. To obtain that object, all parties, <lb/>
Confederates and Antis, Tories and <lb/>
Liberals-nay, even proprietors them<lb break="no"/>selves, should join hands. Possibly this <lb/>
may be the last opportunity we shall ever <lb/>
see; one was lost at Quebec, which, if <lb/>
judiciously used, might have led to the <lb/>
happiest results. <lb/></hi></p>

<p>"It is useless to waste regrets over <lb/>
the past. Over the present and future <lb/>
we may exercise some influence. We <lb/>

<pb n="198" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_198.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">198</fw>

ask the people throughout the length <lb/>
and breadth of the Dominion, to give us <lb/>
the assistance of the moral lorce' of <lb/>
public opinion, and to express that <lb/>
opinion in tones loud enough to be <lb/>
heard, and emphatic enough to be under<lb break="no"/>stood at Downing Street. We ask local <lb/>
Legislatures to insist on the maintenance <lb/>
of the North American Act in its in<lb break="no"/>tegrity, particularly as regards the <lb/>
pecuniary relations of the several Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. We despair of rendering the <lb/>
complicated question of our land tenures <lb/>
clearly intelligible to readers outside the <lb/>
Island, but we may ask Canadians how <lb/>
they would feel if a third part of their <lb/>
vast and noble territory belonged to <lb/>
absentee and resident proprietors, who <lb/>
thus acquire power to exercise an im<lb break="no"/>portant influence the welfare of thou<lb break="no"/>sands! or, if another third part of its <lb/>
area had been lately rescued from similar <lb/>
baneful influence, by purchase,at a great <lb/>
national sacrifice. We ask short, <lb/>
how they would leel if one-third of their <lb/>
people paid rent—if many owed arrears <lb/>
—if not a few held farms on short leases <lb/>
and'lived in fear of ejectment! Or, how <lb/>
they would feel if another third was <lb/>
engaged in paying instalments of pur<lb break="no"/>chase money, which. would be devoted <lb/>
not to purposes of local improvement. <lb/>
but to the liquidation of proprietors <lb/>
claims. <lb/></p> 

<p>"We do not anticipate much success <lb/>
from Canadian diplomacy. The Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of Council do not write with the <lb/>
precision and correctness of men <lb/>
thoroughly conversant with their sub<lb break="no"/>ject. although they were abundantly sup<lb break="no"/>plied with all pnblic documents bearing <lb/>
on the land question. Thanks to the <lb/>
Land Purchase Bill, farms can now he <lb/>
obtained otherwise than on lease, and <lb/>
the remaining proprietors are not, as <lb/>
stated in the Committee's report, all <lb/>
absentees. They have made a mistake, <lb/>
we think, in developing their plan be<lb break="no"/>fore they ascertained the intentions of <lb/>
the Imperial Government, intending <lb/>
probably to reconcile objections in Prince <lb/>
Edward Island, they have—too liberally, <lb/>
we think—engaged to assume liabilities <lb/>
which we regard as strictly imperial, in <lb/>
case the Secretary of State repudiates <lb/>
them. It is true there have been occa<lb break="no"/>sions when we would have been content <lb/>
to settle the proprietary claims from our <lb/>
own resources; but <hi rendition="simple:italic">then</hi> we were not <lb/>
asked to join the Confederacy, and run <lb/>
a race, carrying weight, against other <lb/>
Provinces carrying none. We are aware <lb/>

<cb/> 

that there are many persons, for whose <lb/>
opinion we entertain the highest respect, <lb/>
who ask us: what matter whence the <lb/>
indemnity comes, provided our people <lb/>
reap the benefit? We consider that if <lb/>
the land question was justly settled .by <lb/>
Britain, nearly the whole of our debt, <lb/>
which has been incurred in the purchase <lb/>
of land, Would be cancelled. We might. <lb/>
then receive from Canada without dis<lb break="no"/>grace, the increased amount of the dif<lb break="no"/>erence between her debt and ours. <lb/>
Moreover, we could treat, if our people <lb/>
desire it, about Union, unembarrassed <lb/>
by any difficulties arising from differ<lb break="no"/>ences between our land tenures and hers. <lb/>
But if we adopt. the Dominion proposals, <lb/>
and accept $800,000 as an indemnity for <lb/>
the loss of'territorial revenue, and to <lb/>
purchase the right of the remaining pro<lb break="no"/>prietors—for which latter purpose that <lb/>
sum would little more than suffice,—we, <lb/>
irreflect, sell our liberty of action in ex<lb break="no"/>change lor free land.   <lb/></p> 

<p>"We acknowledge. with satisfaction, <lb/>
the kindliness of tone which pervades <lb/>
the report of the Honorables Messrs. <lb/>
Kenny, Tilley, and the genial French <lb/>
Canadian Baronet, Sir George Cartier. <lb/>
There should be no bitterness of feeling <lb/>
between the Dominion and the Island. <lb/>
Canada has done tnuch for us in undertak<lb break="no"/>ing to advocate our cause at the Colonial <lb/>
Office, and for that she certainly merits <lb/>
our best thanks." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>These were the whole of the articles from <lb/>
which the hon member for the city quoted <lb/>
last night; and he (Mr.,R.) was surprised <lb/>
that he had attempted from these to <lb/>
place him (Mr R.) in a false position. <lb/>
If the time should come that confedera<lb break="no"/>tion was inevitable, he would deem it his <lb/>
duty to accept the best terms that could <lb/>
be got for the colony; but he had not <lb/>
yet arrived at the conclusion that it was <lb/>
inevitable, nor had the people. By <lb/>
holding out against union at the time the <lb/>
other provinces were confederated, they <lb/>
had now before them much better terms <lb/>
than were contained in the Quebec <lb/>
scheme; and be (Mr. R.) believed that <lb/>
better terms still would yet be offered. <lb/>
The only doubt he ever had on <lb/>
his mind was, that the question might be <lb/>
forced upon us; but on account of the <lb/>
trouble at Red River, and the dissatis<lb break="no"/>faction in Nova Scotia. he was beginning <lb/>
to think it problematical whether the <lb/>

<pb n="199" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_198.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">199</fw>

confederacy would stand at all or not. <lb/>
The Home Government was taking away <lb/>
all her troops, as if she was preparing to <lb/>
cast these colonies adrift But if it. <lb/>
should come that we would have to cast <lb/>
in our lot with the Dominion, it would <lb/>
not take a great deal of eloquence to <lb/>
convince the people of what would be to <lb/>
their interests; and if the time arrived <lb/>
when it would be proper for them to <lb/>
state the terms which would suit the <lb/>
colony, he would be prepared to do the <lb/>
best be could for them. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> did not find fault with <lb/>
the hon. member (Mr. Reilly) for chang<lb break="no"/>ing his mind, but for comparing these <lb/>
who favored confederation with Castle<lb break="no"/>reagh. He also said to go into Confed<lb break="no"/>eration on any terms, was to sink into <lb/>
degradation; it would be taxation with<lb break="no"/>out representation, and many other evils; <lb/>
and no terms could be offered which we <lb/>
could accept. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> had never proposed the <lb/>
absurd doctrine that no terms. could be <lb/>
offered which would be advantageous to <lb/>
the people, but he believed Canada <lb/>
would never offer us terms which we <lb/>
could accept. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> had taken the authority <lb/>
of the Ottawa <hi rendition="simple:italic">Citizen</hi>, and the editor of <lb/>
that paper had pronounced a eulogium <lb/>
upon the Queen's Printer, and looked <lb/>
upon him as an advocate of confed<lb break="no"/>eration. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName> was a "no-terms" <lb/>
man, and never expected to change his <lb/>
opinions on the subject, as he had heard <lb/>
no argument. as yet to induce him to do <lb/>
so. it had been said that the Dominion <lb/>
was going to have an exclusive tariff, <lb/>
and that our trade with that country <lb/>
would be destroyed, and, as a conse<lb break="no"/>quence, we should. become bankrupt. <lb/>
He (Mr. D.) was satisfied there was no <lb/>
danger in this respect. Nova Seotia <lb/>
'and New Brunswick were not going to <lb/>
be customers for our outs, for they were <lb/>
now sending cats to England themselves. <lb/>
The timber was getting cut away in <lb/>
those countries, and more land was cul<lb break="no"/>tivated than formerly. He (Mr D.) <lb/>
would read an extract from a letter sent <lb/> 

<cb/>

to the St. John Telegraph from the north <lb/>
shore of New Brunswick:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Mussel mud is being got up in immense <lb/>
quantities this year. It is one of [illegible] <lb/>
things for hay that can be got. Hay is cheap, <lb/>
only ten or twelve dollars per ton, and oats <lb/>
seem to be a drag, no person wants them at <lb/>
any price." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Here was a country which we supplied <lb/>
with oats some years ago, now growing <lb/>
more than required for their own use, so <lb/>
that a high tariff would make very little <lb/>
difference to us. Another extract would <lb/>
show the state of trade in St. John:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Every branch of trade in the city des<lb break="no"/>perately dull; one hears the same story every<lb break="no"/>where he goes. An enterprising house, with <lb/>
capital, might purchase some millions of bush<lb break="no"/>els of oats in Lower Canada at 22 cents per <lb/>
bushel." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Oats were selling in Canada at. 22 cents, <lb/>
which was equal to 1s 4d of our money, <lb/>
while they were now selling on, the island <lb/>
at 2s 2d, so, at that rate, we need not be <lb/>
very anxious to keep the Dominion market <lb/>
open for our oats. Canada could also sup<lb break="no"/>ply Halifax with pork, and when the rail<lb break="no"/>road would be extruded. they would have <lb/>
greater facilities, and could supply the <lb/>
market more readily than we could, and we <lb/>
would be obliged to send our pork to Eng<lb break="no"/>land to find a market, Barley was low in <lb/>
the Dominion, and last year Canada sup<lb break="no"/>plied Halifax and St. John. Some hon. <lb/>
member had referred to our dependence on <lb/>
the Dominion for our supply of coal; but <lb/>
they would never refuse to sell us coal if <lb/>
we paid for it. The following statistics in <lb/>
the year 1861, the last time the census was <lb/>
taken, would show tint. we were not behind <lb/>
the Canadians. For each inhabitant, P. E. <lb/>
Island made 5 1/4 yards cloth; Canada. 2 1/2 <lb/>
yards—P. E. Island milled one and a-half <lb/>
yards cloth, Canada, half a yard—P. E. i. <lb/>
grew 4 1/2 bush. wheat, Canada, 9 bush; <lb/>
P. E. I. 2 3/4 bush. barley, Canada. 1 2/3 bush; <lb/>
P. E. I , 4 1/4 bush. turnips, Canada, 6 1/2 bush; <lb/>
P. E. I., 27 1/2 bush. oats, Canada, 14 bush; <lb/>
P. E. 1., 36 3/4 bush. potatoes, Canada, 11 2/3 <lb/>
It should be stated, however, that Canada <lb/>
rained some Rye and Corn which we did <lb/>
not. At the same time, P. E. I. had for <lb/>
every one hundred inhabitants 23 horses., <lb/>
Canada, 22; P. E. I. 74 cattle. Canada. 75; <lb/>
P. E. I., 132 sheep, Canada, 78; P. E. L, <lb/>
88 pigs. Canada, 38. And when we con<lb break="no"/>sidered our present position, and the pro<lb break="no"/>gress we had made since 1861, we need not <lb/>
fear a comparison with Canada. From the <lb/>
Year Book of the Dominion for 1868. It <lb/>
appeared that Canada paid in duties $2.12 <lb/>
per head of the population: Nova Scotia, <lb/>
$3.1; New Brunswick, $2.92. while, at the <lb/>

<pb n="200" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_200.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">200</fw> 

same time, poor P.E. Island paid $2.17, <lb/>
with a much lower tariff on teas, tobacco <lb/>
and rum. This showed that we were greater <lb/>
consumers than the Canadians, and were <lb/>
we united, and under their tariff, we would <lb/>
contribute more to the revenues, in propor<lb break="no"/>tion to our population, than Canada. It <lb/>
had been said that our pork was too fat <lb/>
for the English market, and if so, the peo<lb break="no"/>ple could keep a larger number of pigs and <lb/>
not make them so far, so that we would <lb/>
always find a market for our pork. Al<lb break="no"/>though the people of the Dominion paid <lb/>
such high duties last year, Nova Scotia had <lb/>
only $1677 of a surplus ; New Brunswick, <lb/>
$1574 ; while P. E. Island, with a much <lb/>
lower tariff, had a surplus of $8400. The <lb/>
reason he (Mr. D.) was opposed to any <lb/>
terms, was because Canada would never <lb/>
offer us terms by which she would be a <lb/>
loser, and no terms could be offered by <lb/>
which either P. E. Island or Canada would <lb/>
not be a loser. They had large tracts of <lb/>
fertile land, which would soon be under <lb/>
cultivation, and would yield more than they <lb/>
could consume, and they grew the same <lb/>
kind of crops that we did. If they put a <lb/>
high tariff on our produce, it would only <lb/>
fall on their own fishermen and lumbermen. <lb/>
The following was an extract from a letter <lb/>
received by a person in this Island from a <lb/>
firm in St. John, N. B. One of the firm <lb/>
was a good confederate three years ago :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"When do you expect to cast in your mito <lb/>
with us in this glorious confederation? We <lb/>
are looking for you to be badgered or bribed, <lb/>
or coaxed into signing your death warrant <lb/>
before long ; then good-bye freedom and pros<lb break="no"/>perity <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mrs. P. E. Island</hi>—your birthright gone <lb/>
for less than a mess of pottage, and, like an <lb/>
endorser on a bad note, you must <hi rendition="simple:italic">pay the piper</hi>. <lb/>
Far better to remain as you are at present, <lb/>
simply holding the candle. But many a foolish <lb/>
act is perpetrated to gain a name. You have a <lb/>
local habitation, and if you expect to add a <lb/>
name thereto in this way, you will inevitably <lb/>
join our good confederates in this Province, in <lb/>
the mental ejaculation, sold!" <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>There was a great deal said about paying <lb/>
rent, but if we would raise our tariff as <lb/>
high as the Dominion, we would soon have <lb/>
money enough to pay for all the proprie<lb break="no"/>tors' lands. The hon. leader of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment said we would not give up on our con<lb break="no"/>stitutions until the land question was set<lb break="no"/>tled, but he (Mr. D.) did not believe in <lb/>
giving it up at all. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> had said the question <lb/>
should not be put before the people, until <lb/>
the land question was settled. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName>.—Did that imply that <lb/>
as soon as we got free land we should go <lb/>
for confederation. <lb/></p>

<cb/> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName>—No. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName>.—The time had now <lb/>
come when every person who was a con<lb break="no"/>federate, should say so, and every person <lb/>
who was anti-confederate should let it be <lb/>
known. A great deal had been said about <lb/>
the union of Scotland and England, but <lb/>
there was no analogy between their condi<lb break="no"/>tion and ours. If Scotland had never en<lb break="no"/>tered the union, her coals and her iron, and <lb/>
shipbuilding would have made her rich. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CALL1">Hon. Mr. CALLBECK</persName> believed it was <lb/>
the duty of the people's representatives <lb/>
to express their opinions on this great <lb/>
question. He had always held anti-con<lb break="no"/>federate views. The minute of council <lb/>
had been pretty freely criticised by hon. <lb/>
members opposite, but taking it as a <lb/>
whole he was prepared to stand by it. <lb/>
Some might quote from that document <lb/>
portions to suit their own purposes, yet <lb/>
if fairly considered throughout it would <lb/>
not bear the construction they had put <lb/>
upon it. He would first read an extract <lb/>
from the report of the committee of <lb/>
council of Canada :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The Committee of Council have had under <lb/>
consideration, a memorandum, dated. 11th <lb/>
December, 1869, from the Hon. Sir George E. <lb/>
Cartier and Messrs. Tilley and Kenny, stating, <lb/>
that at the desire of their colleagues they visit<lb break="no"/>ted the Island of Prince Edward, in August last, <lb/>
and having, while there, had the opportunity <lb/>
of discussing, informally, with members of the <lb/>
Government, and other leading public men. <lb/>
the question of the political union of the Island <lb/>
with the Dominion," &amp;c. <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>It would be seen by the report of the gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen here referred to what took place <lb/>
when they visited the Island—that their <lb/>
discussion with the members of the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment on union were merely informal, <lb/>
the same as it was with other public <lb/>
men. He would next read from the <lb/>
same report, the conclusion which the <lb/>
Canadian committee of council came to <lb/>
with respect to the land question of this <lb/>
Colony :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"They submit that much discontent has for <lb/>
many years existed amongst the inhabitants of <lb/>
the island, arising from the fact that the Lands <lb/>
of the Colony had been granted by the Imper<lb break="no"/>ial Government in large blocks, and chiefly to <lb/>
persons resident abroad, thus leaving the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment of the Island no lands, the proceeds <lb/>
of the sale of which could, as in the other Brit<lb break="no"/>ish Colonies, he appropriated towards Local <lb/>
improvements and the maintenance of the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Now, he. (Mr. C.) thought this a very <lb/>
important admission on the part of the <lb/>
government of Canada. It was quite <lb/>
evident that had our lands not been <lb/>
granted away, they would have been a <lb/> 

<pb n="201" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_200.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">201</fw> 

source of revenue to this colony, as the <lb/>
public lands of the provinces in the Do<lb break="no"/>minion were to them. He noticed, in <lb/>
looking over some appropriations in <lb/>
Canada, that in one place where $9,000 <lb/>
were voted for the roads and other public <lb/>
works, that $8,000 of that sum were <lb/>
taken from the crown land funds. If <lb/>
we were running a race with horses, we <lb/>
would try ad not have too much weight <lb/>
on our favorite steed ; so in the same <lb/>
way if we were going to run a race with <lb/>
Canada, we should see to it that we <lb/>
were not weighed down with heavier <lb/>
burdens than our neighbors before we <lb/>
consented to start on the course. We <lb/>
had obtained from the statesmen of <lb/>
Canada, this acknowledgement, that we <lb/>
had been denied our rights in this colony, <lb/>
as would be seen by the paragraph of <lb/>
their report, which he would now read: <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That up to the present time, the Island Go<lb break="no"/>vernment have failed to secure a consideration <lb/>
in lieu of the lands thus granted by the Crown. <lb/>
Notwithstanding the efforts that have been <lb/>
made by the Government and Legislature of <lb/>
the Island, to remove the obstruction to the <lb/>
settlement of the Colony, arising from this <lb/>
cause, there still remains about one-third of <lb/>
the Island owned by absentee Proprietors, a <lb/>
very considerable portion of which is unoccu<lb break="no"/>pied and in the condition of a wilderness." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Then followed the proposals of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion committee to remedy the evil:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That in the event of the Island becoming <lb/>
part of the Union, the Government of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion will endeavor to secure for the Island, <lb/>
from the Imperial Government fair compensa<lb break="no"/>tion for the loss of Crown Lands. Should the <lb/>
Dominion Government fall in their efforts to <lb/>
secure such compensation, they will undertake <lb/>
to raise by Loan, guaranteed by the Imperial <lb/>
Government, or upon their own securities, <lb/>
should such guarantee be refused, eight hun<lb break="no"/>dred thousand dollars ($800,000), and pay the <lb/>
same to the Island Government as a compen<lb break="no"/>sation for the loss of such Crown Lands—this <lb/>
sum to be in addition to the other sums men<lb break="no"/>tioned in the preceding proposals. That the <lb/>
Dominion Government will also use their in<lb break="no"/>fluence to secure such Legislation as will enable <lb/>
the Government of the Island to purchase the <lb/>
Land, now held in large blocks, upon terms <lb/>
just and equitable to all parties concerned." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>We must here notice that it is only in <lb/>
the event of the Island becoming a part <lb/>
of the Dominion, that the government <lb/>
of Canada would endeavor to secure for us <lb/>
from the Imperial Government compen<lb break="no"/>sation for the loss of our crown lands. <lb/>
They did not promise to put forth any <lb/>
effort to obtain for us our rights until <lb/>
we went into the union. This be (Mr. <lb/>
C.) thought was a very important point, <lb/>
and it had not been lost sight of by the <lb/>
Island Executive, as would be seen by <lb/>

<cb/> 

the concluding paragraph of their minute <lb/>
of Feb 4:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Under these circumstances, the intimation <lb/>
conveyed by the Council in their short Minute <lb/>
that the settlement of the Land. Question much <lb/>
be a condition precedent to the discussion of a <lb/>
union, is in reality on a prudent precaution <lb/>
on the part of a Government acting on behalf of <lb/>
a people now invited to perform the important <lb/>
and irretrievable public act of choosing their <lb/>
future national destiny." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>If the Island were once to become part <lb/>
of the Dominion, the general govern<lb break="no"/>ment might say to us, "You have been <lb/>
dabbling about this land question for a <lb/>
long time, and you cannot expect us to <lb/>
settle it immediately"—thus years might <lb/>
pass in negotiation, and in the end o <lb/>
really satisfactory arrangement be made. <lb/>
But another point in the extract which <lb/>
he had read should be noticed—"the <lb/>
settlement of the land question must be <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">precedent to the discussion</hi> of a union." <lb/>
There was no admission of the principle <lb/>
of confederation here ; the council only <lb/>
said the settlement of the land question <lb/>
would clear the way for a discussion of <lb/>
confederation, not for its acceptance. <lb/>
No other construction could fairly be <lb/>
put upon the resolution of Council of the <lb/>
7th January, which was as follows: <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That inasmuch as said terms do not com<lb break="no"/>prise a full and immediate settlement of the <lb/>
Land Tenures and indignity from the Imper<lb break="no"/>ial Government, for loss of territorial Revenues, <lb/>
the Committee cannot recommend said terms to <lb/>
the consideration of their constituents and the <lb/>
public.: <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Here the Council said they could not <lb/>
recommend the terms of union proposed <lb/>
by the Dominion government, even to <lb/>
the consideration, of their constituents <lb/>
ad the public, much less to their ap<lb break="no"/>proval, He (Mr. C.) therefore contended <lb/>
that the Executive had made no compro<lb break="no"/>mise at all on the question of confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. The answer from the Imperial <lb/>
government, contained in the late de<lb break="no"/>spatch of the Colonial Minister, was <lb/>
little else than what we might expect, <lb/>
considering the manner in which our <lb/>
land question had been treated at Down<lb break="no"/>ing Street in times past. In the matter, <lb/>
too, of the payment of the Governor's <lb/>
salary, we were powerless. As the <lb/>
money came from the Imperial chest, if <lb/>
the Home Government refused to pay <lb/>
the salary what could this colony do <lb/>
but yield. But in this respect we were <lb/>
not one whit inferior to the Dominion <lb/>
Government itself. When the Ottawa <lb/>
parliament attempted to reduce the <lb/>
salary of the Governor General from <lb/>
£1,500 to £1,300, sterling, the Imperial <lb/>

<pb n="202" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_202.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">202</fw> 

government would not sanction the <lb/>
change. Here, then, the Dominion in a <lb/>
matter where the money was to come <lb/>
solely out of their own treasury, were <lb/>
not allowed to say what the amount <lb/>
should be, whereas in this Island we <lb/>
had been allowed to reduce the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor's salary. This showed that the <lb/>
Dominion was in no better position to con<lb break="no"/>trol its own affairs, than this colony. He <lb/>
(Mr. C.) had never said he was prepared <lb/>
to accept the terms proposed by the Do<lb break="no"/>minion government, even though the <lb/>
land question was settled. He believed <lb/>
Canada was not in a position to offer <lb/>
terms that owuld be fair to us and satis<lb break="no"/>factory to her people. It was, in his <lb/>
opinion, very doubtful whether the Do<lb break="no"/>minion would carry out the guarantee <lb/>
to this Island, after we had entered the <lb/>
union. For example, were we to re<lb break="no"/>ceive $800,000 from Canada to settle our <lb/>
land question, this would be a wrong <lb/>
to the other provinces, for they did not <lb/>
take our lands from us, and some mem<lb break="no"/>ber might rise in the Dominion parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, and say Prince Edward Island <lb/>
was getting too much, and propose that <lb/>
it should be reduced, which could be <lb/>
easily carried. Again, since we were <lb/>
less burdened with debt than Canada, <lb/>
he (Mr. C.) did not see what we were to <lb/>
gain by entering the union. The hon. <lb/>
member for the city (Mr. Brecken) had <lb/>
referred to the return of Howe and <lb/>
Archibald in Nova Scotia, and said that <lb/>
it gave the lie to what was stated in the <lb/>
minute of council respecting that pro<lb break="no"/>vince. He (Mr. C.) thought differently. <lb/>
That question, however, he did not in<lb break="no"/>tend to dewll upon, as the hon. member <lb/>
for Murray Harbor (Mr. Henderson) <lb/>
into the union contrary to the wishes of <lb/>
her people. Once they were into the <lb/>
Dominion, the only thing they could do <lb/>
was to petition the British parliament; <lb/>
and it was after this failed that the elec<lb break="no"/>tions took place to which allusion had <lb/>
been made. The people were, it might <lb/>
be said, in the lion's mouth; they could <lb/>
not get out again, and they made the <lb/>
most of their situation by returning the <lb/>
best men they could find to represent <lb/>
them at Ottawa. Reference had also <lb/>
been made to the union of Scotland and <lb/>
Ireland with England, and to other <lb/>
unions which had taken place. He was <lb/>
not going to argue that Scotland had <lb/>
not benefitted from Union; but it was <lb/>
well known that the Scotch were an in<lb break="no"/>dustrious and successful people. He <lb/>

<cb/>
 
thought, however, there was scarcely <lb/>
any similarity between her union and <lb/>
that proposed to this Island. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>.- If the cases were <lb/>
dissimilar, why were they devetailed to<lb break="no"/>gether in the minute of council. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CALL1">Hon. Mr. CALLBECK</persName>.- The reason was <lb/>
that we considered Ireland and Scotland <lb/>
were bribed, and that if we accepted union <lb/>
on the terms proposed, we would be in a <lb/>
similar position. In the tabular statement <lb/>
which had been published by the Union <lb/>
Association, the interest of the $800,000 <lb/>
had been put down to the credit of the <lb/>
colony, instead of assigning the money to <lb/>
its proper purpose to buy land. This was <lb/>
not right, for if that amount was to be <lb/>
granted to place us in an equal position <lb/>
with the other Provinces as regards our <lb/>
lands, it should not be taken into account <lb/>
in the yearly income of the colony. He <lb/>
(Mr. C.) saw it reasoned in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Argus</hi> news<lb break="no"/>paper, that if this Island were in the Do<lb break="no"/>minion, we coujld successfully engage in <lb/>
manufactures. There was just one ques<lb break="no"/>tion, which he would like to ask, namely, <lb/>
who here would be so rash as to attempt <lb/>
manufacturing anything for the outside <lb/>
world? In the winter such manufacturing <lb/>
capital would be locked up, for no exporta<lb break="no"/>tion could take place, and stock would <lb/>
accumulate to the loss of the manufacturer, <lb/>
who would require a ready market to turn <lb/>
his capital around with profit. If we were <lb/>
a part and parcel of the Dominion, he (Mr. <lb/>
C.) contended that our manufactures would <lb/>
be under a greater disadvantage than at <lb/>
present, as they had now the of <lb/>
our tariff. It had been said that Mr. Stan<lb break="no"/>field had removed from Tryon to Truro, in <lb/>
Nova Scotia, in order to be in the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion, so that he could avail himself of the <lb/>
market which that country offered for his <lb/>
manufactures. It was not merely to be in <lb/>
the Dominion, that he removed, because <lb/>
he thought that this Island would have <lb/>
been into confederation before now; but <lb/>
the reason of his going to Nova Scotia, was, <lb/>
that he found he would have to import <lb/>
material for the articles which he intended <lb/>
to manufacture, and it would not pay to do <lb/>
so, and have his stock locked up here during <lb/>
the winter season. What he (Mr. C.) had <lb/>
said during the debate on the Address, <lb/>
about bonded warehouses, had not been <lb/>
fully reported. His statement was that if <lb/>
we were in the union, and imported goods <lb/>
not manufactured in the Dominion, we <lb/>
would have to pay 15 per cent, but if we <lb/>
remained out of confederation, we could <lb/> 

<pb n="203" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-07_Page_202.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">203</fw>

purchase them in bond in the other Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, and only pay 11 per cent. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.- Was our tariff going to <lb/>
remain at 11 per cent? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CALL1">Hon. Mr. CALLBECK</persName> thought it was just <lb/>
as likely that ours would remain at 11 per <lb/>
cent as that of the Dominion would remain <lb/>
at 15 per cent. he (Mr. C.) had also said, <lb/>
in the course of his speech, already referred <lb/>
to, that the salary of a certain Dominion <lb/>
officer, (the Receiver General) was £1250 <lb/>
sterling, but in the report, it was set down <lb/>
in Island currency. He had obtained his in<lb break="no"/>formation from the Colonial Office List, and <lb/>
he thought it should be correct. The popu<lb break="no"/>lation of the Dominion, he found, was about <lb/>
3,879,812; and the customs revenue, for the <lb/>
year ended June 30, 1868, as given in the <lb/>
Canadian Year Book, was $8,624,318, and <lb/>
the inland revenue, including stamps, $3,<lb break="no"/>125,904; then came the miscellaneous, a <lb/>
part of which might be taken into account, <lb/>
but he would omit it, to give his calculation no <lb/>
semblance to being overdrawn. The amount <lb/>
for customs and excise together, therefore, <lb/>
would come to $11,750,223, which <lb/>
amount, divided by the number of the <lb/>
population, would show the taxation, <lb/>
under these two heads alone, to be <lb/>
$3.02 per head. Then, take this Island, <lb/>
and put down its population at 95,000, and <lb/>
its revenue last year from customs and <lb/>
excise at £61,664, and we would find that <lb/>
our taxation, per head, from those, almost <lb/>
the only sources of revenue in the colony, <lb/>
was $2.16. Here, consequently, we had <lb/>
the proof that taxation in the Dominion <lb/>
was about 40 per cent heavier than it was <lb/>
in this Island. Some maintained that the <lb/>
Canadians were larger consumers of dutiable <lb/>
goods than the people of this Island; but <lb/>
Hon. Mr. Galt had admitted the contrary, <lb/>
and this being the case, the difference in <lb/>
taxation was solely attributable to the high <lb/>
tariff and excise duties imposed by Canada. <lb/>
Reciprocity had been spoken of. He (Mr. <lb/>
C.) would not say that we could get reci<lb break="no"/>procity any sooner than the Dominion; but <lb/>
he thought we would obtain it just as soon. <lb/>
His opinion was that the leading politicans <lb/>
of Canada were not favorable to free trade; <lb/>
theirs was a producing country now, and <lb/>
they wished to make it a manufacturing <lb/>
one also, consequently their policy was <lb/>
protection. The Canadians were not so much <lb/>
interested in free trade as the people of <lb/>
this Island, for they were in a position to <lb/>
build up manufactories. It was said, too, <lb/>
that connection with the Dominion would <lb/>
give us more influence,- we could get a <lb/>
better hearing at Downing Street. But he <lb/> 

<cb/>

would like to ask what kind of hearing <lb/>
Nova Scotia received in the Imperial parlia<lb break="no"/>ment? Some had argued that we would <lb/>
not be loyal if we opposed confederation; <lb/>
but he did not think people could be called <lb/>
disloyal if they were only wishing to retain <lb/>
their just rights. The tenantry of this <lb/>
Island had borne the land grievance, and <lb/>
still were loyal, and he did not think they <lb/>
should be accused of it now when merely <lb/>
seeking to retain their constitution. He <lb/>
could not see his way clear to give up the <lb/>
little authority we had at present. Now, <lb/>
the power was in our own people; they <lb/>
had the choosing of those who were in im<lb break="no"/>pose their burdens; but once in the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion, it would not be so; we would literally <lb/>
have no voice in the Ottawa parliament. <lb/>
Besides, the Dominion was not at peace <lb/>
within herself, and he thought we had <lb/>
better remain as we were, and retain the <lb/>
control of our own affairs. <lb/></p> 

<p>Debate adjourned.<lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>