<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1864-04-18"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1864-04-18">18 April 1864</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1864">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1864, Being the Second Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1864"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Protestant" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="42"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_037.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_038.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_039.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_040.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_041.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_042.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-05">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_037">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_037.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_038">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_038.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_039">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_039.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_040">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_040.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_041">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_041.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_042">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_042.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>

<text>
<body>

<div type="debate"> <pb n="37" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_037.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">37</fw>

<!-- DL 2018-06-05 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--
<p>1864 PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER. 37<lb/></p> 

<p>our independent position, and hence I consider that the resolution<lb/>
proposed by the hon. leader of the Government, is the only one<lb/>
we can safely adopt. We must not commit ourselves to the<lb/>
union as the other Colonies, by their Resolutions, appear to have<lb/>
done. We should first consider the expedience of a union ; but<lb/>
before we can be in a position to do so, we must hear the argu<lb break="no"/>ments and reasons which may be offered in support of it, and<lb/>
therefore, it is our duty to appoint delegates ; to refuse this much,<lb/>
would be uncourteous to our sister Colonies. Besides, we can<lb break="no"/>not lose by obtaining information; upon all colonial questions<lb/>
which may have a tendency to affect us as a government or a<lb/>
people. If the time should arrive when we might be necessitated<lb/>
to enter into a union, by refusing to confer on the subject now,<lb/>
we might be placed in a disadvantageous position hereafter.<lb/>
But while we appoint delegates, we must not tie up our hands,<lb/>
and commit ourselves to a union, without knowing what equiva<lb break="no"/>lent we are to receive. I admit that it might add to our im<lb break="no"/>portance to be a part of a larger Province which might be called<lb/>
Acadia or Cabotis, or any thing else, still this would not satisfy<lb/>
our people unless there was some material and great permanent<lb/>
advantage to be gained by the change. Though united with<lb/>
Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, we could do little in giving<lb/>
battle to a government like the United States, if it should ever<lb/>
be the policy of that country to go to war with England or her <lb/>
North American Colonies ; consequently, I can see no force in<lb/>
the argument drawn from probable occurrences in that country.<lb/>
We must look to ourselves, and our own interests, and act ac<lb break="no"/>cordingly. The practical difficulty that would be experienced<lb/>
by us in sending Representatives across our ice-bound Strait in<lb/>
the winter season to attend the United Legislature in Halifax, or<lb/>
some other favored city on the other side of the water, seems to<lb/>
me at present almost sufficient to overbalance every argument in<lb/>
favor of the project, unless indeed, Charlottetown were made<lb/>
the capital of the United Provinces, which we could not expect<lb/>
it would be. The question is, then, should we give up our <lb/>
independent position—our separate Government—and become a<lb/>
part of a greater Province ? My own opinion is decidedly in the<lb/>
negative, but the question can only be satisfactorily answered<lb/>
when we ascertain the terms of union, which it would be the<lb/>
duty of delegates, if appointed, to learn ; therefore, I will support<lb/>
the resolution before the Committee authorizing such appointment,<lb/>
reserving to ourselves, as a Legislature, our own action hereafter<lb/>
upon the results of that Delegation.<lb/></p> 

<p>Adjourned for one hour.<lb/></p> -->

<p><hi rendition="simple:right">MONDAY AFTERNOON, April 18<lb/></hi></p> 

<p>Committee on despatches resumed.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACA1">Hon. Mr. SPEAKER</persName>.—Mr. Chairman, since I have had<lb/>
a seat in this House, many questions of moment have<lb/>
been introduced and discussed, but although I was a<lb/>
member of the Legislature at the times when the princi<lb break="no"/>ples of Responsible Government, Free Trade, and an Elec<lb break="no"/>tive Legislative Council were debated, yet the subject on<lb/>
which we are now engaged, is, in my opinion, of import<lb break="no"/>ance paramount to any which has ever engaged the at<lb break="no"/>tention of our local legislature. The question at issue is<lb/>
briefly, whether we are to have a Legislature of our own,<lb/>
or whether we shall be absorbed by union with Nova<lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick. This is a subject which can<lb/>
be discussed without party bias, and it is the duty of<lb/>
every hon. member to give his individual opinion on a <lb/>
matter of such importance, irrespectively of the obliga<lb break="no"/>tions which the interests of political combination in many<lb/>
cases impose. This question of a union of the Maritime<lb/>
Colonies is not a new one. In 1814, the father of Her<lb/>
Majesty, the late Duke of Kent, while Commander-in-<lb break="yes"/>Chief of the Province of Nova Scotia, corresponded on<lb/>
the subject with Judge Sewell in Canada. The Duke was<lb/>
of opinion that these Colonies, without a political union,<lb/>
would never occupy the influential position to which they<lb/>
were entitled by the elements of material prosperity<lb/>
which they possessed. It was urged this morning as an<lb/>
argument in favor of the union, that, in the event of a<lb/>
cessation of the present civil war in the States, we would<lb/>
be powerless against a northern army or against the<lb/>
united forces of the restored union. If that be the only<lb/>
argument which can be advanced by the advocates of the<lb/> 

<cb/>

suggested, association, their position is weak indeed ; for<lb/>
I ask, what could the united colonies effect against the<lb/>
forces which could be brought against them ? Assuming<lb/>
the population of the Canadas to be two and one-half<lb/>
millions, and that of the Lower Provinces half a million,<lb/>
can it be expected that we could, in case of invasion, offer<lb/>
successful resistance to the disciplined armies which a<lb/>
population exceeding twenty millions could send forth ?<lb/>
The minds of hon. members may be seduced from a sober<lb/>
consideration of this question, by the idea that we would<lb/>
be laying the foundations of a great country, and I admit<lb/>
the influence of that feeling on my own mind last Session.<lb/>
But, Sir, I confess that a change has come o'er the spirit<lb/>
of my dream. What benefits are we to reap from the <lb/>
proposed reunion, for we were united up to 1769 ? New<lb/>
Brunswick has a large funded debt, in comparison to<lb/>
which our public liabilities, the fruitful subject of so<lb/>
much grumbling, are mere matter of moonshine. The<lb/>
public debt of the Island amounts to not more than<lb/>
£60,000 or £ 70,000, and we have the public domain to<lb/>
the credit of the country. Although the resolution sub<lb break="no"/>mitted does not commit this House to the expression of<lb/>
any opinion on the subject of the union of the colonies, it<lb/>
is but right that the delegates, who may be appointed as<lb/>
the representatives of the Island at the proposed conference,<lb/>
should have their position fortified by the avowed senti<lb break="no"/>ments of members of the Legislature—that they should<lb/>
be able to tell the representatives of the sister colonies<lb/>
what are the feelings of those whom they represent. I<lb/>
am decidedly of opinion that we should, as an act of com<lb break="no"/>mon courtesy, assent to the appointment of delegates, if<lb/>
for no other purpose than that of hearing what proposi<lb break="no"/>tions may be offered by the representatives of the other<lb/>
provinces. With this view, I shall support the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, but I entertain very decided objections to the pro<lb break="no"/>posed union. In New Brunswick, the Railway barely<lb/>
supports itself, and earns nothing towards repayment of<lb/>
the money borrowed for its construction. In looking<lb/>
over the Journals of the House of Assembly of that Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, I find that its Railway Debentures require no less<lb/>
than £58,000 annual interest, to be paid at Baring's in<lb/>
London. In his speech on the Union of the Lower Colo<lb break="no"/>nies, the Hon. Mr. Tupper, Provincial Secretary of Nova<lb/>
Scotia, said that the time had not yet arrived for an<lb/>
union with Canada because of the large debt of that<lb/>
Colony. " I thank thee, Jew, for teaching me that word, "<lb/>
for the argument deduced from it, is applicable against<lb/>
our union with the other colonies. Canada is burdened<lb/>
with a debt of more than sixty millions of dollars, and<lb/>
there is an annual deficit in the revenue of a million. As<lb/>
to the idea attributed to the Imperial Government that<lb/>
these Colonies are able to bear the burden of defending<lb/>
themselves against the invasion of a foreign foe, the<lb/>
sooner Great Britain awakes from that delusion the<lb/>
better. Our small annual appropriation of £400 for the<lb/>
volunteer organization is not passed without strong ex<lb break="no"/>pressions of disapprobation, while Nova Scotia grants<lb/>
$20,000 for that service. If we are to have a union, I<lb/>
should hope that it would be of a Federative, not Legis<lb break="no"/>lative, character, so that we might retain our Local<lb/>
Legislature, and our people have the management of our<lb/>
affairs. Our <hi rendition="simple:italic">status</hi>, if united, would, I am bound<lb/>
to assume, be adjusted on the basis, either of territorial area<lb/>
or numerical ratio of population. If the first criterion be<lb/>
adopted, we would occupy a very inconsiderable position<lb/>
in the United Legislature. If our representation is to be<lb/>
regulated by population, the official statistics on that<lb/>
point afford but little prospect of Prince Edward Island<lb/>
exercising much influence in the halls of the United<lb/>
Colonies. The House of Assembly in Nova Scotis is com<lb break="no"/>posed of some 55 members, New Brunswick has 42 or 43,<lb/>
and in any political combination of the kind foreshadowed,<lb/>
we might expect to receive the treatment that Scotland<lb/>
and Ireland were subjected to when their separate Legis<lb break="no"/>latures were abolished. I own, Mr. Chairman, to a feel<lb break="no"/>ing of surprise when I read the allusion made by the Hon.<lb/>

<pb n="38" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_038.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">38</fw>

Provincial Secretary of Nova Scotia in the personal<lb/>
character of the debates in this House, as an argument for<lb/>
the inference that our union with that Colony and New<lb/>
Brunswick would tend to elevate the character of our<lb/>
Legislative discussions. I admit and deplore the fre<lb break="no"/>quent introduction of offensive personalities here ; but I<lb/>
ask why should we be twitted with such a charge, when<lb/>
any one who will take the trouble to read the recorded<lb/>
speeches of Nova Scotian legislators will readily ac<lb break="no"/>knowledge that it would be more becoming in them to <lb/>
take the beam out of their own eyes, ere they allude to<lb/>
the more in ours. And in New Brunswick during the<lb/>
present session, a scene of unparalleled, I might almost<lb/>
say disgusting personal abuse, occurred on the floor of the<lb/>
Assembly between the Attorney General and a member<lb/>
of the House. In view of those facts, it would be as well<lb/>
if they would confine their imputations of personalities<lb/>
to themselves. At present, the money that we raise<lb/>
among ourselves is spent on the Island, and I ask, what<lb/>
guarantee have we that, once absorbed in the Union, we<lb/>
may not have to pass a budget framed to meet the rail<lb break="no"/>way charges of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick ? I<lb/>
know not what may result from this overture, but I<lb/>
caution hon. members that if they sell their birthright,<lb/>
they may expect their country to retrograde as Cape<lb/>
Breton has done since her annexation to Nova Scotia.<lb/>
We have at present the system of self government and<lb/>
self taxation, and if there be some defects in the practical<lb/>
working of our institutions, it is " better to bear the ills<lb/>
we have, than fly to others that we know not of. " We<lb/>
have already an independent judiciary, and if our pro<lb break="no"/>fessional men and their clients should have to appear in<lb/>
the Great Supreme Court of Acadia, I do not see what<lb/>
improvement would be effected by the change. At pre<lb break="no"/>sent, we enjoy the advantages of the Railways in the<lb/>
neighbouring provinces without the burden of the coal, and<lb/>
if we were prevented from those advantages, I admit an<lb/>
argument might be drawn in favor of the Union, but it<lb/>
should also be borne in mind that the Railway in New<lb/>
Brunswick derives a large amount of income from this<lb/>
island. I was surprised at hearing the Hon. Colonial<lb/>
Secretary this morning when he spoke in terms of dis<lb break="no"/>paragement of our legislation. A reference to our<lb/>
Statute Book will shew that in many instances we have<lb/>
led the van of these Colonies in Legislative action. I<lb/>
will merely refer to our law of evidence, and our Elective<lb/>
Council Bill as proving the truth of my assertion. And I<lb/>
cannot think that facts were strong in favor of his state<lb break="no"/>ment that our judiciary was so limited that others than<lb/>
the judges were frequently called on to preside at the<lb/>
trials of cases in which the judges, while at the bar, had<lb/>
been retained as Counsel or Attornies. I know of but<lb/>
one such case, which was tried at St. Eleanor's two or<lb/>
three years ago. The hon. Col. Secretary also told us<lb/>
that our internal communications would be improved by<lb/>
the increased outlay which the revenue of the united<lb/>
colonies could afford and that capital would flow in on<lb/>
us after our separate constitution shall be merged in the<lb/>
union. As to the first argument, my impression is very<lb/>
decidedly opposed to it, and I cannot conceive that our<lb/>
identification with other countries, deeply involved in<lb/>
debt, will have the effect of inducing men of wealth to<lb/>
invest their property in the Colony. The statistics of the<lb/>
Island shew that, without the public lands, which they<lb/>
possess, without the Imperial Expenditure for naval and<lb/>
military purposes, which has been so abundantly, nay,<lb/>
lavishly disbursed in Nova Scotia and New Brunswick,<lb/>
we have thriven and advanced in material prosperity, as<lb/>
did the old thirteen Colonies, by our own unaided re<lb break="no"/>sources. The very first result of a union with those<lb/>
provinces would be a uniform tariff ; and while we hear<lb/>
complaints of our present scale of duties, let it be remem<lb break="no"/>bered that in the neighboring colonies the people are<lb/>
taxed far more heavily. In view of all these facts, I<lb/>
repeat the question, what are we to gain by a union ?<lb/>
Consider further, Mr. Chairman, the peculiarity which<lb/>

<cb/>

would necessarily arise from our insular position. All <lb/>
who hear me know that our Colonial Legislatures meet<lb/>
in the winter season ; and I ask hon. members, on either<lb/>
side, if they would fancy the idea of crossing the Straits<lb/>
of Northumberland in January or February, to attend to,<lb/>
their Legislative duties. Sir, I believe that this scheme<lb/>
has been devised, more in the interests of the ruling<lb/>
parties in the neighboring colonies, than in regard for<lb/>
those of the people. The Tilleys and Tuppers would fair<lb/>
have a wider field for the exercise of their talents and the<lb/>
extention of their sway, but it is our duty to protect the<lb/>
rights of those whose representatives we are, and what<lb/>
public man will not hesitate, ere he votes that our insti<lb break="no"/>tutions shall become nonentities ? We have been told,<lb/>
and with truth, that Scotland prospered after, and in<lb/>
consequence of, her union with England, in 1707. There<lb/>
might be some cogency in the argument, if, before the<lb/>
union, she had possessed free institutions ; but such was<lb/>
not the case, and she benefited by the change, and stands<lb/>
now among the foremost of civilized nations. The same<lb/>
remark is applicable, to a great extent, to Ireland, whose<lb/>
parliament could not levy a tax, until under the law<lb/>
known as " Poynings, " the proposition received the<lb/>
previous sanction of the English Cabinet. We all know<lb/>
that there has been for years an agitation for the repeal<lb/>
of the union, and we see at this day a people asking for<lb/>
a restitution of the privileges which we are invited to<lb/>
surrender. The mode in which the union between Great<lb/>
Britain and Ireland was carried through the Legislature<lb/>
of the latter country, I have no hesitation in denouncing<lb/>
as a gigantic piece of villainy. Millions of British gold<lb/>
were used in influencing the decisions of the Irish Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, in fact, so gross and patent was the corruption<lb/>
practised, that the Speaker of the House of Commons ac<lb break="no"/>quired the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Soubriquet</hi> of " the Undertaker " from his<lb/>
guaranteeing to the Government a sufficient number of<lb/>
votes to be obtained at certain prices. Here, thank God,<lb/>
we have a parliament which is, at all events, pure from<lb/>
any such taint. The argument, that we shall be mat<lb break="no"/>erially benefitted by forming a part of a country which<lb/>
will count its population by millions, finds no acquiescence <lb/>
in my mind, when I reflect on what Tell achieved for<lb/>
Switzerland against the most powerful nation of his time,<lb/>
and that Greece, under the protection of the leading<lb/>
nations of Europe has maintained her separate nation<lb break="no"/>ality. While the Mother Country remains true to her<lb/>
traditions, are we to be coerced by threats of the Stars<lb/>
and Stripes of the Northern States ? I have no fear that<lb/>
the Aegis, under which we have hitherto prospered, will<lb/>
be withdrawn, or that " the meteor flag of England " will<lb/>
be replaced in those colonies by that of the United States.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HENS1">Hon. Mr. HENSLEY</persName>. - Mr. Chairman, acknowledging<lb/>
that the resolution does not pledge the House to an ap<lb break="no"/>proval of an union of the Lower Provinces, I yet consider<lb/>
that the range which the debate has taken is within the<lb/>
legitimate bounds of discussion. Without offering any<lb/>
observations upon the probable consequences to the Island<lb/>
of a cessation of the civil war which has so long raged in<lb/>
the States, I see no special reason to apprehend a suc<lb break="no"/>cessful invasion of the Colony, by the disengaged forces<lb/>
of the Republic. That subject, I am, however, willing to<lb/>
leave to the more qualified judgement of the hon. leader<lb/>
of the Government and the Speaker, who are both military<lb/>
men. The extensive land frontier of Canada justified the<lb/>
Imperial authorities in urging upon its Government the<lb/>
propriety and necessity of that great dependency taking<lb/>
measures for its own protection against hostile incursions,<lb/>
but nothing has yet transpired, as far as my knowledge<lb/>
extends, which is indicative of any intention on the part<lb/>
of the Mother Country to abandon her Colonial posses<lb break="no"/>sions. The naval power of Great Britain is our best<lb/>
protection, and I believe that it would be as available in<lb/>
our defence as ever. With reference to the suggested<lb/>
union, I must confess that I cannot foresee the advantages<lb/>
to be derived from it ; but I think it but reasonable to<lb/>

<pb n="39" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_039.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">39</fw>

appoint a delegation, if for no other object than a discus<lb break="no"/>sion of the question in all its bearings. I have listened<lb/>
with pleasure to the able and eloquent remarks of his<lb/>
Honor the Speaker, and in his sentiments I fully coincide.<lb/>
The allusion he made to the personalities attributed to<lb/>
our debates by the Provincial Secretary of Nova Scotia,<lb/>
was not only justified by facts, but, it appears to me,<lb/>
came with much propriety from a gentleman holding the<lb/>
high position of Speaker of this House. Much as I regret<lb/>
the style which sometimes characterises our discussions<lb/>
of public measures in our halls of Legislation and the<lb/>
columns of our press, I yet maintain that we compare<lb/>
favorably, in this respect with our fellow subjects of the<lb/>
neighboring Colonies. I cannot but consider that an<lb/>
almost insuperable objection to the proposed union will<lb/>
be found in the difficulty of any Island Representatives<lb/>
attending in the winter season in a Parliament to be con<lb break="no"/>vened in either Nova Scotia or New Brunswick. When<lb/>
Dr. Tupper, in Nova Scotia, urged that union with Canada<lb/>
was not desirable, on the ground that his country would<lb/>
not have an equal number of Representatives in the Leg<lb break="no"/>islature, I would have liked to have asked him whether Nova<lb/>
Scotia or New Brunswick would be prepared to admit us<lb/>
to an equal voice in the deliberations of the associate<lb/>
Lower Colonies. Although the union between Upper<lb/>
and Lower Canada was arranged on the basis of each<lb/>
Colony having an equal number of Representatives, it is<lb/>
now sought by the latter to regulate representation ac<lb break="no"/>cording to population. In view of this fact, what guar<lb break="no"/>antee have we that, after having cast in our lot with our<lb/>
neighbors on the principle of numerical equality of repre<lb break="no"/>sentation we may not hereafter have that principle abro<lb break="no"/>gated ? I see many difficulties of a practical nature in<lb/>
the way of this projected union, in addition to those<lb/>
which have been referred to. The rate of taxation would<lb/>
require to be adjusted with reference to our financial<lb/>
condition, as distinct from those of the other Provinces.<lb/>
The holding the winter terms of our Supreme Court would<lb/>
afford matter for serious consideration, for it could hardly<lb/>
be expected that the judges should cross the Straits in<lb/>
an ice boat. While such questions as these are present<lb/>
to my mind, I still vote for the resolution which has been<lb/>
submitted, as being so cautiously worded that it commits<lb/>
members to nothing but the sanction of a delegation by<lb/>
whom the subject may be discussed, and our ultimate<lb/>
action can afterwards be had.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WARB1">Hon. Mr. WARBURTON</persName>.—Pleased as I have been, Mr.<lb/>
Chairman, at hearing the pertinent and lucid observations<lb/>
which have fallen from the lips of the hon. Sopeaker, I<lb/>
should have been more gratified if he had announced his<lb/>
intention of voting against the resolution, as I can see no<lb/>
necessity of putting the country to the expense of the<lb/>
proposed delegation. With that limitation, I heartily<lb/>
endorse every word of his eloquent speech.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. Mr. POPE</persName>.—I must say, Mr. Chairman, that the<lb/>
speech which we have heard from the hon. and learned<lb/>
speaker does that gentleman great credit, and I feel my<lb break="no"/>self constrained to record my opinions as being decidedly<lb/>
opposite to those enunciated by the Hon. Col. Secretary.<lb/>
Without reviewing the statistics which have been brought<lb/>
before the Committee, I agree in the opinion that the<lb/>
appointment of a delegation is but an act of common<lb/>
courtesy. I cannot but admit the force of the argument<lb/>
that our isolated situation during the winter months<lb/>
presents almost insuperable objections to our Legislative<lb/>
union with the other Colonies. Had we been always<lb/>
united with them, we might be content to continue the<lb/>
connection, but, as the case is, we should retain possess<lb break="no"/>ion of what privileges we enjoy. It may be said that we<lb/>
are a small country for the machinery of a separate<lb/>
government, but we would be in a far inferior position, if<lb/>
united. If representation is to be based upon the relative<lb/>
numbers of population, we, with a population of 84,000<lb/>
would have our influence merged in a union with Nova<lb/>

<cb/>

Scotia's 300,000 and the 200,000 of New Brunswick.<lb/>
Both of these colonies are burdened with heavy liabilites<lb/>
incurred on account of their Railways, the benefits of<lb/>
which we enjoy without the burden of their cost. As to<lb/>
the argument that the union would introduce capital into<lb/>
the Island, I cannot recognize its force. Capitalists will<lb/>
invest their means in countries which, from the extent of<lb/>
their geographical area, and the consequent varieties of<lb/>
resources, offer the amplest fields for investment, and the<lb/>
brightest prospects of advantageous returns. The prin<lb break="no"/>cipal dependence of the people of this Island is on agri<lb break="no"/>culture, and no man of realized wealth is likely to invest<lb/>
it in a country where, for half the year, his attention must<lb/>
be devoted to keeping himself and his cattle from freezing.<lb/>
We have resources which, in some respects, render us,<lb/>
small as is our territorial extent, second to none of our<lb/>
Sister Colonies ; and if, as has been suggested, the busi<lb break="no"/>ness of shipbuilding should decline, our fisheries may<lb/>
justly be regarded as a permanent source of wealth. I<lb/>
can see no advantage likely to accrue from our union with<lb/>
Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, or with either of them ;<lb/>
and it is but right that members should express their<lb/>
opinions on the subject to be discussed by our delegates,<lb/>
who, by the express terms of the resolution, are precluded<lb/>
from pledging the action of the Legislature of the Colony.<lb/>
If the Capital of the United Provinces were to be fixed in<lb/>
the Island, there might be some reasons for our advocacy<lb/>
of a political association ; but as that is not to be expected,<lb/>
I cannot imagine any benefits we are to receive from the<lb/>
change in our constitution.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>.—Mr. Chairman, I rise to express my<lb/>
gratification at what has fallen from the hon. Speaker,<lb/>
and, for one, I would not object to vote for the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of delegates if the representatives of the three<lb/>
colonies were to meet in the Island.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:KELL1">Hon. Mr. KELLY</persName>.—If I had a thousand votes, I would<lb/>
give them all in opposition to the resolution. What is<lb/>
the necessity of appointing gentlemen to consult on the<lb/>
subject of a union from which we can derive no benefits ?<lb/>
I heartily concur in the expressions of approval which<lb/>
have been made of the remarks of the hon. Speaker, and<lb/>
agree with him in his opposition to the scheme.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI1">Hon. Mr. DAVIES</persName>.—Mr. Chairman, this subject of a<lb/>
union of the Colonies has been matter of speculation<lb/>
among their public men for several years. While<lb/>
I have always been of opinion that benefits would<lb/>
accrue from the union of these Colonies, I readily admit<lb/>
the force of the argument drawn from the fact that we<lb/>
derive benefits from the Railways in Nova Scotia and New<lb/>
Brunswick, without being required to contribute to the<lb/>
cost of their construction. The proposed amalgamation<lb/>
would not, as far as I am capable of forming an opinion<lb/>
on the subject, afford additional protection to the Island<lb/>
from hostile invasion. While each of the Provinces<lb/>
referred to is burdened with heavy debts, our compa<lb break="no"/>tively trifling liabilities, not amounting, after crediting<lb/>
the value of our public lands, to more than about £50,000,<lb/>
will require careful consideration in any negotiations on<lb/>
the subject of our union. The people of the Island feel<lb/>
that our tariff is at present sufficiently heavy for the<lb/>
resources of the Colony and the means of the inhabitants,<lb/>
and one serious objection would be removed from my<lb/>
mind by the proper adjustment of our separate public<lb/>
debt in any scheme of union. My own opinion is, that a<lb/>
union is only a question of time—that is must occur<lb/>
sooner or later. Situate as we are at present, we are<lb/>
powerless at the Colonial Office on the most important<lb/>
subject of the Land Question, and it cannot be doubted<lb/>
that we would occupy a more influential position, if we<lb/>
formed a part of a great united province. The enlarged<lb/>
field of subjects of political discussion would elevate the<lb/>
minds of the people, and extinguish the narrow feelings<lb/>
which at present embitter the parties into which we are,<lb/>
and have been, divided. The assimilation of our currency<lb/>

<pb n="40" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_040.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">40</fw>

be that of the other __ would give an impetus to <lb/>
trade by facilitating business transactions. It is in the<lb/>
resolution of hon. members that our possession of a<lb/>
separate Government has been compared, abroad, to the<lb/>
placing of a large steam engine into a small canoe, and it<lb/>
does appear a paltry matter to assemble a legislature,<lb/>
such as ours, to regulate the disbursement of some £30,000<lb/>
or £40,000 sterling. The causation of our petty squabbles<lb/>
will have the effect of inducing many gentlemen of means<lb/>
to take up their abodes with us, as they formerly did,<lb/>
and I cannot see how a judiciously framed union can<lb/>
have the effect of diminishing our resources. At all<lb/>
events, I think it but right that we should accede to the<lb/>
invitation to be represented at the proposed conference.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.–It is so seldom that questions in this House <lb/>
rise above the influence of mere party interests, that I must ex<lb break="no"/>press my satisfaction at the tone and spirit which has character<lb break="no"/>ized this debate. In common with my hon. colleague, I have<lb/>
not adopted a decided opinion on the subject, but I agree with<lb/>
him that it is due to common courtesy that we should appoint<lb/>
delegates. This subject should be dealt with cautiously, for its<lb/>
results will affect not ourselves alone, but our childrens' children<lb/>
for all time; for let it be borne in mind that any steps taken in<lb/>
the direction of the union, it will be difficult, if not impossible,<lb/>
to retrace. I listened with pleasure to the remarks of the hon<lb/>
Speaker, which were worthy of his high position, and the frank<lb/>
and manly avowal of his change of opinion is ample guarantee of<lb/>
his sincerity. I have always considered that our institutions<lb/>
were not permanent, and that opinion is being daily confirmed.<lb/>
The hon. leader of the Government laid great stress on the<lb/>
probable result of the armed hordes now engaged in active war<lb break="no"/>fare in the States, being disengaged by the establishment of<lb/>
peace in their distracted country. But I cannot see why, if we<lb/>
owe allegiance to the Crown of Great Britain at present, and as<lb/>
I presume our union is not intended to dissolve that bond, the<lb/>
same means of protection will not be still available for us. Ad<lb break="no"/>mitting and regretting that our discussions are too often distin<lb break="no"/>guished by offensive personalities, I cannot assume the benefits<lb/>
attributed by the leaders of the Government of Nova Scotia to<lb/>
our union with that Province in the improvement in the charac<lb break="no"/>ter of our debates. Gladly would I hail the subsidence of the<lb/>
angry feelings which embitter the relations of our political men<lb/>
but when the Provincial Secretary of that Colony sees fit to<lb/>
rebuke us, I answer that he had better look at home–he need<lb/>
not go from his own country for specimens of gross and undigni<lb break="no"/>fied language need in the Legislature and the press of the Colony,<lb/>
amalgamation with which would, forsooth, purify and exalt the<lb/>
character of our public discussions. Although, in the event of<lb/>
the union taking place, we may not be bound in specific terms to<lb/>
the payment of the heavy debts of the other Colonies, yet the<lb/>
proceeds of a common tariff would be paid into a common trea<lb break="no"/>sury, and we should thus be, indirectly, contributing to the<lb/>
payment of the interest on their liabilities. As to the differences<lb/>
of currency which has been alluded to, that is a matter which<lb/>
depends on the state of trade more than on legislation. While<lb/>
my present impressions are adverse to the union, I am in favor<lb/>
of the appointment of delegates who, I have no doubt, will be<lb/>
cautious in what they say or do, remembering that this suggested<lb/>
union will bear a striking analogy to a matrimonial connection,<lb/>
which, however, pleased the parties may have been with each<lb/>
other, during their days of single blessedness, in many cases they<lb/>
find it desirable, but impossible, to dissolve. The report of the<lb/>
delegates will show what benefits our people are to derive from<lb/>
the measure, and when that shall have been before us, it will be<lb/>
time enough to discuss the advisability of our casting in our lot<lb/>
with our neighbors. The reference made by the hon. Speaker<lb/>
to the representative basis on which the two Canadas were<lb/>
united, has great weight in my mind. At the time of the con<lb break="no"/>solidation of that union, the population of the Lower Provinces<lb/>
was in excess of that of the Upper– but numerical equality of<lb/>
representatives was decided on. But now, when the proportion<lb/>
was reversed, the Upper Canadians are seeking to have the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of representation according to population, the Lower<lb/>
Province objects to this as involving a breach of the conditions<lb/>
on which the union was formed. At present, we have the<lb/>
largest representation of any country, with the legislative statis<lb break="no"/>tics of which I am acquainted. We have 1 representative to every<lb/>

<cb/>

of the population, and, if united, as the scale of represen<lb break="no"/>tation existing in the neighboring Provinces, instead of thirty<lb/>
members in the Assembly, we would not be awarded more than<lb/>
thirteen. The argument that our comparatively small represen<lb break="no"/>tation in the United Legislature could ensure our local interests,<lb/>
by turning the scale as occasion might require between the<lb/>
members from New Bruncwick and Nova Scotia, militates<lb/>
against the principle of union, and would place us in a position<lb/>
not very dignified. Besides, the similarity and almost identify<lb/>
of interests of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick would<lb/>
our shifting position of very little moment to set Legislature<lb/>
If we were territorially connected with those<lb/>
Provinces, I would support the union, for although their Rail<lb break="no"/>ways have imposed heavy burdens on their resources, still their<lb/>
people receive vast benefits from, and all the money expanded<lb/>
on their construction is spent among themselves.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Mr HOWLAN</persName>, I cannot conceive, what benefits we are likely <lb/>
to receive from the political amalgamation of our 80,000 people<lb/>
with 600,000. We have been ridiculed on account of our inferi<lb break="no"/>ority in territorial area, and amount of population, and I do not<lb/>
believe that the Union suggested would give any addition to the<lb/>
rights which we at present possess. It becomes the duty of<lb/>
any legislature to deliberate seriously are they surrender the<lb/>
parliament of their country, and the privileges of its people. It<lb/>
is true, that we do not possess the same amount of talent that is<lb/>
to be found in the larger population of our sister Colonies, but<lb/>
I maintain that we are every day manifesting improvement, and<lb/>
I fail to perceive how Union with Nova Scotia, and New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, will benefit us in this respect. The first result, say, con<lb break="no"/>dition of our Union with these provinces would probably be a<lb/>
tariff of 15 per cent, with a Railway tax of 21 in addition.<lb/>
The practical result of the schema will be simply the extinction<lb/>
of our Legislature, and of the control of our revenues, and tax<lb break="no"/>ation, and in my humble opinion this is but the first step towards<lb/>
a general amalgamation of all the North American Colonies, and<lb/>
I believe that Canada is holding aloof, merely till the Union of<lb/>
the Lower Provinces shall be consummated. As to the ___<lb/>
conjured up by the hon leader of the Government, that we might<lb/>
be subjected to an invasion by 600,000 men, when the civil war<lb/>
in the States shall cease, I think they would find more alluring<lb/>
arenas for the gratification of their propensities for ___, than<lb/>
this little Island affords. If we are not considered worthy of the<lb/>
protection of the mother country, as provincials, we have nothing<lb/>
to lose. It has been said that the tariff of the States is the<lb/>
cause of the war. Such is not the case, for the __ tariff was<lb/>
enacted under the presidency of Buchanan. The true origin of<lb/>
the present deplorable struggle is to be found in the initiation<lb/>
of slavery, and I, for one, hope that the North will wipe out<lb/>
the foul stain. But, Mr Chairman, to revert to the subject of<lb/>
the proposed Union, there is a strong argument against it, in the<lb/>
fact of so many countries trying to regain their lost Constituencies.<lb/>
Take Ireland, as an instance. Some years ago, when I stood in<lb/>
its Halls of Legislation once graded by the presence of such men<lb/>
as Grattan, Curran and others of hsitoric reputation, my<lb/>
thoughts were indeed melancholy, as I reflected on the altered<lb/>
features of the scene around me. But I need not travel so far<lb/>
for an illustration of my argument. Cape Breton lost her separ<lb break="no"/>ate Constitution, and in vain has she endeavored to regain<lb/>
it. The Honorable Colonial Secretary, has pointed our<lb/>
future prospects in gloomy colours, but he has not shown how<lb/>
they are to be improved by the Union. We would still retain<lb/>
our agriculture, and our fisheries. The latter will in a few years<lb/>
be the greatest source of our prosperity. Already we had every<lb/>
summer 1200 or 1400 sail carrying away vast amounts of<lb/>
wealth from our shores to enrich a town built on a barren rock.<lb/>
Before I sit down, I must allude to the reference made by the<lb/>
Hon Col. Secretary to the religious ___ existing in our<lb/>
midst. History will record, and posterity will believe that __<lb/>
member was the first to throw the ___ of religious __<lb/>
among a once united people. The hon. member then submitted<lb/>
the following amendment, which was ___ by the Hon Mr<lb/>
Warburton :<lb/> </p> 

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That it is expedient under present circumstances, to <lb/>
appoint delegates to confer with those who may be appointed by<lb/>
the Governments of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick for the<lb/>
purpose of discovering the expediency of a union of the __<lb/>
Provinces, &amp;c.<lb/></p>

<pb n="41" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_041.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">41</fw> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName> - I have listened to the arguments very ably <lb/>
put before the Committee, and I must say that my opinions<lb/>
remain unchanged from what they were last year. I still<lb/>
hold to the view that it would not be well for us to be unifed<lb/>
with the larger Provinces. It is ??? should we go into<lb/>
the union, and find it did not meet our expectations, whether<lb/>
we could get our independence again. Some appear to think<lb/>
that union would be the means of allaying the little animosi<lb break="no"/>ties which exist in our community. Larger countries do not<lb/>
seem to be exempt from these more than our own, for I was<lb/>
just reading the other day of an election in some part of<lb/>
England, and even there great difficulties were experienced<lb/>
on this very point ; consequently, I believe it to be a mis<lb break="no"/>taken view that small places alone are disturbed by such<lb/>
feelings. In the old country, candidates are sometimes<lb/>
pelted with brickbats and rotten eggs ; now, Sir, we have<lb/>
scarcely come to that in our little Colony. Were the Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces united, they would each probably require to be<lb/>
divided into municipalities ; and in electing the officers for<lb/>
such, the same feelings would likely arise which are com<lb break="no"/>plained of at present. I also believe that in the event of a<lb/>
union the taxation would be almost doubled. Deciding upon<lb/>
the seat of Government would likewise be a difficulty ; and<lb/>
however the question might be settled, we could scarcely ex<lb break="no"/>pect that the capital would be on this Island. I am opposed<lb/>
to union, still I think it would be treating the other Colonies<lb/>
with sparcely proper courtesy not to accede to the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of a delegation.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MONT1">Mr. MONTGOMERY</persName> - I will support the resolution author<lb break="no"/>izing the appointment of delegates, but only on condition<lb/>
that they have no power independent of the Legislature. <lb/>
They should only, as it were, spy out the land, and report to<lb/>
this House. It is because the resolution merely contemplates<lb/>
this that I do not object to it.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACA1">Hon. Mr McAULAY</persName> read the amendment proposed by Mr <lb/>
Howlan, and objected to it, because it was so worded as to <lb/>
say that this House would not agree to union on any terms. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HASL1">Mr HASLAM</persName>. -Mr Chairman, we are only, as it were, <lb/>
reasoning on the proposal of our sister Colonies—only desir<lb break="no"/>ing to obtain information as to what terms they would agree <lb/>
to take us into a union, and for this purpose the resolution <lb/>
is very cautiously worded. The delegates will only be re<lb break="no"/>quired to meet those appointed by the other Provinces, listen <lb/>
to their suggestions, and report again to this Legislature.<lb/>
When we look at the debt of Nova Scotia end New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, it appears to me that we should hesitate before we <lb/>
enter into a union. Whatever advantage we might gain from <lb/>
it, it is evident that we could obtain very little more benefit <lb/>
from their railways than at present. It costs a considerable <lb/>
sum to convey our mails here in the winter season, an ex<lb break="no"/>pense which we wold probably have to still bear though a<lb/>
union were consummated. We might derive the benefit of<lb/>
an increase of trade, but this would not amount to much ;<lb/>
therefore, taking a view of the whole case, I think we ought<lb/>
to be careful how we act in this matter. As to the religious<lb/>
bickerings alluded to by former speakers, they have been<lb/>
got up for a certain purpose, and may not continue for any<lb/>
length of time. I detest them, and say that they have no<lb/>
business in the halls of legislation. They are extraneous<lb/>
matter in this debate, and should not be allowed to weigh<lb/>
our decisions on this question. I differ with the hon. Col.<lb/>
Secretary in thinking that a union would increase our<lb/>
capital. I believe we would still have to depend on our own<lb/>
resources. We ought to be cautions how we proceed,<lb/>
but I can see no difficulty in the way of supporting the<lb/>
resolution proposed by the hon. leader of the Government.<lb/>
These Colonies are undoubtedly destined to become a great<lb/>
country ; and should a union, after mature consideration, be<lb/>
deemed advisable, I would be prepared to fall in with the<lb/>
movement.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon Mr COLES</persName> again spoke at considerable length. He <lb/>
said that be had been listening to the arguments of the <lb/>
different speakers, and had come to the conclusion that to <lb/>
authorize the appointment of delegates would be a bogus <lb/>
affair, as it appeared that not more than one hon. member or <lb/>
two were at all in favor of union. The hon. Colonial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary was the only one who entirely approved of it. Now, <lb/>
what end would it serve to appoint delegates if we were de<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

termined not to enter into a union. It has been argued that<lb/>
we should send delegates as a matter of courtesy, but this<lb/>
was too serious a question for more forms. The other Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces seemed to have resolved on union whether we want<lb/>
into it or not, so that means unions we were prepared to go the<lb/>
whole course. We had better decline to appoint delegates. It<lb/>
had been stated that a delegation would be the means of ob<lb break="no"/>taining information. This was a very weak arguement, for<lb/>
we already know exactly the state of the other Colonies. By<lb/>
sending delegates, we might be thought to commit ourselves<lb/>
to union ; he therefore thought it a safer course to support<lb/>
the amendment proposed by the hon. member for Cascumpeo..<lb/>
When he (Mr C.) spoke in the morning, he saw no serious objec<lb break="no"/>tion to the resolution proposed by the hon. leader of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, but then he was not aware that hon. members were<lb/>
so unanimously opposed to giving up our Legislature. Our<lb/>
speeches would probably be referred to, so we might as well<lb/>
maintain our consistency, and vote against even the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of a delegation. Were it a federal union of the whole<lb/>
of the Provinces that was proposed, he (Mr C.) would more<lb/>
readily give it his support.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. GRAY</persName> replied, that this morning the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber did not seem disposed to make this a party question ; but<lb/>
it appeared now that simply because the resolution had been<lb/>
proposed by himself (Col. Gray) as leader of the Government<lb/>
- what was his duty to do on account of the communica<lb break="no"/>tion received from the Government of Nova Scotia-the hon.<lb/>
leader of the Opposition did not intend to treat it as an open<lb/>
question. He had spoken in favor of a federal union of the<lb/>
Provinces, but this was not the matter before the House.<lb/>
He had also stated that all hon. members, with one of two<lb/>
exceptions, were opposed to the proposed union. He (Col. G.)<lb/>
had not said that he was opposed to the union. If the other<lb/>
Colonies would agree to build the Provincial Buildings here,<lb/>
and engage to aid us in abolishing our landlord system, he <lb/>
might give it his hearty support. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. Mr COLES</persName> said a march had been stolen on the Op<lb break="no"/>position. We were told that it was not a party question, and <lb/>
was certainly so understood by the hon. the Speaker this <lb/>
afternoon when he delivered one of the best speeches ever <lb/>
given within these walls. The hon. leader of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, however, now threw out the hint to his supporters that <lb/>
the resolution was brought forward by the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WHEL1">Hon. Mr WHELAN</persName>.—Before the question is taken, Mr <lb/>
Chairman, I will say a few words on the subject; and in <lb/>
the first place, I have to express my regret at not having <lb/>
heard the remarks of the hon. Speaker which those more <lb/>
fortunate than I, have characterised so highly. Before en<lb break="no"/>tering upon the discussion of a question of such pre- eminent <lb/>
importance, the Government should have given notice of a <lb/>
particular day to be appropriated to it, and it is amusing to <lb/>
hear the disclaimer that it 1s to be considered as a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment measure. Never was a more momentous question sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to this Legislature; and since the Government decline <lb/>
to pledge themselves to it, the sending of a delegation to the <lb/>
proposed conference is nothing but a farce. I care not for <lb/>
the nature of the union whether it be Federal or Legislative, <lb/>
either will be absurd while we remain tied to the apron-<lb break="yes"/>strings of our venerable mother—Great Britain. The time <lb/>
will come when, as foreshadowed by the statesmen and poli<lb break="no"/>ticians of Britain, the Colonies will be cast off; and when <lb/>
that time shall arrive, they may with far more propriety <lb/>
than at present discuss the principle and details of a union, <lb/>
either Federal or Legislative. The anticipated invasion of <lb/>
hordes of hostile Marauders from the States is not likely to <lb/>
occur; but if it should take place, the people of Great Britain, <lb/>
not of this Island, would be responsible for it -and we would <lb/>
not be under the necessity of sacrificing our blood and our <lb/>
treasure in a vain endeavor in a struggle which we had no <lb/>
part in creating. The opinion that it would be advantageous <lb/>
to separate the connection which binds the Colonies to the <lb/>
Mother Countly is gaining ground in Britain, and if it <lb/>
should assume a practical shape, we would be as well off in <lb/>
our separate condition as we would be us a member of a <lb/>
Confederacy with the neighboring Provinces. These Colo<lb break="no"/>nies are as old as, some older, than were the thirteen which, <lb/>
in 1775, revolted from Great Britain ; but are we as prosper<lb break="no"/>ous as they? Is this lsland in wealth equal to the little <lb/>

<pb n="42" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1864-04-18_Page_042.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">42</fw> 

State of Rhode Island! Are these maritime Colonies as ad<lb break="no"/>vanced as any of the states to which I have referred! The<lb/>
answer is obvious, and equally so is the reason-it is to be<lb/>
found in our dependent position. It is simply a scheme<lb/>
mockery for us to go through the farce of phasing through<lb/>
the Legislature acts, the face of which meet the announced to<lb/>
us by the Colonial Minister after the laps of some 8 or 9<lb/>
Months. [illegible] particular instances to prove the<lb/>
truth of my assertion, they are too numerous and too well<lb/>
Known to hon. members on either side of the House to re<lb break="no"/>quire specific mention. If our Legislative and Constitutional<lb/>
privileges were as free and unrestrained in operation as<lb/>
those of Rhode Island, we would not be waking months in<lb/>
distracting matters which are more appropriate subjects for<lb/>
The deliberations of the Court of Quarter Session or a Vestry.<lb/>
If the proposed union would give us so much influence as to<lb/>
leave our Legislative action unfettered by the underhand<lb/>
intrigues and influence of the proprietors as the Colonial<lb/>
Office, I would support it; for here, with an Assembly of 60,<lb/>
and a Legislative Council of 17 members, any of our pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings can be set at naught by the Colonial Minister for<lb/>
the time being, who knows nothing of the Colony. The<lb/>
present position of our legislature, representing but some<lb/>
80,000 people, is powerless against the secret influence of<lb/>
the proprietors at the Colonial Office. The style of the<lb/>
remarks of the hon. Colonial Secretary earns from me no<lb/>
tribune of respect for his sincerity, for he has not openly<lb/>
advocated a policy or necessity of a union; he knows<lb/>
full well that if we were merged in a large united Province,<lb/>
his occupation of stirring of religious opposition as a means<lb/>
of acquiring political power, would be, like that of Othello,,<lb/>
gone. The area of the British North American Colonies<lb/>
exceeds that of the United States, and we are, as far as<lb/>
resources are concerned, more advantageously situated to<lb/>
carry on Government than were the old Colonies at the time<lb/>
of the revolution. The imports and exports far exceeded those<lb/>
of the latter, when they asserted their independence and 1776.<lb/>
While our present relation to the Imperial Government sub<lb break="no"/>sists, any union would place of us in a position similar to that<lb/>
of Ireland and Cape Breton. Previously to 1772, Ireland<lb/>
had her own King, Lords and Commons -her commerce in<lb break="no"/>creased, and it until her Legislature was corrupted, her pros<lb break="no"/>perity was steadily advancing. The Colonial Office acts<lb/>
towards us on the presumption that the Island is under the<lb/>
absolute control of the proprietors, and the idea of George<lb break="no"/>town, Summerside, or St. Eleanor's, being independent of<lb/>
our legislative control is not more absurd than the supposi<lb break="no"/>tion That we will be allowed the reality of representative<lb/>
institutions, while in our isolated condition we are bound by<lb/>
the data of a Colonial Minister, in whose appointment we<lb/>
have no voice, and who can treat our remonstrances with<lb/>
disdain. Without subjecting myself to the charge of dis<lb break="no"/>loyalty, (for I wish to continue the connection with the<lb/>
brightest crown which ever graced the brow of the monarch)<lb/>
I repeat, that while the price of irresponsible interference in<lb/>
our affairs is continued, annexation to any foreign power<lb/>
would be preferable to the insulting mockery by which the<lb/>
people of this Island, slaves to Sir Samuel Cunard and others<lb/>
of the proprietors, are told that they have the right of self-<lb break="yes"/>government. If the truth of my assertion is disputed, I ask<lb/>
any hon. member, it he will tell the country that our Legis<lb break="no"/>lation use a operative to settle the main question within the<lb/>
consent of the gentleman I am named. The resolution<lb/>
would not be so objectionable, to my mind, if it embodied an<lb/>
expression of opinion for or against the union: but the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, I believe, are disposed to amuse the people and<lb/>
provide, at the public expense, a pleasure trip for some of<lb/>
their friends, as was the case last year. As to the exemption<lb/>
of the Island from the Railway debts of the Sister Colonies,<lb/>
in common fairness, it should be borne in mind that the<lb/>
Island to rise great benefit from them, and that it is not<lb/>
unreasonable that an honest acknowledgment of that fact<lb/>
should be made.<lb/></p> 

<p>The question was then put on Mr. Howlan's amendment, <lb/>
which was lost, and the original resolution carried. When the<lb/>
House resumed, and the Speaker put the question on the main<lb/>
resolution, Mr. Howlan again moved his amendment, and the<lb/>
House divided as follows :<lb/></p> 

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">For the amendment</hi> - Messrs. Howlan, Sutherland, Sinclair <lb/> 

<cb/>

Conroy, Hons. Kelly. Thornton, Whelan, Cole, Warbur<lb break="no"/>ton, - 9. <lb/></p> 

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">For the resolution</hi> - Hon . Col. Gray, Col. Secretary, J. C.<lb/>
Pope, Longworth, Laird, [illegible], Davies, [illegible]<lb/>
[illegible], Montgomery, Haslam, Ramsay, Mc[illegible], J.<lb/>
Y.,, [illegible], - 18.<lb/></p> 

<p>So the resolution was carried, and after the transaction of a<lb/>
little routine business the House was adjourned.<lb/></p> 

<!-- DL 2018-06-05 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--
<p>WEDNESDAY, MARCH 30.<lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. HASLAM presented a position from inhabitants of Strath-<lb break="maybe"/>albyn, praying for the establishment of a Small Debt Court in<lb/>
that locality.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Col GRAY obtained leave to introduce a Bill [illegible] to<lb/>
the fraudulent mathing of merchandise. He explained the<lb/>
object of the measure and showed how the interests of manufac<lb break="no"/>turers of good articles were injured on account of their trade<lb/>
marks being pirated by others, as well as purchasers imposed<lb/>
upon by the practice they paying a high price under the im=<lb/>
pression that they were procuring the genuine article.<lb/></p> 

<p>The Bill relating to the office of Commander-in-Chief was <lb/>
read a third time and passed.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Col. GRAY introduced a Bill to amend the Act, register<lb break="no"/>ing the [illegible] currency of P. E. Island. He said [illegible]<lb/>
to be an omission in the Act granting a charter to the Bank of<lb/>
P. E. Island, namely a clause securing those holding the paper<lb/>
of the Bank from the necessity of receiving more than a limited<lb/>
quantity in silver. The same omission had been made in the<lb/>
Union Bank Act, and he thought it necessary to have the Act<lb/>
regulating the specie currency amended so as to protect parties<lb/>
from loss, who might wish to have Bank paper changed, when<lb/>
about to leave the Colony. To remedy this, he now introduced<lb/>
the Bill which provided that no more than £3 of silver should<lb/>
be a legal tender.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Col. SECRETARY presented to the House the Trea<lb break="no"/>surer's Accounts for 1863 - referred to the Committee on Public<lb/>
Accounts.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. HENSLEY having obtained leave, introduced a Bill<lb/>
to repeal the Acts now in force establishing and regulating the<lb/>
rate of interest. He explained that the law, as it at present<lb/>
stood, restricted the rate of interest to six per cent, on landed<lb/>
security. He considered this unfair, for why should less gain or<lb/>
interest be allowed on money than on any other commodity ?<lb/>
For example, if a person by borrowing 30s, could buy a barrel<lb/>
of flour for that sum instead of at £3 on credit, why should not<lb/>
the individual lending the 30s. have a share of the profit ? There<lb/>
was a great variety of usury laws, but they were generally being<lb/>
done away with now in England and other countries where ad<lb break="no"/>vances had been made in political economy. He here referred<lb/>
to some of the absurd laws of this nature that had been on the<lb/>
statute book of England. The Bill, he said, did not contemplate<lb/>
interfering with any existing contract, but only those which<lb/>
might be made hereafter.<lb/></p> 

<p>The Bill was read a first time and ordered to be read a second<lb/>
time to-morrow.<lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. LONGWORTH, having obtained leave, introduced <lb/>
a Bill to amend the Act to incorporate the Union Bank of Prince<lb/>
Edward Island. He explained that the Bill was framed in ac<lb break="no"/>cordance with suggestions contained in a despatch of His Grace<lb/>
the Duke of Newcastle.<lb/></p> 

<p>On mation of Hon. Col. Gray, the consideration of the Des- <lb break="maybe"/>patches on the table was made the order for the day for Thurs<lb break="no"/>day, March 31st. Adjourned till to-morrow.<lb/></p> -->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>