<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-03-09"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-03-09">9 March 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1870, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1870"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="42"/>
</bibl>

<list>

<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_028.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_030.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_032.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_034.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_036.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_038.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_040.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_042.hocr.html"/>
</item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-14">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_028">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_028.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_030">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_030.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_032">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_032.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_034">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_034.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_036">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_036.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_038">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_038.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_040">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_040.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_042">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_042.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="29" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_028.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">29</fw>

<head rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, March 9.</head><lb/>

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="30" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_030.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">30</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="31" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_030.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">31</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre">Debate on the Address resumed.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WIGH1">Hon. the SPEAKER</persName> said he was an <lb/>
anti-confederate, had been one from the <lb/>
first, and none of the arguments used <lb/>
had in the least induced him to change <lb/>
his opinion. He was sorry that since <lb/>
last session the learned member for <lb/>
Charlottetown had strayed from the <lb/>
anti-confederate ranks, and whose able <lb/>
support they had thereby lost ; but the <lb/>
hon. member might have had good rea<lb break="no"/>son for changing his mind on this sub<lb break="no"/>ject. He would look for a moment at <lb/>
the finance side of the question. We <lb/>
were to receive £100,00, and for which <lb/> 

<cb/>

we were asked to give up the rights and <lb/>
liberties of the peoples of this Island. He <lb/>
would ask was much such a sum a sufficient <lb/>
compensation for the liberties, rights, <lb/>
privileges and revenues of this Colony ? <lb/>
Our revenue this year was up to £90,<lb break="no"/>000, and he did not doubt but then in <lb/>
two years more it would reach £100,000. <lb/>
If we became, or were now a part of the <lb/>
Dominion, we would then have a uni<lb break="no"/>form tariff. Ours now was but 11 per <lb/>
cent, while that of the Dominion was 14 <lb/>
or 15 per cent. If our tariff had been as <lb/>
high as that of the Dominion for the past <lb/>
year, the revenue would have come up <lb/>
to that figure. Out of union, as we now <lb/>
were, with the tariff of this year, he felt <lb/>
that, according to the increase of popu<lb break="no"/>lation, in two years our revenue would <lb/>
be equal to the amount we would re<lb break="no"/>ceive, and that in ten years it would <lb/>
greatly exceed that amount. He would <lb/>
like to know to whom would this in<lb break="no"/>creased revenue belong? Would Canada <lb/>
put her hands into her own treasury and <lb/>
pay that surplus over to us ? In con<lb break="no"/>sideration of the loss sustained by this <lb/>
Colony in having been deprived of its <lb/>
public lands, it was proposed to allow <lb/>
us £200,000, which sum, if possible, was <lb/>
to be obtained from the Imperial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment ; if not thus secured, Canada <lb/>
proposed to give us the money herself, <lb/>
but he doubted very much if she would <lb/>
ever pay it. The amount of our indebt<lb break="no"/>edness, £150,000, had been incurred for <lb/>
a landable purpose. So much was this <lb/>
the case, he had never heard any com<lb break="no"/>plaints from the people respecting it. <lb/>
No, not even among those who were on <lb/>
properties for which the Government <lb/>
had been allowed to purchase at rates <lb/>
which made it necessary to fix the price <lb/>
higher than twelve or thirteen shillings <lb/>
per acre which was the highest price <lb/>
fixed by law for these lands. The coun<lb break="no"/>try was improving from one end of the Is<lb break="no"/>land to the other ; homesteads were being <lb/>
erected, and the people were contented. <lb/>
He could not, therefore, but conclude <lb/>
that the purchasing of the lands had been <lb/>
a benefit to the country. It was, he con<lb break="no"/>sidered, the duty of the land office to see <lb/>
that the lands <hi rendition="simple:italic">sold were paid for</hi> as the <lb/>
instalments became due ; of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment Surveyor to mark out and describe <lb/>
lands that were to be disposed of, in the <lb/>
different parts of the country, and of the <lb/>
Government to use their efforts to have <lb/>
them taken up and improved. By pur<lb break="no"/>suing this course our debt would be <lb/>
gradually wiped off, without the aid of <lb/>

<pb n="32" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_032.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">32</fw>

Canadian money. He did not doubt but <lb/>
that Great Britain desired this Colony to<lb/>
unite with Canada, but did not believe<lb/>
she would use force or compel us to do<lb/>
so against our will. Under our consti<lb break="no"/>tution, every man had freedom of speech<lb/>
and action, and as there were no more<lb/>
loyal people under the British flag than<lb/>
those of this colony, he had no fears that<lb/>
coercive measures would ever be adopted.<lb/>
Great Britain had no claims upon us.<lb/>
We paid our civil list, were buying out<lb/>
our lands, and had made provision for the<lb/>
payment of the Lieutenant Governor's<lb/>
salary. In this he thought we had acted<lb/>
prematurely. We should have tested<lb/>
the home government more fully on this<lb/>
question. However, as we had now to<lb/>
pay him, he thought we should have the<lb/>
privilege of appointing that officer.<lb/>
Having been thrown upon our own re<lb break="no"/>sources, we ought to be left to enjoy our<lb/>
own opinions. This colony was small in<lb/>
comparison with Canada, but, like those<lb/>
of the New Dominion, we were an agri<lb break="no"/>cultural people, and their products were<lb/>
similar to our own. Any market Can<lb break="no"/>ada could offer us were, like Halifax,<lb/>
easily supplied. We had had markets<lb/>
in England, Newfoundland, the West<lb/>
Indies and the United States, but none<lb/>
suited us so well as the latter. Since the<lb/>
repeal of the reciprocity treaty in 1864,<lb/>
we found the British market a good one.<lb/>
He did not know but that we had done<lb/>
as well since 1864 as we had from 1854<lb/>
up to that time. In all the markets we<lb/>
go to, except Canada, where our pro<lb break="no"/>ducts were taken, there we could pur<lb break="no"/>chase our supplies. In England we<lb/>
should buy our goods, because they took<lb/>
our products in return; while in the<lb/>
Dominion if we bought goods, we had<lb/>
to pay for them with the gold and silver<lb/>
which was required for circulation among<lb/>
ourselves. We were told that an inter-<lb break="yes"/>colonial free trade would spring up, but<lb/>
how, he was at a loss to see. When the<lb/>
despatches were laid upon the table the<lb/>
question would be more fully considered,<lb/>
meantime he would prefer to bear the<lb/>
ills we have than, fly to those we knew<lb/>
nothing of.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Dr. JENKINS</persName>, in rising to speak, did so <lb/>
under a deep sense of responsibility, and<lb/>
felt how unable he was to set the ques<lb break="no"/>tion before the public in its proper light.<lb/>
He had always been in favor of confed<lb break="no"/>eration in the abstract, but opposed the<lb/>
Quebec Scheme because he considered it<lb/>
was unjust to this Island. He consider<lb break="no"/>

<cb/> 

ed it an important question, and thought <lb/>
the committee should look at it from such<lb/>
a stand point of view as would enable it<lb/>
to see what its duty was. He thought<lb/>
all would concede that our entering the<lb/>
Dominion was a matter of indifference<lb/>
to her people. Canada would scorn to<lb/>
give us £200,000 to induce us to unite<lb/>
with her. When confederation was first<lb/>
mooted it was a matter of indifference to<lb/>
Canada whether we joined them or not;<lb/>
it was the same still. Canada, in this<lb/>
matter, was merely the month-piece of<lb/>
the mother country. The Dominion<lb/>
counted their revenue by millions; we<lb/>
counted ours by thousands. Our revenue<lb/>
would be about the fortieth part of<lb/>
theirs. He could not see that our<lb/>
entering into confederation would be<lb/>
the least advantage to Canada. The<lb/>
reason the 800,000 dollars was offered<lb/>
us, was simply because Great Britain<lb/>
suggested that she should deal liberally<lb/>
with the Island, and he could not see<lb/>
that it was fair to say Canada would<lb/>
take it out of us in another way, for the<lb/>
Dominion could not tax us without tax<lb break="no"/>ing her own people. In many parts of<lb/>
the Dominion they were already com<lb break="no"/>plaining, and even groaning under<lb/>
their municipal taxes, and no doubt they<lb/>
would resist any undue increase in their<lb/>
tariff. He believed the holding of those<lb/>
colonies was a source of weakness to<lb/>
Great Britain, and the means through<lb/>
which the United States caused her<lb/>
much annoyance; and that if she should<lb/>
even be forced to protect these North<lb/>
American colonies against the United<lb/>
States, it would cost an immense loss of<lb/>
blood and treasure; and even then he<lb/>
doubted it it could be successfully done.<lb/>
Great Britain seemed to say to the col<lb break="no"/>onies, "you have grown to your man<lb break="no"/>hood. It is dangerous for us to hold you<lb/>
any longer; we will allow you to do for<lb/>
yourselves." It was a step toward in<lb break="no"/>dependence, and one that would even<lb break="no"/>tually lead to annexation. He did not<lb/>
intend to enter minutely into the<lb/>
financial part of the argument, but would<lb/>
merely say that, assuming we were, by<lb/>
the terms, to lose something, he thought<lb/>
it unreasonable for this colony to sup<lb break="no"/>pose it would be allowed to resist the<lb/>
Imperial policy. If we did not unite and<lb/>
become a province of Canada, we would<lb/>
be tacked on as a dependency of the<lb/>
Dominion. It appeared to him that the<lb/>
people had been struck with a panic,<lb/>
and that the officers (he meant the govt.)<lb/>
should have endeavored to rally and in<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="33" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_032.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">33</fw>

spire them with new courage; instead of <lb/>
thus acting, the officers in command told<lb/>
the people to run from the imaginary<lb/>
foe–confederation. He came in contact<lb/>
frequently with the country people, had<lb/>
a firm faith in their good sense and in<lb break="no"/>telligence, and believed they were pre<lb break="no"/>pared to deal with this question properly.<lb/>
The present leaders of the people seemed<lb/>
to think that by trimming their sails to<lb/>
meet the popular breeze they would be<lb/>
able to command the ship of state and<lb/>
steer it into the harbor whither they<lb/>
wished to go. But candor induced one<lb/>
of the officers to admit last evening that<lb/>
the probability was the popular breeze<lb/>
would land him in the bosom of his own<lb/>
family. The time he believed had ar<lb break="no"/>rived when public men would have to<lb/>
take a stand upon this question. If we<lb/>
refused fair terms, he was persuaded a<lb/>
pressure would be brought to bear upon<lb/>
us. He would prefer that Great Britain<lb/>
should compensate us for the loss of our<lb/>
public lands, but if this could not be<lb/>
effected, he could see no valid reason for<lb/>
refusing to accept payment from the Do<lb break="no"/>minion. The idea that it would entail<lb/>
disgrace upon us to accept the $800,000<lb/>
was ridiculous.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName> said the hon. member for <lb/>
Charlottetown (Dr. Jenkins) seemed to<lb/>
think the people had been struck with a<lb/>
panic. It was not so, and the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber would find that the antis had as<lb/>
much courage as himself; not could he<lb/>
(Dr. Jenkins) prove his assertion. It<lb/>
was the mature and deliberate opinion of<lb/>
the people of this Island that to enter<lb/>
confederation would he to give up their<lb/>
liberty, and he would have the hon.<lb/>
member to know that the people were<lb/>
not so ignorant, or easily struck with a<lb/>
panic; neither would he find them ready<lb/>
to run from an imaginary foe. They<lb/>
valued their privileges and were prepar<lb break="no"/>ed to defend them. The hon. member<lb/>
for the city (Mr. Brecken) said that the<lb/>
game of isolation was played out, and<lb/>
that we could not expect to be allowed<lb/>
to remain much longer as we were. In<lb/>
a few minutes afterwards he said the<lb/>
government ought to make proposals to<lb/>
the Dominion, and if they were not ac<lb break="no"/>cepted we could fall back into our for<lb break="no"/>mer position. If isolation was played<lb/>
out, he did not see how it could be<lb/>
possible that we, after making proposals<lb/>
to Canada, could fall back into our for<lb break="no"/>mer position. The hon. member said<lb/>
also that after the next general election<lb/>
the members around this board would be<lb/> 

<cb/>

all antis, and that they would be an <lb/>
inferior class of politicians. This cer<lb break="no"/>tainly was not very complimentary to<lb/>
the people of this colony, eight out of<lb/>
every nine of whom were anti-confeder<lb break="no"/>ates. Did the hon. member believe that<lb/>
all the talent and respectability of the<lb/>
colony was confined to this small min<lb break="no"/>ority? The hon. member appeared to<lb/>
have arrived at such an absurd conclu<lb break="no"/>sion. That they were so incapable of<lb/>
judging for themselves he (Mr. H.) did<lb/>
not believe. He was aware an impres<lb break="no"/>sion prevailed, or was attempted to be<lb/>
created, to the effect that if the $800,000<lb/>
was received as an equivalent for the loss<lb/>
of our public lands that they were to be<lb/>
had by the tenants as a free gift. He<lb/>
(Mr. H.) endeavored to disabuse some<lb/>
people of this impression by assuring<lb/>
them that it would in no way alter the<lb/>
arrangements now in operation under the<lb/>
land purchase bill, but that the tenants<lb/>
would have to pay for their lands by in<lb break="no"/>stalments as they now did. He did not<lb/>
believe we, even if we were to join the<lb/>
Dominion, would receive that money.<lb/>
The despatch merely said they would<lb/>
use their endeavors to obtain it; and he<lb/>
felt satisfied the Dominion government<lb/>
would keep the question open for an in<lb break="no"/>definite period of time. This Island<lb/>
did not want Canadian money to buy<lb/>
out the lands of the proprietors; if the<lb/>
proprietors would sell, there was money<lb/>
enough in the colony to pay for those<lb/>
estates.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> said our position was <lb/>
different from that of Nova Scotia or<lb/>
New Brunswick. When confederation<lb/>
took place, they were from the first a<lb/>
part of the New Dominion, and the ex<lb break="no"/>ceptions which had since been effected<lb/>
in favor of Nova Scotia, and which were<lb/>
complained of in Ontario, could not apply<lb/>
to this Island, for if we were going to<lb/>
join the Union, we would be doing so<lb/>
for the first time. Nova Scotia entered<lb/>
the union and afterwards complained of<lb/>
the terms. Her case was therefore like<lb/>
that of a contractor who, after he com<lb break="no"/>pleted his engagement, demanded a<lb/>
larger sum than he was to receive. The<lb/>
hon. member should recollect that the<lb/>
powers of parliament were unlimited,<lb/>
and those power might yet be used to<lb/>
cripple us. In our present position,<lb/>
upon what were we dependent but the<lb/>
good faith and protection of the British<lb/>
government? With respect to isolation,<lb/>
his opinion was that it was played out.<lb/></p>
 
<pb n="34" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_034.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">34</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. MCNEILL</persName> understood the hon. member <lb/>
yesterday to say that annexation would take<lb/>
place unless we went into confederation.<lb/>
Now if such a consequence were to result<lb/>
from our keeping out of the Dominion, he<lb/>
would not be surprised if the United States<lb/>
would reduce their tariff in favor of this<lb/>
Island, for, doubtless, if we had free trade<lb/>
with the United States, very few persons<lb/>
would be heard favoring confederation.<lb/>
Notwithstanding all he (Mr. McNeill) had<lb/>
heard, he still saw no reason why he should<lb/>
not remain as we were ; for he thought it<lb/>
mattered little to Canada whether we united<lb/>
with her or not, for Canada, he believed,<lb/>
would eventually amalgamate with the<lb/>
United States. The hon. member for the<lb/>
city (Dr. Jenkins) said so, only he would<lb/>
like to see us unite first with Canada, in<lb/>
order that it might be the sooner brought<lb/> 

<cb/>

about. It seemed to the opinion of <lb/>
several distinguished men that annexation<lb/>
would, in the course of time, take place ;<lb/>
and if it was true that it could not take place<lb/>
until we united with Canada, then, if such<lb/>
was the case, he did not wonder that Great<lb/>
Britain felt some anxiety on the subject,<lb/>
especially if she had a wish to retain the<lb/>
colonies. He thought the offer for union,<lb/>
if we desired it, should have been made by<lb/>
us, but as we had declared ourselves opposed<lb/>
to entering confederation, he thought the<lb/>
Dominion should not have made proposals<lb/>
to us at all. An argument had been at<lb break="no"/>tempted to be drawn in favor of confedera<lb break="no"/>tion from the union effected in Germany;<lb/>
but he thought it did not apply to our case<lb/>
at all. If he understood what a panic was,<lb/>
he thought it was a feeling suddenly<lb/>
effected—something that took place very<lb/>
quickly—which he thought would not apply<lb/>
to the question of confederation, which had,<lb/>
in one form or other, been for six years<lb/>
before the people of this Island, who were<lb/>
as much opposed to it to-day as when the<lb/>
question was first mooted. Perhaps our<lb/>
yound men now in college, when they came<lb/>
to occupy our places, might not see so much<lb/>
danger in the connection ; and no doubt by<lb/>
that time it would be better understood.<lb/>
Public opinion might change, but at present<lb/>
it was entirely opposed to altering our<lb/>
position, and he felt convinced it would be<lb/>
dangerous for any Government to seriously<lb/>
entertain the question. Probably it was<lb/>
premature to provide so readily for the<lb/>
payment of the Lieut. Governor's salary,<lb/>
but he considered it was the last demand<lb/>
that could be made upon us, and perhaps<lb/>
none voted for it with more reluctance than<lb/>
he did. He thought that demand would<lb/>
yet appear as a blot upon Great Britain,<lb/>
whenever the history of the Island was<lb/>
considered, and the transaction recalled.<lb/>
Her statesmen might yet regret that they<lb/>
were parties to a demand which reflected<lb/>
dishonor upon those who made it. All we<lb/>
wished was fair play, and to be left alone.<lb/>
The force of argument which the confed<lb break="no"/>rates might have, and the influence they<lb/>
could command, we might safely meet with<lb/>
the unwavering fortress of public opinion.<lb/>
The people would refuse to accept of con<lb break="no"/>federation upon any terms until the British<lb/>
Government did justice to this colony ; and<lb/>
if that were done, our next duty wouldbe<lb/>
to see if a union was likely to prove a<lb/>
cordial one ; if not, it would be far better<lb/>
to keep out of it altogether. As long as he<lb/>
had a right to raise his voice in the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, he would maintain that this colony<lb/>
was unjustly treated by Great Britain.<lb/> 

<pb n="35" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_034.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">35</fw> 

They separated us from Nova Scotia for the <lb/>
benefit of the proprietors ; had made us pay<lb/>
our own civil list, and make provision for the<lb/>
payment of the Lieut. Governor's salary ;<lb/>
all of which this colony was now doing ; and<lb/>
it was also fast buying out the estates of the<lb/>
proprietors. It would, therefore, be ex<lb break="no"/>ceedingly unjust to force us to unite with<lb/>
Canada.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MCCORMACK</persName> thought the question had <lb/>
been pretty well ventilated, and when the<lb/>
proper time came to discuss the subject,<lb/>
he would be prepared to give his opinion. He<lb/>
was opposed to confederation, and repre<lb break="no"/>sented a district that was also opposed to<lb/>
enter into a union with Canada, and his<lb/>
intentions were to oppose entering into<lb/>
confederation as long as it would be possible<lb/>
to do so ; not could he understand why<lb/>
Canada should manifest so much anxiety to<lb/>
get this Island into the Dominion. He<lb/>
though it was a matter which concerned the<lb/>
people of this Island only, and Canada, in<lb/>
his opinion, should allow us to do our own<lb/>
work. He was satisfied we could manage<lb/>
our own little ship much better than they<lb/>
could do it for us, and thought if we went<lb/>
into the Canadian cradle and asked them to<lb/>
take care of us, we should receive a very<lb/>
severe rocking at their hands.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Mr. G. SINCLAIR</persName> said the protection of our <lb/>
little colony was a matter of grave import<lb break="no"/>ance, and caution should be used lest we<lb/>
hastily or unguardedly disposed of our<lb/>
rights. His opinions had not undergone<lb/>
any change from the first. He was opposed to<lb/>
it still, even in the abstract. The hon<lb/>
member for the city said isolation was<lb/>
played out, but he (Mr. S.) saw no occasion<lb/>
for drawing such a conclusion, or for making<lb/>
such a statement. Confederation did not<lb/>
originate with the Imperial Government.<lb/>
A proposal was made by Nova Scotia for a<lb/>
legislative union of the Maritime Provinces,<lb/>
and the hon member for Georgetown (Mr.<lb/>
Haviland) did not then regard the movement<lb/>
as emanating from the Home Government,<lb/>
but as one evincing the desire of some of<lb/>
the colonial politicians who desired a wider<lb/>
field and broader basis for the display of<lb/>
their abilities. To the meeting originating<lb/>
out of that proposal of Nova Scotia the<lb/>
Canadian politicians came, and they, by<lb/>
proposing a wider sphere than the Maritime<lb/>
Provinces as a political field, aimed through<lb/>
the movement at settling the dispute be<lb break="no"/>tween Upper and Lower Canada, and<lb/>
thereby had succeeded in having the two<lb/>
Canadas separated, and a stop put to the<lb/>
continual bickerings which took place be<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

tween them. He believed all the interests <lb/>
of the other Provinces would be much better<lb/>
promoted had they yet retained their former<lb/>
position, and had full control as formerly in<lb/>
the management of all their local affairs.<lb/>
Reference had been made to a panic ; but it<lb/>
was well known that the people of New<lb/>
Brunswick were induced by some such means<lb/>
to vote themselves into confederation, and<lb/>
he believed all would now allow that Nova<lb/>
Scotia was not fairly treated ; and, knowing<lb/>
as we did, that Nova Scotia had made so many<lb/>
fruitless efforts to free herself, and that<lb/>
discontent still existed in New Brunswick,<lb/>
what would likely be our condition in the<lb/>
future when such was now the case with<lb/>
those who were geographically united with<lb/>
Canada ? Our position was such that no<lb/>
terms could be offered to induce us to unite<lb/>
with the Dominion, or that it would be our<lb/>
duty to accept, which would be fair to the<lb/>
other parts of the Dominion to offer. He<lb/>
did not think that we should, even if going<lb/>
into union, accept of a fixed revenue. No<lb/>
man would accept of a position for a fixed<lb/>
salary where the expenses and labor would<lb/>
be constantly increasing ; neither should<lb/>
this Island, even if it was going into union<lb/>
with Canada. Our wants would increase, and<lb/>
with them our expenses also. If we were<lb/>
in the Dominion we would have to bear the<lb/>
fortieth part of their expenses for all<lb/>
general purposes, and if we looked at the<lb/>
difference between our indebtedness and<lb/>
that of Canada, we would find that ours was<lb/>
by £20,000 less than it would have been<lb/>
had we been, previous to this, a part of the<lb/>
Dominion ; hence, had we, after the union<lb/>
of the Provinces, been separated from the<lb/>
others, like Ontario from Quebec, we would<lb/>
have been allowed £20,000 less than was now<lb/>
offered us, and if we went on at the same<lb/>
rate, our position would be constantly im<lb break="no"/>proving. He thought that for several years<lb/>
to come we would not require a railroad,<lb/>
and therefore could live under a cheap mode<lb/>
of taxation. The country was yet in its<lb/>
infancy, and had but merely commenced the<lb/>
development of its resources, so that in<lb/>
twenty years time he believed the com<lb break="no"/>mercial and agricultural prosperity of this<lb/>
Island would be such that we ourselves<lb/>
would be astonished when we compared it<lb/>
with the past. We required to improve our<lb/>
facilities for trade ; to buy in the cheapest<lb/>
market and sell our products where they<lb/>
would command the best price. As to the<lb/>
advantages to be derived from a free trade<lb/>
with the Dominion, he saw little to encour<lb break="no"/>age us to hope for many benefits from that<lb/>
source. If the Dominion succeeded, we<lb/>
could ask to be admitted at any time. With<lb/>

<pb n="36" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_036.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">36</fw> 

respect to the $800,000, it had little in<lb break="no"/>fluence with him. He thought it would be<lb/>
a long time before we should receive it ; nor <lb/>
did he see what security or guarantee we<lb/>
had that we should ever obtain it. He was<lb/>
included to oppose confederation in toto.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> said it was difficult, <lb/>
if not impossible, to ascertain what the<lb/>
views of hon members were on the govern<lb break="no"/>ment side of the House on this question. <lb/>
He understood the hon member (Mr.<lb/>
Callbeck) to say that when he first saw the<lb/>
proposals of the "better terms" that he<lb/>
was in favor of them, and the same views<lb/>
were said to be entertained by Hon. Col.<lb/>
Secretary.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CALL1">Hon. Mr. CALLBECK</persName> thought the hon <lb/>
member must have misunderstood him.<lb/>
What he said was that he took the terms<lb/>
home and gave them a careful perusal ; and,<lb/>
after doing so, was convinced they were not<lb/>
just to Prince Edward Island.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> still thought the <lb/>
spirit of the hon member's address was, that <lb/>
he considered the terms favorable when<lb/>
he first read them ; at all events he (Mr.<lb/>
H.) so understood him. He had listened to<lb/>
the remarks of the hon member for Bedeque,<lb/>
and admitted that they had more weight<lb/>
with him (Mr. H.) than those of all the<lb/>
other hon members who had spoken, for it<lb/>
was obvious the hon member had studied<lb/>
the subject ; but still he must confess he<lb/>
could not tell to which side the hon member<lb/>
belonged, for, during the delivery of his<lb/>
able address, he first inclined to one side,<lb/>
and then to the other. But in his state<lb break="no"/>ments he led the committee into a few of<lb/>
the secrets contained in the correspondence<lb/>
which took place between the Government<lb/>
and the Canadian delegates. The hon<lb/>
member for Princetown stated that had we<lb/>
been in the Dominion at the time of the<lb/>
union, it would have made a difference of<lb/>
£20,000 in the annual amount we would<lb/>
have received out of the general revenue.<lb/>
But the hon member should recollect that<lb/>
the debt of Canada had been caused by the<lb/>
construction of important public works,<lb/>
which cost us nothing, but from which we,<lb/>
in common with them, would receive im<lb break="no"/>portant advantages. One of the chief<lb/>
complaints of Upper Canada was, that<lb/>
Lower Canada received more than her fair<lb/>
proportion of the revenue for her public<lb/>
works, and the same objection was now<lb/>
being made respecting the Maritime Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. If, as some hon members concluded,<lb/>
confederation or annexation was our<lb/>
destiny, and if the views of hon members<lb/>
entertaining such sentiments were correct,<lb/>

<cb/>

they would do well to study the constitution <lb/>
of the United states ; for if they did, they<lb/>
would find that each state must defray all<lb/>
state expenses by a state tax, and that no<lb/>
state received aid for any purpose out of the<lb/>
general revenue. Hence, confederation<lb/>
presented advantages superior to annexation<lb/>
in this respect.<lb/></p> 

<p>Adjourned for one hour.<lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">AFTERNOON SESSION.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName>, in reply to the <lb/>
hon member from St. Peters, Mr. (Mc<lb break="no"/>Cormack) who said he did not under<lb break="no"/>stand what Canada wanted us, stated<lb/>
that Canada wanted us to assist her in <lb/>
forming one united nation, extending<lb/>
from the Atlantic to the Pacific, without<lb/>
any hostile tariffs to obstruct trade, a<lb/>
uniform currency, and a connected postal<lb/>
service. There were reasons laid down<lb/>
by some of the ablest statesmen in favor<lb/>
of union, Lard Carnarvon, in a de<lb break="no"/>spatch sent to our Lieutenant Governor<lb/>
in 1867, stated -- <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"That in time of war and tumult, the armed <lb/>
forces of British North America should be one<lb/>
under one supreme command-that in time of<lb/>
peace, their commerce, their post, their great<lb/>
lines of communication, and with due regard<lb/>
to local usuage, their civil and criminal juris<lb break="no"/>prudence, should be governed by the same<lb/>
rules ; that an extended public opinion should<lb/>
be brought to bear on the settlement of narrow<lb/>
local controversies, and that the most import<lb break="no"/>ant affairs of British North America should be<lb/>
administered by a combination of the ablest<lb/>
men whom it can furnish - these benefits ap<lb break="no"/>pear to me so indisputable, so pervading, and<lb/>
so permanent in their character, that I should<lb/>
be wanting to my duty if I did not express to<lb/>
you, and through you to the community over<lb/>
which you preside, my earnest hope that no<lb/>
trifling obstacle will be allowed to interfere<lb/>
with their full attainment." <lb/></p></quote>

<p>The principles enunciated by Lord <lb/>
Carnarvon had been endorsed by the<lb/>
government which now wields the des<lb break="no"/>tinies of the British Empire, by its lead<lb break="no"/>ing men-Mr. Gladstone and Mr. Bright.<lb/>
Mr. Bright had been looked upon as a<lb/>
man who was anxious to get rid of these<lb/>
colonies, but this was a great mistake.<lb/>
Despatches had been sent out by the<lb/>
Colonial Minister, giving reasons for<lb/>
confederation. The British government<lb/>
wished us to unite, not that she might<lb/>
get rid of us, but that we might be no<lb/>
longer in leading strings, but become a<lb/>

<pb n="37" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_036.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">37</fw> 

powerful nation under the meteor flag of <lb/>
Great Britain. The London <hi rendition="simple:italic">Times</hi>, the<lb/>
leading newspaper of England, as had<lb/>
been quoted by Mr. Brecken last night,<lb/>
repudiated the idea of Britain giving up<lb/>
her colonies - Englishmen would shed<lb/>
the last drop of their blood in defence of<lb/>
these colonies. We had also the opin<lb break="no"/>ion of a statesman, who was even, if<lb/>
possible, more radical than John Bright,<lb/>
Mr. Forster, who said --<lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"I rejoice that the question of the colonies<lb/>
has been brought forward, inasmuch as it has<lb/>
made it clear to me that neither in England nor<lb/>
it the colonies do we intend that the empire<lb/>
should be broken up."<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>He (Mr. Haviland) did not wish for <lb/>
either annexation or independence. but <lb/>
to retain our connection with Great <lb/>
Britain. While we were under the aegis<lb/>
of Great Britain there would be no dan<lb break="no"/>ger of our being swallowed up by the <lb/>
United States, but if we retained our <lb/>
present isolated position, that result <lb/>
would be almost inevitable. It was not <lb/>
the glory argument alone that would in<lb break="no"/>duce England to retain her hold of these <lb/>
colonies, there was also the necessity for <lb/>
having a friendly port for her ship's in <lb/>
case of war with America. It was not <lb/>
boasting to say that Britain was mistress <lb/>
of the seas. The Americans themselves <lb/>
acknowledged than they had no navy that <lb/>
could cope with that of England ; and <lb/>
when the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Monarch</hi>, that took the remains <lb/>
of George Peabody to America, dropped <lb/>
anchor in American waters, she had been <lb/>
thronged almost day and night with an <lb/>
admiring crowd. When Mason and <lb/>
Slidell were taken out of a British ship <lb/>
by the Americans, England demanded <lb/>
them back, and sent the flower of her <lb/>
army across the Atlantic to be prepared <lb/>
for any contingencies that might arise. <lb/>
A great deal had been said about the <lb/>
Munroe doctrine, held by the Americans, <lb/>
but that did not interfere with us, it was <lb/>
only to prevent nations of Europe from <lb/>
establishing new colonies on this conti<lb break="no"/>nent. The hon. member from Wilmot <lb/>
Creek (Mr. Laird) had laid down the <lb/>
principle that the Dominion would never <lb/>
prosper because they had paid gold for <lb/>
some of their territory; but the United <lb/>
States was a prosperous country and a <lb/>

<cb/>

great part of their territory had been<lb/>
purchases. In 1808 the United States<lb/>
purchased the whole of the region west<lb/>
of the Mississippi, then called Louisiana,<lb/>
which included not only the present<lb/>
States of that name, but Arkansas, Mis<lb break="no"/>souri, Wisconsin, Iowa and the vast<lb/>
wild region of the West, for fifteen mil<lb break="no"/>lions of dollars. In 1818, the disputes<lb/>
with Spain were settled by a treaty<lb/>
ceding the whole territory of Florida to<lb/>
the United States as an indemnity for <lb/>
the claims of American merchants against <lb/>
that power. Five millions of dollars <lb/>
were paid by the American government <lb/>
to the claimants, which may be consider<lb break="no"/>ed the purchase money of Florida. New <lb/>
Mexico and Upper California were pur<lb break="no"/>chased from Mexico in 1848 for fifteen <lb/>
millions of dollars. They had also re<lb break="no"/>cently purchased Russian America for a <lb/>
considerable sum. The States of Ameri<lb break="no"/>ca would never have become such a great <lb/>
nation had they remained separate. The <lb/>
whole revenue that could be raised by <lb/>
the States before they united was only <lb/>
three hundred thousand dollars, although <lb/>
their population was about four millions ; <lb/>
while the revenue of the Dominion with  <lb/>
about the same population amounted to <lb/>
fourteen million dollars. If the Do<lb break="no"/>minion was going to come to grief, as <lb/>
had been stated by some hon. members <lb/>
why was it that the Americans were <lb/>
watching the course of events in these <lb/>
colonies so anxiously. The governors of <lb/>
some of the States had thought it ne<lb break="no"/>cessary to warn their legislatures against <lb/>
'what was now taking place in these <lb/>
Provinces. They knew that if we had <lb/>
not a bond of union, we would be like <lb/>
the bundle of sticks—very weak when <lb/>
separated, and likely soon to join the <lb/>
Republic. Governor Chamberlain, of <lb/>
the State of Maine, had made use of the <lb/>
following language to his legislature: — <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The effort is now made in the British <lb/>
Parliament to effect the consolidation of the <lb/>
Provinces. If it is successful, the result cannot<lb/>
but be injurious to us. The friends of this<lb/>
country in the Provinces are earnestly oppos<lb break="no"/>ing the scheme. It is a matter of more concern<lb/>
to us than may appear at first sight, and I can<lb break="no"/>not fail to press the subject upon your attention,<lb/>
not doubting that you will see occasion to make<lb/>
such remonstrance as you are able, and to secure<lb/>

<pb n="38" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_038.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">38</fw>  

the most potent disuasions of the United States <lb/>
Government." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>The speech of Senator Sumner had <lb/>
ended in a fizzle, but it had put the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of Great Britain on their mettle, and<lb/>
they had stated that they were prepared<lb/>
to defend their Government in the posi<lb break="no"/>tion she had taken on the Alabama ques<lb break="no"/>tion. One of the greatest statesmen of<lb/>
America, Secretary Seward, gave the<lb/>
following as his opinion of British<lb/>
America :—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Hitherto, he says, "in common with many <lb/>
of my countrymen, I have thought Canada, or,<lb/>
to speak more properly British America, a<lb/>
mere strip lying north of the United States,<lb/>
easily detachable from the parent state, but in<lb break="no"/>capable of maintaining itself, and, therefore,<lb/>
ultimately, nay, right soon to be taken in by the<lb/>
Federal Union, without materially changing or<lb/>
affecting its condition. <hi rendition="simple:italic">I have dropped this<lb/>
opinion as a national conceit</hi>. I see in B. N.<lb/>
America, reaching, as it does, across the conti<lb break="no"/>nent, from the shores of Labrador and New<lb break="no"/>foundland to the Pacific, and occupying a con<lb break="no"/>siderable belt of the temperate zone, traversed<lb/>
equally with the United States by the Lakes,<lb/>
and enjoying the magnificent river St. Law<lb break="no"/>rence, with its thousands of islands in the river<lb/>
and gulf, <hi rendition="simple:italic">a region grand enough</hi> for the seat of<lb/>
a great empire. In its wheat-fields, its inex<lb break="no"/>haustible lumber lands, the most extensive now<lb/>
remaining on the globe, its invaluable fisheries,<lb/>
and its yet undisturbed mineral deposits, I see<lb/>
the elements of wealth. I find its inhabitants<lb/>
vigorous, hardy, energetic, perfected by the<lb/>
Protestant religion and British constitutional<lb/>
liberty. I find them jealous of the United States<lb/>
and of Great Britain, as they should be, and,<lb/>
therefore, when I took at their resources, I<lb/>
know they cannot be conquered by the former,<lb/>
nor permanently held by the latter.<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Those opinions of a great statesman did <lb/>
not coincide with that of hon. members <lb/>
who looked upon the Dominion as a <lb/>
narrow, insignificant strip. The Amer<lb break="no"/>icans had a great deal to do with respect <lb/>
to the disturbance in the North-west <lb/>
territory ; Americans had been settling <lb/>
there with the expectation that it would <lb/>
finally become a state of the Union. The <lb/>
New York Chamber of Commerce had <lb/>
sent their opinions of this great region to <lb/>
Congress :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The region of Lake Winnipeg, like the <lb/>
valley of the Mississippi, is distinguished for<lb/>
the fertility of its soil, and for the extent and<lb/>
gentle slope of its great plains, watered by rivers<lb/>
of great length and admirably adapted to steam<lb/>
navigation. It will, in all respects, compare<lb/>
favorably with some of the most densely peo<lb break="no"/>pled regions of Europe. In other words, it is<lb/>
admirably fitted to become the seat of a nu<lb break="no"/>merous, hardy and prosperous community. It<lb/>
has an area equal to eight or ten first-class<lb/>
American states. Its great river, the Saskat<lb break="no"/>

<cb/> 

chewan, carries a navigable water line to the <lb/>
base of the Rocky Mountains. It is not at all<lb/>
improbable that the valley of this river may<lb/>
offer the best route for a railroad to the Pacific.<lb/>
Red River, in the north, navigable in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with Lake Winnipeg for eight hundred<lb/>
miles, directly north and south, is one of the<lb/>
best adapted for steam in the world, and waters<lb/>
one of the finest regions of this continent.<lb/>
Along the shores of this lake for a distance of<lb/>
two hundred miles northwards, the mean sum<lb break="no"/>mer heat is equal to that of Bordeaux in France,<lb/>
and at Cumberland, on the Saskatchewan, the<lb/>
summer temperature is higher than that of<lb/>
Paris. The soil is for the most part a black<lb/>
mould of great depth and fertility, producing a<lb/>
plump and heavy wheat of from twenty to<lb/>
forty bushels to the acre. Potatoes, barley and<lb/>
oats can be profitably cultivated between the<lb/>
forty-ninth and fifty-fourth parallels of latitude,<lb/>
and Indian corn to the fiftieth. A hundred<lb/>
miles to the east of the Rocky Mountains com<lb break="no"/>mences a great coal-bed, sixty miles in width,<lb/>
and extending over sixteen degrees of latitude,<lb/>
to the Arctic Sea."<lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Had quotations been taken from the <lb/>
periodicals of the Dominion, hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers might say the descriptions had been <lb/>
too highly colored, but as they had been <lb/>
taken from those who were almost <lb/>
enemies of the Dominion, they would <lb/>
not likely be overdrawn. Since the <lb/>
Canadians had obtained this vast terri<lb break="no"/>tory, and the emigration fever was rife <lb/>
in Great Britain, it was probable the <lb/>
population of the Dominion would in<lb break="no"/>crease very rapidly ; and stalwart ener<lb break="no"/>getic men, when they took up their <lb/>
abode in a new country, soon earned for <lb/>
themselves a competency, and added to <lb/>
the material wealth of the country. <lb/>
Some hon. members had stated that if <lb/>
we bought any goods in the Dominion <lb/>
we would have to pay for them in gold, <lb/>
but statistics showed that we exported <lb/>
to the Dominion, in 1868, £107,478 19s <lb/>
1d. worth of our products, while, during <lb/>
the same year, we sent to England, not <lb/>
taking into account new ships, £103,764<lb/>
13s. 8d worth, and to the Republic only<lb/>
£48,031 19s. 7d. worth, so that our ex<lb break="no"/>ports to the Dominion were greater than<lb/>
to England and nearly three times as<lb/>
much as to the States. Woollen cloths<lb/>
could be purchased more cheaply in the<lb/>
Dominion than in Great Britain, for the<lb/>
manufacturers of Canada were now ex<lb break="no"/>porting to the old country and competing<lb/>
with British manufacturers, although<lb/>
obliged to pay a fifteen a per cent. tariff.<lb/>
Boots and shoes also, and ironmongery<lb/> 

<pb n="39" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_039.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">39</fw>  

of all descriptions were manufactured in <lb/>
Canada, and under confederation we<lb/>
should get all these articles duty free.<lb/>
A great deal had been said about bribery,<lb/>
but if the confederates were taunted with<lb/>
having received Canadian gold, they<lb/>
could retort by saying that their oppo<lb break="no"/>nents had received annexation green<lb break="no"/>backs, but he (Mr. Haviland) did not<lb/>
believe that either party had received<lb/>
any bribes. Confederation was only a<lb/>
question of time, but all reforms were<lb/>
agitated a long time before they were<lb/>
carried, because there was a certain class <lb/>
of persons who were always averse to <lb/>
change. He (Mr. Haviland) was sur<lb break="no"/>prised that there were so many members <lb/>
in the House who had not spoken against <lb/>
the principle of confederation, but had <lb/>
only objected to the terms which the <lb/>
Dominion had offered us. It was a <lb/>
childish argument to say that Canada <lb/>
would not pay the $800,000, as it could <lb/>
be definitely settled how and when the <lb/>
money should be paid, before we con<lb break="no"/>tented to unite. If hon. members were <lb/>
of opinion that confederation would be <lb/>
an advantage to the people of this Colony, <lb/>
and would be the means of extending the <lb/>
period of British rule on this side of the <lb/>
Atlantic, it was their duty to let the <lb/>
Dominion Government know on what <lb/>
terms they would consent, to go into the <lb/>
Union, and if Canada refused to comply <lb/>
with reasonable terms, the fault of not <lb/>
having these colonies united would lie <lb/>
with her and not with us. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> said that when this ques<lb break="no"/>tion of confederation was mooted a few <lb/>
years ago, he was one of the first to take <lb/>
up the subject in the press and show the <lb/>
injustice of the Quebec scheme. He was<lb/>
gratified at the time to find that the<lb/>
views of the vast majority of the people<lb/>
of the country accorded with his own,<lb/>
and on reviewing the position then taken,<lb/>
the only mistake he had to acknowledge<lb/>
as having made at that time was stating <lb/>
that the scheme had been got up by<lb/>
ambitions colonial politicians, whereas<lb/>
it was now known that it was the settled<lb/>
policy of the Imperial parliament. He<lb/>
desired to approach the subject with<lb/>
calmness and not be guilty of using such <lb/>

<cb/> 

unparliamentary language as the hon. <lb/>
member for Charlottetown (Mr. Breck<lb break="no"/>en) had used towards hon. members on <lb/>
this side of the House, when he referred <lb/>
to them as this and that man. Such<lb/>
language was inexcusable in one who<lb/>
prided himself on his parliamentary ex<lb break="no"/>perience. A union of these Colonies<lb/>
founded on proper principles, might, at<lb/>
some indefinite period in the future,<lb/>
prosper ; but the scheme had been too<lb/>
hurriedly prepared during the progress<lb/>
of the American civil war, when, as it<lb/>
appeared to him, the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment became alarmed at the colossal<lb/>
military strength, displayed by the Re<lb break="no"/>public, and wished to have a nation <lb/>
established on this continent that would <lb/>
be a counterbalance to republicanism. <lb/>
In this the Imperial Government were <lb/>
perfectly right, and he regretted that the <lb/>
treatment of the parent state towards   <lb/>
this Colony had been such as to have its <lb/>
call upon our loyalty responded to with <lb/>
coolness and indifference. There was not <lb/>
the slightest fear but that the British Gov-   <lb/>
ernment would always protect Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's subjects, for a proof had been given <lb/>
when they expended such a large sum of   <lb/>
money in rescuing a few captives in <lb/>
Abyssinia, and also in the case of Mason <lb/>
and Slidell. A nation that was to last <lb/>
throughout time should be gradually <lb/>
formed, and a great mistake had been <lb/>
made in forcing confederation on these <lb/>
Colonies in such a hurry ; and to this <lb/>
cause might be attributed the disturbance <lb/>
at the Red River and the disaffection in<lb/>
Nova Scotia. The people of this Island<lb/>
had opposed the Quebec scheme because<lb/>
it was unjust, and he (Mr. Reilly) was<lb/>
prepared to oppose the present terms, for<lb/>
they were better than those of the Que<lb break="no"/>bec scheme only in a pecuniary point of<lb/>
view—there was no difference in consti<lb break="no"/>tutional points. The people of this<lb/>
Island had been unjustly dealt with by<lb/>
Her Majesty's Government, in regard to<lb/>
the land question, and although they<lb/>
were still thoroughly loyal, yet if an<lb/>
attempt were made to force them into<lb/>
confederation, it would test their loyalty<lb/>
pretty severely. When the people of<lb/>
this Island were called upon to surrender<lb/>

<pb n="40" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_040.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">40</fw>   

their free government and joins a people <lb/>
with whom they had hitherto had little <lb/>
connection, they were justified in acting <lb/>
very cautiously. The system of repre<lb break="no"/>sentation in the Dominion Senate was <lb/>
unjust-Canada had an overwhelming <lb/>
majority. In the republic of America, <lb/>
the smallest state had the same represen<lb break="no"/>tation in the senate as the largest. The <lb/>
Dominion would have many railroads <lb/>
and other public works, for which, in <lb/>
the event of union, we would have to <lb/>
help to pay, while we could make no use <lb/>
of them for many months in the year. <lb/>
Instead of receiving the fixed sum of <lb/> 
eighty cents per head, we should receive <lb/>
a certain amount in proportion to our. <lb/>
taxation so that as our revenue increased <lb/>
we would get the benefit of it. These <lb/>
were some of the reasons which induced <lb/>
so many persons to avow themselves <lb/>
anti-confederates, and which he would, <lb/>
when the propositions came before him, <lb/>
enter into more fully. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Charlottetown had not been very <lb/>
courteous in designating those who op<lb break="no"/>posed confederation, " powder monkeys," <lb/>
" camp followers'," and " smelt fishers " <lb/>
When the union of Ireland and England <lb/>
was consummated, Catholic emancipa<lb break="no"/>tion was guaranteed, but over twenty <lb/>
years elapsed before it was obtained, and <lb/>
the land question was still unsettled. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> said that Catholic. <lb/>
emancipation had not been mentioned <lb/>
in the act of union between England and <lb/>
Ireland, but only promised by some <lb/>
members of parliament, and they had <lb/>
failed to carry it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> said that we had only the <lb/>
promise of a government which having so <lb/>
many difficulties to contend with, could<lb/>
not reasonably be expected to carry out<lb/>
their promises, were they ever so desir<lb break="no"/>ous of doing so. The people of this Is<lb break="no"/>land had so far worked out their destiny,<lb/>
and they could get along very well for<lb/>
the future without uniting with Canada.<lb/>
He (Mr. Reilly) would never agree to<lb/>
any action being taken on this question<lb/>
without the consent of the people.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> - Did the Queen's Printer <lb/>
allude to him when he said that some<lb/>
hon. member had called him (Mr. Reilly)<lb/>
" that man "? If he (Mr. B.) has used<lb/>
the expression, he had done so uninten<lb break="no"/>

<cb/> 

tionally, and would withdraw it. That <lb/>
hon. member was in error when he<lb/>
charged him with calling persons in this<lb/>
House "powder monkies."<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> understood him to use the<lb/>
expression.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> - It was applied to parties<lb/>
outside of the House. The hon. member<lb/>
had twitted him (Mr. B.) with using<lb/>
disrespectful language, but such a charge<lb/>
came with a very bad grace from one<lb/>
who, through the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Vindicator</hi>, had at<lb break="no"/>tacked female virtue, and defames the<lb/>
teacher of the Normal School.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> would not allow the hon.<lb/>
member to misrepresent him, or proceed<lb/>
without proof for his assertions.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> - The documents were in<lb/>
the library, and could be obtained if<lb/>
necessary. The hon. member had denied<lb/>
that he was in favor of confederation,<lb/>
but he (Mr. B.) could prove that his<lb/>
views on that question were the same as<lb/>
his own. It was amusing to see him<lb/>
stand up here and claim to be an anti-<lb break="yes"/>confederate, when every person knew<lb/>
that he had been playing fast and loose<lb/>
on the matter. It would have been<lb/>
more honorable in him to have given<lb/>
some credit to another journalist in the<lb/>
colony, who had been a much more con<lb break="no"/>sistent opponent of confederation than<lb/>
the Queen's Printer. The hon. member<lb/>
had referred to the Abyssinian war, and<lb/>
to the Mason and Slidell affair in sup<lb break="no"/>port of the view that the mother country<lb/>
would protect her colonies. These cases<lb/>
were inded evidence that Great Britain<lb/>
would not allow her subjects to be ill<lb/>
used by savages, nor her flag to be dis<lb break="no"/>honored on the high seas. The abroga<lb break="no"/>tion of the reciprocity treaty was a charge<lb/>
which had been brought against the Cana<lb break="no"/>dian government, but he (Mr. B.) had<lb/>
good reason to know it was the Ameri<lb break="no"/>cans themselves who abrogated the treaty.<lb/>
We had heard that when the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for St. Peters came into this House<lb/>
a political child, he came in an anti-<lb break="yes"/>confederate. True, he did ; and when<lb/>
we remembered that he had, through the<lb/>
agitation of this question, been enabled<lb/>
to defeat an honorable and talented<lb/>
gentleman, who had long served his party<lb/>
faithfully and well it did not much re<lb break="no"/>donned to his credit. Yes, that gentle<lb break="no"/>man, after his faculties had become<lb/>
impaired, he (Mr. Reilly) had bitterly<lb/>
attacked, and sought to deprive of his<lb/>
bread, though trained in this office and<lb/>

<pb n="41" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_040.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">41</fw>   

taken into his confidence ; and it was not <lb/>
until the clods of the valley had closed<lb/>
over one to whom he owed so much,<lb/>
and who could no longer meet him in the<lb/>
political field, that he passed upon him a<lb/>
feeble eulogy. There was no doubt that<lb/>
the hon. member for St. Peters had ob<lb break="no"/>tained his seat in this House because he<lb/>
was an anti-confederate, but what were<lb/>
his opinions now? His paper had been<lb/>
until lately pretty silent on the question,<lb/>
but it had hinted that it was this Island's<lb/>
best policy to get as favorable terms as<lb/>
she could, and enter the union; and he<lb/>
had heard a similar expression of opin<lb break="no"/>ion from himself.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> asked what he had heard<lb/>
from himself.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> - That as Hon. Mr. Howe<lb/>
had accepted the situation on receiving<lb/>
better terms for Nova Scotia, our true<lb/>
interest was to get the best terms we<lb/>
could and go into the union also.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> denied it.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> - He might deny it as<lb/>
much as he pleased, but it was neverthe<lb break="no"/>less true. Yet this was the gentleman0<lb/>
this was the hon. member who stood up<lb/>
here and told him (Mr. B.) that he ought<lb/>
to carry out the wishes of his constitu<lb break="no"/>ents. There was no occasion for such<lb/>
advice, for, though he (Mr. B.) had the<lb/>
whole power in his own hands, he would<lb/>
not vote the Island into confederation<lb/>
without the consent of the people. He<lb/>
entirely disapproved of the manner in<lb/>
which Nova Scotia had been thrust into<lb/>
confederation by her legislators.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> said the hon. member had <lb/>
travelled away from the subject under<lb/>
consideration to bring up matters con<lb break="no"/>nected with a newspaper, of which he<lb/>
(Mr. B.) had been part proprietor, but<lb/>
of which he had not been responsible<lb/>
editor ; but he could say this, that the<lb/>
statements referred to as having been<lb/>
libelious in that paper have been proved<lb/>
by the affidavits of parties some of whom<lb/>
were now in their graves. With respect<lb/>
to the Hon. Mr. Whelan, he admitted<lb/>
that he had been for a short time in<lb/>
that gentleman's office, but when there<lb/>
he had always held his own independent<lb/>
views. He was under no obligation<lb/>
whatever to Mr. Whelan. We were<lb/>
both at one time opposed to union, and<lb/>
it was he that receded from that position.<lb/>
After the step which Mr. Whelan had<lb/>
taken, much as he (Mr. R.) admired his<lb/>
genius and respected him for the valuable<lb/>
service he had rendered the cause of Liber<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/> 

alism in this colony, there was no course <lb/>
open to him (Mr. R.) but to oppose him<lb/>
on the question of confederation. It was<lb/>
not true that he had taken bread from<lb/>
the late Queen's Printer. The office<lb/>
which he (Mr. R.) now held, he had<lb/>
never solicited from the party. With<lb/>
respect to his silence on confederation,<lb/>
he contended that it was not his place,<lb/>
while communications were being held<lb/>
with the government to discuss the<lb/>
question. But he would ask where the<lb/>
hon. member for Charlottetown was now<lb/>
himself, if not on the fence? He had<lb/>
been a supporter of Mr. J. C. Pope's no-<lb break="yes"/>terms resolution, and here he was to-day<lb/>
speaking in favor of confederation.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> explained that when he <lb/>
supported the no-terms resolutions,<lb/>
though he did not then like the wording<lb/>
of them, it was because he believed that<lb/>
the Quebec scheme would be adhered<lb/>
to. It was said at the time that not a<lb/>
word of it would be altered, to the dot<lb break="no"/>ting of an " i " or the crossing of a " t ";<lb/>
and if that were the case he thought it<lb/>
would be dangerous to open negotiations.<lb/>
In voting for these resolutions, he con<lb break="no"/>sidered it advisable to let his consistency<lb/>
go, and do the best for the country.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName> said the hon. Leader <lb/>
of the Opposition had this afernoon, in <lb/>
justification of the purchase of the North <lb/>
West by Canada, called his attention to <lb/>
the fact that the United States had fre<lb break="no"/>quently purchased territory. But be <lb/>
(Mr. L.) would. ask whether the Republic <lb/>
had ever purchased territory where the <lb/>
people a! the place were opposed to the <lb/>
transfer? He thought the hon member <lb/>
could not point out a single instance of <lb/>
the kind. And more than that, he would <lb/>
ask when the Thirteen Colonies united <lb/>
whether any one of them received a sum <lb/>
of money to induce it to enter the con<lb break="no"/>federacy ? They could not afford such <lb/>
things ; they had no pampering mother <lb/>
ready to guarantee them loans to make <lb/>
purchases or offer inducements ; their <lb/>
very poverty was a guarantee that the <lb/>
arrangements between them would be <lb/>
founded on justice and fair play. The <lb/>
hon Leader of the Opposition had stated <lb/>
that the Dominion was the third maritime <lb/>
power in the world ; this! might be true <lb/>
of Canada commercially speaking, but <lb/>
where was her navy, or the funds to <lb/>
build it? One of the causes of the Red <lb/>
River rebellion he said, was the influx <lb/>
from the United States of immigrants who <lb/>
had gone there to stir up opposition to the <lb/>
transfer of the territory to the Dominion. <lb/>

<pb n="42" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_042.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">42</fw>

He (Mr. L.) would pit against this state<lb break="no"/>ment that of a greater statesman than<lb/>
even the Leader of the Opposition,<lb/>
namely, the Hon. Joseph Howe, who<lb/>
said that the North West troubles chiefly<lb/>
arose from the disaffection of the em<lb break="no"/>ployees of the Hudson Bay Company,<lb/>
who thought they would get nothing by<lb/>
the sale of the territory- that all the<lb/>
money would go to the shareholders of<lb/>
the Company, and their claims would<lb/>
probably be entirely overlooked. The<lb/>
inhabitants of Red River were not<lb/>
all half breeds and indians, but many of<lb/>
them were Scotchmen, who would not<lb/>
like to see their liberties trampled upon;<lb/>
however, though, they were all half<lb/>
breeds that was no reason why their<lb/>
rights should not be respected. If any<lb/>
government was to propose purchasing<lb/>
this Island irrespective of the wishes of<lb/>
the people, he (Mr. L.) could fancy how<lb/>
the [illegible] tones of the hon Leader of the<lb/>
Opposition's voice would be raised in<lb/>
indignantly denouncing the proceedings.<lb/>
The hon member had also referred to the<lb/>
importance of having a railway running<lb/>
through British territory to the Pacific.<lb/>
Hundreds of miles of country through<lb/>
which such a railway would have to<lb/>
pass were barren, and the whole of it<lb/>
covered with snow nearly six months in<lb/>
the year, consequently, the expense of<lb/>
keeping the line clear, together with the<lb/>
limited traffic it wold draw for some<lb/>
time, would make it no very desirable<lb/>
undertaking. He (Mr. L.) thought it<lb/>
necessary to allude to remarks several<lb/>
times made by hon members of the<lb/>
Opposition respecting the course pursued<lb/>
by parties outside this House, He main<lb break="no"/>tained that if any hon member wished to<lb/>
reply to statements outside, he should go<lb/>
outside to meet his opponent, and not<lb/>
come in here to make accusations under<lb/>
the protection of the sergeant-at-arms.<lb/>
Some gentlemen appeared to be horrified<lb/>
because one portion of the press had<lb/>
charged the other with "birbery and<lb/>
corruption."<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> said his remarks<lb/>
on this subject were in reply to the hon<lb/>
member, Mr. McNeill.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>.- Forty eight hours<lb/>
ago, before Mr. McNeill had spoken in<lb/>
this debate, the hon Leader of the Oppo<lb break="no"/>sition had referred to the charges of<lb/>
bribery and corruption made outside the<lb/>
House, and he (Mr. L.) would ask what<lb/>
right had the squabbles of the press to be<lb/>
dragged in here?<lb/></p> 

<cb/> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> said he had the<lb/>
right to speak in this House on any out<lb break="no"/>side question he pleased.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName>.- Let the press outside<lb/>
answer the press outside; but since the<lb/>
matter had been brought up here, he would<lb/>
venture to say, judging from documents<lb/>
which had been published, that a portion of<lb/>
the press of the Colony had been tampered<lb/>
with, he would not say through the agency<lb/>
of Canadian, but of confederate gold.<lb/>
When he used the expression confederate<lb/>
gold, he meant some inducement that caused<lb/>
a reversion of policy. Now, this was rather<lb/>
a serious matter, for if the press which was<lb/>
the fourth estate, could be tampered with,<lb/>
might not hon members of this House be<lb/>
dealt with in the same way, and then what<lb/>
would become of the rights of the colony?<lb/>
Hon. members need not be so very indignant<lb/>
about the alarm sounded by the press;<lb/>
bribery had been brought to bear in the<lb/>
case of larger unions than ours. Look at<lb/>
the conduct of certain members of the Irish<lb/>
parliament at the time that country became<lb/>
united with England. [illegible] had been<lb/>
the results of that union, and he (Mr. L.)<lb/>
contended that where money was held out<lb/>
as an inducement to any country to unite<lb/>
with another no union on such a basis<lb/>
could be expected to succeed.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> would call it bribery when<lb/>
any inducement was held out to a public<lb/>
man to make him swerve from his own<lb/>
opinions. But he did not think that if a<lb/>
person shose to invest some hundreds of<lb/>
pounds in a printing establishment, it could<lb/>
be called bribery. It was easy to under<lb break="no"/>stand the difficulties with which the press<lb/>
had to contend in this country. They took<lb/>
up a certain course and pursued it, and if<lb/>
the cause they advocated should break<lb/>
down, they had then to turn right round.<lb/>
The hon member for Bedeque no doubt<lb/>
referred to a certain case which had lately<lb/>
occurred in this city, where a bill of sale had<lb/>
been given. If [illegible] talents and ac<lb break="no"/>quirements had been bought over to advo<lb break="no"/>cate a question, then it would be bribery;<lb/>
but, on the other hand, if it were only presses<lb/>
and type that had been bought, it would be<lb/>
simply a mercantile transaction. He (Mr.<lb/>
B.) had great respect for a portion of the<lb/>
anti-confederate press; it had hitherto ac<lb break="no"/>corded him justice, and sometimes perhaps<lb/>
more than justice, but if he should now<lb/>
happen to differ from it, he felt assured that<lb/>
such divergence would only be for a short<lb/>
time. He (Mr. B.) could not agree with<lb/>
the hon member for Bedeque when he<lb/>
argued that the government had only met<lb/>

<pb n="43" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-09_Page_042.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">43</fw>

the delegates from Ottawa informally, or<lb/>
simply as private gentlemen. If this was<lb/>
the case, why, he would ask, was their visit<lb/>
referred to in the opening speech? The<lb/>
delegates were authorized to come here by<lb/>
a resolution of the Dominion parliament,<lb/>
and it was not very probable that they<lb/>
would consider their mission fulfilled by<lb/>
merely holding a conference with the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the government as private gentle<lb break="no"/>men. No, no; Sir George Cartier, the<lb/>
Hon. Mr. Pilley, and the Hon. Mr. Kenny<lb/>
were too shrewd and experienced politicians<lb/>
to lay themselves open to the taunt of Mr.<lb/>
Galt and others in the Canadian parliament<lb/>
that they had offered terms to the Island<lb/>
government which the latter would not<lb/>
accept. He (Mr. B.) presumed that the<lb/>
proposals from Ottawa were something like<lb/>
the terms which the delegates had been<lb/>
given to understand, by the government,<lb/>
would be acceptable. If not, it was strange<lb/>
that the Dominion government should waste<lb/>
paper in sending down these proposals here.<lb/>
If the hon Colonial Secretary had used the<lb/>
strong language in presence of the Canadian<lb/>
delegates which he had in this House, and<lb/>
the hon member, Mr. Callbeck, had told<lb/>
them it was better for this colony to wait<lb/>
until we saw how the Dominion succeeded,<lb/>
he (Mr. B.) felt certain we would not have<lb/>
had such proposals brought to our notice.<lb/>
Whether it was before or after the visit of<lb/>
the delegates that the hon member for<lb/>
West River took the terms home with him,<lb/>
lighted a candle, and in the silence of night<lb/>
studied over them until he arrived at the<lb/>
conclusion that they were neither just nor<lb/>
liberal to this colony, he (Mr. B.) was<lb/>
unable to say, but he hoped that [illegible] this<lb/>
time the Canadian gentlemen had received<lb/>
the benefit of his cogitations (Laughter.)<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. COLONIAL SECRETARY</persName> said that the<lb/>
hon member for Charlottetown had referred<lb/>
last night to the blind king of Hanover<lb/>
being driven from his throne, and instanced<lb/>
Britain's non-intervention in the matter as<lb/>
an evidence that she was in favor of Prussian<lb/>
confederation. The conduct of the British<lb/>
government with regard to that king, and<lb/>
the German question generally, was more<lb/>
influenced by the opinions of the Manchester<lb/>
school of politicians, than by any desire to<lb/>
see the consolidation of the Prussian empire.<lb/>
With respect to the taunts of the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion about the government, not h aving power<lb/>
to settle the land question, he (Col. Sec.)<lb/>
believed they were just as able to settle<lb/>
the land question here as Mr. Gladstone<lb/>
was to settle the same question in Ireland.<lb/>
Probably most hon members had seen that<lb/>

<cb/> 

the Canadian government had advertised<lb/>
for six schooners to protect the fisheries.<lb/>
He contended they would do no good as<lb/>
regarded the fisheries, and would be very<lb/>
apt to create a disturbance with the<lb/>
American government, and bring on a war,<lb/>
which might involve this colony in trouble<lb/>
and expense.<lb/></p> 

<p>Adjourned till to-morrow.<lb/></p> 

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>