<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1868-04-06"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1868-04-06">06 April 1868</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1868">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1868, Being the Second Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1868"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Patriot" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="137"/>
<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="143"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-06_Page_136.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-06_Page_137.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-06_Page_142.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-06_Page_143.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-11">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-06_Page_136">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-06_Page_136.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-08_Page_137">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-08_Page_137.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-08_Page_142">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-08_Page_142.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-08_Page_143">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-08_Page_143.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>
<div type="debate">

<pb n="136" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-06_Page_136.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">136</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACNEILL</persName>.-- Mr. Chairman, it is rather un-<lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

<p>It will not be denied that some of the people then broke <lb/>
the law, though in only trifling matters' but the organs <lb/>
of the Opposition magnified the matter, and endeavored <lb/>
to prove that the country was in a state of rebellion. <lb/>
What was the reason the association was denounced by <lb/>
these organs? Because it had opposed Confederation. <lb/>
If it had not been for the influence of the Tenant Union <lb/>
we would probably have been in Confederation to-day; <lb/>
if we had not opposed the latter vigorously, we might <lb/>
have been pushed into it. The tenantry were blamed <lb/>
for burning barns and houses, and for threatening to <lb/>
take the lives of their neighbours, because they opposed <lb/>
the proprietry system and Confederation. The Posse <lb/>
Commissions was turned out to assist the Sheriff, and a <lb/>
splenind affair it was. But there was no man who did <lb/>
not beleive that the late Government had some other <lb/>
and in view, when they endeavored to make matters <lb/>
appear a thousand times worse than they really were. <lb/></p>

<pb n="137" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-08_Page_137.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">137</fw>

<p>That Government must have known that they could not <lb/>
stifle public opinion by bringing the troops here; but <lb/>
we must make some allowance for the hon. member for <lb/>
Murray Harbor, as he had been brought up under strong <lb/>
descipline. He should remember that there is no simile <lb/>
between this Island and the antipodes, and that the spirit <lb/>
of British Americans cannot be kept down and trodden <lb/>
upon like that of Europeans. As the Tenant League <lb/>
was crushed, the people waited patiently till the next <lb/>
election came round, and then displaced the party that <lb/>
had trampled upon them. There was a great cause for <lb/>
the formation of this association, for it would be im<lb break="no"/>possible to get up such an organization as this without <lb/>
a reason why. Why did not the Confederate party who <lb/>
were high in office under the late Government, get up <lb/>
an association for the purpose of furthering their object? <lb/>
Simply because that object was unjust and unreasonable. <lb/>
The Conservatives when in power, could not be mistaken <lb/>
as to the condition of the country, for even the Spy in his <lb/>
report showed the stated of the people, and the effects of the <lb/>
rent-paying system. When we reflect that to man was <lb/>
given dominion over the creatures, and that no man has <lb/>
a right to claim exclusive right to the lands of any coun<lb break="no"/>try, is it any wonder that the law was broken in this <lb/>
instance? The troops were brought here to damage the <lb/>
character of the people of this Island as much as possible <lb/>
—to create the impression in the Mother Country that <lb/>
we were not worthy or capable of governing ourselves; <lb/>
and thereby to get this Colony forced into Confederation <lb/>
against the consent of its inhabitants. But I do not <lb/>
say that all the members of the late Government had <lb/>
this object in view. Such despotic measures and foul <lb/>
schemes had never been resorted to, even in unhappy <lb/>
Ireland on the eve of its union with Great Britain. I <lb/>
believe the hon. Leader of the Opposition was favor<lb break="no"/>able to Confederation because he thought it would be a <lb/>
benefit to his country; since the people were opposed to <lb/>
it, he thought it no harm to do evil that good might <lb/>
come. We know that Brutus said that he killed his <lb/>
best friend for the good of Rome; but I shall say no <lb/>
more about the hon. Leader of the Opposition, as he is <lb/>
not in his place. What had those members of the late <lb/>
Government who were opposed to Confederation in view; <lb/>
They must have had some object before them, because <lb/>
any person who raises his voice in favor of the people <lb/>
is put down by these hon. members as a political <lb/>
demagogue, and as one who wishes to make political <lb/>
capital; or, as the hon. member for Charlottetown calls <lb/>
it, political dishonesty. If the members of any other <lb/>
part had acted in the same manner, that hon. member <lb/>
would say that they were political scoundrels. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="142" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-08_Page_142.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">142</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> —No. We know that in <lb/>
 this Island every teacher who received a license had to <lb/>
 speak the English language, and the French teachers <lb/>
who qualified themselves for that office had to first learn <lb/>
the English language. This resolution provides that <lb/>
any teacher who will qualify himself to teach the <lb/>
French language, and who can obtain a certificate to <lb/>
that effect, shall be entitled to receive £5 additional <lb/>
salary from the Treasury, provided the district will <lb/>
make up the same amount. The French language is re<lb break="no"/>garded as the best, and many consider it well worth <lb/>
learning, and no scholar feels that his education is com<lb break="no"/>plete without he knows it. If we should happen to be <lb/>
driven into the Dominion, and any hon. members from <lb/>
this House should go there, they would find it would be <lb/>
an advantage to understand it. I believe all Ambas<lb break="no"/>sadors of the Crown require to understand French, and <lb/>
that their correspondence is carried on in that language. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.— Mr. Chairman, no doubt any educa<lb break="no"/>tion is incomplete without a knowledge of French, but I <lb/>
do not agree with the learned Attorney General that it <lb/>
is the best language, although I admit that in Europe <lb/>
every person is expected to know it. I doubt whether <lb/>
instruction in French, as spoken here, would be under<lb break="no"/>stood or regarded as French by good scholars in that <lb/>
language, for there cannot be any doubt but that, owing <lb/>
to the isolation of those who speak that language here. <lb/>
it must have lost among them much of its original <lb/>
purity. I am rather surprised to hear Confederation <lb/>
referred to as an argument in favor of the resolution, <lb/>
for, on that ground alone, some might object to it. But <lb/>
we may yet be brought into contact with our neighbors <lb/>
in Canada, and, if so, it would be well for our people to <lb/>
be acquainted with the French language. if it is in<lb break="no"/>tended as an encouragement for the cultivation of that <lb/>
language in its purity, it would be money well appro<lb break="no"/>priated ; but it would be well to know if it is wholly <lb/>
intended for the few French teachers of the Island. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName>.— I have no objection to do <lb/>
full justice to the French people, but I doubt the utility <lb/>
of teaching that language in our common schools, or <lb/>
that a large number will ever be required to go from <lb/>
here to represent us in the New Dominion. You know , <lb/>
Sir, as well as I do, that the French teachers, before <lb/>
they can now receive a License, have to first learn a <lb/>
language that is not their vernacular, and the Gaelic, <lb/>
people have to graft the English upon their mother <lb/>
tongue before they can become teachers, and these <lb/>
people love their Gaelic just as much as it is possible for <lb/>
any people to esteem a language. If this resolution is <lb/>
to be carried, I would like to introduce a similar one in <lb/>
favor of the Gaelic speaking people of this Island. for I <lb/>
think it will be admitted that they were on a par with <lb/>
those who have to graft the native Saxon upon their <lb/>
French. One thing I have observed is, that the French <lb/>
people of this Island use more words of broken English <lb/>
than the same class do in Lower Canada, or did when I <lb/>
was among them. The Gaelic speaking people are en<lb break="no"/>titled to the same privileges that the French are. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:ARSE1">Mr. ARSENAULT</persName>.— Mr. Chairman, the hon. member for <lb/>
Charlottotown (Mr. B ) is doubtful whether the French <lb/>
language spoken in this Island is French at all, and is <lb/>
doubtful if it is as good as that which is spoken in France <lb/>
or Canada. Well I do not know much about the French <lb/>
language as spoken in France, as I have never been <lb/>
there, but I presume it is the same language as is con<lb break="no"/>tained in books written in French and when we use <lb/>
these same books in our schools I do not see why we <lb/>
should learn good French ; and as to Canada I believe <lb/>
the French inhabitants of this Island speak the language <lb/>

<pb n="143" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-08_Page_143.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">143</fw>

as well as they do in Canada. In the second place he <lb/>
asks if this privilege is intended for French teachers <lb/>
only, but, Sir, the resolution does not apply any more to <lb/>
French teachers than to any other, so far as I understand, <lb/>
but simply to those teachers who will qualify themselves <lb/>
to teach the French language, and shall teach a class of <lb/>
not less than ten pupils in his or her school. Now, I   <lb/>
ask is there anything unfair when it is intended to apply <lb/>
to all alike ? or even if the Government allowance was <lb/>
given to teachers teaching the French language only to the <lb/>
French speaking people of this Island, when their teachers <lb/>
are as well qualified in the French language, as the <lb/>
English speaking teachers are in the English language, <lb/>
that there would be anything unfair in it. But when all  <lb/>
that is asked for in the resolution is a small allowance <lb/>
for an encouragement to teach the French language, I <lb/>
do not think any liberal minded gentleman will refuse it. <lb/>
The hon member for Murray Harbor asks what is the <lb/>
utility of the French language on this Island? and asks <lb/>
why not encourage the Gaelic as well? I will somply say <lb/>
this, that we sometimes hear French phrases used in this <lb/>
hon. House, and I am frequently amused at the awkward <lb/>
pronunciation given to them (laughter) for instead of <lb/>
pronouncing them with that soft accent with which they <lb/>
should be pronounced, they always use the hard, sharp <lb/>
English pronunciation. A to the Gaelic, we never hear   <lb/>
a word of it. If we go to the other side of this building,   <lb/>
where all the big volumes are kept, we will find among <lb/>
them a good many in French, but none in Gaelic.  Al-  <lb/>
though I am not an admirer of Confederation, yet, what <lb/>
do we know but at some future time we may form a part <lb/>
of the New Dominion, and I ask in what position would <lb/>
any of our Island delegates to Ottawa find themselves in <lb/>
if they did not understand the French language. When  <lb/>
a speech in that language would be delivered, no doubt <lb/>
they would like to be able to understand the language <lb/>
then. I feel pleased that this small encouragement is <lb/>
proposed to be given to encourage the study of that lan<lb break="no"/>guage, and only regret the number of whom it is pro<lb break="no"/>posed to be given is limited to twenty. I would prefer  <lb/>
that all our teachers would qualify themselves to teach <lb/>
that language, and thereby diffuse a knowledge of it <lb/>
throughout the Island. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>