<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1871-03-30"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1871-03-30">30 March 1871</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1871">
               <title>The Parliamentary Reporter of Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly</title>.
          <date from="1871" to="1872"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Examiner</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="283"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_276.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_278.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_280.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_282.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-07-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-07-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_276">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_276.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_278">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_278.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_280">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_280.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_282">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_282.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1871-03-30_Page_276"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_276.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">276</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1871</fw>
            
            <p>The
               
   
     <fw type="dateline">1871</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">277</fw> 
 
 great question of Confederation when first<lb/>brought before the people was not under<lb break="no"/>stood, but after a little while they carefully<lb/>considered it and understood it thoroughly.<lb/>Perhaps it were just as well that it was not<lb/>hurried on too rapidly, and that there was<lb/>given for fully considering it. It is now<lb/>altogther out of place to spend the people's<lb/>money is discussing such an important<lb/>measure as the construction of a railroad,<lb/>without bringing it before the people for their<lb/>decision.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <cb/>
            
            <p>Confederation was at that time the order of<lb/>the day, and the people passed a strong re<lb break="no"/>solution against it. If they had broken the<lb/>law we would be in Confederation to-day.<lb/>The people knew that if they broke the law<lb/>there would, in all probability, be numbers<lb/>of them shot down. One of the most in<lb break="no"/>nocent men on the Princetown Road was<lb/>hand-cuffed and brought to jail, but no charge<lb/>whatever could be brought against him.<lb/>Mr. Edmund Crabb having come out to his<lb/>own gate, was taken for a spy, pushed into<lb/>a wagon, and taken off to prison, for no<lb/>cause whatever. I merely make these state<lb break="no"/>ments to show that the actions of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of that day were calculated to<lb/>irritate the people to that degree. Some of<lb/>the members of the Government are mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Opposition with saying they are<lb/>not honest in carrying out the railway<lb/>scheme. I want to show that the people<lb/>have reason to be suspicious of the present<lb/>Government in all their public actions, and<lb/>that confederation may be connected with<lb/>the very matter now before the Committee.<lb/>It is true the Government are solemnly<lb/>pledged against Confederation for the pre<lb break="no"/>sent term; but if we get deeply involved<lb/>by adding a million of money to our present<lb/>debt, we shall all be compelled to pump to<lb/>to keep the ship of state from sinking; and<lb/>though we are pledged against Confedera<lb break="no"/>
            
               
               <pb n="1871-03-30_Page_278"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_278.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">278</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1871</fw>
        
        
     tion, my hon. friend from Bedeque (Mr. 
     <lb/>Howat), would be the first to square away<lb/>the yards to keep the ship afloat, if neces<lb break="no"/>sary. It matters come to that pass I think<lb/>we should be compelled to put into the Do<lb break="no"/>minion as the only means of saving the ship.<lb/>The hon. member for Charlottetown asked<lb/>us twelve months ago whether the sun<lb/>would not rise and the grass grow if we<lb/>entered the Dominion. I say yes; the sun<lb/>would rise and the grass would grow, but<lb/>our people would become the slaves of the<lb/>Dominion, this Island would become the<lb/>down-trodden Poland of America, and<lb/>a mere appendage of Canada and burdened<lb/>with a heavy debt. In forcing the con<lb break="no"/>struction of a railroad upon the country,<lb/>and involving it in such a heavy debt, the<lb/>Legislature would be going beyond all<lb/>bounds. I would be sorry indeed to do<lb/>anything which I would be afraid to bring<lb/>before the people at the polls, which would<lb/>involve the Colony to such extreme done<lb/>extent in proportion to our revenue. This<lb/>is one of the mos important measures, and<lb/>involving the largest amount of money ever<lb/>brought before the Legislature of this Is<lb break="no"/>land. The House has spoken a great deal of<lb/>time in discussing this, but it appears the<lb/>Government have no renounced the idea of<lb/>carrying the measure. Hon. members can<lb/>do as they think proper; but, for my party<lb/>I would be sorry to lend my vote to a<lb/>measure which would involve the country<lb/>to such an extent that it would never re<lb break="no"/>cover from the effects of it. I would not<lb/>disgrace the memory of those who helped in<lb/>clear away the forces by supporting a mea<lb break="no"/>sure which might be the means of the loss of<lb/>our constitution.<lb/>
            </p>
            

            <fw type="num">1871</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">279</fw>
            <p>[<persName ref="pers:CAME5">Mr. CAMERON</persName>]
     We hear a great deal said about 
     <lb/>Confederation in connection with this ques<lb break="no"/>tion; it has been stated that the con<lb break="no"/>struction of a railroad would be a step<lb/>towards it, and that it would infallibly lend<lb/>to it. Now, I fail to see any connection<lb/>whatever between the two questions. If this<lb/>Colony stands in danger of going into Con<lb break="no"/>federation, it is owing to the views enter<lb break="no"/>tained by the majority of the people, not on<lb/>account of the undertaking of a great public<lb/>work. If the construction of a railway would<lb/>entail a very heavy debt upon the Colony,<lb/>there would be less inducement for the Ca<lb break="no"/>nadians to make any effort to get us into<lb/> Confederation.
            </p>
            
            
            <pb n="1871-03-30_Page_280"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_280.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">289</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1871</fw>
            
            
            <p>
     MR. REILLY would, in reference to what 
     <lb/>had fallen from hon. members, first reply to<lb/>what the hon. member of Cavendish (Mr.<lb/>McNeill), had said, who in his observations<lb/>seemed to regard the railway project as a<lb/>scheme to draw the Island into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. From such a view he (Mr. R.), <choice><sic>di<lb break="no"/>sented</sic><corr>dissented</corr></choice>. Nor did he see what ground the<lb/>hon. member had for arriving at such a<lb/>conclusion. He (Mr. R.) never had but<lb/>one idea on that question. Nor did he be<lb break="no"/>lieve the Dominion Government felt dispos<lb break="no"/>
     
     
     <fw type="dateline">1871</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">281</fw>
     
     

     ed to come down to them with any new pro<lb break="no"/>positions. Nor if they were to consent to<lb/>unite with the Dominion of Canada would<lb/>they gain thereby. The Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment never intended to give anything to this<lb/>Island for which they were not to receive<lb/>more than an equivalent in return. Yet the<lb/>hon. member appeared to imagine that if<lb/>this Colony ran itself in debt, the Canadians<lb/>would, if they united with them, pay the<lb/>debt of this Colony, and out of pure compas<lb break="no"/>sion relieve this Colony out of its difficulties.<lb/>He thought there could not possibly be a<lb/>greater delusion. Would a union with the<lb/>Dominion under any circumstances produce<lb/>such a result? It was absurd to suppose<lb/>anything of the kind. The argument,<lb/>therefore, of the hon. member, would not go<lb/>for anything, for it contained an assertion<lb/>which could not be proved, inasmuch as it<lb/> was opposed to reason and common sense.
            </p>
            
            
            <pb n="1871-03-30_Page_282"
                facs="final/images/PEI_LA_Page_1871-03-30_Page_282.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">282</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1871</fw>

            <p>
     It have also been assorted 
     <lb/>that those newspapers under the influence<lb/>of the Government were employed to bring<lb/>about Confederation. To that he could but<lb/>say he thought if such was the care they<lb/>were fearfully neglecting their duty for he<lb/>read them all, but failed to notice a single<lb/>article in ous of them in favor of a union of<lb/>this Colony with the Dominion of Canada.<lb/>
            </p>
            
     
            <fw type="num">1871</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">283</fw>
            
            
            <p>[<persName ref="pers:DAVI1">Hon. D. DAVIES</persName>]
     On a former occasion, the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Cavendish (Mr. McNeil) at<lb break="no"/>tested to what he (hon. D. D.) had said 
     <lb/>
     about bringing the troops to the Colony. 
     <lb/>
     In doing so the hon. member had endeavor<lb break="no"/>ed to show that the object at that time of 
     <lb/>
     the Government was to bring about a state 
     <lb/>
     of affairs in the country which might be 
     <lb/>
     used as a pretext for placing the Island into 
     <lb/>
     Confederation with the Dominion of Canada. 
     <lb/>
     In reply to such assertions, he would content 
     <lb/>
     himself by simply asserting that they were 
     <lb/>
     not correct. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
      In so for as 
     <lb/>
     he (Hon. D. D.) was personally concerned 
     <lb/>
     he never had but one idea respecting Con<lb break="no"/>federation, and that was that this Colony 
     <lb/>
     was too small and unimportant a country to 
     <lb/>
     be allowed to remain out of Confederation 
     <lb/>
     with the Dominion. But he had no wish 
     <lb/>
     or desire to do anything to bring about such 
     <lb/>
     a result, before the people were prepared and 
     <lb/>
     willing for the change. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>