<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-04-05"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>


<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-04-05">5 April 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1870, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1870"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="175"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>

<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_160.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_162.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_164.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_166.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_168.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_170.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_172.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_174.hocr.html"/>
</item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-16">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-16">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_160">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_160.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_162">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_162.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_164">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_164.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_166">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_166.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_168">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_168.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_170">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_170.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_172">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_172.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_174">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_174.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="161" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_160.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">161</fw>   

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, April 5.</p><lb/>

<pb n="162" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_162.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">162</fw> 

<p>[...]</p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">AFTERNOON SESSION.</p>

<p>[...]</p>

<cb/>

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre">Confederation.<lb/></p> 

<p>House again in committee on the <lb/>
despatches. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCAU1">Hon. Mr. MCAULAY</persName>.—Those who had <lb/>
spoken upon this subject had taken a <lb/>
wide range; they had alluded to coun<lb break="no"/>tries and states not mentioned in the <lb/>
despatches. But their references were <lb/>
confined to one part of the world. If <lb/>
they had wished to make their statements <lb/>
general, they would have appealed to <lb/>
the histories of states of a greater anti<lb break="no"/>quity, and also to some of a more modern <lb/>
date than those which they had cited. At <lb/>
the opening of the session this House <lb/>
promised to His Honor the Adminis<lb break="no"/>trator to consider the question under <lb/>
consideration calmly, and be hoped he <lb/>
would be able to adhere to such a good <lb/>
resolution. Why we should give up the <lb/>
constitution of the colony, and consent <lb/>
to be annexed to Canada, he could not <lb/>
conceive. No state or country so far <lb/>
from the seat of government as this <lb/>
Island was from Ottawa, was ever con<lb break="no"/>tented. Ireland was referred to yester<lb break="no"/>day as having received benefit from <lb/>
union with England. If such had been <lb/>
the case, he (Mr. McA.) did not know <lb/>
it. Since the union, Ireland had pro<lb break="no"/>duced few great men besides O'Connell. <lb/>
Allusion had also been made to Scotland <lb/>
in this debate. There had once been a <lb/>
place called Scotland, but it was now <lb/>
North Britain. England at one time <lb/>
knew there was a Scotland. It had been <lb/>
said that the Scotch were an idle people; <lb/>
but there was a day when the were not <lb/>
idle—that was on the field of Bannock<lb break="no"/>burn. (Laughter.) She had had distin<lb break="no"/>guished men; but not so many now <lb/>

<pb n="163" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_162.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">163</fw> 

since her union with England. He, <lb/>
however, would refer to other unions. <lb/>
England herself was once a province of <lb/>
Rome. Would England be the great <lb/>
country she was to-day, if she had con<lb break="no"/>tinued a Roman provmce? France was <lb/>
once a province of the same kind; but <lb/>
in that position she could not have be<lb break="no"/>come rest, as she was too far distant <lb/>
from the seat of government at Rome. <lb/>
If we went farther back still, we would <lb/>
find other instances to prove the same <lb/>
thing. When Greece was growing into <lb/>
a country her people sent to Egypt to <lb/>
see what kind of government she had. <lb/>
They discovered nothing there worth <lb/>
imitating. After their masses are re<lb break="no"/>turned home, the Greeks founded a great <lb/>
confederacy—so compact and so power<lb break="no"/>ful that when Artaxerxes came against <lb/>
it his hosts were defeated. The <lb/>
Greeks gave a noble account of their <lb/>
valor at the pass of Thermopylae. They <lb/>
afterwards thought of punishing Persia <lb/>
for her attack upon them; they did so <lb/>
under Alexander, who conquered, that <lb/>
great country, but his victory was the <lb/>
ruin of Greece. A central state always <lb/>
absorbed the wealth of the outlying pro<lb break="no"/>vinces to their injury. This being the <lb/>
case we should be careful about acceding <lb/>
to the wooing of the Canadians who <lb/>
came here asking us to join them. He <lb/>
did not apprehend that Great Britain <lb/>
ever expected this Island would enter <lb/>
the Dominion. In the British American <lb/>
Act the two Canadas were allowed <lb/>
twenty-four senators each, and Nova <lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick each twelve. <lb/>
This being the full number of twenty-four <lb/>
for the Lower Provinces, where was <lb/>
there a place for Prince Edward Island? <lb/>
As he read the Act, if this Colony were <lb/>
admitted into the confederacy, it might <lb/>
be a generation before she would attain <lb/>
her representation in the senate, because <lb/>
the number of senators for Nova Scotia <lb/>
and New Brunswick was not to be re<lb break="no"/>duced except by death or resignation. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon Mr. HAVILAND</persName>, said his hon. <lb/>
colleague was in error. He could not <lb/>
have read the Act with sufficient atten<lb break="no"/>tion. This Island would get her four <lb/>
senators as soon as she became a part of <lb/>
the Dominion, but the number would <lb/>
not be reduced in Nova Scotia and New <lb/>
Brunswick until it was effected by the <lb/>
means which the hon. member described. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCAU1">Hon. Mr. MCAULAY</persName> thought he under<lb break="no"/>stood the Act correctly enough, but he <lb/>
would pass on to look at another aspect of <lb/>
the question. The neighboring Provinces, <lb/> 

<cb/>

Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, were <lb/>
blessed with great resources with which <lb/>
those of this Island could not compare. The <lb/>
mines of Nova Scotia yielded her a large <lb/>
revenue, and the timber of New Brunswick <lb/>
did the same for that province. All these <lb/>
thin would help to augment the wealth of <lb/>
the Dominion, but what was to augment <lb/>
our wealth ? He was ashamed to say there <lb/>
was nothing. Why then should we go into <lb/>
confederation? Were we not just as able <lb/>
to manage our own affairs as the Canadians <lb/>
were ? He believed we would be committing <lb/>
an act of political suicide by joining the <lb/>
Dominion. A short time ago Canadian <lb/>
affairs came to a dead lock, and gentlemen <lb/>
were sent down to attend the conference of   <lb/>
Lower Province delegates, to attempt to <lb/>
wheedle our statesmen into a union with <lb/>
Canada. They took our men off in a <lb/>
steamer to a place in Lower Canada called <lb/>
Quebec, where certain resolutions were <lb/>
agreed upon. But our people had <lb/>
sense enough not to accept the Quebec <lb/>
Scheme, which empowered the Dominion to <lb/>
raise money by any mode or system of tax<lb break="no"/>ation whatever. By going into confedera<lb break="no"/>tion we would enable the people of Canada <lb/>
—for they were the power—to tax us to <lb/>
any extent; and as according to all accounts <lb/>
they were always needing money—like the <lb/>
grave ever needing and never satisfied—he <lb/>
thought it would be well for us to retain <lb/>
our resent constitution. We could not, if <lb/>
in to Dominion, in any wise control the <lb/>
votes of the general parliament; our five <lb/>
men would have no voice amid the large <lb/>
number in that body; and the money, when <lb/>
once it was raised from us, would probably <lb/>
be taken to build a railway to the Pacific. <lb/>
The debt of the Dominion was about <lb/>
$24,000,000 sterling; he, however, was not <lb/>
very sure about the amount—indeed he did <lb/>
not know whether the Canadian statesmen <lb/>
were certain about the amount themselves. <lb/>
If the government here were to act in that <lb/>
way, we would be very apt to turn them out <lb/>
of office. It was a sign of corruption when <lb/>
the statesmen of a country did not know <lb/>
what its debt was. Confederation was a <lb/>
very pretty word, but the thirteen colonies <lb/>
were confederated and what was the result? <lb/>
A war broke out which deluged that country <lb/>
with the blood of its people. The govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Great Britain had sent word across <lb/>
the Atlantic to this Island that the colony <lb/>
was to be governed according to the well <lb/>
understood wishes of the people. He con<lb break="no"/>tended, therefore, that the confederates <lb/>
were those amongst us who were disloyal. <lb/>
(Applause.) It was not fair that they <lb/>
should be railing against us as they were <lb/>


<pb n="164" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_164.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">164</fw>  

doing. He would conclude by saying that <lb/>
he was an honest anti-confederate, and <lb/>
would show his opinions by tabling a <lb/>
resolution, which he would now read :— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">Whereas</hi>, His Excellency Sir John Young, <lb/>
Governor-General of the British North Ameri<lb break="no"/>can Provinces, in a Despatch to His Honor the <lb/>
Administrator of the Government of this Col<lb break="no"/>ony, dated at Ottawa, on the fourteenth day of <lb/>
December last, proposed certain terms on <lb/>
which this Colony would be admitted into the <lb/>
Canadian Union ; and <lb/></p> 

<p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">Whereas</hi>, a union of this Colony with the <lb/>
Dominion of Canada, would not be advantage<lb break="no"/>ous to Prince Edward Island ; and as the in<lb break="no"/>habitants of this Colony are not desirous of dis<lb break="no"/>turbing their existing connection with Great <lb/>
Britain. <lb/></p> 

<p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">Therefore, Resolved</hi>, That this House, on <lb/>
behalf of the Colony, decline to become part of <lb/>
the Dominion of Canada." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName>, in rising to <lb/>
support the hon. member's (Mr. Mc<lb break="no"/>Aulay's) amendment, was free to ac<lb break="no"/>knowledge that he had nothing particu<lb break="no"/>larly new to offer on confederation ; nor <lb/>
was it necessary that he should, for his <lb/>
views in regard to it were still un<lb break="no"/>changed, and as their correctness had <lb/>
not been disproved, he should hold them <lb/>
firmly until the force of truth convinced <lb/>
him of some error. After having ma<lb break="no"/>turely considered the report of the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Conference, in 1864, it was his <lb/>
humble opinion that little P. E. Island <lb/>
would prove, at any future time, of as <lb/>
much importance to the other provinces <lb/>
as they would be to her. And now, <lb/>
after the lapse of more than five years, <lb/>
the documents before this hon. commit<lb break="no"/>tee endorsed the correctness of that <lb/>
opinion ; for the one which contained <lb/>
the better terms assumed it as a fact <lb/>
that the Quebec Conference under-esti<lb break="no"/>mated the importance of the Colony to <lb/>
the Dominion by the sum of $800,000. <lb/>
It was very evident that our people were <lb/>
never more determined to keep aloof <lb/>
from the proposed union than they were <lb/>
at this moment. But they and their re<lb break="no"/>presentatives also were prepared to give, <lb/>
to all concerned, just and sufficient <lb/>
reasons for that determination. This <lb/>
implied that the representatives especi<lb break="no"/>ally had carefully studied all the more <lb/>
prominent events which led to the es<lb break="no"/>tablishment of the Dominion, as well as <lb/>
the public character and conduct of the <lb/>
principal actors in those events. And it <lb/>
implied, besides, that they had paid par<lb break="no"/>ticular attention to the policy pursued <lb/>
by the Dominion government during its <lb/>
short history, as well as to the present <lb/>
state and future prospects of the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion. Conclusions based on anything <lb/>

<cb/> 

short of this would not be just to them <lb/>
nor creditable to ourselves. That the <lb/>
confederation scheme took its rise in <lb/>
Canada, and had had for its chief object <lb/>
the relief of Canadian difficulties, both <lb/>
political and financial, did not now <lb/>
admit the shadow of a doubt. Was not <lb/>
the coalition government in 1864 formed <lb/>
to save the country, for a time at least, <lb/>
from positive anarchy ? If any hon. <lb/>
member had any doubt on the subject he <lb/>
must, to say the least of it, be unin<lb break="no"/>formed in respect of their "sixes and <lb/>
sevens" and their frequent dead locks ! <lb/>
Canada West had entirely outgrown the <lb/>
provisions of the Union Act of 1841, and <lb/>
the coalition government were charged <lb/>
with the confederation of the two Canadas, <lb/>
which involved serious risks, for they could <lb/>
not avoid the opening up of old sores that <lb/>
might result in another rebellion. This <lb/>
state of feeling accounted for the eagerness <lb/>
with which they availed themselves of the <lb/>
first chance that offered to attempt the <lb/>
accomplishment of a general union, whose <lb/>
foreign elements might, to some extent, <lb/>
neutralize the bitterness of their home dis<lb break="no"/>putes. It must thus appear to unpreju<lb break="no"/>diced minds that Canadian necessities and <lb/>
selfishness, so to speak, took the lead in <lb/>
concocting the Quebec Scheme, and stamped <lb/>
their own impress upon it, as well as upon <lb/>
every other step and movement in New <lb/>
Brunswick and Nova Scotia, that contri<lb break="no"/>buted to the formation of the Dominion as <lb/>
it now existed. This colony had had its <lb/>
peculiar disadvantages of position and cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, totally ignored by the Quebec <lb/>
Conference and equally so by the concoctors <lb/>
of the North American Act. These were <lb/>
among the facts that had aroused the <lb/>
people's opposition to confederation, and <lb/>
when coupled with the extreme extrava<lb break="no"/>gance of the Dominion government their <lb/>
opposition to it was greatly enhanced. <lb/>
Looking at the question from these points <lb/>
of view, it was by no means surprising that <lb/>
they could not regard any overture made <lb/>
to us by the Canadians without extreme <lb/>
suspicion, and hence their desire for no <lb/>
terms. He had already hinted at the man<lb break="no"/>ner in which New Brunswick and Nova <lb/>
Scotia had been treated in connection with <lb/>
confederation. But feeling as he did that <lb/>
now was the time when the people should <lb/>
have all the reliable and pertinent informa<lb break="no"/>tion which had transpired, he must contri<lb break="no"/>bute a few additional and telling facts. In <lb/>
regard to New Brunswick, it would suffice <lb/>
to say, that Canadian agents from among <lb/>
themselves and from Canada, grossly im<lb break="no"/>posed upon the people, with respect to <lb/> 


<pb n="165" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_164.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">165</fw>  

county branch lines of railway and other <lb/>
promises, which had not been, and never <lb/>
were intended to be performed. And as to <lb/>
the official coercion brought to bear upon <lb/>
the government by the Lieutenant Gover<lb break="no"/>nor, it was a matter of more public notorie<lb break="no"/>ty than the other. But if that province <lb/>
was now reaping a golden harvest from its <lb/>
connection with Canada, all he could say <lb/>
was, that the repeated and positive state<lb break="no"/>ments of its own confederate journals must <lb/>
be very untrue. With respect to Nova <lb/>
Scotia, the manner in whic it had been <lb/>
dragged into the union, constituted one of <lb/>
the darkest pages to be met with in the <lb/>
very dark and uninviting history of such <lb/>
unions. The Quebec Scheme was no sooner <lb/>
published than the people of that noble <lb/>
province became greatly alarmed for their <lb/>
own safety ; and in 1865, 183 petitions, <lb/>
signed by 15,000 of the people, were sent <lb/>
into the Legislature against that scheme. <lb/>
In the session of 1866, owing to the intense <lb/>
feelings and opposition of the people, the <lb/>
question of confederation was not as much <lb/>
as once alluded to in the Governor's speech. <lb/>
The country was thus led to believe itself <lb/>
secure, and this state of things continued <lb/>
until the session was pretty far advanced. <lb/>
By this time, however, craft and deception <lb/>
had proved successful in New Brunswick. <lb/>
The leading confederates thus encouraged, <lb/>
would, no doubt, ply the same weapons in <lb/>
Nova Scotia and their success might be <lb/>
judged of by the results ; for a conspiracy <lb/>
had been evidently formed between the <lb/>
government and opposition, and a resolu<lb break="no"/>tion carried by a large majority, to send <lb/>
delegates to England, to barter away their <lb/>
country's dearest rights for some infamous <lb/>
consideration ! It is note-worthy that <lb/>
some nineteen of this majority, gave a <lb/>
silent vote for the resolution ! This event <lb/>
filled the province with surprise and amaze<lb break="no"/>ment. But let us briefly follow the ques<lb break="no"/>tion as it came before the Imperial Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. Able and influential delegates were <lb/>
sent to England on behalf of the people, <lb/>
also, to oppose any act that would include <lb/>
Nova Scotia in the confederation. 'In this <lb/>
they were supported by a petition bearing <lb/>
31,000 signatures, and which was presented <lb/>
to the House of Commons by Admiral <lb/>
Erskine. We had it on good authority, <lb/>
that, "in the Commons the petition was <lb/>
never read and scarcely referred to. In <lb/>
the Lords its existence was hardly recog<lb break="no"/>nised, * * and the allegiance and affec<lb break="no"/>tion of a high--spirited and loyal people was <lb/>
treated with supreme indifference" "On <lb/>
the second reading of the bill (N. American <lb/>
Act) in the House of Commons, (in 1867) <lb/>

<cb/> 

the hon. member for Stockport (Mr. <lb/>
Watkin) declared that at the general elec<lb break="no"/>tion, in Nova Scotia in 1863, the question <lb/>
of confederation had been discussed at <lb/>
every polling-booth in the country. The <lb/>
House of Commons with this false state<lb break="no"/>ment ringing in the ears of its members, <lb/>
passed the bill without a [illegible]. "In <lb/>
the recent debate, on Nova Scotia's petition <lb/>
for repeal, both Mr. Adderly and Mr. <lb/>
Cardwell flatly contradicted Mr. Watkin, <lb/>
and admitted that at the elections in 1863, <lb/>
the question had not been discussed at the <lb/>
hustings. But strange to say that both <lb/>
those gentlemen misled the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons by drawing an inference from it of <lb/>
the most vital import in such a controversy, <lb/>
not only unsupported by, but utterly at <lb/>
variance with the facts. Both assured the <lb/>
House that the subject was not mentions, <lb/>
only because all the public men were in <lb/>
favor of confederation, and the people <lb/>
fully instructed and prepared for it!" This <lb/>
statement was made by Messrs. Cardwell <lb/>
and Adderly, in 1868, some six months <lb/>
after the general election of the previous <lb/>
year, and of which the following is an ab<lb break="no"/>stract:— <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">"FOR THE GENERAL PARLIAMENT,</p>

<table>
<row><cell>Members opposed to Confederation</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">18</cell></row>
<row><cell>Members in favor of Confederation,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">1</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">19</cell></row>
</table>

<p rendition="simple:centre">"FOR THE LOCAL PARLIAMENT,</p>

<table>
<row><cell>Members opposed to Confederation,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">36</cell></row>
<row><cell>Members in favor of Confederation,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">2</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">38"</cell></row>
</table>

<p>It will thus be seen how completely the <lb/>
statement of those colonial office worthies <lb/>
paled before the above figures, which re<lb break="no"/>presented the <hi rendition="simple:italic">truth</hi>. But it may be asked <lb/>
'what these details have to do with the <lb/>
question now under consideration? He <lb/>
contended that they had much to do with <lb/>
it from two distinct points of view. The <lb/>
first was that the men who had directly or <lb/>
indirectly to do with those dark affairs, <lb/>
from the moment of their conception, until <lb/>
each of them had become an accomplished <lb/>
fact, were the very same men through <lb/>
whose brains and hands the "Better Terms" <lb/>
had to pass before they were proposed to <lb/>
us. And if that fact was not sufficient to <lb/>
inspire us with caution—suspicion if you <lb/>
will—in regard to them, we must be very <lb/>
deficient in common sense. The second <lb/>
was, that it was the next thing to an im<lb break="no"/>possibility for a union, consummated by <lb/>
such means, and consisting of such jarring <lb/>
elements as the Dominion now was, to <lb/>

<pb n="166" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_166.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">166</fw>  

become strong or successful without a radi<lb break="no"/>cal change. If it ever should, the thing <lb/>
might be noted as an event contrary to the <lb/>
laws of nature. This being the case, our <lb/>
watchword should be, <hi rendition="simple:italic">no-terms</hi>-no sur<lb break="no"/>render. Those who could not produce a <lb/>
better argument, were fond of saying that <lb/>
loyalty demanded a sacrifice at our hands. <lb/>
In reply it was natural to ask what it was <lb/>
that constituted true practical loyalty? In <lb/>
the meantime he would submit a definition <lb/>
of his own. True loyalty, he contended, <lb/>
comprehended obedience to the laws- active <lb/>
obedience to all good laws, when required, <lb/>
and passive obedience to bad laws until they <lb/>
were constitutionally repealed; coupled <lb/>
with a firm constitutional defence of our <lb/>
own rights and liberties. If a British <lb/>
colony ever existed that made greater <lb/>
sacrifices than this colony had done, to the <lb/>
old policy of the British Government, with <lb/>
respect to its public lands, he must confess <lb/>
that he was ignorant of its history. We <lb/>
had had to expend many thousand of pounds <lb/>
in the erection of barracks, and for other <lb/>
military purposes, entirely on account of <lb/>
our land question. And what the people <lb/>
had sustained in the loss of time, and sub<lb break="no"/>scriptions paid to the escheat and other asso<lb break="no"/>ciations, it was utterly impossible to esti<lb break="no"/>mate. But no sooner had we appeared to <lb/>
be getting our heads above water, in the <lb/>
struggle of purchasing back our lands, <lb/>
which had been given or thrown away, <lb/>
than repeated and peremtory demands were <lb/>
made upon us, till we consented to pay our <lb/>
Governor's salary. We now paid our own <lb/>
civil list entirely, and any other expense <lb/>
that the British Government were put to, <lb/>
purely on our account, was merely nominal. <lb/>
Yet after having thus survived the wrongs <lb/>
and hardships of our very checkered <lb/>
history, we were asked, virtually, to sacri<lb break="no"/>fice our all to Canadian cupidity, and the <lb/>
Manchester policy of the present British <lb/>
Government. With the Canadians, for<lb break="no"/>sooth, we were asked to cast in our lot, as <lb/>
if we had not been sufficiently fleeced al<lb break="no"/>ready - as if we could envy the people with <lb/>
whom everything was tared down to the <lb/>
very dogs, to satisfy the extravagance of <lb/>
their government. If we had become <lb/>
Arabs that policy might succeed, but if we <lb/>
were Britons still it could not. Among <lb/>
the most remarkable speeches of this ses<lb break="no"/>sion, if the Reporter was correct, was that <lb/>
piece of special pleading set up by the hon. <lb/>
member (Mr. Brecken) in defence of the <lb/>
public men of Canada, who had been active<lb break="no"/>ly engaged in the rebellions of 1837-8. <lb/>
Those men were not only excused but <lb/>
praised also, simply on the plea that they <lb/>

<cb/> 

rebelled for the purpose of obtaining re<lb break="no"/>sponsible government. But the anti-con<lb break="no"/>federates of this Island - representatives <lb/>
and people- were, by the confederate <lb/>
press, denounced as disloyal, because they <lb/>
were determined to the utmost of their <lb/>
constitutional power, to preserve the re<lb break="no"/>sponsible government which they obtained <lb/>
by truly loyal means! A precious speci<lb break="no"/>men this of confederate consistency! With <lb/>
these general remarks he was prepared to <lb/>
support the amendment. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> thought the hon. member <lb/>
(Mr. Henderson) made an ingenious <lb/>
statement when he said that he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
stood by, and perhaps was prepared to <lb/>
close with the offer of the Canadian <lb/>
Statesmen. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName> would be sorry <lb/>
to misrepresent the hon. member; and <lb/>
he (Mr. B.) knew that nothing but a <lb/>
sense of duty would induce him (Mr. <lb/>
H.) to oppose the representative for the <lb/>
city. Yet he knew the hon. member, <lb/>
with his flowery arguments and elo<lb break="no"/>quence, could make his words carry a <lb/>
meaning which might deceive some <lb/>
people; but presumed the hon. member <lb/>
was himself the best judge of what he <lb/>
intended to say. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> had to charge the hon. <lb/>
member with misrepresenting him. He <lb/>
(Mr. H.) was afraid to speak out his <lb/>
mind fairly and freely on the question <lb/>
of Confederation, yet he would charge <lb/>
Dr. Tupper with inconsistency. If the <lb/>
hon. member had but taken the trouble <lb/>
to read the despatch which came to them <lb/>
last year, and calmly pondered over it <lb/>
and spoken the sentiments it would <lb/>
have produced, it would have been more <lb/>
to the purpose. He had before him the <lb/>
speech delivered by the hon. member <lb/>
last year. His reasons last year were <lb/>
different from those with which the hon <lb/>
member had now favored the hon. com<lb break="no"/>mittee. He thought the hon. member <lb/>
had not taken a statesmanlike view of <lb/>
the matter, and he (Mr. B.) would <lb/>
appeal to his common sense for proof in <lb/>
favor of his (Mr. B.'s) assertion. (The <lb/>
hon. member then fully referred to the <lb/>
history of the Nova Scotia difficulty, in <lb/>
that province and in England, and <lb/>
pointed out the result of the recent <lb/>
partial elections in that province.) <lb/>
When he (Mr. B.) first saw the Quebec <lb/>
Scheme he opposed it. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber (Mr. H.) had boasted of his loyalty, <lb/>
and hinted at contending for his rights, <lb/>
but he (Mr. B.) would remind the hon. <lb/> 

<pb n="167" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_166.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">167</fw>  

member, that while they had rights to <lb/>
protect and look after, they owed duties <lb/>
also to the Home Government which he <lb/>
thought the hon. member had entirely <lb/>
forgotten. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName> thought the <lb/>
hon. and learned member for Charlotte<lb break="no"/>town had misunderstood his remarks. <lb/>
He (Mr. H.) had said that some of his <lb/>
(Mr. B.'s) remarks early in the session, <lb/>
if correctly reported, appeared as an <lb/>
apology for the public character and <lb/>
policy of Canadians rebels, and contended <lb/>
still that the drift and general tendency <lb/>
of that speech was calculated to make <lb/>
that impression. But if the hon. member <lb/>
would affirm that such was not the im<lb break="no"/>pression he intended to make, he (Mr. <lb/>
H.) would accept such disavowal. Nor <lb/>
did he see how the hon. member could <lb/>
now with any consistency defend those <lb/>
whom he had so lately characterized as <lb/>
"an extravagant set." The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber had given a glowing description of <lb/>
the public works of Canada, &amp;c., but he <lb/>
(Mr. H.) would ask, had they been con<lb break="no"/>structed with Canadian money? Or <lb/>
were they not built at the expense, to <lb/>
a great extent, of the British Government? <lb/>
It was not so in Prince Edward Island. <lb/>
Our lands, public works, and buildings, <lb/>
had been secured and constructed at the <lb/>
expense and labor of our own people. <lb/>
Some who favored confederation ap<lb break="no"/>peared to look upon Canadian taxation <lb/>
as a light matter. Yet it was well <lb/>
known that even the printer's types <lb/>
were taxed 15 per cent; an ordinary <lb/>
mechanic's shop £3 15s. 0d. per annum, <lb/>
and other things in the same proportion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>, believed the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber felt himself in a very tight place, <lb/>
especially when a perusal of his speech <lb/>
last year was compared with his remarks <lb/>
in the debate then going on. He (Mr. <lb/>
B.) would read from the Parliamentary <lb/>
Reporter of 1869, page 156:- <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"Hon. Mr. HENDERSON. - If this debate is to <lb/>
be closed this evening, I wish to make a few <lb/>
remarks on the matter before the Committee. <lb/>
I gave my first impressions on the subject, but <lb/>
left the door open for myself to follow any course <lb/>
I saw fit and proper. I took up the common <lb/>
aspect of the question and spoke of the injustice <lb/>
of the demand; that was the sum and substance <lb/>
of my remarks. The debate which has taken <lb/>
place has not changed my opinion on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject-any change of sentiment has been the result <lb/>
of my own reflection. As to the character of <lb/>
the despatches from the Colonial Office, in re<lb break="no"/>ference to Nova Scotia, we know thata they <lb/>
were as foreign to the strict honest facts of the <lb/>
case, morally or politically, as any statements <lb/>
could possibly be. Notwithstanding the fact <lb/>

<cb/> 

that the hon. Joseph Howe went home and <lb/>
stated the case, backed up by a petition, from <lb/>
18,000 of the loyal inhabitants of Nova Scotia-<lb break="yes"/>because the Imperial Government had the fact <lb/>
that the Legislature of Nova Scotia had con<lb break="no"/>sented, by the most foul and unjustifiable [illegible] <lb/>
to the union of that country with Canada- they <lb/>
heeded not the petition nor the representations <lb/>
of that gentleman, although they [illegible] they <lb/>
were acting against the well-understood wishes <lb/>
of the people. Then assuming that the address <lb/>
of this House, or any portion of it, were pre<lb break="no"/>sented to the House of Commons, and that the <lb/>
Colonial Minister, backed up by his predecessor, <lb/>
got up and made a statement contrary to the <lb/>
prayer of our appeal, what would be the effect <lb/>
upon the House of Commons? It would [illegible] <lb/>
to the winds any impression made by the ad<lb break="no"/>dress upon that body, and the result would be <lb/>
that there would be no chance for little Prince <lb/>
Edward Island to obtain her wishes. There <lb/>
seems now to be no alternative for us, but of <lb/>
two evils to choose the least. When I consider <lb/>
that Newfoundland is about being legislated <lb/>
into Confederation, that a ring is being formed <lb/>
around us, and that the British Government <lb/>
have reduced our defences as far as they have <lb/>
done, I cannot but come to the conclusion that <lb/>
it would be unsafe to risk the result of refusing <lb/>
to accede to this demand. I am as [illegible] <lb/>
that the people should be relieved from every <lb/>
burden, as any hon. member of thise House, but <lb/>
I think it necessary to submit to this demand, <lb/>
for I believe that the British Government would <lb/>
not be particularly scrupulous, in regard to <lb/>
forcing us into the Confederation against our <lb/>
wishes, if they had what they thought a slight <lb/>
pretext for doing. I would not favor any <lb/>
movement on the part of this House which <lb/>
might call for reflection in future. I shall, <lb/>
therefore, support the resolution introduced by <lb/>
the hon. Leader of the Government." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>Those were the statements which the hon <lb/>
member made when the despatch having <lb/>
reference to the Lieutenant Governor's <lb/>
salary was under consideration. The <lb/>
whole burden of that speech went to <lb/>
show that if the House refused to vote <lb/>
that salary, the colony might be forced <lb/>
into confederation with Canada. He <lb/>
would be sorry to charge the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber with inconsistency; he (Mr. B.) <lb/>
merely thought the hon. member had a <lb/>
bad memory. Last year the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber thought it better to vote £2,100 a <lb/>
year, rather than to offer a point blank <lb/>
refusal to the demands of the Imperial <lb/>
government, and what he (Mr. B.) now <lb/>
wished the hon. member to do, was to <lb/>
give a satisfactory reason to justify his <lb/>
action on the question under con<lb break="no"/>sideration when he was so tame last <lb/>
year. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName> had not been <lb/>
put in a "tight place" by the hon. <lb/>
member, in consequence of his speech <lb/>
last year. Being required to pay the <lb/>
Lieutenant Governor's salary was one <lb/>
thing, to give up our constitution was <lb/>

<pb n="168" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_168.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">168</fw>   

another and much more serious demand. <lb/>
He consented to the former as a matter <lb/>
of policy, thereby depriving the British <lb/>
government of the last plea they could <lb/>
use to justify a coercive policy to place <lb/>
us in the Dominion. But while he gave <lb/>
his consent to that measure, he con<lb break="no"/>demned the injustice of the demand; <lb/>
and if a demand or command to join the <lb/>
Dominion should be transmitted to us <lb/>
from the Colonial Minister, our reply <lb/>
should be a respectful but emphatic no ! <lb/>
A beautiful affair, indeed, if our dearest <lb/>
rights were to be sacrificed, and this <lb/>
colony to be made a prop to support <lb/>
Canadians who had once forfeited their <lb/>
constitution and had so often been a bill <lb/>
of expence to the mother country, while <lb/>
Prince Edward Island had done full <lb/>
justice and honor to its constitution ! <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> was not satisfied with <lb/>
the explanation of the hon. member in <lb/>
answer to the challenge which he (Mr. <lb/>
B.) had given. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName> never denied <lb/>
that Great Britain had the physical power <lb/>
to coerce them into confederation, but <lb/>
could not believe she had the moral <lb/>
power to perpetrate so great a wrong. <lb/>
It was all very well for the hon. member <lb/>
to ring the challenge on what he would <lb/>
fain prove inconsistent on his (Mr. <lb/>
K.'s) part, but with all his eloquence he <lb/>
might as well have tried to prove a horse <lb/>
chestnut was a chestnut horse as to <lb/>
attempt to upset the logic of facts. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—The hon. member <lb/>
need not reter to the horse chesnut, he <lb/>
had but to refer to himself. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName> was a good deal sur<lb break="no"/>prised when he heard the hon. and learned <lb/>
member for Charlottetown commenting <lb/>
last night upon sdme remarks which a <lb/>
gentleman in the other end of the build<lb break="no"/>ing had made at a public meeting in the <lb/>
country. He (Mr. L. was surprised <lb/>
that the hon. member for the city, (Mr. <lb/>
B.), had the presumption to compare <lb/>
himself with that hon. gentleman, for if <lb/>
he had for a moment considered his own <lb/>
past political career, he would not have <lb/>
compared his with that of the Hon. Poore <lb/>
Haythorne. He thought his (Mr. B.'s) <lb/>
egotlsm would hardly have allowed him <lb/>
to presume for a moment to think he   <lb/>
should, as a public man, be placed beside <lb/>
that gentleman. When he (Mr. L.) <lb/>
considered the manner in which the <lb/>
quotation from that gentleman's speech <lb/>
was taken, and used, and reflected how <lb/>

<cb/> 

unfair it was, he could not but feel sur<lb break="no"/>prised to think the hon. member should <lb/>
have risen in his place and spoken as he <lb/>
did. And when he (Mr. L.) further re<lb break="no"/>flected upon the high position which Mr. <lb/>
Haythorne occupied, he must regard the <lb/>
manner in which he had been attacked <lb/>
as unmanly. If what Mr. Haythorne <lb/>
said at that meeting was fairly consider<lb break="no"/>ed, and looked at as a whole, it would <lb/>
not bear the construction which was <lb/>
attempted to be put on it. Why did <lb/>
not the hon. member (Mr. B.) read the <lb/>
last part of the speech, in connection <lb/>
with what he quoted? The hon. Mr. <lb/>
Haythorne connected with the terms <lb/>
which he thought the country might <lb/>
accept, the construction of a railroad <lb/>
throughout the Island. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber had no proof which he could produce, <lb/>
to show that the views of Mr. Haythorne <lb/>
and his, were similar. The hon. Mr. <lb/>
Haythorne had been but a short time in <lb/>
public life; he now held the highest <lb/>
position in the gift of the people to which <lb/>
any man could attain. He (Mr. Laird) <lb/>
would ask that hon. committee to con<lb break="no"/>trast that position with the one attained <lb/>
by the hon. member for Charlotte<lb break="no"/>town, who, though much longer in poli<lb break="no"/>tics, had attained no higher dignity than <lb/>
that of a political threshing machine. <lb/>
Mr. Haythorne said, should an offer of <lb/>
confederation be made, he should give <lb/>
it his consideration; and after making <lb/>
that statement, he had been elected by one <lb/>
of the largest constituencies in this col<lb break="no"/>ony; and now when a public meeting <lb/>
was held in a part of his district, he mere<lb break="no"/>ly said that he looked forward to the time <lb/>
when terms might be offered which he <lb/>
would be willing to accept. But did he <lb/>
mention that time? No, he did not. It <lb/>
might be after that line of railroad was <lb/>
built from Cascumpec to Georgetown. <lb/>
But the Hon. Mr. Haythorne very <lb/>
prudently said the time for confed<lb break="no"/>eration had not yet arrived. But how <lb/>
was it with the hon. member for the city, <lb/>
(Mr. B.) who, he supposed, prided him<lb break="no"/>self as being the orator of that hon. com<lb break="no"/>mittee. He formerly voted for a no-<lb break="yes"/>terms resolution, and when his hon. <lb/>
colleague (Dr. Jenkins) was returned <lb/>
for the city, at the last election, the <lb/>
hon. gentleman (Mr. B.) regretted that <lb/>
his constituents had returned a confeder<lb break="no"/>ate along with him. The hon. member <lb/>
(Mr. B.) took the votes of his constitu<lb break="no"/>ents as a no-terms man, and as such, <lb/>
told them that he regretted the citizens <lb/>
of Charlottetown should have sent to his <lb/>
 
<pb n="169" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_168.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">169</fw>

assistance a gentleman who held oppos<lb break="no"/>ite views. But to him, (Mr. Laird,) <lb/>
nothing was more amusing than to hear <lb/>
the hon. member for the city comparing <lb/>
himself with a gentleman who would <lb/>
scorn to do a mean act, whose past poli<lb break="no"/>tical history was so consistent. Every <lb/>
man who knew Mr. Haythorn's char<lb break="no"/>acter had confidence in his unswerving <lb/>
integrity. He might not have the fear<lb break="no"/>less courage of the hon. member for <lb/>
Charlottetown, but he had the courage <lb/>
to be consistent. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> said the hon. member <lb/>
for Bedeque had pretty well abused him. <lb/>
He (Mr. B.) had not compared himself <lb/>
with Mr. Haythorne, nor had he attack<lb break="no"/>ed that gentleman's character. He had <lb/>
just as much respect for the Hon. Mr. <lb/>
Haythorne as the hon. member (Mr. <lb/>
Laird) had. The hon. member had called <lb/>
him (Mr. B.) a political threshing ma<lb break="no"/>chine; but as it was then late, he would <lb/>
defer replying to the silver-tongued, <lb/>
ponderous, political philosopher of Wil<lb break="no"/>mot Creek, until to-morrow evening. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName>, in rising to address the hon. <lb/>
committee upon the all-important topic of <lb/>
confederation, had before his mind the ad<lb break="no"/>vice of His Honor the Administrator of the <lb/>
Government, to use calmness and delibera<lb break="no"/>tion in the consideration of the question; <lb/>
and he had also in view the manner in <lb/>
which he had been treated by the advocates <lb/>
of the scheme, both inside and outside of <lb/>
this House. The suggestion of the vener<lb break="no"/>able and honored gentleman who so worthily <lb/>
represented our good and virtuous Sovereign <lb/>
in this colony, would not be forgotten; <lb/>
neither would the defamation and foul<lb break="no"/>mouthed abuse of those who desired that <lb/>
he, like themselves, should turn traitor to <lb/>
his constituents, and accept a paltry bribe, <lb/>
in prospect, as a recompense for a violation <lb/>
of conscience. He had never, during all the <lb/>
years that this matter had been before the <lb/>
public, declared the absurd doctrine that <lb/>
there were "no-terms" upon which a union <lb/>
between this colony and the Dominion of <lb/>
Canada could be advantageously effected. <lb/>
On the contrary, he believed that there <lb/>
were terms upon which a union might be <lb/>
consummated; at the same time he was <lb/>
also bound to express his earnest con<lb break="no"/>viction, that Canada would never offer terms <lb/>
which it would be worth our while to <lb/>
accept. He had looked upon the scheme of <lb/>
confederation in all its length and breadth, <lb/>
heighth and depth, and he could see the <lb/>
advantages of intercolonial free trade, <lb/>
uniform laws, tariffs, currency, and mutual <lb/> 

<cb/>

defence. He would even sacrifice a portion <lb/>
of his private convictions to attain those <lb/>
objects, and to do away with those bitter <lb/>
politico-religious feuds which had marred <lb/>
the history of this colony--feuds in which <lb/>
he himself had been mixed up--feuds which <lb/>
had been forced upon him and often by the <lb/>
very parties who were now casting the <lb/>
reproach upon his co-religionists of having <lb/>
been the slanderers of female virtue, be<lb break="no"/>cause they repelled, as best they could, the <lb/>
foul and unprovoked abuse heaped upon <lb/>
them for political purposes. Our zealous <lb/>
Bishop, our wives, our daughters, and our <lb/>
religion--in fact, all that we esteemed most, <lb/>
was ridiculed and spat upon by those who <lb/>
then sought to blindfold the people in order <lb/>
to retain sway over the destinies of this <lb/>
colony, and who now adopt similar tactics <lb/>
to accomplish the scheme of confederation. <lb/>
Religious feuds, in the first instance, were <lb/>
employed to array the population into hos<lb break="no"/>tile factories; and it was only the keen point <lb/>
of the bayonet which finally opened the <lb/>
eyes of all classes to the sinister designs of <lb/>
our aristocratic leaders. By these means, <lb/>
they sought to recover that which they had <lb/>
lost, and that which they had long been <lb/>
accustomed to regard as their hereditary <lb/>
right--he meant the absolute management <lb/>
of the affairs of this colony. To retain <lb/>
their position was all they aimed at; to <lb/>
maintain themselves in luxury was their <lb/>
only desire. The people might groan under <lb/>
a landed system as iniquitous and oppressive <lb/>
as that which crushed the serfs of Russia, <lb/>
and which made exiles of four millions of <lb/>
Irish peasants within twenty years; they <lb/>
might be arraved into hostile factions, ready <lb/>
to cut each other's throats in the name of <lb/>
God; and they might be wheedled into a <lb/>
confederacy, in which their last condition <lb/>
would be worse than their first-- in <lb/>
which the evils of dominionism would be ten <lb/>
times more oppressive than the misfortunes <lb/>
of short leases and rent paying. All these <lb/>
things must happen, as long as our aris<lb break="no"/>tocracy were permitted to hold sway. The <lb/>
Tory Samson clung to the pillars of the <lb/>
edifice, and sooner than surrender his <lb/>
cherished and long-enjoyed privileges, he <lb/>
was resolved to perish in the ruins of the <lb/>
edifice which sheltered him, rather than en<lb break="no"/>joy equal privileges with his fellow-citizens. <lb/>
But he (Mr. R.) was quite ready to admit that <lb/>
a broader field of politics, which was destined <lb/>
to cut the ground beneath the feet of <lb/>
political traders and knaves, and which <lb/>
would place beyond their reach the power <lb/>
to divide a people whose interests were <lb/>
identical, into hostile factions, either in the <lb/>
name of religion or of politics, had its ad<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="170" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_170.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">170</fw> 

vantages. In times past, all that a political <lb/>
rogue, intent upon some selfish scheme, <lb/>
had to do to accomplish his object, was <lb/>
to elongate his visage to an unusual <lb/>
extent, to give the whites of his eyes an <lb/>
extra roll heavenwards, and trail his re<lb break="no"/>ligions coat-tail in the mire. The result, <lb/>
as we a11 well know, was a " ruction,'' (as <lb/>
his fellow-countrymen would say) which <lb/>
would put Donnybrook in the shade. What <lb/>
had happened in the past was just as likely <lb/>
to occur in the future, but not, he must <lb/>
admit, to as great an extent, even should <lb/>
our state be that of isolation. However, <lb/>
he for one was prepared to submit to these <lb/>
little inconveniences rather than surrender <lb/>
our rights to self-government, trusting that <lb/>
all his fellow-colonists would come to the <lb/>
conclusion to exercise forbearance, charity <lb/>
and goodwill towards each other under all <lb/>
and every circumstance, His inward con<lb break="no"/>victions were embodied in the words of <lb/>
Shakespeare, whose sentiments and advice; <lb/>
it appeared to him (Mr. R.) were appropriate <lb/>
and applicable to all times and places :— . <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">"'Tis better to bear the ills we have <lb/>
Than fly to those we know not of." <lb/></p> 

<p>It might, possibly, be his opinion that con<lb break="no"/>federation would he forced upon us. It was <lb/>
the only doubt he had, upon this question ; <lb/>
and because he had the temerity to express <lb/>
that doubt, he was set upon a few nights <lb/>
ago by one of the representatives of the <lb/>
capital of this colony, and denounced as a <lb/>
deceiver and hypocrite. Everything that <lb/>
could possibly be said and distorted in de<lb break="no"/>famation of him (Mr. R.) was used to <lb/>
destroy his prospects and whatever influence <lb/>
he might be supposed to have. The living <lb/>
and the dead were arrayed against him. <lb/>
The former were in a position that sheltered <lb/>
them from the reply which, under other <lb/>
circumstances, he should have made, and the <lb/>
dead forbade retort. The good taste and <lb/>
propriety of the attack was for the public <lb/>
to consider; but personally, he must say, <lb/>
that from a review of the antecedents and <lb/>
history of the gentleman, he could expect <lb/>
nothing better than the ruthless, unpro<lb break="no"/>voked, and malignant attack which he had <lb/>
made uppn him (Mr. R.) Believing in <lb/>
the description which he had given of <lb/>
him, of being the political gas-bag of this <lb/>
House—the member with the most wind <lb/>
and brass and the least information and <lb/>
reading—he (Mr. R ) had allowed many of <lb/>
his statements to pass with silent contempt. <lb/>
He (Mr. R.) would not say that he himself <lb/>
was a paragon of political virtue ; but be sub<lb break="no"/>mitted that the hon. member was not in a <lb/>
position to read lectures to others upon <lb/>

<cb/> 

honesty or consistency. The hon member <lb/>
had called him a " political upstart." He <lb/>
would ask, why not say "upstart" un<lb break="no"/>qualified by any epithat ? He would tell <lb/>
him - it was because he dare not. It was the <lb/>
acts of a coward who raised his arm to <lb/>
strike; but had not the courage to give the <lb/>
blow. He would not call him a villain, <lb/>
because it would be unparliamentary. He <lb/>
would not call him a fool, because he happen<lb break="no"/>ed to be a lawyer ; but he would say, he <lb/>
was one who had abused the privileges of <lb/>
parliament and the freedom of debate, to <lb/>
the uttering of language, which, is spoken <lb/>
out of the House, should be answered <lb/>
only with a blow, The hon member <lb/>
had charged him. with many things <lb/>
which were mean and contemptibly false, <lb/>
but he (Mr. R.) scorned to answer <lb/>
and man for his conduct, whether he <lb/>
were a political coxcomb, or whether he <lb/>
fought himself into power by a false glare <lb/>
of courage or not, so long as his accusa<lb break="no"/>tions were based upon falsehood. The hon <lb/>
member's fanatical aire had no influence <lb/>
upon him, (Mr. R.) nor upon the majority of <lb/>
his constituents, as he himself anticipated, <lb/>
when he informed us, at the conclusion of <lb/>
a scene which he (Mr. R.) had hoped never to <lb/>
see repeated that he did not expect to <lb/>
make another speech in this House. The <lb/>
result of the forthcoming election would <lb/>
realize his prophecy ; because he was al<lb break="no"/>ready known as a traitor to his country, <lb/>
and because he had proved false, at a most <lb/>
important crisis, to his solemnly recorded <lb/>
votes and promises. But he would leave <lb/>
the hon. member with his constituets to <lb/>
be dealt with, neither caring himseld for <lb/>
his smiles or his frowns, so long as he dis<lb break="no"/>charged his duty to the people. And now, <lb/>
if ever he desired the gift of eloquence,-<lb break="yes"/>it was at the present juncture, when the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of confederation was brought before us. <lb/>
He should desire to speak now, or for ever <lb/>
hold his peace : now, when the dearest <lb/>
rights and liberties for which a people ever <lb/>
fought were hanging in the balance, - now, <lb/>
when the enemy lurked in the secret places, <lb/>
with honeyed words, and gilded palms-and <lb/>
now, when gold, or abuse and misrepre<lb break="no"/>sentation where equally ready to be em<lb break="no"/>ployed to accomplish the transfer of our <lb/>
liberties to Canada. Over five years ago, <lb/>
a scheme was submitted to us for colonial <lb/>
union, which pronounced just and equi<lb break="no"/>table by those who now sought to impress <lb/>
upon us the idea that confederation was <lb/>
inevitable, and that we should never obtain <lb/>
better propositions than those before us. <lb/>
Our best policy, in their estimation, was to <lb/>
grasp at the proffered terms, or suggest <lb/>

<pb n="171" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_170.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">171</fw> 

those which we would be williing to accept. <lb/>
Our confederate friends, philosophers and <lb/>
guides, were not correct in asserting that <lb/>
the terms of the Quebec Scheme were just <lb/>
and equitable - nay, even liberal, as far as <lb/>
Prince Edward Island was concerned. We <lb/>
had now the evidence before us, in minutes <lb/>
of Council of the Dominion Government <lb/>
itself, and in the tabular statements of <lb/>
their advocates and admirers here, whereby <lb/>
it was shown that they were willing to <lb/>
supplement their former offer by an increase <lb/>
of £25,520 per annum for local govern<lb break="no"/>mental purposes. He would submit, that <lb/>
having proved false prophets once, they <lb/>
were likely to prove so again, and the people <lb/>
of this colony, having gained that amount <lb/>
by their opposition, they would act the <lb/>
prudent part by still continuing their hosti<lb break="no"/>lity to the scheme. To the stout-hearted <lb/>
men who scorned the Quebec Scheme, was <lb/>
due the credit of these better terms ; and <lb/>
to the same class would be due the credit <lb/>
of still better terms, should it ever prove <lb/>
the misfortune of the colony to join the <lb/>
Dominion ; but he earnestly trusted that <lb/>
the day was far distant when such a cala<lb break="no"/>mity would befal us. He held in his hand <lb/>
the original Quebec Scheme, wherein we <lb/>
were promised the munificent sum of 80 <lb/>
cents per head for the transfer of our <lb/>
liberty, and the consoling representation in <lb/>
the Senate of the Dominion, of four, and in <lb/>
the commons, of five—a representation, in <lb/>
all, of nine out of 258. That feature of <lb/>
the scheme, which placed as utterly at the <lb/>
mercy of our purchasers, had been rendered <lb/>
worse by the North American Act of 1867, <lb/>
inasmuch as it reduced the representation <lb/>
of the maritime Provinces; and who was <lb/>
there amongst us, except those favored <lb/>
few, possessed of property to the extent <lb/>
of $4000, anxious to bask in the sun<lb break="no"/>shine which beamed around Ottawa, or <lb/>
the few needy hangers-on in our midst to <lb/>
whom every change was acceptable, who <lb/>
would not just as soon see the Island thrust <lb/>
into the confederacy without a representa<lb break="no"/>tive at all as with the contemptibly limited <lb/>
number allowed us by the act referred to ? <lb/>
Had we no representation, we could, at all <lb/>
events, appeal to the sense of justice of <lb/>
mankind for fair play ;   we could adopt the <lb/>
patriotic cry of the people of the early <lb/>
American colonies—the New England <lb/>
States—that taxation without representa<lb break="no"/>tion was tyranny, but by the proposed <lb/>
arrangement—although we in effect would <lb/>
have no influence whatever in regulating <lb/>
taxation, yet we might be fleeced to any <lb/>
extent, as the Act in question permitted— <lb/>

<cb/>
 
our mouths would be closed, because we had <lb/>
five commoners and four lords to represent <lb/>
us, and we could not say that we had been <lb/>
taxed without our own consent. In the <lb/>
better terms, he noticed the offer of $800,<lb break="no"/>000 to settle our land question. He thank<lb break="no"/>ed Canada for the assurance. We granted <lb/>
the money for the purpose, but he thought <lb/>
the duty of relieving our hard-workding <lb/>
tenants from the thraidom into which they <lb/>
had been cajoled, devolved rather upon the <lb/>
Imperial government than upon the Cana<lb break="no"/>dians. Knowing, as we did, that it was <lb/>
the former and not the latter that inflicted <lb/>
the evil upon the colony, - and that it was <lb/>
the same power which now desired to place <lb/>
these colonies in the position of a target <lb/>
against republicanism, and make these <lb/>
Provinces the battle-ground for the feuds <lb/>
between Europe and America. And this <lb/>
we were requested to do at a time when <lb/>
the Imperial troops were being withdrawn <lb/>
from the colonies, and when we stood in <lb/>
the relative proportions of four to forty <lb/>
millions of people. With reference to the <lb/>
financial part of the scheme, we would, <lb/>
according to the new arrangement, have <lb/>
received last year £103,518 3s 10d, as an <lb/>
offset to £77,998 3s 10d, which we raised as <lb/>
our revenue proper, leaving a balance in <lb/>
our favor, as shown by the tabular state<lb break="no"/>ment of a confederate committee, who <lb/>
applied the Dominion tariff to our imports. <lb/>
The calculation was correct enough, barring <lb/>
the error of several thousands of pounds <lb/>
which had no right to be placed to our <lb/>
credit; but even admitting that the state<lb break="no"/>ment was correct in every particular, was <lb/>
it a sufficient inducement for us to enter <lb/>
the Dominion? It was a matter of fact <lb/>
that our revenue nearly doubled itself every <lb/>
twelve years, and estimating it at that of <lb/>
last year, £90,000, how, he might ask, <lb/>
would the account stand between us and <lb/>
Canada twelve years hence? Why, we <lb/>
should be a loser to the extent of £77,000 <lb/>
in round numbers; and as our tariff was <lb/>
only eleven per cent, whilst that of Canada <lb/>
was fifteen—with the strong probability of <lb/>
being raised to twenty - and as the sum <lb/>
proposed for the management of our local <lb/>
affairs was, with the insignificant exception <lb/>
of the 80 cent arrangement, a fixed one, <lb/>
the probability was that if the colony was <lb/>
to keep pace with its past prosperity, our <lb/>
loss would increase with our increasing <lb/>
prosperity; and our increasing wants would <lb/>
have to be supplied by direct taxation—by <lb/>
repulsive stamp and newspaper taxes, to <lb/>
which, hitherto, we had, happily, been <lb/>

<pb n="172" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_172.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">172</fw>  

strangers. There was no promise made for <lb/>
public works in this Island, surrounded by <lb/>
an ice barrier for five months out of the <lb/>
year, for whilst we were called upon to <lb/>
contribute equally with our fellow-colonists <lb/>
on the mainland, to the construction and <lb/>
maintenance of costly public works, such <lb/>
as railroads, &amp;c., which enhanced the value <lb/>
of their property, contributed to their wealth, <lb/>
and were available at all times, we were, by <lb/>
a special clause of the B. N. A. Act, de<lb break="no"/>barred from such works unless at our own <lb/>
expense. But as an offset to these prac<lb break="no"/>tical suggestions, our loyalty and religious <lb/>
convictions were appealed to. We had any <lb/>
number of promises; and prophetic visions <lb/>
were as plentiful as misquitoes in summer. <lb/>
The land question was to be settled, uni<lb break="no"/>versal harmony was to prevail, and com<lb break="no"/>merce was to raise us to the very pinnacle <lb/>
of prosperity. History, it was said, but <lb/>
repeated itself; and looking at the argu<lb break="no"/>ments of the friends of confederation, he <lb/>
was almost a believer in the doctrine of the <lb/>
transmigration of souls, and fancied that <lb/>
they were animated by the spirits, nay, the <lb/>
very language of those who were instru<lb break="no"/>mental in effecting the union between Eng<lb break="no"/>land and Ireland in the early part of the <lb/>
present century. Reviewing the prophetic <lb/>
visions of national prosperity in which the <lb/>
Irish ministers indulged, the illustrious <lb/>
Grattan remarked: <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The minister has not done with bribes; <lb/>
whatever economy he shows in argument here <lb/>
he has been generous in the extreme. Parson, <lb/>
priest (I think one of his advocates hints the <lb/>
Presbyterians) are not forgotten; and now the <lb/>
mercantile body are all to be bribed, that all <lb/>
may be ruined. He holds out commercial <lb/>
benefits for political annihilation; but offers you <lb/>
a abundance of capital, but first he takes it <lb/>
away; he takes away a great portion of the <lb/>
landed capital of the country by the necessary <lb/>
operation of Union; he will give you, however, <lb/>
commercial capital in its place; but first he will <lb/>
give you taxes. It seems it is only necessary <lb/>
to break the barrier of liberty, and the tides of <lb/>
commerce will flow in of course; take away her <lb/>
rival in a landed capital, and then commercial <lb/>
capital advances without fear. Commerce <lb/>
only wants weight, i.e. taxes, it seems, in <lb/>
order to run with new spirit. He not only <lb/>
finds commerce in the retreat of landed capital, <lb/>
but he finds corn also. His whole speech is a <lb/>
course of surprises; the growth of excision, the <lb/>
resource of incumbrance, and harvests sown <lb/>
and gathered by the absence of the proprietors <lb/>
of the soil and of their property. All these <lb/>
things are to come. When? He does not tell <lb/>
you. Where? He does not tell you. You take <lb/>
his word for all this. I have heard of a bank<lb break="no"/>er's bill of exchange, Bank of England's notes, <lb/>
Bank of Ireland's notes; but a prophet's pro<lb break="no"/>missory note is a new traffic; all he gets from <lb/>
Ireland is our solid loss; all he promises are <lb/>
visionary, distance, and prophetic advantages. <lb/>
He sees, I do not, British merchants and Brit<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

ish [illegible] sailing to the provinces of Connaught <lb/>
and Munster; there they settle in great multi<lb break="no"/>tudes, themselves and families. He mentions <lb/>
not what description of manufacturers; who <lb/>
from Birmingham; who from Manchester; [illegible]   <lb/>
matter, he cares not; he goes on asserting and <lb/>
asserting with great ease to himself, and with <lb/>
out any obligation to fact. Imagination is the <lb/>
region in which he delights to disport; where <lb/>
he is to take away your parliament, where he <lb/>
is to take away your final judicature, where he <lb/>
is to increase your taxes, where he is to get an <lb/>
Irish tribute, there he is a plain, direct, matter-<lb break="yes"/>of-fact man; but where he is to pay you for all <lb/>
this, there he is poetic and prophetic; no longer <lb/>
a [illegible], but an inspired accountant. [illegible]    <lb/>
gives her wand; [illegible]  takes him by the  <lb/>
hand; Ceres is in her train." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Is not this precisely the style of <lb/>
argument employed by colonial confed<lb break="no"/>erates? What our burdens, taxation <lb/>
and helplessness in the confederacy <lb/>
will be, we are informed accurately <lb/>
enough; but when we ask the con<lb break="no"/>federates to point out to us the advan<lb break="no"/>tages of union, then they are poetical <lb/>
and visionary, and talk largely of the <lb/>
glory of the belonging to a great country, <lb/>
and the benefits of intercolonial free <lb/>
trade, as if we were not already part and <lb/>
parcel of one of the first nations of the <lb/>
earth, and as if intercolonial free trade <lb/>
could not be accomplished without a <lb/>
political union. The history of Ireland <lb/>
has been quoted to us to prove that no <lb/>
greater blessing could have befallen that <lb/>
country than the surrender of its par<lb break="no"/>liament. We are told that the people <lb/>
of Ireland should rejoice at the destruction <lb/>
of a corrupt parliament, and unusual <lb/>
prosperity is attributed to the union. <lb/>
The confederates are unfortunate in <lb/>
their illustrations. The Legislature of <lb/>
Ireland was undoubtedly corrupt; but, <lb/>
bad as it was, the people of Ireland never <lb/>
consented to its annihilation, for the <lb/>
very good reason that they had no voice <lb/>
in the matter. As a matter of fact, we <lb/>
know that of the 300 men who committed <lb/>
that act of "damnable violation," as an <lb/>
eminent Irish member of the House of <lb/>
Commons termed it, 116 were actually <lb/>
placemen, and 216 the representatives of <lb/>
boroughs, and manors, and nominees <lb/>
of patrons, returned without the exer<lb break="no"/>cise of the shadow of elective right by <lb/>
the people. Placemen and all, as these <lb/>
so-called representatives were, yet, how<lb break="no"/>ever, it required a lavish expenditure of <lb/>
gold to blunt their consciences to com<lb break="no"/>mit the deed which they knew would at <lb/>
once destroy the independence of the <lb/>
country, and blast its prosperity. The <lb/>
coercive Bills, Algerine Acts, and Mar<lb break="no"/>tial Law, of the first twenty years of <lb/>

<pb n="173" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_172.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">173</fw>  

union; the agitations of O'Connell, the <lb/>
famines of 1846-47 and 48, with the <lb/>
wholesale exodus consequent thereon; <lb/>
and the Fenian conspiracies of the pre<lb break="no"/>sent day, testify in unmistakable terms <lb/>
as to the folly of destroying, instead of <lb/>
reforming, the Irish Parliament. But <lb/>
he would not detain the committee by <lb/>
going over the history of Ireland's miser<lb break="no"/>ies. He would simply say, that as the <lb/>
members of this House, were the free <lb/>
choice of the people, he trusted that <lb/>
they would prove worthy of the con<lb break="no"/>fidence reposed in them, and that no con<lb break="no"/>siderations of honor or emolument would <lb/>
ever induce them to betray their con<lb break="no"/>stituents in so important an affair as the <lb/>
surrender of the constitution of the <lb/>
colony. The government, he was happy to <lb/>
find, had acted promptly and openly in <lb/>
the matter. The dates of the various <lb/>
despatches and documents, relating to <lb/>
the "better terms," clearly showed that <lb/>
the government lost no time in coming <lb/>
to a decision thereon, and the charge of <lb/>
waiting to see the direction of the popu<lb break="no"/>lar breeze, therefore, fell to the ground. <lb/>
As far as this government and assembly <lb/>
were concerned, the country was safe <lb/>
with regard to confederation. It would <lb/>
be for the people to see that the next <lb/>
Legislature was equally honest and <lb/>
patriotic. Bribery and deception would <lb/>
doubtlessly be tried at the general elec<lb break="no"/>tion to swell the number of confederate <lb/>
members; but he had sufficient confi<lb break="no"/>dence in the intelligence of the people, <lb/>
and the love of liberty by which they <lb/>
were animated, to cherish the belief that <lb/>
they could not be cajoled by any specious <lb/>
artifices on the part of the confederates; <lb/>
and that they would adopt the most effi<lb break="no"/>cacious means by rejecting every unionist <lb/>
who might offer himself for election, to <lb/>
preserve the privileges which they en<lb break="no"/>joyed under the present constitution <lb/>
and form of government. The exper<lb break="no"/>ience of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, <lb/>
and the difficulties which beset the Do<lb break="no"/>minion to the Red River revolt, should <lb/>
not be lost upon us. For himself, he <lb/>
(Mr. R) had discharged his duty to his <lb/>
constituents by opposing the "better <lb/>
terms". Were he to do otherwise, he <lb/>
would consider himself a traitor of t he <lb/>
blackest dye, in whom no honest elector <lb/>
should place confidence. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PROW2">Mr. PROWSE</persName> said as this question of <lb/>
confederation was one on which every <lb/>
hon. member of the House should ex<lb break="no"/>press his opinions, he would not be doing <lb/>

<cb/> 

his duty did he not fearlessly express his <lb/>
sentiments. Were the committee dis<lb break="no"/>cussion a resolution which could put us <lb/>
into confederation, he (Mr. P.) would <lb/>
feel himself bound, by his obligations to <lb/>
his constituents, to oppose anything <lb/>
which would put the Island into con<lb break="no"/>federation without the consent of the <lb/>
people. But as the members of the <lb/>
Legislature would soon have to go back <lb/>
to the people for re-election, they should <lb/>
now express their honest convictions on <lb/>
this question, and not act in a double-<lb break="yes"/>dealing manner, as he (Mr. P.) believed <lb/>
the government of the day were doing. <lb/>
This question had been the means of <lb/>
showing up the present government in <lb/>
their true character, and he (Mr. P.) <lb/>
thought it would be safer to trust the <lb/>
country in the hands of men who hon<lb break="no"/>estly avowed themselves in favor of con<lb break="no"/>federation, and yet would promise not <lb/>
to vote for union without an appeal to <lb/>
the people, than to men who had acted <lb/>
like the present government. The gov<lb break="no"/>erment were now upon their trial for <lb/>
their actions during the recess, and the <lb/>
House was asked to pass a resolution <lb/>
endorsing the sentiments of two minutes <lb/>
of council. One of these minutes read <lb/>
as follows:- <lb/> </p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That inasmuch as said terms do <lb/>
not comprise a full and immediate settlement of <lb/>
the land tenures, and indemnity from the Im<lb break="no"/>perial government for the loss of territorial rev<lb break="no"/>enues, the committee cannot recommend said <lb/>
terms to the consideration of their constituents <lb/>
and the public." <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>The only interpretation which could <lb/>
possibly be put on this, minute of coun<lb break="no"/>cil, was that, if the British Government <lb/>
settled our land question, we would go <lb/>
into confederation. Afterwards the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment wrote a longer minute of coun<lb break="no"/>cil than the one just quoted, on the same <lb/>
subject, but he (Mr. P.) could not under<lb break="no"/>stand what the longer document was <lb/>
for, except to darken the meaning by a <lb/>
multiplicity of letters and words. The <lb/>
government stated that the land ques<lb break="no"/>tion was one of great importance, and <lb/>
they stipulated that it should be settled <lb/>
before we joined Canada, but if we could <lb/>
obtain the settlement of [illegible] question, <lb/>
it did not matter much where the money <lb/>
came from; he (Mr. P.) would not blush <lb/>
to take the money from Canada. We <lb/>
were badly treated by the Imperial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment with regard to our lands, they <lb/>
took away our crown lands to pay the <lb/>
debts of the empire. Canada was a part <lb/>
of that empire; she owed debts to Great <lb/>

<pb n="174" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_174.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">174</fw>  

Britain, and if Canada was now willing <lb/>
to reinurse Prince Edward Island for <lb/>
the loss of our crown lands, in consider<lb break="no"/>ation of the obligations she owed to <lb/>
Great Britian, we might as safely accept <lb/>
this indemuity from Canada as from <lb/>
Great Britain. He (Mr. P.) did not <lb/>
wish to be understood to be in favor of <lb/>
the present terms, or of this House ac<lb break="no"/>cepting any terms, for no terms should <lb/>
be accepted without the consent of the <lb/>
people at the polls. If he believed it <lb/>
was possible for this Island to retain its <lb/>
present position, or its isolation, be as <lb/>
prosperous in the future as it had been <lb/>
in the past, he would oppose confedera<lb break="no"/>tion ; but, believing as he did, that isola<lb break="no"/>tion was nearly played out, he consider<lb break="no"/>ed it right that this question should be <lb/>
discussed from one end of the Isalnd to <lb/>
the other. Some years ago the question <lb/>
of our land tenures was entertained by <lb/>
the British Government ; they appointed <lb/>
commissioners to settle it. These com<lb break="no"/>missioners sent in a voluminous report, <lb/>
but there the matter rested. The <lb/>
British Government went so far as not <lb/>
only to admit that grievance existed, <lb/>
but actually submitted to the Island gov<lb break="no"/>ernment a plan for the settlement of that <lb/>
question, but the Island did not approve <lb/>
of the scheme. Soon after, this confed<lb break="no"/>eration scheme was proposed and the <lb/>
people of this Island did not favor it. <lb/>
Ever since that time, our Island govern<lb break="no"/>ment had been snubbed by the British <lb/>
government on this land question, <lb/>
and we were told at last that they would not <lb/>
discuss the matter with us, but very <lb/>
significantly told us that this question <lb/>
would be taken upon by the Dominion <lb/>
Government in the event of our joining <lb/>
confederation. A great deal had been <lb/>
said about giving up our liberties, but <lb/>
he (Mr. P.) believed we would have as <lb/>
much liberty when united with Canada, <lb/>
as we now enjoyed. We had a beautiful <lb/>
exhibition of liberty when the highest <lb/>
legislative body on the Island—the lords <lb/>
in the other end of the building—could <lb/>
not pass a bill for the appointment of <lb/>
one of their own officers without adding <lb/>
a suspending clause,—that was the lib<lb break="no"/>erty the Legislature of this Island en<lb break="no"/>joyed ! (Hear, hear.) He (Mr. P.) did <lb/>
not think it the proper time to discuss <lb/>
the financial part of the question, as he <lb/>
was not prepared to advocated the present <lb/>
terms, but there were arguments which <lb/>
might be used to show that this Island <lb/>
was justly entitled to much better terms <lb/>
than had yet been offered to us—and it <lb/>

<cb/> 

was the duty of the party in power to <lb/>
state what terms should be accepted by <lb/>
this Island. The settlement of the land <lb/>
question should always be kept in view <lb/>
by the government. It was the burden <lb/>
of the song of the late leader of the <lb/>
liberal party, hon. George Coles, who <lb/>
did not think it derogatory to the dig<lb break="no"/>nity of the Legislature of the Island to <lb/>
demand, when in Canada, the price of <lb/>
the lands from the Dominion govern<lb break="no"/>ment ; and he (Mr. P.) thought no <lb/>
member of the present government <lb/>
would claim to be above him (Mr. Coles) <lb/>
in intelligence and legislative ability. <lb/>
It appeared that every means was taken <lb/>
to blacken confederates' conduct on this <lb/>
question. He. (Mr. P.) had been accused <lb/>
of taking an undue advantage of his <lb/>
position, and of changing his opinion on <lb/>
the subject ; but he would state that he <lb/>
never was a "no-terms" man. The first <lb/>
time he (Mr. p.) had said anything in <lb/>
public on this question was at a meeting <lb/>
in his district at which the Hon. Mr. <lb/>
Duncan was present, after the return of <lb/>
the delegates from Quebec in 1864, and <lb/>
when he (Mr. D.) expressed himself <lb/>
opposed to any terms, and desired the <lb/>
meeting to pass a no-terms resolution. <lb/>
he (Mr. P.) had differed with him, and <lb/>
stated that if he (Mr. D.) was opposed <lb/>
to any terms, he, as a member of the <lb/>
government, should not have voted for <lb/>
sending delegates to Quebec. It had <lb/>
been stated that we did not want to <lb/>
trade with the Dominion, but from the <lb/>
tabular statement which ahd been got <lb/>
up by gentlemen of ability, as well as <lb/>
from other sources, it could be easily <lb/>
ascertained that we had a large and ever <lb/>
increasing amount of exports to the <lb/>
Dominion, and we must conclude that a <lb/>
remunerative market was obtained there, <lb/>
or so much would not be sent. We <lb/>
were also in a large measure dependent <lb/>
upon the Dominion for our fuel, so that <lb/>
our trade with that country was not so <lb/>
small as some hon. members tried to <lb/>
make out. The main question, however, <lb/>
was whether we could maintain our <lb/>
isolated policy in the future, as we had <lb/>
done in the past, when it was plainly the <lb/>
policy of Great Britain to increase the <lb/>
pressure until we joined the union. <lb/>
This policy of Great Britain was plainly <lb/>
observable in their conduct with regard <lb/>
to the land question and the payment of <lb/>
the governor's salary. He (Mr. P.) had <lb/>
voted for paying the Governor's salary, <lb/>
for he believed our refusal to do <lb/>
so might have been made a pretext for <lb/>

<pb n="175" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-05_Page_174.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">175</fw>   

putting us into confederation, and he <lb/>
did nto wish to see this Island placed <lb/>
into union as Nova Scotia had been. A <lb/>
great deal had been quoted from news<lb break="no"/>papers and speeches to show the dissa<lb break="no"/>tisfaction which prevailed in parts of <lb/>
the dominion, but these statements ahd <lb/>
been put forth by those who were op<lb break="no"/>posed to the government of the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion, or were dissappointed office hunters ; <lb/>
and if we would judge by the statements <lb/>
of the opposition in any country, we <lb/>
should have a very poor idea of the state <lb/>
of public matters, although a good <lb/>
healthy opposition to a government was <lb/>
one of the greatest blessings to the coun<lb break="no"/>try. At one time on this Island a great <lb/>
cry was raised about the corruptions of <lb/>
the family compact, and almost every <lb/>
man you met was talking about the <lb/>
Blue Book, while many of them hardly <lb/>
knew what it was. Soon after, another <lb/>
party took the reins of government, and <lb/>
then the religious question arose and <lb/>
the cry was raised that the Roman <lb/>
Catholics were going to ride rough-shod <lb/>
over the country. And so it would <lb/>
always be, one party trying to make out <lb/>
that the other was the worst in the <lb/>
world, which shewed that we could not <lb/>
judge of the prosperity of a country or <lb/>
of the purity of a party without hearing <lb/>
both sides of the question. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName> said he must have <lb/>
misunderstood the hon. member who <lb/>
had just spoken, at the Murray Harbor <lb/>
meeting to which he referred. At that <lb/>
meeting the hon. member, as he (Mr. D.) <lb/>
thought, was so opposed to confedera<lb break="no"/>tion that he found fault with the govern<lb break="no"/>ment for sending delegates to Canada at <lb/>
all. He (Mr. D.) had pled guilty to the <lb/>
fault, and excused himself as best he <lb/>
could by saying that the delegates had <lb/>
gone further than he ever expected them <lb/>
to go, and that he would never consent <lb/>
to another delegation being sent. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PROW2">Mr. PROWSE</persName> carried a resolution at <lb/>
the meeting. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName> was outdone. If <lb/>
the hon. member had carried a resolu<lb break="no"/>tion against him, he (Mr. D.) could have <lb/>
no more to say. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> asked how it came <lb/>
that the hon. member (Mr. Duncan) sup<lb break="no"/>ported, at the last election, the return of <lb/>
his friend (Mr. Prowse), if that gentle<lb break="no"/>man was a staunch confederate, and had <lb/>
opposed him at meetings. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName> could assure the <lb/>
hon. committee that he had supported <lb/>

<cb/> 

the hon. member (Mr. Prowse) because <lb/>
he believed him to be a good anti-con<lb break="no"/>federate; but he had been deceived. <lb/>
(Laughter.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> said he asked the <lb/>
question, because he observed by one of <lb/>
the newspapers, that the people in the <lb/>
Murray Harbor district had proposed <lb/>
at a recent meeting, to pledge their next <lb/>
representatives against confederation, <lb/>
upon oath in writing. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> observed that he <lb/>
saw in the same paper that the govern<lb break="no"/>ment should be recommended for being <lb/>
anti-confederate. He (Mr. H.) thought <lb/>
this was strange, when the leader of the <lb/>
government himself had declared that he <lb/>
was in favor of the principle of confed<lb break="no"/>eration. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PROW2">Mr. PROWSE</persName> explained that he was <lb/>
opposed to the late government sending <lb/>
delegates to Canada, because he believed <lb/>
that some of them could not be trusted <lb/>
on the confederation question ; and the <lb/>
people of the district had approved of <lb/>
the hon. member (Mr. Duncan) in taht <lb/>
respect. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName>.—Hon. members <lb/>
were wheeling round so that he did not <lb/>
know what to do. The question which <lb/>
he went down at that time to ascertain <lb/>
the views of his constituents upon, was <lb/>
the school Act. <lb/></p> 

<p>The debate was then adjourned. <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>