<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-03-07"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-03-07">7 March 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1869, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1870"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="16"/>
</bibl>

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_011.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_012.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_013.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_014.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_015.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-03-08_Page_016.hocr.html"/>
</item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-13">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>

<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_011"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_011.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_012"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_012.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_013"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_013.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_014"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_014.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_015"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_015.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_016"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_016.jpg"/></surface>

</facsimile>
<text>
<body>
<div type="debate">

<pb n="11" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_011.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">11</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BELL3">Mr. BELL</persName> wished to reply to the remarks <lb/>
of the hon. Leader of the Opposition re<lb break="no"/>specting Mr. I. C. Hall. The trade of this <lb/>
Island was crippled for want of a market for our produce, and since the abrogation of <lb/>
the Reciprocity Treaty, the duty of two <lb/>
dollars per barrel on mackerel, 10 cents per <lb/>
bush. on oats, and twenty-five cents per <lb/>
bush. on potatoes, had almost closed the <lb/>
American market against these articles al<lb break="no"/>together. The hon. Leader of the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion might be very loyal, as he had nothing <lb/>
to lose on account of this prohibitory tariff, <lb/>
but others felt the loss of the American <lb/>
market most keenly. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> stated that he did <lb/>
not object to Mr. Hall trying to get a treaty, <lb/>
but to his saying that the majority of the <lb/>
people of this Island were disloyal. <lb/></p>

<cb/>

<p><persName ref="pers:BELL3">Mr. BELL</persName> said it was the opinion of the <lb/>
greatest statesmen in the world that the <lb/>
whole continent of North America would <lb/>
eventually form one great nation. If Mr. <lb/>
Hall had stated that the majority of the <lb/>
people of this Island were in favor of An<lb break="no"/>nexation, the hon. Leader of the Opposition <lb/>
could not say that it was untrue; he did not <lb/>
know the feelings of the people in the <lb/>
country. When a poor man had a large <lb/>
family to support, he would be very much <lb/>
inclined to pursue for his family without <lb/>
troubling himself much acout loyalty. If <lb/>
Mr. Hall succeeded in getting us a market <lb/>
for our produce, for which there was at <lb/>
present scarcely any demand, he deserved <lb/>
more praise from the people of this Island <lb/>
than those obstructionists, who were con<lb break="no"/>tinually crying out that we must not do this <lb/>
or that on account of our loyalty. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> remarked that the name of <lb/>
a gentleman had been brought up in this <lb/>
debate who was a high-minded, liberal <lb/>
man, and who, while carrying on a successful <lb/>
business in this Island, had done a great <lb/>
deal for large numbers of men whom he <lb/>
employed. That man had a large interest <lb/>
at stake, and he had a perfect right to go to <lb/>
Washington to negotiate a treaty, but he <lb/>
had no right to tamper with out political <lb/>
position, and say that the people of this <lb/>
Island were willing to annex themselves to <lb/>
the United States. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BELL3">Mr. BELL</persName> asked if the hon. member (Mr. <lb/>
Brecken) could say that the majority of the <lb/>
people of this Island were not in favor of <lb/>
Annexation. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> said that he had been born <lb/>
under the stars and stripes, he should have <lb/>
gloried in being a son of the Great Repub<lb break="no"/>lic, for he believed the Americans were as <lb/>
far ahead of us as the white man was in advance of the indian, but his lot having <lb/>
been cast under the British flag, he believed <lb/>
in remaining true to it. If Confederation <lb/>
succeeded, the tie that bound us to the Moth<lb break="no"/>er Country would be drawn more closely, <lb/>
but if Confederation did not succeed, the <lb/>
next alternative would be Annexation. <lb/></p>

<p>The House then went into Committee <lb/>
on the Address in answer to His Honor's <lb/>
speech. <lb/></p>

<p>Hon. Mr. Kelly in the Chair. <lb/></p>

<p>On the first paragraph being read-- <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName>, in rising to move its <lb/>
adoption, admitted that the hon. Leader <lb/>
of the Opposition was right when he said <lb/>

<pb n="12" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_012.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">12</fw> 

that he (Mr. R.) should have made a <lb/>
speech when moving the Address, but he <lb/>
had lately been reading May on Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, and had there learned that he <lb/>
should also have appeared in court dress, <lb/>
so be hoped that he might be excused for <lb/>
having neglected both. He felt certain <lb/>
that the paragraph just read, which ex<lb break="no"/>pressed satisfaction that His Honor the <lb/>
Administrator enjoyed the confidence of <lb/>
Her Majesty, and continued to adminis<lb break="no"/>ter the Goverrnent of the Colony, would <lb/>
receive the cordial approval of this com<lb break="no"/>mittee, for he believed that it enunciated <lb/>
not only the views of the house but of <lb/>
the whole country. <lb/></p>

<p>The second paragraph of the Address, <lb/>
that relating to the visit of Prince Arthur, <lb/>
was then read. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName> said that the para<lb break="no"/>graph now before the committee expressed <lb/>
the belief that the auspicious <lb/>
event to which it referred would still <lb/>
further strengthen those feelings of <lb/>
loyalty and attachment to Her Majesty's <lb/>
person and throne, for which the people <lb/>
of this Islaud had ever been characterized. <lb/>
He had never heard in the country that <lb/>
there was any doubt entertained as to <lb/>
the loyalty of the Government, but from <lb/>
the remarks which had fallen from the <lb/>
hon. Leader of the Opposition it would <lb/>
appear that they were about to be put to <lb/>
the test on this question. That hon. <lb/>
member had, in effect, said, that opposi<lb break="no"/>tion to Confederation was disloyalty. <lb/>
Now, he (Mr. L.) had lately read that a <lb/>
distinguished Canadian statesman had <lb/>
reamarked that independence and annex<lb break="no"/>ation were co-relative terms. The Bri<lb break="no"/>tish Government, which might be called <lb/>
the government of governments, did not <lb/>
seem to object to independence, for an <lb/>
hon. gentleman of influence and position <lb/>
in the Dominion, who had declared that <lb/>
he looked forward to the time when <lb/>
Canada would become independent, was <lb/>
afterwards knighted by his sovereign. <lb/>
It was, therefore, evident that the free <lb/>
expression of such opinions was not re<lb break="no"/>garded with disfavor by the Imperial <lb/>
authorities, and why, he would ask, should <lb/>
we be branded with disloyalty if we pre<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

ferred remaining a part of the British empire <lb/>
to becoming a mere province of the <lb/>
Dominion of Canada? He (Mr. L.) did <lb/>
not, perhaps, attach as much importance <lb/>
to the Prince's visit as some persons, <lb/>
still he did not doubt that the presence <lb/>
amongst us of a son of our virtuous <lb/>
Queen tended to call forth feelings of <lb/>
respect for her person and loyalty to her <lb/>
government. In some quarters, he be<lb break="no"/>lieved, the hope was expressed that a <lb/>
scion of the royal House of Britain would <lb/>
yet occupy the throne of the Dominion. <lb/>
If such was the expectation of the British <lb/>
Government he feared they would be <lb/>
disappointed. Residents in America <lb/>
generally were too much afraid of ex<lb break="no"/>pense to think of a monarchy. One rea<lb break="no"/>son why independence was so much <lb/>
talked of now was because the present <lb/>
government in the mother country, which <lb/>
might be said to be largely influenced by <lb/>
the Manchester school of politicians, was <lb/>
attempting economy, in order to decrease <lb/>
taxation, and, therefore, the Colonies <lb/>
were looked upon as a burden. But he <lb/>
was of opinion that were the question put <lb/>
to the British people, a large majority <lb/>
would declare therselves opposed to the <lb/>
dismemberment of the empire. It was <lb/>
very evident that should the Dominion <lb/>
become independent, it would be a very <lb/>
expensive country to govern, as it was <lb/>
composed of merely a strip of habitable <lb/>
territory. If this Colony, then, refused <lb/>
to become incorporated with the Dominion, <lb/>
in order to save ourselves from its <lb/>
burdens, he did not think we should be <lb/>
charged with disloyalty, particularly as <lb/>
we wished to return our connection with <lb/>
Britain. We were no expense to the <lb/>
Mother Country. The Governor's salary <lb/>
itself was now paid out of the Island <lb/>
treasury. Even this paltry amount was <lb/>
refused us, though we have had to pay <lb/>
out of our own pockets for lands which <lb/>
the other Colonies received for nothing. <lb/>
Thousands upon thousands, too, were ex<lb break="no"/>pended in supporting military establish<lb break="no"/>ments in the other Provinces, while, if <lb/>
troops were sent to this Island, we had to <lb/>
pay for them to the last shilling. But <lb/>
the state of the Dominion generally was <lb/>
not such as to invite us to become a part <lb/>

<pb n="13" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_013.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">13</fw> 

of the confederacy. Her statesmen were <lb/>
accusing each other of corruption and <lb/>
dishonesty, words which, notwithstand<lb break="no"/>ing our sharp discussions, never disgraced <lb/>
our Legislature. Nova Scotia was not <lb/>
yet very contented, nor was the Red <lb/>
River trouble settled, therefore, taking all <lb/>
those things into consideration, he thought <lb/>
the people of this Island might very well <lb/>
shrink from entering the Dominion; and <lb/>
he had yet to learn that desiring to re<lb break="no"/>main a separate dependency of the British <lb/>
empire could be called disloyalty, or that <lb/>
the wishes of the Imperial Government <lb/>
should deter us from declining to accept <lb/>
the proposals of Canada. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>--This question was one <lb/>
to which, in the language of the address, <lb/>
we should give "our calm and deliberate <lb/>
attention." We were bound to return to <lb/>
the people the trust which we received <lb/>
from their hands; but every hon member <lb/>
ought to express his convictions on the <lb/>
subject under discussion, and not merely <lb/>
the sentiments which he thought would <lb/>
catch the popular breeze. The statesmen <lb/>
and the press of England seem disposed <lb/>
to allow the colonists to take the course <lb/>
which they consider most conducive to <lb/>
their interests, whether to retain their <lb/>
connection with the Mother Country, <lb/>
choose independence, or form an alliance <lb/>
with the great republic. The latter did <lb/>
not involve very great changes. We <lb/>
were really the same people, for we had <lb/>
the same origin, langauge and literature. <lb/>
A person taken blindfolded from these <lb/>
Colonies and set down in the United <lb/>
States, would scarcely distinguish that he <lb/>
had pased into a foreign country. But <lb/>
when we discussed the question of con<lb break="no"/>solidation with the neighboring States, <lb/>
we should not make ourselves contempt<lb break="no"/>ible by talking of it as a step which this <lb/>
Colony could take alone. We would go <lb/>
into annexation, if it ever came, just as <lb/>
soon as the rest of British America, and <lb/>
not one day sooner. Though the people <lb/>
here were to meet Mr. I. C. Hall on his <lb/>
return, and literally bow down on their <lb/>
knees and worship him for what he had <lb/>
said and done in Washington, it would <lb/>
not make the slightest difference with <lb/>
respect to united this Island with the <lb/>

<cb/>

republic. The hon member from Bedeque <lb/>
had stated that some eminent Canadian <lb/>
statesman had said that independence and <lb/>
annexation meant the same thing, and <lb/>
that Hon. Mr. Galt, for he believed that <lb/>
was the statesman alluded to, looked <lb/>
forward to the time when Canada would <lb/>
become independent; hence the hon. <lb/>
member seemed to argue that our going <lb/>
into Confederation would only hasten <lb/>
these events. But Mr. Galt was a con<lb break="no"/>federate, and he must believe that con<lb break="no"/>federation would succeed first, else how <lb/>
could he expect that independence would <lb/>
come? If confederation could do this <lb/>
for the Provinces, make them populous, <lb/>
wealthy and prosperous, so that they <lb/>
could set up as an independent country, <lb/>
then confederation must be a good thing. <lb/>
Canada could not become independent <lb/>
with a sparse population engaged in <lb/>
clearing away the forests and driving out <lb/>
the foxes. She must induce the people <lb/>
from the crowded cities and districts of <lb/>
the Mother Country to come and occupy <lb/>
her lands and build up her manufacturing <lb/>
industries, and Mr. Galt's position was <lb/>
that confederation would do this for her, <lb/>
and, as a consequence, independence <lb/>
would follow. And he (Mr. B.), if he <lb/>
might be allowed to couple his name <lb/>
with such a talented and distinguished <lb/>
man, would say that he agreed with Mr. <lb/>
Galt. He might be told that this was <lb/>
putting a different aspect on the question <lb/>
from the no-terms resolutions, which he <lb/>
supported, though at the time he did so he <lb/>
objected to the wording of them. The <lb/>
case, however, was quite different now. <lb/>
Then Confederation was onlyy a theory, <lb/>
now, with the exception of Newfound<lb break="no"/>land, it was an accomplished fact. Men<lb break="no"/>tion had been made of the charges <lb/>
preferred by Canadian politicians against <lb/>
each other. He supposed the allusion <lb/>
had reference to Sir Francis Hincks; <lb/>
but was that an argument why we should <lb/>
not go into the Dominion? Did the <lb/>
hon member for Bedeque, who brought <lb/>
up this matter, though he paid a com<lb break="no"/>pliment to our legislature, think that <lb/>
the people of this Colony were all so <lb/>
moral that there would never arise the <lb/>
person here who would tamper with the <lb/>

<pb n="14" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_014.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">14</fw> 

public funds? Were we so much better <lb/>
than our neighbours? Look at the United <lb/>
States. Where was the case of Andrew <lb/>
Johnson, the late President of that <lb/>
country, who was accused of almost <lb/>
every crime, and yet retained his position <lb/>
in spite of the House of Representatives? <lb/>
The hon member was also boastful about <lb/>
our position; we did not, he said, receive <lb/>
a shilling from the Home Government; <lb/>
the Governor's salary itself was paid by <lb/>
the Colony, and we were now ready for <lb/>
the fight. Well, all he (Mr. B.) could <lb/>
sayd was that a very different tone char<lb break="no"/>acterized the remarks of the Leader of <lb/>
the Government last session when he <lb/>
introduced the salary question. That <lb/>
gentleman, who was not now a member <lb/>
of this House, he highly esteemed in all <lb/>
the relations of life. Though he held an <lb/>
office which he (Mr. B.) would rather <lb/>
have seen given to another, yet his pre<lb break="no"/>sence on the Bench never suggested to <lb/>
him that he had been a political opponent. <lb/>
He believed that the scales of justice <lb/>
were safe in his hands, and he could <lb/>
further say that all his business inter<lb break="no"/>course with him during his political career <lb/>
had been pleasant and agreeable. That <lb/>
hon gentleman, when he proposed the <lb/>
payment of the Governor's salary, argued <lb/>
that no course was open to the House <lb/>
but to submit to the desire of the Home <lb/>
Government as expressed in the despatch <lb/>
of the Colonial Minister. At first he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) thought the point might be per<lb break="no"/>haps as well be yielded without any <lb/>
further objection. But, on reflection, <lb/>
after the first day's discussion of the <lb/>
subject, he suggested that as we had a <lb/>
good claim on account of the manner in <lb/>
which our lands were disposed of by the <lb/>
British Government, it might be well to<lb/>
try another remonstrance. But he was <lb/>
met by the hon members of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment with a declaration that such a step <lb/>
would be useless; that there was a threat <lb/>
in the despatch, and if we did not pay <lb/>
the Governor's salary, oh we would be <lb/>
forced into Confederation! The Oppo<lb break="no"/>sition had a caucus on the question, <lb/>
the only one they held last session, and <lb/>
there Hon. Mr. Palmer, who was an <lb/>
anti-Confederate, expressed the opinion <lb/>

<cb/>

that there was no danger of being coerced <lb/>
into Union, though we declined to vote <lb/>
the salary, as the British American Act <lb/>
expressly declared that admission into <lb/>
the Dominion was to be by joint ad<lb break="no"/>dresses of both branches of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature. This provision in that Act was <lb/>
mentioned in the House, but it would <lb/>
not do, nothing would satisfy the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment but to go down on their knees <lb/>
and vote the Governor's salary. If <lb/>
the hon member for Bedeque was <lb/>
sincere then, when he voted away a paltry <lb/>
£2100, which he said he had no right to <lb/>
do, how was it he had become so bold now <lb/>
that he can afford to speak lightly of <lb/>
the earnest wishes of Her Majesty's <lb/>
Imperial Government? <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR1">Hon. Mr. LAIRD</persName> had been ac<lb break="no"/>customed to look upon the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Charlottetown as a credit <lb/>
to the House, but to-night he had <lb/>
somewhat lost that favorable opin<lb break="no"/>ion. The hon member while talking <lb/>
about loyalty had remarked that Mr. <lb/>
Galt had said Confederation meant inde<lb break="no"/>pendence, and independence meant an<lb break="no"/>nexation, and, as the hon member agreed <lb/>
with Mr. Galt, he must be an annex<lb break="no"/>ationist. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> would not be misunder<lb break="no"/>stood. He was not in favor of annex<lb break="no"/>ation, but he looked upon isolation as <lb/>
played out. Either confederation or an<lb break="no"/>nexation must come, and he believed that <lb/>
confederation would carrry the day. <lb/>
British institutions were being put on <lb/>
their trial on this continent, and if they <lb/>
failed of success, he would admit he was <lb/>
wrong in advocating confederation. He, <lb/> 
however, looked upon our entering the <lb/>
Dominion as a necessity. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName>.--The hon. member for <lb/>
Charlottetown said there were only two <lb/>
courses before us, confederation or an<lb break="no"/>nexation. He (Mr. H.) did not think so. <lb/>
The Channel Islands, near Britian, had <lb/>
never been confederated with her, and <lb/>
yet he believed their inhabitants were <lb/>
loyal. The very way to make the people <lb/>
here disloyal would be to coerce them to <lb/>
join the Dominion. This fuss about <lb/>
loyalty did not amount to much, for the <lb/>
moment Canada became independent, <lb/>
were we connected with her, our alle<lb break="no"/>giance to the British Crown could cease. <lb/>
He believed there was not a more loyal <lb/>
people anywhere than the inhabitants of <lb/>

<pb n="15" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_015.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">15</fw>

this Island, if they were only left alone. <lb/>
Unless the Imperial Government was <lb/>
mocking us, we were at perfect liberty to <lb/>
enter or remain out of Confederation. <lb/>
If Canada became independent, her ex<lb break="no"/>pensese would be greatly increased. His <lb/>
opinion, therefore, was that we should <lb/>
stay out of the Dominion, remain loyal, <lb/>
and let the people of Canada, if they <lb/>
chose, become rebels as they were once <lb/>
before. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> admitted there had been <lb/>
a rebellion in Canada, but he had heard <lb/>
old residents of the province say that <lb/>
Papineau and those who took part with <lb/>
him in that disturbance were right. There <lb/>
hd been wrongs and grievances in that <lb/>
country which required to be redressed, <lb/>
and the course which these men took, <lb/>
call them rebels if you will, resulted in <lb/>
obtaining for Canada the boon of respon<lb break="no"/>sible government. The British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had admitted the justice of their <lb/>
cause when it came forward and indem<lb break="no"/>nified them for their losses. Lafontaine, <lb/>
one of their leaders, was afterwards <lb/>
made Chief Justice of Lower Canada, <lb/>
another, for whose head a reward was <lb/>
offered, was made a baronet, and Sir <lb/>
George Cartier, who also took part in the <lb/>
rebellion, had been honored by his sove<lb break="no"/>reign and privileged to dine at Bucking<lb break="no"/>ham Palace. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SINC5">Hon. P. SINCLAIR</persName> thought there must <lb/>
be something wrong with either the head or <lb/>
the heart of the hon member for Charlotte<lb break="no"/>town, when he said that a Canadian was <lb/>
made a baronet for resisting the laws of <lb/>
his country. He (Mr. S.) believed that <lb/>
the members of the Tenant League in <lb/>
this Island, so strongly condemned here <lb/>
from time to time, by some of the Oppo<lb break="no"/>sition party, had a much more just and <lb/>
righteous cause of complaint than the <lb/>
Canadian rebels of 1837, and yet had not <lb/>
adopted so high-handed a course to seek <lb/>
redress. The hon. member for Char<lb break="no"/>lottetown also said that the Government <lb/>
should have refused to pay the Governor's <lb/>
salary. Lst session, he was so indignant <lb/>
on this point, at last, that, notwithstand<lb break="no"/>ing the strong terms of the Coloninal <lb/>
Minister's despatch, he almost offered to <lb/>
go and plead the cause of the Colony at <lb/>
the bar of the House of Commons; but <lb/>
this year, simply because the British <lb/>
Governmnet expressed a wish that we <lb/>
should enter Confederation, he would <lb/>
give up the rights of the Colony at once, <lb/>
and comply with their desire. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> presumed that the prin<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

ciple on which the so-called rebels of <lb/>
Canada had been rewarded was because <lb/>
they had rendered a service to their <lb/>
country. By indemnifying them, the <lb/>
British Government had admitted that <lb/>
the grievances of which they complained <lb/>
should have been redressed before the <lb/>
rebellion occurred. The hon member <lb/>
for New London had dragged in the <lb/>
complaints of the Tenant League in com<lb break="no"/>parison with those which caused the dis<lb break="no"/>turbance in Canada. It was tiem this <lb/>
smelt-fishing in politics was given up. <lb/>
No resemblance existed between the two <lb/>
cases; yes, there was one point in which <lb/>
they might be said to agree - one of the <lb/>
Canadian rebels had been made a baronet <lb/>
and the hon. member for Belfast, Colonial <lb/>
Secretary. But, in other respects, there <lb/>
was a wide difference, for no bill of in<lb break="no"/>demnity had been passed for the benefit <lb/>
of these unfortunate members of the <lb/>
league who had suffered imprisonment. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> was amused to <lb/>
hear the utterances of the hon. member <lb/>
for Charlottetown in this debate. While <lb/>
the Liberal party were working out <lb/>
principles which that aristocrat had <lb/>
opposed, he had become republican in <lb/>
sentiment. The hon. member had also <lb/>
taken the position of justifying the <lb/>
Canadian rebellion; some of his remarks, <lb/>
in fact, were almost bordering on <lb/>
sedition. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> contended that if <lb/>
the hon. member for Charlottetown had <lb/>
uttered seditious sentiments, it was his <lb/>
(Col. Secy's) place, as first officer of the <lb/>
Government, to have him prosecuted. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:CAME5">Mr. CAMERON</persName> thought the paragraph <lb/>
before the committee had been over<lb break="no"/>looked. The hon.  member for Char<lb break="no"/>lottetown had said that isolation was <lb/>
played out, which meant that we must <lb/>
become confederated with Canada, or <lb/>
annexed to a foreign power. There <lb/>
might be some persons in the country in <lb/>
favor of one or other of these changes, <lb/>
but the large majority of the people was <lb/>
opposed to them both. He (Mr. C.) had <lb/>
as yet heard no argument advanced to <lb/>
show that the British Government was <lb/>
going to coerce us into Confederation. <lb/>
The people had a perfect right, he <lb/>
thought, to act as they pleased in this <lb/>
matter; and as they believed that union <lb/>
with Canada would increase their ex<lb break="no"/>penses and bring to corresponding <lb/>
benefit to the country, they were gene<lb break="no"/>rally opposed to it. He did not see why <lb/>
this Island should not remain an inde<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="16" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_016.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">16</fw>

pendent Colony as well as others. If <lb/>
the Colonies in all parts of the world <lb/>
were to be confederated, some more <lb/>
general arrangement would have to be <lb/>
made than any yet brought to our <lb/>
notice. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCAU1">Hon. Mr. McAULAY</persName> read the paragraph <lb/>
in the Address referring to Confederation, <lb/>
which promised that the House would <lb/>
give the subject "calm and deliberate <lb/>
attention," and asked whether hon. <lb/>
members had forgotten it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. McNEILL</persName> had the misfortune dur<lb break="no"/>ing his short political life to lose two <lb/>
political leaders, and was now serving <lb/>
under the third or fourth, but he had <lb/>
learned to attach little importance to <lb/>
loud professions. It was generally a <lb/>
sign of a weak cause. When a mere lad, <lb/>
an old friend had warned him to beware <lb/>
of those who boasted of their honesty, as <lb/>
they rarely could be trusted. He <lb/>
thought he might apply the advice to <lb/>
the loud professions of loyalty on the <lb/>
part of some hon. members in this dis<lb break="no"/>cussion. He was in Canada about the <lb/>
time of the rebellion there, and was <lb/>
aware that it resulted in good. Lafon<lb break="no"/>taine got possession of the Government, <lb/>
and then those who were displaced from <lb/>
power memorialized the sovereign against <lb/>
those who had shed blood receiving the <lb/>
seals of office. But no attention was <lb/>
paid to their remonstrance. In process <lb/>
of time he had no doubt that the tenant <lb/>
leaguers would be looked upon pretty <lb/>
much in the same light as the Canadian <lb/>
rebels. He had yet to learn that those of <lb/>
them who were lodged in jail had been <lb/>
urged by any person to act as they had <lb/>
done, but this, he knew, that they did <lb/>
not want the sympathy of the hon. <lb/>
member for Charlottetown. But to turn <lb/>
to the question of union, that gentleman <lb/>
appeared to think that there were only <lb/>
two courses open to us, confederation or <lb/>
annexation. He (Mr. McN.) could not <lb/>
see this. Why should we be under the <lb/>
necessity of going into annexation now, <lb/>
more than we ever were? There might <lb/>
possibly be a few more people in its <lb/>
favor than formerly, but he believed we <lb/>
could remain out of annexation as long <lb/>
as Canada could. In his opinion, the <lb/>
time was not far distant when European <lb/>
rule must cease in America. Look at <lb/>
Cuba, where Spanish rule was struggling <lb/>
for an existence, and at the failure of <lb/>
France to uphold an empire in Mexico. <lb/>
He agreed with the remark once made <lb/>
by the Hon. Mr. Howe, that the best <lb/>

<cb/> 

course for Canada to pursue was to re<lb break="no"/>main quiet; if she did so, she might <lb/>
prosper. But if she went about setting up <lb/>
a kingdom, and provoked the United <lb/>
States to war, she might be overrun in <lb/>
one week. Why the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was so anxious to get this Island, <lb/>
he (Mr. McN.) could not understand. <lb/>
They had already plenty of territory. <lb/>
Canada, he contended, lowered herself <lb/>
in making this offer to the Island, for it <lb/>
looked as if they thought we were setting <lb/>
ourselves up for sale. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. MR. HAVILAND</persName> remarked that he <lb/>
did not intend to speak on confederation <lb/>
now. When the despatches and corres<lb break="no"/>pondence in possession of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and the despatches that might <lb/>
come during the session, were before the <lb/>
House, he would be prepared to go into <lb/>
this great question. And he hoped when <lb/>
the discussion of this important subject <lb/>
came on. There would be nothing heard <lb/>
in this House about bibery and corrup<lb break="no"/>tion, or Canadian gold. He believed <lb/>
that no person in this Island had received <lb/>
Canadian gold to advocate confederation, <lb/>
nor did he think that any person had re<lb break="no"/>ceived American gold to advocate an<lb break="no"/>nexation. Let us have none of these vile <lb/>
insinuations that had passed through the <lb/>
press. Some of the main arguments in <lb/>
favor of Confederation were, that we <lb/>
might have a central authority for the <lb/>
direction of troops, and a breaking down <lb/>
of those hostile tariffs which prevented a <lb/>
free interchange of commodities. The <lb/>
United States, which some hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers in this House so much admired, <lb/>
would not have become so great had <lb/>
these tariffs between them not been <lb/>
swept away. But this was not the pro<lb break="no"/>per time to go into these questions. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CALL1">Hon. MR. CALLBECK</persName> argued with the <lb/>
hon. Leader of the Opposition, that this <lb/>
was not the proper time to discuss the <lb/>
confederation question; but if we gave <lb/>
no expression upon it, it might be said <lb/>
that we were waiting for the current of <lb/>
public opinion. He believed it was our <lb/>
duty when proposals came from the <lb/>
Dominion Government to give them our <lb/>
calm consideration. It had been said by <lb/>
hon. members on the other side of the <lb/>
House, that, as we had to pay the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor's salary, we would be under the <lb/>
same necessity to yield to the wishes of <lb/>
the British Government with respect to <lb/>
Confederation. He (Mr. C.) did not <lb/>
think so. We had no means of compet<lb break="no"/>ing the home Government to pay the <lb/> 

<pb n="17" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-03-07_Page_017.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">17</fw>

Governor's salary, and now since we <lb/>
had voted it, we stood in a good position <lb/>
to give this question a deliberate con<lb break="no"/>sideration. When the proposals came, <lb/>
he took them home, and studied them <lb/>
over in his mind, and the conclusion at <lb/>
which he arrived was that they were not <lb/>
fair to this Island. He thought that <lb/>
while Canada continued in her present <lb/>
unsettled state, we might as well remain <lb/>
as we were. If, after a time, we saw that <lb/>
confederation was going to be an advan<lb break="no"/>tage, we might then enter the Dominion. <lb/>
He believed that when the United States <lb/>
were confederated, Rhode Island obtain<lb break="no"/>ed as good terms when she entered the <lb/>
Union as those states which entered at <lb/>
first. The people of this Island would <lb/>
bear taxes sufficient for the wants of the <lb/>
Colony; but they would object to see <lb/>
their money taken away and expended <lb/>
on works in Canada which would yield <lb/>
them no benefit. <lb/></p> 

<p>The debate was then adjourned. <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>