<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1868-04-20"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1868-04-20">20 April 1868</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1868">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1868, Being the Second Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1868"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Patriot" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="210" to="212"/>
</bibl>
 
<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_210.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_211.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_212.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-11">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_210">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_210.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_211">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_211.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_212">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_212.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>

<body>



<div type="debate">
<pb n="210" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_210.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">210</fw> 

<head rendition="simple:right">MONDAY, April 20.</head><lb/>

<!-- DL 2018-06-11 commented out below as is incomplete -->

<!--<p> Resolved, That a further Conference be desired with<lb/></p>
<p> grossed. <lb/></p>-->

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="211" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_211.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">211</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. MCNEILL</persName>--</p>

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="212" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-20_Page_212.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">212</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p>I was astonished to hear the <lb/>
hon. Leader of the Government state in this House a short <lb/>
time ago that the persons belonging to the Tenant League <lb/>
agitation would have made some apology for their con<lb break="no"/>flict? Who would draw up that apology? What <lb/>
language should they employ? It would be a curiosity in<lb break="no"/>deed? I should like to know what kind of a document it <lb/>
would be? Would it be kept in some of the public offices <lb/>
in Charlottetown for the Tenant Union men to sign their <lb/>
recantation before it, before being permitted to hold any <lb/>
public office? Was it because the Tenant Union men did <lb/>
away with the religious excitement caused by the hon. <lb/>
members on the other side of the House, that they were to <lb/>
make an apology? There is only one gentleman present <lb/>
who has tried to say one word in defence of the actions of <lb/>
the late Government. The religious excitement got up by <lb/>
that party was the means of causing trouble and serious <lb/>
disturbances, and if these disturbances had not been stopped <lb/>
no man could tell in what they would have ended. Again, <lb/>
are the Tenant Leaguers to apologise because they de<lb break="no"/>nounced Confederation—because they protested against the <lb/>
proceedings of the Quebec Convention where there was not <lb/>
one word of sympathy for this Colony? The Tenant <lb/>
Union declared against Confederation, and that declaration <lb/>
had its effect. The British Government knew all about <lb/>
our troubles and the peculiar circumstances in which they <lb/>
have placed us; why then do they make this unfair de<lb break="no"/>mand upon us? I, for one, will never give my vote for the <lb/>
payment of the salary of an officer appointed by the British <lb/>
Government, as long as that Government leaves our griev<lb break="no"/>ances unredressed. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

<cb/>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName>.—I am of opinion that this move of <lb/>
the Imperial Government is ??? of side wind to work <lb/>
this Colony into Confederation and that the demand <lb/>
amounts to this, that union to join the other Colonies, <lb/>
we must pay our own Governor. We may be forced to <lb/>
pay this salary, but it is better to be us than to go into <lb/>
Confederation. A great question, ??? to our own <lb/>
the Irish Grants—couples the minds of the question of <lb/>
Great Britain at the present time. This Colony, above <lb/>
all the others, has above a great wish, to all ???, to <lb/>
marry out the Royal Instructions, and there ??? govern<lb break="no"/>ment made in 1851, that to consideration of the ??? <lb/>
which this Colony has sustained, the Imperial Government <lb/>
would pay the salary of the Lieutenant Governor. It has <lb/>
been shown ver clearly that the Island has been placed <lb/>
in anomalous position by the Home Gouvernment. We <lb/>
know that the late Secretary of the State for the Colonies <lb/>
was very much in favor of Confederation, and this is one <lb/>
reason why we are now asked to pay the demand made <lb/>
upon us. I think any Government would be ???? to <lb/>
their duty, if they did not resist this unjust pressure <lb/>
which has been brought to bear upon us, and I do hope <lb/>
that our rights will be sustained. As long as our Land <lb/>
Question remains unsettled, and as long as the Imperial <lb/>
Government refuses to give a guarantee for our Loan, to <lb/>
arrange for the purchase of the Proprietary Lands, this <lb/>
demand will be most unreasonable and unwarrantable. I <lb/>
cannot understand the movements of the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in regard to the means of getting this Colony join<lb break="no"/>ed to the Confederation, for it has been clearly shown to <lb/>
them, tha ta very large majority of our people are against <lb/>
it. Why should we be told to pay salary of our <lb/>
Lieutenant Governor on the one hand and on the other, <lb/>
that we shall receive $3000,000 if we unite with Canada? <lb/>
At present the British Government will not sanction <lb/>
coercive measures in buying up the proprietors lands; <lb/>
but we are told that if we enter Confederation measures, <lb/>
coercive or otherwise, would be carried into effect for the <lb/>
purpose of giving us free land. As we have neither Crown <lb/>
Lands nor Minerals, from which to draw a Revenue, the <lb/>
demand made upon us is unfair, and therefore if we are <lb/>
compelled to pay our Governor, we will appoint him our<lb break="no"/>selves. I quite agree with the remarks made by the hon. <lb/>
member for Murray Harbor on the subject, and I think <lb/>
we should send home a delegate for the purpose of repre<lb break="no"/>senting our claims, rather than yield to the demand. <lb/> </p>

<p>[...]</p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>