<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1865-03-24"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1865-03-24">24 March 1865</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>

<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1864">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1865, Being the Third Session of the Twenty-Second General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1865"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Protestant" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="45"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_038.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_039.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_040.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_041.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_042.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_043.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_044.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_045.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-05">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_038">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_038.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_039">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_039.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_040">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_040.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_041">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_041.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_042">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_042.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_043">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_043.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_044">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_044.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_045">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_045.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">
<pb n="38" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_038.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">38</fw>

<p><hi rendition="simple:centre">AFTERNOON.</hi></p>

<pb n="39" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_039.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">39</fw>

<p><hi rendition="simple:centre">UNION OF THE COLONIES.</hi><lb/></p> 

<p>On motion of the Hon. Col. Secreatry, the House went<lb/>
into the order of the day, viz : the consideration of the<lb/>
Report of the Quebec Conference, and the Despatches and<lb/>
papers relating thereto. The question, it was agreed,<lb/>
should be discussed with the Speaker in the chair ; and<lb/>
the rule was suspended which prevents a Member from<lb/>
addressing the House more than once on the same reso<lb break="no"/>lution.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE3">The COL. SECRETARY</persName>.—Mr. Speaker : with your per<lb break="no"/>mission I shall initiate the discussion of the important<lb/>

<cb/>

subject which is this evening to engage the attention of <lb/>
this House, by submitting the following Resolutions:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>1. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That the best interests, and present and future <lb/>
prosperity of British North America, would be promoted by a <lb/>
Federal Union, under the Crown of Great Britain, provided such <lb/>
Union could be effected on principles just to the several Provinces <lb/>
and Colonies. <lb/></p> 

<p>2. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That the existence of immense Military and <lb/>
Naval forces in the neighbouring Republic, renders it specially <lb/>
incumbent on the people of British North America to take the <lb/>
most efficient precautionary measures by which their independ<lb break="no"/>ence against Foreign aggression may be secured. <lb/></p> 

<p>3. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That a Union, such as in times of extraordinary <lb/>
danger would place the Militia, the Revenues, and the Resources <lb/>
of the several Provinces, at the disposal of a General Parliament, <lb/>
is necessary in order to maintain the independence of British <lb/>
North America against Foreign aggression, and to perpetuate our <lb/>
connection with the Mother Country. <lb/></p> 

<p>4. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That a Federal Union of British North America, <lb/>
based upon the Resolutions adopted at the Conference of Dele<lb break="no"/>lgates from the Provinces of Canada, Nova Scotia and New <lb/>
Brunswick, and the Colonies of Newfoundland and Prince <lb/>
Edward Island, held at the City of Quebec, 10th October, 1864, <lb/>
as the basis of a proposed Confederation of those Provinces and <lb/>
Colonies, would, among other advantages, promote the develop<lb break="no"/>ment of the trade and manufacturing capabilities of these <lb/>
Provinces and Colonies, and advance the general prosperity, by <lb/>
inducing the substitution of a customs tariff, uniform and com<lb break="no"/>mon to the Confederation, in lieu of the various tariffs now in <lb/>
force in the several Provinces and Colonies. <lb/></p> 

<p>5. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That the Report of the Conference of Delegates <lb/>
from the British North American Provinces and Colonies held <lb/>
at Quebec in October last, taken as a whole, contains a declar<lb break="no"/>ation of princlples—as the basis of a Federal Union—which this <lb/>
House considers just to the several Provinces and Colonies. <lb/></p> 

<p>6. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That this House, believing it is only by mutual <lb/>
concessions and compromises the several British North American <lb/>
Provinces and Colonies can ever agree upon those principles <lb/>
which shall form the basis of a Union, orders that the report of <lb/>
the Conference of Delegates from these several Provinces <lb/>
and Colonies held at Quebec in October last, be published <lb/>
throughout this Colony for the deliberate consideration of the <lb/>
people, on whom will devolve the acceptance or rejection of the <lb/>
proposed Union. <lb/></p> 

<p>7. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That until the larger Maritime Provinces and <lb/>
Canada shall have mutually agreed upon terms of Union, it is <lb/>
inexpedient that the people of Prince Edward Island should be <lb/>
called upon to decide on the question. <lb/></p> 

<p>8. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That in case the Provinces of New Brunswick, <lb/>
Nova Scotia and Canada, should at any time mutually agree <lb/>
upon the basis of a Union, the question be then forthwith sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to the decision of the people of this Island. <lb/></p></quote> 

<p>I have submitted these resolutions together, in order that <lb/>
honorable members may at once be made aware of the <lb/>
views which the advocates of Confederation, upon the <lb/>
terms proposed in the Report of the Quebec Conference, <lb/>
intend to submit by resolution to this House. Although <lb/>
I have submitted these resolutions together, my intention <lb/>
is, to take the opinion of the House upon each. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon. J. C. POPE</persName>.—Mr. Speaker, I wish to state that the <lb/>
Col. Sec. is somewhat out of order, as I gave notice yes<lb break="no"/>terday that I would propose a resolution on the subject. <lb/>
Pursuing the course that he has done, he ought at least <lb/>
to have intimated that this was an open question, and <lb/>
that a free expression of opinion was expected upon it <lb/>
from hon. members on both sides of the House. I do not <lb/>
desire to obstruct the Colonial Secretary in his speech <lb/>
now since he has commenced, but merely to inform the <lb/>
House that the resolutions which he has submitted do <lb/>
not express the views of the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE3">Col. SECRETARY</persName>.—Mr. Speaker, I am satisfied that I <lb/>
am in order. I did not deem it necessary formally to<lb/>
declare to this House that the resolutions just submitted<lb/>
do not express the views of the Government. It is well<lb/>
known, Sir, not only in this House, but from one end of<lb/>

<pb n="40" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_040.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">40</fw>

the Island to the other, that the members of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, with two exceptions, are hostile to the proposed<lb/>
Confederation. The Report of the resolutions of the<lb/>
Quebec Conference does not come before this House as a<lb/>
Government measure. Confederation is an open question,<lb/>
and in this discussion I recognize but two parties-the one<lb/>
composed of the four or five members who are favourable to<lb/>
Confederation, and the other consisting of the six and<lb/>
twenty members who I believe to be opposed to Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. Mr. Speaker, I enter upon the discussion of the<lb/>
questions involved in the Report of the Quebec Conference,<lb/>
deeply sensible of their magnitude and importance, and<lb/>
of my utter incompetency to do them justice ; but, Sir, in<lb/>
this House the number of those who advocate Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, which this Report contemplates, is so very small-<lb break="yes"/>consisting of some four or five only-that we cannot afford<lb/>
that even one should remain silent. In taking the lead in<lb/>
the discussion of this subject, I am encouraged by the<lb/>
consciousness that the gentlemen who will follow me, in<lb/>
support of these resolutions, are abler than I am to do<lb/>
justice to the great question in which they relate. It is<lb/>
generally known, Sir, that the Quebec Conference had its<lb/>
origin in the resolutions which, last Session, were passed<lb/>
by the Legislatures of Nova Scotia, New Brunswick and<lb/>
Prince Edward Island, authorizing a convention of<lb/>
Delegates for the purpose of conferring upon the subject<lb/>
of a Legislative Union of these Provinces. When the<lb/>
resolution assenting to the Convention, of which I have<lb/>
spoken, was before this House last Session, I declared<lb/>
myself in favor of the Legislative Union which it contem<lb break="no"/>plated, and at the same time expressed regret that the<lb/>
Legislatures of the neighboring Provinces had not proposed<lb/>
the larger scheme of Union, which should include all the<lb/>
British possessions in North America. Of the thirty<lb/>
members of which this House is composed, but two<lb/>
declared themselves in favor of a Legislative Union of<lb/>
these three Maritime Provinces, although several hon<lb/>
members expressed themselves as not averse to a Federal<lb/>
Union of all the Provinces. In due time Delegates from<lb/>
Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, and Prince Edward Island,<lb/>
assembled in Conference in this Building. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada had been sent to this Island a deputation<lb/>
composed of the leading statesmen of that Province.<lb/>
These gentlemen were admitted to the Conference shortly<lb/>
after its proceedings were opened, and at their instance<lb/>
the Conference postponed the further discussion of the<lb/>
question of the proposed Legislative Union, in order to<lb/>
allow the Canadian Government to submit a scheme for a<lb/>
general Confederation of the Provinces of British North<lb/>
America. After a tour through the Lower Provinces the<lb/>
Canadians returned to Quebec. With the sanction of the<lb/>
Crown, and at the request of His Lordship the Governor<lb/>
General, the Governments of Nova Scotia, New Brunswick,<lb/>
Newfoundland and Prince Edward Island, sent Delegates<lb/>
to Quebec, for the purpose of discussing with the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada, the practicability of a Federal Union of<lb/>
the Provinces of British North America under the Crown<lb/>
of Great Britain. I have heard a great deal said against<lb/>
the Government of this Island for acceding to the request<lb/>
of the Governor General. I need not inform this House<lb/>
that the request of the Governor General, that Delegates<lb/>
should be sent to represent this Island at the proposed<lb/>
Conference, was one which the Government would not<lb/>
have been justified in refusing. Exception has also been<lb/>
taken to the constitution of the delegation. It was<lb/>
understood by the members of the respective Governments<lb/>
represented at Charlottetown, that the gentlemen who had<lb/>
composed that Conference should be members of the<lb/>
Conference to be held at Quebec. The Government of<lb/>
the Island considered it very desirable that the Quebec<lb/>
Conference all political parties should be fairly and fully<lb/>
represented. I admit Mr. Speaker, that at the time of<lb/>
the appointment of Delegates to proceed to Quebec, I<lb/>
unanimously agree to recommend to the Legislature and<lb/>
people of this Island the adoption of the resolutions of the<lb/>

<cb/>

Conference, such resolutions, being so recommended, <lb/>
would be accepted alike by the Legislature and<lb/>
the people. At the Charlottetown Conference this<lb/>
Island was represented by five Delegates. The party in<lb/>
opposition to the Government, in each branch of the<lb/>
Legislature, was represented by one member-by the Hon<lb/>
Mr Coles of the Assembly, and the Hon A. A. McDonald<lb/>
of the Legislative Council. This Delegation, it was con<lb break="no"/>sidered, did not sufficiently represent the Opposition in<lb/>
this House ; therefore the Hon Edward Wheland, whose<lb/>
abilities and long parliamentary experiences render him<lb/>
eminently a representative man of his party, was requested<lb/>
to join the Delegation to Quebec. The present Solicitor<lb/>
General was also requested to give us the aid of his<lb/>
knowledge and experiences. Prince Edward Island, it will<lb/>
be seen, was fully represented at the Quebec Conference ;<lb/>
and although the seven gentlemen who composed the<lb/>
Delegation declared, in Canada, the report of the Con<lb break="no"/>ference such as they could recommend for the adoption of<lb/>
the Legislature and people of this Island, I regret to say,<lb/>
Sir, that very few, either in the Legislature or among the<lb/>
people, are at present disposed to adopt the resolutions of<lb/>
the Conference. the Conference assembled at Quebec,<lb/>
and the important subject, for the consideration of which<lb/>
the leading public men of five Provinces and Colonies had<lb/>
met together, was entered upon, in a spirit of patriotism,<lb/>
by gentlemen deeply impressed with the magnitude, and<lb/>
with the difficulties of the task which lay before them-<lb break="yes"/>the devising a constitution which should unite, under<lb/>
one general government, the Provinces of Canada, Nova<lb/>
Scotia, New Brunswick, and the Colonies of Newfoundland<lb/>
and Prince Edward Island, in each of which is maintained<lb/>
a distinct and different tariff- a different currency- in<lb/>
short an entirely distinct government- and which con<lb break="no"/>tained in the aggregate a population approaching four<lb/>
millions. The Report now under consideration is the<lb/>
result of their labors. In all their deliberations, the<lb/>
Delegates kept in mind that it was absolutely necessary<lb/>
that mutual concessions should be made. The many<lb/>
difficulties with which they had to contend, could only have<lb/>
been surrounded by mutual deference and concession.<lb/>
The resolutions passed by the Conference were not, in<lb/>
any particular, in accordance with the views of the<lb/>
Representatives of each Province and Colony. Taken<lb/>
together, they embodied a constitution which, as I con<lb break="no"/>sidered, received the unanimous support of the members<lb/>
of the Conference. Gentlemen with whom I was associated<lb/>
in the Delegation representing this Island, have, I am<lb/>
aware, since their return to the Island, donounced that<lb/>
which in Canada they approved. It is not my intention,<lb/>
Mr. Speaker, on the present occasion to call in question<lb/>
the right of these gentlemen to change their views ; nor<lb/>
shall I charge them with inconsistency. I do not feel<lb/>
myself at liberty to allude to the course pursued by hon<lb/>
gentlemen at the Conference, nor to quote from their<lb/>
speeches delivered there. There is one very strong reason<lb/>
why the expressions of members, while at the Conference,<lb/>
should not be quoted. It is this. It was understood that<lb/>
the deliberations should be considered private. There is<lb/>
no record to which to appeal in the events of the correct<lb break="no"/>ness of statements attributed to hon members being called<lb/>
in question. I shall endeavor to deal with the resolutions<lb/>
as reported from the Conference, and not with the sug<lb break="no"/>gestions or amendments of any hon member made at the<lb/>
Conference previously to the passing of these resolutions.<lb/>
It has been objected that the deliberations of the Con<lb break="no"/>ference were conducted with closed doors. The reasons<lb/>
for such an arrangement are obvious. The admission of<lb/>
the public would, for some extent, have prevented that<lb/>
free and full discussion which was so desirable, while the<lb/>
daily publication of the expressions of members would<lb/>
have prevented unanimous conclusions. It has been urged<lb/>
against the Confederation of the Colonies, proposed in the<lb/>
Report of the Quebec Conference, that the scheme had its<lb/>
origin in the local difficulties of the Canadians. It is true<lb/>
that the sectional difficulties of Canada during the last year<lb/>

<pb n="41" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_041.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">41</fw>

occasioned a " deadlock." I cannot, however, discover <lb/>
any force in this objection. This crisis in the political <lb/>
affairs of Canada led the statesmen of that Province to <lb/>
consider their position, with iivicw to remedy evils which <lb/>
were such as to render imprnetioiihlo the further govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the Province under the existing constitution. I <lb/>
need not enumerate the many reasons which induced <lb/>
those statesmen to propose a Confederation of all the <lb/>
Provinces. They realized, among other things, the <lb/>
position in which these Provinces stand in relation to the <lb/>
neighboring Republic, which, within the short space of<lb/>
four years, from being a purely commercial and agricul<lb break="no"/>tural people had become one of the greatest military and<lb/>
naval powers in existence. They had also received an<lb/>
intimation from the Imperial Government to the effect that<lb/>
the people of the Colonies would be required to contribute<lb/>
largely to the cost of Fortifications, and other means of<lb/>
defence, as a condition of England's undertaking to co<lb break="no"/>operate in their defence. The Colonies have heretofore left<lb/>
it to England to provide and maintain fleets and armies<lb/>
for the security of their country at the cost of the taxpayers<lb/>
of Great Britain ; and, Sir, I can see nothing unreasonable<lb/>
in the people of the Colonies being, at this day, called upon to<lb/>
contribute of their ability, to the cost of their defence. As<lb/>
subjects of the Crown of Great Britain, we have a right<lb/>
to demand the protection of the Mother Country ; but if<lb/>
we have this right, we are most certainly under the<lb/>
obligation to contribute of our ability to the maintenance<lb/>
of those fleets and armies which are necessary for the<lb/>
defence of the Empire of which we form a part. If, Sir,<lb/>
the existence upon our borders of a vast military and naval<lb/>
power, rendering it prudent for the Colonies to prepare<lb/>
means for their defence, together with other reasons, can be<lb/>
adduced to prove that Confederation is essential to the<lb/>
maintenance of our institutions, and that it will promote<lb/>
our common prosperity, it matters not what were the<lb/>
peculiar circumstances in which the project of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion had its origin ; whether it arose out of the political<lb/>
dissentions between Upper and Lower Canada, or<lb/>
resulted from less important causes. The first of the<lb/>
Resolutions just submitted reads as follows:—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>1. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That the best interests, and present and future <lb/>
prosperity of British North America, would be promoted by a <lb/>
Federal Union, under the Crown of Great Britain, provided such <lb/>
Union could be effected on principles just to the several Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces and Colonies. <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>I would willingly have advocated a Legislative Union of <lb/>
all these Provinces, but such a Union was believed to be <lb/>
unattainable. The resolution just read, is identical with <lb/>
the resolution of the Quebec Conference, and will, I <lb/>
believe, be supported by a large majority of this House <lb/>
The leader of the Opposition—the Hon Mr Coles—will <lb/>
certainly support me, so far as this resolution is con<lb break="no"/>cerned, seeing that the sentiment which it expresses was<lb/>
received by the Conference with acclamation. Union is<lb/>
stength, and strength in British America is certainly<lb/>
desirable. The second and third Resolutions are as<lb/>
follow :—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>2. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That the existence of immense Military and <lb/>
Naval forces in the neighbouring Republic, renders it specially <lb/>
incumbent on the people of British North America to take the <lb/>
most efficient precautionary measures by which their independ<lb break="no"/>ence against foreign aggression may be secured <lb/></p> 

<p>3. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That a Union, such as in times of extraordinary<lb/>
danger would place the Militia, the Revenues, and the Resources<lb/>
of the several Provinces, at the disposal of a General Parliament,<lb/>
is necessary, in order to maintain the independence of British<lb/>
North America against foreign aggression, and to perpetuate our<lb/>
connection with the Mother Country.<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>To these, I apprehend, there will be no objection on the<lb/>
part of any honorable member. To defend our hearths<lb/>
and homes is, I trust, regarded by all as a sacred duty.<lb/>
It will, I assume, be generally admitted that the people<lb/>
of the British North American Colonies cannot defend<lb/> 

<cb/>

themselves against the power of the Great Republic upon <lb/>
our borders, should that warlike nation resolve to "gobble<lb/>
us up." Our safety, therefore, can only be secured by<lb/>
the powerful protection of the Mother Country ; and in<lb/>
the event of a war with the United States of America, the<lb/>
resources of Britain, great as they are, would be taxed<lb/>
to the utmost, in order to save the Colonies from subjuga<lb break="no"/>tion. England well knows this, and we may depend upon<lb/>
it that her statesmen are too wise, too mindful of the<lb/>
national honor to send out a few regiments, or a small<lb/>
fleet to suffer defeat. If we neglect to discharge our duty<lb/>
in providing for our safety, we may reasonably expect<lb/>
that England will withdraw her military and naval<lb/>
forces, and leave us to our fate. But on the other hand, if<lb/>
we show ourselves anxious to maintain our connection with<lb/>
England, and do that which is reasonably required of us,<lb/>
England will defend us to the utmost. It is to my mind<lb/>
very evident that we must choose between consolidation<lb/>
of the different Provinces and Colonies, and absorption<lb/>
into the American Republic. Consolidation,— the placing<lb/>
the revenues and the men of the several Provinces under<lb/>
the control of a central power would, in the event of a<lb/>
war, be absolutely necessary in order to the efficient<lb/>
organization of our colonial resources. In Britain as well<lb/>
as in the Colonies, the opinion is widely entertained, that<lb/>
our absorption into the Great Republic is inevitable. In<lb/>
the event of a war between England and the United States<lb/>
of America, the battle ground would be the British<lb/>
Provinces. It has therefore been contended by some that<lb/>
in order to avert so great a calamity, the connection<lb/>
between the Provinces and the Mother Country should be<lb/>
severed by mutual consent, and that we should become<lb/>
an independent nation. Others, Sir, consider that it would<lb/>
be more to our interest to retain our connection with<lb/>
England, and to endure, if necessary, the horrors of war—<lb/>
that we should remain a portion of the Great Empire of<lb/>
Britain, continue to live under the glorious old flag, and<lb/>
our Monarchical institutions. The latter is the prevailing<lb/>
opinion. There is an influential party in England who, I<lb/>
believe, desire to get rid of these Colonies on the ground that<lb/>
they are an expense to the Empire; and because colonists do<lb/>
not accommodate their Customs Tariff to suit the<lb/>
manufacturers of Sheffield and Manchester. I have<lb/>
yet to learn, Sir, that the people of this Island have<lb/>
not a right to enjoy all the privileges of Englishmen to an<lb/>
equal extent with either Mr Cobden, Mr Bright, or<lb/>
Professor Goldwin Smith. Our right to these privileges,<lb/>
I consider, exists in virtue of our allegiance, and cannot<lb/>
be affected by our neglect to patronize or encourage the<lb/>
manufacturers of Sheffield or Manchester. I have said,<lb/>
Sir, that as British subjects, we have our rights ; but<lb/>
let it not be forgotten, Sir, that we have our obligations ;<lb/>
and that chief among these obligations is that which<lb/>
demands that we shall contribute our full share to the<lb/>
cost of defending the Empire. With the strength of<lb/>
England available for our defence, I fear not the sub<lb break="no"/>jugation of the Provinces, so long as the inhabitants<lb/>
remain loyal. The inevitable result of a war with the<lb/>
United States of America would be the occupation of large<lb/>
portions of our territory by hostile soldiery ; but the<lb/>
strongholds open to the sea would be held even against the<lb/>
gigantic power of the United States. If we once separate<lb/>
from Great Britain, we need not depend upon England's<lb/>
assistance should we ever be so unfortunate as to become<lb/>
embroiled with our neighbours. The manner in which<lb/>
the English Government recently acted towards Denmark<lb/>
is calculated to teach us a valuable lesson. Under a<lb/>
general organization the four millions of inhabitants in<lb/>
the Provinces could supply a formidable military force.<lb/>
Without such organization—which would be the result of<lb/>
Confederation—the Provinces separately can do little or<lb/>
nothing. We have recently had a discussion in this<lb/>
House on the subject of our Militia. To train the Militia of<lb/>
this Island would require an annual outlay nearly equal<lb/> 
to our entire Revenue ; and were our Militia to be <lb/>

<pb n="42" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_042.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">41</fw>

rendered efficient, of what service would they be unless<lb/>
they were available for the defence of the frontiers of<lb/>
Canada or of New Brunswick? That our sons would<lb/>
be required to shoulder arms and march to the frontiers<lb/>
of Canada has been urged as an argument against Con<lb break="no"/>federation. This Island is of no importance in a military<lb/>
point of view. It will never be a battlefield. A Gunboat or a<lb/>
Privateer might enter into any one of our numerous<lb/>
harbors do a great deal of mischief, and depart before<lb/>
our defenders could be mustered. Unless under a general<lb/>
organization our Militia will necessarily be useless. I am<lb/>
not aware, Sir, that I am the most inefficient officer in the<lb/>
service, although I have held a commission for a quarter<lb/>
of a century, and have never seen the company to which I<lb/>
am supposed to be attached. Although opposed to<lb/>
spending money uselessly upon our Militia, I am in favor<lb/>
of training every man in the Provinces capable of bearing<lb/>
arms, provided such training be conducted under a general<lb/>
organization, believing that readiness on our part for<lb/>
defence, would be our best protection against invasion.<lb/>
The fourth resolution reads thus :—<lb/></p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>4. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That a Federal Union of British North America,<lb/>
based upon the Resolutions adopted at the Conference of Delegates<lb/>
from the Provinces of Canada, Nova Scotia and New Brunswick,<lb/>
and the Colonies of Newfoundland and Prince Edward Island,<lb/>
held at the City of Quebec, 10th October, 1864, as the basis<lb/>
of a proposed Confederation of those Provinces and Colonies,<lb/>
would among other advantages, promote the development of<lb/>
the trade and manufacturing capabilities of these Provinces and<lb/>
Colonies, and advance the general prosperity, by inducing the<lb/>
substitution of a Customs Tariff, uniform and common to the<lb/>
Confederation, in lieu of the various Tariffs now in force in the<lb/>
several Provinces and Colonies.<lb/></p></quote> 

<p>The most effectual means of advancing our prosperity would be<lb/>
found in a Union, such as is proposed in the Report of the Quebec<lb/>
Conference. A great deal has been said and written on the<lb/>
subject of the proposed Confederation by our Island statesmen,<lb/>
who have told the people of the disastrous effects the Union<lb/>
would exert upon our trade and manufactures. If the gentle<lb break="no"/>men, to whom I allude, have not instructed, they have, at least,<lb/>
amused the more intelligent of their hearers and readers. It<lb/>
is true, Sir, that our trade is chiefly in agricultural produce, that<lb/>
our manufactures are few, and that there are physical disabilities<lb/>
which will prevent us from becoming a great manufacturing<lb/>
country. For five months in the year we are cut off from com<lb break="no"/>munication with our neighbors, yet, Sir, our manufactures are<lb/>
capable of expansion, and under Union they would expand. At <lb/>
present the manufacturers of Leather and of Cloth are obliged to<lb/>
limit their operations. If they manufacture more than they can sell<lb/>
in this little Island they have to export, subject to a heavy duty.<lb/>
Yet even in the face of this duty we now export Island Manufac<lb break="no"/>tured Leather to New Brunswick. But, Sir, Union would<lb/>
develop the enormous manufacturing capabilities of Nova Scotia<lb/>
and New Brunswick. Great, Prince Edward Island never can<lb/>
become, her geographical position , her limited area, her small<lb/>
population, and the absence of all mineral deposits, preclude us<lb/>
from becoming a great country ; but, Sir , the Provinces with<lb/>
which it is proposed that we should unite, contain every element<lb/>
of greatness ; there is no reason, then, why they should not become<lb/>
a great and prosperous country, or why we should not share their<lb/>
greatness. It is argued that the Canadian Tariff would follow<lb/>
Union, and that the people of Prince Edward Island would,<lb/>
under its operation, be necessitated to pay an increased amount<lb/>
of duties. I do not believe such would be the case. It is true that <lb/>
the Canadian Tariff is very much higher than the Tariff of this<lb/>
Island. Tea and Sugar , imported under the Canadian Tariff,<lb/>
would probably cost higher than they cost at present ; but, it is<lb/>
equally true that a variety of articles on which we now pay<lb/>
duty, would then, as the manufactures of the Confederation<lb/>
come to us duty free, and the saving which we should effect on<lb/>
these articles of Home Manufacture, would very materially ex<lb break="no"/>ceed the excess of duty which we should pay upon foreign im<lb break="no"/>portations. It has been urged, that under Confederation,<lb/>
although we might obtain from within the Confederation many<lb/>
articles, the manufactures of Canada, Nova Scotia and New<lb/>
Brunswick, the Canadian Tariff would prevent such articles from<lb/>
being imported from Britain and the United States. But, Sir,<lb/>
if, under Confederation, the people of Prince Edward Island<lb/>

<cb/>

should be able to procure British Colonial Manufactures cheaper<lb/>
than they can now procure similar articles from the United States<lb/>
or Britain, they would evidently be gainers by Confederation.<lb/>
The great wealth and prosperity of Britain are mainly attributa<lb break="no"/>ble to the coal and iron which she possesses. The importance<lb/>
of the possession of iron was recognized many ages ago. When<lb/>
Croesus exhibited to Solon his treasures of gold and silver, the<lb/>
Philosopher is said to have remarked to the King, " that when<lb break="no"/>soever another should come who had better iron than he, he<lb/>
would be master of all his gold and silver." Coal and iron have<lb/>
caused Britain to become the workship of the world. Where is<lb/>
there, on the face of the earth, a country that possesses more<lb/>
valuable deposits of iron and of coal than Nova Scotia ? She<lb/>
has an inexhaustible supply of the most valuable iron, coal, and<lb/>
limestone, in close proximity to each other and to navigable har<lb break="no"/>bors, and in addition has an abundance of fertile land. Sir, Nova<lb/>
Scotia with all these advantages must become a great country.<lb/>
(Hear, hear.) Why, I would ask, as a British American, do we<lb/>
not make an effort to develope our boundless manufacturing capa<lb break="no"/>bilities ? Were you, Sir, to go to the enterprising people of the neigh<lb break="no"/>boring republic, and to enter their manufactories, you would there<lb/>
learn the fact that a large number of their most skilful mechanics<lb/>
are men from these British Provinces ; this Island has contributed<lb/>
her proportion of these valuable men ; they year after year leave<lb/>
their native country and never return to it, because, Sir, there is, at<lb/>
home, no employment for them. (Hear, hear.) The sooner the<lb/>
Colonists set to work to establish manufactories, the better will it<lb/>
be for all of us. But, Sir, to this, Confederation is requisite.<lb/>
Tariffs between the Provinces must be abolished. The population<lb/>
of Nova Scotia is too limited to support extensive manufactures,<lb/>
and the same thing may be said of New Brunswick. In illustration.<lb/>
I may be permitted to state that the latter Province is capable of<lb/>
producing an unlimited supply of very valuable coal oil—an arti<lb break="no"/>cle on which we last year paid in duty nearly £1,000.—The pro<lb break="no"/>prietors of the coal oil works produce the article only in limited<lb/>
quantity. They cannot send their oil to Nova Scotia or to this<lb/>
Island, by reason of the duty which, in each of the Provinces,<lb/>
is imposed upon its importation, and therefore their mines are<lb/>
only partially worked. Unite the several Provinces, as proposed<lb/>
in the Report of the Quebec Conference, give to Nova Scotia to<lb/>
New Brunswick, to Prince Edward Island four millions of cus<lb break="no"/>tomers. If this should be done, our young men, who have be<lb break="no"/>come skilful artizans in the workshops of the United States,<lb/>
would find employment in their native Provinces. Sir, it is im<lb break="no"/>possible to over estimate the manufacturing greatness which<lb/>
Nova Scotia is capable of attaining. The iron and coal of that<lb/>
Province are now exported to Europe and to the United States<lb/>
where they are employed in the manufactures of aricles which<lb/>
we now import from these countries. The time is propitious for<lb/>
Confederation. We may reasonably hope for the restoration of<lb/>
peace in the United States. Intercolonial free trade would in the<lb/>
words of the resolution promote the development of the trade and<lb/>
manufacturing capabilities of the Colonies and advance the great<lb/>
prosperity, but intercolonial free trade is impracticable without<lb/>
Confederation. The proceedings of the Conference at Char<lb break="no"/>lottetown and Quebec were wached with interest by the civil<lb break="no"/>ized world. The people of those countries of Europe which<lb/>
send emigrants to America have had their attention directed to<lb/>
the British Provinces. Let these Provinces become consolidated,<lb/>
and then emigrants to come from Europe, as well as many now<lb/>
in the Republic, will seek the British Provinces as a home in<lb break="no"/>stead of the United States, now so heavily taxed. I come now,<lb/>
Sir, to the 5th and 6th Resolutions :—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"5. That the Report of the Conference of Delegates from the<lb/>
British North American Provinces and Colonies held at Quebec<lb/>
in October last, taken as a whole, contains a declaration of<lb/>
principles—as the basis of a Federal Union—which this House<lb/>
considers just to the several Provinces and Colonies."<lb/></p> 

<p>"6. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That this House, believing it is only by mutual<lb/>
concessions and compromises the several British North American<lb/>
Provinces and Colonies can ever agree upon those principles<lb/>
which shall form the basis of a Union, orders that the report of<lb/>
the Conference of Delegates from these several Provinces and<lb/>
Colonies held at Quebec in October last, be published through<lb break="no"/>out this colony for the deliberate consideration of the people, on<lb/>
whom will devolve the acceptance or rejection of the proposed<lb/>
Union."<lb/></p></quote> 

<p>I am sorry to say, Sir, that I have no hope of carrying a majority<lb/>
in favor of the declaration, that the principles of Union contained<lb/>

<pb n="43" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_043.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">43</fw>

in the Report of the Quebec Conference are just to this Island. <lb/>
I, believe them to be so. I declare I myself in favor of this<lb/>
Report, while at the Conference, because I so believed, and, Sir,<lb/>
I trust I have too high a respect for myself to say now, that the<lb/>
principles of Union therein laid down are not just to this Island,<lb/>
because the great majority of the people regard them as unjust.<lb/>
The resolutions which form the Report, as I have already stated<lb/>
are the results of mutual deference and concession, and in my<lb/>
humble judgment are such as we should eagerly accept. I have<lb/>
been told, Sir, that by advocating the adoption of the principle<lb/>
of the Quebec Report, I am placing myself in antagonism to the<lb/>
people of this Island, and especially to my own constituents. I,<lb/>
Sir, should consider myself unworthy of the confidence reposed<lb/>
on me, as a Representative of the people, were I to shrink from<lb/>
the full expression of my opinion upon a great subject deeply<lb/>
affecting the interests of the Colony, simply because my con<lb break="no"/>stituents, or the people of the Colony, are supposed to entertain<lb/>
any question, can, in themselves, have no influence upon my<lb/>
opinion. In the present instance, I believe Confederation would<lb/>
promote the best interests of the Island. I may be aware that<lb/>
my constituents think otherwise, and are opposed to Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. My individual opinion may remain unchanged, but a<lb/>
knowledge of the views and wishes of my constituents, would<lb/>
most materially influence my conduct. Popular opinion<lb/>
is proverbially changable, and I expect ere long to hear<lb/>
many of those who now denounce the Report of the Quebec<lb/>
Conference admit that after mature deliberation, they have<lb/>
come to the conclusion that its principles are just. I re<lb break="no"/>gard the terms of the Report of the Quebec Conference—so<lb/>
far as they relate to Prince Edward Island—to be, in a financial<lb/>
aspect, just and even liberal. The average indebtedness of the<lb/>
Provinces generally, is equal to $25 per head of the population.<lb/>
The debt of Prince Edward Island is, in reality, but little in<lb/>
excess of $2 per head. By the terms of the Report we should<lb/>
receive annually from the General Government the interest of an<lb/>
amount equivalent to $25 per head of our population—less the<lb/>
interest of our actual indebtedness—or in other words we should<lb/>
receive annually £30,000 currency from the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, over and above the interest upon our public debt. I shall,<lb/>
doubtless, be told that under Confederation our Tariff would be<lb/>
raised so as to yield a revenue equivalent to $25 per head of the<lb/>
aggregate population of the Provinces, and that therefore we<lb/>
should pay annually, in extra taxation, a sum exceeding £30,000.<lb/>
I, Sir, contend that, under Confederation, we should, for reasons<lb/>
which I have already stated, pay less in duties than we pay at<lb/>
present, notwithstanding the higher Tariff. If I am correct in<lb/>
this view of the matter, it is clear that the £30,000 a year<lb/>
would be gained, as a consequence of Confederation. This<lb/>
£30,000 a year, together with the annual allowance of 80 cents<lb/>
per head of our population, estimated according to the census of<lb/>
1861, and a few other items, would be sufficient for our re<lb break="no"/>quirements. (Laughter.) But, say the opponents of Confed<lb/>
eration, "our population will, in a few years, be double what<lb/>
it now is, while our income from the General Government will<lb/>
not increase." I think I am justified in asserting that the<lb/>
expense of maintaining our Government would not be materially<lb/>
increased, although our population should be doubled. The<lb/>
allowance of 80 cents per head is fixed alike to all the Provinces.<lb/>
When the population of Canada, Nova Scotia, New Brunswick,<lb/>
and Newfoundland, shall be increased to 7,000,000 or 8,000,000,<lb/>
those Provinces will receive no more than 80 cents per head of<lb/>
heir population in 1861. In all the British North American<lb/>
Provinces, Revenue is derived chiefly, from Customs and Excise.<lb/>
When the population of the Confederation shall be double what<lb/>
it now is, the consumption of articles paying duty will be vastly<lb/>
increased, and the revenue proportionally augmented. Reduction<lb/>
of taxation would follow, as a matter of course. The great<lb/>
Public Works of Canada will by-and-bye by completed, her<lb/>
Strongholds fortified, her Canals widened and completed, and her<lb/>
Lakes and Rivers rendered navigable; and, Sir, I consider myself<lb/>
fully justified in assuming that the increase of population<lb/>
throughout the Confederation, and more especially in Canada,<lb/>
will be so rapid, the consumption of duty paying articles so<lb/>
great, that at no distant day the rate of taxation per head, re<lb break="no"/>quired for the maintenance of the General Government, will be<lb/>
less than is now paid in Prince Edward Island, the least taxed of<lb/>
the Provinces. In Canada, Roads, Bridges, and other local<lb/>
works are not provided for from the general Revenue, as in<lb/>
Prince Edward Island. The alleged excessive local taxation<lb/>

<cb/>

in some of the municipalities of Upper Canada has been <lb/>
adduced, in order to terrify the people of this Island, and cause<lb/>
them to oppose Confederation. The people of Prince Edward<lb/>
Island would not be, in any degree, affected by the local or<lb/>
municipal taxation in Upper Canada. If taxation for local or<lb/>
municipal purposes be excessive in Canada, does not this fact<lb/>
warrant the assumption that the people of Upper Canada would<lb/>
be our allies in the work of keeping,as low as possible,the general<lb/>
taxation, by which alone we should be affected. Mr Speaker, let<lb/>
it be assumed that there are disadvantages to which Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion would subject us. Assume, Sir, that we should have to<lb/>
pay for our Tea and Sugar one penny per pound more than we<lb/>
pay at present, and a halfpenny a yard more for Calico. Do<lb/>
not such disadvantages fade into insignificance when contrasted<lb/>
with the benefits which would result from Confederation ?<lb/>
The old Colonies—now included in the United States of<lb/>
America—in little more than half a century, under Confederation,<lb/>
became one of the most prosperous nations on the face of the<lb/>
earth. Those Colonies entered upon their Confederate existence<lb/>
possessing fewer advantages than we now enjoy. Why should<lb/>
not we emulate their example ? Why shall we not unite our<lb/>
resources, and enter upon the career of prosperity which is<lb/>
clearly open to us ? What Confederation did for the older<lb/>
Colonies, it would do for us. We have Railways, and Steam<lb break="no"/>boats, and machinery which they had not. We have a country<lb/>
in many respects equal to theirs. Are we prepared to admit<lb/>
that our people are inferior to the old Colonists, or to the<lb/>
Americans of the present day? We have hitherto imported tabs,<lb/>
and buckets, and wooden wares, from the United States. Have<lb/>
we not wood wherewith to manufacture these articles ? Why<lb/>
should we send to the United States, or across the broad<lb/>
Atlantic for the simplest iron castings, seeing that we export<lb/>
from Nova Scotia to those countries, both coal and iron ? Con<lb break="no"/>federation would prove our best security against foreign invasion,<lb/>
and preserve to us our Monarchical Institutions. I feel, Sir,<lb/>
that I am approaching what my eloquent friend, the member for<lb/>
Charlottetown, Mr Brecken, is pleased facetiously to designate<lb/>
the "glory argument." I attach great importance to this glory<lb/>
argument. I desire to live under Monarchical Institutions, and<lb/>
the glorious flag of old England. Sir, there are in this House<lb/>
honorable members who smile when the glory argument is<lb/>
mentioned. Their fathers made great sacrifices in order that<lb/>
they might enjoy those privileges which are the inheritance of<lb/>
British subjects. In the Maritime Provinces are now to be found<lb/>
the descendants of men who left the United States upon the<lb/>
declaration of Independence, abandoning their property and the<lb/>
homes in which their children had been born, impelled to do so by<lb/>
the "glory argument." The American loyalists were attached<lb/>
to Monarchical Institutions. They valued their privileges as<lb/>
British subjects ; and rather than become Republicans they made<lb/>
the greatest sacrifices, and sought new homes on British soil, in<lb/>
the wilderness in Nova Scotia, New Brunswick and Prince<lb/>
Edward Island. But,Sir, to return to the commercial argument.<lb/>
Confederation would give us better markets than we now have<lb/>
for our agricultural produce. Halifax, Boston and St John would<lb/>
become great and populous cities, the emporiums of trade and<lb/>
manufactures; and, with these capitals we have, even now, daily<lb/>
communication. In these cities we should find ready and greatly<lb/>
increased markets for our produce, and consequently should be<lb/>
better able to bear increased taxation, than we are at present to<lb/>
also give us the Inter-colonial Railway, with its many advantages.<lb/>
But, Sir, one at least of the opponents of Confederation—a<lb/>
gentleman high in position in this Island—has argued as a reason<lb/>
why we should not accept Confederation, that the Inter-colonial<lb/>
Railway would injure the people of this Colony. It would, says<lb/>
the gentleman to whom I allude, be the means of bringing under<lb/>
cultivation large tracts of wilderness land in New Brunswick,<lb/>
the produce of which would compete with the productions of this<lb/>
Island. The Inter-colonial Railway, argues the same authority,<lb/>
" word afford great facilities for supplying the St John and<lb/>
Halifax markets with grain and other agricultural produce to be<lb/>
bought from Upper Canada." These, Sir, are specimens of the<lb/>
arguments which have caused the people of this Island to regard<lb/>
Confederation as a project which would ruin them. Imagine,<lb/>
Mr Speaker, the farmers of the far West, by means of this<lb/>
railway supplying the markets of St John and Halifax with<lb/>
"grain and other agricultural produce"—potatoes?—to the<lb/>
prejudice of the people of Prince Edward Island. In the markets<lb/>
of Upper Canada the prices of grain, and other agricultural products<lb/>

<pb n="44" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_044.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">44</fw>

are usually higher than in Prince Edward Island, and the nearest <lb/>
of those markets, is at least one thousand miles further from St<lb/>
John or Halifax, than is any portion of Prince Edward Island. <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>7. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>. That until the larger Maritime Provinces and <lb/>
Canada shall have mutually agreed upon terms of Union, it is<lb/>
inexpedient that the people of Prince Edward Island should be<lb/>
called upon to decide on the question.<lb/></p> </quote>

<p>Prince Edward Island is the smallest of the Provinces or Colonies, <lb/>
and no action which this Legislature may take, will, in the<lb/>
smallest degree, affect the great question of Confederation. If<lb/>
New Brunswick and Nova Scotia reject Confederation, we shall<lb/>
not be allowed to avail ourselves of the privileges which<lb/>
Confederation would confer upon us; on the other hand, should<lb/>
New Brunswick, Nova Scotia and Newfoundland adopt the reso<lb break="no"/>lutions of the Quebec Conference, the Opposition of Prince<lb/>
Edward Island would be of no importance, we should in the latter<lb/>
case be obliged to enter the Confederaion. It must, therefore,<lb/>
be evident that, until the larger Provinces agree to Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, it will be inexpedient to appeal to the people of this Island<lb/>
upon the question. The concluding resolution proposes:—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>8. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That in case the Provinces of New Brunswick, <lb/>
Nova Scotia and Canada, should at any time mutually agree<lb/>
upon the basis of a Union, the question be then forthwith sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to the decision of the People of this Island.<lb/></p></quote> 

<p>I, this afternoon, observed that the countenances of several of <lb/>
my colleagues in the Goverment, wore a more than usually pleas<lb break="no"/>ing expression. The occasion of this happiness was a telegram<lb/>
which had been received, announcing the defeat of the Hon Mr<lb/>
Tilley the leader of the government of New Brunswick, and of<lb/>
several of his colleagues. This, my friends, regard as the de<lb break="no"/>feat of the Confederation scheme in that Province, and they<lb/>
are happy. I, Sir, deeply regret the result of the recent elec<lb break="no"/>tions in New Brunswick. I dread the consequences. My hon<lb break="no"/>orable friend, Mr Tilley, informs me that, although "beaten," he is<lb/>
not "conquered." I, Sir, would much prefer to share defeat with<lb/>
that gentleman, in the great cause in the advocacy of which he<lb/>
has fallen, than participate in the victory which his opponents<lb/>
imagine they have gained. No honorable member should, in my<lb/>
opinion, object to the resolution just read. I hold, Mr Speaker,<lb/>
that, circumstanced as we are, and knowing as we do that<lb/>
nine-tenths of the Electors of this Island are opposed to confed<lb break="no"/>eration, it would be improper in us to pledge our constituents to<lb/>
the scheme of Confederation. On the other hand, Sir, I contend<lb/>
that this House, acknowledging, that the people should be con<lb break="no"/>sulted, before any such proposition shall be accepted, is not jus<lb break="no"/>tified in declaring that the people will accept Confederation.<lb/>
The subject will, hereafter, receive more deliberate considera<lb break="no"/>tion than has heretofore been given to it, and I confidently look<lb/>
forward to a great change in public opinion. There are several<lb/>
subjects in the Report upon which I have not remarked. There<lb/>
will be dealt with by the gentleman who will follow me, and at<lb/>
the close of the debate, I shall endeavor to reply to some of the<lb/>
many objections, which I believe will be urged against Confed<lb break="no"/>eration.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon J. C. POPE</persName>.—Mr Speaker, I submit that the Hon Col. <lb/>
Secretary, in moving the House into the consideration of the<lb/>
subject now before you, has manifested a very great want of<lb/>
courtesy towards myself, as a member of this House. It<lb/>
is a well observed rule that any member having given notice of<lb/>
his intention to move in any matter, shall, as a matter of course, <lb/>
have the privilege of introducing the subject of which he has given<lb/>
the notice, and of opening the debate ; and it is not expected<lb/>
that any other member shall, as the Col Secretary has done,<lb/>
watch an opportunity of moving in it ; but having done so, it was<lb/>
his duty, as a member of the Government, to have explained to<lb/>
the House that it was not a Government party question, and one<lb/>
on which the Government generally took a very different view<lb/>
from that entertained by himself. The conduct of the Colonial<lb/>
Secretary is calculated to place the Government, of which he is<lb/>
a member, in a false position, and looks to me as if he wished<lb/>
to put himself right, as a delegate, with the people of Canada.<lb/>
Knowing well the strong feelings entertained by all the<lb/>
members of the Government except two, and by the people of<lb/>
this Island generally against a Federal Union of the Provinces,<lb/>
he should, I think, have pursued a different course. He has, to<lb/>
say the least of it, acted most uncourteously, and I must now<lb/>
return the compliment by moving that the whole of the Resolutions<lb/>
submitted by him be struck out and the following submitted :—<lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"1. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That Prince Edward Island, being entirely <lb/>

<cb/>

dependant on its Agriculture and Fisheries, has nothing to <lb/>
export for which Canada can furnish a market. That while<lb/>
such is, and ever must be the relative commercial position of<lb/>
this Island and Canada, the products of our soil and Fisher<lb break="no"/>ies find in the extensive markets of our parent country, the<lb/>
United States and the West Indies, ready and profitable cus<lb break="no"/>tomers. The proposed Union, while admitting the produce<lb/>
and manufactures of Canada into this Island free, would by<lb/>
assimilation of taxes enormously increase the duty to which<lb/>
those of Great Britain and the United States are at present<lb/>
subject, thereby compelling this Island to take a large por<lb break="no"/>tion of its imports from Canada, making payment therefor in<lb/>
money instead of procuring them from countries which would<lb/>
receive our produce in exchange,—an arrangement so incon<lb break="no"/>sistent with the fundamental principles of commerce must<lb/>
greatly curtail our commercial intercourses with the United<lb/>
States, and would, in the opinion of this House, materially<lb/>
diminish our Exports to that country, and prove most injur<lb break="no"/>ious to the agricultural and commercial interests of this<lb/>
Island.<lb/></p> 

<p>"2. That if the relative circumstances of Canada and this <lb/>
Island rendered a Union practicable, the evident injustice of<lb/>
the terms agreed to by the Quebec Convention would prevent<lb/>
their being ratified by the Legislature of this Island. With<lb break="no"/>out alluding to all, it is proper to notice some of the objection<lb break="no"/>able features of the Report. Without admitting the principle<lb/>
of Representation according to Population under all circum<lb break="no"/>stances to be sound, it is, in the opinion of this House,<lb/>
particularly objectionable as applied to this Island in con<lb break="no"/>nexion with Canada, taking into consideration that the<lb/>
number of our inhabitants is, and must continue compara<lb break="no"/>tively small, owing to the fact that we have no Crown Lands,<lb/>
mines, minerals, or other resources sufficient to induce immi<lb break="no"/>grants to settle here, and that we never can expect to become<lb/>
to any extent a manufacturing people, in consequence of our<lb/>
navigation being close for nearly half the year, and all<lb/>
trade and communication with other countries stopped.<lb/>
Under this principle, the City of Montreal alone would,<lb/>
at the present time, have a representation greater than the<lb/>
whole Province of Prince Edward Island, and under the<lb/>
provisions of the Convention which regulate the mode of re<lb break="no"/>adjusting the relative representation of the various Provinces<lb/>
at each decennial census, looking at the rapid increase of the<lb/>
population of Upper and Lower Canada heretofore—particu<lb break="no"/>larly the former,—and the certainty of a still greater increase<lb/>
therein in the future, over that of the population of this Is<lb break="no"/>land, it follows as a certain and inevitable consequence, if a<lb/>
Federation of the Provinces were consummated upon the<lb/>
basis of the said Convention, that the number of our Repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives would, in the course of a comparatively short<lb/>
number of years, be diminished to a still smaller number than<lb/>
that allotted at the outset to us.<lb/></p> 

<p>"3. That the old Imperial error in granting all the lands <lb/>
in large tracts to absentees, which deprives this Island of the<lb/>
Revenue drawn by the sister Colonies from these sources,<lb/>
our insular position and numerous harbors, furnishing cheap<lb/>
and convenient water communication which render expensive<lb/>
Public Works here unnecessary, the Revenue to be drawn<lb/>
by the proposed Federal Government from this Island, and<lb/>
expended among the people of Canada and the other Colonies<lb/>
in constructing Railways and other Public Works, thereby<lb/>
creating a trade which would build up cities and enhance<lb/>
the value of property in various localities there—advantages<lb/>
in which this Island could enjoy a very small participation.<lb/>
Our complete isolation during five months of the year, when<lb/>
ice interrupts our trade and communication with the Main<lb break="no"/>land, and during which period the Island could derive no<lb/>
possible benefit from the Railroads and other Public Works<lb/>
which they would be (equally with the people of those Colo<lb break="no"/>nies) taxed to construct; these and many other considerations,<lb/>
but which seem to have been entirely ignored, ought, in the<lb/>
opinion of this House, to have produced an offer of a finan<lb break="no"/>cial arrangement for this Island very different in its terms<lb/>
from that contained in the Report of the Convention.<lb/></p> 

<p>"4. That while this House recognizes the duty of this <lb/>
Colony to use every means, to the extent of its limited re<lb break="no"/>sources, to defend its inhabitants from foreign invasion, it<lb/>
cannot recognize the necessity of uniting in a Confederation<lb/>
with Canada for the purpose of defence upon terms which,<lb/>

<pb n="45" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1865-03-24_Page_045.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">45</fw>

in other respects, are, in the opinion of this House, so unair <lb/>
to the people of Prince Edward Island ; thus sacrificing our <lb/>
commercial and financial interests for the sake of securing <lb/>
the co-operation of Canada in a military point of view, feel<lb break="no"/>ing assured that so long as we remain a loyal and attached <lb/>
Colony of Great Britain. the powerful aid of that great <lb/>
country will continue, as heretofore, to be extended to us, in <lb/>
common with the other North American Dependencies of the<lb/>
British Crown.<lb/></p> 

<p>"Lastly, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That this House disagrees to the re<lb break="no"/>commendations of the Quebec Convention, and, on the part of<lb/>
Prince Edward Island, emphatically declines a Union which,<lb/>
after a serious and careful consideration, it believes would<lb/>
prove politically, commercially and financially disastrous to<lb/>
the rights and interests of its people."<lb/></p></quote> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE3">Hon Col SECRETARY</persName>—I submit to you, Mr Speaker, for <lb/>
your judgment, the question whether the leader of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment having given notice of his intention to move the House on <lb/>
this matter, it was not competent for me or any other member to <lb/>
propose other resolutions for the approval of the House. The <lb/>
subject comes before us as an avowedly open question, and <lb/>
therefore I assert that my action evinces no want of courtesy to<lb/>
the leader, or any member, of the Government.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:POPE2">Hon Mr POPE</persName> —The question, Mr Speaker, which forms the <lb/>
subject of both sets of resolutions, is the most important which <lb/>
has ever occupied the attention of the Legislature of this Colony ; <lb/>
and approving of the abstract principle of the proposed Union, <lb/>
regret that I must oppose the measure, for the reason that the <lb/>
details, as adopted by the Quebec Conference, do not offer, in <lb/>
my opinion, fair terms to the people of the Island. It must be <lb/>
remembered, in the discussion of this question, that our insular <lb/>
position, the absence from our soil of minerals, and the difficulty, <lb/>
I might almost say, impossibility, of communication with our sister <lb/>
Colonies during half the year, place us, in dealing with this <lb/>
question, in a position totally different from that of Nova Scotia <lb/>
or New Brunswick. These Provinces are geographically con<lb break="no"/>nected with Canada, and have, within themselves, the materials <lb/>
requisite to constitute them manufacturing countries. As to the <lb/>
argument that our trade would be increased by the Union with <lb/>
Canada, I cannot recognize its force, for we produce the same <lb/>
description of articles as that country can or could supply us <lb/>
with. Our trade must naturally be with Great Britain, the <lb/>
United States, and the West Indies, the products and manufac<lb break="no"/>tures of which we require. The high tariff of Canada would <lb/>
raise the cost to the consumer of goods from those countries much <lb/>
higher than it is at present on the Island, and firmly believing <lb/>
that the true principle of trade is to buy in the cheapest, and sell <lb/>
in the dearest, market, I should be doing violence to my own <lb/>
convictions, if I affirmed by my vote any other rule. I have <lb/>
said, Sir, that I entertained objections to the details of the <lb/>
scheme. Among these objections I may mention the principle <lb/>
of representation by population. A very simple calculation will <lb/>
show that the adoption of this as a standard would entitle the <lb/>
city of London to send to the British House of Commons no less <lb/>
than seventy representatives, and the city of Montreal in the <lb/>
Confederate Parliament would have a representation greater than <lb/>
that of this whole Island. Its statistics warrant the belief that in <lb/>
a few years the population will be so increased by the influx of <lb/>
the tide of immigration that the Island would lose in the halls of <lb/>
legislation even the small voice which she might raise at her <lb/>
entrance into the Union. It is not to be supposed that the <lb/>
increased taxation which, it is not denied, the Canadian tariff <lb/>
imposes, will have any other effect than that of driving from our <lb/>
shores those who would naturally seek in enlarged fields of action <lb/>
more ample returns for their labor, and greater means of meeting<lb/>
the liabilities imposed upon them. The military phase of the <lb/>
question is not worthy of much consideration, for if an invasion <lb/>
of Canada by the people of the United States should take place,<lb/>
it would involve, as a matter of course, the necessity of retaining<lb/>
all available strength in each of the other Provinces for the<lb/>
defence of their respective territories. While I admit, as<lb/>
cordially as any, that it is the duty of every man to contribute,<lb/>
as far as in him lies, to the defence of the country in which he<lb/>
lives, and that it is not fair to the taxpayers of Britain that they<lb/>
should be at the exclusive cost of our protection, I am willing to<lb/>
trust a reasonable portion of that duty to the Mother Country,<lb/>
the army and navy of which must be kept somewhere; and her<lb/>
experience shows that nowhere can they be maintained as<lb/>
cheaply as in the Colonies. In conclusion, I may state that<lb/>

<cb/>

while I give the delegates credit for sincerity in their proceedings, <lb/>
my opinion is that they went further than they were authorised<lb/>
or justified to go.<lb/></p> 

<p>In accordance with a suggestion of Hon Mr WHELAN, the <lb/>
discussion was postponed until the papers connected with the<lb/>
subject should be printed.<lb/></p> 

<!-- DL 2018-06-05 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>SATURDAY, March 25. <lb/></p> 

<p>Debate on the Union of the Colonies resumed. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon Col GRAY.—Mr Speaker, It might reasonably be <lb/>
expected, and honorable members may consider that it would be<lb/>
more in accordance with the elevated character of a project,<lb/>
which, having engrossed the minds of the statesmen of British<lb/>
America for many years, has at length culminated in the phase<lb/>
in which it now attracts the attention of the people of not only<lb/>
these Provinces and Great Britain, but also of our neighbors in the<lb/>
Great Republic who are anxiously watching our proceedings,<lb/>
that I should elaborate the argument in support of my own views.<lb/>
But, Sir, I do not at present intend to enlarge upon the grander<lb/>
features of this great question—a Confederation of the varied<lb/>
and gigantic interests involved, the benefits which must inevitably<lb/>
accrue to all British America were we confederated in one strong<lb/>
and indissoluble bond of brotherhood from Newfoundland to<lb/>
Vancouver. However desirous I might be, under a state of<lb/>
public opinion other than that which at present exists, to ap<lb break="no"/>proach in a far more extended sense than one of mere local<lb/>
interest, the consideration of a measure which has for its object<lb/>
the consolidation of any hitherto isolated and disjointed<lb/>
fragments into a Confederation which will form a state as large<lb/>
as the entire Continent of Europe, yet it is not my present<lb/>
intention to do so ; neither do I intend to offer any comments<lb/>
upon the resolutions which my hon friend, the leader of the<lb/>
Government, in accordance, doubtless, with the desires of a large<lb/>
majority of members of this House, has now submitted for our<lb/>
consideration, but I shall confine myself solely to a few obser<lb break="no"/>vations on those points which apply more particularly to the<lb/>
immediate condition of the people of this Island separately, as<lb/>
evidencing the motives and reasons which actuated me in ear<lb break="no"/>nestly desiring that we may have the good fortune to be admitted<lb/>
within, and to become an integral part of, the proposed Confed<lb break="no"/>eration. Mr Speaker, we all know that our free trade with the<lb/>
United States is about to cease. Already had notice for the<lb/>
abrogation of the Reciprocity Treaty been given by the American<lb/>
authorities, and, when this shall have been finally acted upon, we<lb/>
must look elsewhere for markets for our produce, or submit to a<lb/>
taxation on it in the ports of the United States which will be<lb/>
almost prohibitory ; therefore, as we are peculiarly an agricul<lb break="no"/>tural people, the great object of our solicitude should be to look<lb/>
around and enquire where we may best secure ready markets,<lb/>
and as near to our own doors as possible ; for it is obvious that if<lb/>
we can have easy access to markets in rich and populous cities<lb/>
in our midst, we will receive far better returns than if driven to<lb/>
have recourse to places remote, and only to be reached after<lb/>
long and tedious voyaging. Sir, I believe that we may safely<lb/>
assume that in a very few years, when confederated, that<lb/>
Halifax and St. John alone will be ready to absorb all we can<lb/>
raise unless every acre in this Island be cultivated like a kitchen<lb/>
garden. Let us consider the future of these two cities, for, great<lb/>
as their natural advantages now are, all pales before the con<lb break="no"/>templation of what they are destined ultimately to become. Let<lb/>
me instance the rise and progress of two places somewhat<lb/>
similarly situated, in the past—Singapore and Chicago. When<lb/>
that eminent man, Sir Stamford Raffles, first suggested the<lb/>
idea of founding that famous emporium for the China trade,<lb/>
how the enemies of progress lifted up their eyes in amaze<lb break="no"/>ment ! how they ridiculed the idea! how great the ruin<lb/>
which must ensue from the adoption of the policy<lb/>
proposed! But what was the result? Soon he was enabled<lb/>
to write, (I quote from memory his own words), "From an<lb/>
insignificant fishing village, our town, in three years, has a<lb/>
population of ten thousand; our lands are rapidly rising in<lb/>
value, and we have every reason to expect, that, in a very<lb/>
few years, we shall have ten times our numbers." How<lb/>
truly the prognostics of this great man have been fulfilled,<lb/>
this wonderful mart of commerce, with its hundred thousands<lb/>
of population, bears, at this day, ample witness. Look again<lb/>
at Chicago. In the year 1833, it was a town of fifty inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants ; twenty years after it had a population of eighty<lb/>
thousand. The tide of emigration must flow to British<lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>