<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1867-05-14"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1867-05-14">14 May 1867</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1867">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1867, Being the First Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1867"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Patriot" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="133"/>
</bibl>

<list>

<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_131.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_132.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_133.html"/>
</item>

</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-11">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_131">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_131.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_132">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_132.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_133">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_133.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="131" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_131.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">131</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName> would give his support to the amend<lb break="no"/>ment. The hon. Attorney General seemed to complain <lb/>
that we would not exempt the Volunteers from bur<lb break="no"/>dens imposed upon other people. He was going to <lb/>

<cb/>

draw the Volunteers into the service with kindness. <lb/>
Then if one of these same Volunteers wished to be <lb/>
made a Constable, there was the fact of his being a <lb/>
Volunteer to exclude him from that appointment, or <lb/>
any other public duty which others had to bear? <lb/>
Some hon. members referred to him as the third mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Charlottetown; but certain men in the city <lb/>
seemed to claim more privileges than they were en<lb break="no"/>titled to. He hoped to see the day when persons from <lb/>
the country would exercise more power in this House <lb/>
than they did now. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon LEADER OF THE OPPOSITION</persName> asked <lb/>
if the hon. member meant Mr. Callbeck ? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. HOWAT</persName> said we were not to be frightened, <lb/>
or bribed into it, which he believed was attempted to <lb/>
be done. Now were we going to put military service <lb/>
upon the people until they were aware of it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PROW2">Mr. PROWSE</persName> remarked that no doubt the House <lb/>
Government wished us to go into Confederation, and <lb/>
would like to see the whole military force of the Col<lb break="no"/>onies put together. If we wished to avoid this, we <lb/>
would have to give due attention to our military de<lb break="no"/>fences. He did not see how we could treat this Bill <lb/>
lightly, in the face of the telegram which he had just <lb/>
taken from the Report's desk.—"Earl Derby says <lb/>
the Government will not make public the real history <lb/>
of the recent Fenian uprising, on account of appre<lb break="no"/>hended trouble with certain Foreign Governments <lb/>
which are involved in the plot." When hon. members <lb/>
considered this announcement, he did not think they <lb/>
would say that it was a matter of indifference whether <lb/>
we gave attention or not to military preparations. <lb/>
He believed would justly compel us to go into Confed<lb break="no"/>eration from a military necessity, if in these matters <lb/>
we did not do our duty. He would not give the Vol<lb break="no"/>unteers more privileges than the Militia. He under<lb break="no"/>stood that the Bill was similar to the Act in operation <lb/>
in Nova Scotia, and if they, who were going into <lb/>
Confederation, gave such attention to these duties, <lb/>
sure we who were not going into it, should be pre<lb break="no"/>pared to keep ourselves out of trouble. He would <lb/>
heartily support the Bill. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERNMENT</persName> thought <lb/>
that if the Volunteers were to throw up their arms every <lb/>
time they took offence at something, there was not much <lb/>
dependence to be placed in them. He would like them <lb/>
to know more about the duty they owed to their superior <lb/>
officers. He did not hesitate to say again that in so far <lb/>
as the present manner of calling out the Militia was <lb/>
concerned, it was nothing but a piece of "tomfoolery." <lb/>
When called out and put through the drill, what was the <lb/>
result ? A few might have learned to wheel a little bet<lb break="no"/>ter than the others, but the bulk of them paid very little <lb/>
attention to the drill, and were none the better qualified <lb/>
for the discharge of military duties ; and he would still <lb/>
say that it was wrong to be calling out the Militia for <lb/>
ten or fifteen days, when the people could ill afford to <lb/></p>

<pb n="132" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_132.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">132</fw>

<p>lose the time. He considered it a serious matter to in<lb break="no"/>terrupt the agricultural mercantile, and mechanical pur<lb break="no"/>suits of the whole people for such a period, when it was <lb/>
well known that fifteen days' drilling would never <lb/>
qualify them for soldier's duty; but the volunteers could <lb/>
meet and drill as often as they pleased. If a foreign <lb/>
invasion was to take place, or was likely to happen it <lb/>
would be different; every man would then be in earnest, <lb/>
and would feel it to be a please and a duty to do all in <lb/>
his power for the defence of the country. But at present <lb/>
there was no more necessity for anything of the kind, <lb/>
than there was for our getting alarmed at the telegram <lb/>
read by the hon. member for Murray Harbor. The terror <lb/>
of Fenianism must not frighten us into foolish acts. As <lb/>
to the Bill, he thought hon, members opposite were under <lb/>
a mistake, and had been fighting with a phantom. The <lb/>
Bill brought down by the Government last year had been <lb/>
amended in committee, and surely members of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment might submit an amendment to this one. It <lb/>
had been said that indifference on the part of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment in this matter might be usual as an argument for <lb/>
Confederation. The Government had not shown indif<lb break="no"/>ference on military matters. They intended to support the <lb/>
volunteers, and this they had made manifest in the appro<lb break="no"/>priation for that service. Before the general election the <lb/>
late Government were going to do something for the <lb/>
volunteers, but these becoming offended. threatened their <lb/>
representative or the Government with their opposition. <lb/>
Again if the Commander-in-Chief did that they considered <lb/>
not fully right, they would not retain their arms. Men so <lb/>
acting lost respect for themselves. It was too much like <lb/>
a Bull's Run affair. He hoped, bye-and-bye, that the <lb/>
Volunteers would do better than to throw down <lb/>
their arms one day and take them up another. As to <lb/>
the exemption from statute labor, it was but three shill<lb break="no"/>ings a year, and was not a matter worth an exemption. <lb/>
If the bulk of the people on a road in the winter were <lb/>
exempted, there would not be enough to turn out to break <lb/>
the roads, and travelling for a time might be entirely <lb/>
stopped. In the summer it would not be of so much <lb/>
importance. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

<pb n="133" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1867-05-14_Page_133.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">133</fw>

<p>them rather go naked than vote for him (Dr. Jen<lb break="no"/>kins.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName> was surprised at the <lb/>
manner in which the hon. Leader of the Government <lb/>
was acting in relation to his Bill. There appeared <lb/>
to be some misunderstanding between him and His <lb/>
Excellency the Lieut. Governor. He was astonished <lb/>
that some hon. members should contend that raw <lb/>
recruits were as good as trained soldiers. They might <lb/>
with equal justice, say that the shop boy with one <lb/>
day's acquaintance with his business was as good as <lb/>
the trained clerk. He did not understand how the <lb/>
Militia movement could be regarded as a Confederate <lb/>
"dodge." Confederation was a new question, while <lb/>
Militia acts were of old standing. Though he did <lb/>
not advocate carrying the matter of Militia training <lb/>
too far, still it was absurd to suppose that people <lb/>
could be prepared for action in the field with only <lb/>
a few days' notice. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. ATTY. GENERAL</persName> would assure the hon. <lb/>
member for Murray Harbor, that there was no mis<lb break="no"/>understanding with His Excellency in the matter of <lb/>
this Bill. all anxiety on that point might be dis<lb break="no"/>missed. <lb/></p> 

<p>The amendment that the words "and the perform<lb break="no"/>ance of the Statute labor," be struck out of the clause, <lb/>
was then put and carried. <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

<!-- DL 2018-06-11 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>Wednesday, May 15. <lb/></p>-->

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>