<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1869-03-31"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1869-03-31">31 March 1869</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>


<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1869">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1869, Being the Third Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1869"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edward Reilly, Queen's Printer</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="157"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1869-03-31_Page_156.hocr.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1869-03-31_Page_157.hocr.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-12">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1869-03-31_Page_156"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-03-31_Page_156.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1869-04-01_Page_157"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-03-3_Page_157.jpg"/></surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">



<pb n="156" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-03-31_Page_156.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">156</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p>An appeal was <lb/>
made by the Nova Scotians for a repeal of the <lb/>
Union, but it was refused. If the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had not been in favor of the Union of Nova <lb/>
Scotia with Canada, would not the people of the <lb/>
latter country have had a hearing? The British <lb/>
Government had the constitutionality of the mea<lb break="no"/>

<cb/> 

sure, of course, in favor of their action but if they <lb/>
know it was not in accordance with the principles <lb/>
of Responsible Government and the well-under<lb break="no"/>stood wishes of the people would they have been <lb/>
justified in acting as they did? They were cog<lb break="no"/>nizant of this, but it was to their interest to do as <lb/>
they did. And we stand pretty much in the same <lb/>
position as Nova Soctia; for we have asked for <lb/>
what they have no interest in giving us. If the <lb/>
poor among them were not burdened by the tax <lb/>
for the payment of this salary, the Home Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would let us along; but they are burdened. <lb/>
If we insist, therefore, upon their paying this sal<lb break="no"/>ary, they will say to us 'You must go into Con<lb break="no"/>federation and get it paid,' The Leader of the <lb/>
Government, in taking his present course, had his <lb/>
supporters, and I believe they were all convinced <lb/>
that the only safe course to pursue was for us to <lb/>
pay the salary. After we are prepared to do this, <lb/>
we can state our grievances to the Imperial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName>.— <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

<p>As to the character of the despatches from the <lb/>
Colonial Office in reference to Nova Scotia, we <lb/>
know that they were as foreign to the strict hon<lb break="no"/>est facts of the case, morally or politically, as any <lb/>
statements could possibly be. Notwithstanding <lb/>
the fact that the hon. Joseph Howe went hom <lb/>
and stated the case, backed up by a petition from <lb/>
13,000 of the loyal inhabitants of Nova Scotia— <lb/>
because the Imperial Government had the fact <lb/>
that the Legislature of Nova Scotia had consented, <lb/>
by the moat foul and unjustifiable means, to the <lb/>
union of that country with Canada—they needed <lb/>
not the petition, nor the representation of that <lb/>
gentleman, although they knew they were acting <lb/>
against the well understood wishes of the people. <lb/>
Then assuming that the address of this House, or <lb/>
of any portion of it, were presented to the House <lb/>
of Commons, and then that the Colonial Minister back<lb break="no"/>ed up by his predecessor, got up and made a state<lb break="no"/>ment contrary to the prayer of our appeal, what <lb/>
would be the effect upon the House of Commons? <lb/>
It would scatter to the winds any impression made <lb/>
by the Address upon that body, and the result <lb/>
would be that there would be no chance for little <lb/>
Prince Edward Island to obtain her wishes. There <lb/>
seems now to be no alternative for us, but of two <lb/>
evils to choose the least. When I consider that <lb/>
Newfoundland is about being legislated into Con<lb break="no"/>federation, that a ring is being formed around us, <lb/>
and that the British Government have reduced <lb/>
our defences as far as they have done. I cannot <lb/>
but come to the conclusion that it would be unsafe <lb/>

<pb n="157" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1869-03-31_Page_157.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">157</fw> 

to risk the result of relishing to accede to this de<lb break="no"/>mand. I am as desirous that the people should <lb/>
be relieved from every burden as any hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber of this House, but I think it necessary to sub<lb break="no"/>mit to this demand, for I believe that the British <lb/>
Government would not be particularly scrupulous <lb/>
in regard to forcing us into the Confederation <lb/>
against our wishes, if they had what they thought <lb/>
a slight pretext for so doing. I would not favor <lb/>
any movement on the part of this House which <lb/>
might call for reflection in future. I shall, there<lb break="no"/>fore, support the Resolution introduced by the <lb/>
hon. Leader of the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>