<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPEILA_1870-04-12"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1870-04-12">12 April 1870</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1870">
               <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1870, Being the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
          <date when="1870"/>. 
          <pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Patriot Book and Job Printing Rooms</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="231"/>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="238"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_230.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_234.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_236.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_238.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
        
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-07-03">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-07-03">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_230">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_230.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_234">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_234.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_236">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_236.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_238">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_238.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="230" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_230.jpg"/>
            
            
            <!-- GL, 2018-07-03, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day -->      
           <!-- <fw type="num">230</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER. 1870</fw>
            <p>
     his position. In saying this, he (Mr. B ) 
     <lb/>
     alluded to the remarks the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     made about theopposition. He (Mr. B.) 
     <lb/>
     believed when the better'terms came 
     <lb/>
     down, the hon. member, Mr. Callbeck, 
     <lb/>
     was enamoured with them. But the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member was correct in what he 
     <lb/>
     told the House; he retured to his cham<lb break="no"/>ber alone to peruse them, and afterwards 
     <lb/>
     thought his first impression was but a 
     <lb/>
     will-o'-the-wisp. But he believed the 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member was, previous to that, 
     <lb/>
     a confederate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. CALLBECK said he read the 
     <lb/>
     proposals carefully before he gave ex<lb break="no"/>pression to any opinion respecting them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> had a great deal of re<lb break="no"/>spect for the hon. gentleman, but thought 
     <lb/>
     his. memory was faulty; and while he 
     <lb/>
     did not think he would willingly express 
     <lb/>
     that which was not correct, yet he could 
     <lb/>
     not but think the hon. gentleman had 
     <lb/>
     trimmed. He (Mr. B.) would merely 
     <lb/>
     ask the hon. leader of the government, 
     <lb/>
     in this House, in what position, as a 
     <lb/>
     statesman, did he stand? There was 
     <lb/>
     not one word in the minute of Council 
     <lb/>
     respecting the commercial aspect of the 
     <lb/>
     question, yet the hon. gentleman devoted 
     <lb/>
     the greater portion of his long a eech, to 
     <lb/>
     the commercial prospects whic he fan<lb break="no"/>cied were involved in the question to 
     <lb/>
     the entire exclusion of that view of the 
     <lb/>
     matter to which his attention should 
     <lb/>
     have been directed. Statesman should 
     <lb/>
     take a broader and more comprehensive 
     <lb/>
     view of that important subject, than was 
     <lb/>
     involved within the narrow view to 
     <lb/>
     which the hon. gentleman had so elabor<lb break="no"/>ately drawn the attention of that hon. 
     <lb/>
     committee. He (Mr. B.) despised the 
     <lb/>
     attempt which had been made to pre<lb break="no"/>judice Scotchmen against him, because 
     <lb/>
     he said that at the time of the union, 
     <lb/>
     Seotchmen, to a great extent, were a 
     <lb/>
     lawless people. All knew that it was 
     <lb/>
     not until 1745, that the administration 
     <lb/>
    of justice could be fairly dispensed in 
     <lb/>that country, and he would say now, 
     <lb/>what he did on a former occasion, that 
     <lb/>Scotchmeu, from that position, soon be<lb break="no"/>came, in every respect, the reverse of 
     <lb/>what they formerly had been, and no 
     <lb/>country in the world, considering its 
     <lb/>area and population, could boast of as 
     <lb/>many men occupying important posi<lb break="no"/>tions in the world, as Scotland could. 
     <lb/>Even the wise man from the East, he 
     <lb/>meant the hon. member for Souris, was 
     <lb/>a Scotchman. But as his hon. colleague 
     <lb/>said, there was noanalogy between the 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     union of Scotland or Ireland, with that 
     <lb/>
     existing between the Provinces of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. The former was a legisla<lb break="no"/>tive, the latter a federal one ; and hon. 
     <lb/>
     members who reason from the effects of 
     <lb/>
     the one; to show the probable results of 
     <lb/>
     the other, ought to have more fully con<lb break="no"/>sidered the question before they made 
     <lb/>
     the statements they did. If this Island 
     <lb/>
     went into confederation, and sent proper 
     <lb/>
     men to represent her in the Dominion, 
     <lb/>
     they would find that the island would 
     <lb/>
     be as fairly treated as the upper Province. 
     <lb/>
     Did not Mr. Tilley speak, and had he 
     <lb/>
     not as much influence there as any man 
     <lb/>
     from Ontario?   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> had seen a confed<lb break="no"/>erate paper, published in New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, which represented Mr. Tilley as 
     <lb/>
     the silent minister of New Brunswick. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—He had been repre<lb break="no"/>sented as the silent minister, as he 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. B.) understood, simply because he 
     <lb/>
    did not think proper, recently, to ye 
     <lb/>expression to his opinions. But New 
     <lb/>Brunswick never had a son better able 
     <lb/>to maintain their rights, or one that she 
     <lb/>should feel prouder of than Mr. Tilley. 
     <lb/>He (Mr. B.) would like to see the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment ta e up the question fairly, and 
     <lb/>express their real sentiments without 
     <lb/>reserve. Their children would consider 
     <lb/>whether in the course they might then 
     <lb/>pursue, they had attended to the true 
     <lb/>interests of the country. He had been 
     <lb/>compared to an Arnold, and told that he 
     <lb/>should resign his seat, but be (Mr. B.) 
     <lb/>felt there was a great principle at stake 
     <lb/>in the question, and would not have been 
     <lb/>true to himself, his constituents, or his 
     <lb/>country, had he failed to give expression 
     <lb/>to his views on the proposals which were 
     <lb/>recently sent down to the government 
     <lb/>by the Dominion, and did hope there 
     <lb/>would have been public spirit enough in 
     <lb/>the government to have given expression 
     <lb/>to their opinions upon this nest on, but 
     <lb/>instead of that, attacks ha been made 
     <lb/>upon himself, and when such was the 
     <lb/>case, he claimed the right of reply. All 
     <lb/>kinds of questions ha been referred to 
     <lb/>by the government, such as the army, 
     <lb/>militia, and commerce, but Earl Gran<lb break="no"/>ville's despatch had not been approached. 
     <lb/>The hon. member was afraid of it, and 
     <lb/>probably had good reasons. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName>.—No! he was not. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> Would tell the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber when he went into figures, after 
     <lb/>signing the minute of Council, he had 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>-->
            <fw type="dateline">1870</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">231</fw>
   
            <!--<p>
     forgotten his duty. But he did not wish 
     <lb/>
     to severe upon the hon. member, for 
     <lb/>
     it was a matter of small consequence to 
     <lb/>
     this Island what the immediate advan<lb break="no"/>tages were which confederation might 
     <lb/>
     confer. There was a nobler principle 
     <lb/>
     involved, and one more worthy the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the statesmen of Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Progress was reported, when the House 
     <lb/>adjourned until to-morrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
            <head rendition="simple:right">Tuesday, April 12.</head>
            <pb n="234" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_234.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">234</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1870</fw>
            
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
            
            <p>The House again in committee on the<lb/>Despatches.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KICK1">Mr. KICKHAM</persName> said he had some con<lb break="no"/>versation on the subject of confederation<lb/>with Hon. Mr. Tilley last summer. His<lb/>opinions on the question were the same<lb/>then as they are now. He told that<lb/>hon. gentleman that he (Mr. K.) could<lb/>not go for confederation without the<lb/>
          
          
            <cb/>
          
          
     consent of his constituents, Mr. Tilley<lb/>said, he (Mr. K.) might call his con<lb break="no"/>stituents together; but he replied that<lb/>many of them were out fishing. He<lb/>(Mr. K.) was opposed to confederation,<lb/>unless the people desired it, and that<lb/>being his view of the question, he would<lb/>not take up the time of the committee,<lb/>as there were others who liked to hear<lb/>themselves speaking. (Laughter.)<lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ARSE1">Mr. ARSENAULT</persName>.—The beauties of con<lb break="no"/>federation had been so well pictured,<lb/>that there was scarcely anything left for<lb/>him to say. He would not undertake to<lb/>shew its benefits or disadvantages, at<lb/>such length as some hon. members.<lb/>If admitting the principle of confedera<lb break="no"/>tion was sufficient to set one down as a<lb/>unionist, he believed he might be called<lb/>one. He thought, however, that he was<lb/>in good company, for he considered there<lb/>were very few in this House who had<lb/>not admitted the principle. He had not<lb/>said that he was anxious to see the union<lb/>consummated; but he believed that it<lb/>would some day take place. It was the<lb/>policy of the Home Government, and he<lb/>believed that something would be done<lb/>to induce us to go into it. We had not<lb/>heard many hon. members say that they<lb/>would go for no terms at all. Only two<lb/>or three had openly said so in this<lb/>House, and that showed that the others<lb/>believed union would take place at some<lb/>future day. To hear some persons<lb/>speaking, you would think this Island was<lb/>a very garden of Eden—that we had all<lb/>we desired, and all we could wish to<lb/>have. He (Mr. A.) could not say that.<lb/>It was not long ago since there was any<lb break="no"/>thing but peace and contentment on the<lb/>Island; he referred to the time of the<lb/>Tenant League agitation. The land<lb/>question had been a bone of contention<lb/>for the last fifty years, and a stepping<lb break="no"/>stone for politicians to get into places of<lb/>honor. When the better terms were first<lb/>proposed, he (Mr. A.) thought that if<lb/>they were carried out faithfully, they<lb/>would benefit the Island with respect to<lb/>this question, and he thought so still.<lb/>Some had had an opportunity to pur<lb break="no"/>chase their lands; but others were not<lb/>able to pay for them, and, in the case of<lb/>not a few of these, it was because they<lb/>had not had advantages. It was said,<lb/>he believed, by the hon. member for<lb/>Alberton, (Mr. Bell) that the people were<lb/>contented and happy. This might be<lb/>the case with some, but not with all.<lb/>Where there were fishing stations, the<lb/>people were no better off than at other<lb/>
       
       
         
         
     <fw type="dateline">1870</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">235</fw>       


     places, for fishermen neglected their<lb/>farms, and those who supplied them<lb/>became the proprietors of their farms.<lb/>Such was the state of affairs in almost<lb/>all fishing countries. He had no objec<lb break="no"/>tion to the minute of Council, which<lb/>made the land question, the main obstacle 
     <lb/>
     in the way of accepting the better terms; 
     <lb/>
     and therefore would agree to the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion introduced by the hon. leader at the 
     <lb/>
     government in this House. He knew 
     <lb/>
     there was much truth in the saying, that 
     <lb/>
     we might not feel the loss of our privi<lb break="no"/>leges until they were no, consequently 
     <lb/>he believed it was right to deal cautious<lb break="no"/>ly in treating of this question. At the<lb/>same time, he was not a no-terms man ;<lb/>he was in favor of the principle of union.<lb/>He would support the resolution to<lb/>which he had already referred; but he<lb/>would not pledge himself to support any<lb/>other, for he believed there were many<lb/>resolutions yet to be proposed.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BELL3">Mr. BELL</persName> would reiterate what he had       
     <lb/>stated, that the people here were content<lb break="no"/>ed and happy. Any person in this Is<lb break="no"/>land, who would work, need not be in<lb/>want. It was a country for the poor<lb/>man. Every day brought out facts to<lb/>show that we were better off as we were,<lb/>than by going into confederation. The<lb/>Finance Minister of the Dominion had<lb/>just introduced into parliament a mea<lb break="no"/>sure for issuing a large quantity of irre<lb break="no"/>deemable paper, and a country that had<lb/>to resort to such means, to keep up its<lb/>credit, could not be prosperous. Why<lb/>did not the hon. member, from Egmont<lb/>Bay, refer to the case of Cape Breton?<lb/>(Mr. B.) saw a man from that island<lb/>who said it had never recovered from<lb/>the effects of its union with Nova Scotia.<lb/>Scarcely any outlying portion of a coun<lb break="no"/>try prospered. Why could we not be<lb/>left here to collect our own revenues, as<lb/>well as the Isle of Man, which was so<lb/>near Britain herself?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> agreed with<lb/>most of the remarks that had fallen from<lb/>the last speaker. Poor people could not<lb/>expect that they would gain anything by<lb/>union. Persons in high positions might<lb/>receive a benefit by getting good offices.<lb/>If the advantages which we possessed, as<lb/>a separate colony, were taken away, we<lb/>would know, when perhaps too late,<lb/>what we had lost. Any man here, who<lb/>was industrious and careful, might be<lb break="no"/>come independent. The policy of the<lb/>government on this question had been<lb/>attacked, but if it was reviewed from<lb/>
         
         
            <cb/>
           
           
     
     first to last, it would be found that they        
               <lb/>had taken a straightforward course.<lb/>They had never sought an intercourse<lb/>with the Canadian government, and<lb/>when the delegates came here, we treated<lb/>them with the respect to which they were<lb/>entitled. They endeavored to ascertain<lb/>why it was that we would not go into con<lb break="no"/>federation. They were told that it was<lb/>doubtful whether any terms would be<lb/>acceptable until the land question was<lb/>settled. It had been said that the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment looked upon receiving com<lb break="no"/>pensation for the loss of territorial rev<lb break="no"/>enues as a mere parliamentary matter; but<lb/>we told the delegates that it was doubt<lb break="no"/>ful, even though that question was set<lb break="no"/>tled, whether we should go into confed<lb break="no"/>eration. To show that he (Col. Sec.)<lb/>was not in error, take up the proposals<lb/>of the 14th December, transmitted by<lb/>Sir John Young. In them his government<lb/>admitted that the loss of our lands was<lb/>a real grievance, and promised that they<lb/>would endeavor to get redress from the<lb/>Imperial government. And they said<lb/>that failing to get justice from Great<lb/>Britain, the Dominion government would<lb/>give $800,000 towards settling these<lb/>claims. When these proposals came<lb/>down, he (Col. Sec.) saw that a great<lb/>admission had been made by the Can<lb break="no"/>adian government, but he had no idea<lb/>that the answer given to them by the<lb/>government here, as contained in the<lb/>minute of Council, would have so soon<lb/>received a reply from the Colonial Min<lb break="no"/>ister, who had put his own construction<lb/>on that minute. His Lordship said that<lb/>the terms were rejected by the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, because they did not include a<lb/>settlement of the land claims; but the<lb/>truth was that we would have been free<lb/>to have entered confederation or not,<lb/>though compensation had been given for<lb/>these claims. Some hon. members tried<lb/>to make it appear that the government<lb/>were in favor of union; the Colonial<lb/>Minister, however, said that they had<lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">rejected</hi> the terms, how then could any<lb/>one say that the minute of Council was<lb/>favorable to confederation? He (Col.<lb/>Secy.) thought one of the great advan<lb break="no"/>tages which had been gained by this<lb/>correspondence, was that the Canadian<lb/>government had acknowledged that this<lb/>Island was entitled to receive compen<lb break="no"/>sation for the loss of her crown lands.<lb/>The Home government, by the Colonial<lb/>Minister's despatch, refused to grant this<lb/>compensation, and the government here,<lb/>by the minute of Council, were tied to<lb/>
          
          
            <pb n="236" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_236.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">236</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1870</fw>
      
      
     the principle that they could not receive 
     <lb/>
    compensation from the Dominion treas<lb break="no"/>ury. This was just the position in 
     <lb/>which he (Col. Sec.) wished to be placed. 
     <lb/>He now felt free to go for a no-terms 
     <lb/>resolution: We had good encouragement 
     <lb/>to believe that our affairs would be at<lb break="no"/>tended to by the Home Government 
     <lb/>with as much alacrity as those of the 
     <lb/>Dominion, from the readiness with which 
     <lb/>they had complied with our request to 
     <lb/>lower the postage to Britain.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">DR. JENKINS</persName> said it should borne 
     <lb/>in mind that this government had hinted 
     <lb/>to the Home Government their intention 
     <lb/>to demand from them compensation for 
     <lb/>the loss of crown lands, previous to the 
     <lb/>time when this celebrated Minute of 
     <lb/>Council now under discussion, was 
     <lb/>penned. Two years ago a delegation 
     <lb/>had been sent to the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to endeavor to get a guarantee for 
     <lb/>a loan, which appeared to be a very 
     <lb/>humble method of demanding compen<lb break="no"/>sation. The course the government had 
     <lb/>taken had destroyed every chance of 
     <lb/>getting anything from the British Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment; but had they allowed the 
     <lb/>Canadian Government to take this matter 
     <lb/>up, something might have been done. 
     <lb/>He (Dr. J.) believed this Minute of 
     <lb/>Council was intended to take the place 
     <lb/>of a, " no-terms" resolution, which the 
     <lb/>government were afraid to adopt. It 
     <lb/>was said that the last despatch received 
     <lb/>from the Colonial Office had settled the 
     <lb/>subject of confederation; but the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment would find out pretty soon that 
     <lb/>such was not the case. This despatch 
     <lb/>was only a mild remonstrance, but 
     <lb/>every word of it plainly signified that 
     <lb/>we must go on with negotiations, and if 
     <lb/>we stopped negotiating, he (Dr. J.) 
     <lb/>believe we should soon hear something 
     <lb/>hotter. He believed the Leader of the 
     <lb/>Government (Hon. Mr. Haythorne) was 
     <lb/>honest when he stated he would take 
     <lb/>fair terms, and he (Dr. J.) was proud 
     <lb/>that he took the same ground on this 
     <lb/>subject. The question of, a railroad had 
     <lb/>been brought up in this discussion, 
     <lb/>and he (Dr. J.) had been the first to 
     <lb/>bring that matter to the notice of the 
     <lb/>House, and he hoped to see the iron 
     <lb/>horse traversing our Island before many 
     <lb/>years. A railroad was indispensable to 
     <lb/>develop the resources of the country, 
     <lb/>as our roads were absolutely impassable 
     <lb/>at certain seasons of the year, and at the 
     <lb/>rate they were being macadamized we 
     <lb/>would be all in our graves before even a 
     <lb/>few miles in the vicinity cf the towns 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <cb/>
       
       
     would be covered with stone. The 
     <lb/>
     harbors at the eastern end of the island 
     <lb/>
     were open later in autumn than those 
     <lb/>
     in other parts of the Island and had we 
     <lb/>
     a railroad, farmers would be able to 
     <lb/>
     ship their produce late in the season, and 
     <lb/>
     would not be obliged to kill their horses 
     <lb/>
     hauling heavy loads over very bad 
     <lb/>
     roads. There was also a great deal of 
     <lb/>
     timber in thewestern part of the Island 
     <lb/>
     that would furnish work for a railroad 
     <lb/>
     to transport it to Charlottetown. He 
     <lb/>
     (Dr. J.) did not think the government 
     <lb/>
     were on the fence, but behind it, and at 
     <lb/>
     next election they would find a fence a 
     <lb/>very poor shelter.<lb/>
     
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> wished to reply 
     <lb/>
     to a few remarks made by the hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber from Alberton (Mr. Bell) who stated 
     <lb/>
     that the outlying portions of a country 
     <lb/>
     never prospered: but if that hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber would go to the United States, he 
     <lb/>
     would find that California, which was 
     <lb/>
    an outlying State, had progressed as 
     <lb/>rapidly as many of the States nearer 
     <lb/>the seat of government. Then again he 
     <lb/>(Mr. Bell) said we should be left like 
     <lb/>the Isle of Man, which paid no duties to 
     <lb/>the British Government; but he was 
     <lb/>mistaken, for the revenues of the Isle of 
     <lb/>Man were collected by the Imperial 
     <lb/>Government.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BELL3">Mr. BELL</persName> said the revenue of the Isle 
     <lb/>
     of Man was not collected by the British 
     <lb/>
     Government.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> said a long time 
     <lb/>
     ago the people of the Isle of Man col<lb break="no"/>lected their own revenue, but it became 
     <lb/>
     such a nest of smugglers that the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Government had to take it under 
     <lb/>
     their protection. The Col. Secretary 
     <lb/>
     had stated that our affairs were attended 
     <lb/>
     to with as much alacrity as the aflairs of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion by the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Hon. COL. SECRETARY</persName> said he had 
     <lb/>
     proved it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon Mr. HAVILAND said he (Col. 
     <lb/>
     Secretary) pretended to prove it by re<lb break="no"/>ference to the change made in the postal 
     <lb/>department; but the truth was, the 
     <lb/>British Government passed a law to 
     <lb/>have letters going to the Dominion 
     <lb/>charged only three pence postage, and 
     <lb/>we were so insignificant they forgot to 
     <lb/>include this Island in the arrangement, 
     <lb/>and, through the neglect of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment to look after it, we had to pay the 
     <lb/>old rate of postage six months longer 
     <lb/>than the Dominion. 1t appeard that 
     <lb/>the Col. Secretary did not know much 
     <lb/>
      
      
       
       <fw type="num">1870</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="num">237</fw>
       
        
        
     about the postal laws, for a government 
     <lb/>resolution was introduced this session to<lb/>make packages and parcels, passing<lb/>through the Post Office, liable to be<lb/>seized by the Collector of Customs, and<lb/>the Col. Secretary quoted some old law,<lb/>as old as Responsible Government, to<lb/>prove that such parcels should be de<lb break="no"/>tained, and he appeared totally ignorant<lb/>of the new law on the subject. He<lb/>(Col. Sec.) also seemed to know nothing<lb/>of the despatches laid on the table by<lb/>the government, for among them there<lb/>was one stating that under Imperial rule<lb/>samples of merchandise should be sent<lb/>from England by post, and asking this<lb/>Island to reciprocate, and nothing had<lb/>yet been said on the subject.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> said the subject to<lb/>which that despatch alluded would be<lb/>brought up in the proper time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. Mr. HAVILAND</persName> said the govern<lb break="no"/>ment had never said anything about these<lb/>despatches, and if hon members had not<lb/>taken the trouble of examining them,<lb/>they would never have known they<lb/>existed. He (Mr. H.) believed the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment were so inflated with the Minute<lb/>of Council that if the House was not<lb/>providentially prorogues within a week<lb/>they would burst. There was also a<lb/>despatch relating to the Governor's<lb/>Salary Bill, which the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment wished to be amended, but nothing<lb/>had been said about it. There was also<lb/>a despatch stating that Governors of<lb/>Colonies, when they hoisted the national<lb/>flag on joyful occasions, should have a<lb/>badge on it; but our government had<lb/>done nothing in the matter. Perhaps<lb/>they thought we were going into con<lb break="no"/>federation, and we should have the 
     <lb/>Dominion beaver and maple leaves for 
     <lb/>our Colonial Arms. There were several 
     <lb/>of those despatches which required 
     <lb/>legislation, an although the session was 
     <lb/>nearly ended, nothing had been done. 
     <lb/>The hon. Col. Secretary thought the 
     <lb/>land question was now forever settled 
     <lb/>by the last despatch from Lord Gran<lb break="no"/>ville, and if so, his (Col. Sec's.) political 
     <lb/>stock in trade was lost. He (Mr. B.) 
     <lb/>supposed, after that declaration from the 
     <lb/>Col . Secretary, that we should hear no 
     <lb/>more of the wrongs of the tenantry; but 
     <lb/>landlord and tenant would smoke the 
     <lb/>pipe of peace together like brothers. 
     <lb/>The Col. Secretary had changed his 
     <lb/>opinions on confederation since he spoke 
     <lb/>a few evenings since; then he was in a 
     <lb/>spirit to please the Imperial Government 
     <lb/>


            <cb/>
          
          
     and the Dominion Government, and 
     <lb/>
    warned the hon. member from Tryon 
     <lb/>against a "no-terms" resolution, lest, if<lb/>it were passed, Lord Granville should<lb/>coerce us into union ; but now he (Col.<lb/>Sec.) appeared to be in favor of a "no-<lb break="yes"/>terms" resolution. The Col. Secretary<lb/>had also given the House a great defini<lb break="no"/>tion of the work "reject," which was<lb/>in the despatch, but unfortunately he<lb/>stopped at that word.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName> said the Leader of 
     <lb/>the Opposition had, all the afternoon,<lb/>been into the despatches like a horse<lb/>poking his head into hay, and now it<lb/>appeared he had found a "mare's nest."<lb/>He (Leader of the Opposition) appeared<lb/>like a bottle of ginger beer - he went off<lb/>with a pop - he had travelled out of the<lb/>record, but he would have to keep calm<lb/>and bottle up his effervescence, and<lb/>patiently wait until these despatches<lb/>were brought up in regular order. One<lb/>would have thought, from the discussion<lb/>about Post Offices, that he (Leader of<lb/>the Opposition) knew something about<lb/>them, but it appeared there were some<lb/>things he could not understand. the<lb/>question discussed in committee of way<lb/>and means was regarding the sending of<lb/>jewelry through the Post Office, and this<lb/>despatch related to books and pamphlets.<lb/>
     The Leader of the Opposition would try 
     <lb/>
    to make the House believe that the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment were remiss in their duty in not<lb/>sooner getting a reduction of letter post<lb break="no"/>age between this Island and England ;    
     <lb/>but as soon as they found out, that an 
     <lb/>arrangement was made with the Do-. 
     <lb/>minion, they applied to the British Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to have the same beneflts ex<lb break="no"/>tended to us, and our postage would be 
     <lb/>uniform with that of the Dominion 
     <lb/>in June next. It was impossible for the 
     <lb/>government to know what correspond<lb break="no"/>ence was taking place between the 
     <lb/>Postmaster General of the Dominion 
     <lb/>and the Postmaster General of England. 
     <lb/>As regarded the badge for our flag, the 
     <lb/>government had acted upon the des<lb break="no"/>patch; but this was not the proper time 
     <lb/>to discuss these matters, as confederation 
     <lb/>was the subject before the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> thought if the minute of 
     <lb/>
     Council had the effect some hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers attributed to it, it was a master 
     <lb/>
     stroke of policy on the part of the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to have drawn up such a docu<lb break="no"/>ment, inasmuch as it had been the means 
     <lb/>of placing the colony in a position which 
     <lb/>left the people entirely free in the 
     <lb/>
          
          
            <pb n="238" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1870-04-12_Page_238.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">238</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</fw> <fw type="dateline">1870</fw>
    
    
     matter. The people know also that the 
     <lb/>
     government  had been true  to  their 
     <lb/>
     pledge; and when the document which 
     <lb/>they drew up had been compared to<lb/>what was worthy of a Machiavelli, or a<lb/>Talleyrand, he did not think they had any<lb/>
     
     
     
     cause to be ashamed of it.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName> said, judging from what 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for St. Peter's said, 
     <lb/>
     he gloried in a Machiavellian policy on the  
     <lb/>
     part of the government, in producing 
     <lb/>
     a document which did not mean what 
     <lb/>
     it wast intended to convey to the mind of 
     <lb/>
     those who read it.  Glorying that his 
     <lb/>
     party was so wise as to be able to de<lb break="no"/>ceive the Home Government. Such a 
     <lb/>
     policy was indeed worthy of a Machiavelli. 
     <lb/>
     He (Mr. B.) looked upon such a course, 
     <lb/>
     to be as stupid as it was dishonest.   A 
     <lb/>
     Machiavellian policy was that of duplicity 
     <lb/>
     and hypocrisy, and yet it was the policy  
     <lb/>
     Her most gracious Majesty's Queen's 
     <lb/>
     Printer thought so clever.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:REIL1">Mr. REILLY</persName> considered the policy that 
     <lb/>
     was adopted, the very best which, under 
     <lb/>
     the circumstances, the government could 
     <lb/>
     have pursued. And though the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member (Mr. B.) might call the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment what he pleased, yet he could 
     <lb/>not show that they had proved untrue 
     <lb/>to the promises made, or to the general 
     <lb/>interests of those who sent them there. 
     <lb/>By the course pursued, the onus of re<lb break="no"/>sponsibility had been glued upon the  
     <lb/>Home government, and, as to the des<lb break="no"/>patch, it showed clearly that the Imperial 
     <lb/>Government cared very little whether this 
     <lb/>Island united with Canada or not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DUNC1">Hon. Mr. DUNCAN</persName> thought the anti- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     confederate party was likely to have 
     <lb/>
     even the strongest of those who once 
     <lb/>
     opposed them on  their side, and the 
     <lb/>
     arguments used a few days ago, by his 
     <lb/>
     hon. colleague, were correct, the Island 
     <lb/>
     now belonged to the people, and he was 
     <lb/>
     pleased to see how many who once 
     <lb/>
     opposed his (Mr. Duncan's) views, were 
     <lb/>
     now coming to see the matter as he did. 
     <lb/>
     It had been asked where would they go 
     <lb/>
      to get money to buy out the lands of the 
     <lb/>
     proprietors. Borrow it in England, was 
     <lb/>
     the answer, and all knew the result. 
     <lb/>
     He would, however, inform the <choice><sic>com<lb break="no"/>mitte</sic><corr>committee</corr></choice> that there was then in the Union 
     <lb/>Bank:—<lb/>
            </p>

    
<table>
<row><cell>Deposits on call</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">£15,331 19 2</cell> </row>
<row><cell>Treasury credit,</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">14,464 0 0</cell></row> 
<row><cell>Deposits on interest,</cell>  <cell rendition="simple:right">9,778 18 0</cell></row> 
<row><cell>Total in Union Bank,</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">£89,564 17 2</cell></row> 
</table>

    
            <cb/>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     BANK OF P. E. ISLAND. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<table>
 <row><cell>Deposits on call,</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">£17,158 2 3</cell> <cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Treasury credit,</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">10,778 18 1</cell><cell></cell></row>
   <row><cell>Deposits on interest,</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">31,048 11 3</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">—58,985 11 1</cell></row>
   <row><cell>Making a total of</cell><cell></cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">£98,550 3 9</cell></row>
</table>
          
          
   
            <p>
     The greater portion of this amount was 
     <lb/>waiting investment when a larger inter<lb break="no"/>est could be obtained than the Banks<lb/>would give. He had made a similar<lb/>statement at the time the Loan Bill was<lb/>passing through the House, and thought<lb/>now if the government wanted to bor<lb break="no"/>row money, they knew where to look<lb/>for it with a better prospect of success<lb/>than when they sent to England for it.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     After a few remarks from two or three 
     <lb/>other hon members, the debate was<lb/>adjourned.<lb/>
            </p>
           
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>