<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1868-04-13"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title>
<name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1868-04-13">13 April 1868</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1868">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1868, Being the Second Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1868"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Patriot" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="192"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_190.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_191.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_192.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-12">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_190"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_190.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_191"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_191.jpg"/></surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_192"><graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_192.jpg"/></surface>
</facsimile>

<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="190" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_190.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">190</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. LEADER OF THE GOVERNMENT</persName>.—It is with feelings<lb/>
of deep regret that I have to announce to this House the <lb/>
sad news reported by telegraph, that the Hon. T. D'Arcy <lb/>
McGee was assassinated at Ottawa, on the morning of the <lb/>
7th instant. There are few hon. members present who <lb/>
have not seen him, and those who have not, have heard <lb/>
of his patriotic movements in Canada, before the Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces were united, and from all they know, they must <lb/>
feel as I do, a deep regret that so worthy a man should be <lb/>
assassinated by his fellow-man. I do not intend to enter <lb/>
into a long display of words upon this occasion, but I <lb/>
admired the man who was a co-delegate at the late Con<lb break="no"/>ference on Confederation, and who always showed a feel<lb break="no"/>ing to do justice to the Lower Provinces, as well as to his <lb/>
adopted country. I can bear willing testimony to the <lb/>
love of justice and fair play which actuated the noble <lb/>
heart and able mind of this distinguished statesman and <lb/>
orator. I have always held him in high esteem, and <lb/>
nothing has given me a greater shake than to bear that <lb/>
this worthy and noble man has been assassinated for <lb/>
speaking the truth, and uttering the sentiments of his <lb/>
mind. All hon. members present must feel that an <lb/>
assassin could deprive them of life, and might do so if <lb/>
they merely speak the simple truth, and therefore it behoves <lb/>
all public men to deprecate this atrocious act <lb/>
Having had the honor of an acquaintance with Mrs. <lb/>
McGee, I deeply sympathize, as I believe the whole House <lb/>
does with her in her bereavement. It is with a deep feeling <lb/>
of sorrow that I move the following :— <lb/></p>

<p>The assassination of the Hon. T. D'Arcy McGee, of <lb/>
the Dominion of Canada, having been reported by telegram— <lb/></p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Therefore, Resolved</hi>, That this House regards with <lb/>
horror and detestation the atrocious and blood-thirsty act ; <lb/>
deeply sympathizes with the bereaved widow and orphans, <lb/>
and sincerely regrets that the Dominion Government <lb/>
should have lost such an able and patriotic statesman. <lb/></p></quote>

<p>This, I believe, expresses the sentiments of this hon. <lb/>
House. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HAVI1">Hon. LEADER OF THE OPPOSITION</persName>.—As the Leader of <lb/>
the Opposition, I have the painful satisfaction of second<lb break="no"/>ing the resolution which has just been moved by the hon. <lb/>
Leader of the Government on the death of the Hon. T. <lb/>
D'Arcy McGee. I bad the pleasure of his acquaintance <lb/>
in 1864, while attending the Quebec Conference, and <lb/>
from what I saw of him then, both in public and private, <lb/>
I came to the conclusion, Sir, that he was one of the <lb/>
greatest men of which British North America could boast. <lb/>
I have never altered the conclusion I then came to, and <lb/>
day by day, and year by year, subsequently, I have been <lb/>
more convinced than ever, that he was a bright and <lb/>
shining light. As a public man in British America, and <lb/>
one who had at heart the welfare and prosperity of all <lb/>
the inhabitants of these Provinces, he stood in the front <lb/>
rank, and I am certain, however hon. members in this <lb/>
House may differ with him as regards the means of carry<lb break="no"/>ing out his great object, they must all be convinced that <lb/>
he had no selfish purposes to serve in advocating the <lb/>
Union of British America; because, if he would wish to <lb/>
make himself popular for the moment, he would have <lb/>
taken the opposite course. But he had large conscienti<lb break="no"/>ousness and matured views upon this important question, <lb/>
and could speak with greater weight upon that topic than <lb/>
any other man, because in his early days, before his <lb/>
judgment was matured, he was tinged strongly with re<lb break="no"/>publican principles, and firmly believed that his beloved <lb/>
country could never prosper unless under the republican <lb/>
system of government. When that unfortunate crisis ar<lb break="no"/>rived, in his native country in 1848, he took up his abode <lb/>
in the United States, believing that he could there enjoy <lb/>
greater liberty than under the flag of England; but he <lb/>

<cb/>

did not remain there for many years before he saw that what <lb/>
at first seemed to him very beautiful and fair was far <lb/>
from sound and correct in principle. He crossed the line <lb/>
and found the people of Canada enjoying more real <lb/>
liberty than their neighbors in the United States. After <lb/>
experiencing the various forms of government, he came to <lb/>
the conclusion in his matured judgment, that there was <lb/>
more liberty as regards action and the rights of conscience <lb/>
under a constitutional monarchy, than could be enjoyed <lb/>
under a republican government. From that time to the <lb/>
day of his sudden and cruel death, he devoted himself to <lb/>
ttie cause of his country, and after leaving the Legislative <lb/>
Halls of the Dominion on the morning of the 7th instant, <lb/>
having just delivered a very able speech, he was sent into <lb/>
eternity by the shots of an assassin, without a moment's <lb/>
warning. He is not the first statesman who has fallen in <lb/>
that manner; a Prime Minister of England was sent into <lb/>
eternity in the same way within the present century, and <lb/>
again the late President of the United States fell also by <lb/>
the brutal assassin's hand. We cannot find words, for <lb/>
the tongue refuses to perform its functions, when we con<lb break="no"/>template the tearful end of the great Canadian states<lb break="no"/>man. A great and noble man has fallen in the zenith of <lb/>
his political power; and, therefore, I am sure there will <lb/>
not be a dissentient voice to the resolution. In medi<lb break="no"/>tating upon the sad death of this true patriot, we are re<lb break="no"/>minded of the language of the poet Longfellow, when he <lb/>
said :— <lb/></p>

<p rendition="simple:centre">"The lives of great men all remind us
We can make our lives sublime,
And departing, leave behind us
Footprints on the sands of time."</p>


<p>The resolution was here again read at the Clerk's <lb/>
table. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCAU1">Hon. Mr. MCAULAY</persName>.—There is no individual, Sir, in <lb/>
whose breast the tender feeling of humanity exists, but <lb/>
must have formed a favorable opinion of the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man whose career has been suddenly out short in the <lb/>
midst of youth. Although he ran in the path of error, <lb/>
when young, experience calmed him down, and he re<lb break="no"/>pented in maturer years. I am not aware that a greater <lb/>
man exists in these Colonies; although I have never seen <lb/>
his person, I have read his writings and his speeches with <lb/>
profound admiration. When we think of his patriotism, <lb/>
his love of constitutional liberty and his superior attain<lb break="no"/>ments, we must, under these circumstances, conclude that <lb/>
the world has lost a great man. We may say truly that <lb/>
"a great man has fallen in Israel." We must deeply re<lb break="no"/>gret that any community should shelter in its bosom a <lb/>
person capable of perpetrating such an atrocious crime, <lb/>
and must sincerely hope that he will be brought to <lb/>
justice. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HOWL2">Hon. Mr. HOWLAN</persName>.—I am sorry that we should be <lb/>
called upon to pass a resolution of this kind. When we <lb/>
see a man of such a stamp as the Hon. T. D'Arcy McGee, <lb/>
who had one of the noblest and most cultivated minds the <lb/>
world has ever seen, and the largest heart that has ever <lb/>
throbbed in sympathy with his fellow-creatures, cut down <lb/>
in the prime of life, the heart is made sore at the thought <lb/>
that any man could launch such a noble soul into eter<lb break="no"/>nity. This great and honorable man occupied a position <lb/>
and earned a name in his adopted country which cannot <lb/>
be forgotten; and though he erred in his early days, <lb/>
there was an ample excuse for him when we take into <lb/>
consideration the views and prevailing ideas which agi<lb break="no"/>tated his native country at the time. His experience <lb/>
afterwards taught him the folly of the course which he <lb/>
had pursued, and he took the side of justice and true <lb/>
liberty; while little minds would have followed on in their <lb/>
foolish course, and would have carried the errors of youth <lb/>
into middle age, he saw the right path and walked in it. <lb/>
While smaller minds would have taken credit to them<lb break="no"/>selves if they had acted as be did in 1848, in his native <lb/>
country, he was not the man to do so. He thought that <lb/>
he had thrown away his early days, that he had some re<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="191" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_191.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">191</fw> 

compense to make, and that he could do it better in the <lb/>
new country than in the old one. He might have oc<lb break="no"/>cupied an enviable position in the United States, but be <lb/>
thought that in this new country he could be of some use, <lb/>
that his soul would find some rest, and that he would yet <lb/>
be able to make some recompense to the public of British <lb/>
America and to the Mother Country for the errors of his <lb/>
youth. I have never seen him, nor do I agree with him <lb/>
on the great question of Confederation; but in view of <lb/>
the events which are now taking place, every British sub<lb break="no"/>ject in America must feel that we have lost one of the <lb/>
greatest minds that have ever been amongst us. I believe <lb/>
that as a poet he was unequalled in these Colonies, and I <lb/>
hoped that in his old age he would have rested from his <lb/>
political labors, and settled down in some quiet retreat <lb/>
with his mind richly stored; and thus to have an opportunity <lb/>
of adding considerably to our British American <lb/>
literature. He might have written a history of the <lb/>
events which have lately taken place in these Colonies. <lb/>
I trust that the Dominion of Canada, to which he has <lb/>
given the best years of his valuable life, will not forget <lb/>
his family; they should not be thrown upon the charity <lb/>
of a cold world. His name and his eloquence have resounded <lb/>
throughout all the Lower Provinces, and when <lb/>
we hear all tongues full of his praise for his generosity, <lb/>
patriotism, ability and attainments, I think we can only <lb/>
come to the one conclusion, that British America and <lb/>
British interests have lost one of the greatest friends <lb/>
they have ever had in these Provinces. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HENS1">Hon. Mr. HENSLEY</persName>.—If an individual in the most obscure <lb/>
position in the land were hurried into eternity in <lb/>
the same manner as the Hon T. D'Arcy McGee has been, <lb/>
I believe that every member in this House would at once, <lb/>
with a natural impulse, express their indignation and <lb/>
abhorrence at the unnatural and cruel act. But how <lb/>
much we detest the assassination of a man whose life has <lb/>
been so valuable to the people of British America, and <lb/>
who was so remarkable for his virtues, his patriotism and <lb/>
his attainments. It is a lamentable fact that these das<lb break="no"/>tardly acts have not been unfrequent of late, for it is not <lb/>
long since the President of the neighboring Republic was <lb/>
cut down, and now the Hon. T. D'Arcy McGee is the <lb/>
victim. I have not been so well acquainted with the <lb/>
latter gentleman as the hon. Leader of the Government <lb/>
and the hon. Leader of the Opposition were, but I know <lb/>
him by his speeches, his writings and his actions; and if <lb/>
ever there was a statesman for whom I had respect, it <lb/>
was for the Hon. Mr. McGee. I recollect the part he <lb/>
took in the troubles of 1848, as well as his subsequent <lb/>
change of opinion on these events; and I have admired <lb/>
the path which he has taken since that time. He went <lb/>
into a country where there was a different form of government <lb/>
and judged its merits for himself; he afterwards <lb/>
returned to that country to which his allegiance was first <lb/>
given. In spite of the opinion of some, he came and declared <lb/>
openly that there was no form of government to <lb/>
be compared with a limited monarchy, such as that of <lb/>
Great Britain, and that no government afforded such <lb/>
freedom to its subjects or citizens. His country was <lb/>
justly proud of his talents, and indeed the whole United <lb/>
Kingdom was proud of him as an orator, and as one who <lb/>
threw himself into the patriotic movement with heart <lb/>
and soul. The atrocious crime which has been perpe<lb break="no"/>trated, has deprived the outcry to which be belongs of <lb/>
an able statesman, and there must be but one feeling of <lb/>
detestation and horror at the blood-thirsty act. I am <lb/>
glad to hear that this resolution will not only be communicated <lb/>
to the Speaker of the Dominion Parliament, <lb/>
but to the poor widow, though it will be but a small <lb/>
tribute. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—I have a sort of melancholy gratifica<lb break="no"/>tion in hearing the hon. Leader of the Government move <lb/>
this resolution. It is but a tribute of respect due to the <lb/>
memory of that great man who has lately been removed <lb/>
from life by the ruthless hand of the assassin. From <lb/>

<cb/>

what little I have beard and read of his career, I believe <lb/>
that he was one of the most valuable men that Her <lb/>
Majesty had on this side of the Atlantic. He was a gentleman <lb/>
remarkable for his great talents, large soul and <lb/>
high attainments; and as a statesman be was eminently <lb/>
successful in carrying out his designs, the principal of <lb/>
which was the union of the North American Provinces. <lb/>
D'Arcy McGee was a literary man of the first order, and <lb/>
his abilities as a journalist, as well as the able articles he <lb/>
wrote, attracted the notice of the great Daniel O'Connell, <lb/>
the famous Irish agitator. We know that be had in his <lb/>
youth no love nor admiration for the institutions of our <lb/>
mother country, as he had in his later days, but having <lb/>
worked out the political problem on the spirit of <lb/>
our institutions, his unflinching interest in the cause of <lb/>
these principles which he then adopted, rendered him one <lb/>
of the most useful men in British North America. <lb/>
No man has done more for his country than D'Arcy <lb/>
McGee, and no man was more beloved by his countrymen <lb/>
than he. No man has been more deservedly popular in <lb/>
Canada for his unflagging labors in behalf of the cause <lb/>
of constitutional liberty, and the welfare and prosperity <lb/>
of his adopted country. In the prime of life be has been <lb/>
sent to his long home through the malice of his cruel <lb/>
enemies, for opposing all which would retard his country's <lb/>
progress, and for advancing its true interests. He has <lb/>
left a widow and children behind him, but they will not <lb/>
be allowed to remain unprovided for. In his efforts in <lb/>
behalf of the cause of Confederation, nothing but a spirit <lb/>
of fairness, integrity, and true patriotism, characterized <lb/>
his actions. I can imagine the desolation that will not <lb/>
only weigh down his own family, but his political friends, <lb/>
as well as all whose hearts were full of hope for the <lb/>
future progress and prosperity of the New Dominion. I <lb/>
am glad that this small tribute has been awarded to his <lb/>
memory by this hon House. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HEND3">Hon. Mr. HENDERSON</persName>.—I believe, Sir, that no hon. <lb/>
member of this House can approach this subject without <lb/>
feelings of deep emotion — at least I cannot. I had not <lb/>
the honor nor the pleasure of being personally acquainted <lb/>
with the departed, whose melancholy end has been the <lb/>
subject of discussion, but I have carefully pursued his <lb/>
speeches and pamphlets. I speak from my heart, and <lb/>
express it as my honest conviction, that what that gentleman <lb/>
was in his youth he was to the last day of his life— <lb/>
a sincere patriot. What I mean to say is, that what he <lb/>
believed to be his duty, he did with transparent honesty <lb/>
and purity of motive. When he walked in the path <lb/>
which be afterwards found to be not that of Wisdom, he <lb/>
gave the clearest proofs that he acted from unselfish <lb/>
motives, and when be saw his error, he made ample <lb/>
recompense for all his former mistakes. He reviewed his <lb/>
past conduct, which is certainly the best of teachers, and <lb/>
gave utterance to what he believed to be his duty. We <lb/>
must cheerfully admit that what he believed to be his <lb/>
duty he pursued, whether that course was under the <lb/>
frowns or the smiles of his fellow-countrymen; and al<lb break="no"/>though they sometimes thought he was in error and <lb/>
opposed to them, he was at all times their true friend and <lb/>
protector; this is the conviction of my mind. And now <lb/>
under present circumstances, I cannot but sympathise <lb/>
deeply with all that has been expressed by hon. members <lb/>
in regard to that gentleman. He, from the depths of his <lb/>
warm and noble heart, gave utterance to beautiful and <lb/>
patriotic language, when he apprehended no danger from <lb/>
speaking freely in the Halls of the Dominion Parliament, <lb/>
but on his way home he fell by the hand of the treacherous <lb/>
assassin. I can fancy to myself that if Mr. McGee's late <lb/>
prototype were in this House to-day, he would deliver a <lb/>
speech upon this sad event, equal in power and effect to <lb/>
the noble speech which he delivered on the patriotic fund, <lb/>
for his large and warm heart was want to sympathize <lb/>
in cases of this kind. If the Hon. T. D'Arcy McGee <lb/>
had fallen in the Crimea, while advancing in that great <lb/>
charge near Balaclava, my mind would be possessed of <lb/>

<pb n="192" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-04-13_Page_192.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">192</fw> 

very different feelings from what it is to-day, for then he <lb/>
would have died as a noble warrior, by the band of a <lb/>
powerful enemy; but no, he died by the hand of the <lb/>
brutal assassin. All high-minded and far-seeing statesmen <lb/>
will agree with me that he died in the cause of liberty, <lb/>
as well as those who fell in the Crimea, while <lb/>
doing battle for their country. I certainly concur with <lb/>
every sentiment of regard and of sympathy, that has been <lb/>
expressed by the hon. members who have preceded me in <lb/>
their remarks, for the relatives and friends of the <lb/>
deceased; and if anything is required for the support of <lb/>
the mourning widow and her family, Prince Edward <lb/>
Island will not be behindhand in doing her part, for it <lb/>
should be deemed a duty to support the bereaved family. <lb/></p>

<p>Hons. Kelly, Davies, Laird, and Callbeck; and Messrs. <lb/>
Reilly, McNeill, and Bell, then severally expressed <lb/>
their approval of the sentiments conveyed in the reso<lb break="no"/>lution before the House, and their deep and unfeigned <lb/>
sorrow on the lamentable death of the distinguished <lb/>
statesman. <lb/></p>

<p>The resolution was then unanimously agreed to. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:COLE1">Hon. LEADER or THE GOVERNMENT</persName>.—Mr. Speaker, I <lb/>
wish this resolution to be sent to the widow, as well as to <lb/>
the Speaker of the Dominion Parliament, through your <lb/>
hands. <lb/></p>

<p>This motion was also carried. <lb/></p>

<p>House adjourned. <lb/></p>

<p rendition="simple:right">I OXENHAM, Reporter.<lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>