<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xml:id="lgPEILA_1868-03-11"
 xml:lang="en"
 type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPEILAssem">Legislative Assembly of Prince Edward Island</name>, <date when="1868-03-11">11 March 1868</date>, Prince Edward Island Confederation with Canada.</title>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> 
<!-- xml markup only - not proofed --> 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>


<bibl corresp="bibl:lgPEILA_1868">
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly of Prince Edward Island, for the Year 1868, Being the Second Session of the Twenty-Third General Assembly.</title>.
<date when="1868"/>. 
<pubPlace>Charlottetown, P.E.I.</pubPlace>: <publisher>"The Patriot" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="42"/>
</bibl>
 

<list>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-03-11_Page_041.html"/>
</item>
<item>
<ptr target="final/hocr/PEI_LA_1868-03-11_Page_042.html"/>
</item>
</list>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<samplingDecl>

<p/>
</samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-11">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-03-11_Page_041">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-03-11_Page_041.jpg"/>
</surface>
<surface xml:id="PEI_LA_1868-03-11_Page_042">
<graphic url="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-03-11_Page_042.jpg"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="41" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-03-11_Page_041.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">41</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. MACNEILL</persName>—I have just got what I wanted to <lb/>
get out of the hon. member; and I wish, through the <lb/>
Reporters, to let my constituents know that the hon. <lb/>
member for Charlottetown called me a "fire-brand." I <lb/>
am glad also to hear him say that he was sorry that Mr. <lb/>
Dodd was not a member of this House. Mr. Dodd was  <lb/>
the man who wrote this vile slander against the people <lb/>
of this Colony, and, therefore, I am glad that he is not <lb/>
here. A man who could put upon paper that which <lb/> </p>

<pb n="42" facs="final/images/PEI_LA_1868-03-11_Page_042.jpg"/>
<fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY REPORTER.</hi></fw>
<fw type="num">42</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p>I believe that our late Con<lb break="no"/>servative Government wished, if possible, to induce the <lb/>
Imperial Government to force us into Confederation; <lb/>
but of the folly of such proced ures the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment have had enough in what has since transpired in <lb/>
 Nova Scotia. But notwithstanding the foul libels <lb/>
heaped upon the people of this Colony by the late Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, the Colony has maintained her reputation <lb/>
and her independence. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREC1">Mr. BRECKEN</persName>.—  <lb/></p> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p>ber. Let him now demand such an examination and  <lb/>
he will find that Mr. Dodd has nothing to fear. If the <lb/>
Tenant Union was pursuing a right and proper course, <lb/>
why was it that it crumpled up so suddenly, when Her <lb/>
Majesty's troops came here ? The men, Sir, whom I <lb/>
blame the most are not the body of the people who uni<lb break="no"/>ted themselves with that organization, but their leaders. <lb/>
Those men knew that Her Majesty's Despatch made it <lb/>
unlawful to resist the just claims of the proprietors. <lb/>
They knew that her troops did not come here to enforce <lb/>
obedience to unlawful demands ; and no man, who duly <lb/>
respected the honor and good nature of the country, <lb/>
would have justified the action of that organization at <lb/>
that time. I may be told that I am slandering the <lb/>
Tenant Union ; but will the hon. member (Mr. Mc<lb break="no"/>Neill) rise here, and propose a resolution that will justify <lb/>
the one adopted by that body, which said they would <lb/>
hold no communication, except in cases of necessity, <lb/>
with any person who would not support their organiza<lb break="no"/>tion ? Let him bring such a resolution forward and I <lb/>
will call him a patriot, though a misguided one. Let <lb/>
the hon. member give notice of this on the Order Book, <lb/>
and then we will see where his political manliness rests. <lb/>
I do not glory in the unfortunate state of affairs, which <lb/>
called forth Mr. Dodd's letter ; on the contrary, I regret <lb/>
it as much as any man in the country, for I know there <lb/>
is a good deal of truth in what the hon. member has <lb/>
said, but at the same time, had the hon. member and <lb/>
the League with whom he was associated, had their own <lb/>
way at that time, they would have done more to have <lb/>
forced us into Confederation than any Government <lb/>
could. Before Responsible Government was granted to <lb/>
us, it was doubted whether we were able to work it out <lb/>
successfully, and to duly prize the privileges it would <lb/>
confer ; but the only time when any portion of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple showed that they did not appreciate it, was when a <lb/>
portion of them were led by that hon member. Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government was granted on conditions which were <lb/>
binding upon us and upon the Home Government ; and at <lb/>
that time the Home Government might justly have said <lb/>
to us you have not adhered to those conditions ; you <lb/>
do not appear to be a low abiding people, and we will <lb/>
wash our hands clear of you by handing you over to <lb/>
Canada ! Let the hon member read the Bloody Des<lb break="no"/>patch as carefully as he has Mr. Dodd's letter, and he <lb/>
will be convinced of the truth of what I say. It was <lb/>
not to support the Liberals that the hon. member was <lb/>
sent here by the League ; for if that was their object, <lb/>
why did Mr. Ross oppose the Leader of the Government, <lb/>
after he had accepted office? <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

</div> </body> </text> </TEI>