<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1866-03-12"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-03-12">12 March 1866</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Third Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
          <date when="1866"/>.  
          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="70"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-03-12_Page_070.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-11-02">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="DLANG4" when="2017-11-02">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-03-12_Page_070">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-12_Page_070.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="70" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-12_Page_070.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">70</fw> 
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
            
            <div type="section"> 
               <p>       
     <persName ref="pers:SHAN2">Hon. Mr. SHANNON</persName> referred to the attempt<lb break="no"/>ed alteration of the city license law last year. 
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> remarked that the town of 
     <lb/>
     Picton was also excluded from the operation 
     <lb/>
     of the general law. Such legislation was not 
     <lb/>
     adapted to the wants of the country, and he 
     <lb/>
     did not see why these exceptions should be 
     <lb/>
     made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName> said that as the organ of the 
     <lb/>
     Temperance body had been referred to, he 
     <lb/>
     would say a word on the subject, though he 
     <lb/>
     felt surprised that the hon. member for Inver<lb break="no"/>ness had thought it worth while to refer to it.— 
     <lb/>
     That paper would seem to insinuate that that 
     <lb/>
     gentleman and himself were occupying a po<lb break="no"/>sition inconsistent with their legislative duties 
     <lb/>
     in being retained by any body of persons. The 
     <lb/>
     facts were, that after the passage of the law. a 
     <lb/>
     number of gentlemen called upon them for 
     <lb/>
     advice, and, in discharge of their professional 
     <lb/>
     duties, that advice was given. A journal 
     <lb/>
     which went out of its way to make an insinu<lb break="no"/>ation that the retainer had been accepted in a 
     <lb/>
     legislative capacity, was not likely to promote 
     <lb/>
     the objects it had in view. He did not think 
     <lb/>
     the proposed separation a wise policy, and had 
     <lb/>
     heard no argument advanced in its support 
     <lb/>
     that was entitled to a great deal of weight.— 
     <lb/>
     That had been his opinion of the matter long 
     <lb/>
     before the Grocers' and Liquor Dealers' Associ<lb break="no"/>ation had been in existence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr ARCHIBALD</persName> said he had been desirous that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Blanchard should have an opportunity 
     <lb/>
     of explaining his postion in reference to the 
     <lb/>
     matter, and was glad to find that that gentle<lb break="no"/>man's views coincided with those of the pro<lb break="no"/>moters of the change, and with the views en<lb break="no"/>tertained by the great majority of the people 
     <lb/>
     The hon member for Richmond entertained dif<lb break="no"/>ferent sentiments, and he was entitled to hold 
     <lb/>
     these, and to give an opinion upon the law 
     <lb/>
     without the imputation of improper motives. 
     <lb/>
     He trusted that the observations to which these 
     <lb/>
    gentlemen refered would not prevent them   
     <lb/>from carrying out their convictions as to the 
     <lb/>course which should be adopted; but so far 
     <lb/>from thinking that the latter gentleman was 
     <lb/>right in treating the organ of the Temperance 
     <lb/>body with contempt, he considered a paper 
     <lb/>fighting in the cause of Temperance and mora<lb break="no"/>lity, against such opposition as it must have to 
     <lb/>encounter, should be referred to with respect. 
     <lb/>He had never seen anything in that paper to 
     <lb/>lead him to think it other than the organ of a 
     <lb/>very large influential, and respectable class of 
     <lb/>people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> said he had never considered this 
     <lb/>
     a question with which the House should deal; 
     <lb/>
     it was a matter for the the City Council and the 
     <lb/>
               Sessions, because the Province derived no re<lb break="no"/>venue from the licenses. The Mayor and Cor<lb break="no"/>poration of the city where entrusted with mat<lb break="no"/>ters far transcending this in importance, and 
     <lb/>
     they should be the judges of what was a good 
     <lb/>
     license law. He thought the conduct of the ci<lb break="no"/>tizens of Halifax was as orderly as that of any 
     <lb/>
     other people in British America or the United 
     <lb/>
     States. The leader of the Opposition had once 
     <lb/>
     contended that the country should be governed 
     <lb/>
     by cold water principles, but that gentleman 
     <lb/>
     seemed to have changed his opinions, and to 
     <lb/>
     have come to the conclusion that hot piety and 
     <lb/>
     cold water were not best after all. Even the 
     <lb/>
     Chairman of Railways would admit that some<lb break="no"/>thing besides cold water was necessary in his 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
          
     department. The law which had existed up to 
     <lb/>
     last session imposing heavy fines upon persons 
     <lb/>
     selling liquor without license, was an instance 
     <lb/>
     of a law which was too stringent to be carried 
     <lb/>
     into effect. —and as to the expediency of the 
     <lb/>
     separation claus, very great doubts existed in 
     <lb/>
     the community. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> said he did not see why 
     <lb/>
     authority should be given to the City Council 
     <lb/>
     to deal differently with the community of Hali<lb break="no"/>fax from any other portion of the Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The bill was read a first time. 
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">           
               <head rendition="simple:centre">MISCELLANEOUS.</head>
               <p>
                  
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. S. MACDONNELL</persName> presented a petition 
     <lb/>
     from Inverness against the Union of the Col<lb break="no"/>onies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Also, a petition from the same county, ask<lb break="no"/>ing the establishment of a daily mail to Port 
     <lb/>
     Hood and Margaree. This petition he urged 
     <lb/>
     very strongly upon the notice of the Government 
     <lb/>
     ment, alluding particularly to the fact that a 
     <lb/>
     daily mail now crossed the Gut of Canso on its 
     <lb/>
     way to Sydney. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LONG1">Mr. LONGLEY</persName>, in accordance with leave pre<lb break="no"/>viously obtained, introduced a bill in reference 
     <lb/>
     to a public landing at Paradise. 
           
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">           
               <head rendition="simple:centre">RAILWAY DAMAGES.</head>
               
               <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FRAS2">Mr. D. FRASER</persName> presented a petition from 
     <lb/>
     certain inhabitants of Pictou, praying tor an 
     <lb/>
     alteration in the 70th chapter of the Revised 
     <lb/>
     Statutes, respecting Railways. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> called attention to the pro<lb break="no"/>priety of taking the petition into careful con<lb break="no"/>sideration, and expressed his Opinion that the 
     <lb/>
     power given by the law to cut down timber, 
     <lb/>
     &amp;c., for public purposes, should be carefully 
     <lb/>
     restrained. No individual should be more 
     <lb/>
     overridden than is absolutely necessary for 
     <lb/>
     the promotion of the public interests. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FRAS2">Mr. D. FRASER</persName> introduced an Act to amend 
     <lb/>
     chap. 70 R. S., in accordance with the prayer of 
     <lb/>
     the petition.
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SECY</persName>. said that he hoped that 
     <lb/>
     the hon member would be able to suggest a 
     <lb/>
     means by which the interests of the public, as 
     <lb/>
     well as those of private individuals, would be 
     <lb/>
     equally protected. He was not prepared to 
     <lb/>
     say that sub-contractors might not occasional<lb break="no"/>ly take a course under the present law which 
     <lb/>
     would be exceedingly inconvenient to the own<lb break="no"/>ers of private property, but the proper time for 
     <lb/>
     parties to remonstrate was when the Railway 
     <lb/>
     Act was being passed. The House should not
     <lb/>
     forget that an expenditure of $2,000,000 was 
     <lb/>
     now going on for a great public work, which, 
     <lb/>
     whilst of undoubted advantage to the whole 
     <lb/>
     Province, would especially benefit Pictou, and 
     <lb/>
     largely increase the value of property within 
     <lb/>
     miles of the railway. Under such circumstan<lb break="no"/>ces he thought it strange to see persons object<lb break="no"/>ing to incur a small amount of inconvenience 
     <lb/>
     in connection with a work which was to be of 
     <lb/>
     such signal advantage to them. He had no ob<lb break="no"/>jection to the introduction of the bill, though 
     <lb/>
     he would like to see how the public as well as 
     <lb/>
     private interests were to be at the same time 
     <lb/>
     protected. He had heard of parties who had 
     <lb/>
     combined to put a price of 60 cents upon rail<lb break="no"/>way sleepers, and yet had sold them subse<lb break="no"/>quently for 10 cents to the parties who actually 
     <lb/>
     got the contracts. It was as well to understand 
     <lb/>
     whether those engaged in the construction of 
     <lb/>
     our Railways were to be called upon to pay 
     <lb/>
     inordinate prices through such combinations. 
            </p>
         </div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>