<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNSLA_1867-05-07" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1867-05-07">7 May 1867</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> <!-- xml markup only - not proofed -->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA"> <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
<date when="1867"/>.
<pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="207"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-05-07_Page_0207.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-19">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-05-07_Page_0207"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-07_Page_0207.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="207" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-07_Page_0207.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY</fw>
<fw type="num">207</fw> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> laid on the table instructions <lb/>
relative lo the division of road moneys for <lb/>
the County of Halifax,for the information of <lb/>
the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">EXPLANATION. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName>—The hon. Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary, On a former day, made a special allusion <lb/>
to myself in respect to an attempt I was mak<lb break="no"/>ing to find a seat in the New Dominion. I may <lb/>
say to the hon. gentleman that so far as I am <lb/>
concerned I have not authorized any one to <lb/>
make such an offer, as it has been stated, has <lb/>
been made. I may say further that overtures <lb/>
have been made to me from several counties, <lb/>
but to all I have given invariably a denial,— <lb/>
only under very peculiar circumstances would <lb/>
I offer for a seat in either parliament. I am <lb/>
very much like the soldier at Inkerman, I am <lb/>
going into a soldier's battle, and I am willing <lb/>
to assist anybody but myself. I therefore <lb/>
may say explicitly that the statement in res<lb break="no"/>pect to the County of Queens was altogether <lb/>
unauthorized. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SECY</persName>.—Perhaps I should not <lb/>
have made the remark I did. I had, however, <lb/>
letters shewn me by the members who repre<lb break="no"/>sent Queens stating the fact that I mentioned, <lb/>
that overtures had been made to certain elec<lb break="no"/>tors in the interest of the hon. gentleman. I <lb/>
must say that I envy somewhat the position <lb/>
which the hon. member proposes to occupy. <lb/>
Those who engage in political life do so at a <lb/>
great personal sacrifice. So far as politicians <lb/>
are concerned, we who are laymen have not <lb/>
the gaol ahead of them that members of the <lb/>
Bar have. When they enter into these poli<lb break="no"/>tical struggles, they have before them a pros<lb break="no"/>pect of a time when they can leave public <lb/>
life and serve their country in an influential <lb/>
position. There is, however, no position more <lb/>
honorable or more important than that of a <lb/>
public servant. The public business must be <lb/>
done by some one ready to give up a consi<lb break="no"/>derable portion of his time for the sake of <lb/>
his country. In doing so, however, he must <lb/>
expect to sacrifice his personal comfort and <lb/>
private interest to no inconsiderable degree. <lb/>
There are many gentlemen in this Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture who could have acquired any reasonable <lb/>
amount of wealth—who could have enjoyed <lb/>
the greatest personal luxury and comfort, <lb/>
but they have forgone all that in order to <lb/>
give their services to their country. As this <lb/>
is the last occasion on which I shall be able to <lb/>
make any remarks on the floor of this Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture, I must say I feel a great deal is due not <lb/>
only to the kindness and courtesy of gentlemen <lb/>
on this side who have sustained me through<lb break="no"/>out my public career, but also to the courtesy <lb/>
and kindness of those who discharge the im<lb break="no"/>portant duties of an Opposition in the House <lb/>
since I have had the honor of a seat on the <lb/>
Government benches. I can say further that <lb/>
there is nothing that I regret more at the close <lb/>
of my career in this Legislature, than at anv <lb/>
time, in the heat of debate on Public matters, I <lb/>
should have forgotten what was due to the per<lb break="no"/>sonal feelings of gentlemen to whom I was op<lb break="no"/>posed, and should have used expressions <lb/>
which, in my calm and reflecting moments it <lb/>
would have pained me excessively to have ut<lb break="no"/>tered. I trust that the good feeling which has <lb/>
characterized this Legislature—and I have <lb/>
never seen a Session in which there was such <lb/>

<cb/>

a large amount of personal good feeling and <lb/>
less political asperity exhibited—will continue <lb/>
to animate gentlemen when we separate, and <lb/>
that all will leave animated by the most kind-<lb break="yes"/>lv sentiments for the prosperity of each other <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">MISCELLANEOUS.<lb/></p> 

<p>On motion of the Hon. Financial Secretary, <lb/>
seconded by Mr. Armand, each of the Clerks <lb/>
was voted an additional hundred dollars for <lb/>
their services during the Session, the number <lb/>
of bills passed having been unusually large. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACF1">Hon. Mr. MACFARLANE</persName> reported from a <lb/>
special committee to whom was referred the <lb/>
petition of Mr. J. Campbell, claiming to be the <lb/>
first discoverer of gold, that it had been found <lb/>
impossible to examine into the subject at the <lb/>
present session. <lb/></p> 

<p>It was suggested that the Commissioner of <lb/>
Mines should inquire into the subject during <lb/>
the recess, so as to be able to give the next <lb/>
House the necessary information. <lb/></p> 

<p>At three o'clock His Excellency came down <lb/>
and prorogued the House with the follow-<lb break="yes"/>Speech:— <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:italic">Mr. President, and Honorable Gentlemen of the <lb/>
Legislative Council: <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of <lb/>
Assembly: <lb/></p> 

<p>It affords me much pleasure to release you <lb/>
from further attendance during the present <lb/>
Session, which will doubtless be the last of the <lb/>
existing Parliament. <lb/></p> 

<p>The numerous and valuable measures which <lb/>
you have passed will, I doubt not, largely con<lb break="no"/>tribute te the prosperity of the Province. <lb/></p> 

<p>Under the operation of the laws effecting <lb/>
Constitutional changes in the Local Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and Parliament of Nova Scotia, the busi<lb break="no"/>ness of the country will,1 believe, be efficiently <lb/>
conducted at a large saving of public expen<lb break="no"/>diture. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of <lb/>
Assembly: <lb/></p> 

<p>I thank you for the supplies voted for the <lb/>
public service. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:italic">Mr. President, and Honorable Gentlemen of the <lb/>
Legislative Council: <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of <lb/>
Assembly:   <lb/></p> 

<p>I cannot close this Session without expres<lb break="no"/>sing the deep gratification with which I have <lb/>
witnessed the action of both Branches of the <lb/>
Legislature on the question of Union of the <lb/>
two Canadas, Nova Scotia and New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, under one Government and Parliament, <lb/>
as 1 firmly believe that your adoption of that <lb/>
measure will not only greatly increase the <lb/>
general prosperity of British America, and <lb/>
elevate all these Provinces in the scale of <lb/>
Nations, but that the Union was imporatively <lb/>
demanded, in order to give stability to the In<lb break="no"/>stitutions you enjoy, and permanent security <lb/>
to this portion of Her Majesty's dominions as <lb/>
an integral portion of the Empire. <lb/></p> 

<p>In the sincere hope that Almighty God will <lb/>
bless and prosper you all, and that the loyal <lb/>
people of this my native Province may be hap<lb break="no"/>py and prosperous, I now close this Session of <lb/>
the Legislature. <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>