<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1865-04-21"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-04-20">20 April 1865</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:YU1">Thomson Yu</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          
          
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Second Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1865"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          
          
          <biblScope unit="page" from="288" to="299"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_288.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_289.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_290.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_291.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_292.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_293.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_294.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_295.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_296.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_297.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_298.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_299.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-10-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="YuYom" when="2017-10-23">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_288">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_288.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_289">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_289.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_290">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_290.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_291">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_291.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_292">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_292.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_293">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_293.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_294">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_294.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_295">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_295.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_296">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_296.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_297">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_297.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_298">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_298.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_299">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_299.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="288" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_288.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">288</fw>
            <p> he said of them that they saved that
much. The <lb/>
Hon Finl. Sec. undertook to prove that the <lb/>
member for Colchester was wrong in his state- <lb break="maybe"/>
ment that a larger expenditure would be re- <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>
            <p> uired for the future, for the maintenance
of <lb/>
the railroads, than had been necessary<unclear n="Period should be deleted.">.</unclear> in
the <lb/>
past. Upon referring to the returns he found <lb/>
that the cost of maintenance had been steadily <lb/>
increasing year by year. He would be the <lb/>
last person to alarm people as to the state of <lb/>
the railroads, but every body knew that every <lb/>
year the roads necessarily became more worn <lb/>
out, and required repair. In 1861, the cost of <lb/>
maintenance amounted to $34,000;
in 1862, <lb/>
$37,000. In '63, $47,000, and in the nine months <lb/>
of 1864 $50,000. He did not
wish to detain the <lb/>
House much longer, but he would give them a <lb/>
few figures shewing what Cape Breton would <lb/>
have to pay towards the railway system <lb/>
of Nova Scotia. She would be required to <lb/>
pay one-fifth of the whole debt—or $128,000.
<lb/>
The hon. member for Halifax talked about <lb/>
mud roads as if they were of no consequence <lb/>
at all. If he represented a country constitu- <lb break="maybe"/>
ency he would find it a matter of a little more <lb/>
importance then he seemed to think it now. <lb/>
He is only willing to give us $100,000
for what <lb/>
he calls mud roads, but is perfectly ready to <lb/>
vote $556,000 a year for iron
roads. Now he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) would yield to no man, in his opinion <lb/>
as to the importance of railroads to a country, <lb/>
but if they were only to be obtained by sacrifi- <lb break="maybe"/>
cing the common roads which were of so much <lb/>
importance to the great mass of the people he <lb/>
would be inclined to pause,
before incurring <lb/>
any greater liability. At all events he could <lb/>
not see how any one could doubt the propriety <lb/>
of adopting the course proposed by the mem- <lb break="maybe"/>
ber for Colchester, to wait for a twelve month,<lb/>
and see how affairs looked then, we would <lb/>
then be able to ascertain how much the Pictou <lb/>
road was actually going to cost. At present that <lb/>
was uncertain. He had had a conversation <lb/>
with contractors who had been employed on <lb/>
the Truro road and they laughed at the idea of <lb/>
its being built for two millions of dollars. Un- <lb break="maybe"/>
der these circumstances as a member of the <lb/>
house, and a representative from Cape Breton <lb/>
he was not prepared to authorize the enormous <lb/>
expenditure contemplated by the resolution <lb/>
before the house and he should
vote against <lb/>
them. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> FRIDAY, April 21. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> The adjourned debate on
the <unclear n="Should be 'railway'">railwvy</unclear> reso-<lb break="maybe"/>
lution was resumed. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Hon. ATTY.
GEN. said—I do not intend to <lb/>
address the house at any very great length <lb/>
upon this question, but I cannot allow the ob- <lb break="maybe"/>
servations of the hon. leader of the opposition <lb/>
to pass unanswered. This is a
subject with <lb/>
which every gentleman in
this house is so well <lb/>
acquainted, that I think it is hardly necessary <lb/>
to direct attention back for the last eleven<lb/>
years in order to ascertain the policy of'
the <lb/>
house on the subject of
railways. The idea of <lb/>
building a railroad to Annapolis dates as far <lb/>
back as 1854, when the country was led to be- <lb break="maybe"/>
lieve that for a million of money they were <lb/>
going to have railway communication from <lb/>
Halifax to the Gulf of' St.Lawrence on the <lb/>
one hand, and the waters of the Bay of Fundy <lb/>
on the other. In fact, in
all
discussions upon <lb/>
the subject, the people were
educated up to <lb/>
the belief that for the
small amount I
have <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p> PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> named, the points referred to could be
reached.<lb/>
The experience of a few years, however, soon<lb/>
dissipated that idea; and although the
policy<lb/>
has partially failed for want of
means, yet the<lb/>
house remained pledged to carry on these im-<lb break="maybe"/>
portant works so soon as the finances of the <lb/>
country would admit.  It was, therefore, no <lb/>
new policy that the government introduced <lb/>
last year, but one that was initiated and ap-<lb break="maybe"/>
proved of years ago.  Such. then, being the <lb/>
case, it is not for us now to consider the cor- <lb break="maybe"/>
rectness or incorrectness of the idea.  The <lb/>
country at that time was divided upon the <lb/>
question of building railways.  Some
thought
<lb/>
it inadvisable to embark in the enterprise at <lb/>
all; some were in favor of
their being built by <lb/>
government; whilst others—and they
formed a
<lb/>
large section of this house and
of the country <lb/>
—were in favor of their
construction by private <lb/>
companies under legislative subventions. <lb/>
Those who were opposed altogether to rail- <lb break="maybe"/>
roads formed but a small class in the country, <lb/>
and I am happy to find that one of the repre- <lb break="maybe"/>
sentatives of that section has at length given <lb/>
in his adhesion to the system, and approves of <lb/>
their construction under the policy first inau-<lb break="maybe"/>
gurated.  As to whether that is
the best sys- <lb break="maybe"/>
tem or not it is unnecessary to advert in the <lb/>
present discussion; that question was settled <lb/>
last year, and nothing has since occurred to <lb/>
alter the position of affairs.  The only point, <lb/>
then, that now arises for consideration is the <lb/>
question as to whether the finances of the pro- <lb break="maybe"/>
vince are in a condition to warrant the con- <lb break="maybe"/>
struction of these works in the modified form <lb/>
proposed by the resolution now
before the <lb/>
house. </p>
            <p>There are many considerations to be thought
<lb/>
of in connection with this subject, but
the pa- <lb break="maybe"/>
ramount one is to keep up the
credit of the <lb/>
country and to maintain mviolate the
good
<lb/>
faith of the province.  If we can do this, then <lb/>
I think we are warranted in going on with <lb/>
these works.  In the consideration of this ques- <lb break="maybe"/>
tion I intend principally to refer to the opposi- <lb break="maybe"/>
tion given to it by the hon.
member for South <lb/>
Colchester (Mr. Archibald) and to the course <lb/>
he has thought proper to pursue; and I cannot <lb/>
avoid saying that the position taken by
that
<lb/>
hon. gentleman, in regard to one or two other <lb/>
important subjects to which he had been pre- <lb break="maybe"/>
viously committed, has rather astonished me. <lb/>
In regard to the School Bill, for instance, no <lb/>
one was more thoroughly committed to that <lb/>
measure by his action
last
session than the <lb/>
hon. gentleman; in fact, he
went even further <lb/>
than the views of the government on the sub-
<lb break="maybe"/>
uject; while this year he has
adopted a policy <lb/>
totally inconsistent with the
course he then <lb/>
pursued.  I think that hon. gentleman ought <lb/>
to have more regard for the position he occu- <lb break="maybe"/>
ies as leader of the opposition than to come <lb/>
here, as he did yesterday, and, in
relation to <lb/>
this question, admit that he
had made such <lb/>
gross mistakes in his
calculations; and my <lb/>
hon. friend the Financial Secretary was quite <lb/>
justified in the remark that it was highly cul-<lb break="maybe"/>
pable in one occupying his position
to found <lb/>
arguments upon a subject to which he confess- <lb break="maybe"/>
ed he had not given that consideration
which <lb/>
its importance demanded.  He has given evi- <lb break="maybe"/>
dence upon other occasions, of
his power to<lb/>
sift and analyze financial statements; and<lb/>
there is no doubt that, if he
had had the incli-<lb break="maybe"/>
nation, he was quite competent to ascertain,<lb/>
what amount the government had in hand at
<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="289" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_289.jpg"/>
            <p>
     the end of last year;  In charging the govern- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment with falsifying the public accounts, he 
     <lb/>
    evidently tried very hard to manufacture a 
     <lb/>mountain out of a molehill. He knew very 
     <lb/>well, or ought to have known, that in the sum 
     <lb/>represented as being in the treasury at the end 
     <lb/>of the year there was not included the amount 
     <lb/>due by parties holding province notes, and 
     <lb/>those indebted to the savings' bank, amounting 
     <lb/>to over $80,000. There was no mystery about 
     <lb/>the matter. lf he had given proper attention 
     <lb/>to the subject, he would have seen that the 
     <lb/>statements he made were grossley inaccurate, 
     <lb/>and with the evidence before him, it is perfect- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ly inexplicable to me how he could have done 
     <lb/>so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     I have taken a few notes of his speech, and 
     <lb/>
     shall endeavour to point out the inaccuracies 
     <lb/>
     with which it abounds. In the first place he 
     <lb/>
     assumed that it would be necessary to provide 
     <lb/>
     for one-half of the whole cost of the Pictou 
     <lb/>
     railroad this year. Now we have provided 
     <lb/>
     $30,000 for interest this year, which is about 
     <lb/>
     one-third of the interest of the whole sum re- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     quired, while it is calculated that not more 
     <lb/>
     than a fourth will be wanted, and therefore 
     <lb/>
     that little over a fourth of the whole cost will 
     <lb/>
     be required this year. Then, again, the leader 
     <lb/>
     of the Opposition has undertaken to state that 
     <lb/>
     the St. Peter's Canal will cost at least $200,000. 
     <lb/>
     I am at a loss to know where he got the data 
     <lb/>
     for his calculations, or whether he is more 
     <lb/>
     qualified to judge than those who were employ- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ed for that purpose; but all I can say is that he 
     <lb/>
     differs widely from the engineer who was em- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ployed to survey it, and whose report is upon 
     <lb/>
     the table, showing the estimated cost to be at 
     <lb/>
     the farthest $170,000 that the specification 
     <lb/>
     requiring only $130,000 is the one adopted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. gentleman also referred to other 
     <lb/>
     public works, and put down the interest on the 
     <lb/>
    Pictou road at $150,000, the Moncton road at  
     <lb/>$144,000, and strange to say, although he had 
     <lb/>the same reasons for exaggeration as regards 
     <lb/>the Annapolis railroad, he had put the interest 
     <lb/>for that line down at $5,000 less that it really 
     <lb/>would be accordong to the proposals on the 
     <lb/>table. In order then to raise the amount he 
     <lb/>puts down the interest on the St. Peter's Canal,  
     <lb/>at $12,000. He has, therefore, made a mistake 
     <lb/>in his calculations of $30,000 a year in the  in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>terest on the Pictou road, and $22,000 on the 
     <lb/>Moncton road.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
    

            <p>
     Now, however much we may be inclined to 
     <lb/>
     give the hon. gentlemen credit for skill as a 
     <lb/>
     financier in the case of the  St. Peter's Canal,  
     <lb/>
    he can hardly be imagined to know more than 
     <lb/>the Engineer who bored every rod, and made<lb/>his calculations from actual experiments. We<lb/> are driven, therefore, to the conclusion that the  
     <lb/> hon. gentleman founded a great many of his 
     <lb/>assertions upon mere assumption, without the<lb/>slightest particle of proof. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The hon. gentleman, amongst other things,  
     <lb/>alluded to the Shubenacadie Canal, and seems<lb/>to have based his calculations as to the cost of<lb/>St. Peter's upon the expenditure incurred upon<lb/>that work. Now, we all know the history of<lb/>that unfortunate canal, and the causes of its<lb/>failure, but I am at a loss to perceive how any<lb/>comparisons can be instituted between a work<lb/>of such magnitude as that, and a canal of half<lb/>a mile long. And so with the Welland Canal.<lb/>Is it well known that the reason why that cost<lb/>so much was because it was turned into a ship<lb/>canal, instead of a boat canal, as at first intended. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The hon. leader of the opposition made ano- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ther singular statement to which I shall allude<lb/>for a moment. He said that the issue of deben-<lb break="maybe"/>tures for the construction of the road to Monc-<lb break="maybe"/>ton would depreciate the value of those already<lb/>issued. How this can be I am at a loss to ima-<lb break="maybe"/>gine. We all know that the debentures that<lb/>are already sold have the first claim upon the<lb/>revenues of the Province and take precedence<lb/>over all others. How, then, can they be affect-<lb break="maybe"/>ed by those subsequently issued? He knows<lb/>very well that a second mortgage does not take<lb/>priority over the first.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     The hon. gentleman said that in New Bruns- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     wick western extension received the most fa- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     vor, and that no provision would be made to 
     <lb/>
     build their line to the borders. I tell him that 
     <lb/>
     the line to the borders has been secured, and 
     <lb/>
     that an undertaking has been entered into be- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tween the Government of New Brunswick and 
     <lb/>
     contractors to build their portion of the line, so 
     <lb/>
     soon as Nova Scotia makes arrangements to 
     <lb/>
     connect with it. I take it for granted the in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     coming Government will not repudiate the 
     <lb/>
     agreement of their predecessors.      
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>The hon. gentlemen  charged the Govern- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ment with withholding Mr. Livesey's offer  
     <lb/>made in November, because they had an elec-  
     <lb break="maybe"/>tion to run in the West.  I tell him that when 
     <lb/>the Government got the House to adopt this 
     <lb/>policy last year they- intended to carry it out 
     <lb/>in good faith. They felt it their duty then, 
     <lb/>as they feel it now, to get the road to An-<lb break="maybe"/>napolis built upon the best terms they could.<lb/>They have never failed to do their duty to the<lb/>West, whenever the opportunity offered, and it<lb/>is with that view that the present resolutions<lb/>have been introduced. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The hon. member for Colchester drew a fear-<lb break="maybe"/>ful picture of the ruin that was going to over-<lb break="maybe"/>whelm the country. He said that the price of <lb/>goods was going to fall to such an extent as to<lb/>reduce the revenue and diminish our resources.<lb/>Now, sir, I do not agree with him at all. I do<lb/>not think that the fall in the price of cottons is<lb/>going to have so much effect upon the revenue.<lb/>For several years past the price of this article<lb/>has been so great, that the majority of the peo-<lb break="maybe"/>ple were beginning to dispense with its use, <lb/>and to substitute other articles for it, so that<lb/>the consumption of cotton goods has not been<lb/>so great of late years as formerly. I hold,<lb/>therefore, that if the price of cotton does fall,<lb/>that from the increased quantity that will be<lb/>imported, the amount of duties, instead of de-<lb break="maybe"/>creasing, will increase for the first year or two.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The question to be considered, however, is<lb/>not so much as to the revenue of this year as<lb/>to how these considerations would affect us in<lb/>two years' time when this liability will accrue.<lb/>It is our duty, then, to take a more expansive<lb/>view of the subject, and endeavor, as far as<lb/>possible, to ascertain what position we would<lb/>be in, in a few years' time. If we contrast our<lb/>present position with that of a few years back<lb/>we have every reason to be encouraged - our<lb/>revenues have trebled since the railway sys-<lb break="maybe"/>tem has been commenced, and there is every<lb/>reason to believe that with increased facilities<lb/>in that respect the will continue to increase<lb/>in a large ratio.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A few years ago gold was discovered in this<lb/>Province, and, as was the case in most coun-<lb break="maybe"/>tries, it proved a bad speculation to most of<lb/>those who rashly entered into it. But of late<lb/>the position of affairs has changed; a number<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="290" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_290.jpg"/>
            <p>
     of capitalists have come into the country, and 
     <lb/>
     by the application of science, and skill, and 
     <lb/>
     means, very (different results have been produ- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ced. Then, again, look at our coal mining in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     terests, and the large amount of capital recent- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ly brought into the country to develop this im- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     portant branch of industry. Everything in 
     <lb/>
     the way of capital brought into a country helps 
     <lb/>
     the agricultural and laboring classes and in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     creases the general prosperity, and conse- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     quently increases the revenue.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But it is said that a commercial crisis is go- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ing to take place in the United States, and that 
     <lb/>
     the business of this country is in an unsettled 
     <lb/>
     state. If a crisis does arrive (and I see no rea- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     son to anticipate it,) we, at all events will be 
     <lb/>
     in a better position to meet it than a country 
     <lb/>
     like the United States, overhead and ears in 
     <lb/>
     debt. But I see no necessity for indulging in 
     <lb/>
     such a gloomy view of affairs. Looking at the 
     <lb/>
     increasing prosperity of the country, arising 
     <lb/>
     from the causes to which I have referred, I 
     <lb/>
     think there can be no doubt that we can afford 
     <lb/>
     to provide $313,000 for railway interest, without 
     <lb/>
     interfering with the ordinary services of the 
     <lb/>
     country. The hon. member for Colchester 
     <lb/>
     seemed to doubt whether the expenditure of 
     <lb/>
     money for railway purposes was of any benefit 
     <lb/>
     to a country. . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      Mr. ARCHIBALD—I did not say that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. ATTY. GEN—I do not wish to misrepre- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sent the hon. gentleman, but he certainly said 
     <lb/>
     it was not calculated to increase the revenue. 
     <lb/>
     I ask him whether he was serious? Does he 
     <lb/>
     not know that the increased labor which the 
     <lb/>
     construction of these public works brings into a 
     <lb/>
     country necessitates the consumption of a lar- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ger quantity of articles upon which duty is le- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     vied—that in proportion to the number of the 
     <lb/>
     non-producing class will be the increased cen- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sumption of goods, and consequent increase of 
     <lb/>
     revenue. I hold, then, that the various enter- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     prises now going on in this country are going 
     <lb/>
     largely to increase the importation of dutiable 
     <lb/>
     goods. Smuggling from the United States will 
     <lb/>
     be rendered impossible in consequence of the 
     <lb/>
     high rate of duties which will be kept upon 
     <lb/>
     goods in that country, and the trade will be 
     <lb/>
     largely with Europe for years to come, and the 
     <lb/>
      chances of smuggling in that proportion dimi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nished. I, therefore, come to the conclusion 
     <lb/>
     that there is not the slightest grounds for the 
     <lb/>
     danger apprehended by the hon. leader of the 
     <lb/>
     Opposition as to the falling off of the revenue. 
     <lb/>
     He endeavored to show that we could not ex- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
    ect any beneficial effect upon our revenues 
     <lb/>from the construction of railroads, because du- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ring the years that the present lines were in 
     <lb/>course of construction no sensible increase was 
     <lb/>produced. But that is not a fair comparison.<lb/>From 1855 to 1858 but a small section of the 
     <lb/>road was open—only about 9 miles—and it 
     <lb/>could not be expected that any advantages 
     <lb/>would be felt until the system had had a fair 
     <lb/>trial, and the people had begun to appreciate 
     <lb/>the convenience and benefits of railroad com- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>munication; still I contend that the expendi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ture of the money itself had a beneficial effect 
     <lb/>upon the revenues of these years.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The hon. leader of the Opposition endeavor- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ed to give as unfavorable an account as he pos— 
     <lb/>sibly could of the present condition of our rail- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>roads, and tried to make us believe that they 
     <lb/>were nearly worn out. It is true that some 
     <lb/>portions of the road have worn, but they have 
     <lb/>been renewed, and are as good as new, and, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     with some trifling exceptions, it is in as good 
     <lb/>
     a condition as it ever was. And I have good, 
     <lb/>
     authority for saying that it is likely to last for 
     <lb/>
     eight years more with but little expense beyond 
     <lb/>
     a little ordinary wear and tear. The most of 
     <lb/>
     expense incurred for the last few years has 
     <lb/>
     been for fencing and renewing sleepers—the 
     <lb/>
     rails and chairs are as good as ever, and will 
     <lb/>
     last for years longer, and the rolling stock has 
     <lb/>
     been completely renovated. I think, then, that 
     <lb/>
     the facts will not bear out the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     in the gloomy picture he has drawn.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The next thing he endeavored to do was to 
     <lb/>
     show that the revenue for this year would pro- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     bably fall short of that of last year by 200,000 
     <lb/>
     dollars. I ask him upon what foundation he 
     <lb/>
     rests his statement? If that be true, then the 
     <lb/>
     estimate laid upon the table by the Financial 
     <lb/>
     Secretary is erroneous, and ought not to have 
     <lb/>
     been adopted by the house. He begun by 
     <lb/>
     stating that the December quarter of 1864 was 
     <lb/>
     short by 63,000 dollars of the corresponding 
     <lb/>
    quarter of 1863, and he stated that that was 
     <lb/>the largest quarter of the year.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     I find upon referring to the returns that the 
     <lb/>
     amount received in that quarter of 1863 was 
     <lb/>
     $303,123 and in 1864 $413,164. I do not know 
     <lb/>
     how he undertakes to make his calculations, if 
     <lb/>
     not by comparing one quarter with another. If 
     <lb/>
     he takes one month of one year and compares 
     <lb/>
    it with that of another, that is not the fair way 
     <lb/>of treating the subject, as the arrival of the 
     <lb/>fall or spring stocks maybe thrown into one 
     <lb/>month or another, or even into a different 
     <lb/>quarter by the accident of a few days in the 
     <lb/>date of arrival. Now sir I shall endeavour to 
     <lb/>shew that instead of their being any probabil-  
     <lb break="maybe"/>ity of a. falling off in 1865 there is every  pros- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>pect of an increase. The December quarter 
     <lb/>which belongs to this year has produced $413,- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>164, and the March quarter $129,820 making 
     <lb/>for the first half of 1865 $542,936. From 
     <lb/>that date we may fairly assume that  
     <lb/>the July and September quarters will not 
     <lb/>fall short sufficient to absorb the large surplus  
     <lb/>for the two past quarters. What ground then 
     <lb/>I ask has the hon. gentleman for assuming 
     <lb/>that there will be a decrease of  $200,000, when 
     <lb/>the two first quarters show an increase of $123,- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>793, and more than this I have the best reason 
     <lb/>for knowing that the month of April this year 
     <lb/>will show a surplus of $20,000 over that of last. 
     <lb/>Now then let anyone compare the statement 
     <lb/>of both of us, and see where the facts would 
     <lb/>place the decision . I shall now call the atten- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tion of the house for a moment to a financial 
     <lb/>statement I hold in my hand, and which I 
     <lb/>think will convince any one that we are in a  
     <lb/>good condition to undertake the construction 
     <lb/>of these works. It is well known that the road 
     <lb/>grant this  year is unusually large-$264,000- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>while the largest regular appropriation ever be-   
     <lb break="maybe"/>fore made for that service was $160,000. We 
     <lb/>can then take this $104,000 of extra grant, and 
     <lb/>still appropriate the largest sum ever given in  
     <lb/>any previous year towards the ordinary road  
     <lb/>and bridge servies of the country. We can 
     <lb/>give the usual grant for navigation securities 
     <lb/>—we can provide for the St. Peters Canal, and  
     <lb/>the extension of the Lunatic Asylum, as well 
     <lb/>as all the other public services, including the 
     <lb/>largely increased School grant, and we can 
     <lb/>provide for the railways also.     
     <lb/>Takin then the Extra Road Grant this year-$140,000     
     <lb/>Add Extra Grant this year for Navigation  
     <lb/>Securities................................................................. 39,000 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="291" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_291.jpg"/>
            <p>
      Add Interest  of Pictou Railway provided  
     <lb/>
      for in the Estimate...........................................80,000  
     <lb/>
      Add for increase of Revenue for the present  
     <lb/>Lines...................................................................150,000<lb/>
    Add increase of Casual Revenue….............50,000      
     <lb/>"     increase of General Revenue three year <lb/>  hence $60,000, average annual increase...180,000<lb/>And we have a total of                                $543,000<lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
            <p>
      Which we may reasonably calculate to have      
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     of increase of means to meet the liabilities for 
     <lb/>
     the Pictou Branch and the two lines now un- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     der consideration.   The hon. leader of the op- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     position said that the net revenue of the rail- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ways for 1863 was $22,000, and that of 1864 only 
     <lb/>
     $1,000 more and he argued from that that we 
     <lb/>
     could not expect a larger increase. His state- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment only included three quarters of the past 
     <lb/>
     year and I have reason to know that the nett 
     <lb/>
     revenue will come up to $35,000 this year in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     stead of $28,000 as stated by him. I have also 
     <lb/>
     abundant evidence to prove that the sum of 
     <lb/>
     $15,000 was expended in repairs last year 
     <lb/>
     which might more properly have been done 
     <lb/>
     this year, so that the cost of maintenance this 
     <lb/>
     year will be lessened bythat amount. Then 
     <lb/>
     again when we consider the increased accom- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     modation that will be afforded to the travelling 
     <lb/>
     public by the construction of these two ad- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ditional  lines, and the increased traffic that 
     <lb/>
     will result, I think we have every reason to 
     <lb/>
     anticipate in three years hence a revenue of 
     <lb/>
     $150,000 as against the interest we will be then 
     <lb/>
     first called upon to pay. Then as regards the 
     <lb/>
     casual revenue, I think in view of the exten- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sive mining operations in Cape Breton and 
     <lb/>
     elsewhere, I am largely within bounds in put- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ting down an increase of $50,000 and double 
     <lb/>
     that sum would he nearer the true estimate. 
     <lb/>
     Now, sir, I have endeavoured to give the reason 
     <lb/>
     'why I anticipate an increaseof the revenue, 
     <lb/>
     and to show that the gloomy forebodings of the 
     <lb/>
     hon. leader of the opposition are totally un- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     founded. But I shall refer him to the finan- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     cial statement of his own finance minister (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Annand) and show that they are directly at 
     <lb/>
     issue. [Mr. H. here read in corroboration of 
     <lb/>
     his statement.]      
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I shall also read an extract from the speech 
     <lb/>
     of that same hon. gentleman upon a  different 
     <lb/>
     subject, (Confederation,) and although I may 
     <lb/>
     not approve of the object for which  the calcu- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     lations were used, it matters not if  the figures 
     <lb/>
     are correct. Mr. Annand, in his speech at 
     <lb/>
     Temperance Hall, went into calculations to 
     <lb/>
     prove that we were able to build all the Rail- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ways in question without any additional taxa- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tion. After referring to statements of Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Jones, proving the same position, he says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The present total Provincial expenditure under 
     <lb/>
     the estimate of 1864, including interest, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Amounts to.............................................................$1,222,355 
     <lb/>
     Supplementary Estimate..............................................5,811 
     <lb/>Pictou Railway...........................................................120,000<lb/>Subsidy to Annapolis Railway, 60 miles, £6-<lb break="maybe"/>  000 per mile, at 4 per cent., 20 years..............86,800<lb/>Subsidy to Railway from Truro to N.B. Fron-<lb break="maybe"/>  tier, 70 miles, £10,000 per mile at 4 per<lb/>cent. 20 years............................................................112,000<lb/>$1,546,566<lb/>Add for Militia.......................................................78,000<lb/>$1,624,000<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Revenue for 1854, per Esti- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>mate........................................$180,000<lb/>Gain on Gold fields in 1864...15,000<lb/>" Casual Revenue, 1864..........10,000<lb/>" Custom and Excise, 1864..150,000<lb/>$1,355,000   1,355,000<lb/>Deficiency..........$269,566<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
    

            <p>
     It will be perceived, then, that under our present 
     <lb/>
     tariff which is by far the lowest in America, at the 
     <lb/>
     end of the present year the revenue would be suffici- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ent  to pay the interest on the Pictou the Annapolis 
     <lb/>and the lntercolonial railway  provide for every pub- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>lic service as liberally as in 1864 , leaving a deficiency 
     <lb/>of only $269,566 to be provided for—[cheers]. This 
     <lb/>too, is assuming that these railways were all now con- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>structed and the entire interest on the outlay pay- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>able from the treasury. We have now in hand a sum 
     <lb/>of money  sufficient to pay the entire interest on the 
     <lb/>cost, of the Pictou Railway, as well as $55,000 additi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>onal,  and this derived from the increase of revenue 
     <lb/>in 1864 alone—[cheers.] But as these railways cannot 
     <lb/>possibly be all constructed in less than three years 
     <lb/>from this date, let us see how we would stand at that 
     <lb/>period. I find upon  examination of the amount of 
     <lb/>revenue collected in an average of five years, from 
     <lb/>1858 to 1863, that the mean increase yearly on the to- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tal revenue was $166,369! and that on the 10 per cent 
     <lb/>advalorem duties alone the average  increase was dur- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ing those five years $68,013—[cheers.] Now, sir, I 
     <lb/>might take the average of the total revenue, commen- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>cing on the 1st of January, 1865, for the next three 
     <lb/>years, at $166,369 a year; but as our revenue may fluc- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tuate, I take the increase at the very moderate aver- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>age of" $60,000, and find that in three years the in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>crease would amount to $180,000; add increased earn- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ings of present railways, $75,000, and we have $255,- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>000 to meet a deficiency of $269,566; and this result, 
     <lb/>this startling and astonishing result, may be attained, 
     <lb/>let it be recollected and understood, without the im- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>position of one farthing additional taxation—[loud 
     <lb/>and protracted cheering.]       
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Now, sir, l have given my own figures as to 
     <lb/>the amount of liability we are going to assume 
     <lb/>under the resolutions before the house; and I 
     <lb/>have given the calculations of the late Fin. 
     <lb/>Sec'y (Mr. Annand,) who puts the gross amount 
     <lb/>as the interest of the lines from Truro to Pictou, 
     <lb/>and New Brunswick and the line to Annapo- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>lis down at $313,000 a your, and I have  endea- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>voured to show, by a fair estimate of our pro-  
     <lb break="maybe"/>bable increased revenue in three years hence, 
     <lb/>amounting to $543,000, that that liability is with- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>in the compass of our resources, and will not 
     <lb/>infringe  unnecessarily upon any ordinary 
     <lb/>public service.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> This no doubt is an important question and 
     <lb/>it is the duty of every one to give it  an atten- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tive consideration. I have endeavoured to 
     <lb/>deal with it to the best of my judgment, and if I 
     <lb/>have made any mistakes in my calculations I 
     <lb/>am ready to correct them if any one can detect 
     <lb/>them. I think that this question ought not to 
     <lb/>be postponed any longer; it is of the utmost 
     <lb/>importance to this country that we should con- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>nect our Railway system with that of New 
     <lb/>Brunswick, and thus be brought into connec- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tion with the United States and Canada. By 
     <lb/>this route we could go to Montreal as  quickly 
     <lb/>as  by the Intercolonial Railway, the only  dif- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ference being that in the one case, we would 
     <lb/>travel wholly through our own territory; with 
     <lb/>this   connection  complete  the  great object 
     <lb/>would be attained of making Halifax the near- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>est stopping place for all steamers from Europe. 
     <lb/>Passengers for Canada and the United States, 
     <lb/>after a long sea voyage would prefer taking rail 
     <lb/>for their various destinations, rather than em- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>bark again  by steamer. Besides all this we 
     <lb/>must consider the immense amount of traffic 
     <lb/>which would be brought from  Prince Edward 
     <lb/>Island; Cape Breton, and the Eastern Counties; 
     <lb/>and also from Cumberland and the neigbour- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ing Province.  Then again the Annapolis road 
     <lb/>will be the means of  diverting trade which  
     <lb/>now finds its outlet at St. J ohn, and  will open 
     <lb/>up all the rich agricultural counties  between  
     <lb/>Windsor and Annapolis. The hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>concluded by alluding to the  advantages  de- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>
            <pb n="292" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_292.jpg"/>
            <p>
     292 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p> rived from railway extension, as a means of 
     <lb/> bringing the people into closer communication 
     <lb/> with, each other, and of liberalizing their minds 
     <lb/> by intercourse with the people of other coun- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tries.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. LONGLEY said that at that hour of the 
     <lb/>
     evening, and at that late period of the session, 
     <lb/>
     he supposed gentlemen would prefer going to 
     <lb/>their homes rather than listen to anything he 
     <lb/> might have to say; but he felt that he would 
     <lb/> not be doing justice to his own feelings and to 
     <lb/>the position he occupied, if he failed to make a 
     <lb/> few observations upon the subject under dis- 
     <lb break="maybe"/> cussion. The desirability of extending railway 
     <lb/> communication east and west had always been 
     <lb/>admitted, and it was only a question of time as 
     <lb/> to when it should be undertaken. He had 
     <lb/> turned his attention to the subject, and he was 
     <lb/> prepared to show that the country was in a 
     <lb/>better position at present to undertake railway 
     <lb/>extension to both the New Brunswick border 
     <lb/>and Annapolis, than she was in 1855, when the 
     <lb/> railway system was inaugurated. At that 
     <lb/>time the entire revenue did not exceed £130,000, 
     <lb/>while last year it was £330,000. If any gentle- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>man would take the trouble to make the calcu- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>lation, he would see that we are in a better po- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>sition to pay the interest upon the cost of the 
     <lb/>whole undertaking contemplated by the reso- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>lution before the house. than we were to pay 
     <lb/>£60,000 a year in 1855. He had the figures be- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>fore him, the accuracy of which could not be 
     <lb/>disputed, and to which he would shortly refer. 
     <lb/> He estimated the revenue in 1855 to have been 
     <lb/>£130,000, and the amount of railway debt then 
     <lb/>incurred at £60,000 a year. Now it did not re- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>quire much argument to prove that we could 
     <lb/> better afford to pay £150,000 with our present 
     <lb/>revenue, than £60,000 with the revenue of 1855. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> What would be the amount of our liability 
     <lb/>after the whole works had been constructed? 
     <lb/>He put down the cost of the Pictou extension 
     <lb/>at £30,000 a year; the extension to the borders 
     <lb/>of New Brunswick as £30,000 more; the road 
     <lb/>to Annapolis at £22,000—£142,000 a year in all, 
     <lb/>including £60,000 which we now pay, or £11,000 
     <lb/>a year less in proportion as compared by the 
     <lb/>burden borne by the revenue of 1855. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     There were various other considerations that 
     <lb/>
     should not be lost sight of in the discussion of 
     <lb/>
     this question. There were various incidental 
     <lb/>
     advantages which the country derived from 
     <lb/>
     the construction of railroads which could not 
     <lb/>
     be estimated in figures—such as the stimulus 
     <lb/>
     given to trade, an the development of our re- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sources induced by the increased facilities those 
     <lb/>
     works afforded. But without referring more 
     <lb/>
     particularly to these at present, he would en- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     deavor to show how the amount of annual in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     terest the Province would have to pay was go- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ing to be gradually reduced by the earnings of 
     <lb/>
     the road.      
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p> He estimated the nett revenue of the road 
     <lb/>this year at, $12,000, that deducted from the 
     <lb/>whole liability would leave £130,000 annual in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>terest to be paid. When the Pictou line was 
     <lb/>opened, of course the paying qualities of the 
     <lb/>road between Truro and Halifax would be pro- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>portionately increased, and he thought that he 
     <lb/>would be safe in putting  that down at 2 per 
     <lb/>cent. in addition to present receipts, or £12,000 
     <lb/>more, reducing interest to £118,000. Then he 
     <lb/>assumed that the tenth section of: the Pictou 
     <lb/>line -between Fisher's  Grant and the coal 
     <lb/>fields would not be in operation a single year 
     <lb/>without Paying working expenses and 6 per 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     cent interest besides; That reduces the entire 
     <lb/>
     amount of interest to £112,000 a year. He cal- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     culated that when the entire lines were comple- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ted, at the expiration of five years, they would 
     <lb/>
     pay at least three per cent. over and above 
     <lb/>
     working expenses. These calculations have 
     <lb/>
     reference to construction of the whole by Go- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     vernment. It must not be forgotten that in 
     <lb/>
     proportion as the lines were extended so would 
     <lb/>
     the traffic increase with very little additional 
     <lb/>
     cost. The annual interest will then be reduced 
     <lb/>
     in five years after the whole railway system 
     <lb/>
     has been completed to £71,000, or only about 
     <lb/>
     £10,000 a year more than the present liability. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. member for Halifax alluded to the 
     <lb/>
     indirect advantages which a country derives 
     <lb/>
     from railroads. He (Mr. L.) had taken pains 
     <lb/>
     to make some calculations on that point, and 
     <lb/>
     he thought that they would be borne out by the 
     <lb/>
     facts.      
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The net receipts from the railroads last year 
     <lb/>
     amounted to nearly £9,000. He would pause 
     <lb/>
     for a moment, to contrast the position of rail- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     way matters in New Brunswick with these pf 
     <lb/>
     this country. That Province, with a' popula- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tion much less than ours, owes about a million 
     <lb/>
     of dollars more than we do; and then it should 
     <lb/>
     not be forgotten that her tariff is 15 1/2 per cent, 
     <lb/>
     while ours is only 10—being a difference of 
     <lb/>
     more than 50 per cent. The receipts from their 
     <lb/>
     road, he regretted to say, had fallen off this 
     <lb/>
     year; while our passenger traffic had increased 
     <lb/>
     13,000, with corresponding receipts in traffic 
     <lb/>
     department; and there was every reason to 
     <lb/>
     anticipate a larger revenue this year, from the 
     <lb/>
     increased mining operations in Cape Breton 
     <lb/>
     and other parts of the Province. He would 
     <lb/>
     turn for a moment to some calculations he had 
     <lb/>
     made, based upon the working of the road in 
     <lb/>
     1863, and he thought that they would hear the 
     <lb/>
    strictest scrutiny. He found in that year that 
     <lb/>110,137 persons had been carried over the road, 
     <lb/>and most of these from extreme points, so that 
     <lb/>he would be safe in putting down the time and 
     <lb/>cost of travel saved to these persons at a dol- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>lar a head;    
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     That would amount to '  $110,137 
     <lb/>
     There was carried over the road 56,471    
     <lb/>
     tons of freight, saving per ton, $2, 112,942 
     <lb/>
    9,640 horses, at a saving of $1 each, 9,640 
     <lb/>5,462 head of horned cattle, at a saving   
     <lb/>of $1.50 each,  8,193 
     <lb/>19,970 sheep and lambs, at a saving of    
     <lb/>20 cents each,      3,994 
     <lb/>2,309 calves and pigs, at a saving of    
     <lb/>30 cents each.   0,692 
     <lb/>        $245,598 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Gain by rendering valuable what would, ' 
     <lb/>be otherwise useless,      40,000 
     <lb/>   £71,399, or $285,598 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Making the indirect gain of £10,000        
     <lb/>more than the interest now paid.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> In making these statements he knew that he 
     <lb/>should be met by his opponents with the taunt 
     <lb/>that all this was very different from the views 
     <lb/>and opinions he formerly held. He was pre- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>pared to admit that his views on this sub ect 
     <lb/>had undergone some change.  He thought then 
     <lb/>that it was a serious undertaking to pledge the 
     <lb/>revenues of the Province to the extent of £60,- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>000 a year; but now, as we had become involv- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ed in these great public works, it was to the 
     <lb/>interests of the people to go on steadily in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>creasing them east and west. until the system 
     <lb/>had become perfected and placed in a position 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="293" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_293.jpg"/>
            <p>
     to be remunerative. That must be done, either 
     <lb/>
     by the Government or by the aid of capitalists 
     <lb/>
     from abroad.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It' seemed to him now as it did last winter, 
     <lb/>
     'that' if we could secure the extension of the 
     <lb/>
     road to Annapolis by an annual subvention of 
     <lb/>
    but little more than £20,000, it would be to the   
     <lb/> interest of the Province to do so. He thought 
     <lb/>that the west was fairly entitled to this consi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>deration. The members for that section of the 
     <lb/>Province had always aided the Eastern mem- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>bers in their public works, and he had no hesi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tation in saying that the vote given by them 
     <lb/>last session for the Pictou railroad had not re- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ceived that consideration it deserved. He 
     <lb/>thought that the true policy had been adopted, 
     <lb/>then of securing the trade of Prince Edward 
     <lb/>Island and the eastern part of the Province. 
     <lb/>For the same reasons as to means of making 
     <lb/>the roads more remunerative, he justified the 
     <lb/>present extension, and he thought he had 
     <lb/>shewn by figures that challenged investiga- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tion, that it was clearly within our means to go 
     <lb/>on with these works. The hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>then alluded to the great saving in the way of 
     <lb/>time and freight which this road would afford 
     <lb/>to the farmers or the west. Now, by the pre- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>"sent road it cost $1,20 a hundred weight  for 
     <lb/>truckage from Windsor to Annapolis, whereas 
     <lb/>it could be taken by rail for 25c., thus saving 
     <lb/>$19 a ton, and there was also time saved, as he 
     <lb/>had shewn, so that in every shape the question 
     <lb/>was viewed, whether as regards the direct or 
     <lb/>indirect advantages, it must be looked upon as 
     <lb/>a great boon to the country.  He had made a 
     <lb/>few calculations of the position of railway af- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>fairs in other countries.  He found that the 
     <lb/>State of Massachusetts, with a. population of 
     <lb/>about 1 ,400 ,000, had about the same number of 
     <lb/>miles of railway, or about a mile to every 1000 
     <lb/>of population, and their railway debt is about 
     <lb/>$55 per head, while ours, estimating our popu- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>lation at 250,000, does not exceed $18 per head, 
     <lb/>or about one-third as much in proportion as 
     <lb/>Massachusetts. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     I have made a few estimates of the probable 
     <lb/>
     cost and advantages of the Annapolis railway: 
     <lb/>
     Cost of railway to Annapolis, 30 miles, at £6000 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     permile........................................................  .£480,000 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Interest at 4 per cent ............                        19,200 
     <lb/>
     Cost of bridging the Avon £40 ,000-     
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>

            <p>
     interest at 5 per cent .........                          2,000 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                                                             £21,000 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
              Probable returns:  
     <lb/>
     Population of Kings, Annapolis, Digby and 
     <lb/>
     Yarmouth say ........................................... 70,000 
     <lb/>
     Assume that one-half the population of these 
     <lb/>
     counties travel over the road once a year, 
     <lb/>
     and the gain to each $2 ...................... £17,500 
     <lb/>
     Assume 12,000 tons of freight annually, at a 
     <lb/>
     gain of $2 per ton  .................................... 6,000 
     <lb/>
                                                                  £23,500 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Here we have more than the annual cost of  
     <lb/>interest at once; but these are far from being<lb/>all the advantages that will result. Let us en-<lb break="maybe"/>quire the present cost of getting to Halifax, say<lb/>from the centre of Annapolis, and as the dis-<lb break="maybe"/>tance is extended the gain is increased:<lb/>Fare by coach to Windsor, say....................................$5,00<lb/>By rail...................................................................................1,33<lb/>
     Time consumed 4 days a $1 per day........................ ..4 00 
     <lb/>
     Expenses while absent, $1..............................................4,00 
     <lb/>
                                                                                     $14. 35 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     
      With the railway to Annapolis completed, 
     <lb/>
      how would it stand?   
     <lb/>
     Fare per rail, say.. ...................................... $3.00 
     <lb/>
     Two days consumed, a$l ..... .................... 2.00 
     <lb/>
     Expenses per day, $1 .. .… . .. ................... 2 00 
     <lb/>
                                                                         $7 000 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Gain to each person passing over the line $7.35 
     <lb/>
     The above are given as approximate calcula— 
     <lb/>
     tions and results, but they cannot be regarded 
     <lb/>
     as extravagant. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>The hon. gentleman concluded by saying 
     <lb/>that he would not weary the House by any 
     <lb/>further remarks at that late period of the ses- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>sion. He was convinced that in proposing this 
     <lb/>extension, the Government were acting for the 
     <lb/>best interests of the country and in accordance 
     <lb/>with sound policy, and he should vote for the 
     <lb/>resolution before the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Mr. MACDONNELL said that he felt called 
     <lb/>
     upon to make a few observations after the re- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     marks that had fallen from the member for 
     <lb/>
    Annapolis, who had just addressed the house. 
     <lb/>That hon. gentleman had called upon the mem- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>bers for the Eastern part of the Province to 
     <lb/>assist him in carrying this scheme, on the 
     <lb/>grounds that the Western members had aided 
     <lb/>in passing the Pictou railroad bill. He (Mr. 
     <lb/>McD.) could not agree to the question being 
     <lb/>put on that plea. He had always, upon every 
     <lb/>occasion when he had expressed an opinion, 
     <lb/>denied that the East had derived  any more ad- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>vantage from the Pictou railroad than the 
     <lb/>West. When the distance of the Counties of 
     <lb/>Cape  Breton from the present termini of the 
     <lb/>railroads  was considered, it would be seen that 
     <lb/>they derived no' more direct benefit than the 
     <lb/>Western Counties. He was sorry, then, to find 
     <lb/>this cry of last session reiterated— that the 
     <lb/>East alone was going to be benefitted by the 
     <lb/>Pictou railroad. It could have no other effect 
     <lb/>than to produce sectional jealousies, which in a 
     <lb/>question of' this kind should be kept out of 
     <lb/>sight. If this policy of railway extension was 
     <lb/>sound, it should stand upon its own merits, 
     <lb/>and be justified upon provincial grounds, and 
     <lb/>not as being of advantage, to any particular 
     <lb/>locality. As regards the resolution upon the  
     <lb/>table, he would say that if it went no further 
     <lb/>than to authorize the construction of the line 
     <lb/>to the borders of New Brunswick, he should 
     <lb/>have supported it, because he believed that 
     <lb/>that extension would be of great benefit to the 
     <lb/>whole Province; but he could not see what ad- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>vantage would flow from the Annapolis line. 
     <lb/>It could not be said that it was for the purpose 
     <lb/>of obtaining the trade of New Brunswick, be- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>cause that would be accomplished by the con- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>struction of the Trunk line, and the one would 
     <lb/>only interfere with the other. He should be 
     <lb/>compelled, then,h to vote against the resolution 
     <lb/>in its present shape. After a deliberate revi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>sion of the financial condition of the country, 
     <lb/>he had arrived at the conclusion, that it would 
     <lb/>be unwise to undertake the construction of  
     <lb/>both lines at the present time. It was true 
     <lb/>that a resolution of a somewhat similar cha- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>racter had received his support last year; but 
     <lb/>in voting for it then, he had been actuated 
     <lb/>principally  by a desire to secure the construc-  
     <lb break="maybe"/>tion of the line to the borders, and with no 
     <lb/>idea that the Annapolis road would become a  
     <lb/> reality. He was rather surprised to hear some  
     <lb/>of the arguments used by the member for An- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>napolis,He commenced by comparing the<lb/>state of our finances now with their position in<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="294" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_294.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">294</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>
            <p>
     1855, and gave the railroads the credit for all 
     <lb/>
     the improvements; but he for ot that the ad 
     <lb/>
     valorem duties then were only five per cent and 
     <lb/>
     now they are ten. And then, again, he calcu- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     lated that the Annapolis road would pay three 
     <lb/>
     per cent.; but he also forgot that'it would be in 
     <lb/>
     the hands of a company, and that they would 
     <lb/>
     receive the benefit, if any. He would not de- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tain the house at any greater length, but he 
     <lb/>
     felt that from the course he had previously 
     <lb/>
     taken he could not give a silent vote. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. CHURCHILL said that he would have 
     <lb/>
     been better pleased if this resolution of the 
     <lb/>
     Government had gone further, and authorized 
     <lb/>
     these two branches to be immediately put 
     <lb/>
     under contract. It was quite time that the 
     <lb/>
     iron road should traverse the fertile vales of 
     <lb/>
     Kings and Hauts; and he could not see how 
     <lb/>
     any financial considerations should deter the 
     <lb/>
     Government from at once prosecuting this 
     <lb/>
     work to a conclusion. The country was in 
     <lb/>
     want of increased accommodation in the way 
     <lb/>
     of paper currency, and he did not see why a 
     <lb/>
     few hundred thousand pounds more of paper 
     <lb/>
     could not be easily floated. It would accom- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     modate the public, and could be floated with- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     out any detriment to the public credit. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman alluded to his recent visit to 
     <lb/>
     the United States, and the advantages he had 
     <lb/>
     witnessed there from railway extension. He 
     <lb/>
     trusted that the resolutions now on the table 
     <lb/>
     would receive the unanimous approval of 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen on both sides; and the Government 
     <lb/>
     would be prepared to presecute the work with 
     <lb/>
     energy and vigor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. O. J. CAMPBELL said that be admired the 
     <lb/>
     consistency of the Atty; Genl., although he 
     <lb/>
     'could not commend his advocacy of the propo- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sed policy. He found that the present railway 
     <lb/>
     yielded about half per cent on their cost, leav- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ing the province to bear the remaining five and 
     <lb/>
     a half per cent. He contended that the in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     crease of our taxation was injurious to the best 
     <lb/>
     .interestsof the country, and that the improve- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment of the localities through which the exist- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ing lines ran was not so great as had been rep— 
     <lb/>
     resented. He read from a speech delivered 
     <lb/>
     last session by Mr. Churchill, (in which that 
     <lb/>
     gentleman said that our railways were as a 
     <lb/>
     millstone about our neck), as a contrast to the 
     <lb/>
     speech delivered last evening. He concurred 
     <lb/>
     in these sentiments; he believed that the ex- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tension would benefit only Halifax, and could 
     <lb/>
     not advance the interests of Cape Breton. He 
     <lb/>
     denounced the policy of exacting so large an 
     <lb/>
     an amount of royalty from our'mines, and said 
     <lb/>
     that the sum received from that source should 
     <lb/>
     not be confidently reckoned on. ' 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. LOCKE said that they had arrived at 
     <lb/>
     that period of the session when short speeches 
     <lb/>
     were necessary and he should not therefore de- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tain the house more than a few moments. 
     <lb/>
     From the time of the first inception of the rail- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     way system in i851 up to last session, he had 
     <lb/>
     always advocated the construction of those 
     <lb/>
     public works. At that time he was obliged to 
     <lb/>
     vote against the extension to Pictou because 
     <lb/>
     he thought that it would interfere with the 
     <lb/>
     larger scheme of an intercolonial railroad, and 
     <lb/>
     that both of them could not be undertaken at 
     <lb/>
     the same time." The same reason would com- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     pel him now to vote against the' present reso- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     lution, because he did not believe that the fi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nances ofthe country would admit of exten- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sion east and west at the same time.  He be- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     lieved that if both these lines are undertaken 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     it will involve an annual liability of $600,000 
     <lb/>
     and he contended that the Province was not in 
     <lb/>
     a position to bear that. It was beginningto be 
     <lb/>
     admitted now that the estimate, he had made 
     <lb/>
     last year of the cost of the Pictou line, which 
     <lb/>
     he had put down at between £600,000 and 
     <lb/>
     £700.000 would not be far out of the way. He 
     <lb/>
     should oppose this proposition to engage in 
     <lb/>
     any new undertaking until the Pictou road 
     <lb/>
     was completed, because he thought it would 
     <lb/>
     not be done without breaking faith with either 
     <lb/>
     the east or the west. He disapproved of ac— 
     <lb/>
     cepting the offer of Mr. Livesey, because we 
     <lb/>
     would bein the position of having; placed one 
     <lb/>
     portion of our lines under the contract of a 
     <lb/>
     company while the rest would be under the 
     <lb/>
     management of the government. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>He doubted very much the correctness of the 
     <lb/>anticipations of the hon. Fin. Sec. as to the in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>crease of the revenue. Every one who knew 
     <lb/>any thing about trade, knew that this quarter 
     <lb/>exhibited the largest returns, and it afforded no 
     <lb/>criterion for the rest of the year.  H e would 
     <lb/>find that the importations next quarter would 
     <lb/>fall ten per cent. short of this; and there would 
     <lb/>be a large decrease in the amount collected. for 
     <lb/>ad valorem duties. He believed that if the 
     <lb/>Province was able to construct these roads 
     <lb/>under the scheme proposed, it would be only 
     <lb/>under great difficulties, and not without se- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>riously embarrassing the resources for a long 
     <lb/>time to come; He did not think that the Go- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>vernment should force this measure through at 
     <lb/>that time, but should agree to the proposition 
     <lb/>to wait 'for a twelvemonth, until the Pictou 
     <lb/>road was finished, and they would be able to 
     <lb/>see how the revenue stood. He concluded by 
     <lb/>expressing his hope that the Government 
     <lb/>would not press the measure, when it was 
     <lb/>manifestly against the wishes of many gentle- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>men in the house, some of whom had always 
     <lb/>been the strongest supporters of railway ex- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tension. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. CHURCHILL, in alluding to the remarks 
     <lb/>made by the member for Victoria, in which he 
     <lb/>had quoted a speech made by him on a pre- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>vious occasion, complained that he omitted the 
     <lb/>latter portion of it, which explained his mean- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ing. When he said that the railroad debt was 
     <lb/>like a millstone round our necks, he meant 
     <lb/>that it was like any other debt, an encum- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>brance to us. But he did not mean that. that 
     <lb/>was any reason why we should not engage   in 
     <lb/>the construction of these works. He had al- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ways been an advocate of progress, and any 
     <lb/>one acquainted with his past history knew 
     <lb/>that he had always endeavored to do his ut- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>most to develope the resources of his native 
     <lb/>Province.     
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. STEWART CAMPBELL said that he felt 
     <lb/>a reluctance at that late period of the   session 
     <lb/>to trouble the House with remarks upon any 
     <lb/>question, but in a matter of su¢h importance 
     <lb/>as this he could not content himSelf with giv- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ing a silent vote. At an early period of his 
     <lb/>legislative career he had committed. himself to 
     <lb/>the policy of railway construction by govern- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ment, and he was happy to say that that po- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>licy had resulted beneficially to the country 
     <lb/>He observed with pleasure that the example 
     <lb/>set by this small colony was about to be fol- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>lowed by the  parent state, and that in that 
     <lb/>country'the question was now being consider- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ed as to whether it would not be advisable to 
     <lb/>take the control of the railways out of the 
     <lb/>hands of private companies, and place it with 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="295" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_295.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">PARLAMENTARY</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES</fw>
            <p>
     the government. He was disposed to object to 
     <lb/>
     this resolution because it departed from the 
     <lb/>
    policy adopted by the government when the sys- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tem was inaugurated in times gone by, and he 
     <lb/>thought that this was aview of the subject which 
     <lb/>deserved consideration. They had only to look 
     <lb/>back for a short period and see what had taken 
     <lb/>place in Canada in order to appreciate the effects 
     <lb/>of placing the control of the public works of a 
     <lb/>country in the hands of large and influential 
     <lb/>corporations. He objected then to the scheme 
     <lb/>because it would introduce into this country 
     <lb/>something of the same kind. The effect of this 
     <lb/>subvention of these two lines of railroad would 
     <lb/>be that the coompany receiving it would neces- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>sarily be brought into close connection with 
     <lb/>the government of the day, and to a large ex- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tent would be subordinate to them and under 
     <lb/>their influence.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>These lines of railroad would run through 
     <lb/>various counties of the province -Colchester, 
     <lb/>Pictou and Cumberland on the-one hand, and 
     <lb/>Hants, Kings and Annapolis on the other. - 
     <lb break="maybe"/>They all knew then how many representatives 
     <lb/>would be directly interested in their construc- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tion- no less a number than sixteen would be 
     <lb/>more or less interested in their completion. 
     <lb/>He would ask then whether it would conduce 
     <lb/>to the best interests of the country, or the in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>dependence of the legislature, that so 1arge a 
     <lb/>proportion of the people's representatives 
     <lb/>should be in a position to be influenced by the 
     <lb/>companies who would receive this subvention, 
     <lb/>and who, again, must necessarily be so closely 
     <lb/>connected with the government of lthe day. 
     <lb/>He had listened with great interest to the fi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>nancial picture of the affairs of this country, so 
     <lb/>ably drawn by the hon. leader of the opposi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tion, and he thought that the house would 
     <lb/>agree with him that there was no gentleman    
     <lb/>  in that house or  the country whose opinions 
     <lb/>were more entitled to respect upon questions 
     <lb/>of finance than that hon. gentleman.  The hon.  
     <lb/>Provincial  Secretary had on some occasions  
     <lb/>been rather severe upon the hon. member for 
     <lb/>Colchester, as regards  his skill as a financier; 
     <lb/>but from what had  taken place  recently be- 
     <lb break="maybe"/> tween them upon another. question of great 
     <lb/>public împortance, he thought. that he was not 
     <lb/>in a position to question his accuracy now. He<lb/>did not wish to make any invidious compari-<lb break="maybe"/>sons between the leader of the opposition and<lb/>the present Financial Secretary as regards<lb/>their financial capacity but as one was com- 
     <lb break="maybe"/> paratively new to the businees and the other  
     <lb/>had; made it his study fonyears, it followed 
     <lb/>  that he must necessarily have more acquaint-  
     <lb break="maybe"/>ance with the subject, and his opinions were 
     <lb/>therefore entitled to greater weight.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The member for Colchestor had re- 
     <lb break="maybe"/> referred  to the  past  financial  position,  of 
     <lb/>this country, and to our prospects for<lb/>the future, and he had called upon the hon.<lb/>members for Halifax and Richmond to dispute 
     <lb/>the position  he took. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>Halifax (Mr. Tobin) had since addressed the<lb/>house, but he had not ventured to controvert<lb/>the assertion he made, that the present<lb/>was not the time to embark in these works.<lb/>The member for Richmond (Mr. LeVesconte)<lb/>had not yet spoken but, from what had fallen<lb/>from him on a previous occasion, when the<lb/> sale of provincial debentures was under con- 
     <lb break="maybe"/> sideration, he did not think that he would be 
     <lb/>inclined to disagree with the opinions of that  
     <lb/>hon. gentleman.  On a previous occasion the 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     hon. Prov; Secy. in , reference to the fisheries  
     <lb/>
     said that his (Mr. C.'s) constituents had better 
     <lb/>
     look round, and find some representative bet- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ter acquainted with trade and commerce than 
     <lb/>
     he was. I'He thought that he had better apply 
     <lb/>
     his. remarks to his own government and to 
     <lb/>
     his financial Secy., and get sombody more 
     <lb/>
     conversant with  the intricacies of finance 
     <lb/>
     than that  honourable  gentleman from.   his 
     <lb/>
     previous training could  be expected to 
     <lb/>
     be. He thought that it was a lament- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     able defect  in the composition of the pre- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sent executive that it did  not posses a  
     <lb/>
     single individual amongst its members in any  
     <lb/>
     way identified with the trade or commerce of 
     <lb/>
     the country. He may be told that there was  
     <lb/>
     one gentleman who had formerly been engag- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ed in trade, but from what he knew of that 
     <lb/>
     gentleman's connection with the late govern- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment he did not think that  his judgment  ap-  
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     proved of entering upon the scheme of railway 
     <lb/>
     extension now proposed altho' from his being 
     <lb/>
     a member of the government he was to a cer- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tatin extent committed to  it. lt was well 
     <lb/>
     known that the government; was principally 
     <lb/>
     if not entirely carried on by the two or three 
     <lb/>
     members of it who sat at the table of that 
     <lb/>
     house, and that in point of fact they were the  
     <lb/>
     real dictators of the affairs of this country.  He 
     <lb/>
     could easily fancy then how the opinions of 
     <lb/>
     the  hon. gentleman to whom he had  alluded  
     <lb/>
     would be set on one side and everything would 
     <lb/>
     be made subservient to the political necessities 
     <lb/>
    of those who held seats in that house.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Reference had been made to the time when  
     <lb/>railroads were first commenced in  this coun-  
     <lb break="maybe"/>try, and to the fact that our revenues  
     <lb/>then comparatively  insignificant. That, no 
     <lb/>doubt, was the fact; but it must not be  forgot-   
     <lb break="maybe"/>ten, that our obligations were also much less 
     <lb/>ready  assumed including the  Pictou line,  
     <lb/>amount" to  something like four-fifths of the  
     <lb/>entire revenue of 1851;  but it seems that this 
     <lb/>oad is not enough for Nova Scotia to bear 
     <lb/>and  we must add  this additional burden for 
     <lb/>the construction of branch lines to Annapolis 
     <lb/>and, the borders of New Brunswick, which 
     <lb/>        will make the entire amount to be borne by 
     <lb/>the revenues of the Province about $500,000 a  
     <lb/>year. Now blue nose was a very good natured 
     <lb/>fellow, no doubt, but it does not do  to push a 
     <lb/>willing horse too far; and he cautioned hon.  
     <lb/>gentlemen how they committed themselves to 
     <lb/>a scheme which was going to entail such heavy   
     <lb/>burdens upon the people. He had no wish to  
     <lb/>condemn railroards in the abstract;  he believed  
     <lb/>that when a man had plenty of money, he had  
     <lb/> a right to spend it as he pleased ; but  where a  
     <lb/>person is only possesed of limited means, he 
     <lb/>stands in a different position, and should only<lb/>spend his money upon necessaries, and not<lb/>upon luxuries. That was just the position the 
     <lb/>    province was in. Railroads, no doubt, were a 
     <lb/>great convenience, but if they could only be  
     <lb/>obtained by  the  sacrifice"; of other important  
     <lb/>interests, they should be left alone.       
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
      The government should make themselves 
     <lb/>
     acquainted with the wants and necessities of  
     <lb/>
     the country before they talk about every ser-  
     <lb break="maybe"/>
    vice being properly provided for. He should  
     <lb/>like to take some of them over some of the 
     <lb/>roads in the county he represented, and show 
     <lb/>them the inconveniences under which the peo- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ple labored, and the grievances which he had<lb/>so often and so unsuccessfully brought to their<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="296" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_296.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">296</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLAMENTARY DEBATES</fw>
            <p>
     notice; and he thought that they would come 
     <lb/>
     back with their views considerably changed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      (The hon. gentleman referred to a case of a 
     <lb/>
     petition he had presented to the  government, 
     <lb/>
     signed by hundreds of influential persons in his 
     <lb/>
     county, asking for aid to an important public 
     <lb/>
     road, but which  was refused any considera- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tion at all. So indignant was one gentleman 
     <lb/>
     at the treatment they had receive,  that he 
     <lb/>
     offered to lend £700 himself to carry on the 
     <lb/>
     work which it was the duty of the government 
     <lb/>
     to construct.) This was only one of many in- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     stances, in which the government had turned 
     <lb/>
     a deaf ear to the wants of the county of Guys- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     borough. How then could he justify himself 
     <lb/>
     to his constituents, if he voted for these reso- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     lutions? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. member for Hants (Mr. Chuchill) 
     <lb/>
     had exhibited himself on the previous evening 
     <lb/>
     in rather an extraordinary attitude, but it ap- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     peared that there weresome favored ones in that 
     <lb/>
     house who could do as they chose provided 
     <lb/>
     they gave the government a. vote.  That hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman had thought proper to absent him- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     self for the greater part of the session from 
     <lb/>
     his duties, first at his own home and after- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     wards in a neighbouring country, attending to 
     <lb/>
     his private interests. Whether that was a pro- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     per course for a representive to take was ex- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ceedingly questionable; and now he comes 
     <lb/>
     back and undertakes to impute motives to 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentlemen for the course pursued by 
     <lb/>
     them on this question. He thought that when 
     <lb/>
     it was considered that this railroad would for 
     <lb/>
     a long distance go through the. county that: 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman represented, and that large 
     <lb/>
     sum of money would be spent at his very door, 
     <lb/>
     that the less he challenged  the motives of 
     <lb/>
     others the better. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     He trusted that in the opposition he was 
     <lb/>
     obliged to give to this measure that factious 
     <lb/>
     motives would not be imputed to him. He had 
     <lb/>
     only to point to the couse he pursued last ses- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sion—on the Pictou railroad—to shew that he 
     <lb/>
     was not influenced by any factious spirit. It 
     <lb/>
     was then in the power of the opposition, if they 
     <lb/>
     had had the desire, to have seriously embar- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     rassed the government on that question. He 
     <lb/>
     had, however. taken a higher view of the ques- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tion, and had supported that measure al- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     though Pictou was not a bit nearer to him than 
     <lb/>
      Annapolis or Windsor. He hoped, therefore, 
     <lb/>
     that: the government would not attribute to 
     <lb/>
     him any motives of that description. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     At that late period of the session he would 
     <lb/>
     not. detain the house at any greater length. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. gentleman concluded by deprecating 
     <lb/>
     any immediate action in the way of incurring 
     <lb/>
     any further liability. He was afraid it would 
     <lb/>
     have the effect of depreciating the value of the 
     <lb/>
     debentures already issued. He appealed to 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen on both sides of the house, to the 
     <lb/>
     supporters of the government; as well as their 
     <lb/>
     opponents, not to he influenced by a mere de- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sire for a party triumph in voting for a resolu- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tion which he believed on sober reflection they 
     <lb/>
     would find to be detrimental to the best inter- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ests of the country.    
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      MR. KILLAM alluded to the offer of the Interna- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tional Contract Company, and compared, it with 
     <lb/>
     the terms oifered by the resolution of last session. 
     <lb/>
     He remarked that the question stood in quite 
     <lb/>
     another position from what it did in the previous 
     <lb/>
     Session. In proposing to place the work in  the 
     <lb/>
     hands of a. company, the government must have 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     placed very little confidence in their own . officers,  
     <lb/>
     for the Commissioner of Railways had given to 
     <lb/>
    the House as his opinion that in a few years the 
     <lb/>road would pay three per cent above its working   
     <lb/>expenses ; if that were correct the best course 
     <lb/>would be for the government itself to undertake 
     <lb/>the construction. He said that the terms of the 
     <lb/>offer were entirely altered, and it would therefore 
     <lb/>be perfectly consistent in the House to reject the  
     <lb/>resolution. The determination of the government 
     <lb/>seemed to be to keep themselves afloat, whatever 
     <lb/>became of the country.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Hon. Mr. MGFARLANE replied to a remark of Mr. 
     <lb/>Killam. He said that four different surveys of 
     <lb/>routes had been made, but the route was to be  
     <lb/>finally selected by the government, acting under 
     <lb/>the. advice of the very able engineer now in their 
     <lb/>employ.       
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Mr. ARCHIBALD contended that to give to the 
     <lb/>
     government the discretion proposed by the resolu- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tion would. be to hand over to them the entire con- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     trol of the public chest. So great had been the 
     <lb/>
     mystification of figures on the question that the 
     <lb/>
     member for Halifax, although a merchant, had 
     <lb/>
     made a mistake in stating   the public debt, to the 
     <lb/>
     extentof two million of dollars, a sum sufficient 
     <lb/>
    to build the Pictou railway. He had a great  
     <lb/>appreciation of the value of railways, and he 
     <lb/>hoped that the time had arrived when we could 
     <lb/>connect our road with the other lines of the conti- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>nent ; but the circumstances which had exhibited 
     <lb/>themselves in the trade of the country had con- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>vinced him that our prospects were not so good as 
     <lb/>to warrant us in increasing the large liability that 
     <lb/>would be necessary to carry on even that work.  
     <lb/>He was greatly pleased to find that our present  
     <lb/>railways had not only become able to pay their 
     <lb/>working expenses, but had commenced to yield 
     <lb/>something towards the interest. There was, how- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ever, one important circumstance which had been<lb/>left out of consideration,—in nearly all railways 
     <lb/>the duration of the iron was estimated at eight 
     <lb/>years, and the companies made a practice et set- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ting aside a certain sum every year to, meet the 
     <lb/>cost of renewing. Our road was not as much 
     <lb/>worked as others and might be expected to last 16 
     <lb/>years, 8 of which had already expired, and, he  
     <lb/>found that the cost of replacing the line, after de-  
     <lb break="maybe"/>ducting the value of the old iron would be $4,- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>000 per mile, in addition to $400 per mile for 
     <lb/>labour, making a. total for the'work of $431,000,  
     <lb/>so that we ought at present to be setting aside for 
     <lb/>that service aboutt $53,800 a year. The remarks 
     <lb/>of the Commissioner of Railways had given him 
     <lb/>no little amusement, That gentleman had pre- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>viously assigned railways to not very complimen- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tary company, but now, with the ardor which  
     <lb/>always characterized one newly converted from a 
     <lb/>heathen to a saint, was outstripping in his zeal 
     <lb/>those who had been trained for a. lifetime to the 
     <lb/>policy to which he had been converted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr; Archibald. after some further remarks 
     <lb/>
    moved the following amendment :—   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     "Whereas—The location of the Pictou Railway 
     <lb/>
    has added largely to the length of the road contem- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>'plated to be constructed by the Railway bill last 
     <lb/> year ; and whereas in view of the heavy liabilities)  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="297" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_297.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">PARLIAMENTARY</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES.</fw>
            <p>
     which the construction of that work will entail, and<lb/>the paramount necessity at the present exigency of<lb/>preserving the public credit unimpaired, it is desi-<lb break="maybe"/>rable not to enter at present any new Railway<lb/>enterprises.<lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>

            <p>
     Therefore Resolved—That this house is of opinion<lb/>,that beyond the completion of the Picton Railway<lb/>no additional railway liability should be gone on<lb/>with by the government untill the House is enabled,<lb/>at its next session, to pass an opinion on its neces-<lb break="maybe"/>ity."<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>HON PROV. SEC. said that he admired the pluck<lb/>which the leader of the opposition shewed in<lb/>dancing on nothing after the platform had been<lb/>taken from under him by the Financial Secretary<lb/>and Attorney General. The attitude of that gen-<lb break="maybe"/>tleman was only suitable for one who had oppo-<lb break="maybe"/>sed railway construction from the first. The <lb/>government on this occasion proposed no new<lb/>policy, but merely asked the House to extend to<lb/>the amount of £5100 the terms of last year. It<lb/>was not the first time that the cry "one year<lb/>more" had been heard. It was raised at the <lb/>time when our delegates had obtained for us the<lb/>most favourable terms in connection with our<lb/>mines and minerals, and if the pressure had then<lb/>been yielded to a monopoly would still have con-<lb break="maybe"/>trolled the resources which now enrich the <lb/>country. The proposed expenditure for a con-<lb break="maybe"/>nection with the European and North American<lb/>line would be only £53,000, while the former go-<lb break="maybe"/>vernment had passed an act offering £50,000 for <lb/>our share of the Intercolonial road, an undertak-<lb break="maybe"/>ing with infinitely less paying qualities than the <lb/>other, and that too without giving us a line to <lb/>the fertile West, or to the neighbouring Provinces.<lb/>He then referred to the arguments advanced by<lb/>Mr. Killam.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Archibald's amendment was lost 27 to 19.<lb/>For—Heffernan, Ross, Killam, Hatfield, Par-<lb break="maybe"/>ker, Ray, McLellan, Miller, Roberston, Mc-<lb break="maybe"/>Donnell, C J. Campbell, Blackwood, Archibald,<lb/>Blanchard, Locke, Caldwell, Balcam, Annand.<lb/>Against--Donkin, Shannon, McFarlane, Fin.<lb/>Secretary, Bill, Longley, Bill, Atty General E.<lb/>L. Brown, McKay, More, Juo Campbell, Law-<lb break="maybe"/>rence, Pryor, Whitman, D. Fraser, Kaulback<lb/>Hamilton, Tobin, Jost, Bourinot, J. Fraser,<lb/>Churchill, LeVesconte, Prov. Secretary. Mckin-<lb break="maybe"/>non, Robicheau.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Miller then moved the following resolu-<lb break="maybe"/>tion:—"That in the opinion of this House, it is <lb/>expedient to define with accuracy the nature and<lb/>extent of the subvention to be given towards the <lb/>construction of lines of Railway to New Brunswich <lb/>and Annapolis, and not leave the same to be <lb/>gathered from proposals which are capable of mis-<lb break="maybe"/>representation, and have been so differently in-<lb break="maybe"/>terpreted in the discussion on the resolution be-<lb break="maybe"/>fore the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Miller explained that the resolution he<lb/>had read had been handed him by the hon. <lb/>member for Colchester. He had framed himself<lb/>one similar to it, with the intention of moving it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. ATTY, GENERAL said that the Govern-<lb break="maybe"/>ment intended bringing in a bill, defining the <lb/>powers to be given under the original resolution.<lb/>The present amendment was a direct insult to the<lb/>Government.<lb/>38.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Mr. Archibald said that it was only due to<lb/>the House that the resolution to beadopted should<lb/>be definite in its character.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. PROV. SEC. said that this resolution was<lb/>altogether unnecessary, after the explanations <lb/>that had been given by the Government, that it <lb/>was intended to submit a bill, distinctly defining <lb/>the powers that were to be given to them in con-<lb break="maybe"/>nection with this question, He challenged the <lb/>hon. leader of the opposition to produce a prece-<lb break="maybe"/>dent where the Government had been treated as <lb/>on the present occasion.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The amendment was lost by 28 to 18.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>For--E. Brown, Heffernan, Ross, Hatfield,<lb/>Parker, Ray, Killam, McLellan, Miller, Robert-<lb break="maybe"/>son, McDonnell, Archibald, S. Campbell, Black-<lb break="maybe"/>wood, Blanchard, Locke, Annand, Balcom.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Against—Pryor, Juo Campbell, C J. Camp-<lb break="maybe"/>bell, Atty. Gen., McKay, Moore, Shannon, Law-<lb break="maybe"/>rence, Donkin, Whitman, Longley, D. Fraser,<lb/>Kaulback, Hamilton, Tobin, Jost, Bourinot, J.<lb/>Fraser, Churchill, LeVesconte, McFarlane, Robicheau,<lb/>Calwell, Fin. Secretary.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The original resolution then passed by a vote of <lb/>28 to 18.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House adjourned at about half-past 12.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>CLOSE OF CONFEDERATION DEBATE.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON.PROV. SEC. moved that the adjourned<lb/>debate on the Union of the Colonies be resumed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. ARCHIBALD said—At this late period<lb/>the session, it is impossible to resume the debate<lb/>on this question without wearing the patience of <lb/>the House on all sides. The Supreme Court meets<lb/>here next Tuesday, and the legal gentlemen in<lb/>this House have necessarily much to occupy their<lb/>attention. Besides nothing practical can grow<lb/>out of this discussion. The House are already<lb/>committed by the resolution of last year to a <lb/>Union of the Maritime Provinces, and the on y<lb/>difficulty that may prevent gentlemen agreeing to<lb/>the present resolution is its preamble. I there-<lb break="maybe"/>fore rise to suggest to the Provincial Secretary,<lb/>whether he would not be willing to withdraw this<lb/>preamble, which is a matter of no importance.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON.PROV. SEC.—My colleagues and myself,<lb/>entirely concur in the opinion that it is very de-<lb break="maybe"/>sirable that the House should preserve the same <lb/>attitude it assumed last session in reference to a <lb/>Union of the Maritime Provinces. I think it is<lb/>only justice to the delegates from these Provinces<lb/>to say that it was not their fault that the Con-<lb break="maybe"/>ference held under the resolution of last session<lb/>had not a different result. It is only fair that I<lb/>should also say that I am now much less san-<lb break="maybe"/>guine than I was last year of any practical result<lb/>growing out of this resolution. It is a secret no<lb/>where, that as far as the Island of Prince Edward<lb/>is concerned, they have decided to have nothing<lb/>to do with anybody under any circumstances,<lb/>nad to remain in their present isolated condition.<lb/>Since I addressed the House on the last occasion<lb/>I notice that two prominent members of the New<lb/>Brunswick Government have pledged themselves<lb/>against a Legislative Union of the Maritime Pro-<lb break="maybe"/>vinces. It will be our duty, however, to ascer-<lb break="maybe"/>tain the feelings of the Government of that Pro-<lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>
            <pb n="298" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_298.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">298</fw>
            <p>
     vince on the subject, and to bring it to a termina- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tion. I can but add, that, if removing the 
     <lb/>
     preamble to this resolution will enable the House 
     <lb/>
     to come to the some unanimous conclusion they 
     <lb/>
     did last year, I will cheerfully consent to the 
     <lb/>
     proposition made by my hon. friend opposite 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. ANN AND.— I am glad the Prov. Secy. 
     <lb/>
     has made the announcement he has, that he will 
     <lb/>
    withdraw the preamble. This portion of the reso- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>lution was distasteful to many gentlemen, and 
     <lb/>prevented them assuming the same position they 
     <lb/>did last year. It is apparent that the proposed 
     <lb/>Union with New Brunswick cannot possibly be 
     <lb/>consummated — a union I heartily desire — and it 
     <lb/>would, be therefore, useless at the present stage 
     <lb/>of the session, to proceed any further with the 
     <lb/>matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL— I have come to the 
     <lb/>
     conclusion that I will not have the pleasure of ad- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     dressing the House, for the reasons given by the 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen who have spoken. There is now a con- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     siderable amount of business that must be trans- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     acted without delay. I have no hesitation in say- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ing that if the course now suggested is not ad- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     opted, the House must be delayed at least a fort- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     night longer. I have reluctantly yielded to the 
     <lb/>
     suggestion to close the debate. I have listened 
     <lb/>
     with a great deal of attention, to the gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     who have spoken on this subject, and I certainly 
     <lb/>
     must say, that I had hoped to have been able 
     <lb/>
     to reply to their observations. I have not 
     <lb/>
     yet had an opportunity of fully expres- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sing my opinions as one of the delegates. I did 
     <lb/>
     not consider that it was necessary for me at the 
     <lb/>
     outset of this debate to address the House, but al- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     lowed gentlemen to procede me. I must con- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     gratulate gentlemen in the Opposition on this 
     <lb/>
     question, that they have had an opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     fully explaining their views, and placing them 
     <lb/>
     before the country to an extent that the friends of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation have not. Looking, however, at 
     <lb/>
     the time that must be occupied if the debate is 
     <lb/>
     continued, and the delay of public business that 
     <lb/>
     must result, I have waived my own feelings in 
     <lb/>
     the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. TOBIN. — Whilst I am not going to oppose 
     <lb/>
     the resolution, I must express my conviction that 
     <lb/>
    a Union of the Maritime Provinces cannot bring 
     <lb/>with it any positive advantages. There is very 
     <lb/>little trade and business between Nova Scotia and 
     <lb/>New Brunswick. We can never gain na- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tionality by means of such a Union. I am quite 
     <lb/>Sure, too, that New Brunswick has no desire 
     <lb/>whatever to unite with us. I firmly believe, if we 
     <lb/>cannot be united to a large country like Canada, 
     <lb/>it is better for us to remain as we are. I expressed 
     <lb/>the same opinions last year, and I see no reasons 
     <lb/>now for changing them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. S. McDONNELL—I must confess that I vote 
     <lb/>for the resolution with no little reluctance. That 
     <lb/>the time of the House would be wasted in the dis- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>cussion of this question, I do not believe. A ques- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>tion that has engaged the attention of so many 
     <lb/>prominent public men in these Provinces, and has 
     <lb/>agitated the public mind to so large an extent, is   
     <lb/>surely worth a few day's debate. The country has 
     <lb/>expected that every man would express his 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.' 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     opinion on the subject In view, however, of the 
     <lb/>
     desire of the House to bring the discussion to a close, 
     <lb/>
     and of the fact that the Prov. Secy. has consented 
     <lb/>
     to withdraw the preamble, I shall agree to allow 
     <lb/>
     the resolution to pass without making any further 
     <lb/>
     observations 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. MILLER —I feel just as reluctant as other 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen, to allow the question to pass without 
     <lb/>
     expressing my views, especially after the position 
     <lb/>
     which I occupied last year, and have since taken 
     <lb/>
     in reference to it. However, I heartily concur with 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen as to the necessity of saving the public 
     <lb/>
     time. Besides the debate would not really elicit 
     <lb/>
     much new information, for nearly all the facts 
     <lb/>
     connected with it have already  been put before the 
     <lb/>
     country. I don't desire to divide the House on the 
     <lb/>
     resolution, but I wish it to be understood distinct- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ly that I am not at all committed to it. I enter- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tain views similar to those expressed by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Halifax (Mr. Tobin,) respecting a 
     <lb/>
     Union ot the Maritime Provinces. If I have any 
     <lb/>
     desire for a Union it is for the larger one. The 
     <lb/>
     opinions I held last year I hold now. My oppo- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sition has not been to the Union' in the abstract 
     <lb/>
     but to the terms on which it was secured. I 
     <lb/>
     defy any one to find a passage in anything I have 
     <lb/>
     said since last session, which proves that I am op- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     posed to a Union on fair and equitable terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. FIN. SEC.—Any one must see that that if 
     <lb/>
     this debate were continued, we must be here a 
     <lb/>
     good many days longer. I take it for granted that 
     <lb/>
     every gentlemen in this House will feel that he 
     <lb/>
     should give his constituents the benefit of the 
     <lb/>
     views he entertains, and define the position which 
     <lb/>
     he occupies, but that he can do equally as well 
     <lb/>
    when he visits his county. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Mr. S. CAMPBELL—As I have offered no re- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
    marks upon the question during the debate which 
     <lb/>has ensued, I now rise to make a speech. It will 
     <lb/>be a very short one; it is that the question be now 
     <lb/>put<lb/> 
               <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The resolution then passed as amended without 
     <lb/>
     a division. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>[The remaining days, till the prorogation. 
     <lb/>were taken up with merely routine business, 
     <lb/>summaries of which have already appeared 
     <lb/>in the city papers-Reporter] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>TUESDAY, MAY 2. 
     <lb/>PROROGATION PF THE LEGISLATURE. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The session of the Provincial Parliament 
     <lb/>
     was prorogued this afternoon at half-past four 
     <lb/>
    o'clock, by His Excellency the Lieutenant 
     <lb/>Governor, with all the usual formalities. After 
     <lb/>the usual! preliminaries His Excellency Sir 
     <lb/>Richard Graves Macdonnell closed the session 
     <lb/>with the following 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>  Speech : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. President and Honourable Gentlemen of the Le- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
    gislature Council: 
     <lb/>Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of Assembly: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     1: I am happy that the state of the public 
     <lb/>
     business enables me to release you from further 
     <lb/>attendance on your legislative duties<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     2. It gives me much pleasure, in closing the 
     <lb/>
    second session of the twenty-third General 
     <lb/>Assembly of the Provincial Parliament, to be<lb/>able to congratulate you on the many useful<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="299" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-21_Page_299.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">PARLIAMENTARY</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES. 299</fw>
            <p>
     and important measures which your labours 
     <lb/>
     have matured. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr.  Speaker and Gentlemen of the House of Assembly : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     3. I. have to thank you for tho liberal provi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sion which you have made for the public sur- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     vices. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. President and Honourable Gentlemen of the Legis- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     lative Council:   
     <lb/>
     Mr. Speaker and Gentlemen of the House of Assembly : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     4. The action taken by New Brunswick early 
     <lb/>
     in the session, apparently placed a decision on 
     <lb/>
     the question of a general Confederation of Bri- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tish North America, to which at tha opening 
     <lb/>
     of the session 1 had invited your attention, 
     <lb/>
     under the disadvantage of leading to no im- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     mediate practical result. I am confident that 
     <lb/>
     otherwise you would have felt it your duty to 
     <lb/>
     have fully discussed the most important. and 
     <lb/>
     interesting question, with no earnest desire to 
     <lb/>
     meet the views of Her Majesty's Government, 
     <lb/>
     in every way compatible with the wishes and 
     <lb/>
     interests of this Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. Under the impression, therefore, that the 
     <lb/>
     above circumstances, over which you could 
     <lb/>
     have exercised no control, had for a time pre- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     eluded any useful consideration of the larger 
     <lb/>
     question, you have meantime reverted to the 
     <lb/>
     project of a Union of the Maritime Provinces, 
     <lb/>
     and reiterated your opinion of last session as 
     <lb/>
     to the expediency of appointing Reprasenta-<lb break="maybe"/> 
               <lb/>
     tives of this Province to confer thereon.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     shall have much pleasure in transmitting that 
     <lb/>
     resolution to the Lieut. Governors of the adja- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     cent Provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6. l most sincerely hope that the important 
     <lb/>
     principle of Free Schools, based on a moderate 
     <lb/>
     county assessment, may realize your expecta- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tions, by obtaining the support of all classes of 
     <lb/>
     the people, and effecting the most valuable re- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     suits in the general diffusion of education. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     7 . The largely increased provision for the 
     <lb/>
     local defence of the country conclusively proves 
     <lb/>
     the importance which, as Representatives of a 
     <lb/>
     loyal people, you attach to British connection, 
     <lb/>
     and the determination of this Provinco to as- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sume a fair share of the burdens of protecting 
     <lb/>
     her existing institutions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     8. The increased provision made for extention 
     <lb/>
     of Railway communication to the borders of 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick and Annapolis will, I hope, 
     <lb/>
     ensure those undertakings, being effectively 
     <lb/>
     prosecuted at an early day, with the happiest 
     <lb/>
     results; to the trade and general prosperity of 
     <lb/>
     the Provinces.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     8.I am gratified to learn that an Act has been   
     <lb/>
     passed providing: for the completion of the St. 
     <lb/>
     Peter's Canal, and that provision has been 
     <lb/>
     made for the extension of the Hospital of the 
     <lb/>
     Insane. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     10. With heartfelt thankfulness for the con- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tinued peace and prosperity which, under 
     <lb/>
     Providence, we have so long enjoyed, and with 
     <lb/>
     sincere prayers for the continuance of these 
     <lb/>
     blessings, I now declare this Session closed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>