<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1866-02-22"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>  
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-02-22">22 February 1866</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          
          
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Third Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1866"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          
          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-02-22_Page_001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-02-22_Page_002.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-10-26">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="davelang68" when="2017-10-26">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-02-22_Page_001">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-02-22_Page_001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-02-22_Page_002">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-02-22_Page_002.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-02-22_Page_001.jpg"/>
         <div type="section">                 
            
         <head rendition="simple:centre"> DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS <lb/>
            
     OF THE<lb/>
    
            
     HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY OF NOVA SCOTIA. 
     <lb/>
            
            1866.</head></div>
     <div type="section">        
            <p rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, Feb. 22.</p>
            
            <p>
     Shortly before 2 o'clock p. m. the SPEAKER 
     <lb/>
     took the chair of the house, and after a few 
     <lb/>
     minutes the Gentleman Usher of the Black 
     <lb/>
     Rod conveyed the command of His Excellency 
     <lb/>
     for the attendance of the House in the Council 
     <lb/>
     Chamber. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The House of Assembly having attended in 
     <lb/>
     obedience to His Excellency's command, His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency opened the Session with the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing Speech:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. President, and Honorable Gentlemen of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Council:</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of 
     <lb/>
        
     Assembly:</hi>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. It affords me unfeigned satisfaction, in 
     <lb/>
     meeting, for the first time, the Legislature of 
     <lb/>
     this my native Province, to be able to congra<lb break="no"/>tulate you upon a condition of prosperity never 
     <lb/>
     before equalled in the history of the Colony. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. While we have enjoyed the blessings of 
     <lb/>
     peace and immunity from pestilence,the labors 
     <lb/>
     of the Husbandman and the Fisherman have 
     <lb/>
     been crowned with success: and the sale of 
     <lb/>
     Crown Lands, the development of our Coal and 
     <lb/>
     Gold Mines, the receipts from our Railways, 
     <lb/>
     and the Trade and Revenue of our Provmce, 
     <lb/>
     are greatly in excess of any preceding year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. A soldier myself, and intimately connect<lb break="no"/>ed with the organization of the Volunteer 
     <lb/>
     movement both in Great Britain and in this 
     <lb/>
     Province, you can well understand the deep 
     <lb/>
     gratification it has afforded me to find the 
     <lb/>
     spirited manner in which my countrymen have 
     <lb/>
     responded, by the organization of a Militia 
     <lb/>
     Force so efficient, to the call to prepare for any 
     <lb/>
     emergency which may at any time demand 
     <lb/>
     stout hearts and trained arms for the defence 
     <lb/>
     of the inestimable privileges we enjoy as sub<lb break="no"/>jects of the Crown of Britain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of 
     <lb/>
    Assembly.</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     4. The Public Accounts will shortly be 
     <lb/>
     placed before you. The Estimates for the 
     <lb/>
     year will be prepared with as much regard to 
     <lb/>
           

    
            <cb/>
          
     economy as due consideration for the interests 
     <lb/>
     of the country will permit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. President, and Honorable Gentlemen of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Council:</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of 
     <lb/>
     Assembly:</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     5. You will learn with regret that, notwith<lb break="no"/>standing the united efforts of the British North 
     <lb/>
     American Colonies, the Government of the 
     <lb/>
     United States have adhered to their determina<lb break="no"/>tion to abrogate the arrangements for Recipro<lb break="no"/>cal Trade which have for the past eleven years 
     <lb/>
     contributed so largely to the harmony and 
     <lb/>
     commercial prosperity of both the neighboring 
     <lb/>
     Republic and these Colonies; but I am san<lb break="no"/>guine that by mutual aid and co-operation 
     <lb/>
     among the Provinces, and under the fostering 
     <lb/>
     care of the Mother Country, the trade of Bri<lb break="no"/>tish North America may be so directed into 
     <lb/>
     new channels, and our valuable fisheries so 
     <lb/>
     protected, as to meet the emergency thus 
     <lb/>
     forced upon us and avoid any material com<lb break="no"/>mercial inconvenience. The correspondence 
     <lb/>
     upon this subject will be submitted to you. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6. You will be gratified to be informed that 
     <lb/>
     the efforts to represent the products of this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince at the Dublin Exhibition resulted very 
     <lb/>
     favorably—a large number of medals having 
     <lb/>
     been awarded to our exhibitors; and from the 
     <lb/>
     necessity which now exists to make known as 
     <lb/>
     widely as possible the great natural resources 
     <lb/>
     of these Provinces, you will, I doubt not. make 
     <lb/>
     suitable provision for the due representation 
     <lb/>
     of Nova Scotia at the great International Exhi<lb break="no"/>bition to take place in Paris in 1867. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     7. Contracts, based upon the legislation of 
     <lb/>
     last Session, have been entered into during the 
     <lb/>
     recess of Parliament for the extension of the 
     <lb/>
     Railways from Truro to the border of New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick, and from Windsor to Annapolis. 
     <lb/>
     These documents, and the papers connected 
     <lb/>
     therewith, will be laid before you at an early 
     <lb/>day.<lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     8. In accordance with instructions received 
     <lb/>
     from Her Majesty's Government, circulars 
     <lb/>
     were transmitted to the persons in charge of all 
     <lb/>
            <pb n="2" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-02-22_Page_002.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
            
     the Prisons in the Province, making enquiries 
     <lb/>
     as to their condition. These documents, with 
     <lb/>
     the answers to the enquiries made, will be sub<lb break="no"/>mitted for your consideration; and I will be 
     <lb/>
     glad if some means should be devised for the 
     <lb/>
    due inspection of all places of imprisonment, in 
     <lb/>order to promote an improvement in the system 
     <lb/>and uniformity of discipline. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     9. Your attention will also be invited to the 
     <lb/>
     important question of Immigration, in the hope 
     <lb/>
     that a larger number of those seeking a new 
     <lb/>
     home may be made acquainted with the great 
     <lb/>
     advantages which are here offered to industry, 
     <lb/>
     capital, or skill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     10. I confidently hope that, deeply impressed 
     <lb/>
     with the gratitude due to a beneficent Provi<lb break="no"/>dence for the blessings so liberally bestowed 
     <lb/>
     during the past year, your united deliberations 
     <lb/>
     will result in promoting the continued pros<lb break="no"/>perity of this highly favored land. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
     </div>
     <div type="section">      
            
            
     <head rendition="simple:centre">
     THE LUNENBURG ELECTION.</head>
     
           <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName>, upon the return of the House, 
     <lb/>
     proceeded to read His Excellency's speech.— 
     <lb/>
     The Speaker also announced the demise, dur<lb break="no"/>ing the vacation, of Dr. Slocumb, one of the 
     <lb/>
     representatives of Lunenburg, and the issue of 
     <lb/>
     a writ to supply the vacancy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>, by command of His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency, laid on the table of the House,the return 
     <lb/>
     to the writ for the election of a member for the 
     <lb/>
     county of Lunenburg, which was then read, 
     <lb/>
     announcing. the election of Abraham Hebb, 
     <lb/>Esq.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. J. H. ANDERSON</persName> and <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">HON. A. KEITH</persName>, 
     <lb/>
     the Commissioners for administering the oaths, 
     <lb/>
     then took their places, and Mr. Hebb being 
     <lb/>
     introduced by Messrs. Annand and Ray, ad<lb break="no"/>vanced and was sworn in. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
        <p>     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> announced that the usual 
     <lb/>order for the franking privilege had been 
     <lb/>made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
     </div>
           
            <div type="section">
            
     <head rendition="simple:centre">BILL PRO FORMA.</head> 
     <lb/>
            
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. S.MACDONNELL</persName> then asked leave to 
     <lb/>
               introduce <hi rendition="simple:italic">pro forma</hi> a bill entitled " An act for 
     <lb/>
     the patenting of useful inventions." The bill 
     <lb/>
     was read a first time, and ordered' to be read a 
     <lb/>
     second time on a future day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
           
           <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">ANSWER TO THE ADDRESS MOVED.</head> 
   
            

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAMI1">Dr. HAMILTON</persName> said—I rise, Mr. Speaker, for 
     <lb/>
     the purpose of moving the answer to the 
     <lb/>
     speech with which his Excellency the Lieut. 
     <lb/>
     Governor was pleased to open the third session 
     <lb/>
     of the twenty-fourth Parliament of Nova
     <lb/>
     Scotia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Every Novascotian, and especially the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of this House, must feel gratified that 
     <lb/>
     Her Majesty has thought proper to select and 
     <lb/>
    appoint as her representative in this colony, 
     <lb/>one of Nova Scotia's sons, whose talents and 
     <lb/>bravery have won him so distinguished a 
     <lb/>name in the British Empire, not only as the 
     <lb/>heroic defender of Kars, but in other import<lb break="no"/>ant positions. As our Governor, we must feel 
     <lb/>confident that in the exercise of his great 
     <lb/>abilities and practical knowledge, Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>has been placed under the most favorable 
     <lb/>circumstances at this time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     It must be gratifying, too, for His Excellency 
     <lb/>
     to meet the Legislature of this his native 
     <lb/>
     Province under such favorable circumstances, 
     <lb/>
     for I believe never before, in the history of 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia, was every branch of productive 
     <lb/>
     industry in so healthy and flourishing a 
     <lb/>
     condition as at present. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     The returns from the various sources of 
     <lb/>
     revenue, which have been made public, enable 
     <lb/>
     the Government to meet the House with no 
     <lb/>
     demands against the treasury, but, on the 
     <lb/>
     contrary, with a large surplus. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If there is one thing more than another 
     <lb/>
     which should inspire confidence in a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in the management of the public affairs, 
     <lb/>
     it is the fact that the productive industry and 
     <lb/>
     the various sources of wealth are steadily on 
     <lb/>
     the increase. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A full treasury not only enables the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to meet all the existing and necessary 
     <lb/>
     appropriations, but it does more—it enables 
     <lb/>
     them to make provisions for the extension of 
     <lb/>
     the public works and other improvements 
     <lb/>
    which from time to time are required by the 
     <lb/>people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Now, I do not feel disposed, in making these 
     <lb/>
     statements and exhibiting the figures which 
     <lb/>
     will follow, to attribute all the increase in the 
     <lb/>
     trade, commerce, navigation, agricultural pro<lb break="no"/>duce, fisheries, mines and minerals, &amp;c., to the 
     <lb/>
     management of the gentlemen who compose 
     <lb/>
     the present government, but this much I may 
     <lb/>
     say, that just in so far as the people have con<lb break="no"/>fidence in the integrity, practical ability and 
     <lb/>
     good intentions ot' those gentlemen. so far do 
     <lb/>
     people feel security in entering into the 
     <lb/>
     prosecution of those various sources of industry 
     <lb/>
     and trade, which result in the enjoyment not 
     <lb/>
     only of all the luxuries of life, but in the in<lb break="no"/>crease and extension of the productive sources 
     <lb/>
     of wealth. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I believe in every department from which re<lb break="no"/>turns are collected, the increase over previous 
     <lb/>
     years is remarkable, and as far as the produc<lb break="no"/>tive resources of our Province are concerned, 
     <lb/>
     viz., the fisheries, agriculture, mines, minerals, 
     <lb/>
     and other departments they are all equally in 
     <lb/>
     a healthy and flourishing condition. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A few facts and comparisons might not be 
     <lb/>
     amiss, and while I do not feel disposed to make 
     <lb/>
     any invidious comparison with former govern<lb break="no"/>ments under different parties, I must be per<lb break="no"/>mitted to refer to a few figures to illustrate 
     <lb/>
     the progress which has been made and first let. 
     <lb/>
     us take the exports of Nova Scotia— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     In 1860, under the management of our prede<lb break="no"/>cessors, the whole exports amounted to 
            </p>
              
              <table>
<row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$6,619,534</cell></row> 
                 <row><cell>While, in 1865, they were no less than</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">8,830,633</hi></cell></row> 
<row><cell>Being an increase of no less than</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">$2,211,099</cell></row> 
              </table>
   
            <p>
     If there can be any doubt about the state of 
     <lb/>
     our country in this respect, a reference to her 
     <lb/>
     exports will prove her prosperity, and the great 
     <lb/>
     increase for the last six years shows pretty 
     <lb/>
     plainly that Nova Scotia is progressing in her 
     <lb/>
     productive capabilities most rapidly, and we 
     <lb/>
     must certainly hope it may long continue. I 
     <lb/>
     might mention that during the years 1861-62-63; 
     <lb/>
     the exports of the Province fell off no less than 
     <lb/>
     $1,242,169. so that the increase has been most 
     <lb/>
     rapid. amounting, since 1862, to no less a sum 
     <lb/>
     than $3,153,672. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     These very large exports and imports pro<lb break="no"/>duce a trade from which a large revenue is col<lb break="no"/>lected, and as far as the Government and the re<lb break="no"/>presentatives of the people are concerned, noth<lb break="no"/>ing is more gratifying than to have a large sur<lb break="no"/>plus revenue to return to the people in the 
     <lb/>
     shape of grants for roads and bridges, schools 
     <lb/>
     and navigation securities, and which also en [...]
            </p>
         </div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>