<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1865-04-11"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-04-11">11 April 1865</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          
         
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Second Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1865"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          


          <biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="221"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_217.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_218.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_219.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_220.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_221.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-21">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_217">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_217.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_218">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_218.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_219">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_219.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_220">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_220.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_221">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_221.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="217" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_217.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</fw> <fw type="num">217</fw>

<!-- GL, 2017-03-15, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

           <!-- <p> ment of
New Brunswick, though on this latter<lb/>
point I am not prepared to express any opi<lb break="no"/>nion.</p>
            <p>But suppose
the government of New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick is not prepared to concur in Union of the<lb/>
Maritime Provinces, it was desirable that that<lb/>
point should be definitely known, and the<lb/>
public mind be no longer distracted with the<lb/>
consideration of that question.<lb/>
By this resolution the government will be <lb/>
authorized to open negotiations, and see what<lb/>
prospect there is of obtaining a legislative<lb/>
union with that province. The opponents of<lb/>
Confederation here have professed to be in fa<lb break="no"/>vour of the Union of the Maritime Provinces,<lb/>
and as far as I have an opportunity of know<lb break="no"/>ing that has been the view of some of the op<lb break="no"/>ponents of Confederation in New Brunswick.<lb/>
Whatever view, therefore, this house may take<lb/>
of the larger question of a Union of British<lb/>
North America, I trust they will sustain the <lb/>
resolution now submitted to their consideration.</p>-->

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, APRIL 11</head>

            <p>House met at 3 o'clock.</p>

</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">THE SCHOOL BILL.</head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon PROV. SEC</persName>. moved the third reading of<lb/> the bill "For the
                  better encouragement of edu<lb break="no"/>cation."</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LOCK1">Hon. Mr. LOCKE</persName> opposed the principle of as<lb break="no"
                  />sessment as most obnoxious to the people, and<lb/> moved a resolution to this
                  effect: -</p>
            <p>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Whereas</hi>, the system of direct taxation for the <lb/>
support of schools has been condemned by and<lb/>
is obnoxious to the wishes of the people of this<lb/>
Province, and instead of promoting had retard<lb break="no"/>ed the progress of education;</p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Therefore Resolved</hi>, That this bill be
referred <lb/>
back to committee for the purpose of striking<lb/>
out so much thereof as establishes that princi<lb break="no"/>ple, and that there should be substituted there<lb break="no"/>for clauses provinding for subscriptions or con<lb break="no"/>tributions by fees to supplement the propos<lb break="no"/>es grant for the support of schools.</p>
   <p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. said that the resolution ask<lb break="no"/>ed
                  the house to stultify itself and to resort to<lb/> an old system which had been
                  tried and found<lb/> inadequate. He hoped a majority would not <lb/> be found, for
                  party purposes, willing to adopt<lb/> such a course.</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LOCK1">Mr. LOCKE</persName> disavowed all party feeling in<lb/> the matterm and
                  expressed the opinion that the<lb/> present law had retarded education and
                  closed<lb/> one half the schools. He thought the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture had
                  no right to meddle with the pockets<lb/> of the people as the bill proposed.</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. ATTY. GEN</persName>. said he had yet to learn<lb/> that the people
                  were willing to go back to the <lb/> old system which had been abandoned last<lb/>
                  year by a vote of nine-tenths of the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture. For years past
                  all parties had acknow<lb break="no"/>ledged its inadequacy to meet the
                  requirements<lb/> of the country, and the necessity of an im<lb break="no"/>proved
                  system of education. Notwithstanding<lb/> all the difficulties that naturally
                  arose in put<lb break="no"/>ting into operation a bill new to the people, the<lb/>
                  results on the whole had been satisfactory and <lb/> encouraging. Under all the
                  circumstances, it<lb/> was absurd for the hon. gentleman to ask the<lb/> house to
                  go back to a system which had been<lb/> condemned by nine-tenths of the members
                  last <lb/> year.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> made a few remarks in sup<lb break="no"/>port of
                  the principle of assessment, which had<lb/> been advocated by leading minds in the
                  House <cb/> and country for many years. He would not<lb/> support a resolution
                  which went to establish a<lb/> principle which he felt was unsuited to the<lb/>
                  public requirements, and was condemned by a <lb/> large majority last winter. The
                  bill of last<lb/> year was objectionable in many respects, but<lb/> the object of
                  the present measure was to re<lb break="no"/>move many of the injurious features
                  of the for<lb break="no"/>mer, and place education on a more satisfac<lb
                     break="no"/>tory basis. - Some details he strongly objected<lb/> to still, but
                  of its vital principle he approved.</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. STEWART CAMPELL</persName> said that the ques<lb break="no"/>tion as to
                  whether the rejection of the assess<lb break="no"/>ment principle would destroy
                  the bill, and em<lb break="no"/>barrass the Government, was not the point to<lb/>
                  be considered at all. What they were called<lb/> upon to ascertain was whether
                  that principle<lb/> was in accordance with the feelings and wish<lb break="no"/>es
                  of the country. If it was, then let it be ac<lb break="no"/>cepted; but if not,
                  irrespective of any party<lb/> considerations whatever. He differed entirely<lb/>
                  from the hon. Provincial Secretary, when he <lb/> said that they would stultify
                  themselves<lb/> by rejecting the assessment clause; on the con<lb break="no"
                  />trary, he thoughthat it would be the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment that stultified
                  themselves when they call<lb break="no"/>ed upon the house to pass a measure which
                  for<lb/> the last twelve months had received universal<lb/> condemnation
                  throughout the country. The<lb/> hon. Provincial Secretary stated that the
                  house<lb/> had already acted upon this principle. That<lb/> vote was taken in a
                  thin house, when fifteen<lb/> gentlemen recorded their votes against it, and<lb/>
                  eighteen for it: and he believed that if they<lb/> were not influened by pressure
                  since brought<lb/> to bear, the majority would be the other way.<lb/> He denied
                  that the bill of last year had been a <lb/> success in the country. Even admitting
                  that in<lb/> some populous districts it had met with support,<lb/> that was no
                  answer to the fact that the large<lb/> majority of districts lying outside of
                  these were<lb/> deprived of the meand of education altogether.<lb/> He disclaimed
                  all idea in opposing this bill, of<lb/> wishing to embarrass the government. If
                  it<lb/> had that effect, they had brought it on their<lb/> own heads. He opposed
                  it because he knew<lb/> it to be obnoxious to his constituents. If it was <lb/> a
                  good bill, he called upon the government to<lb/> appeal to the peopl and allow
                  them to pass<lb/> their judgment upon it; but he did not think<lb/> that ever they
                  believed that it was in accor<lb break="no"/>dance with the wishes of the people.
                  He call<lb break="no"/>ed upon gentlemen opposite to record their <lb/> opinions
                  upon this question, according to their<lb/> own convictions and what they knew was
                  the<lb/> feeling of the country. He did not think that<lb/> it was the duty of any
                  gentlemen, however<lb/> much they might desire to sustain the govern<lb break="no"
                  />ment, to perpetuate a system so obnoxious to<lb/> the people.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p>The assertion of the hon. Atty. Gen., that
<lb/>
education was in a better position now than<lb/>
under the old law, had been so often refuted<lb/>
that he would not take up time by alluding to<lb/>
it now. The petitions upon the table shewed<lb/>
the contrary; and it would have been better<lb/>
for the government to have paid some regard<lb/>
to them, rather than pass them by unnoticed.</p>
            <p>The hon'ble gentleman concluded by calling
<lb/>
upon gentlemen opposite to act independently<lb/>
and fearlessly upon this question - their duty<lb/>
to their constituents should be their considera<lb break="no"/>tion - that to the Government was only secon<lb break="no"/>dary. He would rather always remain in op<lb break="no"/>position than be a slave to any Government.<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="218" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_218.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">218</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>
            
<p> Was this a time, he would ask, to force
an <lb/>
obnoxious measure upon the people of this <lb/>
country—a time, if we could
believe the opin<lb break="no"/>ions of gentlemen opposite—when danger is <lb/>
threatened—and it was therefore
of more than <lb/>
ordinary importance that the affection and con<lb break="no"/>fidence of the people should be reposed in the <lb/>
Government of the day. Let us then encour<lb break="no"/>age these feelings—let us have
willing hearts <lb/>
as well as hands to defend us, and although <lb/>
our numbers may be few—and the danger <lb/>
great—he believed that there was
sufficient <lb/>
courage, energy and spirit in the people of this <lb/>
country to sustain them in the hour of need. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BLAN2">Mr. BLANCHARD</persName> did not intend to have ad<lb break="no"
                  />dressed the House, but the question having <lb/> assumed such proportions, he
                  felt it his duty to <lb/> offer a few observations. This question of as<lb
                     break="no"/>sessment for the support of schools was by no <lb/> means a new
                  one. Upon looking back to the <lb/> Journals of 1856, he found that the subject
                  was <lb/> debated in the House and the following resolu<lb break="no"/>tions were
                  then moved :- <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>" Whereas the principle of assessment is
the <lb/>
only permanent foundation for the common <lb/>
school education of the country, and as this <lb/>
principle is the leading feature of
the measure <lb/>
now under consideration and the details may <lb/>
be modified and improved,- <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" Resolved, therefore, that the bill
entitled <lb/>
an act for the better encouragement of educa<lb break="no"/>tion be referred to a select committee with in<lb break="no"/>structions to consider the same, and report <lb/>
thereon at a future day.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> " For the motion thirty-seven against it
nine." <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The men whose names he found recorded in <lb/>
favor of that resolution he had
been accus<lb break="no"/>tomed from his boyhood to look up to with re<lb break="no"/>spect and esteem; and when that resolution <lb/>
was carried it met with his hearty approval. <lb/>
From his earliest recollections, he had been <lb/>
educated in the belief that the principle of as<lb break="no"/>sessment was the only correct one; and in sup<lb break="no"/>porting it now he certainly could not be sus<lb break="no"/>pected of being a slave to the Government.<lb/>
He was sorry that he was
compelled to differ <lb/>
from those for whose opinions he had always <lb/>
entertained the highest respect; but he
felt <lb/>
that he would be recreant to the duty he owed <lb/>
to the country, and to the opinions he always <lb/>
entertained, if he voted for the resolution of <lb/>
the hon. member for Shelburne. He was not <lb/>
disposed now to enter into an argument to <lb/>
prove that assessment was the
true principle. <lb/>
This had been proved so often that it was
un<lb break="no"/>necessary. When this principle was intro<lb break="no"/>duced into the bill of last year,
he told the hon. <lb/>
Prov. Sec. that if it was founded upon the pro<lb break="no"/>per basis, he would give his assistance in car<lb break="no"/>rying it out. He thought that the time had <lb/>
come when the principle should be fairly tried, <lb/>
and he now felt that if he voted
for the reso<lb break="no"/>lution before the house, he would be
taking a <lb/>
step in a backward direction. At the same <lb/>
time, he must not be understood as giving his <lb/>
entire approval to the whole bill,—there
were <lb/>
many objectionable features in
it, which he <lb/>
had done his best to remove. For instance, <lb/>
the construction—of the Council of Public In<lb break="no"/>struction was particularly
obnoxious to him ; <lb/>
but this feature he could not
object to. He did <lb/>
not support it with a view of assisting the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, but because he felt it was the only <lb/>
sound basis upon which the common school <lb/>
system of the country should rest.
<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BLAC7">Mr. BLACKWOOD</persName> said that there were many  <cb/> clauses of this
                  bill exceedingly objectionable to <lb/> him, and none more so than the mode in
                  which <lb/> the Council of Public Instruction was constitu<lb break="no"/>ted. He
                  should have been very glad if that had <lb/> been re-considered, or at all events
                  remodelled, <lb/> so as to remove some of its objectionable fea<lb break="no"
                  />tures. But, as regards the feature of the bill <lb/> now under consideration, he
                  felt called upon to <lb/> sustain it, for he was convinced that, when pro<lb
                     break="no"/>perly carried out, it was the only proper basis <lb/> upon which
                  the common school system of the <lb/> country should rest. He was sorry that he
                  <lb/> was obliged to differ with his friend the mem<lb break="no"/>ber for
                  Shelburne; but he could not consistent<lb break="no"/>ly vote for his motion
                  without acting contrary <lb/> to the opinions he had always entertained. He <lb/>
                  did not support the measure with the view of <lb/> assisting the Government—for he
                  would scorn <lb/> to bolster up any Government by supporting <lb/> them in
                  carrying out what he did not believe <lb/> was for the interests of the whole
                  country. He <lb/> wished, then, in giving his vote for the measure, <lb/> to put
                  himself right before the house and his <lb/> constituents—and to let them
                  understand that, <lb/> in the course he was taking, he was not sus<lb break="no"
                  />taining a Government—but a principle, which <lb/> he believed was calculated to
                  benetit the cause <lb/> of education. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. JOST</persName> had already stated that he was op<lb break="no"
                  />posed to the principle of compulsory taxation. <lb/> He wished the matter to be
                  left in the hands of <lb/> the people. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. BILL</persName> said that the house was aware that <lb/> he had
                  presented petitions signed by many <lb/> hundreds of persons against assessment
                  for the <lb/> support of schools. It was a system that look<lb break="no"/>ed very
                  well upon paper, but it was not so easy <lb/> to carry it out. When he made up his
                  mind to <lb/> vote for assessment, he was at the same time <lb/> determined to
                  vote for separate schools, for he <lb/> did not think it just to have the one
                  without the <lb/> other. He regretted very much that he felt it <lb/> his duty to
                  support the resolution. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:KILL2">Mr. KILLAM</persName> said that it was evident that the <lb/> system of
                  county assessment proposed by the <lb/> bill would not give the amount required
                  for the <lb/> support of the schools—and they would have to <lb/> raise the
                  balance by subscriptions from the <lb/> people. He objected in committee to the
                     prin<lb break="no"/>ciple upon which the bill distributes the public <lb/>
                  money, and he should vote for the resolution <lb/> before the house. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p> A call of the house was had.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CAMP4">Mr. C. J. CAMPBELL</persName> said that it was clearly <lb/> understood
                  when this bill was sent to commit<lb break="no"/>tee that no one was committed to
                  the principle. <lb/> He was glad it was not going to be made a <lb/> party
                  question, as it left it open to the support<lb break="no"/>ers of the Government
                  to take an independent <lb/> course. He agreed with the member for Kings, <lb/>
                  that, if they had direct taxation, they must <lb/> have seperate schools. He
                  though, if they were <lb/> going to have free Schools, the better plan <lb/> would
                  be to appropriate the surplus revenne in <lb/> the Provincial chest for their
                  support, and, if <lb/> that was not enough, he did not think the peo<lb break="no"
                  />ple would object to an increase of the advalo<lb break="no"/>rem duties. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:ROSS10">Mr. Ross</persName>, in reference to a statement made <lb/>
on a previous evening by the Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary, that there were 62 schools
in operation in <lb/>
Victoria county, said that he was not in a posi<lb break="no"/>tion to contradict him then,
but he had tele<lb break="no"/>graphed down to the county, and had
received <lb/>
an answer that there were only 27. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SECY</persName>. said that his information <lb/>
                  <pb n="219" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_219.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">219</fw> was derived from the report of the Superinten<lb
                     break="no"/>dent of Education. He did not say that 62 <lb/> schools were in
                  operation, but that 62 school <lb/> sections had organized under the law. He had
                  <lb/> listened with some surprise to the style of ar<lb break="no"/>gument used by
                  the member for Guysborough. <lb/> He had listened to rather extraordinary ap<lb
                     break="no"/>peals in that house, and had seen great liber<lb break="no"/>ties
                  taken with hon. gentlemen, but he had ne<lb break="no"/>ver heard of such a
                  liberty as that which had <lb/> just been taken by the member for Guysbo<lb
                     break="no"/>rough with the gentlemen who supported the <lb/> Governmentt.
                  He(Mr.C.)could not say that the <lb/> principle of assessment was bad, for hehad
                     af<lb break="no"/>firmed it over and over again, but he called <lb/> upon hon.
                  gentlemen to vote against the bill <lb/> from the small, paltry consideration of
                  losing <lb/> a few votes among their constituents. <lb/>
               </p>

   
            <p> He did
not consider the present position of <lb/>
the cause of education in this
country, nor <lb/>
what was due to the people he represented;
<lb/>
but he called upon hon. gentlemen to consider <lb/>
only what was due to themselves, and from <lb/>
personal motives to defeat a measure designed <lb/>
to improve the common school system of the<lb/>
country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>He (the
Pro. Sec.) would ask whether this <lb/>
was a dignified or honorable position to occupy
<lb/>
—to call upon gentlemen on that side of the <lb/>
house to abandon a government that had had <lb/>
the courage to grapple with a
great question, <lb/>
which they knew was fraught with
great dan<lb break="no"/>ger, but which they felt the
best interests of <lb/>
the country demanded should be dealt with at <lb/>
their hands? He did not envy that
hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman the position he occupied, and he should <lb/>
look with interest at the
division, to see how <lb/>
many would be guided by his advice.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. STEWART CAMPBELL</persName> said that the hon. <lb/> Provincial
                  Secretary had expressed surprise at <lb/> his moving a call of the house. His
                  reason was <lb/> plain; three or four gentlemen who had ex<lb break="no"/>pressed
                  themselves opposed to the bill had <lb/> been about the house all day; but where
                  were <lb/> they now? His object was to bring every man <lb/> here to record his
                  vote, as it was his duty to <lb/> do. The hon. Pro. Sec. had taken exception to
                  <lb/> the appeal he had made to the house. He <lb/> thought that when the house
                  remembered the <lb/> appeal that hon. gentleman once made to the <lb/> house and
                  the country on the subject of re<lb break="no"/>trenchment—an appeal which it is
                  true achiev<lb break="no"/>ed its purpose and gave him power,—a power <lb/> he did
                  not envy him, when gained by such un<lb break="no"/>worthy means—they would agree
                  with him <lb/> that he was the last man to criticise the mo<lb break="no"/>tives
                  of any hon. gentleman in that house. </p>
            <p>The question was then taken upon Mr. Chas.
<lb/>
Campbell's amendment, which was
lost by a <lb/>
large majority. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Locke's motion was then put, and lost <lb/>
by a vote of 30 to 16.  <lb/>
            </p>
 
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">For</hi>—Messrs.
Heffernan, Ross, Hatfield, Kil<lb break="no"/>lam, Ray, Bill,
Miller, C. J. Campbell, Robert<lb break="no"/>son, Locke, Bourinot, Stewart
Campbell, Cald<lb break="no"/>well, Robichau, Coffin, Balcam—16.  <lb/>
            </p>
 
            <p> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Against</hi>—D. Fraser, Shannon, Tobin, Donkin, <lb/>
Hill, Longley, McFarlane, McKay, King,
Law<lb break="no"/>rence, Allison, Pryor, Parker, Whitman,
Kaul<lb break="no"/>back, Moore, Hamilton, Pro. Sec., J. Fraser, J. <lb/>
Campbell, McLelan, Blackwood, Atty.
Gen., <lb/>
Blanchard, Annand, Cowie, Mckinnon, C. J. <lb/>
Campbell, Fin. Sec., Archibald—30. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> moved that the bill be re<lb break="no"
                  />committed for the purpose of striking out the <cb/> clause relating to the
                  Council of Public In<lb break="no"/>struction and substituting the following:
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>" The Governor may appoint not
more than <lb/>
nine and not less than
seven persons, of whom <lb/>
the Superintendent of Education shall be one,
<lb/>
to be a Council of Public
Instruction, and such  <lb/>
persons shall hold their office during pleasure, <lb/>
and shall be subject to all lawful orders and <lb/>
directions, in the exercise of their duties which <lb/>
may from time to time be issued by the Go<lb break="no"/>vernor in Council." <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On the question being taken, there appeared <lb/>
for it 16 against 29. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>For:—Ross, Parker, Heffernan, Ray, Bill,
<lb/>
Blanchard, Locke, McLelan, Blackwood,
Ro<lb break="no"/>bertson, S. Campbell, Annand, Archibald, <lb/>
Coffin, Balcam, Robichau—16. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Against:—C. J. Campbell, Hill, Bourinot, <lb/>
Longley, Tobin, Killam, McFarlane, McKay, <lb/>
Hatfield, Lawrence, Hatfield, D.
Fraser, Whit<lb break="no"/>man, Kaulback, Moore, Hamilton, Miller, J. <lb/>
Campbell, Donkin, Prov. Secretary, Caldwell, <lb/>
King, Cowie, Colin Campbell, McKinnon, Fin. <lb/>
Secretary, Shannon, Atty. General—29. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. BILL</persName> moved the following amendment: <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>" Resolved—That thss bill be re-committed <lb/>
for the purpose of amending the
second section <lb/>
thereof, so as to include the Lieut. Governor
<lb/>
for the time being, in the Council of Public <lb/>
Instruction, and that he be the head thereof." <lb/>
            </p>
   <p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. felt it his duty to say, that <lb/> he had good
                  reason for believing that the <lb/> Lieut. Governor entertained the strongest
                     ob<lb break="no"/>jection to occupy the position contemplated by <lb/> this
                  amendment.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. BILL</persName> was rather surprised at this, for he <lb/> was under
                  the impression that his Excellency, <lb/> wished to identify himself with the
                  education <lb/> of the country. In a speech which he deliver<lb break="no"/>ed at
                  a banquet last summer to the Canadian <lb/> Delegates, he expressed himself to
                  that effect, <lb/> and said that he considered it not only his duty <lb/> but his
                  privilege to take an interest in the edu<lb break="no"/>cational system of the
                  country. The senti<lb break="no"/>ments he then expressed met with the cordial
                  <lb/> approval of thousands of the intelligent people <lb/> of this country; and
                  with the permission of <lb/> the house he would read an extract from it. <lb/> The
                  hon. gentleman then read as follows:- <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>" It would afford me great satisfaction were <lb/>
I to realize in the future course of my admi<lb break="no"/>nistration one-half of what the Provincial Sec. <lb/>
has ventured to anticipate. Whatever I might <lb/>
wish to effect
or whatever an individual <lb/>
might hope to accomplish is nothing in com<lb break="no"/>parison to that which a free and intelligent <lb/>
people
have it in their own power to accom<lb break="no"/>plish for themselves. I have had some experi<lb break="no"/>ence,
gentlemen, in public affairs, and have at
<lb/>
all events been able to learn
this during my <lb/>
term of office,
that there is no greater mistake <lb/>
in governing than governing too much. In a <lb/>
country like this a Governor must rely on his <lb/>
Ministry and on the people, whose
representa<lb break="no"/>tives they are, if he hopes to effect an real <lb/>
public benefit; yet whilst he
looks to the Minis<lb break="no"/>try and to the people for
assistance it is his <lb/>
duty
to aid, by every means in his power, the <lb/>
development of the intellect and
education of <lb/>
the country." <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> He felt that this was rather a
delicate sub<lb break="no"/>ject to treat upon, and he was under the im<lb break="no"/>pression  that he had only to mention it, when
<lb/>
it would be at once agreed to. He was at a  <lb/>
loss to understand what objections his Excel<lb break="no"/>lency could have to be connected with the<lb/>
        


            <pb n="220" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_220.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">220</fw>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>
          
Council of Public Instruction, and he
regretted <lb/>
it exceedingly as he thought his presence there, <lb/>
and the benefit of his experience would be of <lb/>
great value to the deliberations of that body. <lb/>
He would not press the matter
any further, as <lb/>
the Prov. Sec. had stated that it would be dis<lb break="no"/>tasteful to the feelings of his Excellency, and <lb/>
he would therefore withdraw his motion. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. trusted that the hon. gentle<lb break="no"
                  />man would withdraw his motion, and not put <lb/> the Government in the
                  unpleasant position of <lb/> having to vote against it. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> expressed his regret to hear <lb/> the
                  statement made by the Prov. Sec., that his <lb/> Excellency had expressed his
                  unwillingness to <lb/> be connected with the Council of Public In<lb break="no"
                  />struction. He looked upon his presence there <lb/> as a matter of
                  greatimportanee, but after what <lb/> the Prov. Sec. had stated, the member for
                  <lb/> Kings had done right in withhrawing his mo <lb/> tion. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BLAN2">Mr. BLANCHARD</persName> moved that the bill be re<lb break="no"
                  />committed for the purpose of striking out cer<lb break="no"/>tain clauses
                  relating to the City of Halifax, a re<lb break="no"/>solution had been placed in
                  his hands which had <lb/> been passed by the City Council by a vote of 10 <lb/> to
                  5, and altho he did not agree with it in all its <lb/> points, he thought the
                  house ought to pay pro<lb break="no"/>per respect to the voice of the City as
                  heard <lb/> through its representatives. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p> The hon. gentleman read the resolution
from <lb/>
the City Council as follows:- <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That that portion of the
school bill <lb/>
which specially relates to the City of Halifax <lb/>
is arbitrary in the principle of compulsory <lb/>
assessment, and is inapplicable to the circum<lb break="no"/>stances of the City of Halifax,—and
this <lb/>
Council representing the various wards of the <lb/>
City protest against its passage through the <lb/>
Legislature." <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> When it was considered that the City <lb/>
Council, elected by the citizens and repre<lb break="no"/>senting their interests were refused power <lb/>
by the house to tax the people for the pur<lb break="no"/>chase of what they considered valuable <lb/>
property, it was no wonder that they com<lb break="no"/>plained that the power of taxation for <lb/>
the erection of school houses, should be <lb/>
taken away from them, and vested in irres<lb break="no"/>ponsible commissioners. He would
ask the <lb/>
house whether they were prepared to place in <lb/>
the hands of those men uncontrolled powers <lb/>
to tax the people for the erection of school <lb/>
houses in each ward of the city. Not only <lb/>
was this objectionable feature in the bill, but <lb/>
the necessary consequence of the passage of <lb/>
these clauses would be the establishment of <lb/>
separate schools in the City of Halifax. There <lb/>
were two denominations prepared to come in <lb/>
and take advantage of these clauses in the <lb/>
bill, the Episcopalians and the Roman Catholics <lb/>
—and there were no other
denominations in a <lb/>
position to do so. He did not wish to make <lb/>
any invidious remarks in reference to these <lb/>
two denominations. It was greatly to their <lb/>
credit that they had erected handsome school <lb/>
houses, but that was no reason why they <lb/>
should come in and monopolize
the public <lb/>
moneys to the exclusion of all
other bodies. <lb/>
He did not see why the city should be placed <lb/>
upon a different footing from the rest of the <lb/>
province, and why it should be allowed to <lb/>
elect its own Trustees, with uncontrolled pow<lb break="no"/>ers of taxation. As he before remarked the <lb/>
taxation of the city was
increasing to an <lb/>
alarming extent, and he was surprise at the <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
          
 silence of the representatives for the
city, who <lb/>
were more immediately interested
in the sub<lb break="no"/>ject.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SHAN2">Hon. Mr. SHANNON</persName> said that the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber
                  for Inverness seemed anxious that his own <lb/> constituents and the people far
                  away should <lb/> be taxed, and he himself escape. Now, as re<lb break="no"/>gards
                  the position of the city of Halifax, they <lb/> had had a law on the statute book
                  for years <lb/> which had never been carried out; and his ob<lb break="no"/>ject
                  was to get a law that could be carried out. <lb/> This bill had been for sometime
                  before the <lb/> house and the country, and where were the pe<lb break="no"
                  />titions from the city against it? Not one. It <lb/> was true that the City
                  Council were now mov<lb break="no"/>ing in the matter, but they did not object to
                  <lb/> any particular clause of the bill, their resolu<lb break="no"/>tion is
                  against the whole bill. If they had said <lb/> they objected to the mode of
                  appointment of <lb/> trustees, he could have understood them, but <lb/> they went
                  against the whole principle of assess<lb break="no"/>ment. He could not understand
                  the force of <lb/> the remarks of the member for Inverness as to <lb/> separate
                  schools. The congregation of St. <lb/> Luke's had an admirable school house. If an
                  <lb/> arrangement could be made with them—not to <lb/> hand over the school monies
                  to the Dean and <lb/> Chapter, but to get them to hand over the <lb/> school house
                  to the Council of Public Instruc<lb break="no"/>tion for a free school, he did not
                  see what ob<lb break="no"/>jection there could be; and so with the Roman <lb/>
                  Catholics, who were about erecting a handsome <lb/> school house, and so with the
                  National school, <lb/> and others in the different wards; if they could <lb/> be
                  obtained no great necessity would exist for <lb/> taxation for the erection of
                  school houses. He <lb/> was not at all afraid of this bugbear of separ<lb
                     break="no"/>ate schools—raised by the member for In<lb break="no"/>verness.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BLAN2">Mr. BLANCHARD</persName> denied that he made any <lb/> such statement as
                  that his constituents might <lb/> be taxed, while the citizens of Halifax should
                  <lb/> go free. He said that taxation was heavy <lb/> enough already, in Halifax,
                  and he was not <lb/> willing to give uncontrolled powers to persons <lb/>
                  responsible to nobody. He was not afraid to <lb/> give his constituents power to
                  tax themselves, <lb/> but the member for Halifax appeared to be so. <lb/> The hon.
                  gentleman says this idea of separate <lb/> schools is only a bug-bear; and he
                  talks about <lb/> St. Luke's, and the Roman Catholics handing <lb/> their school
                  houses over to the Council of <lb/> Public Instruction. Does anybody believe <lb/>
                  that the Dean and Chapter of St. Luke's <lb/> would hand over their handsome
                  school <lb/> houses, without retaining the power to control <lb/> the school? or
                  that the Roman Catholics <lb/> would hand over theirs without retaining the <lb/>
                  appointment of the teachers? He thought not. <lb/> If they were going to have
                  separate schools, <lb/> let them say so at once; but don't let it be <lb/> done in
                  such an underhand way. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName> should vote against Mr. Blan<lb break="no"
                  />chard's motion for the very reasons he had <lb/> given in its favor. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> hoped that the hon. member <lb/> would not press
                  his motion. This subject <lb/> should be approached with delicacy and mode<lb
                     break="no"/>ration; and unless each one was prepared to <lb/> give way, to a
                  certain extent, to the other, it <lb/> would be impossible to carry out the
                  system. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. PRYOR</persName> said he gave his cordial support <lb/> to the
                  clauses in the bill relating to the city of <lb/> Halifax, and he was prepared to
                  take the <lb/> responsibility of the course he had pursued. <lb/>
               </p>
            <pb n="221" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-11_Page_221.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">221</fw>
           

 <p> He wished to give the system a fair trial, and <lb/>
if it did not succeed, it could be altered. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BLAN2">Mr. BLANCHARD</persName> under the circumstances <lb/> withdrew his
                  motion. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:LEVE1">Mr. LE VESCONTE</persName> moved the clause which <lb/> he had read on a
                  previous day as to the rights <lb/> of minorities—which was lost—31 to 8. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">For</hi>.—Miller,
Bill, LeVesconte, McDonnell, <lb/>
Tobin, McKinnon, Robichau, Caldwell—8. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Against</hi>.—John
Campbell, Pryor, Moore, D. <lb/>
Fraser, McFarlane, C. J. Campbell, Black<lb break="no"/>wood, Hamilton, Allison,
Laurence, Ray, Par<lb break="no"/>ker, McKay, Chipman, Kaulback, Hill, Long-
<lb break="yes"/>
ley, Donkin, Prov. Secy., Blanchard, S. Camp<lb break="no"/>bell, Annand, Balcom, Ross, Robertson, Shan<lb break="no"/>nan, Locke, Finl. Secy., Cowie, Archibald. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. STEWART CAMPBELL</persName> moved that the <lb/> bill be deferred to
                  that day three months. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:LEVE1">Mr. LEVESCONTE</persName>, although opposed to the <lb/> bill, should
                  vote against this motion, as it <lb/> would be ten times worse to go back to the
                  <lb/> bill now on the statute book. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName> wished to remove a misappre<lb break="no"/>hension
                  upon that subject. It did not at all <lb/> follow, that if they rejected this bill
                  they must <lb/> fall back upon the old law. A measure might <lb/> be framed in
                  consonance with the wishes and <lb/> feelings of the people. The hon. gentleman
                  <lb/> commented upon the bill of last session at <lb/> some length, and argued
                  that by amendments <lb/> it had been stripped of a great many of its ob<lb
                     break="no"/>noxious features, and was not at all the bill <lb/> as originally
                  introduced. Therefore it was <lb/> not right for the hon. gentleman to say, that
                  <lb/> the house had only the option of accepting this <lb/> bill, or being driven
                  back to the obnoxious <lb/> bill of last session. The hon. gentleman reca<lb
                     break="no"/>pitulated the reasons why he should be com<lb break="no"/>pelled to
                  vote against this bill upon its third <lb/> reading.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. ATTY. GENL</persName>. contended that the <lb/> clauses relating to
                  the city of Halifax, were <lb/> totally inapplicable to thinly settled districts.
                  <lb/> The principle might be carried out in the more <lb/> populous districts,
                  where the different deno<lb break="no"/>minations had school houses of their own.
                  <lb/> The hon. gentleman referred to the fact that, <lb/> in Nova Scotia, no
                  distinction was made be<lb break="no"/>tween any sect or creed, and he hoped that
                  <lb/> none would ever seek for any preference. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p> After some further
slight discussion, the <lb/>
question was taken upon Mr. Stewart
Camp<lb break="no"/>bell's motion—to defer the Bill
for 3 months- <lb/>which was lost, 20 to 8. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">For</hi>.—Killam,
Heffernan, Parker, Ray, Hat<lb break="no"/>field, Miller, S. Campbell, Balcom—8. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Against</hi>.—D.
Fraser, Shannon, Atty. Genl.,
<lb/>
Donkin, Le Vesconte, Finl. Sec. Colin Camp<lb break="no"/>bell, Lawrence, J. Campbell, McKay,
Allison, <lb/>
Moore, Whitman, Kaulback, Longley, Prov. <lb/>
Secy., Hill, McKinnon, Tobin, Cowie—20. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. STEWART CAMPBELL</persName> gave notice to re<lb break="no"/>scind.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. Prov. SEC</persName>. expressed his astonishment <lb/> that after
                  having had a call of the house, he <lb/> should persist in a notice to rescind.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. STEWART CAMPBELL</persName> replied that he <lb/> did so because not
                  half of the house was pre<lb break="no"/>sent. <lb/>
               </p>
   <p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. Prov. SECY</persName>. moved that the bill be <lb/> read a third time
                  and finally pass. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p> Some discussion then ensued upon a
ques<lb break="no"/>tion of order, as to whether
that motion could <lb/>
be put—pending the notice to rescind. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Speaker took time to consider. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The house
adjourned until the next day at<lb/>
o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-03-15, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<milestone type="unknown"/> 
            <p>WEDNESDAY, Apri1 12. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
The house met at 3 o'clock.  <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Mr. LEVESCONTE, chairman of the commit<lb break="no"/>tee on fisheries, reported.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. TOBIN would like to know whether the <lb/>
committee had considered a subject which had <lb/>
been brought to their notice by petitions from <lb/>
Margaret's Bay, relative to the practice
of <lb/>
setting seines; and whether they had suggest<lb break="no"/>ed any remedy for the grievance complained of. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. LEVESCONTE said the committee had <lb/>
carefully considered the subject, but could not <lb/>
arrive at any definite conclusion.
They found <lb/>
it impossible to divise a law applicable to the <lb/>
whole Province.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. SHANNON enquired if any action, had <lb/>
been taken as regards the trawl
fishery. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. LEVESCONTE said that there was not <lb/>
sufficient information before the committee to <lb/>
warrant them to interfere.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. TOBIN alluded to the want of attention- <lb break="yes"/>
this important branch of industry received
<lb/>
from the house. He saw a number of gentle<lb break="no"/>men around the benches who should take an <lb/>
interest in the subject; and yet here was a re<lb break="no"/>port brought in by a committee
after two <lb/>
months deliberation, and scarcely a remark
<lb/>
was elicited from them. The hon. gentleman <lb/>
alluded to the abolition of the
office of Fish <lb/>
Inspector, which he thought had rather depre<lb break="no"/>ciated the character of our fish in foreign
mar<lb break="no"/>kets. He thought that something might be <lb/>
done to improve the breed of fish. In France <lb/>
they imported spawn for this purpose, and he <lb/>
did not see why caplin could not be made to <lb/>
breed upon our shores, so as to improve the <lb/>
character of fish used for bait. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. S.
CAMPBELL thought that the hon. <lb/>
member for Halifax instead of lecturing
the <lb/>
committee ought to have addressed his re<lb break="no"/>marks to another quarter. He should like to
<lb/>
know why the government ignored their
duties <lb/>
in connection with the preservation of
the fish<lb break="no"/>eries any more than in relation to agriculture <lb/>
or any other branch of industry.
He thought <lb/>
that there was a particular reason why the
<lb/>
remarks of Mr. Tobin upon the improvement <lb/>
of bait should have been made to the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, for if there was a body
of gentlemen <lb/>
who understood the use of bait, it was the <lb/>
Executive of Nova Scotia. (Laughter.) And <lb/>
as they had taken charge of all the schools
of <lb/>
the province, perhaps it would be just as well <lb/>
if they also assumed the
protection of schools <lb/>
of fish. This subject of the trawl
fishery <lb/>
should engage the earnest attention
of the <lb/>
government, as if something was
not done <lb/>
very soon, the
valuable cod fishery of our
<lb/>
coast would be completely destroyed.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Hon.
PRO. SEC. said that no doubt this sub<lb break="no"/>ject was a most important one, and deserving <lb/>
the serious attention of the house and the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, but he thought that if hon. gentlemen <lb/>
who represented fishing interests instead of <lb/>
making it a subject of attack
upon the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the day would devote a little attention <lb/>
to the subject themselves, it would look
more <lb/>
like a desire to benefit that branch of provin<lb break="no"/>cial industry. He had sat there
eight years, and <lb/>
although the member
for Guysborough repre<lb break="no"/>sented a constituency largely engaged in
the <lb/>
fishing business, he never heard him open
his <lb/>
mouth to give advice upon the subject.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
He thought that if the constituencies of those <lb/>
fishing counties, instead of
selecting gentlemen <lb/>
of the legal profession as their representatives, <lb/>
            </p>-->

       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>