<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1866-04-16"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-04-16">16 April 1866</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA">
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          
          
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Second Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1866"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="240" to="258"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_240.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_241.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_242.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_243.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_244.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_245.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_246.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_247.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_248.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_249.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_250.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_251.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_252.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_253.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_254.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_255.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_256.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_257.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_258.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-06-05">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_240">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_240.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_241">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_241.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_242">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_242.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_243">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_243.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_244">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_244.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_245">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_245.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_246">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_246.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_247">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_247.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_248">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_248.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_249">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_249.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_250">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_250.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_251">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_251.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_252">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_252.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_253">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_253.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_254">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_254.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_255">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_255.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_256">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_256.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_257">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_257.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_258">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_258.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="240" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_240.jpg"/>
       
            <fw type="num">40</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
           
<!-- GL, 2018-06-05, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

 <!--<p>
      for being present and giving so much informa<lb break="no"/>tion on the subject As respects Lunenburg he 
     <lb/>
     believed if it were not for the Education Mea<lb break="no"/>sure he could have brought in a government 
     <lb/>
     candidate pledged to support a Union of the Col<lb break="no"/>onies As respects the other county mentioned 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Yarmouth (Mr Killam) 
     <lb/>
     could not get his own candidate in, and Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Townsend had been returned. He (Dr T ) 
     <lb/>
     believed that Yarmouth might be considered 
     <lb/>
     opposed to Union, but every one knew what 
     <lb/>
     was the ruling sentiment in that county At a 
     <lb/>
     meeting held in that county for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     sending delegates to the Detroit Convention. 
     <lb/>
     leading  men came forward with the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man for Yarmouth and declared that if the 
     <lb/>
     treaty were abrogated the sooner Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>
     was annexed to the United States the better 
     <lb/>
     He was informed that the other hon. member 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Townsend) stood up manfully. and said 
     <lb/>
     they ought to be ashamed. Under such circum 
     <lb/>
     stances it was not strange that a portion of the 
     <lb/>
     county of Yarmouth opposed the Union of the 
     <lb/>
     Colonies 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr.  Colin Campbell said that the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Yatmouth would know the sentiments of 
     <lb/>
     the representatives of the county of Digby at 
     <lb/>
     the proper time They were prepared to as<lb break="no"/>sume themselves the responsibility of dealing  
     <lb/>
     with the question in that spirit and manner that 
     <lb/>
     would best advance the interests of the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Killam said that he would deal with 
     <lb/>
     the question ot Confederation at the proper 
     <lb/>
     time He had not attempted to influence the 
     <lb/>
     constituency against Mr Townsend He was 
     <lb/>
     not aware that any opinions in respect to annex<lb break="no"/>ation had been m oted in the meeting referred to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr HATFIELD regretted that so much time 
     <lb/>
     had been wasted that might be more profitably 
     <lb/>
     employed.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      Mr. MCLELAN said that he believed the ef 
     <lb/>
     fect of Confederation would be to annex the 
     <lb/>
     Provinces to the United States 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr C J. CAMPBELL presented a petition from 
     <lb/>
     H. Cameron and others against Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The  subject then dropped 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr.  WHITMAN introduced a bill to legalize as 
     <lb/>
     sessment rolls of the county of Annapolis. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The house then adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <head rendition="simple:right">
     MONDAY, April 16. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
     The House met at 3 o'clock 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr BOURINOT introduced a bill to incorporate 
     <lb/>
     the Myra Bay Harbor Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. S  CAMPBELL presented a petition for the 
     <lb/>
     alteration of a mail route. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Also, two petitions  against Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr PRYOR reported  favorably on a number of 
     <lb/>
     bills from the committee on private and local 
     <lb/>
     bills, and unfavorably of the bill relative to the 
     <lb/>
     siection of a lock-up at Waverly these objections 
     <lb/>
     being already provided for by existing statutes 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. PROV SEC laid on the table a report of 
     <lb/>
     the Officer commandin H. M. S. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lilly</hi> in reference 
     <lb/>
    to the fog trumpet at Sambro. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
  <cb/>

<div type="section"> 
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     UNION OF THE COLONIES 
            </head>

<p>
     The adjourned debate was resumed. </p>
  


            <p>
     Mr C. J. CAMPBELL said : The Provincial 
     <lb/>
     Secretary told us,  some days ago, that the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment  were awaiting the action  of New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick on the question or Confederation. I 
     <lb/>
     do not think that this Province should place 
     <lb/>
     itself in that position Nova Scotia is the most 
     <lb/>
     important of the Maritime Provinces, and I do 
     <lb/>
     not see why we should wait for others to lead us 
     <lb/>
     on this important que stion. It is the duty of the 
     <lb/>
     Government and  of this Legislature to take a 
     <lb/>
     leading part in the discussion of this measure. 
     <lb/>
     When the question was introduced a year or two 
     <lb/>
     ago, much diversity of opinion existed as to the 
     <lb/>
     details which had  been arranged at Quebec, and 
     <lb/>
     matters stood in a different light from that in 
     <lb/>
     which they now appear At that  time we looked 
     <lb/>
     forward to peace and tranquillity with the United 
     <lb/>
     States ; we had free trade with that  coun<lb break="no"/>try. But how has the aspect changed since 
     <lb/>
     then. We do not stand in the same posi<lb break="no"/>tion as we stood in six months ago. The 
     <lb/>
     United States have shewn every disposition 
     <lb/>
     to annex these Provinces, and have shewn a 
     <lb/>
     determination to punish us by every means  in 
     <lb/>
     their power. Besides that  we have been threaten<lb break="no"/>ed with an invasion and it becomes  our duty to 
     <lb/>
     come forward like loyal citizens and to unite our<lb break="no"/>selves for purposes of defence. There are senti<lb break="no"/>ments in this Assembly favorable to annexation, 
     <lb/>
     and if the country were informed of the fact those 
     <lb/>
     sentiments would be hooted at from one end of No<lb break="no"/>va Scotia to the other. Whatever objections   the 
     <lb/>
     people entertained to the Quebec scheme twelve 
     <lb/>
     months ago matters have entirely changed. There 
     <lb/>
     is not a man in my county who is not loyal to the 
     <lb/>
     heart and who would not consent to any scheme 
     <lb/>
     that would save us from annexation or from in<lb break="no"/>vasion Mr. Annard told us that twenty  years ago 
     <lb/>
     the country was calm,  so it was; the dangers of 
     <lb/>
     to-day were then far in the distance and the people 
     <lb/>
     felt at liberty to discuss the minor points of the 
     <lb/>
     scheme of union, and to thwat the government 
     <lb/>
     from motives of self interest, but the aspect has 
     <lb/>
     greatly changed. All the triffling disputes which 
     <lb/>
     have engaged  our attention should be at once 
     <lb/>
     buried  before the great object of maintaining Bri<lb break="no"/>tish connection. The advice of the British  Go<lb break="no"/>vernment and press should lead us to look forward 
     <lb/>
     to the time when we shall become an ally instead 
     <lb/>
     of Colonies of Great Britain,—that is the proud 
     <lb/>
     position of which many of us have looked forward 
     <lb/>
     ever since  we came to the country. Can any one 
     <lb/>
     pretend to say that Great Britain would allow 
     <lb/>
     us to annex ourselves to the United States  when 
     <lb/>
     the Government of that country are threatening 
     <lb/>
     her in every possible manner?  Would the 
     <lb/>
     mother country part with all the resources at her 
     <lb/>
    command in this Province, and allow them to be 
     <lb/>handed over to her bitter enemy ? The idea is 
     <lb/>preposterous. Mr Annand has told us that the 
     <lb/>Railway should precede the union-that might 
     <lb/>be an advantage, but he knows that though that 
     <lb/>matter has been agi'ated for ten or twelve years 
     <lb/>we have failed in obtaining the road  It is quite 
     <lb/>evident that we cannot have these advantages 
     <lb/>
         

            <pb n="241" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_241.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">241</fw>
      

     without union He then proposes a delegation 
     <lb/>
     from the Maritime Provinces to agree on a plat<lb break="no"/>form before submitting the matter to the British 
     <lb/>
     Government, but such a course I do not consider 
     <lb/>
     wise. I may say that I had objections to the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec scheme but when the great necessities 
     <lb/>
     to which I have referred arose these objections 
     <lb/>
     vanished like smoke. Before knowing the wish 
     <lb/>
     of the British government, I had objections to the 
     <lb/>
     details of that scheme, but knowmg now the 
     <lb/>
     opinions they entertain and the offers held  out to 
     <lb/>
     us of becoming a nationality as soon as we are 
     <lb/>
     able to protect our selves these objections have 
     <lb/>
     been  overcome How does  the matter stand  now! 
     <lb/>
     To obviate any objections existing it is proposed 
     <lb/>
     to submit  the  whole matter to the mother country   
     <lb/>
     to arbitrate between the Provinces and to form a 
     <lb/>
     scheme equitable to all parties. The proposition   
     <lb/>
    of Mr. Annand seems to me, as I have said, 
     <lb/>objectionable and would only have the effect of 
     <lb/>deferring the object in view. The  scheme has 
     <lb/>been  before the country for two years, and if we 
     <lb/>are to come to a decision at all it is time we 
     <lb/>should do so now. The plan proposed in the 
     <lb/>resolution appears to me to be unobjectionable 
     <lb/>while the Opposition appears in a great strait to 
     <lb/>make any suggestion, and as a last resort have 
     <lb/>proposed representation in the Imperial Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. The idea of such  a representation I 
     <lb/>consider ridiculous If it were granted 
     <lb/>to Nova Scotia it would have to be done 
     <lb/>to all the other Colonies, and the Crystal 
     <lb/>Palace would not be large enough to hold the 
     <lb/>Parliament. That plan was proposed ten years 
     <lb/>ago by the hon. member's ender, but it fell to the 
     <lb/>ground without much attention being paid to it. 
     <lb/>Looking at the Lower Provinces, it will be seen 
     <lb/>how subject they are to an attack from the 
     <lb/>United States; and it has been the policy of that 
     <lb/>country to thwart the proposed union in order 
     <lb/>that we may be more willing to annex. It has 
     <lb/>been proved by history that small countries are 
     <lb/>always swallowed up by the larger. At this mo<lb break="no"/>ment it is not improbable that the United States 
     <lb/>would negotiate with Nova Scotia for admitting 
     <lb/>her fish and coal free, and the good feeling be<lb break="no"/>tween this Province and Canada would be there<lb break="no"/>by destroyed and variances in interest and feeling 
     <lb/>created. One after another of the Colonies 
     <lb/>would by that policy be made willing to be an<lb break="no"/>nexed on such terms as the United States would 
     <lb/>dictate. The conduct of some members of the 
     <lb/>House appears childish in the extreme — one day 
     <lb/>they advocate sending to Great Britain for ships 
     <lb/>and men to protect our fisheries, and the next day 
     <lb/>they oppose with all their might the proposition  to 
     <lb/>pay any regard to the wishes of the Government 
     <lb/>to which we send for aid. My collegue urged 
     <lb/>the  Government to send vessels to protect the 
     <lb/>fisheries on the Cape Breton Coast while at the 
     <lb/>same time he is a strong opponent of Union.   
     <lb/>What do we see every day? War ships, guns 
     <lb/>and ammunition gathering round to protect us 
     <lb/>without the cost to us of a shilling, and at the 
     <lb/>same time we presume to set at defiance the de 
     <lb/>mands of  that Government, which gives us these 
     <lb/>means of self-protection, that we should unite for 
     <lb/>
       

            <cb/>
          

     defence. If we are able to defend ourselves 
     <lb/>
     without the assistance of Great Britain, let us say 
     <lb/>
     so; but if we are not, let us concede what the 
     <lb/>
     mother country desires. Going along the dock  
     <lb/>
     the other day, I looked at our Provincial navy,  
     <lb/>
     and the whole affair seemed utterly contempt<lb break="no"/>ible There was the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Daring</hi>. with a two- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     pounder to protect our harbors and fisheries, and 
     <lb/>
     yet we feel quite conceited and clamour against 
     <lb/>
     Confederation.  My idea is, that instead of await<lb break="no"/>ing the action of New Brunswick, We should take 
     <lb/>
     the lead. Ours is the most populous Province of  
     <lb/>
     the two and should set the example. I think 
     <lb/>
     the country should be made aware of the princi<lb break="no"/>ples of those members who oppose the measure. 
     <lb/>
     The hon gentleman  whose name has been intro<lb break="no"/>duced into the discussion, ever since his return, 
     <lb/>
     has been boldly proclaiming annexation senti<lb break="no"/>ments in the streets and in the lobby of the House. 
     <lb/>
     Gentlemen holding: such views are getting more 
     <lb/>
     and more bold The history of small countries 
     <lb/>
     has been that from animosities they have been set: 
     <lb/>
     to fight against each other until they have been 
     <lb/>
     so weakened as to be unable to present a front to 
     <lb/>
     the common enemy. So  lt will be with us if we 
     <lb/>
     do not take steps to strengthen ourselves and to 
     <lb/>
     become one people. As I have already said, I 
     <lb/>
     think the Government should take such steps as 
     <lb/>
     will shew the other Provinces that we are not 
     <lb/>
     backward in this matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SPEECH OF MR. LOCKE. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. LOCKE said :—It was correctly remarked 
     <lb/>
     the other day that the opponents of Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation are in an unfortunate position in having 
     <lb/>
     nine lawyers and a doctor worth three more, 
     <lb/>
     opposed to us, We cannot be expected to 
     <lb/>
     exhibit the same ability that will be displayed. 
     <lb/>
     upon the other side, but we stand here backed 
     <lb/>
     by the strong opinions of our constituents.— 
     <lb/>
     Those opinions we believe to be correct and 
     <lb/>
     sound, and we feel that the principles which 
     <lb/>
     we maintain are correct. This is a question of 
     <lb/>
     the deepest moment to the country, we are 
     <lb/>
     bartering away our rights and privileges if we 
     <lb/>
     hand over this fine Province of ours to Canada 
     <lb/>
     and I feel disposed to say, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p>
     " Breathes there a man with soul so dead. 
     <lb/>
    Who never to himself hath said. 
     <lb/>This is my own my native land." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

    

            <p>
     In adopting this scheme we are giving our 
     <lb/>
     country to Canada to be swallowed up with 
     <lb/>
     grand schemes and projects of aggrandisement, 
     <lb/>
     to a colony notedly disloyal Coming as I do 
     <lb/>
     from a county whose inhabitants have come 
     <lb/>
     from loyalist stock, a country settled by men 
     <lb/>
     who have sacrificed their best interests for the 
     <lb/>
     sake of British connection, I feel at liberty to 
     <lb/>
     express my opinion freely and without fear of 
     <lb/>
     the charge of disloyalty. The question of  Con<lb break="no"/>federation has been before the country now for 
     <lb/>
     two years. and its aspect has recently been 
     <lb/>
     materially changed. What brought. about this 
     <lb/>
     change? We saw gentlemen on both sides of 
     <lb/>
     the House last Session exceedingly hostile to 
     <lb/>
     the scheme, but a. change has come over the 
     <lb/>
     spirit of their dreams. We had the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Richmond advocating one side of the 
     <lb/>
     question with all the eloquence at his com<lb break="no"/>mand, we had the member for Inverness, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McDonnell, taking the same side with the 
     <lb/>
       

            <pb n="242" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_242.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">242</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
 

     some ability, and all at once these gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     rise and propose that another scheme be resort<lb break="no"/>ed to and state that circumstances lead 
     <lb/>
     to the belief that a better  scheme can be pro<lb break="no"/>cured. I ask, then, " what has brought about  this 
     <lb/>
     change? The  Prov. Secretary spoke of influ<lb break="no"/>ences, had we not every reason to suppose that 
     <lb/>
     influences were at work? What these influ<lb break="no"/>ences were it was not our business to enquire, 
     <lb/>
     but the suddenness of the change shewd that 
     <lb/>
     there were such and that they were of a strong 
     <lb/>
     kind. Three months ago these gentlemen  were 
     <lb/>
     denouncing the Quebec scheme and now they 
     <lb/>
     come forward and advocate a new delegation, 
     <lb/>
     although we know to a certainty that the new 
     <lb/>
     scheme will be the Quebec scheme; there may 
     <lb/>
     be slight variations, but in the main and sub<lb break="no"/>stantial particulars it will be the same. Loy<lb break="no"/>alty to the Crown, it has been said, requires 
     <lb/>
     that we should Confederate, because the Lieut. 
     <lb/>
     Governor has been sent here expressly to carry 
     <lb/>
     the measure out. No remarks in reference to 
     <lb/>
     that officer will be constructed, I suppose, into 
     <lb/>
     disloyalty to the Queen, and when the  Prov. 
     <lb/>
     Secretary spoke about the scheme being urged 
     <lb/>
     upon us by such impressiveness as Royal lips 
     <lb/>
     alone could evince, and by his mention of the 
     <lb/>
     appointment of Sir W. F. Williams to carry it 
     <lb/>
     out he invited comment. If it be declared to 
     <lb/>
     be disloyal to refer to the action of the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor I will ask the House to let me refer to 1861 
     <lb/>
     when an election was being run in Victoria 
     <lb/>
     County. In the Prov. Secretary's own organ I 
     <lb/>
     find this language; and although I quote from 
     <lb/>
     a paper that was particularly under his direc<lb break="no"/>tion, and the very style. cannot he mistaken, as 
     <lb/>
     he used the same or nearly the same words on 
     <lb/>
     the floor of the House :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
   
            <p>
      "Taking into account the position of the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment and the unscrupulous means resort<lb break="no"/>ed to by them we can scarcely imagine the pos<lb break="no"/>sibility of Mr. Campbell being elected. lt is 
     <lb/>
      now understood that Lord Mulgrave made it 
     <lb/>
     an express condition with the usurpers that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Campbell must he unseated and Victoria 
     <lb/>
     carried or he would he compelled in his own 
     <lb/>
     defence to dissolve the Assembly." And fur<lb break="no"/>ther on he says: " Mr. Hugh Munroe was al<lb break="no"/>lowed by Lord Mulgrave to abandon the im<lb break="no"/>portant duties of his office as Chairman of the 
     <lb/>
     Board of Works and head of the Lunatic Asy<lb break="no"/>lum, in order to take part in an election strug<lb break="no"/>gle, contrary to the spirit of the law and policy 
     <lb/>
     of the legislature who had removed that officer 
     <lb/>
     from politics. The Governor and Government 
     <lb/>
     having thus combined against the liberties of 
     <lb/>
     the people and determined to obtain a support<lb break="no"/>er from Victoria, it is not to be supposed that 
     <lb/>
     any means would he left untried." He ends 
     <lb/>
     by saying: " If there be any man in Nova Sco<lb break="no"/>tia  who doubts the completely partizan charac<lb break="no"/>ter of the Lieut. Governor let him ponder upon 
     <lb/>
     these two recent outrages for which Lord Mul<lb break="no"/>grave is directly responsible. Sending the 
     <lb/>
     Chairman of the Board of Works and the 
     <lb/>
     Sheriffs of other Counties to add the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in the Victoria Election." In another is<lb break="no"/>sue of the paper he says: "That the Chairman 
     <lb/>
     of the Board of Works, who could not leave 
     <lb/>
     the important duties of his office without the 
     <lb/>
     leave of Lord Mulgrave, was immediately des<lb break="no"/>patched with 400 a year of the people's money 
     <lb/>
     in his pocket to aid the Queen's Printer who 
     <lb/>
     carried the bag in the Cumberland Election in 
     <lb/>
       

            <cb/>
      

     corrupting and intimidating the Electors of 
     <lb/>
     Victoria. We venture  to assert that the histo<lb break="no"/>ry of the Colonies will be perused in vain to 
     <lb/>
     discover such daring innovations of the liber<lb break="no"/>ties of the people by any Governor. Does 
     <lb/>
     Lord Mulgrave think the free spirit of Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotians is to be trampled out by means so 
     <lb/>
     ingiolous and corrupt ?" 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     If that  is not treasonable language to be used 
     <lb/>
     towards a Governor, then nothing that has been 
     <lb/>
     said in this debate can be considered  so. Mr. 
     <lb/>
   Cardwell  has taken strong  ground us we believe 
     <lb/>against the interests  of this   country, and in dele<lb break="no"/>gating a Governor expressly  to carry out the 
     <lb/>scheme of Confederation, we   have every right to 
     <lb/>believe  that Her  Majesty's  Government are work<lb break="no"/>ing against our interest .  There is no  thing dis<lb break="no"/>loyal in that statement, because it is well under<lb break="no"/>stood the Queen can do no wrong, her Ministers 
     <lb/>being  responsible. I may say that it is because I 
     <lb/>believe that this scheme of annexation to  Canada 
     <lb/>will drive us into annexation to the United States 
     <lb/>that I oppose it. What are the  antecedents of 
     <lb/> Canada? One of the gentlemen taking a  leading 
     <lb/>part in the movement, one who has lectured in 
     <lb/>various   places in the subject of union, is well 
     <lb/>known to have been an Irish rebel. Many of the 
     <lb/>leading men of Canada  have stood in the same 
     <lb/>position, in their conduct during the Canadian 
     <lb/>rebellion. These are the people with whom we 
     <lb/>are asked to confederate If we yield, their 
     <lb/>Orange and Ribbon Societies and other such 
     <lb/>principles will circulate amongst us, and we 
     <lb/>would become equally disloyal If, then, annex<lb break="no"/>ation is to be brought about, would   it not be 
     <lb/>better to go in at once to the American Union ? 
     <lb/>
   Because we would thus obtain all the advantages 
     <lb/>
     of a separate State, while if Confederation goes on 
     <lb/>
     probably in a few years more we will have to go 
     <lb/>
     in as a mere  County of Canada. It is said that 
     <lb/>
     trade relations are an inducement, but why can<lb break="no"/>not we obtain them without a political union? 
     <lb/>
     The moment Canada finds it necessary to have 
     <lb/>
     free trade with this Colony, she  will content to 
     <lb/>
     the arrangments being made, it being a sound 
     <lb/>
     principle that trade regulates itself. What will 
     <lb/>
     the position of our credit be if we unite? At this 
     <lb/>
     day our bonds stand higher in the market than 
     <lb/>
     those of Canada. Confederate with Canada, and 
     <lb/>
     let her carry on her canals and  other works, and 
     <lb/>
     through the means of her large debt and great 
     <lb/>
     expenditure her bonds will go down and ours 
     <lb/>
     with them, we being a part and portion of the 
     <lb/>
     country. By a political union we  must be ab<lb break="no"/>sorbed and swallowed up We will lose our 
     <lb/>
     identity and be subject to their will. It is well 
     <lb/>
     known that Nova Scotia stood by the Crown 
     <lb/>
     during the American rebellion. Nova Scotia was 
     <lb/>
      loyal then and is now, and by uniting herself to 
     <lb/>
     such a country as Canada she will gain nothing. 
     <lb/>
     We have enjoyed a Parliament of our own for a 
     <lb/>
     hundred years, with all the privileges that a free 
     <lb/>
     people could ask ; we have gone on progressing, 
     <lb/>
     and after obtaining responsible Government 
     <lb/>
    we have become so free that we require no<lb break="no"/>thing more in the way of independence. What 
     <lb/>will the people say to this Parliament being 
     <lb/>taken from them? We may be told that the 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="243" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_243.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">[OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw> <fw type="num">243</fw> 


     local legislatures will remain but who can tell 
     <lb/>
     us anything of their formation? I presume that 
     <lb/>
      nothing that we can urge will prevent the 
     <lb/>
     adoption of the scheme but I contend that it 
     <lb/>
     would be unfair for the British governement  to 
     <lb/>
     adopt such a measure without he sanction of 
     <lb/>
     our people. In connection with this subject I 
     <lb/>
     will quote from the London <hi rendition="simple:italic">Review</hi> of March 
     <lb/>
     17th: — 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     THE RECALL OF SIR CHARLES DARLING.— 
            </p>
<p>
     Mr. Cardwell has found it necessary to recall 
     <lb/>
     Sir Charles Darling, the Govornor of the colo<lb break="no"/>ny of Victoria, and we think it will be general<lb break="no"/>ly admitted that he has not taken this step on 
     <lb/>
     insufficient grounds. It will be in the recol 
     <lb/>
     lection of our readers that the two branches of 
     <lb/>
     the Legislature of the colony came into conflict 
     <lb/>
     upon the financial schemes of the Government 
     <lb/>
     for the time being. The Lower House passed. 
     <lb/>
     the Upper House it was known would reject, 
     <lb/>
     the budget. In order to surmount this difficul<lb break="no"/>ty, the Appropriation Bill was tacked to the 
     <lb/>
     Bill imposing new customs duties. The Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Council was thus presented with the al 
     <lb/>
     ternative of submitting to the dictation of the 
     <lb/>
     House of Assembly, or of leaving the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment without  any legal power to levy taxes or 
     <lb/>
     to defray expenses; but, eventually, they chose 
     <lb/>
     the latter course, as they had a perfect right to 
     <lb/>
     do. Pressed by the difficulties of their situa<lb break="no"/>tion, the Colonial Ministry, thereupon, resorted 
     <lb/>
    to more than one irregular  and illegal means of 
     <lb/>raising the wind. It was clearly the duty of 
     <lb/>Sir Charles Darling, as the representative of 
     <lb/>the Queen, to refuse his sanction to acts of such 
     <lb/>a character. But he not only gave his cordial 
     <lb/>and earnest support to the politicians who 
     <lb/>were violating the Constitution, he did some<lb break="no"/>thing even still more objectionable. Comment<lb break="no"/>ing on a despatch to the Colonial Secretary up<lb break="no"/>on an address from the Legislative Council, he 
     <lb/>took it upon himself to express a hope that the 
     <lb/>gentlemen who had signed it would never be 
     <lb/>designated for the position of confidential ad<lb break="no"/>visers to the Crown, because it is "impossible 
     <lb/>that their advice could be received with any 
     <lb/> other feelings than those of doubt and distrust." 
     <lb/>When a Governor thus converts himself into a 
     <lb/>partisan, and descends from his constitutional 
     <lb/>eminence as the representative of the Crown, 
     <lb/>to participate in the party conflicts of the colony 
     <lb/>placed under his rule. it is clear that he can no 
     <lb/>longer discharge his delicate and dignified du<lb break="no"/>ties with success. His usefulness is at an end, 
     <lb/>and nothing remains but to replace him by 
     <lb/>some one who can maintain with greater firm<lb break="no"/>ness a position of impartiality, and can hold 
     <lb/>himself aloof with greater self-command from 
     <lb/>the excited passions which it is his duty to mo<lb break="no"/>derate. ln a despatch of stinging but well- 
     <lb break="yes"/>merited rebuke. Mr. Cardwell has insisted up<lb break="no"/>on these obvious considerations, and has reliev<lb break="no"/>ed sir Charles Darling from the further exer. 
     <lb/>cise, of functions which he has so grievously 
     <lb/>abused.—<hi rendition="simple:italic">London Review</hi>, March 17. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The cases it may be said are not exactly 
     <lb/>
     similar because that governor went into oppo<lb break="no"/>sition to the legislature of the Colony but our 
     <lb/>
     Lieut Governor knows from the petitions that 
     <lb/>
     have been presented that the feeling of the 
     <lb/>
     country is against the scheme, and that if 
     <lb/>
     members would  but rise and express the views 
     <lb/>
     of their constituents they would be found in 
     <lb/>
     opposition to the measure. Mr. Cardwell 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     should surely stay his hand before giving his 
     <lb/>
     assistance to the completion of the union under 
     <lb/>
     these circumstances. I will now read from the 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">New York Albion</hi> a paper well known to be 
     <lb/>
     thoroughly <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> though published on this side 
     <lb/>
     of the Atlantic:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     REMOVAL OF A COLONIAL GOVERNOR— 
            </p>
<p>
     Careless observers of the working of British 
     <lb/>
     institutions have been in the habit of assuming 
     <lb/>
     that the Imperial Government desired above 
     <lb/>
     all things to maintain its own supremacy in 
     <lb/>
     remote settlements, and that it is always dis<lb break="no"/>posed to back up its own local representative. 
     <lb/>
     These erroneous imprchions may perhaps 
     <lb/>
     have been partially disturbed by the strange 
     <lb/>
     spectacle lately patent in Jamaica; and they 
     <lb/>
     will receive another rude shock in the news 
     <lb/>
     that has just reached us from Downing Street. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Cardwell, the Colonial Secretary, has ad<lb break="no"/>vised the Queen to recall Sir Charles Darling, 
     <lb/>
     some time Governor of the Colony of Victoria. 
     <lb/>
     The circumstances of the quarrel that arose 
     <lb/>
     between the House of Assembly and the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Council, in which quarrel Sir Charles 
     <lb/>
     interfered injudiciously, or illegally, or both, 
     <lb/>
     are detailed in extracts from London papers 
     <lb/>
     cited above. We have only to add that Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Cardwell's despatch, displacing the Governor, 
     <lb/>
     most emphatically insists upon the determi<lb break="no"/>nation of the Colonial Office  at home to leave 
     <lb/>
     the Colonists to manage their own affairs, and 
     <lb/>
     points out most cogently the great blunder of 
     <lb/>
     the Governor in identifying himself irretrieva<lb break="no"/>bly with any political parties. The despatch, 
     <lb/>
     we doubt not, will cause a flutter among the 
     <lb/>
     occupants of high places. For us, it has but a 
     <lb/>
     partial interest; because we knew well before<lb break="no"/>hand that British statesmen, one and all, have 
     <lb/>
     long since abandoned the idea of ruling free<lb break="no"/>men by edicts from home. If Jamaica be 
     <lb/>
     under the present melancholy state of things, 
     <lb/>
     an exception to this rule, it is because the free  
     <lb/>
     Blacks have shown themselves unworthy of 
     <lb/>
     free Government.     
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When the Lieut. Governor ventures to carry 
     <lb/>
     out any scheme of union in opposition to the 
     <lb/>
     wishes of the people he identifies himself im<lb break="no"/>properly with a party. This House is elected 
     <lb/>
    to legislate according to the well understood  
     <lb/>wishes of the people, and this particular 
     <lb/>scheme, changing the constitution, it was 
     <lb/>never empowered to carry out. In adopting 
     <lb/>the scheme we do not carry out those wishes 
     <lb/>and if the people, had the opportunity of 
     <lb/>expressing their views they would return such 
     <lb/>a majority that twelve members would not be 
     <lb/>found to support the scheme. The Prov. Sec. 
     <lb/>said that it had been used as an argument on 
     <lb/>our side, in other places, that if  this scheme 
     <lb/>were carried out not one of its supporters 
     <lb/>would get a seat at Ottawa. This I think very 
     <lb/>probable, but it makes our prospects still more 
     <lb/>unfavorable. We have in this House support<lb break="no"/>ing Confederation a set of trained politicians   
     <lb/>If these gentlemen went to the hustings, in all 
     <lb/>probability they would be rejected, and this 
     <lb/>would be a positive loss to the country. You 
     <lb/>would then have a new set of men. meeting 
     <lb/>more astute statesmen, and the interests of the 
     <lb/>country would be insecure. I assure the Prov. 
     <lb/>Secretary of these facts for his own interest.; 
     <lb/>and while I might consider that he would  be 
     <lb/>no loss to us, we have men who have hereto<lb break="no"/>fore acted with and led us to care for the true 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="244" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_244.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">244</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
       

     interests of the countrv, who would be. Tak<lb break="no"/>ing the first view of the question which I took— 
     <lb/>
      that annexation to the United States will follow 
     <lb/>
     annexation to Canada, it will be seen that we 
     <lb/>
     are doing a positive injury to Great Britain by 
     <lb/>
     confederating, because the moment she loses 
     <lb/>
     her Colonies England must become a second or 
     <lb/>
     third rate power. It will be recollected that 
     <lb/>
     the celebrated "Junius" said in one of his 
     <lb/>
     letters, "The feathers which adorn the royal 
     <lb/>
     bird support its flight;" strip it of its plumage 
     <lb/>
      and you fix it to the earth." The moment you 
     <lb/>
     take away the Colonies from Great Britain the 
     <lb/>
     feathers which support her flight are taken 
     <lb/>
     away, and she ceases to be a first rate power. 
     <lb/>
     As loyal men, we should stand by our country 
     <lb/>
     in this emergency. It is not certain that New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick will fall in with the scheme. A 
     <lb/>
     telegram informs us that a majority of the As<lb break="no"/>sembly will move for the recall of the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor and that will postpone Confederation for 
     <lb/>
     sometime. It seems to me that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment are too hot and too hasty in this matter 
     <lb/>
     Give us time to consider the question. I do 
     <lb/>
     not ask them to dissolve and go to the 
     <lb/>
     country, but I think we should have the 
     <lb/>
     chances of one year more to see if the 
     <lb/>
     people will he indoctrinated into favouring 
     <lb/>
     the measure, not that I expect them to willingly 
     <lb/>
     favor such a union, for I want none, we are 
     <lb/>
     prosperous and happy as we are. I ask the 
     <lb/>
     House not to agree to the proposed delegation. 
     <lb/>
      for we very well know that the delegates wil 
     <lb/>
     come back with the Quebec scheme. Mr. Card<lb break="no"/>well having taken a decided stand in its favor. 
     <lb/>
     I, therefore, call upon the government to stay 
     <lb/>
     their hand and to give the country time to con<lb break="no"/>sider what is the best course to pursue. But if 
     <lb/>
     this new scheme to send a delegation to Eng<lb break="no"/>land to settle terms of union there, should be 
     <lb/>
     carried in this House, I would demand as a 
     <lb/>
     right of the people of this Province, that after 
     <lb/>
     terms being agreed upon by the British Go 
     <lb/>
     vernment and the delegates, that it should be 
     <lb/>
     referred back to this people for their sanction. 
     <lb/>
     If any other course be pursued, you trifle wïth 
     <lb/>
     the liberties and privileges of a free people in 
     <lb/>
      bartering them away without. giving, them a 
     <lb/>
     voice in the matter, and the consequences, be 
     <lb/>
     what they may, will rest upon the men who 
     <lb/>
     have so acted. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SPEECH OF MR. BLANCHARD. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. BLANCHARD said:—The hon. member 
     <lb/>
     who has just sat. down has very forcibiy ex<lb break="no"/>pressed the opinion that this is one of the 
     <lb/>
     greatest questions ever presented for our con<lb break="no"/>siderations; and I feel that I approach it under 
     <lb/>
     no ordinary responsibilities, and with the con<lb break="no"/>viction that I am dealing with the great inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the Province of Nova Scotia. We have 
     <lb/>
     been told by that. hon. gentleman that in favor 
     <lb/>
     of Confederation are arrayed the chief legal 
     <lb/>
     talent and nearly all the trained politicians  of 
     <lb/>
     the country I consider this a strong argument 
     <lb/>
     in favor of Confederation that the trained poli<lb break="no"/>ticians of all the Provinces—the men who are 
     <lb/>
     accustomed to look at great questions and to 
     <lb/>
     judge of them. have deliberately made up their 
     <lb/>
     minds that the scheme of Union is favorable to 
     <lb/>
     the interests of the Province and to our con<lb break="no"/>nection with the British Crown. Let us look 
     <lb/>
     at any of the deliberative assemblies, and 
     <lb/>
     will we not find that when the leading men 
     <lb/>

<cb/>

     adopt any particular view of a question, in nine 
     <lb/>
     hundred and ninty-nine cases out of a thousand 
     <lb/>
     they are right. I might refer to a great variety 
     <lb/>
     of instances in support of this position. In the 
     <lb/>
     history of Pitt it is seen that in some cases Fox, 
     <lb/>
     Burke, and Sheridan, his greatest adversaries, 
     <lb/>
     were found coinciding with him, and history 
     <lb/>
     proves that in all such cases they were right. 
     <lb/>
     I do not think the hon member did justice to 
     <lb/>
     himself in saying that the <hi rendition="simple:italic">trained</hi> politicians 
     <lb/>
     were all on one side, for his speech showed an 
     <lb/>
     amount. of eloquence and research seldom ex<lb break="no"/>hibited on such occasions. That we have 
     <lb/>
     nine lawyers upon this side of the question is 
     <lb/>
     true; but I claim that we occupy the right po<lb break="no"/>sition, and one which many of the lay mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the house will willingly endorse.— 
     <lb/>
     The hon. member for Shelburne also told us 
     <lb/>
     that he represented a people truly loyal, the 
     <lb/>
     descendants of those who sacrificed much for 
     <lb/>
     their principles and for their attachment to the 
     <lb/>
     mother country. Sir, I yield to no man in the 
     <lb/>
     loyalty of myself or of my constituents. I too 
     <lb/>
     am a descendant of a loyalist who sacrificed 
     <lb/>
     as much for his loyalty as any of the men who 
     <lb/>
     came to Shelburne at that time; nineteen- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     twentieths of those whom I represent are 
     <lb/>
     Scotchmen, and what race have done and 
     <lb/>
     suffered so much for their country, and where 
     <lb/>
     do you find patriotism if not among them? 
     <lb/>
     It has been said that there are influences at 
     <lb/>
     work in reference to this question. Sir they 
     <lb/>
     have no effect upon me. My friend can say 
     <lb/>
     nothing to me upon that score. My position 
     <lb/>
     has all along been different from that. of those 
     <lb/>
     who actively opposed the measure and who, 
     <lb/>
     I presume, are prepared to give good reasons 
     <lb/>
     for their change of mind. I feel that I am not 
     <lb/>
     called on, nor would it be advisable that I 
     <lb/>
     should go into a discussion of the merits of 
     <lb/>
     the scheme recently submitted to the country 
     <lb/>
     or of its details. That theme has been ex<lb break="no"/>hausted, and there will be little  effort on my 
     <lb/>
     part to crush down the opposition to confede<lb break="no"/>ration. I do not therefore intend to discuss 
     <lb/>
     the details of the question, but to explain the 
     <lb/>
     position which I occupy, which is very differ<lb break="no"/>ent from that of many gentlemen around me. 
     <lb/>
     I have felt that the question should be ap 
     <lb/>
     proached with great care I have felt it my 
     <lb/>
     duty as a representative of the people serious<lb break="no"/>ly to right it before coming to a conclusion, 
     <lb/>
     and no man can say that, up to this time, I am 
     <lb/>
     bound by any pledges or promises to take any 
     <lb/>
     particular position. We have heard about 
     <lb/>
     "traitors" and "treachery," and "Cana<lb break="no"/>dian gold;" I feel it is hardly worth 
     <lb/>
     while for me to contradict the state<lb break="no"/>ments upon these subjects as far as I am 
     <lb/>
     concerned. I have not come from a school of 
     <lb/>
     traitors, and the reproach cannot fall upon me. 
     <lb/>
     I regret that I am called upon in connection 
     <lb/>
     with this subject, to differ from some of my 
     <lb/>
     friends, and I regret that personal recrimina<lb break="no"/>tions, private conversations, have been intro<lb break="no"/>duced into this discussion. This is a matter 
     <lb/>
     which ought to be discussed calmly, and with<lb break="no"/>out temper. We live in an age in which pro<lb break="no"/>gress is not to be measured as it once was, it is 
     <lb/>
     execedingly rapid at the present day, and men 
     <lb/>
     live more in one year now than they formerly 
     <lb/>
     lived in twenty. Changes are rapidly ap<lb break="no"/>proaching, and it is now our duty to look them 
     <lb/>
     fairly in the face, and honestly to consider the 
     <lb/>
     probable future. The question before the house 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="245" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_245.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY</fw>
            <fw type="num">245</fw>
    

     is, in my opinion, whether we shall unite with 
     <lb/>
     the adjoining colonies or remain disunited, 
     <lb/>
     and involved with the chances of annexation. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Locke has said that Confederation will 
     <lb/>
     lead to the latter—if he could convince me of 
     <lb/>
     that he would find an opponent of the measure 
     <lb/>
     as determined as any man in this country, but 
     <lb/>
     I support it because I feel and believe, and am 
     <lb/>
     convinced in my heart and conscience that if we 
     <lb/>
     remain as we are the time will soon come 
     <lb/>
     when we will be absorbed into the American 
     <lb/>
     Republic. My hon. friend from Halifax, who 
     <lb/>
     is leading the present opposition, published 
     <lb/>
     that which met my approbation a short time 
     <lb/>
     ago, when he declared that a change was ap<lb break="no"/>proaching, that something must be done, that. 
     <lb/>
     this country could not remain as it was, and 
     <lb/>
     that our future must be looked in the face. I 
     <lb/>
     felt and still feel that these were the words of 
     <lb/>
     truth and soberness, and I believe that unless 
     <lb/>
     these Colonies proceed to Confederate we can<lb break="no"/>not long continue dependencies of the British 
     <lb/>
     Crown. What. has occurred since last session? 
     <lb/>
     When the friends of the measure stated last year 
     <lb/>
     that they believed that the Reciprocity Treaty 
     <lb/>
     was about to be abrogated we were told that 
     <lb/>
     this was nonsense, that American interests 
     <lb/>
     were too deeply concerned, and that they va<lb break="no"/>lued reciprocity as much as we—yet have we 
     <lb/>
     not seen it come to pass in the teeth of offers, 
     <lb/>
     on the part of our government, such as none 
     <lb/>
     of us would have thought of making a few 
     <lb/>
     years ago, and such as few men in this country 
     <lb/>
     would be disposed to concur in. So determined 
     <lb/>
     were the Americans to abolish that treaty that 
     <lb/>
     not only were the arguments of our delegates 
     <lb/>
     treated with disdain, but afterwards, when a 
     <lb/>
     bill was brought into Senate in connection 
     <lb/>
     with the subject, containing propositions that 
     <lb/>
     would be indignantly refused here, they re<lb break="no"/>fused to receive . Why did they refuse such a 
     <lb/>
     measure introduced by their leading minds, 
     <lb/>
     and approved by Mr. Morrill? What answer 
     <lb/>
     do their leading or ans give to the question? 
     <lb/>
     They tell us that it was because they expect. 
     <lb/>
     soon to be able to annex these Colonies,—that 
     <lb/>
     without free trade with them we cannot. exist, 
     <lb/>
     and that we will soon be glad to seek for ad<lb break="no"/>mission to the Union. The paid officer of the 
     <lb/>
     American Government in reporting on this 
     <lb/>
     question broadly put to the government and 
     <lb/>
     Senate that the only alternatives were reci<lb break="no"/>procity or absorption, and while declaring that 
     <lb/>
     reciprocity was beneficial to them—yet advis<lb break="no"/>ed its refusal as favourable to Annexation. 
     <lb/>
     They have refused to renew that treaty influ<lb break="no"/>enced by these motives. It has been said that 
     <lb/>
     the United States have no desire to annex 
     <lb/>
     these Colonies  Can we believe such a state<lb break="no"/>ment? Look at our fisheries at our mineral 
     <lb/>
     resources, at the extent of our wood lands and 
     <lb/>
     can we imagine that they are not most anxi<lb break="no"/>ous to possess these Provinces, and especial<lb break="no"/>ly Nova Scotia. I feel, therefore, in looking 
     <lb/>
     at the question, and for other reasons not neces<lb break="no"/>sary to mention,  that without confederation 
     <lb/>
     annexation is before us. The abrogation of 
     <lb/>
     the treaty over its  origin to the desire of the 
     <lb/>
     American  people to bring us within their bor<lb break="no"/>ders, and I an firmly and honestly convinced 
     <lb/>
     that it is my duty to say to my constituents 
     <lb/>
     and to the people of Nova Scotia that I am 
     <lb/>
     willing to do anything—to resort to almost. any 
     <lb/>
     measure rather than run the risk of such a 
     <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
 

     consequence as that. I do not mean to say by 
     <lb/>
    this that the scheme before us will not be very 
     <lb/>beneficial to the people of this country. My 
     <lb/>own opinions have undergone no change on 
     <lb/>this subject, but I have resolved to take this 
     <lb/>bold and straightforward stand—to declare that 
     <lb/>we should confederate, and that we should do 
     <lb/>it <hi rendition="simple:italic">now</hi> because I feel that the s ep is demand<lb break="no"/>ed by the exigencies which surround us, I 
     <lb/>trust in God that I may never live to see the 
     <lb/>Stars and Stripes floating over Citadel  Hill,—I 
     <lb/>trust that before we are annexed I ard my 
     <lb/>children shall have gone to the land of the 
     <lb/>shades, and that not one of us may be left to 
     <lb/>see our country in such a position. We have 
     <lb/>been told by the gentleman who preceeded me 
     <lb/>that Confederation would weaken the ties 
     <lb/>that bind us to the parent state,— but have we 
     <lb/>its subordinate officers, and the press of that 
     <lb/>not the government of Great Britain and all 
     <lb/>country, and among ourselves our best minds, 
     <lb/>lay and clerical, urging it on us. Do they look 
     <lb/>favourably on the scheme because they believe 
     <lb/>it, will weaken the ties that bind us to 
     <lb/>them? I was sorry to hear one member say 
     <lb/>that the English people would be glad to be 
     <lb/>rid of us; I do not believe that such a feeling 
     <lb/>exists in Great Britain, nor that with few ex<lb break="no"/>ceptions there are any men in great Britain 
     <lb/>willing or anxious to part with us. The only 
     <lb/>real question remaining in my mind is wheth<lb break="no"/>er an appeal to the people should not have 
     <lb/>been had. It was suggested by Mr. Annand 
     <lb/>that the people be called on to vote on the 
     <lb/>question of Confederation alone, but I cannot 
     <lb/>think that he seriously proposed that we should 
     <lb/>do what no British country ever did before— 
     <lb/>resort. to a <hi rendition="simple:italic">plebiscite</hi> on this question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Mr. S. CAMPBELL —It has been done in No<lb break="no"/>va Scotia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. BLANCHARD  continued:—This reference 
     <lb/>
     is to the vote taken upon the Municipal Cor<lb break="no"/>porations' bill, but this was simply as to the 
     <lb/>
     adoption in each county of a purely local 
     <lb/>
     measure; but did any one ever hear of a ques<lb break="no"/>tion of Colonial policy being so sub<lb break="no"/>mitted? That precedent  is no parallel to 
     <lb/>
     this case, and I challenge gentlemen who 
     <lb/>
     take that side of the question  to lay their hands 
     <lb/>
     upon any case in which a question of this kind 
     <lb/>
     was sent in that wav to the people. If such a 
     <lb/>
     mode is un-British, uncertain, and unreliable, 
     <lb/>
     how are we to adopt it? What are we to 
     <lb/>
     depend on for the decision? We recently took 
     <lb/>
     away from a large portion of tho people the 
     <lb/>
     electoral franchise, are we to send this question 
     <lb/>
     to the electors, or to the whole people, and 
     <lb/>
     under what regulations? We have heard a 
     <lb/>
     good deal about appeals to the people, and I 
     <lb/>
     would like to look back at the history of this 
     <lb/>
     country to shew, as I believe I can, that such 
     <lb/>
     an appeal is not desirable or necessary. What 
     <lb/>
     did we do a few years ago? We passed a bill 
     <lb/>
     by which the franchise was nearly doubled in 
     <lb/>
     the numbers of the persons called on to exer<lb break="no"/>cise it; and is not the franchise the source of 
     <lb/>
     all right and power? Did the opponents of 
     <lb/>
     that measure ask an appeal to the people? 
     <lb/>
     Not at all. Afterwards the suffrage was still 
     <lb/>
     further extended and made almost universal 
     <lb/>
     without a word about appeals to the people. 
     <lb/>
     Not long ago, when Mr. Johnston was in 
     <lb/>
     power he introduced a bill altering to a large 
     <lb/>
     extent, the franchise and re-distributing the 
     <lb/>
        

            <pb n="246" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_246.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">246</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
          

     seats; did his worst opponent say anything 
     <lb/>
     then about an appeal to the people? No, the 
     <lb/>
     whole matter was discussed without such a 
     <lb/>
     question being raised. If, when I quote the 
     <lb/>
     acts of the conservative party, I am met with 
     <lb/>
     the answer from gentlemen on this side that 
     <lb/>
     this is poor authority. I ask did we (the liberal 
     <lb/>
     party) not within a short time, feeling that 
     <lb/>
     the franchise was too extensive, and that the 
     <lb/>
     time had come when the property of the coun<lb break="no"/>try should be represented by the property 
     <lb/>
     holders pass a bill striking down one- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     third, if not one half the electors. There was 
     <lb/>
     no appeal to the people in that case, this house 
     <lb/>
     did not ask it, although it was sought. by a gen<lb break="no"/>tleman in the Upper House. Am I not there<lb break="no"/>fore acting in accordance with the policy of 
     <lb/>
     my party, who maintained that the people 
     <lb/>
     were here  present by their representatives?— 
     <lb/>
     Let me come now to another time. Had we 
     <lb/>
     not in 1864 a resolution brought into the legis<lb break="no"/>lature, by the leading minds upon both sides, 
     <lb/>
     for the Union of the Maritime Provinces? Not 
     <lb/>
     to confederate them, but to unite them under 
     <lb/>
     one government and legislature. Was any<lb break="no"/>thing said about an appeal to the people then? 
     <lb/>
     No; it was said that the delegates should re<lb break="no"/>turn, in order that we, the legislature, might 
     <lb/>
     ratify their arrangements. I ask the house 
     <lb/>
     whether or not, if the legislature of the differ<lb break="no"/>ent. Colonies had accepted a scheme of <choice><sic>legisla<lb break="no"/>lative</sic><corr>legislative</corr></choice> union of the Maritime Provinces, there 
     <lb/>
     would have been on appeal to the people? We 
     <lb/>
     have heard about traitors to the country, and 
     <lb/>
     traitors to the party. We are told that the Li<lb break="no"/>beral party are opposed to the scheme, and my 
     <lb/>
     position is not at all agreeable to my friends 
     <lb/>
     who sit beside me, or to myself, in separating 
     <lb/>
     from them. I got my liberalism very early: I 
     <lb/>
     drew it with my earliest breath and learned 
     <lb/>
     its principles at the feet of such men as Dr. 
     <lb/>
     McCulloch and Jotham Blanchard; and I 
     <lb/>
     claim to have been as consistent a member of 
     <lb/>
     that party as any one in Nova Scotia, here or 
     <lb/>
     elsewhere What was the watchword of that 
     <lb/>
     party? They have always claimed as their 
     <lb/>
     watchword, Reform and Progress,—and that 
     <lb/>
     this movement is a progressive one, I firmly 
     <lb/>
     believe. This is a measure of progress, and if 
     <lb/>
     opposition was to be expected, we had little 
     <lb/>
     reason to look for it among the Liberals of the 
     <lb/>
     country. I feel that I have not forsaken Libe<lb break="no"/>ral principles and that it would be as hard to do 
     <lb/>
     so as for the "Ethiopian" to change his skin or 
     <lb/>
     the leopard his spots." I feel that I am where I 
     <lb/>
     ought to be and where I wish every liberal in 
     <lb/>
     the country was following our principles to 
     <lb/>
     their legitimate end, going forward and not 
     <lb/>
     adhering to the ol fogy and tory principles of 
     <lb/>
     keeping every thing in the old position with<lb break="no"/>out making an advance, and opposing every 
     <lb/>
     change, just because it is change. As I said, I 
     <lb/>
     was brought up a liberal, as I advanced in life 
     <lb/>
     I sustained the leaders of the liberal party. 
     <lb/>
     When I first came into this house, under a good 
     <lb/>
     deal of temptation and trial, I sustained Wil<lb break="no"/>liam Young  and Joseph Howe in their princi<lb break="no"/>ples, and if I am to be told that I am deserting 
     <lb/>
     the party now I reply that I do not feel 
     <lb/>
     ashamed to follow the liberal <hi rendition="simple:italic">par excellence</hi> of 
     <lb/>
     British American, the hon. George Brown and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Tilley of New Brunswick, men who ate 
     <lb/>
     liberals at the heart's core, men who have 
     <lb/>
     long fought. for the principles of their party, 
     <lb/>
         
<cb/>

and under their flag and in their ranks I am 
     <lb/>not ashamed to stand. Coming home I ask 
     <lb/>whether when I am in association with the lead<lb break="no"/>er of the opposition in this House and in the 
     <lb/>other, and assisting in carrying forward the 
     <lb/>question so long and so often proposed by the 
     <lb/>liberal party of this country, I am not where 
     <lb/>a liberal should be found. It was not my in<lb break="no"/>tention to address the house at length, and I 
     <lb/>will not continue longer. The principles which 
     <lb/>I now to maintain are those of the party of pro<lb break="no"/>gress; we have with us the young men of Nova 
     <lb/>Scotia, who are identified with its future pro<lb break="no"/>gress—the best and most intelligent men in all 
     <lb/>the provinces, and all who look forward to be<lb break="no"/>ing not merely Nova Scotians, Canadians, or 
     <lb/>New Brunwickers, but citizens of British 
     <lb/>North America, and all who desire to see our 
     <lb/>country occupying her true position. With 
     <lb/>their assistance these objects must be soon at<lb break="no"/>tained. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">REMARKS OF MR. TOWNSEND. 
     <lb/>
            </head>


            <p>Mr. TOWNSEND spoke substantially as fol<lb break="no"/>lows:—I feel a great deal of  reluctance is rising 
     <lb/>to address the house on the present occasion, 
     <lb/>when I see all the legal talent arrayed against 
     <lb/>the on this important question. I feel, how<lb break="no"/>ever, that I stand here with the great mass of 
     <lb/>the people at my back. I contend that we have 
     <lb/>no right to deal with the question; the people 
     <lb/>did not send us here to deal with it; they do 
     <lb/>not yet know its merits. I cannot believe that 
     <lb/>such immense advantages will spring from 
     <lb/>Union as some gentlemen profess to see 
     <lb/>ahead. You cannot force trade out of its natu<lb break="no"/>ral channels. The State of Maine, and not 
     <lb/>Nova Scotia, is the natural frontage of Cana<lb break="no"/>da. The interests of the people do not lie in 
     <lb/>the direction of connection with Canada. As 
     <lb/>far as my own people are concerned, I know 
     <lb/>if you were to ask them if they would prefer 
     <lb/>Annexation to Confederation,  they would an<lb break="no"/>swer, yes. Their commercial interests are 
     <lb/>intimately bound up with those of the 
     <lb/>United States, and it is not therefore sur<lb break="no"/>prising that such a sentiment should prevail.— 
     <lb/>They say, give us connection with a country 
     <lb/>that will protect us. Canada cannot take care 
     <lb/>of us. I do not feel this way myself, but still 
     <lb/>I know what I state is perfectly correct. I 
     <lb/>know that, simple man as I am, I cannot 
     <lb/>change your sentiments on this question. All 
     <lb/>the leading talent of the house is against it.— 
     <lb/>We have no leader; I do not acknowledge the 
     <lb/>hon. member for East Halifax as such. The<lb/>leader of the Opposition is with the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment on this question; he supports them on 
     <lb/>the School Bill and Confederation, and I am 
     <lb/>only surprised that he is not one of their 
     <lb/>number. I deny that Mr. Annand is my lead<lb break="no"/>er. Can I take a man that says a thing on the 
     <lb/>street, and then comes here to prove it? I have 
     <lb/>yet to hear the arguments to satisfy me of the 
     <lb/>necessity for this Confederation. Is it advisa<lb break="no"/>ble to unite with a. country with such large 
     <lb/>debts and duties? to have to pay for the en<lb break="no"/>largement of her canals, and extension of her 
     <lb/>railways? A large proportion of our popula<lb break="no"/>tion fire fishermen and heavy consumers, and 
     <lb/>under Confederation when you increase the 
     <lb/>duties you must increase their expenses. The 
     <lb/>Intercolonial Railway will only benefit us so 
     <lb/>far as it connects us with St. John. You can<lb break="no"/>not carry flour in quantity for any great dis<lb break="no"/>
       

            <pb n="247" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_247.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY</fw>
            <fw type="num">247</fw>
          

tance over the railways; the barrels are injur<lb break="no"/>ed; water communication is infinitely prefera<lb break="no"/>ble. lt is only  to winner that the road will be 
     <lb/>
     found of any particular advantage What I 
     <lb/>
     fear is  that if you pass this measure  in the 
     <lb/>
     mode proposed  you will convulse the country 
     <lb/>
     from one end to the other. All we require 
     <lb/>
     is to be allowed to manage our own 
     <lb/>
     affairs in our own way. 1 do not think 
     <lb/>
     that we can be better off than we are  
     <lb/>
     now under  any circumstances. Why  
     <lb/>
     not then let well enough alone, and cease dis<lb break="no"/>turbing the country at what gentlemen say is 
     <lb/>
     a critical period  of its history? The Quebec 
     <lb/>
     scheme  is as good a scheme as any you can 
     <lb/>
     devise, but I don't it want any at all.  I know 
     <lb/>
     that the constituents are to a man opposed to 
     <lb/>
     the proposed Confederation, and I am deter 
     <lb/>
     mined to stand by them. I feel that they will 
     <lb/>
     look upon   the present action with horror and 
     <lb/>
     alarm. My people, I say, would prefer An<lb break="no"/>nexation to Confederation, but only let a 
     <lb/>
     thousand   Fenians come among them, and the 
     <lb/>
     fellows would not he heard of. Let England 
     <lb/>
     or  Canada be assailed, and two thuds of our 
     <lb/>
     young men will volunteer to take care of the 
     <lb/>
     country. But still we do not wish to be hur<lb break="no"/>ried into Confederation. We want the people 
     <lb/>
     to have a voice in the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SPEECH OF THE HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Hon ATTY GENERAL said :—I have been la<lb break="no"/>bouring for some days past under a hoarseness, 
     <lb/>
     which is not at all pleasant, and I do not feel 
     <lb/>
     now in a condition to do justice to the import<lb break="no"/>ant subject before the House; but as gentle<lb break="no"/>men appear indisposed to speak on the subject, 
     <lb/>
     I shall endeavour, without preparation, to give 
     <lb/>
     my thoughts as concisely as is possible. The 
     <lb/>
     question is one of such great magnitude that I 
     <lb/>
     feel I am hardly doing my duty in addressing 
     <lb/>
     the House under the circumstances I have 
     <lb/>
     stated. The present question is one which is 
     <lb/>
     fraught with most fruitful consequences to the 
     <lb/>
    people of this province, as well as of all British 
     <lb/> North America. We have thrown upon us a 
     <lb/>responsibility by the tide of events which we 
     <lb/>must assume, unless we are willing to fail in 
     <lb/>the duty we owe to the people. It will be for 
     <lb/>gentlemen, looking at the whole position 
     <lb/>calmly and dispassionately, to deal with the 
     <lb/>question as subjects of our beloved Queen, 
     <lb/>anxious to perpetuate the connection with the 
     <lb/>British Empire. All considerations of party 
     <lb/>politics should be laid aside, and no influences 
     <lb/>should prevail, except the desire to arrive at a 
     <lb/>conclusion that will benefit the people whose 
     <lb/>interests we have in charge. I contend that, 
     <lb/>as subjects of the Queen of England, as mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the province of Nova Scotia, we have 
     <lb/>duties now to discharge of a most onerous 
     <lb/>character. We have been accustomed from 
     <lb/>our childhood to take an interest in the great 
     <lb/>country from which we have sprung. We 
     <lb/>have drawn from that country the principles 
     <lb/>that lie at the foundation of all our institu<lb break="no"/>tions. We should look at the present question, 
     <lb/>not merely in the capacity of provincial repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives, but as subjects of the great empire 
     <lb/>of Great Britain. I hold this doctrine, and I 
     <lb/>believe it is a patriotic one, that we should 
     <lb/>consider in our deliberations that we are act<lb break="no"/>ing not only for the advantage of Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>but also in the interests of the great empire on 
     <lb/>which the sun in said never to set. I have 
     <lb/>
          


    
            <cb/>
       

     listened with some interest to the speech just 
     <lb/>
     delivered by the hon. member for Yarmouth 
     <lb/>
     (Mr.  Townsed), and although I must condemn 
     <lb/>
     his disloyal sentiments, yet I feel he is at all 
     <lb/>
     events entitled to some credit for the candor 
     <lb/>
     with which he stated them. I can understand 
     <lb/>
     that hon. member coming forward and pro<lb break="no"/>claiming, to the House and country that the 
     <lb/>
     people of Yarmouth have no loyalty except 
     <lb/>
     what puts money into their pockets. We can 
     <lb/>
     understand  that argument against the 
     <lb/>
     union of the Provinces, and need not therefore 
     <lb/>
     be surprised that nine-tenths of the people of 
     <lb/>
     that section are opposed to Confederation.— 
     <lb/>
     We therefore see plainly why the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man is opposed to a union of British North 
     <lb/>
     America. We can understand gentlemen who 
     <lb/>
     argue this  way, who prefer annexation with 
     <lb/>
     the " Stars and Stripes" to England's " Meteor 
     <lb/>
     flag," but  what are we  to think of gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     who come forward and say that they are 
     <lb/>
     actuated by very different motives —that they 
     <lb/>
     wish to keep up the connection with the 
     <lb/>
     British Crown; they say they are loyal, but 
     <lb/>
     that if we confederate, we must be eventually 
     <lb/>
     annexed to the United States. That is an 
     <lb/>
     argument which requires some explanation 
     <lb/>
     before it can satisfy those who have studied 
     <lb/>
     the question of union and have come to the 
     <lb/>
     conclusion that a union ol the Provinces is 
     <lb/>
     necessary to the continuance ol their connec<lb break="no"/>tion with Great Britain, and their only safety 
     <lb/>
     against annexation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When the resolution was passed in this 
     <lb/>
     House, providing for a Conference to consider 
     <lb/>
     the question of a union of the Maritime Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, we all believed that a union with Cana<lb break="no"/>da was impracticable at that time—that she 
     <lb/>
     would not be moved by an appeal from these 
     <lb/>
     colonies—that any movement on our part would 
     <lb/>
     not influence her. That was the sole reason 
     <lb/>
     why Canada is not included in the resolution 
     <lb/>
     in question. We believed that union of the 
     <lb/>
     Maritime  Provinces was alone practicable, and 
     <lb/>
     thatit it would lead to the larger Union. A dele<lb break="no"/>gation was sent to Charlottetown, but before it 
     <lb/>
     took place what was announced in all the news. 
     <lb/>
     papers? What was everywhere known and 
     <lb/>
     understoood? What was the understanding of 
     <lb/>
     every man that went on that delegation? Why, 
     <lb/>
     that the delegates of the Maritimes Provinces 
     <lb/>
     were to meet a delegation from Canada at 
     <lb/>
     Charlottetown in reference to a Union of Bri<lb break="no"/>tish North America. Gentlemen, now busily 
     <lb/>
     occupied in opposing union, were aware what 
     <lb/>
     was to take place at that convention. I have 
     <lb/>
     no hesitation in saying that the fact was known 
     <lb/>
     to Mr. Howe, and publicly stated in his pre<lb break="no"/>sence at the dinner given to the Canadian gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen, but who, in a number of articles, has 
     <lb/>
     been obstructing union for the last eighteen 
     <lb/>
     months—who has called these connected with 
     <lb/>
     the Quebec scheme "traitors"; thereby stigma<lb break="no"/>tizing his own political friends and allies as 
     <lb/>
     well as those who have been opposed to him in 
     <lb/>
     public life, He has charged them with having 
     <lb/>
     sold and bartered away the rights of the people 
     <lb/>
     of the country, and when a gentleman under 
     <lb/>
     his own hand, makes such charges against 
     <lb/>
     others, he need not be surprised that they are 
     <lb/>
     thrown back against the individual who made 
     <lb/>
     them. That gentleman knew that the Dele<lb break="no"/>gates were to meet for the purpose stated. He 
     <lb/>
    did not wait to he asked to join that delega<lb break="no"/>tion, but personally solicited the appointment. 
     <lb/>
        


    
            <pb n="248" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_248.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">248</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
           

     When he was appointed and found that a man- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     of-war was ready to take him to Newfoundland, 
     <lb/>
     and that. he could not go to Prince Edward Is<lb break="no"/>land, be expressed his deep regret that he could 
     <lb/>
     not join us. Believing and expecting that 
     <lb/>
     something would grow out of that meeting, he 
     <lb/>
     wrote to the Government expressing regret 
     <lb/>
     that he could not join the delegation, but that 
     <lb/>
     when he returned in October he would be hap<lb break="no"/>py to aid them in any scheme that. might be ar<lb break="no"/>ranged. It is not necessary for me to go over 
     <lb/>
     the evidence that he was always in favor of a 
     <lb/>
     union of the Provinces. Whilst conducting a 
     <lb/>
    leading public jounal he advocated it for years;  
     <lb/>within these walls be repeatedly referred to 
     <lb/>the subject in a manner that was calculated to 
     <lb/>bring conviction to the people of this country. 
     <lb/>Who does not remember the story he told so 
     <lb/>often that. when he arrived in Liverpool a con<lb break="no"/>sul from the United States, the bearer of im<lb break="no"/>portant despatches, was allowed to go ashore, 
     <lb/>whilst he had to remain in the ship. Should a 
     <lb/>Colonist, he said, be considered so little entitled 
     <lb/>to consideration? Should not the Colonies as<lb break="no"/>sume a position that would entitle them to 
     <lb/>more respect among the nations of the world? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I am not going to recapitulate what occurred 
     <lb/>at Charlottetown, or enter into any elaborate 
     <lb/>exposition: of the necessity and advantages of 
     <lb/>union ; it has been throughly discussed in the 
     <lb/>press and on the platform, and on the floors of 
     <lb/>this House. I have yet, to hear, in this debate, 
     <lb/>anything on the subject that has not been often 
     <lb/>said before. It is complained that. there are 
     <lb/>eleven lawyers in this House in favor of the 
     <lb/>scheme; but are not the best minds in the coun<lb break="no"/>try also supporting it ? I need not tell gentle<lb break="no"/>men who are opposing this great measure of 
     <lb/>intercolonial progress, and who the "head cen<lb break="no"/>tre" is. He is well known in this House and 
     <lb/>country; he has been receiving pay from the 
     <lb/>Imperial Government for the past two years, 
     <lb/>but,opposed to the views of that Government, 
     <lb/>has been secretly using every means to thwart 
     <lb/>them. and at the same time tried to de ude the 
     <lb/>people by a letter that he was not opposing the 
     <lb/>measure in any shape. Now that his pay has 
     <lb/>ceased, the mask in thrown off, and we find 
     <lb/>him openly in antagonism to the measure 
     <lb/>which he pretended he had not endeavored to 
     <lb/>thwart. He, a servant of the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, has been for months past insidiously la 
     <lb/>boring to destroy a scheme that he knew had 
     <lb/>secured the approval of that Government, of 
     <lb/>the British Parliament and people, and the best 
     <lb/>minds in British North America. This is a 
     <lb/>free country, and every man is at liberty to 
     <lb/>write what he wishes; but there are responsi<lb break="no"/>bilities thrown upon some persons in reference 
     <lb/>to many public measures that should induce 
     <lb/>them to act with great discretion. That discre<lb break="no"/>tion has not been observed by Mr. Howe. He 
     <lb/>has forgotten the responsibility that he owes to 
     <lb/>the people of this country. He was not called 
     <lb/>upon as a public man, for he occupied no posi<lb break="no"/>tion in this country that required his action. 
     <lb/>but he has gone out of his way to oppose this 
     <lb/>measure, and to slander and villify members of 
     <lb/>this House, on both sides. We are told that. 
     <lb/>this is the patriot of Nova Scotia, and that 
     <lb/>therefore he is entitled to consideration. Let 
     <lb/>us see the position that the hon. gentleman oc<lb break="no"/>cupies before the people of Nova Scotia, and 
     <lb/>scrutinize his claims to the confidence of the 
     <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
          

     country. He went to England on a railway 
     <lb/>
     mission, three or four years ago, and entered 
     <lb/>
     into an arrangement. by which the people of 
     <lb/>
     this province would have to pay three and a 
     <lb/>
     half twelfths of the entire cost of the intercolon<lb break="no"/>ial Railway, and then came back and, by the 
     <lb/>
     power of a small majority, whilst an employee 
     <lb/>
     of the British Government, passed an act to 
     <lb/>
     carry it out. Now, when the road is to be 
     <lb/>
     built on most advantageous terms, he is found 
     <lb/>
     opposing a scheme of union without which its 
     <lb/>
     construction must be delayed for years He 
     <lb/>
     went to the county of Lunenburg at the general 
     <lb/>
     election in 1863, and the people rejected him by 
     <lb/>
     an overwhelming majority. He has since then 
     <lb/>
     been in the pay of the British Government, but 
     <lb/>
     during that time what evidence did he give of 
     <lb/>
     his patriotism ? Did he serve the interests of 
     <lb/>
     the  people on any single occasion? No; his 
     <lb/>
     patriotism was subdued by his salary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This gentleman, whose ability is undoubted, 
     <lb/>
     whose speeches I have listened to on the floor 
     <lb/>
     of this House with the greatest. interest, as<lb break="no"/>sumes to be the guide of the people. Let us 
     <lb/>
     see what claims he has to that position. We 
     <lb/>
     all know that the Reciprocity Treaty was en<lb break="no"/>tered into in 1854. It came to be ratified in this 
     <lb/>
     House, and where do we find that hon.  member? 
     <lb/>
     We found him endeavoring to defeat that mea<lb break="no"/>sure, and dividing the House on the question. 
     <lb/>
     If the hon. member had been successtul, we 
     <lb/>
     would never have had any Reciprocity Treaty, 
     <lb/>
     as far as Nova Scotia is concerned, and the ad<lb break="no"/>vantages of that measure and the favorable 
     <lb/>
     position it now so strongly enables us to take 
     <lb/>
     in dealing with that question, would have been 
     <lb/>
     wholly lost. Again, the question of the settle<lb break="no"/>ment of the Mines and Minerals came up for 
     <lb/>
     consideration in l858. It was arranged by a 
     <lb/>
     gentleman taken from each side of the House— 
     <lb/>
     by the present Judge in Equity and the hon. 
     <lb/>
     leader of the Opposition. Mr. Howe led up an 
     <lb/>
     opposition to the measure, and did all in his 
     <lb/>
     power to frustrate the arrangements that the 
     <lb/>
     delegates had made in London. These were 
     <lb/>
     two important questions which have proved 
     <lb/>
     most advantageous to the people, and yet Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Howe, the patriot, was found throwing obsta<lb break="no"/>cles in their way. Again, the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     became a railway commissioner, and I need 
     <lb/>
     not remind the House that, in 1856, he was con<lb break="no"/>stantly found button-holing members, and en<lb break="no"/>deavoring to upset the Government of his own 
     <lb/>
     party, whose subordinate officer he was. If 
     <lb/>
     that Government, which he represented as rest<lb break="no"/>ing over a volcano, was not immediately 
     <lb/>
     broken up, it was not his fault. Things went 
     <lb/>
     on this way until 1857, when the Gourley shanty 
     <lb/>
     riots occurred. We all remember the religious 
     <lb/>
     animosities that were excited. Who was the 
     <lb/>
     origin? This same gentleman. He destroyed 
     <lb/>
     his own political friends by forcing measures 
     <lb/>
     upon them which they could not with safety 
     <lb/>
     adopt, and which divided, as he knew it would, 
     <lb/>
     his own party. He raised religious strife in this 
     <lb/>
     country for his own personal objects, and ex<lb break="no"/>cited neighbor against neighbor who had lived 
     <lb/>
     for years in peace and quietude. He managed 
     <lb/>
     by this means to get into power in 1859, but do 
     <lb/>
     you think he endeavored to preserve consis<lb break="no"/>tency of action? Nothing of the kind. After 
     <lb/>
     his success, by a. small majority, which was 
     <lb/>
     subsequently melting away. and feeling the 
     <lb/>
     power unrighteously obtained fast slipping 
     <lb/>
        

            <pb n="249" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_249.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY</fw>
            <fw type="num">249</fw>
     

     away, and in order to avert it, he did not hesi<lb break="no"/>tate to seek aid from the very men he had pro<lb break="no"/>scribed, and to assert that his professions to 
     <lb/>
     others were false, and that he had only wanted 
     <lb/>
     a little capital by which to get back into power 
     <lb/>
     This is the gentleman who now attempts to 
     <lb/>
     deal with the people of Nova Scotia, and tell 
     <lb/>
     them that they should follow his advice. He 
     <lb/>
     has been opposed to the continuance in office 
     <lb/>
     of the present Government, and he made over<lb break="no"/>tures to Opposition gentlemen likely to support 
     <lb/>
     the Confederation scheme, asked them not to 
     <lb/>
     allow the present Government to carry it, that 
     <lb/>
     if they would only help him to overthrow the 
     <lb/>
     present Administration he and they might, if 
     <lb/>
     necessary, pass the measure when they got into 
     <lb/>
     power. I am not making this statement, rashly. 
     <lb/>
     I can prove it by what has passed between them 
     <lb/>
     within and without the walls of this building. 
     <lb/>
     His opposition is, I am satisfied, not so much to 
     <lb/>
     Union as that the men in power should carry 
     <lb/>
     the measure. That is the patriotism that in<lb break="no"/>fluences the hon. member. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>There is another gentleman opposite who op<lb break="no"/>poses this measure, and that is the hon. member 
     <lb/>for East Halifax. I regret to say anything se<lb break="no"/>vere about that gentleman, for he has passed 
     <lb/>through an ordeal in this house which entitles 
     <lb/>him to commisseration. He endeavored to 
     <lb/>blacken the character of men connected with 
     <lb/>the Quebec scheme. We all know the state<lb break="no"/>ment made concerning Hon.George Brown, and 
     <lb/>the refutation it has met, even from his attempt 
     <lb/>at escape by denying his own words, uttered in 
     <lb/>our presence. I ask the hon. member to consid<lb break="no"/>er the position he occupies on this question. I 
     <lb/>am prepared to prove by the most conclusive 
     <lb/>evidence that the hon member, within the last 
     <lb/>two or three weeks, would have been willing to 
     <lb/>go for this very resolution, without any stipu 
     <lb/>lation as to an appeal to the people. What has 
     <lb/>changed the hon member since? Have there 
     <lb/>been any new arrivals in this country since he 
     <lb/>formed and uttered this intention? Has there 
     <lb/>been any influence brought to bear upon him? 
     <lb/>A gentleman has written article after article 
     <lb/>on the subject, who has stated deliberately that 
     <lb/>he would be willing to support this scheme, 
     <lb/>now comes here and tells us that he has yet 
     <lb/>to hear "the first argument in favor of union 
     <lb/>with Canada." He attempted to define his 
     <lb/>position the other day, but I am quite sure that 
     <lb/>when he was done, nobody knew where to find 
     <lb/>him.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On the several occasions that this question 
     <lb/>
     has been before the House, I have not said a 
     <lb/>
     single word on the subject. It was one of those 
     <lb/>
     questions that I did not wish to deal hastily 
     <lb/>
     with; I was anxious to ascertain how it could 
     <lb/>
     be carried out in accordance with the public in<lb break="no"/>terests, and how far the measure could be prac<lb break="no"/>tically dealt with. We went to Quebec, and I 
     <lb/>
     listened attentively to the arguments in con<lb break="no"/>nection with the subject of Union. When, I 
     <lb/>
     saw that a practicable scheme could he mature 
     <lb/>
     ed which would do justice to all interests, and 
     <lb/>
     believing it was necessary for the welfare and 
     <lb/>
     prosperity of the people of British North Ame<lb break="no"/>rica, then alone did I consent to be a party to 
     <lb/>
     it. As respects the Quebec Scheme, I may 
     <lb/>
     state that I had my doubts as to the correctness 
     <lb/>
     of some of its features. and divided the conven<lb break="no"/>tion on them. I objected to the pardoning 
     <lb/>power given to the local governors, who are 
     <lb/>simply delegates from the General Govern<lb break="no"/>
         

            <cb/>
       
ment, believing that feature would be regarded 
     <lb/>
     by the British Government as against principle. 
     <lb/>
     I objected again to that portion of the scheme 
     <lb/>
     by which the number of the Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cil is stereotyped; I held that it was preferable 
     <lb/>
     to continue the principle of the British Consti<lb break="no"/>tution, which allows the Crown to add to the 
     <lb/>
     number of the Upper House, but I was over<lb break="no"/>ruled by the allegation of the difficulty of ar<lb break="no"/>ranging the numbers which might be added so 
     <lb/>
     as not to alter the relative numbers from all 
     <lb/>
     the Provinces. I felt, however, although op<lb break="no"/>posed to some of the details, that it would be 
     <lb/>
     for the interest of the Provinces to adopt it as a 
     <lb/>
     whole. I felt that whilst they remain isolated, 
     <lb/>
     instead of becoming more intimately connect<lb break="no"/>ed and better acquainted, they were likely to 
     <lb/>
     become more an more antagonistic to each 
     <lb/>
     other. I had before me the position of two Aus<lb break="no"/>tralian Colonies which came nearly to war in 
     <lb/>
     consequence of some financial dispute between 
     <lb/>
     them. Some goods were seized by the one, and 
     <lb/>
     attempted to be rescued by the other, and they 
     <lb/>
     were only restrained from the adoption of ex<lb break="no"/>treme measures by being Colonies instead of 
     <lb/>
     independent countries. We have trade rela<lb break="no"/>tions between the Provinces that are injurious 
     <lb/>
     to all of them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. member for East Halifax says that 
     <lb/>
     we can have changes, and those relations im<lb break="no"/>proved without union. Well, the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man tried that on one occasion, and found that 
     <lb/>
     the difficulties that met him were of a most in<lb break="no"/>surmountable character. We are told that the 
     <lb/>
     currency could be assimilated, but the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member must have changed his opinions on 
     <lb/>
     this subject very recently, or he would not now 
     <lb/>
     desire to alter or assimilate the currency. A 
     <lb/>
     few years ago I introduced a bill for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of giving the country a decimal currency, 
     <lb/>
     founded on the basis of the American, Canadi<lb break="no"/>an and New Brunswick currency; but he voted 
     <lb/>
     against it, and he and his party did all they 
     <lb/>
     could to prevent us assimilating our currency 
     <lb/>
     to that of the neighboring States and Provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. member denies that Union can in<lb break="no"/>crease our capacity for defence, but no one is 
     <lb/>
     likely to believe that his opinions are entitled 
     <lb/>
     to greater weight than the eminent statesmen 
     <lb/>
     and generals who have given their views on 
     <lb/>
     the subject. At present each of the provinces 
     <lb/>
     looks to its own safety, and does not trouble 
     <lb/>
     itself much about its neighbour. We can hear 
     <lb/>
     with comparative quietude that the Fenians 
     <lb/>
     are about to land in New Brunswick,but if we 
     <lb/>
     hear that Nova Scotia is endangered and its 
     <lb/>
     soil invaded, our blood is excited, and we feel 
     <lb/>
     we must rise and defend our hearths and 
     <lb/>
     homes. If we were all united in one, if the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian felt that the soil of Nova Scotia is 
     <lb/>
     as dear to him as that of Canada—if Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia felt that Canada is a part of itself—we 
     <lb/>
     would all have a greater guarantee of security. 
     <lb/>
     We are told that disunited we can as effectu<lb break="no"/>ally defend ourselves. I would call attention 
     <lb/>
     to the position of Wellington in Spain. Whilst 
     <lb/>
     trammeled by the orders of the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, Spanish Junta, etc., he was powerless, 
     <lb/>
     but the moment he determined to act on his 
     <lb/>
     own responsibility, success crowned his arms 
     <lb/>
     Everybody must see the great advantage  that 
     <lb/>
     is derived from the concentration of authority 
     <lb/>
     in one hand. The most powerful government 
     <lb/>
     for speedy action is that which is despotic. If 
     <lb/>
     we have one concentrated authority in the 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="250" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_250.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">250</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
        

     country—one general command—our strength 
     <lb/>
     will be vastly increased, by the ability to con<lb break="no"/>centrate force when necessary at any import<lb break="no"/>ant point. The hon. member for East Halifax 
     <lb/>
     would have the people of the province pay 
     <lb/>
     pound for pound with those of Liverpool, Man<lb break="no"/>chester and London, and leave the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture to the British Government irresponsible 
     <lb/>
     of any power. We would then have no con<lb break="no"/>trol over the expenditure, and could no super<lb break="no"/>vise those who would expend the moneys thus 
     <lb/>
     raised. If we were united under one Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and had one Central Legislature, then 
     <lb/>
     the money would be under its control; and 
     <lb/>
     our own representatives would see that it was 
     <lb/>
     judiciously expended. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. member for East Halifax told us 
     <lb/>
     that the necessities of Canada forced them to 
     <lb/>
     unite with us. I tell the hon. gentleman Union 
     <lb/>
     was spoken of, and introduced by the gentle<lb break="no"/>man whose mouth-piece he is, long before it was 
     <lb/>
     thought of seriously in Canada. They had no 
     <lb/>
     necessities that forced them to a union with 
     <lb/>
     the Maritime Provinces. All that they had to 
     <lb/>
     do was to agree to the principle that is intro<lb break="no"/>duced into the Quebec scheme, Representation 
     <lb/>
     by population ; and I believe they will be 
     <lb/>
     found ready to adopt that principle in their 
     <lb/>
     own local affairs if this scheme fails. When 
     <lb/>
     this question is settled they have no important 
     <lb/>
     difficulties to disturb them. If the question of 
     <lb/>
     Union has attained its present position rapid<lb break="no"/>ly, it has been aided by the resolution that his 
     <lb/>
     own government introduced and carried in 
     <lb/>
     this House some years ago without a division. 
     <lb/>
     When Canada found that the Lower Provinces 
     <lb/>
     were taking measures for a union among them<lb break="no"/>selves, her public men asked if we could not 
     <lb/>
     unite in a Confederation of all the Provinces. 
     <lb/>
     When we went to Charlottetown, we found 
     <lb/>
     that, owing to the opposition both of New 
     <lb/>Brunswick and P. E. Island ,the smaller Union 
     <lb/>was impracticable. Not a word was said about 
     <lb/>union with Canada until it was found that 
     <lb/>union ot the Maritime Provinces could not be 
     <lb/>brought about. I may add, that the question 
     <lb/>of a Legislative union of the Maritime Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces was again brought up at the Quebec 
     <lb/>Convention. Canada and Nova Scotia urged 
     <lb/>that union, but gentlemen representing the two 
     <lb/>provinces named would not consent to that 
     <lb/>union. If, therefore the Maritime union has 
     <lb/>not been carried, it is not the fault of Nova 
     <lb/>Scotia or Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
      Reference has been made to the financial 
     <lb/>
     necessities of Canada. We know from our 
     <lb/>
     own experience that the revenue will fall off 
     <lb/>
     considerably during some years; one year 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia had a deficiency of £39,000. Three 
     <lb/>
      or, four years in succession of failure of crops af<lb break="no"/>fected the importations into Canada, and con<lb break="no"/>sequently caused a deficiency in the revenue, 
     <lb/>
     but I can assure gentlemen that Canada is not 
     <lb/>
     now in any position to require assistance. Yet 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen who would object to Confederation 
     <lb/>
     with Canada for fear of extra taxation, would 
     <lb/>
     have no unwillingness to annex us to the Uni<lb break="no"/>ted States, with its immense war debt and ex<lb break="no"/>hausting taxation. Canada now is as pros<lb break="no"/>perous as any  portion of the  globe. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. member told us that the Imperial 
     <lb/>
     Government had no policy until after the. re<lb break="no"/>port of the delegates. In this he may be cor<lb break="no"/>rect. The British government, looking at the 
     <lb/>
     fact that leading men representing both politi<lb break="no"/>
   

            <cb/>
     

     cal parties in the provinces were in favour of 
     <lb/>
     union and had adopted a measure for their 
     <lb/>
     confederation, had every reason to suppose 
     <lb/>
     that they represented the feelings and wishes 
     <lb/>
     of the country when the British public saw 
     <lb/>
     that the Colonies were entertaining the scheme 
     <lb/>
     for Union—that the leading men had concur<lb break="no"/>red in its details, they felt that. this was a mea<lb break="no"/>sure that invited their serious consideration 
     <lb/>
     and approval. I tell the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Shelburne that it is not only Mr. Cardwell 
     <lb/>
     who has spoken strongly on this question ; if 
     <lb/>
     he did not support it, I believe he could not 
     <lb/>
     remain in his present position. No govern<lb break="no"/>ment could be formed in England unless it en<lb break="no"/>couraged and stimulated this union, for public 
     <lb/>
     opinion in that country is almost unanimously 
     <lb/>
     in favor of that scheme. I know this from 
     <lb/>
     leading supporters as well as opponents of 
     <lb/>
     that government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have already pointed to some of the parties 
     <lb/>
     who are opposing the Union of the British 
     <lb/>
     North American Provinces. I have shown you 
     <lb/>
     that some of these gentlemen profess to be 
     <lb/>
     Annexationists to the American Republic— 
     <lb/>
     But we had on the promulgation of the Que<lb break="no"/>bec scheme opposition from another quarter.— 
     <lb/>
     It will be remembered that there was a paper 
     <lb/>
     published in Halifax under the not. very eu<lb break="no"/>phonious title of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bullfrog</hi>, patronised and 
     <lb/>
     encouraged very largely by gentlemen in the 
     <lb/>
     Anti-Confederate interest. This paper was 
     <lb/>
     edited principally by gentlemen in the Royal 
     <lb/>
     Artillery in this garrison, who have since pub<lb break="no"/>lished a work on Confederation, which I find 
     <lb/>
     reviewed in an English paper. I must. say that, 
     <lb/>
     if the Review expresses their views, these gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen have been guilty of the grossest libel 
     <lb/>
     upon the loyal people of Nova Scotia that was 
     <lb/>
     ever penned. When we look at a man's con<lb break="no"/>duct in all its relations, then only can we form 
     <lb/>
     a just conclusion as to the motives that actuate 
     <lb/>
     him. I will now read to you from a review of 
     <lb/>
     the work in question :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Confederation of British North America</hi>. By E. 
     <lb/>
     C BOLTON and H. H.  WEBBER, Royal Artillery.— 
     <lb/>
     London: Chapman and Ball. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The authors at this volume go dead against a 
     <lb/>
     scheme which was received with much approval in 
     <lb/>
     this country, and was believed to have been also on 
     <lb/>
     the whole, favourably looked upon in the colonies — 
     <lb/>
     We mean, of course, the proposal for the Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion of the British North American Provinces. lt 
     <lb/>
     seems , however, according to the authors of the work 
     <lb/>
     before us that we were all  wrong on the  subject — 
     <lb/>
     Confederation, they declare, is neither posible  nor 
     <lb/>
     desirable—indeed. ls not desired, in the wide sense of 
     <lb/>
     the word, at all. The maritime provinces. while 
     <lb/>
     they are favorable to a federation among themselves, 
     <lb/>
     are bitterly inimical to a union with Canada: while 
     <lb/>
     all the Colonies—Canada, New Brunswick. Nova Sco<lb break="no"/>tia, Prince Edward Island—<hi rendition="simple:italic">are much more inclined to 
     <lb/>
     be annexed to the United States than  to the confedera<lb break="no"/>tion proposed, and only value British connection for 
     <lb/>
     the sake of Imperial expenditure among them. The 
     <lb/>
      Confederation sheme the authors pronounce to be a 
     <lb/>
     farce; and, if carried out, a ruinous farce</hi>. The colo<lb break="no"/>nies wish to do nothing. and will do nothing to pro<lb break="no"/>vide defences for themselves. The mother country, 
     <lb/>
     they think, cannot do without them— in fact, would  
     <lb/>
     sink into the position of a third-rate power were her 
     <lb/>
     American colonies severed from her, while they 
     <lb/>
     would still retain their trade with the United States, 
     <lb/>
     with England and with the rest of the world. <hi rendition="simple:italic">The 
     <lb/>
     people of all the Provinces are we are told far more 
     <lb/>
     Yankee than British in their characters and their ha<lb break="no"/>bits, and even in their sympathis; and the loyalty to 
     <lb/>
     the Crown, of which we hear so much is, if we may 
     <lb/>
     trust Messrs. Bolton and Webber, only a mere lip af<lb break="no"/>fair, put on to keep up appearances and induce a con<lb break="no"/>
           

 <pb n="251" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_251.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">251</fw>
         

     tinuance of grants for public works, for fortifications, 
     <lb/>
     audfor the maintenance of troops in the provinces and 
     <lb/>
     of the navy on the station."</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Here you see the supporters of the Anti-Con<lb break="no"/>federation doctrines perpetrating this disgrace<lb break="no"/>ful libel upon the people of Nova Scotia. I 
     <lb/>
     hold that these gentlemen are no worse, how<lb break="no"/>ever, than those who here advocate annexe 
     <lb/>
     tion. We are told that our loyal is only a 
     <lb/>
     more lip service, that we value Brit sh connec<lb break="no"/>tion only for the advantages it brings with it— 
     <lb/>
     {or the money it affords us in connection with 
     <lb/>
     naval and military expenditures. I ask the 
     <lb/>
     hon member for East Halifax and those who 
     <lb/>
     are associating with him, ought they not to be 
     <lb/>
     proud of their connection with these gentle<lb break="no"/>men who hus libel our country? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are told that we should not go into this 
     <lb/>
     Union—that Nova Scotia is now happy and 
     <lb/>
     prosperous, and does not require union to 
     <lb/>
     make her more so. Let me ask how are we 
     <lb/>
     going to provide for the continuance of that 
     <lb/>
     prosperity? Who of all the Anticonfederates 
     <lb/>
     can show ns where, without union, we will be 
     <lb/>
     in two years?-who can guarantee us our po<lb break="no"/>sition for that period or less time? We only 
     <lb/>
     jeopardize it whilst we remain isolated as at 
     <lb/>
     present. Look at the geographical position of 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia, at her great resources, and ask it 
     <lb/>
     she should not wish to be even more prosper<lb break="no"/>ous than she actually is, or without union can 
     <lb/>
     ever expect to be. What is it that placed 
     <lb/>
     England in her present exalted position 
     <lb/>
     among thenatlons of the world? What is it 
     <lb/>
     that has given her continued supremacy on 
     <lb/>
     the sea, and as a manufacturing country? 
     <lb/>
     Ber mines of coal and iron. What have we in 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia? She is partly a fishing and 
     <lb/>
     partly an agricultural country, but she has 
     <lb/>
     also most valuable mineral resources only is 
     <lb/>
     the infancy of their development. If you con<lb break="no"/>sider her water power, and mines of coal and 
     <lb/>
     iron, and her geographical situation you see 
     <lb/>
     all the elements of a rest manu acturiug 
     <lb/>
     country on this side of the country. Whilst 
     <lb/>
     we have no market we cannot expect to see 
     <lb/>
     our manufacturing system develop itself, but 
     <lb/>
     if we had a market of four millions of consu<lb break="no"/>mers, then we might expect, in a fair competi<lb break="no"/>tion, to see them progress. Give her the popu<lb break="no"/>lation, and I am con dent that she will take a 
     <lb/>
     position in the manufacturing world that no 
     <lb/>
     country of the same size can far surpass. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are told that we can have free trade 
     <lb/>
     without union, but that cannot be roved; we 
     <lb/>
     are told it I repeat, but not the slightest evi<lb break="no"/>dence is adduced to show how we can obtain 
     <lb/>
     it. There are intercolonial commercial rival<lb break="no"/>ries that prevent that object being attained as 
     <lb/>
     applicable to manufactures. Wherever an at<lb break="no"/>tempt has been made in this direction, failure 
     <lb/>
     has followed, and <hi rendition="simple:italic">will</hi> follow hereafter. No<lb break="no"/>thing is more certain than the truth of the 
     <lb/>
     principle that when you attach a small coun<lb break="no"/>try having all the elements of manufacturing, 
     <lb/>
     to a greater one th a large population, you 
     <lb/>
     benefit that smaller country. Situated as we 
     <lb/>
     are on the broad Atlantic, with our ports open  
     <lb/>
     at all seasons of the year, with our fisheries, 
     <lb/>
     mineral and other resources, we may become 
     <lb/>the entrepot for a large extra trade between<lb/>the other British North America colonies and<lb/>the West Indies and other parts of the world,<lb/>and only require a union with a larger coun<lb break="no"/>try to become great and prosperous to an unli<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
   

     mited degree. A trade will arise that will 
     <lb/>
     give employment toour shipping, and we may 
     <lb/>
     at (i will no doubt, add largely to that ship<lb break="no"/>ping and the amount of our carrying trade. 
     <lb/>But sir, if no increased prosperity will <choice><sic>re<lb break="no"/>ult</sic><corr>result</corr></choice> from union, I again ask who can <choice><sic>guaran<lb break="no"/>ee</sic><corr>guarantee</corr></choice> to Nova Scotia the position she now occu<lb break="no"/>pies ? Look at the state of things on. 
     <lb/>this continent, and ask yourselves is not the 
     <lb/>danger imminent if we remain isolated as at 
     <lb/>present. If, on the other hand, we are able to; 
     <lb/>get by the union a guarantee of the continu<lb break="no"/>ance and increase of this prosperity—if we can 
     <lb/>by it perpetuate the connection with the great 
     <lb/>
  
     Empire of which we form a part, is it not our 
     <lb/>
     duty as well as interest to do so without de<lb break="no"/>lay, and not risk the continuance of that con<lb break="no"/>nection by a selfish and exclusive policy 
     <lb/>
     against the unanimous wish of the people who 
     <lb/>
     protect us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are told by the hon. member for East 
     <lb/>
     Halifax that there is a sentiment prevalent in 
     <lb/>
     England in favor of getting rid of these Colo<lb break="no"/>nies. I had a better opportunity than the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman of judging the state of public 
     <lb/>
     opinion, and I travell over the country more 
     <lb/>
     than he did. I can unhesitatingly state that 
     <lb/>
     in no part of the mother country did I discover 
     <lb/>
     any such sentiment as he speaks of. We have 
     <lb/>
     heard of the Manchester school of politicians 
     <lb/>
     who are said to be unfavorably disposed to<lb break="no"/>wards those Colonies of the Crown; and de<lb break="no"/>sirous for their separation. That party is 
     <lb/>
     small," it is all, which I very much doubt; 
     <lb/>
     and it certainly does not represent the senti<lb break="no"/>ment of the people. I had the honour on one 
     <lb/>
     occasion, during my late visit to England, of 
     <lb/>
     sitting down to a luncheon, at Rochdale, a lit<lb break="no"/>tle out of Manchester, with some one hundred 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen of standinh and influence. I was 
     <lb/>
    presented to them during the entertainment as 
     <lb/>having one been of the delegates who went 
     <lb/>from Nova Bcotia to the Quebec Conference,to 
     <lb/>frame the scheme of the nice of the Provin<lb break="no"/>ces. I can only say that the statement was re<lb break="no"/>ceived with universal applause, and I was call<lb break="no"/>ed upon torespoud to the toast. I never felt, 
     <lb/>grander in in life than to hear in that very   
     <lb/>heart of the Manchester district the cheers that 
     <lb/>rang from one end of the building to the other; 
     <lb/>when I promulgated the opinion that it  
     <lb/>would not be longl before the Colonies were 
     <lb/>united. A few politicians representing that   
     <lb/>part of the country may spout such ideas, 
     <lb/>

     but I am certain the hearts of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple are not with them. I believe that   
     <lb/>
     a similar feeling prevails among all classes of   
     <lb/>
     the people of Great Britain. I any such sen<lb break="no"/>timent entertained by parties in England 
     <lb/>
     as the hon member says, it is perhaps not diffi<lb break="no"/>cult to account for it. Persons there may be 
     <lb/>
    deluded into the idea that the Maritime Colo<lb break="no"/>nies are opposed to Confederation, thanks to 
     <lb/>the hon member and his associates. But if the 
     <lb/>hon member is correct, and England does <lb/>wish to throw us off, what ten, is to be our<lb/>fate? Where are we? What country do we<lb/>belong to? What must be the fate of $50,000<lb/>people left isolated and alone? Annexation<lb/>must inevitably follow. Therefore admitting<lb/>that such a feeling does exist in the mother<lb/>country, we have an additional argument in<lb/>favor of the necessity of Confederation—of a <lb/>union that will give unity and solidity; a po<lb break="no"/>pulation of four millions of souls bound toge<lb break="no"/>
      

            <pb n="252" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_252.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">252</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
       

     ther by the closest ties, determined to aid and 
     <lb/>
     strengthen one another and perpetuate the 
     <lb/>
     hallowed connection with our honored parent. 
     <lb/>
     If the mother country receives from us a pledge 
     <lb/>
     of earnestness in this matter, and believes that 
     <lb/>
     our great object is to keep up the connection 
     <lb/>
     with her, she will feel doubly bound to give 
     <lb/>
     renewed assurances for the continuance of 
     <lb/>
     that connection, and to sustain and protect us 
     <lb/>
     in the hour of need. She will feel that the co<lb break="no"/>lonies united in one great country will be a 
     <lb/>
     source of strength instead of weakness. If 
     <lb/>
     the colonies are consolidated—if they present 
     <lb/>
     a united population of millions of loyal sub<lb break="no"/>jects, England will feel a greater degree of se<lb break="no"/>curity than she can possibly do while they re<lb break="no"/>main more isolated communities without unity 
     <lb/>
     of purpose or design. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We are told that it is unconstitutional to 
     <lb/>
     pass the Resolution before the house—that the 
     <lb/>
     question should be referred to the people at 
     <lb/>
     the polls, but where is the argument that has 
     <lb/>
     been adduced in support of this reposition? 
     <lb/>
     We are told that it is a terrible thing to take 
     <lb/>
     away the rights of the people. Do these gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen correctly estimate the position we oc<lb break="no"/>cupy? Do they forget that we have certain 
     <lb/>
     responsibilities as forming a portion of the Em<lb break="no"/>pire of Great Britain? We have a constitu<lb break="no"/>tion of our own, I admit, and have the right 
     <lb/>
     to manage our own local affairs. We had con<lb break="no"/>ceded to us years ago the principle of Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government: but did we also obtain the 
     <lb/>
     right of exercising it against the rest of the 
     <lb/>
     Empire on a question involving Imperial as 
     <lb/>
     well as Inter-colonial interests? Are we to 
     <lb/>
     use it to the detriment of the mother-country 
     <lb/>
     and the sister-colonies? When Responsible 
     <lb/>
     Government was conceded to us, the principle 
     <lb/>
     of total independence did not accompany it.— 
     <lb/>
     We may pass an act here, but it must be rati<lb break="no"/>fied by the home government. We are depend<lb break="no"/>ent, and should where necessary, modify our 
     <lb/>
     views and measures to some extent when im<lb break="no"/>perial and inter—colonial interests are at stake. 
     <lb/>Whilst we are a dependency, we have the pro<lb break="no"/>tection of the mother-country, and she can at 
     <lb/>the same time ask from us the yielding of cer<lb break="no"/>tain rights as British subjects, for the benefit 
     <lb/>of the whole Empire. We are asked to—(Mr. 
     <lb/>Killam—To sell us)-the hon. member says to 
     <lb/>sell us; I would tell him that he would not ask 
     <lb/>a great deal to sell us to the United States to<lb break="no"/>morrow. (Cheers in the galleries.) I contend 
     <lb/>whenever overpowering interests of the em<lb break="no"/>pire demand it, the Imperial Government may 
     <lb/>fairly ask us to modify and amend our consti<lb break="no"/>tution, and that the representatives of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple can constitutionally consider and pass upon; 
     <lb/>the subject. Let us then look calmly at the 
     <lb/>position we occupy. We are told that this 
     <lb/>matter should be submitted to the people. I 
     <lb/>would ask these gentlemen to give us exam<lb break="no"/>ples where such a course has been pursued. 
     <lb/>Have they cited one case? Not one. How was 
     <lb/>the constitution changed in New Zealand? By 
     <lb/>the Legislature first adopting the measures for 
     <lb/>Union, and subsequently by an Imperial act. 
     <lb/>I can understand why,  if a resolution was 
     <lb/>moved for Annexation to the United States; 
     <lb/>some gentlemen would not see anything im<lb break="no"/>proper in it, but when we move one, under the 
     <lb/>authority  of the British Government, with the, 
     <lb/>view of joining the sister colonies, in order to 
     <lb/>give us strength and security, they prate about 
     <lb/>
     

            <cb/>
        

     the constitutionality of the proceeding. Sup<lb break="no"/>pose the British Parliament in the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the Empire should pass an Act for 
     <lb/>
     the consolidation of those Provinces, could 
     <lb/>
     the constitutional right of doing so be impugn<lb break="no"/>ed? The British Government have not inti<lb break="no"/>mated a desire to pursue that course but no 
     <lb/>
     person can deny its right to adopt that course. 
     <lb/>
     All, however, that they have done is to mani<lb break="no"/>fest their desire that we should manage the 
     <lb/>
     affair in our own way, and to give us their 
     <lb/>
     opinion that it is for own advantage that we 
     <lb/>
     should unite without delay. When gentle<lb break="no"/>men attempt to introduce a novel doctrine 
     <lb/>
     in this Legislature they should adduce some 
     <lb/>
     argument derived from the practice of other 
     <lb/>
     countries in support of their position. Can 
     <lb/>
     they show us an instance of a question after it 
     <lb/>
     has passed the Legislature, having been sent 
     <lb/>
     to the people? When a government intro<lb break="no"/>duces, but fail to carry, a measure, they can go 
     <lb/>
     to the country and test the public opinion. 
     <lb/>
     When a measure is proposed by a government 
     <lb/>
     and passed, the constitutional doctrine pre<lb break="no"/>vails that the gentlemen within these walls re<lb break="no"/>present the feelings  of their constituents. That 
     <lb/>
     must be the constitutional test, otherwise every 
     <lb/>
     measure of importance should be submitted to 
     <lb/>
     the people after its passage through the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature. We are told that the people are op<lb break="no"/>posed to this scheme but that has to be prov<lb break="no"/>ed. The people are hardly yet aware of the 
     <lb/>
     exact nature of the resolution, and therefore 
     <lb/>
     cannot be said to be  opposed to it. Some per<lb break="no"/>sons have objected to the Quebec scheme ; some 
     <lb/>
     have favored a legislative union; others are 
     <lb/>
     in favour of a modification of the former mea<lb break="no"/>sure. Various opinions prevail, but nearly all 
     <lb/>
     wish union, of some shape or other. I  hold 
     <lb/>
     that it is perfectly constitutional to pass this 
     <lb/>
     resolution—that we have an undoubted right 
     <lb/>
     to do so—gentlemen will remember that it is 
     <lb/>
     only a short time since that the Legislature of 
     <lb/>
     Jamaica passed an act to destroy its own con<lb break="no"/>stitution? Did these Anti-Confederate gentle<lb break="no"/>men come forward and declare that to be un<lb break="no"/>constitutional? Not at all. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We propose only to transfer certain powers 
     <lb/>
     to a Legislative body comprising a fair repre<lb break="no"/>sentation of our own, chosen on the principle 
     <lb/>
     of population. It is not a Confederation in the 
     <lb/>
     strict term of the word. it is a Legislative 
     <lb/>
    union to a large extent. The peeple will elect 
     <lb/> their  representatives as they do now, and 
     <lb/>each county will have its member in the Ge<lb break="no"/>neral Parliament. Objection has been taken 
     <lb/>to the principle of representation based on po<lb break="no"/>pulation, but what else can you have? We 
     <lb/>could not expect to have as large a represen<lb break="no"/>tation as Canada, nor could Prince Edward 
     <lb/>Island ask as many representatives as Nova 
     <lb/>Scotia or New Brunswick, and if the numbers 
     <lb/>were not to be equal, I ask these gentlemen 
     <lb/>upon what principle would they be regulated 
     <lb/>except on that of population What was the 
     <lb/>cause of the difficulties that have arisen be<lb break="no"/>tween Upper and Lower Canada? It was be<lb break="no"/>cause that principle was not. incorporated in 
     <lb/>the Act of Union. After a few years Upper 
     <lb/>Canada, at first less than Lower  Canada but 
     <lb/>subsequently largely increased in population , 
     <lb/>did not consider that it was fully represented,  
     <lb/>and demanded that its  representation should 
     <lb/>be based on numbers. We are told that this 
     <lb/>is not a Legislative Union, because all the sub<lb break="no"/>
         

            <pb n="253" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_253.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">253</fw>
        
jects that come before a Legislature are not 
     <lb/>
     embraced in it. If they are not embraced in it 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia has not therefore much cause for 
     <lb/>
     complaint. Education, Roads and Bridges, 
     <lb/>
     the control of our jurisprudence, and other 
     <lb/>
     subjects in which we take the deepest interest 
     <lb/>
     are left to our own controul. Then we have 
     <lb/>
     the same amount per head for our local 
     <lb/>
     government that they have in Canada, 
     <lb/>
     and if we manage to spend more money in 
     <lb/>
     proportion to our population than she does, it 
     <lb/>
     is only right we should pay for it. We go into 
     <lb/>
     that Union on the same terms. Every man, 
     <lb/>
     woman, and child will owe the same debt— 
     <lb/>
     receive the same amount from the general ex<lb break="no"/>chequer—as each man, woman, and child in 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and we shall have our full share of 
     <lb/>
     all the expenditures by the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment for important public objects. We are 
     <lb/>
     told, however, nineteen members will have no 
     <lb/>
     influence in the General Legislature. I con<lb break="no"/>tend they will have as much influence rela<lb break="no"/>tively as the eight gentlemen representing 
     <lb/>
     Cape Breton now exercise in this house of fif<lb break="no"/>ty-five. That island is felt to be a part of our 
     <lb/>
     country, and entitled to a share of the general 
     <lb/>
     prosperity, and in Union each of the Provinces 
     <lb/>
     will feel an interest in the prosperity of the 
     <lb/>
     others. There may be some little rivalries, as 
     <lb/>
     we have now, but these will not exist as to lo<lb break="no"/>cal expenditures so much as affecting general 
     <lb/>
     principles and measures. Talent and energy 
     <lb/>
     will assert their proper positions in the gene<lb break="no"/>ral legislature as it does here and everywhere 
     <lb/>
     under free institutions. Nova Scotia may be a 
     <lb/>
     small Province, but her men will be able to 
     <lb/>
     hold their own I trust in the United Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. The nineteen men she will select to re<lb break="no"/>present her will, I have no doubt, be able to 
     <lb/>
     protect her interests. As I have just said, 
     <lb/>
     Cape Breton receives a large influence in this 
     <lb/>
     House; her members have received everything 
     <lb/>
     that they can reasonably ask. Party Govern<lb break="no"/>ment must prevail in the new Parliament.— 
     <lb/>
     here must, as in all countries under Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government be a Government and an 
     <lb/>
     Opposition, and Nova Scotia will exercise with 
     <lb/>
     her nineteen members a sufficient influence.— 
     <lb/>
     There is no party, however strong. that can af<lb break="no"/>ford to neglect the legitimate local interests of 
     <lb/>
     any one of their supporters. This government 
     <lb/>
     came into power some years ago, with a ma<lb break="no"/>jority such as was never seen before in Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia, and who can allege that the local in<lb break="no"/>terests of any section were neglected. It is 
     <lb/>
     true that no government can satisfy the 
     <lb/>
     demands of all their followers—nor can they 
     <lb/>
     in adopting a general line of policy satisfy 
     <lb/>
     their friends; but I am now referring to the 
     <lb/>
     local interests that are to be represented. If 
     <lb/>
     any gentlemen have withdrawn their support 
     <lb/>
     from the government it is on general subjects; 
     <lb/>
     no one can say that local interests are disre<lb break="no"/>garded; and I am free to say that the gentle<lb break="no"/>men from Nova Scotia will get their fair share 
     <lb/>
     of everything that they require for there is no 
     <lb/>
     party at Ottawa that could refuse it to them 
     <lb/>
     with impunity. We all know that the Irish 
     <lb/>
     party, comparatively few in number, to a large 
     <lb/>
     extent, controlled public matters for years 
     <lb/>
     in the British Parliament.  
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>We have had all sorts of aspersions thrown 
     <lb/>upon us. It is said that we are actuated sole<lb break="no"/>ly by selfish motives. One gentleman is to be 
     <lb/>a governor, another a judge, everybody is to 
     <lb/>
   

            <cb/>
        

     get something. I believe that the gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     who talk this way have some ideas floating in 
     <lb/>
     their minds that by opposing this scheme they 
     <lb/>
     may become something of the kind them<lb break="no"/>selves. They believe, and the secret was let 
     <lb/>
     out by the hon. member for East Halifax, that 
     <lb/>
     the government is unpopular, in consequence 
     <lb/>
     of the School Bill; that if they can only keep 
     <lb/>
     things as they are for a few months longer, 
     <lb/>
     until a general election, they may come into 
     <lb/>
     power themselves; that when the present go<lb break="no"/>vernment is defeated, and they step out of of<lb break="no"/>fice, they can, if necessary, carry Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion themselves—then, no doubt, the people 
     <lb/>will be in favor of it—nothing will be then 
     <lb/>said about the constitutionality of dealing with 
     <lb/>it irrespective of an appeal to the people; or, 
     <lb/>they will have their choice of leaving things as 
     <lb/>they are, and holding an office as long as they 
     <lb/>can. Visions of Financial and other secretary<lb break="no"/>ships; offices of Queen's Printer and others, 
     <lb/>are no doubt urging their powerful influences 
     <lb/>upon the patriotic minds of these gentlemen. 
     <lb/>80 we may fairly suppose that these are 
     <lb/>the reasons that sway some hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen, rather than these suggestions 
     <lb/>of patriotism of which we hear so 
     <lb/>much, but in practice see so little. They 
     <lb/>wish to have the alternative of choosing or re<lb break="no"/>jecting Confederation, according as it may suit 
     <lb/>their own personal interests. Therefore they 
     <lb/>urge delay on the part of the present govern<lb break="no"/>ment in reference to the question. What un<lb break="no"/>selfish patriots! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     The hon member for Halifax has admitted 
     <lb/>
     that he said to gentlemen in this house that he 
     <lb/>
     would go to New Brunswick to see some An<lb break="no"/>ti-confederates for the purpose of ascertaining 
     <lb/>
     whether they would not agree to a resolution 
     <lb/>
     something like the present one. He will allow 
     <lb/>
     me to say that if he had gone to the sister Pro<lb break="no"/>vince he would not have found Mr. Smith op<lb break="no"/>posed to a union of the Provinces. I am not 
     <lb/>
     taking a liberty with that gentleman when I 
     <lb/>
     say that he has never pronounced himself 
     <lb/>
     against a scheme which would remove the ob<lb break="no"/>jections he entertains to the Quebec plan of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. The state of things in that 
     <lb/>
     Province itself proves that the large mass of 
     <lb/>
     the people entertain similar views on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     I know that I have not dealt with this ques<lb break="no"/>tion as its importance demands, but although 
     <lb/>
     unprepared and not expecting to speak to day 
     <lb/>
     I could not allow the resolution to pass with a 
     <lb/>
     silent vote. Present and aiding in the Char<lb break="no"/>lottetown and Quebec Conventions, I came to 
     <lb/>
     the conclusion that it was for the interest of 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia as well as her duty to the great 
     <lb/>
     Empire to which she belongs, that she should 
     <lb/>
     adopt this Union. I have endeavoured to 
     <lb/>
     give these crude observations in a dis<lb break="no"/>passionate and calm manner. I have gi<lb break="no"/>ven some of the reasons that influence my 
     <lb/>
     judgment in favour of the resolution before 
     <lb/>
     the house and now say most emphatically that 
     <lb/>
     if there are any persons who prefer annexation 
     <lb/>
     to the United States, let them, in Heaven's 
     <lb/>
     name, follow the example of the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Yarmouth, but do not let them attempt 
     <lb/>
     by false representations to thwart the efforts 
     <lb/>
     of those who would bring about a Union of the 
     <lb/>
     Provinces. I say, however, to gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     around these benches, who value the flag that 
     <lb/>
     " for a thousand years has braved the battle 
     <lb/>
        

            <pb n="254" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_254.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">254</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
        

     and the breeze," and that has planted liberty 
     <lb/>
     and freedom in every quarter of the globe—to 
     <lb/>
     all those who are inspired by a desire to per<lb break="no"/>petuate the connection with the British Em<lb break="no"/>pire, come forward and support the measure, 
     <lb/>
     which will at once achieve this result, and at 
     <lb/>
     the same time give that dignity of position 
     <lb/>
     and security to the Provinces that in their 
     <lb/>
     present isolated position they can never hope 
     <lb/>
     to obtain. (Cheers). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
      SPEECH OF MR. KAULBACK. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. KAULBACK said :—I feel some diffidence 
     <lb/>
     in addressing the House upon a question of such 
     <lb/>
     importance; but I consider it a duty devolving 
     <lb/>
     on me to express my views upon it, and in 
     <lb/>
     doing so I shall have occasion to refer to the 
     <lb/>
     arguments of some gentlemen who have preceded 
     <lb/>
     me. I conceive that this subject, having been 
     <lb/>
     long before the country, is no new question; 
     <lb/>
     it has been before the people for more than half 
     <lb/>
     a century, and has been agitated by our leading 
     <lb/>
     men for a great span of years. Every man con<lb break="no"/>sidering the question should surely have solved 
     <lb/>
     it and matured his mind by this time. In 1814 
     <lb/>
     Judge Sewell, of Quebec, urged the necessity of 
     <lb/>
     a scheme of British North America on the 
     <lb/>
     Duke of Kent. A Union of the Colonies 
     <lb/>
     was urged by the Earl of Durham in 1839 when 
     <lb/>
     a scheme analogous to that now before us was 
     <lb/>
     mentioned. In 1849 a British American League 
     <lb/>
     was formed in Toronto who seemed to have had 
     <lb/>
     the matter fully before them. In 1854 we had 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Johnston moving in the matter, supported 
     <lb/>
     by Mr. Howe and Mr. Young. From 1854 to 
     <lb/>
     1860 we have correspondence on the subject. In 
     <lb/>
     1857 Mr. Johnston was delegated to go to Eng<lb break="no"/>land in connection with Intercolonial matters. 
     <lb/>
     In 1858 there was a delegation from Canada of 
     <lb/>
     the same kind. In 1860 Dr. Tupper delivered 
     <lb/>
     lectured on a. Union of the Colonies; in 1861 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Howe moved a resolution which was adopted 
     <lb/>
     by the House. In 1862 Mr. Annand, Mr. Howe 
     <lb/>
     and Mr. McCully went to Canada on the subject. 
     <lb/>
     In 1863 Mr. McGee lectured in Halifax, and in 
     <lb/>
     1864 I was present at a banquet in this city 
     <lb/>
     when Mr. Howe gave an eloquent address on 
     <lb/>
     the question. It cannot therefore be said, that 
     <lb/>
     the time has not arrived when the question 
     <lb/>
     should be solved. The hon. member for Shel<lb break="no"/>burne made a reference to some distinguished 
     <lb/>
     Canadian politicians and styled one of them an 
     <lb/>
     Irish rebel. I have only to reply that we find 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Howe, in 1863, on a platform in Tem<lb break="no"/>perance Hall, eulogized Mr. D'Arcy McGee, and 
     <lb/>
     declared that he "was with him in all he said" 
     <lb/>
     in favor of a Union of all the British North 
     <lb/>
     American Colonies ;—now he ridicules Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McGee, and denounces any Union with Canada: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     In 1863 Mr. Howe declared in Temperance Ball 
     <lb/>
     -<hi rendition="simple:italic">" Task of the Fall Quebec being a source of sorrow 
     <lb/>
     to the inhabitants of this province. It would be more 
     <lb/>
     if the St Lawrence were in the hands of our enemies.</hi> 
     <lb/>
     WE SHOULD BE COMPELLED TO BEG PERMISSION TO 
     <lb/>
     TEAR DOWN THE BRITISH FLAG <hi rendition="simple:italic">What he wished for 
     <lb/>
    Nova Scotia was that she may be the frontage of a 
     <lb/>mighty Colony upon which it may be truly said, the 
     <lb/>sun never sets "</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

    

            <p>
     Notwithstanding this we find Mr. Howe wri<lb break="no"/>ting the Botheration articles, and his public 
     <lb/>
           

            <cb/>
       

     character is open to much doubt from that time. 
     <lb/>
     As others who were present at the dinner to the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian guests, in 1864, have said, the question 
     <lb/>
     of Union was then in the public mind. I well 
     <lb/>
     recollect the speech made by Mr. Howe on that 
     <lb/>
     occasion ; and as his observations were more 
     <lb/>
     eloquent than anything that I can say, I will 
     <lb/>
     ask attention to a few of his sentences :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " He was not one of those who thanked God that 
     <lb/>
     he was a Nova Scotian merely, for he was Canadian 
     <lb/>
     as well. He had never thought he was a Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotian, but he had looked across the broad continent, 
     <lb/>
     at the great territory which the Almighty had given 
     <lb/>
     us for an inheritance, and studied the mode by which 
     <lb/>
     it could be consolidated, the mode by which it could 
     <lb/>
     be united, the mode by which it could be made strong 
     <lb/>
     and vigorous, while the old flag still  floated  over the 
     <lb/>
     soil. (Loud cheers ) He was delighted to see such a 
     <lb/>
     scene as this, which gave promise to that which was 
     <lb/>
     the dream of his boyhood would he realised betore 
     <lb/>
    he died. " 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     " Thank God the time had come when Her Majes<lb break="no"/>ty's subjects. whether English, French, Scotch, or 
     <lb/>
     Irish, might meet together under the old flag, and 
     <lb/>
     maintain common sentiments of unity, and look for<lb break="no"/>ward to the time when we should make a new Eng<lb break="no"/>land here; not a <hi rendition="simple:italic">new</hi> England with republican insti<lb break="no"/>tutions. but a new England with monarchical institu<lb break="no"/>tions. He had always  been in favor of the intercolo<lb break="no"/>nist Railway. He wished every now and  again to see 
     <lb/>
     the seething falls of Montmorenci, to see  the indians 
     <lb/>
     of Lorette dancing about the silvery stream; he wan<lb break="no"/>ted to visit Canada not once in a lifetime, not once 
     <lb/>
     in five or six years, but once or twice a year " 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " With the territory of Canada, with the rivers of 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia. with the inexhaustible fisheries what a 
     <lb/>
     country to live in! And why should Union not be 
     <lb/>
     brought about! Was it because we wished to live 
     <lb/>
     and die in our insignificance, that we would sooner 
     <lb/>
     make money rather than that our country should 
     <lb/>
     grow? God forbid! He felt that it was too late to 
     <lb/>
     say much, though there was much to say. (" Go on, 
     <lb/>
     go on.") He knew that the Canadian gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     would take in good par what he was going to say.— 
     <lb/>
     He had always been in favor of uniting any two. three 
     <lb/>
     four, or the whole five of the Provinces. Well, they 
     <lb/>
     knew the history et the past in Canada; they knew 
     <lb/>
     what division had produced there, and how, under 
     <lb/>
     the divine dispensation, they at last became united 
     <lb/>
     into one magnificent colony. There now came ru<lb break="no"/>mors across the land that they were going to split Ca<lb break="no"/>nada into two parts again; that they  were going to 
     <lb/>
     reduce that low country to its low status of two pro<lb break="no"/>vinces instead of one. O, my friends. said the hon. 
     <lb/>
    gentleman. go back to your homes, and say that there 
     <lb/>is at least one Nova Scotian honest  enough to say to 
     <lb/>you this,—that, if you do that, you will commit an 
     <lb/>act of political suicide, and although I ought not per<lb break="no"/>haps to give you the advice. I would rather see every 
     <lb/>public man  upon both sides of politics crucified, than 
     <lb/>I would divide Canada now that Canada is united. 
     <lb/>Join the Maritme Provinces if you can; but, at any 
     <lb/>rate, stick together —hold your own. Let the dog re<lb break="no"/>turn to his vomit rather than Canada to division. 
     <lb/>(Cheers.) In conclusion. Mr. Howe said that he was 
     <lb/>pleased to think the day was rapidly approaching 
     <lb/>when the Provinces would be united with  <hi rendition="simple:italic">one flag 
     <lb/> above their heads, one thought in all their bosoms. with 
     <lb/>one Sovereign and one Constitution</hi>. (Loud and pro<lb break="no"/>longed Cheers.) 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>I would ask what is Mr. Howe's position on 
     <lb/>this question to-day ? He now appears advocat<lb break="no"/>ing a new line of policy one day, and another the 
     <lb/>next. The dream of his childhood be told us 
     <lb/>was Colonial Union, and now he says that it 
     <lb/>would be ruinous to the constitution. In his  
     <lb/>recently published letter he has gone far beyond 
     <lb/>what any public man should go, and his senti<lb break="no"/>ments I consider a di ace not only to himself 
     <lb/>but to those who accord with them. He tells us 
     <lb/>that we have an enemy before us whose number 
     <lb/>
     

    
            <pb n="255" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_255.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY</fw> <fw type="num">255</fw>
        

     and power are not to be despised in the Fenians, 
     <lb/>
     whose views are sympathized in by the Ameri<lb break="no"/>cans, and what does he advise us to do in the 
     <lb/>
     matter? Does he advise us to stand by our 
     <lb/>
     country and our flag? No, he desires us to 
     <lb/>
     lay down our weapons ; he tells us it is too late 
     <lb/>
     that we cannot defend ourselves, and that we 
     <lb/>
     are at the mercy of the enemy. His statements 
     <lb/>
     are the strongest argument that can be adduced 
     <lb/>
     in favour of a Union of the Colonies—they prove 
     <lb/>
     that the time is at hand for this measure, and 
     <lb/>
     that no time is to be lost. He speaks about put<lb break="no"/>ting on a blue-jacket and assisting in our de<lb break="no"/>fence; I consider that a man holding such sen<lb break="no"/>timents as his would be dangerous in such a 
     <lb/>
    position, for he has been endeavoring to excite 
     <lb/>a rebellion throughout the country, telling the 
     <lb/>people that they cannot defend themselves, that 
     <lb/>our connection with the mother country is un<lb break="no"/>safe, and that at this moment our better course 
     <lb/>is to lay down our arms on the approach of an 
     <lb/>enemy. He tells us that those who advocate the 
     <lb/>Union now will not be the men who will go to 
     <lb/>Canada, and the meaning of his letter seems to 
     <lb/>be that we must wait for him; only bring him 
     <lb/>back to power and he will not trouble himself to 
     <lb/>enquire whether he has been elected on this 
     <lb/>question or not. He will be the first man to 
     <lb/>advocate the Union when he returns to office and 
     <lb/>position. I am inclined to believe that all the 
     <lb/>opposition on this question are in favour of 
     <lb/>Union, and that they oppose it because they can<lb break="no"/>not avail themselves of the highest positions. 
     <lb/>Mr. Howe opens his second letter by saying 
     <lb/>" my advice has not been taken"; we have taken 
     <lb/>the advice he gave us formerly as to a Union of 
     <lb/>the Colonies, but how could his more recent 
     <lb/>advice be taken when it is well known that he 
     <lb/>is writing disloyal letters injurious to the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. I say, sir, that we have seen enough of 
     <lb/>this gentleman to know that he has broken faith 
     <lb/>on every public question, and that everything he 
     <lb/>can say must be received with a large amount 
     <lb/>of doubt. When in days gone bye he advocated 
     <lb/>Union, did he ask for an appeal to the people? 
     <lb/>No, the Legislature was to decide the question, 
     <lb/>and yet he tells us it is unconstitutional to take 
     <lb/>such a course. That is the position which this 
     <lb/>gentleman has aasumed. He declared some 
     <lb/>time ago that Halifax would not be safe without 
     <lb/>connection with Canada by rail; now he tells 
     <lb/>us that Canada is only a source of weakness. 
     <lb/>These are inconsistencies which no man can 
     <lb/>reconcile. Again he agreed that Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>should build three-and-a half twelfths of the 
     <lb/>whole cost of the Intercolonial Railway. We 
     <lb/>are now to get the Railway built for one-twelfth, 
     <lb/>and yet he comes out in opposition to the whole 
     <lb/>thing.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
    

    

            <p>
     Reference has been made to the recent election 
     <lb/>
     in the county of Lunenburg; all I can say is 
     <lb/>
     that the result proves to my mind that there is a 
     <lb/>
     large  majority of the people in favour of Con<lb break="no"/>federation. The government were perfectly 
     <lb/>
     indifferent to the election, and it was only the 
     <lb/>
    day previous to the nomination that, to my great  
     <lb/>surprise, I received a telegram stating that the 
     <lb/>Provincial Secretary was coming down. All 
     <lb/>
          

            <cb/>
        

     the opposition made most strenuous efforts ; 
     <lb/>
     they came down and made no secret that they 
     <lb/>
     intended to buy the county. Their friends said 
     <lb/>
     at a caucus that they could not carry the county 
     <lb/>
     on the issue of Confederation, for the people 
     <lb/>
     were largely in favour of it. They then resort<lb break="no"/>ed to every subterfuge to win the election. The 
     <lb/>
     result proves that of 3200 voters only 1300 were 
     <lb/>
     in favour of Mr. Hebb. The School Bill was 
     <lb/>
     the question that settled the election. I had 
     <lb/>
     not taken any part in the affair, until I saw that 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Richmond had come down. 
     <lb/>
     I did not feel inclined to take any active part 
     <lb/>
     because we had no man up. There were two 
     <lb/>
     men actually on the same side. I preferred Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Zwicker, however, because he declared himself 
     <lb/>
     for PROGRESS; but on Nomination Day be de<lb break="no"/>clared against the School Bill and Confederation. 
     <lb/>
     He spoke, then, however, under excitement, and 
     <lb/>
     his card led us to believe he was not as likely to 
     <lb/>
     oppose all measures of improvement and progress 
     <lb/>
     as Mr. Hebb. He was, therefore, in some res<lb break="no"/>pects preferable to the latter. We went into the 
     <lb/>
     township of Chester where the question of Con<lb break="no"/>federation was raised and discussed. The day 
     <lb/>
     before Nomination Day we had a meeting in the 
     <lb/>
     town, which lasted till a very late hour. And 
     <lb/>
     what was the result at every polling place ? The 
     <lb/>
     friends of the Quebec scheme were two to one. 
     <lb/>
     That was the only township where the scheme 
     <lb/>
     was put to the people I am no new convert to 
     <lb/>
     Union; but from the first hour it has been before 
     <lb/>
     the people I have been in favor of it. I believe 
     <lb/>
     in all sincerity, after the consideration I have 
     <lb/>
     given the subject, that our future prosperity de<lb break="no"/>pends largely on the issue of the present move<lb break="no"/>ment. I would be willing to go back to-morrow 
     <lb/>
     to my own county on this question, but I want 
     <lb/>
     to have the same people that sent me here pass 
     <lb/>
     on my acts. I wish to have the same franchise 
     <lb/>
     that returned me to the Assembly. The leading 
     <lb/>
     minds in the county of Lunenburg are in favor 
     <lb/>
     of Confederation. Have you seen more than a 
     <lb/>
     single petition against the scheme from my peo<lb break="no"/>ple? There is one purporting to be signed by 
     <lb/>
     111 persons, but any one who reviews it will 
     <lb/>
     see that the majority of the names are all 
     <lb/>
     written by one or two persons, and evidently at 
     <lb/>
     the same time. They had to scour the whole 
     <lb/>
     county, too, before they got the names they 
     <lb/>
     have to this document. Every man who got 
     <lb/>
     up the petition is known to be hostile to the 
     <lb/>
     School Bill. This is the way the House is led 
     <lb/>
     to believe that the people are opposed to Con<lb break="no"/>federation. It is the easiest thing in the world 
     <lb/>
     to get people to sign petitions; that everybody 
     <lb/>
     knows. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have heard with much regret the expres<lb break="no"/>sions that some gentlemen have been using on 
     <lb/>
     the floor as well as in the lobby of the House 
     <lb/>
     of Assembly. I could hardly control my feel<lb break="no"/>ings when I listened to the disloyal statements 
     <lb/>
     of some gentlemen in reference to the Queen and 
     <lb/>
     the representative oi her Majesty in this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. They have been positively insulting to 
     <lb/>
     Her Majesty and the ' Hero of Kars " Then 
     <lb/>
     we are told it is better to be annexed to the 
     <lb/>
     United States than to unite with Canada. What 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="256" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_256.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">256</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
        

     is the use of our Militia and preparations for 
     <lb/>
     defence, if we are to be handed over to the 
     <lb/>
     American Republic so summarily ? Every man 
     <lb/>
     who loves the flag under which he lives should 
     <lb/>
     sink all personal and political considerations, 
     <lb/>
     and join with those who are laboring to unite 
     <lb/>
     the Provinces more closely to the British 
     <lb/>
     Empire. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is not necessary that the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     East Halifax should utter disloyal expressions on 
     <lb/>
     the street; we have only to read the articles in 
     <lb/>
     his own paper. The logic of events for months 
     <lb/>
     past. has been telling us of the danger that is 
     <lb/>
     imminent. We know that the Fenian organiza<lb break="no"/>tion has attained to most formidable dimensions 
     <lb/>
     The President of the United States has himself 
     <lb/>
     deigned to receive deputations from these men. 
     <lb/>
     At so critical a period we have the hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber copying from papers in England (the Pall 
     <lb/>
     Mall Gazette for instance ) and endorsing their 
     <lb/>
     statements, I prove that we are not safe—that 
     <lb/>
     all the money England could expand upon us 
     <lb/>
     would be spent in vain—that we must be event<lb break="no"/>ually absorbed into the American Union. Is it 
     <lb/>
     any wonder, then, that men in the States are to 
     <lb/>
     be found in favor of Annexation ? Here is a 
     <lb/>
     specimen of what we read in the hon. member's 
     <lb/>
     journal — 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " At present we are arming and drilling expending 
     <lb/>
     money, time and men without stint, that. we may re<lb break="no"/>sist invasion of our territories by the Fenians. Is 
     <lb/>
     this because we are Colonists, or beceuse we are Bri<lb break="no"/>tons? It might be supposed from statement  of the 
     <lb/>
     Press that it is as Colonists we are arming ; but such 
     <lb/>
     is not the case. We are arming and drilling not so 
     <lb/>
     much to defend our homes, not so much to defend 
     <lb/>
     Canada, New Brunswick or Nova Scotia, as such, but 
     <lb/>
     to defend the honor, the integrity, and prestige of 
     <lb/>
     Britons. <hi rendition="simple:italic">All the expense annoyance and danger to 
     <lb/>
     which we are exposed is for the sake of Britain, not 
     <lb/>
     for our own. We are free from Britain we should 
     <lb/>
     hear nothing  of invasion by the Fenians."</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     What feeling is a statement like that inclined 
     <lb/>
     to make among our own people ? We are told 
     <lb/>
     that we are in bondage to Great Britain—that 
     <lb/>
     we are endangered by our connection with her, 
     <lb/>
     and that our safety lies in getting rid of her 
     <lb/>
     This is the way that these gentlemen have been 
     <lb/>
     endeavouring to indoctrinate the people with 
     <lb/>
     their Annexation ideas. They would rather 
     <lb/>
     belong to the United States than even remain 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotians. Shame, I say, upon men who 
     <lb/>
     can come into the presence of this loyal assem<lb break="no"/>blage with sentiments like these in their hearts! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When the hon member was Financial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary in 1862, the government brought up and 
     <lb/>
    carried this very question. He went then on a 
     <lb/>
     delegation to Quebec for the express purpose of 
     <lb/>
      carrying out the resolution passed unanimously 
     <lb/>
     in this House, and uniting us to Canada. Now 
     <lb/>
     he veers round when his former political asso<lb break="no"/>ciates, Mesrs Archibald and McCully wish to 
     <lb/>
     carry the question, and opposse all Untou. Last 
     <lb/>
     session he stated that the local revenue under 
     <lb/>
     Confederation would be $390 427- the same 
     <lb/>
     years he says in his paper that It would be 
     <lb/>
     only $62 700. Again, last session he admitted 
     <lb/>
     that this province under Confederation would 
     <lb/>
     receive from the General Government (beside 
     <lb/>
     the 80  cents per head of our population) $731,595 
     <lb/>
     On December 12th of  same year he says that all 
     <lb/>
          

            <cb/>
      

     the surplus over 80 cents a head would go to the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest of Canada. Could inconsistency go 
     <lb/>
     further ? Then he spoke to us about taxation in 
     <lb/>
     Canada - that we would have to pay double what 
     <lb/>
     we now pay. The fact is that the people of Ca<lb break="no"/>nada are not taxed, man for man, as much as we 
     <lb/>
     are. He tells us Canada is in debt. So are we. 
     <lb/>
     But Canada can point to public works equivalent 
     <lb/>
     to her debt—which is more than we can do. The 
     <lb/>
     hon member should know that if Canada falls, we 
     <lb/>
     fall too ; if she is safe, we are safe. Has not Mr 
     <lb/>
     Howe told us this himself? But what more does 
     <lb/>
     Mr Annand do? He has actually proposed to 
     <lb/>
     tax the people to a larger extent than they can, 
     <lb/>
     by any possibility, be taxed under Confederation. 
     <lb/>
      He is ready to pass a law by which the men of 
     <lb/>
     this country shall be sent to Canada when there 
     <lb/>
     is no Confederation —when we have no legislative 
     <lb/>
     control over her—when we are different countries. 
     <lb/>
     He even goes so far as to express his willingness 
     <lb/>
     to pay in the same proportion for defence as all 
     <lb/>
     other portions of the British Empire. Remem<lb break="no"/>ber, this is not for the protection of British North 
     <lb/>
      America alone, but for the whole Empire. Yet 
     <lb/>
     this is the gentleman who objects to  Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion because it may heavily burthen us. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve that if we have railway communication with 
     <lb/>
     Canada, it will be the means of making this coun<lb break="no"/>try safe from invasion. When we feel we are one 
     <lb/>
     people—when we have a national sentiment—
     <lb/>
     when we can present a united population of four 
     <lb/>
     millions of people animated by the same interests 
     <lb/>
     and affections, we shall have a guarantee of secu<lb break="no"/>rity and prosperity that we cannot have now.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Howe has told the people that the Citadel 
     <lb/>
     of Halifax would not he safe unless we had con<lb break="no"/>nection with Canada by means of an Intercolonial 
     <lb/>
     Railway. I think that neither he nor his friend, 
     <lb/>
     the hon member for East Halifax should talk 
     <lb/>
     about persons being bought. I heard the hon 
     <lb/>
     member quite distinctly say that he could have 
     <lb/>
     had money from hon George Brown if he had 
     <lb/>
     wished it, and place and preferment too, if he 
     <lb/>
     would only promise to support Confederation— 
     <lb/>
     If any person should attempt to bribe me with 
     <lb/>
     Canadian or American gold, I  would look upon it 
     <lb/>
     as the greatest insult that could be offered to a 
     <lb/>
     man, however humble. Mr. Brown must have 
     <lb/>
     had a very low estimate of the hon member if he 
     <lb/>
     made such an offer; but now the hon member at<lb break="no"/>tempts to deny that he ever made the statement 
     <lb/>
     he did on Friday last on the subject. Well, I 
     <lb/>
     shall not press the matter further, for he has al<lb break="no"/>ready been very thoroughly exposed, and all I can 
     <lb/>
     say is, that I think the hon member is the last 
     <lb/>
     person in the house to charge others with being 
     <lb/>
      bought.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. member told us that he had yet to 
     <lb/>
     hear the first argument in favor of union, though 
     <lb/>
     he had been a delegate on the question to Canada 
     <lb/>
     in 1862. Now, I find that in November last, 
     <lb/>
     1865, he expressed another opinion on the same 
     <lb/>
     subject— he wanted another delegation. He 
     <lb/>
     thought then he might have a chance of being 
     <lb/>
     one of the members sent on the mission. He 
     <lb/>
     says:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " This is our case. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>"The Confederation Scheme matured at 
     <lb/>
       

            <pb n="257" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_257.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">257</fw>
        

     Quebec having fallen to secure the approval of 
     <lb/>
     any one of the four Maritime Provinces, we 
     <lb/>
     would suggest that, <hi rendition="simple:italic">with a view to the future of 
     <lb/>
     British America</hi>, a convention be summoned, 
     <lb/>
     with the sanction of the Crown to deliberate upon 
     <lb/>
     the many weighty matters and things which 
     <lb/>
     would necessarily be involved in debate upon <hi rendition="simple:italic">a 
     <lb/>
     question of such magnitude and importance</hi>. That 
     <lb/>
     the convention should be held at such place and 
     <lb/>
     at such time as the Governor General, acting 
     <lb/>
     under the authority of the Crown, shall deter<lb break="no"/>mine. And that in the selection of delegates 
     <lb/>
     from the several Provinces, due regard shall be 
     <lb/>
     observed, besides allotting to each Province a 
     <lb/>
     like number of delegates, that the views and 
     <lb/>
     opinions of all parties are fairly represented. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <p>
     " This is our mode of dealing with the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of union. The convention might not, 
     <lb/>
     perhaps, agree to any scheme for the future Go<lb break="no"/>vernment of the North American Colonies and 
     <lb/>
     their relations with the Mother Country, <hi rendition="simple:italic">although 
     <lb/>
     we believe they would</hi>. And whatever the result, 
     <lb/>
     every one would feel that the questions of the 
     <lb/>
     deepest importance, involving the present welfare 
     <lb/>
     and happiness of four millions of people, had 
     <lb/>
     been discussed with a full view of their conse<lb break="no"/>quences as well to them as to millions yet 
     <lb/>
     unborn, and with the full benefit of all that has 
     <lb/>
     been said and written to illustrate this truly 
     <lb/>
     great theme since the schem  of Confederation 
     <lb/>
     was first proposed a little over a year ago "- 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Morning Chronicle</hi> Nov 15th 1865 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Yet, this is the hon. member who has yet to 
     <lb/>
     hear the first argument in favor of Union with 
     <lb/>
     Canada. The hon. member's inconsistencies are 
     <lb/>
     so glaring that I feel I need hardily pursue fur<lb break="no"/>ther so fruitful a topic. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It has been asked, will Confederation save us 
     <lb/>
     We have been told over and over again that there 
     <lb/>
     is no danger from the United States—that they 
     <lb/>
     do not want these Provinces. The lessons of 
     <lb/>
     history will tell us the reverse. These gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     have proved false prophets for the past, and are 
     <lb/>
     likely to be so for the future. The whole police 
     <lb/>
     of the United States has been the acquisition of 
     <lb/>
     territory. Their ambition is insatiable. They 
     <lb/>
     wish to have dominion from the North Pole to 
     <lb/>
     the Gulf of Mexico, and from the Atlantic to the 
     <lb/>
     Pacific. They have got Texas and California, 
     <lb/>
     and a slice of New Brunswick, within a few 
     <lb/>
     years, and now they yearn after British North 
     <lb/>
     America.  If they have had one reason more than 
     <lb/>
     another for abrogating the Reciprocity Treaty, is 
     <lb/>
     is that they think they will force us to come into 
     <lb/>
     the American Union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The question that we have to decide is, whether 
     <lb/>
     we shall belong to the United States or to Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain. Shall we have the Red Cross of England, 
     <lb/>
     or the Stars and Stripes of the American Repub<lb break="no"/>lic float over our heads in the future? Shall we 
     <lb/>
     have the Queen at St. Jame's as our Ruler, or 
     <lb/>
     the President at the White House in Washing<lb break="no"/>ton ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     What will be the result of annexation I need 
     <lb/>
     hardly tell you. We shall be ruined by most 
     <lb/>
     frightful taxation ; our fishermen, all our indust<lb break="no"/>rial class, will be burthened beyond their capacity 
     <lb/>
     to bear. Our object should be to continue the 
     <lb/>
    

            <cb/>
          

     connection with the great empire from which we 
     <lb/>
     have sprung, and under whose protecting care 
     <lb/>
     the institutions of this country have grown up, and 
     <lb/>
     our prosperity has been secured. No one, as I 
     <lb/>
     just said, can look at the feeling in the neighboring 
     <lb/>
     Republic without seeing that these Provinces are 
     <lb/>
     at present in a position of great jeopardy. In the 
     <lb/>
     first place, there is the Fenian organization grow<lb break="no"/>ing up into most formidable pretensions, and be<lb break="no"/>hind them is the great mass of the American 
     <lb/>
     people animated by the most deadly hostility 
     <lb/>
     against England arrising out of the late civil war. 
     <lb/>
     Then there is the question of the fisheries again 
     <lb/>
     looming up, and no one can under-estimate the 
     <lb/>
     difficulties and disputes it may originate. We see 
     <lb/>
     the Senate of the country itself exhibiting a spirit 
     <lb/>
     that looks warlike, and should put us on our 
     <lb/>
     guard. They are ready to support their fisher<lb break="no"/>men, if they should enter our harbours and bays, 
     <lb/>
     and enfringe upon our rights. Suppose war 
     <lb/>
     should arise out of this state of things; in what 
     <lb/>
     position would Nova. Scotia be, isolated as she is 
     <lb/>
     now? Comparatively defenceless. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Union, then, will ensure us security; will give 
     <lb/>
     us an immense expansion of trade; raise up 
     <lb/>
     manufactures, enlarge the political arena; give us 
     <lb/>
     the Intercolonial Railway; and above all preserve 
     <lb/>
     us from being absorbed by the rapacious Ameri<lb break="no"/>can Republic. We have great natural resources. 
     <lb/>
     but they must be dormant whilst we have no po<lb break="no"/>pulation or market to raise up manufactures in 
     <lb/>
     our midst. As respects the Intercolonial Rail<lb break="no"/>way, it is unnecessary for me to repeat what is 
     <lb/>
     now an established fact  that we cannot have it 
     <lb/>
     without union. The futile efforts of public men 
     <lb/>
     of all parties in this Province to obtain its con<lb break="no"/>struction are matters of history, and general no<lb break="no"/>toriety. Complete that railroad, and Halifax be<lb break="no"/>comes one of the greatest commercial emporiums 
     <lb/>
     of this continent—the New York or Liverpool of 
     <lb/>
     the British North American Confederation. No 
     <lb/>
     one who looks at the map can believe for a mo<lb break="no"/>ment that Nova Scotia was intended to remain 
     <lb/>
     politically divided from her sister colonies of Bri<lb break="no"/>tish North America. She is destined by nature — 
     <lb/>
     to quote the sentiment of Mr Howe— 'to be<lb break="no"/>come the frontage of a mighty Empire." Give us 
     <lb/>
     union, and the stream of immigration will be di<lb break="no"/>rected to our shores, for then we can offer those 
     <lb/>
     inducements to capital and labour that we cannot 
     <lb/>
     give in our present isolated condition. If we re<lb break="no"/>main disunited, then the prophecies of these gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen in respect to annexation will be realized. 
     <lb/>
     The time may come when we shall have the Bri<lb break="no"/>tish flag lowered beneath the stars and stripes, 
     <lb/>
     and the last gun fired from the Citadel as a British 
     <lb/>
     fort Let the American peeple feel that there is 
     <lb/>
     no British sentiment among us—let us obstinate 
     <lb/>
     ly reject the advice of the British government and 
     <lb/>
     people, and annexation will be the inevitable is<lb break="no"/>sue. Then the wish of the hon. member for East 
     <lb/>
     Halifax will be realized. <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Fenians will have 
     <lb/>
     full sway in these Provinces, and the stars and 
     <lb/>
      stripes shall float over Citadel Hill</hi>. But I believe 
     <lb/>
     that there is a better fate awaiting us—that the loy<lb break="no"/>alty of the people of Nova Scotia is sincere, and 
     <lb/>
     that they will see the necessit of union. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve Confederation is close at hand, and that the 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="258" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-16_Page_258.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">258</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
          

     efforts of those who would lead us into annexa<lb break="no"/>tion, will be effectually foiled by the loyal people. 
     <lb/>
     As far as I am concerned, all my interests are 
     <lb/>
     bound up with those of this Province—when she 
     <lb/>
     is prosperous then I feel satisfied. I am sprung 
     <lb/>
     from the early pioneers who helped to build up 
     <lb/>
     the prosperity of this country, and all I desire is 
     <lb/>
     to see it progress. I feel I would be recreant in 
     <lb/>
     my duty to those who have preceded me, as well 
     <lb/>
     as to those who may follow me and hear my name 
     <lb/>
     if I stood, at this crisis of our history, opposing a 
     <lb/>
     scheme which the best minds of Great Britain 
     <lb/>
     and British America have declared is indispens<lb break="no"/>able to the continuance ot our prosperity, and our 
     <lb/>
     connection with the fatherland. On the 24th 
     <lb/>
     June, '65, the British Government told us through 
     <lb/>
     the Colonial Secretary : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " You will at the same time express the strong 
     <lb/>
     and deliberate opinion of Her Majesty's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment that it is an object much to be desired that 
     <lb/>
     all the British North American Colonies should 
     <lb/>
     agree to unite in one Government. In the terri<lb break="no"/>torial extent of Canada, and in the Maritime and 
     <lb/>
     Commercial enterprise of the Lower Provinces, 
     <lb/>
     Her Majesty's Government see the elements of 
     <lb/>
     power, which only require to be combined in 
     <lb/>
     order to secure for these Provinces, which shall 
     <lb/>
     possess them all, a place among the most con<lb break="no"/>siderable communities of the world <hi rendition="simple:italic">In the 
     <lb/>
     spirit of loyalty to the British Crown of attachment 
     <lb/>
     to British connexion, and of love for British Insti<lb break="no"/>tutions, by which all these Provinces are animated 
     <lb/>
     alike, Her Majesty's Government recognize the 
     <lb/>
     bond by which all may be combined under one Go<lb break="no"/>vernment</hi>. Such an union seems to Her Majes<lb break="no"/>ty's Government to recommend itself to the 
     <lb/>
     Provinces on many grounds of moral and material 
     <lb/>
     advantages—as giving a well-founded prospect 
     <lb/>
     of improved administration and increased pros<lb break="no"/>perity 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " But there is one consideration which Her 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's Government feel it more especially 
     <lb/>
     their duty to press upon the Legislature of Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia. Looking to the determination which this 
     <lb/>
     country has ever exhibited in regard to the 
     <lb/>
     defence of the Colonies as a matter of Imperial 
     <lb/>
     concern, the Colonies must recognize a right and 
     <lb/>
     even acknowledge an obligation incumbent on 
     <lb/>
     the Home Government to urge with earnestness 
     <lb/>
     and just authority the measures which they con<lb break="no"/>sider most expedient on the part of the Colonists 
     <lb/>
     with a view to their own defence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " Nor can it be doubtful that the Provinces of 
     <lb/>
     British North America are incapable, when sepa<lb break="no"/>rate and divided from each other of making those 
     <lb/>
     just and efficient preparations for national de<lb break="no"/>fence which would be easily undertaken by a 
     <lb/>
     Province uniting in itself all the population and 
     <lb/>
     all the resources of the whole." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Here you find the British Government implor<lb break="no"/>ing us if we are animated by a sincere spirit of 
     <lb/>
     loyalty, by a desire to remain connected with 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain, to unite without delay. Can any 
     <lb/>
     one read these words unmoved? Let me trust 
     <lb/>
     that the people will respond to the demand made 
     <lb/>
     upon them by those who have the best right to 
     <lb/>
     proffer their advice, and hasten the time when we 
     <lb/>
     shall be united in one grand Confederation, "with 
     <lb/>
  
<cb/>

     one flag above our heads, one sentiment in our 
     <lb/>
     hearts, with one Sovereigh and one Constitution." 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2018-06-05, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
   
           <!-- <p>
     TUESDAY, April 17, 1866. 
     <lb/>
     The House met at 3 o'clock. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>UNION OF THE COLONIES. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. MILLER presented a large number of 
     <lb/>
     petitions from Antigonish on the subject of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. ROSS presented two petitions from St. 
     <lb/>
     Anns' on the same subject. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The adjourned debate was resumed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. S. CAMPBELL said:—I quite concur with 
     <lb/>
     those gentlemen who have attributed to this 
     <lb/>
     subject a magnitude and importance second 
     <lb/>
     to none that has ever been discussed in this 
     <lb/>
     House. Notwithstanding that there has been 
     <lb/>
     a good deal of excitement brought into this 
     <lb/>
     debate, and something more than excitement, 
     <lb/>
     a good deal of temper, it shall be my endeavor 
     <lb/>
     so to moderate my tone and language that not 
     <lb/>
     only shall these be in keeping with Parliament<lb break="no"/>ary decorum, but the remarks which I have to 
     <lb/>
     offer shall be otherwise entitled to the calm 
     <lb/>
     and sober consideration and reflection of the 
     <lb/>
     members around these benches. In short I 
     <lb/>
     shall not, in addressing this Assembly, ex<lb break="no"/>hibit any other demeanor or style of inter<lb break="no"/>course than that which I practice everywhere. 
     <lb/>
     On looking at the past I find satisfaction and 
     <lb/>
     comfort in the reflection that my bearing in 
     <lb/>
     the debates that have taken place here has 
     <lb/>
     been such as to enable me to meet gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     on all sides in pleasant relations, and I hope 
     <lb/>
     that in the future nothing will transpire to 
     <lb/>
     alter the character in those relations. On this 
     <lb/>
     subject, sir, I cannot but express regret that 
     <lb/>
     those from whom a better example should 
     <lb/>
     have proceeded should not have preserved 
     <lb/>
     something like moderation and decorum. 
     <lb/>
     Those who are in opposition are always most 
     <lb/>
     likely to be excited, but those in charge of a 
     <lb/>
     great measure such as this, especially the 
     <lb/>
     members ot'the government of the country, 
     <lb/>
     should ever feel it incumbent upon them 
     <lb/>
     so to guard themselves in this respect that 
     <lb/>
     no one here or elsewhere can possibly offer 
     <lb/>
     an objection to the course they have pursued. 
     <lb/>
     And, sir, I feel in observing on this portion of 
     <lb/>
     the discussion, that I have reason to charge 
     <lb/>
     the Provincial Secretary with having import<lb break="no"/>ed into this debate matters which should ne<lb break="no"/>ver have been brought here. He has alluded 
     <lb/>
     to the press—that is a branch of our constitu<lb break="no"/>tion, if I may so term it, that ought not to be 
     <lb/>
     so frequently and so prominently referred to 
     <lb/>
     here. We know that on all sides and on all 
     <lb/>
     subjects political characters are apt to speak 
     <lb/>
     and write strongly and to go to those extremes 
     <lb/>
     which cannot be justified in or out of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. But in my view, it was unjust in him 
     <lb/>
     to attribute licentiousness to one portion of 
     <lb/>
     the press rather than to others, for on all sides 
     <lb/>
     we find observations, criminations, and recri<lb break="no"/>minations, which render both liable to censure. 
     <lb/>
     The less that is said in this place about the 
     <lb/>
     press the better, and with this remark I shall 
     <lb/>
     dismiss all further allusions to that branch of 
     <lb/>
     the subject. But the Provincial Secretary was 
     <lb/>
     not coulent with references to the press, c be in<lb break="no"/>troduced into the debate other authorities and 
     <lb/>
     influences that should not have been referred 
     <lb/>
     to here. Least of all should he have brought 
     <lb/>
     here the name of that illustrious lady, the 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>