<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1866-03-09"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-03-09">9 March 1866</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Third Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
          <date when="1866"/>.  
          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="61"/>.
        </bibl>
       

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-03-09_Page_061.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-11-02">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="DLANG4" when="2017-11-02">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-03-09_Page_061">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-09_Page_061.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="61" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-09_Page_061.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">61</fw>
   
   
     <div type="section"> 
     <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. RAY</persName> presented a petition from Mr. G. R. 
     <lb/>
     Grassie for remuneration for Crown Services 
     <lb/>
     performed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> presented a petition from 225 of 
     <lb/>
     of the congregation of the German Evangeli<lb break="no"/>cal Lutheran Church of Lunenburg against 
     <lb/>
     the bill introduced yesterday by Mr. Jost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The bill and petitions were referred to the 
     <lb/>
     Committee on Private Bills. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FRAS2">Mr. D. FRASER</persName> presented a petition from 
     <lb/>
     Pictou for a grant to build a hospital. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. ATTY.GEN</persName>. laid on the table for infor<lb break="no"/>mation of members a copy of the bill introduc<lb break="no"/>ed by the Committee of Ways and Means into 
     <lb/>
     the United States House of Representatives 
     <lb/>
     containing the duties proposed to be levied on 
     <lb/>
     articles heretofore included in the free list. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">           
            <head rendition="simple:centre">BILLS.</head>
            <p>
     The bills to incorporate the Washington Pier 
     <lb/>
     and Harbor Company, the Nova Scotia Cham<lb break="no"/>ber of Commerce, the Ophir Mining Company, 
     <lb/>
     the Merrigomish Coal Mining Company, and 
     <lb/>
     the Strait of Canso Marine Railway Company, 
     <lb/>
     were read a second time and referred to the 
     <lb/>
     Committee on Private Bills. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">           
            <head rendition="simple:centre">UNION OF THE COLONIES.</head>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon PROV. SEC</persName>.—By command of His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency I beg leave to lay on the table of the 
     <lb/>
     House copies of correspondence relating to 
     <lb/>
     the Union of the Colonies. The House is aware 
     <lb/>
     that both branches of the Legislature at the 
     <lb/>
     last Session passed a resolution in favor of re<lb break="no"/>opening negociations for the Union of the Mari<lb break="no"/>time provinces. When that resolution was 
     <lb/>
     under discussion I stated that we had not only 
     <lb/>
     no reason to suppose that Prince Edward 
     <lb/>
     Island would he prepared to co-operate with 
     <lb/>
     the other Colonies in this matter, but we had 
     <lb/>
     every reason to anticipate that she would de<lb break="no"/>cline to re-open negociations. At the same 
     <lb/>
     time it was thought desirable that an effort 
     <lb/>
     should be made to ascertain whether Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia and New Brunswick could not be 
     <lb/>
     brought under the government by a legislative 
     <lb/>
     union. The government and the legislature 
     <lb/>
     had initiated the policy of a Legislative Union 
     <lb/>
               of the Maritime Provinces at the previous ses<lb break="no"/>sion, and owing to circumstances detailed last 
     <lb/>
     year the negociation arising from their action 
     <lb/>
     had been postponed, and the greater question 
     <lb/>
     of a union of all British North America was 
     <lb/>
     brought under consideration. When, however, 
     <lb/>
     an immediate union of that kind was found im<lb break="no"/>practicable from the fact that the people of 
     <lb/>
    New Brunswick had returned a majority in 
     <lb/>the new House opposed to the scheme, the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment felt it their duty to revert to their 
     <lb/>former policy, and in discussing that resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, I stated that so far from a legislative 
     <lb/>union of this and the adjoining Province in the 
     <lb/>slightest degree impeding the larger union, we 
     <lb/>regarded it as likely to promote that union 
     <lb/>and as being indispensable to the latter. Upon 
     <lb/>this subject have always entertained very 
     <lb/>strong opinions, and have always felt there 
     <lb/>were a great many reasons why it was desira<lb break="no"/>ble that the Governments of the three Mari<lb break="no"/>time Provinces should be carried on in a united   
     <lb/>form in case they agreed to enter into the pro<lb break="no"/>posed Confederacy. The resolution to which 
     <lb/>I have referred met with the unanimous appro<lb break="no"/>val of the House. I do not mean to say that 
     <lb/>there were not individual gentlemen who did 
     <lb/>not concur in the policy proposed, but the reso<lb break="no"/>
               
            <cb/>
     
     lution must be accepted as the unanimous ex<lb break="no"/>pression of the opinion of the Legislature. The 
     <lb/>
     attention of the Government of New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick was invited to the action thus taken, and 
     <lb/>
     corresponding action was adopted by the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature of that Province. Subsequently a dele<lb break="no"/>gation to England took place from the Govern<lb break="no"/>ments of the two Provinces, and although the 
     <lb/>
     two Governments differed widely in their opin<lb break="no"/>ions upon the larger questiou they were com<lb break="no"/>pletely in accord as to the desirability of a 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Union of New Brunswick and No<lb break="no"/>va Scotia, and the views which the delegates 
     <lb/>
     for New Brunswick expressed upon this mat<lb break="no"/>ter entirely corresponded with our own. I am 
     <lb/>
     aware that these gentlemen urged all the rea<lb break="no"/>sons in their power on the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to induce their concurrence in the policy 
     <lb/>
     adopted. I have stated in detail the results of 
     <lb/>
     that delegation and the reception it met at the 
     <lb/>
     hands of Her Majesty's Government, and I am 
     <lb/>
     frank to say that after the fullest and most un<lb break="no"/>reserved communication on the question we 
     <lb/>
     were given to understand that while no antipa<lb break="no"/>thy existed to the Legislative Union proposed, 
     <lb/>
     that Government having so fully committed 
     <lb/>
     themselves to the scheme of Confederation, 
     <lb/>
     were unwilling to revert to any policy which 
     <lb/>
     would seem to indicate that their opinions had 
     <lb/>
     undergone a change or modification and under 
     <lb/>
     these circumstances they were not prepared to 
     <lb/>
     give authority to revert to the question of a 
     <lb/>
     legislative union, except that question were 
     <lb/>
     taken up and passed upon as auxiliary to, and 
     <lb/>
     intended to promote, the larger union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     While we were quite at liberty to urge our 
     <lb/>
     opinions in favor of a union of the martime pro<lb break="no"/>vinces as being conductive to that object, we 
     <lb/>
     were not prepared, and the Government of 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick were by no means prepared, 
     <lb/>
     to adopt the policy with that view, for, as is 
     <lb/>
     well known they were specially charged to op<lb break="no"/>pose confederation upon the basis of the Quebec 
     <lb/>
    scheme. While the delegates, used every 
     <lb/>means to induce her Majesty's Government to 
     <lb/>concur with reference to the union of the lower 
     <lb/>colonies, that Government refused their assent 
     <lb/>upon the grounds stated. The correspondence 
     <lb/>contains copies of despatches in reference to 
     <lb/>the adoption of confederation, which the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Government continue to urge on all the 
     <lb/>colonies by every argument in their power, and 
     <lb/>by the use of that influence which they consider 
     <lb/>themselves entitled to exercise, from the rela 
     <lb/>tive postion of the countries in a question 
     <lb/>which they regard as vitally affecting the pros<lb break="no"/>perity of British North America. It also con<lb break="no"/>tains despatches setting forth their reasons for 
     <lb/>declining to assent to the re-opening of the 
     <lb/>proposed negociations.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
               <p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon PROV SECY</persName> laid on the table a state<lb break="no"/>ment asked for by the hon memeber for Inver<lb break="no"/>ness (Mr. Blanchard) in reference to payments 
     <lb/>for-road services. Also, plans and specifica<lb break="no"/>tions of bridges and returns of engineers, in<lb break="no"/>spectors, &amp;c.. on the Pictou Railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr BLANCHARD introduced a bill to incor<lb break="no"/>porate the Nova Scotia Slate Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
         <div type="section">           
            <head rendition="simple:centre">EDUCATION.</head>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon PROV SECY</persName> then said :—Mr Speaker, as 
     <lb/>
     chairman of the Committee of Education, I 
     <lb/>
     beg leave to report in part, from that commit<lb break="no"/>tee, a bill to amend the act "for the better en<lb break="no"/>couragement of Education," both in relation to [...]
            </p>
         </div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>