<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNSLA_1867-04-15" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1867-05-07">7 May 1867</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> <!-- xml markup only - not proofed -->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA"> <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
<date when="1867"/>.
<pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="130"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="148"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0130.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0143.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0144.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0145.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0146.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0147.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0148.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-19">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0130"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0130.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0143"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0143.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0144"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0144.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0145"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0145.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0146"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0146.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0147"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0147.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0148"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0148.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="130" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0130.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw> 
<fw type="num">130</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">MONDAY, April 15.</p>

<!-- DL 2018-06-19 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>dering how far it was legitimate for any gen<lb break="no"/>tleman to sit in the other branch of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, when, according to the Royal Instruc<lb break="no"/>tions he had deprived himself of the right to <lb/>
the seat. It was well known that a member <lb/>
of the Legislative Council could not take his <lb/>
seat if he was absent for a year from the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince without permission under the Royal sign <lb/>
manual. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. S. CAMPBELL said that it was hardly to <lb/>
be expected that he should rise to speak in <lb/>
reference to this matter, since it appeared to <lb/>
be simply a personal question between the <lb/>
Government and a gentleman in the other <lb/>
branch. He thought, however, the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers had hardly done justice to the case as <lb/>
stated in the paper in his hand. As he remem<lb break="no"/>bered it, the suggestion that the question should <lb/>
he submitted to the committee on Privileges <lb/>
did not originate with the hon. gentlemen re<lb break="no"/>ferred to, but with the President of the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. PROV. SECY.—Who made the motion? <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. S. CAMPBELL said that looking over the <lb/>
report he found that he was quite right. The <lb/>
President of the Council was reported to have <lb/>
said previously to the remarks of the Hon. Mr. <lb/>
Almon:— <lb/></p> 

<p>"Hon. President was very desirous to meet <lb/>
the views of the Government, but he thought <lb/>
that by passing the resolution the house would <lb/>
not be acting in conformity with its privileges <lb/>
and dignity. He disliked that part of the re<lb break="no"/>solution which gave a member the opportunity <lb/>
of being absent from the house for two years. <lb/>
The seat of a member absent for one year <lb/>
should be declared vacant. The resolution <lb/>
ought to be referred to the Committee on Pri<lb break="no"/>vileges." <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. PROV. SECY. said that it was, however, <lb/>
the hon. Mr. Almon who had made the mo<lb break="no"/>tion to refer the question to the Committee on <lb/>
Privileges. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. ANNAND said if the measure was a good <lb/>
one—if the Government believed it was sound <lb/>
in principle, he did not see why the action of <lb/>
any gentleman in the other branch should <lb/>
divert their attention from it. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. PROV. SECY. said that the object in <lb/>
view would still be carried. The motion made <lb/>
by Mr. Almon was only prevented being <lb/>
brought to a vote by the initiation and adop<lb break="no"/>tion of a new resolution. If the house pro<lb break="no"/>ceeded any further in the matter, it would be <lb/>
tantamount to an admission that there was <lb/>
something in the charge that had been made. <lb/>
Nobody would deny that the house had a per<lb break="no"/>fect right to touch the constitution of the <lb/>
Council. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. McLELAN said it was perfectly legiti<lb break="no"/>mate for any member of the Council to ques<lb break="no"/>tion any resolution that came up from the <lb/>
house. <lb/></p> 

<p>The subject then dropped. <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="143" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0143.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
<fw type="num">143</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE INTERCOLONIAL RAILWAY.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PRO. SEC'Y</persName>. introduced an Act to <lb/>
amend the Act incorporating the St. Lawrence <lb/>
and Bay of Fundy Company; its object is to <lb/>
prevent the Company interfering or coming <lb/>
into conflict with the Inter-Colonial Railway. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. S. CAMPBELL</persName>—Will the railway come as <lb/>
far as the borders of Nova. Scotia? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PRO. SEC'Y</persName>.—I suppose that the hon. <lb/>
member's enquiry was made in jest, but I <lb/>
would remark that his question may become <lb/>
one of very serious consideration. If his friends <lb/>
could secure a majority opposed to Union and <lb/>
pledged to obstruct it, the parties under whose <lb/>
control the construction would be might ques<lb break="no"/>tion the propriety of extending the road beyond <lb/>
the borders of New Brunswick. If a large ob<lb break="no"/>structionist party could be got together with a <lb/>
prospect of detaching Nova Scotia from the <lb/>
Union, there is no knowing what effect it might <lb/>
have on the building of the road. Those op<lb break="no"/>posed to Union after failing to defeat the Rail<lb break="no"/>way project by representing that the debt would <lb/>
be repudiated and that the road would not pay <lb/>
grease for the wheels, may yet succeed in get<lb break="no"/>ting up such hostility as will prevent the city <lb/>
from obtaining the benefits of the line. If the <lb/>
road be built to Halifax it will be because those <lb/>
with whom the hon. gentleman is acting were <lb/>
powerless to prevent what every Nova Scotian <lb/>
regards as the greatest boon that his country <lb/>
can enjoy. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. S. CAMPBELL</persName>— The hon. gentleman has <lb/>
attributed to me a desire to obstruct the interests <lb/>
of the country in this particular, but I think <lb/>
that the charge is not justified by my action in <lb/>
the House. My remark, however, in reference <lb/>
to this bill was not without meaning, for the <lb/>
delegates have not taken care as they should <lb/>
have done, that the road should be commenced <lb/>
at both ends. Again, only three millions are <lb/>
guaranteed, and as this sum would be insuffi<lb break="no"/>cient, I ventured to doubt that the road <lb/>
would reach the point of communication refer<lb break="no"/>red to. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PRO. SEC</persName>.—I understand the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber then to repudiate the action of the people's <lb/>
delegates,—if he does not do so he is responsi<lb break="no"/>ble for their acts. Those gentlemen laid upon <lb/>
the table of the Imperial Parliament a declara<lb break="no"/>tion drawing attention to the fact that all the <lb/>
money which Mr. Howe had asked for was <lb/>
three millions, and that this was all that the <lb/>
Imperial Government were pledged to. They <lb/>
thus endeavored to prevent our getting another <lb/>
shilling beyond the three millions. If they had <lb/>
been believed, the credit of British America <lb/>
would have been destroyed, and their determin<lb break="no"/>ed and avowed policy was to oppose the con<lb break="no"/>struction of a single mile of railway. When <lb/>

<cb/>

the hon. member for Guysboro' heard his friend <lb/>
acknowledge the truth of these charges on the <lb/>
floor of the House, and when he continues in <lb/>
co-operation with the hon. member for East <lb/>
Halifax, I ask if he does not place upon his own <lb/>
shoulders the responsibility of endeavoring to <lb/>
obstruct the work. I was glad when I heard <lb/>
him (Mr. Campbell) declare that the Union <lb/>
having become a fixed fact, he was prepared to <lb/>
give his best energies to carry out the new <lb/>
system, and to obtain all the advantages that <lb/>
could be obtained for the country. That de<lb break="no"/>claration was creditable to the heart and to the <lb/>
head of the hon. gentleman, because every in<lb break="no"/>telligent man knows that the people would turn <lb/>
their backs with scorn and indignation upon <lb/>
the men who would shrink from taking such a <lb/>
position as the interests of the Province demand. <lb/>
But when the press advocating that gentleman's <lb/>
views has repudiated those doctrines, and has <lb/>
declared that so far from endeavoring to make <lb/>
the change beneficial to Nova Scotia their ob<lb break="no"/>ject is to obstruct and destroy and defeat the <lb/>
advantages which the country might expect, <lb/>
whatever his views upon the question of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, every man actuated by a spirit of <lb/>
manly patriotism must act upon the view enun<lb break="no"/>ciated by the hon. member for Guysboro'. But <lb/>
that gentleman's associates have proclaimed <lb/>
that instead of seeking an onward course for <lb/>
Nova Scotia their only motto is obstruction. <lb/>
The hon. gentleman's sentiments having been <lb/>
thus repudiated, he must come out from the <lb/>
company of his associates or must take the res<lb break="no"/>ponsibility of standing in the company of men <lb/>
whose only aim is to impede the country's pro<lb break="no"/>gress. Am I not right, then, in saying that <lb/>
under certain circumstances there is a possibility <lb/>
of the railway stopping at our borders? But I <lb/>
believe that when the true position of these <lb/>
gentlemen is placed before the intelligent con<lb break="no"/>stituencies of the country; when they are called <lb/>
upon to choose between the friends of union <lb/>
who will be prepared to combine in making the <lb/>
union as largely beneficial to the country as <lb/>
possible and their opponents who are opposed <lb/>
to everything like progress, there is not a con<lb break="no"/>stituency but will turn their backs with con<lb break="no"/>tempt upon the men who being unable to carry <lb/>
out their individual opinions are prepared to <lb/>
trample underfoot the prosperity of the coun<lb break="no"/>try. The men who crossed the water as the <lb/>
people's delegates, the hon. member knows <lb/>
have defamed and libelled the fair credit of the <lb/>
country, giving the lie to all their past lives, <lb/>
and stating that the railway which they had <lb/>
held out as the highest boon would not pay <lb/>
grease for its engines, and were compelled to <lb/>
admit that they urged the British Government <lb/>
to spend their money in iron-clads and every<lb break="no"/>thing but in giving to the Province that position <lb/>
which God and nature intended she should oc<lb break="no"/>cupy. And in what position are these gentle<lb break="no"/>men to-day? Is it the position of myself and <lb/>
my colleagues who having fought the battle <lb/>
through and accomplished the great union, are <lb/>
prepared to commit their fame and future for<lb break="no"/>tune to the hands of the free electors of Nova <lb/>

<pb n="144" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0144.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw> 
<fw type="num">144</fw>

Scotia? The only man amongst the people's <lb/>
delegates who had a seat in this Assembly has <lb/>
shrunk from the averted faces of his country<lb break="no"/>men, knowing the doom that must fall upon <lb/>
him. Instead of appealing to the constituency <lb/>
that hitherto supported him, he has sent his <lb/>
emissaries abroad to see if in some outlying <lb/>
county a seat cannot be obtained for him in any <lb/>
Parliament. I ask the hon. member for Guys<lb break="no"/>oro' if he does not think it would be wise for <lb/>
him to take a note of that? I ask the men <lb/>
throughout the country who are opposed to union <lb/>
if they do not think it a significant fact that the <lb/>
man who controls a portion of the press enunci<lb break="no"/>ating anti-Union sentiments is at present like <lb/>
Japhet in search of a father, and if they think <lb/>
it would be well for them now to respond to the <lb/>
call of the men who, having done all they could <lb/>
to trample down the credit of the country, are <lb/>
now reduced to the position which I have des<lb break="no"/>cribed? With the messengers which the hon. <lb/>
member for East Halifax has sent out coming <lb/>
back to him without being able to find a place <lb/>
on which he can rest his foot, I ask the hon. <lb/>
member for Guysborough if he does not think <lb/>
it would be wise for him to come back to the <lb/>
patriotic stand which he took in declaring that <lb/>
he would endeavour to work out the new sys<lb break="no"/>tem for the benefit of the country? I have lit<lb break="no"/>tle fear as to the result of the contest which is <lb/>
approaching, for I believe that the people will <lb/>
not look for men belonging to one party or the <lb/>
other, but will elect the men who regardless of <lb/>
the past are prepared to obtain all possible ad<lb break="no"/>vantages for the country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE4">Mr. MCLELAN</persName>-I have been much amused at <lb/>
some of the remarks of the Prov. Sec., and espe<lb break="no"/>cially at the remark he made in reference to <lb/>
the hon. member for East Halifax not being <lb/>
able to find a constituency. I am surprised <lb/>
that the hon gentleman should make such an <lb/>
observation, after the issue of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Colonist</hi> on <lb/>
last Saturday, which shows him to be in that <lb/>
very position. The Prov. Sec. has been driven <lb/>
from the constituency in which his daily life <lb/>
and the motives which have actuated him <lb/>
are best understood. His own messengers <lb/>
have not yet came back to tell him whether a <lb/>
place for his foot can be found or not. He says <lb/>
that we are arrayed to obstruct the progress of <lb/>
the country, but will he put his finger upon one <lb/>
advantage that is to flow from union. The <lb/>
only benefit which they promise is the construc<lb break="no"/>tion of the Intercolonial railroad, and the hon. <lb/>
member for Guysboro, and those who concur <lb/>
with him, are therefore in a position to enquire <lb/>
whether for that work we are not to pay more <lb/>
than it is worth,—whether we are not to be tax<lb break="no"/>ed to an extent that would be sufficient to build <lb/>
the whole road. Surely if these are the facts it <lb/>
would have been better to forego the railroad <lb/>
on such hard terms. Is the member for Guys<lb break="no"/>boro' wrong when he says that the delegates <lb/>
failed to secure to us that one benefit on which <lb/>
the friends of union relied on so much? Any <lb/>
one who compares Mr. Fleming's estimate with <lb/>
the amount guaranteed will see that sufficient <lb/>
care has not been taken to ensure the building <lb/>

<cb/>

of the road through this province. They fail<lb break="no"/>ed in discharging the trust which they under<lb break="no"/>took, and in condemning their want of attention <lb/>
we are not to be met by the charge of obstruct<lb break="no"/>ing the progress of the country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName>—It is a very singular that fact the <lb/>
men who have been obstructing the passage of <lb/>
the Imperial Act—doing all that men could do <lb/>
to prevent the consummation of union—are <lb/>
now the most desirous to go to Ottawa. I find <lb/>
that there is an election card out for this city, <lb/>
containing four names of the most determined <lb/>
opponents of union. I know something about <lb/>
the retirement from this constituency of the hon. <lb/>
Provincial Secretary. If he had wished it, I <lb/>
know he could have beaten every Anti-Unionist <lb/>
who might have the hardihood to run against <lb/>
him. I have conversed with highly intelligent <lb/>
men, from East and West—with professional men, <lb/>
clergymen, and others of weight and influence <lb/>
—and my conviction is that there is not a <lb/>
shadow of a doubt that all such persons are in <lb/>
favour of union. I say to the Union party: <lb/>
Wait, have patience for a days, for there will be <lb/>
candidates in the field worthy of your support, <lb/>
—men who will reflect credit upon the consti<lb break="no"/>tuency of this metropolitan county. The game <lb/>
is not up yet, but will be fought to the bitter <lb/>
end by men of tried value and of ability. I am <lb/>
convinced that there are in this city four Union<lb break="no"/>ists to one Anti-Unionist. An unfair advan<lb break="no"/>tage has been taken of the fact that the Provin<lb break="no"/>cial Secretary has retired, and it is said that he <lb/>
did so for want of support. Never would an elec<lb break="no"/>tion have been more easily won, if he had run <lb/>
it. If he felt it his duty to go back to his own <lb/>
county, that is his own affair, but I believe <lb/>
he could have won an easy victory <lb/>
in Halifax. Don't let gentlemen believe <lb/>
that this struggle has even yet com<lb break="no"/>menced. I regret the more that the Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary retired, because at the mo<lb break="no"/>ment he did so a requisition was about being <lb/>
handed him with some 1600 of the best names <lb/>
in this city and county. Let me here take an <lb/>
opportunity of stating that there will be a pub<lb break="no"/>lic meeting held in this city, a few days hence <lb/>
and every part of the county will be asked to <lb/>
send their delegates. Then there will be given <lb/>
a full expression of the public opinion of this <lb/>
county, and candidates worthy of support will <lb/>
be nominated to represent the constituency in <lb/>
Ottawa and in the Local Legislature. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>.—I thank the hon member <lb/>
(Mr. McLelan) for having afforded me this op<lb break="no"/>portunity of giving some explanations on the <lb/>
subject to which he has referred. As my hon. <lb/>
friend (Mr. Tobin) has intimated, some gentle<lb break="no"/>men will soon find, to use a homely phrase, that <lb/>
they have hallooed before they were out of the <lb/>
wood. I came into this Legislature, it is well <lb/>
known, in conjunction with my hon friend, Mr. <lb/>
McFarlane. We have been long allied as mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the same Government. In order to dis<lb break="no"/>charge the important duties of the position to <lb/>
which my country has called me, I was obliged <lb/>
to remove from Cumberland, and have since <lb/>
lived in this city, whilst my hon friend re<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="145" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0145.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
<fw type="num">145</fw> 

mained a resident of his native county. I need <lb/>
not say that I have felt the strong claims he <lb/>
has to continue to represent the county where <lb/>
he lives in the United Parliament. I was, <lb/>
therefore, in a manner, bound to wave any <lb/>
claim I might have to that constituency in his <lb/>
favor and seek a seat elsewhere. But there was <lb/>
another reason which operated both upon my <lb/>
honorable friend and myself, and that <lb/>
was, that the position I had taken in <lb/>
reference to the Union and other measures <lb/>
would make it easy for me to find a constitu<lb break="no"/>ency outside of my own county. The hon. <lb/>
member for North Colchester lives close enough <lb/>
to Cumberland to know that every attempt to <lb/>
find a man either in or out of the county to <lb/>
come forward as an anti-Union candidate, has <lb/>
failed. Deputation after deputation has gone to <lb/>
gentlemen in this city, and there has not been a <lb/>
man found—and I do not believe one will be <lb/>
found—who will dare to go to the hustings to <lb/>
test the feeling of the people either with myself <lb/>
or any other Unionist. If there is such a man <lb/>
I shall be proud to meet him, and I am convin<lb break="no"/>ced that I do not misjudge my own constituents <lb/>
when I say that they will give such an account <lb/>
of themselves as will prove that they fully ap<lb break="no"/>preciate the character and tendency of the anti-<lb break="yes"/>Union policy. I may also tell the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man that his party have gone again and again <lb/>
to one of the most influential men of the coun<lb break="no"/>ty who lives here, and he has refused to come <lb/>
out, because he is unwilling to take a position <lb/>
hostile to a movement which must do so much <lb/>
for the county of Cumberland. When I waived <lb/>
my claim to the county in favor of my hon. <lb/>
friend, I did so—and gentlemen of both parties <lb/>
are aware of the fact—with the knowledge that <lb/>
the men who had always supported me were <lb/>
ready to return me more triumphantly than <lb/>
ever before. But that is not all. I was return<lb break="no"/>ed at the last election by acclamation, by my <lb/>
own party; but I can now go into the county <lb/>
and rally to my support not merely the friends <lb/>
who have always sustained me, but men who op<lb break="no"/>posed me, in former times. From Wallace to <lb/>
Parrsboro' such men are ready to give me the <lb/>
most enthusiastic support. Yet in the face of <lb/>
facts like these, persons have dared to send the <lb/>
libel throughout this country that I was in doubts <lb/>
of being elected for the county I have so long re<lb break="no"/>presented. Under such circumstances I was <lb/>
asked if I would allow myself to be put into <lb/>
nomination for the county of Halifax. I said if <lb/>
there was a battle to be fought anywhere, I was <lb/>
prepared to fight it; if the friends of Union re<lb break="no"/>quired my services, they were at their disposal. <lb/>
At a few hours' notice a meeting was held at <lb/>
the house of Dr. Parker—such a meeting as <lb/>
never before assembled in this city at the house <lb/>
of any gentleman,—it was not only large in <lb/>
numbers, but powerful in respect to the influ<lb break="no"/>ence and wealth it represented. More than <lb/>
that, it embraced gentlemen representing every <lb/>
shade of political opinion, creed, and class. No <lb/>
man could hear the names of these gentlemen <lb/>
without feeling that the moment they support<lb break="no"/>ed a candidate for this city, his election was <lb/>

<cb/>

sure. When not only the great bulk of the <lb/>
Conservative party but the most able and intel<lb break="no"/>ligent supporters of the Liberal party are array<lb break="no"/>ed, as they are now, in support of Union, can <lb/>
any one doubt the result in this city and coun<lb break="no"/>try? I felt that it would be very questionable <lb/>
if there was a contest here at all. When I re<lb break="no"/>tired, it was not because I feared the result— <lb/>
for that was certain—but it was because I felt <lb/>
that the moment the county that had always so <lb/>
nobly sustained me required my services, it was <lb/>
my duty to respond. I have heard the names <lb/>
of some gentlemen mentioned as likely to run on <lb/>
the anti-Union ticket, but I feel that such parties, <lb/>
situated as they are, would hardly venture to go <lb/>
to the polls at all. In a few days the people of the <lb/>
county will be asked to support Union candi<lb break="no"/>dates, not nominated in a private office, but at a <lb/>
meeting of the electors. Then will be put before <lb/>
the constituency such a platform as they can sup<lb break="no"/>port. I feel that the people will respond as <lb/>
they should; that they will not permit any ob<lb break="no"/>structionists to impede the progress of a great <lb/>
measure which is to open up a new career of <lb/>
prosperity to this country. It has been said, <lb/>
time and again, by the opponents of Union <lb/>
that we could hardly get men to go to Ottawa; <lb/>
for it was too far off, or to go to the local par<lb break="no"/>liament,—so contemptible would it become <lb/>
under Union. What do we see to-day? No <lb/>
sooner is the measure of Union accomplished <lb/>
than we see that the men who are most anxious <lb/>
to go to Ottawa and to the local legislature as <lb/>
well are the men who have been opposing <lb/>
Union. Hitherto no merchant could be obtain<lb break="no"/>ed, except my hon. friend, to run for this city, <lb/>
whilst Nova Scotia was isolated and a separate <lb/>
province. Now we see four bankers taken in <lb/>
tow by Captain Balcam, and rushing to Ottawa <lb/>
and the local legislature. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName>.—Hardly four bankers,—not more <lb/>
than two. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>.—As respects the Intercolo<lb break="no"/>nial Railway, let me say that it did not depend <lb/>
upon the Imperial guarantee at all. Canada is <lb/>
able to build it without the assistance of the <lb/>
Maritime Provinces. Her bonds before this <lb/>
Union was effected were selling in the market <lb/>
higher than those of either Nova Scotia or New <lb/>
Brunswick. If the Imperial Parliament had <lb/>
refused to guarantee a single dollar the Interco<lb break="no"/>lonial Railway would have been built as rapidly <lb/>
as it was possible to carry it on. By having the <lb/>
money loaned at four per cent., of course, it is <lb/>
obvious that a great advantage is gained. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName>—I feel it due to make a few re<lb break="no"/>marks after the allusions made to me by the <lb/>
Provincial Secretary. I imagined when I came <lb/>
here this afternoon that I was in the Assembly, <lb/>
but as the speeches proceeded I almost began <lb/>
to doubt that fact and to imagine that these ad<lb break="no"/>dresses were being made to the constituents <lb/>
outside. I do not wonder that the Provincial <lb/>
Secretary ventured upon the broad and glaring <lb/>
mis-statement that the anti-Union ticket for Ha<lb break="no"/>lifax county included four bankers, for this is <lb/>
characteristic of his general accuracy. But I <lb/>
am not aware that it is such a great offence to <lb/>

<pb n="146" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0146.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw> 
<fw type="num">146</fw>

be a merchant or a banker,—I believe that the <lb/>
hon. member for Halifax who has spoken is him<lb break="no"/>self a banker—and I am inclined to think that <lb/>
the selection of four merchants and a gentleman <lb/>
from the shore to represent the constituency of <lb/>
Halifax will be proved by the result to be a re<lb break="no"/>spectable and taking nomination. We have <lb/>
been told that the friends of Confederation will <lb/>
carry the county four to one. We were only <lb/>
afraid this morning that our candidates would <lb/>
have no opposition, and I am relieved to hear <lb/>
the hon. member for West Halifax say that <lb/>
there will be opposition, and that the game is <lb/>
not up yet. I have a strong desire to see that <lb/>
gentleman upon the hustings, and I sincerely <lb/>
regret that the Provincial Secretary has retired <lb/>
from the contest, for I should like to see him <lb/>
face the constituency of Halifax, where it has <lb/>
been said that the Union sentiment prevailed <lb/>
more strongly than in any other place. The <lb/>
men who formerly supported Confederation in <lb/>
this city feel that they cannot rally to the sup<lb break="no"/>port of these gentlemen who have deprived <lb/>
them of the privileges of freemen. I was <lb/>
amused to hear him speak the other day as one <lb/>
of the sovereign people. What right has he to <lb/>
speak here in that capacity? The sovereign <lb/>
people have been denied the right to speak, and <lb/>
the measure of Union has been forced on them <lb/>
contrary to their well known sentiments. They <lb/>
were almost told in terms that they were not <lb/>
intelligent enough to decide the question, and <lb/>
are now appealed to by the very men who con<lb break="no"/>sidered them so besotted and ignorant that the <lb/>
measure should be passed over their heads.— <lb/>
The hon. gentleman seemed surprised that the <lb/>
anti-Unionists should aspire to a seat at Ot<lb break="no"/>tawa. They will go there as the Nova Scotian <lb/>
party, not to be mixed up with the politics of <lb/>
Canada, to commit themselves to the support <lb/>
of either party, or to identify themselves with <lb/>
Canadian factions, but to be there to watch over <lb/>
the interests of Nova Scotia and to throw them<lb break="no"/>selves into any scale in which they may secure <lb/>
the best advantages for their country. The <lb/>
House has been told that I shrank from <lb/>
offering myself to a constituency; it is well <lb/>
known that four years ago I decided upon <lb/>
the course which I have taken, and when I re<lb break="no"/>turned from England, and before I learned the <lb/>
result of the exertions of the delegates, I visit<lb break="no"/>ed my constituency and gave those who sup<lb break="no"/>ported me to understand, as I had previously <lb/>
given my family to understand, that it was not <lb/>
my intention again to offer. When asked if I <lb/>
would serve in the Dominion Parliament, I an<lb break="no"/>swered no. When asked if I would serve in the <lb/>
Local Parliament, I answered no, and when <lb/>
asked if I would continue in this House provi<lb break="no"/>ded no change were made, my answer was "no; <lb/>
I have had twenty-five years' public service, <lb/>
and you had better select a younger man for the <lb/>
work." When the Union measure passed, and <lb/>
the time came for consultation, I was pressed <lb/>
urgently to allow myself to be put in nomina<lb break="no"/>tion by leading Conservatives and Liberals. I <lb/>
still firmly refused, and will continue to do so <lb/>
unless a nineteenth member of the Nova Scotia <lb/>

<cb/>

Party is wanted to go to Ottawa. The Prov. <lb/>
Sec. spoke in glowing terms about the offers of <lb/>
support which were made to him; we know <lb/>
how he has been canvassing the city and the <lb/>
rebuffs he received from quarters where he ex<lb break="no"/>pected the opposite treatment. He thought <lb/>
that he could bring to his support his old friends <lb/>
and perhaps that the old Conservative cry <lb/>
could he raised, but he found that not only he, <lb/>
but his friend, Mr. Tobin, had worn out their <lb/>
public reputation, and then it became conve<lb break="no"/>nient that his colleague in the representation of <lb/>
Cumberland should make way on the plea that <lb/>
the local interests of that county woul be bet<lb break="no"/>ter represented by the Provincial Secretary. <lb/>
What have the local interests of Cumberland to <lb/>
do with the matter? I thought these gentle<lb break="no"/>men prided themselves on rising above local <lb/>
feeling, and considered such matters as lunatic <lb/>
asylums, ferries, roads and bridges were be<lb break="no"/>neath their notice. But under cover of this <lb/>
plea the hon gentleman shrinks from facing the <lb/>
constituency of Halifax. He has said that no <lb/>
one was prepared to contest Cumberland with <lb/>
him, but I can tell him that he is mistaken. I <lb/>
would ask him what to day is the feeling in <lb/>
Parrsboro, Malagash, Wallace, and other popu<lb break="no"/>lous districts of Cumberland? That part of the <lb/>
county will have to be revolutionized before it <lb/>
will support a union candidate, and I pledge my <lb/>
word that the hon gentlemen will have opposi<lb break="no"/>tion. We have been treated this afternoon to <lb/>
more declamation on the subject of the Inter<lb break="no"/>colonial Railway. I repeat now, as solemnly <lb/>
as I made the statement before, that for <lb/>
a railway which may or may not be beneficial <lb/>
I should be very sorry to give up the privi<lb break="no"/>leges of the country, its free government, its <lb/>
right of self-taxation, its right to appropriate <lb/>
its own revenues and to place it under a load <lb/>
of taxation from another province. I would <lb/>
have been recreant to my duty to the people if <lb/>
I did not for the sake of destroying a scheme <lb/>
fatal to their interests, use every effort to im<lb break="no"/>pede one of its essential parts. I only hope <lb/>
that the road will be built, but if Canada alone <lb/>
is able to build it, as has been asserted, why <lb/>
did she not step forward years ago. We <lb/>
might have had it in 1851 or 1862 only for <lb/>
the bad faith of the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. If Canada could borrow the necessary <lb/>
money, how was it that she was struggling with<lb break="no"/>in a year to borrow at eight per cent.? True, <lb/>
her bonds have gone up in the market, and <lb/>
well they might, in view of the fact that she is <lb/>
about to get the control of the more prosper<lb break="no"/>ous revenues of the Maritime Provinces. De<lb break="no"/>prive Canada of the revenues which she will <lb/>
get from us, and her bonds will go down again, <lb/>
not perhaps to the same point as before, be<lb break="no"/>cause it must be borne in mind that the bonds <lb/>
of all the Colonies of the Empire rose simul<lb break="no"/>taneously when money became plentiful and <lb/>
cheap in the market of the world. It can be <lb/>
clearly shown that the money to be drawn out <lb/>
of the treasury, and out of the people by Con<lb break="no"/>federation, would under a Canadian tariff in a <lb/>
few years more than pay the entire cost of the <lb/>
railway. Assuming the cost to be three mil<lb break="no"/>lions, and that that sum were borrowed at four <lb/>
per cent.,—our revenues would enable us to <lb/>

<pb n="147" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0147.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
<fw type="num">147</fw> 

build the road to Riviere du Loup, and for this <lb/>
work we are asked to give up treasure that <lb/>
would cover the country with railroads, and to <lb/>
reduce ourselves to the position of accepting a <lb/>
paltry pittance in the shape of a subsidy from <lb/>
Canada. The three millions guaranteed are <lb/>
not likely to build the road, and if it is to be <lb/>
commenced as the Canadian papers state, at <lb/>
Riviere du Loup, what is to become of the <lb/>
Nova Scotia end? It was proclaimed by Mr. <lb/>
Tilley all through New Brunswick that St. <lb/>
John was to be the terminus, and this three <lb/>
millions may be just sufficient to connect with <lb/>
St. John. <lb/></p> 

    <p><persName ref="pers:pers:TUPP1">Hon. ATTY. GENERAL</persName>:—I ask if there can <lb/>
be any stronger inducement to the people of <lb/>
this country to give a favourable consideration <lb/>
to their position than the very argument that <lb/>
the three millions guaranteed will only be suffi<lb break="no"/>cient to establish the terminus at St. John. I <lb/>
ask the people what position Nova Scotia <lb/>
would have been in if Canada and New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick had formed the union without us and <lb/>
built the road to St. John. If the member for <lb/>
East Halifax and his colleagues had succeeded <lb/>
they would have deprived the people of this <lb/>
country of the benefit of having the terminus <lb/>
located among them, and the trade of Halifax <lb/>
and of the western part of the Province would <lb/>
have been drawn to St. John. So obvious is <lb/>
the truth of this argument that in England the <lb/>
exclamation was repeatedly heard, " what are <lb/>
the people of the city of Halifax thinking of? <lb/>
That a man among them should oppose union <lb/>
is something miraculous, for the road is going <lb/>
to build up their city till it will be second to <lb/>
none on the continent." When therefore the <lb/>
hon. member shows his anxiety that the privi<lb break="no"/>leges of Halifax should be preserved and that <lb/>
security should have been obtained that the <lb/>
terminus should be here I feel that his anxie<lb break="no"/>ty on these points would have been more use<lb break="no"/>ful and appropriate if displayed in England. <lb/>
He has told us that we did not procure money <lb/>
enough, but does it lie with him to say that? <lb/>
What was the conduct of some of the people's <lb/>
delegates in England even after the union bill <lb/>
passed? They tried to induce the people there <lb/>
to believe that Nova Scotians were not loyal, <lb/>
that we would soon be annexed to the United <lb/>
States and that the debt would be repudiated. <lb/>
What would have been the conduct of any pa<lb break="no"/>triot under the circumstances? Would it not be <lb/>
to say, " I represent the true interests of Nova <lb/>
Scotia, its people are opposed to Confederation <lb/>
and I am bound to take every legitimate <lb/>
means to oppose it, but having failed my next <lb/>
course is to use every means to obtain for the <lb/>
country the railway as cheaply as possible?" <lb/>
That is the stand that any patriotic man would <lb/>
have taken but I say and can substantiate my <lb/>
statement that up to the last moment, when <lb/>
the guarantee bill was awaiting its passage, <lb/>
the gentlemen who professed to represent the <lb/>
people of Nova Scotia left no stone unturned to <lb/>
destroy the good opinion of the people of Eng<lb break="no"/>land in these Colonies and to lead them to be<lb break="no"/>lieve that we would pay neither interest nor <lb/>
principal of the loan. They used every effort <lb/>
to prevent the passage of the bill and if they <lb/>
had succeeded, what position would we have <lb/>
been in? We would have had to build the <lb/>
road by a loan at six per cent. Under the pre<lb break="no"/>sent arrangement in thirty-seven years the <lb/>

<cb/>

debt will be paid off, and in the meantime we <lb/>
are only to pay five per cent., four per cent. for <lb/>
interest and one per cent. as a sinking fund, <lb/>
but without the guarantee, we must have paid <lb/>
six per cent. and would have had the principle <lb/>
to pay after that. <lb/></p> 

<p>These, then, are the patriots who now come <lb/>
forward and tell us we did not obtain enough, <lb/>
when we got all we did in opposition to their <lb/>
most strenuous exertions. Their position is <lb/>
that of a counsel who, after the verdict is given <lb/>
against him, taunts the opposite parties with <lb/>
not getting more. They have suddenly become <lb/>
very solicitous that the interests of Nova Scotia <lb/>
will not be looked after. They voted in favor of <lb/>
a bill by which £50,000 a year was to be laid <lb/>
as a tax on the people of this country for the <lb/>
railroad, and when they applied to the British <lb/>
Government they only asked three millions. <lb/>
I ask the people of this country, if three mil<lb break="no"/>lions is all we could obtain, and if we had diffi<lb break="no"/>culty in getting that, who are to blame but the <lb/>
member for East Halifax and his colleagues, <lb/>
who went across the water to oppose us? Sup<lb break="no"/>pose they had never gone, how different would <lb/>
have been the position of the delegates; as it is, <lb/>
we obtained what we asked for, but how much <lb/>
more confidently could we have asked a larger <lb/>
sum under the circumstances. They took pains <lb/>
to inform the British Government that three <lb/>
millions was all that had been promised, and <lb/>
that a delegate some years ago agreed to take <lb/>
that sum and build the road. The British <lb/>
Government, after this intimation, felt disin<lb break="no"/>clined to give the guarantee unless we would <lb/>
say that the amount would be sufficient to <lb/>
complete the work. Of course we had to ask <lb/>
to be relieved from that condition, and we <lb/>
asked for all that we could reasonably ask, <lb/>
and for all that Mr. Howe had asked. In an<lb break="no"/>swer to the complaint that no provision had <lb/>
been made for the work being begun at both <lb/>
ends, I ask where was the provision in the bill <lb/>
that these gentlemen passed some years ago? <lb/>
If they were so careful of the interests of the <lb/>
country, why did they not provide, in the mea<lb break="no"/>sure which they passed by a party vote, that <lb/>
the work should be commenced at Truro? If <lb/>
they did not consider any such provision neces<lb break="no"/>sary, I ask with what face he can get up and <lb/>
complain of our not doing what they thought <lb/>
was unnecessary? For all time to come, there<lb break="no"/>fore, when any complaint is made of our not <lb/>
procuring a larger guarantee, we will be in a <lb/>
position to say—" Go to these gentlemen who <lb/>
professed to represent the people, and ask <lb/>
them." If they had not been there, no com<lb break="no"/>plaint could have been made. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE4">Mr. MCLELAN</persName>.—The hon. gentleman has <lb/>
made this important admission—that the de<lb break="no"/>legates only asked for three millions, and he <lb/>
says that this was the sum asked for in 1862. <lb/>
In 1862 it was supposed that that sum would <lb/>
build the entire road, but recent surveys have <lb/>
demonstrated the impossibility of that, and <lb/>
there is therefore an important distinction be<lb break="no"/>tween the position of the delegates and their <lb/>
predecessors. In view of the fact that such a <lb/>
sum had been shown insufficient, the delegates <lb/>
were in duty bound to have asked for a larger <lb/>
guaranty. The terms which they secured <lb/>
were not so advantageous as the terms obtain<lb break="no"/>ed in 1862, for then we were allowed a breath<lb break="no"/>ing space before commencing to form the sink<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="148" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-15_Page_0148.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw> 
<fw type="num">148</fw>

ing fund; but we are now bound to commence <lb/>
paying off the debt immediately. As to the <lb/>
assertion that St. John would have been made <lb/>
the terminus if Nova Scotia had not gone into <lb/>
the Union, it is plain that that city would not <lb/>
have been the terminus unless it was consider<lb break="no"/>ed capable of supplying the wants of Canada; <lb/>
and when we see Mr. Fleming estimating the <lb/>
cost of the road to St. John at fifteen million <lb/>
dollars, and we see exactly that sum provided, <lb/>
the fair inference is that St. John is to be the <lb/>
terminus. <lb/></p> 

<p>As to the conditions of the guarantee, we are <lb/>
in about the same position as we were under <lb/>
the terms of 1862; for the stipulation then was <lb/>
that the act should not go into operation unless <lb/>
the proposal for a sinking fund was ratified by <lb/>
the Canadian Parliament, and we know that <lb/>
that Parliament repudiated the arrangement. <lb/>
Mr. Adderley said, in reference to the terms <lb/>
agreed upon by the delegates, that the guaran<lb break="no"/>tee would not be given unless the Confederate <lb/>
Parliament assented to the formation of a sink<lb break="no"/>ing fund. It was said by the Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary that under certain circumstances we <lb/>
might have lost the benefit of the road, and <lb/>
have failed in getting connection with Monc<lb break="no"/>ton; but we know that New Brunswick has <lb/>
already contracted for the building of the road <lb/>
to the Nova Scotia border. Our increase of <lb/>
revenue last year was about $184,000—more <lb/>
than enough to pay the interest for the Pictou <lb/>
extension—and with such prosperity we could <lb/>
easily have connected with New Brunswick. <lb/>
But supposing the Intercolonial line is built, <lb/>
does any one suppose that cargoes would be <lb/>
brought over here and shipped at Halifax, <lb/>
when an open port could be had at St. John, or <lb/>
within thirty-seven miles of the place where <lb/>
the road will be tapped? I am convinced <lb/>
that the much talked of prosperity which is <lb/>
promised to accrue to Halifax is all imagin<lb break="no"/>ation, and that no part of Nova Scotia will <lb/>
suffer so much from Confederation as this <lb/>
city. I fear that this city will decline and <lb/>
diminish under the burthens that will be <lb/>
placed upon it and that the " dead march in <lb/>
Saul" will ere long be appropriate to its con<lb break="no"/>dition. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO4">HON. FIN. SEC</persName>.—One advantage is possess<lb break="no"/>ed by hon. gentlemen opposite—that being gift<lb break="no"/>ed with vivid imaginations, they do not shrink <lb/>
from placing before the people as facts the re<lb break="no"/>sults which their fancy depicts. On this side <lb/>
of the House we have some desire to be con<lb break="no"/>sistent, because we feel that the common sense <lb/>
of the country demands consistency in the ar<lb break="no"/>guments and public conduct of its representa<lb break="no"/>tives. The hon. member who has just spoken <lb/>
has followed in the footsteps of the people's <lb/>
delegates, and used the arguments of the men <lb/>
who have endeavored to thwart and prevent <lb/>
the accomplishment of a work which for <lb/>
twenty-five years was the watchword of his <lb/>
party. The policy of constructing that road <lb/>
was the policy sustained by his father and the <lb/>
men whom he supported. The work was held <lb/>
forth by his party as the only thing that would <lb/>
give to this country its proper position in re<lb break="no"/>lation to the commerce of British America— <lb/>
the only mode of'expanding our resources and <lb/>
makin our Provmce the most desirable coun<lb break="no"/>try in world. That was the position of <lb/>
these gentlemen, until, to suit another purpose, <lb/>

<cb/>

they had the hardihood to propound doctrines <lb/>
which totally differed from the teachings of <lb/>
their lifetime. What wonder was it that Mr. <lb/>
Lowe and other leading commercial men of <lb/>
the day in England declared that the road <lb/>
would not only not be a paying investment, <lb/>
but that it would be ruinous to the colonies, <lb/>
when they were being indoctrinated for months <lb/>
with the news which these gentlemen now <lb/>
enunciate? <lb/></p> 

<p>The house adjourned. <lb/></p>

<p>[...]</p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>