<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNSLA_1867-04-24" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1867-04-24">24 April 1867</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> <!-- xml markup only - not proofed -->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA"> <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
<date when="1867"/>.
<pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="151"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-24_Page_0150.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-24_Page_0151.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-19">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-24_Page_0150"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-24_Page_0150.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-24_Page_0151"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-24_Page_0151.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="150" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-24_Page_0150.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw> 
<fw type="num">150</fw>

<p>[...]</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre">UNION ACT.<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. laid on the table a copy of <lb/>
the Act for a Union of the British North Ame<lb break="no"/>rican Colonies, as it passed the Imperial Par<lb break="no"/>liament, there having been some slight verbal <lb/>
alterations from the copy previously submitted. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName> enquired whether some clauses <lb/>
had not been added in the House of Commons. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. said that as the clauses re<lb break="no"/>lating to the monetary arrangements had to be <lb/>
inserted by the Commons, they were printed <lb/>
in red ink in the bill introduced in the House <lb/>
of Lords. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName> asked whether it was the in<lb break="no"/>tention of the Government to have any copies <lb/>
of the bill printed for circulation throughout <lb/>
the country. It contained the constitution <lb/>
under which we would hereafter live, and it <lb/>
was most desirable that it should be distri<lb break="no"/>buted in some durable shape; and this would <lb/>
have the effect of preventing the misrepresen<lb break="no"/>tations which were being made from one end of <lb/>
the country to the other. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. S. CAMPBELL</persName> remarked that the Act <lb/>
had been already published in the newspapers. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName> replied that in that form the <lb/>
bill could not be preserved, and it was not <lb/>
probable that fifty persons in the country <lb/>
could put their hands upon a copy. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PRO. SEC</persName>. said it was of the highest <lb/>
importance that correct information on the <lb/>
subject should be widely circulated. News<lb break="no"/>paper publications were so ephemeral that <lb/>
when in one issue of a journal published by <lb/>
an hon. member opposite, he saw a statement <lb/>
glaringly inconsistent with the one that pre<lb break="no"/>ceded it, he found difficulty in making an ac<lb break="no"/>curate comparison. The Act would be placed <lb/>
in the hands of the public printer for publica<lb break="no"/>tion in the Journals of the House, and at the <lb/>
same time a number of extra copies could be <lb/>
procured without much additional expense. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> said he did not object to the <lb/>
publication as the information which the bill <lb/>
would give was very valuable, but he would <lb/>
suggest that as the Government had been ma<lb break="no"/>king free with the public monies in circulating <lb/>
a recently issued pamphlet on the benefits of <lb/>
Confederation, an equal sum should be placed <lb/>
at the disposal of the opposition for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of distributing a reply to that production. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. replied that the proposition <lb/>
would receive a favorable consideration when<lb break="no"/>ever a document of equal value and containing <lb/>
an equal amount of accurate and reliable in<lb break="no"/>formation was produced. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:KAUL1">Mr. KAULBACK</persName> thought that the recent <lb/>
pamphlet of Mr. Howe on the Organization of <lb/>
the Empire should be published. It had been <lb/>
printed in the paper of the hon. member for E. <lb/>
Halifax, and had been endorsed by that gen<lb break="no"/>tleman as the scheme propounded by him and <lb/>
his colleagues, and placed before the people of <lb/>
England. That production was considered <lb/>
utterly fruitless and futile by those whom it <lb/>
was intended to influence, but it was useful <lb/>
as showing what the scheme of the opposition <lb/>
was. Those gentlemen proposed that the ques<lb break="no"/>tion should be settled, not by the people them<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="151" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-24_Page_0151.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
<fw type="num">151</fw> 

selves, as they recently contended, but by their <lb/>
representatives. Attempts were being made <lb/>
to frighten people by the idea that they would <lb/>
be drafted for military service in Canada, but <lb/>
that scheme proposed that Nova Scotians <lb/>
should be taxed to an unlimited extent, and <lb/>
be liable to be drafted away to any part of the <lb/>
world. That was the scheme of these gentle<lb break="no"/>men—they admitted that a change was neces<lb break="no"/>sary, and they were willing that it should be <lb/>
made by the people's representatives with the <lb/>
arbitrament of the Imperial Parliament. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COFF1">Mr. COFFIN</persName> said that the hon. member must <lb/>
fancy himself stumping the County of Lunen<lb break="no"/>burg . <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCFA1">Hon. Mr. McFARLANE</persName>, from the committee <lb/>
on Mines and Minerals, introduced a bill to <lb/>
amend the present law relating to mines, one <lb/>
of its objects being to prevent pilfering at the <lb/>
gold mines. <lb/></p> 

<p>The house adjourned. <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>