<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNSLA_1865-04-13" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-04-13">13 April 1865</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA">
          

               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          
         
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Second Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1865"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Reporter" Office</publisher>.
  

          <biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="245"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_238.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_239.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_240.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_241.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_242.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_243.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_244.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_245.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-04-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-04-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_238">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_238.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_239">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_239.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_240">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_240.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_241">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_241.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_242">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_242.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_243">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_243.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_244">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_244.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_245">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_245.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="238" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_238.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">238</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>

<!-- GL, 2017-04-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
 <!--<p>
     wrong the government who have educated the 
     <lb/>
     people up to it—who have taught them that, in 
     <lb/>
     order to carry certain objects, the will receive 
     <lb/>
     such large sums are alone to blame. I con<lb break="no"/>sider, however, all the money is required for the 
     <lb/>
     roads and bridges. You will see by the figures 
     <lb/>
     1 have given that the sum required for the roads 
     <lb/>
     and bridges would nearly swallow up the sub<lb break="no"/>sidy. Can you reduce the grants for educa<lb break="no"/>tion, to the hospital for the insane, for relief, 
     <lb/>
     the penitentiary, and other services? You 
     <lb/>
     know you cannot without emperilling the pub<lb break="no"/>lic service. Therefore the inevitable result is, 
     <lb/>
     as Mr. Galt has told you, in his speech, if the 
     <lb/>
     local revenues are not sufiicient, you must re<lb break="no"/>sort to direct taxation. There is no doubt what<lb break="no"/>ever that this must be the case if this 
     <lb/>
     scheme is carried out. When I feel that the 
     <lb/>
     institutions of our country are to be swept 
     <lb/>
     away, and that the control of our resources 
     <lb/>
     is to be handed over to a people with whom 
     <lb/>
     we have no sympathy, am I not right in 
     <lb/>
     asking this House to pause? What chance 
     <lb/>
     would there be, in such an event, of our 
     <lb/>
     being able to push forward those public im<lb break="no"/>provements that are now being carried on? 
     <lb/>
     All our surplus revenue, as I have said, will go 
     <lb/>
     to Ottawa; and I ask gentlemen who look for<lb break="no"/>ward to the time when railway communication 
     <lb/>
     will extend from Pictou to Antigonishe, to 
     <lb/>
     Guysboro, aye, even through the Island of 
     <lb/>
     Cape Breton, and again westward to Annapo<lb break="no"/>lis and Digby and Yarmouth, what chance 
     <lb/>
     will there be of having their anticipations real— 
     <lb/>
     ized? Only those who are to be elevated from 
     <lb/>
     this country to Ottawa can be satisfied with a 
     <lb/>
     state of things so disastrous to the Province of 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
                     —- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>-->
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     THURSDAY, April 13. 
                </p>

            <p>House met at 3 o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:PRYO1">Mr PRYOR</persName> introduced a bill relating to 
     <lb/>
     traffic on the streets of Halifax. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The following bills were read a third time:— 
     <lb/>
     To provide for the salary of the Governor's 
     <lb/>
     Private Secretary ;—to incorporate the Home 
     <lb/>
     Missionary Board of the Baptist Church;—to 
     <lb/>
     change the name of Ratchford River;—to in<lb break="no"/>corporate the Oak Point Pier Company;—to 
     <lb/>
    provide for certain Bridges in the County of 
     <lb/>Hants;—to incorporate the Trustees of St. 
     <lb/>Matthew's Church ;—to amend the law relat<lb break="no"/>ing to licenses.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">CONFEDERATION. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

    
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName> said that he wished to call the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the house to a subject of conside<lb break="no"/>rable importance at the present moment; and 
     <lb/>
     he regretted that in doing so he had not the 
     <lb/>
     advantage of the presence of the members of 
     <lb/>
     government, who ought to be in their places 
     <lb/>
     attending to the business of the country. He 
     <lb/>
     need not remind the house that one of the most 
     <lb/>
     momentous questions that ever agitated the 
     <lb/>
     public mind was then under discussion—the 
     <lb/>
     question of the union of the British North Ame<lb break="no"/>rican Colonies. He thought that in view of 
     <lb/>
     the aspect that question had lately assumed- 
     <lb/>
     in view of the unmistakeable evidences of pub<lb break="no"/>lic opinion which had recently been given— 
     <lb/>
     there was but little room to doubt that nine<lb break="no"/>teen-tenths of the people of Nova Scotia were 
     <lb/>
     opposed to the scheme propounded by the Ca<lb break="no"/>nadian delegates. He believed that it must be 
     <lb/>
     admitted on all sides that almost the only spot 
     <lb/>
     in Nova Scotia where the subject received any 
     <lb/>
        
            <cb/>
       

     favor, was the city of Halifax; and he was 
     <lb/>
     sorry to be obliged to say that some of the citi<lb break="no"/>zens of Halifax had acted in a manner insolent 
     <lb/>
     and overbearing to the rest of the inhabitants 
     <lb/>
     of the province. (Laughter from the members 
     <lb/>
     for Halifax.) The hon. gentlemen laugh, but 
     <lb/>
     he (Mr. M.) would tell them that this was too 
     <lb/>
     grave a matter to he laughed at. He would 
     <lb/>
     tell them in the face of the house and the coun<lb break="no"/>try that the people of Nova Scotia were not to 
     <lb/>
     be laughed at either by the citizens of Halifax 
     <lb/>
     or their representatives in that house. He 
     <lb/>
     trusted that beforethis discussion was finished 
     <lb/>
     they would be given to understand that there 
     <lb/>
     were other people in the province, whose views 
     <lb/>
     were entitled to respect, besides those who re<lb break="no"/>sided within the limits of the metropolis.— 
     <lb/>
     That morning , upon taking up the organ of the 
     <lb/>
     government he found a notice of a public de<lb break="no"/>monstration that was to take place that even<lb break="no"/>ing in honor of the Canadian delegates, who 
     <lb/>
     were expected to arrive in the steamer, on their 
     <lb/>
     way to England to advocate the scheme of the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec conference. Notwithstanding. as he 
     <lb/>
     had said, that it was well known to those ac<lb break="no"/>quainted with public sentiment in this province 
     <lb/>
     t at nineteen-twentieths of the whole popula— 
     <lb/>
     tion were opposed to the scheme, he could not 
     <lb/>
     help looking on this demonstration as an at<lb break="no"/>tempt to misrepresent the state of feeling that 
     <lb/>
     existed in the minds of a great majority of our 
     <lb/>
     people—to mislead the delegates and the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of England touching our views of this great 
     <lb/>
     question, and to exasperate and insult the in<lb break="no"/>telligence of this country. Perhaps, however, 
     <lb/>
     he would not have felt it his duty to have call<lb break="no"/>ed the attention of the house to the subject but 
     <lb/>
     for a circumstance connected with the demon<lb break="no"/>stration, which was deserving of public notice. 
     <lb/>
     Be perceived a place assigned in the pro<lb break="no"/>gramme to the Volunteer Artillery, and the 
     <lb/>
     other volunteer companies. Now, he would 
     <lb/>
     ask, was it right or proper that the Volunteer 
     <lb/>
     force of this province, which had ever been kept 
     <lb/>
     aloof from party or political influences, should 
     <lb/>
     be asked to take part in a demonstration which 
     <lb/>
     was not only political in its character, but hos<lb break="no"/>tile to the feelings of a vast majority of the 
     <lb/>
     people of this country. He had no objections 
     <lb/>
     to the citizens of Halifax as citizens indulging 
     <lb/>
     in any demonstration they pleased, provided 
     <lb/>
     it would not misrepresent the whole province, 
     <lb/>
     but he thought that gentlemen on both sides 
     <lb/>
     would agree with him that this attempt to 
     <lb/>
     draw the Volunteer organization into the mat<lb break="no"/>ter, was, to say the least of it, unwise and in— 
     <lb/>
     judicious in the extreme. It was well known 
     <lb/>
     that these gentlemen who were going across 
     <lb/>
     the water were going with no feelings of appro<lb break="no"/>val of the conduct of the people of the Mari<lb break="no"/>time Provinces. For aught that was known 
     <lb/>
     they were going charged with the duty of forc<lb break="no"/>ing upon this people a union hostile to their 
     <lb/>
     feelings and their interests. It was understood 
     <lb/>
     that in England and elsewhere Halifax would 
     <lb/>
     be considered to represent the public sentiment 
     <lb/>
     of Nova Scotia, and when the delegates go 
     <lb/>
     home they will be able to point to their recep<lb break="no"/>tion in this city as a proof of our desire for con<lb break="no"/>federation. He believed this was the object of 
     <lb/>
     the procession that would take place that night. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Was it not then the duty of every one who 
     <lb/>was opposed to the scheme publicly to de<lb break="no"/>nounce a demonstration got up in the capital 
     <lb/>for the purpose of influencing the public senti<lb break="no"/>ment of the mother country, and of producing 
  

            <pb n="239" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_239.jpg"/>
           <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">239</fw>


     the impression that the popular voice of the 
     <lb/>
     Province was in favor of a measure which had 
     <lb/>
     been almost universally condemned. Let these 
     <lb/>
     delegates go home, encouraged by all the 
     <lb/>
     cheers and plaudits they would receive through 
     <lb/>
     the streets of Halifax, but let the mind of these 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen and the public mind of England be 
     <lb/>
     disabused of the idea that this demonstration 
     <lb/>
     was in accordance with the feelings of the 
     <lb/>
     great majority of the people of Nova Scotia.— 
     <lb/>
     The hon. gentleman concluded by calling upon 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen opposed to the scheme to join with 
     <lb/>
     him in denouncing the attempt to misrepresent 
     <lb/>
     the opinion of the country upon the question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LEVE1">Mr. Le Vesconte</persName> thought his colleague was 
     <lb/>
     perfectly right in bringing this matter to the 
     <lb/>
     notice of the house. As it was well known 
     <lb/>
     that nine-tenths of the people of the Province 
     <lb/>
     were opposed to the question of Union, he 
     <lb/>
     thought that this demonstration exhibited very 
     <lb/>
     bad taste,—independent altogether of the im<lb break="no"/>propriety of bringing in the Volunteer force, 
     <lb/>
     which was organised for the defence of the 
     <lb/>
     country, and not to take part in political 
     <lb/>
     demonstrations of this kind. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     He would conclude by a motion, so as to be 
     <lb/>
     in order. The hon. gentleman then read the 
     <lb/>
     following:—" Resolved that this House disap<lb break="no"/>proves of the Volunteer organization (as such<lb/>organization) taking part in any party demon<lb break="no"/>stration."<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> said he believed this was a free 
     <lb/>
     country, where everybody could enjoy his own 
     <lb/>
     opinions, and he thought that the citizens of 
     <lb/>
    Halifax had a perfect right to get up any 
     <lb/>demonstration they please upon any subject, 
     <lb/>provided they did not infringe the law. As 
     <lb/>regards the feelings of the citizens of Halifax, 
     <lb/>they differed upon this question of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, as the people did everywhere else—there 
     <lb/>were some warm supporters of it, and some 
     <lb/>equally warm opponents. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     He was happy to be able to say, that the 
     <lb/>
     conduct of the citizens of Halifax on all public 
     <lb/>
     occasions was temperate and orderly—they in<lb break="no"/>sulted nobody; and he did not see how this 
     <lb/>
     demonstration could be construed as an insult 
     <lb/>
     to this House, or the people of this Province. 
     <lb/>
     Sometimes they would show a little ebullition 
     <lb/>
     of feeling, when any thing distasteful to their 
     <lb/>
     feelings was said, as the hon. gentleman for 
     <lb/>
     Richmond had himself experienced on one oc<lb break="no"/>casion, and perhaps that was the cause of the 
     <lb/>
     temper; which be exhibited in introducing this 
     <lb/>
     subject . 
      </p>
            <p>  As regards the question of Confederation, he 
     <lb/>did not hesitate to say that he was a most en<lb break="no"/>thusiastic supporter of it. He considered it 
     <lb/>one of the grandest schemes ever offered to a 
     <lb/>free people; and, to his mind, it was matter of 
     <lb/>wonder that any one could wish that Nova 
     <lb/>Scotia should remain in her present position. 
     <lb/>What was there in this country, he would ask, 
     <lb/>to satisfy the ambition of her young men—or 
     <lb/>what scope did our limited means afford for 
     <lb/>the exercise of their talents? If honorable 
     <lb/>gentlemen were satisfied with this state of 
     <lb/>things, he, for one, was not; and he believed 
     <lb/>that when the people of this country came 
     <lb/>properly to understand it, instead of nine- 
     <lb break="yes"/>tenths being against it, more than that num<lb break="no"/>ber would declare in its favor. He did not in<lb break="no"/>tend to make a speech on Confederation; but 
     <lb/>but while upon the subject, he would read a 
     <lb/>letter he had recently received from one of 
     <lb/>Nova Scotia's ablest sons-one whose career 
     

            <cb/>
     

     had reflected honor open himself and his na<lb break="no"/>tive country, and whose portrait. he was happy 
     <lb/>
     to say, adorned the walls of the Council Cham<lb break="no"/>ber of that building. What does he say upon 
     <lb/>
     this great subject? The hon. gentleman here 
     <lb/>
     read an extract from a letter of General 
     <lb/>
     Williams, as follows: 
     <lb/></p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     
<p rendition="simple:right">MONTREAL, March 3rd. 1865. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     My life has been spent in the service of the Empire, 
     <lb/>
     and I have had neither time nor opportunity to mix 
     <lb/>
     myself up in your politics; and while I respect every 
     <lb/>
     man's opinions in relation to them, l do most sincerely 
     <lb/>
     hope that every Nova Scotian will cast away party 
     <lb/>
     ties and political aspirations, and embrace the present 
     <lb/>
     golden opportunity which passing events, both in Eu<lb break="no"/>rope and America, now offer for the knitting together 
     <lb/>
     of these magnificent colonies into one great and loyal 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. We shall then have combined <hi rendition="simple:italic">strength</hi>, 
     <lb/>
     instead of divided <hi rendition="simple:italic">counsels</hi> and all its consequent evils. 
     <lb/>
     The position I hold under the Crown precludes the pos<lb break="no"/>sibility of my taking an active part in your discussions; 
     <lb/>
     but if were once more in private life, I would zealous<lb break="no"/>ly preach intercolonial, prompt intercolonial action, 
     <lb/>
     throughout the length and breadth of Nova Scotia. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>
     This, he thought, was strong testimony from 
     <lb/>
     one who was uninfluenced by the feelings 
     <lb/>
     which might affect the judgment of others 
     <lb/>
    placed in different circumstances, and there— 
     <lb/>fore was entitled to greater consideration. He 
     <lb/>hoped that hon. gentlemen would approach   
     <lb/>the discussion of this question in an enlighten— 
     <lb/>ed spirit, and would not be influenced by party 
     <lb/>or local prejudices. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LOCK1">Mr. LOCKE</persName> said that the member for Rich<lb break="no"/>mond deserved the thanks of the House for 
     <lb/>
     bringing this subject forward, and he agreed 
     <lb/>
     with him that this demonstration was exas<lb break="no"/>perating and insulting in the extreme to the 
     <lb/>
     people of this country. What was the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of this meeting tonight? Evidently to 
     <lb/>
     mislead the people of England as to the feel<lb break="no"/>ing of this country on the subject of Confede<lb break="no"/>ration. The steamer that takes these dele<lb break="no"/>gates home will also carry the account of this 
     <lb/>
     demonstration, and the impression which 
     <lb/>
     would naturally be conveyed would be that it 
     <lb/>
     reflected the feelings of the whole Province. 
     <lb/>
     This he denied most emphatically; and he 
     <lb/>
     thought it was the duty of every gentleman 
     <lb/>
     opposed to the measure thus publicly to de<lb break="no"/>nounce so unfair an attempt to produce a wrong 
     <lb/>
     impression. As regards the opinions of Gen. 
     <lb/>
     Williams, he woul say that they all respected 
     <lb/>
     him; but it must be remembered that although 
     <lb/>
     a Nova Scotian by birth, he was thoroughy 
     <lb/>
     English in all his ideas, and he thought upon 
     <lb/>
     this subject as all Englishmen did. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SHAN2">Hon. Mr. SHANNON</persName> was surprised at the re<lb break="no"/>marks that had been made, and he could not 
     <lb/>
     understand what reference this demonstration . 
     <lb/>
     had to the Legislature, or how it could be con<lb break="no"/>strued into an insult upon the people's repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives. That time last year there was a de<lb break="no"/>monstration'of another character, in honor of 
     <lb/>
     Shakspeare, and the house adjourned to hear 
     <lb/>
     the oration that was then delivered-but this 
     <lb/>
     demonstration would not interfere with the 
     <lb/>
     public duties of any hon. gentleman. It was to 
     <lb/>
     take place at night—those who did not choose 
     <lb/>
    to attend could stay away—and he really did 
     <lb/>not see what right that house had to interfere 
     <lb/>with the citizens of Halifax in a matter of this   
     <lb/>kind. He could understand how some hon; 
     <lb/>gentlemen, who had been hissed down by a 
     <lb/>Halifax audience, should not entertain very 
     <lb/>friendly feelings   towards the citizens; but he   
     <lb/>did not think the time of the house should be 
     <lb/>wasted on such matters.       
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="240" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_240.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">240</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>


            <p> <persName ref="pers:KILL2">Mr. KILLAM</persName> supposed that the object of
the <lb/>
demonstration was to produce the same im<lb break="no"/>pression upon the minds of the British
people<lb/>
as had been produced upon Mr. Cardwell, viz:<lb/>
that the feeling of this country was in
favor of<lb/>
Confederation. As that was at variance
with <lb/>
the facts, it was right that the matter
should be<lb/>
brought before the house, so that any
erroneous<lb/>
impression might be removed.</p>



            <p><persName ref="pers:LEVE1">Mr. LEVESCONTE</persName> said that when some years<lb/>
ago a volunteer company took part in a
demon<lb break="no"/>stration in honor of the election of Lord
Pal<lb break="no"/>merston, attention was called to the fact
in the<lb/>
House of Commons. The only excuse that<lb/>
was given on that occasion was that the
affair<lb/>
had occurred through animadertance. He<lb/>
contended that the volunteers, which were<lb/>
supported by the people's money, had no
right<lb/>
to take part in any political demonstration<lb/>
whatever. Partcularly careful should they
be<lb/>
to give their countenance to a scheme to
which<lb/>
seven-eighths of the people were
unfavorable.</p>





            <p><persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> called attention to the
programme,<lb/>
and justified the action of the citizens.
He<lb/>
thought if the hon. member was going to
load<lb/>
his gun with patriotic powder he should try<lb/>
and aim at something more tangible than
the <lb/>
present matter.</p>



            <p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PRO. SEC</persName>. said that he rose for the
pur<lb break="no"/>pose of movin that the house pass to the
or<lb break="no"/>der of the day. He would not feel disposed
to<lb/>
interfere with any desire of the hon.
member<lb/>
for Richmond (Mr. Miller) to favor the
house<lb/>
with those rhetorical outbursts of
indignation<lb/>
with reference to the very contemptible
cha<lb break="no"/>racter and position that Halifax occupied
in the<lb/>
Province of Nova Scotia. That hon. member<lb/>
had rendered himself famous for such
exhibi<lb break="no"/>tions, and it would be a pit to interfere
in the <lb/>
slightest degree with any anxiety that he
might<lb/>
have to place the city in antagonism to
the <lb/>
country. It was not the most laudable ambi<lb break="no"/>tion in the world for any one to endeavor
on<lb/>
every possible occasion to excite
unpleasant<lb/>
feelings between different sections of the
coun<lb break="no"/>try. The hon. member's talents and
exertions<lb/>
might be directed to a far worthier
object. It<lb/>
might not be worth while, perhaps,
noticing the<lb/>
hon. member's attempts to show the people<lb/>
that he had take them under his patriotic
care,<lb/>
and in fact to relieve their apprehensions
of<lb/>
being trampled down by Halifax influence;<lb/>
but when a resolution was moved which, if<lb/>
passed would place the house in a false
posi<lb break="no"/>tion, it was that he (Dr. T.) should
briefly<lb/>
call attention to the real circumstances
of the<lb/>
case. He would state, at the commencement,<lb/>
that the first time he had seen the
programme<lb/>
was at eleven or twelve o'clock when he
hap<lb break="no"/>pened to take up one of the morning
papers. I<lb/>
was well known that there existed in this
city<lb/>
an organization called the Union League. It<lb/>
was not of a secret character; its meetings<lb/>
were called by public notice in the
newspapers,<lb/>
and every man favorable to the cause of
union<lb/>
was invited to attend them. Most of the
lead<lb break="no"/>ing and influential and respectable
citizens of <lb/>
Halifax were engaged in that organization
for<lb/>
the purpose, as they believed, of
promoting the<lb/>
best interests of the Province of British
North<lb/>
America and of Nova Scotia especially. No<lb/>
one could deny that even if the sentiments<lb/>
they held were favorablt entertained by
only<lb/>
one-tenth of the people, yet they had a
perfect<lb/>
right to use all legitimate means of
inculcating<lb/>
their opinions without hindrance on the
part<lb/>
of any one.<lb/>
            </p>

            <cb/>


            <p> He would confess that he had read with<lb/>
some little surprises the fact that the Volunteer<lb/>
Companies were to take part in this demon<lb break="no"/>stration. The question at issue, it was true,<lb/>
was one that perhaps more than any other,<lb/>
would warrant the Volunteers giving it their<lb/>
countenance. It was known that a delegation<lb/>
was on its way from Canada to England for<lb/>
the purpose of discussing with the Imperial<lb/>
Government the question of defence, the Reci<lb break="no"/>procity Treaty, and Confederation. Gentle<lb break="no"/>men who had the Union cause at heart, felt<lb/>
that they would be wanting in their duty if<lb/>
they did not show this delegation, on its ar<lb break="no"/>rival that night, that there was in the City of<lb/>
Halifax a large and influential body of citizens<lb/>
who were favorable to the Confederation of<lb/>
British North America. If it was possible<lb/>
that there could be an occasion when the<lb/>
Volunteer organisation would be entitled to<lb/>
turn out, it was when gentlemen were touching<lb/>
our shores on their way to the Imperial Go<lb break="no"/>vernment to provide for the defence and secu<lb break="no"/>rity of British North America. Divided, how<lb break="no"/>ever, as public sentiment was in this country <lb/>
on this great question, he did not think it ad<lb break="no"/>visable that the Militia, or Volunteer, or Artil<lb break="no"/>lery organization, should turn out in their uni<lb break="no"/>forms. Since this debate had commenced,<lb/>
without any communication on his own part,<lb/>
he had received an intimation from Captain<lb/>
Chearnley, who commanded the organization,<lb/>
that any members of that organization might<lb/>
attend the demonstration as citizens, but non<lb/>
as Volunteers.</p>
            <p>It might be attempted to array the country<lb/>
against Halifax, but no one could prevent the <lb/>
fact being made known that in the political<lb/>
and commercial metropolis of the Province<lb/>
there was a deeply rooted public sentiment<lb/>
prevading the minds of the most leading and<lb/>
influential men of all classes, that the future<lb/>
prosperity of Nova Scotia, as well as of all the<lb/>
Provinces of British North America, depended<lb/>
on the success of the scheme of Confederation.<lb/>
When you read the programme for that even<lb break="no"/>ing's celebration, you saw that not only the<lb/>
most highly educated and intelligent members<lb/>
of the mercantile community, but the bone and <lb/>
sinew of the city, the artizans and the working<lb/>
men, proposed to lend their aid in paying due<lb/>
honor to those who were laboring to promote<lb/>
the best interests of British North America at<lb/>
this critical period of the world's history. He<lb/>
could not understand why the feeling of some<lb/>
gentlemen were so excited on this subject.-<lb/>
Was there a man who would deny that an<lb/>
overwhelming body of the citizens of Halifax<lb/>
was in favor of Union. When the meetings in<lb/>
respect to that question were held in the city,<lb/>
Temperance Hall was densely packed, night<lb/>
after night. So strong was the current of pub<lb break="no"/>lic sympathy in favor of Union, that, at times,<lb/>
it was almost impossible for the friends of Con<lb break="no"/>federation to proceed, so enthusiastic were the<lb/>
plaudits that met them. When it was also at<lb break="no"/>tempted to make the House believe that nine-<lb break="yes"/>
tenths of the people of this country were against<lb/>
Union, a liberty was taken with the true facts<lb/>
that was unworthy of any public man. Al<lb break="no"/>though great exertions had been made, and <lb/>
large amounts of money expended all over the<lb/>
face of the country, only fifteen or sixteen thou<lb break="no"/>sand persons had been persuaded to sign the <lb/>
same, or get some one else to sign them - for <lb/>
very many are signed by a cross - to petitions<lb/>
          

            <pb n="241" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_241.jpg"/>

<fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">241</fw>

 in
reference to the question of Confederation.<lb/>
Let it be marked, too, that of this number
only<lb/>
3000 could be induced to express the
opinion<lb/>
that they disapproved of the Confederation
of <lb/>
British North America. The remaining num<lb break="no"/>ber only said that they were not able to
make<lb/>
up their minds on the subject - they wanted<lb/>
more information. Contrast the meagre
results<lb/>
after the tremendous efforts that had been<lb/>
put forth, with those that had been
attained,<lb/>
some years ago, by one party alone in this<lb/>
country. In the course of some three or
four<lb/>
weeks, some 26,000 petitioners had
approached<lb/>
the House asking for a dissolution on the <lb/>
ground that the ment then in power did not
pos<lb break="no"/>sess the confidence of the country.<lb/>
            </p>

<p>The time would come when the people could<lb/>
legitimately be called upon to give their <lb/>
opinion on the question - when they were
fully<lb/>
informed, they would support it in the most<lb/>
convincing manner. He had had an opportu<lb break="no"/>nity of testing the feelings of the
country al<lb break="no"/>ready. He went up into the County of Hants,<lb/>
and at a large public meeting held in the
town<lb/>
of Windsor, had conclusive proof that the <lb/>
sentiment there, at all events, was in
favor of<lb/>
the scheme. Again, at a meeting held at<lb/>
Kentville - on that was called by the oppo<lb break="no"/>nents of Confederation, in a County where
the<lb/>
most deceptive and fallacious statements
had<lb/>
been promulgated - after a lengthy
discussion, <lb/>
a resolution to defer the consideraton of
the<lb/>
question was voted down at the close.
Again,<lb/>
he had delivered a lecture on the subject
in<lb/>
connection with the collegiate institution
in <lb/>
that country, and on that occasion the
demon<lb break="no"/>strations given were of the most
satisfactory<lb/>
character. Then he had attended a meeting
in<lb/>
Colchester, and he would ask gentlemen op<lb break="no"/>posite whether the Southern district would<lb/>
not rise up to-morrow, almost to a man, in
fa<lb break="no"/>vor of a Union of British North America? In<lb/>
Cumberland he travelled for a hundred miles<lb/>
- from Mill Village to Cornwallis - and
found<lb/>
the publlic sentiment, not only of one,
but of<lb/>
both political parties, in favour of the
scheme.<lb/>
Then he went into Annapolis, and attended
a <lb/>
meeting called at Bridgetown by the oppo<lb break="no"/>nents of Confederation. He found he did not<lb/>
stand alone there, but was supported by
some<lb/>
of the most highly educated, respectable
and<lb/>
intelligent men that had opposed the
Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. When the recently returned member<lb/>
(Mr. Ray) moved a resolution simply asking<lb/>
for delay, he (Dr. T.) called upon the
meeting<lb/>
to vite it down, and not even give a
semblance<lb/>
of opposition to a union of British North
Ame<lb break="no"/>rica. The hon. member then called upon the
<lb/>
supporterd of the reolution to follow him
out, <lb/>
and when they had done so, they were
hardly <lb/>
missed in that densely crowded house.
Again, <lb/>
he went to Annapolis, and there the same
hon.<lb/>
member, who acted with a great deal of
tact,<lb/>
saw that, in the temper of his
constituents, it<lb/>
was not wise to move a resolution similar
to<lb/>
the one at Bridgetown.</p>



            <p>Was it to be said, then, that nine-tenths
of <lb/>
the people of this country were opposed to<lb/>
Confederation? He believed there were cer<lb break="no"/>tain sections that had never hesitated to
oppose<lb/>
it - some there were whose predilections
were <lb/>
not so much in favour of British
institutions,<lb/>
but whose feelings as well as commercial
re<lb break="no"/>lations drew them largely towards the
neigh<lb break="no"/>boring republic. But no large body of peo<lb break="no"/>ple were found actually hostile to this
great

            <cb/>
       

 question. Was it not known that the head of<lb/>
the Episcopal Church - one of the most highly<lb/>
educated and influential gentlemen in this <lb/>
country - one who stood aside from all political<lb/>
parties - whose great object was the advance<lb break="no"/>ment of his church and the common interests<lb/>
of the province in which he lives - was openly<lb/>
and unequivocally in favor of union. Again,<lb/>
His Grace the Archbishop - a gentleman whom<lb/>
all creeds and classes respect - one of the most<lb/>
sagacious and far-seeing men in the country <lb/> had come out boldly and fearlessly to vindicate<lb/>
union. That eminent man did not believe the <lb/>
scheme would sell us to Canada; on the con<lb break="no"/>trary, that it would promote the security of<lb/>
Nova Sotia and preserve its present institu<lb break="no"/>tions and its connection with the mother coun<lb break="no"/>try, and, at the same time, advance, in common<lb/>
with the rest of those of the people, the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of which he is the ecclesiastical head. The<lb/>
organs of the Presbyterian church, (the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Pres:<lb/>
byterian Witness</hi>,) of the Methodist, (the <hi rendition="simple:italic">We<lb break="no"/>leyan</hi>,) and of the Baptist, (the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Christian Mes<lb break="no"/>senger</hi>,) were all known to support the Con<lb break="no"/>federation of these provinces. Was it to be <lb/>
said, then, in the light of such facts as these<lb/>
that nine-tenths of the people were opposed to<lb/>
this great sheme?</p>
            <p>Over in New Brunswick the opponents of <lb/>
confederation had had a very doubtful suc<lb break="no"/>cess. Notwithstanding all their exertions - all<lb/>
the misrepresentations of the opponents of<lb/>
confederation, they had only got in the whole<lb/>
of the province a bare majority of the votes of<lb/>
the people. So closely balances was the vote<lb/>
on either side that it was almost impossibe to<lb/>
draw the line between them. In fact, the op<lb break="no"/>ponents of confederation having polled 500<lb/>
votes more than the friends of the scheme.<lb/>
Yet the people of England was to be made to <lb/>
believe that not only nine-tenths of the people<lb/>
in Nova Scotia, but in New Brunswick as <lb/>
well, were opposed to the confederation of Bri<lb break="no"/>tish America. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>In the conclusion, he called upon the House to <lb/>
consider the position in which it would be <lb/>
placed if it passd the resolution. Would it <lb/>
elevate itself in the opinion of strangers, if it<lb/>
were to so far forget what was due to its posi<lb break="no"/>tion and dignity as to express unfriendly feel<lb break="no"/>ings on an occasion when some of the most<lb/>
eminent statesmen of British North America were <lb/>
touching our shores? He would recall the at<lb break="no"/>tention of gentlemen to the kindliness and ge<lb break="no"/>nerosity with which the people of Canada had<lb/>
greeted the Delegated from the Maritime Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. So far was the feeling in Quebec at the<lb/>
commencement from being cordial towards the<lb/>
object of the delegates, that the chairman of the <lb/>
Board of Trade, at the dinner, actually felt<lb/>
himself bound to say that that Association did<lb/>
not feel itself prepared to express any appro<lb break="no"/>val of Union. The Delegates went to that din<lb break="no"/>ner under the conviction that a large number<lb/>
of the most eminent merchants of Quebec were<lb/>
in a position of avowed hostility to the objects<lb/>
of the Conference. But they did not attempt<lb/>
to hiss the Delegates when they explained their<lb/>
position, - they behaved themselves like edu<lb break="no"/>cated gentlemen, - they felt they could tender <lb/>
their hospitalities without compromising their<lb/>
own opinions. The feeling that prevailed all <lb/>
through Canada, wherever the Delegates went, <lb/>
was that the visit was an occasion for the dis<lb break="no"/>play of inter-provincial courtesy. Political<lb/>
men of all shades of opinion vied with each<lb/>
           

            <pb n="242" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_242.jpg"/>
         <fw type="num">242</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>

 other how they might best testify their
respect <lb/>
and regard which they had for
the Province of <lb/>
Nova Scotia. At the dinner at Montreal there <lb/>
were scores of opponents of the scheme—Do<lb break="no"/>rion and Holton for instance, who had fought
<lb/>
against it to the death on the floors of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. John Sandfield McDonald also treated <lb/>
the delegates with the same consideration. In <lb/>
what position, then, would this country be pla<lb break="no"/>ced, if it were to display, through its Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture, feelings of hostility to
the statesmen of a <lb/>
country who had treated our own public men, <lb/>
irrespective of party, with so much courtesy <lb/>
and attention? He would only add, that he felt <lb/>
when he had made the observation
that he did <lb/>
in reference to the volunteers, that he was ma<lb break="no"/>king a reflection upon Canada, for one of the <lb/>
finest displays that met the eye of the Dele<lb break="no"/>gates had been the march of the splendid vo<lb break="no"/>lunteer artillery past the hotel in Montreal.— <lb/>
One part of the reception. at Toronto that had <lb/>
been arranged, but prevented by
the weather, <lb/>
was a grand display of all the volunteers that <lb/>
could he collected in the city. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. STEWART CAMPBELL</persName> said that the Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary, a few days ago,
had himself <lb/>
related an anecdote of a person who could al<lb break="no"/>ways tell who had the worst of a controversy. <lb/>
Whenever one of the individuals engaged in <lb/>
the dispute showed a great deal of temper and <lb/>
excitement, then it was sure evidence that he <lb/>
was getting the worst of it. On
the present <lb/>
occasion the Provincial Secretary
had exhibit<lb break="no"/>ed a great deal of unnecessary temper. <lb/>
            </p>
   <p> <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>.: I am quite ignorant of
it, <lb/>
at all events. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. CAMPBELL</persName>: The hon. gentleman had re<lb break="no"/>flected upon the course taken by the hon. <lb/>
member for Richmond in bringing this matter <lb/>
to the notice of the house. Now if there was <lb/>
any one in the house who was better justified <lb/>
than another in bringing it up, it was that <lb/>
same hon. member. Any one who was ac<lb break="no"/>quainted with the question through its various <lb/>
phases, must be aware that on a certain occa<lb break="no"/>sion at Temperance Hall, that gentleman was <lb/>
treated with an indignity which he did not de<lb break="no"/>serve. It was felt to be an insult not to him <lb/>
alone, but to the people thrbugh the length and <lb/>
breadth of Nova Scotia. He (Mr. C.) was also <lb/>
one of those who felt that the City of Halifax <lb/>
was not the Province of Nova Scotia. It had <lb/>
been said that there were certain individuals <lb/>
about the streets who were underrating the <lb/>
position of members of the House who came <lb/>
from the rural districts. These individuals <lb/>
might have stock in the bank—real estate in <lb/>
this city and country,—but they had never ap<lb break="no"/>pealed to any constituency in this Province <lb/>
and obtained the confidence of the people. <lb/>
Therefore they had no right to talk in <lb/>
such disparaging terms of gentlemen who <lb/>
for years had represented the rural dis<lb break="no"/>tricts. He was one of those who objected <lb/>
to the demonstration—not because it was <lb/>
intended, as the Provincial Secretary would <lb/>
make the House believe, as a reception <lb/>
to gentlemen from a sister colony. He objected <lb/>
to it because he could see through the motive <lb/>
and design with which the demonstration was <lb/>
got up. The people of the parent country had <lb/>
all been misled upon the question, and the <lb/>
course now about to be taken was for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of keeping up that deception.  Now he <lb/>
wished the people of England to be informed, <lb/>
as far as the house could inform them, of the <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
          

 sense of the people of this country. The <lb/>
delegates reported to Great Britain when there <lb/>
was no legislature in session, and they had it <lb/>
all their own way. They misled the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of England, and as to the feelings
of the <lb/>
people of these colonies; and he therefore <lb/>
thought the house, being now in session, owed <lb/>
it to themselves and those they represented, to <lb/>
take care that nothing tool: place with the con<lb break="no"/>currence of the government that
could have <lb/>
the slightest tendency in the same direction.
<lb/>
It was the Hon. Provincial Secretary himself <lb/>
that was attempting to place the house in a <lb/>
false position. He wished to have the impres<lb break="no"/>sion go abroad that the house
sympathized <lb/>
with the sentiments of those gentlemen who <lb/>
were now taking part in the demonstration in <lb/>
question. The hon. gentleman had alluded to <lb/>
the Union League, and had not paid a very <lb/>
high compliment to many
gentlemen who, in <lb/>
times past, has been his valuable and active <lb/>
supporters. He had instituted a comparison <lb/>
between the members of the League and those <lb/>
who were opposed to it. He had ventured to <lb/>
say that the—to use his own language—most <lb/>
leading, influential, respectable
citizens of Ha<lb break="no"/>lifax were members of the League.
Then it <lb/>
may be a natural deduction that those who did <lb/>
not belong to this organization did not compare <lb/>
in point of respectability or position with its <lb/>
members. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The hon. Provincial Secretary had gone <lb/>
through the Province and expressed his opi<lb break="no"/>nion as to the feeling of the country from what <lb/>
took place at some meetings at which he was <lb/>
present. Now few gentlemen would be ready <lb/>
to accept his version of the results of those <lb/>
meetings. Now talk was all very
good, but it <lb/>
would have been more satisfactory
if they had <lb/>
the best evidence that could be given of the <lb/>
feeling of the country—the evidence obtained <lb/>
from the votes of the people themselves.
He <lb/>
challenged the hon. gentleman to produce one <lb/>
petition that had been sent to the house, en<lb break="no"/>dorsing this scheme of Confederation. The <lb/>
hon. Provincial Secretary had stated that the <lb/>
majority of the petitioners before the house <lb/>
expressed no positive opinion with reference <lb/>
to the question. But these petitions said in <lb/>
effect to the Provincial Secretary: You have <lb/>
said that the people of this country are in fa<lb break="no"/>vour of this measure—that if you don't obtain <lb/>
the approval of the representatives of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple you will dissolve the house; now we call <lb/>
upon you to fulfill your promise, and dissolve <lb/>
the Legislature if you dare. Need the house <lb/>
he told that the hon. gentleman had paid some <lb/>
heed to the language of these petitions? He <lb/>
knew the feeling of the people and dared not <lb/>
test it. <lb/>
            </p>





            <p> The hon. Provincial Secretary had taken -
a<lb/>
liberty with an eminent Divine in this country <lb/>
which it was difficult to believe
he was justified <lb/>
in taking. Every one who knew the Lord Bishop<lb/>
of Nova Scotia, was aware that no one coul <lb/>
charge him with having ever taken a part in <lb/>
any political demonstration, or even expressed <lb/>
any feeling in reference to party matters, in <lb/>
this country. It was very bad taste for the <lb/>
Provincial Secretary, under the circumstances, <lb/>
to bring the name of that dignitary, without <lb/>
his concurrence, before the house. Until he <lb/>
heard from another month than the Provincial <lb/>
Secretary's that that gentleman is in favour of<lb/>
the measure, he would be disposed to doubt <lb/>
not only the authority that hon. member had for <lb/>
         

            <pb n="243" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_243.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">243</fw>

bringing his name there, but also the
existence <lb/>
of those opinions. His Grace the Archbishop<lb/>
had also been referred to—as every one was
<lb/>
aware, that eminent gentleman, respected bu<lb/>
all creeds and classes, had made his
opinions<lb/>
known. These opinions had had their course<lb/>
through the country, and thier effect would<lb/>
appear in due time. The Presbyterian
clergy<lb break="no"/>men had also been alluded to, but how long<lb/>
was it that the Provincial Secretary had
placed<lb/>
such confidence in the ministry of that
deno<lb break="no"/>mination. A very strange revulsion of
feeling<lb/>
had taken place in that hon. gentleman. A<lb/>
few years ago he could not find anything,
too <lb/>
coarse in the vocabulary of Billingsgate
against<lb/>
Presbyterian clergymen, but he had changed<lb/>
his tone all at once.</p>




            <p>The hon. member for Halifax (Mr. Shannon)<lb/>
had attempted to justify this demonstration<lb/>
by reference to what took place last year
in<lb/>
connection with the illustrious name of
Shake<lb break="cb"/>spere. No analogy could be drawn between<lb/>
the two demonstrations. That of last year<lb/>
was a national demonstration; not merely in<lb/>
Halifax and Nova Scotia, but in all
portions of<lb/>
the British empire—wherever literature and
<lb/>
civilization are prized. It was an honour
to <lb/>
our common humanity—not an honour to any<lb/>
particular nationality, but one to the
name of<lb/>
man. Therefore it was that men of every
cli<lb break="no"/>mate and every nation vied with each other
in <lb/>
paying tribute to a name that will live as
long<lb/>
as this world will last. Another individual<lb/>
had been mentioned as approving of the <lb/>
scheme of Confederation—General Williams.<lb/>
No man of Nova Scotia was prouder of the <lb/>
fame of that distinguished Nova Soctian
than<lb/>
he himself, and it was a proud day when he
<lb/>
sat in the Speaker's chair and put the
resolu<lb break="no"/>tion by which the House paid him honour. He<lb/>
admired that illustrious gentleman's
talents,<lb/>
but upon this question the people of Nova
Sco<lb break="no"/>tia and their representatives were as
competent<lb/>
to form a sound and safe opinion as even
the <lb/>
hero of Kars.</p>



            <p>The hon. Provincial Secretary defended the
<lb/>
demonstration on the ground that it was
only<lb/>
right that we should return the courtesies
paid <lb/>
to the delegates. There was no doubt that
the <lb/>
various bodies in Canada did treat these
gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen in the handsomest style. Although<lb/>
this province paid very handsomely for the<lb/>
visit they made, yet he rather believed
that<lb/>
they travelled free—that all their
expenses,<lb/>
even their washing bills were paind in Ca<lb break="no"/>nada. No one could have the slightest
objection<lb/>
to the hon. Provincial Secretary or the
Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General cracking as many bottles of <lb/>
Champagne as they pleased as private indivi<lb break="no"/>duals with these Canadian gentlemen, but it<lb/>
was not just or right that the governemnt
of <lb/>
this country should endorse the action of
the<lb/>
city of Halifax in respect to this
demonstra<lb break="no"/>tion. Without dwelling further on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject he would read the following
resolution as<lb/>
expressing the views of himself, and as be
be<lb break="no"/>lieved, of a majority in the House:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas a public demonstration is pro<lb break="no"/>posed to take place this evening in the city of<lb/>
Halifax for the purpose of giving a public re<lb break="no"/>ception to certain gentlemen who formed a <lb/>
portion of the late convention at Quebec.</p>

            <p>And whereas by the programme of the de<lb break="no"/>monstration, it appears that a portion of the <lb/>
Volunteers force are to take part in such de<lb break="no"/>monstration. <lb/>
            </p>

            <cb/>
            

<p>Resolved, as the sense  of the house of this <lb/>
demonstration, that it is not, and must not be,<lb/>
taken to evince the feeling of the majority of this<lb/>
house or of the people of this province as being<lb/>
favourable to the Union of British Colonies as<lb/>
settled by the Quebec conference, and further<lb/>
that in the event of the local forces taking part<lb/>
in such demonstration, such action would be<lb/>
highly derogatory to their true position and<lb/>
distasteful and displeasing to the house, and <lb/>
that the house entertaining these views can<lb break="no"/>not proceed to the order of the day without in<lb/>
the first place, in the present emergency, ex<lb break="no"/>pressing the foregoing sentiments.</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KILL2">Mr. KILLAM</persName> said as the government had <lb/>
conceded the position, he did not see it was ne<lb break="no"/>cessary to keep up the matter further. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOUR5">Mr. BOURINOT</persName> said that the Provincial<lb/>
Secretary, in the course of his second Confede<lb break="no"/>ration speech had stated that the petitions now<lb/>
on the table of the house did not show that the <lb/>
public opinion of Nova Scotia was opposed to<lb/>
this scheme of union devised at the Quebec<lb/>
Conference. Now he had the honour of repre<lb break="no"/>senting one of the largest constituencies in the <lb/>
province; he had individually expressed no<lb/>
opinion against Confederation, but at the same<lb/>
time he could not help seeing that the public<lb/>
sentiment of the country was opposed to the <lb/>
scheme. As respects the resolution before the <lb/>
house, it would not have been presented at all<lb/>
if it had not been stated in the programme that<lb/>
the volunteers would form part of the con<lb break="no"/>templated procession. The Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary had, however, stated that the volunteers<lb/>
were not to be present, and therefore the whole<lb/>
thing was at an end. He looked upon this de<lb break="no"/>monstration in a different light to any member<lb/>
who had spoken upon the subject. Gentlemen<lb/>
would re-call the demonstrations that took<lb/>
place during the summer months. He was<lb/>
glad that our people had given the Canadian <lb/>
visitors a reception that did honour to Nova <lb/>
Scotia. On this occasion, however, there was<lb/>
an expression of opinion given in favor of<lb/>
union. As far as the sentiment of Halifax<lb/>
audiences went, it was in support of union;<lb/>
but that feeling was not responded to by the <lb/>
country. The delegation representing Nova <lb/>
Scotia, thinking they were representing public<lb/>
opinion in this province, went to Canada and<lb/>
agreed to the scheme which was not before<lb/>
the people. Every one knew what a feeling of<lb/>
hostility existed in all the rural districts<lb/>
against this proposed Confederation, Now he<lb/>
looked upon this demonstration as one<lb/>
which the citizens of Halifax were at<lb/>
perfect liberty to make apart from any boday of<lb/>
men such as the Volunteers, but why was this<lb/>
affair got up. It was intended to exhibit sym<lb break="no"/>pathy for those despondent men who were<lb/>
coming among a population who recieved them<lb/>
so heartily last year. Every thing that could<lb/>
soothe their disappointment at the failure of<lb/>
their grand scheme would be doubtless done<lb/>
that night. He trusted it would have a bene<lb break="no"/>ficial effect upon them, but despite all this, let<lb/>
it be remembered, that Confederation was not<lb/>
and would not be adopted.</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName> said that he rose chiefly to make a <lb/>
a few remarks in respect to the hon. member for<lb/>
Halifax, (Mr. Shannon), who had the bad taste<lb/>
to refer, in connection with the Union agitation, <lb/>
to some of the disgraceful scenes witnessed in <lb/>
Temperance Hall. He did so, because that gen<lb break="no"/>
          
            <pb n="244" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_244.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">244</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>

tleman had on other occasions gone out of
his way<lb/>
to attack him. He had been often amused at
the <lb/>
manner in which the hon. member was in the
<lb/>
habit of approaching the discussion of
questions<lb/>
in the House. He (Mr. M.) had now been in
the <lb/>
Legislature for two years, and previously
had <lb/>
been frequently in the galleries, and he
had yet<lb/>
to learn, from personal devotion or
otherwise, <lb/>
that that hon. gentleman had distinguished
him<lb break="no"/>self for industry or ability in connection
with the<lb/>
public business. Yet you saw this
gentleman, <lb/>
when a question came up in which his
feelings<lb/>
were enlisted, getting up and addressing
the<lb/>
House with a patronizing air, and in that
peculiar<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">dilettanti</hi> style in which he delighted.
He could<lb/>
tell that hon. gentleman it would have
been more<lb/>
to his credit, and those with whom he
apparently<lb/>
sympathized in the remarks he had just
made, if<lb/>
he had endeavoured, instead of bringing
the mat<lb break="no"/>ter publicly before the House, to screen
the con<lb break="no"/>duct of those who mis behaved themselves
on that<lb/>
occasion. When that hon. gentleman stated
that<lb/>
he had been hissed in Temperance Hall, he
men<lb break="no"/>tioned a fact of which he was prouder than
any<lb break="no"/>thing else in his public life. He had
never stood,<lb/>
and he never expected hereafter to stand
in a <lb/>
prouder—a position more in sympathy with
the <lb/>
feelings of the people—than when in
response to<lb/>
to a very small portion of the audienc in
Tem<lb break="no"/>perance Hall, who attempted to interfere
with <lb/>
freedom of speech, he told them their
disgrace<lb break="no"/>ful proceedings would go to the country—that<lb/>
their attempt to stifle discussion would
redound<lb/>
upon themselves, and that the little band
with<lb/>
which he was associated would teach the
contemp<lb break="no"/>tible little mob that disturbed the
deliberations of<lb/>
that meeting that they were not the people
of <lb/>
Nova Scotia. Well they had taught these
wor<lb break="no"/>thies in the city that they could not
stifle public <lb/>
discussion. The sentiments uttered that
night<lb/>
even by one so humble as himself had
reverberat<lb break="no"/>ed in the valleys, and along the hill
sides, and<lb/>
found its echo in the Legislature of this
country.<lb/>
That pledge at least had been "nobly
redeemed."<lb/>
Who were those that hissed him for the
utterance <lb/>
of these sentiments on that occasion ? Not the<lb/>
respectable citizens of Halifax? No, he
scouyed<lb/>
the idea—he knew from personal
communication<lb/>
with a large number of the citizens of
Halifax<lb/>
that they condemned such conduct. Those who<lb/>
hissed him were a few government hirelings—a<lb/>
few <hi rendition="simple:italic">claquers</hi> gathered from the street
corners<lb/>
and bar-rooms—whose hostility he had the
good<lb/>
fortune to have gained—men who would bring<lb/>
down every young man who endeavoured, by
fair<lb/>
exertion, to satisfy a laudable ambition
in this <lb/>
country. He was always willing to have the
op<lb break="no"/>position of the crowd. But it was not for
the <lb/>
hon. member for Halifax to taunt him in
connex<lb break="no"/>ion with the subject of Confederation. If
that<lb/>
hon. gentleman had occupied the same
position<lb/>
he (Mr. M.) assumed he would have been
more <lb/>
justified in the arogance of the tone he
had adopted. <lb/>
Where was that hon gentleman when that
question<lb/>
was admitted to the people of this
country? Did he<lb/>
step to the front like others and d clare
his views<lb/>
—did he take the manly position of his
hon. col<lb break="no"/>
            <cb/>

league (Mr. Tobin)?—and determine if he
must<lb/>
go down on the question, to fall like a
man? No; <lb/>
during every demonstration that had taken
place<lb/>
in Halifax you could not see the hon.
gentleman<lb/>
face on the platform, and if you saw him
at all it<lb/>
was in some obscure corner under the
galleries<lb/>
watching the current of popular sympathy,
in <lb/>
order to take advantage of it. This was
the gentle<lb break="no"/>man that came in at the eleventh hour when
he <lb/>
thought his constituents had been won to
the <lb/>
cause by the labour of others, and to show
his<lb/>
zeal justified the disgraceful conduct of
the rabble<lb/>
at Temperance Hall. He did not envy the
hon.<lb/>
gentleman's position, and the people would
ap<lb break="no"/>preciate it. But he would tell the hon.
member <lb/>
that he was not the man to taunt one,
after skulk<lb break="no"/>ing as he had at the proper time from his
legiti<lb break="no"/>mate duty. He now came in when he imagined
he<lb/>
could do so without personal danger,
reminding<lb/>
them of one of those creatures that follow
in the <lb/>
rear of armies to pick up prey that others
win for<lb/>
them</p>



            <p>He was not at all superized at the style
in which <lb/>
the Provincial Secretary had referred to
him. It<lb/>
was what he expected from the hon.
gentleman.<lb/>
Since he had been in public life, he had
the for<lb break="no"/>tune of receiving these attentions more
frequent<lb break="no"/>ly than others. he had got more knocks than<lb/>
anything else, and which he always liked
if possi<lb break="no"/>ble to return, altho he as becoming
indifferent<lb/>
to them by this time. They did him little
harm<lb/>
and perhaps some good  But he was quite
pre<lb break="no"/>pared for the  emarks of the hon. Prov.
Secy—<lb/>
intended as they were for an unworthy
purpose.<lb/>
He understood the policy of that hon.
gentlemen<lb/>
as well as of others by whom he was
surrounded,<lb/>
His object in this instancewas to injure
him in<lb/>
the estimation of the vast majority of the
citizens<lb/>
with whom he was proud to say he stood on
terms<lb/>
of which he needed never be ashamed. He had<lb/>
never, since be had the honour of a seat
in the<lb/>
House, opened his mouth unfairly hostile
towards<lb/>
the city of Halifax. On the contrary, he
could<lb/>
appeal to gentlemen all around if he had
not, on <lb/>
every occasion, when the interests of
Halifax were<lb/>
not at conflict with the legitimate
interests of<lb/>
these he represented, endeavoured to retain<lb/>
their rights, and promote their wishes. He
had <lb/>
been a member of the Committee on City
Bills,<lb/>
for two years, and hardly say he did his
best<lb/>
to advance the business before it, and
guard the<lb/>
interests of the city. He knew that his
exertons<lb/>
were fully appreciated. There was another
por<lb break="no"/>tion of the remarks of the hon. Provincial
Secre<lb break="no"/>tary, that deserved some observation. He
was <lb/>
astonished at the powers of the face with
which<lb/>
that hon. gentleman would stand up before
the <lb/>
people's representatives, and, knowing as
he<lb/>
must the feelings of the country, state
that a<lb/>
vast majority of the people were not
opposed to <lb/>
Confederation.  He did know whether to
admire<lb/>
or condemn the indifference to public
sentiment<lb/>
which that hon. gentleman exhibited  He
could<lb/>
not imagine anything more dangerous to
public<lb/>
liberty, than to have a man occupying the
posi<lb break="no"/>tion he did, prepared so to outrage the
public<lb/>
sentiment of the country, and use the
influence,


            <pb n="245" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-13_Page_245.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">245</fw>

and power
he possessed to carry out his ob<lb break="no"/>ject in definance of the people. Holding
the senti<lb break="no"/>ments he did, there was great room to
fear, that<lb/>
our rights and liberties were endangered ;
and <lb/>
under such circumstances it was time
gentlemen<lb/>
sitting around these benches, should put
thel<lb/>
house in order. It should be recollected
that the<lb/>
leader of the government had great powers
in his <lb/>
hands—he could control the public patronage—<lb/>
he had command of the public funds. He
might<lb/>
be induced to use all influences to
promote a <lb/>
scheme of which he was so enthusiastic an
advo<lb break="no"/>cate.  It would be well for gentlemen to
consider<lb/>
these things before it was too late. He
did not in<lb break="no"/>tend to follow the hon. Provincial
Secretary after<lb/>
the lengthy reply of the hon. member for
Guys<lb break="no"/>bro, and because a  more suitable
opportunity<lb/>
would offer to answer him. But he must den<lb break="no"/>ounce the assertion made for a purpose,
that any<lb/>
large number of the people favored the
scheme of<lb/>
the Quebec Conference. Such an assertion
from<lb/>
any reliable source might do much harm. He<lb/>
did not, however, think any statements of the<lb/>
hon. member were entitled to much credit.  There<lb/>
were few public men in the country who stood in<lb/>
a more unenviable position as respects thier <choice><sic>unre<lb break="no"/>liabilit</sic><corr>unreliability</corr></choice> than the hon. Provincial Secretary.<lb/>
            </p>


            <p>He thought he was done with the hon. member<lb/>
for Halifax, but he found it was not the
case; that<lb/>
hon. gentleman with his usual
appropriateness of<lb/>
illustration, had referred to the
demonstration<lb/>
given in honour of Shakespeare last
spring, which<lb/>
was as far from the present case, as the
hon.<lb/>
memeber himself was from the moon. It was
true<lb/>
the House did adjourn, but it was more in
com<lb break="no"/>pliment to the occasion, than to any
living indi<lb break="no"/>vidual.  What analogy was there between the<lb/>
two cases—between Shakespeare and the Dele<lb break="no"/>gates?  But he (Mr. M.) might be wrong—per<lb break="no"/>haps he was unable to appreciate the great
acute<lb break="no"/>ness of the hon. member. There might be
some<lb/>
point in the comparison. That the
delegates dealt<lb/>
largely in fiction will not be denied, and
if they<lb/>
put their claim to a demonstration on this
ground<lb/>
he could understand them. When the records<lb/>
were examinined it would be found that the
works<lb/>
of fiction of some of these gentlemen were
numer<lb break="no"/>ous indeed.  If this would entitle them to such<lb/>
an ovation as had been accorded to the great<lb/>
dramatist, he would prefer it would be postponed till <lb/>
they were 300 years dead.</p>


            <p><persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. Miller</persName> concluded by saying that as the<lb/>
hon. Provincial Secretary had stated that the<lb/>
Volunteers were not to take any part in the<lb/>
demonstration of that evening his object was<lb/>
gained and it was unnecessary to move any reso<lb break="no"/>lution on the subject.</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. ATTY. GENERAL</persName> said if he had ever wit<lb break="no"/>nessed a tempest in a teapot, it was
during that <lb/>
afternoon.  He could, however, easily
understant<lb/>
how the gentlemen opposite would wich to
make<lb/>
a demonstration which might have some effec<lb/>
across the water. They had stated that
nine-<lb break="yes"/>
tenths of the people were opposed to
Confederad<lb break="no"/>
         

            <cb/>

tion, and ought now to be satisfied. He doubted,<lb/>
however, the worth of the mere assertions they<lb/>
had made, and the value that would be put upon<lb/>
them in the mother country. It was obvious that<lb/>
if gentlemen had not some covert object in view,<lb/>
the whole subject would have been settled in five <lb/>
minutes.  If anyone had, at the outset, asked the <lb/>
question, whether the volunteers were to take<lb/>
part in the intended demonstration, he would <lb/>
have got an answer immediately. It was useless<lb/>
for gentlemen to try and persuade the House that<lb/>
actually nine-tenths of the people were opposed<lb/>
to Confederation. Only 3000 persons came before <lb/>
the House, stating that they were opposed to<lb/>
Confederation. He knew that a large number of<lb/>
the petitioners were induced to sign the petitions,<lb/>
through false representations that were made to<lb/>
them. Here Mr. Henry went on to refer to the<lb/>
fact that when the delegates were in Canada, the <lb/>
volunteers, on several occasions, took part in the<lb/>
celebration.  He thought that some parties in<lb/>
this country had attempted to mix the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of Union with party considerations ever since<lb/>
the celebrated speech at Truro. It was party in<lb break="no"/>fluences that originated the petitions that were got<lb/>
up on this question.  What he desired, was that the<lb/>
people should have every opportunity of discus<lb break="no"/>sing the question in all its bearings.</p>
            <p>The matter then dropped, and the House ad<lb break="no"/>journed over Good Friday until Saturday, at<lb/>
11 o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>

           

<!-- GL, 2017-04-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p> SATURDAY, April 15. <lb/>
ASSASSINATION OF PRESIDENT LINCOLN. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>The House of Assembly met this morning at<lb/>
11 o'clock, and the Provincial Secretary imme<lb break="no"/>diately moved a resolution to adjourn until<lb/>
Monday next. He said:—I need not say that<lb/>
this House has been deeply shocked by the<lb/>
intelligence which has just been received of<lb/>
the death of President Lincoln.   Both branch<lb break="no"/>es of the Legislature having been on Thursday<lb/>
last informed that His Excellency would come<lb/>
down at 3 o'clock for the purpose of assenting<lb/>
to several Bills which have passed, I felt it my<lb/>
duty, proposing as we do, to adjourn this <lb/>
House, to put myself in communication with<lb/>
His Excellency who entirely concurs in the<lb/>
appropriateness of this House marking its sym<lb break="no"/>pathy with the people of the United States,<lb/>
who have thus lost their Chief Magistrate, and<lb/>
their deep abhorrence of the crime by which<lb/>
he had been removed. The House is aware<lb/>
that when exactly four years ago this day the <lb/>
first intelligence reached this country of the<lb/>
commencement of hostilities in the American<lb/>
Republic, this House placed on record its sen<lb break="no"/>timents by the following resolution:—</p>
            <p>Resolved unanimously that the House of Assembly<lb/>
of Nova Scotia have heard with deep regret of the <lb/>
outbreak of civil war in the United States, that this <lb/>
House, without expressing any opinion upon the <lb/>
points in controversy between the contending parties<lb/>
sincerely lament that tjose who speak their language, <lb/>
and share their civilization should be shedding each<lb/>
other's blood, and offer up their prayers to the Father <lb/>
of the Universe for the speedy restoration of peace."</p>
            <p>This resolution sufficiently marked the feel<lb break="no"/>ings with which this House viewed the begin-<lb break="maybe"/>
ing of hostilities which have so long and so <lb/>
terribly distracted the neighboring republic. <lb/>
It is not to be denied that as that struggle ad<lb break="no"/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>