<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1866-03-07"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-03-07">7 March 1866</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Third Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
          <date when="1866"/>.  
          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="55"/>.
        </bibl>
      

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_053.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_054.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_055.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-10-30">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="DLANG4" when="2017-10-30">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_053">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_053.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_054">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_054.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_055">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_055.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="53" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_053.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">53</fw>
            <p>
     [...] maintain their proficiency, and after making 
     <lb/>
     exertions and going out to vessels entering, 
     <lb/>
     their services might be declined, and their trou<lb break="no"/>ble would be in vain, for though vessels not de<lb break="no"/>siring a pilot were required to display a flag at 
     <lb/>
     five miles distance, yet that signal could not 
     <lb/>
     very well be discerned in case of a storm. His 
     <lb/>
     own judgment had gone a long way with the 
     <lb/>
     non member for Richmond last year, but his 
     <lb/>
     views were changed to a great extent by facts 
     <lb/>
     which had come to his knowledge since. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Donald Fraser, in reply to Mr Miller, 
     <lb/>
     said he had been informed by an old pilot that 
     <lb/>
     there had been no instance known of a vessel 
     <lb/>
     being lost while in charge of a pilot in entering 
     <lb/>
     or leaving the port of Pictou. There was a 
     <lb/>
     great difference between Pictou and other har<lb break="no"/>bours, because at that place the pilots were ob<lb break="no"/>liged to keep up superior and more expensive 
     <lb/>
     kinds of boats. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. PROV. SEC. said that the existing regu<lb break="no"/>lations seemed to place Pictou in a different 
     <lb/>
     postion from other ports. The question, 
     <lb/>
     whether the effect of such legislation was to in<lb break="no"/>terfere with the security of property, was a 
     <lb/>
     very serious one. So hard was the operation 
     <lb/>
     of the present law that many of the pilots had 
     <lb/>
     sold their boats and engaged in piloting vessels 
     <lb/>
     to and from the Strait of Canso, leaving the 
     <lb/>
     duties to be discharged in a manner not so effi<lb break="no"/>cient as the shiping interest required. If these 
     <lb/>
     were the facts, some steps should be taken 
     <lb/>
     either by alteration or repeal of the existing 
     <lb/>
     regulations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Miller denied the accuracy of the state<lb break="no"/>ment that existing legislation placed the port 
     <lb/>
     of Pictou in different circumstances from those 
     <lb/>
     of any other port. If the proposed alteration 
     <lb/>
     were merely to the effect that the pilotage 
     <lb/>
     should be raised, that might be a matter worthy 
     <lb/>
     of consideration.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr D Fraser obtained leave to bring in a 
     <lb/>
     Bill, in accordance with the prayer of the peti<lb break="no"/>tion. 
     <lb/>
     </p>

     <div type="section">           
     <head rendition="simple:centre">PETITIONS.</head>
     
            <p>
     Mr HILL presented a petition from the Post 
     <lb/>
     Master of Hantsport asking for an increase of 
     <lb/>
     salary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr S MCDONNELL presented a petition for 
     <lb/>
     the Post Master of Mabou asking for'an in<lb break="no"/>crease of salary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Also, a petition for the establishment of a 
     <lb/>
     Money Order Office at Mabou, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Also, a petition with 433 signatures on the 
     <lb/>
     subject of Confederation.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
     </div>
            
        <div type="section">           
        <head rendition="simple:centre">CONFEDERATION.</head> 

            <p>
     Mr. Annand wished to ask a question of the 
     <lb/>
     government in connection with the subject be<lb break="no"/>fore the House. He had seen a paragraph in 
     <lb/>
     the organ of the government, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Colonist</hi>, 
     <lb/>
     which he thought required an explanation.— 
     <lb/>
     The paragraph alluded to a certain meeting 
     <lb/>
     recently held at Cornwall, known to be repre<lb break="no"/>sented by John Sandfield Macdonald, a late 
     <lb/>
     Premier of Canada; without further preface, he 
     <lb/>
     would read the following curious statement 
     <lb/>
     from the paper referred to:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               " FROM CANADA.—<hi rendition="simple:italic">Cornwall, Canada March</hi> 
     <lb/>
     2.—At a public demonstration and dinner to 
     <lb/>
     the members of the Government last night, 
     <lb/>
     speeches were made by Galt, Howland,' Mac<lb break="no"/>donald and Cartier. Macdonald asserted that 
     <lb/>
    the Confederation of the Provinces was now 
     <lb/>certain to take place in a few weeks." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
     <cb/>
     
     <!-- DL 20171030 stopped here -->
            <p>
     He would attach very little importance to 
     <lb/>
     this declaration if it did not come from a source 
     <lb/>
     like that of the Attorney General West of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and had not been republished by the 
     <lb/>
     organ of the government of Nova Scotia. It 
     <lb/>
     was a matter of very serious import to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of this "province when they learned rom 
     <lb/>
     such authority that their rights and privileges 
     <lb/>
     were to be swept away without their being con<lb break="no"/>sulted. It was time, he thought, to ask the go<lb break="no"/>vernment whether they had any informa<lb break="no"/>tion on the subject which might give the House 
     <lb/>
     and country to understand what was meant by 
     <lb/>
     the significant remarks of the Canadian states<lb break="no"/>man. He would also like to know whether the 
     <lb/>
     government were prepared to state if Confede<lb break="no"/>ration was to take place without consulting the 
     <lb/>
     House or without being referred to the people 
     <lb/>
     of this country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon PROV SEC'Y said that now he had no 
     <lb/>
     difficulty in believing that there was no prece- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     dent—no ordinary rules that could be expected 
     <lb/>
     to measure the scope of the ingenuity of the 
     <lb/>
     hon gentleman who had just addressed the 
     <lb/>
     House. He thought it rather a curious course 
     <lb/>
     for him to ask for an explanation of speeches 
     <lb/>
     made at a public dinner in another province.— 
     <lb/>
     The hon gentleman must certainly be attempt<lb break="no"/>ing a joke at the expense of the administration 
     <lb/>
     when he propounded such a question, and asked 
     <lb/>
     them to give an explicit answer. He (Dr T) 
     <lb/>
     could certainly say that he had no information 
     <lb/>
     that enabled him to state upon what data Mr 
     <lb/>
     Macdonald made such statements as those re<lb break="no"/>ferred to. He had certainly read these state<lb break="no"/>ments with just as much surprise as had the 
     <lb/>
     hon member himself. As respects the position 
     <lb/>
     of the question of Confederation, it was almost 
     <lb/>
     unnecessary to say much to the House. As 
     <lb/>
     every gentleman was aware, it had not at any 
     <lb/>
     time been brought forward as a Government 
     <lb/>
     measure. Inasmuch as the Government had 
     <lb/>
     obtained the services and co-operation of lead<lb break="no"/>ing gentlemen of the Opposition, they could 
     <lb/>
     not bring forward the subject in a party as<lb break="no"/>pect. Gentlemen who had held responsible 
     <lb/>
     positions in connection with the party opposed 
     <lb/>
     to that now in power were invited to give their 
     <lb/>
     assistance to the Government in relation to this 
     <lb/>
    great question. It was therefore impossible to 
     <lb/>present the question except as one in which 
     <lb/>both members of the Government and gentle<lb break="no"/>men connected with the Opposition took a deep 
     <lb/>interest. In that condition the question had 
     <lb/>been brought down to the House to be consid<lb break="no"/>ered and dealt with in such a manner as it 
     <lb/>should direct. Before the question was brought 
     <lb/>up during the session of 1865, circumstances 
     <lb/>transpired in the neighboring Province which 
     <lb/>gave a new aspect to matters. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The Lieutenant Governor of New Brunswick, 
     <lb/>
     in the exercise of his judgment, dissolved the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature, and the result was that an over<lb break="no"/>whelming number of the gentlemen who were 
     <lb/>
     returned declared themselves hostile to the 
     <lb/>
    proposed scheme of Union arranged at Quebec. 
     <lb/>That having taken place, the House would at 
     <lb/>once see that the Government of this Province 
     <lb/>and the gentlemen interested in the question 
     <lb/>found themselves placed in an entirely altered 
     <lb/>position. He had no hesitation in saying that 
     <lb/>whilst he believed that the scheme of Union as 
     <lb/>devised at Quebec was of vast and vital impor<lb break="no"/>tance to British North America—and to no por<lb break="no"/>tion of it more than to Nova Scotia—yet, under 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    
            <pb n="54" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_054.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND</fw>
            <fw type="num">PROCEEDINGS</fw>
            <p>
     existing circumstances, he considered that the 
     <lb/>
     question was in that condition that it could not 
     <lb/>
     be dealt with practically. It was obvious that 
     <lb/>
     whilst New Brunswick assumed such an atti<lb break="no"/>tude, Nova Scotia, however favorable to Union, 
     <lb/>
     could not stir in the matter. When the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature was called together on the present occa<lb break="no"/>sion, the circumstances that existed last year 
     <lb/>
     still continued, and it would be altogether fu<lb break="no"/>tile for Nova Scotia to move at present. Should 
     <lb/>
     the time come when the question could he tak<lb break="no"/>en up, not as a hypothetical measure, but in a 
     <lb/>
     definite, practical shape, it would be quite time 
     <lb/>
     enough for the Government to declare their 
     <lb/>
     policy. He had never shrunk from expressing 
     <lb/>
    his opinions fully and explicitly whenever this 
     <lb/>great question had come up. He could not un<lb break="no"/>derstand the position of the hon. member for 
     <lb/>East Halifax, who declared himself opposed to 
     <lb/>the scheme of Union, and yet at the same time 
     <lb/>exhibited such a strong anxiety to bring the 
     <lb/>question to the notice of the House. He could 
     <lb/>only hope that the hon. gentleman—and he ar<lb break="no"/>gued from his views as propounded elsewhere 
     <lb/>—had seen the error of his ways, and was now 
     <lb/>anxious to make all the atonement he could. 
     <lb/>He believed, indeed, that that hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>had else here gone so far as to charge the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment with a dereliction of duty, because 
     <lb/>they had not pressed the question on the consi<lb break="no"/>deration of the Legislature. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Mr. S. CAMPBELL said that the hon. Provin<lb break="no"/>cial Secretary had not given that answer to the 
     <lb/>
    questions put to him that was expected of him. 
     <lb/>that hon. gentleman had exercised some in<lb break="no"/>genuity in asserting that the statement in ques<lb break="no"/>tion was an after-dinner speech, and that 
     <lb/>therefore there was no reliance to be placed 
     <lb/>upon it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     Hon. PROVINCIAL SECRETARY said that he 
     <lb/>
     would be very sorry to charge the members of 
     <lb/>
     any Administration with making statements 
     <lb/>
     in which no reliance could be placed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. S. CAMPBELL went on to say that the 
     <lb/>
     Provincial Secretary had certainly said that it 
     <lb/>
     was an after-dinner speech; but did not every<lb break="no"/>body know that the British Colonist, the organ 
     <lb/>
     of the Government, had republished the state<lb break="no"/>ment. But not only did the Canadian states<lb break="no"/>man in question make the speech, but there 
     <lb/>
     was a number of other prominent public men 
     <lb/>
     of Canada present who apparently endorsed 
     <lb/>
     the statement. The old adage said, In vino 
     <lb/>
     veritas; and we might therefore fairly assume 
     <lb/>
     that the gentleman who spoke under such in<lb break="no"/>fluences spoke the truth. On the other hand, 
     <lb/>
     it might be considered a legitimate argument 
     <lb/>
     against union with Canada if we were told that 
     <lb/>
     its public men were persons of such a charac<lb break="no"/>ter that no reliance could be placed on their 
     <lb/>
     statements. He could not understand the ar<lb break="no"/>gument of the Provincial Secretary in respect 
     <lb/>
     to New Brunswick. What had that Provmce 
     <lb/>
     to do with Nova Scotia? We were able to at<lb break="no"/>tend to our own affairs, independent of the ac<lb break="no"/>tion of any other Colony. He would not dwell 
     <lb/>
     further on the subject at present, except to say 
     <lb/>
     that the Provincial Secretary had not given an 
     <lb/>
     answer to the question put to him by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for East Halifax, namely—Whether it 
     <lb/>
     was the intention of the Government to force 
     <lb/>
     the measure upon the House and country, with<lb break="no"/>out an appeal to the people? Until that ques<lb break="no"/>tion was answered, the House must believe 
     <lb/>
     that there was something in the significant 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     
    statement made by the Hon. John A. Macdon 
     <lb/>ald . 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. PROV. SECRETARY said that he was 
     <lb/>
     glad that the hon. member for Guysboro had 
     <lb/>
     called his attention to a question which he had 
     <lb/>
     forgotten to answer. He would without hesi<lb break="no"/>tation say that the Government would not be 
     <lb/>
     a party to any action outside of the Legislature 
     <lb/>
     that would interfere with the constitution of 
     <lb/>
     the country . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. ANNAND said that the Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary had sat down without answering the 
     <lb/>
     question put to him—whether any attempt 
     <lb/>
     would be made to obtain Confederation without 
     <lb/>
     an appeal to the people. On that important 
     <lb/>
     point the hon. gentleman had been entirely 
     <lb/>
     silent, and the House and country would un<lb break="no"/>doubtedly understand his reasons. The hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman had said that the question of Union 
     <lb/>
     was an open one, and the enquiry naturally 
     <lb/>
     suggested itself, were the members of the Ad<lb break="no"/>ministration united on the measure or not. 
     <lb/>
     Looking at some of the gentlemen whose 
     <lb/>
     opinions he (Mr. A.) knew pretty well, he be<lb break="no"/>lieved that they were not unanimous. 0n the 
     <lb/>
     other hand, looking at the records to be found 
     <lb/>
     in the Assembly, he would be inclined to sav 
     <lb/>
     that they were unanimous. He would now 
     <lb/>
     ask the Provincial Secretary to explain the 
     <lb/>
     fact, that he had not carried out the pledge he 
     <lb/>
     had made to his colleagues at Quebec—that he 
     <lb/>
     would submit this question to the House and 
     <lb/>
     country. The spirited gentleman, who was re<lb break="no"/>cently Premier of New Brunswick, put the 
     <lb/>
     question to the people of that Province, and 
     <lb/>
     redeemed his pledge. The question had been 
     <lb/>
     submitted for consideration in P. E. Island, and 
     <lb/>
     in Newfoundland.—The Gov. of the latter Pro<lb break="no"/>vince had shown he was bound to submit the 
     <lb/>
     question irrespective of his advisers. How was 
     <lb/>
     it that the Government of Nova Scotia occupied 
     <lb/>
     a position so very different? He thought that 
     <lb/>
     the Provincial Secretary was shirking the 
     <lb/>
     question when he should deal with it manfully 
     <lb/>
     —be prepared to stand or fall upon it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon ATTORNEY GENERAL replied that when 
     <lb/>
     he had read the statement in question, he con<lb break="no"/>sidered that the government of this country 
     <lb/>
     had very little responsibility in connection 
     <lb/>
     with Confederation. In view, however, of all 
     <lb/>
     that the hon. member for East Halifax had ex<lb break="no"/>pressed elsewhere in respect to Hon. J. A. 
     <lb/>
    Macdonald, it was very remarkable that he 
     <lb/>should now be prepared to attach the slightest 
     <lb/>credence to anything that hon. gentleman had 
     <lb/>said . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     He (Mr. H.) could certainly say that he was 
     <lb/>
     not informed whether the expressions referred 
     <lb/>
     to were actually made, or if made, what foun<lb break="no"/>dation they had. He had not the slightest idea 
     <lb/>
     what the object was in making these state<lb break="no"/>ments which appeared to startle some gentle<lb break="no"/>men so exceedingly. It might be supposed 
     <lb/>
     with much reason that the Attorney General 
     <lb/>
     West had heard a good deal about reported 
     <lb/>
     changes of public sentiment in New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, and believed that the Provinces were 
     <lb/>
     nearer to Confederation than they had been 
     <lb/>
     for the past year. Mr. Macdonald might think 
     <lb/>
     that the Legislature of Nova Scotia, when it 
     <lb/>
     found that the neighboring Province was ready 
     <lb/>
     to accept union, would consider whether it 
     <lb/>
     should not take up the question, and deal with 
     <lb/>
     it practically. He (Mr. H.) was, however, en<lb break="no"/>tirely like a man groping in the dark when he 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="55" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-07_Page_055.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF</fw>
            <fw type="num">ASSEMBLY</fw>
            <p>
     attempted any explanations for statements of 
     <lb/>
     which he knew really nothing whatever per<lb break="no"/>sonally. It was difficult to understand how 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Guysboro' could show the 
     <lb/>
     House that this Province might stir in the mat<lb break="no"/>ter of union independent of the action of New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick. A glance at the map, and the 
     <lb/>
     respective geographical positions of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces of British North America , would be a 
     <lb/>
     sufficient answer to any reasonable man. If 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick erected a barrier between 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia and Canada, we had to wait until 
     <lb/>
     she decided to take it down. It was somewhat 
     <lb/>
     amusing to hear the member for East Halifax 
     <lb/>
     complain that the delegates had not carried out 
     <lb/>
     the pledges made at Quebec. If any pledges 
     <lb/>
     had been violated the hon. member surely was 
     <lb/>
     not the proper party to complain. That hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman's policy should bc to say nothing as 
     <lb/>
     long as he saw the Government were not mov<lb break="no"/>ing in respect to a measure to which he pro<lb break="no"/>fessed so much hostility. No doubt the gentle<lb break="no"/>men to whom such pledges were stated to have 
     <lb/>
     been made perfectly understood the position of 
     <lb/>
     this Province—that as long as New Brunswick 
     <lb/>
     opposed the scheme, it was impracticable. The 
     <lb/>
     question was not a Government one. and with 
     <lb/>
     what fairness then were they asked to decide 
     <lb/>
     upon a policy in the formation of which other 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen were entitled to a voice? The ques<lb break="no"/>tion of union was one concerning the whole 
     <lb/>
     people of Nova Scotia, and could not be treated 
     <lb/>
     in a party aspect—Political parties were divid<lb break="no"/>ed on the subject; members of the government 
     <lb/>
     were sustained by influential gentlemen of the 
     <lb/>
     opposition; and it was therefore impossible to 
     <lb/>
     treat it except as an open question. It was 
     <lb/>
     quite time to say whether the question should 
     <lb/>
     be submitted to the people or not. when it 
     <lb/>
     could come up in a practical shape. That was 
     <lb/>
     an important constitutional question that 
     <lb/>
     should be decided within the walls of the legis<lb break="no"/>lature, and the government would be going be<lb break="no"/>yond their functions if they interferred with its 
     <lb/>
     decision. The government had no policy on 
     <lb/>
     the subject, and could not come to any decision 
     <lb/>
     upon it until the necessity for action arose. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. McLELAN said that no doubt the Provin<lb break="no"/>cial Secretary and the Attorney General had 
     <lb/>
     suffcient reason for surprise that the hon mem<lb break="no"/>ber for East Halifax should base an enquiry 
     <lb/>
     upon anything that Canadian statesmen might 
     <lb/>
     say. Perhaps these two gentlemen had had an 
     <lb/>
     opportunity of understanding the character and 
     <lb/>
     habits of some of the public men of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     and were perfectly well aware what faith was 
     <lb/>
     to be put in their after-dinner speeches. But 
     <lb/>
     persons who had not this intimate acquaintance 
     <lb/>
     with the peculiarities of Canadian gentlemen, 
     <lb/>
     naturally felt a great deal of astonishment on 
     <lb/>
     reading such announcements as that in ques<lb break="no"/>tion. When such statements were published in 
     <lb/>
     an organ of the men in power it was high time 
     <lb/>
     for those who valued the rights and liberties of 
     <lb/>
     the people to make a move; and he was there<lb break="no"/>fore glad that the hon member for East Hali<lb break="no"/>fax had made the enquiry he had. No doubt it 
     <lb/>
     would be satisfactory to learn that the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the government were ignorant of any 
     <lb/>
     such arrangement as that intimated by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     John A. Macdonald. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                    PETITIONS. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr C J CAMPBELL presented the following 
     <lb/>
     petitions: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     One from Bedque, asking for a change in a 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     mail route from Plaister Cove to that town. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     One from J S McNeil, of Grand Narrows, 
     <lb/>
     asking for an increase of salary as ferryman at 
     <lb/>
     that place. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     One from a number of inhabitants of Bede- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     que, asking for a special grant for a new lineof 
     <lb/>
     road from Bedeque River to that town. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     One from D Morrison and other inhabitants 
     <lb/>
     of St. Ann's, asking for a new line of road. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     One from M McLean, ferryman, asking for 
     <lb/>
     an increase of salary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     One asking for a grantof money for a road to 
     <lb/>
     Gillis's Point . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     One from 76 inhabitants of Cape North, com<lb break="no"/>plaining of an act passed by the House in 1852 
     <lb/>
     in respect to church property. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     One from inhabitants of Washabuck, for aid 
     <lb/>
     towards a road. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. S. MACDONNELL presented two petitions 
     <lb/>
     (similar to that presented by Mr Campbell from 
     <lb/>
     Cape North) from River Dennis and from 
     <lb/>
     Whycocomagh.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (A bill on the subject of these petitions has 
     <lb/>
     been introduced.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. SHANNON presented a petition,and 
     <lb/>
     introduced a bill, in reference to the Union and 
     <lb/>
     Axe Fire Companies of Halifax; also, the peti<lb break="no"/>tion of J. S. Thompson Superintendent of Mo<lb break="no"/>ney Order Office, Halifax, for an increase of sa<lb break="no"/>lary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Mr. S. MACDONNELL introduced an act to 
     <lb/>
     incorporate the Strait of Canso Marine Railway 
     <lb/>
     Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. PRYOR introduced a bill to incorporate 
     <lb/>
     the Merigomish Coal Mining Company; also 
     <lb/>
     presented a petition from J . Kirby and ninety 
     <lb/>
     others, praying for the substitution of assess<lb break="no"/>ment instead of voluntary subscription for the 
     <lb/>
     support of schools.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr.McKAY presented a petition from 300 
     <lb/>
     persons of West Pictou, asking that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment depute an engineer to lay on a certain 
     <lb/>
     line of road. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. LONGLEY presented a petition from the 
     <lb/>
     inhabitants of Annapolis, living in the vicinity 
     <lb/>
     of Paradise, asking the Legislature to empower 
     <lb/>
     the sessions to lay off a certain space of land 
     <lb/>
     for the purpose of a public landing. He urged 
     <lb/>
     the claims of the petitions to favorable consi<lb break="no"/>deration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. BALCAM presented a petition from Ecum 
     <lb/>
     Secum River, between Guysboro' and East 
     <lb/>
     Halifax,in reference to a line of road. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                             HOSPITAL FOR INSANE. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. PROV. SECY. laid on the table the an<lb break="no"/>nual report of the Medical Superintendent of 
     <lb/>
     the Hospital for the Insane. He stated that 
     <lb/>
     the number of admissions has been forty-six, or 
     <lb/>
     the same as in the previous year. The applica<lb break="no"/>tions have been far beyond the power to re<lb break="no"/>ceive. Fifty were discharged. of whom no less 
     <lb/>
     than fifty-eight were restored. The centre 
     <lb/>
     building and north wing are under contract, 
     <lb/>
     and the work is being vigorously forwarded. 
     <lb/>
     Accomodation will be given for ninety addi<lb break="no"/>tional patients. The necessity for enlargement 
     <lb/>
     was universally acknowledged. A new coal 
     <lb/>
     shed (much required) has been built near the 
     <lb/>
     boiler house; the grounds have been improved, 
     <lb/>
     and additional land brought under cultivation. 
     <lb/>
     An important drain has been constructed into 
     <lb/>
     the harbor, and a new road made. The con<lb break="no"/>tract price of beef, flour, &amp;c., has been higher 
     <lb/>
    than usual, causing an advance in the cost of 
     <lb/>maintenance; the present average for provi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>
         </div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>