<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1866-05-01"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-05-01">1 May 1866</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA">
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          
          
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Second Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1866"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="312"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_309.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_310.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_311.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_312.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-06-05">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_309">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_309.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_310">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_310.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_311">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_311.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_312">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_312.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="309" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_309.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="running">[OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw> <fw type="num">309</fw> 
  

<!-- GL, 2018-06-05, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
   
            <!--<p>
     sequently withdrew the bill on being informed 
     <lb/>
     by Mr. Tobin that a large number of merchants 
     <lb/>
     were opposed to it, and that it would provoke 
     <lb/>
     discussion. It was understood that no new 
     <lb/>
     bills would be introduced that would cause de<lb break="no"/>bate.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon Mr SHANNON also introduced a bil 
     <lb/>
     concerning the erection of buildings in the city 
     <lb/>
     of Halifax ; it was rendered necessary for the 
     <lb/>
     preservation of the public health.    
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The House then went into committee and 
     <lb/>
     passed a number of bills, viz. : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To amend the act incorporating the Evangeli<lb break="no"/>cal Lutheran Church at Lunenburg.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To incorporate the Salt Works Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To extend the time for prepayment of a loan 
     <lb/>
     to Pictou. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To alter and amend chap. relating to Mines 
     <lb/>
     and Minerals. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To amend chap. 94, Deep Sea Fisheries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To regulate Poors' Asylum in Halifax. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The bill relative to Middle River Congrega<lb break="no"/>tion was not pressed, at the sugestion of Mr. C. 
     <lb/>
     J. Campbell and the Financial Secretary, who 
     <lb/>
     thought it advisable to allow such questions to 
     <lb/>
     be settled amicably outside of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The committee rose, and the House adjourn<lb break="no"/>ed.    
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <head rendition="simple:right">
     TUESDAY, May 1. 
            </head>

<p>
     The House met at 3 o'clock. </p>  
 

   
            <p>
     Mr MILLER said he wished to avail himself of 
     <lb/>
     this opportunity of replying to some of the slan<lb break="no"/>ders and misrepresentations which had appeared 
     <lb/>in reference to himself in a portion of the public 
     <lb/>press. A fortnight ago, or thereabouts, an ex<lb break="no"/>citing debate had taken place in which the hon 
     <lb/>member for East Halifax had occupied a po ition 
     <lb/>in which no member of that House ever stood 
     <lb/>before, presenting a spectacle which must con<lb break="no"/>vince the country that if there was a man whose  
     <lb/>utterances were entitled to no respect, it was that 
     <lb/>gentleman.  On that occasion Mr Annand had 
     <lb/>brought two charges against his (Mr M's) veraci<lb break="no"/>ty, which had been conclusively met and exposed 
     <lb/>on the instant; — first as to the conversation with 
     <lb/>hon Geo Brown, in reference to which he (Mr A) 
     <lb/>had said that the report of the conversation as de<lb break="no"/>tailed by him (Mr M) was incorrect;—the second 
     <lb/>in reference to the Inverness petitions Yet, on 
     <lb/>the following day, the hon member had the hardi<lb break="no"/>hood to announce in the Chronicle that he had 
     <lb/>succeeded in bringing home a charge against him. 
     <lb/>If the individual who inspired that journal made 
     <lb/>this charge publicly, in his proper person, it 
     <lb/>would be harmless as the idle words, because 
     <lb/>to enable one man to injure another by fixing any 
     <lb/>charge on him, it was requisite the accusation 
     <lb/>should proceed from an individual who possessed 
     <lb/>some character—otherwise  the attempt merely ex<lb break="no"/>hibited the baseness of the source from which the 
     <lb/>charge proceeded, and would recoil on him who 
     <lb/>made it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     At the instance of Mr S. Campbell the galleries 
     <lb/>
     were cleared, but subsequently re-opened. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr Miller continued:—He did not feel it neces<lb break="no"/>sary to make these observations  merely because 
     <lb/>
     Mr Annand, in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chronicle</hi>, had slandered him, 
     <lb/>
     but because there were many persons who were 
     <lb/>
     not sufficiently intelligent to discriminate between 
     <lb/>
           

            <cb/>
         

     the statements of that journal, which were merely 
     <lb/>
     the effusions of the member for East Halifax, and 
     <lb/>
    the public opinion which it pretended, however 
     <lb/>falsely, to reflect. He asked who was there less 
     <lb/>able than the member for East Halifax to make 
     <lb/>improper charges, or who should be more back<lb break="no"/>ward in maligning and slandering another? That 
     <lb/>member's name recently appeared appended to an 
     <lb/>address to Her Majesty the Queen, the 
     <lb/>first paragraph of which contained an 
     <lb/>expression of the loyalty of those who 
     <lb/>signed it, and yet one had only to turn back his 
     <lb/>recollection a short time to recall the period when 
     <lb/>the hon member expressed the wish that the day 
     <lb/>would come when "the stars and stripes would 
     <lb/>wave over citadel hill!" Was the man who 
     <lb/>could utter such a traitorous sentiment as that in a 
     <lb/>position to makes charge against another ?— 
     <lb/>Within a few weeks the same member had been 
     <lb/>guilty of a similar crime, and had been heard 
     <lb/>expressing the wish in the public streets "that 
     <lb/>50,000 Fenians would land in Canada." And 
     <lb/>nevertheless this was the man who applied the 
     <lb/>term " traitor" to members who were acting in 
     <lb/>accordance with the declared wishes and policy 
     <lb/>of the Queen's Government and the best inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the country. The humiliating apology 
     <lb/>made by the hon member, suffused with shame 
     <lb/>as he stood when charged with these expressions, 
     <lb/>was ample proof of the correctness of the assert<lb break="no"/>ions in reference to the position which he occu<lb break="no"/>pied. The man who thus stood convicted of 
     <lb/>treason by his own admission was the man who 
     <lb/>used the press under his control to disseminate 
     <lb/>falsehoods,  scatter seditious sentiments, broad<lb break="no"/>cast over the country, and create the worst feel<lb break="no"/>ings for the worst purposes. Mr. Annand had 
     <lb/>brought forward letters from his friends to ex<lb break="no"/>culpate himself from this last charge of treason<lb break="no"/>able conduct, but it would be recollected that 
     <lb/>those letters conclusively established his guilt.— 
     <lb/>The hon member had suppressed them in the 
     <lb/>publication of his speech, and had declined to 
     <lb/>lay them on the table. But what more ? In his 
     <lb/>speech on the Resolution for Union that gentle<lb break="no"/>man had asserted that he had been offered   "money 
     <lb/>place and preferment " if he would support Con<lb break="no"/>federation. These words were taken down by a 
     <lb/>number of gentlemen, "and were telegraphed to 
     <lb/>Mr Brown who pronounced the assertion a " <choice><sic>vil<lb break="no"/>lianous</sic><corr>villainous</corr></choice> falsehood." At the conclusion of that 
     <lb/>speech he (Mr M) rose and stated a report of that 
     <lb/>conversation given to him by Mr Annand at the 
     <lb/>time, and the reply then made wad that he had 
     <lb/>not related correctly what was reported as having 
     <lb/>passed, while on the following day the member 
     <lb/>for East Halifax admitted that his (Mr M's) state<lb break="no"/>ment was substantially correct. These facts ap<lb break="no"/>peared in the official reports. That hon member 
     <lb/>had done more—he denied having used the 
     <lb/>word money in connection with Mr Brown's 
     <lb/>name. A dozen gentlemen instantly con 
     <lb/>tradicted him from their notes, and the of<lb break="no"/>ficial report shewed that his denial was in<lb break="no"/>correct. What was the veracity of such a 
     <lb/>man worth? If he, Mr. Miller, had been com<lb break="no"/>pelled to admit himself guilty of traitorous 
     <lb/>
   

            <pb n="310" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_310.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">310</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
        

     language, and was convicted of untruthful 
     <lb/>
     statements on the floors of Parliament, and 
     <lb/>
     had to confess that a gentleman whom he had 
     <lb/>
     flatly contradicted had substantially told 
     <lb/>
     the truth, and at the same time to withdraw 
     <lb/>
     a slander against another man there would 
     <lb/>
     have been good foundation for impugning 
     <lb/>
     his veracity; that was not his case. The 
     <lb/>
     member for East Halifax feeling the hu<lb break="no"/>miliation of his position saw the necessity of 
     <lb/>
     drawing attention from himself to others, 
     <lb/>
     and did what no honorable man under the 
     <lb/>
     same circumstances would do—he meanly 
     <lb/>
     revealed the secrets of confidential inter<lb break="no"/>course, which was in keeping with his 
     <lb/>
     conduct from beginning to end, and had ex<lb break="no"/>cited the disgust even of his friends. It 
     <lb/>
     was such conduct that had induced one 
     <lb/>
     member after another in the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, to scout the hon. member's leader<lb break="no"/>ship as they were obliged to do out of con<lb break="no"/>sideration for their own character and po<lb break="no"/>sition. Private conversations had thus been 
     <lb/>
     revealed by Mr. Annand whenever they 
     <lb/>
     suited him, without any justification on his 
     <lb/>
     part. No men can, for any time, act po<lb break="no"/>litically together without confidential com<lb break="no"/>munications which subsequent differences 
     <lb/>
     justified neither in revealing. He Mr. M. had 
     <lb/>
     been acting with the anti-Confederate party 
     <lb/>
     against the Quebec scheme, but only against 
     <lb/>
     that scheme, and had then much confi<lb break="no"/>dential intercourse with Mr. Annand and  
     <lb/>others, but the first man had yet to hear 
     <lb/>any of it disclosed. A different course was 
     <lb/>now necessary in self-defence. Fortunate<lb break="no"/>ly he had not placed himself in Mr. An<lb break="no"/>nand's power, and could defy his malice. 
     <lb/>The hon. gentleman had produced a paper 
     <lb/>to shew that a statement made by him in 
     <lb/>reference to the Inverness petitions was 
     <lb/>incorrect, and had asserted that he, Mr 
     <lb/>Miller, had denied sending such petitions 
     <lb/>into the country. The House knew he had 
     <lb/>done nothing of the sort, but boldly avowed 
     <lb/>that up to early in the present Session every 
     <lb/>exertion, he could use, and every means 
     <lb/>within his power were put forward to defeat 
     <lb/>Confederation on the Quebec basis. He 
     <lb/>wished to get that scheme before the peo<lb break="no"/>ple, because he knew it would be defeated. 
     <lb/>If this paper proved anything it only was 
     <lb/>that those petitions were sent into Inverness 
     <lb/>six days after instead of a few days before 
     <lb/>the meeting of the Legislature, but that pa<lb break="no"/>per was written before the Legislature met ; 
     <lb/>when it had been handed to the printer he 
     <lb/>could not say. Mr. Annand had subse<lb break="no"/>quently to admit the charge in reference to 
     <lb/>the  two petitions, in connection with which 
     <lb/>the dispute arose, was unfounded,he himself 
     <lb/>
        

            <cb/>
         

     having sent those petitions to Inverness, 
     <lb/>
     and, as a further proof, they were returned 
     <lb/>
     to him when signed. Even without this 
     <lb/>
     admission, any charge from such a quarter 
     <lb/>
     would require some further evidence than 
     <lb/>
     the assertions of a man whose statements 
     <lb/>
     had been publicly branded as villianous 
     <lb/>
     falsehoods. The discrepancy was of little 
     <lb/>
     consequence, whatever it was. Mr. An<lb break="no"/>nand had said, in one of his speeches, that 
     <lb/>
     if it were not that he, Mr. M., had been so 
     <lb/>
     careful of the expenditure of a few shillings, 
     <lb/>
     the petition for Inverness would have been 
     <lb/>
     sent by him. Did not this shew that the 
     <lb/>
     subject was talked over before the franking 
     <lb/>
     privilege was possessed by members? But 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Annand knowing what he did should 
     <lb/>
     be the last to charge penuriousness on him. 
     <lb/>
     No member was less open to such a charge. 
     <lb/>
     In reference to it he, Mr. M., would state a 
     <lb/>
     few undeniable facts ; three years ago when 
     <lb/>
     he had gone to run his election, it had been 
     <lb/>
     stated that he had received a large sum of 
     <lb/>
     money from the Liberal party to secure the 
     <lb/>
     County of Richmond. He had to meet this 
     <lb/>
     slander everywhere during his canvass, but 
     <lb/>
     the truth was that every sixpence of his ex<lb break="no"/>penditure on that occasion had been borne 
     <lb/>
     by himself, and that contest was fairly 
     <lb/>
     gained without the slightest understanding 
     <lb/>
     existing anywhere with reference to his 
     <lb/>
     subsequent action. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If any one here or elsewhere could contra<lb break="no"/>dict him let it be done. He could further 
     <lb/>
     say that his opposition to the Quebec scheme 
     <lb/>
     had cost more than any five of the richest 
     <lb/>
     merchants of Halifax who had the credit of 
     <lb/>
     contributing so largely in support of the 
     <lb/>
     anti-union cause. He, Mr. M., had gone 
     <lb/>
     into the country during the busy seasons 
     <lb/>
     for weeks to canvass and hold public meet<lb break="no"/>ings at a heavy personal expenditure, every 
     <lb/>
     cent of which came out of his own pocket, 
     <lb/>
     although there was a fund from which his 
     <lb/>
     expenses might be paid but which he al<lb break="no"/>ways declined to touch. This contrasted 
     <lb/>
     strongly with the conduct of a member who 
     <lb/>
     would not go on a flying visit to one of the 
     <lb/>
     western counties for two or three days 
     <lb/>
     without having his expenses paid, but who 
     <lb/>
     now made this charge of penuriousness 
     <lb/>
     against one who he knew had acted with a 
     <lb/>
     disinterestedness ill-becoming his means. 
     <lb/>
     In going to Lunenburg he left his business 
     <lb/>
     at much loss and incurred much hardship 
     <lb/>
     and inconvenience and still contributed to 
     <lb/>
     the election fund sufficient to meet his own 
     <lb/>
     expenses, refusing to have anything to do 
     <lb/>
     with the bag which was carried by the 
     <lb/>
     Editor of the Citizen who had since given 
     <lb/>
     no account of the contents although called 
     <lb/>
         

            <pb n="311" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_311.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">311</fw>
        

     upon so to do. Mr. McDonald put nothing 
     <lb/>
     into the fund whatever he may have taken 
     <lb/>
     out, yet he was one of the men to impute 
     <lb/>
     corruption to others. The member for East 
     <lb/>
     Halifax, a few days ago, had taken up 
     <lb/>
     much of the time of the House in defining 
     <lb/>
     his position, but it could be defined in half 
     <lb/>
     a dozen words : his position was that of the 
     <lb/>
     fag of another man. It was notorious that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Annand had no idea or will of his own 
     <lb/>
     but had drawn all his inspiration during 
     <lb/>
     the twenty odd years he had been in public 
     <lb/>
     life from a well known source. He was 
     <lb/>
     simply a puppet in the hands of 
     <lb/>
     another. When the House met that 
     <lb/>
     gentleman's object was to become the 
     <lb/>
     leader of the Anti-Confederate party; 
     <lb/>
     and it was generally supposed that 
     <lb/>
     when in England he had represented 
     <lb/>
     himself in that character to Mr. Cardwell, 
     <lb/>
     who must have conceived a very poor 
     <lb/>
     opinion of that party from that circumstance. 
     <lb/>
     He, Mr. M., had not of course attended the 
     <lb/>
     caucus of the Liberal party at the opening 
     <lb/>
     of the Session, nor had he attended any 
     <lb/>
     caucus, but he was reliably informed that at 
     <lb/>
     that meeting the member for East Halifax 
     <lb/>
     had been left in a minority of one, himself 
     <lb/>
     voting, on the proposition to supplant Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Archibald by Mr. Annand as leader—a mi<lb break="no"/>nority, it would be admitted, neither re<lb break="no"/>spectable in point of numbers nor other<lb break="no"/>wise. From that day the hon. member had 
     <lb/>
     commenced a most tortuous course in rela<lb break="no"/>tion to Confederation, which clearly proved 
     <lb/>
     that personal position was his sole aim. 
     <lb/>
     He had told him, Mr. Miller, that he was 
     <lb/>
     willing to give the whole thing up and that 
     <lb/>
     he intended to visit Fredericton and com<lb break="no"/>municate with Mr. Smith of New Brunswick 
     <lb/>
     on a scheme of Union to be submitted to the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature. That fact was notorious to 
     <lb/>
     many in the city, and it dare not be denied. 
     <lb/>
     For a whole week his departure for that 
     <lb/>
     Province was expected,—he did not go for 
     <lb/>
     reasons unnecessary to mention,but from the 
     <lb/>
     day when his leadership had been repudi<lb break="no"/>ated he had been ready to adopt any com<lb break="no"/>promise, and had spoken to him to that ef<lb break="no"/>fect. This was the action of the gentleman 
     <lb/>
     who had yet to hear the first argument 
     <lb/>
     in favor of Confederation. Early in March 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Annand accosted him, Mr. Miller, at 
     <lb/>
     the door of the Province Building, and sig<lb break="no"/>nified his intention of coming down to the 
     <lb/>
     House to define his position, espousing 
     <lb/>
     Confederation; and proposing a resolution 
     <lb/>
      by which the details of the scheme would 
     <lb/>
     be left, as was then known to be the gene<lb break="no"/>ral wish of the friends of union, to the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Government. In the conversation 
     <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
        

     Mr. Annand added, " if you Eastern men 
     <lb/>
     stick out, you will get into the same 
     <lb/>
     difficulty that your people are in in 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick." Implying a threat as 
     <lb/>
     he, Mr. Miller, believed, that the charges of 
     <lb/>
     disloyalty and sympathy with Fenianism, which 
     <lb/>
     had been made by an injudicious portion of the 
     <lb/>
     Confederate press, of that province against certain 
     <lb/>
     members of the Roman Catholic body who op<lb break="no"/>posed Union, would be brought against gentle<lb break="no"/>men representing the Eastern counties. These 
     <lb/>
     he suspected to be the tactics about to be resort<lb break="no"/>ed to, and, recollecting the past, he justly feared 
     <lb/>
     them. Mr. Annand had at that time expressed 
     <lb/>
     a fervent wish that "Mr. Howe would come 
     <lb/>
     home." Whether that gentleman's arrival had 
     <lb/>
     anything to do with the change in the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber's views and actions he would not pretend to 
     <lb/>
     say. He would admit that the tortuous cause 
     <lb/>
     pursued by the hon. member had some influ<lb break="no"/>ence on his (Mr. Miller's) action, but his mind 
     <lb/>
     was chiefly influenced by higher considerations. 
     <lb/>
     About the same time the last hope of the re<lb break="no"/>newal of the Reciprocity Treaty, by legislation 
     <lb/>
     or otherwise had fled, the Fishery difficulty 
     <lb/>
     was on our hands, Fenianism had assumed an 
     <lb/>
     alarming attitude, and the necessity for action 
     <lb/>
     became imminent. It was under this necessi<lb break="no"/>ty that he reluctantly yielded his opinion in re<lb break="no"/>ference to an appeal to the people—the only point 
     <lb/>
     on which his opponents could charge him with 
     <lb/>
     inconsistency, and which was justified by the 
     <lb/>
     exigencies of the moment. After the Lunen<lb break="no"/>burg election, in conversation, he had told Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Annand that he could not persevere in oppos<lb break="no"/>ing all union, and that the time had come for 
     <lb/>effecting some compromise by which the ob<lb break="no"/>jectionable features of the Quebec scheme could 
     <lb/>be got rid of. Mr. Annand agreed with him, 
     <lb/>and the result of that conversation was the ar<lb break="no"/>ticle of the 24th January, which appeared in the 
     <lb/>Morning Chronicle, suggesting a new Convention 
     <lb/>to promote Union. Mr. A. afterwards com<lb break="no"/>municated with Mr. Smith, and represented that 
     <lb/>gentleman as desirous of a common platform 
     <lb/>for compromise, as that article proposed. The 
     <lb/>views therein stated were publicly to be taken 
     <lb/>as the honest expressions of the hon. member, 
     <lb/>but in conversation with others Mr. Annand 
     <lb/>avowed that he was not sincere, and merely 
     <lb/>desired to get the delegates into a snare by 
     <lb/>inducing them to abandon the Quebec scheme. 
     <lb/>He thus played with the friends of union on 
     <lb/>fair terms and the opponents of all union. Ho 
     <lb/>had done more than that—he had frequently 
     <lb/>when urged by him (Mr. M,), manfully to 
     <lb/>adopt some scheme and deal fairly with the 
     <lb/>question, replied that such a course would not 
     <lb/>best subserve their own interests. But by 
     <lb/>working on the prejudices of the people, and 
     <lb/>exciting them against a union of the Provinces 
     <lb/>he and his friends would have the best chances 
     <lb/>of getting to Ottawa in case Confederation was 
     <lb/>carried, as he believed it must be, and if it were 
     <lb/>not: carried by the Government the Opposition 
     <lb/>would have the honor of carrying it when they 
     <lb/>came into power. Could he (Mr. M.), after 
     <lb/>
        


    
            <pb n="312" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-05-01_Page_312.jpg"/>
     <fw type="num">312</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>

     such dishonesty and tergiversation of the mem<lb break="no"/>ber for East Halifax be blamed for abandoning 
     <lb/>
     at the right moment an associate so dishonor<lb break="no"/>able whose every act was a deception, and 
     <lb/>
     whose only object was personal gain. He 
     <lb/>
     was compelled to make these revelations in self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     defence. He asked the house and the people to 
     <lb/>
     couple his statements with the charges of which 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Annaud stood publicly convicted, should he 
     <lb/>
     venture to deny them. A man whose utterances 
     <lb/>
     had been stamped as "villianous falsehoods" 
     <lb/>
     in one case was not worthy of much credit in 
     <lb/>
     another. He (Mr. M.) was not surprised that the 
     <lb/>
     anti-Confederate party should have assailed him 
     <lb/>
     with such violence as they had done, or that 
     <lb/>
     they should now desire to underrate the support 
     <lb/>
     he gave them, and injure him in every possi 
     <lb/>
     ble way. They had placed a different value on 
     <lb/>
     his efforts as all knew until he felt he could 
     <lb/>
     no longer co-operate with them. Their present 
     <lb/>
     abuse and mis-representations were easily un<lb break="no"/>derstood. They may not have felt his loss, 
     <lb/>
     but certainly they presented a different front 
     <lb/>
     after he adandoned them from what they did 
     <lb/>
     before. They had on all important occasions 
     <lb/>
     sought his services, and had unsought given him 
     <lb/>
     a prominence that would have enabled him to 
     <lb/>
     secure an honorable and lucrative position 
     <lb/>
     when the party came into power, as all ex<lb break="no"/>pected they would by holding together until 
     <lb/>
     the general election. He had sacrificed these 
     <lb/>
     chances, which were not remote; and perhaps 
     <lb/>
     also his prospects in public life for some years 
     <lb/>
     to come irom a sense of duty—but after all the 
     <lb/>
     popular clamour, now attempted to be excited, 
     <lb/>
     would soon subside, and before long the people 
     <lb/>
     would be just to the men who had boldly grap<lb break="no"/>pled with the great question. He could, there<lb break="no"/>fore, treat lightly the insinuations about impro<lb break="no"/>per influences which were not believed by the 
     <lb/>
     men who made them, and were simply intend<lb break="no"/>ed to mislead the country. Such charges could 
     <lb/>
     only trouble one whose conscience told him 
     <lb/>
     they contained some truth. Those who knew him 
     <lb/>
     best, whether they approved or condemned his 
     <lb/>
     recent action, would scout the base insinua<lb break="no"/>tions made against him. While such charges 
     <lb/>
     could be easily made and were calculated to 
     <lb/>
     leave an impression on the ignorant and de<lb break="no"/>praved, no right thinking man would believe 
     <lb/>
     them without proof, because it was impossible 
     <lb/>
     to disprove an undefined charge of that nature. 
     <lb/>
     He had refrained from making these observa<lb break="no"/>tions until he had been coarsely and violently 
     <lb/>
     assailed, and until further silence would have 
     <lb/>
     been misconstrued. They would throw some 
     <lb/>
     light on the honesty and consistency of the 
     <lb/>
     member for East Halifax, and account for his 
     <lb/>
     disappointment and temper at the course which 
     <lb/>
     events had taken. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO6">Mr. S MCDONNELL</persName> asked the Atty General 
     <lb/>
     what had become of the resolution calling upon 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Annaud to lay on the table letters which 
     <lb/>
     he had read, as a part of his speech on a previ<lb break="no"/>ous occasion. The very fact that other mem<lb break="no"/>bers had sent petitions into his county proved 
     <lb/>
     that he had never committed himself in oppo<lb break="no"/>sition to union. He denounced the efforts 
     <lb/>
       

            <cb/>
         

     made by the member for East Halifax to mis<lb break="no"/>lead the public mind and create agitation 
     <lb/>
     throughout the country, and stigmatised the 
     <lb/>
     position in which that gentleman had placed 
     <lb/>
     himself in the recent discussion on the subject 
     <lb/>
     of Confederation.       
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName> said it would be a gross insult 
     <lb/>
     to the House to suppose that any corroboration 
     <lb/>
     was needed for the statements he had previ<lb break="no"/>ously made. The certificate produced in refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the Inverness circular did not prove 
     <lb/>
     that the document was not written before the 
     <lb/>
     meeting of the House, which was the case. In 
     <lb/>
     reference to the Lunenburg election, and in re<lb break="no"/>ply to remarks concerning one of the members 
     <lb/>
     for that county, he would state that the terms 
     <lb/>
     upon which Mr. Hebb had agreed to run his 
     <lb/>
     election were, that his expenses should be paid, 
     <lb/>
     and that he should receive £30, as was agreed 
     <lb/>
     to be paid to Mr. Zwicker, and this money had 
     <lb/>
     been actually given to one of the agents in com<lb break="no"/>pliance with the terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HEBB1">Mr. HEBB</persName> denied that he had been bribed to 
     <lb/>
     run the election,—he had not been desirous of 
     <lb/>
     undertaking the contest; if his wishes had 
     <lb/>
     tended in that direction, he could have been in 
     <lb/>
     the House eighteen years ago.   A free election 
     <lb/>
     had been offered him this time; and for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of inducing his friends to desist from 
     <lb/>
     their entreaties, he said that he would require 
     <lb/>
     to be paid the £30, which Mr. Zwicker was re<lb break="no"/>ported to have got, but since receiving the re<lb break="no"/>quisition he had not for a moment thought of 
     <lb/>
    receiving the money and never should. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOST1">Mr. JOST</persName> introduced a bill to legalize assess<lb break="no"/>ment rolls of the county of Lunenburg. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HEBB1">Mr. HEBB</persName> complained that he had been una<lb break="no"/>ble to have the road scale for Lunenburg ar<lb break="no"/>ranged as he wished it. His colleagues would 
     <lb/>
     not allow him to appoint his own commission<lb break="no"/>ers. The scale had been handed in without his 
     <lb/>
     consent.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Messrs. <persName ref="pers:JOST1">JOST</persName> and <persName ref="pers:KAUL1">KAULBACK</persName> said that they 
     <lb/>
     had given every opportunity to the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber to consult with them in reference to the 
     <lb/>
     distribution of the road money.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BILL1">Hon. ATTY. GENERAL</persName> introduced an act to 
     <lb/>
     amend chap. 70, Provincial Railways; also, a 
     <lb/>
     bill in reference to Crown Lands. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2018-06-05, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
   
           <!-- <p>
     WEDNESDAY, May 2. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The House went into Committee, and passed 
     <lb/>
     the following bills:      
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>To provide for an improved system of sew<lb break="no"/>erage in Halifax ; to enable the trustees of a <lb/>school district in Cumberland country to sell<lb/>certain property ; to legalise assessment rolls<lb/>of county of Queens ; to amend chap. 65 Preser<lb break="no"/>vation of Useful Birds and Animals ; to incor<lb break="no"/>porate Knights Templars Kentville ; to facili<lb break="no"/>tate the settlement of titles in Cape Breton ; in<lb/>respect to trespasses on crown lands; relative<lb/>to the sale of munitions of war ; relative to the<lb/>oath of allegience ; relative to Militia ; to<lb/>enable the College of St. Xaviers, Autigonishe, <lb/>to confer degrees ; to amend chap. 15, Exporta<lb break="no"/>tion of Goods and Drawbacks ; to amend chap.<lb/>70, Provincial Railways ; to provide a summary<lb/>mode for recovering possession of crown<lb/>lands ; to amend chap. 25, Mines and Minerals ;<lb/>to establish a stock farm ; to establish a public<lb/>landing at Paradise.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The bill in respect to river fisheries provoked<lb/>some desultory discussion. Mr. Cowie and<lb/>
            </p>-->

    

    
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>