<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1865-02-09"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-02-09">9 February 1865</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          
         
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Second Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1865"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_002.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_003.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_004.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_001">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_002">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_002.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_003">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_003.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_004">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_004.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_001.jpg"/>
            
<div type="section">

<head> DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS<lb/>
          OF THE <lb/>
         HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY<lb/>
            OF<lb/>
NOVA SCOTIA.<lb/>
1865.</head>


<p>THURSDAY, February 9.</p>

            <p> The
House met at two o'clock, and were <lb/>
summoned by His Excellency the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor to the Legislative
Council Chamber <lb/>
where he read the following <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head> SPEECH: <lb/>
            </head>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr.
President, and Honorable
Gentlemen of the <lb/>
Legislative Council :</hi> <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr.
Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of <lb/>
Assembly:</hi> <lb/>
            </p>

            <lb/>

            <p> 1. It has been in good fortune, in other portions <lb/>
of the British Empire, to have
been brought in con<lb break="no"/>tact, and to have enjoyed much intercourse, With <lb/>
Members of their Legislatures The recollections con<lb break="no"/>nected therewith, and the results of such
mutual ac<lb break="no"/>quaintance, induce me to look forward with
pleasure <lb/>
to the establishment here of similar agreeable rela<lb break="no"/>tions between Her Majesty's
Representative in Nova <lb/>
Scotia and the Members of this Legislature. </p>
            <p> 2. I rejoice that our first rneeting takes place at a <lb/>
moment so auspicious to the material prosperity of the <lb/>
Province, that I am enabled to congratulate you at <lb/>
once on the late bountiful harvest, and on the unpre<lb break="no"/>cedented increase of your
revenue, as well as the re<lb break="no"/>markable development of your
most important Ex<lb break="no"/>ports and Imports. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 3. This unusual degree of prosperity is
the more <lb/>
fortunate, occurring, as it does, at the
time when you <lb/>
are
invited to consider one of the gravest questions- <lb/> probably the gravest and most
momentous question- <lb/>
ever submitted to the Legislature
of this Province. <lb/>
You are thus enabled to bring to its
consideration a <lb/>
greater amount of deliberate and
calm reflection than <lb/>
if harassed by any disturbing
pressure of less fortun<lb break="no"/>ate circumstances. <lb/>
            </p>



            <p> 4. At
the opening of last Session, the Officer then <lb/>
administering the Government
alluded to the identity <lb/>
of the interests of the British North American Mari<lb break="no"/>time Provinces, and laid before you a proposal for <lb/>
devising means of effecting their Union under one <lb/>
Government. The consideration which you then gave <lb/>
to the question led to a resolution requesting the <lb/>
Officer administering the Government to appoint <lb/>
Delegates, not exceeding five in number to confer on <lb/>
that subject with Delegates from New Brunswick and <lb/>
Prince Edward Island. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 5. It became my duty, on receiving
permission from <lb/>
Her Majesty's Government, to
give effect tothe Reso<lb break="no"/>lution. Therefore, with a view to a full and fair dis<lb break="no"/>cussion, I endeavored to bestow
a national character <lb/>
on the Delegation by requesting the aid of prominent <lb/>
representatives of the two great leading parties in the <lb/>
Province. I have directed the report presented to me <lb/>
          

            <cb/>
           
by those gentlemen
to be laid 'before you; you
will <lb/>
thence learn their reasons for deferring the final con<lb break="no"/>sideration of the subject, which you had submitted to <lb/>
them, till another proposal, which had been made in <lb/>
the interim, had been first disposed
of, namely, that <lb/>
of a general Union of British
North America.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 6. When invited by the Governor General
to send <lb/>
Delegates to Quebec to discuss that wider question, I <lb/>
considered it my duty to obtain previously the con<lb break="no"/>sent of Her Majesty's Government. I then appointed, <lb/>
on behalf of this Province, the same gentlemen who <lb/>
had represented her interests in the first Conference. <lb/>
The second Conference commenced its sittings at <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Quebec
on the 10th October, and did not conclude <lb/>
them till the 29th of that month. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 7.
The result of their labors, proposing a Union of <lb/>
British North America, on certain conditions embod<lb break="no"/>ied in seventy-two Resolutions, has already been made <lb/>
public, and will now be officially communicated to <lb/>
you with all the correspondence connected therewith. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 8. The highest authority on such a
subject, the <lb/>
Colonial Minister of the Crown, has recorded
his <lb/>
opinion of the labors of the Delegates.
and has given <lb/>
them credit for the warmest sentiments of loyalty, as <lb/>
also for conducting their deliberations with a patient <lb/>
sagacity, which enabled them to arrive at common <lb/>
conclusions on the most involved
and diiiicult ques<lb break="no"/>tions. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 9. I feel assured that, irrespective of
any political <lb/>
difference of opinion, such
encomlums from such a <lb/>
quarter, on British North American statesmen,
must <lb/>
be deeply gratifying to that
great body of Her Majes<lb break="no"/>ty's subjects, who are proud to identify themselves <lb/>
with the welfare and reputation of these Provinces. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 10. A copy of the Despatch of the Secretary of <lb/>
State, containing those opinions,
and conveying the<lb/>
general approval by Her Majesty's Government of <lb/>
the Quebec Resolutions as " the
best framework of a <lb/>
measure to be passed " by the
imperial Parliament," <lb/>
for the purposes therein more fully adverted to, was <lb/>
received by me on the 22nd December, and
by my <lb/>
orders was published the same day for general infor<lb break="no"/>mation. You have, therefore, been for many weeks <lb/>
in possession of the views of Her Majesty's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and the country has for a stil longer period<lb/>
enjoyed the opportunity for
discussing the expendiency<lb/>
of the project of Union. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 11. It is not my province, and I have no mission <lb/>
to do more than afford you the freestscope for conside<lb break="no"/>ration of a proposal which seriously involves your own <lb/>
prospects, and in reference to which you
should be <lb/>
comptent to interpret the wishes and
determine the <lb/>
true interests of the country. I feel
assured, however, <lb/>
that whatever he the result of your deliberations. you <lb/>
will deprecate attempts to treat in a narrow spirit, or <lb/>
otherwise than with dispassionate care and prudence, <lb/>
a question so broad, that in reality it covers the ground
<lb/>
of all parties and precludes it
from becoming the <lb/>
measure of merely one Government or one party. <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="2" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_002.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2</fw> <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>

            <p> 12. I need only observe further, without
in the <lb/>
least intending thereby to
influence your ultimate <choice><sic>de<lb break="no"/>emination</sic><corr>determination</corr></choice>, that it is obviously
convenient, if not <lb/>
essential, for the Legislatures
of all the Provinces <lb/>
concerned to observe uniformity in the mode of as<lb break="no"/>certaining their respective, decisions on a question <lb/>
common to all. I have, therefore, desired
to be laid <lb/>
before you some correspondence
between the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor General and myself on that.
point. </p>
            <p>13. Scarcely
less important or urgent is the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of internal defense. Much progress was made <lb/>
last year in the general enrolment of the Militia force
<lb/>
of the colony, which numbered upwards
of 56,000 <lb/>
men; of whom nearly 42,000
turned out for inspection <lb/>
and drill. When the heavy, direct tax, paid
by those <lb/>
men and also by the Volunteers,
both in time and <lb/>
labor, is considered, we must
all feel that the country <lb/>
owes them a special debt
of gratitude. </p>
            <p> 14. Nevertheless,
though they have exhibited much <lb/>
military aptitude, no adequate means have yet been <lb/>
taken to render etfective the excellent material of that <lb/>
large force. Without arms, accontrements,
uniforms, <lb/>
or any advantage except a few hours drill in each <lb/>
year, a succession of years similarly
employed would <lb/>
teach them little more. A step in advance is neces<lb break="no"/>sary to fit them fort he most ordinary service in the <lb/>
field. This Province can no longer
expect to contri<lb break="no"/>bute for its defense only a
fortieth part of the annual <lb/>
disbursements of Her Majesty's Commissariat chest <lb/>
at Halifax. Nor do I for a
moment suppose you can <lb/>
either expect or wish the
ample freedom which you <lb/>
enjoy here, to be always exempt
from those honor<lb break="no"/>able obligations which its preservation
entails else<lb break="no"/>where. </p>
            <p>15.
I have therefore directed Estimates to be pre<lb break="no"/>pared for placing the Militia in
a more efficient state, <lb/>
and feel confident that whatever may be the necessary <lb/>
cost, you will regard the defence of the Country not <lb/>
as a burthen, but a privilege and a sacred
duty to be <lb/>
cheerfully performed. ' <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of As<lb break="no"/>sembly:</hi> <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> 16.
The Public Accounts will also be submitted for <lb/>
your inspection, and the General
Estimates be pre<lb break="no"/>pared with every attention to economy which the <lb/>
exigencies of the Public Service
permit. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. President,
and Honorable Gentlemen by the Le<lb break="no"/>gislative Council:</hi> <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of Assem<lb break="no"/>bly :</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 17. You will, I am satisfied, have heard with regret <lb/>
that. proceedings are in progress
to terminate the Re<lb break="no"/>ciprocity Treaty, which has conferred
such extensive <lb/>
benefits on the trade both of this Province and the <lb/>
neighboring States, whilst it has also
essentially pro<lb break="no"/>moted the most friendly
relations betwtcn the two <lb/>
countries. I have directed the correspondence
on <lb/>
that subject to belaid before you, </p>
            <p> 18. Strongly impressed with the advantage of <lb/>
making the great natural resources of this
Colony <lb/>
better understood in the principal commercial centres <lb/>
of Europe, I have promised a
limited amount of aid <lb/>
to a committee of gentlemen who are now employed <lb/>
in securing a due representation
of this Province at <lb/>
the International Exhibition to
be held in Dublin <lb/>
during the present year. I
anticipate your hearty co<lb break="no"/>operation in promoting such a national object, when <lb/>
the papers upon this subject shall have been brought <lb/>
under your consideration. </p>
            <p> 19. some
modification of the law passed
last Ses<lb break="no"/>sion for the better encouragement of Education
will <lb/>
be laid before on, and no doubt you will
gladly en<lb break="no"/>deavor to render more available
and better adapted <lb/>
to the wants of the country,
certain provisions of a <lb/>
measure which so materially concerns
the education <lb/>
of the great body of the people. I count on that im<lb break="no"/>portant subject receiving the most enlightened con<lb break="no"/>sideration at your hands.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 20. In accordance with the Act passed last Session <lb/>
providing for the extension ol the tuilway to Picton, <lb/>
that work was put under contract, and will be com<lb break="no"/>pleted with all possible dispatch.
</p>
            <p>21. Proposals for the construction of Railways to <lb/>
the border of New Brunswick and to Annapolis, will <lb/>
also
require your consideration. </p>

            <cb/>

            <p> 22. The grant
of last Session on account of Saint <lb/>
Peter's Canal has been
expended, and a full Report <lb/>
on that work will be laid before you
at an early day. </p>
            <p> 23. I regret to be obliged to inform you that the <lb/>
crowded state of the Hospital for the Insane has
<lb/>
made it impossible to provide
adequate accommoda<lb break="no"/>tion for the care of these who
unfortunately need an <lb/>
asylum of that description. I trust the appeal thus<lb/>
made to the sympathy of the Legislature will lead to <lb/>
the extension of an Institution so
indespensible.
<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 24.
You will be gratified to learn
that. the traffic on <lb/>
the Provincial Railways continues to exhibit a mark<lb break="no"/>ed and steady improvement over any previous year, <lb/>
and that the increasing sale of the Crown Lands,
and <lb/>
extended working of the Coal
and Gold Mines, all <lb/>
evidence a high degree of prosperity. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 25.
These fortunate circumstances, enhanced as <lb/>
they are by the continuance of peace, will no doubt <lb/>
facilitate your discharge of those public duties for <lb/>
which I have called you together,
and must awaken <lb/>
in us all a grateful recognition of the indulgent bouuty <lb/>
of that Providence whichhas bestowed so
many bles<lb break="no"/>sings on this Province. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 26.
I now declare this Session opened. <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p> Having
returned to the Assembly Room, <lb/>
the Speaker read the Speech to the House. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Hon. PROV.  SEC. laid on the table the
elec<lb break="no"/>tion writs for the Counties of Annapolis and <lb/>
Picton. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. Ray
and Hon. James McDonald were <lb/>
then presented and sworn in, in
the presence <lb/>
of Hon. M. B. Almon, Hon. J. H.
Anderson, <lb/>
and Hon. A. Keith, acting as Commissioners. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Dr. Hamilton
laid on the table, <hi rendition="simple:italic">pro forma</hi>, <lb/>
a bill for the better protection
of the estates <lb/>
and rights of married women. <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head> ANSWER
TO THE ADDRESS. <lb/>
            </head>

            <p> Mr. Kaulback,
in moving the answer to <lb/>
the address, said : The very great
pleasure it <lb/>
gives the in moving the answer to the speech, <lb/>
with which His Excellency
opened this Ses<lb break="no"/>sion, is greatly enhanced by the opening
re<lb break="no"/>marks of His Excellency in which 
he informed <lb/>
us of the unprecedented increase
of our Reve<lb break="no"/>nue as well as the remarkable development <lb/>
of our mont important Exports
and Imports. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> It affords
me great pleasure to congratulate <lb/>
the Government, and the Country on having
a
<lb/>
large Revenue, which tends so much to main<lb break="no"/>tain the confidence and strengthen
the ties be<lb break="no"/>tween Government and
Country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> We the
Representatives of the people, must <lb/>
feel this state of things highly
encouraging <lb/>
to us as well as
the Government, and a hap<lb break="no"/>py relief from the perplexities which attend an <lb/>
empty chest. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> This unusual degree of prosperity is the more <lb/>
fortunate because it occurs at
a time, as His <lb/>
Excellency has been pleased to
remark, when <lb/>
we are invited to consider the greatest ques<lb break="no"/>tion ever submitted to this Legislature,
the <lb/>
Union of British North
America.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> This question
has engaged the attention of <lb/>
the leading public men for more than half a <lb/>
century, not only in those
Colonies, but in <lb/>
England ; and the subject years ago,
and on <lb/>
several occasions was brought to the
conside<lb break="no"/>ration of the Legislature by our leading
pub<lb break="no"/>lic men of all parties. We are now invited by <lb/>
His Excellency to the serious consideration of <lb/>
this question embodied in seventy-two resolu<lb break="no"/>tions ; the framers of which have received the <lb/>
highest praise in England from
the Colonial <lb/>
Minister of the Crown, for the
ability display<lb break="no"/>ed, and for the warm sentiments of loyalty <lb/>
and attachment felt for the mother coun<lb break="no"/>try. We must all, I think, highly approve
of


            <pb n="3" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_003.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">3</fw>
          
the manner in which His Excellency has <lb/>
brought this great matter before us. We have <lb/>
the freest scope given us for the consideration <lb/>
of this question, and it is to be earnestly hoped <lb/>
that His Excellency will realize the assurance <lb/>
Which he expresses. He feels
"That we will <lb/>
"not treat in a narrow spirit a
question so <lb/>
"broad, that in reality it covers
the ground of <lb/>
"all parties and all interests so
completely, as <lb/>
"to preclude it from being made
the measure <lb/>
"of one Government or of one party." <lb/>
The next subject which is referred to in <lb/>
the speech, is that of internal
defence. It will <lb/>
be gratifying to the country to hear that His <lb/>
Excellency appreciates the prompt
manner in <lb/>
which nearly fifty thousand of our people <lb/>
turned outfor inspection and drill. We must <lb/>
all believe it is necessary we
should aid in <lb/>
making them more efficient. Arms and accou<lb break="no"/>trements are necessary, and it is to be hoped <lb/>
will be amply supplied for the protection of our <lb/>
homes and country. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>It is to be regretted that the neighbouring <lb/>
States have taken steps to abrogate the Reci<lb break="no"/>procity Treaty which has
conferred so many <lb/>
privileges, and been profitable alike to all. lt <lb/>
is to be hoped that some means
may be devised <lb/>
to prevent the annulliug of the Treaty. Yet, <lb/>
should the Treaty terminate, it will behove <lb/>
the Governmentaml ourselves to guard and <lb/>
protect well those most important
branches of <lb/>
the products and resources of our
country, <lb/>
which were so summarily disposed
of by that <lb/>
Treaty regulation. Our Fisheries,
in particu<lb break="no"/>lar, which tend so much to the
prosperity of <lb/>
our Province.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>We must feel it a matter of no
ordinary im<lb break="no"/>portance that the natural resources of this <lb/>
Province should be better
understood abroad. <lb/>
No better and more economical way
of effect<lb break="no"/>ing this at present appears to
me
than that <lb/>
brought to our notice in the speech of His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency, by being properly
represented at <lb/>
the Intercolonial Exhibition tobe held in Dub<lb break="no"/>lin this year. We all as Nova Scotians must <lb/>
feel some pride at the notice taken of your
pro<lb break="no"/>ductions at the Great Exhibition in London. <lb/>
The co-operation expected
from us towards <lb/>
advancing this great undertaking, will, no<lb/>
doubt, be cheerfully given.
</p>
            <p>Every member, no doubt, has
been impress<lb break="no"/>ed with the conviction gained
from the short <lb/>
operation of the school bill, that
some modifi<lb break="no"/>cation is required to render it more available <lb/>
and better adapted to the wants
and wishes <lb/>
of the people. All surely will give their best <lb/>
aid to a subject so important
to the interests <lb/>
and well being of the great body of the people
<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Scarcely any appeal is
necessary to our <lb/>
sympathy for those who unfortunately need <lb/>
the
care of the Asylum. More room unfortu<lb break="no"/>nately is required for the safety
and comfort <lb/>
of the patients.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>He (Mr.
K.) thought he could do nothing
<lb/>
better in moving the answer to
the address,<lb/>
than to give them a
comparative statement of <lb/>
the increase of the Revenue during the last <lb/>
year. They
and the country were pleased that, <lb/>
at the last Session
of this House, they had <lb/>
a very large Revenue to meet the requirements <lb/>
of our people ; and
very large grants were <lb/>
given
to the roads of the
country, and other
<lb/>
public works. The Government
have met all <lb/>
the demands upon 
the Treasury for the year
<lb/>
just ended, and leave a balance in
Treasury to 
<lb/>
go for the benefit of the country or $225,150. <lb/>


            </p>

<cb/>

<!-- GL, 2017-03-15, untaggedTable commented out table to be marked-up at later date.

            <p>Increase of Revenue of 1864 over 1863 : <lb/>
Comparative Statement. <lb/>
Railway: Increase of pastsengers.....13,301
<lb/>
Increase
in value.. . . .. . . . . . . .. ... $19,122
<lb/>
Exports 526.328 <lb/>
lmports................ 2,403,251 <lb/>
Excise, Customs, and Light Duty.
. 145,778 <lb/>
Increase for Crown Lands… … . ... 19,000 <lb/>
Gold 6,020 oz. = ................. 106,000 <lb/>
Coal large increase. <lb/>
Balance in Treasury at end of Finan<lb break="no"/>cial year ......... . . . . . . . . . . ...... $225,150 <lb/>
            </p> -->


            <p> I feel very gratified indeed, Mr.
Speaker, to <lb/>
be able to give this statement
of our prosperity <lb/>
to the House and the country ; showing,
as I<lb/>
think it does, an unprecedented state of pros<lb break="no"/>perity in every source of Provincial lncome. <lb/>
For all these and many other blessings,
we <lb/>
should recognize the Giver of all good. I shall <lb/>
now read the following<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>ADDRESS. <lb/>
            </head>


            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">May it please Your Excellency,-</hi></p>


            <p>We, the Representatives of the people of <lb/>
Nova Scotia, thank your Excellency for
the
<lb/>
Speech with which you have been pleased to <lb/>
open this Session. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> We
beg to congratulate your Excellency <lb/>
upon your assumption of the Government
of
<lb/>
this Province, and we have no
doubt that the <lb/>
most agreeable relations will be
established <lb/>
between your Execllency and the Members of <lb/>
the Legislature.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The bountiful
harvest we have enjoyed, and <lb/>
the increase of the trade and revenues of the <lb/>
country, are, indeed, auspicious, placing
us in <lb/>
the best possible position to deal with the <lb/>
great questions submitted for our deliberation. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The Report from the Delegates, appointed to <lb/>
confer upon the Union of the Maritime
Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, and the Resolutions of
the Conference <lb/>
held at Quebec, proposing a
Union of the dif<lb break="no"/>ferent Provinces of British North America, <lb/>
together with the correspondence
upon that <lb/>
subject, will obtain at our hands the deliber<lb break="no"/>ate and attentive consideration
demanded by <lb/>
a question of such magnitude
and importance, <lb/>
and fraught with consequences so momentous' <lb/>
to us and our posterity. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The question of Internal Defence will
not <lb/>
fail to engage our serious
attention, and we <lb/>
will be happy to afford your Excellency every <lb/>
aid in our power in placing that branch
of the
<lb/>
public service in a still more effcctive condi<lb break="no"/>tion.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Public Accounts, when laid
before us, <lb/>
will receive our careful inspection,
and we will <lb/>
be glad to find in the estimates the
evidence of <lb/>
such economy as
is consistent with the exi<lb break="no"/>gencies of the public service.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The abrogation of the Reciprocity Treaty <lb/>
would, in our opinion, operate most unfavor<lb break="no"/>ably upon the trade between tthis Province <lb/>
and the United States, and
certainly
would <lb/>
not improve the friendly relations
which have <lb/>
been so largely promoted by its
operation.<lb/>
We will be glad to receive the correspondence<lb/>
upon this subject. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The papers concerning the
International <lb/>
Exhibition, to be held at Dublin will
recieve <lb/>
the attention due to the proper
representation  <lb/>
of the products of this Province. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>We will not fail to devote our
most earnest <lb/>
efforts to aid in maturing any improvements<lb/>
           



            <pb n="4" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-09_Page_004.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">4</fw> <fw type="num">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>
          
 which may be suggested in the Act for the
bet<lb break="no"/>ter encouragement of Education—a
subject so <lb/>
deeply interesting and important to the whole <lb/>
country. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> It is gratifying to know that
the—Extension <lb/>
of the Railway to Pictou has been placed un<lb break="no"/>der contract, and will be carried on with des<lb break="no"/>patch. <lb/>
            </p>
 
            <p> We will give due consideration to any
pro<lb break="no"/>posals for the construction of the Lines pro<lb break="no"/>vided for in the resolution which passed both <lb/>
Branches of the Legislature last Session. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The Report upon St. Peter's Canal will
ob<lb break="no"/>tain our careful examination. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Fully impressed with the obvious
necessity <lb/>
of making adequate provision for the unfor<lb break="no"/>tunate Insane, we will be prepared to discharge <lb/>
that duty in an efficient manner. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> We are gratified to learn that all the vari<lb break="no"/>ous sources of Provincial Income evidence <lb/>
such a high degree of prosperity ; and for these <lb/>
mercies, together with the blessings of continu<lb break="no"/>ed peace, we desire to return our grateful <lb/>
thanks to the Bountiful Giver of all good. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> In viewing this address, Mr. Speaker, I
feel <lb/>
assured that it will meet the support of every <lb/>
member in this House. I cannot
see that it <lb/>
will, in the slightest manner, compromise my <lb/>
views or action on any question. We are com<lb break="no"/>mitted to nothing but the provision for the ex<lb break="no"/>tension of the Hospital, the
Militia service and <lb/>
to the International Exhibition in Dublin.. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On the great question of the Union, you
will <lb/>
all admit, that less could not have been said, <lb/>
and more might have been unwise. It is <lb/>
the intention of the Government to leave the <lb/>
subject as open as possible, and to the free <lb/>
action of any member of Government and <lb/>
members generally. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. WHITMAN seconded the answer. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The Address was allowed to lie on the
table. <lb/>
The House adjourned until three o'clock the <lb/>
next day.<lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-03-15, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


            <!--<p> FRIDAY, 10th Feb. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> ANSWER
TO THE A""RESS. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The House met at three o'clock. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The Answer to the Address was taken up, <lb/>
and read clause by clause.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. LOCKE said, in reference to the
clause <lb/>
touching upon the Union of the Colonies, that <lb/>
it did not commit any one on the question. <lb/>
Every one was, of course, left perfectly free to <lb/>
deal with it as his judgment should dictate, <lb/>
when all the papers connected with it were <lb/>
before the House. He thought it necessary to <lb/>
say this in order that the country might under<lb break="no"/>stand the position of gentlemen. . <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr.
ARCHIBALD (who was only heard with <lb/>
the greatest difficulty) said that the proper <lb/>
time, of course, for discussing the question <lb/>
referred to, would be when all the papers <lb/>
were before the House. All the House was <lb/>
asked to do at present was to promise that <lb/>
every question should receive their deliberate <lb/>
consideration when it came in due form before <lb/>
them. In looking over the Speech, he
found <lb/>
that the only measure promised, was one con<lb break="no"/>nected with Edugation. He would take this<lb/>
opportunity of calling attention to the fact <lb/>
that he had last session foretold some of the <lb/>
difficulties, that would probably arise from
<lb/>
some features of the bill, to
which he objectcd <lb/>
at the time. He had particularly urged the <lb/>
appointment of a Council of Public Instruction <lb/>
            </p>

 



            <p> which was not composed of the members of
the <lb/>
Executive. Council. He had also
said that, at <lb/>
all events, if the Government were not willing <lb/>
to go as far as he wished, they should place at <lb/>
the head of the Council of Public Instruction <lb/>
the Lieutenant Governor, as his presence <lb/>
would give to the country the guarantee that <lb/>
mere party considerations would not always <lb/>
prevail. He now begged the Government to <lb/>
consider carefully in any amendments to the <lb/>
bill they might introduce, the propriety of <lb/>
avoiding even the semblance of suspicion that <lb/>
party influences prevailed in Educational mat<lb break="no"/>ters. He congratulated the country on the <lb/>
encouraging statements made in the speech,- <lb break="yes"/>
that our revenue was very large, and all our <lb/>
branches of industry prosperous to an unpar<lb break="no"/>alleled extent. Every gentleman, whatever <lb/>
his political prejudices, would learn this fact <lb/>
with the deepest satisfaction.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. Stewart Campbell said that he per<lb break="no"/>fectly concurred with those gentlemen who <lb/>
had spoken of this Answer to the Address as <lb/>
being entirely non-committal in its character. <lb/>
Notwithstanding he held very strong opinions <lb/>
on the subject of the Union of the Colonies, he <lb/>
felt that he had no difficulty whatever in giv— <lb break="maybe"/>
ing his concurrence to the Answer. He em— <lb break="maybe"/>
phatically stated that he wished it to be at <lb/>
once un erstood that he did not endorse the <lb/>
action of the Government in sending a delega—
<lb break="maybe"/>
tion to Quebec. The house had put upon its
<lb/>
journals last session a resolution authorizing <lb/>
the Government to appoint delegates in refer<lb break="no"/>ence to a Union of the Maritime Provinces. <lb/>
Authority, however, had been granted from <lb/>
some quarter to those delegates to go beyond <lb/>
the misson entrusted to them by
the Legislas <lb/>
ture. Therefore, although he concurred in the <lb/>
answer to the address, he wished to guard him<lb break="no"/>self from having it sup posed that he at all
en— <lb break="maybe"/>
dorsed the act of the Government in sending <lb/>
a delegation to Quebec. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> The answer to the address then passed nem</p>
            <p>eon. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The PROVINCIAL SECRETARY stated that<lb/>
His Excellency the Lieutenant Governor
would <lb/>
be ready to receive the answer on Monday <lb/>
next at half-past one. It was therefore agreed <lb/>
that the whole house should present the an<lb break="no"/>swer at that hour.  <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> REVISING COMMITTEE. <lb/>
On motion of the Hon. Prov. Secy., the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing Committee was appointed to select <lb/>
Standing Committees of the House :<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Prov. Secretary, Mr. Blanchard, Hon. <lb/>
Attorney General, Mr. Locke, Mr. Kiliam, Mr.  <lb/>
Archibald, and Mr. Tobin. <lb/> 
sMr. BOURINOT would suggest to.
the Revi<lb break="no"/>sing Committee that they should place upon.<lb/>
the Committee gentlemen who would fairly <lb/>
represent all sections of the
Province. Hither- <lb break="yes"/>
o that rule had not been observed with that <lb/>
strictness which was absolutely requisite
in or<lb break="no"/>der to perform the business of the country as <lb/>
it should be. He had had occasion in pre= <lb/>
vious sessions to suggest changes
in this par<lb break="no"/>ticular, and he hoped that the gentleman
who <lb/>
represented Cape Breton on the
Committee<lb/>
would take care that justice was done to that<lb/>
section in which he ought to be
especially in<lb break="no"/>terested.<lb/> 
            </p>
            <p>Mr. BLANCHARD said that hitherto
the great <lb/>
difficulty had been to find gentletnen willing
<lb/>
to serve on the committees after they had beens<lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>