<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNSLA_1865-04-20" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-04-20">20 April 1865</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA">
          

               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          
         
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Second Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1865"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="288"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_283.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_284.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_285.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_286.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_287.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_288.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-04-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-04-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_283">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_283.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_284">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_284.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_285">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_285.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_286">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_286.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_287">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_287.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_288">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_288.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="283" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_283.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">283</fw>

<!-- GL, 2017-04-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
           <!-- <p> all apparent that the construction of
these rail<lb break="no"/>ways was to impose burthens we could not <lb/>
bear, I would hesitate before adopting the reso<lb break="no"/>lution.  No man in this country, however, can <lb/>
deny that, if we are able to obtain the connec<lb break="no"/>tion with St. John, and with the railway sys<lb break="no"/>tem of the continent, we shall gain vast com<lb break="no"/>mercial advantages.  The increase in trade will <lb/>
soon counterbalance any additional burthens <lb/>
that we may impose upon ourselves.  Rail<lb break="no"/>ways make trade wherever they pass, and no <lb/>
one can doubt that a road to the
fertile coun<lb break="no"/>ties of King's and Annapolis would be not <lb/>
only a great boon to the people of the west, <lb/>
but create an ultimately remunerative traflic. <lb/>
In due time a trade would accumulate that <lb/>
would repay handsomely the Province for the <lb/>
expenditure it might incur. <lb/>
            </p>-->

            <p rendition="simple:right"> Thursday,
April 20.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName>
said that for the last few years so <lb/>
much had been said upon the question of Rail<lb break="no"/>roads, it was impossible to bring forward <lb/>
anything new on the subject.  There were <lb/>
a great many things in the speech of the hon. <lb/>
leader of the opposition, to which he would have <lb/>
liked to refer ; but as he perceived that he was <lb/>
not in his place, he should refrain from doing so. <lb/>
If the present position of this country were con<lb break="no"/>trasted with the condition of affairs
a few years <lb/>
ago, it would be found that from some cause or <lb/>
other, whether from the construction of railroads <lb/>
or the spirit of commercial enterprize, or the <lb/>
gradual expansion of trade, the Revenue had <lb/>
swelled to an extent beyond the expectation of the <lb/>
most sanguine.  He had taken the trouble a year <lb/>
ago, when it was proposed to
extend the railroad <lb/>
to Pictou, to look into the question, and to con<lb break="no"/>trast the state of our Revenue then with what it <lb/>
was before the railway system
was inaugurated, <lb/>
and what did he find ? <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> (The hon. gentleman here said that he had<lb/>
mislaid the memorandum of figures he had prepared ; <lb/>
but speaking from memory) the
Revenue, which <lb/>
in 1851 amounted to £102, 632, had swelled in <lb/>
10 years (1861) to over £281,000,
and this year <lb/>
the Financial Secretary estimates it at over <lb/>
$1,300,000.  So it will be seen
that since the <lb/>
construction of railroads has been commenced, <lb/>
that the trade of the country has increased—labor <lb/>
has been multiplied,—and the expenditure of the <lb/>
Province has been kept within its income.  He<lb/>
had prepared a few calculations as to the amount<lb/>
of liability annually imposed upon this country <lb/>
by the construction of these public works, and <lb/>
first as to the two links already completed to <lb/>
Truro and Windsor.  Some hon gentlemen wish<lb break="no"/>ed to leave these where they were ; but that he <lb/>
never could assent to.  He believed that they <lb/>
never could be made properly remunerative until <lb/>
they tapped the waters of the St.
Lawrence on the <lb/>
one hand, and the Bay of Fundy on the other. </p>
            <p> In approaching this subject, he wished to
do <lb/>
so in a spirit of fairness and candor.  He did not<lb/>
wish to state the liability we would be called upon<lb/>
to assume at a dollar less than it really would
be. <lb/>
For many years we have spent
large sums of the<lb/>
public monies in constructing mud roads.  This <lb/>
session, over $250.000 has been
voted for that 

            <cb/>   

 purpose.  And yet it is argued by some,
that <lb/>
altho' the Province can afford to do that, she <lb/>
cannot undertake the construction of the e public <lb/>
works, which will add so much to the wealth and <lb/>
material prosperity of the country. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p> To return, however, to the subject of liability— <lb/>
he found that the Province had issued debentures <lb/>
to the extent of a million of
pounds for the con<lb break="no"/>struction of the lines to Windsor and Truro—this <lb/>
involved an annual liability of £60,000 for in<lb break="no"/>terest.  No difficulty had ever
been experienced <lb/>
in paying that interest—the
Province had always <lb/>
been prepared when called upon to meet all de<lb break="no"/>mands, and certainly she was in a better condi<lb break="no"/>tion now, than when railway construction was <lb/>
commenced.  Then again, we have, after some <lb/>
delay, undertaken the construction of the line to <lb/>
Pictou—the propriety of that extension has al<lb break="no"/>ways been admitted, and it was only a question <lb/>
of time as to when the finances of the country <lb/>
would admit of its being undertaken.  The esti<lb break="no"/>mated cost of that work is £500,000, which will <lb/>
impose an annual liability of £30, 000.  That <lb/>
liability, however, will not fall upon us imme<lb break="no"/>diately ; but will be extended over three years, as <lb/>
the work goes on—and as the business of the <lb/>
country would also go on increasing, there is no <lb/>
doubt, that there would be no trouble in meeting <lb/>
these obligations.  The
Government now propose <lb/>
to subsidize any company to construct the line to <lb/>
the borders of New Brunswick—which is esti<lb break="no"/>mated to cost £400,000, when
capitalized, involv<lb break="no"/>ing an annual charge on the Revenues of the <lb/>
Province of £24,000 a year. It is also proposed <lb/>
to extend the line to Annapolis.  Last year, a<lb/>
resolution was passed by the House, offering any <lb/>
company that would undertake to construct the <lb/>
line, a subvention of 4 per cent. on £6,000 per <lb/>
mile.  It appears, after a lapse of'a year, that no <lb/>
company is willing to undertake the work, unless <lb/>
the Government will build the bridge over the <lb/>
Avon—that bridge is estimated to
cost £40,000. <lb/>
The cost of the Annapolis road, at £6,000 per <lb/>
mile, will amount to £50,000—if that is capital<lb break="no"/>ized at the same rate of four per cent—it will give <lb/>
£20,400 annual interest to be paid by the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. <lb/>
            </p>





            <p> Then again, take the cost of bridging the
Avon— <lb/>
the hon. leader of the Opposition undertook to ques<lb break="no"/>tion the accuracy of the estimate—but
the only <lb/>means of judging, was from the report of the En<lb break="no"/>gineer, and he did not think that the Government <lb/>
had any motive or desire to conceal from the coun<lb break="no"/>try the real cost of the work—the
interest at six <lb/>
per cent upon the cost—as
estimated <hi rendition="simple:italic">by the Engi<lb break="no"/>neer, will be £2,400 a year</hi>. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> It appears that Mr. Leversey on behalf
of the In—<lb/>
ternational Contract Company, has
offered to con<lb break="no"/>struct
the road to the borders of New Brunswick, <lb/>
provided the Government, or the City of Halifax,<lb/>
take stock to the amount of £100,000.  The
Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, probably looking at all points of the po<lb break="no"/>litical horizon, have come to the conclusion
that<lb/>
they can manage to get the city to assume that <lb/>
amount of stock.  He (Mr. T.) was not going to<lb/>
discuss that question just then—but he thought it <lb/>
would be wise before they
passed any law to make 

            <pb n="284" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_284.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">284</fw> <fw type="num">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>


the city liable, that they should have the agree<lb break="no"/>ment drawn up and the bond signed. He be<lb break="no"/>lieved that if the proper papers had been signed <lb/>
by the properly constituted authorities, there would <lb/>
have been no difficulty—but the members of the <lb/>
City Council felt that they were not bound by any <lb/>
loose expressions or pledges made by some persons <lb/>
at a public meeting in the Temperance Hall, and <lb/>
which never had been ratified by any resolution of <lb/>
the City Council. These are the views of many of <lb/>
the members of the City Council, whether correct<lb/>
or not he was not prepared to say. If the city of<lb/>
Halifax, took stock to the extent of £100,000, she <lb/>
would receive from the Province four per cent. If <lb/>
the Province took it—they would have to pay 2 <lb/>
per cent more. All these sums added together, <lb/>
would give a total annual liability of $578,700,
<lb/>
which the Province would have to pay after the <lb/>
whole of these works were completed—representing <lb/>
a debt of $9.645.000 ; but this
of course would <lb/>
not accrue at once, but would be spread over <lb/>
a number of years. This appeared a pretty <lb/>
large debt for a population of about 350,000 <lb/>
people, amounting to about $1.65
per head. <lb/>
            </p>
  
            <p> <persName ref="pers:LEVE1">Mr. LEVESCONTE</persName>.—Have you taken into con<lb break="no"/>sideration, that the Province only guarantees the <lb/>
amount for 20 years, and that it will not be a per<lb break="no"/>manent debt. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> perfectly understood that the
liabili<lb break="no"/>ty would cease at the end of twenty years—on the<lb/>
extension to Annapolis, and New Brunswick. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:LEVE1">Mr. LEVESCONTE</persName>.—It
does not require as much <lb/>
money to capitalize a sum for 20 years, as if it was <lb/>
for ever. He thought the hon. member had made <lb/>
this mistake.  <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> had made no mistake whatever. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> He had also included the St. Peter's
Canal in <lb/>
his calculations, which he had put down at $125,<lb break="no"/>000. He had also taken the trouble to make an<lb break="no"/>other little estimate of the indirect advantages <lb/>
which had been derived from the construction of <lb/>
the two short lines of railroad to Windsor and <lb/>
Truro. He found upon looking over the returns <lb/>
of 1863 that there were 110,137 passengers carried <lb/>
over the road and 56,471 tons of freight—9,784 free <lb/>
passengers and 1,192 had season tickets—then
<lb/>
take into consideration the time saved in travell<lb break="no"/>ing—a farmer leaving Windsor for Halifax by the <lb/>
old route, would have to stop at the
various places <lb/>
of call on the road, each one
costing him some<lb break="no"/>thing, and by the time he had completed his busi<lb break="no"/>ness to Halifax, it would be several
days before he <lb/>
could get home again—whereas now
by the rail<lb break="no"/>road, he could transact all his
business and be <lb/>
back in two days. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> He put down time saved at $99,161—saving
in <lb/>
freight as compared with the cost of transporta<lb break="no"/>tion over the ordinary road at $282,355—free
pas<lb break="no"/>sengers must have saved in time—at
the rate of <lb/>
$2 each $19,568—season
tickets, these are chiefly
<lb/>
used by parties who have opened up a
number of <lb/>
works along the line, such as slate quarries—<lb/>
powder mills—ice houses—he would put down the <lb/>
direct advantages to the parties at $5
each, which <lb/>
would amount to $5,960—then
add the amount <lb/>
of net proceeds received according to
the Com<lb break="no"/>missioners report, $149,647—42 making a total of <lb/>
           

            <cb/>
   
 $556,718,42-100 while the amount of interest, <lb/>
the Province will be liable for,after the completion <lb/>
of the entire lines, will only be $578,700.
There<lb break="no"/>fore, in view of these
calculations, he thought it <lb/>
would be the best thing to go on with these
works, <lb/>
even if we had to run some risk. It was true that <lb/>
the obligations they were about to assume were <lb/>
heavy, but he believed that the revenue and re<lb break="no"/>sources of the county would increase to such an <lb/>
extent as to meet every liability that they were <lb/>
about to incur. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> No one could deny but that it would be a
great <lb/>
advantage to this country, to have direct railway <lb/>
communication with the whole continent of Am<lb break="no"/>erica, and if New Brunswick has determined to <lb/>
construct her line to the borders,
it surely was <lb/>
the duty as well as the interest
of N ova Scotia to <lb/>
connect with her, and thus open
communication <lb/>
with Canada and the United States of America.
<lb/>
It was well known that people who travelled <lb/>
abroad, had a great repugnance to sea voyages, <lb/>
and no doubt if these lines of railroad were com<lb break="no"/>pleted, travellers from Canada, New Brunswick, <lb/>
and the United States, would come to Halifax,
to <lb/>
take passage to Europe, and thus increase the <lb/>
passenger traffic and
consequently the remunera<lb break="no"/>tive qualities of the road.<lb/>
            </p>


            <p> They had all been accustomed for years to
<lb/>
build great hopes upon the construction of the <lb/>
Intercolonial Railroad. For his part
he must con<lb break="no"/>fess that but as a means for the
consummation of a <lb/>
Union of the Colonies he had no
great faith in it. <lb/>
As a commercial speculation it would be years be<lb break="no"/>fore it could pay. As a national work
however <lb/>
it was a matter of great importance, and as a <lb/>
means of transporting mails and passengers it <lb/>
would be exceedingly valuable. At present the<lb/>
mails and passengers have to be transported<lb/>
through Boston by sufferance.
Suppose any distur<lb break="no"/>bance should take place between England
and the <lb/>
United States and that should happen in mid<lb break="no"/>winter, and it would be necessary to land the <lb/>
mails and passengers, it would take ten or twelve <lb/>
days to transport them over land to Canada. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Unless this line is continued, and the
contem<lb break="no"/>plated union takes place, he had serious doubts <lb/>
whether Canada would long remain in her present <lb/>
position as a province of British
America.  She <lb/>
must have an outlet to the seat. He read a <lb/>
speech the other day of Sir Etienna
Tache in which <lb/>
he said, that unless acrostatic science was<lb/>
more fully developed, Canada could not reach<lb/>
the sea by ballooning. However, it is quite certain <lb/>
she cannot remain much longer in
her present <lb/>
position. He could not help
regretting that Nova <lb/>
Scotia and New Brunswick should
be so unpatrio<lb break="no"/>tic in a matter of such national
and paramount im<lb break="no"/>portance as this, as to talk about dollars and <lb/>
cents, that they should be so unpatriotic to the <lb/>
mother country who had spent so much for
their <lb/>
defence, as to refuse to make
even a small sacrifice <lb/>
for the purpose of helping her to maintain
her <lb/>
power on this <choice><sic>contienent</sic><corr>continent</corr></choice>. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p> He must confess that his
views rather went with <lb/>
the member for Yarmouth in his idea that the<lb/>
Government ought to retain the control over the<lb/>
trunk line to New Brunswick, but if there was <lb/>
          


            <pb n="285" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_285.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</fw> <fw type="num">285</fw>

any doubt as
to whether New Brunswick would <lb/>
build her line to the border, it there was any dan<lb break="no"/>ger of any difficulty occurring, he was willing to <lb/>
agree to this proposition, rather
than run the risk <lb/>
of the line not being built. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On the subject of the Intercolonial railroad he <lb/>
would say that if built by the United Provinces,
<lb/>
even if it remained unremunerative for a while, <lb/>
it would not bear too heavily upon the revenue, <lb/>
because when all our revenues are combined we <lb/>
would be in a better position to bear the burden <lb/>
than we are now.  All the
revenues would go into <lb/>
the common treasury, the public works would be <lb/>
of such a nature that the combined means of all <lb/>
the Provinces would be sufficient to sustain them. <lb/>
It appeared to him surprising that hon.
gentlemen <lb/>
in discussing the question,
appeared to think that <lb/>
Nova Scotia was always
going to be Nova Scotia, <lb/>
they forget that they would all
be British Ameri<lb break="no"/>cans—all our people would be
associated together <lb/>
for business purposes, with one code of laws, one <lb/>
currency, one system of custom duties. </p>
            <p> But he would not say any
more at present, <lb/>
about the union of the
colonies.  The hon gentle<lb break="no"/>man concluded by recapitulating the
advantage <lb/>
Nova Scotia would derive from the extension of <lb/>
railroad communication, if providently and econo<lb break="no"/>mically carried out. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName> said,
he did not intend, at that
<lb/>
period of the session, to weary
the house with <lb/>
any lengthened remarks upon the subject <lb/>
then under discussion.  The resolution
before <lb/>
the house proposes to grant from
the public <lb/>
treasury, as a free gift for the next twenty <lb/>
years, the sum of four per cent. on
$40,000 a <lb/>
mile to a company to complete railway con<lb break="no"/>nection between Truro and Moncton, and the <lb/>
further sum of four per cent. on $24,000 per <lb/>
mile to extend the railway from
Windsor to <lb/>
Annapolis, not including the Avon bridge. <lb/>
This resolution will, therefore,
add to the bur<lb break="no"/>thens of the country about $23,000 for the next <lb/>
twenty years. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> It
would be in the recollection of
the house <lb/>
that when this question was brought up last <lb/>
year, and the subvention resolution was moved <lb/>
by the Provincial Secretary, he (Mr. M.)
moved <lb/>
a resolution, by way of
amendment, to this <lb/>
effect:— </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p> "<hi rendition="simple:italic">Whereas</hi>,
The revenue of this Provinee is now <lb/>
burthened with a liability of  about £60,000
annually <lb/>
for interest on the money
invested in our existing <lb/>
lines of railway.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <hi rendition="simple:italic">And whereas</hi>,
The Act of this Session;
providing for <lb/>
the construction of the line to
Pictou, will entail a <lb/>
further charge of at least £25,000
annually. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Therefore
resolved</hi>, That it is unwise, at
the present <lb/>
time, to pledge the public credit to
the extent re<lb break="no"/>quired by the resolution before the House."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p> That
amendment, he regretted
to say, was <lb/>
lost by a large majority, and by
the votes of <lb/>
many whose duty it was to have sustained it. <lb/>
It was true, that the impression
prevailed at <lb/>
the time, whether rightly
founded or not, that <lb/>
although the subvention for the
Annapolis <lb/>
line was included in the original
resolution, <lb/>
there was no serious intention of carrying it <lb/>
into effect; and some of those
who voted for it <lb/>
might have been influenced 
by that idea. <lb/>
Whether that was a sufficient
excuse for<lb/>
the action of any hon. gentleman
upon a<lb/>
question of such magnitude as this, was <lb/>
not for him to say.  If any such consider<lb break="no"/>
          
            <cb/>

ations controlled the votes of any
members <lb/>
of the house last year, he trusted such would <lb/>
not be the case on the present occasion, <lb/>
and that the people's representatives would <lb/>
consider well the consequences that would <lb/>
flow from the vote they were about to
give—a <lb/>
vote which must add enormously to the taxa<lb break="no"/>tion of the country.  When he
looked at the <lb/>
conduct of the gentlemen who were
now con<lb break="no"/>ducting the government of this
country—when <lb/>
he observed the reckless extravagance of their <lb/>
general policy, and contrasted it with their <lb/>
retrenchment pledges, and the course they <lb/>
pursued a few years ago, when in opposition—<lb/>
especially with regard to railways, he was in<lb break="no"/>clined to look with much suspicion
and dis<lb break="no"/>trust upon their present action
on this subject. <lb/>
What had produced a change so startling and
<lb/>
extreme?  If the government then in power <lb/>
had endeavoured to fasten upon the
resources <lb/>
of the province the liability which
is now <lb/>
sought to be imposed, those gentlemen
would <lb/>
have raised a howl of indignation throughout <lb/>
the whole  country.  He was curious, there<lb break="no"/>fore, to enquire into the
causes which <lb/>
had let to this sudden change of policy. <lb/>
To his mind there was only one satisfactory <lb/>
solution of the inconsistency of the adminis<lb break="no"/>tration, and their apparent desire
to plunge <lb/>
the country inextricably into debt.  They <lb/>
all knew that the members of the
present <lb/>
government were heart and soul
wrapped <lb/>
up in carrying to a successful termination the <lb/>
confederation of the British North American <lb/>
provinces, and that hitherto the
most powerful <lb/>
argument used by the opponents of that mea<lb break="no"/>sure was the increased taxation it would in<lb break="no"/>volve, and the necessity of raising our tariff <lb/>
from ten to twenty per cent.  Now, if they <lb/>
succeed in embarrassing the
finances of the <lb/>
country, if they succeed in burthening our <lb/>
resources with the enormous
debt the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion on the table of the house will
entail, so as <lb/>
to compel us to increase the taxation of the <lb/>
people by doubling our tariff,
they, at the same <lb/>
time do away with one of the principle objec<lb break="no"/>tions to their pet scheme of confederation.  It <lb/>
was hard to fathom the motives of these gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen, but it was clear they
were not govern<lb break="no"/>ed by a prudent regard to the best interests of<lb/>
the country.  Perhaps, also, a desire to secure<lb/>
the political favor of one or two western <lb/>
counties has something to do
with the ex<lb break="no"/>tension to Annapolis.  These were the <lb/>
only motives that suggested themselves to<lb/>
his mind for the
reckless course the govern<lb break="no"/>ment were now pursuing on this question.  <lb/>
When this subject was discussed
last session<lb/>
he had endeavored, feebly no doubt, but
to the<lb/>
best of his ability, to urge his views against<lb/>
the policy then
under consideration, because <lb/>
he keenly felt its injustice to those he
repre<lb break="no"/>sented. 
All he could say then had no effect in
<lb/>
deterring hon. gentlemen from the headlong <lb/>
course of extravagance they seemed deter<lb break="no"/>mined to pursue, and he supposed anything he <lb/>
might say now would be equally useless and<lb/>
unavailing.  He did not intend to go into fi<lb break="no"/>nancial matters, which had been so ably treat<lb break="no"/>ed by the learned leader of the Opposition—<lb/>
but he thought that any one who listened to <lb/>
the arguments of that hon. member—with a<lb/>
sincere desire to arrive at a correct conclusion <lb/>
—could not fail to be convinced of the correct<lb break="no"/>ness of the views he enunciated, and the wis<lb break="no"/>dom of the course he advocated.  That hon. 


            <pb n="286" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_286.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">286</fw> <fw type="num">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>

 gentleman,
with his usual ability had so clear<lb break="no"/>ly justified the attitude of opposition he had <lb/>
assumed to this resolution, and shown it to be <lb/>
the duty of every man who regarded the cre<lb break="no"/>dit and welfare of the country to oppose it, that <lb/>
it was unnecessary to go over the same ground. <lb/>
He could not, however, refrain from alluding <lb/>
to the impropriety of the course pursued by <lb/>
the government, in delaying the consideration <lb/>
of this important question—the most impor<lb break="no"/>tant, financially, that had engaged the atten<lb break="no"/>tion of the house—until this late period of the <lb/>
session, when some of the members had re<lb break="no"/>turned to their homes, and there was no pro<lb break="no"/>bability of its receiving that attention its im<lb break="no"/>portance demanded. Too much of the busi<lb break="no"/>ness of the house was done in that way. On <lb/>
the subject of railway extension, he would say <lb/>
that if the province was justified at all in <lb/>
entering upon any further expenditure, the <lb/>
line to the borders of New Brunswick, to con<lb break="no"/>nect with the railway system of the United <lb/>
States, should be the first to receive conside<lb break="no"/>ration, and he was not prepared to say if that <lb/>
had been proposed by itself, whether it would <lb/>
have received his opposition, provided he <lb/>
could be convinced the country could bear <lb/>
the burthen of its construction
with<lb break="no"/>out injury to other important services. <lb/>
But there certainly could be no doubt that the <lb/>
finances of this province would not admit of <lb/>
the construction of both lines at the same time <lb/>
even if they were admitted to be
necessary to <lb/>
the public convenience. With regard to the <lb/>
Annapolis line he could only look up it as an <lb/>
accomodation to one or two counties at the ex<lb break="no"/>pense of the whole province. Party necessity <lb/>
or political expediency might secure its con<lb break="no"/>struction, but those who helped to place this <lb/>
liability on their constituents would yet have <lb/>
to meet a day of reckoning. The Finl.
Sec. <lb/>
endeavoured to shew in supporting the Rail<lb break="no"/>way policy of the government that certain ser<lb break="no"/>vices could be cut down, some of them of the <lb/>
most vital consequence to the country. Thus <lb/>
admitting that we must hereafter
either lose <lb/>
our pubic grants or be more heavily taxed. <lb/>
He thought that if there was no other reason <lb/>
for opposition if the Finl. Secy. was obliged to <lb/>
admit that he could not expect to meet this <lb/>
expenditure, without depriving them of some <lb/>
of the most essential services the province re<lb break="no"/>quired, that of itself ought to be suffiicient <lb/>
reason to deter gentlemen from voting for this <lb/>
resolution and he begged them to be warned <lb/>
in time. He had promised not to
make any <lb/>
lengthy observations and he should not do so. <lb/>
He had risen principally to make these
expla<lb break="no"/>nations in consequence of the
position he <lb/>
had taken last year, and because the re<lb break="no"/>marks he then made had not been reported. <lb/>
He would ask gentlemen from all parts of
the <lb/>
province, and particularly these representing <lb/>
the more remote sections, whether they were <lb/>
prepared to assume the enormous liability <lb/>
this resolution proposed—a
liability which <lb/>
would cramp our resources, and weigh upon <lb/>
the industry and energies of our people for <lb/>
the next twenty years. He for one was not pre<lb break="no"/>pared to do so; and in voting against the reso<lb break="no"/>lution he considered he was
acting with a due <lb/>
regard to the interests of the whole province, <lb/>
and those especially who had elected him as<lb/>
their representative. The adoption of
this<lb/>
policy, it was
admitted, would lead either to <lb/>
the increase of the tariff or
the reduction of 

            <cb/>
 
 those grants which have been always consi<lb break="no"/>dered essential to the interests of the country. <lb/>
Their constituents might not complain until <lb/>
they experienced that result; but when rail<lb break="no"/>way interest had absorbed all the revenue, <lb/>
and nothing was left for roads, schools, navi<lb break="no"/>gation securities, or other services, gentlemen <lb/>
around these benches would then hear
their
<lb/>
reproaches. Instead of diminishing the grants <lb/>
to these sources as intimated by the Financial <lb/>
Secretary, he contended they should be in<lb break="no"/>creased from year to year with the increasing <lb/>
wants of the country. In that view of the case, <lb/>
then, he did not think it was wise or prudent, <lb/>
but on the contrary the most reckless
folly, to <lb/>
incur this heavy expenditure. He would
be <lb/>
ashamed to show himself among the people of <lb/>
Cape Breton, who are already so largely taxed <lb/>
for railways in Nova Scotia proper, from which <lb/>
they derive little benefit, if he voted for this <lb/>
resolution. He could be guilty of no greater <lb/>
injustice towards them than to add so largely <lb/>
to the railway burdens they now
so unjustly <lb/>
bear. In comparison with this question every <lb/>
other of a financial nature before them this <lb/>
winter was simply insignificant, and no small <lb/>
considerations should influence the course of <lb/>
gentlemen in regard to it. The hon. member <lb/>
concluded by referring to the haste with which <lb/>
this measure was pressed through the house. <lb/>
It took years before the Pictou railway bill <lb/>
was placed on the statute book; and here they <lb/>
were asked with scarcely any discussion on <lb/>
consideration, to pass a measure involving an <lb/>
annual liability of something like $230,000,
in <lb/>
addition to $360,000 which they would at least <lb/>
have to pay on the completion of the Pictou <lb/>
road. He trusted that gentlemen would
pause
<lb/>
before they committed themselves to this mea<lb break="no"/>sure, and would, at all events, wait until the <lb/>
Pictou road was completed before they incurred <lb/>
fresh liabilities—which he was convinced the <lb/>
province was not at present in a position to <lb/>
assume. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:BLAN2">Mr. BLANCHARD</persName>
said that he did not agree <lb/>
with the member for Richmond in his idea, <lb/>
that the government in
introducing this mea<lb break="no"/>sure were influenced by a desire to assist the <lb/>
confederation scheme. In his judgment, the <lb/>
       government, by taking this step, had put
con<lb break="no"/>federation out of the question for at least 20<lb/>
years to come. When these proposed lines of <lb/>
railway are completed, the debt of Nova Scotia <lb/>
will amount to $11,085,000 ; and if he under<lb break="no"/>stood anything about the terms agreed upon <lb/>
at the Quebec Conference, the
Province
was <lb/>
to be admitted into the Union with a debt of <lb/>
$8,000,000—anything beyond that was to be <lb/>
borne by the Province individually—and <lb/>
would have to be raised by direct taxation. <lb/>
Therefore he could not see that the govern<lb break="no"/>ment were serving the best interests of confe<lb break="no"/>deration by the introduction of this
measure. <lb/>
At this late period of the session, when
most <lb/>
of the members had returned to theirhomes, <lb/>
and those" who remained were not in the <lb/>
humor to listen to long
speeches, he did not <lb/>
intend to address the house at any very great <lb/>
length, but he would refer, shortly, to some of <lb/>
the remarks made by the honourable <lb/>
Financial Secretary.  That
honourable gen<lb break="no"/>tleman stated that he based his calculations <lb/>
upon the assumption that the revenue for this <lb/>year would be the same, if not larger, than the<lb/>
last.  On a former occasion he (Mr. B.) had <lb/>
made the assertion that at no time did our <lb/>
          



            <pb n="287" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_287.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">287</fw>

 commercial prospects look more gloomy
than <lb/>
at the present—and he had appealed to the <lb/>
hon. members for Richmond and
Halifax to <lb/>
say whether he was right. Neither of these <lb/>
gentlemen had ventured to endorse the state<lb break="no"/>ment of the Financial Secretary, because being <lb/>
engaged in trade themselves they knew his <lb/>
anticipations of an increased revenue were <lb/>
without foundation. According
to the calcu<lb break="no"/>lation of the member for Colchester (Mr. Arch<lb break="no"/>ibald) an additional burden of $400,000 a year <lb/>
will be placed upon the revenues of the pro<lb break="no"/>vince by the resolution now under
discussion. <lb/>
The member for Halifax (Mr.Tobin) makes <lb/>
out that the whole debt will be $11,085,000, and <lb/>
he calculates the interest at $500,000. How he <lb/>
arrived at that conclusion he (Mr. B.) was at a <lb/>
loss to imagine ; it certainly
was not at six per <lb/>
cent. By his own calculations
he made out <lb/>
the yearly liability to be $665,000
on the debt <lb/>
as stated by Mr. Tobin, and this, deducting the <lb/>
present debt, just agrees with Mr. Archibald's <lb/>
estimate. He would ask the house whether <lb/>
they were prepared to assume an
additional <lb/>
liability of $400,000 per annum
for twenty <lb/>
years to come? If the Financial
Secretary <lb/>
can demonstrate that the financial condition <lb/>
of the country will bear that enormous burden <lb/>
he should be surprised indeed.
How, he would <lb/>
ask, could the members for Cape Breton go <lb/>
back to their constituents and justify
them<lb break="no"/>selves for voting for this resolution which will <lb/>
put £20,000 additional every year upon them. <lb/>
The great cry in that island always had been <lb/>
that Nova Scotia swallowed up the whole <lb/>
revenue, and did not return to Cape Breton a <lb/>
fair share of what she contributed. He for one <lb/>
could not go back to his constituents and tell <lb/>
them that he had consented to put £20,000 <lb/>
more upon them to build a
railroad to Monc<lb break="no"/>ton and Annapolis. The hon. member for
<lb/>
Victoria (Mr. O. J. Campbell) denounced
the <lb/>
resolution introduced last year,
in the strong<lb break="no"/>est manner, in pretty much the same terms as <lb/>
he was then doing; but the
resolution of last <lb/>
year sank into utter insignificance when com<lb break="no"/>pared with those now on the table. When
it <lb/>
was considered that the Pictou railroad was <lb/>
going to cost £100,000 more than was antici<lb break="no"/>pated when it was commenced, he
did not <lb/>
envy the man who undertook to justify to the <lb/>
people of this country the increased
expendi<lb break="no"/>ture which it was proposed to make. He <lb/>
would be the last man to say, that.upon <lb/>
every public question, a
representative <lb/>
was to be bound and influenced
solely <lb/>
by the views of his constituents. It was <lb/>
his duty to regard the interests of the
whole <lb/>
country, but still, in a question
of this kind, it <lb/>
was proper that he should consider
whether <lb/>
he was justified in imposing this additional <lb/>
burden upon them. Any one who took the <lb/>
trouble to look into the statistics
on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject will find that Cape Breton.
paid into the <lb/>
revenue, for loyalty on coal,
$29,000 being ten <lb/>
thousand dollars more than Nova Scotia
pro<lb break="no"/>per, and yet this money is to be expended for <lb/>
the construction of a railroad to the
western <lb/>
part of the province. The Finl. Sec'y appear<lb break="no"/>ed to think that the large expenditure which <lb/>
is going on in Cape Breton will tend to in<lb break="no"/>crease the revenue. He (Mr. B.)
did not think<lb/>
that there was much in that
argument. If any <lb/>
reduction took place in the price of agricultural<lb/>
productions, she would lose more than could  <lb/>
be made up in that respect.  Cape Breton sent <lb/>
         

            <cb/>  

 to market, in
1863, a
million of pounds of but<lb break="no"/>ter; upon that article alone, if the
price re<lb break="no"/>mains as it is, which is about one half of what <lb/>
it was a short time ago, she
will lose $125,000. <lb/>
The advantages derived from the
expenditure <lb/>
of capital in Cape Breton will be more
than<lb/>
counterbalanced by the loss she
will sustain <lb/>
in the price of agricultural productions. The<lb/>
Finl. Sec'y admits that we will incur a liability<lb/>
of $323,000.  Now he would ask
the house to <lb/>
look these figures in the face. 
He
would ask <lb/>
the members for Cape Breton if they were <lb/>
prepared to assume a liability of $323,000
in <lb/>
addition to the sum already borne
by the re<lb break="no"/>venue?</p>
           
 <p>        
The Pro. Sec. says the tariff must be
increas<lb break="no"/>ed in order to provide for the increased expen<lb break="no"/>diture upon the public works.  What a com<lb break="no"/>mentary upon the course pursued by that hon. <lb/>
gentleman a few years ago.  The government <lb/>
then to meet a temporary
emergency were <lb/>
forced to increase the tariff.  Did the Financial <lb/>
Secretary agree to that?  On the contrary he <lb/>
denounced the government and appealed to <lb/>
the country with the cry that this reckless and <lb/>
extravagant government, instead of
retrench<lb break="no"/>ing their expenses, were going to increase the <lb/>
burdens of  the people by adding
to the duties <lb/>
they would have to pay.  He and those asso<lb break="no"/>ciated with him succeeded in frightening the
<lb/>
people for the time, and he attained the object <lb/>
he had in view.  But what did he propose to <lb/>
do now—instead of carrying out the retrench<lb break="no"/>ment he then advocated, he proposes
to add <lb/>
this additional burden of $323,000
a year to our <lb/>
present liabilities and to increase the tariff as <lb/>
well. He also said that there
were certain <lb/>
public services which will not require the as<lb break="no"/>sistance they now receive; and first of all
he
<lb/>
proposes to reduce the grant for navigation <lb/>
securities from $49,000 to $5,000.  If the people <lb/>
of this province will agree to that reduction he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) would be much astonished.  Then <lb/>
again he said the St. Peter's Canal would be <lb/>
finished and that expenditure
would be saved. <lb/>
He was at a loss to know how
that could be <lb/>
the case.  That work would certainly not be <lb/>
completed before this liability would accrue. <lb/>
It was rather singular that
the Financial Se<lb break="no"/>cretary,  in his present retrenchment scheme, <lb/>
should have hit upon the same
figures as the <lb/>
hon. Provincial Secretary used a few years <lb/>
ago; or, at all events, should have arrived at <lb/>
the same result.  He is going to save $80,000 a <lb/>
year—just as the hon.Provincial Secretary in<lb break="no"/>tended to do before he got into office; but the
<lb/>
tables are turned now—he has got into power <lb/>
and not a word is heard about reducing the <lb/>
salaries of public officers. 
His plan now is to <lb/>
reduce the grant to navigation securities and <lb/>
other important services.</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCDO4">Hon. FINL. SEC</persName>.—The only reduction pro<lb break="no"/>posed is with respect to those grants which<lb/>
will terminate in this present session.</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BLAN2">Mr. BLANCHARD</persName>—Then the idea appears to <lb/>
have been to get as much as possible
this ses<lb break="no"/>sion, so that none will be wanted next. year. <lb/>
He agreed entirely with the
member for Ha<lb break="no"/>lifax (Mr. Tobin), in
his
remarks as to the ad<lb break="no"/>vantages of railway extension, but he did not<lb/>
agree with him in some of the
calculations he<lb/>
had made—when
he talked about the saving<lb/>
that was effected by railroad travel, and
put it<lb/>
down at a dollar a day—he forgot that many <lb/>
  of these passengers did not go further
than the<lb/>
four mile <choice><sic>honse</sic><corr>house</corr></choice>, or to Bedford—and
it could not

            <pb n="288" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-04-20_Page_288.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">288</fw> <fw type="num">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>

be said of them that they saved that
much. The <lb/>
Hon Finl. Sec. undertook to prove that the <lb/>
member for Colchester was wrong in his state<lb break="no"/>ment that a larger expenditure would be re<lb break="no"/>quired for the future, for the maintenance
of <lb/>
the railroads, than had been necessary in
the <lb/>
past. Upon referring to the returns he found <lb/>
that the cost of maintenance had been steadily <lb/>
increasing year by year. He would be the <lb/>
last person to alarm people as to the state of <lb/>
the railroads, but every body knew that every <lb/>
year the roads necessarily became more worn <lb/>
out, and required repair. In 1861, the cost of <lb/>
maintenance amounted to $34,000;
in 1862, <lb/>
$37,000. In '63, $47,000, and in the nine months <lb/>
of 1864 $50,000. He did not
wish to detain the <lb/>
House much longer, but he would give them a <lb/>
few figures shewing what Cape Breton would <lb/>
have to pay towards the railway system <lb/>
of Nova Scotia. She would be required to <lb/>
pay one-fifth of the whole debt—or $128,000.
<lb/>
The hon. member for Halifax talked about <lb/>
mud roads as if they were of no consequence <lb/>
at all. If he represented a country constitu<lb break="no"/>ency he would find it a matter of a little more <lb/>
importance then he seemed to think it now. <lb/>
He is only willing to give us $100,000
for what <lb/>
he calls mud roads, but is perfectly ready to <lb/>
vote $556,000 a year for iron
roads. Now he <lb/>
(Mr. B.) would yield to no man, in his opinion <lb/>
as to the importance of railroads to a country, <lb/>
but if they were only to be obtained by sacrifi<lb break="no"/>cing the common roads which were of so much <lb/>
importance to the great mass of the people he <lb/>
would be inclined to pause,
before incurring <lb/>
any greater liability. At all events he could <lb/>
not see how any one could doubt the propriety <lb/>
of adopting the course proposed by the mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Colchester, to wait for a twelve month,<lb/>
and see how affairs looked then, we would <lb/>
then be able to ascertain how much the Pictou <lb/>
road was actually going to cost. At present that <lb/>
was uncertain. He had had a conversation <lb/>
with contractors who had been employed on <lb/>
the Truro road and they laughed at the idea of <lb/>
its being built for two millions of dollars. Un<lb break="no"/>der these circumstances as a member of the <lb/>
house, and a representative from Cape Breton <lb/>
he was not prepared to authorize the enormous <lb/>
expenditure contemplated by the resolution <lb/>
before the house and he should
vote against <lb/>
them. <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-04-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p> FRIDAY, April 21. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> The adjourned debate on
the <unclear n="Should be 'railway'">railwvy</unclear> reso<lb break="no"/>lution was resumed. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Hon. ATTY.
GEN. said—I do not intend to <lb/>
address the house at any very great length <lb/>
upon this question, but I cannot allow the ob<lb break="no"/>servations of the hon. leader of the opposition <lb/>
to pass unanswered. This is a
subject with <lb/>
which every gentleman in
this house is so well <lb/>
acquainted, that I think it is hardly necessary <lb/>
to direct attention back for the last eleven<lb/>
years in order to ascertain the policy of'
the <lb/>
house on the subject of
railways. The idea of <lb/>
building a railroad to Annapolis dates as far <lb/>
back as 1854, when the country was led to be<lb break="no"/>lieve that for a million of money they were <lb/>
going to have railway communication from <lb/>
Halifax to the Gulf of' St.Lawrence on the <lb/>
one hand, and the waters of the Bay of Fundy <lb/>
on the other. In fact, in
all
discussions upon <lb/>
the subject, the people were
educated up to <lb/>
the belief that for the
small amount I
have <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p> PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> named, the points referred to could be
reached.<lb/>
The experience of a few years, however, soon<lb/>
dissipated that idea; and although the
policy<lb/>
has partially failed for want of
means, yet the<lb/>
house remained pledged to carry on these im<lb break="no"/>portant works so soon as the finances of the <lb/>
country would admit.  It was, therefore, no <lb/>
new policy that the government introduced <lb/>
last year, but one that was initiated and ap<lb break="no"/>proved of years ago.  Such. then, being the <lb/>
case, it is not for us now to consider the cor<lb break="no"/>rectness or incorrectness of the idea.  The <lb/>
country at that time was divided upon the <lb/>
question of building railways.  Some
thought
<lb/>
it inadvisable to embark in the enterprise at <lb/>
all; some were in favor of
their being built by <lb/>
government; whilst others—and they
formed a
<lb/>
large section of this house and
of the country <lb/>
—were in favor of their
construction by private <lb/>
companies under legislative subventions. <lb/>
Those who were opposed altogether to rail<lb break="no"/>roads formed but a small class in the country, <lb/>
and I am happy to find that one of the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of that section has at length given <lb/>
in his adhesion to the system, and approves of <lb/>
their construction under the policy first inau<lb break="no"/>gurated.  As to whether that is
the best sys<lb break="no"/>tem or not it is unnecessary to advert in the <lb/>
present discussion; that question was settled <lb/>
last year, and nothing has since occurred to <lb/>
alter the position of affairs.  The only point, <lb/>
then, that now arises for consideration is the <lb/>
question as to whether the finances of the pro<lb break="no"/>vince are in a condition to warrant the con<lb break="no"/>struction of these works in the modified form <lb/>
proposed by the resolution now
before the <lb/>
house. </p>
            <p>There are many considerations to be thought
<lb/>
of in connection with this subject, but
the pa<lb break="no"/>ramount one is to keep up the
credit of the <lb/>
country and to maintain mviolate the
good
<lb/>
faith of the province.  If we can do this, then <lb/>
I think we are warranted in going on with <lb/>
these works.  In the consideration of this ques<lb break="no"/>tion I intend principally to refer to the opposi<lb break="no"/>tion given to it by the hon.
member for South <lb/>
Colchester (Mr. Archibald) and to the course <lb/>
he has thought proper to pursue; and I cannot <lb/>
avoid saying that the position taken by
that
<lb/>
hon. gentleman, in regard to one or two other <lb/>
important subjects to which he had been pre<lb break="no"/>viously committed, has rather astonished me. <lb/>
In regard to the School Bill, for instance, no <lb/>
one was more thoroughly committed to that <lb/>
measure by his action
last
session than the <lb/>
hon. gentleman; in fact, he
went even further <lb/>
than the views of the government on the sub-
<lb break="maybe"/>
uject; while this year he has
adopted a policy <lb/>
totally inconsistent with the
course he then <lb/>
pursued.  I think that hon. gentleman ought <lb/>
to have more regard for the position he occu- <lb break="maybe"/>
ies as leader of the opposition than to come <lb/>
here, as he did yesterday, and, in
relation to <lb/>
this question, admit that he
had made such <lb/>
gross mistakes in his
calculations; and my <lb/>
hon. friend the Financial Secretary was quite <lb/>
justified in the remark that it was highly cul<lb break="no"/>pable in one occupying his position
to found <lb/>
arguments upon a subject to which he confess<lb break="no"/>ed he had not given that consideration
which <lb/>
its importance demanded.  He has given evi<lb break="no"/>dence upon other occasions, of
his power to<lb/>
sift and analyze financial statements; and<lb/>
there is no doubt that, if he
had had the incli<lb break="no"/>nation, he was quite competent to ascertain,<lb/>
what amount the government had in hand at
<lb/>
            </p>-->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>