<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNSLA_1866-03-01" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-03-01">1 March 1866</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA">
               
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
               
               
               <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Third Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
               
               
               <date when="1866"/>.  
               
               
               <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
               
               <biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="29"/>.
            </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-03-01_Page_029.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-10-26">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="DLANG4" when="2017-10-30">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-03-01_Page_029">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-01_Page_029.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="29" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-03-01_Page_029.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">29</fw>
            <p>
     [...] thing else they put their hands to, death fol<lb break="no"/>lowed their efforts. He hoped the present Go<lb break="no"/>vernment would act more consistently with 
     <lb/>
     their duties and interests. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Also a petition from Rev. John Shaw and a 
     <lb/>
     large number of others asking a special grant 
     <lb/>
     to make a road across Cape Smokey which, 
     <lb/>
     he said, was a mountain dividing the county 
     <lb/>
     into two sections. The members in their ap<lb break="no"/>propriations had not been able to give it the 
     <lb/>
     necessary attention, and the barrier formed by 
     <lb/>
     the mountain was so great that travellers were 
     <lb/>
     obliged to lead their horses on one side or the 
     <lb/>
     other which was a great inconvenience to the 
     <lb/>
     two large settlements growing up in that lo<lb break="no"/>cality. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO6">Mr. S. McDONNELL</persName> presented a petition 
     <lb/>
     from Chetticamp, asking the establishment of 
     <lb/>
     a ferry across Little River. He said that some 
     <lb/>
     individuals had hitherto been in the habit of 
     <lb/>
     crossing the river in a boat or scow without 
     <lb/>
     any remuneration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. laid on the table a return 
     <lb/>
     from the Halifax Poor's Asylum, which was 
     <lb/>
     referred to the Committee on Humane Institu<lb break="no"/>tions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCKA1">Mr. MCKAY</persName> presented a petition from the 
     <lb/>
     Postmaster of West River, asking for an in<lb break="no"/>crease of salary, but subsequently withdrew it 
     <lb/>
     for transmission to the Post Master General in 
     <lb/>
     accordance with the practice of last session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:COWI2">Mr. COWIE</persName> presented a petition from an aged 
     <lb/>
     teacher. The petition was referred to the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee on Education. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Also a petition from a person who had in<lb break="no"/>curred expenditure on certain roads while 
     <lb/>
     holding the office of light-house keeper. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO6">Mr. S. MCDONNELL</persName> presented a petition for 
     <lb/>
     an increase of salary of the Postmaster at Ma<lb break="no"/>bou, but the hon gentleman withdrew it for 
     <lb/>
     reference to the Postmaster-General. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

     <div type="section">           
     <head rendition="simple:centre">CONFEDERATION.</head>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> said that in anticipation of a dis<lb break="no"/>cussion upon a highly important subject, he 
     <lb/>
     wished to ask the government to lay on the table 
     <lb/>
     a comparative Return showing the amount oi 
     <lb/>
     revenue derivable under a Canadian Tariff' for 
     <lb/>
     articles chargeable under such a tariff. He inti<lb break="no"/>mated that some difficulty might arise in furnish<lb break="no"/>ing an exact return, but it would be useful as 
     <lb/>
     furnishing information. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV SECRETARY</persName> said he was entirely 
     <lb/>
     ready to afford any information or submit any 
     <lb/>
     document in possession of the Government, but 
     <lb/>
    he did not understand that he was under any 
     <lb/>obligation to furnish such a return as that asked. 
     <lb/>The hon. member asking it had held the office of 
     <lb/>Financial Secretary and was as well acquainted 
     <lb/>with all the papers necessary to the compilation 
     <lb/>as any officer of the Government, and had them 
     <lb/>as entirely under his control. If such a course 
     <lb/>were adopted as that required the greatest obstruc<lb break="no"/>tions would be occasioned. He would submit the 
     <lb/>request to his colleagues, but it appeared to him at 
     <lb/>the first blush to be asking for something outside 
     <lb/>of what it was usual or the government to 
     <lb/>furnish. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> said he differed from the Provin<lb break="no"/>cial Secretary in the remark made to the effect 
     <lb/>
     that the papers were as open to him as to the 
     <lb/>
    Government. He would remind the House that 
     <lb/>the papers had not been laid on the table, and no 
     <lb/>

    
            <cb/>
           
     member, therefore, was in a position to prepare 
     <lb/>
     such a statement as the one asked for ; he did 
     <lb/>
     not see why the Government should shrink from 
     <lb/>
     furnishing such information. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SECRETARY</persName> said that one very 
     <lb/>
     serious objection had been thrown out by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member himself when he intimated that there 
     <lb/>
     would be some difficulty in furnishing an accu<lb break="no"/>rate return, and that the answer must necessarily 
     <lb/>
     be hypothetical. The statement, if prepared, 
     <lb/>
     would admit of discussion as to whether it was 
     <lb/>
     correct and judicious, as the materials did not ex<lb break="no"/>ist for giving an entire analysis. It was therefore 
     <lb/>
     throwing a scarcely legitimate duty upon the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, and as to the observation that the ne<lb break="no"/>cessary papers were not on the table, that difficul<lb break="no"/>ty would probably be removed on the following 
     <lb/>
     day when his colleague who had taken charge of 
     <lb/>
     the Financial Secretary's department would be 
     <lb/>
     prepared to submit the documents furnishing the 
     <lb/>
     necessary data. If such a return were furnished, 
     <lb/>
     instead of its being what a public document 
     <lb/>
     should be-so exact as to command confidence— 
     <lb/>
     a great deal of difference of opinion might arise 
     <lb/>
     upon its merits. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> replied, that no difficulty had 
     <lb/>
     been found in New Brunswick in furnishing this 
     <lb/>
     information, and he did not see why the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should put itself in the position of being 
     <lb/>
     confessedly unable to submit documents which 
     <lb/>
     the Government of the other Province submitted 
     <lb/>
     without hesitation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> enquired what the house had to do 
     <lb/>
     with the Canadian Tariff. If any gentleman was 
     <lb/>
     desirous of addressing the House or the public on 
     <lb/>
     the subject of Confederation, and thought he was 
     <lb/>
     in a position to draw an argument from that 
     <lb/>
     source with advantage, he could go to work and 
     <lb/>
     contrast the public documents and the revenue 
     <lb/>
     laws, the exportations and the consumptions, 
     <lb/>
     without applying to the Government. He did not 
     <lb/>
     rise for the purpose of objecting to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment furnishiug the desired information, but he 
     <lb/>
     thought it a question which no Government 
     <lb/>
     should be bound to answer. This he considered 
     <lb/>
     the introduction of the question of a Union of 
     <lb/>
     British North America in an indirect manner, and 
     <lb/>
     if it were so understood and a discussion were to 
     <lb/>
     follow, he could not shrink from expressing the 
     <lb/>
     opinion he always held Every man looking at the 
     <lb/>
     condition of the British North American Provin<lb break="no"/>ces, must come to the conclusion, that they could 
     <lb/>
     not long remain in their present position. This 
     <lb/>
     was seen and felt in the House, where things had 
     <lb/>
     greatly changed in the progress of six or seven 
     <lb/>
    years. (Mr. Annand here rose to order.) Mr. 
     <lb/>Tobin continued, arguing that the object in mak<lb break="no"/>ing the request was to show that a Union with 
     <lb/>Canada would result in overtaxation, but would 
     <lb/>the Canadian Tariff be the tariff of the United 
     <lb/>Provinces? When the men representing all the 
     <lb/>Colonies met together, they would no doubt frame 
     <lb/>a new tariff with wisdom. If the Government 
     <lb/>chose to furnish the information and to employ 
     <lb/>their clerks in preparing this return it would be 
     <lb/>their own business, but he thought it could be 
     <lb/>done as well by any hon. member. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Tha subject then dropped. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>