<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1865-02-10"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-02-10">10 February 1865</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          
         
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Second Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
                    

          <date when="1865"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="4"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="6"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-02-10_Page_004.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1865-02-10_Page_006.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-21">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-02-10_Page_004">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-10_Page_004.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1865-02-10_Page_006">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-10_Page_006.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="4" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-10_Page_004.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">4</fw> <fw type="num">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES.</fw>

<!-- GL, 2017-03-15, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

           <!-- <p> which may be suggested in the Act for the
bet<lb break="no"/>ter encouragement of Education—a
subject so <lb/>
deeply interesting and important to the whole <lb/>
country. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> It is gratifying to know that
the—Extension <lb/>
of the Railway to Pictou has been placed un<lb break="no"/>der contract, and will be carried on with des- <lb break="maybe"/>
patch. <lb/>
            </p>
 
            <p> We will give due consideration to any
pro<lb break="no"/>posals for the construction of the Lines pro<lb break="no"/>vided for in the resolution which passed both <lb/>
Branches of the Legislature last Session. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The Report upon St. Peter's Canal will
ob<lb break="no"/>tain our careful examination. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Fully impressed with the obvious
necessity <lb/>
of making adequate provision for the unfor<lb break="no"/>tunate Insane, we will be prepared to discharge <lb/>
that duty in an efficient manner. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> We are gratified to learn that all the vari<lb break="no"/>ous sources of Provincial Income evidence <lb/>
such a high degree of prosperity ; and for these <lb/>
mercies, together with the blessings of continu<lb break="no"/>ed peace, we desire to return our grateful <lb/>
thanks to the Bountiful Giver of all good. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> In viewing this address, Mr. Speaker, I
feel <lb/>
assured that it will meet the support of every <lb/>
member in this House. I cannot
see that it <lb/>
will, in the slightest manner, compromise my <lb/>
views or action on any question. We are com<lb break="no"/>mitted to nothing but the provision for the ex<lb break="no"/>tension of the Hospital, the
Militia service and <lb/>
to the International Exhibition in Dublin.. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On the great question of the Union, you
will <lb/>
all admit, that less could not have been said, <lb/>
and more might have been unwise. It is <lb/>
the intention of the Government to leave the <lb/>
subject as open as possible, and to the free <lb/>
action of any member of Government and <lb/>
members generally. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. WHITMAN seconded the answer. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The Address was allowed to lie on the
table. <lb/>
The House adjourned until three o'clock the <lb/>
next day.<lb/>
            </p>-->

<div type="section">

            <head> FRIDAY, 10th Feb. <lb/>
            </head>



            <p> ANSWER
TO THE ADDRESS. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p> The House met at three o'clock. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The Answer to the Address was taken up, <lb/>
and read clause by clause.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:LOCK1">Mr. LOCKE</persName> said, in reference to the clause <lb/> touching
                  upon the Union of the Colonies, that <lb/> it did not commit any one on the
                  question. <lb/> Every one was, of course, left perfectly free to <lb/> deal with
                  it as his judgment should dictate, <lb/> when all the papers connected with it
                  were <lb/> before the House. He thought it necessary to <lb/> say this in order
                  that the country might under<lb break="no"/>stand the position of gentlemen. .
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> (who was only heard with <lb/> the greatest
                  difficulty) said that the proper <lb/> time, of course, for discussing the
                  question <lb/> referred to, would be when all the papers <lb/> were before the
                  House. All the House was <lb/> asked to do at present was to promise that <lb/>
                  every question should receive their deliberate <lb/> consideration when it came in
                  due form before <lb/> them. In looking over the Speech, he found <lb/> that the
                  only measure promised, was one con<lb break="no"/>nected with Edugation. He would
                  take this<lb/> opportunity of calling attention to the fact <lb/> that he had last
                  session foretold some of the <lb/> difficulties, that would probably arise from
                  <lb/> some features of the bill, to which he objectcd <lb/> at the time. He had
                  particularly urged the <lb/> appointment of a Council of Public Instruction <lb/>
                  <cb/> which was not composed of the members of the <lb/> Executive. Council. He
                  had also said that, at <lb/> all events, if the Government were not willing <lb/>
                  to go as far as he wished, they should place at <lb/> the head of the Council of
                  Public Instruction <lb/> the Lieutenant Governor, as his presence <lb/> would give
                  to the country the guarantee that <lb/> mere party considerations would not always
                  <lb/> prevail. He now begged the Government to <lb/> consider carefully in any
                  amendments to the <lb/> bill they might introduce, the propriety of <lb/> avoiding
                  even the semblance of suspicion that <lb/> party influences prevailed in
                  Educational mat<lb break="no"/>ters. He congratulated the country on the <lb/>
                  encouraging statements made in the speech,- <lb/> that our revenue was very large,
                  and all our <lb/> branches of industry prosperous to an unpar<lb break="no"
                  />alleled extent. Every gentleman, whatever <lb/> his political prejudices, would
                  learn this fact <lb/> with the deepest satisfaction.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. Stewart Campbell</persName> said that he per<lb break="no"/>fectly
                  concurred with those gentlemen who <lb/> had spoken of this Answer to the Address
                  as <lb/> being entirely non-committal in its character. <lb/> Notwithstanding he
                  held very strong opinions <lb/> on the subject of the Union of the Colonies, he
                  <lb/> felt that he had no difficulty whatever in giv<lb break="no"/>ing his
                  concurrence to the Answer. He em<lb break="no"/>phatically stated that he wished
                  it to be at <lb/> once un erstood that he did not endorse the <lb/> action of the
                  Government in sending a delega<lb break="no"/>tion to Quebec. The house had put
                  upon its <lb/> journals last session a resolution authorizing <lb/> the Government
                  to appoint delegates in refer<lb break="no"/>ence to a Union of the Maritime
                  Provinces. <lb/> Authority, however, had been granted from <lb/> some quarter to
                  those delegates to go beyond <lb/> the misson entrusted to them by the Legislas
                  <lb/> ture. Therefore, although he concurred in the <lb/> answer to the address,
                  he wished to guard him<lb break="no"/>self from having it sup posed that he at all
                     en<lb break="no"/>dorsed the act of the Government in sending <lb/> a
                  delegation to Quebec. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p> The answer to the address then passed <hi rendition="simple:italic">nem<lb/>
            eon.</hi> <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">The PROVINCIAL SECRETARY</persName> stated that<lb/> His Excellency the
                  Lieutenant Governor would <lb/> be ready to receive the answer on Monday <lb/>
                  next at half-past one. It was therefore agreed <lb/> that the whole house should
                  present the an<lb break="no"/>swer at that hour. <lb/>
               </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head> REVISING COMMITTEE. </head>
<p>
On motion of the Hon. Prov. Secy., the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing Committee was appointed to select <lb/>
Standing Committees of the House :-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Prov. Secretary, Mr. Blanchard, Hon. <lb/>
Attorney General, Mr. Locke, Mr. Kiliam, Mr.  <lb/>
Archibald, and Mr. Tobin. <lb/> 
sMr. BOURINOT would suggest to.
the Revi<lb break="no"/>sing Committee that they should place upon.<lb/>
the Committee gentlemen who would fairly <lb/>
represent all sections of the
Province. Hither<lb break="no"/>to that rule had not been observed with that <lb/>
strictness which was absolutely requisite
in or<lb break="no"/>der to perform the business of the country as <lb/>
it should be. He had had occasion in pre= <lb/>
vious sessions to suggest changes
in this par<lb break="no"/>ticular, and he hoped that the gentleman
who <lb/>
represented Cape Breton on the
Committee<lb/>
would take care that justice was done to that<lb/>
section in which he ought to be
especially in<lb break="no"/>terested.<lb/> 
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BLAN2">Mr. BLANCHARD</persName> said that hitherto the great <lb/> difficulty had
                  been to find gentletnen willing <lb/> to serve on the committees after they had
                  been [...] </p>


            <pb n="6" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1865-02-10_Page_006.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">6</fw> <fw type="num">PARLIAMENTARY DEBTAES.</fw>
            
<p> The
petitions were allowed to lie on the ta<lb break="no"/>ble. <lb/></p>

</div>

<div type="section">
<head>PETITIONS. </head>


            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:LOCK1">Mr. LOCKE</persName>  called the attention of the Go<lb break="no"
                  />vernment to a petition which he held in his <lb/> hand from the inhabitants of
                  the county of <lb/> Shelburne,for a road connection with the Coun<lb break="no"
                  />ty of Annapolis. As the Government intend<lb break="no"/>ed building a railroad
                  to Annapolis, the inha<lb break="no"/>bitants of Shelburne naturally wished to
                  have <lb/> better means of communication with the fine <lb/> agricultural county
                  of Annapolis than they <lb/> now possessed. He believed, if the Union of <lb/> the
                  Colonies was consummated, that Shelhurne <lb/> might become one of the great
                  outlets of trade. <lb/> (Laughter.) All the people asked was an ex<lb break="no"
                  />penditure of $20,000 or $30,000. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BOUR5">Mr. BOURINOT</persName> would suggest that the peti<lb break="no"/>tion
                  lay on the table until such time as the An<lb break="no"/>napolis Railway was
                  completed. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. said that the petition was <lb/> deserving of
                  consideration; but it should he <lb/> sent, in accordance with the rules of the
                  House, <lb/> to the Financial Secretary. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KILL2">Mr. KILLAM</persName> though it would be as well to <lb/> understand
                  whether a petition rom the people <lb/>
               </p>
            <p> askhw for aid towards some particular object <lb/>
should be discussed by the
House, or go first <lb/>
to the Government. As it was now, if the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment did not choose to accede to the <lb/>
prayer of a petition there was
an end of it.- <lb/> nothing was heard about it. He thought it best <lb/>
that every petition should come
first before the <lb/>
House, who might send it to a Committee or to <lb/>
the Government. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. said that he did not see the <lb/> use of
                  interfering now with an established rule <lb/> of the House. If any gentleman
                  considered <lb/> that the Government had not treated any peti<lb break="no"/>tion
                  presented to them as it deserved, it was <lb/> always in his power to move for its
                  production, <lb/> and test the opinion of the House on the sub<lb break="no"
                  />ject. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:LOCK1">Mr. LOCKE</persName> said he would place the pe<lb break="no"/>tition in
                  the hands of the Government, with the<lb/> hope that they would give it that
                  favorable <lb/> consideration which it deserved. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. FIN. SECRETARY</persName> stated that it was his <lb/> intention to
                  publish the petitions handed to <lb/> him, when they made up any number. <lb/>
               </p>
 
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> said that if any gentleman <lb/> wished, he
                  could always call the attention of <lb/> the Government in the house to any
                     particu<lb break="no"/>lar petition in which he felt an interest, and <lb/>
                  then hand it to the Financial Secretary. He <lb/> had no doubt that if a road
                  could be made as <lb/> asked for in the petition in question, a great <lb/> boom
                  would be conferred on the county of <lb/> Shelburne.<lb/>
               </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head> DESPATCH. <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. PROV. SECRETARY</persName> laid on the table <lb/> despatches
                  relative to the appointment of Hon. <lb/> Mr. Johnston as Equity Judge, Hon. W. A.
                  <lb/> Henry as Attorney General, and Hon. J. W. <lb/> Ritchie as Solitcitor
                  General, and member of <lb/> the Executive Council.<lb/>
               </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head> POST OFFICE REPORT. <lb/>
            </head>



            <p>
                  <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName> laid on the table the An<lb break="no"/>nual
                  Report of the Postmaster General. This <lb/> report, the hon. gentleman stated,
                  was most sa<lb break="no"/>tisfactory. Notwithstanding there had been an<lb/>
                  increase of expenditure entailed by the recom<lb break="no"/>mendations of the
                  Post Office Report, the defi<lb break="no"/>ciency in the Departinent was less
                  than during <lb/>
                  <cb/> the previous year. 7 new Post Offices, and 51 <lb/> Way Offices had been
                  provided for Only 3 <lb/> Way Offices had been closed. The number of <lb/> letters
                  carried through the Post Office was <lb/> 1,535,864, being an increase of 66,408
                  over the <lb/> previous year. The number of newspapers <lb/> was 3,941,115, or an
                  increase of 276,793 over <lb/> 1863. 20 new mail routes had been established,
                  <lb/> and 8 closed, - making a balance of 12 estab<lb break="no"/>lished. The
                  number of mail routes was 4,473. <lb/> The amount derived from postage-stamps was
                  <lb/>$48,576, being an increase of over $5,000 over<lb/> 1863. 5 unregistered
                  money letters lost, and <lb/> 3 registered, said to be tampered with. The <lb/>
                  net revenue for 1864 was $.56,207.61, being an <lb/> increase of $8,032.90 over
                  the previous year.- <lb/> The expenditure was $73,163.61, an increase of <lb/>
                  only $2,774.53, whilst the increase of revenue <lb/> was $8,032.90 Hence the
                  deficit was $5,258.37 <lb/>less than the previous year. The amount of <lb/>
                  money-orders on Great Britian was $20,000; <lb/> the amount passing through the
                  Province, <lb/> $120,000. The commissions on money orders <lb/> amounted to
                  $1,120.44: the business in money <lb/> orders has nearly doubled since 1863, and
                  a<lb/> large additional amount of labor is therefore<lb/> entailed upon the person
                  in charge. Under <lb/> these circumstances, the Postmaster General <lb/> asks for
                  an increase of salary for Mr. Thomp<lb break="no"/>son-from $800 to $1, 000 a
                  year. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p> The petition was referred to the Post Office <lb/>
Committee. <lb/>
            </p>


</div>

<div type="section">

            <head> INFORMATION
ASKED FOR<lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> asked the Government to lay on <lb/> the table at
                  an early day, returns exhibiting <lb/> the extent and nature of the trade of the
                     Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces of Canada, New Brunswick, and Prince <lb/> Edward
                  Island, and Newfoundland, including <lb/> a statement showing the value of public
                     pro<lb break="no"/>perty, including railways, steamers, public <lb/> buildings,
                  &amp;c., including all property that <lb/> would he transferred to the General
                     Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in ease of the proposed Union of the Co<lb
                     break="no"/>lonies being consummated.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. PROV. SECRETARY</persName> recognized at once <lb/> the propriety of
                  the Government being able <lb/> to place before the house all the information
                  <lb/> they possibly could in reference to a question <lb/> of such magnitude, but
                  he was afraid that his <lb/> hon. friend had imposed a task which to some <lb/>
                  extent it would he difficult to perform. It <lb/> would be difficult in the case
                  of this province<lb/> and New Brunsuick—to give an  accurate esti<lb break="no"
                  />mate of some of the public property, the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment House for
                  instance . <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> thought there would be some <lb/> difficulty in
                  procuring a reliable statement, <lb/> such as that asked for, from some of the
                     pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, more especially that of Newfoundland.<lb/> He
                  observed that so far as  Canada was con<lb/> cerned the information sought was
                  easily ob<lb break="no"/>tainable.<lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> said that his reason for asking <lb/> for the
                  information was that he had heard <lb/> gentlemen complain that they had not the
                     ma<lb break="no"/>terials within their reach to enable them to <lb/> take up
                  this question, and deal with it as it <lb/> should be dealt with. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BOUR5">Mr. BOURINOT</persName> suggested that the informa<lb break="no"/>tion
                  sought be furnished by the hon. member <lb/> for Colehester, (Mr. Archibald,) who
                  appeared <lb/> to have collected a great variety of statistics<lb/> on the subject
                  of a Union. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> pointed out that a great <lb/> deal of the
                  information required could be ob [..] </p>
    </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>