<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1867-03-16"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1867-03-16">16 March 1867</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA">
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
<date when="1867"/>.  
<pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_002.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_003.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_004.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-06-05">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_001">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_002">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_002.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_003">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_003.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_004">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_004.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_001.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1</fw>

<head rendition="simple:centre">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS<lb/>
   
     OF THE 
     <lb/>
 
     HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY OF NOVA SCOTIA. 
     <lb/>
 1867.</head>


            <head rendition="simple:right">SATURDAY, March 16.</head>


            <p>
     At 2 o'clock p. m. the Speaker took the 
     <lb/>
     chair of the house, and the gentleman Usher of 
     <lb/>
     the Black Rod shortly afterwards announced 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency the Lieutenant Governor's 
     <lb/>
     command for the attendance of the house in 
     <lb/>
     the Council Chamber.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The members having attended in obedience 
     <lb/>
     to this command His Excellency opened the 
     <lb/>
     session with the following 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SPEECH : 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. President, and Honorable Gentlemen of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Council:</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of 
     <lb/>
     Assembly:</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In meeting you at a most important epoch 
     <lb/>
     in the affairs of British North America, it af<lb break="no"/>fords me much pleasure to be able to congra<lb break="no"/>tulate you on the continued peace and prospe<lb break="no"/>rity of the Province during the past year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     While these colonies have been subjected to 
     <lb/>
     the threats of lawless men, our Province has 
     <lb/>
     been exempted from any attack, and although 
     <lb/>
     our local forces nobly responded to the call 
     <lb/>
     which was made upon them in the early part 
     <lb/>
     of the year to arm for the purposes of defence, 
     <lb/>
     happily no necessity occurred to require their 
     <lb/>
     services to repel an invader. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The exigencies of the Province of New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick rendering it necessary for a time 
     <lb/>
     to withdraw a large portion of Her Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     Troops from this Garrison for the protection 
     <lb/>
     of that Colony, it was with the utmost satis<lb break="no"/>faction that I was enabled to fill their places 
     <lb/>
     for Garrison duty by portions of the Halifax 
     <lb/>
     Volunteer and Militia Artillery and the Vol<lb break="no"/>unteer Battalion, and to mark how well that 
     <lb/>
     service was performed. The readiness and 
     <lb/>
     good discipline of the officers and men who 
     <lb/>
     were then employed, show how much has 
     <lb/>
     been effected bv the efforts made during the 
     <lb/>
     last few years to place our local forces in a 
     <lb/>
     proper condition, and how much we can de<lb break="no"/>pend upon them in the hour of need. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <cb/>
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of 
     <lb/>
     Assembly:</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Public Accounts will be submitted to 
     <lb/>
     you without delay, and will exhibit the finan<lb break="no"/>ces of the country in a state of unprecedented 
     <lb/>
     prosperity. Large as was the revenue of the 
     <lb/>
     previous year, the accounts will shew the gra<lb break="no"/>tifying fact that it has been greatly exceeded 
     <lb/>
     by that of 1866. The Estimates for the present 
     <lb/>
     year will also be laid before you. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. President, and Honorable Gentlemen of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Council:</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House of 
     <lb/>
     Assembly :</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have to express my regret that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the United States have adhered to their 
     <lb/>
     policy of last year, obstructing that Trade 
     <lb/>
     which under the Reciprocity Treaty was so 
     <lb/>
     beneficial to their own country as well as to 
     <lb/>
    this Province. I have, however, to state that 
     <lb/>the abrogation of the Treaty has been much 
     <lb/>less prejudicial to us than was anticipated, and 
     <lb/>in some respects has been productive of good, 
     <lb/>by uniting more closely the interests and the 
     <lb/>Trade of this and the other North American 
     <lb/>Colonies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     In accordance with a Resolution of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature passed last session, the Commis<lb break="no"/>sion of the Paris Exhibition was organized, 
     <lb/>
     and by the labors of the gentlemen comprising 
     <lb/>
     this Board, a large number of valuable arti<lb break="no"/>cles, exhibiting the varied resources of the 
     <lb/>
     Province, have been collected and sent for<lb break="no"/>ward to Paris; and it is confidently expected 
     <lb/>
     that the results of this exhibition will be of 
     <lb/>
     material advantage to the best interests of the 
     <lb/>
     Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Owing to financial difficulties in the Money 
     <lb/>
     Market of Great Britain last year, no progress 
     <lb/>
     was made in the construction of the Windsor 
     <lb/>
     and Annapolis Railway; but it affords me much 
     <lb/>
     pleasure to state that by a new contract made 
     <lb/>
     under the provisions of the law relating there<lb break="no"/>to, this important work has been now placed 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="2" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_002.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>


     in the hands of competent parties, with every 
     <lb/>
     prospect of satisfactory accomplishment. 
     <lb/>
     Great progress has been made in the construc<lb break="no"/>tion of the Pictou Railroad, a portion of which 
     <lb/>
     has been already opened for the accommoda<lb break="no"/>tion of the public, and it is fully anticipated 
     <lb/>
     that it will be completed at the time men<lb break="no"/>tioned in the contract. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The papers and reports of the Joint Commis<lb break="no"/>sion to Brazil and the West Indies will be laid 
     <lb/>
     before you, and it is hoped much good will re<lb break="no"/>sult from the efforts thus made to extend the 
     <lb/>
     commerce of the British North American Col<lb break="no"/>onies with those portions of the globe. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is gratifying to me to advert to the great 
     <lb/>
     progress made in the important cause of Educa<lb break="no"/>tion under recent enactments. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I rejoice to be able to congratulate you upon 
     <lb/>
     the success which has attended the Delegation 
     <lb/>
     sent by me under your authority to confer with 
     <lb/>
     Her Majesty's Government on the Union of the 
     <lb/>
     Colonies. The papers relating to this import<lb break="no"/>ant subject will be immediately laid before you. 
     <lb/>
     In the firm conviction that the Union of Cana<lb break="no"/>da, New Brunswick, and Nova Scotia, upon the 
     <lb/>
     terms provided in the Bill submitted by Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's Government to the Imperial Parliament, 
     <lb/>
     will largely increase the prosperity of all these 
     <lb/>
     Provinces, and contribute to the strength and 
     <lb/>
     stability of those British Institutions which it is 
     <lb/>
     their good fortune to enjoy, I commend to your 
     <lb/>
     consideration such changes and amendments in 
     <lb/>
     our existing laws as may be found necessary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     BILL PRO FORMA. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KAUL1">MR. KAULBACK</persName> asked leave to introduce a 
     <lb/>
     bill entitled an act to amend the Laws relating 
     <lb/>
     to patents for useful inventions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     ANSWER TO THE SPEECH. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOUR5">Mr. BOURINOT</persName> said :—Mr. Speaker, I hold in 
     <lb/>
     my hand the reply to the speech of His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency, which has been entrusted to me and 
     <lb/>
     I must here express my regret that some one 
     <lb/>
     better qualified for the task of making this mo<lb break="no"/>tion has not been selected. I desire to make a 
     <lb/>
     few observations on some of the points referr<lb break="no"/>ed to in His Excellency's address, and I shall 
     <lb/>
     do so in the order in which they appear. Be<lb break="no"/>fore proceeding further, however, 1 cannot help 
     <lb/>
     observing, and in this particular many of those 
     <lb/>
     who hear me will coincide in my remark, that 
     <lb/>
     I was much pleased to observe the presence of 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency Vice Admiral Sir James 
     <lb/>
     Hope at the opening of the Legislature. It is 
     <lb/>
     an unusual circumstance for the Admiral in 
     <lb/>
     command on this station to be present, and I 
     <lb/>
     cannot help referring to it. In addition to this 
     <lb/>
     remark I must express my regret that Sir 
     <lb/>
     James Hope is about to leave our shores. He 
     <lb/>
     will leave behind him many pleasing reminis<lb break="no"/>cences of the period of his command. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The most important topic contained in the 
     <lb/>
     speech was that embodied in the last clause, 
     <lb/>
     but to that I will not refer at this stage of my 
     <lb/>
     remarks. First of all our attention has been 
     <lb/>
     called to the fact that we have great cause for 
     <lb/>
     gratitude and rejoicing on account of the pros<lb break="no"/>perity which this country has enjoyed, especi<lb break="no"/>ally in view of the devastations which war 
     <lb/>
     has inflicted upon some of the countries of Eu<lb break="no"/>rope. In the second portion of the address a 
     <lb/>
    well deserved tribute is paid to the volunteer 
     <lb/>
          

            <cb/>
         

     forces of the provinces. It will be well re<lb break="no"/>membered that during last session we were 
     <lb/>
     much alarmed at the threatened invasion, and 
     <lb/>
     that the moment an appeal was made to the 
     <lb/>
     noble men composing the military force of the 
     <lb/>
     country, they responded with the utmost ala<lb break="no"/>crity and hastened to fill up the positions va<lb break="no"/>cated by the troops who were despatched to 
     <lb/>
     the frontier. This conduct was deserving of 
     <lb/>
     the highest praise, and I only wish I possessed 
     <lb/>
     the eloquence of the leader of the government, 
     <lb/>
     that I might use in connection with this sub<lb break="no"/>ject such language as would bc worthy of the 
     <lb/>
     occasion, and as the country would be pleased 
     <lb/>
     to hear. I would observe also that the same 
     <lb/>
     alacrity was evinced in every part of the pro<lb break="no"/>vince, showing that when an emergency ar<lb break="no"/>rives we shall tind our 50,000 militia men 
     <lb/>
     ready to defend their country from the inva<lb break="no"/>ders. Not one of them I believe will shrink 
     <lb/>
     from the duty that may then be imposed upon 
     <lb/>
     him. It is gratifying to us to know that in 
     <lb/>
     two or three years our Militia Force has made 
     <lb/>
     such improvements in organization. It is true 
     <lb/>
     that much remains to he done, but we may 
     <lb/>
     rest assured that in a short time a state of 
     <lb/>
     thorough efficiency will be attained. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The next clause of the address refers to the 
     <lb/>
     public revenue,and in connection with that I am 
     <lb/>
     gratified to be able to say, and it will be agree<lb break="no"/>able to those who hear me to learn that the 
     <lb/>
     balance in the hands of the financial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary at the end of the last financial year, after 
     <lb/>
     paying all demands against the treasury,shews 
     <lb/>
     a large surplus. I must now refer to the ab<lb break="no"/>rogation of the reciprocity treaty and its effect 
     <lb/>
     upon our commercial prosperity. We all know 
     <lb/>
     that the country has felt that abrogation to a 
     <lb/>
     considerable extent, more especially in the 
     <lb/>
     high duties which have been imposed upon 
     <lb/>
     our principal exports. In relation to this sub<lb break="no"/>ject I may say that I am of opinion that bye- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     and-bye the old system will be revived, and in 
     <lb/>
     this view I am supported by many persons of 
     <lb/>
     experience. Since the abrogation of the treaty 
     <lb/>
     this country has prospered to a degree that 
     <lb/>
     was not at all anticipated, and there is one 
     <lb/>
     circumstance in connection with it to which I 
     <lb/>
     would especially refer: namely, the mission to 
     <lb/>
     Brazil and the West Indies, the report on 
     <lb/>
     which is in our hands. That report contains 
     <lb/>
     valuable statistics shewing new channels into 
     <lb/>
     which our commerce can profitably be turned. 
     <lb/>
     In Upper Canada alone there is a consumption 
     <lb/>
     of 200,000 or 300,000 tons of coal. Why cannot 
     <lb/>
     that market be supplied by Pictou or Cape 
     <lb/>Breton? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Then there is the other topic of the Paris 
     <lb/>
     Exhibition Commission. I was glad to find 
     <lb/>
     that the commissioners had bestowed so much 
     <lb/>
     attention upon their duties, and believe that at 
     <lb/>
     the Exhibition we will appear to great advan<lb break="no"/>tage, taking a place second only to Canada 
     <lb/>
     among the B. American colonies. Our column 
     <lb/>
     of coal and our specimens of gold would alone 
     <lb/>
     make us prominent in any exhibition. There 
     <lb/>
     is one circumstance in connection with this 
     <lb/>
     topic which rather puzzles me. I am curious 
     <lb/>
     to know why the commissioners selected 
     <lb/>
     Louisburg as a place to be represented by a 
     <lb/>
     painting at the exhibition. Was it to remind 
     <lb/>
     the French that there they had sustained a de<lb break="no"/>feat, or was it shew the present nakedness 
     <lb/>
     and desolation of the old city? The contrast is 
     <lb/>
     great between the present and past condition 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="3" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_003.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">3</fw>
       

     of that place, and if Dr. Honeyman should 
     <lb/>
     point to the picture and say, " Louisburg once 
     <lb/>
     belonged to you," the answer would be, " but 
     <lb/>
     it is not now what it was in old times, 
     <lb/>
     as can be seen by its ruinous and forsaken 
     <lb/>
     condition." I have before now told the 
     <lb/>
     house, and Mr. Fleming's report corrobor<lb break="no"/>ates my statement, that Louisburg is the 
     <lb/>
     port nearest to Europe on this continent, and 
     <lb/>
     I trust the time will come when it will have 
     <lb/>
     the advantages of railway communication. Its 
     <lb/>
     harbour is accessible at all seasons ot the year, 
     <lb/>
     it was the old capital under the French rule, 
     <lb/>
     it was for a long time the rendezvous for the 
     <lb/>
     French West Indies, Louisiana and Quebec 
     <lb/>
     mercantile fleet, and I am convinced that it 
     <lb/>
     will at no very distant day be a city 
     <lb/>
     not even second to Halifax, if to any 
     <lb/>
     in British America. It is one of those 
     <lb/>
     places which under Confederation will receive 
     <lb/>
     a large measure of attention, and I may say 
     <lb/>
     here that; one of the reasons why I supported 
     <lb/>
     that measure was that under the Nova Scotia. 
     <lb/>
     Government Cape Breton never received am<lb break="no"/>ple justice;—under Confederation we will be 
     <lb/>
     treated as an important integral part of the 
     <lb/>
     nationality.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The railway question has received some 
     <lb/>
     attention ; and as to the Annapolis Railway, I 
     <lb/>
     suppose our friends from the westward will 
     <lb/>
     speak eloquently on the subject. I am glad to 
     <lb/>
     find that the promises held out in relation to 
     <lb/>
     that work are being fulfilled, notwithstanding 
     <lb/>
     the fears which existed to the contrary. As 
     <lb/>
     regards the Pictou line. I had the pleasure of 
     <lb/>
     travelling over it from West River, and I must 
     <lb/>
     say that the section opened is an admirable 
     <lb/>
     one. I hope that the next time I come here 
     <lb/>
     I shall be able to travel over it from Pictou. 
     <lb/>
     When I had the honour of addressing the 
     <lb/>
     House formerly on this question, I mentioned 
     <lb/>
     that the benefits to be conferred by the line on 
     <lb/>
     the Cape Breton Counties would be by keep<lb break="no"/>ing up the communication by a line of steam<lb break="no"/>ers by Mabou or St. Peter's Canal to Sydney. 
     <lb/>
     I am still of that opinion, and learn it is in<lb break="no"/>tended, when the railway is completed, to es<lb break="no"/>tablish such a line 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The next point referred to is the subject of 
     <lb/>
     Education. You are aware that I never gave 
     <lb/>
     a very hearty support to the present educa<lb break="no"/>tional measure, but I am happy to inform the 
     <lb/>
     house that in the county which I represent the 
     <lb/>
     Act is working well, and I believe that in the 
     <lb/>
     lapse of time the system will be found to im<lb break="no"/>prove more and more. The greatest difficulty 
     <lb/>
     in connection with the system is the want of a 
     <lb/>
     good staff of educators. This want, however, 
     <lb/>
     will be supplied bye-and-bye. I have now 
     <lb/>
     come to the most important question of 
     <lb/>
     all, and it is one that has been for some time 
     <lb/>
     engrossing the attention of the house and of 
     <lb/>
     the country,—I allude to the question of Con<lb break="no"/>federation. In the remonstrance which Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Howe and his friends recently address<lb break="no"/>ed to the Colonial Secretary, they did me 
     <lb/>
     the honor to refer to a speech made by me in 
     <lb/>
     1865, and brought a charge for inconsistency 
     <lb/>
     against me, for having in 1866 supported the 
     <lb/>
     resolution for Union. It is somewhat strange 
     <lb/>
     that such a charge should emanate from Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Howe, who has been so inconsistent on this 
     <lb/>
     great question. He is a gentleman from 
     <lb/>
     whose high abilities I will not detract, but he 
     <lb/>
    ought to know well that a politician is some<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
         
times called upon to change his views in an 
     <lb/>
     age of progress like this. But if I was open to 
     <lb/>
     the charge of inconsistency it was in opposing 
     <lb/>
     Confederation in 1865, for in 1861, in course of 
     <lb/>
     an address to the house, I took occasion to 
     <lb/>
     make these observations:—  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " And I may add that a Union of the Colonies 
     <lb/>
     should have formed the chief feature of the session. 
     <lb/>
     It has already become the great question of the day, 
     <lb/>
     and one which now occupies the thoughts of every 
     <lb/>
     statesman who looks forward to the future greatness 
     <lb/>
     of British North America, for by it alone can we 
     <lb/>
     claim rank among the favoured nations of the earth." 
     <lb/>
     And again: "Linked with it is the often proposed 
     <lb/>
     great Intercolonial Railway, which I shall always 
     <lb/>
     advocate. By all these now neglected measures can 
     <lb/>
     we become prosperous. An imperisbable  one 
     <lb/>
     that will never die, will the statesman gain who ma<lb break="no"/>tures and renders them acceptable to these, pro<lb break="no"/>vinces."    
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>
     These were the sentiments expressed by me 
     <lb/>
     six years ago, and therefore I say that if there 
     <lb/>
     was any inconsistency on my part it was in 
     <lb/>
     opposing Confederation at all. The reasons for 
     <lb/>
     my opposition to the Quebec scheme are known 
     <lb/>
     to many of my friends, and as I have stated 
     <lb/>
     them at large to the house, I need not refer to 
     <lb/>
     them again, excepting to say that I support 
     <lb/>
     the measure from conviction. My mind was 
     <lb/>
     not influenced by any freak of a moment, 
     <lb/>
     or by any desire for office. It is well known 
     <lb/>
     that I have never held office, and that I 
     <lb/>
     do not desire any either under the general or 
     <lb/>
     local government. In the opinion of some 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen every man does wrong who does 
     <lb/>
     not strictly conform to their views; but I can 
     <lb/>
     fully justify the course I have taken. When 
     <lb/>
     I came to the session last year there were 
     <lb/>
     many conflicting reasons operating in my mind 
     <lb/>
     and I was not fully determined as to whether 
     <lb/>
     I should support or oppose Union. In the first 
     <lb/>
     place I found on reading attentively that the 
     <lb/>
     opinions of the most intelligent men in Eng<lb break="no"/>land were favourable to Confederation; then I 
     <lb/>
     saw that the organs of the various religious 
     <lb/>
     denominations were likewise favorable, and 
     <lb/>
     that the proposition had received the support 
     <lb/>
     of the leading men of every political creed.— 
     <lb/>
     Everywhere evidence was to be found that the 
     <lb/>
     wish of the Imperial Government was to see 
     <lb/>
     Union consummated; then came the Fenian 
     <lb/>
     excitement, and the abrogation of the <choice><sic>Recipro<lb break="no"/>ty</sic><corr>Reciprocity</corr></choice> Treaty; and, at length, when our own terri<lb break="no"/>tory was menaced, I felt that the moment had 
     <lb/>
     arrived when a true and patriotic lover of his 
     <lb/>
     country should decide. I then came to the re<lb break="no"/>solution that I should support Confederation, 
     <lb/>
     in order that we might be prepared to meet the 
     <lb/>
     emergencies which were approaching. I gave 
     <lb/>
     the proposition my support, however, with the 
     <lb/>
     understanding that the Quebec scheme should 
     <lb/>
     undergo modification, and I am pleased to ob<lb break="no"/>serve that there is a great improvement in the 
     <lb/>
     Bill, which is likely to become the law of the 
     <lb/>
     land. The Quebec Scheme gave us 10 mem<lb break="no"/>bers in the Senate, but the bill gives us 12, 
     <lb/>
     which will be a much larger representation in 
     <lb/>
     proportion to our population than Canada, 
     <lb/>
     has. With regard to the amount of reve<lb break="no"/>nue to be placed at the disposal of the local 
     <lb/>
     legislature, under the Quebec scheme we 
     <lb/>
     were to have had about $260,000 based   
     <lb/>
     on the census of 1861, but under the Bill the  
     <lb/>
     allowance will be increased until the popula<lb break="no"/>tion reaches 400,000. Altogether, including the 
     <lb/>special grant the local subsidy will be increased 
     <lb/>
      

            <pb n="4" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-03-16_Page_004.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">4</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
         

     about $120,000 more than the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     scheme would have given us for local pur<lb break="no"/>poses. There are other important modifica<lb break="no"/>tions but to these I shall not refer at the pre<lb break="no"/>sent time. The bill which has been introduc<lb break="no"/>ed into the Imperial Parliament has received 
     <lb/>
     the support of our late respected Governor, 
     <lb/>
     the Marquis of Normanby, of Earl Russell, of 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Watkin, and of the foremost men of the 
     <lb/>
     mother country, and who are its opponents? 
     <lb/>
     The principal opponents are Mr. Bright and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Ayrton, whose opposition is founded on 
     <lb/>
     the expense that will be caused by colonial 
     <lb/>
     defence, and on the indiposition which they 
     <lb/>
     feel to support the guarantee for the Interco<lb break="no"/>lonial Railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have the honor to represent the largest 
     <lb/>
     constituency in the province, with the excep<lb break="no"/>tion of Halifax, (for Pictou, which follows Ha<lb break="no"/>lifax in population, is divided), and I feel it 
     <lb/>
     gratifying to be able to say that I never pre<lb break="no"/>sented a petition against Confederation, and 
     <lb/>
     that no public meetings against it have been 
     <lb/>
     held in the county. It is true I received a do<lb break="no"/>cument signed by a few persons, whom I high<lb break="no"/>ly esteem, shortly after the division had taken 
     <lb/>
     place, asking that I should oppose the measure, 
     <lb/>
     and I will frankly say that even had I received 
     <lb/>
     it before the division my action would 
     <lb/>
     not have been different, for I feel that 
     <lb/>
     I represent the whole of Nova Scotia, 
     <lb/>
     and must regard the interests of all 
     <lb/>
     its people, rather than the wishes of the 
     <lb/>
     few individuals to whom I refer. In looking 
     <lb/>
     at the prospects of the Confederation 
     <lb/>
     which is to be, I feel that we have all the ele<lb break="no"/>ments of greatness within us We have a ter<lb break="no"/>ritory larger then that of the United States, 
     <lb/>
     we have a supply of those minerals upon 
     <lb/>
     which the might and prosperity of England 
     <lb/>
     have so long rested, we have gold, we have 
     <lb/>
     our fisheries and our timber and the agricul<lb break="no"/>tural capabilities of Canada which is only se<lb break="no"/>cond among grain producing countries of this 
     <lb/>
     continent, and is one of the granaries 
     <lb/>
     of the world. Then there is our mer<lb break="no"/>cantile marine, the third or fourth in the world, 
     <lb/>
     and I feel that the time will come when we 
     <lb/>
     will stand among the very first on the list. 
     <lb/>
     Some of the subjects to which I have referred 
     <lb/>
     are of such importance that I could not refrain 
     <lb/>
     from these observations and I will now con<lb break="no"/>clude by moving the following reply to His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency's address:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     REPLY TO ADDRESS: 
     <lb/>
     
            </head>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">May it please Your Excellency,—</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1. We thank Your Excellency for the speech 
     <lb/>
     with which you have been pleased to open the 
     <lb/>
     present session, and we are much gratified 
     <lb/>
     that your Excellency can again congratulate 
     <lb/>
     us upon the continued peace and prosperity of 
     <lb/>
     this Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. We are much pleased to learn that the 
     <lb/>
     manner in which the loyal population of this 
     <lb/>
     Colony responded to the call made upon them 
     <lb/>
     for the defence of our country, and the zeal 
     <lb/>
     and ability with which they discharged the du<lb break="no"/>ties required of them, were such as to earn the 
     <lb/>
     warm commendation of your Excellency. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. It affords us much pleasure to find that the 
     <lb/>
     revenue has increased, and we will give our 
     <lb/>
     best attention to the public accounts when 
     <lb/>
     laid before us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. We are glad to know that the interruption 
     <lb/>
      

            <cb/>
          

     of the trade of this Province, caused by the ab<lb break="no"/>rogation of the Reciprocity Treaty, has been 
     <lb/>
     largely compensated by the increased impetus 
     <lb/>
     given to commercial intercourse with the other 
     <lb/>
     Provinces.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. We learn with much satisfaction that the 
     <lb/>
     difficulties in connection with the prosecution 
     <lb/>
     of the Windsor and Annapolis Railway have 
     <lb/>
     been overcome, and that the extension of the 
     <lb/>
     Railway to Pictou has been vigorously prose<lb break="no"/>cuted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6. We trust the efforts made to represent the 
     <lb/>
     resources of Nova Scotia, at the International 
     <lb/>
     Exhibition about to be held at Paris will be 
     <lb/>
     productive of much good to the Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     7. We reciprocate the hope that the joint 
     <lb/>
     missions to Brazil and the West Indies will 
     <lb/>
     result in the extension of commerce between 
     <lb/>
     those places and British North America. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     8. It is very gratifying to know that great  
     <lb/>
     progress is been made in the Education of all 
     <lb/>
     classes of the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     9. We have learned with deep satisfaction 
     <lb/>
     that the efforts to effect a satisfactory Union 
     <lb/>
     of the British North American Colonies have 
     <lb/>
     been so successful, and entertain no doubt 
     <lb/>
     that the best interests of all these Provinces 
     <lb/>
     will be greatly enhanced, and that their con<lb break="no"/>nection with the Crown and the Parent State 
     <lb/>
     will be thereby permanently secured. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CHUR2">Mr. CHURCHILL</persName>:—I rise to second the reply 
     <lb/>
     to the Address of the Lieutenant-Governor, 
     <lb/>
     and I do so with feelings of pleasure. I feel 
     <lb/>
     gratified at the fact that the Windsor and An<lb break="no"/>napolis Railway is under progress, and the 
     <lb/>
     Pictou line will be carried to early completion, 
     <lb/>
     for I feel that will wipe out the reproach so 
     <lb/>
     long resting upon us that we had two pieces 
     <lb/>
     of Railway beginning nowhere and ending no<lb break="no"/>where. In these facts I especially rejoice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. STEWART CAMPBELL</persName>:—I rise to ask that 
     <lb/>
     the usual courtesy be shown in reference to 
     <lb/>
     the reply to the Address, and to request that 
     <lb/>
     it be allowed to lie on the table until Monday. 
     <lb/>
     It may be convenient for the government to 
     <lb/>
     know, and it is but candid in me to inform 
     <lb/>
     them, that it is our intention to move an 
     <lb/>
     amendment to the Address in reference to the 
     <lb/>
     subject of Confederation. In that amendment 
     <lb/>
     we desire solemnly to affirm the right of the 
     <lb/>
     people of this country to be heard on a measure 
     <lb/>
     involving so largely their best interests. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SECY</persName>.:—I need hardly say that 
     <lb/>
     the usual course will be adopted and that the 
     <lb/>
     Address will be allowed to lie over for the 
     <lb/>
     consideration of gentlemen opposite. I am 
     <lb/>
     glad that the hon. member has frankly stated 
     <lb/>
     his intention to move an amendment, and I 
     <lb/>
     will await with the utmost confidence the 
     <lb/>
     decision of what I believe will be the over<lb break="no"/>whelming majority of the House upon this 
     <lb/>
     most momentous question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Address was laid on the table until 
     <lb/>
     Monday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The house adjourned to Monday at 3 o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<!-- GL, 2018-06-05, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

           <!-- <p>
     UNION OF THE PROVINCES. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     MONDAY, March 18. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>The House met at 3 o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The adjourned debate on the Answer to the 
     <lb/>
     Address was resumed and all the clauses ex<lb break="no"/>cepting the last were adopted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>