<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1866-04-14"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-04-14">14 April 1866</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA">
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          
          
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Second Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1866"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="240"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_238.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_239.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_240.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-05-30">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-05-30">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_238">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_238.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_239">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_239.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_240">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_240.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="238" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_238.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">238</fw>   <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
            

<p>
     [...] sented to-day.   I was prepared then as now, 
     <lb/>
     to defeat the Quebec scheme. Let me state to the 
     <lb/>
     house that a committee was appointed in  the 
     <lb/>
     city to operate against the Quebec scheme; and 
     <lb/>
     at the last meeting, when it was wished to adopt a 
     <lb/>
     policy adverse to all union, I told them then that 
     <lb/>
    I would not assist them. My opposition was en<lb break="no"/>tirely to the Quebec scheme. It was then deter<lb break="no"/>mined to send these petitions over the face of the 
     <lb/>country. I went to Lunenburg, and assisted in 
     <lb/>returning the gentleman who now sits here. In 
     <lb/>respect to the petitiors, I said I would send them 
     <lb/>into Richmond, but I would not interfere with 
     <lb/>Mr. McDonnell's county. I was going to write ' 
     <lb/>to Mr. McDonriell, but I heard he was coming 
     <lb/>up to Halifax. I then saw Mr. Annand, in his 
     <lb/>own office, and he suggested the very words 
     <lb/>that are written in the paper which he has just 
     <lb/>read . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName>.—Oh! Oh! 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. Miller</persName>.—It is true; it was at his own 
     <lb/>
     table they were suggested, and they were printed 
     <lb/>
     in his office. He presented, the other day, peti<lb break="no"/>tions from Dr. Cameron, which he had sent with 
     <lb/>
     his own frank. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName>.—I did; at the hon. member's 
     <lb/>
     instance.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName>.—I denied at the time having sent 
     <lb/>
    these petitions, and yet he contradicted me; 
     <lb/>now he acknowledges having franked them.</p>

 
  <p> <persName ref="pers:DESB2">Hon. FIN. Secretary</persName>.—I must corroborate 
     <lb/>to the fullest extent the language taken down by 
     <lb/>the Provincial Secretary. I took the words 
     <lb/>down at the same time. The hon. member said 
     <lb/>—" I would have received money or office if I 
     <lb/>had wished it." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO6">Mr. MCDONNELL</persName>.—I also took the same 
     <lb/>
     words down. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName>.—The hon. member now stands 
     <lb/>
     convicted before the house and country of having 
     <lb/>
     uttered a " villainous falsehood." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LOCK1">Mr. LOCKE</persName>.—The word <hi rendition="simple:italic">money</hi> never struck 
     <lb/>
     my ear. I heard preferment and place—that is<lb/> 
               <lb/>all.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BILL1">Hon. ATTY. GENERAL</persName>—Then the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber must have a deaf ear for some things. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     C. J. CAMPBELL.—Was not the language read 
     <lb/>
     here in his presence, and he never contradicted 
     <lb/>
     it?   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName>.—Substantially it was the same 
     <lb/>
     statement made by the hon. member for Rich<lb break="no"/>mond. It differs, however, in the fact that Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Brown used the word interest. What is the dif<lb break="no"/>ference between interest and money ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BILL1">Hon. ATTY. GEN</persName>.—The hon. gentleman first 
     <lb/>
     referred to Canadian gold, and then said he 
     <lb/>
     himself could have had money if he had wished 
     <lb/>
     it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SECY</persName>—The present question is 
     <lb/>
     one of great importance, for it involves the char<lb break="no"/>acter of a public man. The question came up in 
     <lb/>
     reference to a paragraph which the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     had put in his paper concerning some remarks on 
     <lb/>
     the sale of Louisiana, by Mr. Brown. That gen<lb break="no"/>tleman said, even if the Union of the Provinces 
     <lb/>
     did cost Canada something for a few years it was 
     <lb/>
     but a small matter in comparison with their 
     <lb/>
     value. The hon. member for Halifax knew that 
     <lb/>
        

            <cb/>
          
   
         

     he was guilty when he made the charge he did 
     <lb/>
     against Mr. Brown of the greatest crime  of 
     <lb/>
     which a public man can be guilty—that of put<lb break="no"/>ting a false construction on the language of 
     <lb/>
     another, for the purpose of misleading the public 
     <lb/>
     mind. Mr. Brown said—suppose Canada has to 
     <lb/>
     contribute a few dollars more to the intercolonial 
     <lb/>
     union —what does it amount to? Look at the 
     <lb/>
     sale of Louisiana to the United States. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. member knows that this was a <hi rendition="simple:italic">bona fide</hi> 
     <lb/>
     transaction ; there was no secret service money 
     <lb/>
     connected with it. Mr. Brown is one of the most 
     <lb/>
     sagacions statesmen in British North America; 
     <lb/>
     but a man would be an idiot if he were to come 
     <lb/>
     forward on the present occasion and say—Cana<lb break="no"/>da was going to use secret service money for 
     <lb/>the acquisition of these Provinces. The hon. 
     <lb/>member must have known that he was putting a 
     <lb/>false estimate on the language of Mr. Brown. 
     <lb/>When he was met by a derisive cheer from this 
     <lb/>side of the house, he said that he had an inter<lb break="no"/>view with Mr. Brown, and followed that up with 
     <lb/>the declaration that he could have had money if 
     <lb/>he wished it,—that he was proffered place and 
     <lb/>preferment in Canada. Then I felt this was a 
     <lb/>grave charge, requiring investigation. All I   
     <lb/>can say is, if any one had attempted to bribe me, 
     <lb/>I would have felt that it would never do for me 
     <lb/>months afterwards to come forward and mention 
     <lb/>it. I knew enough of Mr Brown to be aware 
     <lb/>that wherever he was known the charge would 
     <lb/>be scouted as too absurd I read the words at 
     <lb/>the table. and stated my intention to telegraph 
     <lb/>them to Mr. Brown He would not repeat the 
     <lb/>words. but said the official reporter had taken 
     <lb/>them down I did all I could to enable him to 
     <lb/>correct me if I was wrong. He did nothing of 
     <lb/>the kind and therefore I telegraphed to Mr 
     <lb/>Brown, whose answer is now before you. The 
     <lb/>country will now understand the value of char 
     <lb/>ges of corruption coming from such a quarter. 
     <lb/>Now he comes forward and denies his own lan<lb break="no"/>guage, and gives the same version of the conver<lb break="no"/>sation with Mr. Brown that was given by Mr. 
     <lb/>Miller, and which he contradicted at the time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> —I will merely say to the Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary that I have not backed down. 
     <lb/>
     What Mr Brown stated to me made the impres<lb break="no"/>sion upon my mind-that it was for my inter<lb break="no"/>est that I should join him and his friends in 
     <lb/>
     carryig Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PRO. SEC</persName> —The hon member only en<lb break="no"/>dorsed the statement made on Friday by the 
     <lb/>
     hon member for Richmond. Under the cir 
     <lb/>
     cumstances not the slightest imputation can rest 
     <lb/>
     upon Mr Brown's character. All that he said 
     <lb/>
     was, that a man of Mr Annand's position ought 
     <lb/>
     to be able to make himself some standing in 
     <lb/>
     the Confederation. He would have as good a 
     <lb/>
     chance as any one else. Perhaps if Mr Brown 
     <lb/>
     understood  the talents or the position of the 
     <lb/>
     hon member he would not have said so much. 
     <lb/>
     What would he thought of a hon. member who 
     <lb/>
     was going about day by day. and button-holing 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen. and telling them that the best way 
     <lb/>
     to get to Ottawa is by opposing the scheme of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. Is that corruption ? I do not  
     <lb/>
     think the non. gentleman would like to say so? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="239" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_239.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY</fw> <fw type="num">239</fw> 


   
            <p>
     Mr MILLER —The hon. member has brought 
     <lb/>
     two charges against my veracity First, with 
     <lb/>
     regard to the conversation with Mr. Brown 
     <lb/>
     which he now admits to he substantially true. 
     <lb/>
     Secondly, with regard to the petitions which he 
     <lb/>
     presented here on the day I explained my posi<lb break="no"/>tion on the question He accused me of having 
     <lb/>
     sent these particular petitions to lnverness, and 
     <lb/>
     I denied it on the instant I never denied that 
     <lb/>
     I was a party to sending petitions through the 
     <lb/>
     country He now admits that he sent and frank<lb break="no"/>ed these petitions himself Where, then, is his 
     <lb/>
     charge of want of veracity on either side? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr ANNAND —The hon member was one of 
     <lb/>
     an organization in the city who unfortunatelv 
     <lb/>
     had too much confidence in him ; for it now ap<lb break="no"/>pears he was only there as a spy. On one oc<lb break="no"/>casion in the presence of some of the most in<lb break="no"/>fluential merchants ot the city, so inflated was 
     <lb/>
     he that he offered to take charge of the whole 
     <lb/>
     lsland of Cape Breton, and send petitions to it 
     <lb/>
     The hon. gentlemen told you that I with my 
     <lb/>
     own stamp, sent these petitions to Dr. Cameron, 
     <lb/>
     but I did so at his request . because he said he 
     <lb/>
     did not wish to come  into conflict with Mr Mc 
     <lb/>
     Donnell The hon member thought so much 
     <lb/>
     of his own shillings and pence that he would not 
     <lb/>
     take his own stamps The hon gentlemen said 
     <lb/>
     that I dictated the paper in question;  but can 
     <lb/>
     you believe   that a gentleman   of his importance, 
     <lb/>
     who offered to take charge of the whole island 
     <lb/>
     of Cape Breton. would allow any one to dictate 
     <lb/>
     to him ? All l can say is, the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     wrote it with his own hands 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName>—I think we have had about 
     <lb/>
     enough of these contradictions and I do trust 
     <lb/>
     that a question  of such importance as the pre<lb break="no"/>sent will be deliberately and calmly discussed 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName> — It was the hon member for 
     <lb/>
     East Halifax who brought the matter here, and 
     <lb/>
     he also is blameable for the discussion that has 
     <lb/>
     ensued I thought, when the hon gentleman 
     <lb/>
     got up, he was going to expose me but now i find 
     <lb/>
     that all he has done is to bring a charge ot va<lb break="no"/>nity against me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon ATTY GEN—I recollect distinctly yes. 
     <lb/>
     terday when the hon member for Richmond 
     <lb/>
    gave the version of the conversation with Mr. 
     <lb/>Brown,  the. hon member for East Halifax 
     <lb/>got up and contradicted it: now he says it is 
     <lb/>substantially the same version. But we all 
     <lb/>know the hon gentleman's speech was not in<lb break="no"/>tended tor this house. The object was to irritate 
     <lb/>the public mind of this country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     A good deal of further desultory conversa<lb break="no"/>tion ensued, which it is impossible to give in 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">extenso</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr BLACKWOOD thought every gentleman 
     <lb/>
     should be only held  responsible for the opinons 
     <lb/>
     he held and  expressed himself   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr LOCKE said that the country had not pe<lb break="no"/>titioned very tar ely during the present session, 
     <lb/>
     in as much as the impression  prevailedd that the 
     <lb/>
     question of Union would not come up 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon PROV SEC said that he was prepared 
     <lb/>
     by the most conclusive evidence to prove  that 
     <lb/>
     the whole effect of the policy of the Anti- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Union party was to annex us to the American 
     <lb/>
          

            <cb/>
          

     States He then went on to say that they dar<lb break="no"/>ed not send petitions to the country against all 
     <lb/>
     Union, for they knew that the Union sentiment 
     <lb/>
     among the intelligent masses was very strong. 
     <lb/>
     All that they could do was to get signatures to 
     <lb/>
     petitions taking objections to certain features of 
     <lb/>
     the Quebec scheme. Yet despite the efforts 
     <lb/>
     made by the wealthy and powerful Anti-Union 
     <lb/>
     organization in this city, only about 15000 
     <lb/>
     names of men, women and children, could be 
     <lb/>
     got last year in the whole province. He had 
     <lb/>
     himself in a few weeks, some years ago, got 
     <lb/>
     25000 persons to petition for a matter of com<lb break="no"/>paratively small importance, namely a dissolu<lb break="no"/>tion of the Assembly. Now another year had 
     <lb/>
     passed, and despite all the agitation in the press 
     <lb/>
     and otherwise, only four or five thousand peti<lb break="no"/>tioners appeared in opposition—not to Union, 
     <lb/>
     but to some details of the Quebec scheme. 
     <lb/>
     Now when the opponents of that scheme came 
     <lb/>
     forward an I offered to meet the friends of Union 
     <lb/>
     half way, it was the duty of the latter to con<lb break="no"/>sent, in view of the prevalent sentiment of the 
     <lb/>
     country. He had heard from Annapolis and 
     <lb/>
     the Western counties and was proud to be. able 
     <lb/>
     to say that the course the government wished 
     <lb/>
     to pursue in respect to Union met with the en<lb break="no"/>thusiastîc approval of the people 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr LOCKE said that the government had ap<lb break="no"/>pealed to three constituencies since the question 
     <lb/>
     of Confederation came up, and had lost them. 
     <lb/>
     If the hon Provincial Secretary was convinced 
     <lb/>
     that the people were not opposed to Union why 
     <lb/>
     did not he dissolve and appeal to them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr BLANCHARD said that the house had heard 
     <lb/>
     the way the petitions against Confederation got 
     <lb/>
     into the country, and yet despite all the efforts 
     <lb/>
     that had b: been made, only a few hundred names 
     <lb/>
     had been received from lnverness with a popu<lb break="no"/>lation ot 20 000 people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr KILLAM said that the people of Yarmouth 
     <lb/>
     were against confederation. He knew that the 
     <lb/>
     people of Digby were also opposed to Union. 
     <lb/>
     He presumed when the vote was taken, the 
     <lb/>
     members of that county would act in accordance 
     <lb/>
     with the sentiments of their constituents 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BILL1">Hon. ATTY GEN</persName>. said that no gentleman in 
     <lb/>
     favour ot Annexation would be expected to 
     <lb/>
     favour Confederation 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr Ross saint that it had been understood in 
     <lb/>
     Victoria that the question of Confederation  would 
     <lb/>
     not come up this session, amt therefore it was 
     <lb/>
     not thought necessary to get up pettions. The 
     <lb/>
     best way to test the feeling of the people would 
     <lb/>
     be to appeal to them 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName> said that the election in 
     <lb/>
     Annapolis was not decided on the Confederation 
     <lb/>
     scheme. The Dalhousie College question, the 
     <lb/>
     Pictou Railway and the School B<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> were the 
     <lb/>
     questions that influenced the election The 
     <lb/>
     Quebec scheme had only just been propounded 
     <lb/>
     when the election was over, and was not one of 
     <lb/>
     the issues Not one word  was said about it on 
     <lb/>
     the hustings. At a public meeting subsequently 
     <lb/>
     held in it that county where he had been present, 
     <lb/>
     the Anti Unionists could not pass a resolution 
     <lb/>
     against Union Again in the shiretown the only 
     <lb/>
     resolution passed was one of thanks to himself 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="240" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-14_Page_240.jpg"/>
        

            <fw type="num">240</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
        

      for being present and giving so much informa<lb break="no"/>tion on the subject As respects Lunenburg he 
     <lb/>
     believed if it were not for the Education Mea<lb break="no"/>sure he could have brought in a government 
     <lb/>
     candidate pledged to support a Union of the Col<lb break="no"/>onies As respects the other county mentioned 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Yarmouth (Mr Killam) 
     <lb/>
     could not get his own candidate in, and Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Townsend had been returned. He (Dr T ) 
     <lb/>
     believed that Yarmouth might be considered 
     <lb/>
     opposed to Union, but every one knew what 
     <lb/>
     was the ruling sentiment in that county At a 
     <lb/>
     meeting held in that county for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     sending delegates to the Detroit Convention. 
     <lb/>
     leading  men came forward with the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man for Yarmouth and declared that if the 
     <lb/>
     treaty were abrogated the sooner Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>
     was annexed to the United States the better 
     <lb/>
     He was informed that the other hon. member 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Townsend) stood up manfully. and said 
     <lb/>
     they ought to be ashamed. Under such circum 
     <lb/>
     stances it was not strange that a portion of the 
     <lb/>
     county of Yarmouth opposed the Union of the 
     <lb/>
     Colonies 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP8">Mr.  Colin Campbell</persName> said that the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Yatmouth would know the sentiments of 
     <lb/>
     the representatives of the county of Digby at 
     <lb/>
     the proper time They were prepared to as<lb break="no"/>sume themselves the responsibility of dealing  
     <lb/>
     with the question in that spirit and manner that 
     <lb/>
     would best advance the interests of the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KILL2">Mr. Killam</persName> said that he would deal with 
     <lb/>
     the question ot Confederation at the proper 
     <lb/>
     time He had not attempted to influence the 
     <lb/>
     constituency against Mr Townsend He was 
     <lb/>
     not aware that any opinions in respect to annex<lb break="no"/>ation had been m oted in the meeting referred to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr HATFIELD regretted that so much time 
     <lb/>
     had been wasted that might be more profitably 
     <lb/>
     employed.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Mr. MCLELAN</persName> said that he believed the ef 
     <lb/>
     fect of Confederation would be to annex the 
     <lb/>
     Provinces to the United States 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr C J. CAMPBELL presented a petition from 
     <lb/>
     H. Cameron and others against Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The  subject then dropped 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr.  WHITMAN</persName> introduced a bill to legalize as 
     <lb/>
     sessment rolls of the county of Annapolis. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The house then adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<!-- GL, 2018-05-29, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

           <!-- <p>
     MONDAY, April 16. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The House met at 3 o'clock 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr BOURINOT introduced a bill to incorporate 
     <lb/>
     the Myra Bay Harbor Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. S  CAMPBELL presented a petition for the 
     <lb/>
     alteration of a mail route. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Also, two petitions  against Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr PRYOR reported  favorably on a number of 
     <lb/>
     bills from the committee on private and local 
     <lb/>
     bills, and unfavorably of the bill relative to the 
     <lb/>
     siection of a lock-up at Waverly these objections 
     <lb/>
     being already provided for by existing statutes 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. PROV SEC laid on the table a report of 
     <lb/>
     the Officer commandin H. M. S. Lilly in reference 
     <lb/>
    to the fog trumpet at Sambro. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     UNION OF THE COLONIES 
     <lb/>
     The adjourned debate was resumed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr C. J. CAMPBELL said : The Provincial 
     <lb/>
     Secretary told us,  some days ago, that the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment  were awaiting the action  of New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick on the question or Confederation. I 
     <lb/>
     do not think that this Province should place 
     <lb/>
     itself in that position Nova Scotia is the most 
     <lb/>
     important of the Maritime Provinces, and I do 
     <lb/>
     not see why we should wait for others to lead us 
     <lb/>
     on this important que stion. It is the duty of the 
     <lb/>
     Government and  of this Legislature to take a 
     <lb/>
     leading part in the discussion of this measure. 
     <lb/>
     When the question was introduced a year or two 
     <lb/>
     ago, much diversity of opinion existed as to the 
     <lb/>
     details which had  been arranged at Quebec, and 
     <lb/>
     matters stood in a different light from that in 
     <lb/>
     which they now appear At that  time we looked 
     <lb/>
     forward to peace and tranquillity with the United 
     <lb/>
     States ; we had free trade with that  coun<lb break="no"/>try. But how has the aspect changed since 
     <lb/>
     then. We do not stand in the same posi<lb break="no"/>tion as we stood in six months ago. The 
     <lb/>
     United States have shewn every disposition 
     <lb/>
     to annex these Provinces, and have shewn a 
     <lb/>
     determination to punish us by every means  in 
     <lb/>
     their power. Besides that  we have been threaten<lb break="no"/>ed with an invasion and it becomes  our duty to 
     <lb/>
     come forward like loyal citizens and to unite our<lb break="no"/>selves for purposes of defence. There are senti<lb break="no"/>ments in this Assembly favorable to annexation, 
     <lb/>
     and if the country were informed of the fact those 
     <lb/>
     sentiments would be hooted at from one end of No<lb break="no"/>va Scotia to the other. Whatever objections   the 
     <lb/>
     people entertained to the Quebec scheme twelve 
     <lb/>
     months ago matters have entirely changed. There 
     <lb/>
     is not a man in my county who is not loyal to the 
     <lb/>
     heart and who would not consent to any scheme 
     <lb/>
     that would save us from annexation or from in<lb break="no"/>vasion Mr. Annard told us that twenty  years ago 
     <lb/>
     the country was calm,  so it was; the dangers of 
     <lb/>
     to-day were then far in the distance and the people 
     <lb/>
     felt at liberty to discuss the minor points of the 
     <lb/>
     scheme of union, and to thwat the government 
     <lb/>
     from motives of self interest, but the aspect has 
     <lb/>
     greatly changed. All the triffling disputes which 
     <lb/>
     have engaged  our attention should be at once 
     <lb/>
     buried  before the great object of maintaining Bri<lb break="no"/>tish connection. The advice of the British  Go<lb break="no"/>vernment and press should lead us to look forward 
     <lb/>
     to the time when we shall become an ally instead 
     <lb/>
     of Colonies of Great Britain,—that is the proud 
     <lb/>
     position of which many of us have looked forward 
     <lb/>
     ever since  we came to the country. Can any one 
     <lb/>
     pretend to say that Great Britain would allow 
     <lb/>
     us to annex ourselves to the United States  when 
     <lb/>
     the Government of that country are threatening 
     <lb/>
     her in every possible manner?  Would the 
     <lb/>
     mother country part with all the resources at her 
     <lb/>
    command in this Province, and allow them to be 
     <lb/>handed over to her bitter enemy ? The idea is 
     <lb/>preposterous. Mr Annand has told us that the 
     <lb/>Railway should precede the union-that might 
     <lb/>be an advantage, but he knows that though that 
     <lb/>matter has been agi'ated for ten or twelve years 
     <lb/>we have failed in obtaining the road  It is quite 
     <lb/>evident that we cannot have these advantages 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

    
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>