<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNSLA_1867-05-02" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>,
<date when="1867-05-02">2 May 1867</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName> <!-- xml markup only - not proofed -->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA"> <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
<date when="1867"/>.
<pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="198"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0191.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0192.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0193.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0194.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0195.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0196.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0197.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0198.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="DLANG4" when="2018-06-19">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0191"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0191.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0192"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0192.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0193"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0193.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0194"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0194.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0195"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0195.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0196"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0196.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0197"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0197.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0198"> <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0198.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="191" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0191.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
<fw type="num">191</fw> 

<p>[...]</p>

<p>force Confederation on the country. The <lb/>
Prov. Sec. accused us of claiming credit for all <lb/>
the good measures which were introduced <lb/>
when we were in office, but if ever there was <lb/>
a set of men who adopted the measure of their <lb/>
predecessors, with the exception of retrench<lb break="no"/>ment, it is the present government. The policy <lb/>
of the late administration was railway exten<lb break="no"/>sion, and that is the only policy in connection <lb/>
with which these gentlemen can truly boast of <lb/>
success. We bequeathed to them the tariff <lb/>
under which they have collected the revenue, <lb/>
and the railway policy which they have been <lb/>
so successful in carrying out. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. PROV. SECY.—I will not detain the <lb/>
House by an address of any length, but I wish <lb/>
to express my regret that by a memorandum <lb/>
prepared from the Journals in the Financial <lb/>
Secretary's office, I was led into an error as to <lb/>
the amount taken by Mr. Howe for the dele<lb break="no"/>gation to Canada. The sum charged against <lb/>
him, I understand, includes the expenses of <lb/>
two of his colleagues. The effect of this is to <lb/>
reduce the $4,000, which I stated as drawn by <lb/>
him during his term of office, to $3,600 as <lb/>
against $2,500 drawn by me, leaving him <lb/>
still $1,100 over the sum which I received. I <lb/>
am glad that the hon. member has referred to <lb/>
the civil list, because he has thus enabled me <lb/>
to state what I had before overlooked; the <lb/>
very important fact that the moment the go<lb break="no"/>vernment accomplished the object of getting <lb/>
power to deal with the civil list, they intro<lb break="no"/>duced a retrenchment bill which reduces the <lb/>
amounts to be paid to the Legislature and the <lb/>
different public officers by $30,000 a year; and <lb/>
the hon member true to his principle of resist<lb break="no"/>ing everything like retrenchment, resisted <lb/>
that measure as far as he was able, and that <lb/>
amount will be saved to the country, because <lb/>
we were enabled to carry the bill in spite of <lb/>
all the opposition which he and his friends <lb/>
could give to it. I will not go into the ques<lb break="no"/>tion whether Mr. Howe could or could not <lb/>
have retained his office for a longer time; but <lb/>
the statement of the hon member tallies <lb/>
strangely with the despatch to Mr. Howe, <lb/>
which is on record, recommending him to close <lb/>
the business of his commission as soon as pos<lb break="no"/>sible. A more imperative command to a pub<lb break="no"/>lic officer to stop drawing the public money <lb/>
never was put on record, and yet we are to ac<lb break="no"/>cept the assurance that Mr. Howe would have <lb/>
been allowed to hold on. I did not bring any <lb/>
such charge against Mr. Howe as that he had <lb/>
sought his own interests only on the delega<lb break="no"/>tion, butI said that the only result of that <lb/>
delegation, for which the hon member for <lb/>
East Halifax, as Financial Secretary, paid Mr. <lb/>
Howe $1,500, was to obtain a good office for <lb/>
himself, and that it therefore ill became his <lb/>
friend to talk about delegations. The hon. <lb/>
member tells us that Mr. Howe did every<lb break="no"/>thing in his power to accomplish the Intercolo<lb break="no"/>nial Railway, but does it lie in his mouth to <lb/>
say that he was engaged in promoting the <lb/>
interests of this country when he was forward<lb break="no"/>ing a measure by which the province was to <lb/>
pay £50,000 per annum for a railway which <lb/>
was so worthless that it would not pay for <lb/>
grease for the wheels? I want to know what <lb/>
excuse he had to make for drawing $1,500 <lb/>
from the pockets of the people and for en<lb break="no"/>deavoring to fasten on the country a liability <lb/>
of £50,000 per annum in connection with a <lb/>

<cb/>

work which was so worthless as that. We <lb/>
were told that the government had adopted <lb/>
the policy of their predecessors. Surely that <lb/>
should not be made a charge against us; but <lb/>
there is a great deal of truth in it; and the fact <lb/>
is, that on every occasion on which we have <lb/>
come forward and carried to maturity the <lb/>
measures on which the hon. member and his <lb/>
friends had staked their public reputation. we <lb/>
were met by the most determined hostility <lb/>
from him and his colleagues <lb/></p> 

<p>On every question affecting the progress of <lb/>
this Province. the hon-gentleman has assum<lb break="no"/>ed the position of an obstructive. All the mea<lb break="no"/>sures which my colleagues 'and myself have <lb/>
been able to promote have been passed in the <lb/>
face of the obstruction of the hon. member. <lb/>
What did he do in reference to the Pictou Bail<lb break="no"/>way? He got over the hon. member for <lb/>
Yarmouth, and every one he could <lb/>
from this side of the house, in order to defeat <lb/>
and obstruct the Government in their progres<lb break="no"/>sive policy. So in respect to the great ques<lb break="no"/>tion of Union, to which he and his friends were <lb/>
so solemnly pledged, he stood forth the un<lb break="no"/>compromising opponent of the Government <lb/>
and the gentlemen who united with them to ac<lb break="no"/>complish that measure of progress. The same <lb/>
course has been pursued by him with respect <lb/>
to the Inter-colonial Railway. No sooner did <lb/>
the present Government take it up and deal <lb/>
with it with the some success that has charac<lb break="no"/>terized their whole action in respect to all <lb/>
measures of progress, then he came forward <lb/>
and did all that man could do to prevent the <lb/>
people of this Province obtaining that great <lb/>
work. It was only necessary for the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, in fact, to propound their policy on any <lb/>
question, and the hon. member ever came out <lb/>
to oppose them. I am quite willing that the <lb/>
hon. member should charge us with having <lb/>
adopted principles which he and his friends <lb/>
had propounded. It is the first duty of a pub<lb break="no"/>lic man to adoptthat policy, and to promote <lb/>
these measures'which they believe are essen<lb break="no"/>tial to the prosperity and development of the <lb/>
country. But we have always stood true to <lb/>
the principles we have ado ted, and carried <lb/>
them successfully through while the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber has deserted them. We have not spent <lb/>
the public moneys on fruitless delegations, but <lb/>
can point to the accomplishment of great mea<lb break="no"/>sures as the evidence of our energy and zeal in <lb/>
the public service. I feel, however, that it is <lb/>
altogether unnecessary for me, to labour this <lb/>
question, for I feel that the honseas well as <lb/>
the country fully! appreciate the position of the <lb/>
hon. member. e stands before the people the <lb/>
opponent of measures of progress. <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon. member has said that we were un<lb break="no"/>able to give such a large grant to the road and <lb/>
bridge service this year in consequence of <lb/>
Confederation. He knows that the press un<lb break="no"/>der his control told the people some months <lb/>
ago that the country was in a bankrupt con<lb break="no"/>dition. Yet this Session he has told us that we <lb/>
were able to build a railway to Annapolis, the <lb/>
Inter—colonial road, and one to Cause as well. <lb/>
But the hon. member must know that it would <lb/>
be impossible to continue the extraordinary <lb/>
grants hitherto given to the road and bridge <lb/>
service the moment we had to bear the annual <lb/>
interest on the Pictou railway. He knows, too, <lb/>
that if it had not, been for Confederation we <lb/>
would not have been able to give the large ex<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="192" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0192.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">192</fw>
<fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw> 

tra grant for the road and bridge service. Our <lb/>
financial position, when the expenses of our <lb/>
great public works are assumed by the Gene<lb break="no"/>ral Government, would be far better than it <lb/>
would be if we remained without uniting our<lb break="no"/>serves with the other Provinces. Then we <lb/>
have made a large saving in the public ex<lb break="no"/>penditure by the measures we have passed <lb/>
this Session in reference to the local constitu<lb break="no"/>tion. The hon. member says we have increas<lb break="no"/>ed the public debt by $200,000; suppose we <lb/>
had, although I deny the accuracy of his state<lb break="no"/>ments, have we got nothing to show for it? <lb/>
How long will it take us to make up that <lb/>
amount? If he looks at the Provincial Build<lb break="no"/>ing being constructed opposite, at the exten<lb break="no"/>sion of the Hospital for the Insane,the St. Pe<lb break="no"/>ter's Canal, and other works of Provincial im<lb break="no"/>portance, he will soon find where $200,000 has <lb/>
gone to. But before I conclude, let me allude <lb/>
to another matter which was a disputed point <lb/>
between us. He questioned the accuracy of <lb/>
my memory as to the amount expended in con<lb break="no"/>nection with laying the corner stone of the Asy<lb break="no"/>lum. I gave the amount at £300,but he stated it <lb/>
was only £320. Now I must admit that I was <lb/>
wrong, and I cheerfully make the correction <lb/>
required. But how was I mistaken? Why, I <lb/>
understated the amount. I find on referring <lb/>
to a speech of Mr. Howe, that that gentleman <lb/>
gives it at £313 7s. 10. I hope, therefore, the <lb/>
hon. member will acknowledge that my ver<lb break="no"/>sion is at least as reliable as his own. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName>—I feel it due to acknowledge <lb/>
an inaccuracy in stating the amount expended <lb/>
by the late Government in the entertainment <lb/>
to which the Provincial Secretary has referred. <lb/>
I spoke, not from memory, but from informa<lb break="no"/>tion given by a friend who sat beside me. But <lb/>
I cannot allow the Provincial Secretary to sit <lb/>
down without replying to the remark in which <lb/>
he accused me of being an obstructionist. I <lb/>
tell him that in all the valuable services which <lb/>
the Government have rendered I was with <lb/>
him. I never voted against the grant for edu<lb break="no"/>cation, nor for roads and bridges, nor naviga<lb break="no"/>tion securities; I never opposed the extension <lb/>
of the railway to Pictou. It is true that I differ<lb break="no"/>ed from the Government on some points of <lb/>
policy, and I have felt it my duty to bring <lb/>
them to book and to ask them why they have <lb/>
not redeemed the pledges which they gave to <lb/>
the country. The Provincial Secretary has re<lb break="no"/>ferred again and again to the action of the <lb/>
People's delegates on the subject of the Inter<lb break="no"/>colonial Railway. My remark that the road <lb/>
would not pay grease for the wheels was the <lb/>
remark of an eminent engineer who had given <lb/>
the subject his attention,—and I must say that <lb/>
my faith in that road, as a means of through <lb/>
traffic, was very much shaken by the report of <lb/>
Mr. Fleming. After a very thorough examina<lb break="no"/>tion, that gentleman demonstrated that the <lb/>
railway would not be a paying concern, and he <lb/>
led us to believe that the terminus would be <lb/>
at St. John. But, as Mr. McLelan proved the <lb/>
other day, our revenues would have enabled <lb/>
us to build the road ourselves, and would aln<lb break="no"/>have enabled us to go on extending our raso <lb/>
ways East and West to the extreme bouil<lb break="no"/>daries of our Province. When I am told that <lb/>
that work is to be a great boon. I ask what are <lb/>
we to pay for it ? On four articles alone we <lb/>
are to pay $300,000 &amp; year; that, with the in<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

crease of the advalorem duties, would give <lb/>
half a million of dollars, and the entire cost of <lb/>
the road, £3,000,000 at 4 per cent., would only <lb/>
be $600,000. And, let me ask, what is to be<lb break="no"/>come of our railway extension hereafter ? <lb/>
Who supposes that we will get it from Canada, <lb/>
with their grand projected fortifications and <lb/>
their expensive canal extension ? But even if <lb/>
the railroad were a great boon, it would be no <lb/>
compensation for the loss of our government <lb/>
and our revenues. We were told the other day <lb/>
by the Attorney General that the People's dele<lb break="no"/>gates continue to oppose the guarantee for <lb/>
the railway even after the Confederation bill <lb/>
had passed. I tell him he is entirely wrong <lb/>
and I hold in my hand a letter from Mr. Howe, <lb/>
stating that the moment he and his friends <lb/>
found Confederation was sure to pass, they <lb/>
withdrew their opposition to the railway. I <lb/>
make that explanation in justice to Mr. Howe; <lb/>
and as for myself,I could not offer opposition. <lb/>
when I was on this side of the water. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Attorney General also taunted us with <lb/>
not having presented the petitions from the <lb/>
people. Let me tell him that that taunt does <lb/>
not become him or his colleagues, for I have <lb/>
good reason to believe that they did their best <lb/>
to prevent our being recognized at the Colonial <lb/>
Office, but in that step they did not succeed— <lb/>
we were heard; and they then used every ex<lb break="no"/>ertion to prevent the voice of the people from <lb/>
being heard. But the Attorney General should <lb/>
have known better than to charge us with not <lb/>
presenting those petitions, for the records of the <lb/>
Imperial Parliament show that those petitions <lb/>
were presented by Admiral Erskine, on the 5th <lb/>
of March, while the bill was in committee. It <lb/>
is stated to have been the largest petition pre<lb break="no"/>sented to the Commons of England. <lb/></p> 

<p>I have been told that the press under my <lb/>
control represented the country as in a bank<lb break="no"/>rupt condition before Confederation; at that <lb/>
time I was not here, and I do not know that I <lb/>
ever read the articles referred to, but is it not a <lb/>
fact that money could not be procured to meet <lb/>
the checks drawn on the treasury of this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. FIN. SEC</persName>.—It is not true, and never was. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> continued :—I am not able to <lb/>
state the facts from my own knowledge, but <lb/>
the general impression in the community to <lb/>
this day is that the assertions were true, and <lb/>
that being the case, it was the duty of the press <lb/>
to represent the facts. The Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary has said that we cannot expect to get so <lb/>
large a sum hereafter for our roads and bridges, <lb/>
but let me ask why not? We have seen the <lb/>
revenue increase in one year by $185,000, being <lb/>
$35,000 more than the interest on the Pictou <lb/>
railway, and if our customs revenue had not <lb/>
been taken away, and handed over to another <lb/>
country, we could have covered the country <lb/>
from end to end with roads. I would like to <lb/>
see the face of the Province covered with rail<lb break="no"/>ways; and as to the Annapolis road, I may say <lb/>
that I think that line should have been carried <lb/>
on by paying a company a subsidy for twenty <lb/>
years, and then we would be done with the <lb/>
liability, and could have gone on with our ex<lb break="no"/>tensions. The subsidy would then have been <lb/>
returned to the treasury, to be re-employed in <lb/>
the construction of other railways and public <lb/>
works. Thus the country would have gone on <lb/>
and prospered, and blossomed as the rose. But <lb/>

<pb n="193" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0193.jpg"/> 
<fw type="num">193</fw>
<fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw> 

under the arrangement which has been effected <lb/>
we are cut short in our career of progress, and <lb/>
the splendid prospect before us is marred. We <lb/>
are to remain, in future, a dependency, not of <lb/>
the mother country, because direct communi<lb break="no"/>cation with the Crown is cut off, but of Canada, <lb/>
and we are to be subjected to her taxation, and <lb/>
to be drawn into her broils and her isolation. <lb/>
That word isolation has been used in reference <lb/>
to Nova Scotia, but Nova Scotia can never be <lb/>
isolated as long as she remains beside the sea, <lb/>
forming a part of the magnificent Empire to <lb/>
which I am proud to belong, and commanding <lb/>
the ports to which every Englishman sailing <lb/>
from the Mersey or the Thames resorts. We <lb/>
are to become a dependency of Canada—to <lb/>
submit to new trade regulations imposed by a <lb/>
country cut off from the rest of the world, whose <lb/>
policy is protection, and to share in her isola<lb break="no"/>tion ; and our people, peaceful, prosperous and <lb/>
happy, are to be identified with the factions, <lb/>
and I might almost say, the bankruptcy of <lb/>
Canada. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CAMP4">Mr. C.J. CAMPBELL</persName>—We have heard a good <lb/>
deal about expenditures for wines, but I can <lb/>
assure the hon. member for East Halifax that <lb/>
it was not all used by the supporters of the <lb/>
government. As regards the expenditure in <lb/>
the Board of Works, it is no good defence to <lb/>
say that the late government did wrong, be— <lb/>
cause every one knows that they were turned <lb/>
out of office for their misdeeds. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. ATTY. GENERAL</persName>—Several matters con<lb break="no"/>nected with the closing of the business of the <lb/>
legislature have called my attention away <lb/>
from the debate up to this time, but I under<lb break="no"/>stand it was produced by an attack made on <lb/>
the Government by the hon. member for North <lb/>
Colchester, which was followed up by a series <lb/>
of attacks on the part of the hon member for <lb/>
East Halifax. There are persons connected <lb/>
with dramatic performances who, after being <lb/>
lost sight of for a time, make their appearance <lb/>
in so different a costume that they can hardly <lb/>
be recognized. If the hon. member would only <lb/>
look in the glass occasionly, and try himself by <lb/>
the different phrases of character which he has <lb/>
assumed for the last twenty—five years, he <lb/>
would hardly know whether he was a repre<lb break="no"/>sentative of East Halifax in this legislature or <lb/>
a native of the South Sea Islands. From the <lb/>
various positions he has assumed, there is no <lb/>
man in the country who can undertake to say <lb/>
whether he is in favor of government construc<lb break="no"/>tion of railways or construction by companies, <lb/>
or whether he is in favor of a capitalization or <lb/>
an annual subsidy for the companies. There <lb/>
is an old adage which tells us that certain per<lb break="no"/>sons of doubtful character should have good <lb/>
memories, but unfortunately the hon. member <lb/>
has not a good memory, and he reminds me of <lb/>
those birds who cover their heads, and think <lb/>
that their whole body is concealed,—having a <lb/>
bad memory himself he is led away by the <lb/>
delusion that every one else has a bad memory <lb/>
also. <lb/></p> 

<p>He accuses us of telling the House that the <lb/>
people's petitions were not presented, but he told <lb/>
us so himself the other day, and gave us the <lb/>
reasons, telling us that he and his colleagues <lb/>
behaved so badly that they could not find a <lb/>
man to present them. I felt that if the 40,000 <lb/>
signers of the petition were satisfied with that <lb/>
excuse we had no great reason to complain, <lb/>
but he went further and gave us another reason <lb/> 

<cb/>

—the assertion that there was not time for them <lb/>
to be presented. I thought that the intelligent <lb/>
public outside would hardly accept these state<lb break="no"/>ments as correct, and when in the face of those <lb/>
assertions he now tells us that his excuses <lb/>
were all a sham, that we did not prevent the <lb/>
petitions from being presented, and that they <lb/>
were really presented, I ask whether the mem<lb break="no"/>bers who have heard him, or the people who <lb/>
read the debates, can place any reliance on <lb/>
what he says. If the petitions were not pre<lb break="no"/>sented, his statement of to-day is untrue,—if <lb/>
they were presented, his charge against the <lb/>
delegates of preventing their presentation is <lb/>
groundless. He made another statement to<lb break="no"/>day with just as much confidence as if he spoke <lb/>
from his own knowledge—that the authorized <lb/>
delegates did all in their power to prevent him <lb/>
and his colleagues from being heard and recog<lb break="no"/>nized. I deny the truth of that assertion and I <lb/>
demand the proof ; —from my knowledge of the <lb/>
feelings of every one of my colleagues, I deny <lb/>
that, by act, word or deed, we did anything to <lb/>
prevent those gentlemen from being heard. If <lb/>
the hon. member does not produce the proof of <lb/>
his assertion, he must stand condemned as a <lb/>
man who will hazard an assertion which he <lb/>
makes out of whole cloth without having the <lb/>
slightest corroboration to support it. <lb/></p> 

<p>But the honorable member went further <lb/>
and not only told us what took place <lb/>
while he was in England, but undertook <lb/>
to contradict my statement of what took <lb/>
place after he left. He says it is not true that <lb/>
the people's delegates tried to prevent the pas<lb break="no"/>sage of the guarantee bill when they found <lb/>
that the Confederation bill was likely to pass, <lb/>
but I ask him did he sign a document bearing <lb/>
his name which was presented to the House of <lb/>
Commons, and which made use of every argu<lb break="no"/>ment to induce the Parliament and the public <lb/>
of England to come to the conclusion that if the <lb/>
railroad were built it would not pay grease for <lb/>
the wheels? But I take the statement which <lb/>
he has just made, and which he gives not only <lb/>
on his own behalf but on that of his colleagues, <lb/>
that the opposition to the guarantee bill was <lb/>
withdrawn, and I make to the House a state<lb break="no"/>ment not from hearsay, but from actual know<lb break="no"/>ledge: the gentleman who led the hon. member <lb/>
from East Halifax and others into opposition <lb/>
to union, in my presence and in the presence of <lb/>
members of the Imperial Parliament after the <lb/>
union bill had passed a second reading, and it <lb/>
was known that it was merely awaiting the <lb/>
guaranty, used language calculated to raise <lb/>
distrust in the colonies, and as far as words <lb/>
could go, induced those who heard him to be<lb break="no"/>lieve that the guaranty would have to be re<lb break="no"/>deemed out of the pockets of the people of Eng<lb break="no"/>and. <lb/></p> 

<p>That is my answer to the hon. gentleman's <lb/>
assertion, and I give it thus specifically be<lb break="no"/>cause he has challenged it. The reply I made <lb/>
at the time was to this effect: "Is that the lan<lb break="no"/>guage that is now used to the people of Eng<lb break="no"/>land ? I can recollect when a gentleman came <lb/>
from Nova Scotia whom the people expected to <lb/>
return with seven millions of dollars, and they <lb/>
were viewing with each other to reward him for <lb/>
this very work." Then the hon. member tells <lb/>
us that the petition was the largest ever pre<lb break="no"/>sented in England but he must have a very <lb/>
imperfect knowledge of the number of names <lb/>
usually appended to petitions in England, or <lb/>

<pb n="194" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0194.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">194</fw>
<fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw> 

he would have known that hundreds of thou<lb break="no"/>sands of names are sometimes presented. He <lb/>
asked us also why we should not hereafter <lb/>
have as large a sum as hitherto for our roads <lb/>
and bridges. Does he expect an answer to that <lb/>
question when himself and others who are ob<lb break="no"/>structing us, have so lately declared that there <lb/>
would be no means by which the annual lia<lb break="no"/>bility for the construction of the Annapolis <lb/>
Railway could be met ? I can answer him in <lb/>
his own words, but one who heard his declara<lb break="no"/>tion to-day, that even with Confederation, by <lb/>
holding on to the subvention, the whole debt <lb/>
connected with that extension would be paid <lb/>
in twenty years, and the picture presented by <lb/>
the future before us waul be a most beautiful <lb/>
one to contemplate. If he makes the calcula<lb break="no"/>tion he will find that, by putting away $5000 <lb/>
a year, he will effect that object even yet. We <lb/>
were to give $16,500 a year, under the former <lb/>
arrangement to the Company, and now we are <lb/>
to give $11,000, so that by investing the balance <lb/>
we will have the debt paid in twenty years. <lb/>
The hon member ridiculed the idea of Nova <lb/>
Scotia being isolated while the flag of England <lb/>
remained to protect us. Let me ask him if that <lb/>
is the language he always holds, and if he and <lb/>
his colleagues did not say to the people of <lb/>
England that a sufficient number of troops <lb/>
could be raised in the State of New York in <lb/>
a month to take these Colonies from the the <lb/>
grasp of England ? If that assertion was true, <lb/>
and the Colonies united would be in so bad a <lb/>
position, I ask him where would little Nova <lb/>
Scotia be with her population of 300,000 inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants ? Her position on the sea renders her <lb/>
more open to attack, unless she has something <lb/>
more reliable than her own resources for de<lb break="no"/>fence. <lb/></p> 

<p>As I said at the outset I have not been able to <lb/>
give much attention to the debate, but I will now <lb/>
refer to the action of the member for North Col<lb break="no"/>chester who, a case in which a complaint was <lb/>
urged against a certain expenditure by the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment He was a member of the Committee <lb/>
on Public Accounts, and, in connection with his <lb/>
duty, had laid before him certain accounts of the <lb/>
Board of Works concerning which he makes a <lb/>
variety of complaints. Now, I ask, has he done <lb/>
his duty to the other members of the Committee, <lb/>
or not? Did he do his duty to the country, if, <lb/>
having complaints to make, he did not bring <lb/>
them to the notice of the gentlemen operating <lb/>
with him in the Committee ? Did be send for the <lb/>
Chairman or any member ofthe Board of Works <lb/>
to explain the alleged irregularities ? As far as <lb/>
I can learn he took no such action, and I regret <lb/>
that the hon member is not in his place to an<lb break="no"/>swer those questions. Why he has thus run <lb/>
away before his conduct was enquired into, is for <lb/>
him to settle with the House, but I can only say <lb/>
that if he desired that justice should be done and <lb/>
a fair investigation had, why did he say nothing <lb/>
in the committee or to the Government about the <lb/>
matters in connection with which he experienced <lb/>
difficulty ? It is evident that the correction of the <lb/>
accounts and the saving of the public money were <lb/>
not his objects, for he waited till the committee <lb/>
reported, and then brought here charges against <lb/>
individuals without taking the trouble to ascer<lb break="no"/>tain whether they were correct or not. His de<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

sire, without doubt, was to get something on <lb/>
which he could attack the Government, making <lb/>
his constituency believe that there was something <lb/>
wrong in the public departments without giving <lb/>
us the slightest opportunity for defence. That is <lb/>
not a position which will recommend itself to the <lb/>
House or to the country, as one that an honora<lb break="no"/>ble and prudent man would occupy. The hon <lb/>
member avoids this by saying that on another <lb/>
subject he applied to the Fin Secretary's office for <lb/>
information and could not obtain it ; but let, us <lb/>
see whether he was not going beyond his com<lb break="no"/>mission. <lb/></p> 

<p>It is a safe rule I think that a man who sticks <lb/>
to his business is most likely to be successful in <lb/>
its accomplishment, and let us see what the hon. <lb/>
member's duties were. He is appointed to take <lb/>
up and examine the Public Accounts to 30th <lb/>
Sep., and he went and applied for a statement of <lb/>
balances due by the Collectors to 30th March. <lb/>
This is the information which he complained of <lb/>
not getting, but I hold it was not within the scope <lb/>
of his duty to ask for it ; he was, arrogating to <lb/>
himself duties which did not belong to him. I do <lb/>
not wish to say anything offensive to the hon. <lb/>
member, but I desire that the public should know <lb/>
that when he was refused that information he had <lb/>
departed from the duty assigned him. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LONG1">Mr. LONGLEY</persName>: — I was not in the House to-day <lb/>
when the hon. member for East Halifax made an <lb/>
attack on the government, and I may not there<lb break="no"/>fore be fully aware of the tenor of his remarks, <lb/>
but I am informed that he made an allusion to <lb/>
the wood contract recently entered into on the <lb/>
Railway Department. Being a party to the con<lb break="no"/>tract I am willing to hear my share of responsibi<lb break="no"/>lity and I think I can shew that the contract was <lb/>
not a disadvantageous one. I will state the prices <lb/>
which the department has paid for wood during <lb/>
the three or four years preceding the commence<lb break="no"/>ment of Mr. Hyde's contract, and also the prices <lb/>
paid outside of that contract because the agree<lb break="no"/>ment does not include the Windsor branch. In <lb/>
1863 we paid for wood $2.31 per cord, in 1864, <lb/>
$2.38, in 1866, $2 52, in 1866, $2 91. <lb/></p> 

<p>Now it must be borne in mind that though the <lb/>
contract is dated lst April, 1865, yet up to the <lb/>
year terminating 30th Sepr , we had used only <lb/>
2000 cords from Mr. Hyde, and yet the average <lb/>
price of wood for that year including Mr. Hyde's <lb/>
wood was, as I have said, $2 91. It is believed <lb/>
that the wood furnished by Mr. Hyde will be <lb/>
worth ten per cent more than that furnished here<lb break="no"/>tofore, because he is not only obliged to keep a <lb/>
large supply on hand, but he is to furnish season <lb/>
ed wood for shed-assuming, however, the quality <lb/>
to be the same as heretofore, it will be $2.72 per <lb/>
cord or 19 cents less than the regular price, and <lb/>
if it is to be worth ten per cent more, then its cost <lb/>
would only amount to $2 00. <lb/></p> 

<p>But there are other facts to shew that the con<lb break="no"/>tract will be advantageous. We paid at Shuben<lb break="no"/>acadie and Stillwater, right in the woods, in 1866, <lb/>
$2.89 per cord. In 1863 the consumption of <lb/>
wood by the department was 4,150 cords; the con<lb break="no"/>sumption in the nine months of 1864 was 3,400 <lb/>
cords ; and that of 1866 was nearly 7,000 cords. <lb/></p>

<pb n="195" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0195.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
<fw type="num">195</fw> 

<p>Not only has the price, therefore, been rapidly in<lb break="no"/>creasing, but the consumption has been increas<lb break="no"/>ing in the same ratio, and I am not quite sure <lb/>
but we would have had to pay by tender and con<lb break="no"/>tract, in 1867, fully $3 00 even for the wood in an <lb/>
imperfect state. There is the best evidence that <lb/>
before the end of the five years we would have <lb/>
had to pay $3.25 or $3.50 per cord ; and I there<lb break="no"/>fore think that the hon. member is likely to make <lb/>
about as much advantage out of this transaction <lb/>
as out of the others which he so bungled. He <lb/>
evidently feels that be cannot do worse than he <lb/>
has done, and he continues floundering about in <lb/>
the hope that something will occur to better his <lb/>
position. In connection with this subject, I am <lb/>
in a positition to furnish the opinion of one whose <lb/>
experience of twenty-five or thirty years should <lb/>
entitle his views to some consideration. Before <lb/>
entering into the contract, having some doubts <lb/>
as to the propriety of making an agreement run<lb break="no"/>ning so far ahead, I made enquiries of the loco<lb break="no"/>motive superintendent, and he stated that his ex<lb break="no"/>perience led him to believe that wood obtained at <lb/>
$3 per cord is cheaper to burn than coal. It is <lb/>
supposed by many that as the railway will run to <lb/>
Pictou harbor, opposite the coal fields, where an <lb/>
inexhaustible supply is to be obtained, it would <lb/>
be cheaper to burn coal ; but experience shows <lb/>
that the contract with Mr. Hyde was dictated by <lb/>
economy, and is likely to prove advantageous to <lb/>
the department. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName>—As the hon. gentleman has cho<lb break="no"/>sen to make an attack upon me, I would only <lb/>
tell him that if I were disposed to give him a cer<lb break="no"/>tificate of character, I would quote the language <lb/>
of Mr. Archibald, who described a certain build<lb break="no"/>ing across the harbor as the appropriate place for <lb/>
the Railway Commissioner. It is unfortunate <lb/>
that the hon. gentleman did not hear my remarks, <lb/>
for they did not relate to the prices, as I knew no<lb break="no"/>thing of them ; but I contended that it was a piece <lb/>
of administrative mismanagement, with the rail<lb break="no"/>way running into the heart of a coal region, to <lb/>
enter into a contract for the supply of wood for <lb/>
five years. I am content to leave it to the judg<lb break="no"/>ment of any engineer to say whether that was a <lb/>
provident bargain or not, and I know it is contra<lb break="no"/>ry to the reports made by the engineers of previous <lb/>
governments. The hon. member is one of those <lb/>
gentlemen who came in on the cry of retrench<lb break="no"/>ment, and his idea was that the late comissioner <lb/>
should receive £250 instead of £600 per annum, <lb/>
but he himself has found no difficulty in taking <lb/>
£600 a year while he has been in office. The <lb/>
hon. member's consistency, however, shews itself <lb/>
in everything. A few years ago he proclaimed <lb/>
that " rum and railways were the ruin of the <lb/>
country." I am not prepared to say whether he <lb/>
has changed his views as to rum, but we know <lb/>
that he has not hesitated to accept the post of <lb/>
Chief Commissioner of Railways. As to his ca<lb break="no"/>pacity for that position, we will ascertain whether <lb/>
the General Government, requiring the services <lb/>
of first-rate men, will continue his engagement. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>.—As to the statement that <lb/>
the hon. member for East Halifax and his col<lb break="no"/>leagues on the delegation withdrew their hos<lb break="no"/>tility to the Intercolonial Railway immediate<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

ly on the passage of the Union Bill, I would <lb/>
ask whether he has any information of Mr. <lb/>
Howe going to the gentlemen whom he had <lb/>
urged to oppose the guaranty—whose opposi<lb break="no"/>tion he had boasted of—to one of the most <lb/>
talented members of the Commons, Mr. Lowe <lb/>
and confessed to them that he had deceived <lb/>
and misled them. If he did so, and if he asked <lb/>
permission to withdraw the statement that our <lb/>
credit was not worth a dollar, and that a man <lb/>
trusting British America a pound would lose <lb/>
it, because we would repudiate the debt, then <lb/>
he is in a position to say that their oppo<lb break="no"/>sition to the railway was withdrawn, but he <lb/>
must not tell me that the opposition was <lb/>
withdrawn. After the Union Bill was endors<lb break="no"/>ed by an ovewhelming majority, that hon. <lb/>
member in the House and in the press did his <lb/>
best to defeat the project and to prevent the <lb/>
Provinces having the benefit of three millions <lb/>
of pounds sterling expended among them. I <lb/>
could take up the paper edited by the hon. <lb/>
gentleman and could shew the House that day <lb/>
by day he denounced the railway as a worth<lb break="no"/>less expenditure of the public money. If he <lb/>
and the party with which he co-operates could <lb/>
succeed in deluding the people of the County <lb/>
of Halifax and of the country, into believing <lb/>
his statements and supporting their candidates <lb/>
they would prevent the construction of a mile <lb/>
of railway in the Province. The portion of <lb/>
the line which is ready to be taken up at once <lb/>
is the portion between Truro and Monoton, but <lb/>
if these gentlemen could succeed in procuring <lb/>
the return of nineteen members to the House <lb/>
of Commons, pledged to demand a repeal of <lb/>
the Union they would cut off this Province <lb/>
from the rest of British America, and what go<lb break="no"/>vernment could be found in Canada willing to <lb/>
expend a dollar on a line of railway until the <lb/>
lapse of half a dozen years when the safety of <lb/>
the experiment was tried ? <lb/></p> 

<p>If the hon. member can convince the people <lb/>
of Canada and New Brunswick, who will be <lb/>
united, because New Brunswick will send a <lb/>
united phalanx of union men to strengthen the <lb/>
hands of the first government to be formed to <lb/>
secure the construction of the road, that he has <lb/>
withdrawn his opposition in the face of his de<lb break="no"/>claration that the business of the remaining <lb/>
portion of his life would be to cut off Nova Sco<lb break="no"/>tia from the rest of British America, making <lb/>
St. John the terminus as a matter of necessity, <lb/>
then he will have to take back these declara<lb break="no"/>tions which he has made in the press and on <lb/>
the platform. But while the paper under his <lb/>
control, and the party with whom he acts are <lb/>
putting repeal on their banners and showing <lb/>
a determination to obstruct the union, if I <lb/>
were a Canadian or a New Brunswicker with <lb/>
a seat in Parliament, I would say, " Hold your <lb/>
hand ; if Nova Scotia is determined not to as<lb break="no"/>sist in carrying out the great objects of union, <lb/>
and to break up the Confederation, it would be <lb/>
an act of insanity to spend a dollar in Nova <lb/>
Scotia until the question is fully tried out, and <lb/>
until ten years hence it is seen whether repeal <lb/>
is to be the motto, or whether Nova Scotia is <lb/>
prepared to show the benefits flowing from the <lb/>
Act of Union." The position of the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber and of every anti-unionist at this hour is <lb/>
the position of total antagonism to the Interco<lb break="no"/>lonial Railway, and if the people of Halifax <lb/>
and the rest of the Province expect such men <lb/>

<pb n="196" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0196.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">196</fw>
<fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw> 

as their representaves, I do not hesitate to say <lb/>
that we could not expect such an act of in<lb break="no"/>sanity as the expenditure of a pound on the <lb/>
portion of the railway which should run <lb/>
through Nova Scotia. If there are men among <lb/>
us so reckless of their own position in the eye <lb/>
of the public as to take up the attitude of ob<lb break="no"/>struction, and to place themselves in a position <lb/>
to be over-ridden by the public sentiment of <lb/>
the country, I have no fear of the action of the <lb/>
intelligent citizens of Halifax, knowing how <lb/>
deeply they are interested in giving such co<lb break="no"/>operations as will secure to this city all the <lb/>
benefits to result from the construction of the <lb/>
great highway of nations, and the action which <lb/>
I think will take place in this constituency will <lb/>
be endorsed by every intelligent constituency <lb/>
in the Province. The hon. member for East <lb/>
Halifax has gone too far in his declarations re<lb break="no"/>specting the position of this Province and the <lb/>
Intercolonial Railway, to obtain the confidence <lb/>
of an number of the electors. Whoever will <lb/>
be elected, the selection will be made from <lb/>
among those who have a regard for the posi<lb break="no"/>tion and prosperity of the Province. for the <lb/>
people know that to elect the men who have <lb/>
been traducing every public man who has <lb/>
given his aid to the union, and have been <lb/>
trampling on and treating with contempt the <lb/>
credit of Canada, would be only explicable on <lb/>
the ground that they are utterly blinded to <lb/>
their interests and to the prosperity of the <lb/>
country. Now that the policy of union is set<lb break="no"/>tled, many of its strongest opponents will be <lb/>
found like the Custos of this country, who, in <lb/>
taking his seat as chairman of the meeting the <lb/>
other evening, and that he had taken a very <lb/>
active part in politics, but he felt that, regard<lb break="no"/>less of the past, now that union has become the <lb/>
law of the land, as loyal citizens we are bound <lb/>
to come out, and giving the law our support, <lb/>
place the resentation in the hands of the <lb/>
friends of union. Suppose that to-morrow the <lb/>
member for East Halifax were elected to serve <lb/>
in the House of Commons, with what face could <lb/>
he rise in that Parliament and ask the aid of a <lb/>
single man on one side or the other in any <lb/>
question in which the interests of Nova Scotia <lb/>
were concerned? After the assertion that Ca<lb break="no"/>nada was in a bankrupt condition, made not<lb break="no"/>withstanding that her debentures and ours are <lb/>
the highest of any of the Provinces, from the <lb/>
fact that, although she had made enormous ex<lb break="no"/>penditures in connection with defence and in <lb/>
the extension of her canals. her surplus was <lb/>
so large as to warrant her credit being placed <lb/>
as high as ours, flourishing as is the financial <lb/>
condition of Nova Scotia. I ask even if a con<lb break="no"/>stituency in Nova Scotia were found to elect <lb/>
him to-morrow, where would he hide his <lb/>
head? To ask for any consideration for his <lb/>
country would require an amount of audacity <lb/>
even exceeeding that which he displayed in at<lb break="no"/>tacking the financial policy of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment The ground on which I confidently ex<lb break="no"/>pect that the interests of Nova Scotia will be <lb/>
considered paramount to those of any section <lb/>
of British America is that we have men of <lb/>
standing and ability who will go to the united <lb/>
Parliament and lay before it claims which no <lb/>
Parliament could ignore. We will find men <lb/>
in the ranks of both the Liberal and Conser<lb break="no"/>vative parties, who, without reference to the <lb/>
political differences heretofore existing among <lb/>
us, will go there and claim that consideration <lb/>

<cb/>

which is due to those who have carried for<lb break="no"/>ward the great measure of union on which our <lb/>
common prosperity depends. <lb/></p> 

<p>The union bill was carried in the British <lb/>
Parliament notwithstanding all that the hon. <lb/>
member for East Halifax and his colleagues <lb/>
could do to damage the credit of the Province, <lb/>
to represent the railway as a useless undertak<lb break="no"/>ing, and to make it appear that the object of <lb/>
Nova Scotia was to break up and destroy the <lb/>
Confederation. We have had it represented <lb/>
to-day, and have heard through the anti-union <lb/>
press, that Nova Scotia is in so helpless a con<lb break="no"/>dition that all the government of the United <lb/>
States has to do is to refuse to establish com<lb break="no"/>mercial relations with us in order to embarrass <lb/>
our trade, and that they can come down when<lb break="no"/>ever they please and seize on the colonies. I <lb/>
ask if that is the way to advance the interests <lb/>
of the country—to proclaim that we must fall <lb/>
a helpless prey to the first aggressor? He says <lb/>
that to attempt to open up a trade with any <lb/>
other country than the States is useless, and <lb/>
he follows it up by denouncing the men who <lb/>
have striven to place us in a most prosperous <lb/>
condition commercially, and to bring to our <lb/>
aid the whole force of the Empire in the event <lb/>
of an attack. I do not wonder that this gen<lb break="no"/>tleman, instead of being like the delegates sent <lb/>
by this legislature, ready to go back and place <lb/>
their future fate and fortunes in the hands of <lb/>
the electors ; conscious of what he deserves, <lb/>
skrinks from the defeat to which he must ex<lb break="no"/>pose himself in going before any constituency. <lb/>
He sends to the county of Queens to see if <lb/>
that constituency will afford him an escape <lb/>
from the averted faces of the electors of East <lb/>
Halifax, and back comes the modifying reply <lb/>
that, though money to any amount had been <lb/>
offered by the capitalists who are ready to <lb/>
back him, an anti-unionist could be returned <lb/>
for Queens. That is the position in which he <lb/>
has placed himself by endeavoring to place the <lb/>
country in such a condition as would make us <lb/>
a bye-word and laughing-stock for all time to <lb/>
come.   Having committed himself to that <lb/>
course it is too late for him to say that it was a <lb/>
little piece of deception used for another ob<lb break="no"/>ject; he cannot thus wipe out the record that <lb/>
will stand against him to the end of time. I <lb/>
do not wonder in the face of that record that <lb/>
on his return from England, as he told us the <lb/>
other day, on making a hasty visit to his con<lb break="no"/>stituents, he told his friends in Halifax that he <lb/>
had made up his mind to bid good—bye to pub<lb break="no"/>lic life. I can only say as regards myself that <lb/>
I should like to do the same, I have accom<lb break="no"/>plished as much for my country as most pub<lb break="no"/>lic men could have done, and would be glad <lb/>
now to escape from the turmoil and responsi<lb break="no"/>bility of the public service, but I feel that hav<lb break="no"/>ing undertaken a great responsibility in deal— <lb/>
ing with the question of union, it would ill be<lb break="no"/>come me, having no such record against me as <lb/>
that which stands against the hon member for <lb/>
East Halifax, to shrink from devoting my <lb/>
services still further to my country, more espe<lb break="no"/>cially as my exertions in connection with this <lb/>
great question will give me an advantage over <lb/>
most of my countrymen in claiming consider— <lb/>
ation for the claims of the Province. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> - It must be evident that the hon <lb/>
gentleman is in a most desperate condition when <lb/>
he is willing to place the whole fate of his party <lb/>

<pb n="197" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0197.jpg"/> 
<fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
<fw type="num">197</fw>
 
on the single question of the Intercolonial Rail<lb break="no"/>way. I am surprised that he of all others should <lb/>
rise here and speak of the people—he who sold <lb/>
their interests and denied them the right even to <lb/>
speak by petition to the House of Commons. <lb/>
How has he the audacity to mention the people or <lb/>
to present himself before any constituency? Are <lb/>
the people of Nova Scotia less worthy than those <lb/>
of New Brunswick, who have been allowed to <lb/>
speak twice, when we are denied the privilege al<lb break="no"/>together ? If the people of Nova Scotia gave <lb/>
him the treatment he might expect, they would <lb/>
pitch him over the first hustings at which he pre <lb/>
sented himself. The Prov. Secretary undertook <lb/>
to censure my language in reference to the public <lb/>
men of Canada, but we find the leader of the <lb/>
opposition of that country styling them the " cor<lb break="no"/>ruptionists of Canada." What is the history of <lb/>
their finances but a continuation of deficiencies <lb/>
from year to year ? <lb/></p> 

<p>I am told that I tried to destroy the public <lb/>
credit. That is not true; but in speaking of <lb/>
British America under Canadian rule, I had a <lb/>
right to draw the inference that these "corrup<lb break="no"/>tionists" would be faithless to their engagements <lb/>
with the mother country. If the credit of Cana<lb break="no"/>da has risen lately, as was bosted so loudly, it <lb/>
was by means of manipulations which we fully <lb/>
understand; but I hold in my hand a copy of the <lb/>
Canadian News, the organ of the Grand Trunk <lb/>
Railway Company, and l find it states that the <lb/>
debentures of Nova Scotia are at present from 97 <lb/>
to 99 while those of Canada are from 95 to 97. <lb/>
With that damming fact stated by their own au<lb break="no"/>thorities, how dare any one make the assertion <lb/>
that the credit of Canada is superior to that of <lb/>
Nova Scotia? If the Intercoloulal Railway had <lb/>
been fifty times as valuable as it is, my action <lb/>
would have been the same, and I would not even <lb/>
for that consideratron have given up the liberties <lb/>
of my country. We knew that the railway scheme <lb/>
was an essential part of the union arrangement, <lb/>
and we hoped, by combining the opposition on <lb/>
these two measures, to defeat the bill. We are <lb/>
told that we may not have the terminus of the <lb/>
railway if we send nineteen members of the Nova <lb/>
Scotia party to Ottawa. If Halifax be the natural <lb/>
terminus, and the interests of trade require that <lb/>
the road should extend here, it would be imma<lb break="no"/>terial whether Nova Scotia formed part of the <lb/>
Confederation or not. But we find Mr. Adderly, <lb/>
the Assistant Secretary for the Colonies, stating <lb/>
that the cost, of the road would be four millions <lb/>
sterling, and we find that only three millions have <lb/>
been provided. We see also that this three mil<lb break="no"/>lions will just build the road to St. John ; and 1 <lb/>
therefore charge it upon the delegates that they <lb/>
were recreant to their duty in not making it a part <lb/>
of the agreement that the construction of the rail<lb break="no"/>way should commence simultaneously at Riviere <lb/>
du Loup and Truro. In that case the interests <lb/>
of Nova Scotia would have been safe, which they <lb/>
are not now. It is true the Union Act declares <lb/>
it to be the duty of Canada to carry the road to <lb/>
completion; but we see the Canadians were not <lb/>
bound by their minute of council in 1862, and if <lb/>
it were not for their breach of faith on that occa<lb break="no"/>sion, we might now be connected by rail with <lb/>

<cb/>

Quebec. We are asked what we have to expect <lb/>
in sending nineteen anti-unionists to Ottawa. We <lb/>
expect to be represented by men who will not d-— <lb/>
ny the people the right to speak—who will, as a <lb/>
body of Nova Scotians, protect us, guarding our <lb/>
rights from invasion, and who will not act like the <lb/>
delegates who went to Canada, forgetting their <lb/>
country as soon as they turned their backs upon it. <lb/>
The gentlemen going from Nova Scotia will, I <lb/>
trust, stand in one firm phalanx, true to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple who send them there. I am asked if we re<lb break="no"/>quested Mr. Lowe to withdraw his opposition to <lb/>
the Intercolonial Railway: that I cannot say, but <lb/>
I have it from Mr. Howe that the moment Con<lb break="no"/>federation was settled he ceased opposition, and <lb/>
I believe put himself in communication with <lb/>
those from whom he expected support, and ask<lb break="no"/>ed that their opposition cease. As to Mr. Lowe, <lb/>
I can only say that the first intimation we had <lb/>
that that gentleman would oppose the guarantee <lb/>
was received from an intimate acquaintance of the <lb/>
Provincial Secretary on the other side of the wa<lb break="no"/>ter. The Provincial Secretary, as I have said, is <lb/>
the last man to rise here and make a passionate <lb/>
appeal. If he had done by the people as Mr. <lb/>
Tilley did by the people of New Brunswick, and <lb/>
the electors had given their solemn assent to the <lb/>
measure, I would not have said another word; <lb/>
but as the people have been denied their ordinary <lb/>
rights, I for one will not cease to agitate for <lb/>
the return to Ottawa of men who possess the pub<lb break="no"/>lic confidence - men who would not have denied <lb/>
the peeple the right to speak. If the people of <lb/>
this Province were to address the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons in something like this language : "You<lb break="no"/>have been imposed on ; the chairman of the Grand <lb/>
Trunk Railway told you that the question had <lb/>
been before us at every hustings, whereas our <lb/>
voice has never been asked until recently,when we <lb/>
hurled all these men from power who have ven<lb break="no"/>tured thus to mislead you,"— I ask, would there <lb/>
be any harm in requesting the British Parliament <lb/>
to release us, and to restore the old relations mak<lb break="no"/>ing as once more a colony not of Canada, but of <lb/>
England? Surely there can be no treason in that <lb/>
sentiment, and it could not but benefit this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince to have restored to it the large and increas<lb break="no"/>ing revenues which we possess, and to remain a <lb/>
dependency of England. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon PROV SEC</persName>—I have only one remark to <lb/>
make, and that is in relation to the action of New <lb/>
Brunswick. We have given the Opposition two <lb/>
years to find a case in which a minister, with a <lb/>
majority in Parliament, ever appealed to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple, and not being able to produce one such case, <lb/>
they yet rise and repeat the old story about the <lb/>
rights of the people having been invaded. In <lb/>
New Brunswick the Premier thought to advance <lb/>
the measure by dissolving the House, and what a <lb/>
spectacle was presented. By means of certain <lb/>
influences brought to hear an overwhelming ma<lb break="no"/>jority was returned against the measure, and a <lb/>
second appeal resulted in the people sending an <lb/>
overwhelming majority to its en support. Would <lb/>
that be a creditable spectacle for Nova Scotia to <lb/>
present? But let me ask the hon member if he <lb/>
did not, on the face of public document, declare <lb/>
that the action of New Brunswick was the greatest <lb/>

<pb n="198" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-05-02_Page_0198.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw> 
<fw type="num">198</fw>  

brand of disgrace that could rest on a people, and <lb/>
ywas only to be compared to a corrupt verdict <lb/>
given by a brow-beaten jury ? <lb/>
The House then adjourned. <lb/></p> 

<!-- DL 2018-06-19 commented out below as it is not part of this debate day -->

<!--<p>FRIDAY, MAY 2 <lb/></p> 

<p>House met at 11 o'clock. <lb/>
Mr WHITMAN presented a report from the <lb/>
Committee on Crown Lands, and introduced in <lb/>
Accordance therewith a bill to make void a grant <lb/>
of Crown Lands. <lb/></p> 

<p>BILLS. <lb/></p> 

<p>The House then went into Committee on Bills, <lb/>
and passed the bill to provide for the road ser<lb break="no"/>vice in the County of Digby ; the bill to provide <lb/>
for the building of a bridge across the Salmon <lb/>
River in the County of Guysboro' ; the bill rela<lb break="no"/>tive to the Station for the Windsor and Annape-<lb break="maybe"/>lis Railway ; the bill to repeat Chap 19 of the <lb/>
Acts of 1-59, and to substitute other provisions <lb/>
in lieu thereof ; the bill to amend Chap 70, R S, <lb/>
"Of Railroads," being in reference to the appor<lb break="no"/>tionment of railway damages in Hants County ; <lb/>
the bill to legalize the list of electors, and the bill <lb/>
to enable the Trustees of Preston School Sectiol <lb/>
to obtain certain lands. <lb/></p> 

<p>The bill introduced by the Crown Land Com <lb/>
mitee, to make void the grant to Mary McDon<lb break="no"/>ald and others, was then taken up. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon FIN SEO said that this bill would have the <lb/>
effect of setting aside a judgment delivered by one <lb/>
of his colleagues and himself. A person named <lb/>
Ronald McDonald some years ago, had lodged <lb/>
money for a grant, and before the grant was is<lb break="no"/>sued Mr P Smyth obtained a judgment against <lb/>
him. On the death of McDonald the grant was <lb/>
claimed by the wife and heirs on the one side, and <lb/>
Mr Smyth on the other. The decision had been <lb/>
in favor of the former. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon ATTY GEN explained that Mr Smyth was <lb/>
not only a judgment creditor, but had taken out <lb/>
letters of administration, under which this pro<lb break="no"/>perty had been sold to pay the debts of McDon<lb break="no"/>ald, and the grant, therefore, interfered with the <lb/>
rights of the other creditors. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr ARCHIBALD expressed himself adverse to <lb/>
the policy of making the grant, but said that if the <lb/>
principle of the bill were adopted it would make <lb/>
the rights of property dependant on a vote of the <lb/>
Legislature. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr S MCDONNELL said that if McDonald were <lb/>
living his heirs would not receive the grant, and <lb/>
their rights should not prevail over Mr Smyth's <lb/>
who stood in the place of their father as regards <lb/>
his title. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr MILLER agreed that nothing but an ex<lb break="no"/>treme case would justify the legislation proposed, <lb/>
but this was an extreme case. A serious wrong <lb/>
had been done and some remedy should be given. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon MR SHANNON, as one ofthe members of <lb/>
the Executie who gave the decision, said that <lb/>
the conclusion they had arrived at so far com<lb break="no"/>mended itself to his judgment, that he would take <lb/>
the same course if the matter were open again. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon FIN SECRETARY thought that the Judge <lb/>
in Equity should have the power possessed by <lb/>
the Chancellor in England of making void any <lb/>
grant by which a palpable wrong was done. He, <lb/></p> 

<p>however, sustained the grant which had been <lb/>
made to the widow and heirs. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr ARCHIBALD suggested that the matter be <lb/>
compromised by Mr Smith being compensated for <lb/>
whatever injury he had sustained. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr C J CAMPBELL said that the Crown Land <lb/>
Committee were forced on a consideration of the <lb/>
whole case to the conclusion at which they arriv<lb break="no"/>ed. The revocation of the grant would leave the <lb/>
parties in their original position, and they could <lb/>
then take their legal remedy. He was opposed to <lb/>
compensation being made from the treasury. <lb/></p> 

<p>Ilon ATTY GENERAL agreed with Mr Archi<lb break="no"/>bald that the proposed legislation would be un<lb break="no"/>constitutional. He supported the propsal for <lb/>
compensation. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr TOWNSEND was of opinion that the go<lb break="no"/>vernment had done perfectly right in making the <lb/>
grant. He thought it would be outrageous to <lb/>
give Mr. Smyth the amount of the judgement ;<lb break="no"/>how could it be ascertained what protion of it was <lb/>
paid ? <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr MILLER replied that Mr Smyth's affidavit <lb/>
that the debt was still outstanding; was attached <lb/>
to the paper. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr C J CAMPBELL said that this case shewed <lb/>
the necessity for pacing at the heads of depart<lb break="no"/>ments men who were fitted for the work. The <lb/>
general opinion seemed to be that the lawyers <lb/>
were fitted for everything. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr MILLER said that the dispute would be <lb/>
greatly multiplied if it were not for the legal <lb/>
training of the men of whose unfitness the hon <lb/>
member complained. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon ATTY GEN moved that the bill be referred <lb/>
to a select Commitee to report the amount which <lb/>
would compensate Mr Smyth for the injury done <lb/>
himm. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr TOWNSEND moved that the proposal for <lb/>
compensation be not agreed to. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr HATFIELD seconded. The original reso<lb break="no"/>lution passed 18 to 12. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Committee adjourned. <lb/></p> 

<p>Halifax Road Scale <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon Mr SHANNON laid on the table the road <lb/>
scale for Halifax Co. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr ANNAND regretted that a difficulty had <lb/>
arisen this session for the first time between his <lb/>
colleagues from West Halifax and himself on the <lb/>
subject of the road monies. He contended that <lb/>
the special grant for the County should be subdi<lb break="no"/>vided before the prorogation of the legislature. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon Mr SHANNON did not see what the road <lb/>
scale had to do with the special grant, which was <lb/>
always left in the hands of the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr ANNAND said that the hon gentleman was <lb/>
himself a member of the Government, and under <lb/>
the arrangement proposed, would himself control <lb/>
the special grant entirely. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr PRYOR said that the course pursued was the <lb/>
one always adopted. <lb/></p> 

<p>The House adjorned. <lb/></p> 

<p>AFTERNOON SESSION <lb/></p> 

<p>The house resumed at 3 o'clock. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. PROV. SEC. laid on the table corres<lb break="no"/>pondence relative to the Naval Brigade. <lb/></p>

<milestone type="unknown"/>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>