<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNSLA_1867-04-08"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1867-04-01">1 April 1867</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNSLA">
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
<title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Fourth Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
<date when="1867"/>.  
<pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="116"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0110.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0111.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0112.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0113.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0114.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0115.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0116.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
 
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-13">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-06-13">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0110">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0110.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0111">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0111.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0112">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0112.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0113">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0113.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0114">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0114.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0115">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0115.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0116">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0116.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="110" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0110.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">110</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
           
<!-- GL, 2018-06-20, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

 <!--<p>
     Mr. CHURCHILL presented to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment a petition from Five-mile River. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>The house then adjourned till Monday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <head rendition="simple:right">
     MONDAY, April 8th. 
     <lb/>
     
         </head>

            <p>The house met at 3 P. M. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     MISCELLANEOUS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
    <persName ref="pers:MCDO4">Hon. FIN. SEC</persName>. introduced a bill to amend 
     <lb/>
     chap. 2 Acts of 1866. He said that the object 
     <lb/>
     was to enable parties to withdraw from bond<lb break="no"/>ed warehouses articles for manufacture, giving 
     <lb/>
     bonds for the payment of the duties. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> said that some cargoes of mer<lb break="no"/>chandize, after being deposited in the ware<lb break="no"/>house, could be re-guaged before being taken 
     <lb/>
     out, and the duty paid according to the last 
     <lb/>
     measurement, but articles of bulk could not be 
     <lb/>
     re-weighed. There was frequently a great loss 
     <lb/>
     of weight in a cargo of sugar, after remaining 
     <lb/>
     warehoused for some months; and it was un<lb break="no"/>fair to dealers and consumers to charge the 
     <lb/>
     duty according to the original weight. This 
     <lb/>
     circumstance had seriously diminished the 
     <lb/>
     trade with Canada, for purchasers there had 
     <lb/>
     preferred going to New York, where they could 
     <lb/>
     get the article re-weighed. There was no dan<lb break="no"/>ger of embezzlement from the warehouse, and 
     <lb/>
     it was unfair to make parties pay for quanti<lb break="no"/>ties which they did not get. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO4">Hon. FIN. SEC</persName>. thought that the practice of 
     <lb/>
     paying duties on the original weight must have 
     <lb/>
     originated in a desire on the part of the whole<lb break="no"/>sale dealers to sell at the original marks. There 
     <lb/>
     was no desire to exact a revenue from that 
     <lb/>
     which did not go into use. He would make en<lb break="no"/>quiries and ascertain the position of the mat<lb break="no"/>ter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Legislative Council announced that they 
     <lb/>
     had agreed to the bill concerning departmental 
     <lb/>
     officers and their salaries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. S. CAMPBELL</persName> presented two petitions— 
     <lb/>
    one for the removal of obstructions in Salmon 
     <lb/>River, the other for a way office at Indian Har<lb break="no"/>bor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> presented a petition from A. M. 
     <lb/>Uniacke and 1500 other citizens of Halifax, 
     <lb/>against the bill to amend the charter of the 
     <lb/>City Street Railway Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HILL1">Mr. Hill</persName> presented a petition from Hants, on 
     <lb/>
     the same subject. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> presented three petitions from 
     <lb/>
     Dartmouth, Bedford, and Elmsdale, on the 
     <lb/>
     same subject. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCKA1">Mr. MCKAY</persName> presented four petitions from 
     <lb/>
     Pictou, on the same subject. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PRYO1">Mr. PRYOR</persName> presented a petition from citizens 
     <lb/>
     of Halifax, praying for an amendment of the 
     <lb/>
     charter of the City Street Railway Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> presented a petition from Wa<lb break="no"/>verly asking for a change of Polling place. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> presented a petition from 875 
     <lb/>
     merchants, grocers and liquor dealers asking 
     <lb/>
     such a change in the license law as would pre<lb break="no"/>vent the separation of the sale of groceries from 
     <lb/>
     that of liquors. The petition also contained a 
     <lb/>
     recommendation from nine Aldermen. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PRYO1">Mr. PRYOR</persName> presented a petition from forty 
     <lb/>
     junk dealers asking a reduction in the charge 
     <lb/>
     for their licenses. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BROW3">Dr. BROWN</persName> introduced a bill to incorporate 
     <lb/>
     St. George's Lodge of Freemasons, Wolfville. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PARK1">Mr. PARKER</persName> presented five petitions from 
     <lb/>
     Colchester County against the proposed am<lb break="no"/>
       

            <cb/>
         
endment to the Charter of the City Street Rail<lb break="no"/>way Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HATF2">Mr. HATFIELD</persName> introduced a bill to author<lb break="no"/>ise the inhabitants of Argyle to sell a fire en<lb break="no"/>gine. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> called attention to an omission 
     <lb/>
     in the Act recently passed in reference to re<lb break="no"/>presentation: In the Acts of 1859 there was a 
     <lb/>
     statute providing for nominations in the differ<lb break="no"/>ent ridings. There was nothing in the bill to 
     <lb/>
     show in what localities the nominations could 
     <lb/>
     be held under the new law. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HENR1">Hon. ATTY. GENERAL</persName> said that the matter 
     <lb/>
     had not been forgotten, but would be dealt 
     <lb/>
     with when the amendment to the Act relating 
     <lb/>
     to Elections was introduced. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO4">Hon. FIN. SECY</persName>. by command laid on the 
     <lb/>
     table several petitions in reference to loss on 
     <lb/>
     the Railway. They were referred to the Rail<lb break="no"/>way Committee. Also a petition in reference 
     <lb/>
     to loss of money through the Post Office, which 
     <lb/>
     was referred to the Post Office Committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. laid on the table the Cal<lb break="no"/>endar of King's College. Also further papers 
     <lb/>
     relating to the removal of Tweedell from the 
     <lb/>
     Insane Asylum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP4">Mr. C. J. CAMPBELL</persName> asked the government 
     <lb/>
     to lay on the table a return of the quantities of 
     <lb/>
     American coal admitted to the Province during 
     <lb/>
     last year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PRYO1">Mr. PRYOR</persName> presented a petition from a num<lb break="no"/>ber of inhabitants of polling district No. 11, 
     <lb/>
     West Halifax, against a proposed change in 
     <lb/>
     that district. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO6">Mr. MACDONNELL</persName> moved that papers which 
     <lb/>
     he had previously asked the Government to lay 
     <lb/>
     on the table, in reference to a grant of Crown 
     <lb/>
     Lands, be referred to the Crown Land Commit<lb break="no"/>tee. Passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAMI1">Dr. HAMILTON</persName> introduced a bill to authorize 
     <lb/>
     the purchase of land and erection of a poor 
     <lb/>
     house in Cornwallis. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> said that as the time was ap<lb break="no"/>proaching when gentlemen would be anxious 
     <lb/>
     to become acquainted with the financial condi<lb break="no"/>tion of the country, he was desirous of know<lb break="no"/>ing whether any contracts had been entered 
     <lb/>
     into with the Pictou Railway beyond the con<lb break="no"/>tract with Mr. Fleming. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO4">Hon. FIN. SEC</persName>. said that no contracts had 
     <lb/>
     been entered into for matters included in Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Fleming's contract, but purchases of rolling 
     <lb/>
     stock had been made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     WINDSOR AND ANNAPOLIS RAILWAY. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The house then went into Committee on Bills, 
     <lb/>
     and took up the bill to incorporate the Wind<lb break="no"/>sor and Annapolis Railway Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KILL2">Mr. KILLAM</persName> thought that this was not the 
     <lb/>
     time for such a measure. It was essential to 
     <lb/>
     ascertain the financial state of the country, so 
     <lb/>
     as to see how the construction was to be pro<lb break="no"/>vided for. He did not wish to oppose the ex<lb break="no"/>tension, provided the Province had sufficient 
     <lb/>
     means, and it should be remembered that the 
     <lb/>
     revenues would be very small after Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. It would be seen also that the bill was 
     <lb/>
     not the same as last Session, and the House 
     <lb/>
     should be cautious in making the change which 
     <lb/>
     would leave too much power in the hands of 
     <lb/>
     the contractors. The bill gave them the right 
     <lb/>
     to build the road to Annapolis or Troop's Point, 
     <lb/>
     and as to the bridge, it was stipulated to be 
     <lb/>
     built of iron, or otherwise as they might think 
     <lb/>
     proper, while the former agreement was for a 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="111" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0111.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">111</fw>
       

     bridge with a roadway for the accomodation of 
     <lb/>
     the public. These matters should not be left 
     <lb/>
     indefinite in a work of such extent and impor<lb break="no"/>tance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP8">Mr. COLIN CAMPBELL</persName> said he was glad to 
     <lb/>
     hear the member for Yarmouth express his 
     <lb/>
     views on this question, as he (Mr. C.) intended 
     <lb/>
     to ask for an extension to Digby. It was evi<lb break="no"/>dent that danger might arise from leaving too 
     <lb/>
     much power in the contractors' hands, and he 
     <lb/>
     hoped that the Government would not allow 
     <lb/>
     the terminus to be at Troop's Point. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PRO. SEC</persName>., as to the financial part of the 
     <lb/>
     question, said that under Confederation Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia would be allowed to come in with a 
     <lb/>
    debt of eight millions, and in case the debt ex<lb break="no"/>ceeded that amount, the assets representing 
     <lb/>the increased amount would belong to the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. The delegates had found it impossible 
     <lb/>to make a contract for the extension except on 
     <lb/>the terms of allowing the contractors to choose 
     <lb/>from the routes surveyed by Mr. Fleming, but 
     <lb/>the best guarantee that could be desired was 
     <lb/>the fact that those gentlemen were investing 
     <lb/>large sums of their own money, and their in<lb break="no"/>terest depended on a selection that would be 
     <lb/>favorable for traffic. The reason why a road<lb break="no"/>way had been stipulated for in the Windsor 
     <lb/>Bridge was that a sum was provided for its 
     <lb/>construction, and that sum was more than 
     <lb/>sufficient for a wooden railway bridge, but the 
     <lb/>cost of an iron one would be largely in excess, 
     <lb/>and therefore the company could not be asked 
     <lb/>to provide a roadway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. S. CAMPBELL</persName> said that when the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment or their officer made a contract under 
     <lb/>
     the authority of an Act, the terms of that act 
     <lb/>
     should be kept in view. The law authorized 
     <lb/>
     the Government to enter into a contract for an 
     <lb/>
     extension from Windsor to Annapolis, while 
     <lb/>
     the agreement left a discretionary power which 
     <lb/>
     had not been authorized. It could not be said 
     <lb/>
     that Annapolis county was meant, for in that 
     <lb/>
     case the road might stop at the very border. 
     <lb/>
     if the agreement were not consistent with the 
     <lb/>
     Act it was not binding in the Legislature. The 
     <lb/>
     Government, therefore, had not shewn that re<lb break="no"/>gard for the law which they should have shewn, 
     <lb/>
    and they might as well have contracted for the- 
     <lb break="yes"/>road to be carried to any other part of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince as to Troop's Point. As to the bridge, 
     <lb/>he thought it was understood that ample ac<lb break="no"/>commodation should be afforded for the ordi<lb break="no"/>nary traffic, but this had been lost sight of. 
     <lb/>These facts should throw matters connected 
     <lb/>with the work into their original position, and 
     <lb/>that being the case it would be wise to con<lb break="no"/>sider whether the country was in a position to 
     <lb/>carry on the extension. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> said that his position prevent<lb break="no"/>ed him on most occasions from mingling in 
     <lb/>
     debate, and he regretted that the Government 
     <lb/>
     had not enabled him by allowing the House to 
     <lb/>
     go into committee on the general state of the 
     <lb/>
     Province, to express his views on the great 
     <lb/>
     public question before. He, however, had at 
     <lb/>
     last an opportunity of giving to his constituen<lb break="no"/>cy his views on the subject. The railway 
     <lb/>
     policy was one that he had been educated up 
     <lb/>
     to by Mr. Howe, and ever since that gentleman 
     <lb/>
     moved on the question, he had felt that that 
     <lb/>
     subject and the question of the Union of the 
     <lb/>
     Colonies, to which public attention was then 
     <lb/>
     turned, were matters which, in the interest of 
     <lb/>
     the Province, should be steadily kept in view. 
     <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
          

     In speaking upon the latter question, it was 
     <lb/>
     not improbable that he spoke to his own pre<lb break="no"/>judice; but he was not the man who would fail 
     <lb/>
     to give the people his views, or who would pan<lb break="no"/>der for a seat in the house when a question in<lb break="no"/>volving the interests of the Empire was brought 
     <lb/>
     forward. He would be happy to resign his 
     <lb/>
     seat and retire from public life, if called upon 
     <lb/>
     to do so, on the question of Confederation. He 
     <lb/>
     put the two questions of Railway Extension 
     <lb/>
     and Union on the same ground as regards the 
     <lb/>
     breadth of view in which they should he re<lb break="no"/>garded. It was greatly to be regretted that 
     <lb/>
     such opposition had been shown to the West<lb break="no"/>ern Extension, and it was surprising to see the 
     <lb/>
     rejoicing when Knight and Company failed in 
     <lb/>
     their engagements. As to the objections raised 
     <lb/>
     by the member for Yarmouth it was well 
     <lb/>
     known that the previous agreement was word<lb break="no"/>ed in precisely the same way. He would have 
     <lb/>
     preferred that all mention of Troop's Point had 
     <lb/>
     been omitted; but any man knowing the West<lb break="no"/>ern part of the country would have no hesita<lb break="no"/>tion in saying that the road could not stop there. 
     <lb/>
     He well recollected the opposition given in 
     <lb/>
     1851 by the member for Yarmouth to railway 
     <lb/>
     construction, and the cry all through the coun<lb break="no"/>try was that the country would be ruined, and 
     <lb/>
     the tax-gatherer would be at every door, but 
     <lb/>
     it was found that notwithstanding the exten<lb break="no"/>sion to Pictou, our road and bridge service was 
     <lb/>
     doubly as well provided for as it was in 1851. 
     <lb/>
     The same difficulties as to the terminus had 
     <lb/>
     arisen in connection with the Pictou line, and 
     <lb/>
     the same local feeling would always exist, but 
     <lb/>
     members must rise superior to such influences. 
     <lb/>
     There could he no doubt that this line, instead 
     <lb/>
     of stopping either at Annapolis or Troop's 
     <lb/>
     Point, must eventually reach the Bay of Fun<lb break="no"/>dy, and for that purpose must go to Digby Gut. 
     <lb/>
     In a few days his colleague would move a 
     <lb/>
     resolution, which he trusted, would receive the 
     <lb/>
     unanimous assent of the house, authorizing the 
     <lb/>
     Government to contract for the extension of 
     <lb/>
     the road to the waters of the Bay of Fundy. 
     <lb/>
     With such a line of communication, the dis<lb break="no"/>tance from Halifax to Portland would be 
     <lb/>
     lessened by hundreds of miles. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HENR1">Hon. ATTY. GEN</persName>. said he was not surprised 
     <lb/>
     at the obstruction to the bill. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment were told, in introducing the resolution 
     <lb/>
     for the extension, that they were not sincere, 
     <lb/>
     and had taken the step merely to secure sup<lb break="no"/>port for the Pictou line, that had been repeated 
     <lb/>
     over and over again, and some members in<lb break="no"/>terested in the Western counties were rather 
     <lb/>
     pleased when the commercial depression in 
     <lb/>
     London enabled them to point to the scheme 
     <lb/>
     as a failure. He had never felt any duty a 
     <lb/>
     more pleasing one than when he took steps to 
     <lb/>
     carry out the terms of the act, and to give to 
     <lb/>
     the western people the road which they had 
     <lb/>
     been expecting. Mr. Killam's desire seemed 
     <lb/>
     to be that the people should consider the mat<lb break="no"/>ter and decide,—if he knew anything of the 
     <lb/>
     people they were anxious to keep their honor<lb break="no"/>able obligations, and you had only to shew 
     <lb/>
     them that they were in justice bound to do 
     <lb/>
     anything in order to induce them to demand 
     <lb/>
     that it should he done. It was not at that time 
     <lb/>
     to be considered whether the road should be 
     <lb/>
     built,—that had been decided long ago. The 
     <lb/>
     opposition had increased very much in their 
     <lb/>
     solicitude to secure the advantages of the road 
     <lb/>
     to Annapolis since the time when they voted 
     <lb/>
        

            <pb n="112" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0112.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">112</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEDINGES</fw>
          

     against giving the road at all,—he congratulat<lb break="no"/>ed members on their change of views, and was 
     <lb/>
     willing to admit that further security should be 
     <lb/>
     pressed for if it could be obtained, but it should 
     <lb/>
     be remembered that the original Act said 
     <lb/>
     nothing about the bridge excepting for the rail<lb break="no"/>way traffic, and £40,000 was agreed on as the 
     <lb/>
     sum that the Province should pay for that 
     <lb/>
     work, but it was found that a substantial 
     <lb/>
     bridge, affording the desired accommodation, 
     <lb/>
     could not be built for double the money, and it 
     <lb/>
     had to be left with the Company to build as 
     <lb/>
     good a wooden bridge as they could, if not of 
     <lb/>
     stone, and it would be to their interest to make 
     <lb/>
     it substantial as the cost of its maintenance 
     <lb/>
     would rest on them. Nothing was said in the 
     <lb/>
     act of last year about the bridge, and it was 
     <lb/>
     only in London, in 1865, that the first mention 
     <lb/>
     was made of it, and the company asked the 
     <lb/>
     insertion of a clause to authorize them to build 
     <lb/>
     an iron or stone bridge if possible, but not ob<lb break="no"/>liging them to make the roadway in addition. 
     <lb/>
     The Government then had acted in this matter 
     <lb/>
     according to their instructions, and would have 
     <lb/>
     been blamed for going beyond their commis<lb break="no"/>sion if the negociations had failed in conse<lb break="no"/>quence of further accommodation being insist<lb break="no"/>ed upon. As to the route, a survey had been 
     <lb/>
     made, and the company insisted on having the 
     <lb/>
     selection of lines; but one great inducement to 
     <lb/>
     the enterprise was that the road might be made 
     <lb/>
     the through route to the United States, con<lb break="no"/>necting Halifax with some place from which a 
     <lb/>
     ready passage could be made to New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick and enabling passengers to be in Montre<lb break="no"/>al or Boston as soon as by steamer. In order 
     <lb/>
     to do so the company had resolved to build 
     <lb/>
     such a road that the journey to Annapolis could 
     <lb/>
     he made in four hours, and they would require 
     <lb/>
     bridges of a very substantial kind. The true 
     <lb/>
     interests of the country had been well cared 
     <lb/>
     for in securing a first class road for the amount 
     <lb/>
     of the subvention. So strong was the opinion 
     <lb/>
     in the minds of some that no company could be 
     <lb/>
     got to do the work for the sum offered, that a 
     <lb/>
     member of the Upper house had voted last 
     <lb/>
     year against the bill on that ground. The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had, however, been enabled to com<lb break="no"/>plete the contract for the amount offered, and 
     <lb/>
     the effect of the capitalisation would be highly 
     <lb/>
     favorable in a financial point of view. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As to Annapolis being mentioned in the ori<lb break="no"/>ginal bill as the terminus, it would be observed 
     <lb/>
     that in the contract Troop's Point was also 
     <lb/>
     mentioned, and the contract was embodied in 
     <lb/>
     the act; but even if it had been otherwise, the 
     <lb/>
     duty of the Legislature was to take a fair and 
     <lb/>
     broad view of the matter, and not to take techni<lb break="no"/>cal objections. When the question had been 
     <lb/>
     previously under discussion, it was considered 
     <lb/>
     that Annapolis might not be the best terminus 
     <lb/>
     in consequence of the tide and for other rea<lb break="no"/>sons; and although it would have been prefer<lb break="no"/>able to have had the line to that place, in order 
     <lb/>
     to extend it to Digby and Yarmouth, yet all 
     <lb/>
     the interests bad to be looked to, and the con<lb break="no"/>tractors insisted on having the alternative. The 
     <lb/>
     act, however, provided that not a mile should 
     <lb/>
     be built except on the recommendation of the 
     <lb/>
     engineer, and the contractors possessed no pow<lb break="no"/>er to force it to Troop's Point. All these stipu<lb break="no"/>lations were in the former agreement with 
     <lb/>
     Knight &amp; Co., which was ratified last year, and 
     <lb/>
     the objections, therefore, came a year too late. 
     <lb/>
     The fears of some gentlemen, however as to 
     <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
         

     the road being built to Troop's Point, were 
     <lb/>
     groundless; it would be built to Annapolis and 
     <lb/>
     was located there already. Some gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     would, no doubt, be sorry it would not go to 
     <lb/>
     Troop's Point, so that they could have some<lb break="no"/>thing to grumble at. The arrangement made 
     <lb/>
     by the delegates in reference to this railway 
     <lb/>
     was the only railway negotiation that had been 
     <lb/>
     effected during the year, owing to the depressed 
     <lb/>
     condition of business; and the Government 
     <lb/>
     having so far succeeded, and having acted in 
     <lb/>
     good faith, the house was in duty bound to ful<lb break="no"/>fil the engagements entered into under its au<lb break="no"/>thority. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> expressed his pleasure at 
     <lb/>
     hearing the announcement that the road would 
     <lb/>
     go to Annapolis and not to Troop's Point. He 
     <lb/>
     was not aware of this in making his previous 
     <lb/>
     observations, but he had felt little doubt on the 
     <lb/>
     subject from what he knew of the locality. As 
     <lb/>
     he would not be in a position to speak to the 
     <lb/>
     resolution for the extension to Digby when his 
     <lb/>
     colleague might move it, he would say a few 
     <lb/>
     words on that subject. He did not wish that 
     <lb/>
     proposition to interfere with the bill under dis<lb break="no"/>cussion, but when the latter was disposed of 
     <lb/>
     no gentleman could fairly consider the request 
     <lb/>
     that would be made an unreasonable one. 
     <lb/>
     Any one acquainted with the Western part of 
     <lb/>
     the country and its capabilities must be aware 
     <lb/>
     that the people would not remain satisfied so 
     <lb/>
     long as the public improvements they required 
     <lb/>
     were within the means of the Province. It 
     <lb/>
     would seem that the hon. member for Yar<lb break="no"/>mouth was desirous of preventing the railway 
     <lb/>
     moving any further Westward than at present, 
     <lb/>
     but if he would soften a little in his desire to 
     <lb/>
     oppose the Government he would feel it his 
     <lb/>
     duty to come to the aid of Western countries. 
     <lb/>
     In five or seven years the road might be ex<lb break="no"/>pected to reach the town of Yarmouth, for as 
     <lb/>long as the public finances warranted it, the 
     <lb/>Western extension would he demanded. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LONG1">Mr. LONGLEY</persName> regretted that the members 
     <lb/>
     for Yarmouth and Guysboro felt it their duty 
     <lb/>
     to oppose the bill; the former had a direct in<lb break="no"/>terest in the extension, and the latter was in 
     <lb/>
     no position to complain after the favorable con<lb break="no"/>sideration that the Eastern interest had receiv<lb break="no"/>ed. By the projected railway Yarmouth would 
     <lb/>
     be placed within a day's journey of the capital, 
     <lb/>
     and it was therefore difficult to believe that 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member was truly representing his 
     <lb/>
     constituency in making the captious objections 
     <lb/>
     he had made to the contract. The members 
     <lb/>
     for the Western counties had supported the 
     <lb/>
     Pictou extension from a sense of duty, and had 
     <lb/>
     thereby established a strong claim to the sup<lb break="no"/>port of the other members on this question. 
     <lb/>
     Too much credit could not be accorded to the 
     <lb/>
     Government for their untiring efforts in relation 
     <lb/>
     to this contract. But for the presence of the 
     <lb/>
     delegates and their exertions in London no 
     <lb/>
     contract would be in existence. The Annapo<lb break="no"/>lis Railway would be built on much more 
     <lb/>
     favorable terms than the existing lines. As to 
     <lb/>
     the extension to Digby, he thought that when 
     <lb/>
     the road reached Annapolis all would have 
     <lb/>
     been done that could reasonably have been 
     <lb/>
     asked. The measure was entitled to the sup<lb break="no"/>port of all members representing the Western 
     <lb/>
     constituencies, for the terms were so favorable 
     <lb/>
     that not only local, but the general interests of 
     <lb/>
     that part of the country were benefited. As 
     <lb/>
     to the Pictou line, he rejoiced to be able to say 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="113" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0113.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">113</fw>
         


     that by the 31st May it would be in a fit condi<lb break="no"/>tion to carry the whole traffic, and this was 
     <lb/>
     under an arrangement that was so emphati<lb break="no"/>cally condemned a year ago. The question of 
     <lb/>
     our railway extension was involved with the 
     <lb/>
     question of Confederation, and the success of 
     <lb/>
     the Government in maturing the contract was 
     <lb/>
     to a great extent due to the fact that the Union 
     <lb/>
     of the Colonies had been secured. Too much 
     <lb/>
     praise could not be accorded to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in relation to the bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> expressed his regret at hearing 
     <lb/>
     the opposition styled obstructive, because they 
     <lb/>
     had discharged their duty in criticising the 
     <lb/>
     measure before the house. It was not correct 
     <lb/>
     to say that he was opposed to western exten<lb break="no"/>sion, but he denied the right of the Government 
     <lb/>
     to insert any provision in relation to Troop's 
     <lb/>
     Point in the contract. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HENR1">Hon. ATTY. GEN</persName>. said that the name was 
     <lb/>
     used in the contract which was part of the act 
     <lb/>
     of last year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> denied that the act of 1866 au<lb break="no"/>thorized the use of the word. It was well 
     <lb/>
     known that the cost of construction would be 
     <lb/>
     cheaper on the north side of the river than on 
     <lb/>
     the south side, and that it might be a gain to 
     <lb/>
     the contractors to adopt the northern route; but 
     <lb/>
     looking to the interests of the country, and the 
     <lb/>
     probability of an extension to Yarmouth at 
     <lb/>
     some future day, he thought it should termin<lb break="no"/>ate at Annapolis. Troop's Point is a quarter 
     <lb/>
     of a mile above the ferry and deep water, and 
     <lb/>
     would therefore be quite useless as a terminus. 
     <lb/>
     This fact should have induced the Government 
     <lb/>
     to secure the line and terminus beyond the dis<lb break="no"/>cretion of the contractors. It would, too, be of 
     <lb/>
     importance to consider this question in rela<lb break="no"/>tion to the financial position of the Province 
     <lb/>
     under Confederation. The debt incurred by 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia beyond the eight millions would 
     <lb/>
     be treated as a loan, on which five per cent. 
     <lb/>
     must be paid to Canada; and as the country 
     <lb/>
     was in a transition state, he thought a little 
     <lb/>
     more enquiry should be bestowed on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject. He assumed that the indebtedness of 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia amounted to considerably over 
     <lb/>
     five millions, in addition to two and a half mil<lb break="no"/>lions for the Pictou railway and rolling stock. 
     <lb/>
     This, with over a million for the Annapolis line, 
     <lb/>
     would probably bring our debt up to nine mil<lb break="no"/>lions. Assuming this to be the case, we would 
     <lb/>
     commence Confederation with a debt ofa mil<lb break="no"/>lion of dollars, which would stand as a first 
     <lb/>
     charge on the local revenues. As to the bridge 
     <lb/>
     he would only say that as under the original 
     <lb/>
     agreement it was intended to give accomoda<lb break="no"/>tion for foot passengers and vehicles, a great 
     <lb/>
     wrong had now been done to the inhabitants of 
     <lb/>
     Hants and Kings in not making such a provi<lb break="no"/>sion as would give them a free passage over 
     <lb/>
     the river for all time to come. He thought the 
     <lb/>
     house should pause, and take up the question 
     <lb/>
     after fuller information had been given. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HENR1">Hon. ATTY. GEN</persName>. said that there was no 
     <lb/>
     doubt a great deal in the suggestion of the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member, and that an estimate of the character 
     <lb/>
     asked for would be of value. But the present 
     <lb/>
     was not the time to bring up such an estimate. 
     <lb/>
     The Province had already incurred liabilities 
     <lb/>
     in connection with this railway, and must 
     <lb/>
     carry out its agreement. A proper time no 
     <lb/>
     doubt would come when the hon. member could 
     <lb/>
     have his wishes gratified. It was a great pity 
     <lb/>


            <cb/>
          

     that hon. gentlemen would not take the trouble 
     <lb/>
     of reading public documents before coming for<lb break="no"/>ward and making incautious and incorrect 
     <lb/>
     statements. If the hon. member would look at 
     <lb/>
     the act of 1866 he would find that it recited the 
     <lb/>
     agreement. (The hon. Atty. General here read 
     <lb/>
     from the act to show that the agreement was 
     <lb/>
     made part of it.) That being so, he went on to 
     <lb/>
     say, were they not justified in assuming that 
     <lb/>
     the house would ratify the agreement that was 
     <lb/>
     made conditionally, in case it should be shown 
     <lb/>
     to be the best line?  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. S. CAMPBELL</persName> said that it was the pri<lb break="no"/>vilege of the minority to criticise the acts of 
     <lb/>
     the Government, for they were there for that 
     <lb/>
     purpose. The question he had to consider was 
     <lb/>
     not whether he was opposed to the Annapolis 
     <lb/>
     Railway or not, but whether the Government 
     <lb/>
     had performed their duty in a business-like 
     <lb/>
     manner. He contended that they had failed to 
     <lb/>
     do so. The hon. member had referred to the 
     <lb/>
     Act of 1866, but the articles of agreement recit<lb break="no"/>ed the Act of 1865. They were bound by the 
     <lb/>
     terms of that act and should not go one iota 
     <lb/>
     beyond it. The house should not be asked to  
     <lb/>
     take the mere ipse dixit of the hon. gentleman, 
     <lb/>
     that the company had abandoned Troop's 
     <lb/>
     Point—it should be shown in black and white.  
     <lb/>
     He (Mr. C.) felt that it was his duty not merely 
     <lb/>
     to protect the rights of the people of Guysbo<lb break="no"/>rough, but of the whole Province as well. 
     <lb/>
     When he saw an injustice being done to any 
     <lb/>
     portion of the people, he was bound to state 
     <lb/>
     his objections. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. said that the arguments of 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen opposite shewed very clearly how 
     <lb/>
     difficult they found it to find fault with the 
     <lb/>
     Government. No observations could be more 
     <lb/>
     puerile than those that had been made in the 
     <lb/>
     course of the afternoon by the opposition. The 
     <lb/>
     house had solemnly pledged itself to the con<lb break="no"/>struction of the railway, and after a year's de<lb break="no"/>liberation had re-affirmed that decision. The 
     <lb/>
     Government having been charged to make a 
     <lb/>
     contract for the construction of the line immedi<lb break="no"/>ately set to work to perform the duty entrust<lb break="no"/>ed to them. They entered into a contract with 
     <lb/>
     parties to build a railway to Annapolis town 
     <lb/>
     or to Troop's Point, and the house, with that 
     <lb/>
     contract before them, deliberately re-affirmed 
     <lb/>
     their former decision and authorized the carry<lb break="no"/>ing out of their agreement. Though the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member was told that the representatives of 
     <lb/>
     the Government, when in London, could only 
     <lb/>
     make the contract by leaving it optional with 
     <lb/>
     the company to go to Annapolis or Troop's 
     <lb/>
     Point—both of which points had been left by 
     <lb/>
     the house to the choice of a previous contrac<lb break="no"/>tor—yet he now declared that they should not 
     <lb/>
     have entered into the agreement at all for the 
     <lb/>
     construction of the road, but should have de<lb break="no"/>prived the western counties of that means of 
     <lb/>
     railway communication with the capital which 
     <lb/>
     they so anxiously desired, and to which the 
     <lb/>
     faith of the Province had been pledged. He 
     <lb/>
     felt it was the greatest compliment that could 
     <lb/>
     be paid to the Government for gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     opposite to take up the time of the house with 
     <lb/>
     objections and assertions which everybody 
     <lb/>
     must feel were perfectly puerile and unworthy 
     <lb/>
     the serious consideration of any intelligent 
     <lb/>
     man. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The house would remember that these hon. 
     <lb/>
     members once undertook to settle the railway 
     <lb/>
         

            <pb n="114" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0114.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">114</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
         

     policy of this country, but did they carry the 
     <lb/>
     road to Annapolis? They put on the Statute 
     <lb/>
     Book an act pledging themselves to carry the 
     <lb/>
     road to Victoria Beach, instead of going to the 
     <lb/>
     town of Annapolis, to which they now declared 
     <lb/>
     it should go. The Government were author<lb break="no"/>ized by the deliberate vote of the house a year 
     <lb/>
     ago to carry the road to Troop's Point, if ne<lb break="no"/>cessary; not a single member then rose to ob<lb break="no"/>ject to such a policy. When the Government 
     <lb/>
     came to negotiate this matter, the best terms 
     <lb/>
     they could obtain were that they should leave 
     <lb/>
     this matter an open question for the contract<lb break="no"/>ors to decide. As respects the other matter in 
     <lb/>
     question, he would again mention that as the 
     <lb/>
     iron bridge would cost a great deal, the com<lb break="no"/>pany were unable to include the roadway at 
     <lb/>
     the same time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr. S. CAMPBELL</persName> said that the agreement 
     <lb/>
     did not state that the bridge would be of iron. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon PROV. SEC</persName>. replied that the agreement 
     <lb/>
     provided that the bridge should be constructed 
     <lb/>
     in one way or the other. If it was built of wood 
     <lb/>
     then the roadway would have to be included. 
     <lb/>
     If it was, on the other hand, constructed of 
     <lb/>
     iron, the roadway would not be made. By the 
     <lb/>
     following letter it would be seen that the com<lb break="no"/>pany had decided to build the work of iron:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">24 Great George Street, 
     <lb/>
     Westminister, S. W., February</hi> 25, 1867. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>


            <p>DEAR SIR,— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     " We have very great pleasure in informing 
     <lb/>
     you that we have made all arrangements 
     <lb/>
     necessary for the due completion of this line. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Our first and most important step, that of 
     <lb/>
     providing the capital necessary for the com<lb break="no"/>pletion and equipment of the line, we have 
     <lb/>
     arranged with an eminent city firm; and for 
     <lb/>
     the security alike of the Province, the capital<lb break="no"/>ists just alluded to, and ourselves, we have 
     <lb/>
     deemed it advisable to let the contract to Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Thomas Brassey, who has undertaken the 
     <lb/>
     same, and is now incorporated with us in the 
     <lb/>
     company established for the purposes of the 
     <lb/>
     railway.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We may add, that it is our intention to ex<lb break="no"/>ecute the works in a manner that we believe 
     <lb/>
     will give you entire satisfaction, and <hi rendition="simple:italic">we have 
     <lb/>
     concluded to build the Windsor bridge of iron</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As this latter work will have to be prepared 
     <lb/>
    here, we have telegraphed to our agent, Mr. 
     <lb/>Grant, to come over with the plans of this and 
     <lb/>the other bridges by the next steamer, that the 
     <lb/>work may be immediately let; and we have 
     <lb/>made such arrangements as we believe will 
     <lb/>enable us to finish the principal bridges during 
     <lb/>the coming season, and the whole line by the 
     <lb/>end of the year 1868." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p rendition="simple:right">
     We have, &amp;c.. 
     <lb/>
     W. H. PUNCHARD, 
     <lb/>
     EDWIN CLARK, 
     <lb/>
     FREDERICK BARRY. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>To the Hon. CHARLES TUPPER, Provincial 
     <lb/>Secretary. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KILL2">Mr. KILLAM</persName> said that he thought it unwise to 
     <lb/>
     have allowed the contractor to take his choice 
     <lb/>
     of two points of termination, or to build the 
     <lb/>
     bridne of iron or wood. He was of opinion that 
     <lb/>
     the Government should have kept the company 
     <lb/>
     to the roadway. What he urged particularly, 
     <lb/>
     however, was that the Government should show 
     <lb/>
     the House and country what our financial posi<lb break="no"/>tion was likely to be. It was now admitted that 
     <lb/>
           

            <cb/>
     

     if we exceeded the debt of $8,000,000, we would 
     <lb/>
     have to pay the excess, though the assets would 
     <lb/>
     be placed to our credit. The assets, in the case 
     <lb/>
     of the present railway, would be nothing, for 
     <lb/>
     they belonged to the company. It was the duty 
     <lb/>
     of the Government to show how we were to raise 
     <lb/>
     the large sum required for the work and at the 
     <lb/>
     same time have money enough to provide for 
     <lb/>
     other things. When the House was called upon 
     <lb/>
     previously to deal with this question, it was un<lb break="no"/>der very different circumstances, then we had 
     <lb/>
     our revenue to fall back upon, whereas now the 
     <lb/>
     largest portion was handed over to Canada. If 
     <lb/>
     things remained as they were we could build the 
     <lb/>
     railways to Annapolis, to New Brunswick, to 
     <lb/>
     Pictou, and eventually to Yarmouth—in fact, 
     <lb/>
     from one end of the Province to the other. He 
     <lb/>
     believed that the terms of the contract were in<lb break="no"/>jurious to the best interests of the country. The 
     <lb/>
     company were allowed to choose the way 
     <lb/>
     through the counties of Annapolis and Kings, 
     <lb/>
     besides to obtain gratis all lands required for the 
     <lb/>
     railway track and appurtenances. They were 
     <lb/>
     to build such a railway as they might think pro<lb break="no"/>per—in reality, there was nothing binding on 
     <lb/>
     them. They could use a rail that would not 
     <lb/>
     weigh much above 30 lbs. to the yard. He cal<lb break="no"/>culated the cost for a mile of rails would be 
     <lb/>
     $1320; the cost of sleepers would be about $400; 
     <lb/>
     and the whole cost of a mile of roadway would 
     <lb/>
     be $1720. It was quite evident that the com<lb break="no"/>pany would have to take little or nothing out of 
     <lb/>
     their own pockets. He did not like to see the 
     <lb/>
     government getting mixed up with private com<lb break="no"/>panies. But when they did make a bargain, 
     <lb/>
     they should take care that it was a safe one for 
     <lb/>
     the Province. If we went on as we are now, 
     <lb/>
     and built all the railways ourselves, our debt 
     <lb/>
     would reach say $13,000,000, on which we 
     <lb/>
     would have to pay an interest of about $750,000. 
     <lb/>
     Our revenues from excise and customs would 
     <lb/>
     amount to at least $1,250,000. We would, 
     <lb/>
     therefore, have $500,000 independent of the rail<lb break="no"/>way interest, with a duty of say 10 per cent. 
     <lb/>
     With our revenues under our own control, we 
     <lb/>
     could increase them it necessity compel<lb break="no"/>led us. Besides there was no doubt that the 
     <lb/>
     railways to Annapolis, Pictou and New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, under proper management, would 
     <lb/>
     bring us one or two per cent. Even the pre<lb break="no"/>sent railway, extravagantly as it was worked, 
     <lb/>
     had left something above its working expenses. 
     <lb/>
     As the trade increased, the different railway lines 
     <lb/>
     would become productive, and eventually 
     <lb/>
     we would be in a position to build a road to 
     <lb/>
     Yarmouth. As it was now, however, no such 
     <lb/>
     results could be expected. The revenues were 
     <lb/>
     to be taken from under our own control, and we 
     <lb/>
     were obliged to get along the best way we could 
     <lb/>
     under most adverse circumstances. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HENR1">Hon. ATTY. GEN</persName>. said that it was really most 
     <lb/>
     refreshing to hear the hon. member for Yar<lb break="no"/>mouth, who had so frequently urged that the 
     <lb/>
     country was not in a condition to build rail<lb break="no"/>ways, now declaring that we should go into 
     <lb/>
     debt to the extent of $13,000,000 for such pub<lb break="no"/>lic works. It would be remembered that the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member had, on a former occasion, even 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="115" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0115.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">115</fw>
          

     made an apology for voting for the Pictou Rail<lb break="no"/>way, because it prevented us from going into 
     <lb/>
     debt for the Intercolonial Railway; he voted for 
     <lb/>
     the former because it was the lesser evil. Now 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member said that we should build rail<lb break="no"/>ways to Annapolis, to Pictou, to New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick and everywhere else. In fact there was 
     <lb/>
     not a day that the hon. member did not assume 
     <lb/>
     some inconsistent position; it was impossible to 
     <lb/>
     know where to find him, so erratic was his pub<lb break="no"/>lic policy. The hon. member had just declar<lb break="no"/>ed that the Government should not have enter<lb break="no"/>ed into the agreement but anybody who knew 
     <lb/>
     him would feel that if they had not done so he 
     <lb/>
     would have been the first to complain that they 
     <lb/>
     had sacrificed the interests of the West to the 
     <lb/>
     East. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:COFF1">Mr. COFFIN</persName> said that it was assumed by the 
     <lb/>
     Government that we would pass into Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation with a debt of $8,000,000. Anything that 
     <lb/>
     exceeded that amount would have to be paid 
     <lb/>
     for us. Now it appeared that the first charge 
     <lb/>
     upon the little revenues left us would be the in<lb break="no"/>terest on this railway. If we had no other 
     <lb/>
     means of paying it, we must do it by direct 
     <lb/>
     taxation. He would be quite willing to pay for 
     <lb/>
     the Windsor and Annapolis Railway if he could 
     <lb/>
     seo any way of doing so. We were legislating 
     <lb/>
     ahead of the means at the disposal of the coun<lb break="no"/>try, and saddling it with a debt which it would 
     <lb/>
     be most difficult and burdensome to pay. He 
     <lb/>
     was quite positive that instead of going into 
     <lb/>
     Confederation with a debt of $8,000,000, the 
     <lb/>
     amount would be rather $9,000,000.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName> said that it seemed to him that 
     <lb/>
     gentleman were always looking for troubles, 
     <lb/>
     and anyone listening to the debate that after<lb break="no"/>noon would imagine that the country was on 
     <lb/>
     the verge of ruin. He saw our revenues in<lb break="no"/>creasing, our railways extending and opening 
     <lb/>
     up new sources of trade, all branches of indus<lb break="no"/>try prosperous and progressing, and yet it was 
     <lb/>
     said that we were unable to get along. He saw 
     <lb/>
     ahead, not a prospect of ruin, but of prosperity. 
     <lb/>
     Our revenue in 1850 was not above $382,000. 
     <lb/>
     Then we were told that if we built a single 
     <lb/>
     mile of railway we would be ruined. Now we 
     <lb/>
     had a revenue of nearly a million and a half of 
     <lb/>
     dollars, derived from the same sources. We had 
     <lb/>
     built railways, devoted large sums to educa<lb break="no"/>tion, roads and bridges, and other great public 
     <lb/>
     improvements, and yet the people were not op<lb break="no"/>pressed with taxation, but were less burdened 
     <lb/>
     than any other country in the world. He did not 
     <lb/>
     expect, however ever to find the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Yarmouth satisfied; it was his privilege to 
     <lb/>
     find fault with all Governments. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had only done their duty in redeeming 
     <lb/>
     the pledge they had given to the people of the 
     <lb/>
     West. He was unable to see on what ground 
     <lb/>
     some hon. members argued that the construc<lb break="no"/>tion of the Annapolis Railway would burden 
     <lb/>
     the local revenue. Mere assertion, however, 
     <lb/>
     amounted to nothing, and that was all the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman and his friends indulged in. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> said that his hon. friend had <choice><sic>at<lb break="no"/>empted</sic><corr>attempted</corr></choice> to prove too much. If our revenue 
     <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
    

          
     had more than trebled since 1850, it proved that 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia was now a prosperous country, and 
     <lb/>
     that any change in our political condition was 
     <lb/>
     unnecessary. We were to exchange this pros<lb break="no"/>perous state of things for a union, under which 
     <lb/>
     we would hand over our revenues to Canada, 
     <lb/>
     and only get back a paltry sum in return. He 
     <lb/>
     was also quite prepared to prove by figures that 
     <lb/>
     if we were left in the possession of our revenues 
     <lb/>
     we would soon be in a position to extend our 
     <lb/>
     railways both to Yarmouth and the Gut of 
     <lb/>
     Canso. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO4">Hon. FIN. SECRETARY</persName> said that he would sug<lb break="no"/>gest to the hon. member the advisability of tak<lb break="no"/>ing into consideration the possibility of the pre<lb break="no"/>sent Government having control of the revenues. 
     <lb/>
     The House remembered that, under the finan<lb break="no"/>cial management of the hon. gentleman, the 
     <lb/>
     Province went backward to the tune of many 
     <lb/>
     thousand dollars a year, whereas the revenue 
     <lb/>
     went up the moment he and his friends were out 
     <lb/>
     of power. It would be therefore necessary for 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member, in making hypothetical asser<lb break="no"/>tions as to the revenues and what could be done 
     <lb/>
     with them, to take into consideration who would 
     <lb/>
     have charge of them. Everybody, in the most 
     <lb/>
     remote settlements, always expected to find the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Yarmouth bringing something 
     <lb/>
     about railways into every speech he may make. 
     <lb/>
     When the hon. member asked for information 
     <lb/>
     respecting the financial position of the Province, 
     <lb/>
     he was quite aware that he had every paper un<lb break="no"/>der his hand requisite for his purpose. He did 
     <lb/>
     not wonder at the assertions of the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Shelburne (Mr Coffin) who could not be ex<lb break="no"/>pected to be so well informed on such subjects 
     <lb/>
     as the hon. member for Yaimouth. When the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Shelburne declared that we 
     <lb/>
     would enter the Confederation with a debt of 
     <lb/>
     $9,000,000, he did it for merely electioneering 
     <lb/>
     purposes, and without anything whatever to sus<lb break="no"/>tain him. He was quite gratified, however, at 
     <lb/>
     the arguments adduced by gentlemen opposite, 
     <lb/>
     for they clearly proved that they had really no 
     <lb/>
     substantial reason for finding fault with the 
     <lb/>
     course pursued by the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HATF2">Mr. HATFIELD</persName> said it was the duty of every 
     <lb/>
     body to express his opinion on a subject of such 
     <lb/>
     great importance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAMI1">Dr. HAMILTON</persName> said that he had watched with 
     <lb/>
     much surprise the course pursued by a certain 
     <lb/>
     public journal, and a certain party in this coun<lb break="no"/>try in reference to this railway. It was now , 
     <lb/>
     however, settled despite all the prognostications 
     <lb/>
     of the opposition, that Kings and Annapolis 
     <lb/>
     would have the railway, owing to the strenuous 
     <lb/>
     exertions of the Government. He thought that 
     <lb/>
     the railway had been surveyed through the 
     <lb/>
     wrong route in the county of Kings. He was 
     <lb/>
     quite satisfied, however, to know that we were 
     <lb/>
     to have the road at last constructed. He didn't  
     <lb/>
     attach any importance to the figures which 
     <lb/>
     some gentlemen were so fond of adducing on 
     <lb/>
     every possible occasion. It was well known 
     <lb/>
     that figures could be twisted in any shape one 
     <lb/>
     chose. It was urged many years ago, the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince was not in a position to build railways 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="116" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1867-04-08_Page_0116.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">116</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
         

     and yet she had done so without burthening the 
     <lb/>
     people to any large extent. Our revenues were 
     <lb/>
     increasing, and the country generally was pros<lb break="no"/>perous. As this prosperity increased, the funds 
     <lb/>
     at our diposal would grow larger. Under all 
     <lb/>
     the circumstances he believed that there was no 
     <lb/>
     reason for the fears entertained by some gentle<lb break="no"/>men; they were either chimeras of the imagina<lb break="no"/>tion or got up for electioneering purposes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The bill then passed through committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The House then adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<!-- GL, 2018-06-20, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


           <!-- <p>
     TUESDAY, April 9. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The house met at 3 o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     PETITIONS. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KILL2">Mr. KILLAM</persName> presented a petition from Ar<lb break="no"/>gyle in reference to a light house. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:COFF1">Mr. COFFIN</persName>, a petition from Barrington re<lb break="no"/>lative to the protection of the fisheries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. MORE, petition for the alteration of a 
     <lb/>
     post ride. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     BILL. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. BOURINOT introduced a bill in reference 
     <lb/>
     to a joint stock company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. ATTY. GEN. suggested a general bill for 
     <lb/>
    the winding up of joint stock companies, which 
     <lb/>were now becoming so numerous in this coun<lb break="no"/>try. It would be well to refer the matter to a 
     <lb/>select committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. BOURINOT agreed to the hon. member's 
     <lb/>suggestion, and the committee was composed 
     <lb/>of the Attorney General. Financial Secretary, 
     <lb/>Miller, Blanchard, and S. Campbell. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Hon. PROV. SEC. read a telegram from Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Fleming stating that an engine had gone over 
     <lb/>
     the rails all the way to Pictou, on an experi<lb break="no"/>mental trip. The experiment had succeeded 
     <lb/>
     perfectly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. FIN. SEC. laid on the table the report 
     <lb/>
     of Mr. McNab in respect to a ferry across Len- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nox Passage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The bill in reference to the Windsor and 
     <lb/>
     Annapolis Railway was read a third time and 
     <lb/>
    passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Hon. ATTY. GEN , as chairman of the com<lb break="no"/>mittee appointed to confer with a committee 
     <lb/>
     of the Council, read the following resolution, 
     <lb/>
     which had been adopted :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     "Resolved, That a humble address be pre<lb break="no"/>sented to her Majesty the Queen requesting 
     <lb/>
     that whenever hereafter the members of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Council shall be reduced to 18, the 
     <lb/>
     number shall not be further increased; and 
     <lb/>
     that Her Majesty will be graciously pleased 
     <lb/>
     to establish the number of the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Council of this Province at 18 members, and 
     <lb/>
     to provide that absence for two sessions con<lb break="no"/>secutively shall vacate the seat of a Council<lb break="no"/>lor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     "Resolved, That a conference be requested 
     <lb/>
     with the House of Assembly, by committee, 
     <lb/>
     on the general state of the Province, and that 
     <lb/>
     'the committee of this House be requested to 
     <lb/>
     communicate to the committee of the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly the foregoing resolution." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The House then went into committee on bills, 
     <lb/>
     and passed the bill to incorporate the Prince 
     <lb/>
     of Wales Lodge of Odd Fellows; the bill to 
     <lb/>
     amend the act incorporating the R. C. Bishop 
     <lb/>
     of Arichat; the bill to incorporate the Caledo<lb break="no"/>nia Lodge. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The committee rose and reported. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. MCFARLANE introduced a bill re<lb break="no"/>lative to the Roman Catholic cemetery at Dart<lb break="no"/>mouth. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The bill to provide for the more effectual 
     <lb/>
     prevention of cruelty to animals was read a 
     <lb/>
     second time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The House adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     WEDNESDAY, April 10 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>The House met at 3 o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. HEBB presented a petition relative to 
     <lb/>protection of the fisheries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName> presented a petition from Tan<lb break="no"/>gier and another from Spry Harbor on the 
     <lb/>
     same subject. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. BALCAM presented a petition from East<lb break="no"/>ern Passage and another from Shoal Bay, re<lb break="no"/>lative to inspection of fish. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. BOURINOT asked the government to lay 
     <lb/>
     on the table the memorial and plans connect<lb break="no"/>ed with the bridge over Little Bras d'Or. Also 
     <lb/>
     the papers connected with the erection of the 
     <lb/>
     lighthouse at Gurgon Island. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. DONKIN introduced a bill to amend 
     <lb/>
     chap. 49 R. S., relating to County Assess<lb break="no"/>ments. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr LOCKE introduced a bill relative to the 
     <lb/>
     Fall term of the Supreme Court at Shelburne. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon PRO SEC., by command, laid on the 
     <lb/>
     table papers relating to the sale of a school 
     <lb/>
     house at Shelburne. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     PETITIONS. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Hon. FIN. SEC. laid on the table the follow<lb break="no"/>ing list of petitions for money votes:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Post Communication. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mail Carrier, 6 Mile Brook— 
     <lb/>Inhabitants, Weymouth—presented by Mr. 
     <lb/>Campbell, 
     <lb/>Do. Kentville 
     <lb/>J. C Morse, Sandy Co. Digby. 
     <lb/>J, Calahan, Sydney. 
     <lb/>C. P. Jones, Weymouth. 
     <lb/>H. B. Prince, Renfrew. 
     <lb/>A Martell, Cow Bay, C. B. 
     <lb/>J. B. Gray, Halifax. 
     <lb/>Inhabitants, Weymouth. 
     <lb/>Do. Lingan. 
     <lb/>Do. Albion Mines. 
     <lb/>H. B. McNutt, Co. Cumberland—presented by 
     <lb/>Hon Mr MrFarlane, 
     <lb/>Postmaster, Co. Inverness. 
     <lb/>Inhabitants, Broad Cove. 
     <lb/>W. O. Keeper, West Dublin. 
     <lb/>Inhabitants, Co. Lunenburg—Presented by 
     <lb/>Mr. Kaulback, 
     <lb/>Do Do 
     <lb/>Do Do. 
     <lb/>Do Do. 
     <lb/>W. O. Keeper, Do. 
     <lb/>Inhabitants, Summerville.     
     <lb/>Do Co Lunenburg—presented by Mr. 
     <lb/>Jost, M. P. P 
     <lb/>Do Long Island, Co. Digby. 
     <lb/>Do Mr. Uniacke, Gold Mines, 
     <lb/>Do Cape George Mr. Henry, 
     <lb/>C. R. Warner, Melford—Mr. Hamilton, " 
     <lb/>Inhabitants, Waterville— " " 
     <lb/>J. M. Parker, Berwick—   " " 
     <lb/>Postmaster, Laurencetown.   
     <lb/>Inhabitants, Newport, Co. Hants.   
     <lb/>Postmaster, Co. Queen's—presented by Mr. J.  
     <lb/>Campbell,  
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>