<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgNSLA_1866-04-03" type="full">
 
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
        
            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNSLAssem">Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-04-03">03 April 1866</date>, Nova Scotia Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LANG4">Dave Lang</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
               <editor>John George Bourinot</editor>.
          <title>Debates and Proceedings of the House of Assembly, During the Third Session of the Twenty-Third Parliament of the Province of Nova Scotia.</title>.
          <date when="1866"/>.  
          <pubPlace>Halifax, N.S.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Crosskill and Bourinot, "Evening Reporter" Office</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="193"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_185.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_186.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_187.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_188.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_189.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_190.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_191.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_192.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_193.hocr.html"/>
               </item>    
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-11-02">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="DLANG4" when="2017-11-02">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_185">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_185.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_186">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_186.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_187">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_187.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_188">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_188.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_189">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_189.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_190">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_190.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_191">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_191.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_192">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_192.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_193">
         <graphic url="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_193.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="185" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_185.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">185</fw>
            
            
<!-- DL, 2017-11-27, commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

            <!--<div type="section"> 
               <p>       
     [...] country, and in proportion to the number of 
     <lb/>
    children in each section. The money should 
     <lb/>be under the control of the commissioners and 
     <lb/>superintendent, and so divided that there 
     <lb/>would be no mistake about it. The great ob<lb break="no"/>ject should be to distribute the advantages of 
     <lb/>education as equally as possible. 
     </p>    

            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. COLIN CAMPBELL</persName> said that he was in 
     <lb/>
     favor of sectional assessment as being the most 
     <lb/>
     equitable principle. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BROW3">Dr. BROWN</persName> doubted the advisability of de<lb break="no"/>nuding the Commissioners so largely of power, 
     <lb/>
     though he thought the bill was in many res<lb break="no"/>pects an improvement 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KILL2">Mr. KILLAM</persName> questioned the propriety of al<lb break="no"/>tering the policy of dividing the school grant 
     <lb/>
     by population. He <choice><sic>movod</sic><corr>moved</corr></choice> an amendment that 
     <lb/>
     the "Provincial grant be divided among the 
     <lb/>
     counties as heretofore." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On a division the clause passed by a very 
     <lb/>
     large majority. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Committee rose and reported progress. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SHAN2">Hon. Mr. SHANNON</persName> reported up an act in 
     <lb/>
     reference to the Board of Health in Halifax.
            </p>
            <p>
     The house adjourned.
            </p>
            </div>-->
            
            <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY APRIL 3.</head>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">UNION OF THE COLONIES.</head>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">SPEECH OF MR. MILLER.</head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL3">MR. MILLER</persName> said—I rise, Mr. Speaker, to 
     <lb/>
     address the House on a question of the deepest 
     <lb/>
     importance to the people of this country—a 
     <lb/>
     question in comparison with which all other 
     <lb/>
     public questions may be truly said to sink into 
     <lb/>
     insignificance—I mean the great question of 
     <lb/>
     British Colonial Union. If, sir, the subject 
     <lb/>
     was less important than it is, I would not ven<lb break="no"/>ture, as I now do, to trespass on the attention 
     <lb/>
     of hon. gentlemen in reference to it, in the ab<lb break="no"/>sence of any motion before this House. The 
     <lb/>
     course I am about to adopt is the result of 
     <lb/>
     much deliberation, and I shall bring myself 
     <lb/>
     within the rules of the House by making an 
     <lb/>
     enquiry of the Government before I resume 
     <lb/>
     my seat. Sir, on no occasion during my com<lb break="no"/>paratively short professional and public ca<lb break="no"/>reer, have I risen to address any body of men 
     <lb/>
     impressed with a deeper sense of the grave 
     <lb/>
     responsibilities of my position than I now feel 
     <lb/>
     But, on the other hand, I can truly say, on no 
     <lb/>
     occasion, involving public responsibilities, 
     <lb/>
     have I been animated by stronger convictions 
     <lb/>
     of the propriety of the step I am about to take 
     <lb/>
     than I am at this moment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     For the past two years, Mr. Speaker, the 
     <lb/>
     question of an Union of the British North 
     <lb/>
     American Provinces has been before the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of this country, and I need hardly state my 
     <lb/>
     views have obtained some publicity, and my<lb break="no"/>self some prominence, in opposition to the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec scheme of Confederation. To that 
     <lb/>
     scheme, I am now as hostile as I have ever 
     <lb/>
     been. I believe it to be unjust to the people of 
     <lb/>
     the Maritime Provinces in some of its most 
     <lb/>
     important features. I believe to force it upon 
     <lb/>
     us without important modifications, would 
     <lb/>
     frustrate the end it is intended to promote— 
     <lb/>
     the permanency of British Institutions on this 
     <lb/>
     continent. These were my opinions in 1864. 
     <lb/>
     They have undergone no change. They are 
     <lb/>
     my opinions to-day.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But, Sir, it is well known to this house and 
     <lb/>
     to the people of the country, that, not with<lb break="no"/>standing the strenuous and unwavering oppo<lb break="no"/>
  
            <cb/>
               
     sition I have given to the Quebec scheme of 
     <lb/>
     confederation, I have invariably declared
     <lb/>
     myself in favor of an equitable union of these 
     <lb/>
     colonies. During the agitation of this question, 
     <lb/>
     I have spoken on it in Parliament and at Pub<lb break="no"/>lic meetings, in several counties of this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, and nowhere have I failed to express in 
     <lb/>
     unequivocal language my desire for union on 
     <lb/>
     fair terms. I can appeal to those who have 
     <lb/>
     listened to me in both extremes of Nova Scotia, 
     <lb/>
     whether in Cape Breton or in Lunenburg, in 
     <lb/>
     support of this assertion. But, Sir, I can 
     <lb/>
     appeal to something stronger, if the consis<lb break="no"/>tency of my conduct in this Legislature is 
     <lb/>
     called in question,—I can appeal to the official 
     <lb/>
     records of this House. I can go even further 
     <lb/>
     and appeal to the gentlemen with whom I 
     <lb/>
     have co-operated for the last eighteen months 
     <lb/>
     in opposition to the scheme of the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     Conference, many of whom are opposed to all 
     <lb/>
     union, and who will hear me ready witness 
     <lb/>
     that my co-operation in the anti-union move<lb break="no"/>ment in this Province, has only extended to 
     <lb/>
     the details of that scheme. The subject of an 
     <lb/>
     union of British America, since I have been 
     <lb/>
     capable of forming a judgment on the question, 
     <lb/>
     has found favor with me. Apart from the 
     <lb/>
     material advantages of such an union, there is 
     <lb/>
     something in the assurance of national 
     <lb/>
     strength and greatness to be derived from it, 
     <lb/>
     which is in sympathy with the best feelings and 
     <lb/>
     aspirations of every British American whose 
     <lb/>
     future is wrapped up with the future of this 
     <lb/>
     country. For years past I have entertained a 
     <lb/>
     strong opinion on the subject,—an opinion that 
     <lb/>
     the period was fast approaching when these 
     <lb/>
     North American colonies must cast off their 
     <lb/>
     present political habiliments, and assume 
     <lb/>
     others more consistent with their advanced 
     <lb/>
     position, their surroundings, and their altered 
     <lb/>
     relations to the Empire. I was in favor of their 
     <lb/>
     political union before the subject was pre<lb break="no"/>sented to the country in any tangible shape. 
     <lb/>
     I am in favor of it now, after having given the 
     <lb/>
     question much attention and thought, and 
     <lb/>
     after the bitter and prolonged agitation it has 
     <lb/>
     produced in this Province. The first opinion 
     <lb/>
     I publicly expressed in favor of it, was in the 
     <lb/>
     debate in this House on the resolution intro<lb break="no"/>duced in 1864, by the hon. Provincial Secretary 
     <lb/>
     for a union of the maritime provinces, when I 
     <lb/>
     am correctly reported to have used this lan<lb break="no"/>guage:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

     <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     <p>
     "If the resolution before the House contemplated 
     <lb/>
     an union of all the Provinces of British North Ameri<lb break="no"/>ca on equitable terms no one could hail it with more 
     <lb/>
     satisfaction than himself. Such an Union he trusted 
     <lb/>
     ta no distant period would become both a commer<lb break="no"/>cial and political necessity. He looked forward hope<lb break="no"/>fully to the day when the inhabitants of these noble 
     <lb/>
     Provinces, united under one government, might 
     <lb/>
     stand before the world in the proud national charac<lb break="no"/>ter of British Americans. From such an association 
     <lb/>
        they would indeed derive national strength and dig<lb break="no"/>nity worth some sacrifice to obtain. they would 
     <lb/>
     then possess a population and country whose imme<lb break="no"/>diate status and inevitable future destiny would com<lb break="no"/>mand respect. An union of the Maritime Provinces 
     <lb/>
     and the great territory beyond would give us a coun<lb break="no"/>try extending from the Atlantic to the Pacific, with 
     <lb/>
     all the diversified resources necessary to the most 
     <lb/>
     unlimited material progress. In favor of such a pro<lb break="no"/>posal most of the arguments urged in this debate 
     <lb/>
     would have real point and force, and not appear, as 
     <lb/>
     they now did, absurd or inapplicable." 
     </p>
     </quote>
               
            <p>
     From the above paragraph, Mr. Speaker it 
     <lb/>
     will be seen, and indeed the fact is one of noto<lb break="no"/>
     
            <pb n="186" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_186.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">186</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
            
         

     riety in this House, that before the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     scheme of Confederation was in existence, I 
     <lb/>
     had placed on record my decided approval of 
     <lb/>
     an union of British America on equitable 
     <lb/>
     terms. I think I will have no difficulty in shew<lb break="no"/>ing that though prominent in my opposition to 
     <lb/>
     the Quebec scheme of Union, I have always 
     <lb/>
     been favorable to the abstract idea of Union.— 
     <lb/>
     My first appearance before the public in oppo<lb break="no"/>sition to that scheme was at a mass meeting of 
     <lb/>
     the Citizens of Halifax in December, 1864, about 
     <lb/>
     nine months after the above declaration in 
     <lb/>
     Parliament, and although I spoke under cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances of much irritation, I did not allow 
     <lb/>
     any personal annoyance to draw me into an<lb break="no"/>tagonism to the great principle of Colonial 
     <lb/>
     Union. Looking back, sir, to that occasion, 
     <lb/>
     and recollecting the excitement that marked 
     <lb/>
     it, I find no ordinary degree of satisfaction at 
     <lb/>
     the emphatic manner in which I preserved my 
     <lb/>
     consistency on the great principle involved in 
     <lb/>
     that discussion. I said :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               
            <p>
     "I do not wish, Mr. Mayor, that my appearance on 
     <lb/>this platform to-night should be construed into op<lb break="no"/>position to an Union of British America on fair terms. 
     <lb/>I am not opposed to, but on the contrary, would sup<lb break="no"/>port an Union based on sound principles and equita<lb break="no"/>le terms. But the more I investigated the subject, 
     <lb/>the more reason do I find to fear that an equitable 
     <lb/>Union with Canada is not easily attainable. I am not 
     <lb/>willing to purchase Confederation on conditions dis<lb break="no"/>astrous to the people of Nova Scotia. These are the 
     <lb/>reasons why I oppose the measure by which Confede<lb break="no"/>ration is now to be secured. I cannot ratify the im<lb break="no"/>provident bargain our delegates have made, because 
     <lb/>it is unjust to this Province. It is a bargain in which 
     <lb/>the advantages are all on one side, and all against 
     <lb/>us." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </quote>

            <p>
     I repeat, sir, when I look back to the period 
     <lb/>
     at which these remarks were uttered—when I 
     <lb/>
     remember the excitement and personal 
     <lb/>
     acrimony that marked, in some instances the 
     <lb/>
     discussion of this subject in Temperance Hall, 
     <lb/>
     I am exceedingly gratified to-day, that no 
     <lb/>
     temporary provocation could induce me to de<lb break="no"/>nounce all union, as others did; but that I 
     <lb/>
     wisely contented myself with hostility to the 
     <lb/>
     particular scheme then under consideration. I 
     <lb/>
     do not deny that in the warmth of an exciting 
     <lb/>
     platform discussion I may not here used lan<lb break="no"/>guage that I in times of greater coolness 
     <lb/>
     would not have uttered. But no candid man 
     <lb/>
     would think of binding another too strictly to 
     <lb/>
     every expression used before an excited 
     <lb/>
     popular assemblage, amid the cheers of his 
     <lb/>
     friends and the hisses of his opponents. It is 
     <lb/>
     only proper to recollect that everything I then 
     <lb/>
     said—every argument I advanced—was direct<lb break="no"/>ly solely to the end of defeating the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     Resolutions. When the question came before 
     <lb/>
     the Legislature at a late period last session, I 
     <lb/>
     intended to have fully explained my position 
     <lb/>
     and views, but in common with a number of 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen on both sides—for reasons which 
     <lb/>
     will be found in the reported debates—I de<lb break="no"/>nied myself the pleasure of speaking on it at 
     <lb/>
     any length. In the few remarks I did make, 
     <lb/>
     however, I find the following decided reitera<lb break="no"/>tion of all my previous declarations:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">   
            <p>
     "If I have any desire for an union, it is for the lar<lb break="no"/>ger one. The opinion I held last year I hold now. 
     <lb/>My opposition has not been to union in the abstract, 
     <lb/>but to the terms on which it was secured. I defy 
     <lb/>any one to find a single passage in anything I have 
     <lb/>said which proves that I am opposed to an Union on 
     <lb/>equitable terms." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </quote>
    
            <cb/>
           
            <p>
     Sir, I do not think I require to say a single 
     <lb/>
     word in addition to what is contained in the 
     <lb/>
     official records of this House to show that from 
     <lb/>
     my first appearance in this Legislature up to 
     <lb/>
     the present time, I have been favorable to an 
     <lb/>
     union of these Provinces. I am chargeable 
     <lb/>
     with no sudden conversion to that opinion— 
     <lb/>
     nay, more, I am chargeable with no inconsist<lb break="no"/>ency in regard to it. Every one who under<lb break="no"/>stands the difference between the principle of 
     <lb/>
     a measure and its details, is well aware that 
     <lb/>
     in supporting the principle of any scheme a 
     <lb/>
     party does not commit himself to its details. 
     <lb/>
     The absurdity of any other assumption is too 
     <lb/>
     apparent to call for comment. In the same 
     <lb/>
     way, in opposing the details of a measure, it 
     <lb/>
     does not follow that we oppose its principle. I 
     <lb/>
     do not make these obvious remarks for gentle<lb break="no"/>men in this House, but for those elsewhere 
     <lb/>
     who may not as readily appreciate the dis<lb break="no"/>tinction. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     What, then, has been my position on this 
     <lb/>
     great question up to the present time? My po<lb break="no"/>sition has been that of an uncompromising op<lb break="no"/>ponent of the Quebec scheme, yet an advocate 
     <lb/>
     of Union. While, however, my hostility to the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec resolutions has not diminished during 
     <lb/>
     the last eighteen months the subject has been 
     <lb/>
     agitated, I am not prepared to assert that my 
     <lb/>
     attachment to the principle of Union during 
     <lb/>
     the same period, has not increased. Sir, I 
     <lb/>
     frankly admit that it has increased. I am 
     <lb/>
     more firmly convinced at the present moment 
     <lb/>
     than ever, of the desirability of an Union of 
     <lb/>
     British America. There are many reasons to<lb break="no"/>day that did not exist two years ago why 
     <lb/>
     every British American who is not insensible 
     <lb/>
     to the logic of events, should desire an Union 
     <lb/>
     that would tend to consolidate the strength, de<lb break="no"/>velope the resources, protect the rights, and 
     <lb/>
     and promote the mutual interests of these pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. Sir, the Provinces of British North 
     <lb/>
     America are in no ordinary period of their his<lb break="no"/>tory—and that man is heedless of the signs of 
     <lb/>
     the times—is heedless of events that are daily 
     <lb/>
     and hourly transpiring around him, who exhi<lb break="no"/>bits indifference to, or affects to disregard dan<lb break="no"/>ger in, the present state of public affairs on this 
     <lb/>
     continent. I need not remind hon. gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     that the whole aspect of things around us have 
     <lb/>
     been changed within one short year. The 
     <lb/>
     neighboring republic, twelve months ago, was 
     <lb/>
     in the throes of a death-struggle, which threat<lb break="no"/>ened its disruption, has since emerged from the 
     <lb/>
     ordeal, claiming the reputation of one of the 
     <lb/>
     first military nations of the world. Her military 
     <lb/>
     prestige will not diminish the characteristic 
     <lb/>
     arrogance of her international policy. It will 
     <lb/>
     certainly not lessen her disposition to offen<lb break="no"/>siveness in her intercourse with foreign na<lb break="no"/>tions, as it has increased her necessities; it will 
     <lb/>
     not lessen her desire to aggrandize herself at 
     <lb/>
     the expense of her neighbors. We have 
     <lb/>
     grounds of apprehension in this respect pecu<lb break="no"/>liar to ourselves. We know that the late war 
     <lb/>
     in America has created a feeling of animosity 
     <lb/>
     for some fancied grievances, among some 
     <lb/>
     classes of the American people towards Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain and these colonies. I need not specify 
     <lb/>
     these assumed grievances; they are familiar 
     <lb/>
     to every one. They may culminate at no dis<lb break="no"/>tant day in a war between the two countries. 
     <lb/>
     They have already culminated in a species of 
     <lb/>commercial warfare, aimed at the prosperity 
     <lb/>of British America. Does any one doubt that 

            <pb n="187" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_187.jpg"/>
               <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
               <fw type="num">187</fw>
   
     the repeal of the Reciprocity Treaty is intended 
     <lb/>
     partly as a punishment of these provinces for 
     <lb/>
     their sympathy with the Southern States dur<lb break="no"/>ing the late struggle, and partly as an annoyance 
     <lb/>
     to Great Britain for her alleged bad faith as a 
     <lb/>
     neutral power. But sir, there can be less 
     <lb/>
     doubt that it is chiefly relied on—I mean the 
     <lb/>
     repeal of the treaty, as a great means of 
     <lb/>
     fostering annexation sentiments in British 
     <lb/>
     North America. I shall prove this as<lb break="no"/>sertion presently beyond the possibility 
     <lb/>
     of doubt. Assuming it to be correct, is it not 
     <lb/>
     our duty to adopt such steps as may frustrate 
     <lb/>
     any such design? Now, Sir, I ask what step 
     <lb/>
     is so likely to conduce to the result we have in 
     <lb/>
     view, as an union under one Government, 
     <lb/>
     which will give all these colonies a common 
     <lb/>policy, and a common platform of action? 
     <lb/>Isolation in relation to reciprocal trade, in the 
     <lb/>present crisis, has peculiar dangers. It gives 
     <lb/>the Washington authorities complete com<lb break="no"/>mand of the whole situation. It gives them 
     <lb/>the power of playing us off against each other,of 
     <lb/>exciting jealousies, producing dissensions, and 
     <lb/>creating interests which can have but one ten<lb break="no"/>dency. No Government under the sun more 
     <lb/>thoroughly understands that game than the 
     <lb/>Government of the United States. They will 
     <lb/>play it to our ruin and their own advantage, 
     <lb/>if we leave the cards in their hands, I do not 
     <lb/>wish to go further in connection with this 
     <lb/>view of the subject, but it has had a power<lb break="no"/>ful influence on my mind. It affords a most 
     <lb/>weighty argument in favor of immediate 
     <lb/>union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     I have said that the repeal of the Recipro<lb break="no"/>city Treaty is intended to produce annexa<lb break="no"/>tion tendencies in British America. I think I 
     <lb/>can adduce evidence on this point so conclu<lb break="no"/>sive as to amount to a moral demonstration. 
     <lb/>Allow me, in the first place, to revert to the 
     <lb/>history of the Commercial Congress held last 
     <lb/>summer in Detroit, representing the great 
     <lb/>mercantile interests of the U. States and B. 
     <lb/>America. Need I remind hon. gentlemen that 
     <lb/>on that occasion an important functionary 
     <lb/>of the Washington government—a gentleman 
     <lb/>occupying the high position of American Con<lb break="no"/>sul at Montreal, the first city in British Ameri<lb break="no"/>ca, declared that he attended that Congress at 
     <lb/>the request of his goverment, and with autho<lb break="no"/>rity to express their views and wishes with 
     <lb/>regard to reciprocal trade. He earnestly ad<lb break="no"/>vised the abrogation of the treaty, and openly 
     <lb/>and insultingly told the colonial members of 
     <lb/>the Convention that the object of this policy 
     <lb/>was to produce the annexation of British 
     <lb/>America to the Republic. We have, then,the 
     <lb/>fact that Mr. Potter went to Detroit, declaring 
     <lb/>himself in the confidence of his government, 
     <lb/>and the exponent of their views, and we all 
     <lb/>know that his utterances have never been dis<lb break="no"/>owned by his masters, and we have the further 
     <lb/>most important fact that on the first meeting 
     <lb/>of Congress, the policy that gentleman fore<lb break="no"/>shadowed as that of the Washington govern<lb break="no"/>meet was carried out. If, then, Mr. Potter was 
     <lb/>correct in foreshadowing the policy of his 
     <lb/>government, is not the conclusion irresistible 
     <lb/>that he was equally correct as to the wishes 
     <lb/>and motives that were at the foundation of 
     <lb/>that policy? These significant facts cannot 
     <lb/>fail to make a due impression on the mind of 
     <lb/>every man who desires to maintain our con<lb break="no"/>nection with the Empire; and they strongly 
     <lb/>
            <cb/>
     confirm my convictions not only of the desira<lb break="no"/>bility but of the necessity of Union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     We know from the newspaper press of the 
     <lb/>
     United States that the question of an union 
     <lb/>
     of British America has attracted considerable 
     <lb/>
     attention in that country, and that the propo<lb break="no"/>sal is generally received with little partiality. 
     <lb/>
     Those journals especially noted for their vio<lb break="no"/>lent antipathy towards everything British do 
     <lb/>
     not conceal their hostility to the measure, and 
     <lb/>
     the grounds of that hostility. We find that those 
     <lb/>
     who oppose union are applauded as the friends 
     <lb/>
     of annexation, while those who advooate it re<lb break="no"/>ceive very different treatment. Let me treat 
     <lb/>
     the house to an extract from a journal marked 
     <lb/>
     for the vileness and virulence of its abuse of 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain and these colonies—the N. Y. 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi>—as indicative of the hopes entertained 
     <lb/>
     in that quarter as the inevitable result of a 
     <lb/>
     refusal on our part to unite, and concentrate 
     <lb/>
     our strength. The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> of the 10th of March 
     <lb/>
     last, referring to the repeal of the Reciprocity 
     <lb/>
     Treaty, says :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "Meantime, the Provincials who have had a taste 
     <lb/>
     of the blessings of free trade with the ' Yankees' un<lb break="no"/>der this expiring Reciprocity Treaty, are called upon 
     <lb/>
     to consider the question of their 'manifest destiny' 
     <lb/>
     in the proposition from Queen Victoria for a North 
     <lb/>
     American Confederation under the vice-royalty of a 
     <lb/>
     member of her family. This movement contemplates 
     <lb/>
     a consolidation, <hi rendition="simple:italic">which has already been declined by</hi> 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Nova Scotia</hi> and New Brunswick; but it is not thus 
     <lb/>
     to be abandoned. AN AGITATION WILL BE APT TO 
     <lb/>
     FOLLOW, WHICH IN DUE TIME WILL GRAVITATE T0 
     <lb/>
     THE EASY, NATURAL AND ADVANTAGEOUS SOLUTION 
     <lb/>
     OF ANNEXATION TO THE UNITED STATES." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </quote>
            <p>
     Sir, there is something in this language that 
     <lb/>
     should arrest the attention of every man not 
     <lb/>
     blinded by party or other unworthy feelings. 
     <lb/>
     What is the meaning of this "agitation" with 
     <lb/>
     which we are threatened? Is the repeal of the 
     <lb/>
     Reciprocity Treaty merely the initiation of a 
     <lb/>
     systematic design to undermine our allegiance 
     <lb/>
     and annex us? Have the Government of the 
     <lb/>
     United States their agents in this country for 
     <lb/>
     this purpose, as insinuated by the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi>? If 
     <lb/>
     they have, it will not long remain a secret, for 
     <lb/>
     the hour of action is at hand, when we all must 
     <lb/>
     be judged by the sympathies we avow, and the 
     <lb/>
     company we keep. I am aware that no man 
     <lb/>
     would dare openly advocate annexation, but 
     <lb/>
     if there be any among us who desire it, they 
     <lb/>
     will take the more safe and insidious means 
     <lb/>
     of attaining their end by exciting disaffection 
     <lb/>
     on any pretext that will offer itself. The lan<lb break="no"/>guage of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> affords reasonable grounds 
     <lb/>
     for watchfulness, and it is only right that the 
     <lb/>
     country should be on its guard.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, sir, there is another consideration that 
     <lb/>
     has its just weight with me. The Imperial 
     <lb/>
     Government has spoken on this subject in 
     <lb/>terms not to be mistaken, and firmly and per<lb break="no"/>sistently urges on the people of British Ame<lb break="no"/>rica the necessity for Union. I know there are 
     <lb/>persons who talk very flippantly of the inter<lb break="no"/>ference of Colonial Secretaries or the British 
     <lb/>Government, in our affairs. For my part, sir, 
     <lb/>while I would as readily as any one resist im<lb break="no"/>proper interference from any quarter in the 
     <lb/>public affairs of this Province. I would be sor<lb break="no"/>ry to deny the right of the Queen's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to use its just influence and authority in 
     <lb/>all matters of Imperial concern. Much less 
     <lb/>would I dream of anything so absurd 
     <lb/>as to dispute its right to deal with any measure 
     <lb/>affecting the integrity of the Empire. On all 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="188" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_188.jpg"/>
               <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
            
     questions of this character, I, for one, am 
     <lb/>
     ready to yield the most respectful deference to 
     <lb/>
     this high authority. The desire of Her Majes<lb break="no"/>ty's Government for an union of the Colonies 
     <lb/>
     has received the most emphatic expression 
     <lb/>
     that could be given to it—it has been declared 
     <lb/>
     in three consecutive speeches from the Throne. 
     <lb/>
     Now, I ask this House, is there a colony under 
     <lb/>
     the crown that has greater reason to shew 
     <lb/>
     deference to the just wishes of the British 
     <lb/>
     Government than the province of Nova Scotia? 
     <lb/>
     Sir, do I require to point to the evidences of 
     <lb/>
     Imperial solicitude for our safety and welfare 
     <lb/>
     that are before everybody's eyes? Walk out 
     <lb/>
     some fine morning and view the fortifications 
     <lb/>
     of this city, and get, as you can only get, an 
     <lb/>
     imperfect estimate of the immense treasure 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain has spent for the protection of 
     <lb/>
     this people. Visit that citadel, under whose 
     <lb/>
     shadow even now our slumbers are undis<lb break="no"/>turbed—visit Point Pleasant, George's Island, 
     <lb/>
     and a half dozen other places I could name. 
     <lb/>
     Extend your wanderings to the north end of 
     <lb/>
     of this city, and see those magnificent struc<lb break="no"/>tures—the Wellington Barracks,— visit the 
     <lb/>
     Ordnance and Dockyards—and then you will 
     <lb/>
     have only a very faint idea of the amount of 
     <lb/>
     treasure Great Britain has lavished upon us. 
     <lb/>
     How much does the army, supported here for 
     <lb/>
     our protection, spend among us? In a few 
     <lb/>
     short weeks the harbor of Halifax will be alive 
     <lb/>
     with the wooden walls of England. Her brave 
     <lb/>
     tars will be on the spot to protect our interests, 
     <lb/>
     and leave their last dollar with our people. 
     <lb/>
     Should these things be forgotten or winked 
     <lb/>
     out of sight at the present time? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But, sir, it is not alone in this way Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain has shown us favor. She has not only 
     <lb/>
     done every thing for our protection and secu<lb break="no"/>rity, but she has given us the entire control of 
     <lb/>
     our local affairs—Responsible Government, 
     <lb/>
     and every liberty we enjoy having been got 
     <lb/>
     for the asking. Therefore, sir, as a Nova Sco<lb break="no"/>tian, I am ready to yield that deference to the 
     <lb/>
     wishes of the Imperial Government they have 
     <lb/>
     a right to expect. Their past treatment of this 
     <lb/>
     province is a guarantee that they desire to im<lb break="no"/>prove our condition by union. I have no hesi<lb break="no"/>tation in saying, that of all the dependencies 
     <lb/>
     of the Crown, Nova Scotia should be one of 
     <lb/>
     the most disposed to yield a deferential ear to 
     <lb/>
     Imperial counsels. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     It may be said, sir, that my practice is incon<lb break="no"/>sistent with my professions—that for the last 
     <lb/>
     eighteen months I have been opposing the po<lb break="no"/>licy of the British Government. I deny the 
     <lb/>
     imputation. I have never opposed that policy 
     <lb/>
      —on the contrary, I have advocated it. I con<lb break="no"/>sider there are only two classes in the Provin<lb break="no"/>ces who are in antagonism to the Imperial po<lb break="no"/>licy: those who are opposed to all union, and 
     <lb/>those, unwittingly so, yet equally hostile to 
     <lb/>that policy, who would force a scheme of 
     <lb/>union on the Maritime Provinces, which its 
     <lb/>opponents believe to be unjust, and its sup<lb break="no"/>porters know to be obnoxious to the great bo<lb break="no"/>dy of the people. Against that scheme public 
     <lb/>opinion has unmistakeably pronounced, and if 
     <lb/>forced upon us the result will be the opposite 
     <lb/>to that desired. The British Government 
     <lb/>have no especial partiality for the Quebec 
     <lb/>scheme; they desire an equitable union of 
     <lb/>British America, and instead of opposing, I 
     <lb/>have always advocated such an union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     There are one or two other matters to which 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
               
     I shall allude before turning my attention to 
     <lb/>
     the question I intend to ask. A few days ago 
     <lb/>
     this House went through all the solemn forms 
     <lb/>
     of a Conference with the other branch of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature on a subject, the importance of 
     <lb/>
     which is admitted by every one—I allude to 
     <lb/>
     the protection of our Fisheries. What was the 
     <lb/>
     result of the deliberations of the joint com<lb break="no"/>mittee of both Houses on that occasion ?— 
     <lb/>
     What means did they suggest for that great 
     <lb/>
     service? Their report has been placed on our 
     <lb/>
     table, and what does it advise? An humble 
     <lb/>
     petition to the Queen's Government, praying 
     <lb/>
     for assistance. In our necessities we rush to 
     <lb/>
     the Colonial Offîce for aid and protection, and 
     <lb/>
     yet there are those among us who deny any 
     <lb/>
     reciprocal duty on our part—any obligation 
     <lb/>
     even to listen respectfully to the wishes of Bri<lb break="no"/>tish Ministers. We know that although we 
     <lb/>
     may buy a blockade runner, and vote a few 
     <lb/>
     thousand dollars for the service, our Fisheries 
     <lb/>
     can have no adequate protection if England 
     <lb/>
     refuses us her aid. Now, I ask, is it reasonable 
     <lb/>
     to expect a favorable answer to our petition if 
     <lb/>
     we refuse to comply, at such an important pe<lb break="no"/>riod in our history, with the request of Her 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's Government? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. Speaker, there is another subject to 
     <lb/>
     which I must refer, because its bearing on the 
     <lb/>
     question of Colonial Union is too palpable to 
     <lb/>
     escape the commonest observation. Every one 
     <lb/>
     will admit that the clouds impending over our 
     <lb/>
     political horizon at the present time may justly 
     <lb/>
     excite the most serious apprehensions. An 
     <lb/>
     organization, at first regarded with contempt, 
     <lb/>
     has been called into existence on this continent 
     <lb/>
     which has lately assumed very formidable di<lb break="no"/>mensions—I mean the Fenian Brotherhood. 
     <lb/>
     A part of the avowed policy of this organiza<lb break="no"/>tion is the severance of the connection 
     <lb/>
     between these Colonies and Great Britain. 
     <lb/>
     The termination of the civil war in the Uni<lb break="no"/>ted States has thrown loose on that country 
     <lb/>
     nearly half a million of daring and reckless 
     <lb/>
     men, with a taste for the license and excite<lb break="no"/>ment of military life, and a disrelish of the 
     <lb/>
     pursuits of peace. These men, from whom 
     <lb/>
     the Fenian recruits are chiefly drawn, are rea<lb break="no"/>dy to embark in the most lawless and hazard<lb break="no"/>ous enterprises. The organization extends 
     <lb/>
     throughout the Northern and Western States, 
     <lb/>
     and boasts of having at its command any num<lb break="no"/>ber of men and any amount of money for ope<lb break="no"/>rations against the British Empire, which it 
     <lb/>seeks to dismember. It is not concealed that 
     <lb/>the vulnerable point through which this object 
     <lb/>to be attained is British America. Now, sir, 
     <lb/>perhaps this House will be astonished to learn 
     <lb/>that in the published platform of the Fenian 
     <lb/>organizatlon, it is laid down as a lead<lb break="no"/>ing object and duty of that body to 
     <lb/>prevent the consolidation of British power 
     <lb/>on this continent by the proposed union of these 
     <lb/>Provinces under one government. This fact has 
     <lb/>only some to my knowledge within a few weeks. 
     <lb/>I repeat, sir, it is laid down in the platform of the 
     <lb/>Fenian body as the paramount duty of every Fenian 
     <lb/>either in the United States or the British Provinces, 
     <lb/>to oppose and frustrate any union among us. There<lb break="no"/>fore, l say that the man who now opposes union—l 
     <lb/>don't mean the Quebec scheme—but who sets his face 
     <lb/>against all union actually endorses the leading prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of Fenianism! I do not believe there are a dozen 
     <lb/>men in Nova Scotia who would knowingly occupy 
     <lb/>this position, and I feel confident that when this fact 
     <lb/>is understood it will do much to popularize the Union 
     <lb/>sentiment in this Province, whose loyalty is prover<lb break="no"/>
            
            <pb n="189" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_189.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY</fw>
            <fw type="num">189</fw>
            
     bial. If there is a single argument that will more 
     <lb/>
     than another touch the hearts of our loyal popula<lb break="no"/>tion, it is that the enemies of British power 
     <lb/>
     everywhere are hostile to this movement, and the 
     <lb/>
     fact should cause many of us to hesitate and enquire 
     <lb/>
     what is our true position? If we have any regard 
     <lb/>
     for our present happy condition, or any desire to con<lb break="no"/>tinue our connection with Great Britain, it behooves 
     <lb/>
     us to set our house in order, and to see that we are 
     <lb/>
     not, in more ways than one, in the words of the New 
     <lb/>
     York <hi rendition="simple:italic">Herald</hi> "gravitating towards annexation." 
     <lb/>
     No one can doubt the patriotism of the people of 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia, and if a hostile raid were made upon 
     <lb/>
     any portion of our country, the invaders would meet 
     <lb/>
     with a reception they would not soon forget. But who 
     <lb/>
     does not know that the favor and protection of Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain would be to us a source of greater security 
     <lb/>
     than maintaining a standing army of 100,000 men?— 
     <lb/>
     With the power of the greatest Empire under the sun 
     <lb/>
     at our backs we could present a fearless front to all the 
     <lb/>
     world. If it were desirable for no other cause that 
     <lb/>
     these Provinces should be consolidated— than that we 
     <lb/>
     would thereby disappoint the enemies of our country. 
     <lb/>
     it should be a strong inducement to union. But when 
     <lb/>
     in addition to this fact by that step we would secure 
     <lb/>
     the protection of the mother country—when she only 
     <lb/>
     asks from us an act of just filial obedience to induce 
     <lb/>
     her to stretch forth her powerful arm to guard our 
     <lb/>
     property and rights—this ought certainly to be suffi<lb break="no"/>cient. I say, therefore, in view of these facts—in 
     <lb/>
     view of the dangers which have developed themselves 
     <lb/>
     within the last few months. <choice><sic>if</sic><corr>If</corr></choice> we can obtain an equi<lb break="no"/>table union, it is the duty of every man who desires 
     <lb/>
     to uphold British connexion —who is opposed to an<lb break="no"/>nexation—who has no sympathy with Fenians, and 
     <lb/>
     who does not wish to be consigned to the tender mer<lb break="no"/>cies of the lawless gang, to promote such an union of 
     <lb/>
     those provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now sir, holding the opinions I do in <choice><sic>referen e</sic><corr>reference</corr></choice> to 
     <lb/>
     this great question—advocating the principle of 
     <lb/>
     Union and opposing the Quebec Resolutions, I have 
     <lb/>
     been asked by the press of this country, and I admit 
     <lb/>
     not unfairly. asked, to define my position. 1 have 
     <lb/>
     been asked to justify my conduct in opposing a 
     <lb/>
     scheme embodying a principle to which I am commi<lb break="no"/>ted, without offering any other means of attaining 
     <lb/>
     the end I profess to have in view. Well, sir. I am 
     <lb/>
     here to-day to define my position, and to answer the 
     <lb/>
     other objections urged against me. I am also here to 
     <lb/>
     make an important enquiry of the Government. As 
     <lb/>
     to my position, I am in favor of an Union—a Federal 
     <lb/>
     Union of these Provinces. I <choice><sic>b elieve</sic><corr>believe</corr></choice> such a Union 
     <lb/>
     best suited to the exigencies of our situation. It a 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Union were practicable I would prefer 
     <lb/>
     adopting the Federal principle in forming an union 
     <lb/>
     of British America. among the admirable speeches 
     <lb/>
     delivered some years ago, in this House, on this sub<lb break="no"/>ject, that of the present Chief Justice, in which that 
     <lb/>
     able lawyer and shrewd politician contended that a 
     <lb/>
     Federal Union was best suited to our circumstances, 
     <lb/>
     appeared to me the most statesmanlike and sound. 
     <lb/>
     Accepting, then, as I do, the principle of a Federal 
     <lb/>
     Union, 1 desire to ask the Government if there is no 
     <lb/>
     common ground on which the supporters of the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec schemes—abandoning that scheme—can meet 
     <lb/>
     the friends of an Union on more advantageous terms, 
     <lb/>
     and arrange the details of a measure that will be just 
     <lb/>
     and satisfactory to the people? I think there is a 
     <lb/>
     common ground,—a ground on which I am willing 
     <lb/>
     to take my stand regardless of who follows me 
     <lb/>
     If the Government will publicly abandon the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec scheme, and introduce a resolution in favor 
     <lb/>
     of a Federal Union of British America—leaving the de 
     <lb/>
     tails of the measure to the arbitrament of the Imperial 
     <lb/>
     Government properly advised by delegates from all 
     <lb/>
     the Provinces, I promise them my cordial support. 
     <lb/>
     This would be commencing rightly. By getting the 
     <lb/>
     endorsement of the Legislature, in the outset, of the 
     <lb/>
     principle of Union, and its authority to enter on the 
     <lb/>
     settlement of the details of a scheme, the friends of 
     <lb/>
     the measure would occupy a very different position 
     <lb/>
     from that occupied by the delegates to the Quebec Con<lb break="no"/>ference, who went to Canada, in 1864:, without any 
     <lb/>
     authority from Parliament. No small amount of op<lb break="no"/>position was at that time excited against confedera<lb break="no"/>tion from this cause. It had much weight with myself 
     <lb/>
            <cb/>
          
     and many others, who looked upon the action of the 
     <lb/>
     delegates as an improper usurpation of power. An<lb break="no"/>other conference on this side of the water has been 
     <lb/>
     suggested in certain quarters, but if we really desire 
     <lb/>
     a practical result, it cannot be entertained. To re<lb break="no"/>open negociations here at the present time would be 
     <lb/>
     only to retard Union for some years to come. Be<lb break="no"/>sides I believe the most certain means of obtaining 
     <lb/>
     justice for the Maritime Provinces, would be to leave 
     <lb/>
     the settlement of details to the Imperial Government. 
     <lb/>
     I ask is there a tribunal in the world to which Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia might more confidently appeal for justice than 
     <lb/>
     to that august and impartial body? Its integrity— 
     <lb/>
     its wisdom—its intelligence are beyond dispute. I 
     <lb/>
     say that if there be a tribunal, where might will not 
     <lb/>
     prevail against right, it is the one I indicate. If we 
     <lb/>
     can get justice any where we will get it from that 
     <lb/>
     tribunal, and I ask does any Nova Scotian desire 
     <lb/>
     more than justice? This subject has engaged the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the public men of Great Britain. It is well 
     <lb/>
     known in that country that the difficulties in the 
     <lb/>
     way of union are principally with the Maritime 
     <lb/>
     Provinces, and if we throw ourselves confidingly on 
     <lb/>
     the justice of the British Government, I believe we 
     <lb/>
     will receive even a partial arbitration of our rights. I 
     <lb/>
     know of no means by which we can more effectually 
     <lb/>
     conciliate the affections and secure the favorable consi<lb break="no"/>deration of the Queen's Government than by thus 
     <lb/>
     proving our confidence in its justice, and our anxiety 
     <lb/>
     to meet its wishes. I therefore ask the leader of the 
     <lb/>
     Government, and through him the advocates of the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec scheme, whether they are so wedded to that 
     <lb/>
     scheme as to be unable to entertain the proposition 
     <lb/>
     I, as a friend of Colonial Union, now frankly make? 
     <lb/>
     I will not deny that the extraordinary reaction that 
     <lb/>
     has taken place in New Brunswick in regard to Union, 
     <lb/>
     and the admitted partiality of a large majority of the 
     <lb/>
     people of Nova Scotia for the abstract principle, cou<lb break="no"/>pled with the firm but constitutional pressure of the 
     <lb/>
     Imperial authorities, afford grounds to apprehend 
     <lb/>
     that before very long even the Quebec Resolutions 
     <lb/>
     may be carried in the Maritime Provinces. The ob<lb break="no"/>ject of my present movement is—and l fearlessly avow 
     <lb/>
     it—to defeat the Quebec scheme <choice><sic>Before</sic><corr>before</corr></choice> it is too late 
     <lb/>
     —before we are borne down by the powerful influen<lb break="no"/>ces against which we are now contending—while yet 
     <lb/>
     we have a formidable army in the field—while our 
     <lb/>
     opponents respect our strength and hesitate at an en<lb break="no"/>gagement—is it not wise to seek the most advantage<lb break="no"/>ous terms of compromise? Men of extreme views— 
     <lb/>men who desire to make this great subject a stalking 
     <lb/>horse on which to ride into office—in short, individuals 
     <lb/>" with other ends to serve," may condemn the course 
     <lb/>I have taken, but no one values the censure or appro<lb break="no"/>val of such men. I shall lose nothing in severing in 
     <lb/>connection with them, while I feel my conduct, wi 1 
     <lb/>be generally sustained by the intelligent portion of 
     <lb/>my countrymen. But I do confess that this step may 
     <lb/>sever me politically and personally from a few gentle<lb break="no"/>men, sincere in their opposition to all union—whom 
     <lb/>I respect, and whose friendship I value. I shall re<lb break="no"/>gret it, but must frankly say, I desire to maintain no 
     <lb/>connexion. I am prepared to throw away any friend<lb break="no"/>ship, that can only be pr served at the sacrifice of 
     <lb/>my convictions. If I have been marked for anything 
     <lb/>while I have been in this Assembly. it has been for 
     <lb/>independence of action, and fearlessness in the ex<lb break="no"/>pression of my thoughts. I have never acknowledged 
     <lb/>allegiance to any leader or party in this House. I 
     <lb/>have never attended a party caucus in my life. 
     <lb/>Among the gentlemen I address, no one within the 
     <lb/>past two years has come more frequently into keen 
     <lb/>collision here and elsewhere with the occupants of 
     <lb/>the Treasury Benches than myself. I am certainly 
     <lb/>indebted to these gentlemen for no favours, and 1 can 
     <lb/>point to more than one act of personal and political 
     <lb/>injustice received at their hands. But, sir, I would 
     <lb/>be unworthy of my position in this Legislature, if I 
     <lb/>could allow considerations of this nature on one side 
     <lb/>or the other to controul my action in the presence of 
     <lb/>a question of the highest magnitude. I will not deny 
     <lb/>that I have some ambition as a public man, but my 
     <lb/>highest ambition will be gratified, if I can contribute 
     <lb/>an humble stone to the edifice of Colonial Union. 
     <lb/>Before, however. I can yield any assistance to the 
     <lb/>builders, the model of the proposed structure must 
     <lb/>
       

            <pb n="190" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_190.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">190</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
        

     be altered, and the whole design undergo the revi<lb break="no"/>sion of an architect in whom I have confidence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
               
            <p>
     Sir, the hostility I have all along evinced to the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec scheme of Confederation has frequently been 
     <lb/>
     attributed to a desire to defeat the government, and 
     <lb/>
     thus promote my own political prospects. I trust 
     <lb/>
     that the course I have this day taken will be a suffi<lb break="no"/>cient answer to this charge. If such were my desire 
     <lb/>
     my end would be most certainly attained, in the pre<lb break="no"/>sent wide-spread hostility to that scheme, by main<lb break="no"/>taining the position I have occupied for the last 
     <lb/>
     eighteen months, without committing myself to any 
     <lb/>
     proposal for the solution of our difficulties. But as 
     <lb/>
     an avowed Unionist, such a course would be inde<lb break="no"/>fensible, and I am not willing to pursue any course 
     <lb/>
     I cannot defend. Nor do I seek any temporary tri<lb break="no"/>umph over my political opponents at the expense of 
     <lb/>
     the highest interests of my country. If the govern<lb break="no"/>ment are animated by sentiments of moderation, 
     <lb/>
     justice and sound policy, they shall have my humble 
     <lb/>
     aid in the great work in which they are engaged. I 
     <lb/>
     hope we may find a common ground of co-operation 
     <lb/>
     in our efforts to improve our present condition of iso<lb break="no"/>lation and obscurity, and elevate Nova Sootia to the 
     <lb/>
     position nature intended her to occupy. But, sir, do 
     <lb/>
     not let me be supposed to underrate the present posi<lb break="no"/>tion of this Province. Far from it. Even as she is, 
     <lb/>
     I am proud of my country, and grateful for the happy 
     <lb/>
     homes she affords her sons. Yet proud, sir, as I am 
     <lb/>
     of the little sea—girt province I call my native land: 
     <lb/>
     proud as I am of her free institutions—her moral 
     <lb/>
     status—her material wealth; proud as I am of the 
     <lb/>
     name of Nova Scotian—a name which the genius and 
     <lb/>
     valour of my countrymen have inscribed high on the 
     <lb/>
     scroll of fame; proud, I say as I am, and may well be 
     <lb/>
     permitted to be of these things, I have never ceased 
     <lb/>
     to entertain the hope, expressed in this legislature 
     <lb/>
     in 1864, that the day was not far distant, when you, 
     <lb/>
     sir, and I, and those who listen to me—in common 
     <lb/>
     with the inhabitants of these noble Provinces, unit<lb break="no"/>ed under one government, might stand before the 
     <lb/>
     world in the prouder national character of British 
     <lb/>
     Americans. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. PROVINCIAL SECRETARY</persName> replied:— 
     <lb/>
     I have listened with much gratification to the 
     <lb/>
     address which has just been delivered to this 
     <lb/>
     House by the hon. member for Richmond, and 
     <lb/>
     I confess that I am not surprised that, distaste<lb break="no"/>ful as the Quebec scheme of Union has been 
     <lb/>
     to many persons in this country, in the 
     <lb/>
     existing condition of public affairs in British 
     <lb/>
     North America, the attention of the strongest 
     <lb/>
     opponents of that scheme should be directed to 
     <lb/>
     the great question of what solution may be 
     <lb/>
     found for the difficulties of the position in which 
     <lb/>
     we are placed. Having taken a part in matur<lb break="no"/>ing that great measure—having, on former 
     <lb/>
     occasions, felt it my duty to vindicate the 
     <lb/>
     scheme that was propounded for the consider<lb break="no"/>ation of British North America, I cannot be 
     <lb/>
     supposed to enter into the feelings of the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Richmond in his denunciation of 
     <lb/>
     that scheme. I believed then, and I believe 
     <lb/>
     now, that the plan of Intercolonial Union that 
     <lb/>
     was propounded by the Conference at Quebec 
     <lb/>
     and which has obtained so marked a degree of 
     <lb/>
     favour and approval from Her Majesty's Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, did afford the people of British 
     <lb/>
     North America the most ample guarantee for 
     <lb/>
     the rights and privileges of all sections. But I 
     <lb/>
     am not insensible to the fact that many objec<lb break="no"/>tions have been raised against that scheme, and 
     <lb/>
     that many gentlemen who have taken a most 
     <lb/>
     prominent part in opposing various features of 
     <lb/>
     the measure, have in the Press, as the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member has in his place in Parliament, declar<lb break="no"/>ed themselves in favour of a Union of British 
     <lb/>
     North America, that would be acceptable to 
     <lb/>
     the people of this county. I am not, stand<lb break="no"/>ing in the peculiar position I do, able, how<lb break="no"/>
           
            <cb/>
               
     ever, to give a direct and unequivocal state<lb break="no"/>ment of the views of the government or 
     <lb/>
     of the promoters of the Quebec scheme. The 
     <lb/>
     House is well aware that this question has
     <lb/>
     from the first been submitted to the people as 
     <lb/>
     one in which the government divided the 
     <lb/>
     responsibility with gentlemen who were 
     <lb/>
     politically opposed to them. Occupying this 
     <lb/>
     position the government would have been not 
     <lb/>
     only wanting in courtesy to the gentlemen who 
     <lb/>
     had supported them, but would have failed in 
     <lb/>
     their duty in respect to a great public question, 
     <lb/>
     if they had ever treated it in a party aspect.— 
     <lb/>
     In dealing with this question the government 
     <lb/>
     have always consulted the wishes and inclina<lb break="no"/>tions, and carried with them, the co-operation 
     <lb/>
     of the gentlemen who are politically opposed 
     <lb/>
     to them. Under these circumstances it would 
     <lb/>
     be impossible for me to state the views of the 
     <lb/>
     government, except on consultation with those 
     <lb/>
     who have acted with us, and are parties to the 
     <lb/>
     scheme of Union. But as far as I may 
     <lb/>
     state without consultation, I believe that 
     <lb/>
     all the gentlemen who have been 
     <lb/>
     engaged in maturing the Quebec scheme 
     <lb/>
     have had no other desire than to meet 
     <lb/>
     the wishes and consult the best interests of 
     <lb/>
     their countrymen. They have always looked 
     <lb/>
     upon this question as too solemn in its charac<lb break="no"/>ter to allow it for a single moment to be in<lb break="no"/>fluenced by any considerations except the wel<lb break="no"/>fare of the country. I am not at all surprised 
     <lb/>
     at the statements made by the hon. member.— 
     <lb/>
     The last twelve months have been pregnant 
     <lb/>
     with circumstances that must give an impor<lb break="no"/>tance and an urgency to this question of Colo<lb break="no"/>nial Union such as it has never obtained be<lb break="no"/>fore. In view of the altered condition of things 
     <lb/>
     I am not at all surprised that the most strenu<lb break="no"/>ous opponents of the Quebec scheme are ready 
     <lb/>
     to co-operate on some common ground on 
     <lb/>
     which they and the promoters of that scheme 
     <lb/>
     will be prepared, at any sacrifice that they can 
     <lb/>
     make consistently with the great objects to be 
     <lb/>
     obtained, to deal with this question with the 
     <lb/>
     gravity that its importance demands, and ar<lb break="no"/>rive at a consummation that will be accepta<lb break="no"/>ble to the great body of the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANNA1">Mr. ANNAND</persName>—After the very remarkable 
     <lb/>
     address delivered by the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Richmond, I think it right at once to declare 
     <lb/>
     openly that the question asked by the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman has taken this side of the House by sur<lb break="no"/>prise. When he comes to us and propounds a 
     <lb/>
     delegation to the Colonial office—invites the 
     <lb/>
     interposition of the Colonial Government to 
     <lb/>
     settle a question involving the rights and liber<lb break="no"/>ties of this people—asks the Home Government 
     <lb/>
     to arrange the question without reference to the 
     <lb/>
     people, I look at this hon. member with sur<lb break="no"/>prise, and recall the sentiments that he uttered 
     <lb/>
     on former occasions. I feel strongly on this 
     <lb/>
     subject. It is an attempt to barter away, to 
     <lb/>
     sell the rights and liberties of the people. I do 
     <lb/>
     not know the influences that are at work, but 
     <lb/>
     I can imagine them. I never expected to live 
     <lb/>
     to see the time when, on the floors of this Par<lb break="no"/>liament, a gentleman could arise and ask that 
     <lb/>
     our condition should be decided—where? not 
     <lb/>
     in your own Parliament, but by gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     sent across the water with <hi rendition="simple:italic">carte blanche</hi> to set<lb break="no"/>tle the whole matter. The hon. member says 
     <lb/>
     he is in favor of the abstract principle of 
     <lb/>
     Union. I may or may not be in favor of it, but 
     <lb/>
     I cannot be a party to send the question for a 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="191" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_191.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY</fw>
            <fw type="num">191</fw>
            
     final decision to the Colonial office. We know 
     <lb/>
     that the Canadian element is predominant 
     <lb/>
     there, and these Maritime Provinces, however 
     <lb/>
     largely represented, would have little influ<lb break="no"/>ence. The scheme that would come back would 
     <lb/>
     be substantially that of Quebec. I could have 
     <lb/>
     understood the hon. member had he proposed 
     <lb/>
     —and the proposal may be in harmony with 
     <lb/>
     my own views—a Convention of all the Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, called with the sanction of the Crown, 
     <lb/>
     in British North America. Such a Convention 
     <lb/>
     would consider the whole question, and come 
     <lb/>
     to an agreement, which could then be submitted 
     <lb/>
     to the people. If he had proposed some such 
     <lb/>
     scheme as that, I could have understood the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member; but to take the whole question 
     <lb/>
     from this House is what can never be agreed 
     <lb/>
     to by the people. I do not misinterpret the 
     <lb/>
     feeling of this country when I say that there is 
     <lb/>
     a universal feeling against any union with 
     <lb/>
     Canada. I do not say that this feeling is wise, 
     <lb/>
     —there may be a good deal of prejudice mixed 
     <lb/>
     up with it; but to follow the course proposed 
     <lb/>
     would be to destroy all hopes of unity. I am 
     <lb/>
     surprised at the motion of the hon. member, 
     <lb/>
     but I apprehend the result. The Government 
     <lb/>
     are only too glad to see a way of getting out 
     <lb/>
     of their present difficulties. However, I know 
     <lb/>
     if there is a lack of patriotism and intelligence 
     <lb/>
     in this House, it is not the case elsewhere. 
     <lb/>
     Feeling that, I do not hesitate to say this: A 
     <lb/>
     Union of these Provinces, consummated in this 
     <lb/>
     way, contrary to the wishes of the people, will 
     <lb/>
     not be worth the paper upon which it is re<lb break="no"/>corded. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDONNELL</persName> said,—I would not, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, undertake the task of addressing the 
     <lb/>
     House upon this occasion and without more 
     <lb/>
     preparation upon so important a subject, were 
     <lb/>
     it not for the sentiments which have just fallen 
     <lb/>
     from the Hon. Prov. Secretary. Neither do 
     <lb/>
     I do so without a full conviction of the respon<lb break="no"/>sibility I assume in the course I intend to pur<lb break="no"/>sue. I felt happy, Sir, to observe the position 
     <lb/>
     taken by the hon. leader of the Government, 
     <lb/>
     and I trust that this position will be approved 
     <lb/>
     of and endorsed by his hon. colleagues, and by 
     <lb/>
     those associated with him at the Quebec con<lb break="no"/>ference. The hon. gentleman has at length 
     <lb/>
     shown a disposition to abandon that pet 
     <lb/>
     scheme of Union, which, for such a length of 
     <lb/>
     time he and his friends appeared determined 
     <lb/>
     to fasten upon the people,—a scheme, in my 
     <lb/>
     opinion, as obnoxious and distasteful to the 
     <lb/>
     country, as it would prove injurious to its best 
     <lb/>
     interests. I rejoice to find the spirit in which 
     <lb/>
     the enquiry of the hon. member for Richmond 
     <lb/>
     has been met, and I feel I would be wanting 
     <lb/>
     in the performance of duty, if I did not avail 
     <lb/>
     myself of this, the first opportunity of ex<lb break="no"/>pressing my satisfaction. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The question before us, I need not say, is one 
     <lb/>
     which demands mature and deliberate 
     <lb/>
     consideration, and should not be deter<lb break="no"/>mined in a day; but it is now before this 
     <lb/>
     house for the second time, and since it 
     <lb/>
     was first brought under our considera<lb break="no"/>tion it has engaged the attention of our 
     <lb/>
     press, wherein it has been canvassed in all 
     <lb/>
     its features. It has been debated at length 
     <lb/>
     in this Legislature and on the public platform. 
     <lb/>
     And it has brought our ablest an leading 
     <lb/>
     minds into desirable contact in its discussion.. 
     <lb/>Taking the results of its agitation in these dif<lb break="no"/>ferent arenas together, with a glance at the 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     events which have transpired within the last 
     <lb/>
     year, and which are daily being enacted under 
     <lb/>
     our view, there is but one conclusion that can 
     <lb/>
     he arrived at by every honest man—by the ad<lb break="no"/>mirer of British institutions, and that is, that 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Union we must have</hi>. This is a fact which is 
     <lb/>
     admitted almost on every hand—by the oppo<lb break="no"/>nents of the Quebec scheme as well as its sup<lb break="no"/>porters. I was indeed surprised when I saw 
     <lb/>
     the course taken by the hon. member for East 
     <lb/>
     Halifax, who has just set down. When I saw 
     <lb/>
     that hon. gentleman rise to address the house, 
     <lb/>
     I expected it was to approve of the proposition 
     <lb/>
     made by the hon. member for Richmond, and 
     <lb/>
     which was so satisfactorily met by the leader 
     <lb/>
     of the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     How could I expect differently, when I read 
     <lb/>
     the paper which I hold in my hand? Can that 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman pretend to deceive this House 
     <lb/>
     as to his own opinion on the subject? How 
     <lb/>
     dare he say that he "will not inform the House 
     <lb/>
     whether he is for Union in the abstract or not? 
     <lb/>
     He must first deny his connection with one of 
     <lb/>
     the leading organs of opposition to the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     scheme, before he can ask this house to enter<lb break="no"/>tain a doubt as to his real position. Let me 
     <lb/>
     read an extract from the editorial column of 
     <lb/>
     the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Morning Chronicle</hi> of the 24th of January 
     <lb/>
     last, of which that gentleman is Editor: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "And what then? Are we indifferent to the fu<lb break="no"/>ture of British America? Have we arrived at the 
     <lb/>
     conclusion that nothing should be done?—that we 
     <lb/>
     can remain forever in our present condition? On the 
     <lb/>
     contrary, while we claim that these Colonies—at all 
     <lb/>
     events the Maritime Provinces—never can be bet<lb break="no"/>tered by any change in their political situation, we 
     <lb/>
     feel that they cannot, in the very nature of things, 
     <lb/>
     always continue as they are. They may, it is true, 
     <lb/>
     go on for years and enjoy their present prosperity, but 
     <lb/>
     after all the time must come when they will be required 
     <lb/>
     to form new relations, whether with each other and 
     <lb/>
     the mother country will largely depend upon the ex<lb break="no"/>ercise of great tact, wisdom, and forethought on the 
     <lb/>
     part both of British and Colonial statesmen." 
    
            </p> 

            <p>
   "But it is because we feel that we must sooner or 
     <lb/>
     later make our choice between the mother country 
     <lb/>
     and the United States, that we desire to see this 
     <lb/>
     question of Colonial Union, now that it is fresh in 
     <lb/>
     the minds of the people, set at rest." 
     
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     This journal then, sir, the leading one of this 
     <lb/>
     Province in opposition to the Quebec scheme 
     <lb/>
     —the organ of the hon leader of anti-Confede<lb break="no"/>ration in this country—is, as you see, not only 
     <lb/>
     a strong advocate of union, but urges that the 
     <lb/>
     question be immediately, while fresh on the 
     <lb/>
     minds of the people, set at rest, and recom<lb break="no"/>mends the means for doing so. If, then, these 
     <lb/>
     are the sentiments and opinions of the great 
     <lb/>
     leader of anti-Confederation, are we not to as<lb break="no"/>sume, that his followers entertain the 
     <lb/>
     same opinion, but like their leader, have an 
     <lb/>
     object - yes, too apparent an object in offering 
     <lb/>
     a factious opposition. The union of these 
     <lb/>
     Provinces is desired because it is a necessity. 
     <lb/>
     Considering the present happy, peaceful and 
     <lb/>
     prosperous state of this Province I should feel 
     <lb/>
     happy indeed did this necessity not exist; but 
     <lb/>
     while circumstances do exist which to every 
     <lb/>
     sensible man leaves no room to deny this ne<lb break="no"/>cessity, we in the position of the representa<lb break="no"/>tives of the people, holding the destiny of our 
     <lb/>
     common country in our hands, are bound by 
     <lb/>
     the highest duty we owe to the people of this 
     <lb/>
     Province to set this question at rest immedi<lb break="no"/>ately, to use the words of the great leader of 
     <lb/>
     the anti-Confederate party. These circum<lb break="no"/>stances are to well known to every gentleman 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="192" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_192.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">192</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES AND PROCEEDINGS</fw>
            
               
     in this house, and many of them have been too 
     <lb/>
     eloquently descanted upon by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Richmond to require that I 
     <lb/>
     should refer to them at length. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whatever my opinions on this great subject 
     <lb/>
     were a year ago, occurrences transpiring in 
     <lb/>
     the interim, and events which mark the pres<lb break="no"/>ent as a time for action rather than words to be 
     <lb/>
     our duty, leave no room for doubt in my mind 
     <lb/>
     as to what this House owe to the country.—The 
     <lb/>
     repeal of the Reciprocity Treaty is no longer a 
     <lb/>
     matter of doubt, as it was when we last sat here. 
     <lb/>
     The cause of its repeal is ominous of a state 
     <lb/>
     of things and of a feeling which should make 
     <lb/>
     us active for Union. It was not for advantage 
     <lb/>
     to themselves, because there was none, that 
     <lb/>
     the United States determined this treaty; but, 
     <lb/>
     as is well known, to evince the hostility that 
     <lb/>
     the great majority of the people of that coun<lb break="no"/>try entertain toward us as British subjects, 
     <lb/>
     and to injure and embarrass us in the chan<lb break="no"/>nels of our trade. The position of these Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces could not but be regarded as humiliat<lb break="no"/>ing, when obliged to send delegates, in detach<lb break="no"/>ed parties to Washington, to beseech the con<lb break="no"/>tinuance of that treaty. Severed, we are obli<lb break="no"/>ged to apply to foreign and hostile countries 
     <lb/>
     for leave to trade and interchange articles of 
     <lb/>
     commerce with them, while if united as propo<lb break="no"/>sed, we could cultivate and have within our<lb break="no"/>selves all these resources. Since we last met 
     <lb/>
     here, the British Government have declared 
     <lb/>
     and given most unequivocally to us their policy 
     <lb/>
     and advice on this subject. In the despatch 
     <lb/>
     from the Colonial Secretary of the 24th June 
     <lb/>
     last, we find the following expression of that 
     <lb/>
     policy: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "You will at the same time express the strong and 
     <lb/>
     deliberate opinion of Her Majesty's Government that 
     <lb/>
     it is an object much to be desired that all the British 
     <lb/>
     North American Colonies should agree to unite in 
     <lb/>
     one Government. In the territorial extent of Cana<lb break="no"/>da, and in the maritime and commercial enterprise of 
     <lb/>
     the Lower Provinces, Her Majesty's Government see 
     <lb/>
     the elements of power. which only require to be com<lb break="no"/>bined in order to secure for these provinces, which 
     <lb/>
     shall possess them all, a place among the most consi<lb break="no"/>derable communities of the world. In the spirit of 
     <lb/>
     loyalty to the British Crown, of attachment to Brit<lb break="no"/>ish connection, and of love for British institutions, by 
     <lb/>
     which all these Provinces are animated alike, Her 
     <lb/>
     Majesty's Government recognize the bond by which 
     <lb/>
     all may be combined under one Government. Such 
     <lb/>
     an union seems to Her Majesty's Government to com<lb break="no"/>mend itself to the Provinces on many grounds of 
     <lb/>
     moral and material advantages,—as giving a pros<lb break="no"/>pect of improved administration and increased pros<lb break="no"/>perity. "<lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     
     Again in a despatch from Mr. Cardwell of 
     <lb/>
     26th Sep., <choice><sic>1855</sic><corr>1865</corr></choice><!-- this speech from Mr. Cardwell does appear to be from 1865 - reported in the New York Times - LANG4 -->, relating to the appointment of 
     <lb/>
     our present Lieutenant Governor, and in the 
     <lb/>
     appointment of this distinguished officer we 
     <lb/>
     observe in the choice made, which affords all 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotians connected with that appoint<lb break="no"/>ment just pride, and in other circum<lb break="no"/>stances the desire of the Home Government 
     <lb/>
     for this Union, spoken in a most significant 
     <lb/>
     manner. In this despatch I find the following: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     But as he, (Sir R.MacDonnell,) has been appointed 
     <lb/>
     to Hong Kong, expressly on the ground that the <hi rendition="simple:italic">de<lb break="no"/>clared policy</hi> of Her Majesty's Government will, if 
     <lb/>
     successful, lead to the abolition of the office of Lieu<lb break="no"/>tenant Governor of Nova Scotia, it would be evi<lb break="no"/>dently inconsistent with that policy to appoint in his 
     <lb/>
     place another Lieutenant Governor in the ordinary 
     <lb/>
     way. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Here we have the policy of the British Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment plainly declared. There may be gen<lb break="no"/>
            
            <cb/>
            
     tlemen in this house, desirous of frustrating 
     <lb/>
     that policy, but I will not be found among 
     <lb/>
     them. I consider it our bounder duty to aqui<lb break="no"/>esce in the wishes of those to whom we look 
     <lb/>
     for protection, who, during the past year, has 
     <lb/>
     expended in our defence an amount not ex<lb break="no"/>ceeded by our entire revenue. The Quebec 
     <lb/>
     scheme being to a certain extent abandoned, 
     <lb/>
     the only question remaining is, to what tri<lb break="no"/>bunal can we appeal for a settlement of the 
     <lb/>
     terms of Union? I think that the proposal 
     <lb/>
     made by the hon. member for Richmond to 
     <lb/>
     refer the question to the arbitrament of the 
     <lb/>
     Colonial office or of some other tribunal in the 
     <lb/>
     mother country would afford us a guarantee 
     <lb/>
     of our rights, and this proposition emanating 
     <lb/>
     from us must entitle us to peculiar consider<lb break="no"/>ation by any such tribunal. I did not rise to 
     <lb/>
     address the house at any length, but I desired 
     <lb/>
     to take the first opportunity of expressing 
     <lb/>
     these views. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I trust gentlemen will not hesitate to admit it 
     <lb/>
     if they experience a change of opinion on this 
     <lb/>
     great question. Besides the events which have 
     <lb/>
     occurred within the last twelve-month, the 
     <lb/>
     question being of itself of such magnitude, and 
     <lb/>
     contemplating changes so great in our situation 
     <lb/>
     and constitution, is one which would naturally 
     <lb/>
     be looked upon with caution at first, and it is 
     <lb/>
     not inconsistent that these gentlemen should, 
     <lb/>
     after due examination, if it be found to alter 
     <lb/>
     their views act on this convictions. In this 
     <lb/>
     connection, I may read the following from Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Cardwell's despatch, already referred to: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "I am aware that this project, so novel as well as 
     <lb/>
     so important, has not been at once accepted in Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia with that cordiality which has marked its ac<lb break="no"/>ceptance by the Legislature of Canada; but Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's Government trust, that after a full and care<lb break="no"/>ful examination of the subject in all its bearings, the 
     <lb/>Maritime Provinces will perceive the great advanta<lb break="no"/>ges which, in the opinion of Her Majesty's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, the proposed union is calculated to confer up<lb break="no"/>on them all " 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     I feel it to my duty to support <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>     
     <lb/>
     for such a union of these Provinces as will be 
     <lb/>
     found to be based on principles of equity and 
     <lb/>
     justice. I care not how much my personal po<lb break="no"/>sition may suffer in taking this stand, this is 
     <lb/>
     the duty I owe to the country; and every 
     <lb/>
     member who regards the events which are 
     <lb/>
     transpiring among us should seize the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity offered if the proposition made be ac<lb break="no"/>cepted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP1">Mr S. CAMPBELL</persName>—If a gentleman, speaking 
     <lb/>
     with his brief before him, feels inadequate to 
     <lb/>
     the occasion, I, coming here unprepared for the 
     <lb/>
     debate, must have some excuse for the crude<lb break="no"/>ness of my observations. This question is one 
     <lb/>
     of the deepest moment to the people of this 
     <lb/>
     country and to this legislature, and I would 
     <lb/>
     not be worthy of a seat within these walls if I 
     <lb/>
     were not prepared on the instant to express 
     <lb/>
     my sentiments upon a matter so pregnant with 
     <lb/>
     weal or woe to the province. I listened with 
     <lb/>
     interest and pleasure to the hon member for 
     <lb/>
     Richmond, because I felt that he was sincere 
     <lb/>
     in his observations,—I will not attribute any 
     <lb/>
     unworthy motives for the course which he has 
     <lb/>
     taken, but notwithstanding that I give him 
     <lb/>
     credit for candor and sincerity, I am not pre<lb break="no"/>pared to acquiesce in the result at which he 
     <lb/>
     has arrived until the people express themselves 
     <lb/>
     in a different tone and manner from those in 
     <lb/>
     which they have been expressing themselves 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="193" facs="final/images/NS_LA_1866-04-03_Page_193.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="num">193</fw>
           
     for two or three years past. I do not believe 
     <lb/>
     that they desire a change in the constitution, 
     <lb/>
     or that they are willing to have their rights 
     <lb/>
     transferred to any quarter. We have had dur<lb break="no"/>ing the present session, petitions from every 
     <lb/>
     part of the province, praying that the house 
     <lb/>
     will not sanction a scheme of union without a 
     <lb/>
     reference to the people at the polls—that tribu<lb break="no"/>nal alone having the power to change our con<lb break="no"/>stitution, and the hon. member who has ad<lb break="no"/>dressed the house himself presented petitions 
     <lb/>
     to that effect within a few hours. Such peti<lb break="no"/>tions have come from my constituents and I 
     <lb/>
     will not be a traitor to their rights and feelings 
     <lb/>
     by consenting to such a change as is proposed. 
     <lb/>
     I consider that there is another difficulty in this 
     <lb/>
     case: the Quebec scheme was entered into by 
     <lb/>
     several parties. they all concurred in its ratifi<lb break="no"/>cation, and must all be applied to in its abro<lb break="no"/>gation. It is not in the power of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment to say yes or no to the demand which has 
     <lb/>
     been made,—they may express their individu<lb break="no"/>al views but it is not in their power to cancel 
     <lb/>
     and destroy that scheme. I feel that no action 
     <lb/>
     should be taken on this question until the 
     <lb/>
     people have passed upon it and until then I 
     <lb/>
     will not go even with the proposition made by 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Richmond. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL3">Mr. MILLER</persName>:——The hon. member for Halifax 
     <lb/>
     in the course of his speech threw out some 
     <lb/>
     insinuations which I can safely regard with 
     <lb/>
     contempt. There is not a man in the House 
     <lb/>
     from whom I should be more willing to 
     <lb/>
     receive such insinuations. He says I am 
     <lb/>
     acting inconsistently in attempting now to 
     <lb/>
     pass a scheme of union without an appeal to 
     <lb/>
     the people,-—I omitted accidentally to refer to 
     <lb/>
     that subject in course of my remarks, when I 
     <lb/>
     explain my position in that respect my reasons 
     <lb/>
     will I think be satisfactory to the country, but 
     <lb/>
     it is not under the influence of such inuendoes 
     <lb/>
     and taunts as have been thrown out by that 
     <lb/>
     hon. member that I will he induced to express 
     <lb/>
     my views—that is a matter of courtesy and 
     <lb/>
     he has placed himself beyond the bounds of 
     <lb/>
     courtesy by the remarks which he has made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName>:—I trust we will not ap<lb break="no"/>proach a question of so grave a character with 
     <lb/>
     any exhibition of temper, and while I am not 
     <lb/>
     surprised at the feelings of the gentleman who 
     <lb/>
     has just spoken, I depecrate such expressions 
     <lb/>
     upon this occasion. I will say in reference to 
     <lb/>
     some observations that have been made, that 
     <lb/>
     it is going too far to speak of the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     scheme being abandoned. I was not surprised 
     <lb/>
     when the Prov. Sec. rose and stated that he 
     <lb/>
     was not in a position to give an answer to the 
     <lb/>
     question because he can hardly be said to 
     <lb/>
     represent even Nova Scotia, for he was but 
     <lb/>
     one of those who represented this Province.— 
     <lb/>
     It is not very agreeable to gentlemen interest<lb break="no"/>ed in the Quebec scheme to hear the 
     <lb/>
     allusions that have been made; I am 
     <lb/>
     prepared to advocate that scheme as con<lb break="no"/>ferring upon these Provinces everything that 
     <lb/>
     they should ask. At the same time, no 
     <lb/>
     one would be more pleased than I if further 
     <lb/>
     concessions could he obtained; but any such 
     <lb/>
     concession must be obtained at the expense of 
     <lb/>
     some other Province. I agree with the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Richmond that no new scheme 
     <lb/>
     would place us in a worse position. The reti<lb break="no"/>cence with which the Prov. Sec. approached 
     <lb/>
     the question was due to the gentlemen, in this 
     <lb/>
                
            <cb/>
           
     country and beyond, who were connected with 
     <lb/>
     the formation of the present scheme of union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TOBI2">Mr. TOBIN</persName>: I was greatly astonished on 
     <lb/>
     coming into the House to hear the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Richmond addressing the House on this 
     <lb/>
     subject. I would not do anything distasteful 
     <lb/>
     to the great body of the people; and until pro<lb break="no"/>per consultation is had, I think the discussion 
     <lb/>
     out of place. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LOCK1">Mr. LOCKE</persName>: We sometimes read of villages 
     <lb/>
     while in a state of apparent security, being 
     <lb/>
     overturned and overwhelmed by an avalanche. 
     <lb/>
     But the surprise of persons in that situation 
     <lb/>
     could not be greater than that of some gentle<lb break="no"/>men with whom I sit at what has occurred. It 
     <lb/>
     was astonishing to hear the remarks of the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Richmond, who, though he 
     <lb/>
     always favored a union of some sort, was an 
     <lb/>
     uncompromising opponent of the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     scheme; but how much more so to hear the ex<lb break="no"/>pressions of the hon. member for Inverness, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. McDonnell, who was an uncompromising 
     <lb/>
     opponent of any species of union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The discussion then ceased. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">           
            <head rendition="simple:centre">PETITIONS.</head>

            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> presented peti<lb break="no"/>tions signed by the representatives of three 
     <lb/>
     mining Companies in reference to the exten<lb break="no"/>sion of mining leases. They were referred to 
     <lb/>
     the Committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSS10">Mr. ROSS</persName> presented a petition signed by 49 
     <lb/>inhabitants of Victoria County against Con<lb break="no"/>federation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
           
            <p>
     Also a petition of 41 inhabitants of Baddeck 
     <lb/>
     on the same subject. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Also another petition, on the same subject, to 
     <lb/>
     which he said considerable importance should 
     <lb/>
     be attached. as it was signed by the Custos and 
     <lb/>
     all the magistrates, of every political party, 
     <lb/>
     who attended the last Sessions of Victoria 
     <lb/>
     County. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr ANNAND presented two petitions from 
     <lb/>
     Inverness against Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">           
               <head rendition="simple:centre">MILITIA UNIFORMS.</head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. ATT'Y GEN</persName>. laid on the table corres<lb break="no"/>pondence relating to uniforms for the Militia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. PROV. SEC</persName>. said that no doubt great in<lb break="no"/>convenience was caused by drawing 50,000 of 
     <lb/>
     the inhabitants of the Province annually for 
     <lb/>
     five days from their ordinary pursuits, but it 
     <lb/>
     was necessary for placing the country in a pro<lb break="no"/>per attitude of defence. Nothing would more 
     <lb/>
     fully tend to impart a martial spirit to our local 
     <lb/>
     forces than a uniform of some description. He 
     <lb/>
     trusted that some means could be devised by 
     <lb/>
     the committee, for providing a cheap uniform 
     <lb/>
     for the Militia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The papers were referred to the Militia Com<lb break="no"/>mittee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">           
               <head rendition="simple:centre">MISCELLANEOUS.</head>
               
               <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> introduced a bill to amend 
     <lb/>
     the law relating to County Assessments. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> suggested in 
     <lb/>
     view of the importance of the subject, that the 
     <lb/>
     bill be referred to a select Committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> consented to do so, and the 
     <lb/>
    bill was read a second time.   
     <lb/>
            </p> 

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SHAN2">Mr. SHANNON</persName> presented a petition from the 
     <lb/>
     Grand Division of the Sons of Temperance in 
     <lb/>
     favour of the establishment of an Asylum for 
     <lb/>
     Inebriates, and urged the desirability of favor<lb break="no"/>ably considering the prayer thereof. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAC7">Mr. BLACKWOOD</persName> presented a petition from 
     <lb/>
     D. Fraser and 500 others, of Tatamagouche, in [...]
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
         </div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>