<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1890-02-21" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1890-02-21">21 February 1890</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
<date when="1890"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="963" to="1018"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00963.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00965.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00967.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00969.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00971.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00973.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00975.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00977.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00979.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00981.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00983.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00985.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00987.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00989.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00991.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00993.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00995.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00997.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00999.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01001.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01003.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01005.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01007.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01009.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01011.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01013.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01015.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01017.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-28">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-28">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00963"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00963.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00965"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00965.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00967"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00967.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00969"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00969.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00971"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00971.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00973"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00973.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00975"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00975.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00977"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00977.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00979"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00979.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00981"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00981.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00983"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00983.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00985"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00985.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00987"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00987.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00989"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00989.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00991"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00991.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00993"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00993.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00995"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00995.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00997"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00997.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00999"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00999.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01001"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01001.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01003"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01003.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01005"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01005.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01007"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01007.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01009"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01009.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01011"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01011.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01013"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01013.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01015"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01015.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01017"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01017.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="963" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00963.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">963</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">964</fw> 

    <!-- IC, 2018-09-28, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
<!--<p>have every reason to hope that we shall close the <lb/>
debate to-morrow, and I will do my very best to <lb/>
bring it to a close then. <lb/></p> 

<p>Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD. Under these <lb/>
circumstances, I will not oppose the motion of my <lb/>
hon. friend for the adjournment of the debate, and <lb/>
I will move that it be made the first Order of the <lb/>
day to-morrow. <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed to, and debate adjourned. <lb/></p> 

<p>Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD moved the ad<lb break="no"/>journment of the House. <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed to; and Hous eadjourned at 1 <lb/>
a. m. (Friday). <lb/></p> -->

<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</head>

<head rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, 21st February, 1890.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> took the Chair at Three o'clock. <lb/></p> 

<p><emph>PRAYERS.</emph> <lb/></p> 
</div>
<div type="debate">
    
<head rendition="simple:centre">FIRST READING.</head>

<p>Bill (No. 95) respecting Agricultural Fertilisers <lb/>
(from the Senate)—(Sir John A. Macdonald.) <lb/></p> 
</div>
<div type="debate">
<head rendition="simple:centre">THE FRENCH LANGUAGE IN THE NORTH-<lb break="yes"/>WEST.</head> 

<p>House resumed adjourned debate on the pro<lb break="no"/>posed motion of Mr. McCarthy for second reading <lb/>
of Bill (No. 10) to further amend the Revised <lb/>
Statutes of Canada, chapter 50, respecting the <lb/>
North-West Territories; the motion of Mr. Davin <lb/>
in amendment thereto, and the motion of Sir <lb/>
John Thompson in amendment to the amendment. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. Owing to the fact that this <lb/>
House consented, on my motion last night, to ad<lb break="no"/>journ the debate, and owing also to the fact that a <lb/>
great many members desire to leave to-night, I <lb/>
will shorten my remarks as much as possible. <lb/>
Before entering into the merits of the amendment, <lb/>
which we have to discuss and upon which we are <lb/>
called upon to vote, I will say a few words in <lb/>
answer to the speech of the hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy). That hon. gentleman per<lb break="no"/>sists in saying that the treaties never insured to the <lb/>
French Canadians, or to those speaking the French <lb/>
language in this country, the use of that language. <lb/>
He has repeatedly said that the language is the <lb/>
essence of a people's existence, so it must be the <lb/>
first privilege of a people. I will call the attention <lb/>
of the hon. gentleman to the Articles of Capitula<lb break="no"/>tion of Quebec, dated 18th September, 1759, where <lb/>
we find the following as having been demanded <lb/>
and granted:-— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"That the inhabitants shall be preserved in the posses<lb break="no"/>sion of their houses, goods, effects and privileges—" <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>The word "privileges" is there. What privilege <lb/>
is greater than the language of the people? <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>—"granted upon their laying down their arms." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>They laid down their arms, to take them up again <lb/>
for the defence of the British flag. They knew <lb/>
only one language then, but, with their old gun <lb/>
and their old French language, they succeeded in <lb/>
the better preservation and due distribution of the <lb/>
keeping this country in the possession of the <lb/>
British Crown. Now, if the hon. gentleman looks <lb/>

<cb/>

at the capitulation of Montreal, signed in French <lb/>
and English, he will find that it is stipulated that <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The French Canadians shall continue, as subjects <lb/>
of the King, to be governed according to the custom of <lb/>
Paris, and the laws and usages established for this <lb/>
country." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
<p>If that does not include in the first place the lan<lb break="no"/>guage, I do not know what it includes. Then I <lb/>
will refer the hon. gentleman to the Treaty of <lb/>
Paris, which was written only in French. It was <lb/>
signed on the 10th February, 1763. I have had the <lb/>
first article translated, because we do not find it in <lb/>
English. This is what it says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"There will be an universal, and perpetual, Christian-<lb break="yes"/>like peace, as well over land as over sea, and a sincere <lb/>
and immovable friendship will be established between <lb/>
their Britannic Majesties * * * and between their heirs <lb/>
and Successors, Kingdoms, States, provinces, countries, <lb/>
subjects and vassals of whatsoever kind and condition they <lb/>
may be, making no exception for rank or fortune; so that <lb/>
the High Contracting parties will bestow the very greatest <lb/>
attention upon the maintenance between themselves and <lb/>
said States and subjects of this friendship and intercourse, <lb/>
without permitting from henceforth, on one side or the <lb/>
other, the commission of any acts of hostility, either by <lb/>
land or sea, on any pretext whatever; and they will care<lb break="no"/>fully avoid all that which might tend to impair for the <lb/>
future the union so happily established: endeavoring, on <lb/>
the contrary, to secure for each other in turn on all occa<lb break="no"/>sions, all which may contribute to their mutual glory, in<lb break="no"/>terests and advantages. * * * There will be a general <lb/>
forgetfulness of all that may have been done or com<lb break="no"/>mitted before or since the beginning of the war now put <lb/>
an end to." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>You must not lose sight of the events of that time. <lb/>
There had been a fight; both armies had behaved <lb/>
most gloriously; we had about 12,000 men against <lb/>
60,000 on the other side, and sometimes the fortune <lb/>
was for us and sometimes against us. The last <lb/>
battle, which was fought on the field of St. Foye, <lb/>
was in favor of our arms. But then the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor de Vaudreuil, one of the most miserable crea<lb break="no"/>tures that ever came to this country, gave us up. <lb/>
After that our troops went to Montreal; our brave <lb/>
generals were discouraged at seeing such cowardice <lb/>
and such treason on the part of the Governor. But <lb/>
the Governor went up to Montreal and there <lb/>
again capitulated. Then our troops went back <lb/>
to France, and afterwards there was signed in <lb/>
France, a treaty between England, France and <lb/>
Portugal, which was a treaty of peace. The <lb/>
different countries that had been the subject of <lb/>
dispute were divided between these kingdoms, <lb/>
and it was a cession of peace and nothing else. <lb/>
That is the reason why, the other day, when the <lb/>
hon. gentleman spoke of the conquest, I said it <lb/>
was a cession, and not a conquest. I will now <lb/>
draw the special attention of the hon. member to <lb/>
chapter 18 of 14 George III, 1774, which is "An <lb/>
Act to make more effectual provisions for the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the Province of Quebec in North <lb/>
America." The preamble says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Whereas His Majesty, by His Royal proclamation <lb/>
hearing date 7th October in the third year of his reign, <lb/>
thought fit to declare the provisions which had been made <lb/>
in respect to certain countries, territories and isles in <lb/>
America, ceded to His Majesty by the Definitive Treaty <lb/>
of Peace concluded on the 10th of February, 1773." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>I will not take up the time of the House in read<lb break="no"/>ing the Act; but I will quote, for the satisfaction <lb/>
of the hon. member for North Simcoe, sections 4 <lb/>
and 8 of that statute. In those times the use of <lb/>
the French language was looked upon as so im<lb break="no"/>portant that in 1790 an ordinance was passed "for <lb/>
the better preservation and due distribution of the <lb/>
ancient French records." In the face of that I <lb/>

<pb n="965" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00965.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">965</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">966</fw>

wonder how the hon. member can pretend that the <lb/>
use of the French language is not fully recognised <lb/>
by the treaties and the ancient laws. I will not <lb/>
take up the time of the House in reading any of <lb/>
these statutes, but I will remark that the British <lb/>
North America Act virtually makes the English <lb/>
and French languages official in this country. <lb/>
Then we have the Act which erects the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories and which establishes the use of <lb/>
the French language. Now, my hon. friend says <lb/>
that the perpetuation of a race is only possible by <lb/>
means of one language. I admit that there is a <lb/>
great deal in that, though I will not admit it fully. <lb/>
But in his mind thelanguage is the essence of a nation. <lb/>
The second proposal is this: "We have the right <lb/>
to destroy you French, and we will do it." Well, I <lb/>
wonder where he gets that right. Is it in Divine <lb/>
    law, or human law, or in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">jus gentium?</hi> Per<lb break="no"/>haps he gets it out of some wicked hearts, as I do <lb/>
not know where else he could get it. I do not find <lb/>
any source or trace for such a right. He says: <lb/>
"Why do you get excited when I say that? I am <lb/>
calm," he says, "I am moderate, but you get ex<lb break="no"/>cited." Mr. Speaker, a big man may come to you <lb/>
and calmly say, "Please give me your money." <lb/>
He may take a man by the throat and say, "Keep <lb/>
quiet and I will choke you;" and he will be calm, <lb/>
but he will not be just or right. It is perfectly <lb/>
astounding to hear the representatives of three or <lb/>
four millions say to the representatives of one <lb/>
million and a half, "We are going to make you <lb/>
disappear, we are calm, be calm." Well, a man <lb/>
who makes such proposals deserves simply to <lb/>
he laughed at, and that is the only answer I will <lb/>
give the hon. member on that point. Now, he <lb/>
says that we only want one language. Why? Is <lb/>
it for the good of the country? I presume <lb/>
that when there are two or three, or four races <lb/>
in a country, it stimulates them to good objects. <lb/>
Every one wants to do as well or better than <lb/>
his neighbor, and it is for the good of the <lb/>
nation. Is it for the peace of the country? Sir, <lb/>
we have had the two languages here since 1760, <lb/>
and have we had any trouble, have we had any <lb/>
fighting? In the United States they have only one <lb/>
language, it is true, but within a century they have <lb/>
had a war that cost more lives and more money <lb/>
than any other war the world has seen during the <lb/>
last 400 years. I do not see that any good reason <lb/>
has been given for the use of one language only. <lb/>
At all events, if it is necessary, it is now too late <lb/>
to say so. Confederation has gone into effect, and <lb/>
if one language only was necessary we should have <lb/>
been warned of it before we entered Confederation. <lb/>
It is too late now to tell us that we want only one <lb/>
language, one nation. If we want to change the <lb/>
terms and condition of the charter, we shall have <lb/>
to begin over again. If we are not willing to stand <lb/>
by the treaty that has been made, if we desire to <lb/>
change the conditions, then we shall have to begin <lb/>
at the beginning; because in law the consent of <lb/>
the parties is given upon certain facts, and when <lb/>
those facts are erroneous the convention is null and <lb/>
vonl. My hon. friend is too good a lawyer not to <lb/>
know that. Every time the hon. gentleman has a <lb/>
chance he brings up the Riel affair. I wish the <lb/>
hon. gentleman was in his seat; at all events, I will <lb/>
say what I intended, and he will be able to read <lb/>
    it in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Hansard</hi>. What is the Riel affair? He <lb/>
does not seem to have understood it since it occur<lb break="no"/>red, although it is a very simple matter. I shall <lb/>

<cb/>

not undertake to discuss the merits of that affair, <lb/>
but I want to state how, as a matter of fact, it <lb/>
occurred, and how it presented itself to the coun<lb break="no"/>try. Riel had had his trial and had been recom<lb break="no"/>mended to mercy. For my part, I had always <lb/>
looked upon Riel as having been a madman, <lb/>
working for a noble cause, if you will, but still <lb/>
a madman, who, when he spoke of religion or <lb/>
politics, became perfectly insane, so much so that <lb/>
he wanted to go to Rome and be made a pope. <lb/>
He wanted to rule over the whole world. After <lb/>
his condemnation and the recommendation to <lb/>
mercy, it was stated that the man was mad, and <lb/>
the Government became anxious about it, and sent <lb/>
doctors up to examine him, and we know what re<lb break="no"/>port they made. Under the circumstances, peti<lb break="no"/>tions were signed to obtain his pardon, and his <lb/>
pardon was promised us. Then, Mr. Speaker, <lb/>
there is this point to which I wish to draw the <lb/>
attention of my hon. friend: when the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was ready to grant the pardon, or to con<lb break="no"/>fine the man in an asylum for the rest of his <lb/>
days, what occurred? Petitions were presented <lb/>
signed by those whom the hon. member for <lb/>
North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) represents. The <lb/>
question then rested between those petitions <lb/>
and the promises of the Government and the <lb/>
Province of Quebec. It had been promised by <lb/>
the Ministers, that if we prayed for Riel's re<lb break="no"/>lease it would be granted. The Government pre<lb break="no"/>ferred to accede to those people who signed <lb/>
those petitions, and that was the origin of the <lb/>
trouble to-day. The Government preferred to <lb/>
grant the request of those petitioners, and we felt <lb/>
insulted. That is the whole case in a nutshell. If <lb/>
my learned friend cannot understand it, I am <lb/>
sorry; but these facts cannot be changed. Im<lb break="no"/>mediately afterwards the ministerial papers and <lb/>
many others joined hands to form a new party, <lb/>
and, as we had to give it a name, we called it the <lb/>
National party. There is no more harm in calling it <lb/>
by that name than there is in calling our fiscal <lb/>
policy the National Policy. We had a right <lb/>
to use the word National as other men in other <lb/>
countries use it. We chose that name, and since <lb/>
then that party has existed in the Province of <lb/>
Quebec. It commands a majority in the Province, <lb/>
even although my hon. friend opposite (Mr. <lb/>
McCarthy) calls it a bastard party. I do not <lb/>
know anything regarding his domestic habits; but <lb/>
I may tell him that, in our Province, if a man used <lb/>
such an expression, we would say that he had <lb/>
been very badly brought up; and if he were to say <lb/>
that in a private house, he would be put out. I <lb/>
will not give the hon. gentleman any other reply, <lb/>
except the emphatic statement that our party is <lb/>
not bastard. It has for its parents, love of country <lb/>
and self-respect; but we would prefer that it <lb/>
should be bastard rather than it should have a <lb/>
father like the hon. member for North Simcoe <lb/>
(Mr. McCarthy). It was under those circumstances <lb/>
that we broke away from our allegiance to our old <lb/>
chiefs. It pained me to leave the ranks of those <lb/>
with whom I had been fighting for twenty years; <lb/>
it was hard to give up all my old friends; <lb/>
but my conscience dictated my action, and I <lb/>
accepted the consequences. That party exists; <lb/>
and I must say to the hon. member for Iberville <lb/>
(Mr. Béchard) that, if he does not know it, he <lb/>
reminds me of the old Frenchmen who are still <lb/>
working for Napoleon I. <lb/></p>

<pb n="967" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00967.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">967</fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">968</fw> 
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BECH1">Mr. BÉCHARD</persName>. I did not say this party did <lb/>
not exist. I said it did exist; but that the old <lb/>
Liberals still existed too. <lb/></p> 

    <p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. There may be a few—there <lb/>
were not enough at all events, to get power. But <lb/>
please remember it is a political party, whatever <lb/>
there may be in a name. I trust that certain <lb/>
parties will cease presenting the position of that <lb/>
party under false colors. I presume we have <lb/>
the right to form a party, and if it should not <lb/>
please us we have the liberty to give it up and <lb/>
form another. The hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) attacked our schools; I <lb/>
wonder if the hon. gentleman has ever read any of <lb/>
the books which are given to our scholars; I <lb/>
wonder if he knows what is taught in our schools! <lb/>
He seems to ignore the fact that in the Province <lb/>
of Quebec we have Protestant schools which are <lb/>
conducted on the same lines as ours, except that <lb/>
the Protestants teach Protestant doctrines and <lb/>
the Catholics teach Catholic doctrines; but as <lb/>
regards the rest they are the same. If the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man wishes to visit our schools we will admit him with <lb/>
French politeness, with which we are trying to <lb/>
equalise British politeness; and if the hon. <lb/>
gentleman sees what is taught there, he will <lb/>
see that we teach our children to obey the <lb/>
laws of God and man, to be faithful <lb/>
to the Crown and to the laws which ensure <lb/>
the welfare of man and of a country. It is <lb/>
        a singular habit on the part of that sect—I do not <lb/>
        see there is any other name I could give it—to be <lb/>
always making an attack. We never attack. In <lb/>
the Riel matter we were on the defensive. The <lb/>
members of that sect undertake to attack our <lb/>
schools, but we never attack the schools of Ontario. <lb/>
Why do they not leave our schools alone, when we <lb/>
let their schools alone? let everybody mind his <lb/>
own business. Next, the hon. gentleman attacked <lb/>
Mr. Mercier. The politics of Mr. Mercier are dis<lb break="no"/>cussed in the Legislature three months, and every <lb/>
day of the year in the press, and some persons <lb/>
hold that he is very good, while others say that <lb/>
he is very bad. The hon, member for North Sim<lb break="no"/>coe, however, imagines that in two words he will <lb/>
condemn that hon. gentleman in the face of the <lb/>
universe. I only wish he would meet Mr. Mercier <lb/>
on the stump, and then the hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe would find that, in spite of his talents, it <lb/>
would be very hard work to convince his audience <lb/>
that Mr. Mercier is guilty of half the sins <lb/>
with which he is charged. Mr. Mercier has done <lb/>
more for the good of his country since he <lb/>
has been in power than the hon. gentleman <lb/>
will ever be able to do harm. I now come to <lb/>
the Bill which is at present under consideration <lb/>
of the House. I desire to say a word or two in <lb/>
regard to the preamble. There is a great difference <lb/>
between the preamble of this Bill as compare with <lb/>
the preamble of the Jesuit Bill. The preamble of <lb/>
the Jesuit Bill was a recital of facts and nothing <lb/>
else, and we had either to accept the Bill as a <lb/>
whole or to reject it entirely. The preamble of <lb/>
the hon. gentleman's Bill, however, is a preamble for <lb/>
which this House will be responsible, and contains <lb/>
a declaration of principle. As the Bill is unac<lb break="no"/>ceptable to the House, an amendment has been <lb/>
proposed. The hon. member for North Simcoe <lb/>
wants to take away the whole of the French <lb/>
language in the North-West; but the amendment <lb/>

<cb/>

says: no; we will take only part away. It occurs <lb/>
to me that we are legislating to take away from <lb/>
the half-breeds rights secured by statute, without <lb/>
even allowing them to be heard or without con<lb break="no"/>sulting them, and without their being represented <lb/>
in any way; and this is done at a time when no one <lb/>
expected that any such legislation would be pro<lb break="no"/>posed. The amendment seems to be unjust to the <lb/>
people of the Province of Quebec. If we diminish <lb/>
the strength of the French language in any part of <lb/>
the Confederation, we reduce the strength of the <lb/>
language as a whole. That is unjust, because <lb/>
when we entered into Confederation it was pro<lb break="no"/>mised that we would receive full justice and never <lb/>
lose any of our rights. Since that time we have <lb/>
been asked to contribute millions to open up the <lb/>
North-West and to build up magnificent railroads. <lb/>
Yet that is the way we are recompensed now. I <lb/>
think it is both unjust and unfair. I believe, further, <lb/>
that the passing of this Bill would establish a bad <lb/>
precedent, for if we once declare that we will change <lb/>
either the Imperial or Federal charters, the door <lb/>
will be opened for all kinds of trouble and confu<lb break="no"/>sion. Every year we will have petitions sent to <lb/>
England, or forwarded here, asking for repeals and <lb/>
changed, and there will never be peace in the Con<lb break="no"/>federation. We should lay down the rule that our <lb/>
constitutional charters shall never be changed ex<lb break="no"/>cept by the unanimous consent of the parties con<lb break="no"/>cerned. The first change in those charters is to do <lb/>
injustice to these four or five thousand Canadians <lb/>
of French origin who live on the prairies of the <lb/>
North-West, and who have no representative in <lb/>
this Parliament. By the Bill proposed we do not <lb/>
confer any favors on them; we take away from <lb/>
them important rights without any reason whatever. <lb/>
I warn my friends from other Provinces who are in <lb/>
favor of the Federal system, that this first change <lb/>
may lead to other changes and that the end will result <lb/>
in legislative union. There is a germ of legislative <lb/>
union in the Bill of the member for North Simcoe <lb/>
(Mr. McCarthy). It is an insult to nearly half the <lb/>
population of Canada; it contains false principles; <lb/>
and, unfortunately, the Government, to a certain ex<lb break="no"/>tent, yield to it. The Bill is unjust to the half-<lb break="yes"/>breeds, because it takes away from them vested <lb/>
rights granted to them by this Parliament in the <lb/>
Act of 1877. If you give a man a hundred dollars, <lb/>
you have no right to take twenty dollars back <lb/>
from him; and yet this is exactly the way in which <lb/>
Parliament proposes to treat the people of the <lb/>
North-West. This Bill, if adopted, would be <lb/>
unfair to the half-breeds, to whom we owe much, <lb/>
because through them we have been enabled to <lb/>
make treaties with the Indians and to enter peace<lb break="no"/>ably into the North-West. I have documents here, <lb/>
which, if I could detain the House by reading, <lb/>
would show that our possession of that territory <lb/>
is due in a great measure to the half-breeds. For all <lb/>
these benefits we have received, the recompense <lb/>
proposed by the member for North Simcoe (Mr. <lb/>
McCarthy) is that we should take away their lan<lb break="no"/>guage and their rights. For years we have ill-<lb break="yes"/>treated this people. We sent a legion of surveryours <lb/>
amongst them to change the form of their lands, <lb/>
against their wishes, and when they complained we <lb/>
laughed at them. We pushed them to rebellion. <lb/>
When they held indignation meetings to protest <lb/>
against the conduct of the Government, we <lb/>
took that for a declaration of war and we sent <lb/>
our Mounted Police to fire upon them. Then we <lb/>

<pb n="969" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00969.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">969</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">970</fw>

sent four thousand troops against them, and at a <lb/>
cost of a hundred lives and six million dollars we <lb/>
managed to destroy their property and to kill <lb/>
many of them. There were the claims of Indians <lb/>
and half-breeds. To the Indians we gave land which <lb/>
was not transferable, but to the half-breeds we <lb/>
offered land or scrip. These children of the prairie <lb/>
naturally preferred this scrip, and besides the men <lb/>
who gave the scrip were the speculators with <lb/>
money and whiskey, who cheated them out <lb/>
of their property. This I know from my own <lb/>
knowledge, because I have seen it done. I shall <lb/>
not at the present time refer to the letter of <lb/>
Monseigneur Grandin, but we all know his com<lb break="no"/>plaints. It is our duty as a nation, having some <lb/>
respect for itself, that we should cease to inflict <lb/>
evils on the people of these Territories, and that <lb/>
we should not inflict another one on them by <lb/>
depriving them of their language. In the prayer <lb/>
you have just read, Mr. Speaker, we prayed God to <lb/>
have peace and harmony, and we should remember <lb/>
that peace and harmony are as desirable for these <lb/>
poor people as for us in this House. If we want<lb/>
        to be just, if we want to be proud of being Cana<lb break="no"/>dians, we must see that this injustice shall cease. <lb/>
I do not say that it is altogether the fault of the <lb/>
Government, for probably they are not acquainted <lb/>
with the fact that this injustice is inflicted, but <lb/>
they should ascertain it, and I believe that if they <lb/>
did know the facts they would see that justice <lb/>
should be dealt out to these weak people. There <lb/>
is also another grievance to the effect that when <lb/>
the country was divided for election purposes, the <lb/>
division was such that the French people could not <lb/>
elect a representative. The member for North <lb/>
Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) states that there is <lb/>
unanimity in the Council on this question. <lb/>
That is a very poor argument, when it <lb/>
Is remembered that we began by prevent<lb break="no"/>ing the half-breeds from electing the re<lb break="no"/>presentatives they were entitled to. Such an argu<lb break="no"/>ment will, I am sure, have very little weight with <lb/>
an intelligent body of men, such as compose this <lb/>
House. Do you not think, Mr. Speaker, that <lb/>
there is a national danger in abolishing the French <lb/>
language, as is proposed by the member for North <lb/>
Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy)? Do not you think the <lb/>
French language is the best safeguard against an<lb break="no"/>nexation? If the people of this country were all <lb/>
English-speaking, annexation would come in a <lb/>
very short time. What will prevent annexation <lb/>
is the determination of the Province of Quebec to <lb/>
maintain its own language. The people there are <lb/>
not willing to give up the present state of affairs <lb/>
and risk going elsewhere. If we were not a loyal <lb/>
people, if we were not devoted to the Queen, if we <lb/>
were not loyal to the Confederation, does it not <lb/>
strike you, Mr. Speaker, that we might apply <lb/>
to our neighbors in the United States, and to our <lb/>
million of French Canadians there, for help? The <lb/>
United States never took any country by force. <lb/>
but at the same time they never refused a country <lb/>
which wished to be annexed to them. We do not <lb/>
want annexation, however. We want to re<lb break="no"/>main Canadians. We want to form a grand <lb/>
nationality composed of the different races. <lb/>
We want Canada to remain a great country, and <lb/>
we want to form a part of it; but do not abuse <lb/>
that sentiment. You who believe in divorce, do <lb/>
not suppose that we are disposed to endure constant <lb/>
Insults such as those thrown at us by certain por<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

tions of the English press, especially when they <lb/>
are repeated on the floor of this House by a party, <lb/>
led by a man of talent who stands at the head of <lb/>
the bar of Ontario. We are loyal, and we want <lb/>
to remain loyal. I repeat the words I quoted the. <lb/>
other day, that the last gun which will be fired <lb/>
in defence of the British flag on this continent, will <lb/>
be discharged by a French Canadian; but there is <lb/>
another sentence which we must not forget. littered <lb/>
by a traveller, who said that the first gun that <lb/>
would be fired for the independence of Canada, <lb/>
would be discharged by a French Canadian from <lb/>
the States. There is no danger with us. We are <lb/>
frank and loyal and just—just to the minority <lb/>
and just to every one; we never attack; we only <lb/>
want to keep what we have. Under the eyes of <lb/>
God, we want to grow and prosper with our <lb/>
neighbors and friends in this country, peaceably <lb/>
and harmoniously, and I implore that faction to <lb/>
stop their attacks, and to leave us to the <lb/>
peaceablc enjoyment of our rights. What <lb/>
harm is done to them if our farmers speak <lb/>
French in their homes? When we come here as <lb/>
representatives of the people, do you find any<lb break="no"/>thing wrong with us—any dishonesty, any tricks, <lb/>
any complots against you? Are we not loyal sub<lb break="no"/>jects? Then, why not let us alone? What <lb/>
harm will it do you if the ordinances of <lb/>
the North-West Council are printed in French, <lb/>
so that the priests may read them to the loyal <lb/>
subjects who only understand French? What need <lb/>
is there to save a few paltry dollars, if, thereby, <lb/>
you throw the country into an immense danger? <lb/>
The responsibility of that faction is very great, but <lb/>
I know that the good sense of the country will <lb/>
soon put an end to their agitation. I am not <lb/>
threatening; I am only exposing the facts. If we <lb/>
want to form a large and compact country, let us <lb/>
not constantly be putting in the hands of one part <lb/>
of the population weapons which must be opposed by <lb/>
another part. Now, Sir, the hon. Premier through <lb/>
the hon. Minister of Justice, for whom I have the <lb/>
greatest personal respect, proposed the compromise <lb/>
amendment which has been offered to us. That <lb/>
compromise, I believe, is dictated by sincere and <lb/>
patriotic views. Whether I accept it or not, I am <lb/>
happy to see that both parties can forget their <lb/>
differences and join hands, in order to try to put <lb/>
a stop to this harmful agitation. It is true, <lb/>
the amendment itself attacks one of the roots of <lb/>
the tree of Confederation; but I am happy to see <lb/>
that the chiefs of both parties can agree to this <lb/>
compromise, without saying whether I can sanc<lb break="no"/>tion it by my vote or not. In concluding my <lb/>
remarks, which I abridge so as to accommodate my <lb/>
hon. colleagues, I will repeat, that if we want the <lb/>
Confederation to go on, if we want harmony and <lb/>
prosperity in this country, we must cease to attack <lb/>
each other, we must respect the rights of each <lb/>
other, we must leave each one to the enjoyment of <lb/>
his aspirations, his religion and his language; we <lb/>
must give full liberty to everyone, so that all will <lb/>
be free to work for the common good of the country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I ask the in<lb break="no"/>dulgence of the House for a few minutes, while I <lb/>
refer to some matters which I deem it proper to <lb/>
refer to before this debate closes. I can endorse, <lb/>
most heartily, the sentiment given utterance to by <lb/>
the speaker who has just preceded me, as to our <lb/>
regard to the mutual rights of the inhabitants of <lb/>

<pb n="971" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00971.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">971</fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">972</fw>

the various Provinces. If we should treat each <lb/>
other in a spirit of disregard for those rights, it <lb/>
would be a misfortune, a calamity, to the country. <lb/>
I am not able to understand, however, that the <lb/>
rights of the French-speaking community of the <lb/>
North-West, with regard to language, are vested <lb/>
rights. They certainly are not vested rights in the <lb/>
sense of the rights conferred by the British North <lb/>
America Act on the French inhabitants of the <lb/>
Province of Quebec. These rights were granted <lb/>
by the North-West Territories Act in 1877, and, in <lb/>
my belief, it is quite competent for the Legislature <lb/>
which granted those rights to repeal the enactment <lb/>
by which they were granted. Now, I have noticed, <lb/>
in the treatment of this by almost all the speakers <lb/>
opposed to the Bill under consideration, a dis<lb break="no"/>position to magnify the evils which are likely to <lb/>
result from this discussion, and to place on false <lb/>
ground the object sought by the Bill, and the <lb/>
consequences likely to result from its passage. It <lb/>
is asserted that the Bill is conceived in a spirit of <lb/>
enmity to the French race, and that the effect of <lb/>
its passage would be to set the two races at each <lb/>
other's throats and to disturb all the good relations <lb/>
existing between them-that, in short, it is a <lb/>
public calamity, that the subject of the retention <lb/>
of the dual languages in the North-West should be <lb/>
mooted at all. If this is the case, we are unable <lb/>
to approach this subject in any sense without the <lb/>
consequences to which I have alluded. The real <lb/>
subject before us is not a design to assault the in<lb break="no"/>habitants of a great Province in this Dominion, to <lb/>
abridge their rights or to attack their languages or <lb/>
their institutions, or to interfere with vested rights <lb/>
that exist in accordance with the provisions <lb/>
of the British North American Act. That <lb/>
is not the design of this Bill. The hon. <lb/>
gentleman who brings this Bill before the <lb/>
House expressly disavows any such designs. The <lb/>
design of the Bill is to retrace the false setp which, <lb/>
in the estimate of some members of this House, has <lb/>
been taken in forming the institutions of a new <lb/>
land, be repealing clause 110 of the North-West <lb/>
Territories Act and leaving to the people of those <lb/>
Territories the full and free exercise of Provincial <lb/>
rights in establishing their own institutions, with<lb break="no"/>out being handicapped by us by any legislation <lb/>
here, and thus replace them in the position of <lb/>
doing, as they should have had the right to do in <lb/>
the beginning, what they please is this matter. <lb/></p> 

<p>Now, there are three plans before this House: <lb/>
There is the Bill of the hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy); there is the amendment <lb/>
of the hon. member for Assiniboia (Mr. Davin); <lb/>
and there is the amendment of the hon. Minister <lb/>
of Justice (Sir John Thompson). The first of <lb/>
these plans is a direct one, and the one which I <lb/>
prefer. It proposes to settle this question at once, <lb/>
so far as this Parliament is concerned. The second <lb/>
is in some respect of the same character as the <lb/>
first. It proposes to recognise the assertion as <lb/>
true that the existing state of things in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories shall not be insisted on as perma<lb break="no"/>nent by this House; but it proposes to remove <lb/>
from our shoulders the responsibility of dealing with <lb/>
this question and to relegate it to the Assembly of <lb/>
the North-West Territories after the next elections, <lb/>
when that assembly shall have power to deal with <lb/>
the whole question. Plan number three is not <lb/>
only indirect but partial. It proposes, in the same <lb/>
indirect way, to shift the responsibility from our <lb/>

<cb/>

shoulders of dealing with this question and to place <lb/>
it upon the shoulders of the North-West Assembly, <lb/>
but it proposes to deal with only one feature of the <lb/>
case, namely, the use of the French language in <lb/>
the Legislative Assembly, leaving untouched the <lb/>
use of that language in the courts of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West and in the printing of the ordinances. In <lb/>
my opinion, the plan proposed by the hon. Minister <lb/>
of Justice is the least worthy of our consideration <lb/>
and support; and I must say that, after listening <lb/>
attentively to all the arguments advanced during <lb/>
the long debate on this question-which I do not <lb/>
consider a question that ought to create that degree <lb/>
of bitterness of feeling which exists-I am persuaded <lb/>
that we ought to settle this difficulty promptly <lb/>
and peremptorily in our capacity as the sovereign <lb/>
source of power in this matter, by retracing the <lb/>
steps we took in the year 1877. I cannot under<lb break="no"/>stand that the use of the French language in the <lb/>
courts, provided for by the 133rd clause of the <lb/>
British North America Act, contemplates the use <lb/>
of the language in courts such as these established <lb/>
in the North-West. The language of that section <lb/>
    is as follows:— </p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Either the English of the French language may be <lb/>
used by any person in the debates of the House of the <lb/>
Parliament of Canada and of the House of the Legislature <lb/>
of Quebec; and both those languages shall be used in the <lb/>
respective Records and Journals of those Houses; and <lb/>
either of those languages may be used by any person, or <lb/>
in any pleading or process in, or issuing from, any court <lb/>
of Canada established under this Act, and in, or from, all <lb/>
or any of the courts of Quebec." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>Now, here is a remarkable difference in the lan<lb break="no"/>guage used regarding the courts of Quebec and <lb/>
the courts of Canada. Either language is to be used <lb/>
in any and all of the courts of Quebec, but they <lb/>
are both to be used in any court of Canada estab<lb break="no"/>lished under this Act only. What is a court of <lb/>
Canada established under this Act? The 101st <lb/>
section explains that: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The Parliament of Canada may, not withstanding any<lb break="no"/>thing in this Act, from time to time, provide for the con<lb break="no"/>stitution, maintenance and organisation of a general <lb/>
Court of Appeal for Canada, and for the establishment of <lb/>
any additional courts for the better administration of the <lb/>
laws of Canada." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>So that reference is had in this 133rd clause to <lb/>
such courts as may be established in virtue of the <lb/>
    authority conferred under section 101—such as the <lb/>
Court of Appeals, the Exchequer Court, or any <lb/>
court established as a Court of Canada for the <lb/>
settlement of questions pertaining to the Dominion <lb/>
of Canada in which our French subjects and Eng<lb break="no"/>lish subjects will meet for the purpose of trying <lb/>
cases from all the Provinces. But this clause does <lb/>
not, in my opinion, interfere with or apply to the <lb/>
courts of any Province in this Dominion, except <lb/>
the specially named courts of the Province of Que<lb break="no"/>bec. <lb/></p> 

<p>We have had a great deal of talk about <lb/>
Provincial rights in connection with this matter. <lb/>
In my opinion, any action but that proposed by <lb/>
the hon. member for North Simcoe would be a <lb/>
violation of the fundamental principle of Provincial <lb/>
rights. The hon. member for North Simcoe pro<lb break="no"/>poses to repeal clause 110. He proposes to give <lb/>
the inhabitants of the North-West Territories the <lb/>
right to form their own institutions when they be<lb break="no"/>come a Province; he proposes to leave them in the <lb/>
full and unrestricted possession of Provincial <lb/>
rights. But the amendment of my hon. friend <lb/>
  <lb/>

<pb n="973" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00973.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">973</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">974</fw> 

of the hon. Minister of Justice do not propose to <lb/>
do this; they only propose to make the con<lb break="no"/>dition, that we shall retain this authority and <lb/>
power which we have exercised and this law on the <lb/>
Statute-book until we have consulted the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Assembly of the North-West Territories. <lb/>
The amendment of the hon. Minister of Justice <lb/>
proposes further, that we shall absolutely <lb/>
retain a portion of the abuse complained of, and <lb/>
only remove it in so far as it may apply to the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly of the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories; and neither amendment meets so fully the <lb/>
principle of Provincial rights as the proposition of <lb/>
the hon. member for North Simcoe, the essence of <lb/>
which is that we shall withdraw our interfer<lb break="no"/>ence, and allow the people of the North-West <lb/>
to deal with this matter themselves. That is <lb/>
the proper and the direct way to deal with <lb/>
this question. I see no reason to change the <lb/>
opinion I have formed, or to withdraw my sup<lb break="no"/>port from the Bill, which I announced I intended <lb/>
to support. The use of the dual language and <lb/>
Separate Schools are local institutions, which we <lb/>
have no right, as a Parliament, to impose upon <lb/>
any section of this country. They are institutions <lb/>
which should be established, which should be <lb/>
arranged for, which should be legislated upon, by <lb/>
the Provincial authorities of the Province in which <lb/>
they may exist. I do not say that I would not <lb/>
consider that the Governor in Council has not the <lb/>
power to veto a Bill of this kind on the ground <lb/>
of general advantage or in the general interests of the <lb/>
Dominion; but I do say that, in my belief, the <lb/>
Government has no right to establish local institu<lb break="no"/>tions in any portion of the territories of Canada. <lb/>
For that reason, I believe that this clause 110 should <lb/>
be repealed. We must remember that Canada was <lb/>
formerly a military colony; we must remember <lb/>
that divergencies existed between the old French <lb/>
colonies and the English colonies in America; and <lb/>
these differences of opinion, these differences of <lb/>
institutions, and these differences of instincts, have, <lb/>
to a certain extent, come down to the present day. <lb/>
Canada was a military colony; it had feudal in<lb break="no"/>stitutions; and the thirteen colonies were quite <lb/>
different from Canada. The Saxon colonies are <lb/>
quite different in many respects from the colony of <lb/>
Quebec; it is natural, therefore, that friction should <lb/>
arise between these two systems, and it is in the <lb/>
last degree unwise to extend the area of that <lb/>
friction. It would be much better to restrict it to <lb/>
the Province where the question under debate was <lb/>
first at issue, as we would do by repealing this <lb/>
clause and leaving the people of the North-West <lb/>
to settle the matter by themselves, than to set our<lb break="no"/>selves by the ears, from one end of the Dominion <lb/>
to the other, as we have been doing. <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon. the leader of the Opposition has made <lb/>
a speech, which, I can say most sincerely, was, in <lb/>
my estimation, a most able speech, one which I <lb/>
admired exceedingly both for its spirit and tone, <lb/>
and for the tact displayed in it by that hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man in dealing with that question; and one which <lb/>
I admired also for the sentiments it breathed in <lb/>
defence of his race and native tongue, in respect of <lb/>
which I could almost respond to the sentiments <lb/>
he uttered; but I think he was mistaken in <lb/>
saying that this Bill necessarily provokes enmity <lb/>
between the two races, that it necessarily sets <lb/>
them against each other in a spirit of hostility. I <lb/>
do not think it is necessary to take that view. I <lb/>

<cb/>

do not think the scope of the question extensive <lb/>
enough or the issues involved great enough <lb/>
to warrant the two great races setting them<lb break="no"/>selves by the ears in this matter. It is a local <lb/>
question, a question affecting a certain locality <lb/>
in this Dominion, it is in one sense a small question <lb/>
at this moment, affecting only a few thousand <lb/>
people. It may be a great question as to the <lb/>
future, but at present it is a small question compa<lb break="no"/>ratively, and it is a question we may as well settle <lb/>
at once and take out of the way. <lb/></p> 

<p>In the course of the speeches which have been <lb/>
made, I have been severely criticised in some <lb/>
respects. My hon. friend the member for <lb/>
Kent, N.B. (Mr. Landry) took up an extract <lb/>
from a speech made by me at Essex Centre <lb/>
on the 12th July, in which I rather face<lb break="no"/>tiously alluded to the alliance between my hon. <lb/>
friend the Minister of Customs and my hon. <lb/>
friend the Minister of Public Works as being <lb/>
rather incongruous, and said that, when they were <lb/>
lying in the same bed, the representative of the <lb/>
French nationality and the grand master of the <lb/>
Orange Order, that the friendship was rather a <lb/>
peculiar and suspicious one; and that I thought <lb/>
they could not both be acting according to their <lb/>
principles, and that I thought my hon. friend the <lb/>
Minister of Customs would be the one who would <lb/>
be sold. I do not know that that remark should <lb/>
be considered as offensive. We have seen other <lb/>
incongruous spectacles; for instance, during this <lb/>
debate, Pilate and Herod have been made <lb/>
friends together for we have seen the leaders <lb/>
of the two political parties, no doubt from <lb/>
patriotic motives, acting in concert; and that is <lb/>
a very unusual thing to see. They have been en<lb break="no"/>deavoring to arrange this matter in certain ways, <lb/>
whereas I think the simplest way would be to <lb/>
repeal the clause to which I have referred. <lb/></p> 

<p>My hon. friend the member for West Durham <lb/>
(Mr. Blake), in the course of his very able speech, <lb/>
advanced the argument that it was necessary to <lb/>
keep up the French language in the North-West <lb/>
for the purpose of encouraging immigration; and <lb/>
the First Minister said he would be willing to have <lb/>
German made an official language there also, in <lb/>
order to encourage immigration. No doubt, he <lb/>
would be willing to go further and adopt the <lb/>
Gaelic or any other language for that purpose. The <lb/>
question is: is the retention of that language or <lb/>
any other necessary to encourage immigration into <lb/>
that country? In the year 1871, the hierarchy of <lb/>
your own Province, Mr. Speaker, issued a joint <lb/>
letter warning the French Canadians against <lb/>
emigrating to the New England States, which, it <lb/>
was said, would imperil their spiritual interests, <lb/>
which would prove very dangerous to themselves, <lb/>
and which was something they ought not to do. <lb/>
At the same time, the hierarchy requested the <lb/>
people of that Province who might desire to <lb/>
emigrate to migrate to the Canadian North-West. <lb/>
What was the effect of that letter; what was the <lb/>
effect of that warning and of those arguments; <lb/>
what was the effect of these mandates, in the name <lb/>
of the Church, upon the Canadian French of the <lb/>
Province of Quebec? Did they quit going to Massa<lb break="no"/>chusetts and flock in large bodies to the North-<lb break="yes"/>West? Did the existence of the dual language in the <lb/>
North-West draw thousands of the French Cana<lb break="no"/>dian people there, or did the fact that there was <lb/>
no dual language in Massachusetts and Vermont <lb/>

<pb n="975" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00975.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">975</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">976</fw> 

prevent them from going to those States? On the <lb/>
contrary, there are to be found in the New England <lb/>
States more French Canadians than there are inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants in Manitoba, the North-West and British Col<lb break="no"/>umbia together, with a score or more thousand added <lb/>
to that number. They have gone to New England in <lb/>
spite of that mandate; they have gone to a country <lb/>
where English is the only language spoken; they <lb/>
have refused to listen to their own hierarchy; they <lb/>
have done what they were entreated not to do, and <lb/>
they have not done what they were entreated to do. <lb/>
I think that is a fair argument to show that the <lb/>
retention of the French language in the North-West <lb/>
is unnecessary to promote immigration to that <lb/>
country. The Germans go there, and the Ice<lb break="no"/>landers go there, though their languages are not <lb/>
official there, and I do not think that the absence of <lb/>
their language as an official one is the slightest bar <lb/>
to their immigration to that country. <lb/></p> 

<p>In connection with this question of the anxiety of <lb/>
our French friends for the continuance of their rights <lb/>
—and it is a most natural anxiety on their part—it <lb/>
is, perhaps, a little significant that, one after another, <lb/>
the municipalities of the Province of Quebec are <lb/>
abolishing the use of the English tongue. I am in<lb break="no"/>formed that the great majority of those municipali<lb break="no"/>ties have already abandoned it. Wherever a muni<lb break="no"/>cipal council petitions for power to abolish the <lb/>
use of English in its proceedings it is very soon <lb/>
    obtained; an order is issued in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Official Gazette</hi>, <lb/>
and the use of English ceases. In view of this <lb/>
fact, I think our friends should not raise so much <lb/>
trouble in reference to the abolition of the use of <lb/>
French in a country which probably has no more <lb/>
population than an ordinary municipality in the <lb/>
Province of Quebec. <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon. First Minister warned us of the terrible <lb/>
consequences of drawing up two races against <lb/>
each other. He said this was a question which <lb/>
could afford to wait, and a moment afterwards <lb/>
he said: For Heaven's sake, bury this and get <lb/>
it out of sight. It is certainly lamentable that <lb/>
two races should be drawn up against one <lb/>
another; but, if one race is drawn up, if that <lb/>
race is acting and aiming at a common purpose, <lb/>
it may become necessary to have some organ<lb break="no"/>isation in the other race, and our French friends <lb/>
have never, in my recollection, or, so far as I know, <lb/>
in the history of Canada, failed to press their own <lb/>
claims and to stand by their own interests. It may <lb/>
be necessary to watch the opposite party, because <lb/>
their devotion to their language, their religion and <lb/>
their race—which may be perfectly proper in their <lb/>
case and from their standpoint—may lead to <lb/>
demands, which, in the view of an impartial <lb/>
observer, ought not to be granted. In that case, <lb/>
the exhortation of the First Minister to beware <lb/>
of arraying one race against another, is out of <lb/>
place, because the English-speaking population <lb/>
in this country have always acted in a spirit <lb/>
of generosity and a spirit of magnanimity; <lb/>
necessary to take some precautions for the <lb/>
future, it is not in a spirit of enmity to the <lb/>
French population, but, looking at the <lb/>
great North-West with all its resources, <lb/>
regarding it as the foundation of a great empire, <lb/>
we are justified in doing so if we have arrived at <lb/>
the conclusion that it is better at the outset to <lb/>
have the institutions there formed on the proper <lb/>
basis, when it can be done without any great con<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

tention, and to say that we will start with the <lb/>
English language and go on there with that lan<lb break="no"/>guage as the official one. I do not think it can be <lb/>
properly said by the First Minister that those who <lb/>
are in favor of that obviously common-sense ar<lb break="no"/>rangement are arraying one race against another. <lb/></p> 

<p>Some of our speakers on this side appear to me to <lb/>
lack judiciousness. My hon. friend from West <lb/>
Ontario (Mr. Edgar), for instance, warned the <lb/>
French to beware of their enemies. Who are <lb/>
their enemies? I deny that they have an enemy <lb/>
in this House, or in this country, or that any de<lb break="no"/>mand is made in this Bill which indicates enmity <lb/>
to the French race in this Dominion. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber from Iberville (Mr. Béchard), last night, in his <lb/>
temperate speech, spoke of the demagogues, whose <lb/>
designs were to provoke dissension and disaster. <lb/>
Was the hon. gentleman warranted in classing as <lb/>
demagogues those who seek for abolition of the <lb/>
dual language in the North-West? Is there any<lb break="no"/>thing like the spirit of the demagogue in this proposi<lb break="no"/>tion to undo what we sincerely believe to have been <lb/>
a wrong step, and to place upon a proper basis the <lb/>
institutions for the future of a great country? If <lb/>
there is an act which is worthy of being characterised <lb/>
as an act of statemanship which has come under <lb/>
my observation in this Parliament of Canada, it is <lb/>
an act of that character. Then the hon. gentleman <lb/>
read an extract from a speech delivered to his con<lb break="no"/>stituents last summer in which he proposed, as a rem<lb break="no"/>edy for all these unendurable evils which the French <lb/>
race was suffering at the hands of those who asked <lb/>
for equal rights—he proposes as a remedy annexa<lb break="no"/>tion to the United States. Well, Sir, how much <lb/>
better off would his race he in that position? <lb/>
Would there be any less pressure that would tend <lb/>
towards unification of race and language? Would <lb/>
the influence brought to bear upon them be <lb/>
of a less aggravating character, if they wished to <lb/>
retain their isolation? Would the United States <lb/>
treat with a greater degree of forbearance than <lb/>
the Saxon population of this country does, the <lb/>
peculiar institutions of Quebec? Why, there <lb/>
would be danger of their being denied admission <lb/>
to the Union as is the case with Utah until they <lb/>
had adopted a Republican form of government and <lb/>
had rid themselves of medieval institutions. <lb/></p> 

<p>My hon. friend the Minister of the Interior says: <lb/>
"Oh, this is a small matter; what is the use of making <lb/>
this row over a cost amounting to $1,000 a year, or so? <lb/>
Let the whole thing go. Do not make the trouble <lb/>
you are making about this question." As I said <lb/>
before, it is not a matter of the cost; it is not a <lb/>
matter of the pressing importance of the question <lb/>
at this moment in any respect whatever. We are <lb/>
looking to the future, we are looking to the con<lb break="no"/>sequences in the future, and it is, because it is a <lb/>
comparatively small and trifling matter in itself, <lb/>
that we can now deal with it with so much greater <lb/>
facility and ease than we can by-and-bye when it <lb/>
becomes a great matter, involving great issues in the <lb/>
North-West. My hon. friend from the Queen's (Mr. <lb/>
Davies) tells us that the preamble is a matter <lb/>
of no great account. I agree with him. He <lb/>
says: Let the people decide. I agree with <lb/>
him most fully. The only fault I have to find <lb/>
with him is, that he will not act upon his asser<lb break="no"/>tion. He says: Let the people decide the question; <lb/>
and then he proposes to refuse to allow the people <lb/>
to decide the question. I say, let the people decide <lb/>
the question. Repeal the 110th clause, leaving <lb/>

<pb n="977" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00977.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">977</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">978</fw>

them perfectly untrammelled; let them start <hi rendition="simple:italic">de <lb/>
noco</hi> and decide whether they will have the dual <lb/>
language or not; leave them perfectly free to deal <lb/>
with their local institutions, without interference <lb/>
or meddling with them on our part. <lb/></p> 

<p>My hon. friend, the Secretary of State, who, <lb/>
I see, is in his seat, had some strictures to make <lb/>
on my remarks, and I will ask the attention of <lb/>
the House for a moment while I refer to one or <lb/>
two of them. The hon. gentleman told us that <lb/>
the Protestants of Quebec did not complain. Well, <lb/>
I do not know that the Protestants of Quebec <lb/>
have any great reason to complain; it would be, <lb/>
however, only natural, as they are in a very small <lb/>
minority in that Province, that they should be <lb/>
cautious about making complaints, because the <lb/>
evincing of a spirit of captiousness, or what is <lb/>
termed such by the majority, might lead to their <lb/>
having greater reasons for complaint. But I have <lb/>
heard complaints from the Province of Quebec. For <lb/>
instance, I heard complaints last year about the <lb/>
degradation of the degrees of Protestant univer<lb break="no"/>sities. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. That has been remedied. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. Yes, these complaints led to <lb/>
the remedy of that evil. A Bill has been passed <lb/>
to remedy the evil, and the passage of that Bill is <lb/>
equivalent to a confession that the Protestants had, <lb/>
in this matter, just cause of complaint. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LANGELIER</persName> (Quebec). They have no <lb/>
other cause of complaint. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. I believe that all the griev<lb break="no"/>ances and the difficulties between the two races: <lb/>
might be settled in the same spirit. Then we have <lb/>
the question of the division of the school funds. I <lb/>
do not know if that has been settled or not, but <lb/>
there have been some complaints about that— <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. That is before the Council of <lb/>
Education. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>—taking the school funds paid <lb/>
by corporations, such as the Bank of Montreal, the <lb/>
Grand Trunk Railway and the Canadian Pacific <lb/>
Railway, of whom the great majority of the stock <lb/>
holders are Protestants, and dividing the taxes <lb/>
paid by these corporations between Protestants and <lb/>
Catholics in relative proportion to the population, <lb/>
whereas they ought to be divided in proportion to <lb/>
the religion of those who paid the taxes. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LANGELIER</persName> (Quebec). Is that done in <lb/>
Ontario? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. Not now, but I understood <lb/>
that it was the case once. Complaint was made, <lb/>
and I think the evil has been remedied, although I <lb/>
speak under correction with regard to that matter. <lb/>
Then, the hon. gentleman makes an allusion to <lb/>
something which I have said in one of the speeches <lb/>
I made in the country, and which he thinks was of <lb/>
the most insulting character to the French popu<lb break="no"/>lation—something, I think, with regard to cutting <lb/>
a road tothe St. Lawrence with the sword. Well, <lb/>
Mr. Speaker, upon one occasion, I forget where, when <lb/>
we were somewhat warm over these declarations in <lb/>
Quebec—and, by-the-bye, let me state that I am <lb/>
happy to learn that the language attributed to Mr. <lb/>
Mercier has been very much modified by a more <lb/>
authentic report of his remarks—but when we <lb/>
were somewhat roused by the talk about a French <lb/>
nationality, and French national institutions, and <lb/>
the building up of a French state at the mouth of <lb/>

<cb/>

the St. Lawrence, I did say, I think once, in one <lb/>
of my speeches, that if the French inhabitants of <lb/>
Quebec attempted to create a separate nationality. <lb/>
planting themselves upon the St. Lawrence and <lb/>
denying the western Provinces access to the sea, in <lb/>
that case it would lead to an attempt to cut a road <lb/>
to the sea with the sword. I have nothing to re<lb break="no"/>tract upon that score. If that attempt were made, <lb/>
such a result would unquestionably follow. <lb/></p> 

<p>Now, Sir, a few words with regard to my <lb/>
hon. friend from West Durham (Mr. Blake) and <lb/>
the criticisms made by that hon. gentleman upon <lb/>
the remarks I had made just before he spoke. I <lb/>
may say that I spoke without due preparation: I <lb/>
had only the time between ten o'clock in the morning, <lb/>
and three in the afternoon to prepare my brief, and <lb/>
in the haste of preparation I probably did fall into <lb/>
some inaccuracy, and amongst these inaccuracies was <lb/>
one, technical rather in its character, with regard to <lb/>
the course adopted by the United States Govern<lb break="no"/>ment when Louisiana was purchased in 1803. <lb/>
I stated that the United States Government, from <lb/>
the inception, had sought by every means to secure <lb/>
a single language, and had abolished the use of the <lb/>
French. But I find that for the first few years <lb/>
that policy was not so rigorously enforced as later <lb/>
on, and the use of French was permitted, to a <lb/>
limited extent, and in that sense my hon. friend <lb/>
had me at a disadvantage; for I had gone upon the <lb/>
assumption that the well understood general policy <lb/>
of the Government had been more vigorously <lb/>
enforced than probably was the case at the outset. <lb/>
But so far as the policy of the United States Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment was concerned, with the new states along <lb/>
the Mississippi where French settlements were esta<lb break="no"/>blished, and in all these settlements outside of <lb/>
Louisiana proper, the French language was never <lb/>
used officially at all. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAP4">Mr. CHAPLEAU</persName>. The Civil Code of Louisiana <lb/>
was printed in French in 1825. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. I am referring to the terri<lb break="no"/>tories away to the north along the Mississippi and <lb/>
the Missouri. But I am free to admit that in this <lb/>
criticism upon the policy of the United States with <lb/>
regard to Louisiana, I fell into a technical error, <lb/>
although the position I took in regard to the general <lb/>
policy of the United States with regard to Louisiana <lb/>
and to all other portions of the country originally <lb/>
settled by foreign nations and incorporated with <lb/>
the United States, was perfectly correct. Then <lb/>
the hon. gentleman indulged in some criticism <lb/>
about the use of the pronoun "we;" he seemed <lb/>
to be under an apprehension that I would convey <lb/>
the impression that he acted with me, or believed <lb/>
with me, in this matter. Now, Mr. Speaker, I <lb/>
always desire to avoid giving ground for the charge <lb/>
of egotism, and, consequently, avoid, as far as pos<lb break="no"/>sible, the use of the pronoun "I." I do not like <lb/>
to see a large "I" used too freely. But, on this <lb/>
occasion, I find that the hon. gentleman himself <lb/>
used the word "we" in his speech, and used it on <lb/>
several occasions. In speakin upon this occasion <lb/>
when I used the word "we," I used it, not as in<lb break="no"/>cluding those who disagree with me, but referring <lb/>
to those, be their numbers great or small, who <lb/>
agree with me in this matter. Perhaps, if it suits <lb/>
the hon. gentleman, I may use the personal pro<lb break="no"/>noun "I" and ignore the "we"—ignore all who are <lb/>
associated with me in this or other matters. But, <lb/>
iin my opinion, this part of the hon. gentleman's <lb/>

<pb n="979" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00979.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">979</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">980</fw> 

criticism was a very "wee" matter indeed, and the <lb/>
spirit in which it was made was not one I admire <lb/>
very highly. <lb/></p> 

<p>In the course of the speeches made by differ<lb break="no"/>ent members of the House, the motives of those <lb/>
who engaged in the Equal Rights movement during <lb/>
last summer have been very severely criticised. <lb/>
We have been termed fanatics and demagogues, <lb/>
and there is scarcely a term of disrespect in the <lb/>
political vocabulary that has not been applied to <lb/>
those gentlemen who saw fit to associate them<lb break="no"/>selves in this movement in this House and in the <lb/>
country during last summer. I feel bound, under <lb/>
the circumstances, as the question has been raised, <lb/>
to say a few words in regard to this matter. <lb/>
What, probably, were the motives, I would ask, <lb/>
that actuated these thirteen men who stood up in <lb/>
this House and voted against the 188 members? <lb/>
What were, probably, the motives which actuated <lb/>
those men in the course they took after the proroga<lb break="no"/>tion of Parliament? Do you think, Sir, they were seek<lb break="no"/>ing after popularity? Was it with any desire to gain <lb/>
political advantage that those men united and em<lb break="no"/>bittered their foes and made foes of their friends? <lb/>
You, Sir, sat in this House on the night that vote <lb/>
was taken. Do you think any one of the thirteen <lb/>
stood up under flattering and encouraging circum<lb break="no"/>stances or because there was a great advantage to <lb/>
be gained? No; no one will suppose that such <lb/>
was the case; and whatever may have been the <lb/>
motives which actuated those men, you can <lb/>
scarcely, under the circumstances, attribute that <lb/>
action to base, mercenary or dishonest motives. <lb/>
We felt that having taken that stand, it was per<lb break="no"/>fectly proper to defend our position in the country. <lb/>
We felt that we were standing on principles that <lb/>
were just, and it was as proper to vindicate them <lb/>
upon the platform as upon the floor of the House <lb/>
of Commons. We thought we were resisting the <lb/>
investing of a dangerous order with special ad<lb break="no"/>vantages and privileges. We may have been mis<lb break="no"/>taken, but we believed that was the case, and, acting <lb/>
on that view, we submitted to the country similar <lb/>
arguments to those we had presented on the floor <lb/>
of this House. We believed we were resisting <lb/>
an unconstitutional reference to a foreign potentate. <lb/>
I believe it now, and believing it we felt bound to <lb/>
act on that belief. We believed we were resisting <lb/>
sectarian endowment from public funds. We <lb/>
believed this, and we held that it was establishing <lb/>
a precedent of the most dangerous character, and <lb/>
believing that we acted honestly before the country <lb/>
in denouncing it. We believed we were resisting a <lb/>
dangerous encroachment by clerical power. Believ<lb break="no"/>ing this we denounced it. We did not propose, no <lb/>
man who has taken part in this agitation ever pro<lb break="no"/>posed, to deprive any subject in this country of any <lb/>
rights he possessed. No man has ever proposed to <lb/>
ask for himself what he was not prepared to give to <lb/>
every citizen of this country. We ask no special <lb/>
privileges; we merely resist the granting of special <lb/>
privileges. We ask equal rights for all, special <lb/>
privileges to none, a guarantee of the fundamental <lb/>
principle of liberty to the subjects of this country. <lb/>
I understand the hon. member for North Simcoe <lb/>
(Mr. McCarthy) said he did not sympathise with <lb/>
the movement made by the Equal Rights party in <lb/>
discussing this question on the platforms of the <lb/>
country. I believe it was a proper way to <lb/>
influence public sentiment, and that it was neces<lb break="no"/>sary. <lb/></p> 

<cb/>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. Perhaps the hon. gentle <lb/>
man will allow me for a moment to say that I do <lb/>
not think I said that; I did not mean to do so. I <lb/>
said I took no part, because I realised that no <lb/>
object would be gained. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. I understood the reason <lb/>
why the hon. gentleman refrained from doing so <lb/>
was because he disapproved of it, and I am <lb/>
happy to receive his explanation. This move<lb break="no"/>ment, which is decried and condemned in this <lb/>
House, has, I believe, accomplished something; <lb/>
and, I believe, what this movement has accom<lb break="no"/>plished is of the most salutary character. It has <lb/>
certainly awakened public attention to the exist<lb break="no"/>ence of a great public danger. I believe it is due <lb/>
to this movement that the agitation exists in <lb/>
Manitoba with respect to the dual language and <lb/>
the Separate Schools; and the abolition of both of <lb/>
those evils, as I deem them to be, may be justly <lb/>
attributed to the agitation that commenced with <lb/>
the vote taken in this House on 29th March last. <lb/>
I believe this agitation has succeeded in arousing <lb/>
public sentiment in the North-West with respect <lb/>
to the dual language, and the fact that we are <lb/>
discussing to-day a Bill with respect to the <lb/>
abolition of the French language in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, and that we have in the North-West a <lb/>
sentiment so pronounced as to have demanded the <lb/>
introduction of this Bill, is due to the agitation of <lb/>
the question of equal rights up and down through<lb break="no"/>out the country since the prorogation of the <lb/>
House last Session. The harvest is satisfactory; <lb/>
the results so far are abundantly satisfactory, if <lb/>
nothing else is accomplished; and if this Bill <lb/>
passes, or if the North-West is relieved of the <lb/>
burden of the dual language, there is nothing else <lb/>
to ask for, because the Constitution grants the <lb/>
rest. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. What about the agitation in <lb/>
Quebec? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. We do not expect to have <lb/>
any. I do not say there has been such an agitation. <lb/>
I say there has been an agitation in Manitoba <lb/>
against the dual language and separate schools, and <lb/>
there has been an agitation in the North-West <lb/>
Territories, and it is a foregone conclusion that in <lb/>
some way or other the dual language will be re<lb break="no"/>moved there. On broad principles we are dealing <lb/>
with this question, and our sincere desire is to <lb/>
secure homogeneity and assimilation. We desire it, <lb/>
we do not expect to force it, or that it will come <lb/>
immediately; we hope it will come some time by <lb/>
the force of circumstances, and we hope, when the <lb/>
day comes, that solution will be reached by a con<lb break="no"/>census of opinion among the people of the Dominion. <lb/>
We hope for this, and anything that will exert in<lb break="no"/>fluence in this direction without trampling on the <lb/>
rights of other is something we may properly make <lb/>
use of. The North-West is virgin soil, and any <lb/>
seed that is undesirable should not be planted by <lb/>
us there. Our first Act with respect to this ques<lb break="no"/>tion was wrong; I believe we cannot do better <lb/>
than change that Act, and in doing so we will <lb/>
act strictly in consonance with the principle <lb/>
of Provincial rights. With respect to vested rights <lb/>
in the Province of Quebec, I repeat that, so far as <lb/>
I am concerned and my influence extends, I have <lb/>
no idea, thought, desire or purpose to deal with <lb/>
the Provincial rights of Quebec in any sense what<lb break="no"/>ever. I may entertain my opinion as to whether <lb/>

<pb n="981" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00981.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">981</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">982</fw>

it is desirable for Quebec to have different in<lb break="no"/>stitutions, and I may, in a proper way and on a <lb/>
proper occasion, express that opinion, I trust; but <lb/>
so far as regard dealing in any manner with the <lb/>
vested rights of Quebec, I would not be a party to <lb/>
such an attempt or countenance it in any way <lb/>
whatever. The proposal to divide the continent <lb/>
between the two races is unreasonable. I consider <lb/>
this country is under British institutions, and <lb/>
although the French language prevailed when the <lb/>
country was ceded to the British, and although the <lb/>
French language has been recognised and certain <lb/>
vested rights have been granted, yet the proposal <lb/>
to divide this great country between the two races <lb/>
and the two languages is unreasonable and unsatis<lb break="no"/>factory and not calculated to promote the future <lb/>
good of the country. The issue I think we all <lb/>
recognise is inevitable; no matter in what way <lb/>
we may deal with this question the dual language <lb/>
in the North-West is doomed. It is doomed, <lb/>
whether this Bill passes or not, whether the motion <lb/>
of the hon. member for West Assiniboia (Mr. <lb/>
Davin), or even the motion of the hon. the Minister <lb/>
of Justice passes; in either of these cases it is <lb/>
useless to propose that the French language in the <lb/>
great North-West will be retained for any length <lb/>
of time, and to remove a source of irritation we <lb/>
may as well meet the inevitable to-day, and ex<lb break="no"/>punge clause 110 from the North-West Territories <lb/>
Act, and leave those Territories in a position so <lb/>
that when they frame Provincial institutions they <lb/>
may deal with the question as they may choose on <lb/>
the basis of Provincial rights. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Mr. HOLTON</persName>. I wish in a very few words to <lb/>
emphasise the position whichI have so far taken, and <lb/>
in which I propose continuing, with respect to the <lb/>
measure now under the consideration of this House. <lb/>
And at the outset I would say that I fully agree <lb/>
with the majority of the speakers who have pre<lb break="no"/>ceded me, in regarding its introduction under <lb/>
existing circumstances as a grave public calamity. <lb/>
The principle involved in this measure is, of course, <lb/>
a fairly debatable one. Yet after listening very <lb/>
attentively to the discussion of the past week, and <lb/>
more particularly to the speeches of the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), I am <lb/>
unable, in my own mind, to separate the Bill now <lb/>
submitted to us from those speeches, or from the <lb/>
utterances of himself and friends upon the public <lb/>
platforms during the past twelve months. In fact, <lb/>
Sir, the hon. member's advocacy of the proposed <lb/>
enactment is but the fulfilment of the promise or <lb/>
threat repeatedly made by him on the occasions <lb/>
referred to—the first step in his utopian scheme <lb/>
for welding and cementing the inhabitants of this <lb/>
whole country into one harmonious English-<lb break="yes"/>speaking people. I do not wish to impute <lb/>
motives to the gentlemen of the Equal <lb/>
Rights Association? Many of them are per<lb break="no"/>sonal friends of my own; and, whatever I may <lb/>
think of their movement, I very cheerfully credit <lb/>
them with all the sincerity of purpose in it which <lb/>
they claim for themselves, or to which they are <lb/>
entitled. Still, Sir, we cannot blind our eyes to <lb/>
the fact that, as a most lamentable result of the <lb/>
agitation which they have promoted and so per<lb break="no"/>sistently maintained throughout the country, the <lb/>
prejudices and animosities of the different elements <lb/>
of our population have been unduly aroused, so <lb/>
that to-day we find the public mind inflamed to a <lb/>

<cb/>

degree that has probably not been equalled since <lb/>
the unhappy period of half a century ago. And, Sir, <lb/>
with the public mind thus excited and disturbed, <lb/>
this measure is forced upon the attention of the <lb/>
House, and in no sense as oil is poured upon the <lb/>
troubled waters; under such circumstances, the <lb/>
cool, calm deliberation to which a question of this <lb/>
importance is entitled cannot possibly be had. <lb/>
In this fact alone, I find good and sufficient reason <lb/>
for supporting any proposition having for its pur<lb break="no"/>pose the postponement of the consideration of the <lb/>
measure. There is one matter to which I now feel <lb/>
it my duty—as it certainly is my pleasure—to <lb/>
make brief allusion: that is, the gross misconcep<lb break="no"/>tion which unfortunately obtains in many quarters <lb/>
outside the Province of Quebec, as to the true <lb/>
relations existing between the two races in it—a <lb/>
misconception for which I believe the present <lb/>
agitation is very largely responsible. I may pos<lb break="no"/>sibly be told outside of this House, if not in it, <lb/>
that I am neither qualified nor authorised to speak <lb/>
here, for the minority of that Province. Still, <lb/>
Sir, I am one of that minority; I have lived all my <lb/>
days in that Province; my acquaintance with its <lb/>
people is pretty extended. And, I do think, and <lb/>
believe, that I fully represent the great majority <lb/>
of my co-religionists there, when I say that on <lb/>
the whole we have not very much to complain of. <lb/>
I, Sir, am as staunch and pronounced a Protestant, <lb/>
as loyal to my faith, as true to my race, as jealous <lb/>
of my rights, and as fully determined to defend <lb/>
them at all hazards, as any man sitting in this <lb/>
House. But, Sir, I have never yet had reason or <lb/>
occasion to imagine for a moment that my <lb/>
civil or religious liberty—my life, property, or <lb/>
any of the sacred rights which are mine, as a <lb/>
free-born subject of Her Majesty—ever have <lb/>
been, or are ever likely to be, in one whit in <lb/>
greater jeopardy in my native Province, than if <lb/>
I were a resident of any other portion of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion. Of course, Sir, (and more particularly in <lb/>
those parts of the Province where we of the minority <lb/>
are numerically weak) we do labor under certain <lb/>
disadvantages; the inevitable incidents, I presume, <lb/>
of being in a minority. Yet, aside from the incon<lb break="no"/>veniences flowing from that source, and aside from <lb/>
the friction engendered by such movements as the <lb/>
present one, our troubles are but few, and it may <lb/>
be truthfully said that the two races do dwell <lb/>
harmoniously together. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. Hear, hear. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Mr. HOLTON</persName>. Further, Sir, I feel it is but <lb/>
due to my neighbors and fellow-citizens of French <lb/>
origin to declare here on their behalf, that they are <lb/>
not, as a people, the intolerant bigots and fanatics <lb/>
that too many people in certain quarters are in<lb break="no"/>clined to suppose them to be, judging them, as <lb/>
they unfairly and improperly do, from the unwise <lb/>
utterances of excited politicians, the intemperate <lb/>
writings of obscure newspaper people, or the occa<lb break="no"/>sional unlawful acts of an ignorant mob. These <lb/>
things are truly and sincerely deplored and depre<lb break="no"/>cated by the vast majority of French Canadians, <lb/>
and in no sense or degree reflect their real senti<lb break="no"/>ments towards their English and Protestant <lb/>
fellow-citizens. The French people are devoted to <lb/>
their church, loyal to the traditions of race and <lb/>
family, and attached to their country in a manner <lb/>
and to a degree which we would do well to emu<lb break="no"/>late. And in these things they are entitled to our <lb/>

<pb n="983" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00983.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">983</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">984</fw> 

deepest respect. Moreover, they are as peaceable, <lb/>
law-abiding, moral and kindly-disposed citizens as <lb/>
are to be found in any section of the Dominion; <lb/>
and I find that in the same measure that we respect <lb/>
their rights, feelings, opinions, and prejudices <lb/>
even, will they be found to respect ours. And just <lb/>
here, Sir, I would say that the true friends of the <lb/>
minority in the Province of Quebec are not those <lb/>
who, for any reason, seek to stir up religious or <lb/>
racial prejudices on the one side or the other, and <lb/>
that about the most dangerous foes we of that <lb/>
minority have to dread are those, from without the <lb/>
Province, who busy themselves discovering griev<lb break="no"/>ances which we do not feel to be such—or, perhaps, <lb/>
of which we know nothing,—and for which they <lb/>
are ever ready to prescribe heroic treatment. I <lb/>
would warn such to leave us to ourselves, for we <lb/>
are quite capable of protecting our own interests. <lb/>
And, for one, I have confidence enough in their <lb/>
sense of fair play and justice, to believe that, if left <lb/>
to the free exercise of their own impulses, the <lb/>
French Canadian majority will do all that in them <lb/>
lies — by legislation or otherwise— to render <lb/>
our position still more pleasant and secure. <lb/>
The French Canadians are, as a rule, quite as <lb/>
tolerant as their neighbors; and, at times, I am <lb/>
forced to the conclusion that in some things they <lb/>
are, perhaps, even a little more so. In illustration <lb/>
of this I would like to refer briefly to my own <lb/>
personal experience with them in public life; and <lb/>
my statement may, perhaps, prove a revelation to <lb/>
many to whom the idea of French domination is <lb/>
such a terrible bogey. Notwithstanding that about <lb/>
two-thirds of the electors of the County of Chateau<lb break="no"/>guay are French Roman Catholics, that con<lb break="no"/>stituency has been represented in the Parliament <lb/>
of Canada for 30 years by English Protestants, my <lb/>
late father and myself. In my own three elections, <lb/>
my opponents were Roman Catholics; yet, in no <lb/>
instance was there any attempt on the part of <lb/>
residents of the county to raise the race or religion <lb/>
cry against me, and I have yet to learn of the first <lb/>
vote in any of these contests that was influenced <lb/>
by such considerations. I am naturally very proud <lb/>
of this record of my electors; but I must go still <lb/>
further, and say that, since I have enjoyed the <lb/>
honor of a seat in this House, no French Canadian <lb/>
priest or layman has ever intimated to me, directly <lb/>
or indirectly, the faintest whisper of a suggestion <lb/>
as to the course it might he wished I should pursue <lb/>
on any public question whatsoever. Having re<lb break="no"/>peatedly sent me here as their representative, <lb/>
without exacting pledge or promise, they have left <lb/>
me absolutely to the exercise of my own discretion <lb/>
and best judgment. I am, of course, aware that <lb/>
my remarks have been a little aside the question <lb/>
actually before the House— <lb/></p> 

<p>Some <persName ref="pers:ANON1">hon. MEMBERS</persName>. No, no. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Mr. HOLTON</persName>— but the debate has taken a <lb/>
very wide range, including the matters to which I <lb/>
have reference, and I wished, before its close, to <lb/>
say at least this much as a simple matter of <lb/>
justice to my French Canadian friends. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. Mr. Speaker— <lb/></p> 

<p>Some <persName ref="pers:ANON1">hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Question, question. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. That is just what I am going <lb/>
to talk on—the question. After this long debate, <lb/>
I rely on the indulgence of the House to allow me to <lb/>
make just a few remarks. Coming from the west as <lb/>
I do, I hope I am entitled to a certain consideration, <lb/>

<cb/>

because I am very well acquainted with the people <lb/>
whose cause is now to be dealt with. I need not <lb/>
make any reference to the short Bill which has been <lb/>
offered to this House, because we have heard so <lb/>
much about it that I believe it is not now in exist<lb break="no"/>ence; at least, after all the remarks that have <lb/>
fallen from the lips of the hon. members of this <lb/>
House, I do not believe that we shall ever be called <lb/>
upon to decide upon its merits. The cause of all <lb/>
this, Mr. Speaker, is undoubtedly the agitation <lb/>
which has been aroused since last year. When the <lb/>
hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), <lb/>
the other evening, denied that he should be styled <lb/>
an agitator, I believe he did not say exactly what <lb/>
was correct, for anyone who peruses the speeches <lb/>
that hon. gentleman has made on different occa<lb break="no"/>sions must see that the expressions he used in <lb/>
those speeches are proof that he is the principal pro<lb break="no"/>moter of this agitation. I have in my hand a copy <lb/>
of a speech delivered by him in the city of Ottawa <lb/>
before the Equal Rights Association, from which I <lb/>
take the following extracts:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"We have a record for eight months, Mr. Chairman—I <lb/>
mean the Equal Rights Association—which no olitical <lb/>
party could oast of in a decade of years, and if there are <lb/>
men among us now who want to go back to their old pol<lb break="no"/>itical alliance , I say, shame on them! They ought to be sat<lb break="no"/>isfied with what we have accomplished in so short a time. <lb/>
(Loud cheers.) What have we accomplished? Go to the <lb/>
Province of Manitoba. and what do we see there? Why, <lb/>
that Government is going to deal, not only with the dual <lb/>
language question and the iniquitous Act which would <lb/>
fasten it upon them, but with Separate Schools. I had <lb/>
the honor to stand upon the same platform at Portage la <lb/>
Prairie with the Attorney General of the Province"— <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>This is an honor that I do not envy the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>—"when he announced his intention, in anticipation. of <lb/>
the action of his Government, that he would cease to sign <lb/>
the official cheque for the publication of the statutes in <lb/>
the dual language, or cease to be Attorney General. <lb/>
(Cheers.) Do you tell me that the Equal Rights Association <lb/>
had nothing to do with that?" <lb/></p> 
</quote>
<p>Nor Mr. McCarthy, I presume— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Of course, the feeling was there; the grievance exist<lb break="no"/>ed. People's minds had only to be directed to it, and the <lb/>
moment attention was drawn to it the Province of <lb/>
Manitoba rose to a man and said, 'We want no dual <lb/>
language, and away with Separate Schools as well.' <lb/>
(Applause) Let me prove what I say is correct. There <lb/>
ought to be no sympathv between Attorney General <lb/>
Martin and myself, according to old political doctrines. <lb/>
He is a Reformer and I a Conservative; therefore we <lb/>
should be sworn foes." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>But I believe both can be put in the same sack. <lb/>
The hon. gentleman came to Manitoba and he <lb/>
made a speech in the constituency represented by <lb/>
my hon. friend from Marquette (Mr. Watson). I <lb/>
did not see him in my own constituency, because <lb/>
the reception might have been pretty cold there. <lb/>
Hear what he said then: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"He was glad to notice that at last the Protestant <lb/>
minority in Quebec had waked up, and at an early date <lb/>
he hoped to have the pleasure of addressing them in <lb/>
Montreal on the question. They all had their hands full. <lb/>
In Ontario they would have to contend with the question <lb/>
of French teaching in the schools. In Manitoba they <lb/>
had the dual language to deal with, and in the North <lb/>
West they had the same question." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>This is the key: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"As soon as the work had been accomplished, they <lb/>
would then be in the position to master the same diffi<lb break="no"/>culties in the Province of Quebec." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>Well, Mr. Speaker, if, after uttering such speeches, <lb/>
the hon. gentleman cannot be called an agitator, I <lb/>
really do not know what an tutor is. This <lb/>
question of the language as we as that of other <lb/>
privileges, which certain classes of the community <lb/>

<pb n="985" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00985.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">985</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">986</fw>

enjoy under the Constitution, is a very old ques<lb break="no"/>tion: and we have had, in the course of that <lb/>
debate, the history of all those privileges; but on <lb/>
account of the similarity of the case, I will refer to <lb/>
an Address which was passed by the Legislature of <lb/>
Canada, in 1844, to the Queen, asking that the <lb/>
French language be restored to the country. This <lb/>
Address was moved by the Hon. Mr. Papineau, <lb/>
and seconded by the Hon. Mr. Moffatt, on 20th <lb/>
December, 1844, and reads as follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"That an humble Address be presented to Her Majesty, <lb/>
renewing the expression ofthe faithful attachment of this <lb/>
House to Her Majesty's person and Government. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Setting forth, that sensible of the advantages we enjoy <lb/>
from Her Majesty's care and protection, which this <lb/>
House trusts may long be continued to us under Her <lb/>
Majesty's parental sway, it is, at all times, the duty of <lb/>
this House to submit for Her Majesty's most gracious <lb/>
consideration, such matters as may have a tendency, <lb/>
with any class of Her Majesty's subjects, to diminish <lb/>
that contentment which this House is well assured. Her <lb/>
Majesty desires should exist in every portion of Her <lb/>
domains. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Representing, that the French is the native language <lb/>
of a very large class of Her Majesty's subjects in this <lb/>
Province; of this class the great mass indeed speak no <lb/>
other language. In it the largest portion of their laws <lb/>
and the books on the system of jurisprudence are <lb/>
written; their daily intercourse with each other is con<lb break="no"/>ducted: it is the language in which alone they can invoke <lb/>
the blessings of Heaven on themselves and all that are <lb/>
dear to them. A language indispensable to so many of <lb/>
Her Majesty's faithful people, cannot, they will believe, <lb/>
be viewed by their Sovereign as foreign, when used by <lb/>
them. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Stating, that Her Majesty's royal predecessors placed <lb/>
the languages spoken by the two great classes of Her <lb/>
Majesty's subjects in this Province on the same footing, <lb/>
affording, in this respect, equal justice and equal facility <lb/>
to all. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Pointing out, that this principle was never departed <lb/>
from until the Act re-uniting these Provinces was passed; <lb/>
that this House do not question that the best intentions <lb/>
and designs influenced the minds of those who enacted <lb/>
the provision which declared:— <lb/></p> 

<p>"'That all writs, proclamations, instruments for sum<lb break="no"/>moning and calling together the Legislative Council and <lb/>
Legislative Assembly for the Province of Canada, and <lb/>
for proroguing and dissolving the same; and all writs of <lb/>
summons and elections; and all writs and public instru<lb break="no"/>ments whatever, relating to the said Legislative Council <lb/>
and Legislative Assembly, or either of them, and all <lb/>
returns to such writs and instruments; and all journals <lb/>
and entries; and written and printed proceedings, of what <lb/>
nature soever, of the said Legislative Council and Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Assembly, and of each of them respectively; and <lb/>
all written or printed proceedings and reports of Com<lb break="no"/>mittees of the said Legislative Council and Legislative <lb/>
Assembly, respectively, shall be in the English language, <lb/>
only.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"Stating, that in the very first session of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, under that Act, it was indispensable to translate <lb/>
into French every public record and document; that the <lb/>
debates were not and could not, unless a portion of the <lb/>
representatives of the people were silenced, be carried on <lb/>
without its use; that in courts and judicial proceedings, it <lb/>
was found equally necessary as before the Union, and for <lb/>
every other practical purpose, it is as much used as it ever <lb/>
has been. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Urging, that the only distinction which exists, then, <lb/>
is, that the French is not permitted to be the legal <lb/>
language of Parliamentary records; a distinction of little <lb/>
value perhaps in itself,—one that cannot produce any <lb/>
beneficial result on the feelings or habits of the people <lb/>
using it; while it gives rise to a feeling among them <lb/>
injurious to the peace and tranquillity of the Province, <lb/>
namely, that this limited prescription of their language <lb/>
convoys, however undesignedly, an imputation of un<lb break="no"/>favorable distinction towards themselves. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Representing, that desirous that the hearts of all men <lb/>
in this Provmce may be joined in unity, in attachment to, <lb/>
and support of Her Majesty's person and Government, <lb/>
this House humbly petition Her Majesty to endeavor to <lb/>
remove this cause of discontent, and to recommend to <lb/>
Her Imperial Parliament, the repeal of that portion of <lb/>
the law which has given rise to it; assuring Her Majesty <lb/>
that such a course will he hailed, by Her Majesty's loyal <lb/>
Canadian people, as an additional mark of her solicitude <lb/>
for their welfare." <lb/></p>
</quote>
    
<cb/>

<p>This was the position at the time when the French <lb/>
language had been abolished, and, acting upon the <lb/>
request of the Legislature, that language was re<lb break="no"/>instated upon the Statute-books. I have here the <lb/>
translation of a despatch of Lord Elgin on the <lb/>
same subject, in which he said: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"I am very anxious to hear that you have taken <lb/>
measures to abrogate this part of the Union Act that <lb/>
impose restrictions against the use of the French lan<lb break="no"/>guage. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The delay happening in the execution of the promise <lb/>
made, I believe, by Mr. Gladstone upon this subject, is <lb/>
one of the paints urged by Mr. Papineau to promote this <lb/>
agitation. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Again I must avow that I am profoundly convinced <lb/>
of the impoilitic character of all intentions of this kind <lb/>
to denationalise the French. In general it produces the <lb/>
opposite effect to that we have in view, and inflames <lb/>
national prejudices and animosities. <lb/></p> 

<p>"But supposing it revives, what will be the conse<lb break="no"/>quences? You may be able to Americanise them, but <lb/>
believe me, with the same means you can never make <lb/>
Englishmen of the French population of the Province. <lb/></p> 

<p>"On the other hand, they feel that their religion, their <lb/>
customs, their sympathies, and their prejudices, if you <lb/>
will, are taken more into consideration and more respec<lb break="no"/>ted here than in any other part of this vast continent. <lb/>
Who would dare to say that the last arm that will raise <lb/>
the English flag on the American soil will not be that of <lb/>
a French Canadian?" <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>These are the words of Lord Elgin when it was <lb/>
asked that the French language, which had been <lb/>
taken away, should be restored. What is the <lb/>
position to-day? We have in the North—West a <lb/>
small population, it is true, but a population with <lb/>
the same rights as if they were much larger. These <lb/>
people have addressed this House in petitions which <lb/>
have been received here, and which, I must say, in <lb/>
spite of what has been said to the contrary, <lb/>
convey the expression of opinion of a large number <lb/>
of the people. I will read one of them, which is as <lb/>
follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Whereas, under the 'North-West Territories Act' <lb/>
the French is, equally with the English, an official lan<lb break="no"/>guage, the suppression of its use, as such in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, would be a flagrant injustice towards the settlers <lb/>
of French origin, who were the pioneers of this country, <lb/>
and towards those of the same race who, upon the faith <lb/>
of the Constitution and existing laws, came and <lb/>
established themselves in the North-West, and have con<lb break="no"/>tributed, with other citizens of other nationalities, to the <lb/>
development of the resources of the country. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Be it resolved, &amp;c., &amp;c. " <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>I say, therefore, there is a similarity in the two <lb/>
cases, and I hope there will be a similarity in the <lb/>
results. The hon. member for North Norfolk has <lb/>
told us this afternoon that this measure of the hon. <lb/>
member for North Simcoe is not an attack on the <lb/>
rights of any section of our community, nor on the <lb/>
constitution, because, he says, the French have no <lb/>
vested rights in the North-West. Well, Sir, <lb/>
that is a question which may be subject to a <lb/>
certain amount of discussion; but there is no <lb/>
doubt, in my mind, that there are vested rights <lb/>
for the population of the North-West, as well <lb/>
as there are for the French population of <lb/>
the Province of Quebec and other parts of <lb/>
Canada. It is admitted that the British North <lb/>
America Act has restrictive clauses whereby the <lb/>
minority are protected in their rights, and these <lb/>
rights are acknowledged in the letter of the Con<lb break="no"/>stitution. They are of divers kinds. For instance, <lb/>
as has been stated by an hon. gentleman in this <lb/>
debate, in the British North America Act there <lb/>
is a provision whereby a certain number of counties <lb/>
in the Province of Quebec, which are supposed to <lb/>
be populated by English inhabitants, will retain <lb/>
their present limits until the representatives <lb/>

<pb n="987" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00987.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">987</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">988</fw> 

of those counties decide otherwise. This was <lb/>
a sort of protection for the minority. Then <lb/>
we have protection for the minority in the <lb/>
Province of Quebec, in regard to the Protestants, <lb/>
and in regard to their schools, and in regard to <lb/>
their language, and we have protection in the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Ontario for the minority in regard to <lb/>
their schools. All through the Dominion of Can<lb break="no"/>ada we have protection in regard to Federal legis<lb break="no"/>lation, for the French language, and, in Manitoba, <lb/>
which was created by a subsequent enactment, <lb/>
protection is given to the minorities in regard to <lb/>
schools and in regard to language. But, astonish<lb break="no"/>ing to say, when the Province of Manitoba was <lb/>
organised, it was not the Catholic or the French <lb/>
minority that was protected by the enactment, be<lb break="no"/>cause at that time the Catholics and the French <lb/>
were in the majority. Therefore, the laws <lb/>
which were passed in order to give a <lb/>
constitution to the Province of Manitoba, were <lb/>
passed with the view to protect the Protestant <lb/>
and English minority. To-day the reverse exists. <lb/>
The Protestant and English-speaking population <lb/>
has increased, so that now the minority is on the <lb/>
other side. What do we see now? During the <lb/>
existence of the former state of things, did we <lb/>
ever see the majority attempt to take advan<lb break="no"/>tage of their position to take away the rights <lb/>
of the minority? No; but to-day we see that <lb/>
the majority, acting on the views which have <lb/>
been enunciated by the hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), are passing enactments <lb/>
to abolish the French language in Manitoba; <lb/>
and we are also threatened with an Act to <lb/>
abolish the Separate School system there. I may <lb/>
quote from a letter which was recently writ<lb break="no"/>ten by His Grace the Archbishop of St. Boniface <lb/>
on the subject of the Separate Schools, and also on <lb/>
the question of the dual language. It is dated the <lb/>
22nd September, 1889, and in this letter the his<lb break="no"/>tory of the negotiations which took place at that <lb/>
time between the delegates of the North-West <lb/>
Territories and the Canadian Government here is <lb/>
given in full: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"I may be permitted to review certain portions of our <lb/>
history perhaps not too well known. In 1868 two delegates <lb/>
of the Canadian Government, Sir George Cartier and the <lb/>
Hon. Wm. Macdougall, were sent to England to negotiate <lb/>
with the Imperial Government and the Hudson's Buy Co. <lb/>
for the acquisition of Rupert's Land and the North-West, <lb/>
Territories. After long eliberations, the conditions of <lb/>
the transfer were agreed to by the interested parties. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Meanwhile Earl Granville, then Secretary of State for <lb/>
the Colonies, though rejoicing at an agreement he had so <lb/>
largely contributed to secure, felt a little uneasy about <lb/>
the future condition of the old inhabitants of the country, <lb/>
and, to relieve his anxiety, addressed to Sir John Young, <lb/>
then Governor General of Canada, a despatch dated 10th <lb/>
April, 1869, from which I quote the following paragraph: <lb/></p> 

<p>"'I am sure that your Government will not forget the care <lb/>
which is due to those who must soon be exposed to new <lb/>
dangers, and in the course of settlement be dispossessed <lb/>
of the lands which they are used to enjoy as their own, or <lb/>
be confined within unwontedly narrow limits.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"'That Government, I believe, has never sought to <lb/>
evade its obligation to those whose uncertain rights and <lb/>
rude means of living are contracted by the advance of <lb/>
civilised men. I am sure that they will not do so in the <lb/>
present case, but that the old inhabitants of the country <lb/>
will be treated with such forethought and consideration <lb/>
as may preserve them from the danger of the approaching <lb/>
change, and satisfy them of the friendly interest which <lb/>
their new governors feel in their welfare.'" <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>We all know, Sir, what took place at that time <lb/>
on the banks of the Red River. I now proceed to <lb/>
quote from the same letter: <lb/></p> 
    
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"To remedy the evil, Lord Granville telegraphed <lb/>
to the Governor General, advising the issue of a procla<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

mation in the name of Her Majesty, in order to quiet the <lb/>
minds of the disturbed. In that proclamation of the 6th <lb/>
Dec., 1869, we read: <lb/></p> 

<p>"'Her Majesty commands me to state to you that she <lb/>
will always be ready through me, as her representative, <lb/>
to redress all well-founded grievances and any complaints <lb/>
that may be made or desire that may be expressed to me <lb/>
as Governor General. <lb/></p> 

<p>"By Her Majesty's authority I do therefore assure you <lb/>
that, on union with Canada, all your civil and religious <lb/>
rights will be respected.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"Lord Granville, having heard of the proclamation <lb/>
and of the good-will of the Canadian authorities, wrote <lb/>
as follows to Sir John Young on 8th January, 1870: 'I <lb/>
observe with great satisfaction the anxiety manifested by <lb/>
the Canadian Government to avoid any collison with the <lb/>
insurgents in the Red River settlement and to ex<lb break="no"/>haust all means of explanation and conciliation before <lb/>
having recourse to force.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"Unfortunately the difficulties of communication pre<lb break="no"/>vented the knowledge of the proclamation being im<lb break="no"/>parted to the interested parties at Fort Garry, and, on <lb/>
the other hand, the same difficulty of communication <lb/>
left the Canadian officials at Pembina in the greatest <lb/>
uncertainty. Expecting that the affairs were rogressing, <lb/>
as understood when they left Ottawa, they thought they <lb/>
had but to proclaim the transfer and secure by force <lb/>
their entry in the North-West. They acted in accordance, <lb/>
but the result was altogether contrary to their hopes, <lb/>
and the difficulties were increased to such a lamentable <lb/>
extent, that Lord Granville expressed his regrets to the <lb/>
Governor General in a despatch dated 20th January, 1870. <lb/>
* * * 'I much more seriously regret the proclamation <lb/>
put forth by Mr. Macdougall and the commission issued <lb/>
y him to Colonel Dennis * * * Those proceedings <lb/>
do not render Her Majesty's Government less desirous of <lb/>
the restoration of tranquillity under the authority of the <lb/>
Dominion, but they have certainly enhanced the respon<lb break="no"/>sibility of the Canadian Government.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"The trouble had assumed such a dangerous aspect <lb/>
that the Federal authorities demanded the help of men <lb/>
who could command the confidence of the disaffected. <lb/>
The Very Rev. J. B. Thibault, Vicar-General, and Colonel <lb/>
de Salaberry were sent to Fort Garry to make known to <lb/>
the people the good disposition of the Government <lb/>
towards them. A few days later, Douald A. Smith, Esq. <lb/>
(now Sir Donald) was sent as special commissioner under <lb/>
the Great Seal. The three were to act jointly With Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor Mactavish to secure the pacification of the country <lb/>
and to advise the old settlers to send delegates to <lb/>
Ottawa, to make known their grievances and desires. <lb/>
The Rev. Mr. Thibault was to distribute the proclamation <lb/>
on the 6th of December, but only after conferring on the <lb/>
subject with the Hon. Wm. Macdougall, who was sup<lb break="no"/>posed to be still at Pembina. The hon. gentleman <lb/>
ad left, so the Rev. Mr. Thibault could not see him, <lb/>
and the box containing the copies of the proclamation <lb/>
was deposited at Pembina, pending new instructions. The <lb/>
three gentlemen sent from Ottawa did their best to esta<lb break="no"/>blish confidence in Canadian rule. A convention of forty <lb/>
representatives from the different districts of the Red <lb/>
River settlement was summoned for the 25th January, 1870, <lb/>
at Fort Garry, with the object ofconsidering the subject <lb/>
of Mr. Smith's commission and to decide what should be <lb/>
the best for the welfare of the country. The convention <lb/>
assembled and, under the presidency of Judge Black, dis<lb break="no"/>cussed the affair for which they were summoned, until <lb/>
the 10th of February following, and they framed a Bill of <lb/>
Rights. <lb/></p> 

<p>"By a resolution passed unanimously, the convention <lb/>
accepted the proposition made to send a delegation. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The proceedings of the convention came to a close by <lb/>
the nomination of a Provisional Government having a <lb/>
President, a Secretary of State, &amp;c." <lb/></p> 

<p>"The President of the Provisional Government made <lb/>
known to the convention his choice of the persons he <lb/>
would appoint as delegates of the North-West and the <lb/>
Secretary of State notified these gentlemen of the choice <lb/>
the President had made of them. The following is a copy <lb/>
of the letter addressed to one of the delegates: <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:right">"'FORT GARRY, 21st Feb, 1870. <lb/></p>
    
<p>"'Rev. J. RITCHOT St. NORBERT R.R.S. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'REVEREND Sir,—I am directed to inform you that you <lb/>
have been appointed by the President of the North-West <lb/>
Territories as co-commissmner, with John Black and <lb/>
Alfred Scott, Esquires, to treat with the Government of <lb/>
the Dominion of Canada upon terms of confederation. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">"'I am. Reverend Sir, <lb/></p>
<p rendition="simple:centre">'"Your obedient servant, <lb/></p>
<p rendition="simple:right">"'(Signed) THOS. BUNN, <lb/></p>
<p rendition="simple:right">"'Secretary.' <lb/></p>

<pb n="989" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00989.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">989</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">990</fw>

<p>"Unfortunately, the troubles were not at an end; with<lb break="no"/>in a few days most regrettable circumstances occurred, <lb/>
which prevented the fulfilment of what had been decid<lb break="no"/>ed. The delegation was postponed and Bill of Rights put <lb/>
aside. <lb/></p> 

<p>"At the same time Bishop Taché was requested to pro<lb break="no"/>ceed to Fort Garry. The proclamation of the Governor <lb/>
General was handed to the prelate with request to give it <lb/>
to the insurgents, in order to determine them to make <lb/>
known their grievances, complaints or desires to the <lb/>
Governor General. Special importance was attached to <lb/>
a delegation, and to obtain it, Sir John A. Macdonald, <lb/>
in his letter to Bishop Taché, 16th February, says: 'In <lb/>
case a delegation is appointed to proceed to Ottawa, you <lb/>
can assure them that they Will be kindly received and <lb/>
their suggestions fully considered; their expenses coming <lb/>
here and returning, and while staying in Ottawa, will be <lb/>
defrayed by us.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"The new envoy, on his arrival at Fort Garry, commu<lb break="no"/>nicated to the leaders the desire of both Imperial and <lb/>
Canadian Governments with regard to a delegation; he <lb/>
insisted on the necessity of the measure. The Provisional <lb/>
Government were very diffident; the delegates themselves, <lb/>
who had been chosen a month before, were showing great <lb/>
reluctance, specially as they would not be allowed to go, <lb/>
except on the promise of laying and defending before the <lb/>
Government of Ottawa a, new Bill of Rights. After <lb/>
several days, all the details of the delegation had been <lb/>
agreed upon and the delegates received their credentials <lb/>
dated 22nd March, all three alike, with the exception of <lb/>
the names. The following is a copy of the one handed to <lb/>
Judge John Black. <lb/></p> 

<p>"To this I add the list or Bill of Rights mentioned in <lb/>
the same. The document is rather long, but as it has <lb/>
never been published before it may prove interesting to <lb/>
many as an historical document. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Thus equipped the three delegates started on their <lb/>
way to Ottawa, leaving Fort Garry on the 24th of March, <lb/> 
1870. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'To Joan BLACK Esq. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'SIR,—The President of the Provisional Government <lb/>
of Assiniboia in Council, by these presents, grants autho<lb break="no"/>rity and commission to you, John Black, Esq., jointly <lb/>
with the Rev. N. J. Ritohot and the Honorable A. Scott, <lb/>
to the end that you betake yourselves to Ottawa, in <lb/>
Canada; and that when there you should lay before the <lb/>
Canadian Parliament the list entrusted to you with the <lb/>
presents. which list contains the conditions and proposi<lb break="no"/>tions under which the people of Assiniboia would consent <lb/>
to enter into Confederation with the other Provinces of <lb/>
Canada. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'Signed, the 22nd day of March, in the year of Our <lb/>
Lord, one thousand eight hundred and seventy. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">"'By Order, <lb/></p>
<p rendition="simple:right">"'(Signed) THOMAS BUNN, <lb/></p>
<p rendition="simple:right">"'Secretary of State. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'Seat of Government, <lb/></p>
<p>"'Winnipeg, Assiniboia.' <lb/></p>
<p rendition="simple:centre">"'BILL OF RIGHTS. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'Prepared by the Executive of the Provisional Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and handed over to the North-West delegates. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'1. That the Territory of the North-West enter into the <lb/>
Confederation of the Dominion of Canada as a province, <lb/>
With all the privileges common with all the different <lb/>
provinces In the Dominion. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'That this province be governed: <lb/></p> 

<p>"'(1.) By a Lieutenant Governor, appointed by the <lb/>
Governor General of Canada. <lb/>
"'(2.) By a Senate. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'(3.) By a Legislature chosen by the people, with a <lb/>
responsible Ministry. <lb/></p> 

<p>"2. That, until such time as the increase of the popu<lb break="no"/>lation in this country entitle us to a greater number, we <lb/>
have two representatives in the Senate and four in the <lb/>
Commons of Canada. <lb/></p> 

<p>"3. That in entering the Confederation, the Province of <lb/>
the North—West be completely free from the public debt of <lb/>
Canada; and it called upon to assume a part of the said <lb/>
dhebt of Canada, that it be only after having received <lb/>
from Canada the same amount for which the said Province <lb/>
of the North-West should be held responsible. <lb/>
  " '4. That the annual sum of $80,000 be allotted by the <lb/>
Dominion ot Canada to the Legislature ofthe Province of <lb/>
the North-West <lb/>
"'5. That all properties, rights and privileges enjoyed <lb/>
by us up to this day be respected, and that the recognition <lb/>
and settlement of customs, usages and rivileges be left <lb/>
exclusively to the decision of the Local Legislature. <lb/>
"'6. That this country be submitted to no direct taxa-<lb break="yes"/>ion, except such as may be imposed by the Local Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture for municipal or other local purposes. <lb/></p>

<cb/>

<p>"'7. That the schools be separate, and that the public <lb/>
money for schools be distributed among the different <lb/>
religious denominations in proportion to their respective <lb/>
populations, according to the system of the Province of <lb/>
Quebec. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'8. That the determination of the qualifications of <lb/>
members for the Parliament of the Province or for the <lb/>
Parliament of Canada be left to the Local Legislature. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'9. That in this Province, with the exception of the <lb/>
Indians, who are neither civilised nor settled, every man <lb/>
  having attained the age of 21 years, and every foreigner <lb/>
being a British subiect after having resided three years <lb/>
in this country, and being possessed of a house, be entitled <lb/>
to vote at the elections for the members ofthc Local Legis<lb break="no"/>lature and of the Canadian Parliament, and that every <lb/>
foreigner other than a British subject, having resided <lb/>
here during the same period and being proprietor of a <lb/>
house, he likewise entitled to vote on condition of taking <lb/>
the oath of allegiance. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'It is understood that this article is subject to amend<lb break="no"/>ment by the Local Legislature exclusively. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'10. That the bargain of the Hudson Bay Company <lb/>
with respect to the transfer of government of this coun<lb break="no"/>try to the Dominion of Canada never have in any case an <lb/>
effect prejudicial to the rights of the North—West. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'11. That the Local Legislature of this Province have <lb/>
full control over all the lands ofthe North—West. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'12. That a commission of engineers appointed by Can<lb break="no"/>ada explore the various districtsof the North-West, and <lb/>
lay before the Local Legislature within the space of five <lb/>
years a report of the mineral wealth of the country. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'13. That treaties be concluded between Canada and <lb/>
the different Indian tribes of the North-West at the re<lb break="no"/>quest and with the co-operation of the Local Legislature. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'14. That. an uninterrupted steam communication from <lb/>
Lake Superior to Fort Garry be guaranteed to be com<lb break="no"/>pleted within the space of five years, as well as the con<lb break="no"/>struction of a railway connecting the American railway <lb/>
as soon as the latter reaches the international boundary. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'15. That all public buildings and constructions be at <lb/>
the cost of the Canadian exchequer. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'16. That both the English and French languages be <lb/>
common in the Legislature and in the courts; and that all <lb/>
public documents, as well as the Acts of the Legislature, <lb/>
be published in both languages. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'17. That the Lieutenant Governor to be appointed for <lb/>
the Province ofthe North-West be familiar with both the <lb/>
English and French languages. <lb/></p> 

<p>"'18. That the judge oft e Supreme Court speak the <lb/>
English and French languages.   <lb/></p> 

<p>"'19. That all debts contracted by the Provisional Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the Territory of the North-West, now called <lb/>
Assiniboia, in consequence of the illegal and inconsiderate <lb/>
measures adopted by Canadian officials to bring about a <lb/>
civil war in our midst, be paid out of the Dominion <lb/>
Treasury, and that none of the Provisional Government <lb/>
or any of those acting under them, be in any way held <lb/>
liable or responsible with regard to the movement or any <lb/>
of the actions which led to the present negotiations.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"While all this was going on on the banks of the Red <lb/>
River of the North-West, great anxiety and uneasiness <lb/>
continued to prevail in the Colonial Office in Downing <lb/>
street and at Ottawa; numerous despatches and telegrams <lb/>
were exchanged between the two. The following will give <lb/>
an idea of what was desired, hoped or feared:— <lb/></p> 

<p>"On the 5th of March Lord Granville telegraphed to <lb/>
Sir John Young: 'Her Majesty's Government will give <lb/>
proposed military assistance, provided reasonable terms <lb/>
are granted to the Red River settlers.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"On the 17th of March the same to the same: 'Let me <lb/>
know by telegram when you know delegates have started <lb/>
from Fort Garry.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"Sir F. Rogers, Under-Secretary for the Colonies <lb/>
writes on the 22nd March: 'Troops should not be employed <lb/>
in forcing the sovereignty ofCanada on the population of <lb/>
Red River should they refuse to admit it.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"On the 4th of April, the Governor General conveyed <lb/>
by telegram to Earl Granville startling information: <lb/>
'Smith came here on Saturday from Fort Garry with bad <lb/>
news. A Canadian called Scott was, by Riel's orders, <lb/>
tried by court—martial and shot, with the View it is sup<lb break="no"/>posed, of compromising Riel's followers before Taché had <lb/>
arrived. They say the delegates are coming, but it is <lb/>
quite clear Riel will yield to nothing but force. Things <lb/>
now look, I think, very bad.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"On the 7th of April, the same telegraphed to the <lb/>
same: 'Last of the delegates is expected at St. Paul on <lb/>
Thursday the 14th, the others arrived there to-day, and <lb/>
may reach Ottawa on be turday the 9th.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"Distressing as the news was, Earl Granville had still <lb/>
confidence in the negotiations he had so constantly urged; <lb/>
on the 9th of the same month he telegraphed to the Gov <lb/>

<pb n="991" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00991.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">991</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">992</fw> 

ernor General: 'Let me know as soon as you can by <lb/>
telegram result of negotiations with Red River delegates.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"It is evident from the above documents that Her <lb/>
Majesty's Government had no desire to impose by force <lb/>
the sovereignty of Canada on the settlers of Assniboia, <lb/>
but that they were exceedingly anxious of a peaceable <lb/>
settlement through negotiations with the delegates. No <lb/>
need to add that all this was said and done in perfect <lb/>
good faith, on the part of Earl Granville, and that Her <lb/>
Majesty's Government intended to bind themselves to <lb/>
protect and safeguard the agreement, secured not only <lb/>
with their sanction, but at their explicit and repeated re<lb break="no"/>quest. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The two first delegates arrived at Ottawa on the <lb/>
11th; in spite of what had been said and promised, they <lb/>
were arrested. This incident, which could have caused <lb/>
serious complications, was learned with regret by Lord <lb/>
Granville, who telegraphed to the Governor General: <lb/>
'Was arrest of delegates authorised by the Canadian <lb/>
Government? Send full information by telegram.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"Sir John Young answered the next day; 'Arrest of <lb/>
delegates was not authorised by the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"On the 23rd of the same month of April, Earl Gran<lb break="no"/>ville thus informed the Governor General: 'Canadian <lb/>
Government to accept decision of Her Majesty's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment on all portions of the settlers' Bill of Rights.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"The very same day the negotiations began at Ottawa. <lb/>
Sir John A. Macdonald and Sir George Cartier were <lb/>
a pointed by the Canadian Government to treat with the <lb/>
three delegates of the North-West. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The first interview was merely preliminary. On <lb/>
Monday the 25th, the two Ministers and the three dele<lb break="no"/>gates met again; the delegates insisted on a written <lb/>
acknowledgment of their official position and declared <lb/>
that the list or Bill of Rights they had brought with them <lb/>
was the only basis on which they were authorised to treat <lb/>
with the Government. Objections were made, but after <lb/>
a long discussion, it was agreed that the written acknow<lb break="no"/>ledgment would be given next day, and the list be pro<lb break="no"/>duced by the delegates. <lb/></p> 

<p>"On the 26th, at the next meeting the promised letter <lb/>
was given by the Ministers and the List of Rights pro<lb break="no"/>duced by the delegates, and, practically, the official nego<lb break="no"/>tiations began this day and lasted until the 3rd of May, <lb/>
when the principal points on the List of Rights were agreed <lb/>
upon, leaving some details for further consideration. <lb/></p> 

<p>"It is not generally known that the new Bill of Rights <lb/>
was the basis of negotiations, but it is nevertheless the <lb/>
case, and many points granted, as expressed in the Mani<lb break="no"/>toba Act, were demanded in no other document, except <lb/>
on the List of Rights presented by the delegates. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The first article is a very important feature of this <lb/>
new Bill of Rights. It contains the demand for the es<lb break="no"/>tablishment of a Province covering the whole North-<lb break="yes"/>West, with all the privileges and governing machinery <lb/>
appertaining to other Provinces, including a responsible <lb/>
Government. This met with strong objections, but at <lb/>
last was conceded on the condition of reducing the new <lb/>
Province to very small proportions. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Article II also caused a long discussion; it asked for <lb/>
the control of all the lands of the North-West by the Local <lb/>
Legislature. To this, both the Imperial and Canadian <lb/>
authorities refused to accede, but to condone for this re<lb break="no"/>fusal they gave to the children of the half-breed inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants of the country one million four hundred thousand <lb/>
acres of land, which had not been asked for, and with the <lb/>
understanding that by-and-bye they would also give some <lb/>
lands to the parents of those children and to other old <lb/>
settlers. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The question of separate schools, as demanded in the <lb/>
7th article of the List of Rights, was taken into con<lb break="no"/>sideration; the delegates were promised that the would <lb/>
not only have the benefit of the provisions of the 'British <lb/>
North America Act,' but they might rest assured and <lb/>
might assure the people of the Red River, that separate <lb/>
schools would be guaranteed to them. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The recognition of the use of the French language, as <lb/>
an official language,was conceded as expressed in the 16th <lb/>
article of the List of Rights, with the promise that at<lb break="no"/>tention would be paid to the demands of the 17th and <lb/>
18th articles, as in fact it has been done, if not complete<lb break="no"/>ly, at least enough to satisfy the interested parties. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The whole list having been examined, accepted, modi<lb break="no"/>fied or rejected to the satisfaction of the negotiating <lb/>
parties, the Governor General telegraphed to Earl Gran<lb break="no"/>ville on the 3rd ofMay: 'Negotiations with the delegates <lb/>
closed satisfactorily.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"The negotiations had been asked for, they had been <lb/>
urged both by the he Imperial and Federal authorities, the <lb/>
Government of Her Majesty had exacted from the Cana<lb break="no"/>dian Government the acceptance by the latter of the <lb/>
decision of the former on all points of the Bill of Rights. <lb/>

<cb/>

They had sent an official envoy to Ottawa to watch the <lb/>
conference, and when it is announced that the negotia<lb break="no"/>tions are closed satisfactorily it must mean that the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Government is satisfied that its views on this sub<lb break="no"/>ject will be carried out, and that no inferior authority <lb/>
would have power to disturb them. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Lord Granville, in one of his despatches, says: 'I am <lb/>
glad to learn that the proceedings adopted against the <lb/>
Rev. Mr. Ritchot and Mr. Scott were promptly disposed <lb/>
of, and had not been renewed: and I take this oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of expressing the satisfaction with which I have <lb/>
learned from your telegram of the 3rd inst., that the <lb/>
Canadian Government and the delegates have come to <lb/>
an understanding as to the terms on which the settlement <lb/>
of the Red River should be admitted into the Dominion.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"All this is previous to the Manitoba Act; it is a treaty <lb/>
between contracting parties placed on a certain footing <lb/>
of equality, as the Government of Her Majesty had de<lb break="no"/>clared 'troops should not be employed in forcing the <lb/>
sovereignty of Canada on the population of the Red <lb/>
River, should they refuse to admit it.'" <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>These are the conditions upon which all that <lb/>
territory entered into the Confederation, and, <lb/>
therefore, when the hon. member for North Norfolk <lb/>
(Mr. Charlton) said there are no vested rights, I <lb/>
say there are, and those rights are contained in <lb/>
the agreement, or in what I might call the treaty <lb/>
which was entered into between the authorities of <lb/>
this country and the people of the North-West <lb/>
through their representatives. <lb/></p> 

<p>Some <persName ref="pers:ANON1">hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Question. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. I think I am dealing with <lb/>
the question. This question of the dual language <lb/>
has been discussed in the North-West Legislature. <lb/>
We have had here an address from that noble body <lb/>
which I will not read because it is already on record. <lb/>
That address was prepared by a sub-committee of <lb/>
the Council, and upon receiving that address the <lb/>
Council had a debate. The chairman of the com<lb break="no"/>mittee who prepared the address, laid it on the <lb/>
Table, and a short debate followed. From the <lb/>
local paper there I quote the following:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Mr. Justice Rouleau asked hon. gentlemen to give <lb/>
their reasons for wishing to abolish the dual language <lb/>
which had been in their Constitution for so many years. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Mr. Mitchell also asked for reasons. What harm <lb/>
had the French language done? What objection had <lb/>
there been to it? It was a little expensive, but the <lb/>
expensive way was the best. They were asking for a law to <lb/>
deprive the oldest resldents of the country—the pioneers <lb/>
—from reading their own language. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Mr. Oliver supported the contention of the judge. <lb/>
As a matter of courtesy, the members who introduced <lb/>
this question should give an explanation of their rea<lb break="no"/>sons." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>Well, Sir, we have the explanation of the <lb/>
chairman of that committee in bringing down that <lb/>
report. <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Mr. Cayley went over the history of the enactment of <lb/>
the section imposing the dual language in the North <lb/>
West, it having been put in at the instance of Senator <lb/>
Girard fourteen years ago. The discussion in his own dis<lb break="no"/>trict was to one effect, that the continuance of the dual <lb/>
language in the North-West was unnecessary. When a <lb/>
question of this sort, which might hurt the feelings of <lb/>
some of the residents of the country, came up, it was best <lb/>
that members should not state all their private reasons." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>This is the reason given—that is to say, no reason <lb/>
at all was given because it was assumed that it <lb/>
would not well to state the private reasons. So <lb/>
this document, which has been termed an address <lb/>
of the North-West Council to this House, was <lb/>
decided upon not for public purposes, not for the <lb/>
benefit of the public at large, but for private <lb/>
reasons that could not be stated publicly; and we <lb/>
are today called upon to act upon the request of <lb/>
men who pretend to have reasons, but private <lb/>
reasons such as cannot be stated publicly. Mr. <lb/>
Thorborn said: <lb/></p>

<pb n="993" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00993.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">993</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">994
</fw>
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"It was stated as the opinion of the assembly that the <lb/>
sentiment of the people was against the continuance of <lb/>
the section. This was very signally acknowledged by the <lb/>
Executive, on opening the session, by his not reading the <lb/>
speech in French as well as English." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>There we find a reason at last: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Mr. Mitchell again asked what harm the dual <lb/>
language did. They proposed to take away a right from <lb/>
a certain class of the people. There was no common sense <lb/>
in it." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>This is the debate. But no reasons were given, no <lb/>
more reasons were given than those which we see <lb/>
in the reports of the proceedings of that Council. <lb/>
This address was passed, it is true, but we have a <lb/>
very long and able speech made by Mr. Justice <lb/>
Rouleau. Unfortunately that gentleman is only <lb/>
    an <hi rendition="simple:italic">ex-officio</hi> member of the Council, and could <lb/>
not give his vote against the address that was <lb/>
presented at the time. Now, I wish to refer, <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">en passant</hi>, to some of the judge's remarks. <lb/>
It appears that the hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe has some admirers in the North-West <lb/>
Territories; that he has created a certain school, <lb/>
which, however, is no school at all. He has <lb/>
followers there—anti-Frenchmen. When His <lb/>
Excellency the Governor General visited that <lb/>
country last summer, at Calgary they built an <lb/>
arch over the roadway opposite the hotel, and, <lb/>
of course, the most appropriate motto that could <lb/>
    be put on that arch was the motto of His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency's coat-of-arms—<hi rendition="simple:italic">sans changer</hi>. But that <lb/>
was French, and the people had the greatest <lb/>
objection to put a French motto in the streets of <lb/>
Calgary. So they went on and translated it, and <lb/>
put up the words "no change." But as the arch <lb/>
happened to be opposite a hotel, the poor hotel-<lb break="yes"/>keeper did not have a single customer on that day, <lb/>
because everybody was afraid to go in there for <lb/>
fear that they would get no change. But here is <lb/>
something extraordinary, Mr. Speaker, though not <lb/>
a similar case, which happened a few years ago in <lb/>
the Province of Ontario, in a little town called— <lb/>
shall I name it?—St. Thomas. There is in that <lb/>
town a young ladies' school, and although they <lb/>
may be admirers of the hon. member, still they <lb/>
love the French language in that institution. <lb/>
Of course, they had to have a motto for their <lb/>
school. It was somewhat of an ambitious motto, <lb/>
I dare say, and, perhaps, it well became this in<lb break="no"/>stitution, because it was a. very good institution. <lb/>
Of course, an institution, like a nobleman, must <lb/>
have a motto, if nothing else. They had to have <lb/>
a motto from some other language than the Eng<lb break="no"/>lish, and without having the fear of the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for North Simcoe before their eyes, they <lb/>
adopted—not a Latin or a Greek motto—but a <lb/>
French motto, because all great men have French <lb/>
mottoes, and in that respect they differ from my <lb/>
hon. friend, whose motto is anti-French. Well, <lb/>
they selected a sentence in English, which, trans<lb break="no"/>lated into French, would make a splendid motto. <lb/>
Their idea. was to convey the impression that their <lb/>
Institution was second to none in the country; <lb/>
and they took the two shortest words they could <lb/>
find in the English language and translated them <lb/>
Into French. They took "second to none," which <lb/>
means "never behind," and so they looked up a <lb/>
    French dictiona and found that a literal transla<lb break="no"/>tion of "never behind" was <hi rendition="simple:italic">jamais en derruère</hi>. <lb/>
Well, Sir, when I was called away from the ques-<lb break="yes"/>ion a little while ago, I was the history of <lb/>
that address presented by the North-West Council. <lb/>

<cb/>

There is a point upon which I wish to call the atten<lb break="no"/>tion of this House. We have been asked to trust to <lb/>
the majority of the people of the North-West for <lb/>
the future of our interests, to trust them for the pre<lb break="no"/>servation of our rights, for the maintenance of our <lb/>
religion, our schoo s, and even our language. Now, <lb/>
the other day, in voting in favor of the amendment <lb/>
of my hon. friend from Berthier (Mr. Beausoleil), <lb/>
we refused to accept the suggestion that had been <lb/>
made by the hon. member for West Assiniboia (Mr. <lb/>
Davin). I wish to show you that we were perfectly <lb/>
right in refusing to accept the amemlment of <lb/>
the member for West Assiniboia, and in accepting <lb/>
the amendment of the hon. member for Berthier, <lb/>
because the history of what has taken place in <lb/>
Manitoba is certainly not satisfactory, and is a <lb/>
proof that if in the future we are treated in the same <lb/>
manner as we have been in the past, we are not so <lb/>
certain about the safety of our rights and interests. <lb/>
As I told you a little While ago, under the Consti<lb break="no"/>tution of Manitoba we have rights in regard to our <lb/>
language and to our schools, and those rights and <lb/>
claims cannot be interfered with. Moreover, at the <lb/>
time of Confederation, our then Lieutenant Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor, whom I am glad to see on the floor of this <lb/>
House, Sir Adams Archibald, took every precaution <lb/>
to prevent friction between the two classes of <lb/>
the community who were then very excited after <lb/>
the little rebellion that had taken place. <lb/>
The then Lieutenant Governor gave to each class <lb/>
of the community a fair, just and proper repre<lb break="no"/>sentation. Although the French had a small <lb/>
majority and the Catholics a small majority, the <lb/>
Lower House—and we had two Houses—was divid<lb break="no"/>ed into 24 constituencies and sub-divided, so that <lb/>
12 members were given to the English-speaking <lb/>
Protestant community, and 12 members who could <lb/>
be returned by Roman Catholics, whether Irish, <lb/>
English or French. The Upper House was com<lb break="no"/>posed of seven members, and the Roman Catholics <lb/>
were given a majority of one on account of a <lb/>
majority of people of that faith in the Province. <lb/>
Thus the then Lieutenant Governor dealt with the <lb/>
question in a liberal-minded manner, to the satis<lb break="no"/>faction of every class. Later on we were asked to <lb/>
abolish our Legislative Council. The Council was <lb/>
the only safeguard we possessed after the influx of <lb/>
population had taken place, and the Catholic and <lb/>
rench population had een outnumbered, and if the <lb/>
Council had been retained the rights of the major<lb break="no"/>ity could never be endangered. A debate took <lb/>
place in the Legislature on that proposition. In <lb/>
that debate the French members complained <lb/>
strongly that they were asked to vote away the <lb/>
only safeguard they possessed—the Upper House. <lb/>
What took place at that time? The English-speak<lb break="no"/>ing members came to the front, and said: We must <lb/>
do away with the Upper House because the Federal <lb/>
Government, led by the Hon. Mr. Mackenzie, in<lb break="no"/>sisted upon a reduction of the expenses of the <lb/>
Administration and insisted on the abolition <lb/>
of the Upper House, and if the request is not <lb/>
acceded to we will not get the better terms <lb/>
which are so much require. The French mem<lb break="no"/>bers accepted the proposition, on the promise that <lb/>
on no occasion would they have reason to complain <lb/>
of any attempt on the part of the majority to in<lb break="no"/>terfere with the rights of the minority. I have <lb/>
extracts from speeches made at that time. This <lb/>
is what Mr. W. F. Luxton, who was then member <lb/>
for Rockwood, said: <lb/></p>

<pb n="995" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00995.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">995</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">996</fw> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"There were some questions of settlements which lay <lb/>
close to the hearts of the French people, and he could <lb/>
assure them that, notwithstanding the movements of the <lb/>
member for Kildonan (John Sutherland), the English <lb/>
members would not ruthlessly deal with these if the <lb/>
French representatives were sufficiently patriotic to sup<lb break="no"/>port the measure before the House. They would recog<lb break="no"/>nise their generosity and not forget it." <lb/></p>
    </quote>
    
    <p>
Another member, quoting from the late Francis <lb/>
Evans Cornish, who was then representing High <lb/>
Bluff, a distinguished advocate, and at one time <lb/>
Mayor of Winnipeg, sitting in his seat and speak<lb break="no"/>ing on the same question, said: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"He believed the old settlers and the French would <lb/>
make common cause if their rights were infringed upon, <lb/>
and he could assure them when the Canadian party be<lb break="no"/>came the very great majority it would not be found <lb/>
oppressive." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    <p>In its issue of the 12th February, 1876, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Free <lb/>
Press</hi> gave the reasons why the French members <lb/>
voted in favor of the abolition of the Legislative <lb/>
Council: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"0n the profession of liberality made by the English-<lb break="yes"/>speaking representatives upon the floor of the House, <lb/>
under these circumstances, every French member of the <lb/>
Assembly voted in favor of the measure." <lb/></p>
    </quote>
    
    <p>
This is a treaty entered into between the French <lb/>
and English-speaking members of the Legislative <lb/>
Assembly of the Province of Manitoba, when the <lb/>
French members were asked to surrender their right <lb/>
to the Legislative Council, which was their safe<lb break="no"/>guard, and to trust to the future, relying on the <lb/>
promises of the hon. members who were then re<lb break="no"/>presenting the English-speaking portion of the <lb/>
population. What has been the result? To—day <lb/>
legislation is being passed, in that very Legislature, <lb/>
unanimously passed, by the English—speaking mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the House, to abolish the French language, <lb/>
and they are going to abolish the Separate Schools <lb/>
in the face of the agreement solemnly entered upon <lb/>
in the Legislature by their predecessors. In the <lb/>
face of that fact, can it be matter of surprise that <lb/>
we should be reluctant to accept anything less <lb/>
than the fullest guarantee that this House can <lb/>
give? But we have trusted the future before, and <lb/>
we are willing to trust it again; but I hope we <lb/>
will never have the same history repeated as that <lb/>
which we have to record with regard to the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Manitoba. It may be said: You will <lb/>
not meet with the same fate in the North-West. <lb/>
I hope such may be the case; but as all sorts of <lb/>
extraneous matters have been brought into the <lb/>
        discussion, I will quote a paragraph from a news<lb break="no"/>paper. The Moosomin <hi rendition="simple:italic">Courier</hi> on 5th September, <lb/>
1889, published an article headed "One people, <lb/>
one Language." It said: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Are they [the Roman Catholics] a superior kind of <lb/>
people from Protestants, that they hold themselves aloof <lb/>
by having separate schools.   <lb/></p> 

<p>"To private schools no one can object, but we most <lb/>
emphatically protest against separate schools. being <lb/>
maintained by the Government, or any denomination <lb/>
other than Protestants. Our motto is: 'One People, One <lb/>
Country, One Religion.'" <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>This is the kind of literature that is being circu<lb break="no"/>lated by the newspapers in the North-West. <lb/>
Knowing these facts, are we to be blamed if <lb/>
we resist any attempt to deprive us of what <lb/>
we consider and claim to be our vested rights, <lb/>
and if we ask this House, in which we have <lb/>
perfect confidence, not to delegate its power to <lb/>
the Legislatures, which do not view matters in <lb/>
the same light as we view them? I believe we <lb/>
should be t ankful to the hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), for having brought on this <lb/>

<cb/>

debate. We are already beginning to feel the good <lb/>
results that will come out of it. I am to-day in <lb/>
receipt of a newspaper published in Winnipeg, a <lb/>
paper that has always advocated the abolition of <lb/>
the French language in the Province of Manitoba— <lb/>
    the Manitoba <hi rendition="simple:italic">Free Press</hi>. In the course of an article <lb/>
it says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"In Manitoba we have abolished,as we think,the use of <lb/>
the French language and are now proceeding against <lb/>
Separate Schools. From the light of the recent debate <lb/>
at Ottawa. it would not seem so sure that we have been <lb/>
right in assuming to settle the language question alone." <lb/></p>
    </quote>
    <p>
This is the beginning of the result that we are <lb/>
going to derive from this debate, and therefore I am <lb/>
not sorry that it has taken place. I shall lay aside <lb/>
several matters that I intended to bring before the <lb/>
House, and I will conclude my remarks by stating <lb/>
that what has been said by some hon. gentlemen <lb/>
to the effect that the French language was not <lb/>
recognised in the United States was erroneously <lb/>
so stated. I take from "The American Statute <lb/>
Law" the following:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The language taught in the schools is, by the Consti<lb break="no"/>tutions of three States, to be English; but in Louisiana <lb/>
the instruction may be given in French." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>From the same book, "The American Statute <lb/>
Law," I take the following:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"By the constitutions of four States the laws, public <lb/>
records and written legislative and judicial roceedings <lb/>
shall be promulgate, and preserved in the English <lb/>
language only. But in Colorado, laws are also to be pub<lb break="no"/>lished in English and German, and in Louisiana the <lb/>
Legislature may provlde for the publication of laws in <lb/>
the French language, and that Judicial advertisements in <lb/>
certain designated districts may be made in French. So <lb/>
in Missouri, certain charters, &amp;c., in the German <lb/>
language. So in Maryland, proposed amendments to the <lb/>
constitution, in German." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>We see from this that there are only four states <lb/>
where the English language is at all the official <lb/>
language. From this authority (which, being the <lb/>
statute law of the United States, cannot be ques<lb break="no"/>tioned), we can see what takes place with regard <lb/>
to the language question ri ht across the lines; <lb/>
the hon. member for North Norfolk (Mr. Charlton) <lb/>
to the contrary notwithstanding. I could cite <lb/>
some other instances to prove the law in the <lb/>
United States with regard to this matter, but I <lb/>
think this ought to be sufficient to convince <lb/>
hon. gentlemen. Let me just quote something <lb/>
with regard to the French language in the Island <lb/>
of Jersey. So much has been said about the other <lb/>
British colonies that I will not refer to them. I <lb/>
will quote from a book written by Abraham J. <lb/>
LeCras, entitled "The Laws, Customs and Privi<lb break="no"/>leges, and their Administration, in the Island of <lb/>
Jersey," as follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">Language</hi>—Notwithstanding English is now generally <lb/>
spoken in the Island, the language of the State and of <lb/>
the Gourt is a French dialect peculiar to ancient Nor<lb break="no"/>mandy, and which operates very much to the prejudice <lb/>
of English suitors, whose causes are usually the most <lb/>
important that are brought before the local tribunals, <lb/>
because a sworn interpreter is not appointed. In the <lb/>
        case of Godfray on the prosecution of the Crown <hi rendition="simple:italic">v</hi>. <lb/>
Robertson (1838), on the demand of the defendant that <lb/>
the said Godfray, who was a witness, should give his <lb/>
deposition in English, as the former did not understand <lb/>
French, the Court (Bisson and E. Nicolle, on the con<lb break="no"/>clusions of the Attorney General overrul the demand, <lb/>
and decided that it was only Her Majesty in Council <lb/>
who could alter the form of proceeding in this bailiwick." <lb/></p>
    </quote>
    
    <p>
We see from this that even in an English colony <lb/>
the French language alone is official. The hon. <lb/>
member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) has <lb/>
read some telegrams which he has said to have <lb/>
received from the North-West, where assemblies <lb/>

<pb n="997" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00997.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">997</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">998</fw>

or meetings have been held, declaring that the <lb/>
mass of the people were in favor of the abolition of <lb/>
the French language. I am in receipt of an address <lb/>
from Qu'Appelle, dated the 7th of February, 1890, <lb/>
in which it is stated (I translate from the original <lb/>
French): <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Please accept profession of our profound gratitude <lb/>
for the opposition you have given to the Act concerning <lb/>
the abolition of the French language in the North-West <lb/>
Territories and for your vigorous defence of our rights. <lb/>
&amp;c., &amp;c." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>I shall not take time to read the whole document. <lb/>
This is signed by 217 people; and amongst those <lb/>
who signed I find the names of J. B. Farrell, C. B. <lb/>
Spencer, W. H. Finnerty, J. A. Crooks, J. R. <lb/>
Oliver, and others. About one-third of the names <lb/>
are of English, Scotch, Irish, and even German-<lb break="yes"/>speaking persons, and they congratulate me on the <lb/>
stand I took when the first reading of this Bill <lb/>
was proposed to this House. Here are 217 names <lb/>
of opponents to this Bill from one locality alone; <lb/>
so that the unanimity which we have been told <lb/>
existed in the North-West in favor of the abolition <lb/>
of the French language does not exist. I have to <lb/>
thank the House, Mr. Speaker, for the attention <lb/>
which has been paid to my remarks; and I am <lb/>
sorry that I have felt it my duty to detain you so <lb/>
long. I have again to express the hope that the <lb/>
proposition made by the hon. Minister of Justice <lb/>
will be accepted. I, for my part, accept it as a <lb/>
compromise, although I do not admit that this <lb/>
House has the right to ask us to deprive the French <lb/>
people of the North-West Territories of a single <lb/>
portion of what I consider to be their rights. <lb/>
Yet, in order to promote the peace and tran<lb break="no"/>quillity of this Dominion, I accept this amendment <lb/>
as a compromise, and I hope that the House will <lb/>
unanimously endorse it. I trust that in the future <lb/>
we shall have no reason to complain of the position <lb/>
we have taken to-day. <lb/></p> 

<p>It being six o'clock, the Speaker left the chair. <lb/></p> 
</div>
    <div type="debate">
    
<head rendition="simple:centre">After Recess.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:LANG1">Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN</persName>. I would suggest, <lb/>
as this is the seventh day on which we have been <lb/>
discussing the measure which was before the House <lb/>
this afternoon, that the consideration of private <lb/>
Bills should be postponed until Monday. All the <lb/>
members in town having charge of private Bills <lb/>
consent to this postponement. I, therefore, propose <lb/>
that we should go back to the Order of this after<lb break="no"/>noon. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MITC2">Mr. MITCHELL</persName>. I have much pleasure in <lb/>
supporting that. I think it is a very reasonable <lb/>
proposition. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BEAU13">Mr. BEAUSOLEIL</persName>. I desire, with the permis<lb break="no"/>sion of the House, to offer a few remarks in <lb/>
explanation of the reasons why I cannot support <lb/>
the amendment proposed by the hon. Minister of <lb/>
Justice, and seconded by the hon. Secretary of <lb/>
State. It has been stated, in justification of that <lb/>
motion, that it is a compromise between two con<lb break="no"/>tending parties whose extreme views could not be <lb/>
reconciled. But I have not heard that the party <lb/>
most interested in this uestion, that is to say, <lb/>
the French pulation o the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, have been consulted or represented in this <lb/>
compromise; on the contrary, it appears that <lb/>
the two wings of the Government party in this <lb/>
House, French and English, have agreed to settle <lb/>

<cb/>

their differences by sacrificing the rights and privi<lb break="no"/>leges of the French pulation of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West. To effect that object, they agree upon this <lb/>
compromise amendment, which professes to main<lb break="no"/>tain the rights and privileges of the French-speak<lb break="no"/>ing people in the old Provinces of Canada; but <lb/>
the rights and privileges of the French people <lb/>
of the North-West are to be left to the tender <lb/>
mercies of a council, which, according to the hon. <lb/>
member for North Simcoe, has intimated to the <lb/>
Lieutenant Governor that if he should dare to speak <lb/>
French in their presence, they would leave the <lb/>
Chamber in a body. A compromise proposed under <lb/>
such circumstances I cannot accept; I cannot <lb/>
agree that under one pretence or another the con<lb break="no"/>stitutional rights of the minority in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West should be sacrificed. Some people are will<lb break="no"/>ing that those interests should be sacrificed in the <lb/>
name of Provincial rights or Provincial autonomy; <lb/>
but there is no question of Provincial rights or <lb/>
Provincial autonomy in the resent instance. <lb/>
There are no Provinces in the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories which are under the jurisdiction of the <lb/>
Dominion Parliament, and are to a great extent <lb/>
governed by laws enacted by this Legislature. But <lb/>
even were Provincial rights in question, there <lb/>
are some rights which have been put above all <lb/>
others—above even Provincial rights—by the <lb/>
Imperial Parliament; these are the rights of <lb/>
minorities. Now, it is proposed by this com<lb break="no"/>promise amendment, to leave the rights of the <lb/>
minority in the North-West to the control of <lb/>
the Legislative Assembly there after the next <lb/>
general election. If that course is the right one, <lb/>
how is it that the Imperial Parliament, in the <lb/>
Act of 1867, did not leave to the Parliament of <lb/>
Canada the right of deciding whether one language <lb/>
or two shoud be spoken in this chamber, and <lb/>
whether its proceedings and records should be <lb/>
printed in one or two languages? And how is it that <lb/>
the same control was not given to the Legislature of <lb/>
the Province of Quebec over the language of its <lb/>
proceedings and records? The fact that this sub<lb break="no"/>ject, so far as it concerned the Dominion and the <lb/>
Province of Quebec, was settled by the Imperial <lb/>
Parliament in the Confederation Act, proves that <lb/>
it is not of the essence of Provincial rights that a <lb/>
Provincial Legislature should have the power of <lb/>
deciding in what language its proceedings should <lb/>
be carried on, or its records printed. Now, I con<lb break="no"/>tend that we are in the midst of a crusade organ<lb break="no"/>ised by the hon. member for North Simcoe for the <lb/>
purpose of depriving the French population of <lb/>
their language, their institutions, and their <lb/>
schools. His programme has been promulgated in <lb/>
Ontario, Manitoba, and the Territories, and we <lb/>
are asked to-day to help him to carry out his <lb/>
scheme. That hon. gentleman, both in this House <lb/>
and outside of the House, has stated that his pro<lb break="no"/>gramme for his future lifetime is the abolition of <lb/>
the French language in Manitoba and the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, the abo ition of the Separate Schools in <lb/>
Ontario, the abolition of the French language in <lb/>
the House of Commons, and, in the course of <lb/>
time, the abolition of the French language, <lb/>
in the Province of Quebec, although he does <lb/>
not expect to succeed for several years. Now, <lb/>
what is the object of the proposition made <lb/>
by the hon. Minister of Justice, in the opinion of <lb/>
all the newspapers, French and English, Liberal <lb/>
and Conservative, which have discussed the <lb/>

<pb n="999" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_00999.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">999</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1000</fw> 

hon. Minister's proposition during the last three <lb/>
days, as well as in the opinion of a great many <lb/>
members who have discussed the matter? It is <lb/>
agreed that that proposition is really the McCarthy <lb/>
    Bill in disguise. The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Star</hi> of Montreal is a very <lb/>
influential Tory paper, enjoying one of the largest <lb/>
circulations in Canada, and it stated immediately <lb/>
after the amendment was proposed: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The vote on Mr. Beausoleil's amendment to Mr. <lb/>
McCarthy's Bill is an indication that one of the motions <lb/>
now before the House to bring about the abolition of the <lb/>
dual official language system in the North-West Will be <lb/>
carried by a considerable majority. Evidently theHouse <lb/>
will not adopt Mr. McCarthy's motion under any circum<lb break="no"/>stances but for all ractical purposes it does not make <lb/>
much difference whether the ouse takes the bitter <lb/>
McCarthy pill, the same pill sugar-coated by Mr. Davin <lb/>
or the same pill sugar-coated by Sir JohnThompson. * * * <lb/>
Mr. Davin's amendment to allow the North-West As<lb break="no"/>sembly to relieve Parliament of the responsibility of <lb/>
abolishing the dual language system after the next <lb/>
election, and Sir John Thompson's amendment in other <lb/>
words to do precisely the same thing. The difference <lb/>
between Sir John Thompson's amendment and Mr.Davin's <lb/>
is that Sir John's begins by affirming the convenant rights <lb/>
of the French to the official use of the French language <lb/>
and denying that community of language is in the in<lb break="no"/>terests of national unity, and ends by giving the Local <lb/>
Assembly power to smash the alleged convenant and <lb/>
establish communitv of language while Mr. Davin's <lb/>
amendment leaves the covenant alone. * * * Whether <lb/>
Sir John Thompson's amendment or Mr. Davin's amend<lb break="no"/>ment carry, Mr. McCarthy will have brought about the <lb/>
abolition of the dual language system in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
        <p>The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Witness</hi>, which is an extreme Protestant <lb/>
paper, and which, though it pretends sometimes to <lb/>
be Liberal, is very illiberal at bottom, said: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The Dominion Parliament, in passing this resolution <lb/>
and empowering the Assembly to take action, as well as <lb/>
in suggesting it, is responsible, in spite of itself, for the <lb/>
settlement which is to follow. The French-speaking, <lb/>
that is, the French and half-breed population of the <lb/>
North-West is not so insignificant as we assumed from <lb/>
declarations in Parliament, which remains uncontra<lb break="no"/>dicted. In 1885 it formed about twenty-four per cent. of <lb/>
the enfranchised population of the Territories, and about <lb/>
twelve per cent of the whole population, Indian and <lb/>
white. What the verdict of the Territories will be, is <lb/>
clearly evident beforehand especially as the pro ortion <lb/>
of the English-Speaking and French-speaking popu ations <lb/>
has greatly increased during the past four years." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>So much for the English press. If we turn to the <lb/>
    French press, we find <hi rendition="simple:italic">L'Etendard</hi>, both of yesterday <lb/>
and today, has denounced the amendment as being <lb/>
similar, in every respect, to the McCarthy Bill; <lb/>
    and now we have <hi rendition="simple:italic">L'Electeur</hi>, the most important <lb/>
Liberal newspaper in the Province of Quebec, say<lb break="no"/>ing as follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>(Translation). "This last concession was hardly made <lb/>
when we saw Sir John A. Macdonald trying to secure a <lb/>
still more important one and threatening his partisans <lb/>
with an immediate dissolution if they would not yield <lb/>
submissively to this new sacrifice. Sir John has, in <lb/>
fact, caused his Minister of Justice, Sir John Thompson, <lb/>
to move an amendment to the McCarthy Bill, which, on <lb/>
the whole is, in a disguised form, nothing short of the <lb/>
Davin amendment. [We give in another column the text <lb/>
of the Dawn amendment.] Once the principle sanctioned <lb/>
as regards the North-West Legislature shall apply to <lb/>
Manitoba, where our compatriots are still in a minority, <lb/>
and where both parties have agreed to repeal, of their <lb/>
own free will the official use of the French language. It <lb/>
is easy to understand that, once the principle sanctioned <lb/>
the door is open, and that the last bulwark that protected <lb/>
one of our rights is down. The French language will be <lb/>
abolished in the Territories and Manitoba, where the <lb/>
French Canadians have, nevertheless, been the first <lb/>
pioneers, the first civilising people. There is no room <lb/>
left for idle hopes." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>Here is the advice it gives: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Our friends in Ottawa are, unfortunately, on the <lb/>
Opposition side, that is to say, powerless to secure the <lb/>
triumph of their broad and liberal ideas,towhich the <lb/>

<cb/>

Hon. Mr. Blake, a few days ago, gave voice in eloquent <lb/>
words. But we beseech them to stand firm and to do <lb/>
their duty to the end, and we feel that they shall <lb/>
have, not only the sympathies of our co-religionists and <lb/>
fellow-countrymen, but also those of an imposing number <lb/>
of fair-minded English-speaking people who consider as <lb/>
an honor to follow the traditions of the Liberals of old <lb/>
England, and follow the steps of those who, in the old <lb/>
country, defend the cause of Home Rule and equality of <lb/>
rights for all races and all creeds under the British flag." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>I might quote several other newspapers which have <lb/>
declared themselves on this amendment moved by <lb/>
the hon. Minister of Justice, and, without excep<lb break="no"/>tion, they all agree that it is a sacrifice of the <lb/>
rights and privileges of the French population of <lb/>
the North-West, in order to purchase peace in this <lb/>
House, because the Government expect that, if <lb/>
this amendment be adopted, we will hear no more <lb/>
about the repeal of clause 110 of the British North <lb/>
America Act. But I may say that this is only the <lb/>
beginning of the agitation led by the hon. member <lb/>
for North Simcoe, and that so long as there will be <lb/>
a remnant of French or Catholic institutions, <lb/>
whether in the North-West, or in Manitoba, or <lb/>
Ontario, or in any other portion of the Dominion, <lb/>
we will have that hon. gentleman coming into this <lb/>
House, year after year, and endeavoring to per<lb break="no"/>petuate this agitation which has been excited <lb/>
under his leadership. There is only one effective <lb/>
way of finally settling this question, and that is to <lb/>
vote for the amendment I have proposed, and thus <lb/>
clearly put on record our opinion, which is that of <lb/>
almost every hon. gentleman who has spoken, that <lb/>
this Bill of the hon. member of North Simcoe <lb/>
is a mischievous attempt to set race against race <lb/>
and creed against creed. It is for this House, and <lb/>
especially the Government, to take a bold stand, <lb/>
and say, once for all, that such an attempt shall <lb/>
not be tolerated, and by a crushing vote of the <lb/>
whole House against the five or six, or it may <lb/>
be ten, who would follow the hon. member for <lb/>
North Simcoe, declare that we are not prepared <lb/>
to give these men the means of disturbing the good <lb/>
feeling and understanding which now exists be<lb break="no"/>tween the two races in this country, and we will <lb/>
not allow them to perpetuate the division which <lb/>
they have started and which has given rise to <lb/>
feelings it will take a long time to allay. It is <lb/>
not by yielding to the fire-brands who go through <lb/>
the country sowing the seeds of discord, that we <lb/>
will become unite, but it is by showing them <lb/>
that the good sense of the country, as represented <lb/>
in this House, is in a position to deal with them in <lb/>
a summary manner by stamping out this agi<lb break="no"/>tation, and showing them they have no stand<lb break="no"/>ing in the House or the country and that <lb/>
their course will not be tolerated. I am <lb/>
very sorry we are not about to take this course, <lb/>
and all the more so because I am obliged <lb/>
to separate myself from my most esteemed <lb/>
leader, in whom I have always had the greatest <lb/>
confidence. But this question has been left an <lb/>
open one, and I take the opportunity of voting <lb/>
according to my judgment, and in accord with the <lb/>
sentiments I feel so strongly in this matter, even <lb/>
though I be compelled to differ from my leader. <lb/>
Another cause for regret to me is that, by separat<lb break="no"/>ing myself from my leader, I shall be obliged to <lb/>
vote in company with the hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe, but it will be the first time, and I hope <lb/>
the last, because I hope that the next time that <lb/>
hon. gentleman, or any other, attempts to create <lb/>
trouble in the country, a more vigorous policy will <lb/>

<pb n="1001" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01001.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1001</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">1002</fw> 

be followed, and that the House will be almost <lb/>
unanimous against those who attempt to destroy <lb/>
the happiness, the prosperity, and the good feeling <lb/>
that now exists, and I hope will always exist, <lb/>
between the different creeds and races of this <lb/>
country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WALL1">Mr. WALLACE</persName>. It is not my intention, at this <lb/>
late stage of the debate, to make any lengthy re<lb break="no"/>marks, butI cannot allow this question to pass <lb/>
and give a silent vote upon it. We have been, on <lb/>
more than one occasion, brought face to face <lb/>
with racial and religious difficulties. For these <lb/>
difficulties, I think no man in this country is more <lb/>
responsible than the ex-leader of the Opposition, <lb/>
the hon. member for West Durham. That hon. <lb/>
gentleman, nearly twenty years ago, made capital <lb/>
out of the Scott murder case in the endeavor to <lb/>
gain power in Ontario, and when he had accom<lb break="no"/>plished his purpose, he quickly dropped the sub<lb break="no"/>ject so as not to embarrass his friends in the <lb/>
Dominion elections that were then about to follow. <lb/>
At a later date, on the question of the hanging of <lb/>
Louis Riel, the hon. member for West Durham, in <lb/>
his London speech, told the people that he would <lb/>
not make a platform for his party out <lb/>
of the Regina scaffold. Well, every true-<lb break="yes"/>minded patriot in this country commended that <lb/>
sentiment. But what did we find afterwards? <lb/>
when the Government thought that a murderer is <lb/>
a murderer, no matter what his nationality may <lb/>
be, We find the hon. gentleman taking the other <lb/>
side of the question and going back on the record <lb/>
he had made for himself in London, going back <lb/>
upon the declarations he solemnly made in London, <lb/>
though he knew the whole facts of the case then <lb/>
as much as he did afterwards, and as much as he <lb/>
knows them to-day. We find this hon. gentleman <lb/>
in this House, within the last few days, regretting <lb/>
that these difficulties were coming up again; but I <lb/>
believe that no one in this country is more respon<lb break="no"/>sible for these difficulties than the hon. gentleman <lb/>
himself. With reference to the question which is <lb/>
immediately before the House, we have been told <lb/>
that the North-West Council had no mandate <lb/>
from the people to dispose of this question, and <lb/>
we were told by the hon. member for West Dur<lb break="no"/>ham (Mr. Blake) that they were in a state of <lb/>
tutelage. I think there is no portion of the people <lb/>
of this country more intelligent than our North-<lb break="yes"/>West settlers. They are the flower of the older <lb/>
Provinces of Canada; they are young, enterprising <lb/>
and intelligent men; they are young men of edu<lb break="no"/>cation, and I think they are as well calculated to <lb/>
Express an opinion upon questions as they arise as <lb/>
the population of any other portion of this Domin<lb break="no"/>ion. Therefore, while I am in favor of the Bill as <lb/>
introduced by the hon. member for North Simcoe <lb/>
(Mr. McCarthy); and while I regret that the tone <lb/>
of this debate, on the other side, was not in <lb/>
mutation of the moderation of the hon. gentleman <lb/>
who introduced the Bill, I think the people of the <lb/>
North-West themselves are better qualified to <lb/>
pronounce upon this question than even we are in <lb/>
the House of Commons. Another reason is. that <lb/>
the House of Commons to-day may repeal the <lb/>
110th clause of the North-West Territories Act, <lb/>
and next Sessiion, or in the next Parliament, it <lb/>
may re-enact that clause; and, therefore, we <lb/>
would be brought face to face, either at every <lb/>
Session of Parliament or in every new Parlia<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

ment, with this question. If we relegate it to the <lb/>
North-West Council, or to the new Legislatures we <lb/>
are creating in that country, to which each time <lb/>
we are giving largely increased powers, we know <lb/>
this, that when once you give power to a Local <lb/>
Legislature, you can never take it away again. <lb/>
The Local Legislatures are tenacious of any rights <lb/>
and privileges which are given to them; and, <lb/>
therefore, when you clothe them with a certain <lb/>
power, that power remains with them. There<lb break="no"/>fore, if either of these amendments is adopted by <lb/>
the House, you are more permanently settling the <lb/>
question than even by the adoption of the Bill <lb/>
itself. For these reasons, I will favor the amend<lb break="no"/>ment moved by the hon. the Minister of Justice, <lb/>
though it does not go as far as I would like to go, <lb/>
or as far as the amendment of the hon. member <lb/>
for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin), which I more <lb/>
favor. But we cannot have everything our own <lb/>
way. While a spirit of compromise and concili<lb break="no"/>ation is abroad, I think, as patriots, and as loyal <lb/>
citizens of Canada, we should try to meet each <lb/>
other half way. In the first place, therefore, I <lb/>
give my adhesion to the amendment of the hon. <lb/>
the Minister of Justice. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WATS2">Mr. WATSON</persName>. This debate has taken a very <lb/>
wide range, and, to my mind, the practical question <lb/>
before the House has not been discussed as it <lb/>
should have been. If it had been so discussed, <lb/>
this debate would have ended three or four days <lb/>
ago. I am rather surprised that the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man who has just taken his seat (Mr. Wallace) <lb/>
appears to desire to revive the old debate on the <lb/>
Riel question. That is a matter which is entirely <lb/>
foreign to this debate. I think the French people <lb/>
are somewhat to blame for this discussion. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve that clause 110 was, in a sense, smuggled into <lb/>
this Act by Senator Girard in the Senate, and that <lb/>
it should never have been there. From reading <lb/>
the debates, I think that clause was inserted con<lb break="no"/>trary to the wishes of the hon. gentlemen who <lb/>
were then in power, but, as that House was com<lb break="no"/>posed of a majority who were against the policy <lb/>
and principles of the majority in the popular <lb/>
House, they did as they pleased, and, if that <lb/>
clause had not been accepted, that Bill would <lb/>
have been delayed for another season. In regard <lb/>
to the visit of the hon. member for North Simcoe <lb/>
(Mr. McCarthy) to the North-West, he did not <lb/>
trouble me very much on his visit to Portage la <lb/>
Prairie. Even up to the present, I have some <lb/>
doubts as to the honesty of that gentleman, and <lb/>
as to his sincerity, in wanting to do good <lb/>
to people of the North-West. It appears to me <lb/>
that he came there more for the sake of agitation <lb/>
than for any practical good. The hon. member for <lb/>
Provencher (Mr. LaRivière) made a reference to his <lb/>
visit and his speech on that occasion. I think his <lb/>
quotations from that speech are perfectly accurate, <lb/>
but he also referred to the Attorney General of the <lb/>
Province of Manitoba, who stood on the platform <lb/>
on that occasion, and he said he did not envy him <lb/>
his company. It was hardly necessary for the <lb/>
hon. member to make that statement, as this <lb/>
House knows that the hon. member for Provencher <lb/>
(Mr. LaRiviere) has not much use for the Attorney <lb/>
General of Manitoba, and that about the time he <lb/>
came around the legislative halls of that Province, <lb/>
the member for Provencher was very scarce. I <lb/>
believe that no change should be made in the <lb/>

<pb n="1003" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01003.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1003</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1004</fw> 

constitution under which people live without con<lb break="no"/>sulting the people, and, though I believe that sec<lb break="no"/>tion 110 was smuggled into that Act and should <lb/>
never have been there, nevertheless as the people <lb/>
of the North-West have been living under that <lb/>
clause enacted by this Parliament, I do not think <lb/>
we should remove it without consulting them. I <lb/>
am not a lawyer, but I much prefer the amendment <lb/>
of the hon. member for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) <lb/>
to that of the Minister of Justice, which has so <lb/>
many surrounding clauses, which contains so many <lb/>
things that appear to a layman to be a mystery. <lb/>
The amendment of the hon. member for West <lb/>
Assiniboia is plain, and I do not feel disposed to <lb/>
vote for the amendment of the Minister of Justice, <lb/>
as it recites certain things with which I do not <lb/>
agree. It says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"That, on the contrary, this House declares its ad<lb break="no"/>herence to the said covenants audits determination to <lb/>
resist any attempt to impair the same." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>I believe, that at any time when it is in the <lb/>
interests of any Province of the Dominion that <lb/>
even the British North America Act should be <lb/>
changed, it should be changed for the convenience <lb/>
of the people living under that Act. Believing <lb/>
that, I could not consistently vote for the amend<lb break="no"/>ment to the amendment. It is quite possible that <lb/>
the Province from which I come may have occa<lb break="no"/>sion to seek to amend the British North America <lb/>
Act in some measure, to relieve them from some <lb/>
privileges which were granted to a minority in <lb/>
that Province which are objectionable to the <lb/>
majority. The French language is practically <lb/>
done away with in Manitoba, as far as the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature is concerned. It has been abolished by a <lb/>
vote of twenty-four to six, and in a full House of <lb/>
the representatives there would have been a vote <lb/>
of thirty-two to six. The people of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories are similarly situated to those of <lb/>
Manitoba, and I have no doubt they desire to have only <lb/>
one official language in the North-West. Another <lb/>
reason why I cannot vote for the Bill introduced <lb/>
by the hon. member for Simcoe is the fact that I <lb/>
find that six of the gentlemen composing the <lb/>
North-West Council expressed themselves as being <lb/>
favorable to the power being granted them by this <lb/>
Parliament to deal with this question. They did <lb/>
not ask that an Act should be passed to repeal <lb/>
clause 110, as I understood from the hon. member <lb/>
for Simcoe, but they asked that they should have <lb/>
the power to do away with the French language if <lb/>
they saw fit. I will quote some extracts from the <lb/>
speeches delivered by a few of those gentlemen in <lb/>
the North-West Assembly. The hon. member for <lb/>
Provencher stated that Mr. Judge Rouleau had <lb/>
expressed himself as being sorry that he had not a <lb/>
vote, in order that he might cast it against the <lb/>
memorial presented to this House. I find in the <lb/>
    report of the speeches in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Press</hi> the following: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Judge Rouleau spoke at great length upon the ques<lb break="no"/>tion. He claimed that no action could be taken until the <lb/>
people had a chance to express themselves upon the <lb/>
matter. Let the members make it an issue at the next <lb/>
election if they wished. He had spoken French before he <lb/>
had spoken English, and this memorial proposed to de<lb break="no"/>prive him and others of their mother tongue. He closed <lb/>
by again claimin that the question should be decided by <lb/>
the electors, and hinted that some of the members who <lb/>
would probably vote for this now, might suffer at the next <lb/>
election. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Mr. Haultain ointed out that the assembly, in asking <lb/>
for the removal of a restrictive clause, was simply asking <lb/>
for more powers, and that they could make the use of the <lb/>
power to deal with the language question, an issue at the <lb/>

<cb/>

next election. He favored but one official language on <lb/>
the ground of convenience and economy." <lb/></p> 

<p>"Mr. Oliver regretted that the discussion had taken <lb/>
such a wide range." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>I think we can say the same thing in this House.— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"He represented a large number of French-speaking <lb/>
people, and did not consider that he was going against their <lb/>
interest in asking for extended powers, so that we could <lb/>
deal with this matter ourselves. He had always strongly <lb/>
advocated that the people of this country should be <lb/>
allowed to manage their own affairs, and would support <lb/>
the memorial." <lb/></p> 

<p>"Mr. Neff said that the dual language system had <lb/>
been imposed upon us and we were simply asking for the <lb/>
privilege to retain it or not, as we wished. He had no <lb/>
desire to deprive French-speaking people of a luxury; <lb/>
they could not be prevented from speaking their own <lb/>
language, but he obJected to its being an official lan<lb break="no"/>guage. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Mr. Ross,"— <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>I think this gentleman represents Calgary or <lb/>
Moose Jaw.— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Mr. Ross also represented a mixed community. He <lb/>
owed much to the French-speaking electors, in his dis<lb break="no"/>trict, and would be ungrateful if he did them any injus<lb break="no"/>tice, but did not consider that he was doing them any <lb/>
injustice in asking that the people's representatives in <lb/>
the North-West be given the power to deal with this <lb/>
matter."   <lb/></p> 

<p>"Mr. Hoey said this dual language seemed to be a bug<lb break="no"/>bear to some people, and yet not one member had been <lb/>
able to show any injury done by it. No action should be <lb/>
taken until the question was brought before the different <lb/>
constituencies." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>Now, Mr. Speaker, with that evidence before me, <lb/>
I cannot do otherwise than to support the <lb/>
amendment moved by the hon. member for West <lb/>
Assiniboia, because I believe it gives the people <lb/>
the exact power they ask for. To my mind, the <lb/>
amendment to the amendment is simply putting <lb/>
this matter off to another year. It is not giving <lb/>
the power they ask for, and if the amendment of <lb/>
the Minister of Justice is carried, no doubt we will <lb/>
have a repetition of the debate that has taken <lb/>
place here for the last six days, a debate which, I <lb/>
think, is very much to be regretted. There is no <lb/>
doubt it has given rise to race and religious <lb/>
feelings that will not be quieted for years to come. <lb/>
I was a little astonished at a statement made <lb/>
by the Minister of Justice, and also one made <lb/>
by the Minister of the Interior. The Minister of <lb/>
Justice, in speaking in defence of his amend<lb break="no"/>ment, said it would be cruel to deprive <lb/>
those poor people in the North-West of the privilege <lb/>
of using their mother tongue; that a man might be <lb/>
tried there and convicted, and, after the trial was <lb/>
over, he might not know what he was convicted <lb/>
for. Now, it appears to me that there is a good <lb/>
deal of special pleading in a statement like that. <lb/>
I have yet to learn that any British subject, or <lb/>
anyone else, in the Dominion of Canada, be he of <lb/>
British nationality or of any other has suffered <lb/>
from a miscarriage of justice because he did not <lb/>
understand the language in which the statutes <lb/>
were printed. That being the case, I have no <lb/>
doubt that, when the French language is done <lb/>
away with in the North—West, there will be no <lb/>
occasion for saying that these people do not under<lb break="no"/>stand the law because it is not printed in their own <lb/>
language. The hon. Minister of the Interior, in <lb/>
his remarks last night, made rather a startling <lb/>
statement. He said that he visited six townships <lb/>
in Manitoba during his trip last fall, and he found <lb/>
nine different nationalities in those six different <lb/>
townships. <lb/></p>

<pb n="1005" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01005.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1005</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">1006
</fw>
<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. Excuse me, not in Manitoba; <lb/>
but in the North-West, I found in two townships <lb/>
representatives of nine nationalities. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WATS2">Mr. WATSON</persName>. I took down the sentence which <lb/>
followed that statement, in which he said it would <lb/>
be cruel if the laws of the land were not printed <lb/>
in the language of these nationalities. I do not <lb/>
really think he meant it, but, if he did, it would <lb/>
be a very expensive luxury. Sir, I believe the <lb/>
amendment of the hon. member for West Assini<lb break="no"/>boia commends itself to a great number of the hon. <lb/>
gentlemen in this House. There is no doubt that <lb/>
the appeal made by the First Minister yesterday <lb/>
to whip his followers into line had considerable <lb/>
effect. It was a very strong appeal; he rose <lb/>
equal to the occasion, and to my mind made the <lb/>
best speech I ever heard delivered in the House. <lb/>
There were none of those little stories with which <lb/>
that hon. gentleman is accustomed to regale the <lb/>
House. But I hope that the amendment of the <lb/>
Minister of Justice will not be adopted, for the <lb/>
amendment of the member for West Assiniboia is <lb/>
the only one that will satisfy the people of the <lb/>
North-West, will give them the power they ask <lb/>
for, and will prevent a repetition of the unpleasant <lb/>
discussion which has taken place in this House for <lb/>
the last few days. The hon. member for Pro<lb break="no"/>vencher said he considered it a fortunate thing <lb/>
that this question had been brought before the <lb/>
House, but I do not share in his view; I think it <lb/>
a very unfortunate thing. No doubt the hon. <lb/>
gentleman feels a little warm on the question, be<lb break="no"/>cause a similar question is arising in Manitoba in <lb/>
connection with the French language and separate <lb/>
schools, which are going to be done away with <lb/>
in that Province, at least separate schools will <lb/>
henceforth exist in a much modified form. As <lb/>
I said before, I thought the French people were to <lb/>
blame to some extent for this discussion in the <lb/>
House, inasmuch as I believe that this clause was <lb/>
smuggled into the Bill by Senator Girard in the <lb/>
Senate some years ago. I believe that one of the <lb/>
causes of irritation in Manitoba in reference to <lb/>
separate schools is the fact that while the hon. <lb/>
member for Provencher was a member of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of Manitoba be secured special privileges <lb/>
for the separate schools, and when the Protestants, <lb/>
who are the great majority of that Province, found <lb/>
that the separate schools were receiving much <lb/>
more than their share of the grant, they became <lb/>
aroused, and when a change of Government took <lb/>
place they decided that the moment was oppor<lb break="no"/>tune for abolishing the system. With regard to <lb/>
the French language in Manitoba, I may say that, <lb/>
while I do not know what the custom is in the <lb/>
North-West, one of the principal reasons of the <lb/>
abolition of the official French in Manitoba was <lb/>
the expense. It has been stated here that the <lb/>
printing of French in the North-West amounts to <lb/>
only $400. I know that in Manitoba it costs a <lb/>
considerable sum of money, and it costs the gen<lb break="no"/>eral public a large sum of money in addition to <lb/>
what it costs the Government, because under the <lb/>
Land Title system all notices of application to <lb/>
put land under the Torrens system have to be <lb/>
    advertised in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi>. This costs a considerable <lb/>
sum to the applicants. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CASG1">Mr. CASGRAIN</persName>. I do not intend to occupy <lb/>
the time of the House at any length, but I desire <lb/>
merely to state the conclusion at which I have <lb/>

<cb/>

arrived after listening to the discussion. I regret <lb/>
that the amendment introduced by the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Berthier (Mr. Beausoleil) was not carried, <lb/>
as I should like to have seen it adopted. That <lb/>
amendment having been defeated, I think the next <lb/>
best course to take is to adopt the amendment of <lb/>
the Minister of Justice, and I am, therefore, willing <lb/>
to vote for it. I am willing to do so because it <lb/>
contains an emphatic declaration against the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of the Bill proposed by the hon. member for <lb/>
North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy). Of course, if that <lb/>
amendment went further in the direction of extin<lb break="no"/>guishing the question at once I would feel more <lb/>
satisfied, for I am afraid it may come back; but <lb/>
under the circumstances, when I see that the <lb/>
flame is extending over the country, I think <lb/>
the first thing to do is to quench it at once. <lb/>
I place this question above party considerations, <lb/>
and I consider it on the broad principle that we <lb/>
must have peace and amity in this country, <lb/>
and that its future depends upon it. It is no <lb/>
doubt unfortunate that this subject has been <lb/>
brought before the House. It has arrayed a <lb/>
compact body of French members against the <lb/>
English-speaking members, which is a circumstance <lb/>
to be deplored. As the Minister of Public Works <lb/>
said, it has arrayed a compact phalanx of French <lb/>
Canadians in defence of their rights. In order to <lb/>
secure harmony, not only in the House, but through<lb break="no"/>out the country, I am glad to support the conclusion <lb/>
arrived at by the wiser heads on both sides of this <lb/>
House. No none will deny that the leader of the <lb/>
Government is not only a politician but a statesman, <lb/>
and although I am with him this time, it is certainly <lb/>
not because I belong to his following. At the same <lb/>
time I am glad to follow my leader, who on this <lb/>
occasion has shown his patriotism and devotion to <lb/>
his country, and who advocates the principle of <lb/>
the autonomy of the Provinces that has already <lb/>
been sanctioned. I am also very glad to follow <lb/>
the hon. member for West Durham (Mr. Blake), <lb/>
whose brilliant speech must have brought convic<lb break="no"/>tion to many members. From these considerations <lb/>
I accept the amendment proposed by the Minister <lb/>
of Justice, not as the best conclusion possible, <lb/>
but as a means of soothing the bad feelings that <lb/>
have been aroused all over the country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUPO1">Mr. DUPONT</persName>. (Translation.) The imposing <lb/>
debate, Mr. Speaker, brought on by the campaign <lb/>
carried on throughout the country by the hon. <lb/>
member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), and by <lb/>
the measure which he has submitted for the consi<lb break="no"/>deration of this House, clearly shows the impor<lb break="no"/>tance of the privileges and the rights which it <lb/>
attacks. Several of my colleagues, at the opening <lb/>
of the campaign undertaken by the hon. member <lb/>
against the French Canadians, the first inhabitants <lb/>
of this country, believe that the good sense of the <lb/>
English people will consider this quarrel which the <lb/>
hon. member seeks to fasten upon us as a quarrel <lb/>
of but little importance. Several thought, at the <lb/>
beginning, that this mountain in labor would bring <lb/>
forth but a small and ridiculous mouse. Unfor<lb break="no"/>tunately, Mr. Speaker, the hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe has been backed up in his campaign by <lb/>
other gentlemen, whose talent, and the means <lb/>
which they have employed, to excite the prejudices <lb/>
of their fellow-citizens who are not of the same <lb/>
race as ourselves, in the Province of Ontario, it is <lb/>
impossible to ignore. The hon. member has aroused <lb/>

<pb n="1007" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01007.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1007</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1008</fw> 

against us, I repeat, his fellow-countrymen; and <lb/>
as the hon. member for Rouville (Mr. Gigault) has <lb/>
said, there has arisen a dark cloud on our political <lb/>
horizon, carrying within it a war of race, a war of <lb/>
religion, a war against the institutions of the first <lb/>
inhabitants of this country. Happily for us, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, the good sense of the public men on both <lb/>
sides of the ouse has been, in the face of this dark <lb/>
cloud, the light of hope, which has animated the <lb/>
courage of all true patriots within the Dominion. <lb/>
I can only compare some of the speeches of the <lb/>
hon. members, who have endeavored to raise pre<lb break="no"/>judice against us; on account of the small value <lb/>
of their arguments; on account of the lame rea<lb break="no"/>sonings which support them; on account of the <lb/>
few historical precedents which they have quoted <lb/>
in order to justify the attitude which they have <lb/>
taken against us—I can only compare these <lb/>
speeches, set going by these hon. members in the <lb/>
road of public opinion, to light carriages, to cabs <lb/>
which carry no load. On the other hand, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, if I applied the same simile to some <lb/>
of the speeches made by hon. members, as well <lb/>
on this side of the House as on the other, I <lb/>
ought to compare these speeches to massive wag<lb break="no"/>gons pushed alone the road of public opinion by <lb/>
powerful orators; I might say that these waggons <lb/>
carry boxes which contain solid reasoning, formid<lb break="no"/>able reasoning, philosophic reasoning, and histo<lb break="no"/>rical facts. Woe to the light cabs without a load, <lb/>
driven at an immoderate gait, by thoughtless <lb/>
drivers, if they should happen some day to knock <lb/>
against, in the road of public opinion, and in the <lb/>
road of history, these massive waggons which <lb/>
are laden with historical truths and true philo<lb break="no"/>sophical teachings. What are, Mr. Speaker, in <lb/>
short, the complaints of the hon. member for <lb/>
North Simcoe against the French Canadians and <lb/>
the French race, not only in the Province of <lb/>
Quebec but against the small handful of those of <lb/>
our nationality who have tried their fortune on <lb/>
the prairies of the West? The hon. member <lb/>
desires, be the cost what it may, to make the <lb/>
regions of the West, what he calls a British coun<lb break="no"/>try. But is not the Province of Quebec a British <lb/>
country? Are not we in that Province subjects of <lb/>
Her Majesty, equally as are the citizens of the <lb/>
Province of Ontario, and as would be those of the <lb/>
North-West, were they all Saxons, as the hon. <lb/>
member for North Simcoe desires? I do not see <lb/>
what difference there is between an Anglo-Saxon <lb/>
subject, and a British subject of French Canadian <lb/>
origin. I do not see what difference there can be <lb/>
in the minds of English statesmen, in the eyes of <lb/>
the friends of the Empire, between a British sub<lb break="no"/>ject of French origin or of Irish or Scotch origin, <lb/>
or even one of the subjects of Her Majesty in the <lb/>
vast Colony of the East Indies, and a Saxon like <lb/>
the hon. member for North Simcoe; we are all <lb/>
subjects of the same Empire, we are all citizens of <lb/>
the same Empire, and as such we ought to have <lb/>
equal rights. Great use has been made, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, of the word "British, "during this debate; <lb/>
and I have remarked, especially, that the hon. <lb/>
member for Albert (Mr. Weldon), in moderate yet <lb/>
unjust language, has, in a way, profaned this noble <lb/>
expression. Every subject of the British Empire, <lb/>
to whatever race or nationality he may belong, can <lb/>
claim the same title. The hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe and the member for Albert have pretended <lb/>
that if French were spoken in the North-West it <lb/>

<cb/>

would no longer be a British country. And, say <lb/>
they, the French Canadians ought not to delude <lb/>
themselves to the point of believing that the North-<lb break="yes"/>West ought not to be a British country. No, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, we have never been under this impression, <lb/>
we have never asked for it, and we would be the <lb/>
most grieved parties in the Dominion, if the <lb/>
North-West was not going to continue for<lb break="no"/>ever a British country. We wish, just as <lb/>
much as the hon. member for Albert <lb/>
does, or the hon. member for North Simcoe, <lb/>
that the North-West should continue to be a <lb/>
dependency of the Dominion of Canada, or rather <lb/>
form a portion of the Dominion, and that it may <lb/>
be a British country, if it should not be like the <lb/>
Province of Quebec, it would be such to the same <lb/>
extent as is the country whence comes the hon. <lb/>
member for Albert. But what do they mean to <lb/>
say, when using the expression "British?" Does <lb/>
this mean exclusion for some of the subjects of the <lb/>
Empire? Do we understand by that, unequal <lb/>
rights for certain subjects of the Empire, or again <lb/>
the rights of certain subjects of the Empire entirely <lb/>
ignored? Does this mean short-sightedness? No, <lb/>
Mr. Speaker, I have always held the highest <lb/>
opinion of British subjects and of British countries. <lb/>
I have always understood that the British language <lb/>
was a noble language; that a British country was <lb/>
a noble country in which liberty and equal rights <lb/>
reigned supreme. But, as the hon. member for <lb/>
Simcoe understands it, would it be a case of equal <lb/>
rights if all the subjects of the Empire were obliged <lb/>
to adopt the customs and the religion as well as the <lb/>
language of the hon. members for North Simcoe and <lb/>
Albert? Do these hon. members understand by <lb/>
equal rights that one ought not to do anything but <lb/>
what they do, to think only as they think, and to <lb/>
act only as they act? This liberty is a liberty <lb/>
which is not British. The hon. member for Simcoe <lb/>
profanes this noble expression, degrades this noble <lb/>
title, of which every subject of the Empire is proud. <lb/>
He desires to give it a narrow meaning, at which, <lb/>
no matter what English subject, if he but under<lb break="no"/>stands the importance of the title of "British <lb/>
subject," would blush. The hon. gentlemen, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, who share the opinion of the hon. member <lb/>
for North Simcoe, seem to believe that without <lb/>
unity of language the country is exposed to every <lb/>
plague, and that with unity of language a country is <lb/>
secure against all disorders and all misfortunes. <lb/>
They have cited the great American Republic as <lb/>
being a country which has prospered extremely, and <lb/>
they have attributed, so to speak, all this pros<lb break="no"/>perity to the fact that American subjects enjoy <lb/>
this great prerogative, this grand privilege which <lb/>
is the hobby of the hon. member for North Simcoe, <lb/>
namely, unity of language. But why, I ask the <lb/>
hon. member, did a civil war break out in the <lb/>
heart of this same great Republic, which according <lb/>
to him enjoys unity in language? Why did this <lb/>
great civil war, which has had no equal in the <lb/>
annals of modern nations, this great civil war which <lb/>
has been one of the greatest scourges of the Ameri<lb break="no"/>can people, why did it break out in a nation in <lb/>
which unity of language existed? The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers, Mr. Speaker, who have treated so learnedly <lb/>
this subject, my hon. friend from Bothwell (Mr. <lb/>
Mills) the hon. member for West Assiniboia (Mr. <lb/>
Davin), the hon. member for "West Durham (Mr. <lb/>
Blake), and several of their colleagues on both <lb/>
sides of the House, have shown, by the <lb/>

<pb n="1009" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01009.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1009</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">1010</fw>

clearest possible evidence, that it is possible <lb/>
to he a great nation, that it is possible <lb/>
to become a great people while not possess<lb break="no"/>ing unity in religion, unity in language, or unity <lb/>
of race. And, unless we believe that it is by pre<lb break="no"/>sumption, or that he is impelled thereto by an evil <lb/>
genius, I cannot understand what induces the hon. <lb/>
member to persist in this crusade, in the face of <lb/>
historic verity, in face of precedents, which have <lb/>
been held up before his eyes, and which the hon. <lb/>
member ought to have known before they were <lb/>
pointed out to him by his colleagues; for every<lb break="no"/>body knows that the hon. member is a man of <lb/>
great skill, a well informed man, a man who has <lb/>
studied deeply. But, notwithstanding all this, like <lb/>
a blind man, like a deaf man, he cries without <lb/>
ceasing that without unity of language it is impos<lb break="no"/>sible or nearly impossible for this Canada, which <lb/>
we love so much and which we cherish, to become <lb/>
a great country. I say, Mr. Speaker, that the <lb/>
hon. member is unjust towards us. I ask this <lb/>
House, I ask every impartial man, what would <lb/>
Canada be to-day, had it not been for the support <lb/>
of the French nationality in all the great questions <lb/>
which the present Government, and that which <lb/>
preceded it, have carried out? Who was the man <lb/>
who followed up, with the utmost perseverance, <lb/>
the acquisition of those great Territories, respec<lb break="no"/>ting which the hon. member for North Simcoe has <lb/>
embroiled us to-day? Was it not Sir George <lb/>
Etienne Cartier, one of the old colleagues of the <lb/>
hon. the present Prime Minister? Has not the <lb/>
Province of Quebec, Mr. Speaker, paid its large <lb/>
portion, as well of the purchase money of the <lb/>
North-West, and for the construction of the Pacific <lb/>
Railway, as for all the great public works which <lb/>
have been constructed by the Government to open <lb/>
up the North-West to civilisation? And, in spite <lb/>
of all this, what does the hon. member for Simcoe <lb/>
wish to do to-day? What does he undertake? He <lb/>
undertakes to deprive the people of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Quebec, of their just share in this great <lb/>
heritage,—towards the purchase of which, towards <lb/>
the colonisation of which, they have so largely <lb/>
contributed. This, Mr. Speaker, is the unjust <lb/>
undertaking of the hon. member with regard to <lb/>
the Province of Quebec; whereas without us, I do <lb/>
not hesitate to say it, without us there would be <lb/>
no North-West, no Canadian Pacific Railway, no <lb/>
colonisation in the West, and this vast country <lb/>
would be in a wild state. If the Dominion is to<lb break="no"/>day in possession of these rich Territories, she <lb/>
owes them to the French element, which the hon. <lb/>
member fights against with so much vigor. I do <lb/>
not understand how they can require that we <lb/>
should be at the same time loyal subjects of Her <lb/>
Majesty, and that we should be disloyal towards <lb/>
our mother tongue. We must defend it with all <lb/>
our powers; it is our right, and it is our duty. <lb/>
And I declare that the man who voluntarily <lb/>
surrenders his mother tongue, is not a good citizen, <lb/>
he is a man whose loyalty would not remain firm <lb/>
after every trial, as that of the subjects of Her <lb/>
Majesty ought to do. The hon. member for Simcoe <lb/>
has not always reasoned in the same way respect<lb break="no"/>ing minorities. Everybody remembers the attitude <lb/>
taken by the hon. members for North Simcoe, for <lb/>
North Bruce (Mr. McNeill) as well as that of <lb/>
several other members who follow them, when <lb/>
In this House, the resolution asking for "Home <lb/>
Rule" in Ireland was rejected; we all know that, <lb/>

<cb/>

at this period, these gentlemen raised objections <lb/>
to this resolution, stating that we were going to <lb/>
sacrifice the Protestant minority in Ireland, and <lb/>
to place it at the mercy of the Roman Catholic <lb/>
majority. Such were the objections from these <lb/>
hon. gentlemen. Have these hon. members two <lb/>
weights and two measures—the one for the <lb/>
Roman Catholics, the other for their coreli<lb break="no"/>gionists the Protestants? I must hasten to <lb/>
conclude. I know that the House is anxious <lb/>
to close this debate; but I was surprised <lb/>
at the remarks which some of my colleagues <lb/>
speaking the English language made. And I can<lb break="no"/>not pass them over in silence. It has been ad<lb break="no"/>mitted that the hon. the Minister of Public Works <lb/>
(Sir Hector Langevin), was moderate as respects <lb/>
the expressions used in his speech on the present <lb/>
question, but it is alleged that he was too vigorous <lb/>
in its utterance. I cannot conceive how these <lb/>
hon. members can reproach the hon. Minister of <lb/>
Public Works with having testified by a degree of <lb/>
vivacity in his speedy—he, one of the fathers of <lb/>
Confederation, he, the successor of the illustrious <lb/>
statesman, Sir George Etienne Cartier. I think <lb/>
that he would have been wanting in his duty if he <lb/>
had not borne witness against the resolution of <lb/>
the hon. member for North Simcoe, with some<lb break="no"/>thing of indignation. In any case it would not be <lb/>
me who would blame him for it. It is to my <lb/>
knowledge that several of my English colleagues, <lb/>
—and I do not say it of them as a reproach—in <lb/>
support of interests much less serious than those <lb/>
which are now being discussed, displayed much <lb/>
more energy in their language than did the hon. <lb/>
Minister of Public Works. My compatriots, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, the French Canadians of the Province of <lb/>
Quebec, will be doubtless much obliged to many <lb/>
hon. members in this House,—I may say to the <lb/>
great majority of the members of this House—for <lb/>
the sympathy which they have extended to our <lb/>
nationality, during this debate, for the respect <lb/>
which they have shown for the rights of minor<lb break="no"/>ities, and for the firm determination which <lb/>
they have shown to defend them on all occa<lb break="no"/>sions. Among those distinguished men, who <lb/>
have come forward generously in support of <lb/>
the Government, in order to make easier their <lb/>
task, and to assist them in giving us justice, <lb/>
I must mention the hon. member for West Dur<lb break="no"/>ham (Mr. Blake), and I regret that again, this <lb/>
evening, on account of his great liberality towards <lb/>
us, it has been thought proper to attack him some<lb break="no"/>what violently. <lb/></p> 

<p>Some <persName ref="pers:ANON1">hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Hear, hear. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DUPO1">Mr. DUPONT</persName>. The speech of the hon. member <lb/>
for West Durham, as well as the other speakers <lb/>
who have spoken in defence of our cause, will dwell <lb/>
in the shrine of history; they will serve as lessons <lb/>
for our successors in this House, and for our pos<lb break="no"/>terity; they are founded in reason and on justice, <lb/>
and they show the true position in which minorities <lb/>
should be placed, in no matter what country. It <lb/>
might be said that in the family of the hon. member <lb/>
for West Durham,—I must render him this <lb/>
acknowledgment; and you all know, moreover, <lb/>
that he is no political friend of mine, I did not, in <lb/>
general, support his policy when he was leader of a <lb/>
    party in this House,—it might be said, I say, that <lb/>
in questions of right, on great questions of justice, <lb/>
the hon. member has shown that British fair-play <lb/>

<pb n="1011" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01011.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1011</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1012</fw> 

was, so to speak, bred in the bones of the family <lb/>
of Blake. I believe that every good citizen, every <lb/>
man who is a friend to his country, ought to be <lb/>
dismayed at the conclusions arrived at by the hon. <lb/>
member for West Durham. He has concluded his <lb/>
train of reasoning by these forcible words: if justice <lb/>
is not done to the minorities, if we kindle in this <lb/>
country a war of races, a religious war, neither <lb/>
prosperity nor progress will ever be possibilities for <lb/>
us. I do not know, Mr. Speaker, which ought to <lb/>
frighten us the most, whether it be this formidable <lb/>
conclusion or the inevitable contained in this con<lb break="no"/>clusion. If the policy of the hon. member for <lb/>
North Simcoe should prevail, I believe that the con<lb break="no"/>clusion of the hon. member West Durham is inevit<lb break="no"/>able. I think that every patriot who loves his <lb/>
country, no matter to what nationality he may <lb/>
belong, should make superhuman efforts to keep <lb/>
the nation far from the path of discord into <lb/>
which the hon. member for North Simcoe <lb/>
and his friends desire to thrust it. I think that <lb/>
every public man,—and it seems to me that they <lb/>
wish to do it, for the hon. member for Northum<lb break="no"/>berland (Mr. Mitchell), intensely warlike as he is, <lb/>
has spoken with moderation and wisdom. He also <lb/>
has come to the aid of the Government to assist <lb/>
them in settling this difficult matter,—all public <lb/>
men should work together in concert, and with all <lb/>
possible energy, to lift us from the way of discord <lb/>
into which We are entering, and to thrust the na<lb break="no"/>tion from it as from a nest of vipers. Mr. Speaker, <lb/>
with these few remarks I conclude, heartily thank<lb break="no"/>ing the House for having kindly given me their <lb/>
attention. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SCRI1">Mr. SCRIVER</persName>. Mr. Speaker, in view of the <lb/>
great length to which this debate has extended, it <lb/>
having now occupied seven days, and sympathising <lb/>
as I do with the natural impatience of the House, <lb/>
I shall not detain hon. members more than such <lb/>
time as will enable me, in a very few words, to ex<lb break="no"/>plain the position I take on this question. I regret <lb/>
exceedingly that the question which is now before <lb/>
the House has been brought into it. I feared, when <lb/>
the Bill of the hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. <lb/>
McCarthy) was introduced, it would give rise not <lb/>
only to great differences of opinion, but perhaps to <lb/>
angry and intemperate discussion, and would excite <lb/>
great feeling, not only in the House, but through<lb break="no"/>out the length and breadth of the land. The im<lb break="no"/>passioned, not to say intemperate, utterances of <lb/>
some leading members on both sides of the House <lb/>
have satisfied me that my apprehension had some <lb/>
foundation. I was desirous, therefore, that some <lb/>
solution of the question should be reached which <lb/>
would remove it from this House, and relegate it <lb/>
to some authority to which it would be reasonable, <lb/>
just and fair to refer it, and I was glad, therefore, <lb/>
when the hon. member for Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) <lb/>
submitted the amendment he proposed. It met <lb/>
my views completely under the circumstances, and <lb/>
I determined at the time it was submitted that, <lb/>
unless some modification of it was proposed which <lb/>
would more fully meet my views, would support <lb/>
it. With regard to the amendment proposed by <lb/>
the Minister of Justice, it does not meet my views <lb/>
as does the amendment submitted by the hon. <lb/>
member for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin). I think <lb/>
that if the decision of this question is relegated to <lb/>
the people of the North-West, whom it mainly <lb/>
concerns, those people should be given the power <lb/>

<cb/>

to consider it in all its aspects, and it should not <lb/>
be divided into portions as is proposed by the <lb/>
amendment of the Minister of Justice. I agree <lb/>
with the hon. member for Queen's, P. E. I. (Mr. <lb/>
Davies), in considering that a half-hearted measure, <lb/>
and I shall, therefore, feel constrained to vote <lb/>
against the amendment to the amendment, and, if <lb/>
that should be lost, to vote in favor of the amend<lb break="no"/>ment moved by the hon. member for West As<lb break="no"/>siniboia (Mr. Davin). <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PATE1">Mr. PATERSON</persName> (Brant). I recognise that the <lb/>
House is anxious to reach a decision on this <lb/>
question, and I shall, therefore, not attempt to <lb/>
discuss it at any length. I confine myself to the <lb/>
question now before us. It is not a question as <lb/>
between the amendment and the original motion <lb/>
proposing the second reading of the Bill, but is a <lb/>
choice between the amendment by the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin), and the <lb/>
amendment to the amendment proposed by the <lb/>
Minister of Justice. I desire to say that, as I ap<lb break="no"/>prove more highly of the wording of the amend<lb break="no"/>ment offered by the member for Assiniboia than I <lb/>
do of that offered by the Minister of Justice, <lb/>
I shall be forced to vote against the amendment to <lb/>
the amendment. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. Mr. Speaker, a few days ago, <lb/>
in the course of this debate, I stated that my <lb/>
opinion was that the best and most proper time to <lb/>
settle this question would be when Parliament <lb/>
felt that the time had come to extend to the <lb/>
North-West Territories a larger measure of local <lb/>
autonomy than they now enjoy. I voted for the <lb/>
amendment of the hon. member for Berthier <lb/>
(Mr. Beausoleil) on this express condition. I did <lb/>
not approve altogether of the wording of the <lb/>
amendment of my hon. friend; but I thought, on <lb/>
the whole, that the idea therein expressed, that <lb/>
our institutions in the North-West should be <lb/>
permanent, was true to this extent, that they <lb/>
should be permanent in every particular so long as <lb/>
the present form of government in the North-West <lb/>
endured. This view has not prevailed, and the <lb/>
consequence is that the House is not called upon <lb/>
to deal with this question. I then also stated that <lb/>
when the time came, be that time early or late, <lb/>
the only way to deal with the question before <lb/>
the House would be on the broad principle <lb/>
of local autonomy. I thought from the first and <lb/>
I still more than ever believe it, that the only <lb/>
method under which we can carry out the system <lb/>
of Confederation, the only method by which we <lb/>
can give justice and fair play to minorities, wher<lb break="no"/>ever minorities may be situated, will depend alto<lb break="no"/>gether on the adoption of the principle of local au<lb break="no"/>tonomy. It has been stated to-day that there really <lb/>
is no question of autonomy or Provincial rights here. <lb/>
It may be said we have no Provincial rights, in <lb/>
the technical sense, in the Territories, but the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple involved is the same. Although the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories have not been organised into Provinces, the <lb/>
principle applying to the case is the same as if they <lb/>
had been so organised. The only difference is <lb/>
that their powers would be supreme and abso<lb break="no"/>lute if they were organised into Provinces, <lb/>
and that they should not, in my judgment, be <lb/>
subject to the revision of the Central Government. <lb/>
For all that, the principle remains unimpaired, and <lb/>
should be acted upon, that the will of the people of <lb/>
the Territories aected ought to be the will which <lb/>

<pb n="1013" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01013.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1013</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">1014</fw>

should prevail in the solution of this question, and <lb/>
of all other similar questions. My hon. friend, the <lb/>
member for Norfolk (Mr. Charlton), stated this after<lb break="no"/>noon that the best method of solving this question, <lb/>
with a view to Provincial rights, would be simply to <lb/>
affirm the principle of the Bill itself. Surely, my <lb/>
hon. friend was not serious in so speaking. The <lb/>
Bill of my hon. friend from Simcoe proposes to <lb/>
abrogate clause 110 of the North-West Territories <lb/>
Act, which clause provides that either the English <lb/>
or the French language may be used by any person <lb/>
in the debates of the Council or Legislative Assem<lb break="no"/>bly of the Territories. If you simply repeal this <lb/>
clause, you remove from the Legislature of the <lb/>
Territories the power which they now have of using <lb/>
either the French or the English language in their <lb/>
debates. What I understand by Provincial rights <lb/>
—and I suppose what my hon. friend must under<lb break="no"/>stand—is, that the people of the Territories should <lb/>
decide for themselves whether or not they are to <lb/>
    have the privilege or the <hi rendition="simple:italic">onus</hi> of having two official <lb/>
languages. If you remove that law, you take away <lb/>
from them the privilege which they now have of <lb/>
using the two languages. I do not believe that is <lb/>
in the direction of Provincial rights, or Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial autonomy. The amendment of my hon. <lb/>
friend, the Minister of Justice, tends to uphold <lb/>
Provincial rights and local autonomy, and I am <lb/>
happy to extend my congratulations to the Prime <lb/>
Minister, and to his Government that more and <lb/>
more, and day by day, the force of circumstances <lb/>
brings them over to this principle. More and <lb/>
more the principle grows, and they are forced to <lb/>
adopt it, in spite of their former practice in older <lb/>
times. It is stated, however, against this amend<lb break="no"/>ment of the Minister of Justice, that it is not so <lb/>
complete as the amendment moved by the member <lb/>
for Assiniboia (Mr. Davin). It may not be so <lb/>
complete, but it is not the less just, for the amend<lb break="no"/>ment of my hon. friend the Minister of Justice <lb/>
involves this: that in the debates of the Local As<lb break="no"/>sembly of the North-West, and in the recording <lb/>
of their proceedings, they shall have the privilege <lb/>
of using one language or the other, or both, and <lb/>
they shall be empowered to decide for themselves <lb/>
whether they shall have only one official language <lb/>
or two official languages. There is, then, the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of the courts, and it has been stated (and I <lb/>
think properly stated), that the use of the lan<lb break="no"/>guage in courts, would be acknowledged as beyond <lb/>
the power of the Dominion Parliament. There <lb/>
then remains the question of the printing of the <lb/>
statutes. So long as we provide the Territories with <lb/>
a revenue, can any serious objection be taken to <lb/>
the fact that we should provide for the printing of <lb/>
the laws and ordinances in the North-West? I <lb/>
can see very well that if the Territories had to <lb/>
provide that out of their own revenue, to impose any <lb/>
obligations upon them, which they would not want <lb/>
to assume, might be a grievance. But so long as we <lb/>
give them the revenue, surely no man can object; <lb/>
and we who supply the money ought to have the <lb/>
power to put upon it an obligation (which is not <lb/>
after all an unreasonable obligation), and which on <lb/>
the other hand is in the tendency of peace and har<lb break="no"/>mony. It has been stated that this amendment <lb/>
was a compromise. I must say for my part, and <lb/>
the First Minister will hear me out, that there has <lb/>
been no compromise between him and me. I <lb/>
always have stated publicly as well as privately, <lb/>
and I have never disguised my thoughts on this <lb/>

<cb/>

matter, that, in my judgment, sooner or later, and <lb/>
better sooner than later, this question had to be <lb/>
settled upon the broad basis of local autonomy. <lb/>
In fact, if this question has taken a wider range <lb/>
than is involved in the principle of local autonomy, <lb/>
it is simply because the member for Simcoe has <lb/>
chosen to make it so. If the hon. member for Simcoe <lb/>
(Mr. McCarthy), instead of placing as the basis of <lb/>
his Bill, that there should be a community of lan<lb break="no"/>guage, and that this community of language should <lb/>
extend everywhere in the Dominion where French <lb/>
is spoken, had simply left it to the will and the <lb/>
desire of the people of the Territories, we would not <lb/>
have had one-half or one-tenth part of all the <lb/>
trouble we have had over this question. But it <lb/>
is because the people of Quebec have good reason <lb/>
to suppose that this was a preliminary skirmish, <lb/>
soon to be followed by other attacks, soon to be <lb/>
followed by attacks which would reach them in their <lb/>
own Province, that they have been so excited. A <lb/>
few days ago, the hon. member for Simcoe, speak<lb break="no"/>ing in this debate, disclaimed the idea of imposing <lb/>
his will upon the people of Quebec and attempting <lb/>
to deprive them of their language; but it seems <lb/>
that the hon. gentleman is not so brave here as he <lb/>
was in Manitoba; for in Manitoba he is recorded <lb/>
as having stated that if the French language was <lb/>
abolished in that Province, it would be abolished <lb/>
in Quebec. Is it to be wondered that the <lb/>
people of Quebec have felt as they have felt upon <lb/>
this question in face of such a threat as this? <lb/>
I want to say to my fellow-countrymen of French <lb/>
origin that we must expect, in the face of such a <lb/>
declaration, that, some day or other, this agitation <lb/>
commenced here will be carried into our Province. <lb/>
Let us remember this: that if we are prepared to <lb/>
stand by the principle of local autonomy in the <lb/>
North-West Territories, we will stand ten times, <lb/>
and a hundred times, stronger when we have to <lb/>
meet an attack in our own Province. If we are <lb/>
now prepared to stand by the principle of local <lb/>
autonomy, I submit that, when the time comes, <lb/>
we will find a tower of strength in the position <lb/>
which we may take upon this question. This is <lb/>
one of the reasons which impel me to take the <lb/>
action I propose on this measure, that is, to sup<lb break="no"/>port the amendment of the hon. Minister of <lb/>
Justice. I quite realise that it must be painful for <lb/>
many hon. members from the Province of Quebec <lb/>
to vote for a measure which may, perhaps, imply <lb/>
the possibility that the French language should <lb/>
cease to be the official language in the North-West <lb/>
Territories. I have no reason to suppose, and <lb/>
I do not for one moment suppose, that the people <lb/>
of the North-West Territories would act unjustly <lb/>
or unfairly towards the French minority. I know <lb/>
it has been said that, if we vote this meas<lb break="no"/>ure, it is a foregone conclusion that the French <lb/>
language will not be an official language of the <lb/>
North-West, because the Legislature has already <lb/>
expressed its opinion in favor of removing it as an <lb/>
official language. Well, that is true; but we must <lb/>
remember that at present there is not one single <lb/>
member speaking French in that Legislature, and if, <lb/>
after the next election, there should be no change <lb/>
in the representation, if there should be no French <lb/>
representative in the North-West Territories As<lb break="no"/>sembly, surely no one will complain if, under such <lb/>
circumstances, after the attention of the people <lb/>
has been roused to the question, the Local Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture were to adhere to its present intention. I <lb/>

<pb n="1015" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01015.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1016</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1016</fw> 

believe, for all that, that if there were even a <lb/>
sprinkling of French members in the Local Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture, the majority would act with the same spirit <lb/>
of fairness towards them that the Legislature of <lb/>
Upper Canada evinced in 1793, as shown in the in<lb break="no"/>cident to which our attention was directed by the <lb/>
Prime Minister yesterday. I believe that they <lb/>
would act in the same spirit of fairness towards the <lb/>
minority which was evinced by the Legislature of <lb/>
Canada in 1845. As I said a moment ago, I am <lb/>
not at all surprised that some of my fellow-country<lb break="no"/>men should feel strongly upon this question, and <lb/>
that they should propose to adhere to their present <lb/>
intention. As for myself I must say it is a matter <lb/>
of deep anguish to me that upon this question I <lb/>
have to sever my connection with such a life-long <lb/>
friend as the hon. member for Berthier (Mr. Beau<lb break="no"/>soleil). I know he is acting for the best interests <lb/>
of his country accordin to his lights, and I am <lb/>
sure he will give me credit that in voting as I shall <lb/>
have to do with the Government on this question, I do <lb/>
so not out of any love to the Government, but with <lb/>
the conviction that in so doing I am acting in the <lb/>
best interest of my party and my country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. IVES</persName>. I desire to occupy the time of the <lb/>
House only for a moment, in order to say that I <lb/>
am against both the spirit and intention of the <lb/>
Bill of the hon. member for Simcoe. For my <lb/>
own part, I think it would have been far preferable <lb/>
if this House had deferred the settlement of this <lb/>
whole question until such time as the increase of <lb/>
population in the North-West Territories had made <lb/>
it necessary that portions of that territory should <lb/>
be organised into Provinces. I believe it is im<lb break="no"/>possible at the present moment for any member of <lb/>
this House to know what will be the position <lb/>
or character of the population which may settle <lb/>
in that vast domain. We may perhaps have on <lb/>
the Saskatchewan a territory large enough for a <lb/>
Province, including in its population a large <lb/>
majority of people speaking the French language, <lb/>
and we may perhaps have in Alberta a population <lb/>
purely English; and when the different parts of <lb/>
that territory are organised into Provinces, the <lb/>
question could be very easily settled by this <lb/>
Parliament without annoyance to the people of <lb/>
the Territories, and without straining unduly the <lb/>
principle of local autonomy to which my hon. <lb/>
friend who last addressed the House has referred. <lb/>
In that way we might perhaps arrive at a settle<lb break="no"/>ment of this whole question without this debate <lb/>
or this agitation. For these reasons, and because <lb/>
I would not see the French language abolished <lb/>
in this House or in the country, any more than I <lb/>
would see the French Canadians obliged to leave <lb/>
the country, I supported the amendment of the <lb/>
hon. member for Berthier (Mr. Beausoleil). But <lb/>
that motion has been disposed of, and we have <lb/>
now to choose between the amendment of the hon. <lb/>
Minister of Justice and the amendment of the hon. <lb/>
member for Assiniboia (Mr. Davin), and when I <lb/>
have to choose between these two amendments I <lb/>
naturally choose that which least disturbs pre<lb break="no"/>sent conditions. Therefore, I intend to support <lb/>
the amendment of the hon. Minister of Justice. If <lb/>
I could be assured that an amendment would be <lb/>
carried in this House to defer the whole question <lb/>
until the organisation of Provinces in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories, I would support such a motion; <lb/>
but in the division we had on the amendment of <lb/>

<cb/>

the hon. member for Berthier, we saw arrayed on <lb/>
one side almost the whole force of the members <lb/>
from the Province of Quebec, who have no objec<lb break="no"/>tion to the French language or institutions, and <lb/>
we saw arrayed on the other side, all the other <lb/>
members of this House. When our views, therefore, <lb/>
failed to meet with the approval of a majority of <lb/>
the House, I think it is a serious risk to persist, as <lb/>
does the hon. member for Berthier, in rejecting the <lb/>
amendment of the hon. Minister of Justice, which <lb/>
certainly is not a serious interference with the rights <lb/>
of the French Canadians, but is a safe and fair <lb/>
compromise measure, and one which ought to be <lb/>
supported. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. I quite appreciate the <lb/>
desire of the House that this debate should close, <lb/>
and I would not have risen now to say a word if <lb/>
it had not been for the personal attack which, even <lb/>
at this late hour, the leader of the Opposition could <lb/>
not forbear to make upon me. I desire to repudi<lb break="no"/>ate the statement he has made with regard to my <lb/>
saying anything in Manitoba which I have not <lb/>
said here. My reference in Manitoba was not to <lb/>
the French language in the Province of Quebec; <lb/>
but there, as in Montreal, it was to the possibility— <lb/>
which I then thought was within reach, and which <lb/>
I do not yet deny to myself the hope of being <lb/>
accomplished—that the tithe and fabrique ques<lb break="no"/>tions may yet be settled in the Province of Quebec, <lb/>
and settled I dare say with the aid of my hon. <lb/>
friend who now leads the Opposition. That was <lb/>
the question I referred to, and not the question of <lb/>
the French language, as my hon. friend will see if <lb/>
he will do me the justice to read the deliberate <lb/>
statement I made in Montreal. Having troubled <lb/>
the House again, I would like to say this with <lb/>
regard to the amendment before us. It has been <lb/>
stated here that this amendment is a measure of <lb/>
peace; but I wish this House to understand that <lb/>
what may be a measure of peace here, between the <lb/>
hon. members on both sides of this House, may <lb/>
be anything but a measure of peace in this country. <lb/>
For my part, I see in this amendment every <lb/>
possible evil which we have had suggested to us <lb/>
throughout this debate. It relegates a portion of <lb/>
this difficult and disturbing subject to the people <lb/>
of the North-West. That certainly is not a <lb/>
measure of peace, so far as they are concerned. <lb/>
It leaves the remaining part to be dealt with <lb/>
by this Parliament; and the House very much <lb/>
mistakes, no matter what its vote may be to<lb break="no"/>night, if it thinks that this Parliament has heard <lb/>
the last of this question; for I can assure this <lb/>
House that if the matter is disposed of here to<lb break="no"/>night by the adoption of the amendment of the <lb/>
hon. Minister of Justice, I shall bring it up again <lb/>
at the earliest opportunity. If this is so—and that <lb/>
is certainly within my right, as the hon. member <lb/>
for Queen's, P. E. I. (Mr. Davies) said last evening, <lb/>
and not only within my right, but within my duty <lb/>
—then where is the benefit of postponing, or de<lb break="no"/>laying, or procrastinating on a question which we <lb/>
are told involves so many difficulties? This may <lb/>
or may not be a matter for the Territories to settle <lb/>
themselves, or for this Parliament to settle; but <lb/>
this measure raises no question between the right <lb/>
of the Territories and the right of this House to <lb/>
deal with it; because every member of this House <lb/>
knows perfectly well that if the Bill I have intro<lb break="no"/>duced passes this House, it will be with the full <lb/>

<pb n="1017" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-21_Page_01017.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1017</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 21, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">1018</fw>

assent and concurrence of a great majority of the <lb/>
people of the North-West Territories. But whether <lb/>
it is a matter for the Territories or for us to de<lb break="no"/>cide, we are neither doing one thing nor the other <lb/>
by making a pretence here for the sake of peace, <lb/>
by shaking hands across this table, by the leaders <lb/>
on this side and on that side putting their heads <lb/>
    together and coercing their followers,—<lb/> </p> 

<p>Some <persName ref="pers:ANON1">hon. MEMBERS</persName>. No. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>-because an amendment <lb/>
which will satisfy neither one party nor the other <lb/>
is not going to satisfy this country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. PLATT</persName>. Mr. Speaker, the division which <lb/>
we appear about to reach will, I believe, close this <lb/>
debate; but the division list will not define the <lb/>
exact position of those who will vote nay. They <lb/>
are composed of three distinct parties: Those led <lb/>
by the hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. <lb/>
McCarthy), who wish to reach his Bill, in order <lb/>
that they may support it; those led by the hon. <lb/>
member for Berthier (Mr. Beausoleil), who wish <lb/>
to support neither amendment nor the Bill; and <lb/>
those who wish to reach the first amendment, <lb/>
that proposed by the hon. member for Assiniboia <lb/>
(Mr. Davin), in order that they may support it. <lb/>
I wish to define my position to be that I desire to <lb/>
reach the amendment moved by my hon. friend <lb/>
from Assiniboia (Mr. Davin), because I prefer it <lb/>
to the one moved by the hon. the Minister of <lb/>
Justice; but if the choice lay between the amend<lb break="no"/>ment moved by the hon. the Minister of Justice, <lb/>
and the original motion, I should support the <lb/>
amendment of the hon. Minister of Justice. <lb/></p> 

<p>House divided on the amendment to the amend<lb break="no"/>ment (Sir John Thompson): <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>That this House, having regard to the long continued <lb/>
use of the Frenc language in old Canada, and to the <lb/>
covenants on that subject embodied in the British North <lb/>
America Act, cannot agree to the declaration Contained <lb/>
in the said Bill as the basis thereof, that it is expedient in <lb/>
the interest of the national unity of the Dominion that <lb/>
there should be community of language amongst the <lb/>
people of Canada;   <lb/></p> 

<p>That, on the contrary, this House declares its ad<lb break="no"/>herence to the said covenants and its determination to <lb/>
resist any attempt to impair the same; <lb/></p> 

<p>That, at the same time, this House deems it expedient <lb/>
and proper and not inconsistent with those covenants that <lb/>
the legislative Assembly of the N orth-West Territories <lb/>
should receive from the Parliament of Canada power to <lb/>
regulate, after the next general election of the Assembly, <lb/>
the proceedings of the Assembly and the manner of re<lb break="no"/>cording and publishing such proceedings. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
    
    
<head rendition="simple:centre">YEAS:</head>

<head rendition="simple:centre">Messieurs</head>

<table>
    <row><cell>Audet,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Jones (Halifax),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Bain (Soulanges),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Kenny,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Barnard,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Kirk,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Béchard,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Kirkpatrick,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Bergeron,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Labrosse,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Bergin,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Landry,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Bernier,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Langelier (Montmorency),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Blake,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Langelier (Quebec),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Boisvert,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Langevin (Sir Hector),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Borden,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">LaRiviere,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Bowell,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Laurie (Lieut.-General),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Bowman</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Laurier,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Brien,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Lépine,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Brown,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Lister,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Bryson,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Lovitt,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Burdett,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Macdonald (Sir John),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Cameron,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Macdowall,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Campbell,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McCulla,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Cargill,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McDonald (Victoria),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Carling,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McDougald (Pietou),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Carpenter,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McDougall (Cape Breton),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Casgrain,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McIntyre,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Chapleau,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McKay,</cell></row>
    
</table>
<cb/>
        
        <table>
            <row><cell>Choquette,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McKeen,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Chouinard,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McMillan (Vaudreuil),</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Cimon,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Madill,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Cochrane,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Mara,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Cockburn,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Marshall,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Colby,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Masson,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Cook,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Massue,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Corby,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Meigs</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Costigan,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Mills (Annapolis),</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Coughlin,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Mills (Bothwell),</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Coulombe,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Mitchell,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Curran,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Moffat,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Daly,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Monerieff,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Daoust,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Montplaisir,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Davin,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Perley,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Davis,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Pope,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Dawson,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Porter,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>De St. Georges,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Prior,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Desaulniers,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Purcell,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Desjardins,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Putnam,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Dessaint,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Rinfret,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Dewdney,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Riopel,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Dickey,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Robillard,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Dickinson,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Roome,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Dupont,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Ross,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Earle,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Rykert,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Edgar,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Scarth,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Edwards,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Shanley,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Eisenhauer,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Skinner,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Ferguson( Leeds and Gren.),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Small,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Ferguson(Renfrew),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Smith (Sir Donald),</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Ferguson(Welland),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Smith (Ontario),</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Fiset,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Sproule,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Flynn,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Stevenson,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Foster,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Taylor,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Freeman,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Temple,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Gigault,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Therien,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Girouard,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Thompson(Sir John),</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Gordon,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Trow,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Grandbois,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Tupper,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Guay,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Turcot,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Guillet,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Vanasse,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Haggart,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wallace,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Hesson,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Ward,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Hickey,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">White(Cardwell),</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Holton,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wilmot,</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Hudspeth,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wilson(Argenteuil),</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Ives,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wood (Brockville), and</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Jamieson,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wood (Westmoreland), and</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Joncas,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wright.—149.</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Jones(Digby),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
        
        </table>
    </div>
<div type="debate">
    
<head rendition="simple:centre">NAYS:</head>

<head rendition="simple:centre">Messieurs</head>
    
    <table>
        <row><cell>Amyot,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McNeill,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Armstrong,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Mulock,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Bain (Wentworth),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Neveu,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Barron,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">O'Brien,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Beausoleil,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Paterson(Brant),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Bell,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Perry,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Bourassa,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Platt,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Charlton,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Préfontaine,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Couture,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Robertson,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Davies,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Rowand,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Denison,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Ste. Marie,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Doyon,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Scriver,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Ellis,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Semple,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Gauthier,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Somerville,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Geoffrion,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Sutherland,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Gillmor,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Tyrwhitt,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Hale,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Waldie,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Innes,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Watson,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Landerkin,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Weldon (Albert),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Lang,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Weldon (St.John),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Livingston,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Welsh,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Macdonald (Huron),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">White (Renfrew),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>McCarthy,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wilson (Elgin),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>McMillan (Huron),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wilson (Lennox), and</cell></row>
        <row><cell>McMullen,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Yeo.—50.</cell></row>
        
    </table>

<p>Amendment to amendment agreed to <lb/></p> 

<p>Amendment, as amended, agreed to on the same <lb/>
division. <lb/></p> 

<p>Main motion, as amended, agreed to on the <lb/>
same division. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName> moved the ad<lb break="no"/>journment of the House. <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed to; and House adjourned at <lb/>
10.25 p.m. <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>