<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1894-03-21"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1894-03-21">21 March 1894</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1894"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="180"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00159.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00161.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00163.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00165.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00167.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00169.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00171.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00173.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00175.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00177.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00179.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00159">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00159.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00161">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00161.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00163">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00163.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00165">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00165.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00167">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00167.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00169">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00169.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00171">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00171.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00173">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00173.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00175">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00175.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00177">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00177.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00179">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00179.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="159" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00159.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">159</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">160</fw>
            
            
            <!-- GL, 2018-10-19, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day -->    
            <!--<p>
     and $120,526.49 on the 2nd of August. 1892. 
     <lb/>
     No moneys have been paid by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to the possessors of the leasehold inter<lb break="no"/>est in this property. The fee simple has been 
     <lb/>
     obtained and vested in the Queen of the 
     <lb/>
     whole property purchased, which includes 
     <lb/>
     the leasehold. $5,944 was expended in build<lb break="no"/>ing cribwork approach, laying tracks, floors, 
     <lb/>
     &amp;c. The total sttm does not exceed the par<lb break="no"/>liamentary appropriations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     
     THE SCHOOLS OF MANITOBA AND     
     <lb/>THE N.W.T.<lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LARI1">Mr. LaRiVIERE</persName> moved for: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Copies of all petitions, memorials and corres<lb break="no"/>pondence in reference to the appeal made in the 
     <lb/>
     name of the Roman Catholic minority of the 
     <lb/>
     province of Manitoba, in reference to the school, 
     <lb/>
     laws of that province: also, copies of reports to? 
     <lb/>
     and Orders in ('ouncil in reference to the same: 
     <lb/>
     also. copies of the case submitted to the Supreme 
     <lb/>
     Court of Canada respecting aforesaid appeal, and 
     <lb/>
     including factums and all materials in connection 
     <lb/>
     therewith, and copies of all judgments rendered 
     <lb/>
     and answers given by said court on or to the ques<lb break="no"/>tions referred to them. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     He said: Mr. Speaker. in making this mo<lb break="no"/>tion. I do not intend at the present. time to 
     <lb/>
     discuss the merits of the question that is in<lb break="no"/>volved. I shall wait tmtil all the papers are. 
     <lb/>
     put before the House and until the members 
     <lb/>
     are fully cognizant of the details of the ques<lb break="no"/>tion. I have my own opinion as to the mer<lb break="no"/>its of the case, and as to the action that has 
     <lb/>
     been taken thereon, and I intend, later on, 
     <lb/>
     as, I have no doubt, an opportunity will be 
     <lb/>
     given, to express that opinion in an unbiassed 
     <lb/>
     and in a fair and impartial manner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LARI1">Mr. LaRIVIERE</persName> moved for: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Copies of all school ordinances, school regula<lb break="no"/>tions or by-laws and amendments thereto, adopted 
     <lb/>
     by the Legislative Assembly, the Executive. andd 
     <lb/>
     by any Board or Council of Education, in reference 
     <lb/>
     to the establishment, maintenance and administra<lb break="no"/>tion of schools in the North-west Territories since 
     <lb/>
     1885: also, for copies of all petitions, memorials 
     <lb/>
     and correspondence in reference thereto: also, for 
     <lb/>
     copies of all reports to and Orders in Council res<lb break="no"/>pecting the same. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p></quote>
            
            
            <p>He said: My remarks on the previous mo<lb break="no"/>tion also apply to this. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName> moved for: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     1. Copies of all correspondence between His 
     <lb/>
     Grace Archbishop Tache, of St. Boniface, and any 
     <lb/>
     member of the Government since last session, and 
     <lb/>
     in particular of the memorial recently sent to the 
     <lb/>
     Governor General, or to the Prime Minister. res<lb break="no"/>pecting the Manitoba schools, and of the ordinances . 
     <lb/>
     adopted by the Legislature of the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Territories in 1892, and now in force; 2. Copies of 
     <lb/>
     all memorials, petitions and letters addressed to the 
     <lb/>
        
        
            <cb/>
          
          
     Governor General in Council, or to any Minister 
     <lb/>
     asking for the disallowance of the said ordinances: 
     <lb/>
     3. Of correspondence between the Lieutenant 
     <lb/>
     Governor of the North-west Territories or the 
     <lb/>
     Executive Council of the said Territories, and the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Government: 4. Copies of the instruc<lb break="no"/>tions to the Lieutenant Governor of the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Territories, and of communications sent to the 
     <lb/>
     Executive. of the Tcrritories in order to induce them 
     <lb/>
     to amend the ordinances of 1892. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     He said: Mr. Speaker, I feel it to be my 
     <lb/>
     duty to put this motion in your hands and to 
     <lb/>
     offer a few remarks upon it; and, imperfect 
     <lb/>
     as my English may be, I venture to ask the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the House while I attempt to 
     <lb/>
     address it in that language. Since the be<lb break="no"/>ginning of the session hon. members of this 
     <lb/>
     House. on both sides. have carefully dis<lb break="no"/>cussed the commercial and financial position 
     <lb/>
     of this country. Nobody has yet alluded to 
     <lb/>
    its political situation. or rather to the grave 
     <lb/>national crisis with which we are face to 
     <lb/>face today—thanks. I am sorry to say, to the 
     <lb/>unwise, imprudent and irritating policy of 
     <lb/>the Government on the school question. Per<lb break="no"/>mit me. Sir, to use, as a description of that 
     <lb/>crisis, a speech which has recently been de<lb break="no"/>livered in the city of Montreal by one of the 
     <lb/>leading Conservatives of the province of Que<lb break="no"/>bec—fine Hon. T. C. Casgrain. the Attorney 
     <lb/>General in the Taillon Cabinet. That hon. 
     <lb/>gentleman, speaking at a meeting of the 
     <lb/>Cartier-Macdonald Club. a few days ago—I 
     <lb/>quote from the Montreal 'Gazette' of the 
     <lb/>28th of February—expressed himself as fol<lb break="no"/>lows :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     A terrible wind is now blowing even at the very 
     <lb/>
     doors of the province of Quebec ; and the storm is 
     <lb/>
     so strong that it is shaking Confederation to its 
     <lb/>
     very foundations. It is a difficult and delicate 
     <lb/>
     question which I am now taking up, and I wish to 
     <lb/>
     say that I am now speaking only as a citizen of 
     <lb/>
     Canada. I am now speaking of the question of 
     <lb/>
     separate schools in the North-west. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Confederation was the result of a cmnpromise. 
     <lb/>
     In order to protect our fellow-countrymen. who 
     <lb/>
     had carried the seed of civilization to the North<lb break="no"/>west, we stipulated that they should always have 
     <lb/>
     the right to separate schools. Now, I contend that 
     <lb/>
     no one has the right to do indirectly what the law 
     <lb/>
     forbids to do directly. No one had the right to 
     <lb/>
     deprive the Catholics of the North-west of their 
     <lb/>
     separate schools. The Hon. Mr. Haultain, the Pre<lb break="no"/>mier of the North-west Territories, understood 
     <lb/>
     that perfectly well. That is why he went in a 
     <lb/>
     roundabout way. He overhauled all the ordi<lb break="no"/>nances relating to the schools ; and while the new 
     <lb/>ordinance reaffirms the rights of Catholics to sepa<lb break="no"/>rate schools, it makes these dependent on such con<lb break="no"/>ditions that they are virtually suppressed. So that 
     <lb/>Mr. Haultain has done indirectly what he could not 
     <lb/>do directly. The question put to the Federal Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment was, whether the law should be disallowed. 
     <lb/>We have the right to insist that the protection given 
     <lb/>our countrymen shall be respected. If the under<lb break="no"/>standing arrived at when Confederation was formed 
     <lb/>can be violated by one party, then that contract is 
     <lb/>only a paper which can be torn at will. The Fede<lb break="no"/>ral Government has the right, and I will say has the 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="161" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00161.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">161</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 21, 1894]</fw> <fw type="num">162</fw>
        
        
     duty, to disallow all laws contrary to the general 
     <lb/>
     interests of the Dominion, and such is the new 
     <lb/>
     ordinance. Speaking for myself, I say that fana<lb break="no"/>ticism has long enough had its way. We have had 
     <lb/>
     enough of the McCarthy's, O'Briens and of the P. 
     <lb/>
     P. A., which wanted to ostracise everything that is 
     <lb/>
     Catholic. We are citizens and useful citizens of 
     <lb/>
     this country. I can claim to be moderate on these 
     <lb/>
     questions. I fought the Riel agitation. But when 
     <lb/>
     it comes to decide the question whether Catholics 
     <lb/>
     have rights in this country. I say that it is time to 
     <lb/>
     be up and doing. I appeal to all moderate men, 
     <lb/>
     irrespective of creed. Fanatics are not the majority 
     <lb/>
     in this country ; and if, to prove it, it is necessary 
     <lb/>
               to make a daring move—in French, a <hi rendition="simple:italic">coup d'etat</hi>—  
     <lb/>let it be made. The man who will make it shall 
     <lb/>have the united support of the province of Quebec. 
     <lb/>If to succeed it becomes necessary to call around 
     <lb/>our flag all moderate men, we will do it and we will 
     <lb/>again go over the work of Confederation. If we 
     <lb/>allow the sacred rights of our countrymen to he 
     <lb/>violated, we will vainly work for the progress of 
     <lb/>this province. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     These were very strong sentiments, and they 
     <lb/>
     had the more importance because they were 
     <lb/>
     uttered in the presence 0f the Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister of the province of Quebec and four or 
     <lb/>
     five of his colleagues. Naturally enough, 
     <lb/>
    that speech created a great sensation, in the  
     <lb/>province of Quebec at least. It was widely 
     <lb/>discussed. The whole ministerial press, with 
     <lb/>the sole exception of ' La Minerve,' the per<lb break="no"/>sonal organ of my hon. friend the Postmaster 
     <lb/>General endorsed it. ' L'Evénement,' which 
     <lb/>is one of the leading organs of the Conserva<lb break="no"/>tive party in Quebec. and which is to-day 
     <lb/>under the able supervision of my hon. friend 
     <lb/>the member for Gaspé (Mr. Joncas), spoke 
     <lb/>as follows :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
      The speech delivered by the Hon. T. C. Casgrain 
     <lb/>
     at the Conservative Club in Montreal has created 
     <lb/>
     quite a sensation, and will have a telling effect. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Attorney General has echoed the feelings of 
     <lb/>
     all those in this province who understand that the 
     <lb/>
     system of active persecution is organized against 
     <lb/>
     them and that the time has come for us to take 
     <lb/>
     the necessary means of imposing respect for the 
     <lb/>
     rights which have been granted to us by the consti<lb break="no"/>tution. Mr. Casgrain deserves the congratulations 
     <lb/>
     of his countrymen on account of the patriotism, 
     <lb/>
     the firmness and the energy he has shown. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Another paper of great importance, and 
     <lb/>
     which is the organ and the property of one 
     <lb/>
    of the Quebec Ministers—I mean ' Le Courrier  
     <lb/>du Canada '—said : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     We are the more happy to applaud those 
     <lb/>
     vigorous and manly declarations because they re<lb break="no"/>spond to the feeling that our readers have found in 
     <lb/>
     the columns of ' Le Courrier du Canada' during the 
     <lb/>
     last few days. Mr. Casgrain has exclaimed at a 
     <lb/>
     certain moment that if the central power is unable 
     <lb/>
     to protect the minorities, the guarantee contained 
     <lb/>
     in the right of disallowance is nothing less but 
     <lb/>
     worthless paper.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This is exactly our opinion. We said the other 
     <lb/>
     day that in the question of the schools of the North<lb break="no"/>west, the Federal Government had the power to 
     <lb/>
     disallow, that the circumstances justified disal<lb break="no"/>
         
         
            <cb/>
         
         
     lowance, and that if the right of disallowance can<lb break="no"/>not be used to protect minorities it is not worth 
     <lb/>
     much. We congratulate the Attorney General on 
     <lb/>
      the energy and the frankness with which he has 
     <lb/>
      developed this idea that the central power is bound 
     <lb/>
      to protect the oppressed minorities, if the future 
     <lb/>
     of this confederation is going to be assured." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     The newspaper, the 'Empire,' having taken 
     <lb/>
    upon itself to lecture the Attorney General of 
     <lb/>Quebec in the same way as it had lectured 
     <lb/>in former days my hon. friend from North 
     <lb/>Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy). ' Le Courrier du 
     <lb/>Canada'  replied in very plain language : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The ' Empire ' says that nobody has been found 
     <lb/>
      to approve the conduct of Mr. Casgrain. We 
     <lb/>
      have the honour to inform our contemporary that 
     <lb/>
      he labours under a strange error. On the very 
     <lb/>
     evening of his speech, Mr. Casgrain was warmly 
     <lb/>
      cheered by the Conservative meeting to which he 
     <lb/>
     was addressing himself, and since then the most 
     <lb/>
     cordial congratulations and the highest appro<lb break="no"/>bations have come in great numbers to him. The 
     <lb/>
     ' Empire ' is no more veracious when it insinuates 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Casgrain's colleagues blame the Attorney 
     <lb/>
     General. We are better informed than the To<lb break="no"/>ronto newspaper, and we beg him to believe that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Casgrain did not express an isolated opinion 
     <lb/>
     when he spoke as he did in Montreal. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
      A few days afterwards, the Cartier—Macdon<lb break="no"/>ald Club met in the. city of Quebec. That 
     <lb/>
     club is composed of the best class of young 
     <lb/>
     men in the Conservative party at Quebec. 
     <lb/>
     They thought proper to adopt the fullowing 
     <lb/>
      resolution :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
      That, in the opinion of this club, the last 
     <lb/>
     ordinances of the Legislative Assembly of the 
     <lb/>
     North-west relating to education contain disposi<lb break="no"/>tions which affect the established principle of 
     <lb/>
     separate schools and constitutes a new violation of 
     <lb/>
     the rights and privileges possessed by the minorities 
     <lb/>
     in this confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That, while we take into account the spirit of 
     <lb/>
     justice of well-thinking citizens in this country and 
     <lb/>
     their enlightened patriotism, nevertheless in pre<lb break="no"/>sence of the regrettable events, of the increasing 
     <lb/>
     appeals of intolerance and fanaticism, that we have 
     <lb/>
     witnessed for some time past, in some portions of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion, this club thinks it is its duty to 
     <lb/>
     protest more firmly than ever, and beg to state 
     <lb/>
     that it approves on this point the energetic attitude 
     <lb/>
     taken by the Hon. T. C. Casgrain, one of the Min<lb break="no"/>isters of Quebec, and the declarations which he has 
     <lb/>
     publicly made in Montreal, on the 28th of Feb<lb break="no"/>ruary. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
    

            <p>
     Well, it is easy to understand that there 
     <lb/>
     was some reason for such a series of 
     <lb/>
     speeches and articles. What was the rea<lb break="no"/>son ? Of course, we were not allowed to enter 
     <lb/>
     the sanctum sanctorum in which so many 
     <lb/>
     angelical spirits preside over our destiny 
     <lb/>
     Nevertheless, the quarrels of the gods were 
     <lb/>
     made public to us through the indiscretions 
     <lb/>
     of some of their organs. There was a big row 
     <lb/>
     in the ministerial press of Quebec. ' La 
     <lb/>
     Minerve ' supported very warmly and very 
     <lb/>
     ably, my hon. friend the Postmaster General, 
     <lb/>
     and contended that he was the only patriotic 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="163" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00163.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">163</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">164</fw>
         
         
         
     man in this country. On the other side. ' Le                 
     <lb/>
     Moniteur de Levis ' lectured him in a severe         
     <lb/>
     way indeed. Through those indiscretions. it           
     <lb/>
     was made known that a sub—committee of the            
     <lb/>
     Privy Council had been formed. composed           
     <lb/>
     of my hon. friends the Minister of Finance.           
     <lb/>
     the Minister of the Interior, and the Minister            
     <lb/>
    of Agriculture. Those hon. gentlemen set to 
     <lb/>work with all the ability and energy we know 
     <lb/>they possess. They held long and mature deli<lb break="no"/>berations. Still we have not yet been able to 
     <lb/>see the colour of their work. but there was 
     <lb/>a rumour to the effect that the three hon. 
     <lb/>gentlemen could not. agree. Patriotic as they 
     <lb/>were. resolved as they were to work for the 
     <lb/>prosperity of their country. they were not 
     <lb/>able to agree. and the question was referred 
     <lb/>to the whole body of the Privy Council. But 
     <lb/>during the passage from the sub-committee 
     <lb/>to the Privy Council, there were very wicked 
     <lb/>rumours indeed circulated, and circulated by 
     <lb/>the organs of the Ministers themselves. We 
     <lb/>were told very plainly that four of the hon. 
     <lb/>Ministers—three of them I see on the Treas<lb break="no"/>ury benches now-had made up their minds 
     <lb/>that if the Privy Council did not see its way   
     <lb/>to disallow the North-west Ordinances. they: 
     <lb/>would not be in a position to be of any 
     <lb/>more use to the Administration. We   
     <lb/>were even told that three French Ministers 
     <lb/>solemnly took the pledge that they would 
     <lb/>resign together if these Ordinances were not 
     <lb/>disallowed.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LAND2">Mr. LANDERKIN</persName>. Not a bit of danger of 
     <lb/>
     that so long as the salary runs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. That is where it strikes 
     <lb/>an appreciative chord in you.<lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName>. We heard another rumor.<lb/>I hope it is false, but I think I am justified in<lb/>putting it before the House-simply as a<lb/>rumor. It went so far as to say<lb/>that the hon. the Postmaster General(Sir<lb/>Adolphe Caron) went back on his colleagues<lb/>without warning them. I trust the rumor<lb/>is false; I put the question The rumor<lb/>may be false, but still this is the rumor<lb/>that the good friends of the Administration<lb/>have widely circulated. At any rate, one<lb/>thing is perfectly clear. and that is this-<lb break="yes"/>that none of the hon. Ministers have seen<lb/>fit to resign. I just remark that the hon<lb/>Minister is laughing heartily. I may submit<lb/>to him presently. for greater enjoyment. the<lb/>opinion of a journel which is under the direct<lb/>control of the most intimate friends of the<lb/>Minister of Agriculture-I mean 'Le Moniteur<lb/>de Levis':<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Some Montreal newspapers having stated that<lb/>alone amongst all our Ministers Mr. Ouimet had<lb/>differed from the majority of the Cabinet on the<lb/>question of the schools of the North-west, we have<lb/>argued that it could not be so in presence of the<lb/>most significant fact that the sub-committee of the<lb/>Privy Council composed of Messrs. Foster, Angers<lb/>and Daly had not been able to arrive at a con<lb break="no"/>clusion<lb/>
            </p>
            
       
       
            <cb/>
            <p>
     
     Mr. Angers had consequently differed, and that    
     <lb/>difference of opinion had naturally been expressed<lb/>in the Privy Council, especially as Mr. Angers has<lb/>found an ally in Mr. Ouimet. As to Sir Adolphe<lb/>Caron. we have, to inform us on the position he<lb/>has taken in the Council, no other indication to<lb/>that effect that he went two or three days after<lb/>wards to defend the conduct of the Government<lb/>before a political club.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Is it natural to suppose. is it logical to conclude, 
     <lb/>
     that Sir Adolphe Caron would have defended an 
     <lb/>
     opinion which would not have been his own ". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     By publicly taking before all his countrymen the 
     <lb/>
     position that has been indicated in the news<lb break="no"/>papers, has he not sufficiently pointed out to 
     <lb/>
     those who are candid and also those to who are not 
     <lb/>
     candid the role that he has played in the Council : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Our deductions are, then. perfectly logical. ' La 
     <lb/>
     Minerve ' itself, who pretends to laugh. shares our 
     <lb/>
     opinions when it says : " Have there been differ<lb break="no"/>ences between the French Ministers : We don't 
     <lb/>
     know anything about it, but the thing is possible 
     <lb/>
     and even probable." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " Probable." says ' La Minerve.' And why 
     <lb/>
     " probable?" Would there be Ministers who have 
     <lb/>
     betrayed their oath of office to inform ' La Minerve.' 
     <lb/>
     or has ' La Minerve ' arrived at that conclusion by 
     <lb/>
     simple deduction. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "What ' La Minerve ' says on the oath of office is 
     <lb/>
     grave and we invite it not to insist. The lesson 
     <lb/>
     that it wants to teach has been very badly learned. 
     <lb/>
     It is addressed to the wrong party. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Let ' La Minerve ' ask of the party who inspires it 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </quote>
            
   
   
            <p>
     I think my hon. friend the Postmaster Gen<lb break="no"/>eral will understand the hint-<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>——for the narration of a little trip to Mon<lb break="no"/>treal during the last days of January by<lb/>a person in a very high position. If its in<lb break="no"/>vestigation is well conducted. it will learn<lb/>to its great scandal that indiscretions have been<lb/>committed which are of a nature to exempt ,La<lb/>Minerve,' the confidante of the gods, from pro<lb break="no"/>ceeding by way of deduction and which allows us<lb/>to invite it to submit its extracts from Todd to<lb/>other parties than to us.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>If 'La Minerve' wants to know more. we are at<lb/>its disposal at its first request.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
            
            
            <p>Of course, 'La Minerve'did not want to know<lb/>anything more- it had had enough of it:-but<lb/>Sir, we were told that this crises was going<lb/>to be averted by Mr. Haultain, the Prime<lb/>Minister of the North-west Territories, insist<lb break="no"/>ing that the Legislature should amend the<lb/>ordinances of 1892. Mr. Mackintosh. the<lb/>Lieutenant Governor of the territory, by a<lb/>happy accident, was at the time on his way<lb/>to the Capital. A few days afterwards,<lb/>Mr. Haultain. while passing through Winni<lb break="no"/>peg, made a speech, in which he stated that<lb/>he would not submit to any outside interfer<lb break="no"/>ence, that he thought the ordinances fair and<lb/>just, and that he would not be a party to<lb/>any amendment to them. Well, in the<lb/>presence of these statements, I want to know<lb/>how it is that the French Ministers, who had<lb/>put their resignations into the hands of the<lb/>Premier, have been able to retain their seats<lb/>as they do to-day? Mr.Speaker, a question<lb/>
      
      
    
            <pb n="165" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00165.jpg"/>
        
        
     <fw type="num">165</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 21, 1894]</fw> <fw type="num">166</fw>
      
      
      arises—were the Ministers from the province 
     <lb/>of Quebec serious or were they not when 
     <lb/>they instructed their press throughout the 
     <lb/>province of Quebec to state that they were 
     <lb/>asking for justice, and that they were in 
     <lb/>sisting upon the disallowance of these ordin<lb break="no"/>ances ? If they were serious, how is it that 
     <lb/>they are still on the Treasury benches ? If 
     <lb/>they were not serious, they were simply 
     <lb/>pursuing the same imprudent course that has 
     <lb/>characterized the policy of this Government 
     <lb/>on the school question from the beginning ; 
     <lb/>that is to say, they were contributing to 
     <lb/>increase the dangerous agitation that we 
     <lb/>have to face to-day. But, Sir, to save 
     <lb/>themselves from the humiliation in which 
     <lb/>they have been placed by their organs, 
     <lb/>they began to appeal to the most 
     <lb/>dangerous prejudices. Would you allow me 
     <lb/>to quote the last sample of that bigot 
     <lb/>sentiment that the organs of the hon. 
     <lb/>Ministers of the province of Quebec are 
     <lb/>trying to excite to-day? As every one knows, 
     <lb/>my hon. friend from Winnipeg (Mr. Martin) 
     <lb/>was introduced in this House by the hon. the 
     <lb/>leader of the Opposition and by my hon. 
     <lb/>friend from Queen's. P.E.I. (Mr. Davies). It 
     <lb/>is a courtesy that we owe to one another to 
     <lb/>introduce one another in the House. My 
     <lb/>hon. friend (Mr. Martin) was elected, not on 
     <lb/>the school question, but as a tariff reformer ; 
     <lb/>he was elected by the votes of Liberals 
     <lb/>and Conservatives alike. If I went further, 
     <lb/>I would not say, perhaps, that he had 
     <lb/>been elected by the Catholic vote, but 
     <lb/>certainly, as he said the other day, 
     <lb/>he has received a great many Catholic votes. 
     <lb/>And why ? Because the Archbishop of St. 
     <lb/>Boniface thought proper to be interviewed 
     <lb/>during that election. Of course, His Grace 
     <lb/>is not as good a Catholic, or as orthodox, as 
     <lb/>my hon. friend the Postmaster General, still 
     <lb/>he is something of a Catholic. His Grace 
     <lb/>was interviewed on the 11th November, 1893, 
     <lb/>and this is what he is reported to have said : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The interviewer ventured to ask His Grace how 
     <lb/>
     he expected Catholics to vote in the Winnipeg by- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     election. The archbishop replied that he thought 
     <lb/>
     the vote would be divided. If either candidate 
     <lb/>
     were an advocate of separate schools it might be 
     <lb/>
     different, but as the case now stands, those Catho<lb break="no"/>lics who desire tariff reform will many of them vote 
     <lb/>
     for Mr. Martin, though some will withhold their 
     <lb/>
     vote from resentment. Catholics, he said, were 
     <lb/>
     perfectly free to vote whichever way they saw fit. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Well, according to His Grace, the Catholic 
     <lb/>voters of Winnipeg were perfectly free to<lb/>vote as they pleased ; but when my hon.<lb/>friend the leader of the Opposition intro<lb break="no"/>duces to the House a gentleman duly and<lb/>legally elected, he commits a crime against<lb/>heaven and society. Now, let us see the ex<lb break="no"/>tent of that crime according to one of the<lb/>most important ministerial organs in the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Quebec. 'Le Courrier du Canada,'<lb/>the organ of one of the Provincial Ministers<lb/>in Quebec, Mr. Chapais. The heading is<lb/>very suggestive :<lb/>
            </p>
 
 
            <cb/>
    
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <emph>LAURIER MARTIN DAVIES!</emph><lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">A SUGGESTIVE TRIO.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>It is done! We wrote a little while ago that if 
     <lb/>Mr. Laurier dared to do it, he would introduce Mr. 
     <lb/>Joseph Martin, leaning on his arm. into the House 
     <lb/>of Commons, the persecutor of the Catholic minority 
     <lb/>in Manitoba.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Well, Mr. Laurier has dared to do it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Yesterday afternoon. the chief of the Opposition, 
     <lb/>
      escorted by Mr. Davies, introduced into the House 
     <lb/>
    the illustrious Martin. Laurier, Martin, Davies ! ! 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>This spectacle is extremely suggestive. Mr. 
     <lb/>Davies is the author of the persecuting law of Prince 
     <lb/>Edward Island, of 1877. Mr. Martin is the author 
     <lb/>of the persecuting law of Manitoba of 1890. Both 
     <lb/>are fanatical adversaries of separate schools and of 
     <lb/> the rights of minorities. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>And Mr. Laurier, the man that the ' L'Electeur ' 
     <lb/> asks us to aid, opens the session by an official parade 
     <lb/> in company with these two men. Under the exist<lb break="no"/>ing circumstances this introduction, usually a very 
     <lb/> ordinary affair, assumes a very grave character and 
     <lb/>signification. One would suppose that Mr. Laurier 
     <lb/>wished to break the ice, and to show upon the first 
     <lb/>day what the attitude of the Opposition would be 
     <lb/> on the school question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Frankly, politics causes the observer to witness 
     <lb/> strange scenes. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

    
   
            <p>
     My hon. friend from Queen's. P.E.I. (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Davies), is perfectly able to take care of 
     <lb/>
     himself ; still, if he allows me, I will 
     <lb/>
     briefly describe the law that the hon. 
     <lb/>
      member for Queen's passed in 1877. If I am 
     <lb/>
     rightly informed, the first school law in 
     <lb/>
     Prince Edward Island was passed in 1852. 
     <lb/>
     It is natural to suppose that a school law 
     <lb/>
      which had existed for 25 years in a progres<lb break="no"/>sive province, needed to be amended after 
     <lb/>
     so long a period of time. The election of 
     <lb/>
    1876, was carried on the question of 
     <lb/>the necessity of improving the law. It 
     <lb/>was fought, not by one political party 
     <lb/>alone, but by a combination of public 
     <lb/> men belonging to both political parties. My 
     <lb/>hon. friend succeeded at the polls, and he 
     <lb/>then formed a coalition Government, of 
     <lb/>which he was the leader, but the majority 
     <lb/>of his colleagues were Conservatives. The 
     <lb/> law which was passed in 1877 did not change 
     <lb/> the principle of the old law ; it only amended 
     <lb/>it by giving more power to the school trus<lb break="no"/>tees and making some other changes. At 
     <lb/>any rate, the law was adopted. There was 
     <lb/>some little friction, no doubt. Archbishop 
     <lb/> McIntyre thought that the improvements he 
     <lb/>had made on his school property were to be<lb/>imperilled, and he applied, as I understand,<lb/>for the disallowance of the law. His re<lb break="no"/>quest was not granted ; and a short time<lb/>afterwards His Grace and my hon. friend<lb/>came to a perfect agreement, and since that<lb/>time His Grace has declared himself<lb/>entirely satisfied. My hon. friend was de-<lb break="yes"/>defeated in 1879, and his position was taken<lb/>by Mr. Sullivan—now, I think, Chief Justice 
     <lb/>Sullivan—who was a strong Conservative 
     <lb/>and a Roman Catholic. He remained in 
     <lb/>
      
      
            <pb n="167" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00167.jpg"/>
       
       
     <fw type="num">167</fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">168</fw>
     
     
     
     power for the long period of twelye years. 
     <lb/>and no amendment was made to the law. 
     <lb/>Sir, this is the law for whith my hon. 
     <lb/>friend for Queen's has been hurled into eternal 
     <lb/>flames by ' Le Courrier dn  Canada.' Now I 
     <lb/>want to know what we are going to do, and 
     <lb/>what is going to happen in the presence of 
     <lb/>such appeals to prejudices. I suppose my 
     <lb/>hon. friends opposite  will not tell us 
     <lb/>that all these appeals come from this side 
     <lb/>of the House. I have quoted speeches, 
     <lb/>articles and statements made and written 
     <lb/>by their most important friends in the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Quebec, and I will challenge hon. 
     <lb/>gentlemen opposite to find a single statement  
     <lb/>like this coming from any hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>on this side of the House. We have claimed 
     <lb/>justice, we are still claiming justice ; we do 
     <lb/>not claim anything more than justice. I know 
     <lb/>that some of us, especially myself, have been  
     <lb/>shamefully misrepresented by some of the 
     <lb/>Ontario papers. I think I am the oldest 
     <lb/>newspaper man in this Chamber, one of them 
     <lb/>at least. I may have read more newspapers 
     <lb/>for the last twenty years than any other 
     <lb/>member of this House, for the simple reason<lb/>that being able to read both English and 
     <lb/>French, I have read all the papers I could 
     <lb/>from England, from France, from the 
     <lb/>United States and in Canada. Sir, I am 
     <lb/>sorry to speak as I am going to do, but I 
     <lb/>must say that in my long experience I have<lb/>never read a paper more wickedly men<lb break="no"/>dacious than the Toronto 'Mail.' I know I 
     <lb/>am using a very strong expression, but 
     <lb/>I am confident that the fact justifies it. The 
     <lb/>province of Quebec is day by day sys<lb break="no"/>tematically traduced. Its public men are 
     <lb/>calumniated and denounced to their fellow- 
     <lb break="yes"/>countrymen. Yesterday one of my friends 
     <lb/>whom I now see, told me, " Tarte you are 
     <lb/>doing in Quebec just the work that is being 
     <lb/>done by McCarthy in Ontario." I asked him 
     <lb/>this question—because he is a very sen<lb break="no"/>sible gentleman—" Sir, can you read 
     <lb/>French ?" He replied, " Unforttutately, I 
     <lb/>cannot." " Did you ever read any articles 
     <lb/>signed by me ? "—for I generally sign my 
     <lb/>articles so that eyery one may know 
     <lb/>where I am. He said : "No, I can<lb break="no"/>not read French." Then, I asked, " Where 
     <lb/>did you find the evidence that I am 
     <lb/>playing on the feelings of my country<lb break="no"/>men as Mr. McCarthy is doing in your own 
     <lb/>province ?'" Of course he was obliged to 
     <lb/>say : " In the translations that appear in 
     <lb/>some Ontario papers." My own personality 
     <lb/>is insignificant and of very little value, but 
     <lb/>my dear province of Quebec is something 
     <lb/>after all, and I throw back that slur cast 
     <lb/>upon it. We have a right to be respected by 
     <lb/>our fellow-countrymen of English origin ; 
     <lb/>we have a right to be treated like men who 
     <lb/>love their country and do not want to ruin 
     <lb/>it. Well, every day the Toronto ' Mail ' which 
     <lb/>is not refuted, I am sorry to say, by many 
     <lb/>Toronto newpapers, denounces the province 
     <lb/>of Quebec, its men and institutions, in such 
     <lb/>a manner that Ministers of the Crown should 
     <lb/>


            <cb/>
        
        
     take cognizance of it. As a governing body 
     <lb/>
    they should ask their own  organs to be 
     <lb/>more just to us. A few moments ago 
     <lb/>

     I was asking : What is going to happen ? 
     <lb/>
     The Government is amenable to the 
     <lb/>
     charge of being the cause of all the agita<lb break="no"/>tion that is going on to-day. I do not speak 
     <lb/>
     in a party spirit, and I do not want to be 
     <lb/>
     so understood. The prime duty of a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment is to have a distinct and clear policy 
     <lb/>
     on all the important questions of the day. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. gentlemen on the Treasury benches 
     <lb/>
     have endeavoured since the school question 
     <lb/>
     has entered the political  arena to escape  the 
     <lb/>
     responsibilities of their office. What have they 
     <lb/>
     done in the Manitoba school case ? They 
     <lb/>
     proceeded by way of making promises, pri<lb break="no"/>vately and publicly. They proceeded, more<lb break="no"/>over, by way of references to the courts, 
     <lb/>
     their only object being to gain time and 
     <lb/>
     placate public opinion if they could. As a 
     <lb/>
     matter of fact they have taken money from 
     <lb/>
     the public treasury to save their heads as 
     <lb/>
     politicians. What is the result to-day ? The 
     <lb/>
     judgment of the Privy Council was given in 
     <lb/>
     due course. The hon. Prime Minister, who 
     <lb/>
     was then Minister of Justice, had pro<lb break="no"/>claimed that if the Privy Council decided 
     <lb/>
     against the demands of the Catholic minority, 
     <lb/>
     there would be a remedy still. And what<lb break="no"/>ever may be the efforts and ability of 
     <lb/>
     those who may undertake to defend the 
     <lb/>Government and the First Minister, is lan<lb break="no"/>guage means anything. I want to know what 
     <lb/>
     these sentences of his which  have already 
     <lb/>
     been read to the House, but which I will take 
     <lb/>
     the liberty of reading again, can possibly 
     <lb/>
     mean. They are as follows :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     If the legal controversy should result in the deci<lb break="no"/>sion of the Court of Queen's Bench being sustained, 
     <lb/>
     the time will come for Your Excellency to consider 
     <lb/>
     the petitions which have been presented by and on 
     <lb/>
     behalf of the Roman Catholics of Manitoba for 
     <lb/>
     redress under subsections 2 and 3 of the Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     Act, quoted in the early part of this report, and 
     <lb/>
     which are analogous to the proyisions made by the 
     <lb/>
     British North America Act in relation to other 
     <lb/>
     provinces. Those subsections contain in effect 
     <lb/>
     the provisions which have been made as to all the 
     <lb/>
     provinces, and are obviously the provisions under 
     <lb/>
     which the constitution intended the Government 
     <lb/>
     of the Dominion should proceed if it should at any 
     <lb/>
     time become necessary that the Federal power 
     <lb/>
     should be resorted to for the protection of a Pro<lb break="no"/>testant or Roman Catholic minority against any 
     <lb/>
     act of the legislatures of the provinces or of any 
     <lb/>
     provincial authority affecting any right or privilege 
     <lb/>
      of such minority in relation to education. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Well. Sir, that pledge will be remem<lb break="no"/>bered by all men of good faith as 
     <lb/>
     having been made by the Fitst Minister. I 
     <lb/>
     do not accuse the hon. gentleman of bad 
     <lb/>
     faith, but I do accuse him of weakness. 
     <lb/>
     He has unwillingly perhaps, deceived the 
     <lb/>
     Roman Catholic minority. No sensible man 
     <lb/>
     who read the statement at the time—and 
     <lb/>
     observes that it was published broadcast— 
     <lb/>
     could fail to understand that the right hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman pledged himself to provide this 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="169" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00169.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">169</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 21, 1894]</fw> <fw type="num">170</fw>
         
         
     remedy, that if the courts of justice decided 
     <lb/>
     that according to the strict letter of the law, 
     <lb/>
     the Catholic minority has no statutory rights, 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman pledged himself to re<lb break="no"/>cognize and consider the claim that the Catho<lb break="no"/>lic minority in the province of Manitoba was 
     <lb/>
     promised and given, in 1870, the same rights 
     <lb/>
     as the English minority of the province of 
     <lb/>
     Quebec enjoy, and have long enjoyed, with 
     <lb/>
     our cheerful consent. I therefore say the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman is amenable to that grave charge. 
     <lb/>
     I know the Catholics in Manitoba are weak. 
     <lb/>
     It is a fact which there is no use in denying ; 
     <lb/>
     but I will never agree to the idea that in a 
     <lb/>
     British colony, where the people were brought 
     <lb/>
     up under British liberty, the majority would 
     <lb/>
     undertake to trample upon the rights 
     <lb/>
     of the minority. The policy and pledges 
     <lb/>
    of the Government are to-day pretty well 
     <lb/>understood. After the judgment of the Privy 
     <lb/>Council it became the duty of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to keep their pledge and to consider, 
     <lb/>to use the words of the First Minister, the 
     <lb/>petitions of the Roman Catholic minority. 
     <lb/>It did not do so. It had recourse to a 
     <lb/>new referendum, to the courts of justice, and<lb/>the judgment has recently been given. Pe<lb break="no"/>culiar to say, the hon. Solicitor General 
     <lb/>who is an able lawyer, went before the 
     <lb/>Supreme Court and said nothing. The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had one of the most important 
     <lb/>cases that could be presented before a court 
     <lb/>of justice, and still, Sir, the Government had 
     <lb/>nothing to say. They said nothing. and the 
     <lb/>Catholic minority got nothing. I would like 
     <lb/>to repeat a question which I put last year 
     <lb/>to the House, and to which the Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister at the time refused to answer. I want 
     <lb/>to know : What is the policy of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment now ? The Supreme Court has de<lb break="no"/>cided, but as the hon. gentleman knows, 
     <lb/>this decision is not binding. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment is still at perfect liberty to take any 
     <lb/>course they like. They have the respon<lb break="no"/>sibility of the Government, of the peace 
     <lb/>and of the good harmony of this country on 
     <lb/>their shoulders. They are a strong Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, backed by a large majority. Can 
     <lb/>it be possible that on such an important ques<lb break="no"/>tion, involving such  great results, the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment have no policy ? Are they going to 
     <lb/>appeal from the decision of the Supreme 
     <lb/>Court or are they going to abide by it ? I be<lb break="no"/>lieve that we have a full right to re<lb break="no"/>ceive a distinct answer to this question. 
     <lb/>Now, Sir, what has the Government done 
     <lb/>with reference to the North-west Territories 
     <lb/>school question ? The Ordinances were en<lb break="no"/>acted in 1892. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. What have they enacted ? 
     <lb/>
     You have not told us the grievance. Explain 
     <lb/>
     to the House the issue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName>. It the hon. gentleman will 
     <lb/>
     allow me, I will try to explain to his own 
     <lb/>
     satisfaction, if I can, what, I am sure, are 
     <lb/>
     grievances, but just now I am asking what 
     <lb/>
     is the policy of the Government, as it is my 
     <lb/>
     right to inquire. What has been the policy 
     <lb/>
        
        
            <cb/>
        
        
     of the Government, I ask, with regard to the 
     <lb/>
     school question of the North-west Territories ? 
     <lb/>
     'l'he Ordinances were enacted in 1892, and 
     <lb/>
     they were going to be enforced in the course 
     <lb/>
     of the month of February last, if not disal<lb break="no"/>lowed by the Governor Geneml in Council. 
     <lb/>
     As I explained, there were differences of 
     <lb/>
     opinion between the members of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment ; there is no possible doubt about that. 
     <lb/>
     We have been told by the organs of the Min<lb break="no"/>isters, that if the Ordinances were not disal<lb break="no"/>lowed, at least the Catholic and the French 
     <lb/>
     minority of the North-west would still get 
     <lb/>
     justice, because the Government had recom<lb break="no"/>mended to Mr. Haultain, as was its right to 
     <lb/>
     do, to amend these Ordinances. We have 
     <lb/>
     seen that Mr. Haultain has already stated 
     <lb/>
     that he would not consent to amend the or<lb break="no"/>dinances. The Government has not disal<lb break="no"/>lowed the law, but it has given inducements, 
     <lb/>
     it has given what I may fairly call false 
     <lb/>
     hopes, to the Catholic and French minority, 
     <lb/>
     and so the agitation still continues. Well, 
     <lb/>
     Sir, why has not this strong Government a 
     <lb/>
     decided and a strong policy ? Do you think 
     <lb/>
     that it would not he better for all parties 
     <lb/>
     concerned if the Government told us plainly 
     <lb/>
      that these two questions are settled ? If they 
     <lb/>
     told us that, we would know where we are 
     <lb/>
      and what means to take. The Government, by 
     <lb/>
     leaving everything undecided and by giving 
     <lb/>
     false hopes, have encouraged the dangerous 
     <lb/>
     agitation which we must face to-day. It may 
     <lb/>
     be said to me : You evidently want to invade 
     <lb/>
      provincial rights. I claim that this Government 
     <lb/>
     has denied the very principle of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, in placing  provincial rights over the 
     <lb/>
     rights of the people of this Dominion as a 
     <lb/>
      whole. We all know how the Confederation 
     <lb/>
     Act was enacted. Confederation did not take 
     <lb/>
     place out of the love that the different pro<lb break="no"/>vinces professed for one another. No ; Confed<lb break="no"/>eration took place because Upper and Lower 
     <lb/>
     Canada, United Canada, could not get along 
     <lb/>
      together any longer on account of their racial, 
     <lb/>
     religious and national differences. The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment was at a deadlock half the time, and 
     <lb/>
     then the Confederation scheme was adopted. 
     <lb/>
      Now, the very basis of the Confederation Act 
     <lb/>
      was the right of disallowance, that statement 
     <lb/>
     cannot be disputed. Disallowance and the 
     <lb/>
     right of appeal to the Governor General in 
     <lb/>
     Council were insisted upon especially by the 
     <lb/>
     English majority in this Dominion. And to<lb break="no"/>day, when we claim that the right of disal<lb break="no"/>lowance, and the right of appeal should be 
     <lb/>
     exercised towards the French and Catholic 
     <lb/>
     minority, I am sorry to say that we are 
     <lb/>
     treated like fanatics. I want to know, and I  
     <lb/>
     ask the Government : If, in allowing all these 
     <lb/>
     prejudices to take root, they are acting wisely 
     <lb/>
     and as a Government worthy of the con<lb break="no"/>fidence of the people of this country In the 
     <lb/>
     speech which my hon. friend the Attorney 
     <lb/>
     General of the province of Quebec made in 
     <lb/>
     Montreal, he stated that if it was necessary 
     <lb/>
     to make a daring move,  it would be made in 
     <lb/>
     the province of Quebec. I beg, Sir, to dis<lb break="no"/>sent from that opinion. I beg to state, in 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="171" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00171.jpg"/>
       
       
     <fw type="num">171</fw>                  <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw>                   <fw type="num">172</fw>  


     
     the names of my electors, in the name of my<lb/>countrymen- whom I believe I know as well<lb/>
     
     as any other man-that we do not contem<lb break="no"/>plate any daring movement or any 'coup<lb/>
     
     d'e'tat.' We mean to abide by a constitu<lb break="no"/>tional agitation, we mean to abide by the<lb/>
     law of the land, we do not want anything<lb/>
     
     more, but I do not bellieve that we should be<lb/>given anything else. The Government pro<lb break="no"/>fess to be very hostile to my hon. friend from<lb/>
     
     North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) in his policy.<lb/>My opinion is that they are following the<lb/>
     
     
     very same policy, and, if I may be permitted<lb/>to say so, they are driven by him. The hon.<lb/>gentleman from Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) has<lb/>
     
     obtained everything that he wanted to have.<lb/>He wanted to have separate schools abol<lb break="no"/>ished, and theyhave been abolished with<lb/>the concurrence of the hon. gentlemen on the <lb/>
     
     other side of the House. He desired that <lb/>the school laws of Manitoba should not be <lb/>
     
     vetoed, and they have not been vetoed. As<lb/>a matter of fact, the most important plank<lb/>
     of his platform is gone, and, of course, I<lb/>would not be sorry for it, if we had not been<lb/>
     
     
     
     sacrificed by the agitation led by him. My<lb/>hon. friend from Assiniboia, (Mr. Davin)<lb/>
     
     has asked me a question which I am delight<lb break="no"/>ed to answer: he has asked me, what are <lb/>
     
     your grievances in the North-west?  In 1875<lb/>an Act was passed by the unanimous con<lb break="no"/>sent of this Chamber, and by a majority of<lb/>the Senate, establishing separate schools and<lb/>the French language in that country. In<lb/>this Chamber, there was not a dissenting <lb/>vote, and I see here today a great many<lb/>hon. gentlemen who then sat in Parliament.<lb/>Well, Sir, my hon. friend will admit that<lb/>the separate schools have been abolished by<lb/>
    the North-west ordinance.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. No.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName>. My hon. friend says no.<lb/>I will not try to make myself clearer to him<lb/>Does not the Act of 1875 mention Roman<lb/>Catholic separate schools? I want to know<lb/>if, since the passage of the ordinance, there<lb/>are any longer Roman Catholic separate<lb/>schools in the North-west. We are speaking<lb/>here as men of good faith, and let us use<lb/>words in their ordinary signification.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. There are Roman Catholic<lb/>schools in the North-west.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName>. I will illustrate my idea in 
     <lb/>
     a way which I hope my hon. friend will un<lb break="no"/>derstand. Suppose that at the next session 
     <lb/>
     of the Legislaturc of the province of Quebec 
     <lb/>
     —it will never be done. I am only supposing 
     <lb/>
     it—an hon. French member should copy, word 
     <lb/>
     for word, the Ordinance of the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Assembly and should propose to place under 
     <lb/>
     the control of the Government, constituted 
     <lb/>
     the Council of Public Instruction, all the 
     <lb/>
     schools of the province, all the books—in a 
     <lb/>
     word, everything connected with the schools— 
     <lb/>I want to know from any reasonable man,<lb/>


            <cb/>
      
      
     would not the Protestant separate schools of<lb/>the Province of Quebec be thereby abolish<lb break="no"/>ed? We are here, not to play with words, <lb/>but to speak to facts. And now, let me say, <lb/>with the utmost frankness, that in claiming<lb/>our rights we are not acting under the dicta<lb break="no"/>tion of any Roman Catholic or ecclesiastical<lb/>influence. We are accused, especially by the<lb/>'Mail', of being driven and led as a lot of<lb/>cattle by the Roman Catholic clergy. With<lb/>regard to the majority of the members of<lb/>
     
     this side of the House, they have been                 <lb/>fought by the clergy. I claim, and I am<lb/>proud to claim it, that the most enlightened <lb/>part of the Roman Catholic clergy are begin<lb break="no"/>ing to realize where they are now. There<lb/>is not an hon. member on either side of the <lb/>House who will not bear out this statement,<lb/>that my hon. friend the leader of the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion is leading, in the province of Quebec, a<lb/>party which has not received so far the full<lb/>sympathy of the Roman Catholic clergy. And<lb/>yet we are accused by the Ontario organs of <lb/>hon. gentlemen opposite of being directed by<lb/>the hierarchy.  On the question of schools let<lb/>it be well understood, that we are prepared<lb/>to discuss calmly and like business men the <lb/>whole situation. We quite understand that<lb/>things may change: we quite realize that we<lb/>cannot always remain stationary: but our<lb/>position, in regard to which we should have<lb/>the sympathy of every Protestant member<lb/>of this Chamber, is this: We have made a<lb/>bargain, an agreement, and, as one of the<lb/>parties to that agreement we do not<lb/>want our rights to be taken from us,<lb/>at least without being consulted. If the<lb/>English minority in the Province of Quebec. <lb/>which bears the same proportion to the<lb/>French majority there, as the French minor<lb break="no"/>ity bears to the English majority in Mani<lb break="no"/>toba, were treated as the French minority is<lb/>treated, the English majority of the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion would, if necessary, take up arms in<lb/>their defence.  My statement will not be<lb/>challenged, because Englishmen are fond of <lb/>liberty, and are not disposed to submit to<lb/>being trampled upon. Is it surprising that we <lb/>have the very same feeling? But we don't<lb/>go any further. So far as I am con<lb break="no"/>cerned, I always sign my articles. I speak <lb/>here before the representatives of the whole <lb/>Dominion, and I challenge any one to quote<lb/>one single sentence of mine in which I have<lb/>either threatened or attacked the rights of<lb/>the English minority of Quebec. With regard<lb/>to the other part of the question put by my <lb/>hon. friend, I want to know if the minority<lb/>of the Province of Manitoba and in<lb/>the North-west do not suffer from the<lb/>deprivation of the very same rights<lb/>
     
     that the English minority enjoy in the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Quebec. We  had a right to our 
     <lb/>
     language ; we had a right to our 
     <lb/>
     separate schools, those rights have been 
     <lb/>
     abolished. Hon. gentlemen will say that 
     <lb/>
     they have been legally abolished. Every one 
     <lb/>
     of us has known in his experience many 
     <lb/>good cases which have been lost in the<lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="173" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00173.jpg"/>
        
        
     <fw type="num">173</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 21,  1894]</fw> <fw type="num">174</fw>
        
        
     courts of justice ; but, in my experience of 
     <lb/>history I have never yet known the case of<lb/>a people being deprived of their political<lb/>rights through the courts of justice. That<lb/>is the reason why we insist so much that<lb/>this Government should have a policy on<lb/>this matter. I do not know whether any<lb/>of the Ministers will condescend to answer<lb/>me. I am not speaking in my own name alone.<lb/>
    I am speaking on a question which is to-day 
     <lb/>exciting the attention of the whole Domin<lb break="no"/>ion. Would it not be better to have a full dis<lb break="no"/>cussion and the settlement of these grievances 
     <lb/>in this House during this session, than to 
     <lb/>let the agitation in the country be continued ? 
     <lb/>Sir, we often boast that we have a magni<lb break="no"/>ficent country . It is true.  We often boast 
     <lb/>of our desire to build up a nation on this 
     <lb/>soil of British North America. That is 
     <lb/>a legitimate desire. But. how can we 
     <lb/>build up a nation if we are going to 
     <lb/>quarrel with one another ? Is there a man 
     <lb/>of brains who would think for a single 
     <lb/>moment that the English majority of the 
     <lb/>Dominion, strong as it is, could conduct 
     <lb/>public affairs profitably by dictating to the<lb/>French and the Catholic minority ? Nobody 
     <lb/>imagines that. If we want to become a 
     <lb/>nation and live as civilized men and 
     <lb/>Christians should live, let us come to 
     <lb/>some understanding. When we converse 
     <lb/>with one another in this House we 
     <lb/>are all of opinion that we should put a 
     <lb/>stop to all appeals to prejudices and 
     <lb/>bigotry. When it becomes a matter of 
     <lb/>party politics we are driven into the abyss. 
     <lb/>l have perhaps spoken too long, but the 
     <lb/>question is one of very great importance. I<lb/>hope I have dealt with it in a spirit which is<lb/>not offensive to any one. My great aim was<lb/>to put before the House the question as I<lb/>honestly understand it, and nothing more.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I do not rise, I need hardly<lb/>say, to oppose this motion, but to relieve<lb/>the overwrought feelings of this House, after<lb/>the speech of my hon. friend (Mr. Tarte). I<lb/>am sure that the members of this House,<lb/>particularly the French-Canadian members,<lb/>who take a deep interest in the French mino<lb break="no"/>rity in the North-west, must have been deeply<lb/>grieved to hear the striking description of<lb/>the differences existing among us in that<lb/>country. To know something of the griev<lb break="no"/>ances of the kind described by the hon.<lb/>member for L'Islet (Mr. Tarte), and of griev<lb break="no"/>ances of a similar character described from<lb/>another point of view, a North-west member<lb/>has to come to this House. It must have<lb/>struck any rational man, on hearing the<lb/>speech of my hon. friend, that my hon. friend<lb/>has left us still in the dark as to what really<lb/>our grievances are. The speech of my hon.<lb/>friend, if he will excuse me, I will say was<lb/>a vocal scrap-book. He gave us what Mr.<lb/>Casgrain, the Attorney General of Quebec,<lb/>said. He gave us what 'Le Courrier du<lb/>Canada' and the Moniteur de Levis' and<lb/>sundry other papers and people said ; but I<lb/>
        
        
            <cb/>
         
         
     waited in vain to hear my hon. friend, who, I 
     <lb/>believe, is a university man, and must have<lb/>a more or less trained min, state the case<lb/>on which he asks this House to come to an<lb/>opinion. He failed to state the issue or the<lb/>grievances which require remedy. I appeal<lb/>to his own friends whether he has up to this<lb/>minute stated these grievances. I would ask<lb/>him to do so now, and I am sure the House<lb/>will permit me to take my seat if my hon.<lb/>friend describe the grievances which he says<lb/>are existing in the North-west. He has<lb/>given us the opinion that no Roman Catholic<lb/>separate schools exist there. I say they do,<lb/>and I say that not a single Roman Catholic<lb/>separate school has been suppressed by any<lb/>legislation in the North-west.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName>. They are under the control         
     <lb/>of a Protestant Board.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. My hon. friend says they ex<lb break="no"/>ist under the control of a Protestant Board.<lb/>I will describe to the House what has been<lb/>done. It is a mere accident that the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of that board are Protestant. I will read<lb/>to the House what the arrangement is in re<lb break="no"/>gard to that. Hon. gentlemen on one side<lb/>and the other rise up and give the public out<lb break="no"/>side the notion that some portion of our<lb/>people in the North-west is suffering under<lb/>great grievance, and hence these strident ap<lb break="no"/>peals, calculated to do harm to that country.<lb/>It is not extraordinary that my hon. friend<lb/>could quote gentlemen in Quebec by the<lb/>dozen as to the existence of grievances in the<lb/>North-west, and not be able to quote a single<lb/>Roman Catholic opinion in the North-west.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. That is what he is moving<lb/>for-for the petitions.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. That is all right, and you will<lb/>have the petitions. But I ask is it not ex<lb break="no"/>traordinary, that, if there is such a sense of<lb/>grievance in the North-west among the<lb/>Catholic minority, no speaker has said one<lb/>word about these grievances ? What I want<lb/>to point out is this, that I have never my<lb break="no"/>self heard any complaints against the Ordin<lb break="no"/>ances as they exist. What I have heard is<lb/>complaint against certain regulations. Now,<lb/>I will show to the House what actually<lb/>exists. The Council of Public Instruction is<lb/>composed as follows. I am reading the<lb/>Ordinance of 1892 :-<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>The members of the Executive Committee and<lb/>four persons, two of whom shall be Protestants and<lb/>two Roman Catholics, appointed by the Lieutenant-<lb break="yes"/>Governor in Council shall constitute a Council of<lb/>Public Instruction, and one of the said Executive<lb/>Committee, to be nominated by the Lieutenant-<lb break="yes"/>Governor in Council, shall be chairman of the said<lb/>Council of Public Instruction. The appointed<lb/>members shall have no vote and shall receive such<lb/>remuneration as the Lieutenant-Governor in<lb/>Council shall provide.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
            
            
            <p>As to separate schools, section 32 provides :<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>The minority of the ratepayers in any organized<lb/>Public School district, whether Protestant or<lb/>
        
        
            <pb n="175" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00175.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">175</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">176</fw>
       
       
     Roman Catholic, may establish a Separate School 
     <lb/>
     therein, and in such case, the ratepayers establish<lb break="no"/>ing such Protestant or Roman Catholic Separate 
     <lb/>
     Schools shall be liable only to assessments of such 
     <lb/>
     rates as they impose upon themselves in respect 
     <lb/>
     thereof. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Well, certain regulations were made by that 
     <lb/>
     Council of Public Instruction, and they were 
     <lb/>
     objected to. I am not going to say whether 
     <lb/>
     they were rightly or wrongly objected to. 
     <lb/>
     I suppose every one who knows me is aware 
     <lb/>
     that there is probably not a man on the con<lb break="no"/>tinent of America so free from dogmatic pre<lb break="no"/>judices, though they exist among so many of 
     <lb/>
     my fellow-countrymen of opposing opinions, 
     <lb/>
     as I am. Yet I speak with some earnestness 
     <lb/>
     on this subject, and for this reason: I say that 
     <lb/>
     it is more than one's patience can very well 
     <lb/>
     endure, to sit here, as I have for years past, 
     <lb/>
     even before my hon. friend (Mr. Tarte) was 
     <lb/>
     a member of this House, and hear hon. 
     <lb/>
     members, who know absolutely nothing of 
     <lb/>
     the North-west, speaking as though this or 
     <lb/>
     that section were being trampled under foot. 
     <lb/>
     My hon. friend refers to the newspapers. 
     <lb/>
     I never read long articles from newspapers to 
     <lb/>
     this House myself—I know their value. But I 
     <lb/>
     have read articles in one of the best written 
     <lb/>
     papers in the Dominion of Canada—the 
     <lb/>
     Toronto 'Mail '-from which one would sup<lb break="no"/>pose that Mr. Royal, while Lieutenant-Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor, was like a czar driving his political car 
     <lb/>
     over the Protestant sentiment of the North<lb break="no"/>west. It is not necessary to assure this 
     <lb/>
     House that there was nothing of that kind. 
     <lb/>
     It would be simply impossible. What actu<lb break="no"/>ally happened was this : Mr. Royal, when he 
     <lb/>
    first came among us, went beyond the powers  
     <lb/>given him by the Dominion Act in handing 
     <lb/>over everything to the Assembly. The late 
     <lb/>Sir John Macdonald saw what he was doing. 
     <lb/>and reminded him that he must act within 
     <lb/>the Dominion statute. When Mr. Royal 
     <lb/>tried to hark back, and get within the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Act, he seemed to be taking back 
     <lb/>Something he had given, but he was only de<lb break="no"/>claring that he had no power to give that 
     <lb/>which he had assumed to give. Subsequent<lb break="no"/>ly, legislation took place that practically gave  
     <lb/>the Legislative Assembly all the powers of 
     <lb/>a Provincial Assembly, with two or three 
     <lb/>points excepted, and the North-west at the 
     <lb/>present minute is practically in the position 
     <lb/>of a province, save these two or three ex<lb break="no"/>ceptions, and the fact that instead of getting  
     <lb/>a subsidy as the other provinces do, we get 
     <lb/>a grant in bulk but for specific purposes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. What are the ex<lb break="no"/>ceptions ?  
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. We cannot charter insur<lb break="no"/>ance companies and we cannot borrow money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. Cannot charter railway com<lb break="no"/>panies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Railway companies also. 
     <lb/>Now, Sir, I have read these ordinances. Let 
     <lb/>me repeat that I have no brief here for the 
     <lb/>
 
 
            <cb/>
         
         
     existing state of things, or any possible state 
     <lb/>
     of things. The issue I have with my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend from L'Islet (Mr. Tarte), and the issue 
     <lb/>
     I have had with my hon. friends on the Min<lb break="no"/>isterial side, when they have described a 
     <lb/>
     state of things which does not exist in the 
     <lb/>
     North-west, is plain. Certain regulations re<lb break="no"/>lating to the separate schools were passed, 
     <lb/>
     and these regulations were objected to. Now, 
     <lb/>
     what did this Executive Council which my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend (Mr. Tarte) described as a Pro<lb break="no"/>testant council, do ? My friend Mr. Haul<lb break="no"/>tain—who is described as premier, but who 
     <lb/>
     as he is a sensible man, laughs at that de<lb break="no"/>scription of himself—has taken steps to meet 
     <lb/>
     the criticisms of his acts with reference to 
     <lb/>
     these questions, upon which he will have to 
     <lb/>
     appear before the people at no distant day. 
     <lb/>
     Here, I may say, are the modifications of the 
     <lb/>
     regulations, signed by Mr. James Brown, who 
     <lb/>
     is Secretary of the Council of Public Instruc<lb break="no"/>tion : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     In reply to inquiries respecting 'Readers' and 
     <lb/>
     examinations for promotion in Roman Catholic 
     <lb/>
     schools— 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     You see. the schools are there. 
            </p>
            
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName>. Hear, hear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. My hon. friend says, " Hear. 
     <lb/>
     hear." He knows this to be the fact. But 
     <lb/>
     will any man who has listened to him, not 
     <lb/>
     agree with me, that the impression conveyed 
     <lb/>
     by his speech was that the Catholic schools 
     <lb/>
     were done away with ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName>. The words are there, but the 
     <lb/>
     thing is gone. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. DAVIN. Here is the modification that 
     <lb/>
    was made : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     In reply to inquiries respecting ' Readers ' and 
     <lb/>
     examinations for promotion in Roman Catholic 
     <lb/>
     schools, I am directed to forward the following 
     <lb/>
     minutes passed by the Council of Public Instruc<lb break="no"/>tion the l3th of January, 1893 :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The regulations of the Council of Public In<lb break="no"/>struction mailed to all schools on or about 16th 
     <lb/> August last govern all examinations held under the 
     <lb/> direction of the Council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The following Readers are authorized for use in 
     <lb/>Roman Catholic Schools in Standards I. and II., 
     <lb/>and become compulsory after lst January, 1894, 
     <lb/> viz. :— 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

    
   
            <p>
     Protestant Readers ? No. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Dominion Series (Sadlier's Catholic Read<lb break="no"/>ers) Parts I. and II. and the Second Reader; or 
     <lb/>
      "The Ontario Readers " Parts I. and II. and the 
     <lb/>
     Second Reader. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In school districts where French is the vernac<lb break="no"/>ular the school trustees may, upon obtaining the 
     <lb/>
      consent of an Inspector, in writing, use the Ontario 
     <lb/>
      Series of bilingual readers, Parts I. and II. and the 
     <lb/>
      Second Reader, instead of the Dominion Series or 
     <lb/>
     the Ontario Reader. In all standards above the 
     <lb/>
      Second the Ontario Readers are prescribed after lst 
     <lb/>
     January, 1894. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Now, there were some details of such a char<lb break="no"/>acter that upon these, probably, there was 
     <lb/>
          
          
            <pb n="177" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00177.jpg"/>
       
       
     <fw type="num">177</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 21, 1894]</fw> <fw type="num">178</fw>
     
     
     ground of complaint, though I understand<lb/>this ground has been removed. As a fact, 
     <lb/>at this moment the Roman Catholic schools 
     <lb/>there are taught, in some cases by Roman 
     <lb/>Catholic ladies with vow,. and the schools 
     <lb/>are in existence precisely as they were be<lb break="no"/>fore this ordinance was passed. We get a 
     <lb/>grant of something less than $200,000 all 
     <lb/>told. What was the use, Mr. Speaker, of 
     <lb/>having a dual inspection ? As now arranged 
     <lb/>they have a Protestant inspector and a 
     <lb/>Catholic inspector. At one time the Catho<lb break="no"/>lic inspector goes over the district previously 
     <lb/>travelled by the Protestant inspector, and, 
     <lb/>at another, the Protestant takes the ground 
     <lb/>previously travelled by his Catholic colleague. 
     <lb/>Is it to be supposed, when they fix on the 
     <lb/>readers and the character of the instruction 
     <lb/>to be given in the schools that either in<lb break="no"/>spector cannot be trusted to see that the 
     <lb/>system is carried out effectively ? I have 
     <lb/>heard, as I say, from one or two friends in 
     <lb/>conversation, complaints against some of the 
     <lb/>regulations. I cannot say that I have heard 
     <lb/>complaints against the enactment. My hon. 
     <lb/>friend stands here to support the Roman 
     <lb/>Catholic schools for the North-west. He 
     <lb/>may be surprised when I tell him that no 
     <lb/>greater enemy—though he does not mean it— 
     <lb/>—no greater enemy of Roman Catholic. 
     <lb/>schools in the Territories exists in the Do<lb break="no"/>minion of Canada than my hon. friend. The 
     <lb/>speech my hon. friend has made here to-day 
     <lb/>and every such speech, let me tell him. is 
     <lb/>a blow struck at Roman Catholic schools as 
     <lb/>they exist in the North-west. I am dealing 
     <lb/>simply with the question of schools in the 
     <lb/>North-west, and not with any question out<lb break="no"/>side of that. Sir. let me tell you that the 
     <lb/>people of the North-west, Catholic and Pro<lb break="no"/>testant, have, if possible a stronger senti<lb break="no"/>ment of provincial autonomy—because it is 
     <lb/>nascent—than the people of any province 
     <lb/>in the Dominion of Canada where the senti<lb break="no"/>ment is matured. The sentiment that they 
     <lb/>ought to be accorded all the rights and 
     <lb/>all the privileges of a province, is strong 
     <lb/>all over the North-west ; and men who 
     <lb/>have no more prejudice against Roman 
     <lb/>Catholic separate schools than my hon. 
     <lb/>friend, if the Government had disallow<lb break="no"/>ed that Ordinance, would have been agitat<lb break="no"/>ing all over the. country. I said to one gen<lb break="no"/>tleman, who is, I believe a friend of 
     <lb/>my hon. friend on my right, who is a French- 
     <lb break="yes"/>Canadian, and takes a deep interest in this 
     <lb/>question : What do you want ? Could you 
     <lb/>succeed in having the Federal Government 
     <lb/>disallow that Ordinance. you know well the 
     <lb/>result would be that agitation would never 
     <lb/>cease until we had in the North-west a 
     <lb/>Martin Bill. Those are the exact words I 
     <lb/>used. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. Yellow ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Yes. Yellow Martin. An<lb break="no"/>other incident showing the utter ignorance 
     <lb/>
     that prevails as to the state of opinion in 
     <lb/>
     the North-west was the Speech of Mr. Cas<lb break="no"/>grain. Mr. Casgrain, like my hon. friend, 
     <lb/>
       
       
            <cb/>
    

     
     never stated the grievance. It would be very 
     <lb/>
     hard, I think, for my hon. friend, after read<lb break="no"/>ing over that Ordinance, to say that separate 
     <lb/>
     schools do not exist there still ; I will be 
     <lb/>
     very glad if he will show me from that 
     <lb/>
     Ordinance where his grievance is. If there 
     <lb/>
     is a grievance, or any of his friends feel 
     <lb/>
     that there is a grievance, in regard to that 
     <lb/>
     Ordinance, it is his duty to point it out. Now. 
     <lb/>
     I have seen the statement in the papers. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Casgrain mentioned it, and my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend quoted it, that perhaps the Lieuten<lb break="no"/>ant-Governor of the North-west and Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Haultain, were going to fix this thing up. 
     <lb/>
     and they would tell the Legislative Assem<lb break="no"/>bly what to do. Sir, we have not yet got 
     <lb/>
     party Government in the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, and there is no one in the Local 
     <lb/>
     Assembly with what is called a following 
     <lb/>
     in the sense that Mr. Mowat, for instance, 
     <lb/>
     has a following in Ontario, or the right hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman who leads the Government, or 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman who leads the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion, has a following in this House. There 
     <lb/>
     is no man in local politics that has such a 
     <lb/>
     following, and if Mr. Haultain were foolish 
     <lb/>
    enough to make any such suggestion, the 
     <lb/>Assembly would simply go on their way 
     <lb/>without minding the suggestion. There is, 
     <lb/>I repeat, a strong sentiment in favour of 
     <lb/>provincial autonomy in the North-west, and 
     <lb/>I am perfectly certain that it would be a 
     <lb/>pretty dangerous thing for Mr. Haultain to 
     <lb/>go to the country if he attempted to take 
     <lb/>any such course as Mr. Casgrain thinks he 
     <lb/>ought to take. What would be the use of it ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. Perhaps you had better ex<lb break="no"/>plain some of the changes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. The alleged grievances have 
     <lb/>
     not been very clearly explained. One of the 
     <lb/>
     grievances—and it is one that I certainly 
     <lb/>
     condemned myself, but I am under the im<lb break="no"/>pression that it has been remedied—was that 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Goggin, the Educational Superintendent, 
     <lb/>
     laid down that the ladies who taught in Ro<lb break="no"/>man Catholic schools, or the ladies about to 
     <lb/>
     take vows for the purpose of teaching. should 
     <lb/>
     go and be examined either at Calgary or at 
     <lb/>
     Regina, unless they were already qualified. 
     <lb/>
     Well, I considered that that was not neces<lb break="no"/>sary, and that it would be well to adopt the 
     <lb/>
     plan followed in Manitoba some years ago, 
     <lb/>
     namely, that the examiner should go and ex<lb break="no"/>amine those ladies and see that they came up 
     <lb/>
     to the standard required by the Council of 
     <lb/>
     Public Instruction. It is, however, not a 
     <lb/>
     practical question at present, as all the ladies 
     <lb/>
     teaching or desiring to teach in Catholic 
     <lb/>
     schools are qualified. Now, Sir. I hope 
     <lb/>
     that my hon. friend will not think that it 
     <lb/>
     is rude on my part to say that I do 
     <lb/>
     not think he understood this question, al<lb break="no"/>though I am sure he must understand it 
     <lb/>
     now, if he did not before. I think I have 
     <lb/>
     shown the House how the legislation stands ; 
     <lb/>
     I have shown the House how the Council 
     <lb/>
     of Public Instruction is formed, and I think 
     <lb/>
     I have shown the House where the shoe 
     <lb/>
     pinches, if there is any pinch. It was un<lb break="no"/>
        
        
            <pb n="179" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-21_Page_00179.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">179</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">180</fw>
     
     
     derstood that a kind of informal arrange<lb break="no"/>ment had been come to so that the Ordin<lb break="no"/>ance would work, and I am very sorry if any 
     <lb/>
     hitch has occurred. Sir, I repeat that there 
     <lb/>
     never was a more mistaken course taken by 
     <lb/>
     any one who is a friend of separate schools, 
     <lb/>
     than the course of objecting to the state of 
     <lb/>
     things that exists at present. If you agitate 
     <lb/>
     it the result will be that a sentiment, partly 
     <lb/>
     provincial—and I won't say that there is not 
     <lb/>
     another sentiment of a warmer character 
     <lb/>
     than provincial—might be raised, and the 
     <lb/>
     results would be inimical to the very cause 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend has at heart. Now, Sir. my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend speaks of the "dear province of 
     <lb/>
     Quebec." Dear that province is, not only to 
     <lb/>
     him, but to us all. But does he not suppose 
     <lb/>
     that the people of the North-west can say : 
     <lb/>
     " Dear Territories of the North-west " ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName>. We do not abolish separate 
     <lb/>
     schools in the province of Quebec. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName> No, you do not ; but what you 
     <lb/>
     are contending is that something has taken 
     <lb/>
     place in the Territories that causes a great 
     <lb/>
     grievance to you. That is the point. Why, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Speaker, my hon. friends talk about the 
     <lb/>
     French minority in the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. I cannot speak the French language 
     <lb/>
     as my hon friend does ; I cannot appreciate 
     <lb/>
     all the fine and delicate ' nuances ' of expres<lb break="no"/>sion that belong to that magnificent tongue, 
     <lb/>
     as my hon. friend does ; but I can, to a great 
     <lb/>
     extent, appreciate that language, and I need 
     <lb/>
     hardly say that I have no prejudice against 
     <lb/>
     the French language or against French peo<lb break="no"/>ple. But if you are going to talk about the 
     <lb/>
     French minority in the territories, what are 
     <lb/>
     you going to do with the German minority ? 
     <lb/>
     Why, the German minority is of consequence 
     <lb/>
     to-day, and at the rate they are growing, they 
     <lb/>
     will soon compete with the English inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants in the North-west Territories. What 
     <lb/>
     are you going to do in regard to them ? I 
     <lb/>
     am not aware of any French-Canadian in 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories who complains 
     <lb/>
     of any grievance. I am aware that gentle<lb break="no"/>men in high authority have objected to the 
     <lb/>
     regulations in regard to separate schools ; 
     <lb/>
     and I am aware that on the part of my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend, on the part of the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Simcoe, and on the part of several other hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen, there is a hallucination prevail<lb break="no"/>ing as to the dual language question in the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories ; a perfect hallucina<lb break="no"/>tion. The bee buzzes as loudly and as non<lb break="no"/>sensically in the head of my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     as he buzzes in the heads of others. Sir, 
     <lb/>
     there are some other things that I would 
     <lb/>
     like to say on this question, but as the 
     <lb/>
     House is about to adjourn I will defer say<lb break="no"/>ing them now, as I will have another op<lb break="no"/>portunity of speaking before my hon. friend's 
     <lb/>
     motion finally passes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. I would like to 
     <lb/>
     make a suggestion as to the course of public 
     <lb/>
     business. This order cannot be resumed this 
     <lb/>
     evening as public Bills and Orders will come 
     <lb/>
     up after Government Orders, and I think it 
     <lb/>
   
   
            <cb/>
        
        
     would be convenient, therefore, that this 
     <lb/>
     debate should stand adjourned. Tonight, 
     <lb/>
      according to the Order of the House given the 
     <lb/>
     day before yesterday, when the House ad<lb break="no"/>journs it will stand adjourned until Tuesday 
     <lb/>
     next, and inasmuch as a large number of 
     <lb/>
     members desire to take the night trains for 
     <lb/>
     the east and west, I think it would not be 
     <lb/>
     well for us to begin anything like the Budget 
     <lb/>
     business to-night, more especially as the Fin<lb break="no"/>ance Minister, if he took four or five hours 
     <lb/>
     to deliver his Budget Speech, would have no 
     <lb/>
     time to reply to any comments on his speech. 
     <lb/>
     I may say that my colleague is perfectly 
     <lb/>
     ready, if it is the wish of the House, to go 
     <lb/>
     on with the business of this evening. What 
     <lb/>
     I would propose, however, is that we should 
     <lb/>
     adjourn this debate and then adjourn the 
     <lb/>
     House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName> moved the adjournment of the 
     <lb/>
     debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man has the floor. Before moving the ad<lb break="no"/>journment, I ask to have it agreed that the 
     <lb/>
     debate on the Budget, which I suppose will 
     <lb/>
     begin on Tuesday, shall be continued ' de die 
     <lb/>
     in diem' when it reaches the Committee 
     <lb/>
     stage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. I have no objection to 
     <lb/>
     that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. Does the 
     <lb/>
     Finance Minister definitely decide to make 
     <lb/>
     his financial statement on Tuesday ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and debate adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName> moved the adjourn<lb break="no"/>ment of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Motion agreed to; and the House ad<lb break="no"/>journed at 6.10 pm. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   
            <!-- GL, 2018-10-23, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 
            <!--<p>
     HOUSE OF COMMONS. 
     <lb/>
     TUESDAY, 27th March, 1894. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The SPEAKER took the Chair at Three 
     <lb/>
     o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     PRAYERS. 
     <lb/>
     FIRST READING. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Bill (No. 12) to amend the Electoral Fran<lb break="no"/>chise Act by providing for a residential quali<lb break="no"/>fication for all voters—(Mr. Edgar.)  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     REPORTS. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Annual Report of the Department of Rail<lb break="no"/>ways and Canals, for the fiscal year ending 
     <lb/>
     30th June, 1893.—(Mr. Haggart.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>