<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1876-02-11"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1876-02-11">11 February 1876</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1975"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="16"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-02-11_Page_00015.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-02-11_Page_00016.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-02-11_Page_00015">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-02-11_Page_00015.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-02-11_Page_00016">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-02-11_Page_00016.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="15" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-02-11_Page_00015.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Address.</hi></fw> <fw type="dateline">[February 11, 1876]</fw> <fw type="num">15</fw>
           
            <p>When the Bill for the inaugu<lb break="no"/>ration of the North-West Government <lb/>was proposed last Session, I said until<lb/>there is a larger body of people to be<lb/>ruled, the constitutional Governor<lb/>of Manitoba might still be entrusted<lb/>with the management of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West. As the constitutional Governor<lb/>of Manitoba he has little to do, and he<lb/>might very well have given his spare<lb/>time—and he had plenty of it on his <lb/>hands, and, as I understand, did not<lb/>grumble at the labor—to the adminis<lb break="no"/>tration of the affairs of the North-West<lb/>Territories. But my hon. friend the<lb/>Premier, in his usual incisive way,<lb/>said it was absolutely necessary that<lb/>the Government should be established<lb/>without delay, and stationed far away<lb/>from Winnipeg and its influence. I<lb/>was not convinced, but I was silenced,<lb/>and the Bill passed; but we do not see<lb/>that the Government has been estab<lb break="no"/>lished after all. I flatter myself in<lb/>the calm consideration of the subject<lb/>which my hon. friend gave it after the <lb/>prorogation, and in his own chamber,<lb/>that he began to feel there was no<lb/>such imminent necessity as he at<lb/>first thought for the immediate ap<lb break="no"/>pointment of a second Governor. <lb/>At all events no appointment has <lb/>yet been made, and as we have no <lb/>complaint from the North-West,<lb/>and have saved a considerable amount<lb/>from the delay, I presume the hon.<lb/>gentleman will make the saving a<lb/>permanent one by continuing the <lb/>masterly inactivity which he has shown<lb/>hitherto with respect to this Govern<lb break="no"/>
           
            <pb n="16" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-02-11_Page_00016.jpg"/>
            
            
            <fw type="num">16</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The Address.</hi></fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS.]</fw>
       
       ment.</p>     
            
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>