<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1876-03-20" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1876-03-20">20 March 1876</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Third Parliament, Third Session</title>.
<date when="1976"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Maclean, Roger &amp; Co., Wellington Street</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="729" to="731"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00729.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00730.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00731.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00729"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00729.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00730"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00730.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00731"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00731.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="729" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00729.jpg"/> 

    <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Routine Business.</hi></fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 20, 1876.]</fw> <fw type="num">729</fw> 

<head>THE NORTH-WEST COUNCIL.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:SCHU1">Mr. SCHULTZ</persName> moved, seconded by <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WRIG2">Mr. Wright</persName>, that an humble Address <lb/>
be presented to His Excellency the <lb/>
Governor General praying for copies of <lb/>
all acts passed by the North-West Coun<lb break="no"/>cil, and copies of all correspondence <lb/>
between the Government of Canada <lb/>
and the Lieut-Governor of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories relative to any matters <lb/>
engaging the attention of the said <lb/>
Council. Mr. Schultz, said that he <lb/>
would have moved this Address without <lb/>
any reference to the Council whose <lb/>
functions were about to be supplanted <lb/>
by the new order of things, were it not <lb/>
that his attention was directed to <lb/>
the matter by an editorial in the <lb/>
    Toronto <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> of the 25th February, a <lb/>
portion of which he would take the <lb/>
liberty of reading:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Heretofore the North-West Territory east <lb/>
and west of Manitoba has been governed by <lb/>
the Lieutenant-Governor of Manitoba and a <lb/>
species of half advisatory, half legislative, <lb/>
Council of gentlemen chosen from among the <lb/>
residents in Winnipeg and its vicinity. They are <lb/>
themselves not slow to admit that their <lb/>
constitution is a farce, and it requires no <lb/>
effort of imagination in those even who have <lb/>

<cb/>

never been in the North-West to understand <lb/>
the impossibility of merchants and others in <lb/>
Winnipeg acting as a Legislature for the <lb/>
settlements on the Saskatchewan, and nearly <lb/>
a thousand miles away in the neighbourhood <lb/>
of the Rocky Mountains. <lb/></p> 

<p>"At one of the last sittings of this <lb/>
Winnipeg Council, of which the former editor <lb/>
of the Nouveau Monde is a prominent member, <lb/>
it was proposed to incorporate the clergy of <lb/>
the missionary dioceses of the North-West <lb/>
with land-holding powers. The object of this <lb/>
was so apparent to those in Winnipeg, who <lb/>
have seen the effect of the system there, that <lb/>
it was strenuously opposed by some of the <lb/>
English members, but in spite of their efforts <lb/>
it was carried, and would have come to Ottawa <lb/>
with such force as this nondescript Council <lb/>
have been able to give to their legislation had <lb/>
not Lieutenant-Governor Morris refused to <lb/>
assent to the Bill." <lb/></p> 
    
</quote>
    
<p>Here was the utterance of a leading <lb/>
organ as to the value of this Council <lb/>
now about to cease to exist. There <lb/>
was a reference to certain Bills which <lb/>
were brought before the Council to in<lb break="no"/>corporate religious bodies in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, and where it was assumed that <lb/>
the Council had passed these; and they <lb/>
were only prevented from becoming <lb/>
law by the action of the Lieutenant-<lb break="yes"/>Governor who exercised his power to <lb/>
stop them. This statement he (Mr. <lb/>
Schultz) must characterize as ut<lb break="no"/>terly without foundation. It was true <lb/>
that such Bills were before the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil, but when the promoter of them <lb/>
found that the sense of the Council was <lb/>
against them, he withdrew, and it did <lb/>
not need the power of the Lieutenant-<lb break="yes"/>Governor to prevent any ill-considered <lb/>
and rash action of the Council itself. <lb/>
Of course it must always be a matter <lb/>
of opinion as to whether the services <lb/>
of this Council were valuable or not, <lb/>
but we have a more authoritative utter<lb break="no"/>ance than the last, which hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men will find in the last report of the <lb/>
Minister of the Interior, who says:— <lb/>
"It is due to that Council to record <lb/>
" the fact that their legislation and <lb/>
"valuable practical suggestions sub<lb break="no"/>"mitted to Your Excellency from time <lb/>
"to time through their official head, <lb/>
"Lieut.-Governor Morris, aided the <lb/>
"Government not a little in the good <lb/>
"work of laying the foundations of <lb/>
"law and order in the North-West, in <lb/>
"securing the good will of the Indian <lb/>
"tribes, and in establishing the prestige <lb/>
"of the Dominion Government through<lb break="no"/>"out the vast territory." <lb/></p>

<pb n="730" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00730.jpg"/> 

    <fw type="num">730</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The North-West Council.</hi></fw> <fw type="running">[Commons.]</fw>

<p>Here is the estimate which the Hon. <lb/>
Minister specially charged with the <lb/>
care of North-West matters place upon <lb/>
the services of this Council. He (Mr. <lb/>
Schultz) being a member of this Coun<lb break="no"/>cil did not care to say much of its <lb/>
merits or otherwise, and would leave <lb/>
it for time to determine whether a <lb/>
body of men, many of whom if they did <lb/>
not now live in the North-West yet had <lb/>
the practical experience of years in <lb/>
connection with it, were not as <lb/>
to be of service as any Council <lb/>
to be appointed under the new system, <lb/>
and he trusted that the new Council <lb/>
would give that consideration to the <lb/>
suggestions and recommendations of <lb/>
the old which he felt their importance <lb/>
demanded. Among the papers which <lb/>
he hoped to have brought down by this <lb/>
motion, would be found valuable sug<lb break="no"/>gestions as to the preservation of the <lb/>
buffalo. He (Mr. Schultz) would urge <lb/>
the importance of this matter on the <lb/>
Government. So long as the buffalo <lb/>
were numerous there was little danger <lb/>
of difficulty with the Plain tribes of <lb/>
Indians with whom we were not being <lb/>
brought into contact. When these <lb/>
were extinct we must expect to deal <lb/>
with a race of paupers rendered dan<lb break="no"/>gerous by want of food. The Rev. <lb/>
Father Lascombe, a high authority of <lb/>
all such matters, believes in common <lb/>
with many others that is the present <lb/>
rate of destruction goes on the race of <lb/>
buffalo will be extinct in ten years. It <lb/>
is true that since the completion of the <lb/>
Union Pacific Railroad and the estab<lb break="no"/>lishment of military and other settle<lb break="no"/>ments in Missouri, Father Lascombe <lb/>
estimates the number killed yearly <lb/>
during the winter at 80,000, and about <lb/>
the same number in summer. Their <lb/>
present feeding ground comprises a <lb/>
length of, say six hundred miles by <lb/>
about one hundred and fifty, and is <lb/>
bounded on the west by the Rocky <lb/>
Mountains, on the east by the Qu'Ap<lb break="no"/>pelle Lakes, on the south by the Mis<lb break="no"/>souri and the north by the north <lb/>
branch of the Saskatchewan, and this <lb/>
limit is ever decreasing by the destruc<lb break="no"/>tion caused by the hunters of the <lb/>
Saskatchewan on the north, those from <lb/>
the Missouri on the south and the Red <lb/>
River hunters on the east to an extent <lb/>
and rapidity so alarming that it is <lb/>
estimated by the Rev. Father and <lb/> 


<cb/>

others that in ten years they will be <lb/>
extinct. Such a result is not at all im<lb break="no"/>probable, since it is only a few years <lb/>
since the buffalo ranged east of the <lb/>
Red River, and since the last of <lb/>
the wood buffalo, an animal of the <lb/>
same species, but larger size, which <lb/>
ranged between the Saskatchewan <lb/>
and the Slave Lakes, was killed and <lb/>
the whole of the race is extinct. <lb/>
The use of the revolving pistol and the <lb/>
repeating refile instead of the ordinary <lb/>
leading gun has helped to bring this <lb/>
about, aided by the destruction caused <lb/>
by wolves, sickness, accidents of vari<lb break="no"/>ous sorts and the wasteful destruction <lb/>
of the buffalo pound. Unfortunately, <lb/>
too, it is the robe of the female buffalo <lb/>
which is the most valuable and when <lb/>
killed for it she is always with calf. <lb/>
It is her flesh which makes the best <lb/>
meat, and being more easily hunted <lb/>
down than the bulls, it has caused a <lb/>
destruction which has resulted in many <lb/>
of the bands met with last summer <lb/>
being composed of a proporton of six <lb/>
or seven males to one female. The <lb/>
district where buffalo are found has <lb/>
narrowed with startling rapidity during <lb/>
the last ten years, buffalo having about <lb/>
that time been seen by him (Mr. <lb/>
Schultz) east of Red River. These <lb/>
facts point strongly to the necessity of <lb/>
preventive measures, and the facts <lb/>
spoken of are so well known to the In<lb break="no"/>dians and half-breeds that they are <lb/>
anxious the Government should <lb/>
take action in the matter if it were <lb/>
not for the fact that it would be im<lb break="no"/>possible to prevent the killing of cows. <lb/>
At the same time there would be no <lb/>
objection to the killing of buffalo bulls <lb/>
at any season of the years, but since <lb/>
this is impossible a stringent law is <lb/>
demanded which will practically leave <lb/>
these animals undisturbed from the 1st <lb/>
November to 1st May, and an enact<lb break="no"/>ment to prevent the killing of calves at <lb/>
any season. If such a law were passed <lb/>
it is believed that in five years the <lb/>
buffalo would have to increased that <lb/>
these restrictions might be removed. <lb/>
He (Mr. Schultz) hoped that this <lb/>
matter would receive the consideration <lb/>
at the hands of the Government which <lb/>
its importance demanded, and that the <lb/>
papers bearing on this matter would <lb/>
be printed for the general information <lb/>
they would afford. <lb/></p>

<pb n="731" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-20_Page_00731.jpg"/> 

    <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Sanitary Statistics.</hi></fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 20, 1876.]</fw> <fw type="num">731</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said the <lb/>
matter to which the hon member had <lb/>
particularly alluded-the preservation <lb/>
of the buffalo in the western prairies-<lb break="yes"/>has occupied a large share of the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the goverment for a con<lb break="no"/>siderable time. <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>