<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1903-09-24"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1903-09-24">24 September 1903</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Ninth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          <date when="1903"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="12302" to="12330"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12301.xml"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12303.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12305.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12307.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12309.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12311.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12313.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12315.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12317.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12319.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12321.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12323.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12325.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12327.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12329.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-26">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-09-26">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12301">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12301.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12303">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12303.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12305">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12305.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12307">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12307.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12309">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12309.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12311">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12311.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12313">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12313.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12315">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12315.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12317">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12317.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12319">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12319.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12321">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12321.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12323">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12323.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12325">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12325.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12327">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12327.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12329">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12329.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            
            <pb n="12301" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12301.jpg"/>
       
       
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">12302</fw>
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES—REPRE<lb break="no"/>SENTATION IN SENATE.</head>
            
            <p>
               Bill (No.253) to increase the representa<lb break="no"/>tion of the North-west Territories in the<lb/>
               Senate, read a second time, and the House<lb/>
               went into committee thereon.</p>
            
            <p>On Section 1.</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL2">Mr. MACLEAN</persName>. I should think that the<lb/>
               government would incorporate in this Bill<lb/>
               a clause carrying out the pledge to reform<lb/>
               the Senate given to the people by the Lib<lb break="no"/>eral party some years ago. For more months<lb/>
               past the Liberal papers have been declaring<lb/>
               that the Liberals have a majority of from<lb/>
               ten to fifteen in the Senate and that they<lb/>
               now control that body. If that be the fact, <lb/>
               then the pledges of the Liberals made in<lb/>
               1803, that the Senate ought to be re<lb break="no"/>formed—</p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOHN2">Mr. JOHNSTON</persName> (Cape Breton). So it has<lb/>
               been.</p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL2">Mr. MACLEAN</persName>. What the Liberals<lb/>
               pledged themselves to do was not to reform<lb/>
               the personnel of the Senate, but to reform<lb/>
               its constitution, and here is a chance for<lb/>
               them to carry out that pledge. But, if the<lb/>
               government does not carry out its pledge<lb/>
               to reform the Senate, let me point out that<lb/>
               they are responsible for the action of that<lb/>
               chamber, and if a measure designed in the<lb/>
               public interests such as the cattle-guard<lb/>
               clause in the Railway Act, comes to grief<lb/>
               in the Senate, then the government must be<lb/>
               held responsible. In view of the fact that<lb/>
               an election seems to be at hand, and that<lb/>
               strange things may take place within the<lb/>
               coming month in connection with public<lb/>
               legislation. I take this opportunity of point<lb break="no"/>ing out, that whatever the Senate does, the<lb/>
               government must be held responsible for it.<lb/>
               I do not purpose to introduce a measure<lb/>
               to reform the Senate, but I have been wait<lb break="no"/>ing for this opportunity to say, that in view<lb/>
               of the statement in the Liberal press that<lb/>
               the government controls the Senate, they<lb/>
               are responsible for the conduct of the Sen<lb break="no"/>ate, not having carried out their pledge to<lb/>
               reform it.</p>
            
            
            <pb n="12303" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12303.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12303</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">12304</fw>
            
            
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Hon. Mr. HAGGART</persName>.  Does this increas<lb break="no"/>ed number of senators in the North-west  
     <lb/>
     give the same representation by population  
     <lb/>
     as in Quebec and Ontario ?   
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName>. There are  
     <lb/>twenty-four senators for Quebec, twenty- 
     <lb break="yes"/>four for Ontario, and twenty-four for the 
     <lb/>maritime provinces. In addition to that   
     <lb/>provision is made for the representation of   
     <lb/>Manitoba, British Columbia and the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories. The British North Am<lb break="no"/>erica Amendment Act of 1886 chapter 35, 
     <lb/>Imperial Statutes authorizes the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment, and chapter 33 of the Dominion 
     <lb/>Statutes, 1887, provides for the representa<lb break="no"/>tion of North-West Territories in the Sen<lb break="no"/>ate by two members. In 1887, the popula<lb break="no"/>tion of the organized territories was 25,515 ; 
     <lb/>in 1891 it was 66,799, and in 1901, 159,940.<lb/>I need not say that since 1901 the increase<lb/>in population has been at even a greater<lb/>ratio than previous to that year. In 1881<lb/>the population of the unorganized portion<lb/>of the Territories was 30,000, and in 1901<lb/>it had increased to 52,700. Taking the pre<lb break="no"/>sent population of the organized and un<lb break="no"/>organized territories, and allowing for the<lb/>increase since 1901, the unit of representa<lb break="no"/>tion will be practically the same as in On<lb break="no"/>tario, which is about 90,000.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Hon. Mr HAGGART</persName>. There are 210,000 
     <lb/>people in the organized and unorganized<lb/>territories, and that gives you the same<lb/>unit as in Ontario ?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName>. Yes, 
     <lb/>about.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROCH1">Mr. ROCHE</persName> (Marquette). Is each sen<lb break="no"/>ator allowed a territorial district in the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories ? 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName>.  No. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI10">Mr. DAVIS</persName>. A reference to the con<lb break="no"/>federation debates will show that Sir John<lb/>Macdonald explained that representation in<lb/>the Senate was a question of interest, and<lb/>the Senate was a question of interest, and<lb/>not of population. On that principle the<lb/>maritime provinces, Quebec and Ontario<lb/>each got twenty-four senators. Even with<lb/>the increase of two senators proposed in<lb/>this Bill, western Canada only gets eleven<lb/>senators, as against twenty-four in the mari<lb break="no"/>time provinces. If we consider representa<lb break="no"/>tion in the Senate a question of interest<lb/>and not of population, then every one will, <lb/>I think, agree with me, that including<lb/>British Columbia, the North-west Territories,<lb/>Manitoba and the Yukon, the interest of the<lb/>country west of Lake Superior, is at least<lb/>as great as the interest of the maritime<lb/>provinces. Indeed, it may be admitted, that<lb/>if you take all that western country as one,<lb/>its interest is as great as the interest of<lb/>Ontario or Quebec. Therefore I think that<lb/>when this measure was brought down we<lb/>should have been given a full complement<lb/>of senators, as many as are given to the <lb/>maritime provinces.<lb/>
            </p>


            <cb/>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL2">Mr. MACLEAN</persName>. Twenty-four ?</p>
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI10">Mr. DAVIS</persName>. Yes, twenty-four. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACL2">Mr. MACLEAN</persName>. May we take it for 
     <lb/>granted that a member of this House, who<lb/>has already been ordained, is soon to be<lb/>called ?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill reported, read the third time, and 
     <lb/>passed.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <pb n="12305" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12305.jpg"/>
     
     <fw type="dateline">SEPTEMBER 24, 1903</fw> <fw type="num">12306</fw>
     
     
     <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">GOVERNMENT OF THE NORTH-WEST<lb/>TERRITORIES-FINANCIAL AID.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p>House went into Committee to consider the<lb/>following proposed resolution :<lb/>
            </p>
        
        
        <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Resolved that it is expedient to enact as<lb/>follows :—<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>1. The Governor General may, in his discre<lb break="no"/>tion from time to time, advance to the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the North-west Territories any sum<lb/>required for local improvements in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories, not exceeding in the whole<lb/>the sum of two hundred and fifty thousand dol<lb break="no"/>lars.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>2. All sums so advanced to the government<lb/>of the North-west Territories shall be charged<lb/>in an account to be known as ' The North-west<lb/>Territories Debt Account,' and shall, in any<lb/>financial arrangement that may be made in<lb/>connection with the organization of a province<lb/>or provinces in the said territories, be taken<lb/>into consideration as a debt owing by the said<lb/>territories to the Dominion of Canada.—(The<lb/>Minister of Finance).<lb/>
            </p></quote>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName> (Hon. W.<lb/>S. Fielding). This resolution proposes to<lb/>authorize an advance of a sum, not exceeding-<lb break="yes"/>in the whole $250,000, to the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the North-west Territories, from<lb/>time to time, for the construction of any<lb/>public works which they may wish to con<lb break="no"/>struct and may deem to be of a class charge<lb break="no"/>able to capital account. The rapid and very<lb/>gratifying increase in the population of the<lb/>
  
  
            <pb n="12307" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12307.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12307</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">12308</fw>
       
       
       
     North-west Territories makes it desirable 
     <lb/>
     that some additional provision should be 
     <lb/>
     made for the carrying on of the government 
     <lb/>
     of that portion of the Dominion. The time 
     <lb/>
     must be close at hand when it will be neces<lb break="no"/>sary, not only to revise the financial ar<lb break="no"/>rangements of that portion of our country, 
     <lb/>
     but also to take up the larger question of 
     <lb/>
     granting full powers of local government to 
     <lb/>
     the people of that region. In the past, hav<lb break="no"/>ing regard to the comparatively small popu<lb break="no"/>lation and the large area over which they 
     <lb/>
     were dispersed, the conditions did not seem 
     <lb/>
     favourable for the establishment of a gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and legislature with full powers of 
     <lb/>
     a province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The powers granted to the North-west 
     <lb/>
     legislature are, however, quite large ; and, 
     <lb/>
     in very many respects those territories are 
     <lb/>
     to-day exercising the privileges and hear<lb break="no"/>ing responsibilities of self-government. In 
     <lb/>
     some respects, they are not entirely clothed 
     <lb/>
     with the powers of provincial government ; 
     <lb/>
     but I think we all agree that the time is 
     <lb/>
     close at hand when these powers must be 
     <lb/>
     given to them. These powers will not mere<lb break="no"/>ly convey privileges, but will also impose 
     <lb/>
     upon them some responsibility, and I am 
     <lb/>
     not quite sure that, from a purely finan<lb break="no"/>cial point of view, they will be benefited by 
     <lb/>
     establishing provincial autonomy. How<lb break="no"/>ever, I presume the question is not to be 
     <lb/>
     judged from that point of view alone and 
     <lb/>
     that the people in that country which is 
     <lb/>
     now so rapidly being filled up will desire 
     <lb/>
     ordinary powers of provincial government. 
     <lb/>
     In the meantime, as it is not proposed at 
     <lb/>
     the present session to bring forward a mea<lb break="no"/>sure to give them full powers of provin<lb break="no"/>cial government, it is proposed that we 
     <lb/>
     should make a more liberal provision for 
     <lb/>
     the management of their financial affairs. 
     <lb/>
     We, therefore, agree to make a very con<lb break="no"/>siderable increase in the annual grant and 
     <lb/>
     also to make this special provision having 
     <lb/>
     relation to the opening of a capital account. 
     <lb/>
     If they were established as a province, no 
     <lb/>
     doubt they would have a certain sum of 
     <lb/>
     money placed to their credit, the interest 
     <lb/>
     upon which they would be entitled to re<lb break="no"/>ceive and the principal of which they could 
     <lb/>
     make use of for public works. Provision 
     <lb/>
     is made in the existing law for any of the 
     <lb/>
     provinces that have capital account to their 
     <lb/>
     credit that, if they desire, they may with<lb break="no"/>draw an amount for what are called in the 
     <lb/>
     Act local improvements. As a rule, the 
     <lb/>
     provincial government may not be desirous 
     <lb/>
     of withdrawing these sums, because while 
     <lb/>
     they remain to the credit of the province 
     <lb/>
     in the treasury, the province probably ob<lb break="no"/>tains a better rate of interest than it could 
     <lb/>
     manage to obtain otherwise. We think it is 
     <lb/>
     well that, during the present session, we 
     <lb/>
     shouId make a more liberal allowance to 
     <lb/>
     the North-west government in the way of 
     <lb/>
     annual grant, and also by giving them addi<lb break="no"/>tional power, if they wish to exercise it, by 
     <lb/>
     having a capital account on which they 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <cb/>
         
         
     may draw and which will be a matter of 
     <lb/>
     consideration in any financial arrangement 
     <lb/>
     which may be made hereafter with respect 
     <lb/>
     to organizing a government, or, possibly, 
     <lb/>
     more than one government in these territo<lb break="no"/>ries. All that is proposed for the present 
     <lb/>
     by this resolution is that power shall be 
     <lb/>
     conferred upon His Excellency the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor in Council to advance, from time to 
     <lb/>
     time, to the North-west government, if they 
     <lb/>
     so desire, sums of money up to $250,000, 
     <lb/>
     which are to be expended on public works 
     <lb/>
     of a class which may be deemed properly 
     <lb/>
     chargeable to capital. Perhaps, as the two 
     <lb/>
     questions are connected I may call atten<lb break="no"/>tion to the increases that have been made 
     <lb/>
     in the grants to the North-west Territories. 
     <lb/>
     During recent years very considerable in<lb break="no"/>creases have been made, and it is proposed, 
     <lb/>
     in the present year, to make still further in<lb break="no"/>creases. There is one general grant given 
     <lb/>
     to the government of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories which is classed in our estimates as 
     <lb/>
     grants for schools, &amp;c., which, practically 
     <lb/>
     is equivalent to a provincial subsidy. There 
     <lb/>
     are some other grants for special purposes 
     <lb/>
     to which I need not more particularly re<lb break="no"/>fer ; but this annual grant for schools and 
     <lb/>
     other purposes, I think I may say, stands 
     <lb/>
     in about the position of a provincial sub<lb break="no"/>sidy. That grant in 1892 was quite small— 
     <lb/>
     only $40,000. In 1893 it was $198,000 ; in 
     <lb/>
     1894, $199,000; in 1895, $225,000 ; in 1896, 
     <lb/>
     $267,000, which was the figure at which 
     <lb/>
     the grant stood when the present govern<lb break="no"/>ment came into power. In the following 
     <lb/>
     year there appears to have been a slight 
     <lb/>
     falling off, the reason of which I have not 
     <lb/>
     at hand. For the year ending 30th of July, 
     <lb/>
     1897, the grant was $242,000. From that 
     <lb/>
     time it has almost steadily increased. In 
     <lb/>
     1898 the grant was $262,000 ; in 1899, $282,<lb break="no"/>000 ; in 1900, $282,000. In 1901. including 
     <lb/>
     a special grant which was made in con<lb break="no"/>sequence of considerable damage suffered 
     <lb/>
     from floods, the grant was increased to 
     <lb/>
     $424,000. In 1902, the grant was $407,000. 
     <lb/>
     In 1903, the year recently closed, the sums 
     <lb/>
     allowed by parliament were found to be 
     <lb/>
     quite insufficient, and, in our supplement<lb break="no"/>ary estimates for the year recently voted in 
     <lb/>
     this House, we gave an additional grant of 
     <lb/>
     $250,000 so that this general grant, which I 
     <lb/>
     have described as being equivalent to a pro<lb break="no"/>vincial subsidy, stood for the year 1903 
     <lb/>
     at $707,000, as against $267,000 in 1896. For 
     <lb/>
     the coming year, we are proposing to add a 
     <lb/>
     similar sum of $250,000, which will be pro<lb break="no"/>vided in the supplementary estimates. We 
     <lb/>
     are also making a special grant to the local 
     <lb/>
     government to enable them to carry out a 
     <lb/>
     plan which they had some months ago of 
     <lb/>
     rebuilding two important bridges, one the 
     <lb/>
     Pelly river bridge and the other the Old 
     <lb/>
     Man river bridge. The Pelly river bridge 
     <lb/>
     is estimated to cost $55,000 and the Old 
     <lb/>
     Man river bridge $29,000, or $84,000 for 
     <lb/>
     both. The local authorities came to us 
     <lb/>
     several months ago and represented that 
     <lb/>
 
 
            <pb n="12309" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12309.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12309</fw> <fw type="dateline">SEPTEMBER 24, 1903</fw> <fw type="num">12310</fw>
  
  
     these were two important structures, they 
     <lb/>
     needed authority to construct them at once, 
     <lb/>
     and they were without financial means as to 
     <lb/>
     do so. They were assured that the govern<lb break="no"/>ment would place them in funds to con<lb break="no"/>struct these works. In the course of nego<lb break="no"/>tiations it was at one time proposed that, 
     <lb/>
     these bridges, being of a solid and perman<lb break="no"/>ent character, should be made a charge 
     <lb/>
     against capital account, and it was pro<lb break="no"/>posed to place a sum to the credit of the 
     <lb/>
     local government on capital account. The 
     <lb/>
     local government objected to that and we 
     <lb/>
     have, on consideration, decided to make this 
     <lb/>
     the cost of these two bridges a special grant 
     <lb/>
     for the year and not make it a charge 
     <lb/>
     against capital account. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Hon. Mr. HAGGART</persName>. Is that to be de<lb break="no"/>ducted from the $250,000 ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. As I 
     <lb/>
     was saying, it was at first proposed as my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend (Hon. Mr. Haggart) has sug<lb break="no"/>gested that we should deduct it. In 
     <lb/>
     some correspondence I had with the premier 
     <lb/>
     of the North-west government, I expressed 
     <lb/>
     the view that as these bridges were of a 
     <lb/>
     permanent character they were a proper 
     <lb/>
     charge against capital account. However, 
     <lb/>
     the North-west government thought that an 
     <lb/>
     ungenerous view to take and, on considera<lb break="no"/>tion, we have decided to yield to their re<lb break="no"/>presentations and make it a special grant 
     <lb/>
     this year. So, we shall provide for the cur<lb break="no"/>rent year, apart from some ordinary grants 
     <lb/>
     amounting to $90,000 which I do not need 
     <lb/>
     to specialize, and including the special 
     <lb/>
     grants on account of the bridges, $1,046,000, 
     <lb/>
     as against $267,000 which they were receiv<lb break="no"/>ing only a few years ago when the change 
     <lb/>
     of government occurred. I think it will be 
     <lb/>
     seen from the figures I have read that fair 
     <lb/>
     consideration has been given, from time to 
     <lb/>
     time, to the needs of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, and that we are responding with fair 
     <lb/>
     liberality to their increasing necessities. We 
     <lb/>
     are proposing therefore, to give them, for 
     <lb/>
     the current year, either for their own gen<lb break="no"/>eral purposes or for special purposes, a sum 
     <lb/>
     of $1,046,000, and to give them a right to use, 
     <lb/>
     if they wish, a further sum of $250,000. Of 
     <lb/>
     course, if that be not used, there will be no 
     <lb/>
     charge against them, and, if it be used, or 
     <lb/>
     if any portion of it be used, the amount 
     <lb/>
     used will be charged to a capital account, 
     <lb/>
     and, when we come to the question of es<lb break="no"/>tablishing the financial relations of a new 
     <lb/>
     province or, possibly of more than one pro<lb break="no"/>vince, in the new territory, the matter of 
     <lb/>
     the $250,000 will be taken into considera<lb break="no"/>tion in the adjustment of their debt ac<lb break="no"/>count. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACL2">Mr. MACLEAN</persName>. The statement made in 
     <lb/>
     the House by the hon. Minister of Finance 
     <lb/>
     is in the nature of setting the House in 
     <lb/>
     order before an election takes place. I 
     <lb/>
     think that this is a thing that indicates to 
     <lb/>
     us that an election is near at hand more 
     <lb/>
     directly than anything else we have had. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     It is also in the nature of an apology on 
     <lb/>
     behalf of the government for having ne<lb break="no"/>glected hitherto to erect one or more pro<lb break="no"/>vinces in the North-west. I think it is the 
     <lb/>
     feeling of hon. gentlemen on this side that 
     <lb/>
     this should have been done long ago. Cer<lb break="no"/>tainly, it would have my support and the 
     <lb/>
     support of many hon. gentlemen on this 
     <lb/>
     side if not merely one but more provinces 
     <lb/>
     were erected in the North-west Territories. 
     <lb/>
     Still we are glad to hear that the question 
     <lb/>
     is now to be considered, and that it will be 
     <lb/>
     taken up, as I gather, immediately after the 
     <lb/>
     elections are over. From what the Minister 
     <lb/>
     of Finance has said here to-night, they have 
     <lb/>
     been forced to take up this question, and 
     <lb/>
     in the meantime we are going to do some<lb break="no"/>thing for the Territories in a financial way, 
     <lb/>
     and later on we are going to erect them into 
     <lb/>
     provinces. Now, I am in favour of the 
     <lb/>
     most liberal kind of treatment to the North<lb break="no"/>west. I think they ought to be given a 
     <lb/>
     liberal share of the public domain in that 
     <lb/>
     country, it ought to pass under the exclu<lb break="no"/>sive control of the provinces in the same 
     <lb/>
     way that Ontario, Quebec and the lower 
     <lb/>
     provinces are given the Crown Lands. I 
     <lb/>
     hope when this territory comes to be erect<lb break="no"/>ed into provinces that not only a liberal 
     <lb/>
     financial arrangement will be made with 
     <lb/>
     them, but that they will be given control 
     <lb/>
     of a very considerable portion of the public 
     <lb/>
     domain still held by this government in the 
     <lb/>
     western territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OSLE1">Mr. OSLER</persName>. Whatever may be the 
     <lb/>
     reason for the generosity of the government, 
     <lb/>
     I thoroughly approve of the proposal to 
     <lb/>
     grant an extra $250,000 to the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Territories. No one who has been in that 
     <lb/>
     country and knows anything about it, can 
     <lb/>
     help being struck with the enormous expense 
     <lb/>
     that must be made there for bridges and 
     <lb/>
     roads. As the country fills up roads must 
     <lb/>
     be laid out and bridges must be built over 
     <lb/>
     the various streams, and these bridges will 
     <lb/>
     be expensive. I think the time has ar<lb break="no"/>rived, if it has not passed, when they should  
     <lb/>
     be granted more aid. A very liberal treat<lb break="no"/>ment accorded to the North-west will be 
     <lb/>
     approved of by both sides of this House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. It seems to me this 
     <lb/>
     would be a very proper time for the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to explain why they have refused 
     <lb/>
     provincial autonomy to the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories. We know the people of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories have applied or it, the application 
     <lb/>
     has been brought to the notice of the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment at different times and in differ<lb break="no"/>ent ways, with a good deal of force. We 
     <lb/>
     found when in that country last fall 
     <lb/>
     that there was a strong consensus of 
     <lb/>
     opinion in favour of it, and the people 
     <lb/>
     regarded their situation as most unfortu<lb break="no"/>nate because they were not granted provin<lb break="no"/>cial autonomy. The people out there think 
     <lb/>
     they are very much handicapped in carrying 
     <lb/>
     on the operations of life for the want of 
     <lb/>
     it. Then, why have the government not 
     <lb/>
   
   
            <pb n="12311" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12311.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12311</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">12312</fw>
       
       
     considered it ? Are they not prepared to 
     <lb/>
     grant provincial autonomy to the Territories, 
     <lb/>
     and if they are not, what is the reason ? 
     <lb/>
     This grant appears to be in the nature of a 
     <lb/>
     provincial subsidy, and I notice it is to be 
     <lb/>
     charged against them in what is called their 
     <lb/>
     debt account. If it is charged against them 
     <lb/>
     in the way of a debt, is it proposed to charge 
     <lb/>
     them any interest on this debt 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. There 
     <lb/>
     will be no interest at present. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Well, it might be re<lb break="no"/>garded as a debt. I think the government 
     <lb/>
     ought to be prepared to give us some rea<lb break="no"/>son why they have been unable to grant 
     <lb/>
     the request of the Territories for provincial 
     <lb/>
     autonomy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. It is 
     <lb/>
     the great boast of our English system of 
     <lb/>
     government that it is a growth of time, 
     <lb/>
     and that consequently it is not well to do 
     <lb/>
     things too rapidly. Our development should 
     <lb/>
     be like that of British freedom, that ' broad<lb break="no"/>ens slowly down from precedent to prece<lb break="no"/>dent.' It is not well to do these things 
     <lb/>
     with a hop, step and a jump. There has 
     <lb/>
     been some development of the principle of 
     <lb/>
     local self-government in the Territories dur<lb break="no"/>ing recent years. Under this present gov<lb break="no"/>ernment amendments have been made to 
     <lb/>
     the legislation respecting the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Territories, which broadened the powers of 
     <lb/>
     the legislature and gave the people a large 
     <lb/>
     measure of responsible government. I 
     <lb/>
     think the time is close at hand when this 
     <lb/>
     government which is always looking after 
     <lb/>
     these things wisely and well, will have to 
     <lb/>
     go further, and still further broaden these 
     <lb/>
     powers and give to that section of the com<lb break="no"/>munity the larger measure of self-govern<lb break="no"/>ment which the other provinces enjoy. The 
     <lb/>
     conditions in the North-west Territories have 
     <lb/>
     not been the same as those in the older 
     <lb/>
     provinces in past years. But through the 
     <lb/>
     growth of population and the increase of 
     <lb/>
     settlements they are rapidly assuming those 
     <lb/>
     conditions, and I am quite sure it will be 
     <lb/>
     the pleasure of both sides of this House at 
     <lb/>
     a very early day to extend the powers which 
     <lb/>
     have already been given. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILMOUR</persName>. I would like to hear 
     <lb/>
     the Finance Minister say by what rules he 
     <lb/>
     considers this allowance a debt. If he con<lb break="no"/>siders it a debt, I would like him to say 
     <lb/>
     on what footing, on what basis, it is a debt. 
     <lb/>
     I do not understand just where you are 
     <lb/>
     going to begin to reckon up an account with 
     <lb/>
     the Territories. Certainly I think you ought 
     <lb/>
     to be liberal with the territories. I would 
     <lb/>
     also like to hear some reason given why 
     <lb/>
     autonomy is not granted to them. But, 
     <lb/>
     aside from that, I would like to hear the 
     <lb/>
     Finance Minister state, and put it in the 
     <lb/>
     ' Hansard,' put it before all concerned, just 
     <lb/>
     on what basis he is going to begin and 
     <lb/>
     reckon an account between the territories 
     <lb/>
     and the Dominion. It is well that that 
     <lb/>


            <cb/>
         
         
     should be understood now, so that there will 
     <lb/>
     be no difficulty about it in the future when 
     <lb/>
     we come to settle the account. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. If we 
     <lb/>
     were to-day carrying legislation for confer<lb break="no"/>ring full powers of provincial autonomy on 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories, undoubtedly there 
     <lb/>
     would be a sum placed to their credit in 
     <lb/>
     what is called the ' debt account,' just as 
     <lb/>
     is to be found with respect to most of the 
     <lb/>
     other provinces. Instead of waiting for 
     <lb/>
     the moment to introduce legislation creating 
     <lb/>
     provincial autonomy, if we place a portion 
     <lb/>
     of that money to their credit at once, and 
     <lb/>
     charge them no interest upon it, I do not 
     <lb/>
     think we can be held to be imposing a seri<lb break="no"/>ous burden upon them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILMOUR</persName>. I am only asking upon 
     <lb/>
     what basis this is to be considered. If 
     <lb/>
     you pay them all that is due up to this date, 
     <lb/>
     you are not giving them anything now ex<lb break="no"/>cept the interest on this money. So long as 
     <lb/>
     you retain those Territories as wards of the 
     <lb/>
     government, so long will they remain in 
     <lb/>
     your debt. I would like the minister to say 
     <lb/>
     just on what basis he is going to reckon 
     <lb/>
     this as a debt. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. A debt 
     <lb/>
     account does not necesasrily mean that the 
     <lb/>
     balance is against the North-west Territo<lb break="no"/>ries. In this case the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories are to have the debt charged against 
     <lb/>
     them, but they are to pay no interest upon 
     <lb/>
     it, and therefore it becomes no burden 
     <lb/>
     upon them. Just what the precise basis 
     <lb/>
     of the financial arrangement with the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories shall be when we come to establish 
     <lb/>
     a province or provinces is not a matter upon 
     <lb/>
     which it would be wise to commit ourselves 
     <lb/>
     to-day, but we do realize that, having regard 
     <lb/>
     to the fact that they have no land of their 
     <lb/>
     own and that there are special conditions 
     <lb/>
     with regard to the North-west Territories, 
     <lb/>
     when we come to adjust accounts with them 
     <lb/>
     we will have to place to their credit a cer<lb break="no"/>tain amount of money in the debt account. 
     <lb/>
     It may not be a debt in the sense that they 
     <lb/>
     will have to pay it. The probability is 
     <lb/>
     that we will have to pay them interest upon 
     <lb/>
     it. My hon. friend is mistaken when he 
     <lb/>
     says that this is all we are doing for the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories, because we largely 
     <lb/>
     increase their general grant. We are go<lb break="no"/>ing to give them a million dollars, as com<lb break="no"/>pared with a little over a quarter of a mil<lb break="no"/>lion seven years ago. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILMOUR</persName>. I did not say that you 
     <lb/>
     were giving them nothing. I understood 
     <lb/>
     quite well what the hon. Minister of Finance 
     <lb/>
     said, but in view of the fact that you are 
     <lb/>
     establishing what I would consider a debt, 
     <lb/>
     I wished you to make it plain whether or 
     <lb/>
     not you would deduct this when you gave 
     <lb/>
     them provincial autonomy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. I do not 
     <lb/>
    think it would be wise that we should to<lb break="no"/>day undertake to settle the precise basis of 
     <lb/>
       
       
            <pb n="12313" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12313.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12313</fw> <fw type="dateline">SEPTEMBER 24, 1903</fw> <fw type="num">12314</fw>
       
       
     the financial relations that should be estab<lb break="no"/>lished with the provincial government if it 
     <lb/>
     should be established next year, as I hope 
     <lb/>
     it will. We had better wait until that time 
     <lb/>
     and hold ourselves to negotiate and de<lb break="no"/>termine what the basis shall be. As to the 
     <lb/>
     provinces which have money in what is 
     <lb/>
     called the debt account, instead of paying 
     <lb/>
     interest to the Dominion, the Dominion has 
     <lb/>
     to pay interest to them and it may be so 
     <lb/>
     when we come to adjust this account be<lb break="no"/>tween the new province or provinces and 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion. What we do is to give the 
     <lb/>
     local government of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories now one of the privileges which they 
     <lb/>
     would no doubt have if they had provincial 
     <lb/>
     autonomy, and that is the right to have in 
     <lb/>
     the capital account a sum upon which they 
     <lb/>
     may draw for important public works. If 
     <lb/>
     they do not wish to use it, of course we can<lb break="no"/>not complain, but our theory is that if they 
     <lb/>
     undertake any important public structure 
     <lb/>
     which is a matter of permanent improve<lb break="no"/>ment they may wish to charge it against 
     <lb/>
     capital account. If we should give provin<lb break="no"/>cial autonomy to the North-west Territories 
     <lb/>
     we would have to place further sums at 
     <lb/>
     their credit in some way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Is it proposed that when 
     <lb/>
     you finally make a settlement with them 
     <lb/>
     upon the lines of provincial autonomy their 
     <lb/>
     income shall be reduced to the extent of this 
     <lb/>
     loan which we are giving them now ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. That 
     <lb/>
     will have to be a matter of adjustment. 
     <lb/>
     Everything will depend upon the amount 
     <lb/>
     that may be assigned to them. There are 
     <lb/>
     many questions which will have to be con<lb break="no"/>sidered in the adjustment of the finances of 
     <lb/>
     the territories. Their position is peculiar. 
     <lb/>
     They do not stand in the same position as 
     <lb/>
     the other provinces of the Dominion which 
     <lb/>
     have lands, mines, forests and other sources 
     <lb/>
     of revenue. We might have to take all that 
     <lb/>
     into consideration and I do not think it 
     <lb/>
     would be wise to undertake to-day to lay 
     <lb/>
     down the precise basis of the financial ar<lb break="no"/>rangements which we may have to make 
     <lb/>
     even so early as next year. We place this 
     <lb/>
     sum at their disposal and if they need it 
     <lb/>
     they can use it. If they do not need it we 
     <lb/>
     do not want to force it upon them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Hon. Mr. HAGGART</persName>. What is the total 
     <lb/>
     amount you gave them last year ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. Last year, 
     <lb/>
     including the sum voted in the supplemen<lb break="no"/>tary estimates, we gave them $707,974. 
     <lb/>
     Then, in addition there was the sum of 379,<lb break="no"/>000 for special purposes, but I am dealing 
     <lb/>
     with the general grant. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Hon. Mr. HAGGART</persName>. The hon. Minister 
     <lb/>
     of Finance states that he is going to give 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories a grant of $1,<lb break="no"/>200,000 this year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. The 
     <lb/>
     grant is a. little over $1,000,000. This $250,<lb break="no"/>
    
    
            <cb/>
     
     
     000 is an additional provision, but it stands 
     <lb/>
     in a different relation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Hon. Mr. HAGGART</persName>. I understand from 
     <lb/>
     the hon. minister that independently of the 
     <lb/>
     $250,000 the grant which would be given 
     <lb/>
     to the North-west Territories would be a 
     <lb/>
     little over $1,400,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. No, a little 
     <lb/>
     over $1,000,000—actually $1,046,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Hon. Mr. HAGGART</persName>. That is in excess 
     <lb/>
     of the grant last year nearly $200,000. That 
     <lb/>
     includes the bridges over the Pelly river 
     <lb/>
     and the Macleod river costing $89,000. It 
     <lb/>
     occurs to me that it is a very pertinent ques<lb break="no"/>tion to ask what possible credit can the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories have to the debt ac<lb break="no"/>count. They can have none whatever. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. Minister of Finance states that this 
     <lb/>
     $250,000 is to be charged against them pend<lb break="no"/>ing a settlement when they are given auton<lb break="no"/>omy. I do not see any possible credit that 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories can have to the 
     <lb/>
     debt account. The only possible way in 
     <lb/>
     which this $250,000 could be charged would 
     <lb/>
     be upon the per capita allowance of the 
     <lb/>
     province to be deducted at some future 
     <lb/>
     time. The hon. gentleman states that he 
     <lb/>
     does not intend to charge any interest upon 
     <lb/>
     the amount. Does he propose, in giving this 
     <lb/>
     $250,000 to the North-west Territories, to 
     <lb/>
     give them the absolute control of the ex<lb break="no"/>penditure of it for any purpose which they 
     <lb/>
     may think proper, or must it be spent in a 
     <lb/>
     certain direction? If the government intend 
     <lb/>
     to direct how it shall be expended we would 
     <lb/>
     like to know how it is proposed to expend 
     <lb/>
     it. I protest that there is no possible credit 
     <lb/>
     to the debt account which the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Territories can have against the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     government upon entering confederation. 
     <lb/>
     They have no expenditure for Dominion 
     <lb/>
     purposes, they have no expenditure upon 
     <lb/>
     railways that I know of in that section of 
     <lb/>
     the country or anything which would be a 
     <lb/>
     credit to the debt account. The only an<lb break="no"/>swer to the question of my hon. friend from 
     <lb/>
     East Middlesex (Mr. Gilmour) is that this 
     <lb/>
     $250,000 must be a charge against the per 
     <lb/>
     capita allowance of the territories when 
     <lb/>
     they get autonomy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. My hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend has undertaken to settle a question 
     <lb/>
     which I was anxious not to settle at the pre<lb break="no"/>sent time and that is as to what shall be 
     <lb/>
     the financial adjustment between the Do<lb break="no"/>minion and these new provinces. My only 
     <lb/>
     desire is not to commit myself as respects 
     <lb/>
     a single dollar of this amount which we are 
     <lb/>
     voting. I want to be absolutely free when 
     <lb/>
     this question comes up, and I think we all 
     <lb/>
     desire that none of us shall be bound by 
     <lb/>
     anything we may do in the way of granting 
     <lb/>
     temporary aid. In answer to the other ques<lb break="no"/>tion of the hon. gentleman as to whether the 
     <lb/>
     local government is to have control over the 
     <lb/>
     expenditure of this money the answer, is 
     <lb/>
     practically, yes. But technically there is a 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="12315" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12315.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12315</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">12316</fw>
        
        
     qualification to that. We use here the same 
     <lb/>
     words as are found in the existing laws in 
     <lb/>
     respect to the debt accounts of the other 
     <lb/>
     provinces. Every one of the provinces of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion which has a sum to its credit 
     <lb/>
     in the debt account, is entitled under 
     <lb/>
     the act to withdraw that money for 'local 
     <lb/>
     improvements.' Those are the words. The 
     <lb/>
     Governor in Council has, in his discretion, 
     <lb/>
     the right to advance this money. Techni<lb break="no"/>cally he can say that it shall not be ad<lb break="no"/>vanced at all, but my hon. friend as an old 
     <lb/>
     cabinet minister knows that practically that 
     <lb/>
     is not so. What I apprehend will happen 
     <lb/>
     will be that the local government will make 
     <lb/>
     application and will say that it desires to 
     <lb/>
     use this money for some useful public work. 
     <lb/>
     Its application will be approved and the ex<lb break="no"/>penditure will be entirely under its control 
     <lb/>
     and not under the control of the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACL2">Mr. MACLEAN</persName>. The hon. Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Finance spoke of the erection of new pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. Is the hon. minister, or any mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the government, prepared to say 
     <lb/>
     whether all of the correspondence which has 
     <lb/>
     passed between those representing the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories and the members of the government 
     <lb/>
     in connection with the request for the erec<lb break="no"/>tion of a new province or new provinces has 
     <lb/>
     been published ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. I under<lb break="no"/>stand that my right hon. friend the Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister submitted it all to the House a 
     <lb/>
     few weeks ago. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Hon. Mr. HAGGART</persName>. I must protest 
     <lb/>
     against the expenditure of $250,000 under 
     <lb/>
     the direction of the Dominion government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. My hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend misunderstood me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Hon. Mr. HAGGART</persName>. The hon. Minister 
     <lb/>
     of Finance states that a request is made for 
     <lb/>
     the money for local improvements by the 
     <lb/>
     local government and that the disposition of 
     <lb/>
     it depends upon the Governor in Council. 
     <lb/>
     Then, the request must be in consonance with 
     <lb/>
     the desires of the Dominion government as 
     <lb/>
     to the expenditure. I much prefer to see 
     <lb/>
     the amount of $250,000 absolutely given to 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories to be expended 
     <lb/>
     on local improvements in any manner in 
     <lb/>
     which they see fit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. We are 
     <lb/>
     using the precise words of the present law 
     <lb/>
     in respect to all the provinces of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. If the North-west Territories 
     <lb/>
     had been created into a province this year 
     <lb/>
     under a provincial government the same as 
     <lb/>
     the government of Ontario or the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of any of the other provinces, these 
     <lb/>
     are the precise words which would be used 
     <lb/>
     in regard to the advance of public money 
     <lb/>
     out of capital account. The application has 
     <lb/>
     to come from the local government, and the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion government has the right to re<lb break="no"/>
        
        
            <cb/>
    
    
     fuse, I suppose, but practically that is not 
     <lb/>
     the way it operates. The local government 
     <lb/>
     is the judge and we are bound to believe they 
     <lb/>
     expend these moneys for useful purposes, 
     <lb/>
     and unless there is some strong reason, 
     <lb/>
     which I cannot imagine, to refuse the ap<lb break="no"/>plication, it would go as a matter of course. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. The understanding in re<lb break="no"/>gard to this debt account which prevails 
     <lb/>
     in the North-west Territories, is perhaps 
     <lb/>
     not the same as has been voiced so far in 
     <lb/>
     this discussion. The idea that has come to 
     <lb/>
     me and others in the west is : that at confed<lb break="no"/>eration the original provinces were heavily 
     <lb/>
     involved in debt, and when other provinces 
     <lb/>
     were added to confederation which were not 
     <lb/>
     so involved in debt, they received a credit 
     <lb/>
     from what was called the debt account, to 
     <lb/>
     put them on an equal footing with the 
     <lb/>
     original provinces in respect to the in<lb break="no"/>debtedness of these original provinces. It 
     <lb/>
     it under that head that the territories would 
     <lb/>
     claim a credit at the hands of the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     when the time for provincial organization 
     <lb/>
     comes. Believing that the territories would 
     <lb/>
     be entitled to such a credit under the 
     <lb/>
     fundamental arrangements of confederation, 
     <lb/>
     they consider that they have a right to an 
     <lb/>
     advance on that account, if required and as 
     <lb/>
     required. That debt account is based on 
     <lb/>
     the population of the provinces at the time 
     <lb/>
     each entered confederation, and because of 
     <lb/>
     that there is not that unanimous and ur<lb break="no"/>gent demand for provincial organization 
     <lb/>
     in the territories that some of our friends 
     <lb/>
     seem to think. The larger the population 
     <lb/>
     of the territory at the time it enters confed<lb break="no"/>eration as a province, the larger the debt 
     <lb/>
     account in favour of the territories will be, 
     <lb/>
     and therefore the greater the advantage to 
     <lb/>
     the territories, the longer it waits and the 
     <lb/>
     larger its population is. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Are we to infer that the 
     <lb/>
     territories do not want provincial autonomy, 
     <lb/>
     but that they prefer to remain without it 
     <lb/>
     for years until they get a larger population? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. I do not wish the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member to draw any inference. Speaking 
     <lb/>
     for myself, and for those who think with 
     <lb/>
     me—who I believe constitute the over<lb break="no"/>whelming majority of the people in the 
     <lb/>
     territories—we believe that it is better to 
     <lb/>
     wait until we can be assured of a more 
     <lb/>
     satisfactory arrangement based upon in<lb break="no"/>creased population, than we possibly could 
     <lb/>
     expect to get to-day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Then, the argument of 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Haultain in favour of provincial au<lb break="no"/>tonomy would seem to be unfounded. I 
     <lb/>
     judged from the correspondence that the 
     <lb/>
     territories were strongly in favour of auto<lb break="no"/>nomy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">The PRIME MINISTER</persName>. Divided in op<lb break="no"/>inion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. I refer to the resolution 
     <lb/>
     passed by the legislature, and the corres<lb break="no"/>
  
  
            <pb n="12317" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12317.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12317</fw> <fw type="dateline">SEPTEMBER 24, 1903</fw> <fw type="num">12318</fw>
        
        
     pondence submitted to strengthen the ar<lb break="no"/>gument of Premier Haultain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. The conditions surround<lb break="no"/>ing Premier Haultain's proposition might 
     <lb/>
     perhaps be explained a little more fully. 
     <lb/>
     Premier Haultain proposes provincial auton<lb break="no"/>omy, on the basis of the grants that would 
     <lb/>
     be due to the territories, even on their pres<lb break="no"/>ent population under provincial autonomy, 
     <lb/>
     as compared with grants received a few 
     <lb/>
     years age, under the present system. For 
     <lb/>
     a matter of seven or eight years the sub<lb break="no"/>sidy grant to the territories was practically 
     <lb/>
     at a standstill, and at the same time popu<lb break="no"/>lation was increasing, and our responsibili<lb break="no"/>ties were increasing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. I think that the arrange<lb break="no"/>ment made with the territories was, that as 
     <lb/>
     population increased the grant would in<lb break="no"/>crease. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. There was no arrangement 
     <lb/>
     with the territories. The grant is a matter 
     <lb/>
     of ordinary vote by parliament from year 
     <lb/>
     to year. Naturally it the grant is not lib<lb break="no"/>eral and if it is not advanced in amount 
     <lb/>
     according to increased population and re<lb break="no"/>sponsibilities the government of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories falls back at once upon the 
     <lb/>
     rights which it would have were it given. 
     <lb/>
     provincial organization. That was the con<lb break="no"/>dition which gave rise to the present de<lb break="no"/>mand (if you may say so) for provincial 
     <lb/>
     autonomy. Mr. Haultain wanted to get the 
     <lb/>
     benefit of the debt account which he would 
     <lb/>
     have on the then existing population and 
     <lb/>
     to get such other grants as properly belong 
     <lb/>
     to a province, believing that he would then 
     <lb/>
     be financially better off than he was under 
     <lb/>
     the system of granting subsidies, which 
     <lb/>
     practically stood still for a number of years. 
     <lb/>
     But since that time, the subsidies have very 
     <lb/>
     largely increased, and particularly so dur<lb break="no"/>ing the present year. The increase of sub<lb break="no"/>sidy changes the position very considerably 
     <lb/>
     in regard to the demand for provincial or<lb break="no"/>ganization. In my estimation at any rate— 
     <lb/>
     in a country such as the territories, where 
     <lb/>
     the financial needs are very great—the fin<lb break="no"/>ancial question is the chief question. The 
     <lb/>
     obtaining of money with which to carry out 
     <lb/>
     public improvements and to keep educa<lb break="no"/>tional facilities up to a modern standard, 
     <lb/>
     is the great object which the government 
     <lb/>
     desires to attain, and if it be attained, then 
     <lb/>
     the chief object of local government is at<lb break="no"/>tained. And whether it be under the' name 
     <lb/>
     of territorial organization or provincial or<lb break="no"/>ganization, is of secondary moment. It. is 
     <lb/>
     fair matter for consideration, whether we 
     <lb/>
     should press an immediate and urgent de<lb break="no"/>mand upon this parliament, for provincial 
     <lb/>
     organization, or, with the prospect of still 
     <lb/>
     larger and very rapid increase of population, 
     <lb/>
     whether we should wait until that increase 
     <lb/>
     of population should entitle us to still bet<lb break="no"/>ter terms. The area under the jurisdiction 
     <lb/>
     of the territorial government covers by far 
     <lb/>
      
      
            <cb/>
         
         
     the greater part of the agricultural area of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion. If that great agricultural area 
     <lb/>
     —which in all human probability before very 
     <lb/>
     long will be quite fully populated—is or<lb break="no"/>ganized to-day on a provincial basis, with 
     <lb/>
     the debt account according to the present 
     <lb/>
     population, and receiving consideration gen<lb break="no"/>erally according to the requirements of the 
     <lb/>
     present population ; it stands to reason that 
     <lb/>
     inside of a very few years, the concessions 
     <lb/>
     that have been made will be found far fur<lb break="no"/>ther behind the actual requirements than 
     <lb/>
     they have ever been since we organized in 
     <lb/>
     the territories a local government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACL2">Mr. MACLEAN</persName>. Then the ' better terms ' 
     <lb/>
     principle begins to act. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. That is what it amounts 
     <lb/>
     to ; and you will find that in Mr: Haultain's 
     <lb/>
     correspondence he suggests that there shall 
     <lb/>
     be provincial organization at the present 
     <lb/>
     time, on the basis of present population and 
     <lb/>
     a readjustment every five years afterwards 
     <lb/>
     according to population. That is not in ac<lb break="no"/>cord with the principles of confederation, 
     <lb/>
     but if parliament will concede it, why, I 
     <lb/>
     will be willing to go in for provincial or<lb break="no"/>ganization at once. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Does the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     not think that, since the government are not 
     <lb/>
     prepared to give this by way of subsidy 
     <lb/>
     upon any determined basis, it would be 
     <lb/>
     better to take into consideration the excep<lb break="no"/>tional needs of the territories from year 
     <lb/>
     to year and grant a larger subsidy until 
     <lb/>
     such time as we can give them all full 
     <lb/>
     provincial autonomy or establish some ac<lb break="no"/>count with them on a proper basis ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. That. is exactly my posi<lb break="no"/>tion. I think that as long as this parliament 
     <lb/>
     will deal liberally with the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories while they are in their present for<lb break="no"/>mative condition and while their popula<lb break="no"/>tion is increasing as rapidly as it is, and 
     <lb/>
     will adequately recognize that increase of 
     <lb/>
     population, it will be better for the terri<lb break="no"/>tories, financially, to remain under the pre<lb break="no"/>sent condition rather than to be bound by 
     <lb/>
     any definite financial arrangement that will 
     <lb/>
     in future years be entirely inadequate and 
     <lb/>
     will cause the territories to come here again 
     <lb/>
     and again for better terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. I mean that instead of 
     <lb/>
     giving this money by way of loan, we should 
     <lb/>
     take into account the very exceptional needs 
     <lb/>
     of the territories and give a subsidy to suit 
     <lb/>
     their requirements from time to time, not to 
     <lb/>
     give it in the shape of a loan, which would 
     <lb/>
     be regarded as a debt. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. As a member for the ter<lb break="no"/>ritories I have nothing to urge in opposition 
     <lb/>
     to the plan suggested. If parliament will 
     <lb/>
     vote this year the $1,046,000 suggested by 
     <lb/>
     the Minister of Finance and also the sum of 
     <lb/>
     $250,000 for current expenses, I shall cer<lb break="no"/>tainly vote for it and be very glad to sup<lb break="no"/>
         
         
         
            <pb n="12319" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12319.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12319</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">12320</fw>
       
       
       port it, but I may say that such generosity 
     <lb/>
     on the part of parliament is a surprise to 
     <lb/>
     me, and I think that Premier Haultain and 
     <lb/>
     his government, if they are at all inclined 
     <lb/>
     to be fleshy, would be very likely to be 
     <lb/>
     stricken with apoplexy at such an exhibi<lb break="no"/>tion of generosity as compared with the ac<lb break="no"/>tion of parliament on previous occasions. 
     <lb/>
     However, if hon. gentlemen will move that 
     <lb/>
     I will be very glad to support them and 
     <lb/>
     if they would prefer to make it $500,000 in<lb break="no"/>stead of $250,000, I will support that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILMOUR</persName>. Does the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Oliver) consider that up to the present 
     <lb/>
     time the territories have received all they 
     <lb/>
     were entitled to in grants and that this 
     <lb/>
     $250,000 should now he considered as an 
     <lb/>
     advance to them ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. No, I do not think they 
     <lb/>
     have been getting as much as they are en<lb break="no"/>titled to, but I certainly think the grant 
     <lb/>
     this year is fairly liberal. The House will 
     <lb/>
     understand that as one of the members re<lb break="no"/>presenting the North-west Territories, who 
     <lb/>
     have been continually accused since we have 
     <lb/>
     been in the House of demanding too much 
     <lb/>
     from parliament, I have felt some diffidence 
     <lb/>
     in pressing demands for any serious ad<lb break="no"/>vance of money. I certainly felt that a grant 
     <lb/>
     of $1,000,000 in the present year was a very 
     <lb/>
     fair allowance and I was glad to accept 
     <lb/>
     it and also to accept the advance of $250,<lb break="no"/>000 for permanent improvements. But if 
     <lb/>
     the opinion of the House has changed, if it 
     <lb/>
     has become generous in these matters, 1 
     <lb/>
     can assure the House that the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Territories government can expend a larger 
     <lb/>
     amount, and if hon. members are desirous 
     <lb/>
     of voting this $250,000 as an addition to 
     <lb/>
     the yearly grant I will be glad to support 
     <lb/>
     them in that and, as I said, if they will 
     <lb/>
     make it $500,000 I will still support them 
     <lb/>
     and I can assure them that the money will 
     <lb/>
     be well expended.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CLAN1">Mr. CLANCY</persName>. I fully concur in all that 
     <lb/>
     has been said of the necessity of increasing 
     <lb/>
     the grant to the North-west Territories. It 
     <lb/>
     I had any fault to find it would be that the 
     <lb/>
     government have not gone quite so far in 
     <lb/>
     this matter as the present needs of that 
     <lb/>
     growing country require. I am not much 
     <lb/>
     impressed with the reasons given by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Alberta (Mr. Oliver) for 
     <lb/>
     delaying the granting of provincial au<lb break="no"/>tonomy. Speaking for myself I do not be<lb break="no"/>lieve that any party in power can afford to 
     <lb/>
     drive hard and fast bargains with the 
     <lb/>
     newer provinces to be made in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories. A cheese-paring policy 
     <lb/>
     would be the most mistaken policy that any 
     <lb/>
     government could undertake ; it would sim<lb break="no"/>ply mean a recurrence of what we have 
     <lb/>
     had in the past under less stringent con<lb break="no"/>ditions in regard to the provinces that to<lb break="no"/>day constitute confederation, a constant 
     <lb/>
     pressure for additional subsidies. When 
     <lb/>
     provincial autonomy is granted to the ter<lb break="no"/>
      
      
            <cb/>
         
         
     ritories we must expect to make ample pro<lb break="no"/>vision for the support of a government 
     <lb/>
     in these territories. This may be a proper 
     <lb/>
     time to ask the Minister of Finance as to 
     <lb/>
     the correctness of the report that is cur<lb break="no"/>rent in the leading organs supporting the 
     <lb/>
     government, that for the purpose of aiding 
     <lb/>
     in the construction of the Grand Trunk 
     <lb/>
     Pacific Railway or for other purposes of a 
     <lb/>
     similar kind, it is the purpose of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment to set aside a quantity of land in the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories to be sold for these 
     <lb/>
     purposes ? I do not think that this parlia<lb break="no"/>ment or the people of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories or of the rest of this Dominion would 
     <lb/>
     view with greater favour the taking of any 
     <lb/>
     portion of land in the North-west Territor<lb break="no"/>ies for that purpose than the taking of land 
     <lb/>
     in the older provinces, if it were possible, 
     <lb/>
     and the setting aside of such land for the 
     <lb/>
     construction of railways or for other pur<lb break="no"/>poses. If we are to aid railways we must 
     <lb/>
     aid them from other sources of revenue 
     <lb/>
     and if the people of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories should ask for provincial autonomy 
     <lb/>
     to-morrow I do not believe that we should 
     <lb/>
     drive such a hard bargain as the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Alberta has suggested : we should 
     <lb/>
     deal with them on very liberal and gener<lb break="no"/>ous terms and must remember that what 
     <lb/>
     might be a generous appropriation to-day 
     <lb/>
     might be entirely inadequate in a few 
     <lb/>
     years owing to the great growth that is tak<lb break="no"/>ing place in that country. I would like to 
     <lb/>
    ask the Minister of Finance if there is 
     <lb/>any foundation for that report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. No<lb/>legislation of that kind is contemplated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CLAN1">Mr. CLANCY</persName>. I am aware that there is 
     <lb/>
     no legislation of that character ; I ask the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman if that is the policy of the 
     <lb/>
     government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. The 
     <lb/>
     policy of the government for the present 
     <lb/>
     is as I have stated it ; I think the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman will have to let the future take 
     <lb/>
     care of itself. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CLAN1">Mr. CLANCY</persName>. It is a deplorable fact 
     <lb/>
     that we have to do that both as to infor<lb break="no"/>mation and as to everything else. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD3">Mr. BOYD</persName>. I am also pleased with the 
     <lb/>
     increase that has taken place in the appro<lb break="no"/>priation for the North-west Territories, and 
     <lb/>
     I would be much better pleased if the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had intimated that they proposed 
     <lb/>
     giving the people of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories the provincial power which they are 
     <lb/>
     seeking. I am sure that in saying that I 
     <lb/>
     express the opinion of the vast majority of 
     <lb/>
     the people of the North-west Territories. I 
     <lb/>
     am sure that I am expressing the opinion or 
     <lb/>
     the majority of the people of the territories 
     <lb/>
     when I say so. I do not think that it is 
     <lb/>
     pleasant to the people of the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Territories, in fact I know it is humiliating 
     <lb/>
     to them, to have to come here annually as 
     <lb/>
        
        
        
            <pb n="12321" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12321.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12321</fw> <fw type="dateline">SEPTEMBER 24, 1903</fw> <fw type="num">12322</fw>
         
         
     beggars seeking for better terms and find<lb break="no"/>ing themselves in the position in which they          
     <lb/>
    were last year, when their assembly had to 
     <lb/>adjourn for want of funds. They had to 
     <lb/>go back to their homes until they could pro<lb break="no"/>cure money to carry on public business. 
     <lb/>They have been appealing for provincial 
     <lb/>autonomy. Their population has increased, 
     <lb/>as has been pointed out by the Minister of 
     <lb/>Justice, sufficiently to entitle them to ten 
     <lb/>representatives in this House and four sen<lb break="no"/>ators.  A territory of that importance and 
     <lb/>extent should receive that recognition from 
     <lb/>this parliament for which they are asking 
     <lb/>and which they deserve, and that is the 
     <lb/>power to manage their own affairs. The 
     <lb/>difficulty pointed out by the hon. member 
     <lb/>for Alberta regarding population and so on, 
     <lb/>is merely a matter of readjustment, which 
     <lb/>may be made every two, or three, or five 
     <lb/>years, and I cannot see why the govern<lb break="no"/>ment are holding back in that respect. We 
     <lb/>know well enough the reason why they are 
     <lb/>not dealing with this question. It is be<lb break="no"/>cause they fear that ghost in the closet— 
     <lb/>the school question—which they will have to 
     <lb/>deal with whenever they give the terri<lb break="no"/>tories provincial autonomy, but the longer 
     <lb/>they leave it off the worse it will be. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI10">Mr. DAVIS</persName>. Why ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD3">Mr. BOYD</persName>. Because there will be more 
     <lb/>
     people in the territories, and the greater the 
     <lb/>
     number the more difficult will become the 
     <lb/>
     settlement of that question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI10">Mr. DAVIS</persName>. We have separate schools in 
     <lb/>
     the territories now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD3">Mr. BOYD</persName>. What they have and what 
     <lb/>
     they will get according to the arrangements 
     <lb/>
     made in this parliament are entirely dif<lb break="no"/>ferent questions. I have been amongst 
     <lb/>
     these people, I have been at their public 
     <lb/>
     meetings, I have heard their premier give 
     <lb/>
     expression to his views at a very large 
     <lb/>
     gathering, and in that gathering there was 
     <lb/>
     almost a unanimous opinion in favour of 
     <lb/>
     provincial autonomy. What else could we 
     <lb/>
     expect from a body of Canadians and 
     <lb/>
     British people, numbering some 160,000 or 
     <lb/>
     200,000, but that they would want their own 
     <lb/>
     provincial autonomy, the power to make 
     <lb/>
     their own laws and manage their own 
     <lb/>
     affairs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI10">Mr. DAVIS</persName>. How much more power 
     <lb/>
     would they have under provincial autonomy 
     <lb/>
     than they have now ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">The PRIME MINISTER</persName>. There is an old 
     <lb/>
     saying, ' Save me from my friends,' and 
     <lb/>
     the people of the North-west Territories will 
     <lb/>
     have no reason to thank the hon. gentleman, 
     <lb/>
     for if we were to adopt his suggestion they 
     <lb/>
     would be worse off than they are to-day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD3">Mr. BOYD</persName>. I do not think so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">The PRIME MINISTER</persName>. The hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman has said that the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories have a population large enough to 
     <lb/>


            <cb/>
       
       
     entitle them to ten members. He must<lb/>know that such is not the case. He ought<lb/>to know that their population, as shown by 
     <lb/>
     the last census, would not entitle them to 
     <lb/>
     ten members. We are giving them ten 
     <lb/>
     members, not because they are entitled to 
     <lb/>
     that number, but as an act of grace. If 
     <lb/>
     we were to follow my hon. friend's sugges<lb break="no"/>tion, and give them a provincial organiza<lb break="no"/>tion, they would have to come under the 
     <lb/>
     laws that regulate the provinces and be 
     <lb/>
     given a representation according to popula<lb break="no"/>tion, and not by grace, as they are under 
     <lb/>
     this Bill. If the territories want to come in 
     <lb/>
     as a province, my hon. friend would be the 
     <lb/>
     first to say that it would be only fair that 
     <lb/>
     they should have the representation to 
     <lb/>
     which they would be entitled as a province. 
     <lb/>
     But we thought it better to keep them as 
     <lb/>
     territories and give them representation this 
     <lb/>
     year of ten members, because their popula<lb break="no"/>tion is increasing, and will no doubt soon 
     <lb/>
     reach the figures which will entitle them to 
     <lb/>
     that number. My hon. friend has spoken 
     <lb/>
     on the school question, but I doubt whether, 
     <lb/>
     in view of the school taxation, it would be 
     <lb/>
     advisable for the territories to become a 
     <lb/>
     province, because they would then lose the 
     <lb/>
     power they now have of taxing the railway 
     <lb/>
     lands of the Canadian Pacific Railway for 
     <lb/>
     their schools. The question is not so simple 
     <lb/>
     as my hon. friend would make us believe 
     <lb/>
     it is. How many provinces will there be— 
     <lb/>
     one or two ? On that point the people of the 
     <lb/>
     territories are not unanimous. A member 
     <lb/>
     of some prominence in the legislature has 
     <lb/>
     withdrawn his confidence from Mr. Haul<lb break="no"/>tain's government, because it is in favour of 
     <lb/>
     one province, whereas he and others think 
     <lb/>
     there ought to be two provinces. For these 
     <lb/>
     reasons, we had better reflect coolly and 
     <lb/>
     seriously before we make the final jump. 
     <lb/>
     My hon. friend says it is humiliating for 
     <lb/>
     the territories to come here year after year 
     <lb/>
     and ask for better terms. Well, they are 
     <lb/>
     not coming for better terms, but for an al<lb break="no"/>lowance, which parliament has given them. 
     <lb/>
     and which must increase as their population 
     <lb/>
     increases. But when they are organized as 
     <lb/>
     a province, with all the powers of a pro<lb break="no"/>vince, they will have to take all the respon<lb break="no"/>sibilities of a province ; and whether their 
     <lb/>
     population increases or not, their allowance 
     <lb/>
     must remain the same, and we shall have pro<lb break="no"/>bably the spectacle, which we have seen in 
     <lb/>
     other provinces, notably Manitoba, Which 
     <lb/>
     was perhaps organized as a province prema<lb break="no"/>turely—we shall see them year after year 
     <lb/>
     coming for better terms. It would be far 
     <lb/>
     better not to move too hastily. What are 
     <lb/>
     the powers which the territories have not 
     <lb/>
     today which they would have as a pro<lb break="no"/>vince ? If I mistake not, speaking at first 
     <lb/>
     blush, the legislature of the territories has 
     <lb/>
     all the powers enjoyed by a province, with 
     <lb/>
     the exception of the power to borrow money. 
     <lb/>
     My hon. friend has therefore no reason to 
     <lb/>
     get warm and say that they are kept as 
     <lb/>
     slaves, and are not free British subjects. 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <pb n="12323" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12323.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12323</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">12324</fw>
       
       
     They are as free as any one of us, but have 
     <lb/>
     not the power to borrow money, and per<lb break="no"/>haps it is as well to keep that power in 
     <lb/>
     abeyance in a young country like that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACL2">Mr. MACLEAN</persName>. Here is another Libe<lb break="no"/>ral doctrine abandoned, the Liberal doctrine 
     <lb/>
     of self-government. Now the doctrine 
     <lb/>
     preached is that of arbitrary government, 
     <lb/>
     the greater government ruling the smaller 
     <lb/>
     one. So, one by one, all these pledges and 
     <lb/>
     professions of the past are going by the 
     <lb/>
     board. There is a great difference between 
     <lb/>
     provincial autonomy and the kind of gov<lb break="no"/>ernment they have in the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories to-day. The people of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories feel that difference. The 
     <lb/>
     difference is that the provinces have some<lb break="no"/>thing by right, but the people of the North<lb break="no"/>west must come here and take what is given 
     <lb/>
     to them by what the Prime Minister calls 
     <lb/>
     an act of grace or benevolence. The peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the North-west do not wish to be in 
     <lb/>
     the position of suppliants seeking favours; 
     <lb/>
     they wish their rights, and they wish, above 
     <lb/>
     all, the sacred right, which Liberals say 
     <lb/>
     they fought for so many years in this coun<lb break="no"/>try, the right of self-government. I appre<lb break="no"/>ciate this demand of theirs; I know that the 
     <lb/>
     people of the North-west do wish to be 
     <lb/>
     erected into a province and have an endow<lb break="no"/>ment and have the status and the rights of 
     <lb/>
     the people of the rest of Canada. Here 
     <lb/>
     we have an autocratic Czar telling them: 
     <lb/>
     Oh, leave yourselves in our hands; forget 
     <lb/>
     all about self-government and we will look 
     <lb/>
     after you. That is not Liberal doctrine, 
     <lb/>
     that is not what the Canadian people ex<lb break="no"/>pect. There are reasons why the provinces 
     <lb/>
     have not been created. But an election is 
     <lb/>
     near at hand, and these hon. gentlemen feel 
     <lb/>
     constrained to make an apology for their 
     <lb/>
     neglect to erect these territories into pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROCH1">Mr. ROCHE</persName> (Marquette). From the re<lb break="no"/>marks which have fallen from the lips of 
     <lb/>
     the Prime Minister (Rt. Hon. Sir Wilfrid 
     <lb/>
     Laurier), I think the North-west Territories 
     <lb/>
     need not expect self-government in the near 
     <lb/>
     future. The remarks of the Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Finance (Hon. Mr. Fielding) left a different 
     <lb/>
     impression upon the House. That hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman, in the vernacular of the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for East York (Mr. Maclean) at<lb break="no"/>tempted to jolly the people along, holding 
     <lb/>
     out the hope of the early establishment of 
     <lb/>
     provincial autonomy. But the Prime Minis<lb break="no"/>ter adduced arguments that were strong, 
     <lb/>
     no doubt, from his point of view, that the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories should not be grant<lb break="no"/>ed local self—government for many years 
     <lb/>
     to come. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">The PRIME MINISTER</persName>. Hear, hear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROCH1">Mr. ROCHE</persName> (Marquette). The Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister says, 'hear, hear,' so I am not mis<lb break="no"/>stating the case from his viewpoint. One 
     <lb/>
    reason the hon. gentleman states why they 
     <lb/>should not be given local autonomy is the 
     <lb/>


            <cb/>
        
        
     fact that he could not satisfy the people, 
     <lb/>
     because they are divided among themselves 
     <lb/>
     as to the number of provinces into which 
     <lb/>
     the territories should be divided, one or 
     <lb/>
     more. That need not stand long in the 
     <lb/>
     way; the government can soon settle it. 
     <lb/>
     Let them give the people a plebiscite, as 
     <lb/>
     they did on the liquor question, though I 
     <lb/>
     hope not with a similar result. Let the 
     <lb/>
     people decide this matter. This will be an 
     <lb/>
     easy way of settling the question whether 
     <lb/>
     there shall be one province only or more 
     <lb/>
     than one. The Prime Minister says also 
     <lb/>
     that they have almost every liberty that 
     <lb/>
     they would have if provincial autonomy 
     <lb/>
     were conferred upon them, all except the 
     <lb/>
     one of borrowing money, and that it was a 
     <lb/>
     good thing not to trust them lest they 
     <lb/>
     should rush into debt to their own injury. 
     <lb/>
     I think the people of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories are as well able to govern themselves 
     <lb/>
     as the people of the Dominion are. They 
     <lb/>
     are among the most intelligent people of 
     <lb/>
     Canada. They are largely from eastern 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and eulogies have been heaped upon 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Haultain's government by people in this 
     <lb/>
     House and elsewhere for the way it is man<lb break="no"/>aging the affairs of the territories. So, 
     <lb/>
     no valid reason can be given on that account. 
     <lb/>
     It was a rather indefinite reply given by 
     <lb/>
     the Finance Minister to the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Bothwell (Mr. Clancy) as to whether 
     <lb/>
     they were going to set aside the land or 
     <lb/>
     sell the lands and set aside the funds, to 
     <lb/>
     pay for the Grand Trunk Pacific. If I 
     <lb/>
     mistake not, the Minister of the Interior 
     <lb/>
     (Hon. Mr. Sifton) stated that this latter was 
     <lb/>
     the intention. We have heard a great 
     <lb/>
     deal from the government to the effect 
     <lb/>
     that we are giving no land grant to this 
     <lb/>
     railway. But what is the difference if 
     <lb/>
     we are going to sell the lands and hand 
     <lb/>
     the proceeds over for the construction 
     <lb/>
     of the railway line ? Fifty millions 
     <lb/>
     of acres of land the Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior estimated would be released by his 
     <lb/>
     arrangement with the Canadian Pacific Rail<lb break="no"/>way. Putting it at $3 per acre. which is 
     <lb/>
     a very low estimate, that would mean $150,<lb break="no"/>000,000 to go into a sinking fund to con<lb break="no"/>struct a line of railway that the Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister says is only going to cost as $13,<lb break="no"/>000,000. So, I think the Finance Minister 
     <lb/>
     was not so candid as he might have been 
     <lb/>
     in answering the hon. member for Bothwell. 
     <lb/>
     As a western man, I am in favour of grant<lb break="no"/>ing the territories powers of local self-gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. The influx of population into 
     <lb/>
     that country is going to throw heavy liabi<lb break="no"/>lities upon the territorial exchequer to keep 
     <lb/>
     pace with the requirements of the country. 
     <lb/>
     The education of these new-comers must 
     <lb/>
     be looked after. And the territories have 
     <lb/>
     no local revenue except the small tax upon 
     <lb/>
     the land for school purposes. Thus. they 
     <lb/>
     are dependent entirely upon votes of this 
     <lb/>
     parliament to keep up improvements. I 
     <lb/>
     believe that in some years what is spent for 
     <lb/>
     public works and education has more than 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <pb n="12325" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12325.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12325</fw> <fw type="dateline">SEPTEMBER 24, 1903</fw> <fw type="num">12326</fw>
      
      
     eaten up the grants of this parliament. 
     <lb/>
     Like the hon. member for South Lanark 
     <lb/>
     (Hon. Mr. Haggart) I would feel like acting 
     <lb/>
     a little more liberally with the territories, 
     <lb/>
     and would hand over this $250,000 to the 
     <lb/>
     territorial government rather than place 
     <lb/>
     them in debt so that when autonomy is 
     <lb/>
     given them they will find the Dominion of 
     <lb/>
     Canada is already their creditor to a large 
     <lb/>
     extent. I approve the increased grant. I 
     <lb/>
     know that it is necessary in order to keep 
     <lb/>
     up roads, bridges, schools, and other require<lb break="no"/>ments of a growing country, and I am much 
     <lb/>
     more in favour of granting this $250,000 out<lb break="no"/>right than by letting it stand as a debt 
     <lb/>
     against the territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAI1">Mr. BLAIN</persName>. On the question of whe<lb break="no"/>ther the people of the North-west Territories 
     <lb/>
     are in favour of provincial autonomy or not, 
     <lb/>
     I wish to quote a few words of the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for West Assiniboia (Mr. Scott) 
     <lb/>
     last year : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     But I believe I express the opinion of a very 
     <lb/>
     large majority of the people when I say that 
     <lb/>
     the conditions have now reached a stage when 
     <lb/>
     it would be advantageous to those people as 
     <lb/>
     well as to the entire Dominion, to have this 
     <lb/>
     question settled without further loss of time. 
     <lb/>
     Some hon. members may be aware of the fact 
     <lb/>
     that within the past two weeks the question 
     <lb/>
     has been debated in the local legislature at 
     <lb/>
     Regina, and by a vote of 23 to 7, I think, in a 
     <lb/>
     House of 31 members, it was decided that it was 
     <lb/>
     a matter of regret that this question had not 
     <lb/>
     been taken up and an endeavour made to settle 
     <lb/>
     it this present year. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     One other quotation from the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman : 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     I said that I believed the time had come when 
     <lb/>
     the question of giving the territories provincial 
     <lb/>
     rights should be taken up and dealt with. As 
     <lb/>
     far as I am concerned, I believe that the people 
     <lb/>
     in the territories in genenal are ready to accept 
     <lb/>
     provincial autonomy. Of course they are not 
     <lb/>
     unanimous, and I think that it the powers at 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa wait until they are, they will wait 
     <lb/>
     until Kingdom come, because neither on that 
     <lb/>
     or any other question will the people of so 
     <lb/>
     large an area ever entertain one opinion. It 
     <lb/>
     is a fact, as has been stated by my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     opposite, that the population of the territories 
     <lb/>
     now is vastly larger than was that of Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     when that part of the country was formed into 
     <lb/>
     a province. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     That is the statement of a gentleman 
     <lb/>
     who, I think, knows very much more about 
     <lb/>
     it than I do. It seems to me clear that 
     <lb/>
     the people of the North-west Territories are 
     <lb/>
     in favour of provincial autonomy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. There seems to be some 
     <lb/>
     misunderstanding as to what the people of 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories, through their 
     <lb/>
     legislature, were asking for. It is held out 
     <lb/>
     to the House that we were asking for pro<lb break="no"/>vincial autonomy, and the idea is thereby 
     <lb/>
     conveyed that we were asking for it on the 
     <lb/>
     same terms as it is enjoyed by the other 
     <lb/>
     provinces. I wish to say that the North<lb break="no"/>west legislature is not asking for provincial 
     <lb/>
     autonomy on the same terms as it has been 
     <lb/>
     received by the other provinces. It is asking 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <cb/>
     
     
     for provincial autonomy subject to two con<lb break="no"/>ditions radically different from those on 
     <lb/>
     which it has been received by the others. 
     <lb/>
     One condition is that the per capita allow<lb break="no"/>ance shall be revised on the basis of popula<lb break="no"/>tion arrived at by a census taken every 
     <lb/>
     five years; and the other is that the debt 
     <lb/>
     account shall be revised at the end of the 
     <lb/>
     ten-year census. Now it is an essential prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of provincial organization throughout 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion that the per capita allowance 
     <lb/>
     on population remains the same from the 
     <lb/>
     entrance of the province into confederation, 
     <lb/>
     and that the debt account remains the same. 
     <lb/>
     Therefore when the territories ask for pro<lb break="no"/>vincial organization they are asking for it 
     <lb/>
     on radically different terms from those on 
     <lb/>
     which the other provinces have received it. 
     <lb/>
     When hon. members are so ready to grant 
     <lb/>
     provincial organization, it will be interest<lb break="no"/>ing to know whether they are willing to 
     <lb/>
     grant it on those terms. Those are the 
     <lb/>
     terms upon which it is asked, and the in<lb break="no"/>ference is that it would not be acceptable 
     <lb/>
     on any other terms, and circumstances be<lb break="no"/>ing as they are, I take the liberty of saying 
     <lb/>
     that it would not be acceptable on other 
     <lb/>
     terms, terms which did not provide for a 
     <lb/>
     revision of these accounts at reasonable 
     <lb/>
     periods. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. DEPUTY SPEAKER</persName>. I draw at<lb break="no"/>tention to the fact that we are out of order. 
     <lb/>
     We are discussing a question that is really 
     <lb/>
     outside of the resolution when We are dis<lb break="no"/>cussing the propriety of organizing the ter<lb break="no"/>ritories into provinces. That is not the 
     <lb/>
     point in the resolution, and I think we had 
     <lb/>
     better defer that question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BARK1">Mr. BARKER</persName>. We have proceeded so 
     <lb/>
     far upon that subject that it would be in<lb break="no"/>teresting to hear from the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     West Assiniboia (Mr. Scott) what has in<lb break="no"/>duced him to change his opinion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. DEPUTY SPEAKER</persName>. Order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SCOT2">Mr. SCOTT</persName>. The member for West 
     <lb/>
     Assiniboia has expressed no changed opinion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. DEPUTY SPEAKER</persName>. Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD3">Mr. BOYD</persName>. I think when the discussion 
     <lb/>
     has reached this point and when certain 
     <lb/>
     statements have been made— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. DEPUTY SPEAKER</persName>. There will be 
     <lb/>
     another opportunity for discussing the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of provincial autonomy. That is not 
     <lb/>
     in the resolution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CLAN1">Mr. CLANCY</persName>. I think my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     from Macdonald (Mr. Boyd) desires to dis<lb break="no"/>cuss the resolution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. DEPUTY SPEAKER</persName>. If he intends 
     <lb/>
     to discuss the propriety of giving $250,000 
     <lb/>
     to the North-west Territories, and confines 
     <lb/>
     himself to that, he will be perfectly in order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD3">Mr. BOYD</persName>. I merely wish to answer a 
     <lb/>
     couple of questions that havebeen brought 
     <lb/>
     to the attention of the House by the prem<lb break="no"/>
     
     
            <pb n="12327" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12327.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12327</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">12328</fw>
        
        
        ier, but as you have decided that I am out 
     <lb/>
     of order, I will take another opportunity. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. DEPUTY SPEAKER</persName>. If the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman goes on and makes another 
     <lb/>
     speech, then another hon. member will want 
     <lb/>
     to answer him, and I think we had better 
     <lb/>
     stop here. Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HEND1">Mr. HENDERSON</persName>. I desire to discuss 
     <lb/>
     the resolution. But before doing so, I wish 
     <lb/>
     to enter a protest against the chairman 
     <lb/>
     continually calling ' carried ' without putting 
     <lb/>
     the motion. I think it is proper that the 
     <lb/>
     members of the House should in every in<lb break="no"/>stance have a timely intimation that the 
     <lb/>
     chairman is going to put the question, by 
     <lb/>
     asking the committee plainly whether they 
     <lb/>
     are in favour of this resolution or not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. DEPUTY SPEAKER</persName>. The hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman is out of order. He rose to say he 
     <lb/>
     was going to speak to the resolution, and he 
     <lb/>
     is actually speaking to the chairman. In 
     <lb/>
     submitting motions in committee, I say ' Is 
     <lb/>
     this carried ' ?  'I do not say ' Carried ' but 
     <lb/>
     ' Is it carried.' 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HEND1">Mr. HENDERSON</persName>. Well, the only word 
     <lb/>
     we have heard is ' carried.' However, I am 
     <lb/>
     going to deal with the resolution. I think 
     <lb/>
     we are making a mistake in creating a debt 
     <lb/>
     against the territories before we give them 
     <lb/>
     autonomy. I am very sorry indeed. if we 
     <lb/>
     are going to proceed as a parliament next 
     <lb/>
     year to organize those large territories into 
     <lb/>
     one or more provinces, that we shall be 
     <lb/>
     compelled to sit down and adjust a debt ac<lb break="no"/>count. I think it is better to proceed along 
     <lb/>
     the lines we have been following in the 
     <lb/>
     past, giving the territories what we consider 
     <lb/>
     fairly and reasonably sufficient for their 
     <lb/>
     purposes. But by no means let us raise up 
     <lb/>
     a debt account against them, which will be 
     <lb/>
     standing in the way and perhaps be a 
     <lb/>
     troublesome matter to settle when we come 
     <lb/>
     to arrange for the political autonomy of the 
     <lb/>
     provinces. It will make no difference to the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. We are getting no interest, and 
     <lb/>
     I do not suppose for a moment that when the 
     <lb/>
     adjustment is made even the principal will 
     <lb/>
     ever be asked for. If we treat the ter<lb break="no"/>ritories respectfully, treat them handsomely, 
     <lb/>
     and keep them in good humour, I think we 
     <lb/>
     will make better terms with them when we 
     <lb/>
     come to settle all these questions. But 
     <lb/>
     by no means let us do something that will 
     <lb/>
     only prove a vexed question hereafter. Now 
     <lb/>
     with regard to the other question, I have 
     <lb/>
     only to say that the sooner we give these 
     <lb/>
     provinces political autonomy the better, for 
     <lb/>
     then we do away with these annual grants. 
     <lb/>
     As at present they are regarded as wards 
     <lb/>
     of the Dominion, and I think the sooner we 
     <lb/>
     close this account by bringing about a 
     <lb/>
     different arrangement for the government of 
     <lb/>
     these provinces and doing away with these 
     <lb/>
     annual grants, the better for the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     and the better for the territories. I would 
     <lb/>
     advise the Finance Minister to create no 
     <lb/>
     debt account, because if we do anything 
     <lb/>
  
  
            <cb/>
         
         
     of that kind we may have a troublesome 
     <lb/>
     matter to settle when we come to erect 
     <lb/>
     them into provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD3">Mr. BOYD</persName>. Has the territorial govern<lb break="no"/>ment been consulted regarding this $250,<lb break="no"/>000 and has it consented to its being plac<lb break="no"/>ed in the way the hon. minister proposes ? 
     <lb/>
     that is by adding it to the debt and mak<lb break="no"/>ing it a matter of readjustment in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with its account in the future. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. The cor<lb break="no"/>respondence on the subject was brought 
     <lb/>
     down some time ago. I think perhaps I 
     <lb/>
     would not be justified in saying that the 
     <lb/>
     territorial government consented. Really, 
     <lb/>
     it was unnecessary to ask their consent in<lb break="no"/>asmuch as this is not a matter of obliga<lb break="no"/>tion upon them at all. If the territorial 
     <lb/>
     government do not wish to avail themselves 
     <lb/>
     of the privileges of this Act they need not 
     <lb/>
     do so. Therefore, as we are not imposing 
     <lb/>
     any obligation upon them, we did not deem 
     <lb/>
     it necessary to obtain their consent. I 
     <lb/>
     think, perhaps, the territorial government 
     <lb/>
     would be pleased to have as large a grant 
     <lb/>
     as the government would give and that 
     <lb/>
     they would prefer to have this in the form 
     <lb/>
     of a grant and not something to be charg<lb break="no"/>ed to the debt account. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Have they applied for 
     <lb/>
     this subsidy ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. No, but 
     <lb/>
     the territorial government for many years 
     <lb/>
     applied not only to this government. but 
     <lb/>
     to the former government asking for a 
     <lb/>
     larger grant. They always err on the side 
     <lb/>
     of liberality in asking, and I think our re<lb break="no"/>sponses have not been less generous—in 
     <lb/>
     fact, they are inuch more generous—than 
     <lb/>
     they have been under our predecessors. 
     <lb/>
     But, having represented their needs to us, 
     <lb/>
     we have to some extent exercised our own 
     <lb/>
     discretion as to the various methods by 
     <lb/>
     which we could meet their needs. I do 
     <lb/>
     not wish to say that the territorial govern<lb break="no"/>ment have requested that this method shall 
     <lb/>
     be adopted, but I think the territorial gov<lb break="no"/>ernment will find this arrangement useful 
     <lb/>
     to them. If they do not need this money 
     <lb/>
     it will not be pressed on them and no harm 
     <lb/>
     is done. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. I understood the hon. 
     <lb/>
     minister to specify two items in regard 
     <lb/>
     to which it was represented as being neces<lb break="no"/>sary that an expenditure should be made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. As re<lb break="no"/>spects these two particular items they did 
     <lb/>
     apply some months ago and we have decid<lb break="no"/>ed by Order in Council that we shall recom<lb break="no"/>mend parliament to make provision for these 
     <lb/>
     two works. We are proposing in the sup<lb break="no"/>plementary estimates to make that provis<lb break="no"/>ion, not as a charge against this grant, but 
     <lb/>
     out of the ordinary grant for the current 
     <lb/>
     year. The government of the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Territories applied for these special appro<lb break="no"/>
      
      
            <pb n="12329" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-24_Page_12329.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12329</fw> <fw type="dateline">SEPTEMBER 24, 1903</fw> <fw type="num">12330</fw>
        
        
       
       
       priations, but they did not ask for a general<lb/>credit such as we now propose.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILMOUR</persName>. I hope the hon. Minis<lb break="no"/>ter of Finance will consider the propriety<lb/>of continuing the grant. That country is<lb/>being settled far and wide. It is quite dif<lb break="no"/>ferent from any other portion of Canada.<lb/>Bridges have to be built. Of late years<lb/>bridges have been swept away as quickly<lb/>as they have been built. In view of the<lb/>extraordinary circumstances prevailing there<lb/>I hope the hon. Minister of Finance will<lb/>consider the propriety of continuing the<lb/>grant rather than of charging these ad<lb break="no"/>vances to the debt account. This plan<lb/>which he proposes may cause a misunder<lb break="no"/>standing in the future in view of the fact<lb/>that there are no specified terms upon<lb/>which this debt is to be created.<lb/>
            </p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. We do<lb/>both. First we give them a liberal grant—<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILMOUR</persName>. I understand perfectly.<lb/>
            </p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. We are<lb/>not ungenerous. We give them a grant<lb/>this year, about four times as much as it<lb/>was when we came into office.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILMOUR</persName>. I do not say that you<lb/>have been ungenerous. I do say that<lb/>you are creating a debt and they must<lb/>have need of the money or you would not<lb/>be giving them an opportunity of borrow<lb break="no"/>ing it. One of the worst things connected<lb/>with giving them autonomy in my opinion<lb/>is that they would be free to create debts.<lb/>
            </p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. My hon.<lb/>friend has touched the serious objection to<lb/>autonomy. Still there are different kinds<lb/>of debts. When you say that the matter<lb/>is to be subject to adjustment in the debt<lb/>account, it does not absolutely decide on<lb/>which side the debt shall be. In my pro<lb break="no"/>vince we have $1,000,000 in the debt ac<lb break="no"/>count, but instead of being a burden on the<lb/>province the Dominion has to pay interest<lb/>upon it. I do not want to make any dan<lb break="no"/>gerous admissions as to what will be the<lb/>case in regard to the North-west Territories,<lb/>because, having responsibility, it devolves<lb/>upon me to speak with reserve, but when<lb/>the time comes to adjust the debt account<lb/>it does not follow that it will be charged<lb/>against the Territories.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HEND1">Mr. HENDERSON</persName>. Although it may be <lb/>a question as to which party the debt will<lb/>be charged against there is no question<lb/>about the $250,000 referred to in this resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, because the resolution says :<lb/>
            </p>
        
        <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>All sums so advanced to the government of<lb/>the North-west Territories shall be charged in<lb/>an account to be known as ' The North-west<lb/>Territories Debt Account.' and shall, in any<lb/>financial arrangement that may be made in<lb/>connection with the organization of a province<lb/>or provinces in the said territories, be taken<lb/>
         
         
            <cb/>
      
      
      into consideration as a debt owing by the said<lb/>territories to the Dominion of Canada.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
           
           
            <p>This will be owing by the territories.<lb/>That is what I object to. I think we<lb/>should leave them in the position in which<lb/>they are now as we have been satisfying<lb/>the territories very well until we are pre<lb break="no"/>pared to make a different arrangement<lb/>with them which will not be, perhaps, be<lb break="no"/>yond twelve months, according to the<lb/>Minister of Finance. It would be a pity<lb/>to create a debt or anything that could be<lb/>called a debt because it might lead to a<lb/>dispute when the settlement is being brought<lb/>about. We are told that they have not<lb/>been consulted about this, that they have<lb/>not asked for this money and they may<lb/>not ask for it. I think perhaps they may<lb/>be independent enough not to ask for it,<lb/>because I believe it is their right to have<lb/>it and it should not have been charged to<lb/>them as a debt to be held up before them<lb/>one or two years hence when we come to<lb/>finally arrange with them.<lb/>
            </p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. I am<lb/>afraid I have not been able to make my<lb break="no"/>self clear. Suppose when the adjustment<lb/>of accounts takes place between the new<lb/>province and the Dominion it should be<lb/>found that there was—I do not like to name<lb/>the amount—a million dollars to be placed<lb/>at the credit of the North-west Territories<lb/>in the debt account. The only differ<lb break="no"/>ence between the situation then and<lb/>now is that instead of waiting for the<lb/>event and placing the money to their credit<lb/>next year we are giving them the right to<lb/>draw upon it in advance and it then has<lb/>to be adjusted in connection with the gene<lb break="no"/>ral arrangement of the farmers of the pro<lb break="no"/>vince.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HEND1">Mr. HENDERSON</persName>. Does the hon. Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Finance expect that when they are<lb/>organized into a province in that way, and<lb/>when they are supposed to get a credit of<lb/>$1,000,000 they will only get three-quarters<lb/>of a million that it will be satisfactory <lb/>to them ? I do not think it should be so.<lb/>I suggest that the hon. Minister of Finance<lb/>drop the matter and bring it up again<lb/>when he gives them autonomy.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Resolution reported, read the first and<lb/>second times, and agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName> moved<lb/>for leave to introduce Bill (No. 256) to pro<lb break="no"/>vide for advances to the government of<lb/>the North-west Territories.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Motion agreed to, and Bill read the<lb/>first time.<lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>