<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1896-04-26"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1896-04-26">26 April 1896</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Sixth Session</title>.
          <date when="1896"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="4671" to="4676"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04671.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04673.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04675.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-10">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-10">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04671">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04671.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04673">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04673.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04675">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04675.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="4671" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04671.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">4671</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4672</fw>
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES REPRE<lb break="no"/>SENTATION. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName> moved second reading of 
     <lb/>
     Bill (No. 22) further to amend chapter 7 of 
     <lb/>
     the Revised Statutes of Canada, being the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories Representation Act. 
     <lb/>
     He said: Mr. Speaker, this Bill is for the 
     <lb/>
     purpose of changing the law in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories with regard to voting at 
     <lb/>
     elections. I explained the provisions of the 
     <lb/>
     Bill very fully on the first reading. In the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories the Franchise Act is 
     <lb/>
     not in operation. Two years ago the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, when applying the provisions of the 
     <lb/>
     Election Act, with regard to voting by ballot 
     <lb/>
     to the North-west Territories, dealt with the 
     <lb/>
     question of a voters' list. Prior to that 
     <lb/>
    time, there practically was no voters' list in 
     <lb/>the Dominion elections there. A voters' list 
     <lb/>
   
   
            <cb/>
         
         
     was prepared, but, under the provisions of 
     <lb/>
     the Act, any person entitled to be an elector 
     <lb/>
     could have his name added to the list on 
     <lb/>
     election day; so that, for preventing any 
     <lb/>
     one from voting or enabling any one to vote, 
     <lb/>
     the list was of no account. In 1894, when 
     <lb/>
     the provisions with regard to the ballot were 
     <lb/>
     extended to the North-west Territories, the 
     <lb/>
     provisions of the law with regard to voting 
     <lb/>
     there were not changed. that law providing 
     <lb/>
     for a purely manhood suifrage; that is to 
     <lb/>
     say, every person who was a British sub<lb break="no"/>ject, who was twenty-one years of age, and 
     <lb/>
     who had resided a certain time in the elec<lb break="no"/>toral district, was entitled to vote. entirely 
     <lb/>
     irrespective of any other qualification. When 
     <lb/>
     that Bill went to the Senate, a provision 
     <lb/>
     was added, the result of which was to pro<lb break="no"/>vide for a list of electors in the Territories. 
     <lb/>
     which, like the list of electors provided by 
     <lb/>
     the Franchise Act. was to be final. I may 
     <lb/>
     say that that very fundamental change in 
     <lb/>
     the law was never discussed in this House. 
     <lb/>
     When the amendments came back from the 
     <lb/>
     Senate, it is true, they were duly passed by 
     <lb/>
     this House, and appeared, as all such amend<lb break="no"/>ments do, in the Journals : but no one read<lb break="no"/>ing them would know what the effect of 
     <lb/>
     them was. I fancy that most of the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of this House thought they were im<lb break="no"/>material changes, as most of them really 
     <lb/>
     were; but one amendment repealed section 
     <lb/>
     44 of the old North-west Territories 
     <lb/>
    Representation Act, which provided 
     <lb/>that an elector might vote, on having 
     <lb/>his name put on the list by the deputy 
     <lb/>returning officer on the day of election. 
     <lb/>I myself did not observe the change in the 
     <lb/>law. I may say that in the debate that took 
     <lb/>place upon the Bill before it went to the 
     <lb/>Senate, several members discussed this ques<lb break="no"/>tion as to the advisability of leaving the law 
     <lb/>as it was, and it was thoroughly understood 
     <lb/>that it should be left as it was. The atten<lb break="no"/>tion of the House was drawn to the position 
     <lb/>in which the law was up there as to voters' 
     <lb/>lists, and I myself took the ground that the 
     <lb/>voters' lists was an immaterial matter en<lb break="no"/>tirely in the Territories, on account of the 
     <lb/>existence of this particular clause, which 
     <lb/>practically allowed every voter to vote, whe<lb break="no"/>ther his name was on the lists or not. I re<lb break="no"/>member stating that we might as well save 
     <lb/>the expense of a voters' lists, under the cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances. But it was claimed by one of 
     <lb/>the members from the Territories that the 
     <lb/>list was necessary because without it it 
     <lb/>would not be possible to poll all the votes 
     <lb/>within the time limited by the Election Act. 
     <lb/>This very vital change was made in the 
     <lb/>Senate. I think it will be admitted by the 
     <lb/>House that changes of this kind should not 
     <lb/>be made in the Senate. This is one of the 
     <lb/>matters surely which should originate in this 
     <lb/>House—an alteration in the law with regard 
     <lb/>to the constitution at this House. It does 
     <lb/>seem to me that it is going very far for the 
     <lb/>Senate to undertake to make that vital 
     <lb/>change in the law. Of course, it is quite 
     <lb/>
        
        
        
            <pb n="4673" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04673.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">4673</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 26, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">4674</fw>
         
         
         
     true that the Senate has the power to make 
     <lb/>
    a law of that kind and send it back here 
     <lb/>for approval ; but it was entirely unexpected   
     <lb/>that they should think of making any such 
     <lb/>change, and I think it was very unfortunate   
     <lb/>that they should have undertaken to do so. 
     <lb/>It has since been explained in this House 
     <lb/>that the changes made in the Senate were 
     <lb/>made at the instance. I understand. of Sena<lb break="no"/>tor Perley, who acted at the suggestion of 
     <lb/>the hon. member for East Assiniboia (Mr. 
     <lb/>McDonald) ; and I understand that the hon.   
     <lb/>member for East Assiniboia is the only re<lb break="no"/>presentative from the Territories who advo<lb break="no"/>cates the change. I understand the 
     <lb/>reason he gives is the possibilities of false 
     <lb/>voting. personation anti repeating, which, he 
     <lb/>claims, are very prevalent in the Territories. 
     <lb/>We have not the pleasure very often of 
     <lb/>hearing from the hon. member for East 
     <lb/>Assiniboia in this House, and I think, if he 
     <lb/>desires to add to the legislation of Parlia 
     <lb/>ment, he should do so in this House, and not 
     <lb/>through the medium of a friend in the 
     <lb/>Senate. The matter was first brought fully 
     <lb/>to the attention of this House when. in 1895, 
     <lb/>the hon. Minister of the Interior (Mr. Daly) 
     <lb/>introduced a Bill here to remedy some slight 
     <lb/>errors that were made in the legislation of 
     <lb/>1894 : and upon examining these changes, it 
     <lb/>appeared quite evident what a change in the 
     <lb/>law had been made the previous session. 
     <lb/>Very serious protests were made against 
     <lb/>the change in 1895, The hon. Minister was 
     <lb/>urged very strongly by the hon. member for 
     <lb/>Bothwell (Mr. Mills) and other members on 
     <lb/>this side not to press it. and I think the 
     <lb/>position taken by this side was agreed to by 
     <lb/>the hon. member for West Assinihoia (Mr. 
     <lb/>Davin) and not objected to by any hon. 
     <lb/>member for the Territories. The hon. Min<lb break="no"/>ister declined. however. to accede to this pro<lb break="no"/>test ; and as the matter was only brought to 
     <lb/>the attention of the House in the dying days 
     <lb/>of the session of 1895, we had no oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of really discussing the question. In 
     <lb/>the meantime, public attention in the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories had been directed to the matter, and 
     <lb/>the North-west Territories assembly passed 
     <lb/>a resolution, which I read in full on the first 
     <lb/>reading of this Bill of mine. In that reso<lb break="no"/>lution, they drew attention to the very un<lb break="no"/>fortunate position in which the Territories 
     <lb/>would be placed at an election on account 
     <lb/>of this change, and they urged that one of 
     <lb/>three things be done,—either that the Fran<lb break="no"/>chise Act applicable to the rest of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion should be put in force there ; or that 
     <lb/>the territorial law with regard to elections 
     <lb/>should be adopted; or that the law should 
     <lb/>be put back where it was. This resolution 
     <lb/>was introduced in the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories assembly by Mr. Insinger, member for 
     <lb/>the northern part of Eastern Assiniboia, and 
     <lb/>was supported unanimously by the assembly, 
     <lb/>a majority of which are supporters of hen. 
     <lb/>gentlemen opposite. I may say also that the 
     <lb/>amendment by which it is proposed to adept 
     <lb/>the old system as one of the alternatives, 
     <lb/>
   
   
            <cb/>
    

         
         
     was suggested by Mr. Haultain, who occu<lb break="no"/>pies the position practically of Premier of 
     <lb/>
     the Territories. and who is also the candi<lb break="no"/>date, on behalf of the Government, for the 
     <lb/>
     constituency of Alberta. Under these cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, the hon. member for West 
     <lb/>
     Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) introduced Bill No. 
     <lb/>
     20), which has not yet had its second read<lb break="no"/>ing ; and not knowing that that hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man had the matter in hand. I likewise in<lb break="no"/>troduced the present Bill for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     carrying out the desires of the assembly 
     <lb/>
     and of rectifying what I thought was a very 
     <lb/>
     unfair law. I may say that it is quite im<lb break="no"/>possible, at this stage in our hismry. to at<lb break="no"/>tempt to apply the Franchise Act to the 
     <lb/>
     Territories, because there is not now suffi<lb break="no"/>cient time to provide a list under that Act. 
     <lb/>
     Then as to applying the territorial law, there 
     <lb/>
     would perhaps be no very great objection 
     <lb/>
     to that, except that it is not in accord with 
     <lb/>
     the policy of the Government to adopt a 
     <lb/>
     provincial law with regard to voting. We 
     <lb/>
     had at one time the assurance that such a 
     <lb/>
     policy met with the approval of the late Sir 
     <lb/>
     John Thompson while he. was leading this 
     <lb/>
     Government; and we were in hopes, during 
     <lb/>
     the last session he was in the House, that 
     <lb/>
     he would carry out the suggestions which 
     <lb/>
     had fallen from us, at different times, of the 
     <lb/>
     advisability of adopting that principle, name<lb break="no"/>ly, of recognizing the provincial franchise 
     <lb/>
     and electoral lists for this House. 
     <lb/>
     So that, practically, if we a re to rectify this 
     <lb/>
     wrong it comes down to the re-enactment 
     <lb/>
     of section 44, in order that a man who is 
     <lb/>
     entitled to vote may know whether his name 
     <lb/>
     is on the list of voters or not. And the 
     <lb/>
     reason why the assembly were so unani<lb break="no"/>mous in condemning the change in the law, 
     <lb/>
     and the reason why I think I can appeal 
     <lb/>
     confidently to this House to make the change 
     <lb/>
     is that there are no sufficient delays pro<lb break="no"/>vided for, and it is quite impossible, in the 
     <lb/>
     nature of things, to provide sufficient delay 
     <lb/>
     in making this list to enable both parties 
     <lb/>
     fairly to get their names upon it. The list 
     <lb/>
     is not to be made out at all until a pro<lb break="no"/>clamation is issued for an election. As soon 
     <lb/>
     as that proclamation issues, the Government 
     <lb/>
     appoint ennmerators for each polling divi<lb break="no"/>sion. The enumerator makes a list for the 
     <lb/>
     polling subdivision. He has nothing to com<lb break="no"/>mence with except what knowledge he may 
     <lb/>
     have of the subdivision. It is not neces<lb break="no"/>sary under the law for the Government to 
     <lb/>
     appoint a resident of the polling subdivision, 
     <lb/>
     and it might happen, and it would happen, 
     <lb/>
     probably, that the enumerator would have 
     <lb/>
     very little actual knowledge as to which 
     <lb/>
     electors should have their names upon the 
     <lb/>
     list. However, he is to do the best he can 
     <lb/>
     and, certainly, if he were a partisan, and 
     <lb/>
     were inclined to use his position for the 
     <lb/>
     purpose of aiding his party he would have 
     <lb/>
     unlimited opportunities to do so. He could 
     <lb/>
     make the list in any way he sees fit, put<lb break="no"/>ting on names or leaving them off as he 
     <lb/>
     wished. And no delays are given, such as 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <pb n="4675" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-26_Page_04675.jpg"/>
          
          <fw type="num">4675</fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4676</fw>
          
          
          would afford an opportunity to either party<lb/>to really get the list right. The list is to 
     <lb/>be made up in eight days only before the 
     <lb/>polling, that is, it is completed the day 
     <lb/>before nomination. It is then posted—writ<lb break="no"/>ten out, for there is no time to print it—in 
     <lb/>two places in the polling subdivision. 
     <lb/>quite impossible for the electors to know 
     <lb/>where it is posted. no provision con<lb break="no"/>cerning that appears Act. So it 
     <lb/>is a mere matter of chance whether the per<lb break="no"/>son entitled to he an elector sees the list. 
     <lb/>or not. But if he has the good fortune to 
     <lb/>see the list posted up, and tinds on examin<lb break="no"/>ing it that his name is not on the list, he 
     <lb/>must make application within six days, that 
     <lb/>is two days before the election, to the enu<lb break="no"/>merator to have his name put upon the list. 
     <lb/>But first he must find the enumerator : there 
     <lb/>is no place fixed where he can he address<lb break="no"/>ed. As soon as the list is put up the enu<lb break="no"/>merator may leave the subdivision, in fact, 
     <lb/>he may never have been in it at all. If 
     <lb/>the citizen can find him. he has the pri<lb break="no"/>vilege of saying to hint : You have omitted
<lb/>my name from the list. But the enumerator
<lb/>is not: hound to pay the slightest atten<lb break="no"/>tion : he may leave the list uncorrected, and
<lb/>there no means to compel him to cor<lb break="no"/>rect it. There are no provisions, as in the
<lb/>Franchise Act, for the posting in school<lb break="no"/>houses of the list and for distri<lb break="no"/>buting it, giving everybody an opportu<lb break="no"/>nity of learning whether his name is on
<lb/>the list or not, and giving every person
<lb/>time to make proper application to the re<lb break="no"/>vising ottieer to get his name upon the list.
<lb/>As I said before. it is practically no list
<lb/>at all. It simply leaves it in the hands
<lb/>of the men appointed by the Government
<lb/>to do as they see tit. I suppose we have
<lb/>no right to assume that these gentlemen will
<lb/>not do their duty. but that is very little
<lb/>protection. In the matter of the voters' lists.
<lb/>it is most important that every elector
<lb/>should have a fair opportunity of proving
<lb/>his right to be upon the list: and if he
<lb/>proves his right there should be no such
<lb/>provisions in the law as would ensure that
<lb/>natne going upon the list. But no such pro<lb break="no"/>vision appears in this Act. For that rea<lb break="no"/>son, I have felt it my duty to call the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the House to the matter, and
<lb/>so has the hon. member for West Assiniboia
<lb/>(Mr. Davin}. A few days ago, when the
<lb/>Government announced their intention of
<lb/>taking Mondays and Thursdays. I drew their
<lb/>attention to these Bills, and I was assured— <lb/>at any rate, the hon. member for West As<lb break="no"/>siniboia stood in his place and stated—that
<lb/>the Government intended to introduce an
<lb/>Act for the purpose of making this matter
<lb/>right. No such Act has been introduced, <lb/>and, as time is passing, and we are getting
<lb/>close to the end of the session, and as there
<lb/>is a large amount of business to be done—
<lb/>practically no Government business has been
<lb/>done yet—I am much disappointed at not
<lb/>seeing a Bill upon the Order paper for the<lb/>
    
    
            <cb/>
          
          
     purpose: for the assurance given by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for West Assiniboia as to the 
     <lb/>
     Government's intention was corroborated. 
     <lb/>
     I am not sure by whom but I think by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. Minister of Justice Mr. Dickey. And 
     <lb/>
     if that course is adopted—of course I do 
     <lb/>
     not suggest that the Government do not in<lb break="no"/>tend to adopt it—it will he very satisfac<lb break="no"/>tory indeed to the people of the North-west 
     <lb/>
     generally. The only suggestion that I have 
     <lb/>
     to make is that, the Government having de<lb break="no"/>cided to do it, it will be advisable that it 
     <lb/>
     shall he done at an early day in order that 
     <lb/>
     the measure may go to the Senate with 
     <lb/>
     time to he passed there and so heeome law. 
     <lb/>
     I would ask that my Bill be read a second 
     <lb/>
     time in the meantime, and then allowed to 
     <lb/>
     stand. the committee stage not being taken 
     <lb/>
     now, so that the Government may have an 
     <lb/>
     opportunity to bring down their measure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to,and Bill read the second 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>