<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-03-20" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title> 
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-03-20">20 March 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:TAEK1"/>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
          
         
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
   
              

          <date when="1905"/>. 
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="2761" to="2761"/>.
 <biblScope unit="page" from="2839" to="2842"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2761.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2839.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2841.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="sarahtaekema" when="2017-02-09">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="Yu_Thomson" when="2017-03-10"> Marked up people </change>
         
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2761">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2761.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2839">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2839.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2841">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2841.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="2761" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2761.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2761</fw> <fw type="dateline">MARCH 20, 1905</fw> <fw type="num">2762</fw>
     
     <lb/>
           
            <!-- ST, 2017-01-24, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day --> 
            
            <!--<p>department, and we have made arrange<lb break="no"/>ments to pay their expenses. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. AMES. It is out of this appropria<lb break="no"/>tion that Mr. St. George is paid ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. PREFONTAINE. Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. AMES. Is he now permanently in the 
     <lb/>
     employ of the department, and does he 
     <lb/>
     give his entire time to it ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. PREFONTAINE. I do not know that 
     <lb/>
     he gives his entire time. He is obliged, of 
     <lb/>
     course, to do the service that is required 
     <lb/>
     from him. He is obliged to be in attendance 
     <lb/>
     and to superintend the work as an engineer 
     <lb/>
     occupying that position. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Some resolutions reported. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Hon. W. S. FIELDING moved the ad<lb break="no"/>journment of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. R. L. BORDEN. What will we take 
     <lb/>
     up on Monday in case we get through with 
     <lb/>
     private members' business ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. FIELDING. Supply, taking up the 
     <lb/>
     estimates of the Department of Public 
     <lb/>
     Works in case the hon. Minister of Marine 
     <lb/>
     and Fisheries is not here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Motion agreed to, and House adjourned at 
     <lb/>
     11.25 p.m. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   <div type="section">
      <head rendition="simple:centre">
     HOUSE OF COMMONS. 
      </head>
      <lb/>
      <p rendition="simple:right">
             
           MONDAY, March 20, 1905. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> took the Chair at Three 
     <lb/>
     o'clock. 
     <lb/>
         </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PROVINCIAL GOVERNMENT IN THE 
     <lb/>
     NORTHWEST TERRITORIES. 
            </head>
      <p>On the Orders of the Day being called, 
     <lb/>
      </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Rt. Hon. Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName> (Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister). I desire to inform the House 
     <lb/>
     that it is the intention of the government to 
     <lb/>
     proceed with the Autonomy Bill on Wed<lb break="no"/>nesday next as the first order. I may say 
     <lb/>
     to the House also that it is contemplated to 
     <lb/>
     introduce an amendment to section 16, which 
     <lb/>
     amendment will be placed in the hands of 
     <lb/>
     the clerk, I hope, before the adjournment 
     <lb/>
     of the House ; and before the adjournment 
     <lb/>
     I think we will be able to place on the 
     <lb/>
     table of the House the papers which were 
     <lb/>
     asked for the other day by the hon. the 
     <lb/>
     leader of the opposition. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. Of course, it would 
     <lb/>
     be desirable, as I have pointed out to the 
     <lb/>
     right hon. gentleman, that these papers 
     <lb/>
     which are to be brought down, or have been 
     <lb/>
     brought down, should be printed, or put 
     <lb/>
     in some such form that they will be prop<lb break="no"/>erly available to members of the House who 
     <lb/>
     desire to deal with them in the course of 
     <lb/>
     the debate. <lb/>
            </p>
        <cb/> 
         
         </div>
         <div type="section">
         <head rendition="simple:centre">
     THE BUDGET SPEECH.<lb/>
         </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Hon. GEO. E. FOSTER</persName>. Is there any an<lb break="no"/>nouncement by the First Minister or the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Finance as to the budget, or is 
     <lb/>
     that now to be indefinitely postponed ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Hon. W. S. FIELDING</persName> (Minister of Fin<lb break="no"/>ance). I intimated to my hon. friend the 
     <lb/>
     other day that some days might elapse be<lb break="no"/>fore we could make an announcement ; and 
     <lb/>
     in view of the business which is likely to 
     <lb/>
     come before the House, and which is of, 
     <lb/>
     perhaps, more immediate interest, I think 
     <lb/>
     we will have to postpone for a few days the 
     <lb/>
     announcement concerning the budget. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
            <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PRIVATE BILLS. 
            </head>
         
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">MOOSEJAW AND EDMONTON RAILWAY 
<lb/>
     COMPANY.</head>
            
            <p>House in committee on Bill (No. 20) to in<lb break="no"/>corporate the Moosejaw and Edmonton Rail<lb break="no"/>way Company.—Mr. Scott. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. The reason that 
     <lb/>
     this Bill stood was because I desired the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman who has the Bill in charge 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Scott) to explain why it was neces<lb break="no"/>sary to have a capitalization, if I remember 
     <lb/>
     correctly, of $2,000,000, and in addition to 
     <lb/>
     that the power to issue bonds upon the 
     <lb/>
     whole length of the road to the extent of 
     <lb/>
     $25,000 a mile. I would think that perhaps 
     <lb/>
     the bond issue would of itself be amply 
     <lb/>
     sufficient to build and equip the road—per<lb break="no"/>haps more than sufficient—but in addition 
     <lb/>
     to that we have authorized a capitalization 
     <lb/>
     of $2,000,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SCOT2">Mr. SCOTT</persName>. I may say, Mr. Chairman, 
     <lb/>
     that the application of the promoters called 
     <lb/>
     for a capitalization of only $1,000,000 and 
     <lb/>
     it was in the judgment of the standing com<lb break="no"/>mittee on Railways and Canals that the 
     <lb/>
     capitalization was increased to $2,000,000. 
     <lb/>
     I have not the faintest objection to reduc<lb break="no"/>ing that to $1, 000, 000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. What was the 
     <lb/>
     reason for increasing it? Perhaps the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman who was present at the commit<lb break="no"/>tee can give this committee some informa<lb break="no"/>tion as to that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:HYMA1">Mr. HYMAN</persName>. It has been the usual cus<lb break="no"/>tom of the committee in regard to roads of 
     <lb/>
     this character to make the capital stock 
     <lb/>
     in the neighbourhood of $10,000 a mile. 
     <lb/>
     It is necessary under a clause of the 
     <lb/>
     Railway Act to subscribe 15 per cent of the 
     <lb/>
     capital to make a start with the road. With 
     <lb/>
     a road of this character having a capital 
     <lb/>
     of $1,000,000 it would mean $150,000, but 
     <lb/>
               with $2,000,000, capital it would mean $300,<lb break="no"/>000. 
    
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. What is the length of 
     <lb/>
     the road ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:HYMA1">Mr. HYMAN</persName>. About 400 miles. These 
     <lb/>
     matters have all been discussed from that [...]
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="2839" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2839.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">2839</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">2840</fw>
          <p>[...]  ther any one could see those plans ; and if <lb/>
it were necessary to ask that question, what <lb/>
made it necessary,
except that some one was <lb/>
       
            looking for
information contained in the <lb/>
           
          plans
and had gone to
the deputy minister <lb/>
          
           
          to ask for the
information, and out of that <lb/>
fact had arisen the necessity for the inquiry. <lb/>
At what stage would it be premature for <lb/>
the hon.
gentleman to approve of these plans
<lb/>
or to investigate them ? Can it be said to <lb/>
be contemplated by section 122 of the Rail<lb break="no"/>way Act that
the minister, the moment he <lb/>
gets the plans
that are to be prepared under
<lb/>
that section, can seal them up so that neither <lb/>
he, nor his colleagues, nor parliament, nor <lb/>
the railway company themselves can see <lb/>
them or inspect them ? If that be so for a <lb/>
period of seven months, why may it not be <lb/>
so for ten years ? I hope the hon gentle<lb break="no"/>man will accede to the reasonable request <lb/>
from this side of the House, and will show <lb/>
cogent reasons why, at any rate, he should
<lb/>
not loosen, with regard to these particular <lb/>
plans, that principle which he says has been <lb/>
inaugurated in his department, and that he. <lb/>
will see his way to allow this motion to <lb/>
pass. <lb/>
            </p>

        <p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. Just one
word more, if <lb/>
the House will allow me. If the First Min<lb break="no"/>ister were here I would make an appeal to <lb/>
him with reference to the principle involved <lb/>
in this matter; as he is not here, and the <lb/>
Minister of Finance I imagine,
is leading <lb/>
the House, I
will say to him that I think it <lb/>
would be a pity if affirmation were to be <lb/>
made that the House assembled here has <lb/>
not a right to have a document such as this <lb/>
brought down if it wishes it. If this motion <lb/>
is negatived, of course it will affirm that <lb/>
principle. I call the attention of the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Finance to the fact that I do not <lb/>
think any real reason has been given why <lb/>
the public interest would be harmed if they <lb/>
were brought down at once. Then if we <lb/>
have not a reason given, is it not rather peri<lb break="no"/>lous to
affirm a principle which in effect <lb/>
would be this, that the House is not master <lb/>
of the documents which one of its servants, <lb/>
in the form of a member of the government. <lb/>
has in his possession, and has kept sealed <lb/>
in his
possession for months? <lb/>
            </p>

        <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Mr. FIELDING</persName>. I am
afraid that I can<lb break="no"/>not agree with my hon. friend that the <lb/>
House is about to affirm any dangerous prin<lb break="no"/>ciple. Certainly that is not our intention ; <lb/>
nor is it the intention of this House to aflirm
<lb/>
the
principle that parliament has not a right <lb/>
to every public document in relation to all <lb/>
public affairs. But it is a question of dis<lb break="no"/>cretion. It is a constant practice for a min<lb break="no"/>ister, here and elsewhere, when a motion is <lb/>
made for papers, to say that in his judgment <lb/>
it is not wise
to submit those papers to the <lb/>
House. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>.
Is that
sufficient without <lb/>
a reason ? <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Mr. FIELDING</persName>. The
minister has given <lb/>
a reason. My hon. friend may not accept the <lb/>
reason. For myself I would say that any un<lb break="no"/>finished transaction might not necessarily <lb/>
be a proper matter to submit to the House. <lb/>
Any matter which is pending and left un<lb break="no"/>finished might properly be withheld from the <lb/>
knowledge of the public until the discussion <lb/>
is completed. In that aspect of the question, <lb/>
the minister does not say that the House has <lb/>
no right to these papers, he simply says that <lb/>
in his judgment, and for the reasons he has <lb/>
given, he thinks it would not be wise to <lb/>
bring these papers down at the present time. <lb/>
There is no danger in affirming a principle <lb/>
of that character. We are only affirming <lb/>
what is done in all parliaments under the <lb/>
British system for reasons which, in the <lb/>
mind of the minister, he deems to be suffici<lb break="no"/>ent. Sometimes hon. gentlemen might re<lb break="no"/>gard them as insufficient, but that is always <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>a matter of opinion
and judgment. <lb/>
            </p>
           
            <p>Motion negatived on
division. <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">PROVINCIAL
AUTONOMY IN
THE <lb/>
NORTHWEST TERRITORIES—PRE<lb break="no"/>SENTATION OF DOCUMENTS. <lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Hon. W. S. FIELDING</persName>
(Minister of
Fi<lb break="no"/>nance). The House will hardly desire to <lb/>
proceed further with the Orders. Before <lb/>
moving the adjournment, if any hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man has nothing else to bring up, I desire <lb/>
to submit some papers to the House. I lay <lb/>
on the table a copy of the School Ordinances <lb/>
of the Northwest Territories, chaps. 29, 30
<lb/>
and 31, passed in 1901. I also lay on the <lb/>
table a
memorandum giving a summary of <lb/>
legislation relating to subsidies to the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. These are documents which have been <lb/>
asked for by hon. gentlemen opposite. They <lb/>
are both printed, and will be in the distri<lb break="no"/>bution office to-night or to-morrow
morning. <lb/>
I have sufficient copies to-night to hand a <lb/>
few around. I also submit a statement <lb/>
showing the areas of the provisional dis<lb break="no"/>tricts of the Northwest Territories, and <lb/>
other information with respect to lands in <lb/>
the Northwest Territories, numbers of Set<lb break="no"/>tlers and so forth, these being papers which <lb/>
were asked for. They are not in printed <lb/>
form, and I think it would be better to sus<lb break="no"/>pend the rule at once and ask the House to <lb/>
agree to have them printed. I would there<lb break="no"/>fore move that the rule be suspended for the <lb/>
purpose of having these printed. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. Is that
all ? Is there no<lb break="no"/>thing else to come before the House in con<lb break="no"/>nection with the Northwest Territories ?-<lb/> Because the First Minister promised that be<lb break="no"/>fore the sitting closed we would have some<lb break="no"/>thing with regard
to amendments to the <lb/>
Bill. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Mr.
FIELDING</persName>. Immediately on the ad<lb break="no"/>journment I
will send to my hon. friend a <lb/>
copy of the amendment. which will be plac<lb break="no"/>ed on the notice paper. I do not think I <lb/>
         
            <pb n="2841" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-20_Page_2841.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2841</fw> <fw type="dateline">MARCH 21, 1905<fw/> <fw type="num">2842</fw>
 <lb/>
            </fw>
           need to read it, but
I will furnish my hon. <lb/>
friend at once with a. copy.
<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Motion agreed to. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Mr.
Fielding</persName>, House ad<lb break="no"/>journed at 11.25 p.m. <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
            <!-- GL, 2017-02-21, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 

            <!--<p>HOUSE OF COMMONS. <lb/>
TUESDAY, March 21, 1905. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>The SPEAKER took the
Chair at Three <lb/>
o'clock. <lb/>
            </p>
         
            

            <p>VACANCY. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Mr. SPEAKER. I have
the honour to in<lb break="no"/>form the House that my attention having <lb/>
been called, by the hon. member for Toron<lb break="no"/>to North, in his place, to the fact of the de<lb break="no"/>mise of Edward Frederick Clarke, Esq., <lb/>
member for the electoral district of Toronto <lb/>
Centre. I have, in accordance with section <lb/>
8 of chapter 13 of the Revised Statutes of <lb/>
Canada, issued my warrant to the Clerk of <lb/>
the Crown in Chancery to make out a new <lb/>
writ of
election for the said electoral dis <lb/>
trict. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>THE TELEPHONE
QUESTION. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Hon. Sir WILLIAM
MULOCK (Post<lb break="no"/>master General moved : <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>That Messrs. Bergeron
and Geoffrion be ad<lb break="no"/>ded to the
committee appointed on Friday last <lb/>
to consider
the telephone question. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Motion agreed to. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>PACKING AND SALE OF CERTAIN <lb/>
COMMODITIES. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Bill (No. 121) to
amend the Act respecting <lb/>
the packing and sale of staple commodities <lb/>
—Mr. Fisher—read the second time and <lb/>
House went into committee thereon. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>On section
1—-dimensions of apple boxes, <lb/>
penalty; certain packages excepted. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Mr. HENDERSON. I
regret that I am <lb/>
again obliged to enter my strongest protest <lb/>
against the passage of this Bill in the form <lb/>
in which it is at present worded. I do not <lb/>
conceive that it is in the interests of the <lb/>
trade of Canada that the Bill should be so <lb/>
worded. The hon. minister has told the <lb/>
House in discussing the resolution on which <lb/>
this Bill is founded that the fruit associa<lb break="no"/>tions of this country have described the <lb/>
size of box in which apples should be pack<lb break="no"/>ed for export. I think
the minister should <lb/>
have laid upon the table of the House some <lb/>
resolution of some fruit association to show <lb/>
us where the authority came from for fixing <lb/>
the special size of box which is prescribed <lb/>
in this Bill. In sections of the country <lb/>
where the fruit industry is extensively car<lb break="no"/>ried on there is a very strong protest against <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p> <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>the size of box here
prescribed, and it is the <lb/>
more strange to me that the hon. minister <lb/>
should have given us that information, in<lb break="no"/>asmuch as the gentlemen from whom I <lb/>
obtained information are members of fruit <lb/>
associations, and no doubt were present at <lb/>
some of those meetings when the matter of <lb/>
the size of the apple box was discussed. <lb/>
The difference
between the minister and <lb/>
myself is this: I have proposed that a box <lb/>
should be designated in the Act, the size of <lb/>
which would be some well known quantity. <lb/>
For example, I suggested that the box should <lb/>
contain one-quarter of a barrel. The stan— <lb break="maybe"/>
dard barrel of apples is a well known mea<lb break="no"/>sure. In the old country apples are sold by <lb/>
the barrel, and people there understand what <lb/>
a barrel of apples is. We have fixed by law <lb/>
the size of a barrel of apples and the quan<lb break="no"/>tity is known amongst us—and, I believe, <lb/>
correctly—as three bushels. If we are going <lb/>
to authorize the shipment of apples in boxes <lb/>
containing
less than a barrel, I contend that <lb/>
these boxes should contain some well de<lb break="no"/>fined, specific quantity that would be well <lb/>
understood by the purchaser in the old <lb/>
country. The box defined by the Minister <lb/>
of Agriculture is a nondescript box which <lb/>
represents practically nothing specific. It is <lb/>
not one-fourth of a barrel; it is not one- <lb break="yes"/>
third of a
barrel; it is no definite fraction <lb/>
of a barrel that the people will understand. <lb/>
It is less than one-third
of a barrel and it is <lb/>
larger than one-quarter of a barrel. To my <lb/>
mind, the box that would hold one-quarter <lb/>
of a barrel would be a very much better <lb/>
package than one that contains no definite <lb/>
fraction of a barrel. When this matter was <lb/>
last discussed, the Minister of Agriculture <lb/>
almost insinuated that my object in advocat<lb break="no"/>ing a smaller box was that the shippers in this <lb/>
country might take advantage of the buyers <lb/>
in the old country and sell them a smaller <lb/>
quantity with a view of enhancing the <lb/>
price. I had no such intention or thought, <lb/>
but I do tell the minister that the use of the <lb/>
box which he has described will have the <lb/>
effect of defrauding the people of the old <lb/>
country. The purchaser will naturally ask <lb/>
how much there is in the box, and he will <lb/>
be told it is a bushel, or one—third of a bar<lb break="no"/>rel, when, as a matter of fact, it is not. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Mr. CAMPBELL. How
much is it short ? <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Mr. HENDERSON. It is
very consider<lb break="no"/>ably short. The minister shakes his head, <lb/>
but I can tell him that he is all wrong ; he <lb/>
has taken his information from young men, <lb/>
who have not the experience of practical men <lb/>
in the business, who have investigated the <lb/>
matter. Three boxes of the size prescribed <lb/>
in this Bill will not fill a barrel; a fact <lb/>
which has been demonstrated by practical <lb/>
test. The box which the minister proposes
<lb/>
will contain the contents in cubic inches of <lb/>
one-third of a barrel, but he forgets that <lb/>
there is much waste of space when you <lb/>
pack three or four packages instead of <lb/>
one barrel, there being a large amount <lb/>
            </p>-->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>