<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1875-02-22"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1875-02-22">22 February 1875</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1975"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="263"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-02-22_Page_00262.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-02-22_Page_00263.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-07">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-02-22_Page_00262">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-02-22_Page_00262.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-02-22_Page_00263">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-02-22_Page_00263.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="262" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-02-22_Page_00262.jpg"/>
            
          <fw type="num">262</fw> <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS</fw>  
          
            <head>BOUNDARY LINE BETWEEN BRITISH COL<lb break="no"/>UMBIA AND THE NORTH-WEST TERRITORY.</head>
           
            <p><persName ref="pers:THOM5">Mr. THOMPSON</persName> (Cariboo) moved the<lb/>adoption of an address to HIS EXCELLENCY<lb/>the GOVERNOR GENERAL, praying that he<lb/>will take the necessary steps to have the<lb/>boundary line between British Columbia<lb/>and the North-West Territory (especially<lb/>towards the North-Eastern boundary of<lb/>the former) defined without delay, in view<lb/>of the anticipated extensive immigration<lb/>to the recently discovered gold mines on<lb/>the Arctic Watershed. He said he would<lb/>state briefly the reasons which led him to<lb/>submit the motion to the House. The<lb/>miners who had settled in the Stikeen River<lb/>country had ascended the river 160 miles,<lb/>and crossed the high-land separating the<lb/>waters which ran into the Pacific Ocean<lb/>by the Stikeen from those which ultimately<lb/>flow into the Arctic Ocean by the Mack<lb break="no"/>enzie River. During three months, because<lb/>the miners reached there late in the season,<lb/>between one million and one million and a<lb/>quarter of dollars worth of gold was taken<lb/>out of the streams tributary to the Mac<lb break="no"/>kenzie. A number of miners had gone two<lb/>hundred and fifty miles further up than<lb/>
          
            <pb n="263" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-02-22_Page_00263.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="running">FEBRUARY 22, 1875</fw> <fw type="num">263</fw>  
     
           
           any point hitherto discovered ; laid in a<lb/>stock of provisions there, and were en<lb break="no"/>gaged in prosecuting mining operations in<lb/>that section.  In travelling through an<lb/>unsettled country it was impossible for<lb/>those men to know when they crossed the<lb/>boundary line separating British Colum<lb break="no"/>bia from the North-West territory, and<lb/>passed under different jurisdictions. The<lb/>Chief Justice of British Columbia, on a<lb/>trip made into that section last year, took<lb/>observations from which he came to the<lb/>conclusion that the mines then being<lb/>worked were between 58 ° and 59 °<lb/>parallel of north latitude—the boundary<lb/>line being at 60 ° —and when the miners<lb/>proceeded between 250 and 300 miles<lb/>further in a north-easterly direction, it<lb/>was impossible for them to know when<lb/>they might strike one of the boundaries of<lb/>British Columbia, and therefore whether<lb/>they were within the jurisdiction of Brit<lb break="no"/>ish Columbia or the North-West territory.<lb/>He believed there was no officer of the<lb/>North-West Government in that section of<lb/>country, and it was therefore highly im<lb break="no"/>portant that either two boundaries be de<lb break="no"/>finitely settled, or powers be delegated to<lb/>the British Columbia Government to ex<lb break="no"/>ercise jurisdiction on the boundaries of<lb/>the North West territory.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government would have, in the<lb/>first place, to take steps to ascertain, as far<lb/>as possible, from existing documents,<lb/>where this boundary should be located,<lb/>and then they would determine what<lb/>steps should be taken in connection with<lb/>the Columbia Government to determine<lb/>the boundary. Communications woud,<lb/>therefore, have to take place with the Co<lb break="no"/>lumbia Government on the subject. He<lb/>hoped the motion would not be pressed,<lb/>because the matter would be dealt with<lb/>by the Government as a matter of course,<lb/>and it could only be dealt with, in the<lb/>first place, by correspondence with the<lb/>Local Government.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:THOM5">Mr. THOMPSON</persName> said that on the<lb/>understanding that the matter would be<lb/>brought before the Provincial Government<lb/>by the Dominion Government, which he<lb/>hoped would be done without delay, he<lb/>would withdraw the motion.—Motion<lb/>withdrawn.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>