<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1892-05-12"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1892-05-12">12 May 1892</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Second Session</title>.
          <date when="1892"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="2483" to="2487"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013399.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013400-edit7970.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013401-edit7926.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-11-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013399">
         <graphic url="final/images/Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013399.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013400">
         <graphic url="final/images/Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013400.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013401">
         <graphic url="final/images/Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013401.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="2483" facs="final/images/Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013399.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">2483</fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">2484</fw>
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT.</head>
           
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I beg to move that Bill (No.<lb/>
               27) further to amend the Act respectin gthe North-<lb break="yes"/>
               West Territories Act be set down for second reading<lb/>
               on Monday next. I desire to explain, after the<lb/>
               vote taken last night, why I make the motion. I<lb/>
               had intended, at some stage of teh debate, to speak<lb/>
               on the question, and I understood, in fact I was in<lb break="no"/>formed by many hon. gentlement, that other hon.<lb/>
               members also desired to speak on it as well. My<lb/>
               principal object in moving this motion, however, is<lb/>
               to direct attention to the practice which prevails in<lb/>
               this House, without in the slightest degree intend<lb break="no"/>ing to cast any imputation on you, Mr. Speaker, as<lb/>
               to the manner in which the question was put on<lb/>
               this occasion, and indeed on other occasions. One<lb/>
               side of the House cried "carried" and the other<lb/>
               side "lost," and you, Mr. Speaker, announced from<lb/>
               your place, without putting the question, and calling<lb/>
               for the yeas and nays, that the nays had it. That,<lb/>
               of course, properly speaking, put an end to all op<lb break="no"/>portunity for debate. That being done, in order<lb/>
               that the yeas and nays might be recorded, I called<lb/>
               for the yeas and nays. I think the proper prac<lb break="no"/>tice, and it is the English practice, that the<lb/>
               question being put by you, Mr. Speaker, from the<lb/>
               Chair, you should call for the yeas and then call<lb/>
               for the nays, and then declare whether the years or<lb/>
               the nays had it, and it is on appeal from that decision<lb/>
               that the yeas and nays are called for. The House<lb/>
               would then have the fullest opportunity of knowing<lb/>
               when the question was being put, and not, as last<lb/>
               night, be taken by surprise.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. For one, I am not able<lb/>
               to concur in the adoption of this motion, to-day. I<lb/>
               think the House fully understood, when the ques<lb break="no"/>tion was put last night, tha the principle of the<lb/>
               Bill was being voted on, and in relation to a public<lb/>
               measure, as this is, it is a very unusual course to<lb/>
               adopt such a motion. As regards what took place<lb/>
               last night, I feel bound to say that, to my mind,<lb/>
               the Chair showed unusual deliberation in putting<lb/>
               the question. It struck me when the question<lb/>
               was called for, and when both sides of the House<lb/>
               called either "carried" or "lost," that you, Mr.<lb/>
               Speaker, must have been under the imrpession that<lb/>
               a discussion would take place, otherwise you would<lb/>
               not have deliberated so long as you did in announc<lb break="no"/>ing what you thought was the result of the division.<lb/>
               I, therefore, feel bound to say that I think the<lb/>
               Chair cannot rest under any charge of undue ex<lb break="no"/>pedition.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DENI4">Mr. DENISON</persName>. I intended to have said a few<lb/>
               words last night, but, as many hon. members will<lb/>
               recollect, there is one hour allowed for private<lb/>
               Bills, and as the question was called not more than<lb/>
               15 or 20 minutes after eight o'clock, I and many<lb/>
               other hon. members were taken by surprise.
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCMU1">Mr. McMULLEN</persName>. Since the hon. member for<lb/>
               North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) placed the Bill on<lb/>
               the Order Paper it has been called in this House<lb/>
               not less than three or four time. It was called<lb/>
               when he was present, it was allowed to stand, I<lb/>
               presume at his request, from time to time, and<lb/>
               eventualy, at the eleventh hour last night, the<lb/>
               Bill was called. We are now reachign the last<lb/>
               stages of the session. It ws a question that will<lb/>
               cause considerable discussion, and for my part I<lb/>
               am not disposed to vote to reinstate it this session.
            </p>
            
            <cb/>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. My particular object, as I<lb/>
               stated, was to have an understanding, and I think<lb/>
               it is well we should have it as to how questions are<lb/>
               to be put from the Chair. As it seems to be against<lb/>
               the general feeling of the House, I do not desire to<lb/>
               press this motion. I quite realize now, that it<lb/>
               would be the occasion of very great inconvenience<lb/>
               to have a discussion upon this question this session,<lb/>
               but I thought it only due to my friends who desire<lb/>
               to speak on eitherside, and also to myself, to draw<lb/>
               attention to the fact that we were taken by sur<lb break="no"/>prise. I do not desire at all to impute any want<lb/>
               of courtesy to you, Mr. Speaker, or to say that you<lb/>
               did not give us time. There was plenty of oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity, that is quite certain, for any gentleman<lb/>
               here who desired to speak. At the same time I<lb/>
               think I am quite within the mark when I say, as<lb/>
               I do say, that I for one was taken by surprise<lb/>
               when you declared that the "nays" had it, and I<lb/>
               think other gentlemen were in the same position.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. Just allow me to<lb/>
               mention one circumstance which took place when<lb/>
               the hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy<lb/>
               was not in the House ; as completely meeting, I<lb/>
               think, the hon. gentleman's impression that the<lb/>
               advocates of the Bill were taken by surprise. The<lb/>
               Bill was called at a quarter to six, before recess,<lb/>
               and the hon. member for Muskoka (Mr. O'Brien)<lb/>
               rose to discuss it ; but at his request we all agreed<lb/>
               to call it six o'clock, in order that any gentleman<lb/>
               wishing to speak in favour of the Bill might get a<lb/>
               full hearing, and might know that the Bill was<lb/>
               to come up at eight o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. I woudl remind teh hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) that on this<lb/>
               occasion it was exactly as it was two years ago,<lb/>
               when he introduced his Bill with regard to the<lb/>
               French language. At that time, he expounded his<lb/>
               Bill on the first reading, and on the second read<lb break="no"/>ing he moved it without speech, exactly as he did<lb/>
               yesterday. Mr. Speaker gave ample opportunity<lb/>
               last night to any one who desired to speak on the<lb/>
               Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. No doubt.
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. I think two or three minutes<lb/>
               elapsed at least before the Speaker said : "Call in<lb/>
               the members."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BECH1">Mr. BECHARD</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I think the<lb/>
               hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy)<lb/>
               was wrong in saying that he was taken by surprise.<lb/>
               I was in my seat when the Bill ws called, and<lb/>
               when the motion for the second reading was put<lb/>
               everybody was looking for the hon. member to<lb/>
               rise and make a speech, but he was one of the first<lb/>
               to call "yeas" and "nays." It was after that,<lb/>
               that hon. gentlement said "call in the members," and<lb/>
               you, Mr. Speaker, gave the order to call in the<lb/>
               members after a few minutes had elapsed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). I understand the rule<lb/>
               to be that where a Bill is voted down, and not<lb/>
               postponed to any future date, that it can be put<lb/>
               on the Order Paper again by the hon. gentleman<lb/>
               who has charge of it if he sees proper  and it is<lb/>
               not a question of order at all. If the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man wishes to put his Bill on the Order Paper, I<lb/>
               suppose there is nothing in the rule to prevent<lb/>
               him. There is no doubt whatever, it seems to me,<lb/>
               that there was ample opportunity given for hon.<lb/>
               gentlemen who wished to speak. Mr. Speaker<lb/>
        
        
            <pb n="2485" facs="final/images/Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013400.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2485</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 12, 1892.]</fw> <fw type="num">2486</fw>
   
   
     took the chair at the ordinary hour for meeting. 
     <lb/>
     and I know that I came into the House somewhat 
     <lb/>
     after the usual hour and I was here in time to vote 
     <lb/>
     upon the subject. The calling of the "yeas " and 
     <lb/>
     " nays " does not prevent any member from speak<lb break="no"/>ing. It is only after the members are called in that 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentlemen are precluded from entering upon 
     <lb/>
     a discussion.        
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ARMS3">Mr. ARMSTRONG</persName>. I do not share the opinion 
     <lb/>
     of my hon. friend from North Wellington (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McMullen), and I think that in a matter of the 
     <lb/>
     importance of this Bill, time might be given for a 
     <lb/>
     fair consideration of it. I for one, Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>
     was taken by surprise last night. I could not 
     <lb/>
     accept the Bill in its shape as introduced by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), 
     <lb/>
     but I had intended to move an amendment to it 
     <lb/>
     and to substitute something else in the place of it. 
     <lb/>
     I had just begun to write the amendment, think<lb break="no"/>ing that the hon. gentleman would give a reason 
     <lb/>
     for the faith that was in him, a reason why he 
     <lb/>
     moved the second reading of the Bill, and that I 
     <lb/>
     would have had time to write the resolution 
     <lb/>
     amending it. However, the debate was shut off, 
     <lb/>
     after ample opportunity was given to the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman to speak. no doubt, and it simply remain<lb break="no"/>ed to me to vote for or against the Bill. I hope 
     <lb/>
     the House will allow the Bill to be reintroduced. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCGR4">Mr. McGREGOR</persName>. I was present when the 
     <lb/>
     motion for the second reading was called last 
     <lb/>
     evening, and I saw the hon. member for North 
     <lb/>
     Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) sitting in his place, and I 
     <lb/>
     heard the hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. Mc 
     <lb/>
     Carthy) saying "yeas" and "nays," after you, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Speaker, had given ample time for discussion. 
     <lb/>
     We expected that the hon. member would speak 
     <lb/>
     on the motion, but he did not, and I feel satisfied 
     <lb/>
     that ample time was given for discussion. We 
     <lb/>
     have had enough fooling with this question already, 
     <lb/>
     and if the hon.  gentleman is in earnest let him be 
     <lb/>
     in earnest and come forward with his Bill properly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I trust you 
     <lb/>
     will allow me the indulgence of the House to say 
     <lb/>
     this : The reason I did not speak in moving the 
     <lb/>
     second reading of the Bill was just as the hon. the 
     <lb/>
      leader of the  Opposition has said. I made my 
     <lb/>
     statement when I introduced the Bill. That is the 
     <lb/>
     proper time, when introducing a Bill in the hands 
     <lb/>
     of a private member, to explain it, and having only 
     <lb/>
     one opportunity of speaking I exercised my right 
     <lb/>
    to reserve what I had to say until I heard the state<lb break="no"/>ment against the measure. That is the course I 
     <lb/>took two years ago, and that is the course I in<lb break="no"/>tended to take on this occasion.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. I am very sorry indeed that that 
     <lb/>
     hon. member should have thought that I allowed 
     <lb/>him to be taken by surprise when the motion was 
     <lb/>  put to the House last night. I do not understand 
     <lb/>that the rule requires that a motion should be put 
     <lb/>a second time before calling the " yeas " and the 
     <lb/>" nays."  The motion was put from the Chair for 
     <lb/> the second reading of the Bill, and I waited a con<lb break="no"/>siderable time, as every member will bear testi<lb break="no"/>mony, to ascertain whether anybody desired to 
     <lb/>speak, but the cries of "lost" and "carried" 
     <lb/>came from both sides of the House.  In my opinion 
     <lb/>the " nays " had it, and I so expressed it, but even 
     <lb/>then I would have been willing to have allowed the 
     <lb/>discussion to go on if any member had chosen to 
     <lb/>rise after I had so expressed my opinion. After 
     <lb/>
    
    
    

    
            <cb/>
     
     
     the members are called in, however, as every hon. 
     <lb/>
     member knows, no discussion can be permitted. In  
     <lb/>
     future, if the House thinks it desirable that the 
     <lb/>
     question should be put twice from the Chair, I have 
     <lb/>
     no objection.      
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>. No, no. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">An hon. MEMBER</persName>. Hear, hear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. I may say in regard to this 
     <lb/>
     present motion, that it is in order. If the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman desires to withdraw it, it may be with<lb break="no"/>drawn if the House consents to it.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I will withdraw if the House 
     <lb/>
     desires it.         
            </p>
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. Is it the pleasure of the House 
     <lb/>
     that the hon. gentleman shall have permission to 
     <lb/>
     withdraw ?      
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Withdraw. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WALL6">Mr. WALLACE</persName>. I do not think the motion 
     <lb/>
     should be withdrawn, because, from whatever cause 
     <lb/>
     it is, a number of hon. gentlemen in this House who 
     <lb/>
    have been anxious to speak on this question were 
     <lb/>prevented from so doing. I think the blame rests 
     <lb/>with the hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. Mc 
     <lb/>

     Carthy) in the first place, in not allowing it to be 
     <lb/>
     known when such an important measure as this is 
     <lb/>
     coming up, that he intends to bring it before the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the House at a particular time, and 
     <lb/>
     that he does not intend to speak upon it. I know, 
     <lb/>
     for my own part, that I came into the House just 
     <lb/>
     as Mr. Speaker was saying " call in the members." 
     <lb/>
     If I had knownthe Bill would have come up so 
     <lb/>
     early I would have been here to offer a few remarks 
     <lb/>
     on it, as I intended to do ; but, I was prevented from 
     <lb/>
     having the opportunity, I think, therefore, permis<lb break="no"/>sion should be given to reintroduce the Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) I submit that this is not  
     <lb/>
     a question which should be decided specially with 
     <lb/>
     reference to the present metion of the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for North Simcoe  (Mr. McCarthy), because it 
     <lb/>
    involves a parliamentary precedent and a parlia<lb break="no"/>mentary right.  If, when the motion was made 
     <lb/>that the Bill be now read a second time, an amend<lb break="no"/>ment had been moved that the Bill should not be 
     <lb/>read then, but should be read this day three  
     <lb/>months or six months ; then the question would 
     <lb/> have been disposed of entirely. The only question 
     <lb/>before the House last night was . " that the  Bill 
     <lb/>should be now read a second time," and that was 
     <lb/>the only question disposed of entirely. It is open to the 
     <lb/>hon. gentleman, and it is his right, to put his Bill 
     <lb/>on the Order Paper without any motion in this 
     <lb/>House, because the only question which the House 
     <lb/>has passed on is, " Shall the Bill be now read a 
     <lb/>second time ?" As no amendment was then moved 
     <lb/>that the Bill should not be read, it is still before 
     <lb/>Parliament, and still within the hon. gentleman's 
     <lb/>power to put it on the Paper. I deprecate the 
     <lb/>introduction of a new rule in this matter, at 
     <lb/>variance with const it at ional practice and precedents. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. The rule as laid down by Dr. 
     <lb/>
     Bourinot in the last edition of his book is as 
     <lb/>
     follows :—     
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
      " If a resolution adverse to the Bill be resolved in the 
     <lb/>
     affirmative ; or the motion, ' that the Bill be now read a 
     <lb/>
     second time,' be simply negatived on a division, the 
     <lb/>
     measure will disappear from the order book, but it may 
     <lb/>
     be revived at any subsequent time, as the House has only 
     <lb/>
     decided that it should not then be read a second time, 
     <lb/>
     and the order previously made for the second reading re<lb break="no"/>mains good. When a Bill disappeals in this way from 
     <lb/>
   
   
   
            <pb n="2487" facs="final/images/Alb_Sask_H_of_C_Page_013401.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2487</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw>
      
      
     the Order Paper, it is competent for a member to move at 
     <lb/>
     any time: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " ' That it be read a- second time on — next.' 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " On this motion being agreed to, the Bill takes its 
     <lb/>
     place on the orders. The same practice obtains with 
     <lb/>
     'respect to the Bill at any previous or succeeding stage." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
            
            
            <p>My opinion is that a motion must he made to re<lb break="no"/>instate a Bill on the Order Paper, before it can 
     <lb/>reappear  there.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p>MR. SCRIVER. I think that the comparative<lb/>smallness of the vote of last night shows one of<lb/>two things, either that a number of members like<lb/>myself, supposing that the discussion on the Bill<lb/>would continue to a comparatively late hour, did<lb/>not hurry themselves to be present, and were there<lb break="no"/>fore absent, or that a number were conveniently<lb/>absent. I beg to say that I was in the former<lb/>category: and without giving any intimation of<lb/>what I might or might not have done, I may say<lb/>it was my intention to vote on the question and to<lb/>preface my vote with some remarks explanatory of<lb/>my reasons for doing what I proposed to do.<lb/>Having been, unfortunately, absent when the vote<lb/>was taken, through a reason which I do not care<lb/>now to state, I was taken by surprise.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Explain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:SCRI1">Mr. SCRIVER</persName>. And I would be glad of an<lb/>opportunity to vote upon the question. Therefore<lb/>I should be very much pleased, indeed, to see the<lb/>motion of my hon. friend from North Simcoe pre<lb break="no"/>vail and the Order restored to the Order Paper.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:IVES1">Mr. IVES</persName>. It may be, Mr. Speaker, as you have 
     <lb/>said, that the Billy may be restored to the Order<lb/>Paper: but what purpose would be served by re<lb break="no"/>storing it? I fancy that the hon. gentleman who<lb/>last addressed the House showed the object which<lb/>hon. gentleman would gain if the motion were re<lb break="no"/>stored to the Order Paper, namely, to rise in their<lb/>places and in a very few words explain to their<lb/>constituents why they did not vote. I fancy it<lb/>would answer all purposes if we gave a few moments<lb/>to these hon. gentlemen to explain to their consti<lb break="no"/>tuents why they were not here, or why they were<lb/>here and voted but did not speak. But it certainly<lb/>would not serve any good purpose to take up the<lb/>time of the House during one or two or, perhaps,<lb/>three sittings to repeat speeches which we have<lb/>already heard on two or three occasions; and cer<lb break="no"/>tainly, at this late stage of the session, the interests<lb/>of the large majority of the House, who are against<lb/>the second reading of the Bill, ought to be con<lb break="no"/>sidered rather than the interests of the score and<lb/>a half who are in favour of it, and who are not satis<lb break="no"/>fied because they have not had an opportunity of<lb/>explaining to their constituents what they think of<lb/>this matter when their constituents already know<lb/>what their views are.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr . SPEAKER. Shall the hon. gentleman have 
     <lb/>
     leave to withdraw the motion?   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Lost. Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
           
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. If there is a single dissent<lb break="no"/>ing voice the motion cannot be withdrawn.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:OUIM1">Mr. OUIMET</persName>. If the motion is withdrawn the<lb/>question will not be settled, but the motion will be<lb/>presented again, and we will have another discus<lb break="no"/>sion. So, for my part, I object to the motion being<lb/>withdrawn.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p>Motion negatived on a divisions.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>